<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 23:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Tell HN: Beware confidentiality agreements that act as lifetime non competes (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44338562</link>
            <guid>44338562</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 16:02:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44338562">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <tbody><tr id="44340313"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340313" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340313&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I think the Chinese law is effective in this regard: in order to maintain any non-competition agreement, the company must continue to pay you a monthly compensation amount equal to 30% of your total monthly income when you were at the company. Whenever the payment stops, the non-competition agreement is automatically void.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340472"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339541"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339541" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339541&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>It's funny how states like Washington are notorious for  enforceable non-competes, to be "business friendly".</p><p>Meanwhile California bans non-competes, and its GDP is 4th largest in the world if it were a country!</p><p>"incumbent friendly" vs "startup friendly"</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340513"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340513" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340513&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>WA is busy losing its way on taxation vs value provided for taxes paid and reporting burden. so imo these IP issues are almost second order effects at this point. i personally expect a continued exodus over some of the latest tax hikes for example taxing cap gains beyond a certain amount at an additional 7%. as if niit was not bad enough.  if residents could at least see some value from these added taxes maybe it could be something. also the estste tax there kicks in quickly and has hidden gotchas even for people who no longer live there.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339937"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339937" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339937&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I'm not sure what conclusions you think we should draw from that. California's advantage over Washington is primarily one of size - Washington's GDP per capita is actually about 3% higher than California's. The most generous interpretation I can think of is that you're crediting the non-compete difference for California's far larger population, which is tenuous at best.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340256"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339672"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339672" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339672&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I'm pro-California and anti-noncompetes, but I'm not sure if this evidence demonstrates much. The banning of non-competes in California is a very recent thing, and if we're doing a correlation thing, California saw the vast bulk of its growth when non-competes were in effect.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339799"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339760"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339760" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339760&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>California has banned non competes since 1872. You might be thinking about non solicits which was 2024 also reaffirming the ban on non competes</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340124"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340124" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340124&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The Traitorous Eight would only have been possible in California, not Washington, because of the position on noncompetes.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339861"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339861" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339861&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>So happy my union managed to ban broad non-competes in my country ~8 years ago. Now it needs to be <i>very</i> specific if they want to enforce it (not just "development work in the same industry" which most contracts had back when I graduated), only applicable for maximum a year, and they have to pay your salary for the time they stop you working somewhere else.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340095"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340429"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340429" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340429&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>How is a union any different in that respect than a corporation? I mean on a theoretical level. A true free-market firm would just be an association of individuals making individually negotiated transactions, with no employee-employer relationship, and no coordination on the side of purchasing labor. Of course that's very inefficient outside of pure theory. A corporation acts as a coordinating body that collectively negotiates the purchasing of labor contracts, and a union collectively negotiates on the selling side.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340391"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340416"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340312"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340258"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340006"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340006" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340006&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I once declined a job offer because the non-compete made no sense. (It was many pages, claimed that I would be paid during the non-compete period, and impossible to read.) I basically concluded that they (the company) had a lawyer that was basically wanking off.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340195"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340195" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340195&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>In finance, it is common to be paid your base wage during your non-compete. Or at least that is how mine worked.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340287"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340047"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340047" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340047&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>OTOH, beware letting yourself be intimidated by scary looking but unenforcable clauses that are all over contracts. In doubt, spend a bit of money on a lawyer to figure out what your real situation is.</p><p>I know of several cases where lawyers said "don't bother arguing with them about clause X, just sign it and ignore it".</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340052"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340052" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340052&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>In some countries that's illegal. So when presented with a contract that contains such claims, I have 2 options:</p><p>1) ask them to remove it... and so I risk not getting the job</p><p>2) don't say anything, and sign it</p><p>If I'm really interested in the job, I'll go for option 2 because I know they cannot enforce such claims, so I'll be fine.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340144"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340144" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340144&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>sounds crazy. in my country, adding anything that prevents you from finding work in the future to a contract is kind of invalid.</p><p>you do get non competes etc., but it never holds up in court as you can easily prove it prevents you from finding jobs.</p><p>i wish for you in your legislation there might be a similar law, otherwise these things are really evil. i mean, its like prison in some fields niche enough, and those are exactly the fields prone to such overly protective clauses</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340165"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340165" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340165&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; adding anything that prevents you from finding work in the future to a contract is kind of invalid.</p><p>Here it's six months top, and it only applies to management and specialists with critical domain knowledge - and this also has to be reflected in their wage.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340323"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339914"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339914" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339914&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>If I understand it right, those NDAs work as non-competes if “confidential” is defined as restricted just on the basis of some relationship to the business, which is pretty weird attack of legalese on common sense. Let’s say I used some relatively simple chain of thought to derive X about my job at Z. The fact that Z uses or does X is probably confidential, and that’s ok. This would be how I understood a broad definition. But what kind of reasoning would conclude that X is confidential per se, preventing me to use or do X elsewhere, effectively making doing my job impossible? It just doesn’t make sense.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340376"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340349"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339889"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339889" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339889&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; They argue it would be impossible for you to work elsewhere in this industry during your entire career without violating confidentiality with the technical and business instincts you bring to that domain</p><p>In that case you need to ask for a lifetime worth of salary, including growth from being in position to be put in escrow before you sign the dotted line. Otherwise they can hire you and fire you immediately and you'd never be able to work in your field that you spent years/decades training for.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340036"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340036" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340036&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Realistically, most places ban ‘unconscionable’ contract clauses, either explicitly or by making them unenforceable.</p><p>At least in theory, any judge  that saw clauses like that should throw it out for that reason alone in those jurisdictions.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340479"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340479" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340479&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Precisely. And, at least in the US, any contract which makes it impossible for a worker to take a new job in their field is extremely likely to be found unconscionable. It doesn't matter whether the contract is cast as a non-compete or as a NDA; if its effect is to say "you must work for us, or not at all", it's unlikely to hold up.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339828"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339828" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339828&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>This is a state level thing. As is whether IP produced outside of your job, on your own equipment, is yours.</p><p>I moved from New York to California a bit over 20 years ago in large part because I personally encountered this (the IP ownership bit), and preferred to live under California's rules.</p><p>It is worthwhile to read <a href="https://www.paulgraham.com/america.html" rel="nofollow">https://www.paulgraham.com/america.html</a>. Point 7 talks about how easy it is for regulations to accidentally squash startups. I believe that the fact that California makes neither mistake causes us squash fewer startups. It is not sufficient to have made Silicon Valley a startup hub, but it was likely necessary.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339873"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340293"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339853"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340007"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340007" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340007&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>A few years ago an American company that approached me (UK based) about a job opportunity insisted I sign an NDA before I could interview with them. I refused and they couldn't understand why so they even put me in contact with one of their lawyers. I still refused, and they eventually relented, but I could never understand why I'd need to sign an NDA to attend a job interview. There's literally no benefit to me in doing so.</p><p>At the time I was working for a competitor and I figured they could use the fact that I interviewed with them to argue that I - either intentionally or unintentionally - gained proprietary knowledge of their product and my current employer gained from it.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339555"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339555" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339555&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>What exactly should one be on the lookout for? Practically every company has an IP confidentiality agreement.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339845"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339845" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339845&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>ianal but: don't perform personal work while you are employed by an employer in the same industry. Or at least make it like you didn't do that to any observer.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339610"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339610" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339610&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Yeah, good luck being the odd one out who wants special individualized contract. This might work for unicorn value level employees that are poached from one FANG to another but not for the average Joe.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339692"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339692" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339692&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I never said I want an individualized contract, but I reserve the right to reject the offer, and I have, when the contract is unreasonable. What I want to know is when exactly to reject it wrt the confidentiality agreement.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44338688"><td></td></tr><tr id="44340045"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340045" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340045&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>IANAL and I don't know about other countries, but in EU (definitely the country I live in and am pretty sure it goes for the rest as well) any non-compete agreement after two years is void by law.</p><p>You are required to hold confidential stuff for life, like business contracts, but you can use your know-how, if it does not violate any patents, in a competing company as you see fit. This knowledge is a part of you and cannot hold you against employment. Even if you do decide within those two years to employ yourself in competing company, this can be held back by your original company only if they give you X% of your pay at them (X can be 80, or as low as 50, as my friends inform me).</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339729"><td></td></tr><tr id="44338722"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44338722" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44338722&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>So far it seems maybe?, but according to the article some courts and agencies are pushing back. Well the FTC was at least in 2023.</p><p>California bans anything that is effectively a non compete.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339241"><td></td></tr><tr id="44338949"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44338949" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44338949&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I didn't see any references in the article you linked to any cases where it had been enforced. I see a lot of commentary that validates the concern, and a listing of half a dozen states where they are being struck down.</p><p>So the callout to be wary of them is totally legit... but it doesn't look like they are going to be enforceable when such things go through the courts.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44338963"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44338963" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44338963&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Yeah the warning is: you may, like me, find a litigious paranoid former employer who freaks out at everything :-/</p><p>I’d rather not carry the cost of learning it’s not enforceable.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339553"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339553" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339553&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Technically, maybe, but effectively, nobody is going to be able to withstand BigCorp's 100 lawyers whose mission is to bury you in legal fees if you push back. By the time that you confirm these things are unenforceable, you've spent your life savings on $millions in legal fees, and possibly gone into crippling debt. In the legal system, might (wealth + lawyer quantity) makes right.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339899"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339899" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339899&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>As I recall from John Akula's Corporate Law class, judges in the US tend to be sympathetic to the following argument:</p><p>"Defendant has never worked in any other industry. He has three kids. He's gotta work."</p><p>(That's for regular employees--it's a different issue with founders who may have significant equity stake and such.)</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340377"><td></td></tr><tr id="44339998"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339998" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339998&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The "bury in litigation" is overstated. Since it's the _company_ that is going to sue you, there's a limited amount of shenanigans they can do.</p><p>The worst is that they can delay the case for years, leaving you in a legal limbo. Or go after your employer, involving them in the discovery process.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339879"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339879" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339879&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Have an employment attorney always look over said agreements before signing. A local acquaintance who did work for an MSP had said MSP try such a ploy, only for the employment attorney to sue and get it thrown out as unreasonable and unenforceable.</p><p>Never, EVER sign a contract without reading it first, and having your lawyer review it.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340027"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340027" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340027&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I understand that your advice is in good faith - but if we touch grass for a second, only the tiniest fraction of even professional workers have a lawyer at hand. And one that specializes in contract law? Even less.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340486"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44340486" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44340486&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It’s not that difficult to have legal help with your contract. Call your local bar association and ask for an employment law specialist. It will likely cost a couple hundred for them to review your contract.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44339950"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_44339950" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=44339950&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D44338562"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; your lawyer</p><p>That presupposes that people have a lawyer, and one specialized in employment law at that, which is highly unlikely to be the case for 99% of the population.</p></div></td></tr>
</tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="44340339"><td></td></tr>      </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US Congress is making more than 250M acres of public lands available for sale (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wilderness.org/articles/blog/congress-making-more-250-million-acres-public-lands-available-sale</link>
            <guid>44338122</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 15:01:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wilderness.org/articles/blog/congress-making-more-250-million-acres-public-lands-available-sale">https://www.wilderness.org/articles/blog/congress-making-more-250-million-acres-public-lands-available-sale</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44338122">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>  <p>On the heels of the disastrous House reconciliation bill’s passage, Senate Republicans have unveiled their own poisonous version of the bill that will fund President Trump’s agenda—a bill that calls for the outright sale of public lands as a key element.</p>
<p>The provision in question mandates the disposal of between 2 million and 3 million acres of lands managed by the Bureau of Land Management and Forest Service across 11 states: Alaska, Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington and Wyoming. Alarmingly, the provision contains very limited exemptions—Wilderness Study Areas, Areas of Critical Environmental Concern, roadless areas and critical habitat are all considered eligible for sale. <strong>Based on those limited restrictions, more than 250 million acres of public lands will be eligible to be sold to "any interested party."</strong></p>
<p>To illustrate just how much is at stake, we’ve created a map of all public lands that are now at risk of disposal.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft suspended the email account of an ICC prosecutor at The Hague (476 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/20/technology/us-tech-europe-microsoft-trump-icc.html</link>
            <guid>44336915</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 12:06:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/20/technology/us-tech-europe-microsoft-trump-icc.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/20/technology/us-tech-europe-microsoft-trump-icc.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44336915">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/06/20/technology/us-tech-europe-microsoft-trump-icc.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scaling our observability platform by embracing wide events and replacing OTel (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://clickhouse.com/blog/scaling-observability-beyond-100pb-wide-events-replacing-otel</link>
            <guid>44336015</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 09:23:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/scaling-observability-beyond-100pb-wide-events-replacing-otel">https://clickhouse.com/blog/scaling-observability-beyond-100pb-wide-events-replacing-otel</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44336015">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><blockquote>

<p> <strong>Observability at scale:</strong> Our internal system grew from 19 PiB to 100 PB of uncompressed logs and from ~40 trillion to 500 trillion rows.</p>
<p> <strong>Efficiency breakthrough:</strong> We absorbed a 20× surge in event volume using under 10% of the CPU previously needed.</p>
<p><strong>OTel pitfalls:</strong> The required parsing and marshalling of events in OpenTelemetry proved a bottleneck and didn’t scale - our custom pipeline addressed this.</p>
<p><strong>Introducing HyperDX:</strong> ClickHouse-native observability UI for seamless exploration, correlation, and root-cause analysis with Lucene-like syntax.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>About a year ago, we<a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/building-a-logging-platform-with-clickhouse-and-saving-millions-over-datadog"> shared the story of LogHouse </a>- our internal logging platform built to monitor ClickHouse Cloud. At the time, it managed what felt like a massive 19 PiB of data. More than just solving our observability challenges, LogHouse also saved us millions by replacing an increasingly unsustainable Datadog bill. The response to that post was overwhelming. It was clear our experience resonated with others facing similar struggles with traditional observability vendors and underscored just how critical effective data management is at scale.</p>
<p>A year later, LogHouse has grown beyond anything we anticipated and is now storing over 100 petabytes of uncompressed data across nearly 500 trillion rows. That kind of scale forced a series of architectural changes, new tools, and hard-earned lessons that we felt were worth sharing - not least that OpenTelemetry (OTel) isn’t always the panacea of Observability (though we still love it), and that sometimes custom pipelines are essential.</p>
<p><strong>In our case, this shift enabled us to handle a 20x increase in event volume using less than 10% of the CPU for our most critical data source - a transformation with massive implications for cost and efficiency.</strong></p>
<p>Other parts of our stack have also changed, not least due to the <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/clickhouse-acquires-hyperdx-the-future-of-open-source-observability">ClickHouse acquisition of HyperDX</a>. Not only did this give us a first-party ClickHouse-native UI, but it also led to the <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/clickstack-a-high-performance-oss-observability-stack-on-clickhouse">creation of ClickStack </a>- an opinionated, end-to-end observability stack built around ClickHouse. With HyperDX, we’ve started transitioning away from our Grafana-based custom UI, moving toward a more integrated experience for exploration, correlation, and root cause analysis.</p>
<p>As more teams adopt ClickHouse for observability and realize just how much they can store and query affordably, we hope these insights prove as useful as our first post. If you’re curious about this journey, when and where OTel is appropriate, and how we scaled a log pipeline to 100PB…read on.</p>
<div>
<p>Interested in seeing how ClickHouse works on your data? Get started with ClickHouse Cloud in minutes and receive $300 in free credits.</p></div>

<p>Over the past year, our approach to observability has undergone a significant transformation. We've continued to leverage OpenTelemetry to gather general-purpose logs, but as our systems have scaled, we began to reach its limits. While OTel remains a valuable part of our toolkit, it couldn't fully deliver the performance and precision we needed for our most demanding workloads. This prompted us to develop purpose-built tools tailored to our critical systems and rethink where generic solutions truly fit. Along the way, we've broadened the range of data we collect and revamped how we present insights to engineers.</p>

<p>When we last wrote about LogHouse, we were proud to handle 19 PiB of uncompressed data across 37 trillion rows. Today, those numbers feel like a distant memory. LogHouse now stores over 100 petabytes of uncompressed data, representing nearly 500 trillion rows.
Here's a quick look at the breakdown:</p>




















<table><thead><tr><th>System</th><th>Uncompressed Size</th><th>Stored rows</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>SysEx</td><td>93.6 PB</td><td>431 Trillion</td></tr><tr><td>OTel</td><td>14.5 PB</td><td>16.7 Trillion</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p>These numbers also tell a story. In our original post, 100% of our telemetry flowed through OpenTelemetry, with every log line collected via the same general-purpose pipeline. But as the scale and complexity of our data grew, so did the need for specialization.
While our total volume has grown more than 5x, the breakdown reveals a deliberate shift in strategy: today, the vast majority of our data comes from “SysEx”, a new purpose-built exporter we developed to handle high-throughput, high-fidelity system logs from ClickHouse itself. This shift marks a turning point in how we think about observability pipelines - and brings us to our first key topic.</p>
<p>We hope the following helps comprehend the scale at which LogHouse operates.</p>


<p>Initially, we used OpenTelemetry (OTel) for all log collection. It was a great starting point and an established industry standard which allowed us to quickly establish a baseline where every pod in our Kubernetes environment shipped logs to ClickHouse. However, as we scaled, we identified two key reasons to build a specialized tool for shipping our core ClickHouse server telemetry.</p>
<p>First, while OTel capably captured the ClickHouse text log via stdout, this represents only a narrow slice of the telemetry ClickHouse exposes. Any ClickHouse expert knows that the real gold lies in its <strong>system tables</strong> - a rich, structured collection of logs, metrics, and operational insights that go far beyond what’s printed to standard output. These tables capture everything from query execution details to disk I/O and background task states, and unlike ephemeral logs, they can be retained indefinitely within a cluster. For both real-time debugging and historical analysis, this data is invaluable. We wanted all of it in LogHouse.</p>
<p>Second, the inefficiency of the OTel pipeline for this specific task became obvious as we scaled.</p>

<p>The data journey involved:</p>
<ol>
<li>A customer's ClickHouse instance writes logs as JSON to stdout.</li>
<li>The kubelet persists these logs in <code>/var/log/…</code></li>
<li>An OTel collector collects these logs from the disk, parsing and marshalling the JSON into an in-memory representation.</li>
<li>The collector transforms these into the OTel log format - again an in-memory representation.</li>
<li>Finally, they are inserted back into another ClickHouse instance (LogHouse) over the native format (requiring another transformation within the ClickHouse Go client).</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: The architecture described here is simplified. In reality, our OTel pipeline is more involved. Logs were first collected at the edge in JSON, converted into the OTel format, and sent over OTLP to a set of gateway instances. These gateways (also OTel collectors) performed additional processing before finally converting the data into ClickHouse’s native format for ingestion. Each step introduced overhead, latency, and further complexity.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At our scale, this pipeline introduced two critical problems: inefficiency and data loss. First, we were burning substantial compute on repeated data transformations. Native ClickHouse types were being flattened into JSON, mapped into the OTel log format, and then re-ingested - only to be reinterpreted by ClickHouse on the other end. This not only wasted CPU cycles but also degraded the fidelity of the data.
Even more importantly, we were hitting hard resource limits on the collectors themselves. Deployed as agents on each Kubernetes node, they were subject to strict CPU and memory constraints via standard Kubernetes limits. As traffic spiked, many collectors ran so hot they began dropping log lines outright - unable to keep up with the volume emitted by ClickHouse. We were losing data at the edge before it ever had a chance to reach LogHouse.
We found ourselves at a crossroads: either dramatically scale up the resource footprint of our OTel agents (and gateways) or rethink the entire ingestion model. We chose the latter.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Note: To put the cost in perspective - handling 20 million rows per second through the OpenTelemetry pipeline without dropping events would require an estimated 8,000 CPU cores across agents and collectors. That’s an enormous footprint dedicated solely to log collection, making it clear that the general-purpose approach was unsustainable at our scale.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Our solution was to develop the <strong>System Tables Exporter</strong>, or <strong>SysEx</strong>. This is a specialized tool designed to transfer data from one ClickHouse instance to another as efficiently as possible. We wanted to go directly from the system tables in a customer's pod to the tables in LogHouse, preserving native ClickHouse types and eliminating all intermediate conversions. This has the fantastic side benefit that any query our engineers use to troubleshoot a live instance can be trivially adapted to query historical data across our entire fleet in LogHouse, as the table schemas are identical, with the addition of some enrichment columns (such as the Pod Name, ClickHouse version, etc).</p>
<p>Firstly we should emphasize that SysEx performs a <strong>literal byte-for-byte copy</strong> of data from the source to the destination. This preserves full fidelity, eliminates unnecessary CPU overhead, and avoids the pitfalls of repeated marshalling.</p>

<p>The architecture is simple and powerful. We run a pool of SysEx scrapers connecting to our customer's ClickHouse instances. A hash ring assigns each customer pod to a specific scraper replica to distribute the load. These scrapers then run SELECT queries against the source pod's system tables and stream the data directly into LogHouse, without any deserialization. The scrapers simply coordinate and forward bytes between the source and destination.
Scraping system tables requires careful handling to ensure no data is missed due to buffer flushes. Fortunately, nearly all system table data is inherently time-series in nature. SysEx leverages this by querying within a sliding time window, deliberately trailing real time by a small buffer - typically five minutes. This delay allows for any internal buffers to flush, ensuring that when a scraper queries a node, all relevant rows for that time window are present and complete. This strategy has proven reliable and meets our internal SLAs for timely and complete event delivery to LogHouse.</p>
<p>SysEx is written in Go, like most of our infrastructure components for ClickHouse Cloud. Naturally, this raises a question for anyone familiar with the Go ClickHouse client: how do we avoid the built-in marshalling and unmarshalling of data when reading from and writing to ClickHouse? By default, the client converts data into Go-native types, which would defeat the purpose of a byte-for-byte copy. To solve this, we <a href="https://github.com/ClickHouse/clickhouse-go/pull/1233">contributed improvements</a> to the Go client that allow us to <strong>bypass internal marshalling entirely</strong>, enabling SysEx to stream data in its native format directly from the source cluster to LogHouse - without decoding, re-encoding, or allocating intermediary data structures.</p>
<p>This approach is broadly equivalent to a simple bash command:</p>
<pre><code>curl -s -u <span>'default:&lt;password&gt;'</span> <span>"https://sql-clickhouse.clickhouse.com:8443/?query=SELECT+*+FROM+system.query_log+FORMAT+Native"</span> | curl -s -X POST --data-binary @- <span>'http://localhost:8123/?query=INSERT+INTO+query_log+FORMAT+Native'</span>
</code></pre>
<p>An actual go implementation for the curious can be found <a href="https://pastila.nl/?00740eb5/722157a76fc25f54212d7097b805253b#OSfprbH3wM1dGgtyMAnmuw==">here</a>.</p>
<p>Most importantly, SysEx doesn’t require the heavy buffering that OTel does, thanks to its pull-based model. Because scrapers query data at a steady, controlled rate, we don’t risk dropping logs when LogHouse is temporarily unavailable or when the source experiences a spike in telemetry. Instead, SysEx naturally handles backfill by scraping historical windows, ensuring reliable delivery without overloading the system or requiring complex retry buffers.</p>


<p>One of the key challenges with the SysEx approach is that it assumes the source and target schemas match. But in reality, as any ClickHouse user knows, system table schemas change frequently. Engineers continuously add new metrics and columns to support emerging features and accelerate issue diagnosis, which means the schema is a moving target.</p>
<p>To handle this, we generate schemas dynamically. When SysEx encounters a system table, it inspects and hashes its schema to determine if a matching table already exists in LogHouse. If it does, the data is inserted there. If not, a new schema version is created for this system table e.g. <code>text_log_6</code>.</p>
<p>At query time, we use ClickHouse’s <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/clickhouse-release-25-01#better-merge-tables">Merge table engine</a> to unify all schema iterations into a single logical view. This allows us to query across multiple versions of a system table seamlessly. The engine automatically resolves schema differences by selecting only the columns that are compatible across tables, or by restricting the query to tables that contain the requested columns. This gives us forward compatibility as schemas evolve, without sacrificing query simplicity or requiring manual schema management.</p>

<p>As we continued to scale and refine our observability capabilities, one of our primary focuses was capturing in-memory system tables, such as <code>system.processes</code>. Unlike the time-series data we’ve been capturing, these tables provide a snapshot of the server’s state at a specific point in time. To handle this, we implemented a periodic snapshot process, capturing these in-memory tables and storing them in LogHouse.</p>
<p>This approach not only allows us to capture the state of the cluster at any given moment, but also provides time-travel through critical details like table schemas and cluster settings. With this additional data, we are able to enhance our diagnostic capabilities by performing cluster-wide or ClickHouse Cloud-wide analyses. This we can join against service settings or query characteristics like used_functions to pinpoint anomalies, making it easier to identify the root causes of issues as they arise. By correlating queries with particular schemas, we further improved our ability to proactively identify and resolve performance or reliability problems for our customers.</p>

<p>One of the many powerful capabilities we've unlocked with SysEx is the ability to take the same <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/common-issues-you-can-solve-using-advanced-monitoring-dashboards">Advanced Dashboard queries</a>  that customers use to monitor their individual ClickHouse instances and run them across our entire fleet of customer instances simultaneously.</p>
<p>For release analysis, we can now execute proven diagnostic queries before and after deployments to immediately identify behavioral changes across our entire fleet. This has been rolled into our comprehensive release analysis process. Queries that analyze query performance patterns, resource utilization trends, and error rates complete in real time, allowing us to quickly spot regressions or validate improvements at fleet scale.</p>
<p>Secondly, our support dashboards can now embed the same deep diagnostic queries that customers rely on, but with enriched context from our centralized telemetry. When investigating customer issues, support engineers can run familiar Advanced Dashboard queries while simultaneously correlating with network logs, Kubernetes events, data and control plane events - all within the same interface.</p>
<!-- -->

<p>The efficiency gains from this SysEx are staggering. Consider these stats from LogHouse:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>OTel Collectors:</strong> Use over 800 CPU cores to ship 2 million logs per second.</li>
<li><strong>LogHouse Scrapers (SysEx):</strong> Use just 70 CPU cores to ship 37 million logs per second.</li>
</ul>
<p>This specialized approach has allowed us to handle a 20x increase in event volume with less than 10 percent of the CPU footprint for our most important data source. Most importantly, it means we no longer drop events at the edge. To achieve this same level of reliability with our previous OTel-based pipeline, <strong>we would have needed over 8,000 CPU cores</strong>. SysEx delivers it with a fraction of the resources, maintaining full fidelity and consistent delivery.</p>

<p>If you’ve read this far, you might be wondering: when is OpenTelemetry still the right choice, and is it still useful?
We firmly believe that it is. While our architecture has evolved to meet challenges at extreme scale, such as parsing and processing over 20 million log lines per second, OpenTelemetry remains a critical part of our stack. It offers a standardized, vendor-neutral format and provides an excellent onboarding experience for new users - and is hence the default choice for ClickStack. Unlike SysEx, which is tightly integrated with ClickHouse internals, OpenTelemetry decouples producers from consumers, which is a major architectural advantage, especially for users who want flexibility across observability platforms.</p>
<p>It is also well suited for scenarios where SysEx cannot operate. SysEx is pull-based and relies on querying live system tables, which means the service must be healthy and responsive. If a service is crash-looping or down, SysEx is unable to scrape data because the necessary system tables are unavailable. OpenTelemetry, by contrast, operates in a passive fashion. It captures logs emitted to <code>stdout</code> and <code>stderr</code>, even when the service is in a failed state. This allows us to collect logs during incidents and perform root cause analysis even if the service never became fully healthy.
For this reason, we continue to run OpenTelemetry across all ClickHouse services. The key difference is in what we collect. Previously, we ingested everything, including trace-level logs. Now, we collect only info-level and above. This significantly reduces the data volume and allows our OTel collectors and gateways to operate with far fewer resources. The result is a smaller, more focused pipeline that still accounts for the 2 million log lines per second referenced earlier.</p>

<p>Collecting all this data is just the beginning. Making it usable and accessible is what really matters. In the first iteration of LogHouse, we built a highly customized observability experience on top of Grafana. It served us well, but as our internal data sources grew and diversified, particularly with the introduction of SysEx and wide-column telemetry, it became clear we needed something more deeply integrated with ClickHouse.</p>
<p>This challenge was not unique to us. Many teams building observability solutions on ClickHouse have encountered the same issue. Getting data into ClickHouse was straightforward, but building a UI that fully unlocked its value required significant engineering effort. For smaller teams or companies without dedicated frontend resources, ClickHouse-powered observability was often out of reach.</p>
<p>HyperDX changed that. It provided a first-party, ClickHouse-native UI that supports log and trace exploration, correlation, and analysis at scale. Its workflows are designed with ClickHouse in mind, optimizing queries and minimizing latency. When we evaluated HyperDX prior to the acquisition, it was already clear that it addressed many of the pain points we and others had experienced. The ability to query using Lucene syntax dramatically simplifies data exploration and is often sufficient. Importantly, it still allows us to query in SQL - something which we still find essential for more complex event analysis - see “SQL for more complex analysis”.</p>
<p>A key reason HyperDX was such a compelling fit was the schema-agnostic <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/clickstack-a-high-performance-oss-observability-stack-on-clickhouse">approach introduced in v2.0</a>. It doesn't require log tables to conform to a single, rigid structure. This flexibility is critical for a system like LogHouse, which ingests data from numerous sources:</p>
<ul>
<li>It seamlessly handles the standardized, yet evolving, data format from our <strong>OpenTelemetry</strong> pipeline.</li>
<li>More importantly, it works out-of-the-box with the highly specialized, wide-column tables produced by <strong>SysEx</strong> and our other custom exporters. It does this with no prior knowledge of the SysEx schemas, or complex <em>grok pattern</em> specializations. It simply inspects the schema behind-the-scenes and adapts to work with them.</li>
</ul>
<p>This means our engineering teams can add new data sources with unique, optimal schemas to LogHouse without ever needing to worry about breaking or reconfiguring the user interface. By combining HyperDX's powerful UI and session replay capabilities with LogHouse's massive data repository, we have created a unified and adaptable observability experience for our engineers.</p>

<p>It is worth emphasizing that Grafana still has its place in our observability stack. Our internal Grafana-based application has some distinct advantages, particularly in how it handles routing and query scoping. Users are required to specify the namespace (effectively a customer service) they intend to query. Behind the scenes, the application knows exactly where data for each service resides and can route queries directly to the appropriate ClickHouse instance within LogHouse. This minimizes unnecessary query execution across unrelated services and helps keep resource usage efficient.</p>
<p>This is especially important in our environment, where we operate LogHouse databases across many regions. As our previous blog post described, efficiently querying across these distributed systems is critical for performance and reliability. We’re currently exploring how we might push this routing logic to ClickHouse itself, allowing HyperDX to benefit from the same optimization..so stay tuned.</p>
<p>In addition to its routing capabilities, Grafana remains the home for many of our long-standing dashboards and alerts, particularly those built on Prometheus metrics. These remain valuable, and migrating them is not currently a priority. For example, kube_state_metrics has almost become a de facto standard for cluster health monitoring. These high-level metrics are well suited for alerting, even if they are not ideal for deep investigation. For now, they continue to serve their purpose effectively.</p>
<p>For now, the two tools serve complementary purposes and coexist effectively within our observability stack.</p>

<p><em>Store everything, aggregate nothing</em></p>
<p>The development of SysEx has brought more than just technical gains. It has driven a cultural shift in how we think about observability. By unlocking access to system tables that were previously unavailable, where only standard output logs had been captured, we have embraced a model centered on wide events and high cardinality data.</p>
<p>Some refer to this as Observability 2.0. <strong>We simply call it LogHouse combined with ClickStack.</strong></p>
<p>This approach replaces the traditional three-pillar model with something more powerful: a centralized warehouse that can store high-cardinality telemetry from many sources. Each row contains rich context - query identifiers, pod names, version metadata, network details - without needing to pre-aggregate or discard dimensions to fit within the limits of a metric store.</p>
<p>As engineers, we have adapted to this new model, leaving behind outdated concerns about cardinality explosions. Instead of summarizing at ingest time, we store everything as is and push aggregation to query time. This approach allows for in-depth inspection and flexible exploration without sacrificing fidelity.</p>
<p>One pattern we have found particularly impactful is logging wide events that include timeseries attributes in place of traditional metrics. For example, here is a log line from SysEx that tracks data pushed from a source ClickHouse instance to the LogHouse cluster:</p>
<pre><code><span>{</span>
  <span>"level"</span><span>:</span> <span>"info"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"ts"</span><span>:</span> <span>1728437333.011701</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"caller"</span><span>:</span> <span>"scrape/scrape.go:334"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"msg"</span><span>:</span> <span>"pushed"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"podName"</span><span>:</span> <span>"c-plum-qa-31-server-zkmrfei-0"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"podIP"</span><span>:</span> <span>"10.247.29.9"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"spokenName"</span><span>:</span> <span>"plum-qa-31"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"azTopoName"</span><span>:</span> <span>"us-east1-c"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"srcTable"</span><span>:</span> <span>"part_log"</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"windowSize"</span><span>:</span> <span>120</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"insertDuration"</span><span>:</span> <span>0.00525254</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"insertLag"</span><span>:</span> <span>300.011693981</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"startGTE"</span><span>:</span> <span>1728436913</span><span>,</span>
  <span>"stopLT"</span><span>:</span> <span>1728437033</span>
<span>}</span>
</code></pre>
<p>At this point, you may be asking: <strong>how is this different from a traditional metrics store like Prometheus?</strong></p>
<p>The key difference is that we store <strong>every single data point</strong>. We do not pre-aggregate fields like <code>insertDuration</code>; instead, we capture and retain each value and store it together.</p>
<p>In contrast, a system like Prometheus typically stores either a gauge per series or, more commonly, pre-aggregates values into histograms to support efficient querying. This design introduces significant limitations. For example, storing time series for all label combinations in Prometheus would lead to a cardinality explosion. In our environment, with tens of thousands of unique pod names, each label combination would require its own timeseries just to preserve query-time flexibility. Pre-aggregating with histograms helps control resource usage but comes at the cost of fidelity. It makes certain questions impossible to answer, such as:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Which exact insert is represented by this spike in insertDuration - down to the specific instance, table, and time window?"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>With our approach, we avoid these trade-offs entirely. We log each event as a wide row that captures all relevant dimensions and metrics in full. This shifts aggregation and summarization to query time while preserving the ability to drill down into individual events when necessary.</p>
<p>This model isn’t entirely new. Systems like Elasticsearch have long encouraged the ingestion of wide events and flexible document structures. The difference is that ClickHouse makes this approach operationally viable at scale. Its columnar design allows us to store high-cardinality, high-volume event data efficiently - without the runaway storage costs or query latency that traditionally limited these kinds of approaches to storing events.</p>

<p>The power of this approach is in how we can use that single event to draw many different conclusions by visualising its various characteristics, and we can always jump back to the raw logs from any given point on a chart.</p>
<p>First, we can focus on a particular service and see its inserts line by line in series. This is the raw view upon the data.</p>

<p>We can visualize the insert lag for all tables for this individual instance trivially…</p>

<p>We may go a layer up and visualise the insert lag for all servers in a region, which have lag &gt; desired.</p>

<p>And, because Observability is <em>Just another Data Problem</em>, we get to borrow all of the tooling in the data science space for our observability data, so we can visualise our logs in any tool of our choice for which C<a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/integrations/data-visualization">lickHouse either integrates directly</a> or <a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/integrations/language-clients">via a client library</a>. For example, Plotly in a Jupyter notebook;</p>
<pre><code><span>import</span> plotly.express <span>as</span> px
<span>import</span> pandas <span>as</span> pd
<span>import</span> clickhouse_connect

client = clickhouse_connect.get_client(
…
)
query = <span>"""
SELECT
    toInt64(toFloat64(LA['ts'])) AS ts,
    toInt64(LA['startGTE']) AS start,
    toInt64(LA['stopLT']) AS stop
FROM otel.generic_logs_0
WHERE (PodName LIKE 'loghouse-scraper-%'
    AND Timestamp &gt;= '2025-06-10 16:14:00'
    AND Timestamp &lt;= '2025-06-10 18:35:00'
    AND EventDate = '2025-06-10'
    AND Body = 'pushed'
    AND LA['srcTable'] = 'text_log'
    AND LA['podName'] = 'c-plum-qa-31-server-zzvuyka-0'
)
ORDER BY EventTime DESC
"""</span>

df = client.query_df(query)

<span># Convert the 'start' and 'stop' columns from Unix timestamps to datetime objects</span>
df[<span>'start'</span>] = pd.to_datetime(df[<span>'start'</span>], unit=<span>'s'</span>)
df[<span>'stop'</span>] = pd.to_datetime(df[<span>'stop'</span>], unit=<span>'s'</span>)

fig = px.timeline(df, x_start=<span>"start"</span>, x_end=<span>"stop"</span>, y=<span>"ts"</span>)

fig.update_traces(width=<span>40</span>)
fig.update_layout(bargap=<span>0.1</span>)

fig.show()
</code></pre>

<blockquote>
<p>The plot shows scrape time versus wall time, allowing us to inspect each event for duplication. With Plotly, I could size the width of the rectangles as the exact start/end times. The annotations highlight a window where duplicate scrapes occurred, confirming the presence of overlapping data in that range.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
<p>This plot illustrates the varying insert duration for some tables collected by the LogHouse Scraper.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While I tend to prefer Plotly, we recognize that others may favor more modern visualization libraries. Thanks to ClickHouse's broad integration support, our SREs can choose the best tools for their workflows. Whether it’s Hex, Bokeh, Evidence, or any other platform that supports SQL-driven analysis, they are free to work with the approach that suits them best.</p>
<p>Here, we saw five views of the same event - demonstrating the flexibility we have to choose how we render at query time, using different charting tools, always with the ability to drill down into the raw line-by-line events.</p>

<p>HyperDX offers a robust event search interface utilizing Lucene syntax, ideal for quick lookups and filtering. However, to answer more complex observability questions, a more expressive query language is needed. With ClickHouse as the engine behind LogHouse, we can always drop into full SQL</p>
<p>SQL allows us to express joins, time-based operations, and transformations that would be difficult or impossible to perform in typical log query tools. One example is identifying pod termination times by correlating Kubernetes event streams. The query below uses ASOF JOIN to align Killing and Created events for the same container, calculating the time between termination and restart:</p>
<pre><code><span>WITH</span>
    KE <span>AS</span>
    (
        <span>SELECT</span> <span>*</span>
        <span>FROM</span> loghouse.kube_events
        <span>WHERE</span> (FirstTimestamp <span>&gt;=</span> <span>'2025-03-10 01:00:00'</span>) <span>AND</span> (FirstTimestamp <span>&lt;=</span> <span>'2025-03-11 01:00:00'</span>) <span>AND</span> (Reason <span>IN</span> [<span>'Killing'</span>]) <span>AND</span> (FieldPath <span>LIKE</span> <span>'spec.containers{c-%-server}'</span>)
    ),
    CE <span>AS</span>
    (
        <span>SELECT</span> <span>*</span>
        <span>FROM</span> loghouse.kube_events
        <span>WHERE</span> (FirstTimestamp <span>&gt;=</span> <span>'2025-03-10 01:00:00'</span>) <span>AND</span> (FirstTimestamp <span>&lt;=</span> <span>'2025-03-11 01:00:00'</span>) <span>AND</span> (Reason <span>IN</span> [<span>'Created'</span>]) <span>AND</span> (FieldPath <span>LIKE</span> <span>'spec.containers{c-%-server}'</span>)
    )
<span>SELECT</span>
    Name,
    KE.FirstTimestamp <span>AS</span> killTime,
    CE.FirstTimestamp <span>AS</span> createTime,
    createTime <span>-</span> killTime <span>AS</span> delta,
    formatReadableTimeDelta(createTime <span>-</span> killTime) <span>AS</span> readableDelta
<span>FROM</span> KE
ASOF <span>LEFT</span> <span>JOIN</span> CE <span>ON</span> (CE.Name <span>=</span> KE.Name) <span>AND</span> (CE.FirstTimestamp <span>&gt;=</span> KE.FirstTimestamp)
<span>HAVING</span> createTime <span>&gt;</span> <span>'1970-01-01 00:00:00'</span>
<span>ORDER</span> <span>BY</span> delta <span>DESC</span>
LIMIT <span>5</span>

</code></pre>
<pre><code>┌─Name─────────────────────────────┬────────────killTime─┬──────────createTime─┬─delta─┬─readableDelta─────────────────────┐
│ c-emerald-tu-48-server-p0jw87g-0 │ 2025-03-10 19:01:39 │ 2025-03-10 20:15:59 │  4460 │ 1 hour, 14 minutes and 20 seconds │
│ c-azure-wb-13-server-648r93g-0   │ 2025-03-10 11:30:23 │ 2025-03-10 12:28:50 │  3507 │ 58 minutes and 27 seconds         │
│ c-azure-wb-13-server-3mjrr1g-0   │ 2025-03-10 11:30:23 │ 2025-03-10 12:28:47 │  3504 │ 58 minutes and 24 seconds         │
│ c-azure-wb-13-server-v31soea-0   │ 2025-03-10 11:30:23 │ 2025-03-10 12:28:46 │  3503 │ 58 minutes and 23 seconds         │
└──────────────────────────────────┴─────────────────────┴─────────────────────┴───────┴───────────────────────────────────┘

4 rows in set. Elapsed: 0.099 sec. Processed 17.78 million rows, 581.49 MB (180.05 million rows/s., 5.89 GB/s.)
Peak memory usage: 272.88 MiB.
</code></pre>
<p>Sure, we could write a component to track this as a metric, but the power of ClickHouse is that we don’t need to do so. It’s sufficient to store a warehouse of wide events and derive the metric we need at query time from them. So, when a colleague asks, ‘what’s the p95 replacement time for Pods after termination is requested’, we can just find a relevant set of events instead of responding, 'let me ship a new metric ', and getting back to them with an answer after the next release goes out.</p>

<p>Sold on the immense value of having deep, structured telemetry in a high-performance analytics engine, we've been busy adding more data sinks to LogHouse, mainly at the request of our engineering and support team, who love using LogHouse and want all critical data to live in the warehouse. This year, we've embraced a cultural shift towards high-cardinality, wide-event-based observability as shown above.</p>
<p>Some of our new data sources, which adhere to this wide event philosophy, include:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>kubenetmon:</strong> Our open-source tool for monitoring Kubernetes networking, giving us deep insights into cluster traffic. <code>kubenetmon</code> uses Linux's conntrack system to capture L3/L4 connection data with byte/packet counts. This provides three key capabilities: forensics (time-series connection records with per-minute bandwidth), attribution (mapping connections to specific workloads and pods), and metering (cost tracking for expensive data transfer like cross-region egress). The system processes millions of connection observations per minute, helping us identify costly cross-regional downloads, track cross-AZ traffic patterns, and correlate network usage with actual costs. You can find the project at<a href="https://github.com/ClickHouse/kubenetmon"> https://github.com/ClickHouse/kubenetmon</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Kubernetes Event Exporter:</strong> We forked the popular exporter and added a native ClickHouse sink, allowing us to analyze Kubernetes API events at scale. You can find our fork <a href="https://github.com/ClickHouse/kubernetes-event-exporter">here</a>. This is hugely useful for understanding why things changed in K8s over time. We’re not stopping there, however! We’re already working on a plan to ingest not just the events, but the entire k8s object model into LogHouse, with snapshots at every change. This would allow us to model the full state of all clusters at any moment in time over the past six months, and step through all of the changes. Instead of just knowing "Pod X was terminated at 15<!-- -->," we’ll see the full cluster state before and after, understand dependencies, resource constraints, and the cascading effects of changes.</li>
<li><strong>Control Plane Data:</strong> We collect all operational data from our Control Plane department, who had not yet onboarded into LogHouse.</li>
<li><strong>Real User Monitoring (RUM):</strong> In a project that is still a work in progress, we collect frontend performance metrics from our users' browsers, which are pushed via a public gateway into our OTel pipeline.</li>
<li><strong>Istio Access Log:</strong> We ingest HTTP-level traffic data from our Istio service mesh, capturing request/response patterns, latencies, and routing decisions. Combined with ClickHouse's system.query_log and kubenetmon's network flows, this creates a powerful tri-dimensional correlation capability. When network usage spikes occur, our support team can trace the complete story: which specific SQL queries were executing, what HTTP requests triggered them, and the exact packet flow patterns. This cross-layer visibility transforms debugging from guesswork into precise root cause analysis - if we see unusual egress traffic, we can immediately identify whether it's from expensive cross-region queries, backup operations, or unexpected replication, making troubleshooting incredibly efficient for the support team.</li>
</ul>

<p>It’s been an incredible year of growth for LogHouse. By moving beyond a one-size-fits-all approach and embracing specialized, highly efficient tooling, we’ve scaled our observability platform to remarkable new heights while significantly enhancing our cost performance. Integrating HyperDX is a key part of that evolution, providing a flexible and powerful user experience on top of our petabyte-scale data warehouse. We're excited to see what the next year brings as we continue to build on this strong foundation.</p>

<p>While SysEx is designed to be efficient and resource-conscious, customers occasionally notice our scrape queries in their logs and metrics. These queries are <strong>tightly constrained with strict memory limits</strong>, but when they error (as they sometimes do) it can create concern. Although the actual resource impact is minimal, we recognize that even lightweight queries can create noise or confusion in sensitive environments.</p>
<p>To address this, we’re exploring what we call <strong>zero-impact scraping</strong> - the next evolution of SysEx. The goal is to eliminate all in-cluster query execution by entirely decoupling scraping from the live system. One promising direction involves leveraging <strong><a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/operations/storing-data#s3-plain-rewritable-storage">plain rewritable disks on S3</a></strong>, where ClickHouse already writes its service logs. In this model, a pool of SysEx workers would mount these disk-based log tables directly, bypassing the need to query the running ClickHouse instance. This design would deliver all the benefits of our current system - native format, high fidelity, minimal transformation - while removing even the perception of operational impact.</p>
<p>OpenTelemetry remains a critical component of our platform, particularly for early-stage data capture before service tables are available. This is especially useful during crash loops, where structured logs may be unavailable. However, if our zero-impact scraping approach proves successful, it could reduce our reliance on OTel even further by providing a high-fidelity, low-disruption path for log ingestion throughout the lifecycle of a cluster.</p>
<p>This effort is still in progress, and we’ll share more once we’ve validated the approach in production.</p>

<p>The JSON type has been available in ClickHouse for some time and <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/clickhouse-release-25-03">recently reached GA in version 25.3</a>. It offers a flexible and efficient way to store semi-structured data, dynamically creating columns with appropriate types as new fields appear. It even supports <a href="https://clickhouse.com/blog/a-new-powerful-json-data-type-for-clickhouse">fields with multiple types</a> and gracefully handles schema explosion.</p>
<p>Despite these advantages, we’re still evaluating how well JSON fits common observability access patterns at scale. For example, querying a string across an entire JSON blob can effectively involve scanning thousands of columns. There are workarounds - such as also storing a raw string version of the JSON alongside the structured data - but we’re still developing best practices in this area.</p>
<p>Culturally, we have also come to recognize the practical limits of the Map type, which has served us well. Most of our log and resource attributes are small and stable enough that the Map continues to be the right fit. We have found that single-level JSON logs are often all you need, and for exceptions, tools like HyperDX automatically translate map access into <a href="https://clickhouse.com/docs/sql-reference/functions/json-functions#jsonextract">JSONExtract</a> functions. While we plan to adopt JSON more broadly, this is still a work in progress. Expect us to share more in a future update.</p>

<p>Over the past year, LogHouse has evolved from an ambitious logging system into a foundational observability platform powering everything from performance analysis to real-time debugging across ClickHouse Cloud. What began as a cost-saving measure has become a catalyst for both cultural and technical transformation, shifting us toward high-fidelity, wide-event telemetry at massive scale. By combining specialized tools like SysEx with general-purpose frameworks like OpenTelemetry, and layering on flexible interfaces like HyperDX, we have built a system that not only keeps up with our growth but also unlocks entirely new workflows. The journey is far from over, but the lessons from scaling to 100PB and 500 trillion rows continue to shape how we think about observability as a core data problem we are solving at warehouse scale.</p></div><p><a href="https://clickhouse.cloud/signUp?loc=blog-cta-footer&amp;utm_source=clickhouse&amp;utm_medium=web&amp;utm_campaign=blog">Get started</a> with ClickHouse Cloud today and receive $300 in credits. At the end of your 30-day trial, continue with a pay-as-you-go plan, or <a href="https://clickhouse.com/company/contact?loc=blog-cta-footer">contact us</a> to learn more about our volume-based discounts. Visit our <a href="https://clickhouse.com/pricing?loc=blog-cta-header">pricing page</a> for details.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: We moved from AWS to Hetzner, saved 90%, kept ISO 27001 with Ansible (249 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/@accounts_73078/goodbye-aws-how-we-kept-iso-27001-slashed-costs-by-90-914ccb4b89fc</link>
            <guid>44335920</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 09:02:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://medium.com/@accounts_73078/goodbye-aws-how-we-kept-iso-27001-slashed-costs-by-90-914ccb4b89fc">https://medium.com/@accounts_73078/goodbye-aws-how-we-kept-iso-27001-slashed-costs-by-90-914ccb4b89fc</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44335920">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://medium.com/@accounts_73078/goodbye-aws-how-we-kept-iso-27001-slashed-costs-by-90-914ccb4b89fc: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cosmoe: BeOS Class Library on Top of Wayland (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cosmoe.org/index.html</link>
            <guid>44335907</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 09:00:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cosmoe.org/index.html">https://cosmoe.org/index.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44335907">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

    <!-- Hero Section -->
    <section id="hero">

      <img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/hero-bg-abstract.jpg" alt="" data-aos="fade-in">

      <div data-aos="zoom-out">
          <p>A new generation of Cosmoe<br>has arrived</p>
        </div>

    </section><!-- /Hero Section -->

    <!-- About Section -->
    <section id="about">

      <!-- Section Title -->
      <div data-aos="fade-up">
        <h2>Cosmoe - building graphical apps reimagined<br></h2>
		<p>The newest iteration of Cosmoe is a C++ UI library for creating rich, easy-to-code graphical apps for Wayland.  It brings the benefits of the BeOS class library onto a modern kernel and display engine.</p>
      </div><!-- End Section Title -->

      <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">
			<p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/cosmoe1.png"></p>
            <p>
				Cosmoe, like BeOS which inspired it, is designed with these goals in mind:
            </p>
            <ul>
				<li><i></i> <span>Extremely easy-to-use GUI classes make for rapid app development</span></li>
				<li><i></i> <span>Highly multi-threaded for maximum performance on modern hardware</span></li>
				<li><i></i> <span>Very low resource usage</span></li>
            </ul>
          </div>

    </section><!-- /About Section -->

    <!-- About-alt Section -->
    <section id="about-alt">

		<!-- Section Title -->
		<p data-aos="fade-up">
		  <h2>Technologies<br></h2>
		</p><!-- End Section Title -->
  
		</section><!-- /About Alt Section -->

    <!-- Clients Section -->
    <!-- /Clients Section -->

    <!-- Testimonials Section -->
    <section id="testimonials">

      <!-- Section Title -->
      <p data-aos="fade-up">
        <h2>Testimonials</h2>
      </p><!-- End Section Title -->

      <div data-speed="600" data-delay="5000" data-breakpoints="{ &quot;320&quot;: { &quot;slidesPerView&quot;: 1, &quot;spaceBetween&quot;: 40 }, &quot;1200&quot;: { &quot;slidesPerView&quot;: 3, &quot;spaceBetween&quot;: 40 } }" data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100">

            <div>
            	<p>
					<i></i>
					<span>Proin iaculis purus consequat sem cure digni ssim donec porttitora entum suscipit rhoncus. Accusantium quam, ultricies eget id, aliquam eget nibh et. Maecen aliquam, risus at semper.</span>
					<i></i>
                </p>
                <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/testimonials/testimonials-1.jpg" alt=""></p><h3>Saul Goodman</h3>
                <h4>Ceo &amp; Founder</h4>
              </div><!-- End testimonial item -->

            <div>
                <p>
                  <i></i>
                  <span>Export tempor illum tamen malis malis eram quae irure esse labore quem cillum quid malis quorum velit fore eram velit sunt aliqua noster fugiat irure amet legam anim culpa.</span>
                  <i></i>
                </p>
                <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/testimonials/testimonials-2.jpg" alt=""></p><h3>Sara Wilsson</h3>
                <h4>Designer</h4>
              </div><!-- End testimonial item -->

            <div>
                <p>
                  <i></i>
                  <span>Enim nisi quem export duis labore cillum quae magna enim sint quorum nulla quem veniam duis minim tempor labore quem eram duis noster aute amet eram fore quis sint minim.</span>
                  <i></i>
                </p>
                <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/testimonials/testimonials-3.jpg" alt=""></p><h3>Jena Karlis</h3>
                <h4>Store Owner</h4>
              </div><!-- End testimonial item -->

            <div>
                <p>
                  <i></i>
                  <span>Fugiat enim eram quae cillum dolore dolor amet nulla culpa multos export minim fugiat dolor enim duis veniam ipsum anim magna sunt elit fore quem dolore labore illum veniam.</span>
                  <i></i>
                </p>
                <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/testimonials/testimonials-4.jpg" alt=""></p><h3>Matt Brandon</h3>
                <h4>Freelancer</h4>
              </div><!-- End testimonial item -->

            <div>
                <p>
                  <i></i>
                  <span>Quis quorum aliqua sint quem legam fore sunt eram irure aliqua veniam tempor noster veniam sunt culpa nulla illum cillum fugiat legam esse veniam culpa fore nisi cillum quid.</span>
                  <i></i>
                </p>
                <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/testimonials/testimonials-5.jpg" alt=""></p><h3>John Larson</h3>
                <h4>Entrepreneur</h4>
              </div><!-- End testimonial item -->

          </div>

    </section><!-- /Testimonials Section -->

    <!-- Portfolio Section -->
    <section id="portfolio">

      <!-- Section Title -->
      <div data-aos="fade-up">
        <h2>Portfolio</h2>
        <p>Necessitatibus eius consequatur ex aliquid fuga eum quidem sint consectetur velit</p>
      </div><!-- End Section Title -->

      <div data-default-filter="*" data-layout="masonry" data-sort="original-order">

          <ul data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100">
            <li data-filter="*">All</li>
            <li data-filter=".filter-app">App</li>
            <li data-filter=".filter-product">Card</li>
            <li data-filter=".filter-branding">Web</li>
          </ul><!-- End Portfolio Filters -->

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-1.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>App 1</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-2.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>Product 1</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-3.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>Branding 1</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-4.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>App 2</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-5.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>Product 2</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-6.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>Branding 2</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-7.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>App 3</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-8.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>Product 3</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

            <div>
              <p><img src="https://cosmoe.org/assets/img/masonry-portfolio/masonry-portfolio-9.jpg" alt=""></p><div>
                <h4>Branding 3</h4>
                <p>Lorem ipsum, dolor sit</p>
                </div>
            </div><!-- End Portfolio Item -->

          </div><!-- End Portfolio Container -->

        </div>

    </section><!-- /Portfolio Section -->

    <!-- Faq Section -->
    <section id="faq">

      <!-- Section Title -->
      <p data-aos="fade-up">
        <h2>Frequently Asked Questions</h2>
      </p><!-- End Section Title -->

      <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100">

              <div>
                <h3>How can I try out Cosmoe?</h3>
                <p>Cosmoe is still a work in progress, and exists as a source-only technology preview for now.  To run it, clone or download the <a href="https://gitlab.com/haydentech/cosmoe-wayland/">Cosmoe source code repo from Gitlab</a> and compile the code on your Linux distribution of choice.  There are several sample applications included which demonstrate what it is capable of.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3>What are the plans for Cosmoe going forward?</h3>
                <div><p>Cosmoe needs 2 main improvements to be a reliable, full-featured UI library:</p><p>
					<strong>Stability</strong><br>While I've made incredible strides with getting the BeOS class libraries to talk to Wayland, much work still remains to weed out crashes and incorrect behavior.  Wayland is powerful, but not friendly.</p><p>
					<strong>Compatibility</strong><br>Cosmoe implements about 95% of the BeOS API currently.  Notable feature that are not yet implemented include "offscreen" BBitmaps for accelerated drawing, and BFilePanel which implements Open and Save dialog boxes.  Some file-related classes like BVolume are only partially implemented.  Also, for security reasons, Wayland forbids certain Window-related actions such as window positioning and centering, so that functionality can never exist.</p><p>
					For more details on this items and other in-progress aspects of Cosmoe, please see the <a href="https://gitlab.com/haydentech/cosmoe-wayland/-/blob/master/TODO?ref_type=heads">TODO file in the Cosmoe repo</a>.
				</p></div>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3>What license does Cosmoe use?</h3>
                <p>Cosmoe is distributed under the MIT license.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3>What source code comprises Cosmoe?  Where did it come from, and what inspired it?</h3>
                <p>Cosmoe is a fork of the Haiku operating system, which itself is an open-source re-implementation of BeOS.  The current iteration of Cosmoe is implemented as a UI library, but <a href="https://gitlab.com/haydentech/cosmoe-haiku/">the previous iteration (now known as "Cosmoe Classic")</a> was a full port of Haiku to the Linux kernel.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3>How is the current iteration of Cosmoe different from Cosmoe Classic?</h3>
                <p>The <a href="https://gitlab.com/haydentech/cosmoe-wayland/">current iteration of Cosmoe</a> is a shared library which implements the BeOS class library on top of Wayland.  There are no supporting programs, e.g. app_server or registrar, needed to use it.  All the necessary functionality is rolled into the library.  Apps linked with the library run natively on Linux via Wayland.
  <br>The <a href="https://gitlab.com/haydentech/cosmoe-haiku/">previous iteration of Cosmoe (now known as "Cosmoe Classic")</a> is a full port of the Haiku OS to the Linux kernel.  It runs inside an SDL window on Linux.  It would be possible to develop graphics drivers to allow it to run as its own standalone Linux-based OS, but those have not been developed.
<br>Moving forward, my focus is on the shared library version since I believe it has the most practical benefit.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->
            </div>

    </section><!-- /Faq Section -->

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[uBlock Origin Lite Beta for Safari iOS (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://testflight.apple.com/join/JjTcThrV</link>
            <guid>44335664</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 08:10:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://testflight.apple.com/join/JjTcThrV">https://testflight.apple.com/join/JjTcThrV</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44335664">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main" role="main">
        

        <article>
            <div>
                        <header>
                            
                            
                            <h2>
Testing Apps with TestFlight</h2>
                            <p>
Help developers test beta versions of their apps and App Clips using the <span>TestFlight app.</span> Download TestFlight on the <span>App Store</span> for iPhone, iPad, Mac, <span>Apple TV,</span> <span>Apple Vision Pro</span>, Watch, and iMessage.</p>
                        </header>
                    </div>

                <a href="#getting-started">&nbsp;</a>
                <div id="getting-started">
<h2>Getting started</h2><p>To test beta versions of apps and App Clips using TestFlight, you’ll need to accept an email or public link invitation from the developer and have a device that you can use to test. You’ll be able to access the builds that the developer makes available to you.</p><p>Note: Developers can choose to set criteria for their beta, such as a preferred device or OS. You must have the preferred device and OS in order to accept the invitation. You can tap or click Learn More in the invite to view the specific device and OS requirements the developer is looking for.</p><p>If you’re a member of the developer’s team, the developer can give you access to all builds or certain builds</p><h3>Required OS by platform</h3><ul><li>iOS or iPadOS apps: iPhone, iPad, or <span>iPod touch</span> running <span>iOS 14</span> or <span>iPadOS 14</span> or later. App Clips require <span>iOS 14</span> or <span>iPadOS 14,</span> or later.</li><li>macOS apps: <span>Mac</span> running <span>macOS 12</span> or later.</li><li>tvOS apps: <span>Apple TV</span> running <span>tvOS 14</span> or later.</li><li>visionOS apps: <span>Apple Vision Pro</span> running <span>visionOS 1</span> or later.</li><li>watchOS apps: <span>Apple Watch</span> running <span>watchOS 6</span> or later.</li></ul>
<h3>Available languages</h3><h3>iOS, iPadOS, macOS, tvOS, and watchOS</h3><p>Arabic, Catalan, Chinese (simplified), Chinese (traditional), Croatian, Czech, Danish, Dutch, English (Australia), English (U.K.), English (U.S.), Finnish, French, French (Canada), German, Greek, Hebrew, Hindi, Hungarian, Indonesian, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Malaysian, Norwegian, Polish, Portuguese (Brazil), Portuguese (Portugal), Romanian, Russian, Slovak, Spanish, Spanish (Latin America), Swedish, Thai, Turkish, Ukrainian, and Vietnamese.</p><h3>visionOS</h3><p>Arabic, Chinese (Simplified), Chinese (Traditional), English (Australia), English (U.K.), English (U.S.), French, French (Canada), German, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Spanish, and Spanish (Latin America)</p></div>
                <a href="#installing-testing">&nbsp;</a>
                <div id="installing-testing">
<h2>Installing and testing beta apps</h2><p>Each build is available to test for up to 90 days, starting from the day the developer uploads their build. You can see how many days you have left for testing under the app name in TestFlight. TestFlight will notify you each time a new build is available and will include instructions on what you need to test. Alternatively, with TestFlight 3 or later, you can turn on automatic updates to have the latest beta builds install automatically.</p><p>When the testing period is over, you'll no longer be able to open the beta build. To install the <span>App Store</span> version of the app, download or purchase the app from the <span>App Store</span>. In-app purchases are free only during beta testing, and any in-app purchases made during testing will not carry over to <span>App Store</span> versions.</p><p>Note: To automatically download additional in-app content and assets in the background once a beta app is installed in iOS 16, iPadOS 16, macOS 13, tvOS 18.4, or visionOS 2.4, turn on Additional In-App Content in your App Store settings for <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/iphone/manage-purchases-subscriptions-settings-iph3dfd91de/ios">iPhone</a>, <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/ipad/manage-purchases-subscriptions-settings-ipadee10c6e7/ipados">iPad</a>, <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/app-store/change-app-store-preferences-mchlp2257/3.0/mac/13.0">Mac</a>, Apple TV, and Apple Vision Pro.</p>
<h3>Installation</h3><p>To get started, install TestFlight on the device you’ll use for testing. Then, accept your email invitation or follow the public link invitation to install the beta app. The public link invitation will include a description of the beta app and may also include screenshots, the app category, and criteria you must meet to join the beta. You can install the beta app on up to 30 devices.</p><p>If you do not meet the tester criteria, the beta invitation will inform you that the developer requires you to test with a specific device and OS when you tap or click Learn More on the beta invitation. If you have a device that meets the critiera, you can install TestFlight on the device and then accept the beta invitation.</p><p>Keep in mind that you can accept an invitation on a non-preferred device as long as you have a device associated with TestFlight that meets the criteria set by the developer.</p><p>If you do not wish to accept an invitation, you can easily <a href="#giving-feedback">give feedback</a> to help the developer by letting them know why.</p><p><span>Note:</span> When testing your app's subscriptions in TestFlight, the renewal rate is accelerated. Each subscription is renewed daily, up to 6 times within a one-week period, regardless of the subscription's duration.</p><p><span>Note:</span> <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT210737"><span>Managed Apple Accounts</span></a> can't be used to test builds.</p>
<h3 id="installing-ios">Installing a beta iOS or iPadOS app via email or public link invitation</h3><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on the iOS or iPadOS device that you’ll use for testing.</li><li>Open your email invitation and tap "View in TestFlight" or tap the public link on your device.</li><li>If you're a new tester for the app, tap Accept, then tap Install to download the app to your device.</li></ol><p>Note: If a compatible build is available for your device, an Install button will appear, allowing you to accept the invitation and install the compatible build.</p><p>If you’re a returning tester, tap Update or Open.</p>
<h3 id="installing-ios">Installing a beta macOS app via email or public link invitation</h3><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on the Mac that you’ll use for testing.</li><li>Open your email invitation and click "View in TestFlight" or click the public link on your Mac.</li><li>If you’re a new tester for the app, click Accept, then click Install to download the app to your device.</li></ol><p>Note: If a compatible build is available for your device, an Install button will appear, allowing you to accept the invitation and install the compatible build.</p><p>If you’re a returning tester, click Update or Open.</p>
<h3 id="installing-tvos-email">Installing a beta tvOS app via email invitation</h3><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on <span>Apple TV.</span></li><li>Open your email invitation on a mobile device or computer.</li><li>Tap or click "View in TestFlight". You'll be taken to a web page with a redemption code.</li><li>Open TestFlight on <span>Apple TV.</span></li><li>Go to Redeem and enter the redemption code.</li></ol><h3 id="installing-tvos-public-link">Installing a beta tvOS app via public link invitation</h3><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on an iOS or iPadOS device and <span>Apple TV</span> where you can sign in to the same <span>App Store</span> account.</li><li>Tap the public link on your device.</li><li>Tap Accept for the app you want to test.</li><li>Open TestFlight on <span>Apple TV</span>. You must be signed in to the same <span>App Store</span> account you used on your device.</li><li>Install the app you want to test.</li></ol>
<h3 id="installing-ios">Installing a beta visionOS app via email or public link invitation</h3><ol><li>Open your email invitation and touch "View in TestFlight" or touch the public link on your device.</li><li>If you’re a new tester for the app, touch Accept, then touch Install to download the app to your device</li></ol><p>Note: If a compatible build is available for your device, an Install button will appear, allowing you to accept the invitation and install the compatible build</p><p>If you’re a returning tester, touch Update or Open.</p>
<h3 id="installing-watchos">Installing a beta watchOS app via email or public link invitation</h3><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on the iOS device paired with the <span>Apple Watch</span> that you’ll use for testing.</li><li>Open your email invitation and tap "View in TestFlight" or tap on the public link on your iOS device.</li><li>If you’re a new tester for the app, tap Accept.</li><li>If you're testing an app that’s for <span>Apple Watch</span> only, tap "Install" from the Apps list.</li><li>If the app is an iOS app that includes an <span>Apple Watch</span> app, install the iOS app first, then go to the App Details page in the Information section. If the <span>Apple Watch</span> app is available and compatible with your watch, there will be a button to install, update, or open it.</li></ol>
<h3>Testing</h3><br>
<h3 id="testing-imessage-apps">Testing iMessage apps <span>(iOS or iPadOS 10, or later)</span></h3><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on the iOS or iPadOS device that you’ll use for testing.</li><li>Open your email invitation and tap “View in TestFlight” or tap the public link on your iOS device.</li><li>If you’re a new tester for the app, tap Accept.</li><li>Tap Install to install the app on your device.</li><li>If you’re a returning tester, tap Update or Open. </li></ol><p>If you’re testing an iOS app that includes an iMessage app, launch the beta app from the Home Screen.</p><p>If you’re testing an app that’s for iMessage only or a sticker pack, launch it from within Messages.</p>
<h3 id="testing-beta-app-clips">Testing beta App Clips <span>(iOS or iPadOS 14, or later)</span></h3><p>After accepting your email or public link invitation to test the app, you’ll see the option to test the App Clip in TestFlight. You can install either the app or the App Clip on your device (but not both at once), and can replace one with the other at any time. If the app is installed on your device, testing the App Clip will replace the app and some app data may be lost. You can reinstall the app by tapping Install on the app’s page in TestFlight.</p><ol><li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/testflight/id899247664?mt=8">Install TestFlight</a> on the iOS or iPadOS device that you’ll use for testing.</li><li>Open your email invitation and tap “View in TestFlight” or tap the public link on your iOS device.</li><li>If you’re a new tester for the app, tap Accept.</li><li>Tap Install to install the app on your device.</li><li>Go to the app’s page in TestFlight.</li><li>In the App Clips section, tap TEST next to the beta App Clip you want to test.</li></ol>
<h3 id="managing-automatic-updates">Managing automatic updates</h3><p>After installing <span>TestFlight 3</span> or later for iOS, iPadOS, or tvOS, TestFlight for visionOS, or TestFlight for macOS, you’ll be prompted to turn on automatic updates. This allows the latest available beta builds to install automatically. TestFlight will notify you each time a new build is installed on your device. Automatic updates can be turned off at any time.</p><p><strong>Use TestFlight to change automatic update settings for all of the beta apps you’re testing using TestFlight:</strong></p><p><i>Note: This setting will apply to all new beta app builds. Beta apps that have automatic updates set at the individual app level won’t be affected</i></p><p>TestFlight for iOS or iPadOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and tap Settings in the top right.</li><li>Tap Automatic Updates for New Apps.</li><li>Tap On or Off.</li></ol><p>TestFlight for macOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and choose Preferences from the TestFlight menu.</li><li>Under General, select Automatic Updates for New Apps.</li></ol><p>TestFlight for tvOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and click the Settings tab at the top.</li><li>Select Automatic Updates</li><li>Turn Automatic Updates On or Off</li></ol><p>TestFlight for visionOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and from the bottom left, touch open your profile.</li><li>Under App Settings, touch Automatic Updates for New Apps to turn it on or off.</li></ol><p><strong>Use TestFlight to change automatic update settings for individual beta apps you’re testing:</strong></p><p>TestFlight for iOS or iPadOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Under App Information, turn Automatic Updates On or Off.</li></ol><p>TestFlight for visionOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Under App Settings, touch Automatic Updates to turn it on or off.</li></ol><p>TestFlight for macOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Under App Settings, select Automatic Updates.</li></ol><p>TestFlight for tvOS</p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Under the app icon, click More.</li><li>Click Turn On Automatic Updates or Turn Off Automatic Updates.</li></ol>
<h3 id="testing-previous-builds">Testing builds from previous versions and build groups</h3><p>When viewing an app in TestFlight, you'll see the latest available build by default. You can still test all other builds that are available to you.</p><p>If you already have the <span>App Store</span> version of the app installed on your device, the beta version of the app will replace it. After you download the beta app, you’ll see an orange dot next to its name that identifies it as a beta.</p><p>When you accept a TestFlight invitation through a public link, your name and email address aren’t visible to the developer. However, they’ll be able to see your number of sessions and crashes, the day you installed their app, and the latest installed version.</p><p><strong>TestFlight for iOS and iPadOS</strong></p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Tap Previous Builds or, if you're using Xcode Cloud, tap Versions and Build Groups.</li><li>Tap either the Versions tab or Build Groups tab, then tap and install the build you want to test. The build you choose will replace what's currently installed.</li></ol><p><strong>TestFlight for macOS</strong></p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Next to Build Information, click View Previous Builds or, if you're using Xcode Cloud, click Versions and Build Groups.</li><li>Click either the Versions or Build Groups tab, then select and install the build you want to test. The build you choose will replace what’s currently installed.</li></ol><p><strong>TestFlight for tvOS</strong></p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Select View Previous Builds or, if you're using Xcode Cloud, click Versions and Build Groups.</li><li>Click the Versions tab or the Build Groups tab, then select and install the build you want to test. The build you choose will replace what’s currently installed.</li></ol><p><strong>TestFlight for visionOS</strong></p><ol><li>Open TestFlight and go to the app’s page.</li><li>Next to Build Information, touch View Previous Builds.</li><li>Touch either the Versions tab or Build Groups tab, then touch Install next to the build you want to test. The build you choose will replace what's currently installed.</li></ol></div>
                <a href="#giving-feedback">&nbsp;</a>
                <div id="giving-feedback">
<h2>Giving feedback</h2><p>While testing a beta version of an app or App Clip, you can send the developer feedback about issues you experience or make suggestions for improvements based on the “What to Test” content. Feedback you submit through TestFlight is also provided to Apple as part of the TestFlight service.</p><p>If you do not wish to accept a public link invitation, you can easily provide feedback to let the developer know why. After dismissing the beta invitation, you’ll see the Leave Feedback card at the top of the Apps page. Tap or click Leave Feedback, select your reason for declining from the list, and then tap or click Submit. Once you receive confirmation that your feedback has been sent, tap or click Done.</p>
<h3 id="feedback-ios-apps">iOS, iPadOS, macOS, or visionOS apps</h3><p>You can send feedback through the TestFlight app or directly from the beta app or beta App Clip by taking a screenshot, and you can report a crash after it occurs. If you were invited to test an app with a public link, you can choose not to provide your email address or other personal information to the developer. Apple will also receive all feedback you submit and will be able to tie it to your Apple Account.</p>
<h3 id="feedback-testflight">Sending feedback through the TestFlight app</h3><p>For iOS or iPadOS:</p><ol><li>Open the TestFlight app on your device.</li><li>From the Apps list, tap the app you want to send feedback for.</li><li>Tap Send Beta Feedback.</li><li>In the share dialog, tap <span>Include Screenshot</span> to choose a screenshot. If you don’t want to send an attachment, tap <span>Don't Include Screenshot.</span></li><li>Add your comments (up to <span>4,000</span> characters), and optionally enter your email address if you were invited with a public link.</li><li>Tap Submit.</li></ol><p>If your device is running an OS earlier than iOS 13 or iPadOS 13, tap Send Beta Feedback to compose an email to the developer. The feedback email contains detailed information about the beta app and about your iOS device. You can also provide additional information, such as necessary screenshots and steps required to reproduce any issues. Your email address will be visible to the developer when you send email feedback through the TestFlight app even if you were invited through a public link.</p>
<p>For visionOS:</p><ol><li>Open the TestFlight app on your device.</li><li>From the Apps list in the sidebar, touch the app you want to send feedback for.</li><li>Touch Send Feedback.</li><li>In the feedback dialog that appears, add your comments (up to 4,000 characters) by touching the Feedback text field.</li><li>Optionally, attach a screenshot by touching <span>Attach Screenshot</span>.</li><li>Pinch Submit.</li></ol>
<p>For macOS:</p><ol><li>Open the TestFlight app on your Mac.</li><li>From the Apps list in the sidebar, select the app you want to send feedback for.</li><li>Click Send Beta Feedback.</li><li>In the feedback dialog that appears, add your comments (up to 4,000 characters), and optionally enter your email address if you were invited with a public link.</li><li>Optionally, attach a screenshot by clicking Attach Screenshot.</li><li>Click Submit.</li></ol><p>Note: You can drag and drop screenshots into the feedback text field.</p><p>
testflight.template.public.link.content.feedbackText.ios.with.beta.joecolor
</p><p>For iOS or iPadOS:</p><ol><li>Take a screenshot on your device. For details on how to take screenshots, see <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT200289">Take a screenshot on your iPhone</a>, <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT210781">Take a screenshot on your iPad</a>, and <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT210780">Take a screenshot on your iPod touch</a>.</li><li>A thumbnail of your screenshot appears in the lower-left corner of your device. Tap the thumbnail and, if needed, add drawings and text with <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/HT206885">Markup</a>. Then tap Done.</li><li>Tap <span>Share Beta Feedback</span>.</li><li>Optionally, you can add comments (up to <span>4,000</span> characters), and your email address if you were invited with a public link.</li><li>Tap Submit.</li></ol>
<p>For macOS:</p><ol><li>Take a screenshot on your Mac. For details on how to take screenshots, visit <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT201361">Take a screenshot on your Mac</a>.</li><li>A thumbnail of your screenshot appears in the lower-right corner of your Mac. Click the thumbnail to open the <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/view-and-edit-files-with-quick-look-mh14119/11.0/mac/11.0">Quick Look</a> window and, if needed, add drawings and text with <a href="https://support.apple.com/guide/mac-help/mark-up-files-mchl1fd88863/mac">Markup</a>.</li><li>From the Share menu in the Quick Look window, click Send Beta Feedback.</li><li>Optionally, you can add comments (up to 4,000 characters), and your email address if you were invited with a public link.</li><li>Click Submit</li></ol>
<h3 id="sending-crash-information">Sending crash information</h3><p>If you experience a crash while testing a beta app or beta App Clip, you’ll receive an alert asking if you want to send crash details to the developer through TestFlight. Developers can opt out of receiving this type of feedback, so this option is only available if the developer has it enabled.</p><p>When a crash alert displays for TestFlight for iOS or iPadOS, tap Share, add any additional comments, then tap Submit.</p><p>When a crash alert displays for TestFlight for macOS, click Report, add any additional comments, then click OK, Send, or Reopen.</p><p>When a crash alert displays for TestFlight for visionOS, touch Share, add any additional comments, then pinch Submit.</p>
<h3 id="feedback-tvos-apps">tvOS apps</h3><p>To provide feedback on a tvOS app, open TestFlight, go to app’s page, go to the Information section to view the developer's email address, and send them an email. Provide as much information as you can, including screenshots and steps required to reproduce any issues you encountered. Please note that your email address will be visible to the developer when you send email feedback through TestFlight.</p>
<h3 id="contacting-developer">Contacting the developer</h3><p>If you need to contact the developer while you’re testing their beta app for reasons other than feedback, you can view their email address. In TestFlight, go to the app’s page, go to the Information section, and tap App Details to view the developer’s email address.</p></div>
                <a href="#opting-out">&nbsp;</a>
                <div id="opting-out">
<h2>Opting out from testing</h2><p>If you don’t accept your email invitation, the beta app won’t be installed, you won’t be listed as a tester, and Apple won’t take any action with respect to your email address. Additionally, you can unsubscribe using the link at the bottom of the invitation email to notify the developer that you’d like to be removed from their list. If you accepted the invitation and no longer wish to test the app, you can delete yourself as a tester by visiting the app’s Information page in TestFlight and tapping Stop Testing.</p></div>
                <a href="#privacy-data">&nbsp;</a>
                <div id="privacy-data">
<h2>Your Privacy and Data</h2><p>When you test beta apps or beta App Clips with TestFlight, Apple will collect and send crash logs, your personal information such as name and email address, usage information, and any feedback you submit to the developer. Information that is emailed to the developer directly is not shared with Apple. The developer is permitted to use this information only to improve their App and is not permitted to share it with a third party. Apple may use this information to improve the TestFlight app and detect and prevent fraud. For more information, visit <a href="https://www.apple.com/legal/privacy/data/en/test-flight/">TestFlight &amp; Privacy</a>. </p></div>

        </article>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['Gwada negative': French scientists find new blood type in woman (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.lemonde.fr/en/science/article/2025/06/21/gwada-negative-french-scientists-find-new-blood-type-in-woman_6742577_10.html</link>
            <guid>44335517</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 07:38:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/science/article/2025/06/21/gwada-negative-french-scientists-find-new-blood-type-in-woman_6742577_10.html">https://www.lemonde.fr/en/science/article/2025/06/21/gwada-negative-french-scientists-find-new-blood-type-in-woman_6742577_10.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44335517">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main">                      <section id="habillagepub">             <header> <div>     <ul>       <li>  <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/science/">  Science </a>  </li>  <li> <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/health/"> Health </a> </li>    </ul>     <div>   <p>    The patient was undergoing routine tests before surgery when the unknown antibody was detected. </p>  </div>                           </div> </header>       <section> <article>                <p>A French woman from the Caribbean island of Guadeloupe has been identified as the only known carrier of a new blood type, dubbed "Gwada negative," France's blood supply agency has announced. "The EFS has just discovered the 48<sup>th</sup> blood group system in the world!" the agency said in a statement on the social network LinkedIn. "This discovery was officially recognised in early June in Milan by the International Society of Blood Transfusion (ISBT)."</p>              <p>The announcement was made 15 years after researchers received a blood sample from a patient who was undergoing routine tests ahead of surgery, the French Blood Establishment (EFS) said on Friday. The scientific association had until now recognized 47 blood group systems. The discovery was first reported by radio <a href="https://www.radiofrance.fr/franceinter/podcasts/l-info-de-france-inter/l-info-de-france-inter-1294478" target="_blank" rel="noopener" title="Nouvelle fenêtre">France Inter</a>.</p>                   <p>Thierry Peyrard, a medical biologist at the EFS involved in the discovery, told AFP that a "very unusual" antibody was first found in the patient in 2011. However, resources at the time did not allow for further research, he added. Scientists were finally able to unravel the mystery in 2019 thanks to "high-throughput DNA sequencing", which highlighted a genetic mutation, Peyrard said.</p>              <p>The patient, who was 54 at the time and lived in Paris, was undergoing routine tests before surgery when the unknown antibody was detected, Peyrard said. This woman "is undoubtedly the only known case in the world," said the expert. "She is the only person in the world who is compatible with herself," he said. Peyrard said the woman inherited the blood type from her father and mother, who each had the mutated gene.</p>              <p>The name "Gwada negative", which refers to the patient's origins and "sounds good in all languages," has been popular with the experts, said Peyrard. He and colleagues are now hoping to find other people with the same blood group. "Discovering new blood groups means offering patients with rare blood types a better level of care," the EFS said.</p>              <p>The ABO blood group system was first discovered in the early 1900s. Thanks to DNA sequencing the discovery of new blood groups has accelerated in recent years.</p>              <section>  <p>  <span>Le Monde</span>  </p>   </section>    <section>     <a href="https://www.lemonde.fr/en/syndication/" title="Reuse this content" target="_blank">Reuse this content</a>   </section>   </article>   </section>                        </section>          <section id="js-capping" data-full="0" data-mini="0">  <section id="js-capping-content"> <p>Vous pouvez lire <i>Le Monde</i> sur un seul appareil à la fois</p>   <p>Ce message s’affichera sur l’autre appareil.</p>    <a href="https://moncompte.lemonde.fr/" id="js-capping-yellow-button" data-cta="multi">Découvrir les offres multicomptes</a>  </section> <section id="js-capping-bottom">     <ul id="js-capping-faq"> <li> <p>Parce qu’une autre personne (ou vous) est en train de lire <i>Le Monde</i> avec ce compte sur un autre appareil.</p> <p>Vous ne pouvez lire <i>Le Monde</i> que sur <strong>un seul appareil</strong> à la fois (ordinateur, téléphone ou tablette).</p> </li> <li> <p>Comment ne plus voir ce message ?</p> <p>En cliquant sur «&nbsp;&nbsp;» et en vous assurant que vous êtes la seule personne à consulter <i>Le Monde</i> avec ce compte.</p> </li> <li> <p>Que se passera-t-il si vous continuez à lire ici ?</p> <p>Ce message s’affichera sur l’autre appareil. Ce dernier restera connecté avec ce compte.</p> </li> <li> <p>Y a-t-il d’autres limites ?</p> <p>Non. Vous pouvez vous connecter avec votre compte sur autant d’appareils que vous le souhaitez, mais en les utilisant à des moments différents.</p> </li> <li> <p>Vous ignorez qui est l’autre personne ?</p> <p>Nous vous conseillons de <a href="https://secure.lemonde.fr/sfuser/password/lost">modifier votre mot de passe</a>.</p> </li> </ul>   </section> </section> <section id="js-capping-old-article" data-full="0" data-mini="0"> <section id="js-capping-old-article-header"> <span></span> <p>Lecture restreinte</p> </section> <section id="js-capping-old-article-content"> <p>Votre abonnement n’autorise pas la lecture de cet article</p>  <p>Pour plus d’informations, merci de contacter notre service commercial.</p> </section> </section>      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Delta Chat is a decentralized and secure messenger app (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://delta.chat/en/</link>
            <guid>44335065</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 06:29:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://delta.chat/en/">https://delta.chat/en/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44335065">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">














<p>💬 Reliable instant messaging with multi-profile and multi-device support</p>

<p>⚡️ Sign up to <a href="https://delta.chat/en/chatmail">secure fast chatmail servers</a> or use <a href="https://providers.delta.chat/">classic e-mail servers</a></p>

<p>🥳 Interactive <a href="https://webxdc.org/">web apps in chats</a> for gaming and collaboration</p>

<p>🔒 <a href="https://delta.chat/en/2024-03-25-crypto-analysis-securejoin">Audited end-to-end encryption</a> safe against network and server attacks</p>

<p>👉 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Free_software">F</a><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Open-source_software">OSS</a> software, built on <a href="https://github.com/deltachat/deltachat-core-rust/blob/master/standards.md">Internet Standards</a>, avoiding <a href="https://xkcd.com/927/">xkcd927</a> :)</p>

<div>
<a href="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android1.png">
<picture>
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android1-thumbnail.webp" type="image/webp">
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android1-thumbnail.png" type="image/png">
<img src="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android1-thumbnail.png" width="136" height="242" alt="A screenshot of Delta Chat on Android showing chat list">
</picture>
</a>
</div>

<div>
<a href="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android2.png">
<picture>
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android2-thumbnail.webp" type="image/webp">
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android2-thumbnail.png" type="image/png">
<img src="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/android2-thumbnail.png" width="136" height="242" alt="A screenshot of Delta Chat on Android showing a chat">
</picture>
</a>
</div>

<div>
<a href="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/desktop.png">
<picture>
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/desktop-thumbnail.webp" type="image/webp">
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/desktop-thumbnail.png" type="image/png">
<img src="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/desktop-thumbnail.png" width="305" height="242" alt="A screenshot of Delta Chat on desktop">
</picture>
</a>
</div>

<div>
<a href="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/ios.png">
<picture>
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/ios-thumbnail.webp" type="image/webp">
<source srcset="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/ios-thumbnail.png" type="image/png">
<img src="https://delta.chat/assets/home/screenshots/ios.png" width="124" height="242" alt="A screenshot of Delta Chat on iOS">
</picture>
</a>
</div>

<p><a href="https://get.delta.chat/">Download</a></p>

<p>Available on mobile and desktop.</p>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sega mistakenly reveals sales numbers of popular games (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.gematsu.com/2025/06/sega-mistakenly-reveals-sales-numbers-for-like-a-dragon-infinite-wealth-persona-3-reload-shin-megami-tensei-v-and-more</link>
            <guid>44335038</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 06:23:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.gematsu.com/2025/06/sega-mistakenly-reveals-sales-numbers-for-like-a-dragon-infinite-wealth-persona-3-reload-shin-megami-tensei-v-and-more">https://www.gematsu.com/2025/06/sega-mistakenly-reveals-sales-numbers-for-like-a-dragon-infinite-wealth-persona-3-reload-shin-megami-tensei-v-and-more</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44335038">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main">
  
  <article>

    
<header>

  <div>

    <ul>
        </ul>

    
    <p><span>Persona 5 Royal sales top 7.25m.</span>
      </p></div>

  

</header>  

<!-- Moved from templates/posts/default.php -->
<div><figure><img src="https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-320x180.jpg" data-srcset="https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-320x180.jpg 320w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-480x270.jpg 480w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-1280x720.jpg 1280w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-1440x810.jpg 1440w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25.jpg 1920w" data-sizes="auto" srcset="https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-320x180.jpg 320w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-480x270.jpg 480w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-768x432.jpg 768w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-1024x576.jpg 1024w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-1280x720.jpg 1280w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25-1440x810.jpg 1440w, https://www.gematsu.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/SEGA-Sales_06-20-25.jpg 1920w"></figure></div>
    <div><p>Total sales numbers for various <a title="Companies > SEGA [2,672 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/companies/sega">SEGA</a> and <a title="Companies > ATLUS [2,055 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/companies/atlus">ATLUS</a> titles including <em><a title="Games > Like a Dragon: Infinite Wealth [19 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/like-a-dragon-infinite-wealth">Like a Dragon: Infinite Wealth</a></em>, <em><a title="Games > Persona 3 Reload [44 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/persona-3-reload">Persona 3 Reload</a></em>, <em><a title="Games > Sonic Frontiers [26 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/sonic-frontiers">Sonic Frontiers</a></em>, <em><a title="Games > Shin Megami Tensei V [243 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/shin-megami-tensei-v">Shin Megami Tensei V</a></em>, and <em><a title="Games > Persona 5 Royal [61 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/persona-5-royal">Persona 5 Royal</a></em> were mistakenly revealed in a <a href="https://www.segasammy.co.jp/cms/wp-content/uploads/pdf/en/ir/20250618_Management_large_MTG_all_e.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SEGA SAMMY Management Meeting 2025 presentation</a> published on June 18. <span id="more-975176"></span></p><p>The sales numbers, which appear on page 25 of the presentation, are hidden behind a grey block. However, due to the way the PDF file is formatted, simply highlighting the page reveals the presence of text, which can be copied and pasted.</p><p>Here is the fully reconstructed table of sales:</p><!-- AD: content -->
        <table><thead><tr><th></th><th>FY2020</th><th>FY2021</th><th>FY2022</th><th>FY2023</th><th>FY2024</th><th>FY2025</th><th>Total</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><em>Like a Dragon: Infinite Wealth</em></td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1.18m</td><td>480k</td><td>1.66m</td></tr><tr><td><em><a title="Games > Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name [17 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/like-a-dragon-gaiden-the-man-who-erased-his-name">Like a Dragon Gaiden: The Man Who Erased His Name</a></em></td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>740k</td><td>220k</td><td>960k</td></tr><tr><td><em>Persona 3 Reload</em></td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1.22m</td><td>850k</td><td>2.07m</td></tr><tr><td><em><a title="Games > Sonic Superstars [9 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/sonic-superstars">Sonic Superstars</a></em></td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1.81m</td><td>620k</td><td>2.43m</td></tr><tr><td><em>Sonic Frontiers</em></td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>3.2m</td><td>760k</td><td>610k</td><td>4.57m</td></tr><tr><td><em><a title="Games > Total War: Warhammer III [3 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/total-war-warhammer-iii">Total War: Warhammer III</a></em></td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>960k</td><td>580k</td><td>420k</td><td>380k</td><td>2.34m</td></tr><tr><td><em>Shin Megami Tensei V</em> (including <em><a title="Games > Shin Megami Tensei V: Vengeance [13 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/games/shin-megami-tensei-v-vengeance">Shin Megami Tensei V: Vengeance</a></em>)</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>990k</td><td>150k</td><td>10k</td><td>960k</td><td>2.11m</td></tr><tr><td><em>Yakuza: <a title="Series > Yakuza (Like a Dragon) [54 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/series/yakuza">Like a Dragon</a></em></td><td>450k</td><td>720k</td><td>410k</td><td>240k</td><td>680k</td><td>360k</td><td>2.86m</td></tr><tr><td><em>Persona 5 Royal</em> (including remaster version)</td><td>1.03m</td><td>700k</td><td>350k</td><td>1.82m</td><td>1.6m</td><td>1.75m</td><td>7.25m</td></tr><tr><td><em>Team Sonic <a title="Genres > Racing [252 articles]" href="https://www.gematsu.com/genres/racing">Racing</a></em></td><td>1.38m</td><td>870k</td><td>520k</td><td>310k</td><td>200k</td><td>220k</td><td>3.5m</td></tr><tr><td><em>Total War: Three Kingdoms</em></td><td>2.1m</td><td>410k</td><td>230k</td><td>230k</td><td>170k</td><td>70k</td><td>3.21m</td></tr></tbody></table><p><em>*Persona 5 Royal includes the sales units of remaster version released in FY2023/3.</em><br><em>*Shin&nbsp;Megami&nbsp;Tensei&nbsp;V&nbsp;also&nbsp;includes&nbsp;unit&nbsp;sales&nbsp;of&nbsp;Shin&nbsp;Megami&nbsp;Tensei&nbsp;V: Vengeance&nbsp;released&nbsp;in&nbsp;FY2025/3.</em></p><p>Thanks, <a href="https://www.resetera.com/threads/sega-sammy-fiscal-report-mishap-reveals-sales-numbers-for-a-dozen-titles-lad-iw-1-66m-p3r-2-07m-sonic-frontiers-4-57m-p5r-7-25m-and-more.1224501/" target="_blank">ResetEra</a>.</p></div>

        
    
  </article>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Signal – An Ethical Replacement for WhatsApp (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/06/15/signal-an-ethical-replacement-for-whatsapp/</link>
            <guid>44334743</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 05:21:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/06/15/signal-an-ethical-replacement-for-whatsapp/">https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/06/15/signal-an-ethical-replacement-for-whatsapp/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44334743">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-17311">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	
	<div>
		
<p>You may not need any incentive to do this, but I’m going to argue that moving from WhatsApp to Signal is an important action, right now. There are other alternatives to WhatsApp, of course, but several have received criticism over various issues so I’m going to focus on Signal here. Please comment below if you’d like to propose ethical alternatives to WhatsApp. &nbsp;</p>



<p>In March I argued that we should <a href="https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/03/30/bluesky-an-ethical-replacement-for-x-twitter/"><strong>choose Bluesky over X/Twitter</strong></a>, based on the obvious reason of boycotting companies connected to Musk. Bluesky is structured as a benefit corporation (like Patagonia) and based on an open network, two features that create strong incentives for the company to not upset its users.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>This creates an alignment between Bluesky and its users – Bluesky is disincentivized to make a bad user experience. This also acts as a kind of poison pill against a billionaire takeover, or at least a deterrent against this.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Moving from X/Twitter to Bluesky does require some sacrifice for people who worked hard to build up a following on the former. But we’ve reached a point where support of Musk is unconscionable, whatever the sacrifice involved. The move from WhatsApp to Signal, however, is quite straightforward and completely painless. But in this case, some may be wondering, <em>why should I bother moving at all?</em></p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/whatsapp-and-signal-icons.png"><img data-attachment-id="17315" data-permalink="https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/06/15/signal-an-ethical-replacement-for-whatsapp/whatsapp-and-signal-icons/" data-orig-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/whatsapp-and-signal-icons.png" data-orig-size="1200,674" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="WhatsApp and Signal icons" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/whatsapp-and-signal-icons.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/whatsapp-and-signal-icons.png?w=720" width="1024" height="575" src="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/whatsapp-and-signal-icons.png?w=1024" alt="Logos for messaging apps WhatsApp  and Signal are pictured. Both are based around the image of a speech bubble: the WhatsApp logo is in green and white, while the Signal logo is blue and white."></a><figcaption>Logos for messaging apps WhatsApp (left) and Signal (right).</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Ethical issues with WhatsApp</h2>



<p>My biggest issues with using WhatsApp are related to its parent corporation, Meta (formerly Facebook) and its founder/CEO Mark Zuckerberg. But first, I want to mention a few issues specific to WhatsApp.</p>



<p>In early 2021, WhatsApp updated its terms of service, requiring users to opt into <a href="https://www.androidpolice.com/2021/01/12/whatsapps-new-terms-of-service-are-a-facebook-or-die-ultimatum/">sharing their data</a> with Facebook – including network details and location (even if you haven’t turned on location sharing). This 180° reversal on an <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-facebook-undermines-privacy-protections-for-its-2-billion-whatsapp-users">earlier promise</a> made by Zuckerberg that “WhatsApp is going to operate completely autonomously” was one of several events over the last 5 years that accelerated an exodus from WhatsApp to Signal. The large amount of metadata that WhatsApp collects is also shared with law enforcement agencies.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>WhatsApp shares metadata, unencrypted records that can reveal a lot about a user’s activity, with law enforcement agencies such as the Department of Justice. Some rivals, such as Signal, intentionally gather much less metadata to avoid incursions on its users’ privacy, and thus share far less with law enforcement. – <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/how-facebook-undermines-privacy-protections-for-its-2-billion-whatsapp-users">ProPublica</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>I have to admit that I don’t give a huge amount of time fretting over these things during normal times. But we no longer live in normal times – people are now guilty by suspicion (or by association, based on their WhatsApp contacts) and convicted without due process.</p>



<p>Over the years, Zuckerberg and Meta have done more flip flopping than a White Lotus guest (walking around in flip-flops, you see). Facebook has since been <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/commission/presscorner/detail/en/IP_17_1369">fined</a> €110 million by EU antitrust regulators and <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/press-releases/2019/07/ftc-imposes-5-billion-penalty-sweeping-new-privacy-restrictions">$5 billion</a> by the US Federal Trade Commission for deceiving regulators and users. Following this greater level of scrutiny, Zuckerberg has shown himself to be a person of little scruples, capitulating to whoever will do him favors.</p>



<h2>Meta and Zuckerberg</h2>



<p>Meta – a company so bad that it had to change its name to try to clean its reputation. The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Facebook%E2%80%93Cambridge_Analytica_data_scandal">Facebook–Cambridge Analytica scandal</a> involved the collection of user data without consent to create <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychographics">psychographic profiles</a> that were used in Donald Trump’s 2016 election campaign and suppressing Black voters in Trinidad and Tobago. WhatsApp, in particular, played a role in the Brazil’s 2018 election.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The vast majority of false information shared on WhatsApp in Brazil during the presidential election favoured the far-right winner, Jair Bolsonaro. The analysis sheds light on the spread of misinformation on the Facebook-owned app, with fears it could be poisoning political debate in one of the largest democracies in the world. – <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2019/oct/30/whatsapp-fake-news-brazil-election-favoured-jair-bolsonaro-analysis-suggests">The Guardian</a>.</p>
</blockquote>



<blockquote>
<p>Companies supporting Jair Bolsonaro are buying a service called “mass blasts,” using the candidate’s list of WhatsApp users or buying lists from agencies specializing in digital strategy. – <a href="https://www1.folha.uol.com.br/internacional/en/brazil/2018/10/businessmen-fund-whatsapp-campaign-against-pt.shtml">Folha de S.Paulo</a>.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>In 2018, Zuckerberg testified before US Congress, admitting: “It was my mistake, and I’m sorry.”</p>



<p>Aww! You’re totally forgiven, Zuck! You’ve learned your lesson, right?</p>



<p>But wait! Last year, as you probably know, Zuckerberg did the cowardly act of endorsing Trump by implication. I happened to catch this interview with the Zuck live on Bloomberg and was totally gagged (Hey Gen Z readers!). Take a look and marvel at Zuck sticking to his guns and maintaining his neutrality:</p>



<figure><div>
<p><iframe title="Zuckerberg Calls Trump 'Badass' Without Endorsing Him #politics" width="720" height="405" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bE7SyQWf4_U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div></figure>



<p>Post-election, Zuck flew down to Florida for dinner with Trump (I’m imagining scenes from the hunting episode of <em>Succession</em>) and then got rid of DEI and moderation and all that weak stuff. It didn’t take long for Zuck to switch from humility (<em>It was my mistake, and I’m sorry</em>) to going on the Joe Rogan show to say this:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>“Masculine energy is good, and obviously, society has plenty of that, but I think corporate culture was really trying to get away from it,” Zuckerberg continued. “I think having a culture that celebrates the aggression a bit more has its own merits that are really positive.” – <a href="https://mashable.com/article/mark-zuckerberg-joe-rogan-masculine-feminine-energy">Mashable</a>.&nbsp;</p>
</blockquote>



<figure><a href="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/zuckerberg-and-jay-graber-in-opposing-t-shirts-a-world-without-caesars.png"><img data-attachment-id="16916" data-permalink="https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/03/30/bluesky-an-ethical-replacement-for-x-twitter/zuckerberg-and-jay-graber-in-opposing-t-shirts-a-world-without-caesars/" data-orig-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/zuckerberg-and-jay-graber-in-opposing-t-shirts-a-world-without-caesars.png" data-orig-size="1200,674" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Zuckerberg and Jay Graber in opposing T-shirts, A World Without Caesars" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/zuckerberg-and-jay-graber-in-opposing-t-shirts-a-world-without-caesars.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/zuckerberg-and-jay-graber-in-opposing-t-shirts-a-world-without-caesars.png?w=720" width="720" height="404" src="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/zuckerberg-and-jay-graber-in-opposing-t-shirts-a-world-without-caesars.png?w=720" alt="Mark Zuckerberg and Jay Graber in opposing T-shirts. Zuckerberg is wearing a black T-shirt with the message, “Aut Zuck aut nihil”, which translates to &quot;Either Zuck or nothing.&quot;"></a><figcaption>Zuckerberg’s <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/03/19/bluesky-made-more-money-selling-t-shirts-mocking-zuckerberg-than-custom-domains/">shirt declared</a> <em>Aut Zuck aut nihil</em>, which means <em>Zuck or nothing</em>. Zuckerberg is referencing the Latin phrase <em>Aut Caesar aut nihil</em>, drawing a direct parallel between himself and the Roman dictator. Jay Graber’s shirt says <em>Mundus sine Caesaribus</em>, or, <em>a world without Caesars</em>. See more on Graber in <strong><a href="https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/03/30/bluesky-an-ethical-replacement-for-x-twitter/">Bluesky versus Twitter/X</a></strong>.</figcaption></figure>



<h2>Ethical review of Signal</h2>



<p>Signal provides a very similar user experience to WhatsApp, so switching over is pretty seamless. This is not too surprising, considering that the current CEO of Signal LLC., Brian Action, was one of the cofounders of WhatsApp. WhatsApp was acquired by Facebook in 2014, and Acton <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/whatsapp-co-founder-acton-named-signals-interim-ceo-2022-01-10/">left the company</a> three years later due to differences around the use of customer data and targeted advertising.</p>



<p>A year later, Acton contributed $50 million to launch a non-profit, the Signal Foundation and a subsidiary, Signal Messenger, LLC.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>On 21 February 2018, Moxie Marlinspike and WhatsApp co-founder Brian Acton announced the formation of the Signal Technology Foundation, a 501(c)(3) nonprofit organization whose mission is “to support, accelerate, and broaden Signal’s mission of making private communication accessible and ubiquitous”. – <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal_(software)#History">Wikipedia</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>When the Electronic Frontier Foundation <a href="https://www.eff.org/pages/secure-messaging-scorecard">ranked messaging apps</a> for privacy and transparency, Signal was one of the few that received a perfect score. The nonprofit also has an <a href="https://ssd.eff.org/module/how-to-use-signal">updated guide</a> to using Signal, navigating its settings, etc.</p>



<p>The protection of data and personal privacy is important. The nonprofit Signal Foundation is led by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meredith_Whittaker">Meredith Whittaker</a>, a former director of the AI Now Institute at NYU, which examined the social impacts of AI and concentration of power in tech. She is a strong proponent of protecting privacy as a human right and an opponent of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surveillance_capitalism">surveillance capitalism</a>. Signal’s predecessor, Open Whisper Systems <a href="https://cyberscoop.com/tor-signal-funding-donald-trump-steve-bannon-encryption/">received funding from</a> journalism nonprofit Freedom of the Press Foundation.</p>



<p>Signal has been recommended to Democratic Party staffers and officially <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signal_(software)#History">approved</a> by the US Senate in 2017. Just not for texting top secret plans, obviously!</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/signal-and-whatsapp-green-stars-rating-for-ethics-2.png"><img data-attachment-id="17337" data-permalink="https://greenstarsproject.org/2025/06/15/signal-an-ethical-replacement-for-whatsapp/signal-and-whatsapp-green-stars-rating-for-ethics-2/" data-orig-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/signal-and-whatsapp-green-stars-rating-for-ethics-2.png" data-orig-size="1200,674" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Signal and WhatsApp – Green Stars rating for ethics 2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/signal-and-whatsapp-green-stars-rating-for-ethics-2.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/signal-and-whatsapp-green-stars-rating-for-ethics-2.png?w=720" width="720" height="404" src="https://greenstarsproject.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/06/signal-and-whatsapp-green-stars-rating-for-ethics-2.png?w=720" alt="Logos for messaging apps Signal and WhatsApp are pictured. Underneath are graphics showing Green Stars ratings for social and environmental impact: 4.5 out of 5 Green Stars for Signal 0.5 for WhatsApp."></a><figcaption>Green Stars ethical rating for messaging apps Signal (left, 4.5) and WhatsApp (right, 0.5)</figcaption></figure></div>


<h3>Action plan for migrating from WhatsApp</h3>



<p>It’s easy to see how we all get drawn into using specific apps like WhatsApp – the user base reaches a critical size and it becomes the app to find everyone on. At the same time, the company becomes more lucrative (and in many cases is taken over by a bigger fish) and then ethical issues creep in. We learn to suppress our concerns because the app is just too convenient and, to quote The Cranberries, <em>Everybody Else Is Doing It, So Why Can’t We? </em>(R.I.P., Dolores).</p>



<p>The exit plan from WhatsApp is quite simple. Start by installing Signal and setting it up – it takes only a couple of minutes. Then, resume any WhatsApp conversations on Signal if that person is already a Signal user. If they are not, then switch to regular text messaging and gently suggest to that person to switch over to Signal. [Shout out to CeCe for reminding me to install Signal!] Group chats are a good way to get people to switch over as nobody will want to be the person who can’t be bothered making the switch.</p>



<p>The interference with elections is not OK.</p>



<p>I’ll leave the last word to future president, AOC:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Meta as in ‘we are a cancer to democracy metastasizing into a global surveillance and propaganda machine for boosting authoritarian regimes and destroying civil society… for profit!'” – <a href="https://www.cnet.com/tech/services-and-software/facebook-to-meta-a-new-name-but-the-same-old-problems/">Alexandria Ocasio-Cortez</a></p>
</blockquote>

<div>
	
	<hr>
	

	
	<h3>Discover more from The Green Stars Project</h3>
	

	
	<p>Subscribe to get the latest posts sent to your email.</p>
	

	
	
	
</div>
			</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Samsung Embeds IronSource Spyware App on Phones Across WANA (677 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://smex.org/open-letter-to-samsung-end-forced-israeli-app-installations-in-the-wana-region/</link>
            <guid>44334167</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 03:06:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://smex.org/open-letter-to-samsung-end-forced-israeli-app-installations-in-the-wana-region/">https://smex.org/open-letter-to-samsung-end-forced-israeli-app-installations-in-the-wana-region/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44334167">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    
<p>In recent months, we have received numerous reports from users across West Asia and North Africa (WANA) expressing alarm over a little-known but deeply intrusive bloatware application—AppCloud—pre-installed on Samsung’s A and M series smartphones. Without users’ knowledge or consent, this bloatware collects sensitive personal data, cannot be removed without compromising device security, and offers no clear information about its privacy practices.</p>



<p>AppCloud, developed by the controversial Israeli-founded company ironSource (now owned by the American company <a href="https://investors.unity.com/news/news-details/2022/Unity-Announces-Merger-Agreement-with-ironSource/default.aspx">Unity</a>), is embedded into devices sold in countries where such affiliations carry legal implications. Despite the serious privacy and security risks, Samsung has offered no transparency on how AppCloud functions, what data it collects, or why users cannot opt out.</p>



<p>This open letter, addressed to Samsung, calls for immediate transparency, accountability, and dialogue. Users deserve to know what is installed on their devices and how their data is being used, especially amid Israel’s espionage campaigns in the region.&nbsp;</p>



<p>_________</p>



<p>To Whom it May Concern,&nbsp;</p>



<p>We are writing to urgently request that Samsung be transparent regarding the pre-installation of AppCloud on its A and M series smartphones, particularly in West Asia and North Africa (WANA). We ask that Samsung provide information about AppCloud’s privacy practices, opt-out and removal options, and that Samsung reconsider future pre-installations in light of privacy rights. We also request a meeting with Samsung teams to discuss these concerns further.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Since the expansion of Samsung’s <a href="https://www.nasdaq.com/press-release/ironsource-expands-samsung-partnership-launching-on-samsung-mobile-devices-in-mena">partnership</a> with ironSource in 2022, AppCloud has been embedded by default on <a href="https://smex.org/invasive-israeli-software-is-harvesting-data-from-samsung-users-in-wana/">new A and M devices distributed in this region</a>.</p>



<p>According to our <a href="https://smex.org/invasive-israeli-software-is-harvesting-data-from-samsung-users-in-wana/">analysis</a>, this intrusive software is <strong>unremovable</strong>, deeply integrated into the devices’ operating system, making it nearly impossible for regular users to uninstall it without root access, which voids warranties and poses security risks. Even disabling the bloatware is not effective as it can reappear after system updates.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The privacy policy is <strong>opaque, </strong>there is no accessible and transparent privacy policy for this bloatware and users are in the dark about what data is collected and how it is used. There is also no straightforward opt-out mechanism. The bloatware collects sensitive user data, including biometric information, IP addresses, device fingerprints.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The installation of AppCloud is done <strong>without any consent </strong>from the user, which violates GDPR provisions in the EU and relevant data protection laws in the WANA region states.&nbsp;</p>



<p>AppCloud is developed by ironSource, <strong>an Israel-founded company (now acquired by American company Unity),</strong> raising additional legal and ethical concerns in countries where Israeli companies are barred from operating, such as <a href="https://www.lexismiddleeast.com/law/Lebanon/Law_1_1955">Lebanon</a>. ironSource is notorious for its questionable practices regarding user consent and data privacy.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Samsung’s terms of service mention third party applications but do not specifically address AppCloud or ironSource, despite the significant data access and control granted to this bloatware app.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The forced installation of AppCloud <strong>undermines the privacy and security rights of users in the MENA region and beyond.</strong> The lack of transparency and control over personal data is particularly alarming given<a href="https://telecomlead.com/smart-phone/smartphone-strategies-in-middle-east-for-market-share-119061"> Samsung’s <strong>significant market share in the region</strong></a>.</p>



<p>In light of these concerns, we respectfully request that Samsung:</p>



<ul>
<li>Disclose the full privacy policy and data handling practices of AppCloud, making this information easily accessible to all users.</li>



<li>Offer a straightforward and effective method for users to opt out of AppCloud and remove it from their devices without compromising device functionality or warranty.</li>



<li>Provide a clear explanation for the decision to pre-install AppCloud on all A and M series devices in the WANA region.</li>



<li>Reconsider the continued pre-installation of AppCloud on future devices, in line with the right to privacy as established by Article 12 of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.</li>



<li>We also request a <strong>meeting with the relevant Samsung teams</strong> to discuss these issues in detail and to better understand the company’s approach to user privacy and data protection in the WANA region.</li>
</ul>



<p>We look forward to your prompt response and to working together to ensure the privacy and security of all Samsung users.</p>

                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tiny Undervalued Hardware Companions (2024) (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/</link>
            <guid>44333960</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 02:19:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/">https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44333960">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			<p>After playing/working with computers for more then 25 years I started to appreciate small but handy valuable stuff – like adapters or handlers or … yeah – all kind of stuff. With many of them I did not even knew they existed until I find out about them – mostly accidentally or after long searching for some problem solution. Today I will share them with You – so maybe they will end up handy also for You.</p>
<p>… and while they make my life easier – they are mostly very cheap too.</p>
<p>There is also a follow up article – <a href="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2025/06/21/more-undervalued-hardware-companions/">More Undervalued Hardware Companions</a> – available here.</p>
<p>The <em>Table of Contents</em> is below.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>RJ45 Angle Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>RJ45 Angle Cable Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>RJ45 Join Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>SATA to USB-C or USB-A Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>Angle USB-C and USB-A Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>USB-A &lt;=&gt; USB-C Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>Tiny USB WiFi or Bluetooth Dongle</strong></li>
<li><strong>USB-C &lt;=&gt; Micro USB Adapter</strong></li>
<li><strong>USB-C &lt;=&gt; Laptops/Routers/5.5mmx2.5mm Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>Creative BT-W2 USB-A Bluetooth Adapter</strong></li>
<li><strong>External Microphone for SONY Headphones</strong></li>
<li><strong>Headphones Handle</strong></li>
<li><strong>Dual USB-C and USB-A Pendrive (SanDisk)</strong></li>
<li><strong>Tiny USB-A Hub</strong></li>
<li><strong>Quad USB-C / USB-A / Lightning / Micro USB Adapter with MicroSD Card Slot</strong></li>
<li><strong>Angle Power Adapters</strong></li>
<li><strong>C13/C14 Power Adapters with Additional C1/C2 or C5/C6 Sockets</strong></li>
<li><strong>HDMI 3in1 Switch with Remote Control</strong></li>
<li><strong>Cable Organizers</strong></li>
<li><strong>Mouse Jigger</strong></li>
<li><strong>FM Transmitter</strong></li>
<li><strong>Summary</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>The whole article can ‘feel’ like a sponsored entry for the <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> portal – but it is not – its just the most cheap place I was able to find these gems. Feel free to share even cheaper one if You have one.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>RJ45 Angle Adapters</h2>
<p>I mostly use laptops to do various tasks and cables sticking out on the sides perpendicularly does not help. Not many laptops today have the RJ45 LAN socket – but if they do – they are mostly on the side of the laptop.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6246" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/rj45-angle-adapter/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg" data-orig-size="740,460" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="rj45-angle-adapter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg?w=740" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg?w=625&amp;h=389 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg?w=150&amp;h=93 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg?w=300&amp;h=186 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-adapter.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>Thanks to such angle RJ45 adapters it is no longer a problem.</p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$2</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> page – with the <b>RJ45 ANGLE ADAPTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>RJ45 Angle Cable Adapters</h2>
<p>The mentioned earlier <i>RJ45 Angle Adapters</i> are quite bulky – but as an alternative its possible to get a short 40cm cable with smaller plug.</p>
<p>Not sure if its noticeable on the picture below – but I also cut the top ‘cover’ with knife of the plug – so its easier to detach.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6247" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/rj45-angle-cable-1/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg" data-orig-size="740,570" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="rj45-angle-cable-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg?w=740" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg?w=625&amp;h=481 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=116 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=231 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>There are of course all four angles to choose from.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6248" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/rj45-angle-cable-4/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg" data-orig-size="740,650" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="rj45-angle-cable-4" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg?w=740" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg?w=625&amp;h=549 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg?w=150&amp;h=132 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg?w=300&amp;h=264 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-4.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>One may also use the end of that 40cm cable-adapter as a ‘stopper’ to not fall inside the desk hole as shown on the image below.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6249" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/rj45-angle-cable-3/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg" data-orig-size="740,1190" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="rj45-angle-cable-3" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg?w=187" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg?w=637" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg?w=625&amp;h=1005 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg?w=93&amp;h=150 93w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg?w=187&amp;h=300 187w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-angle-cable-3.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$2</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>RJ45 ANGLE ADAPTER CABLE</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>RJ45 Join Adapters</h2>
<p>Often I found myself in a situation that the currently available LAN cable was too short to reach and it needed a lot of work to plot another – longer one.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6250" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/rj45-concatenate-adapter/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg" data-orig-size="740,830" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="rj45-concatenate-adapter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg?w=267" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg?w=625&amp;h=701 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg?w=134&amp;h=150 134w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg?w=267&amp;h=300 267w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/rj45-concatenate-adapter.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>With these simple ‘join’ adapters it is no longer a problem. You would not use them in a serious Data Center with 10+ GE speeds – but for home 1.0-2.5 GE speeds its more then enough.</p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$1-$2</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>RJ45 JOIN ADAPTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>SATA to USB-C or USB-A Adapters</h2>
<p>Multiple times I needed to clone some old disk to new SSD – just to make an old system faster.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6251" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg" data-orig-size="740,540" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="SATA-USB-C-USB-A-adapters" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=625&amp;h=456 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=150&amp;h=109 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=300&amp;h=219 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/sata-usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>I usually boot from some USB drive with FreeBSD and while new SSD is attached with these adapters – I then execute <tt><b>dd(8)</b></tt> command to clone the old HDD disk to new SSD drive … and then just swap them out.</p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$1-$5</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>SATA USB ADAPTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Angle USB-C and USB-A Adapters</h2>
<p>As we already talked about RJ45 angle adapters … there are also USB-C and USB-A angle adapters.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6253" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg" data-orig-size="740,400" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-USB-A-angle-adapters-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg?w=625&amp;h=338 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=81 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=162 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>The do the same good job with cables to not stick out on a side of a laptop.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6254" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg" data-orig-size="740,420" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-USB-A-angle-adapters-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg?w=625&amp;h=355 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=85 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=170 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-2.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6255" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg" data-orig-size="740,410" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-USB-A-angle-adapters-3" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg?w=625&amp;h=346 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg?w=150&amp;h=83 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg?w=300&amp;h=166 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-angle-adapters-3.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$1-$3</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>ANGLE USB ADAPTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>USB-A &lt;=&gt; USB-C Adapters</h2>
<p>In the progressing and always changing world yesterday the USB-A was king and tomorrow the USB-C will be.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6256" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-usb-a-adapters/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg" data-orig-size="740,440" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-USB-A-adapters" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=625&amp;h=372 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=150&amp;h=89 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg?w=300&amp;h=178 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-a-adapters.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>There are multiple cases in which you will need these – from simple USB headphones to USB pendrives and other stuff.</p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$1-$3</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>USB-C USB-A ADAPTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Tiny USB WiFi or Bluetooth Dongle</h2>
<p>Multiple times I have found myself in a situation where it was very convenient to just add some WiFi or Bluetooth chip over USB port and do the job instead of trying to achieve the same without such chips.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6257" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg" data-orig-size="740,470" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg?w=625&amp;h=397 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg?w=150&amp;h=95 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg?w=300&amp;h=191 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/wifi-bluetooth-tiny-chip.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>While I usually omit Bluetooth I can not say the same about WiFi … and as FreeBSD lacks a little in that department – using a very tiny chip such as <a href="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2020/10/30/realtek-usb-wifi-review/">Realtek RTL8188CUS</a> often does the job done.</p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$1-$3</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>WIFI USB</b> or <b>BLUETOOTH USB</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>USB-C &lt;=&gt; Micro USB Adapter</h2>
<p>In the past – in the USB Micro times – I remember using an adapter to be able to charge – then new and uncommon – USB-C devices.</p>
<p>Fast forward several years and now the situation is the other way around (as expected). The USB-C is the standard and USB Micro devices are less and less common … but there are still here. To not have to keep separate dedicated USB Micro cables I use a small USB-C to USB Micro adapters.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6258" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg" data-orig-size="740,360" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-USB-micro-adapter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=625&amp;h=304 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=150&amp;h=73 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=300&amp;h=146 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-usb-micro-adapter.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>Such adapter takes USB-C as input power and is able to charge USB Micro devices.</p>
<p>You can find them for about <b>$1-$2</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>USB-C USB MICRO ADAPTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>USB-C &lt;=&gt; Laptops/Routers/5.5mmx2.5mm Adapters</h2>
<p>When it comes to delivering power to my (and not only) laptops – the new standard seems to be the USB-C connector with ‘requirement’ of 45W or more (it depends).</p>
<p>Not that long ago I discovered that even laptops as old as 13 years – <strong>ThinkPad X220/T420s/W520</strong> – can be powered the same – but with simple and very cheap adapter cables – such as these below. From the left there is <strong>5.5mm/2.5mm</strong> typical router socket – then more modern <strong>ThinkPad X270/T470s</strong> (and many more) – then oldschool models from 2011 year – <strong>ThinkPads</strong> such as <strong>X220/T420s/W520</strong> models.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6259" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg" data-orig-size="740,790" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-laptops-routers-adapters-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg?w=281" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg?w=625&amp;h=667 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg?w=141&amp;h=150 141w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg?w=281&amp;h=300 281w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>All they need is a USB-C power input.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6260" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg" data-orig-size="740,690" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="USB-C-laptops-routers-adapters-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg?w=625&amp;h=583 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=140 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=280 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/usb-c-laptops-routers-adapters-2.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>You need to only meet two requirements – the USB charger that will make enough power for example 20V at 3.25A for 65W that would power <strong>ThinkPad X220/T420s</strong> or 20V at 6.75A for 135W that would power <strong>ThinkPad W520</strong>. While the official power supply for ThinkPad W520 is 170W – its perfectly fine to use the 135W power adapter from <strong>ThinkPad W510</strong> to power <strong>ThinkPad W520</strong> laptop.</p>
<p>This makes organizing cables (and chargers) a lot easier – for example – I would not be able to fit 3 ‘dedicated’ ThinkPad chargers in that white cable organizer behind laptops – but I will fir there two powerful 65W and 85W USB-C chargers perfectly fine.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6262" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/power-angle-adapter-3-x220/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg" data-orig-size="740,470" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="power-angle-adapter-3-X220" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg?w=625&amp;h=397 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg?w=150&amp;h=95 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg?w=300&amp;h=191 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-3-x220.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6263" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg" data-orig-size="740,540" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="power-angle-adapter-4-USB-chargers" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg?w=625&amp;h=456 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg?w=150&amp;h=109 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg?w=300&amp;h=219 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-4-usb-chargers.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>You can find these power adapters for about <b>$1-$3</b> – for example – on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> – with the <b>USB-C ADAPTER LAPTOP ROUTER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Creative BT-W2 USB-A Bluetooth Adapter</h2>
<p>When I have to cope with Bluetooth technology – its ‘tolerable’ on Android devices such as phones/tablets and mostly nowhere else. After bad audio (just not working) Bluetooth possibilities on FreeBSD I decided to try the hardware solution instead. The audio related Bluetooth on FreeBSD have failed me too many times – to the point called <i>enough is enough</i> – that also means I do not want to waste any more time trying to figure the way using FreeBSD Bluetooth stack devices anymore – at least for audio related devices.</p>
<p>Not so long ago I got the <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones. I am/was a big fan of the <i>Technics RP-F290</i> cable headphones (Jack or Mini Jack based). They have so much BASS and ‘power’ that I could not ask for more … and their cost is very low – like <b>$24</b> or less. The only ‘downside’ of the <i>Technics RP-F290</i> headphones is that they are audio only – they do not have any microphone at all – they are dedicated for music only – and that is OK – they do GREAT in that role.</p>
<p>I have tried some Bluetooth based headphones in the past – and they were SHIT to say the least. Not enough ‘power’ – not enough BASS etc. After reading multiple reviews I decided to give <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones a chance … and I was not disappointed. Its the first time after <i>Technics RP-F290</i> cable headphones that ANY Bluetooth based headphone delivered. I was (and I still am) really satisfied with them.</p>
<p>This is where the USB powered <i>Creative BT-W2</i> comes handy. Its also relatively cheap as the cost of used unit is less then <b>$20</b> – at least that is the price I payed for mine in Poland. The <i>Creative BT-W2</i> allows to connect Bluetooth audio devices everywhere – even on OpenBSD – on the system that cut off Bluetooth stack entirely – and it works well on FreeBSD too. The ‘downside’ of the <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones is that they do have microphone – but only in Bluetooth node – they have Mini Jack connector – but for audio only …</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6264" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/creative-bluetooth-adapter/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg" data-orig-size="740,550" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="creative-bluetooth-adapter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg?w=625&amp;h=465 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg?w=150&amp;h=111 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg?w=300&amp;h=223 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/creative-bluetooth-adapter.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>This is also only downside of the <i>Creative BT-W2</i> solution – it transmits only audio – but w/o microphone. Its more then OK for listening music – but if You have to do live conferencing/meetings on FreeBSD as I do – its a dead end.</p>
<p>I have tried to find a solution to this problem – to the point that I wanted to abandon <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones entirely and find some Mini Jack (or Jack) based BASS oriented headphones that will also have a working microphone.</p>
<p>On my journey I have found a solution that I did not expected at all – and that was the solution that solved all my problems – and allowed me to enjoy the <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones – but more about that in the next ‘subsection’.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>External Microphone for SONY Headphones</h2>
<p>You already know the downsides of the <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones that were giving me headaches. Now its time to address them.</p>
<p>After many hours of searching the Internet I have found a very ‘usable’ Mini Jack cable. A cable that came with microphone and a one that perfectly integrated with <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones … and FreeBSD as well.</p>
<p>Its available to buy for <b>$22</b> on <a>amazon.de</a> (and possible other locations) and its called <b>Boom Microphone Cable</b>. Thanks to the knowledge that <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones have Mini Jack port with microphone part – the <b>Boom Microphone Cable</b> cable even comes with volume controls and even come with physical kill switch for microphone.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6265" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/boom-microphone-cable-1/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg" data-orig-size="740,600" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="boom-microphone-cable-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg?w=625&amp;h=507 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=122 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=243 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>After You attach this <b>Boom Microphone Cable</b> to the <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones it looks (and works) like a natural solution.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6266" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/boom-microphone-cable-2/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg" data-orig-size="740,580" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="boom-microphone-cable-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg?w=625&amp;h=490 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg?w=150&amp;h=118 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg?w=300&amp;h=235 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/boom-microphone-cable-2.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>The only ‘downside’ is generally the downside of the <b>Sony WH1000XM4</b> headphones – that You CAN NOT disable their silencing while you speak – so using them in ‘passive’ mode with <b>Boom Microphone Cable</b> is preferred to meet all needs.</p>
<p><strong>EDIT: </strong>After reading comments to this article I learned that this ‘silencing’ is called <em>Speak to Chat</em> and it can be disabled in the SONY Android app or by holding <span>two fingers</span> on the <span>right earcup</span> until the headphones say <em>“Speak to Chat disabled.”</em> Thank You for that.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Headphones Handle</h2>
<p>I got used to the fact that I just put my headphones on the desk … but I wanted something more useful – after some searching it was obvious to me that I needed just some headphones handle that I could attach somewhere.</p>
<p>After another several hours of browsing I have found a ‘part’ that would fit perfectly – a <b>$4-5</b> part from <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> that I could find with the <b>HEADPHONES HOLDER</b> keywords in their search.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6267" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/headphones-handle-1/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg" data-orig-size="740,610" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="headphones-handle-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg?w=625&amp;h=515 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg?w=150&amp;h=124 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg?w=300&amp;h=247 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>Here is how it works on my desk.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6268" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/headphones-handle-2/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg" data-orig-size="740,920" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="headphones-handle-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg?w=241" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg?w=625&amp;h=777 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg?w=121&amp;h=150 121w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg?w=241&amp;h=300 241w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-2.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>… and its 360 degrees adjustable as well.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6269" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/headphones-handle-3/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg" data-orig-size="740,1080" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="headphones-handle-3" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg?w=206" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg?w=702" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg?w=625&amp;h=912 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg?w=103&amp;h=150 103w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg?w=206&amp;h=300 206w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/headphones-handle-3.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>Above the headphones handle You can see the ‘hero’ of the <a href="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2023/07/30/amd-based-freebsd-desktop/">AMD Based FreeBSD Desktop</a> article.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Dual USB-C and USB-A Pendrive (SanDisk)</h2>
<p>With all my ‘bad’ experiences with PTP connections for Android based devices (and other places) I really liked the <b>SanDisk Ultra Dual Drive</b>.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6270" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg" data-orig-size="740,580" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="pendrive-dual-USB-C-USB-A" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg?w=625&amp;h=490 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg?w=150&amp;h=118 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg?w=300&amp;h=235 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/pendrive-dual-usb-c-usb-a.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>Its really handy for many transfers … and its more fast then slow as well.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Tiny USB-A Hub</h2>
<p>When You need to connect several USB-A devices the USB ports count often come short fast – this is where this tiny USB-A hub comes handy.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6272" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/hub-usb-a/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg" data-orig-size="740,520" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="hub-USB-A" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg?w=625&amp;h=439 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg?w=150&amp;h=105 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg?w=300&amp;h=211 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hub-usb-a.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>With its dirt cheap <b>$1-2</b> price (at <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> with <b>USB HUB</b> keywords) its a ‘steal’ … and it is a 3 port hub – there is another USB-A port at the end of it – the one that is not visible.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Quad USB-C / USB-A / Lightning / Micro USB Adapter with MicroSD Card Slot</h2>
<p>… as we are talking various USB-A or USB-C solutions I could not mention this quad port adapter with MicroSD card slot.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6273" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg" data-orig-size="740,550" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="4in1-USB-C-USB-A-USB-micro-adapter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=625&amp;h=465 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=150&amp;h=111 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg?w=300&amp;h=223 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/4in1-usb-c-usb-a-usb-micro-adapter.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>I do not even remember how many times I have used it to copy/backup contents of my phone(s) and/or tablet(s).</p>
<p>Nowadays I believe I use the <b>Dual USB-C / USB-A Pendrive</b> more … but not always.</p>
<p>For <b>$8-9</b> on its not a bad solution to have.</p>
<p>Batteries … I mean SD card – not included 🙂</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Angle Power Adapters</h2>
<p>I have often found that the angle with which the power cord sticks out of a PC is definitely not ideal – this is where angle power adapters come handy.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6274" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/power-angle-adapter-2/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg" data-orig-size="740,870" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="power-angle-adapter-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg?w=255" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg?w=625&amp;h=735 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg?w=128&amp;h=150 128w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg?w=255&amp;h=300 255w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-2.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>Here is how it looks (being used) on my PC.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6275" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/power-angle-adapter-1/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg" data-orig-size="740,870" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="power-angle-adapter-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg?w=255" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg?w=625&amp;h=735 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg?w=128&amp;h=150 128w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg?w=255&amp;h=300 255w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-angle-adapter-1.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>They are available for about <b>$1-2</b> on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> with <b>ANGLE C13 CABLE</b> keywords on the search box.</p>
<h2>C13/C14 Power Adapters with Additional C1/C2 or C5/C6 Sockets</h2>
<p>After You have spent some time to lay down the C13/C14 power cables just to power your PC its really annoying to do the same for another set of C1/C2 or C5/C6 cables/sockets … but not anymore.</p>
<p>Now with single cable adapter You are able to power more then one computer – depending on the needs with additional connectors.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6276" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/power-multiplier-adapter/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg" data-orig-size="740,600" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="power-multiplier-adapter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg?w=625&amp;h=507 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg?w=150&amp;h=122 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg?w=300&amp;h=243 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/power-multiplier-adapter.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>They are available for <b>$1-2</b> on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> with <b>DUAL C13 CABLE</b> keywords on the search box.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>HDMI 3in1 Switch with Remote Control</h2>
<p>I happen to have a 2010 FullHD 50 Inch TV that has ONLY ONE port of HDMI kind … and it was pretty annoying to say the least … up to the time I added a HDMI switch/hub to it.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6277" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/hdmia/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg" data-orig-size="740,740" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="HDMIa" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg?w=625&amp;h=625 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg?w=150&amp;h=150 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg?w=300&amp;h=300 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmia.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>The HDMI switch along with its remote below.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6279" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/hdmib/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg" data-orig-size="740,590" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="HDMIb" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg?w=625&amp;h=498 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg?w=150&amp;h=120 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg?w=300&amp;h=239 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/hdmib.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>For the record – I have used the <b>UGreen 3in1 HDMI Switch with 4K @ 30Hz Capability and Remote</b> and I was able to get one for <b>$16</b>.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Cable Organizers</h2>
<p>To not have a mess in the cables its useful to have them organized in some way.</p>
<p>I use multiple solutions for that.</p>
<p>Lets start with simple organizers.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6280" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/organizer-cables/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg" data-orig-size="740,530" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="organizer-cables" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg?w=625&amp;h=448 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg?w=150&amp;h=107 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg?w=300&amp;h=215 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>… and a larger/taller one for more capacity/possibilities.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6281" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/organizer-cables-larger/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg" data-orig-size="740,430" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="organizer-cables-larger" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg?w=625&amp;h=363 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg?w=150&amp;h=87 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg?w=300&amp;h=174 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizer-cables-larger.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>They are available for <b>$3-9</b> on <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> with <b>CABLE ORGANIZER</b> keywords on the search box.</p>
<p>I also use some IKEA containers …</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6282" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/organizers-containers/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg" data-orig-size="740,520" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="organizers-containers" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg?w=625&amp;h=439 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg?w=150&amp;h=105 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg?w=300&amp;h=211 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-containers.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>… and smaller boxes in which I keep the tiny things.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6283" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/organizers-boxes/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg" data-orig-size="740,510" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="organizers-boxes" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg?w=625&amp;h=431 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg?w=150&amp;h=103 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg?w=300&amp;h=207 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/organizers-boxes.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>I do not even remember after what product these boxes are … and that does not even matter I think.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Mouse Jigger</h2>
<p>While there are many software settings or solutions to prevent screen from locking up – there is one bulletproof solution what just always works – a hardware USB mouse jigger.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6284" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/mouse-jigler/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg" data-orig-size="740,500" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="mouse-jigler" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg?w=625&amp;h=422 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg?w=150&amp;h=101 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg?w=300&amp;h=203 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/mouse-jigler.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>I use a very simple one with 3 modes – but its more then enough for me needs.</p>
<p>Feel free to check other offers with <b>USB MOUSE JIGGER </b>at <a href="https://aliexpress.com/">https://aliexpress.com</a> search box.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>FM Transmitter</h2>
<p>Last but not least – the car FM transmitter.</p>
<p>My daily ‘real’ driver (I mean on the real road outside) is the <b>2006 Dodge Magnum</b> car. I really love it for the simplicity and calm that it provides during the ride – but on the audio side it only has an old FM/AM radio and a CD slot … and not MP3 support in that one.</p>
<p>This is where the FM transmitter such as mine <b>Blow</b> comes really handy.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6286" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/blow-photo-b/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg" data-orig-size="740,380" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="BLOW.photo.b" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg?w=625&amp;h=321 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg?w=150&amp;h=77 150w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg?w=300&amp;h=154 300w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.photo_.b.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>It supports two modes. One is being a Bluetooth slave of your phone – it just plays on the car speakers anything you are currently playing on your phone – it also has microphone builtin – so You can also use it as a ‘loud’ phone talking device.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="6287" data-permalink="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/2024/03/21/tiny-undervalued-hardware-companions/blow-real/" data-orig-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg" data-orig-size="740,780" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="BLOW.real" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg?w=285" data-large-file="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg?w=740" loading="lazy" src="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg?w=960" alt="" srcset="https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg?w=625&amp;h=659 625w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg?w=142&amp;h=150 142w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg?w=285&amp;h=300 285w, https://vermaden.wordpress.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/03/blow.real_.jpg 740w" sizes="(max-width: 625px) 100vw, 625px"></p>
<p>I use it in a more simple mode – I just attach a tiny <b>Lexar S47 32GB</b> pendrive to it – and play a random song of it.</p>
<p>Besides these features it also has additional USB-A port available to attach a cable to it and charge some device.</p>
<p>I was able to get one a new one for about <b>$19</b>.</p>
<p>~</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>The mentioned devices above are probably not the only ones that make my life easier – but definitely the most crucial ones.</p>
<p>Feel free to share your ‘helper’ hardware in the comments.</p>
<p>Regards.</p>
<p>EOF</p>
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Learn You Galois Fields for Great Good (00) (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_00.html</link>
            <guid>44333388</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jun 2025 00:21:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_00.html">https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_00.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44333388">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main">
<h2>Learn you Galois Fields for Great Good (00)</h2>
<p>Navigation |
<a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_00.html">first</a> |
<a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_01.html">next</a></p>
<h2>Introduction</h2>
<p>This is the introduction to a series on Abstract Algebra. In particular, our focus will be on Galois Fields (also known as Finite Fields) and their applications in Computer Science. This is a project I've been excited about for many years now, but have been too busy to dedicate the adequate effort to meet my perfectionism standards (yay perfectionism!).</p>
<h3>Backstory</h3>
<p>Many moons back I was self-learning Galois Fields for some erasure coding theory applications. I was quite disappointed with the lack of accessible resources for computer scientists.
Many resources assumed either:</p>
<ol>
<li>Its beyond your skill level so let's oversimplify (<code>"it's hard, don't worry about it"</code>), or</li>
<li>You had prior Pure Math studies in Abstract Algebra (<code>"it's easy, just use jargon jargon jargon"</code>)</li>
</ol>
<p>Unfortunately, Abstract Algebra is not standard subject matter in most computer science curriculums. Often computer science mathematics start and end
with Discrete Math. If you're lucky, maybe you've also been exposed to Linear Algebra.</p>
<p>So, ultimately, I ended up self-learning Abstract Algebra from a pure math textbook. But for the great majority of computer scientists, there has to be a better way.
This series intends to fill this gap. This is the gentle step-by-step approach with applications implemented with actual code. It's the intro I wanted when I was starting out.</p>
<h3>What is this subject?</h3>
<p>Abstract algebra is a beautiful subject. It's the idea that the numbers you're familiar with don't matter. The numbers are just
arbitrary labels. What matters is the relationships they have with other numbers when you add or multiply them. If the numbers
don't matter, then we can swap those labels for different labels and all the normal math rules will still work.</p>
<p>For example, we could create an algebra that allows us to add or multiply colors:</p>
<p><img src="https://xorvoid.com/color_arithmetic.png" alt="a double rainbow?"></p>
<p>And this is what makes the subject abstract and confusing. How can you just say that numbers don't matter? It doesn't make sense.</p>
<p><img src="https://xorvoid.com/jackie_chan_confused_numbers.jpg" alt="even jackie struggles at math" width="300"></p>
<p>And even so, why would we want to study this? Why would a computer scientist care?</p>
<p>Well, we use computer algorithms to manipulate data. We encode/decode it, we encrypt/decrypt it, we detect corruption, etc.
Wouldn't it be great if we could use normal math to do those things? Wouldn't it be great if would could add or multiply
an 8-bit byte by an 8-bit byte and get another 8-bit byte? And if we could do that, could we also do Linear Algebra over Data? Yes, yes, and more yes.
This is why studying Abstract Algebra is worthwhile.</p>
<p><img src="https://xorvoid.com/color_8_bit_arithmetic.png" alt="color me 42"></p>
<p>(Hint: Neither 263 nor 9282 are answers, they are not 8-bit numbers)</p>
<p>You can also make quirky blog posts that make your friends think you've gone crazy, like <a href="https://xorvoid.com/milk_and_cookies.html">milk and cookies</a> 🥛 🍪 😊</p>
<h3>Applications</h3>
<p>The applications and algorithms are staggering. You interact with implementations of abstract algebra everyday: CRC,
AES Encryption, Elliptic-Curve Cryptography, Reed-Solomon, Advanced Erasure Codes, Data Hashing/Fingerprinting, Zero-Knowledge Proofs, etc.</p>
<p>Having a solid-background in Galois Fields and Abstract Algebra is a prerequisite for understanding these applications.</p>
<h3>Approach: Step-by-step, Active Learning, and Literate Programming</h3>
<p>In this series, we will start from the very basics of theory and build up step-by-step to interesting applications such as Reed-Solomon,
AES, etc. As such, the material will be <b>very</b> cumulative. Many exercises will be included to aid understanding. Each section will build gradually,
but will assume mastery of the previous section. Active learning is <b>strongly encouraged</b>. We will expect that
readers are putting in adequate effort to grok the abstract concepts.</p>
<p>We won't assume too much mathematical background beyond high-school level algebra. However, in some applications (for example: Reed-Solomon),
familiarity with Linear Algebra will be required. We won't explain Linear Algebra since great resources already
exist <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL49CF3715CB9EF31D">here</a>. You are encouraged to supplement as needed.</p>
<p>We will be including code in a Literate Programming style where appropriate.  For example, to aid understanding, we will build some interactive
command-line tools that allow you to play around with various theoretical concepts in practice. All code will be the
<a href="https://www.rust-lang.org/">Rust Programming Language</a>, but advanced features will be intentionally avoided so that the code will be readable
by most experienced computer programmers.</p>
<p>The main goal of this series is understandability and education. As such, the implementations will not be optimal. We will forgo nearly all
optimizations you'd see in a production quality implementation: lookup-tables, vectorized instructions, clever representations, computer
architecture optimizations, etc. It's possible that later posts in the series will discuss optimizations, but this is not a primary goal. At the end,
we hope these implementations will serve as good reference implementations. This can have it's own merit since highly optimized algorithms are
often difficult to read and understand.</p>
<p>For active learning, I strongly encourage you to do your own implementations and to play around with the command-line tools while reading. If you'd
like to open-source your implementations, I'm more than happy to link them here:</p>
<ul>
<li>Original: xorvoid (Rust): <a href="https://github.com/xorvoid/learn_you_galois_fields_for_great_good">here</a></li>
</ul>
<h3>Planning is Essential, Plans are Worthless</h3>
<p>Here's the rough plan. We will see how it actually goes:</p>
<ul>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_01.html">01: Group Theory</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_02.html">02: Field Theory</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_03.html">03: Implementing GF(p)</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_04.html">04: Polynomial Arithmetic</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_05.html">05: Polynomial Fields GF(p^k)</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_06.html">06: Implementing GF(p^k)</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_07.html">07: Implementing Binary Fields GF(2^k)</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_08.html">08: Cyclic Redundancy Check (CRC)</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_09.html">09: Linear Algebra over Fields</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_10.html">10: Reed-Solomon as Polynomial Representation</a></b></li>
<li><b><a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_11.html">11: Reed-Solomon as Linear Algebra</a></b></li>
<li><b>12: AES (Rijndael) Encryption</b></li>
<li><b>... And More ...</b></li>
</ul>
<p>Other possible advanced subjects:</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Rabin Fingerprinting</b></li>
<li><b>Extended Euclidean Algorithm</b></li>
<li><b>Log and Invlog Tables</b></li>
<li><b>Elliptic Curves</b></li>
<li><b>Bit-matrix Representations</b></li>
<li><b>Fast Multiplication with FFTs</b></li>
<li><b>Vectorization Implementation Techniques</b></li>
</ul>
<p>The first few sections are theory. There's not much coding in these sections, but they are very important for success later in the series.
Don't skip them.</p>
<p>Let's <a href="https://xorvoid.com/galois_fields_for_great_good_01.html">get started</a>!</p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Plastic bag bans and fees reduce harmful bag litter on shorelines (235 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adp9274</link>
            <guid>44333187</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jun 2025 23:46:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adp9274">https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adp9274</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=44333187">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adp9274: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>