(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 21:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft is introducing hidden APIs to VS Code only enabled for Copilot (228 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/ChatGPTCoding/comments/1g8xrub/microsoft_is_introducing_hidden_apis_to_vs_code/</link>
            <guid>41907350</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 19:11:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/ChatGPTCoding/comments/1g8xrub/microsoft_is_introducing_hidden_apis_to_vs_code/">https://old.reddit.com/r/ChatGPTCoding/comments/1g8xrub/microsoft_is_introducing_hidden_apis_to_vs_code/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41907350">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://old.reddit.com/r/ChatGPTCoding/comments/1g8xrub/microsoft_is_introducing_hidden_apis_to_vs_code/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Please do not write below the line (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.bbctvlicence.com/Please%20do%20not%20write%20below%20the%20line.htm</link>
            <guid>41907071</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 18:42:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.bbctvlicence.com/Please%20do%20not%20write%20below%20the%20line.htm">http://www.bbctvlicence.com/Please%20do%20not%20write%20below%20the%20line.htm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41907071">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" size="+2" face="Verdana">Please do not write below this line</span></b></span><p><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" size="+1" face="Verdana">I have been vexed for some time by the request at the bottom of
						  each letter that I am not to write below the line. </span></b></span></p><img src="http://www.bbctvlicence.com/Please%20do%20not%20write%20below%20this%20line.jpg" width="538" height="25"> 
						<p><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" size="+1" face="Verdana">I emailed TVL/BBC on 5 November 2006 to find out why:
						  </span></b></span></p> 
						<div> 
								<p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">I've had a letter from TV Licencing and I'm interested in the
										statement at the bottom of the page. It says: 'Please do not write below this
										line'. I would like to know why the letter requests this. The line referred to
										is about half an inch from the bottom edge of the letter. </span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"></span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">What will happen if I write there? How would you know? I am not
										asked to return the letter, so why the request?</span></p><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">Seven weeks later, on 27 December 2006, I receive
								this from one Kelly Wright: </span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Thank you for contacting us. Unfortunately I am unable to deal
										with your request, as you have not provided your address and licence number. If
										you have moved address I will need both your new and old address. Once I have
										this information I will action your request and send you the appropriate form
										or confirmation.</span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">I reply: </span></b></span> <p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">Dear Ms Wright,
										</span></span><br><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">I do not
										have a licence. The letter was sent to me as part of TVL's routine mail-out. It
										was not solicited by me. Copies of these letters are commonly reproduced on the
										internet [example]. </span></span></span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">You will see that these letters say "Please do not
										write below this line". So did the one sent to me. Please explain to me why I
										am not allowed to write below the line. </span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">Evidently, my question was too taxing for Ms
								Wright, as the next response came from Ruairi Mcclean, on 3 January
								2007:</span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">The reason you would receive such letters is because we would have
										no record of a TV licence at your address. </span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"></span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">The reason you cannot write below the line is because the letters
										go through a OCR machine, and anything below the line is rejected.</span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">OCR is an abbreviation for "optical character
								recognition", software that scans documents for editing on a computer.
								</span></b></span><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial"></span></b></span><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">This explanation surprised me. I did not
								understand why, having sent me a letter, TVL wanted it back to scan and edit;
								why not scan it before sending it to me? I responded on 27 January
								2007:</span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">Dear Mr Mcclean
										</span></span><br><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">Thank you
										for your reply. You say that I cannot write below the line because the letter
										will go through a OCR machine, and anything below the line will be rejected.
										</span></span><br><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000"></span></span><br><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">I have two further questions:
										</span></span><br></span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">i) I take it from your reply that
										a TV officer is planning to collect the letter back off me in order to scan it.
										Please tell me what purpose this serves. </span></span><br></span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"><span face="Arial"><span size="-1" color="#000000">ii) Anything I write above the line would also be
										rejected by the OCR. Why am I allowed to write above the line, if I am not
										allowed to write in the narrow strip beneath it? </span></span></span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">On 30 January 2007, I received this reply from Cas
								Scott:</span></b></span> <p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">A
										Licensing officer may call at your property not to collect the letters but to
										check that you are not watching a TV. </span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">You may write above the line but as we advised you
										previously anything written below the line when they go through the OCR machine
										they will be rejected. </span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">If you would like to confirm your address I can up date our
										records to advise no Television is being watched. </span></p><br> 
								<p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Dear Ms Scott</span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Thank you for confirming that I may write above the line.
										</span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"></span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Please explain why, having sent me the
										letter, you want it back for scanning. Also, please explain how I am to get the
										letter to you.</span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">6 February 2007: I have a reply from Gary
								Bessell.</span></b></span> <p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Dear Ms Scott </span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Without your address we are unable to amend our records to show
										that you are not using TV equipment. </span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">To return an enquiry letter to TV licensing,
										simply return it. </span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">I don't seem to be getting a straight
								answer.</span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Dear Mr Bessell</span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Thank you for your reply. The purpose of my query is not to ask
										why you want my address.</span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">The information that I am seeking is why you want the letter back
										for scanning. There was nothing on the letter that said I had to return it.
										</span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Please note that I
										am not Miss Scott.</span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">9 February 2007: a reply from Karen
								Mcallister.</span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">The information about returning the letter was not on the letter
										itself but on the envelope. </span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial"></span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">The only
										reason we ask you to return the letter is to help us update our records,
										however if you could provide us with your address we can update our records
										without you returning the letter. </span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">Having kept all my TVL/BBC envelopes, I examined
								them to see whether any displayed an instruction that I was to return the
								letter. None did. There was a return address but only was for undelivered
								letters. I resist the temptation to pursue this point.
								</span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Dear Ms Mcallister</span><br><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Thank you for your reply. </span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">What I still do not understand is why you would
										wish to OCR my letter in order to update the records. </span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">Obviously, the number below the line must be very
										important. Please could you explain its purpose. </span></p><br><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">A reply from Carl
								Graves:</span></b></span><p><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">I
										apologise that it has not been made clear to you. An OCR stands for a Optical
										Character System. This machine enables us to deal/process with large volumes of
										information in a relatively short space of time. The OCR machine reads the
										information below the line and updates the corresponding records on our
										computer system many times faster than if manually processed.
										</span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">If the information
										below the line is obscured in anyway the OCR machine will be unable to read the
										information effectively. The number below the line is a unique number that
										relates to the specific property that the letter has been sent to. Once this
										number is read by the OCR machine it will automatically update the computer
										records that relate to that letter/property/licence/application.
										</span><span size="-1" color="#000000" face="Arial">I hope the above
										information is helpful. </span></p><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">I am still not satisfied. If I send a letter back
								to TVL/BBC, and they scan the number at the bottom, it will generate the same
								information as they have already got; so, what's the point?
								</span></b></span><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">Let's compare TVL/BBC's operation to another company. Below is a
								scan of a pre-paid return postcard from a company called Santander, in which I
								am a shareholder, which I am invited to return. </span></b></span><p><img src="http://www.bbctvlicence.com/Please%20do%20not%20write%20-%20Santander.jpg" width="553" height="421"></p><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">Santander requests that I do not write below the line but, unlike
								TVL/BBC, there is an explanation which is on the right hand side. It says that
								they will retrieve my personal data (which I have authorised them to hold,
								unlike TVL/BBC) by scanning the barcode and number. This makes perfect
								sense.</span></b></span><span face="Bell MT"><b><span color="#000000" face="Arial">TVL/BBC letters, however, do not ask for its letters to be
								returned, and Cas Scott has said that the letters are not sought by TVL/BBC
								agents who make street visits. Even if they did collect the letters, the number
								at the bottom would duplicate the information that they already hold. So, the
								original question - why we not permitted to write below the line - remains a
								mystery.</span></b></span><br></div> <br> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[U.S. border surveillance towers have always been broken (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/10/us-border-surveillance-towers-have-always-been-broken</link>
            <guid>41906283</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 17:26:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/10/us-border-surveillance-towers-have-always-been-broken">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/10/us-border-surveillance-towers-have-always-been-broken</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41906283">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <article role="article">
  
  
  <div><p><span>A new </span><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/investigations/30-cameras-border-patrols-main-surveillance-system-are-broken-memo-say-rcna175281"><span>bombshell scoop</span></a><span> from NBC News revealed an internal U.S. Border Patrol memo claiming that 30 percent of camera towers that compose the agency's "Remote Video Surveillance System" (RVSS) program are broken. According to the report, the memo describes "several technical problems" affecting approximately 150 towers.</span></p>
<p><span>Except, this isn't a bombshell. What should actually be shocking is that Congressional leaders are acting shocked, like those who recently sent a </span><a href="https://www.foxnews.com/us/whistleblowers-border-patrol-surveillance-cameras-out-service-gop-demands-answers-dhs"><span>letter</span></a><span> about the towers to Department of Homeland Security (DHS) Secretary Alejandro Mayorkas. These revelations simply reiterate what people who have been watching border technology have known for decades: Surveillance at the U.S.-Mexico border is a wasteful endeavor that is ill-equipped to respond to an ill-defined problem. <br></span></p>
<p><span>Yet, after years of bipartisan recognition that these programs were straight-up boondoggles, there seems to be a competition among political leaders to throw the most money at programs that continue to fail. <br></span></p>
<p><span>Official oversight reports about the failures, repeated breakages, and general ineffectiveness of these camera towers have been public since at least the mid-2000s. So why haven't border security agencies confronted the problem in the last 25 years? One reason is that these cameras are largely political theater; the technology dazzles publicly, then fizzles quietly. Meanwhile, communities that should be thriving at the border are treated like a laboratory for tech companies looking to cash in on often exaggerated—if not fabricated—homeland security threats.</span></p>
<h3><strong>The Acronym Game</strong></h3>
<div><p><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/03/cbp-expanding-its-surveillance-tower-program-us-mexico-border-and-were-mapping-it"><img src="https://www.eff.org/files/2024/10/18/eff_map_10-18-2024.png" width="1125" height="729" alt="A map of the US-Mexico border with multicolored dots representing surveillance towers." title="EFF is mapping surveillance at the US-Mexico border"></a></p><p>EFF is mapping surveillance at the U.S.-Mexico border</p></div><p><em><i><span>.</span></i></em></p><p><span></span><span>In fact, the history of camera towers at the border is an ugly cycle. First, Border Patrol introduces a surveillance program with a catchy name and big promises. Then a few years later, oversight bodies, including Congress, conclude it's an abject mess. But rather than abandon the program once and for all, border security officials come up with a new name, slap on a fresh coat of paint, and continue on. A few years later, history repeats. </span></p>
<p><span>In the early 2000s, there was the Integrated Surveillance Intelligence System (ISIS), with the installation of RVSS towers in places like Calexico, California and Nogales, Arizona, which was later became the America's Shield Initiative (ASI). After those failures, there was Project 28 (P-28), the first stage of the Secure Border Initiative (SBInet). When that program was canceled, there were various new programs like the Arizona Border Surveillance Technology Plan, which became the Southwest Border Technology Plan. Border Patrol introduced the Integrated Fixed Tower (IFT) program and the RVSS Update program, then the Automated Surveillance Tower (AST) program. And now we've got a whole slew of new acronyms, including the Integrated Surveillance Tower (IST) program and the Consolidated Towers and Surveillance Equipment (CTSE) program. <br></span></p>
<p><span>Feeling overwhelmed by acronyms? Welcome to the shell game of border surveillance. Here's what happens whenever oversight bodies take a closer look. </span></p>
<h3><b>ISIS and ASI</b></h3>
<div><p><img src="https://www.eff.org/files/2024/10/18/calexico_rvss.jpg" width="1920" height="1346" alt="A surveillance tower over a home." title=""></p><p>An RVSS from the early 2000s in Calexico, California.</p></div>
<p><span>Let's start with the Integrated Surveillance Intelligence System (ISIS), a program comprised of towers, sensors and databases originally launched in 1997 by the Immigration and Naturalization Service. A few years later, INS was reorganized into the U.S. Department of Homeland Security (DHS), and ISIS became part of the newly formed Customs &amp; Border Protection (CBP). <br></span></p>
<p><span>It was only a matter of years before the DHS Inspector General </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/23314612-oig_06-15_dec05"><span>concluded that ISIS</span></a><span> was a flop:</span><span> "ISIS remote surveillance technology yielded few apprehensions as a percentage of detection, resulted in needless investigations of legitimate activity, and consumed valuable staff time to perform video analysis or investigate sensor alerts." </span></p>
<p><span>During </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24483802-chrg-109shrg99863"><span>Senate hearings</span></a><span>, Sen. Judd Gregg (R-NH), complained about a "</span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24483802-chrg-109shrg99863#document/p125"><span>total breakdown in the camera structures</span></a><span>," and that the U.S. government "</span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24483802-chrg-109shrg99863#document/p141"><span>bought cameras that didn't work.</span></a><span>" </span></p>
<p><span>Around 2004, ISIS was folded into the new America's Shield Initiative (ASI), which officials claimed would fix those problems. CBP Commissioner Robert Bonner even <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24483802-chrg-109shrg99863#document/p30">promoted</a> ASI as a "critical part of CBP’s strategy to build smarter borders." Yet, less than a year later, Bonner stepped down, and the Government Accountability Office (GAO) found the ASI had <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/25242401-gao-06-295#document/p2">numerous unresolved issues</a> necessitating a total reevaluation. CBP disputed none of the findings and <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/25242401-gao-06-295#document/p6">explained</a> it was dismantling ASI in order to move onto something new that would solve everything: the Secure Border Initiative (SBI).<br></span></p>
<p><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/23825159-chrg-110hhrg44137#document/p10"><span>Reflecting on the ISIS/ASI programs in 2008</span></a><span>, Rep. Mike Rogers (R-MI) said, "What we found was a camera and sensor system that was plagued by mismanagement, operational problems, and financial waste. At that time, we put the Department on notice that mistakes of the past should not be repeated in SBInet."&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>You can guess what happened next.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h3><b>P-28 and SBInet</b></h3>
<p><span>The next iteration was called Project 28, which then evolved into the Secure Border Initiative's SBInet, starting in the Arizona desert.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>In 2010, the DHS Chief Information Officer summarized its </span><a href="https://s3.documentcloud.org/documents/24487999/itpa-cbp-sbinet2010.pdf"><span>comprehensive review</span></a><span>: "'Project 28,' the initial prototype for the SBInet system, did not perform as planned. Project 28 was not scalable to meet the mission requirements for a national comment [sic] and control system, and experienced significant technical difficulties."&nbsp;</span></p>
<div><p><img src="https://www.eff.org/files/2024/10/18/sbinet.jpg" width="1000" height="750" alt="A convoluted graphic illustrating how SBInet surveillance towers fit into the border security plan." title=""></p><p>A DHS graphic illustrating the SBInet concept</p></div>
<p><span>Meanwhile, bipartisan consensus had emerged about the failure of the program, due to the technical problems as well as contracting irregularities and cost overruns.</span></p>
<p><span>As Rep. Christopher Carney (D-PA) said in his </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/23825159-chrg-110hhrg44137#document/p9"><span>prepared statement</span></a><span> during Congressional hearings:</span></p>
<blockquote><p><span> P–28 and the larger SBInet program are supposed to be a model of how the Federal Government is leveraging technology to secure our borders, but Project 28, in my mind, has achieved a dubious distinction as a trifecta of bad Government contracting: Poor contract management; poor contractor performance; and a poor final product.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span>Rep. Rogers' remarks were even more cutting: "You know the history of ISIS and what a disaster that was, and we had hoped to take the lessons from that and do better on this and, apparently, we haven’t done much better. "</span></p>
<p><span>Perhaps most damning of all was yet another GAO </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24488007-ad1179135"><span>report</span></a><span> that found, "SBInet defects have been found, with the number of new defects identified generally increasing faster than the number being fixed—a trend that is not indicative of a system that is maturing."&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>In January 2011, DHS Secretary Janet Napolitano </span><a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2011/01/dhs-cancels-virtual-border-fence-047625"><span>canceled</span></a><span> the $3-billion program.</span></p>
<h3><b>IFTs, RVSSs, and ASTs<br></b></h3>
<p><span>Following the termination of SBInet, the </span><i><span>Christian Science Monitor</span></i><span> ran the naive headline, "</span><a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2011/0115/US-cancels-virtual-fence-along-Mexican-border.-What-s-Plan-B"><span>US cancels 'virtual fence' along Mexican border. What's Plan B</span></a><span>?" Three years later, the newspaper answered its own question with another question, "'</span><a href="https://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2014/0319/Virtual-border-fence-idea-revived.-Another-billion-dollar-boondoggle"><span>Virtual' border fence idea revived. Another 'billion dollar boondoggle'</span></a><span>?" <br></span></p>
<p><span>Boeing was the main contractor blamed for SBINet's failure, but Border Patrol ultimately awarded one of the biggest new contracts to Elbit Systems, which had been one of Boeing's subcontractors on SBInet. Elbit began installing IFTs (again, that stands for "Integrated Fixed Towers") in many of the exact same places slated for SBInet. In some cases, the equipment was simply swapped on an existing SBInet tower.<br></span></p>
<p><span>Meanwhile, another contractor, General Dynamics Information Technology, began installing new RVSS towers and upgrading old ones as part of the RVSS-U program. Border Patrol also started installing hundreds of "Autonomous Surveillance Towers" (ASTs) by yet another vendor, Anduril Industries, embracing the new buzz of artificial intelligence. <br></span></p>
<div><p><img src="https://www.eff.org/files/2024/10/18/ast_and_rvss.jpg" width="1313" height="941" alt="Two surveillance towers and a Border Patrol vehicle along the Rio Grande" title=""></p><p>An Autonomous Surveillance Tower and an RVSS tower along the Rio Grande.</p></div>
<p><span>In 2017, the GAO </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24733271-gao-18-119#document/p2"><span>complained</span></a><span> the Border Patrol's poor data quality made the agency "limited in its ability to determine the mission benefits of its surveillance technologies." In one case, Border Patrol stations in the Rio Grande Valley claimed IFTs assisted in 500 cases in just six months. The problem with that assertion was there are no IFTs in Texas or, in fact, anywhere outside Arizona. <br></span></p>
<p><span>A few years later, the DHS Inspector General issued yet another </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/23706411-oig-21-21-feb21"><span>report</span></a><span> indicating not much had improved: <br></span></p>
<blockquote><p><span>CBP faced additional challenges that reduced the effectiveness of its existing technology. Border Patrol officials stated they had inadequate personnel to fully leverage surveillance technology or maintain current information technology systems and infrastructure on site. Further, we identified security vulnerabilities on some CBP servers and workstations not in compliance due to disagreement about the timeline for implementing DHS configuration management requirements.</span></p>
<p><span>CBP is not well-equipped to assess its technology effectiveness to respond to these deficiencies. CBP has been aware of this challenge since at least 2017 but lacks a standard process and accurate data to overcome it. <br></span></p>
<p><span>Overall, these deficiencies have limited CBP’s ability to detect and prevent the illegal entry of noncitizens who may pose threats to national security.</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p><span>Around that same time, the RAND Corporation published a </span><a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/24711700-rand_rr4348#document/p60/a2562275"><span>study</span></a><span> funded by DHS that found "strong evidence" the IFT program was having no impact on apprehension levels at the border, and only "weak" and "inconclusive" evidence that the RVSS towers were having any effect on apprehensions.</span></p>
<p><span>And yet, border authorities and their supporters in Congress are continuing to promote unproven, AI-driven technologies as the latest remedy for years of failures, including the ones voiced in the memo obtained by NBC News. These systems involve cameras controlled by algorithms that automatically identify and track objects or people of interest. But in an age when algorithmic errors and bias are being identified nearly everyday in every sector including law enforcement, it is unclear how this technology has earned the trust of the government. <br></span></p>
<h3><b>History Keeps Repeating <br></b></h3>
<p><span>That brings us today, with reportedly 150 or more towers out of service. So why does Washington keep supporting surveillance at the border? Why are they proposing record-level funding for a system that seems irreparable? Why have they abandoned their duty to scrutinize federal programs? <br></span></p>
<p><span>Well, one reason may be that treating problems at the border as humanitarian crises or pursuing foreign policy or immigration reform measures isn't as politically useful as promoting a phantom "invasion" that requires a military-style response. Another reason may be that </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/06/hundreds-tech-companies-want-cash-border-security-funding-heres-who-they-are-and"><span>tech companies and military contractors</span></a><span> wield immense amounts of influence and stand to make millions, if not billions, profiting off border surveillance. The price is paid by taxpayers, but also in the civil liberties of border communities and the human rights of asylum seekers and migrants.</span></p>
<p><span>But perhaps the biggest reason this history keeps repeating itself is that no one is ever really held accountable for wasting potentially billions of dollars on high-tech snake oil.</span></p>

</div>

          </article>
    </div><div>
          <h2>Join EFF Lists</h2>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An amateur historian has discovered a long-lost short story by Bram Stoker (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g9119l64qo</link>
            <guid>41905664</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 16:14:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g9119l64qo">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g9119l64qo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41905664">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>An amateur historian has discovered a long-lost short story by Bram Stoker, published just seven years before his legendary gothic novel Dracula.<!-- --></p><p>Brian Cleary stumbled upon the 134-year-old ghostly tale while browsing the archives of the National Library of Ireland.<!-- --></p><p>Gibbet Hill was originally published in a Dublin newspaper in 1890 - when the Irishman started working on Dracula - but has been undocumented ever since.<!-- --></p><p>Stoker biographer Paul Murray says the story sheds light on his development as an author and was a significant “station on his route to publishing Dracula”.<!-- --></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The ghostly story tells the tale of a sailor murdered by three criminals whose bodies were strung up on a hanging gallows as a warning to passing travellers.<!-- --></p><p>It is set in Gibbet Hill in Surrey, a location also referenced in Charles Dickens’ 1839 novel Nicholas Nickleby.<!-- --></p><p>Mr Cleary made the discovery after taking time off work following a sudden onset of hearing loss in 2021 - during which period he would pass the time at the national library in <!-- --><a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-northern-ireland-51053870">Stoker's native Dublin.<!-- --></a></p><p>In October 2023, the Stoker fan came across an unfamiliar title in an 1890 Christmas supplement of the Daily Express Dublin Edition.<!-- --></p><p>Mr Clearly told the AFP news agency: "I read the words Gibbet Hill and I knew that wasn't a Bram Stoker story that I had ever heard of in any of the biographies or bibliographies."<!-- --></p><p>“And I was just astounded, flabbergasted.<!-- --></p><p>"I sat looking at the screen wondering, am I the only living person who had read it?”<!-- --></p><p>He said of the moment he made the discovery: “What on earth do I do with it?”<!-- --></p><p>The library's director Audrey Whitty said Mr Cleary called her and said: "I’ve found something extraordinary in your newspaper archives - you won’t believe it."<!-- --></p><p>She added that his "astonishing amateur detective work" was a testament to the library's archives.<!-- --></p><p>"There are truly world-important discoveries waiting to be found", she said.<!-- --></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>After his initial sleuthing, Mr Cleary contacted biographer Paul Murray - who confirmed there had been no trace of the story for over a century.<!-- --></p><p>He said 1890 was when he was a young writer and made his first notes for Dracula.<!-- --></p><p>"It's a classic Stoker story, the struggle between good and evil, evil which crops up in exotic and unexplained ways," he added.<!-- --></p><p>Gibbet Hill is being published alongside artwork by the Irish artist Paul McKinley by the Rotunda Foundation - the fundraising arm of Dublin's Rotunda Hospital for which Mr Cleary worked.<!-- --></p><p>All proceeds will go to the newly formed Charlotte Stoker Fund - named after Bram Stoker’s mother who was a hearing loss campaigner - to fund research on infant hearing loss.<!-- --></p><p>The discovery is also being highlighted in the city's Bram Stoker festival later this month.<!-- --></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can SpaceX land a rocket with 1/2 cm accuracy? (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theshamblog.com/can-spacex-land-a-rocket-with-1-2-cm-accuracy/</link>
            <guid>41905215</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 15:27:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theshamblog.com/can-spacex-land-a-rocket-with-1-2-cm-accuracy/">https://theshamblog.com/can-spacex-land-a-rocket-with-1-2-cm-accuracy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41905215">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
	
<p><strong>No. But they don’t need to.</strong></p>



<p>In preparation for the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2-PSODNOwJY">5th test flight of Starship</a>, SpaceX announced that they would try to catch the booster using “Mechazilla’s chopsticks.” Later during pre-launch discussions, SpaceX VP Bill Gerstenmaier claimed that they were confident of success since they had landed the booster in the ocean during Flight 4 with “<a href="https://x.com/jeff_foust/status/1844183958873047215" data-type="link" data-id="https://x.com/jeff_foust/status/1844183958873047215">half a centimeter accuracy</a>.” And then last Sunday they went for the landing and nailed it!</p>



<p>But did they really nail it to within half a centimeter? That number sounds too good to be true, and it sparked quite a bit of skepticism from industry observers. What can SpaceX <em>really</em> expect for their landing accuracy?</p>



<p>My background: I am an aerospace engineer who has designed guidance, navigation, &amp; control (GNC) systems for successful <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_eCvxPieA84" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_eCvxPieA84">orbital launch vehicles</a>, worked with RTK precision GPS systems on the ground, and implemented GNSS systems on satellite constellations. Standard disclaimer that I am only speaking for myself, and am only using public non-ITAR information. I don’t know what SpaceX is using to estimate the position and orientation on their rockets or their exact control schemes, and I might be missing some information that they’ve made public, but I am well versed in what goes into the design space and can hopefully make some good guesses. Please comment if I’m missing or misinterpreting anything. Also this post isn’t meant as a “gotcha” against Bill – take that as an excuse to dive into the cool engineering behind catching the rocket!</p>



<p>So buckle in for a deep dive and let’s look at what goes into landing a rocket!</p>



<figure><p><iframe title="CLOSEUP! SpaceX Super Heavy Booster Catch" width="1200" height="675" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/XGC31lmdS6s?start=6&amp;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></figure>



<h5><strong>Main Points:</strong></h5>



<ul>
<li>Half a centimeter landing accuracy is not possible, and Bill likely misspoke or was talking about control error.</li>



<li>SpaceX Super Heavy booster landing margins are so wide that you could land one with your smartphone electronics.</li>



<li>Falcon 9 is likely harder to land.</li>



<li>Catching the booster is an absolutely tremendous achievement that the team should be incredibly proud of!</li>
</ul>



<h2>Controlling Position</h2>



<h5><strong>How Accurately Can SpaceX Measure Position?</strong></h5>



<p>The position of a rocket can be measured two primary ways. First, using GNSS (GPS) to get an absolute position. Second, by using an inertial measurement unit (IMU) that includes an accelerometer to estimate the distance from a known reference position (the launch pad). These sensors are both necessary and sufficient for rocket flight, so I’ll focus on them.</p>



<p>The Super Heavy booster lands back in the chopsticks 7 minutes after launch. If we use a <a data-type="link" data-id="https://aerospace.honeywell.com/us/en/products-and-services/product/hardware-and-systems/sensors/inertial-measurement-units" href="https://aerospace.honeywell.com/us/en/products-and-services/product/hardware-and-systems/sensors/inertial-measurement-units">nice expensive IMU</a> that has around 0.01 milli-g’s of accelerometer bias, that double integrates up to 8.6 meters of error. So flying by dead reckoning isn’t going to cut it. (This is a very quick-n’-dirty calculation – a real error propagation analysis would find a larger number due to velocity and attitude errors, so think of this as a lower bound).</p>



<p>We need to bring in GPS to get a better absolute position. Let’s look at the datasheet for <a href="https://novatel.com/products/receivers/gnss-gps-receiver-boards">high-end GNSS chips </a>to get a sense of what’s feasible. Civilian GPS is the L1 band at 250 cm accuracy (looking at the 95% confidence sphere), and military GPS adds the L2 band to 240 cm accuracy, so note that even if SpaceX is using the military band that doesn’t do much on its own in an open-air environment. You could use SBAS (Satellite based augmentation systems, over the US it’s the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wide_Area_Augmentation_System" data-type="link" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wide_Area_Augmentation_System">WAAS system</a> which airplanes use for landing at airports) which improves accuracy to 120 cm and is available through just the GPS satellite link. Going further than that requires communication between the booster and the ground. At the most precise, an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real-time_kinematic_positioning" data-type="link" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Real-time_kinematic_positioning">RTK positioning system</a> could lower position accuracy all the way down to 2.5 cm (+1cm per km of distance). If SpaceX put a receiver on the launch tower or the ocean buoys, then the landing position could be incredibly accurate. But even the most advance positioning tech won’t guarantee it down to 0.5 cm. And RTK does rely on being able to acquire and maintain a link between the booster and ground for this precision.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-7.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="940" height="367" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-7.png?resize=940%2C367&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-7.png?resize=940%2C367&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-7.png?resize=580%2C226&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-7.png?resize=768%2C300&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-7.png?w=1453&amp;ssl=1 1453w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a></figure></div>


<p><a data-type="link" data-id="https://www.bzarg.com/p/how-a-kalman-filter-works-in-pictures/" href="https://www.bzarg.com/p/how-a-kalman-filter-works-in-pictures/">Sensor fusion with the accelerometer (aka Kalman filtering)</a> will help fill any gaps in GNSS signals, provide higher rate estimates, and allow for identification &amp; rejection of GNSS errors, but it won’t appreciably improve the absolute position error.</p>



<p>Furthermore, this is just the position of the GPS receiver on the rocket. How does that translate to the position of the landing pins? If there is angular pitch/yaw motion of the rocket, there will be a dynamic offset between the GPS antenna and the landing pins (though this can be calculated and compensated for). There will be manufacturing tolerances which may stack up to less than 5mm, but that would be incredibly tight for something this size. The booster itself will also change dimensions as it is cooled by propellant and heated by reentry. The coefficient of thermal expansion of steel is about 12 μm/m-degC, so for a 71 m booster with liquid oxygen at -183 degC and reentry temperature of (let’s say) 50 degC, that’s a 20 cm change in length. Cut that in half since the LOX tank is half the booster, and you still get 10 cm of elongation. It’s not clear to me whether the booster avionics are near the pins (in which case the local thermal deformation would be minimal) or the engines (in which case it definitely matters), but this shows that thermal effects alone could dwarf half a centimeter accuracy. Additionally, for the Flight 4 landing at sea which quoted the 0.5 cm number, movement of the buoys would be more than this.</p>



<p>SpaceX has said that they use radar altimeters to measure distance to the ground on Falcon 9 landings, which helps constrain the vertical axis error. That would help here as well, though the Super Heavy booster is coming down on an irregular pad rather than a flat landing zone, so a radar return signal would be harder to interpret reliably.</p>



<p>Could you use other real-time distance measurements like laser rangefinding or visual processing? I don’t think so – the surface of the vehicle is too irregular to get a reliable fix point, especially while it is moving, and these are vulnerable to smoke/fog/gas/ambient lighting. Technologies like Ultra Wideband are vulnerable to multipath reflections and attenuation by the booster’s steel walls, and aren’t more accurate than RTK anyway. It is possible that SpaceX has found a proprietary technique for more accurate localization, but at this point we are speculating. And I would point to the SpaceX design philosophy that “the best part is no part” if that extra accuracy isn’t needed. As we’ll see below, it’s not.</p>



<p>So 0.5 cm position accuracy is not possible with applicable technologies. I think the most likely scenario is that Bill misspoke and meant to say “half a meter” or “centimeters level accuracy” and conflated the two.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="940" height="948" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?resize=940%2C948&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?resize=940%2C948&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?resize=580%2C585&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?resize=150%2C150&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?resize=768%2C774&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-10.png?w=1192&amp;ssl=1 1192w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a><figcaption>Just how small half a centimeter is compared to the landing pins, <a href="https://x.com/mcrs987/status/1844189329889071144" data-type="link" data-id="https://x.com/mcrs987/status/1844189329889071144">from twitter</a></figcaption></figure></div>


<h5><strong>How Accurately Can SpaceX Control Position?</strong></h5>



<p>The algorithms here can get arbitrarily precise. I think &lt; 10 cm accuracy is achievable, and 0.5 cm is impressive but not unbelievable. But this is only control of the vehicle relative to where it <em>thinks</em> it is. I think it’s also possible that this metric is what Bill was talking about, though it’s not the ultimate number that matters for landing.</p>



<p>In preparation for this landing attempt, SpaceX undoubtedly performed extensive <a href="https://github.com/scottshambaugh/monaco/blob/main/README.md" data-type="link" data-id="https://theshamblog.com/introducing-the-monaco-monte-carlo-python-library/">Monte Carlo analyses</a>, simulating the flight of the booster millions of times with different variations in vehicle properties, engine performance, environmental effects such as wind, contingency and off-nominal scenarios such as engine failures, timing errors and signal lag, etc. This would result in realistic landing accuracy numbers. Any estimate of how accurately SpaceX can position the rocket <em>must </em>be downstream of a full analysis like this that incorporates the dynamics of the landing event with all sources of uncertainty and error, and is well outside the scope of this post.</p>



<p>But we can bound the estimates by looking at Falcon 9 landings. Reddit user FortisVeritas <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/spacex/comments/b3zr0i/chart_with_the_approximate_falcon_9_landing/" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.reddit.com/r/spacex/comments/b3zr0i/chart_with_the_approximate_falcon_9_landing/">collected the locations of Falcon 9 landings</a> and made the plot below. Looking at just the green landing locations on land (in order to remove the extra error from landing on a moving droneship), they tend to land in approximately a 5-10 meter wide area (the large yellow circle on the landing zone is ~20 meters wide).</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="940" height="741" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png?resize=940%2C741&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png?resize=940%2C741&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png?resize=580%2C457&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png?resize=768%2C606&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-9.png?w=1107&amp;ssl=1 1107w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a></figure></div>


<p>However, Falcon 9 has several disadvantages relative to the Super Heavy booster:</p>



<ul>
<li>It does not have separate landing propellant tanks, so propellant slosh will disturb its trajectory. The Super Heavy booster has <a data-type="link" data-id="https://ringwatchers.com/article/booster-prop-distribution" href="https://ringwatchers.com/article/booster-prop-distribution">dedicated central header tanks</a> for landing propellant, so there should be minimal propellant slosh to disturb the vehicle attitude.</li>



<li>It lands with a single engine which cannot throttle low enough to hover the vehicle, and as such must perform a “hoverslam” maneuver to bring the vehicle to a stop right on the ground. While the Super Heavy booster must perform most of a hoverslam maneuver to slow down just before coming in to the tower, it can hover for the final fine positioning.</li>



<li>Because it lands with a single engine, roll control is minimal close to touchdown when the airspeed is low and the grid fins can impart minimal torque, and is limited to its weaker cold-gas thrusters. The Super Heavy booster can control roll with its 3 engines all the way to the ground.</li>



<li>Falcon 9 has no engine-out capability for landing. SpaceX has not confirmed it for the Super Heavy booster, but I believe one engine out is likely possible (more on this later).</li>



<li>It is smaller with a lower moment of inertia. Rockets get more stable and easier to control the larger they are, much like it’s easier to balance a broom on your finger than a pencil.</li>



<li>It is smaller, and so thanks to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Square%E2%80%93cube_law#:~:text=The%20square%E2%80%93cube%20law%20can,the%20cube%20of%20the%20multiplier." data-type="link" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Square%E2%80%93cube_law#:~:text=The%20square%E2%80%93cube%20law%20can,the%20cube%20of%20the%20multiplier.">cubed-square law</a> has a higher area:mass ratio. This means that it will be more affected by wind gusts that might blow it off course.</li>
</ul>



<p>All this to say that the Super Heavy booster should be easier to control precisely than Falcon 9, and its landings more accurate than a ±2.5 meter range.</p>



<h5><strong>How Accurate Does SpaceX Need Position To Be?</strong></h5>



<p>Pulling from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ub6HdADut50" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ub6HdADut50">Ryan Hansen’s excellent video</a> where he modeled and simulated the Super Heavy catch system, the below arc is the feasible catch zone for the booster. This area is 22 m at its narrowest point, and needs to fit a 9 m booster in it, so this allows for ± 6.5m of side-to-side error. The catch arm area is 18 m long, so call that ± 9 m of front-to-back accuracy required.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="940" height="526" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8.png?resize=940%2C526&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8.png?resize=940%2C526&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8.png?resize=580%2C324&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8.png?resize=768%2C430&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-8.png?w=1253&amp;ssl=1 1253w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a></figure></div>


<p>This side-to-side error range does assume that the catch arms can still close around the booster if it is off-center – can the tower can adjust the arm positions in real time so it doesn’t knock into one side of the rocket first and push it over? In the video below it certainly looks like this is the case. The left arm moves first and we see them come in at different speeds to keep centered around the booster in real time. They start moving before the rocket is between the arms, so I don’t expect this is being controlled by tower sensors such as radars mounted on the arms.</p>



<figure><p><iframe title="TOWER CAM! SpaceX Super Heavy Booster Catch" width="1200" height="675" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JlcrNakUGVs?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></figure>



<p>Vertical distance is likely to be the most constrained. If the engines shut off several meters above the arms, the booster would hit with quite a bit of force and in the worst case may bounce back off. There are pistons on the catch rails that could allow for damping out the impact from a dropped booster, but you still want to avoid this. The way to mitigate this is to center the booster in the right spot and then drop down slowly at a speed which you know is manageable for a successful catch. This is what we see SpaceX do. The limiter here becomes fuel – dropping at a steady speed burns as much as hovering. If you are dropping at 1 m/s, can you do that for 5 seconds? It’s not clear how much fuel margin SpaceX has here. The engines turns off immediately after contact, but that may have been because contact was detected, and SpaceX had more fuel margin to go. With a lot of uncertainty here, let’s ballpark a 5 meter tall box for a range of ±2.5m.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="940" height="527" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=940%2C527&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=940%2C527&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=580%2C325&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=768%2C430&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=1536%2C861&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=2048%2C1148&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?resize=800%2C450&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-3.png?w=2400&amp;ssl=1 2400w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a></figure></div>


<h5><strong>Position Summary</strong></h5>



<p>With standard consumer grade GPS, SpaceX can localize its rocket to within 2.5 meters. Using SBAS which would require no extra complexity, that shrinks to 1.2 meters. To get more accurate than that, they would need to have a communications link between the rocket and a base station on the pad. Using RTK for this they could get as accurate as 2.5 cm, but this adds complexity to the system. On top of this will be several centimeters of hardware offsets due to manufacturing tolerances and thermal effect. On the other hand, the allowable error box is roughly ± 6.5, 9 and 2.5 (?) meters large, for safety margins of 2-8x. This is a little low for a test flight – if I were SpaceX I would try to use RTK or DGPS to make the margins larger, but would also feel good that the simpler system could work as backup. This may also suggest that radar is still being used for vertical accuracy.</p>



<p>Going off of Falcon 9 landing history, that rocket consistently lands within a ±2.5 – 5 meter area. However I would expect the Super Heavy booster to be easier to control for a number of reasons.</p>



<p>One reason that the landing looks so precise is simply that everything is so big, and GPS accuracy doesn’t change with scale. We aren’t surprised when a consumer drone flies back to us autonomously using GPS and lands on the grass at our feet, and this rocket is using the same underlying technology. It’s just that 1 meter error looks really small when your booster is 71 meters tall.</p>



<h2>Controlling Orientation / Attitude</h2>



<h5><strong>How Accurately Can SpaceX Measure Attitude?</strong></h5>



<p>Without a device that measures absolute attitude such as a star tracker, the angular orientation of a rocket will be reliant on measuring angular velocity with its onboard gryoscopes, which is then integrated up into angular position relative to the launch orientation. </p>



<p>The Super Heavy booster landing back in the chopsticks 7 minutes after launch is short enough that you don’t need a very good gyro at all to stay pointed well. Without digging too deep into the details of Allan Deviance, <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC10490716/">the MEMS gryo</a> in an iPhone XR has an angular bias of 27 deg/hr, and s Pixel 7 Pro is 10x more accurate at 1.9 deg/hr. Over 7 minutes, that is an error of 3.2 deg and 0.2 deg respectively. And that’s just using the cheap gyro in your phone! SpaceX is probably using <a href="https://aerospace.honeywell.com/us/en/products-and-services/product/hardware-and-systems/sensors/inertial-measurement-units">a nicer “tactical grade” MEMS gyro</a> with 10x more stability at ~0.25 deg/hr (0.03 deg over 7 minutes), or all the way to “navigation grade” ring laser gyros, which can be 100x more accurate that that. This analysis is very rough, and linear error accumulation ignores other sources of error such as scale factors, bias instability, temperature sensitivity, and G-loading sensitivity. But it also ignores fancier sensor fusion techniques you can use by combining multiple sensors, as well as calibration techniques. So it’s a good order-of-magnitude look.</p>



<p>Perhaps surprisingly, I expect that this error will be dominated by the measurement error of the initial orientation. Ensuring that the rocket is perfectly vertical can be a surprisingly tricky problem. You can measure exterior markers using laser range finding, and you can measure the local gravity vector using accelerometer measurements. But how do you account for mechanical strain under propellant load and thermal contraction which might change the orientation of the IMU during fill operations, and throughout flight? How do you account for mechanical machining tolerances where surfaces are not manufactured perfectly flat and change the static mounting orientation of the IMU relative to other components? Will that thermal deformation be symmetric, or tend to tilt your IMU one way or another? These effects and more can be measured and analyzed, but never perfectly compensated for, especially with very little flight history. I do still expect that the error here will be well under 1 deg.</p>



<figure><p><iframe title="ONBOARD CAM! SpaceX Super Heavy Booster Catch" width="1200" height="675" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ExV6PHRM8eI?start=15&amp;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></figure>



<h5><strong>How Accurately Can SpaceX Control Attitude?</strong></h5>



<p>This can also get arbitrarily precise. Based on eyeballing their Falcon 9 landings, I would guess that SpaceX can definitely control landing attitude to well under 1 degree of error in each of its pitch/yaw/roll axes. The Super Heavy trajectory divert just before landing from a safe impact location to the chopsticks is a much more dynamic maneuver than Falcon 9’s landing, but for much the same reasons as its better position accuracy I would expect better attitude control on the Super Heavy booster.</p>



<p>But again, a full accounting here must be downstream of flight simulations which take into account dynamics and uncertainties.</p>



<h5>How Accurate Does SpaceX Need Attitude To Be?</h5>



<p><strong>Roll</strong>: Pulling from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ub6HdADut50" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ub6HdADut50">Ryan Hansen’s video</a> again, he estimates that there is ±9 deg of baseline roll tolerance to safely catch the pins on the catch rails, and this expands to ±15 deg with moderate compression of the foam padding that hugs the booster core.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="940" height="529" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=940%2C529&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=940%2C529&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=580%2C326&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=768%2C432&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=1536%2C864&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=2048%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?resize=800%2C450&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-13-151637-1.png?w=2400&amp;ssl=1 2400w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a></figure></div>


<p><strong>Pitch</strong>: The head of the pin has a ball joint that connects it to its support structure, and allows it to pivot a bit to accommodate angular error in pitch and yaw. Pitch is the direction of travel as the booster flies in towards the launch mounts and the most dynamic. But it appears that the booster flies to a point a bit above the launch pins, and then lowers itself vertically down. So the dynamic movements should largely be done prior to catch. Any error in the pitch direction would potentially cause the booster to “swing” back and forth towards the tower once it landed, but I don’t see anything inherently wrong with this from a structural perspective. From measuring the booster on the chopsticks, there is likely at least 15 degrees of swing towards the tower that could be accommodated without hitting it.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="940" height="528" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=940%2C528&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=940%2C528&amp;ssl=1 940w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=580%2C326&amp;ssl=1 580w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=768%2C431&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=1536%2C863&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=2048%2C1150&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?resize=800%2C450&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-1.png?w=2400&amp;ssl=1 2400w" sizes="(max-width: 940px) 100vw, 940px"></a></figure></div>

<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="530" height="593" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-2.png?resize=530%2C593&amp;ssl=1" alt=""></a></figure></div>


<p><strong>Yaw</strong>: I think this is likely the angle with the tightest tolerance. Over a roughly 10 meter pin-to-pin distance, every 1 degree of yaw error will result in a 17 cm vertical offset with one pin hitting a catch arm before the other. The catch rails are mounted on pistons which can move vertically by about 85 cm. These could be meant for shock absorption, or they could be meant to differentially lower during a landing event with high yaw. With 85 cm of travel distance, these could offset exactly 5 deg of yaw error – a suspiciously nice number if I put my design requirements hat on!</p>



<p>During the first catch attempt the booster was almost perfectly vertical, and we saw hardly any compression of these rails on first touch. They lowered evenly about half a second after the booster had landed and settled on the rail. So there doesn’t seem to be any “baseline” shock absorption happening. Either this is because this was a clean landing and the shock absorption was not needed, or these are primarily for yaw error compensation. If you didn’t compensate for yaw, then you would impart large twisting forces on the catch arm structure with one pin hitting before the other. This can certainly be designed for, but this adds a lot of further mass needed for structural rigidity and my guess is that the SpaceX engineers would much prefer that the arms be evenly loaded.</p>



<p>The other factor helping SpaceX mitigate yaw errors is that the two arms squeezing the booster will tend to push it towards vertical in that axis. You can somewhat see this in the landing video.</p>



<h5>Attitude / Orientation Summary</h5>



<p>I expect that the Super Heavy booster has attitude knowledge and attitude control both well under 1 degree in all axes. I believe the catch requirements are roughly ± 10 deg in roll, ± 15 deg in pitch, and ± 5 deg in yaw. So under a nominal landing without any hardware failures, SpaceX will have a factor of at least 10x performance margin to requirements. </p>



<p>This margin is large enough that I expect attitude on landing is robust to failure of 1 of the 3 landing engines. With one engine out, the other two would only need to gimbal (very roughly) 2 deg to point through the center of mass, and the booster would come in tilted by that angle in pitch / yaw. But this can be handled with still plenty of angular margin. Whether only two engines have enough thrust to set the rocket down softly is another question.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-6.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="626" height="732" src="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-6.png?resize=626%2C732&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-6.png?w=626&amp;ssl=1 626w, https://i0.wp.com/theshamblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/image-6.png?resize=580%2C678&amp;ssl=1 580w" sizes="(max-width: 626px) 100vw, 626px"></a></figure></div>


<h2>Controlling Velocity &amp; Angular Rate</h2>



<h5>Velocity Accuracy</h5>



<p>GPS is much more accurate at measuring velocity than position. Consumer GPS can be accurate to within 1-2 cm/s by measuring the doppler shift of the GPS signal frequency. Perhaps surprisingly, this is about as good as it gets – even going to RTK doesn’t appreciably improve the accuracy of velocity measurements. During a rocket landing, the vibrations and heavy accelerations will likely degrade this a bit. Using the same IMU as above with 0.01 milli-g acceleration drift over 420 seconds, the dead reckoning integrates up to an error of 4.1 cm/s. The numbers here are close enough that likely neither sensor dominates, and a fused approach is used. For example, if the booster can get a GPS reading of velocity at 1 cm/s just before landing burn ignition, the IMU alone could keep the error at about that level for the final 20 seconds of flight.</p>



<h5>Angular Rate Accuracy</h5>



<p>If we dig into the spec sheet for a cheap consumer IMU like the <a data-type="link" data-id="https://invensense.tdk.com/products/motion-tracking/6-axis/icm-42688-p/" href="https://invensense.tdk.com/products/motion-tracking/6-axis/icm-42688-p/">ICM-42688-P</a>, we see ±15.625 deg/s gyro accuracy at 16 bits of precision, for a resolution of 0.0005 deg/s. Scale factors, gryo bias, and temperature effects will worsen the true accuracy, but these can be largely corrected for. Vehicle modes and heavy vibrations will also inject error into the signal, but this can be filtered out. The point is that this is already 100x the accuracy you might need. Since the gyro measures angular rate directly, the error here is bounded and does not integrate up higher. SpaceX will also undoubtedly be using a nicer gyroscope than this.</p>



<h5>Capability &amp; Requirements</h5>



<p>It’s unclear how accurately SpaceX needs to control velocity and angular rate. This will be driven by the strength of the tower and catch arms to accommodate the force of stopping a moving rocket flying into it. True capability here is also hard to estimate since it is such an incredibly dynamic event. Falcon 9 shows us that SpaceX is very good at performing the hoverslam maneuver for a soft touchdown on a hard surface, and for the same reasons as before the Super Heavy booster should be easier to control. But simulations are again needed to answer this question rigorously, and no one outside SpaceX has all the data needed to do those.</p>



<h2>So What’s the Hard Part?</h2>



<p>SpaceX isn’t using magic to control their rockets. While the size of the booster gives the impression of impossible GNC precision needed to land back in the chopstick arms, it should not come as a surprise that SpaceX actually developed a system with large safety margins using sound engineering principles. They would not have attempted a catch landing without confidence that it could work.</p>



<p>But there’s a large difference between something that could work in theory, and actually work in reality. Spaceflight is such a difficult field of engineering because there is such low margin for failure – a rocket is made up of millions of individual parts, most of which have zero redundancy. The margins in landing position and orientation I look at here only matter if you can get back to the launch pad in the first place. Countless little things could go wrong, and any one of them will end with your rocket blowing up. Gravity is a relentless opponent to fight.</p>



<p>So what do I personally find most impressive about this launch?</p>



<ul>
<li>The real-time solver that generates new reference trajectories to land the booster under hard fuel constraints (SpaceX has a lot of experience with this for Falcon 9, but they are still the only ones who can do this and I remain impressed every time – shoutout to <a href="http://www.larsblackmore.com/index.htm">Lars Blackmore</a>).</li>



<li>The real-time link that seems to exist between the tower and the vehicle during the catch event, which is a new system and would be hard to test.</li>



<li>The speed at which SpaceX is iterating, building, and testing Starship, which blows the rest of the industry out of the water.</li>



<li>The sheer guts it took to risk blowing up the pad during a catch attempt after only one booster touchdown test, in a maneuver that no one has ever done before.</li>



<li>The fact that everything worked first try! There were no unknown unknowns that derailed the catch, no mismatches in configuration tracking with the upgrades rolling into every single vehicle, no engineering assumptions that were too loose, no tricky differences between test and flight, no machining/build errors that would break parts.</li>
</ul>



<p>SpaceX has demonstrated once again that they are performing at the pinnacle of engineering and operational excellence. It seems to me that the question is no longer <em>if </em>Starship will be successful in revolutionizing access to space by slashing launch costs, but <em>when</em>. Hats off to the team for reaching this milestone in such a spectacular fashion, and for sharing the journey so publicly. The videos never get old.</p>



<figure><p><iframe title="SpaceX Starship Flight 5 | Launch &amp; Booster Catch Tracking" width="1200" height="675" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/jFpyZHueLWY?start=422&amp;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></figure>





</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intelsat 33e breaks up in geostationary orbit (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spacenews.com/intelsat-33e-loses-power-in-geostationary-orbit/</link>
            <guid>41904346</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 14:09:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spacenews.com/intelsat-33e-loses-power-in-geostationary-orbit/">https://spacenews.com/intelsat-33e-loses-power-in-geostationary-orbit/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41904346">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="content">
		<main id="main">
													

									<div>

				
				
			<figure>

				<img width="879" height="485" src="https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Epic-satellite-Boeing.jpg?fit=879%2C485&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-hero-candidate="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Epic-satellite-Boeing.jpg?w=879&amp;ssl=1 879w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Epic-satellite-Boeing.jpg?resize=300%2C166&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Epic-satellite-Boeing.jpg?resize=768%2C424&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Epic-satellite-Boeing.jpg?resize=400%2C221&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/Epic-satellite-Boeing.jpg?fit=879%2C485&amp;ssl=1&amp;w=370 370w" sizes="(max-width: 879px) 100vw, 879px">			<figcaption><span>An artist's concept of a Boeing-built Intelsat EpicNG satellite.  <span><span>Credit:</span> Boeing</span></span></figcaption>
			
			</figure><!-- .post-thumbnail -->

		

<article id="post-507397">
	<div>

		
		<p>TAMPA, Fla. —&nbsp;The Intelsat 33e satellite has broken up in geostationary orbit (GEO) and lost power, ceasing communications services for customers across Europe, Africa and parts of Asia Pacific.

</p><p>Intelsat said in an Oct. 19 news release it is working with satellite maker Boeing to address an anomaly that emerged earlier that day, but “believe it is unlikely that the satellite will be recoverable.” An Intelsat spokesperson said the satellite was not insured at the time of the issue.

</p><p>The U.S. Space Force reported Oct. 19 it is tracking around 20 pieces of debris associated with the spacecraft.

</p><p>“U.S. Space Forces-Space (S4S) has confirmed the breakup of Intelsat 33E (#41748, 2016-053B) in GEO on October 19, 2024, at approximately 0430 UTC,” <a href="https://www.space-track.org/">states an alert posted on SpaceTrack</a>, the U.S. Department of Defense’s space-tracking platform.&nbsp;

</p><p>“Currently tracking around 20 associated pieces – analysis ongoing. S4S has observed no immediate threats and is continuing to conduct routine conjunction assessments to support the safety and sustainability of the space domain.”

</p><p>Douglas Hendrix, CEO of ExoAnalytic Solutions, said the U.S.-based space-tracking company identified 57 pieces of debris Oct. 21 associated with the breakup.

</p>

<p>“We are warning operators of any spacecraft that we think are at risk of collision,” Hendrix said via email.

</p><figure><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="780" height="585" src="https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=780%2C585&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=300%2C225&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=768%2C576&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=1536%2C1152&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=1200%2C900&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=800%2C600&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=600%2C450&amp;ssl=1 600w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=400%2C300&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=200%2C150&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=1568%2C1176&amp;ssl=1 1568w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?resize=706%2C530&amp;ssl=1 706w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1.jpeg?w=2048&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/1729433737373-1-1024x768.jpeg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w" sizes="(max-width: 780px) 100vw, 780px"><figcaption><br>A snapshot of Intelsat 33e’s break-up taken Oct. 19 by U.K.-based Spaceflux. 44071 and 58698 are the WGS 10 (USA 291) and Ovzon-3 satellites, respectively, which Spaceflux said are unlikely in danger of being hit by the debris. “The problem is that there is a lot of uncertainty regarding the orbits of these fragments at the moment,” Spaceflux spokesperson Viktoria Urban said Oct. 21. “They can be potentially dangerous for other satellites but we do not know that yet.” Credit: Spaceflux.</figcaption></figure><p>Intelsat said it is working to move customers to other satellites in Intelsat’s fleet or spacecraft operated by third parties.

</p><p>Intelsat 33e launched in August 2016 and entered service in January 2017 at 60 degrees East, about three months later than planned following an issue with its primary thruster.

</p><p>A second propulsion issue that emerged during in-orbit tests helped <a href="https://spacenews.com/intelsat-33e-propulsion-problems-to-cut-service-life-by-3-5-years/">knock off around 3.5 years</a> from the satellite’s initially estimated 15-year lifespan.

</p><p>Intelsat 33e is the second in Intelsat’s EpicNG (next-generation) series of high-throughput satellites.

</p><p>The first, Intelsat-29e, was <a href="https://spacenews.com/intelsat-29e-declared-a-total-loss/">declared a total loss in 2019</a> after just three years in orbit. That failure was pinned on either a meteoroid impact or a wiring flaw that led to an electrostatic discharge following heightened solar weather activity.

</p><p><em>This article was updated Oct. 21 with more details about the incident.</em>


</p>	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->

	<div>
									<p><a href="https://spacenews.com/author/jason-rainbow/" rel="author">
						<img width="80" height="80" src="https://spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Jason-Rainbow-150x150.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Jason-Rainbow.jpg?resize=150%2C150&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Jason-Rainbow.jpg?resize=300%2C300&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Jason-Rainbow.jpg?w=400&amp;ssl=1 400w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Jason-Rainbow.jpg?resize=200%2C200&amp;ssl=1 200w, https://i0.wp.com/spacenews.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Jason-Rainbow-150x150.jpg?w=370&amp;ssl=1 370w">					</a></p><div>
					<!-- .author-bio-header -->

											<p>
							Jason Rainbow writes about satellite telecom, space finance and commercial markets for SpaceNews. He has spent more than a decade covering the global space industry as a business journalist. Previously, he was Group Editor-in-Chief for Finance Information...							<a href="https://spacenews.com/author/jason-rainbow/" rel="author">
							More by Jason Rainbow							</a>
						</p>
					
				</div><!-- .author-bio-text -->

			</div><!-- .author-bios -->

</article><!-- #post-${ID} -->



				</div><!-- .main-content -->

			
<!-- #secondary -->

		</main><!-- #main -->
	</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Epublifier – scrape pages (books, manuals) for offline reading (211 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier</link>
            <guid>41903864</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 13:18:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier">https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41903864">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Epublifier</h2><a id="user-content-epublifier" aria-label="Permalink: Epublifier" href="#epublifier"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Converts websites into epub.</p>
<p dir="auto">A tool that allows you to extract a list of html pages from a website and compile them into an ePub book to be imported into your eReader of choice.</p>
<p dir="auto">For advanced users who can write javascript, you can add additional parser definition to customize parsing of any site.</p>
<p dir="auto">Check out the <a href="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/wiki">wiki</a> for usage.</p>
<p dir="auto">Currently supporting following sites:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Novel Update</li>
<li>Wuxia World</li>
<li>Most sites from <a href="https://github.com/readthedocs-examples/awesome-read-the-docs">awesome-read-the-docs</a></li>
<li>Custom sites with UL/OL elements as table of content, or regex on Link text, or use query selector</li>
<li>Custom web app with predefined Title (header) element and Next button (clickable)</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Firefox: <a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/epublifier/" rel="nofollow">https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/epublifier/</a></li>
<li>Chrome: <a href="https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/epublifier/eopjnahefjhnhfanplcjpbbdkpbagikk" rel="nofollow">https://chrome.google.com/webstore/detail/epublifier/eopjnahefjhnhfanplcjpbbdkpbagikk</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example Usage</h2><a id="user-content-example-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Example Usage" href="#example-usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Extracting list of pages</h3><a id="user-content-extracting-list-of-pages" aria-label="Permalink: Extracting list of pages" href="#extracting-list-of-pages"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/blob/develop/docs/nu.gif?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/raw/develop/docs/nu.gif?raw=true" alt="Novel Update" title="List of Pages" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tranversing Webapp through next button</h3><a id="user-content-tranversing-webapp-through-next-button" aria-label="Permalink: Tranversing Webapp through next button" href="#tranversing-webapp-through-next-button"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/blob/develop/docs/wuxiaworld.gif?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/raw/develop/docs/wuxiaworld.gif?raw=true" alt="Wuxia World" title="Next button" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Extracting other documentation</h3><a id="user-content-extracting-other-documentation" aria-label="Permalink: Extracting other documentation" href="#extracting-other-documentation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/blob/develop/docs/fastapi.gif?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/maoserr/epublifier/raw/develop/docs/fastapi.gif?raw=true" alt="FastAPI" title="Documentations" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building</h2><a id="user-content-building" aria-label="Permalink: Building" href="#building"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Build Environment</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Windows 10</li>
<li>NPM version 8.1.2</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Build Steps</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Install NPM</li>
<li>Run <code>npm install</code> in base directory</li>
<li>Run <code>npm run build_ff</code> for Firefox</li>
<li>Run <code>npm run build</code> for Chrome</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">CI/CD</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgements</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgements" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgements" href="#acknowledgements"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://lelinhtinh.github.io/jEpub/" rel="nofollow">jEpub</a></li>
</ol>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Egypt declared malaria-free after 100-year effort (409 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cm2yl8pjgn2o</link>
            <guid>41903616</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 12:51:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cm2yl8pjgn2o">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cm2yl8pjgn2o</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41903616">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>Egypt has been certified malaria-free by the World Health Organization (WHO) - an achievement hailed by the UN public health agency as "truly historic".<!-- --></p><p>“Malaria is as old as Egyptian civilization itself, but the disease that plagued pharaohs now belongs to its history," said WHO chief Tedros Adhanom Ghebreyesus.<!-- --></p><p>Egyptian authorities launched their first efforts to stamp out the deadly mosquito-borne infectious disease nearly 100 years.<!-- --></p><p>Certification is granted when a country proves that the transmission chain is interrupted for at least the previous three consecutive years. Malaria kills at least 600,000 people every year, nearly all of them in Africa.<!-- --></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>In a statement on Sunday, the WHO praised "the Egyptian government and people" for their efforts to "end a disease that has been present in the country since ancient times".<!-- --></p><p>It said Egypt was the third country to be certified in the WHO's Eastern Mediterranean Region, following the United Arab Emirates and Morocco.<!-- --></p><p>Globally, 44 countries and one territory have reached this milestone.<!-- --></p><p>But the WHO said the certification was only "the beginning of a new phase", urging Egypt to be on the alert to preserve its malaria-free status.<!-- --></p><p>To get the WHO certification, a country must demonstrate the capacity to prevent the re-establishment of transmission.<!-- --></p><p>The UN public health agency said first efforts to limit human-mosquito contact in Egypt began in the 1920s when it banned rice cultivation and agricultural crops near homes.<!-- --></p><p>Malaria is caused by a complex parasite which is spread by mosquito bites.<!-- --></p><p>Vaccines are now being used in some places - but monitoring the disease and avoiding mosquito bites are the most effective ways to prevent malaria.<!-- --></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[IOCCC Flight Simulator (2010) (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.aerojockey.com/iocccsim/</link>
            <guid>41903399</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 12:24:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.aerojockey.com/iocccsim/">https://blog.aerojockey.com/iocccsim/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41903399">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-3974" itemprop="blogPost" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">






<div itemprop="text">
	
	
	
<blockquote><p>
Be sure to visit our <a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/Ioccc-Flight-Simulator/165566243463997">Facebook Page</a>.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>The IOCCC Flight Simulator was the winning entry in the 1998 International Obfuscated C Code Contest. It is a flight simulator in under 2 kilobytes of code, complete with relatively accurate 6-degree-of-freedom dynamics, loadable wireframe scenery, and a small instrument panel.</p>



<p>IOCCC Flight Simulator runs on Unix-like systems with X Windows. As per contest rules, it is in the public domain.</p>



<h3>Documentation</h3>



<h4>Introduction</h4>



<p>You have just stepped out of the real world and into the virtual. You are now sitting in the cockpit of a Piper Cherokee airplane, heading north, flying 1000 feet above ground level.</p>



<p>Use the keyboard to fly the airplane. The arrow keys represent the control stick. Press the Up Arrow key to push the stick forward. Press the left arrow key to move the stick left, and so on. Press Enter to re-center the stick. Use Page Up and Page Down increase and decrease the throttle, respectively. (The rudder is automatically coordinated with the turn rate, so rudder pedals are not represented.)</p>



<p>On your display, you will see on the bottom left corner three instruments. The first is the airspeed indicator; it tells you how fast you’re going in knots. The second is the heading indicator, or compass. 0 is north, 90 is east, 180 is south, 270 is west. The third instrument is the altimeter, which measures your height above ground level in feet.</p>



<h4>Usage</h4>



<p>To use, type:</p>



<pre><code>
cat horizon.sc pittsburgh.sc | ./banks
</code>
</pre>



<p>banks is the name of the program (a quirk of IOCCC rules, and no pun intended). horizon.sc and pittsburgh.sc are scenery files.</p>



<h4>Features</h4>



<ul>
<li>Simulator models a Piper Cherokee, which is a light, single-engine, propeller-driven airplane.</li>
<li>The airplane is modeled as a six degree-of-freedom rigid body, accurately reflecting its dynamics (for normal flight conditions, at least).</li>
<li>Fly through a virtual 3-D world, while sitting at your X console.</li>
<li>Loadable scenery files.</li>
<li>Head-up display contains three instruments: a true airspeed indicator, a heading indicator (compass), and an altimeter.</li>
<li>Flight controls may be mapped to any keys at compile time by redefining the macros in the build file. Nice if your keyboard doesn’t have arrow keys.</li>
<li>Time step size can be set at compile time. This is useful to reduce flicker on network X connections. (But be careful: step sizes longer than about 0.03 seconds tend to have numerical stability problems.)</li>
<li>Airplane never stalls!</li>
<li>Airplane never runs out of fuel!</li>
</ul>



<h4>Scenery</h4>



<p>Each of the <cite>*.sc</cite> files is a scenery file. The simulator program reads in the scenery from standard input on startup. You may input more than one scenery file, as long as there are less than 1000 total lines of input.</p>



<p>Here is a brief description of the scenery files:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>horizon.sc</strong> – A horizon, nothing more. You will probably always want to input this piece of scenery.</li>
<li><strong>mountains.sc</strong> – An alternate horizon; a little more mountainous.</li>
<li><strong>pittsburgh.sc</strong> – Scenery of downtown Pittsburgh. The downtown area is initially located to your right.</li>
<li><strong>bb.sc</strong> – Simple obstacle course. Try to fly over the buildings and under the bridges.</li>
<li><strong>pyramids.sc</strong> – Fly over the tombs of the ancient Pharaohs in this (fictitious) Egyptian landscape.</li>
<li><strong>river.sc</strong> – Follow a flowing river from the sky.</li>
</ul>



<p>A few examples of how to input scenery:</p>



<pre><code>
cat horizon.sc pittsburgh.sc | ./banks
cat mountains.sc bb.sc | ./banks
cat mountains.sc river.sc pyramids.sc | ./banks
</code>
</pre>



<p>You can simulate flying through a cloud bank as well:</p>



<pre><code>
./banks &lt; /dev/null
</code>
</pre>



<p>You will usually want at least a horizon, though.</p>



<p>The format of scenery files is simple, by the way. They’re just a list of 3-D coordinates, and the simulator simply draws line segments from point to point as listed in the scenery file. 0 0 0 is used to end a series of consecutive line segments. Note that in the coordinate system used, the third coordinate represents altitude in a negative sense: negative numbers are positive altitudes.</p>



<p>I’m sure you’ll be making your own scenery files very soon!!!</p>



<h4>Alternate Build Instructions</h4>



<p>Several options must be passed to the compiler to make the build work. The provided build file has the appropriate options set to default values. Use this section if you want to compile with different options.</p>



<p>To map a key to a control, you must pass an option to the compiler in the format “-Dcontrol=key”. The possible controls you can map are described in the table below:</p>



<pre><code>
Control  Description           Default Key
-------  --------------------- -----------
IT       Open throttle         XK_Page_Up
DT       Close throttle        XK_Page_Down
FD       Move stick forward    XK_Up
BK       Move stick back       XK_Down
LT       Move stick left       XK_Left
RT       Move stick right      XK_Right
CS       Center stick          XK_Enter
</code>
</pre>



<p>Values for the possible keys can be found in the X Windows header file &lt;X11/keysym.h&gt;. This file is most likely a cross-reference to another header, &lt;X11/keysymdef.h&gt;.</p>



<p>You must map all seven controls to keys at compile time, or the compilation will fail.</p>



<p>For example, to map Center Stick to the space-bar, the compile option would be “-DCS=XK_space”.</p>



<p>To set the time step size, you must pass the following option to the compiler: “-Ddt=duration”, where dt is literal, and where duration is the time in seconds you want the time step to be.</p>



<p>Two things to keep in mind when selecting a time step. Time steps that are too large (more than about 0.03) will cause numerical stability problems and should be avoided. Setting the time step to be smaller than your clock resolution will slow down the simulator, because the system pauses for more time than the simulator expects.</p>



<p>The best advice is to set time step size to your system timer resolution. Try a
longer period if you’re getting too much flicker.</p>



<h3>Screen Shots</h3>



<p>Here we are flying towards Downtown Pittsburgh. We can see the Point, several buildings including the USX tower, and several bridges including the Smithfield Street bridge. We see three instruments near the bottom.</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="415" height="440" src="https://blog.aerojockey.com/wp-content/uploads/ioccc1.gif" alt=""></figure>



<h3>About the IOCCC Entry</h3>



<p>IOCCC stands for “International Obfuscated C Code Contest.” It is an quasi-annual contest to see who can write the most unreadable, unintelligible, unmanagable, but legal C program.</p>



<p>In the 1998 IOCCC, My flight simulator won the “Best of Show” prize. Here is the source code to the program:</p>



<pre><code>
#include                                     &lt;math.h&gt;
#include                                   &lt;sys/time.h&gt;
#include                                   &lt;X11/Xlib.h&gt;
#include                                  &lt;X11/keysym.h&gt;
                                          double L ,o ,P
                                         ,_=dt,T,Z,D=1,d,
                                         s[999],E,h= 8,I,
                                         J,K,w[999],M,m,O
                                        ,n[999],j=33e-3,i=
                                        1E3,r,t, u,v ,W,S=
                                        74.5,l=221,X=7.26,
                                        a,B,A=32.2,c, F,H;
                                        int N,q, C, y,p,U;
                                       Window z; char f[52]
                                    ; GC k; main(){ Display*e=
 XOpenDisplay( 0); z=RootWindow(e,0); for (XSetForeground(e,k=XCreateGC (e,z,0,0),BlackPixel(e,0))
; scanf("%lf%lf%lf",y +n,w+y, y+s)+1; y ++); XSelectInput(e,z= XCreateSimpleWindow(e,z,0,0,400,400,
0,0,WhitePixel(e,0) ),KeyPressMask); for(XMapWindow(e,z); ; T=sin(O)){ struct timeval G={ 0,dt*1e6}
; K= cos(j); N=1e4; M+= H*_; Z=D*K; F+=_*P; r=E*K; W=cos( O); m=K*W; H=K*T; O+=D*_*F/ K+d/K*E*_; B=
sin(j); a=B*T*D-E*W; XClearWindow(e,z); t=T*E+ D*B*W; j+=d*_*D-_*F*E; P=W*E*B-T*D; for (o+=(I=D*W+E
*T*B,E*d/K *B+v+B/K*F*D)*_; p&lt;y; ){ T=p[s]+i; E=c-p[w]; D=n[p]-L; K=D*m-B*T-H*E; if(p [n]+w[ p]+p[s
]== 0|K &lt;fabs(W=T*r-I*E +D*P) |fabs(D=t *D+Z *T-a *E)&gt; K)N=1e4; else{ q=W/K *4E2+2e2; C= 2E2+4e2/ K
 *D; N-1E4&amp;&amp; XDrawLine(e ,z,k,N ,U,q,C); N=q; U=C; } ++p; } L+=_* (X*t +P*M+m*l); T=X*X+ l*l+M *M;
  XDrawString(e,z,k ,20,380,f,17); D=v/l*15; i+=(B *l-M*r -X*Z)*_; for(; XPending(e); u *=CS!=N){
                                   XEvent z; XNextEvent(e ,&amp;z);
                                       ++*((N=XLookupKeysym
                                         (&amp;z.xkey,0))-IT?
                                         N-LT? UP-N?&amp; E:&amp;
                                         J:&amp; u: &amp;h); --*(
                                         DN -N? N-DT ?N==
                                         RT?&amp;u: &amp; W:&amp;h:&amp;J
                                          ); } m=15*F/l;
                                          c+=(I=M/ l,l*H
                                          +I*M+a*X)*_; H
                                          =A*r+v*X-F*l+(
                                          E=.1+X*4.9/l,t
                                          =T*m/32-I*T/24
                                           )/S; K=F*M+(
                                           h* 1e4/l-(T+
                                           E*5*T*E)/3e2
                                           )/S-X*d-B*A;
                                           a=2.63 /l*d;
                                           X+=( d*l-T/S
                                            *(.19*E +a
                                            *.64+J/1e3
                                            )-M* v +A*
                                            Z)*_; l +=
                                            K *_; W=d;
                                            sprintf(f,
                                            "%5d  %3d"
                                            "%7d",p =l
                                           /1.7,(C=9E3+
                              O*57.3)%0550,(int)i); d+=T*(.45-14/l*
                             X-a*130-J* .14)*_/125e2+F*_*v; P=(T*(47
                             *I-m* 52+E*94 *D-t*.38+u*.21*E) /1e2+W*
                             179*v)/2312; select(p=0,0,0,0,&amp;G); v-=(
                              W*F-T*(.63*m-I*.086+m*E*19-D*25-.11*u
                               )/107e2)*_; D=cos(o); E=sin(o); } }
</code>
</pre>



<p>Note that this program will not compile out-of-the-box. It requires certain compile-time parameters. The folloing script builds it on my Linux system:</p>



<pre><code>
#! /bin/sh
cc banks.c -o banks -DIT=XK_Page_Up -DDT=XK_Page_Down \
        -DUP=XK_Up -DDN=XK_Down -DLT=XK_Left -DRT=XK_Right \
        -DCS=XK_Return -Ddt=0.02 -lm -lX11 -L/usr/X11R6/lib
</code>
</pre>



<p>If you want to try this program, I suggest you download the <a href="http://www0.us.ioccc.org/years.html#1998">1998 IOCCC Winners Distribution</a>.</p>



<p>One of the rules of the contest was that the program could not be longer than 1536 bytes (excluding spaces, tabs, newlines, semicolons, and braces). Needless to say, cramming a flight simulator into such a small file was fairly difficult. I will say that if it weren’t for the wonderful property of orthogonal matrices, this flight simulator would not have been possible.</p>



<h3>Sightings</h3>



<ul>
<li>The IOCCC Simulator appeared in a book, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/exec/obidos/tg/detail/-/0521009626/103-3242838-6683018?vi=glance">Calculated Bets</a> by Steve Skiena.</li>
<li>Wikipedia has a listing of IOCCC Simluator in its <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/International_Obfuscated_C_Code_Contest">IOCCC Entry</a>.</li>
</ul>



<h3>Links</h3>



<ul>
<li>The official <a href="http://www0.us.ioccc.org/">International Obfuscated C Code Contest</a> website</li>
<li>IOCCC Flight Simulator’s <a href="http://www.facebook.com/pages/Ioccc-Flight-Simulator/165566243463997">Facebook page</a>.  (I made this page because random people around the world would send me friend requests and it was creeping me out.)</li>
</ul>



<h3>Downloads</h3>



<p>I do not distribute this program myself. If you want it, you can download the <a href="http://www0.us.ioccc.org/years.html#1998">1998 IOCCC Winners Distribution</a>. The distribution comes with a dozen or so other winning entries, all quite interesting programs.</p>



<p>Note that this is a source distribution, and you will have compile it to run it. I’ve tested it on some versions of Linux, AIX, Irix, and Sun.</p>



<p>IOCCC Flight Simulator source code is in the public domain; there are no copyright restrictions on it whatsoever. However, the winners distribution has been copyrighted by the IOCCC judges. See the hint files in the distribution for details.</p>

	
	
	
	</div>




</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Erin – Open-source and self-hosted TikTok feed for your own videos (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/will-moss/erin</link>
            <guid>41902407</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 09:51:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/will-moss/erin">https://github.com/will-moss/erin</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41902407">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Erin</h2><a id="user-content-erin" aria-label="Permalink: Erin" href="#erin"></a></p>
    <p dir="auto">
      Self-hostable TikTok feed for your clips
      <br>
      Make a TikTok feed with your own videos
   </p>

<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/blob/master/screenshots/SCREENSHOT-1.png"><img width="1604" src="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/raw/master/screenshots/SCREENSHOT-1.png"></a></td>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/blob/master/screenshots/SCREENSHOT-2.png"><img width="1604" src="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/raw/master/screenshots/SCREENSHOT-2.png"></a></td>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/blob/master/screenshots/SCREENSHOT-3.png"><img width="1604" src="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/raw/master/screenshots/SCREENSHOT-3.png"></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h2><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Erin is a simple and self-hostable service that enables you to view your own clips using TikTok's well-known vertical swipe feed.
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/1dogl9d/selfhost_a_site_for_short_videos_like_tiktok/" rel="nofollow">A request was made on Reddit</a>
for a self-hostable app that can show filtered videos using TikTok's interface, so I made it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Erin has all these features implemented :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Display your own videos using TikTok's swipe feed</li>
<li>Mask the videos you don't want to see in your feed*</li>
<li>Choose which feed you want to play**</li>
<li>Autoplay your feed without even swiping</li>
<li>Seek forward and backward using your keyboard, or using double taps</li>
<li>Show video metadata using TikTok's UI***</li>
<li>Simple lazy-loading mechanism for your videos</li>
<li>Automatic clip naming based on file name</li>
<li>Simple and optional security using a master password</li>
<li>Support for HTTP and HTTPS</li>
<li>Support for Docker / proxy deployment</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">On top of these, please note that Erin is only a React app powered entirely by <a href="https://github.com/caddyserver/caddy">Caddy</a>.
Caddy takes care of authentication, serving static files, and serving the React app all at once.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">*: You can mask videos to hide them from your feed. Should you want to see which videos were masked, and even unmask them, you can long-press the <code>Mask</code> button, and the manager will open.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">**: By default, Erin will create a random feed from all the videos in your folder and its subdirectories. However, if you would like to create custom feeds, you can set your URL to any of the subdirectories path. For example: <code>https://my-server.tld/directory-a</code> will create a feed from the videos located in the <code>/directory-a</code> directory, and it works with any path (so, nested folders are supported).</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">***: You can show a channel (with an avatar and name), a caption and a link for all your videos using a metadata file. The metadata file can be located anywhere inside your videos folder, and it must match its associated video's filename, while replacing the extension with JSON. For example: <code>my-video.mp4</code> can have its metadata in <code>my-video.json</code>. The metadata format <a href="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/blob/master/examples/video-metadata.json">is shown here</a>, and note that you can use raw HTML in the caption for custom styling and effects.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">For more information, read about <a href="#configuration">Configuration</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Deployment and Examples</h2><a id="user-content-deployment-and-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Deployment and Examples" href="#deployment-and-examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Before proceeding, regardless of Docker, Docker Compose, or a standalone deployment, please make sure
that you have created a <code>videos</code> directory containing all your video files. Later on, this directory will
be made available to your instance of Erin (by binding a volume to your Docker container, or putting the directory
next to your Caddyfile).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Deploy with Docker</h3><a id="user-content-deploy-with-docker" aria-label="Permalink: Deploy with Docker" href="#deploy-with-docker"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can run Erin with Docker on the command line very quickly.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can use the following commands :</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Create a .env file
touch .env

# Edit .env file ...

# Option 1 : Run Erin attached to the terminal (useful for debugging)
docker run --env-file .env -p <YOUR-PORT-MAPPING> -v ./videos:/srv/videos:ro mosswill/erin

# Option 2 : Run Erin as a daemon
docker run -d --env-file .env -p <YOUR-PORT-MAPPING> -v ./videos:/srv/videos:ro mosswill/erin"><pre><span><span>#</span> Create a .env file</span>
touch .env

<span><span>#</span> Edit .env file ...</span>

<span><span>#</span> Option 1 : Run Erin attached to the terminal (useful for debugging)</span>
docker run --env-file .env -p <span>&lt;</span>YOUR-PORT-MAPPING<span>&gt;</span> -v ./videos:/srv/videos:ro mosswill/erin

<span><span>#</span> Option 2 : Run Erin as a daemon</span>
docker run -d --env-file .env -p <span>&lt;</span>YOUR-PORT-MAPPING<span>&gt;</span> -v ./videos:/srv/videos:ro mosswill/erin</pre></div>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note :</strong> A <code>sample.env</code> file is located at the root of the repository to help you get started</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note :</strong> When using <code>docker run --env-file</code>, make sure to remove the quotes around <code>AUTH_ENABLED</code> and <code>AUTH_SECRET</code>, or else
your container might crash due to unexpected interpolation and type conversions operated by Docker behind the scenes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Deploy with Docker Compose</h3><a id="user-content-deploy-with-docker-compose" aria-label="Permalink: Deploy with Docker Compose" href="#deploy-with-docker-compose"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To help you get started quickly, a few example <code>docker-compose</code> files are located in the <a href="https://github.com/will-moss/erin/blob/master/examples">"examples/"</a> directory.</p>
<p dir="auto">Here's a description of every example :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><code>docker-compose.simple.yml</code>: Run Erin as a front-facing service on port 443, with environment variables supplied in the <code>docker-compose</code> file directly.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><code>docker-compose.proxy.yml</code>: A setup with Erin running on port 80, behind a proxy listening on port 443.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">When your <code>docker-compose</code> file is on point, you can use the following commands :</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Run Erin in the current terminal (useful for debugging)
docker-compose up

# Run Erin in a detached terminal (most common)
docker-compose up -d

# Show the logs written by Erin (useful for debugging)
docker logs <NAME-OF-YOUR-CONTAINER>"><pre><span><span>#</span> Run Erin in the current terminal (useful for debugging)</span>
docker-compose up

<span><span>#</span> Run Erin in a detached terminal (most common)</span>
docker-compose up -d

<span><span>#</span> Show the logs written by Erin (useful for debugging)</span>
docker logs <span>&lt;</span>NAME-OF-YOUR-CONTAINER<span>&gt;</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: Configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To run Erin, you will need to set the following environment variables in a <code>.env</code> file :</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note :</strong> Regular environment variables provided on the commandline work too</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note :</strong> A <code>sample.env</code> file is located at the root of the repository to help you get started</p>
</blockquote>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Parameter</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Default</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>PUBLIC_URL</code></td>
<td><code>boolean</code></td>
<td>The public URL used to remotely access your instance of Erin. (Please include HTTP / HTTPS and the port if not standard 80 or 443. Do not include a trailing slash) (Read the <a href="https://caddyserver.com/docs/caddyfile/concepts#addresses" rel="nofollow">official Caddy documentation</a>)</td>
<td><a href="https://localhost/" rel="nofollow">https://localhost</a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>AUTH_ENABLED</code></td>
<td><code>string</code></td>
<td>Whether Basic Authentication should be enabled. (This parameter is case sensitive) (Possible values : true, false)</td>
<td>true</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>AUTH_SECRET</code></td>
<td><code>string</code></td>
<td>The secure hash of the password used to protect your instance of Erin.</td>
<td>Hash of <code>secure-password</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>APP_TITLE</code></td>
<td><code>string</code></td>
<td>The custom title that you would like to display in the browser's tab. (Tip: You can use <code>[VIDEO_TITLE]</code> here if you want Erin to dynamically display the title of the current video.)</td>
<td>Erin - TikTok feed for your own clips</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>AUTOPLAY_ENABLED</code></td>
<td><code>boolean</code></td>
<td>Whether autoplay should be enabled. (This parameter is case sensitive) (Possible values : true, false)</td>
<td>false</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>PROGRESS_BAR_POSITION</code></td>
<td><code>string</code></td>
<td>Where the progress bar should be located on the screen. (This parameter is case sensitive) (Possible values : bottom, top)</td>
<td>bottom</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Tip :</strong> To generate a secure hash for your instance, use the following command :</p>
</blockquote>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="docker run caddy caddy hash-password --plaintext &quot;your-new-password&quot;"><pre>docker run caddy caddy hash-password --plaintext <span><span>"</span>your-new-password<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note :</strong> When using <code>docker-compose.yml</code> environment variables, if your password hash contains dollar signs: double them all, or else the app will crash.
For example : <code>$ab$cd$efxyz</code> becomes <code>$$ab$$cd$$efxyz</code>. This is due to caveats with <code>docker-compose</code> string interpolation system.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Troubleshoot</h2><a id="user-content-troubleshoot" aria-label="Permalink: Troubleshoot" href="#troubleshoot"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Should you encounter any issue running Erin, please refer to the following common problems that may occur.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">If none of these matches your case, feel free to open an issue.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Erin is unreachable over HTTP / HTTPS</h4><a id="user-content-erin-is-unreachable-over-http--https" aria-label="Permalink: Erin is unreachable over HTTP / HTTPS" href="#erin-is-unreachable-over-http--https"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Erin sits on top of a Caddy web server.</p>
<p dir="auto">As a result :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>You may be able to better troubleshoot the issue by reading your container logs.</li>
<li>You can check the <a href="https://caddyserver.com/docs/caddyfile/concepts#addresses" rel="nofollow">official Caddy documentation regarding addresses</a>.</li>
<li>You can check the <a href="https://caddyserver.com/docs/automatic-https" rel="nofollow">official Caddy documentation regarding HTTPS</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Other than that, please make sure that the following requirements are met :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">If Erin runs as a standalone application without proxy :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Make sure your server / firewall accepts incoming connections on Erin's port.</li>
<li>Make sure your DNS configuration is correct. (Usually, such record should suffice : <code>A erin XXX.XXX.XXX.XXX</code> for <code>https://erin.your-server-tld</code>)</li>
<li>Make sure your <code>.env</code> file is well configured according to the <a href="#configuration">Configuration</a> section.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">If Erin runs inside Docker / behind a proxy :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Perform the previous (standalone) verifications first.</li>
<li>Make sure that <code>PUBLIC_URL</code> is well set in <code>.env</code>.</li>
<li>Check your proxy forwarding rules.</li>
<li>Check your Docker networking setup.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">In any case, the crucial part is <a href="#configuration">Configuration</a> and reading the official Caddy documentation.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Erin says that no video was found on my server</h4><a id="user-content-erin-says-that-no-video-was-found-on-my-server" aria-label="Permalink: Erin says that no video was found on my server" href="#erin-says-that-no-video-was-found-on-my-server"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For Erin to serve your video files, those must respect the following requirements :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>The file extension is one of <code>.mp4</code>, <code>.ogg</code>, <code>.webm</code>. (There are the only extensions supported by web browsers.)</li>
<li>The files are located in <code>/srv/videos</code> on your Docker container using a volume.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To make sure that your videos are inside your Docker container and in the right place, you can :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Run <code>docker exec -it &lt;NAME-OF-YOUR-CONTAINER&gt; sh</code></li>
<li>Inside the newly-opened shell, run : <code>ls /srv/videos</code></li>
<li>You should see your video files here. If not, then check your volume-binding.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If Erin is still unable to find your videos despite everything being well-configured, please open an issue
including the output of your browser's Javascript console and network tab when the request goes to <code>/media/</code>.
It may have to do with browser-caching, invalid configuration, or invalid credentials.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How can I add new videos to my feed?</h4><a id="user-content-how-can-i-add-new-videos-to-my-feed" aria-label="Permalink: How can I add new videos to my feed?" href="#how-can-i-add-new-videos-to-my-feed"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For now, you should just put your new video files into your videos directory that is mounted with Docker.
Erin will automatically pick up these new files, and when you refresh your browser you'll see them.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How should I name my video files?</h4><a id="user-content-how-should-i-name-my-video-files" aria-label="Permalink: How should I name my video files?" href="#how-should-i-name-my-video-files"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Erin will automatically translate your file name into a title to display on the interface.</p>
<p dir="auto">The conversion operated is as follows :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>-</code> becomes <code> </code></li>
<li><code>__</code> becomes <code>-</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Here's a few examples to help you name your files :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>Vegas-trip__Clip-1.mp4</code> becomes <code>Vegas trip - Clip 1</code></li>
<li><code>Spanish-language__Lesson-1.mp4</code> becomes <code>Spanish language - Lesson 1</code></li>
<li><code>Spiderman-1.ogg</code> becomes <code>Spiderman 1</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">In what order will my files appear in the feed?</h4><a id="user-content-in-what-order-will-my-files-appear-in-the-feed" aria-label="Permalink: In what order will my files appear in the feed?" href="#in-what-order-will-my-files-appear-in-the-feed"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Erin randomly shuffles your video files on every browser refresh.</p>
<p dir="auto">As a result, there is no specific order for your videos to appear.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Some of my videos seem to be missing or not loaded at all</h4><a id="user-content-some-of-my-videos-seem-to-be-missing-or-not-loaded-at-all" aria-label="Permalink: Some of my videos seem to be missing or not loaded at all" href="#some-of-my-videos-seem-to-be-missing-or-not-loaded-at-all"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For now, Erin will only attempt to retrieve the videos that have a supported extension.</p>
<p dir="auto">Supported extensions are : <code>.webm</code>, <code>.mp4</code>, and <code>.ogg</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">However, please note that Safari doesn't seem to support <code>.ogg</code>, hence these videos will be ignored for Safari users.</p>
<p dir="auto">Should you have any advice or idea to support more extensions (especially for Safari users), please feel free to open an issue.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">My custom password doesn't work</h4><a id="user-content-my-custom-password-doesnt-work" aria-label="Permalink: My custom password doesn't work" href="#my-custom-password-doesnt-work"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">There seems to be a few caveats when using Docker / Docker Compose with Caddy-generated password hashes.</p>
<p dir="auto">These are the rules you should follow :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>If you deployed Erin using the Docker CLI, via the command <code>docker run ... --env-file .env ...</code>, then your <code>AUTH_SECRET</code> should have no quote at all, and all the dollar signs should stay as they are without escape or doubling</li>
<li>If you deployed Erin using Docker Compose, via a <code>docker-compose.yml</code> file, then your <code>AUTH_SECRET</code> should have its dollar signs doubled. Example : <code>i$am$groot</code> becomes <code>i$$am$$groot</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">That said, remember that your password hash must be generated with the following command :</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="docker run caddy caddy hash-password --plaintext &quot;your-new-password&quot;"><pre>docker run caddy caddy hash-password --plaintext <span><span>"</span>your-new-password<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Something else</h4><a id="user-content-something-else" aria-label="Permalink: Something else" href="#something-else"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please feel free to open an issue, explaining what happens, and describing your environment.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Credits</h2><a id="user-content-credits" aria-label="Permalink: Credits" href="#credits"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Hey hey ! It's always a good idea to say thank you and mention the people and projects that help us move forward.</p>
<p dir="auto">Big thanks to the individuals / teams behind these projects :</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/cauemustafa/tik-tok-clone">tik-tok-clone</a> : For the base TikTok UI and smooth interaction.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/caddyserver/caddy">Caddy</a> : For the lightweight and powerful web server.</li>
<li>The countless others!</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">And don't forget to mention Erin if you like it or if it helps you in any way!</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AWS and Azure Are at Least 4x–10x More Expensive Than Hetzner (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://learn.umh.app/course/aws-and-azure-are-at-least-4x-10x-more-expensive-than-hetzner/</link>
            <guid>41902103</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 09:07:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://learn.umh.app/course/aws-and-azure-are-at-least-4x-10x-more-expensive-than-hetzner/">https://learn.umh.app/course/aws-and-azure-are-at-least-4x-10x-more-expensive-than-hetzner/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41902103">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
    <div data-post-hero="">

    <div data-post-hero-content="">
          

      

        <p>Why We Recommend Hetzner to Try Out the UMH: it is at least 4x–10x less expensive than AWS and Azure for similar VM instances.</p>

        <ul data-post-hero-authors="">
            <li>
              <a href="https://learn.umh.app/instructor/jeremy/">
                  <picture>
  <source srcset="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w30/format/webp/2023/02/Jeremy_huc484169f1c4136c603a7df27dcdff14f_371473_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 30w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w100/format/webp/2023/02/Jeremy_huc484169f1c4136c603a7df27dcdff14f_371473_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 100w" sizes="32px" type="image/webp">
  <img onload="this.classList.remove('blur')" loading="lazy" srcset="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w30/format/webp/2023/02/Jeremy_huc484169f1c4136c603a7df27dcdff14f_371473_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 30w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w100/format/webp/2023/02/Jeremy_huc484169f1c4136c603a7df27dcdff14f_371473_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg 100w" sizes="32px" src="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w30/2023/02/Jeremy_huc484169f1c4136c603a7df27dcdff14f_371473_1200x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" alt="">
</picture>
                <span>Jeremy Theocharis</span>
              </a>
            </li>
        </ul>
      

        <p>Why We Recommend Hetzner to Try Out the UMH: it is at least 4x–10x less expensive than AWS and Azure for similar VM instances.</p>
    </div>

      <figure>
        <picture>
  <source srcset="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w320/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 320w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w640/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 600w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w960/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 960w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w1280/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 480px, 720px" type="image/webp">
  <img loading="eager" srcset="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w320/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 320w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w640/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 600w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w960/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 960w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w1280/format/webp/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 480px, 720px" src="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w30/2024/10/YT_Thumbnail_3_Approach-13.png" alt="AWS and Azure are At Least 4x–10x More Expensive Than Hetzner">
</picture>
        
      </figure>

  </div>
    <section data-post-content="">
      
      <article data-no-overflow="">
        <p><strong>No, you don’t have to use AWS or Azure. </strong>While AWS and Azure are industry leaders, their advantages often only materialize at massive scales. In many cases, they lead to escalating costs and vendor lock-in without delivering proportional benefits.</p><p>If your organization hasn’t yet  committed to a cloud provider or negotiated fixed contracts, it’s worth exploring alternatives like <a href="https://www.hetzner.com/cloud/?ref=learn.umh.app">Hetzner</a>.</p><p>In this article, we provide a technical comparison between Hetzner, AWS, and Azure, focusing on three key aspects:</p><ol><li>Cost Efficiency</li><li>Adequate Performance and Reliability</li><li>Industry Trends</li></ol><h2 id="cost-efficiency-hetzner-vs-aws-and-azure">Cost Efficiency: Hetzner vs. AWS and Azure</h2><p>Below is a direct comparison of equivalent instances from Hetzner, AWS, and Azure as of <em>2024-10-16</em>.</p><h3 id="base-numbers">Base Numbers</h3><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Cloud Provider</th>
<th>Type</th>
<th>vCPUs</th>
<th>RAM</th>
<th>Monthly Cost</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Hetzner Cloud</td>
<td>CPX41</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>16 GB</td>
<td>$32.70 <br> (billed hourly)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS EC2 <br>(1-Year)</td>
<td>c6g.2xlarge</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>16 GiB</td>
<td>$180.60</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS EC2 <br>(On-Demand)</td>
<td>c6g.2xlarge</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>16 GiB</td>
<td>$226.59</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Azure VM</td>
<td>F8</td>
<td>8</td>
<td>16 GiB</td>
<td>$331.42 <br> (billed hourly)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Cost Comparison:</strong></p><ul><li>AWS On-Demand vs. Hetzner: $226.59 / $32.70 ≈ <strong>6.93 times</strong> more expensive</li><li>AWS 1-Year Reserved vs. Hetzner: $180.60 / $32.70 ≈ <strong>5.52 times</strong> more expensive</li><li>Azure vs. Hetzner: $331.42 / $32.70 ≈ <strong>10.14 times</strong> more expensive</li></ul><p>This is not an isolated case. Let’s examine more powerful instances:</p><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Instance Type</th>
<th>vCPUs/CPUs</th>
<th>RAM</th>
<th>Monthly Cost</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Hetzner CPX51</td>
<td>16 vCPUs</td>
<td>32 GB</td>
<td>$71.23</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Hetzner AX102 <br>(Dedicated CPU, 1-month commitment)</td>
<td>16 CPUs (Dedicated)</td>
<td>128 GB</td>
<td>$134.94</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS c6g.4xlarge <br>(1-Year)</td>
<td>16 vCPUs</td>
<td>32 GiB</td>
<td>$361.28</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS c6g.4xlarge <br>(On-Demand)</td>
<td>16 vCPUs</td>
<td>32 GiB</td>
<td>$457.72</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS r6g.4xlarge</td>
<td>16 vCPUs</td>
<td>128 GiB</td>
<td>$453.18</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Not all CPUs are created equal, and performance can vary significantly between different architectures and configurations. AWS’s c6g instances use ARM-based Graviton2 processors, which offer excellent performance per dollar for certain workloads but may present compatibility issues with software not optimized for ARM architecture. When selecting an x86-based instance like AWS’s m7a.2xlarge (8 vCPUs, 32 GB RAM), which utilizes AMD EPYC processors, the cost increases to <strong>$405.47</strong> per month—making it over <strong>5 times more expensive</strong> than Hetzner’s CPX51. </p><h3 id="hidden-costs-in-aws-and-azure">Hidden Costs in AWS and Azure</h3><p>Beyond the base pricing, AWS and Azure often introduce additional expenses that can impact the total cost of ownership:</p><ul><li>Storage Costs: EBS volumes (AWS) and Managed Disks (Azure) are billed separately.</li><li>Data Transfer Fees: Charges apply for data movement between services and outbound internet traffic, which can accumulate based on usage patterns.</li><li>Complex Pricing Models: Layered pricing structures and a multitude of service offerings can make cost estimation and budgeting more challenging.</li></ul><p>In contrast, Hetzner offers straightforward, nearly all-inclusive pricing, simplifying budget management and reducing the risk of unexpected charges. Yes, there are disadvantages about managing your own infrastructure, and we will cover them in the following chapters.</p><h2 id="adequate-performance-and-reliability">Adequate Performance and Reliability</h2><p>For many manufacturing companies and system integrators, the primary requirement is reliable application hosting without the need for massive scaling or global distribution. Most workloads in the manufacturing sector continue to operate on <a href="https://learn.umh.app/lesson/introduction-into-it-ot-system-administration/">virtual machines</a>, often running on-premises Windows servers. In such contexts, the advanced features and managed services offered by AWS and Azure may be excessive and unnecessarily complex.</p><p>Many organizations have small IT teams—sometimes as few as one person—responsible for managing Industrial IoT applications and infrastructure. These teams need straightforward, cost-effective solutions that align with their existing skill sets. Starting with a couple of VMs on Hetzner allows companies to begin their journey into modern IT infrastructure without incurring high costs or requiring specialized personnel.</p><p>In contrast, adopting AWS or Azure from the outset can require a steep learning curve and may necessitate hiring additional staff with specialized expertise. We experienced this firsthand: we spent several weeks trying to perform simple administrative tasks on AWS, such as adding a billing administrator, and found the process unnecessarily complicated.</p><p><strong>Do you really need the advanced features of AWS and Azure right now? Or would a simple virtual machine at a reasonable price be sufficient?</strong> That’s the main question here.</p><p>As the creator of Ruby on Rails puts it:</p><blockquote>I’d rather make some nice software than pay 100 times more for my compute.</blockquote><p>Let's look into what the industry is saying!</p><h2 id="industry-trends">Industry Trends</h2><p>There’s a growing movement among tech companies and startups to opt for more cost-effective hosting solutions like Hetzner. The high costs associated with AWS and Azure are leading many to reconsider their choices.</p><h3 id="ahrefs">Ahrefs</h3><figure><img src="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/2024/10/image-8.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="721" height="1089" srcset="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w600/2024/10/image-8.png 600w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/2024/10/image-8.png 721w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><strong>Ahrefs</strong>, a prominent SEO tool provider, detailed their experience in the article <a href="https://tech.ahrefs.com/how-ahrefs-saved-us-400m-in-3-years-by-not-going-to-the-cloud-8939dd930af8?ref=learn.umh.app">“How Ahrefs Saved US$400M in 3 Years by NOT Going to the Cloud”</a>. Their main points are:</p><p><strong>Vendor Lock-In Concerns:</strong> They emphasized the difficulty of exiting a cloud provider due to convenience and potential vendor lock-in.</p><blockquote>“It is complicated to leave a cloud once you are there… Also, abandoning a cloud infrastructure due to higher costs may not be what the engineering team wants.”</blockquote><p><strong>Performance Advantages</strong>: Owning their hardware allowed for faster and more comprehensive results, enhancing their product.</p><blockquote>“Having faster and better results means that our servers are much faster than what a cloud can provide… Our reports are also generated faster and are more comprehensive.”</blockquote><p><strong>Revenue Implications:</strong> Their total revenue over that period was around $257 million, meaning AWS costs would have exceeded their entire revenue.</p><blockquote>The company revenue wouldn’t even be close to covering the 2½-year AWS usage costs.”</blockquote><p><strong>Massive Cost Savings:</strong> Ahrefs calculated that using AWS would have cost them an additional ~$400 million over 2.5 years compared to their own infrastructure.</p><blockquote>“Ahrefs has saved ~USD 400 million by ensuring its infrastructure is NOT 100% in the IaaS cloud during the last 2½ years.”</blockquote><h3 id="insights-from-industry-leaders">Insights from Industry Leaders</h3><figure><img src="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-17-at-13.30.48.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1278" height="659" srcset="https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w600/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-17-at-13.30.48.png 600w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/size/w1000/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-17-at-13.30.48.png 1000w, https://learn.umh.app/content/images/2024/10/Screenshot-2024-10-17-at-13.30.48.png 1278w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption><span>David Heinemeier Hansson on the Rails World Conference 2024</span></figcaption></figure><p>David Heinemeier Hansson, the creator of Ruby on Rails, <a href="https://youtu.be/-cEn_83zRFw?t=1652&amp;ref=learn.umh.app">discussed at the Rails World Conference</a> how startups can save costs and gain more powerful machines by choosing providers like Hetzner over AWS or Azure. Key points from his keynote include:</p><p><strong>Critique of Cloud Dependency: </strong>He criticized the industry trend of making developers feel incapable of managing servers, leading to over-reliance on expensive cloud services.</p><blockquote>We’ve sort of all turned into pink elephants tied with a tiny rope of learned helplessness when it comes to deployment… The problem is that the entire industry has cultivated a fear of touching a server.”</blockquote><p><strong>Value of Self-Hosting:</strong> He pointed out that you can get substantially more computing power for less money by managing your own servers.</p><blockquote>You can buy… 40 cores, 96 threads, 256 GB of RAM for $220 a month [from Hetzner]… I’d rather make some nice software than pay 100 times more for my compute.”</blockquote><p><strong>Questioning Cloud Economics:</strong> He highlighted the significant markup on cloud services compared to the actual cost of hardware.</p><blockquote>“AWS has a 40% margin… Dell, someone who actually makes the computers, have a 5% margin. That is a failed market.”</blockquote><p>These perspectives reflect a larger industry movement: companies are reevaluating the cost-benefit equation of major cloud providers, especially when high expenses don’t translate into proportional advantages.</p><h2 id="conclusion-what-has-this-to-do-with-umh">Conclusion: What has this to do with UMH?</h2><p>To get started with the <a href="https://www.umh.app/?ref=learn.umh.app" rel="noreferrer">UMH</a>, you need to install it via the <a href="https://management.umh.app/?ref=learn.umh.app" rel="noreferrer">Management Console</a>, either locally using the experimental Docker container or in a virtual machine.</p><p>If you don’t have an on-premises VM, you don’t need to use AWS or Azure either! By choosing Hetzner, you can deploy a UMH cloud instance for approximately <strong>$32 per month</strong>, compared to several hundred dollars on AWS or Azure. This makes it a much easier sell to conservative manufacturing companies, as <strong>the initial proof of concept (PoC) with the free community edition of UMH and a Hetzner cloud instance costs just a $32 per month of software and infrastructure costs</strong>.</p><p>In conclusion, if you’re just getting started and are not yet locked into AWS or Azure, Hetzner offers a cost-effective, reliable, and straightforward alternative. It allows you to deploy applications like UMH without incurring excessive costs or dealing with unnecessary complexity.</p>
      </article>
    </section>

    

        

      <div data-related="posts">
          <h2>Read next</h2>

          
        </div>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Drive Blackout in Italy After Another Major Anti-Piracy Blunder (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://torrentfreak.com/google-drive-blackout-in-italy-after-another-major-anti-piracy-blunder-241020/</link>
            <guid>41901168</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 06:19:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/google-drive-blackout-in-italy-after-another-major-anti-piracy-blunder-241020/">https://torrentfreak.com/google-drive-blackout-in-italy-after-another-major-anti-piracy-blunder-241020/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41901168">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s.png"><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s.png.webp 450w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s-300x186.png.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s.png" alt="piracy-shield-planet-s" width="300" height="186" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s.png 450w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s-300x186.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-planet-s-150x93.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px">
</picture>
</a>Italy has an administrative blocking mechanism and a technical blocking platform, Piracy Shield, operated by rightsholders in the private sector. </p>
<p>Up until now, AGCOM, Italy’s independent telecoms regulator, has been Piracy Shield’s greatest supporter, at least of those not already benefiting financially from the activities of football league Serie A, currently the only beneficiary of Piracy Shield blocking. </p>
<p>To the extent there’s much of a ‘public’ component to Piracy Shield’s activities in Italy, the ‘private’ absolutely dominates. There’s almost zero transparency and any information of any use is routinely withheld from the public, even when that information relates directly to the public. People who demand access to information are routinely ignored, even punished. The only people never punished are those operating Piracy Shield, no matter how big the blunder or how many people are affected.</p>
<p>After blocking Cloudflare a few months ago, on Saturday night another vital online service was rendered inaccessible. The nature and circumstances of this event should be a signal for the Italian government to remove rightsholders’ ability to meddle in internet infrastructure before it’s too late. The details make for very uncomfortable reading.</p>
<h2>Warnings Pile Up, All Ignored, Again and Again</h2>
<p>When reporting on the <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/piracy-shield-cloudflare-disaster-blocks-countless-sites-fires-up-opposition-240226/">Cloudflare debacle</a> in February, we included commentary from Giorgio Bonfiglio, Principal Technical Account Manager at Amazon Web Services. </p>
<p>Bonfiglio’s expert advice was ignored before, during, and after last year’s introduction of new law to support blocking, despite predicting the Cloudflare problem before it actually became one. As far as we can determine, Bonfiglio was first to link Google Drive’s outage on Saturday evening with Piracy Shield blocking.</p>
<p>“Piracy Shield blocked a Google Drive domain,” Bonfiglio <a href="https://x.com/g_bonfiglio/status/1847728976933904453">revealed</a> on X, along with the AGCOM notice displayed on the blocked domain.</p>
<center><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1.png"><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1.png.webp 663w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1-300x181.png.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 663px) 100vw, 663px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1.png" alt="X-block-1" width="663" height="399" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1.png 663w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1-300x181.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1-600x361.png 600w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/X-block-1-150x90.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 663px) 100vw, 663px">
</picture>
</a></center>
<p>The domain/subdomain blocked in the image above is <em>drive.usercontent.google.com</em>; not only does this URL clearly identify Google as its owner, the Google product it serves is on full display too. With no prompting a 10-year-old could identify google.com as important on the internet. So, three broad explanations for how it ended up on the system (ticket below) before causing chaos.</p>
<p><em>1. Domain was accidentally entered into the system, then evaded all subsequent checks<br>
2. Domain was knowingly entered into the system, then evaded all subsequent checks<br>
3. Domain was knowingly entered into the system, and then passed, regardless of risk</em></p>
<center><em>The losing ticket….</em><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1.png"><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1.png.webp 900w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1-300x186.png.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1.png" alt="shield-ticket1" width="670" height="415" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1.png 900w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1-300x186.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1-600x371.png 600w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/shield-ticket1-150x93.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px">
</picture>
</a></center>
<p>For good measure, the relevant Google IP address [142.250.180.129] was also entered into Piracy Shield to be blocked by local ISPs; <a href="https://x.com/g_bonfiglio/status/1847729915858211314/photo/2">this image</a> shows how access to that IP degraded unlike an adjacent one.</p>
<p>Those hoping to access Google Drive were subject to domain hijacking instead, with requests diverted to a blocking page hosted at different IP addresses depending on the ISP involved; 195.162.95.240 [Sky] and 34.110.214.49 [TIM], for example.</p>
<h2>Blocking in 30 Minutes, Unblocking…whenever</h2>
<p>The domain/IP address block began to take effect a little time after 6pm and as the image below shows, three smaller ‘downtime peaks’ were followed by an almost total degradation of service around 9pm. This seems to show that blunders take at least three hours to fix, even a massive one like this. More tellingly, the constant claim of blocking internet resources within 30 mins is at best, very optimistic indeed.</p>
<p>We took a look at Google Trends data for Italy during the same period. The top five queries in Italy all relate to Google Drive (right) and on the left, the topic ‘Google Drive’ dominates by a very wide margin. Nevertheless, the results are sensitive enough to identify AGCOM and piracy as connected to the trending searches. </p>
<center><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends.png"><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends.png.webp 1214w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends-300x129.png.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends.png" alt="piracy-shield-trends" width="670" height="289" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends.png 1214w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends-300x129.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends-600x259.png 600w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/piracy-shield-trends-150x65.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px">
</picture>
</a></center>
<p>More data is needed to draw firm conclusions but under both columns, Google Drive competitor ‘One Drive’ gets a mention. It wouldn’t be unreasonable to conclude that faced with no access to their files on Google Drive, searching for a replacement would be a logical step. The hidden costs of overblocking are perhaps not quite so hidden here.</p>
<h2>Full Unblocking Doesn’t Take 30 mins</h2>
<p>A full twelve hours after the block was put in place, around 20% of the Italian population still had no access to their Google Drives due to the lingering IP address block that underpinned the domain-based blocking.</p>
<center><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay.png"><picture loading="lazy" decoding="async">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay.png.webp 733w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay-300x268.png.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px">
<img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay.png" alt="block-delay" width="670" height="599" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay.png 733w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay-300x268.png 300w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay-600x536.png 600w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/block-delay-150x134.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 670px) 100vw, 670px">
</picture>
</a></center>
<p>Had this disaster happened on a weekday, who knows the damage it could’ve caused. Luckily it didn’t, and everyone can be grateful for that, but the word ‘luck’ in a sentence to describe an event that should not have happened, period, understates the seriousness of the situation.</p>
<p>Whether there will be explanation of any kind on Monday is currently unknown, but there is no explaining this one away. Explanations for the Cloudflare block began with denial, slowly moved towards claims it was only a tiny, tiny block that didn’t last long, before Cloudflare was blamed for having a customer allegedly pirating football matches.</p>
<h2>Drastic Action Required Immediately</h2>
<p>Incompetence doesn’t qualify as an excuse, not when a Google domain is part of the equation. So if not incompetence, surely it must’ve been deliberate? Whatever the reason or excuse, the conclusion is the same; this cannot be allowed to continue, and the government must step in before the unthinkable happens. </p>
<p>Since users are about to be fined for piracy, an alternative would be to introduce heavy fines, directly linked to the potential damage to companies, infrastructure or government, plus compensation paid to citizens, for those who overblock.</p>
<p>Let’s say, a population of 59 million in Italy, a conservative 30 million Google users, one euro compensation each, leading to a 30 million euro fine. It won’t stop incompetence, but it should focus the mind during the 30-day ban on any additional blocking or until the fine is paid in full, whichever comes last.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Software engineer titles have almost lost all their meaning (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.trevorlasn.com/blog/software-engineer-titles-have-almost-lost-all-their-meaning</link>
            <guid>41900456</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 03:33:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.trevorlasn.com/blog/software-engineer-titles-have-almost-lost-all-their-meaning">https://www.trevorlasn.com/blog/software-engineer-titles-have-almost-lost-all-their-meaning</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41900456">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article> <p>Remember when being a “Senior Software Engineer” actually meant something? I do, and I can’t help but feel nostalgic for that clarity. In recent years, our industry has witnessed rampant title inflation, turning what used to be a clear-cut junior-mid-senior progression into a confusing parade of inflated roles.</p>
<p>The “senior” title, once a badge of substantial experience and expertise, has been particularly devalued. Today, developers are being crowned “senior” faster than ever, often with just three to four years under their belts. It’s as if the path to seniority, once a marathon of skill-building and diverse experiences, has turned into a sprinter’s dash.</p>
<p>This explosion of grandiose titles isn’t just confusing—it’s eroding the meaning of career milestones in tech. Each new title tries to outdo the last in impressiveness, while paradoxically meaning less and less. For everyone involved—from job seekers to hiring managers—this inflation has muddied the waters of professional progression and recognition.</p>
<h3 id="what-is-a-senior-engineer-anyway">What is a “Senior” Engineer Anyway?</h3>
<p>Being a senior engineer meant far more than just logging years on the job. It was a title earned through a diverse set of experiences and challenges that shaped not just their technical skills, but their entire approach to software development.</p>
<p>A true senior engineer is a battle-tested problem solver. They’ve faced and conquered complex technical challenges across multiple projects, dealing with more than just tricky bugs. These are the architects who’ve untangled system-wide issues that require deep understanding and creative solutions. They’re the ones who can navigate and refactor sprawling legacy codebases with confidence, understanding the delicate balance between maintaining existing systems and building new ones.</p>
<p>Senior engineers have been through the crucible of major production outages. They’ve felt the heat of a system melting down in real-time and learned to stay calm under pressure. These experiences have taught them to diagnose issues rapidly and lead a team through a crisis, making critical decisions when every second counts.</p>
<p>But technical skills alone don’t make a senior engineer. They’re also architectural visionaries who can see beyond immediate tasks to design scalable, maintainable systems. Their decisions positively impact projects years down the line, showcasing a level of foresight that only comes with extensive experience. They’ve developed the soft skills to be effective mentors and leaders, guiding junior developers not just in coding, but in navigating the complex landscape of software development.</p>
<p>Perhaps most importantly, senior engineers remain humble and curious despite their experience. They’re continuous learners, adapting to new technologies and methodologies, always expanding their toolkit. They’ve developed a strong sense of professional ethics, understanding the broader implications of their work and advocating for responsible development practices.</p>
<p>This depth of experience isn’t typically gained in just a few years. It’s forged through diverse projects, multiple tech stacks, and yes, a fair share of failures and lessons learned along the way.</p>
<h3 id="the-root-cause-of-title-inflation">The Root Cause Of Title Inflation</h3>
<p>The fierce competition for talent has led companies, especially startups, to use titles as a retention tactic. Unable to always match the salaries offered by tech giants, these companies resort to inflating titles as a form of non-monetary compensation. While this might seem like a clever short-term solution, it’s creating long-term problems for the industry by diluting the meaning of these titles.</p>
<p>The rise of professional networking platforms like LinkedIn has exacerbated this issue. These platforms have turned titles into personal branding tools, creating immense pressure for individuals to sport impressive-sounding roles. This “LinkedIn Effect” has everyone, from fresh graduates to seasoned professionals, yearning for titles that look good on their profiles, often prioritizing appearance over substance.</p>
<p>HR departments, grappling with the increasing complexity of tech roles, have contributed to this problem as well. In an attempt to accurately categorize the myriad of specialized positions in our rapidly evolving field, they’ve created a proliferation of niche titles. While these titles might be descriptive, they’ve made it increasingly difficult to compare roles across companies, further muddying the waters of career progression.</p>
<p>Lastly, many companies have begun using title promotions as a retention strategy. The intent is to recognize and retain valuable employees, but this approach often backfires. When titles are handed out like participation trophies, they cease to align with actual growth in responsibilities or skills. This misalignment not only devalues the titles themselves but also sets unrealistic expectations for the newly promoted employees.</p>
<p>In essence, what we’re seeing is a perfect storm of market pressures, personal branding needs, organizational challenges, and short-sighted retention strategies. Together, these factors have inflated titles to the point where they risk losing their meaning entirely.</p>
<h3 id="why-do-we-need-to-address-title-inflation">Why Do We Need to Address Title Inflation?</h3>
<p>Title inflation isn’t just about words on a business card or a LinkedIn profile. It’s a problem that strikes at the heart of our industry’s integrity and functionality. When we inflate titles, we’re essentially lying to ourselves and each other about our capabilities and experience.</p>
<p>This deception has real consequences. It creates a mismatch between expectations and reality, leading to situations where people are placed in roles they’re not prepared for. Imagine a “senior” engineer with three years of experience trying to architect a complex system or mentor junior developers. The potential for failure is high, and the stress on that individual is immense.</p>
<h3 id="what-can-we-do-about-title-inflation">What Can We Do About Title Inflation?</h3>
<p>For those in leadership positions, it’s paramount to resist the temptation of using inflated titles as a quick fix for retention or recruitment challenges. Instead, focus on creating meaningful career progression frameworks that tie advancements to concrete skills and responsibilities. Consider implementing a system similar to those used by larger tech companies, where levels (like L3, L4, L5) provide a more nuanced view of seniority without resorting to title inflation.</p>
<p>Companies can take a stand by standardizing their title structures and being transparent about what each level means. This could involve creating detailed job descriptions that clearly outline the expectations and responsibilities for each role. By doing so, you not only provide clarity for your employees but also contribute to a more standardized industry-wide understanding of titles.</p>
<p>HR departments have a critical role to play. They can work on developing more sophisticated ways to categorize and compare roles across the industry. This might involve collaborating with tech leads to create standardized skill matrices that can be used to evaluate candidates and employees more objectively.</p>
<p>Companies that resist title inflation gain a significant competitive edge. By maintaining meaningful titles, they attract and retain top talent who value authentic growth over inflated roles. This leads to more accurate hiring, improved team dynamics, and enhanced productivity. Realistic titles also foster trust, both internally and with clients, positioning the company as a beacon of integrity in the industry. Ultimately, companies with well-defined, honest title structures build stronger, more capable teams and a reputation for excellence that sets them apart in the market.</p> </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scientists working to decode birdsong (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2024/10/21/how-scientists-started-to-decode-birdsong</link>
            <guid>41900404</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 03:22:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2024/10/21/how-scientists-started-to-decode-birdsong">https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2024/10/21/how-scientists-started-to-decode-birdsong</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41900404">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><figure></figure><p>On a drizzly day in Grünau im Almtal, Austria, a gaggle of greylag geese shared a peaceful moment on a grassy field near a stream. One goose, named Edes, was preening quietly; others were resting with their beaks pointed tailward, nestled into their feathers. Then a camouflaged speaker that scientists had placed nearby started to play. First came a recorded honk from an unpartnered male goose named Joshua. Edes went on with his preening. Next came a honk that was lower in pitch than the first, with a slight bray. Edes looked up. As the other geese remained tucked in their warm positions, incurious, Edes scanned the field. He had just heard a recorded “distance call” from his life partner, a female goose whom scientists had named Bon Jovi.</p><p>Edes and his fellow-geese live near the Konrad Lorenz Research Center for Behavior and Cognition, which is named for a Nobel laureate whose imprinting experiments, in the nineteen-thirties, convinced goslings that he was their mother. (They took to following him in a downy line.) Greylag geese in the area have been studied continually ever since. The director of the center, a biologist and bird ecologist named Sonia Kleindorfer, showed me footage of Edes to demonstrate the subtlety of goose communication.</p><p>Geese maintain elaborate social structures, travel in family groups, and can navigate from Sweden to Spain. In a fight, an unpartnered greylag goose has a higher heart rate than a partnered one, and the heart rate of a recently widowed goose can remain depressed for about a year. These birds have things to discuss. Still, geese are not the Ciceros of the bird world. A lyrebird sings long, elaborate songs; ravens really can say “nevermore.” Geese are known for nasal honks. How much nuance can there be in a honk?</p><p>Greylag geese, it turns out, have at least ten different kinds of calls. “We are completely underappreciating the way they communicate,” Kleindorfer told me. “They give a departure call when they leave, and a contact call after they arrive. They know if their allies are there, if the bold geese are there. There is so much information that geese are getting from calls.”</p><p>Bird vocalizations are usually divided into songs and calls, but these are wobbly categories. What is designated a song in one species may be shorter in duration than what, in another species, is termed a call. Onomatopoeic groupings such as <em>tseets</em>, <em>chirrups</em>, <em>rreeyoos</em>, <em>seeew-soooos</em>, and <em>dahs</em> are also indeterminate: people transcribe the same sounds in different ways, and no bird version of the Académie Française exists to adjudicate. The vocalizations of birds are fundamentally incommensurate with human ones. We have a larynx and two vocal cords; they have what’s called a syrinx, which is a bit like having two larynxes that you can use at the same time.</p><p>Kleindorfer, the daughter of a mathematician and an actress, looks like a cross between a hiker and the film star Sophia Loren. From February to April, she researches Darwin’s finches in the Galápagos; from September to December, songbirds in Australia; and, for the rest of the year, the geese outside her office door. Early in her education, as an undergraduate at the University of Pennsylvania, she was taught that “male songbirds sing, females don’t, and if females do sing it’s an error.” The attitude at the time, she told me, was that “females are drab, inconspicuous, and quiet.” A few years after earning a Ph.D. in zoology at the University of Vienna, Kleindorfer took a job as a research biologist at Flinders University, in Australia, where songbird species originally evolved. “Imagine my surprise,” she told me. “I heard all these females singing songs as complex as the male songs.” Much of her ensuing career has focussed on bird vocalizations that were either underappreciated or unknown.</p><p>Kleindorfer decided to study bird eggs and early development, which were then neglected research topics. “Maybe this was because only females have eggs and I was a woman in science,” she told me. “I don’t have a better reason.” Kleindorfer had noticed that mustached-warbler chicks seemed to respond to the alarm calls of adult warblers, even though the thinking at the time was that such calls were directed at other adults, or possibly at predators. “If I put a snake nearby, the parental alarm call made the chicks in the nest jump,” she said. “If I put a marsh harrier”—a hawklike predatory bird—“nearby, the response to the parental alarm call was that the chicks would duck.” The chicks were responding appropriately to different alarm calls—a satisfying finding.</p><p>Kleindorfer also studied the superb fairy wren, a songbird that weighs about as much as a walnut and sports a flirty, upright tail. Despite their fanciful names, fairy wrens are commonplace in Australia. They are socially monogamous but sexually promiscuous—they are essentially in open marriages—and they bring up their young collectively. Arguably, they have even more to chat about than geese do. Fairy-wren nests are about the size of cupped human hands, built to contain pale, speckled eggs that are smaller than thumbnails. Kleindorfer and her team wired up nests with cameras and microphones and soon discovered something that they hadn’t known to look for. “The mothers in nests were producing an incubation call—a call to the eggs,” she told me. It was like a lullaby. Why would a mother bird make any sound that could attract predators to the nest? “Songbird embryos don’t have well-developed ears, so this was completely unexpected,” she said. “That started a twenty-year project—why is she calling to the eggs?”</p><p>The team compared incubation calls to the begging calls of young chicks. “It was very odd,” Kleindorfer recalled. “Each nest had its own distinct begging call.” What’s more, each begging call matched an element from the mother’s incubation call. This suggested, startlingly, that birds could learn a literal mother tongue while still in ovo. (Humans do this, too; French and German babies have distinct cries.) Even “foster” chicks, who as eggs were physically moved from one nest to another, learned begging calls from their foster mothers, rather than from their genetic mothers. This was big news in the ornithology world. “The paradigm of how songbirds learn—after hatching, from their father’s song—was overthrown,” she said. The same process was soon documented in more songbird species.</p><p>Language is often cited as the quality that distinguishes us as humans. When I asked Robert Berwick, an M.I.T. computational linguist, about birds, he argued that “they’re not trying to <em>say</em> anything in the sense of James Joyce trying to say something.” Still, he and Kleindorfer both pointed out that humans and songbirds share a trait that many animals lack: we are “vocal learners,” meaning that we can learn to make new sounds throughout our lives. (Bats, whales, dolphins, and elephants can, too.) “To me, the most amazing thing is that every generation of vocal learners has its own sound,” Kleindorfer said. “So, just like our English is different from Shakespeare’s English, the songbirds, too, have very different songs from five hundred years ago. I am sure of it.” We humans have long tried, often mistakenly, to differentiate ourselves from nonhuman animals—by arguing that only we have souls, or use tools, or are capable of self-awareness. Perhaps we should see what the birds have to say.</p><p>Animals have prominent speaking roles in many of our oldest stories. Eve has a memorable conversation with a snake. In Norse mythology, two ravens, Huginn and Muninn, serve as spies to the god Odin, whispering to him the news of the world. In many cultures, the “language of birds” refers to a divine or perfect language—the language of angels. In the scientific realm, however, the notion that nonhuman animals use language is often seen as foolish or naïve. Some birds may be excellent mimics, like parrots, but they can also mimic chainsaws or barking dogs; scholars don’t usually consider imitation a form of understanding. The prevailing dogma is that birds sing either to impress mates or to defend their territory. (I suspect that most of human communication could also be slotted into those categories.) In college, I was taught a stranger but similarly diminishing idea: that songbirds sing in the morning to burn fat, so that they are light enough to fly around during the day. Apparently, this idea is no longer taken seriously.</p><p>Even among species we view as being closer to ourselves, such as primates, scientists have tended to talk about “communication” instead of “language.” But it’s tricky to say where the line is, or what we mean by “communication,” since even bacteria communicate, as Berwick pointed out to me. “I think it’s best to think of language not as speech but as a cognitive ability in the mind that sometimes leads to speech,” he said, giving the example of inward conversations we have with ourselves. The linguist Noam Chomsky has said, “It’s about as likely that an ape will prove to have a language ability as there is an island somewhere with a species of flightless birds waiting for humans to teach them to fly.” Chomsky’s 2017 book on the evolution of language, co-authored with Berwick, is titled“Why Only Us.”</p><p>Over the years, however, some researchers have looked closely at the contexts in which certain animal vocalizations are made. In the late nineteen-seventies, two primatologists, Dorothy Cheney and Robert Seyfarth, were studying vervet monkeys in Kenya. Vervets have dark faces and pale fur; they are about the size of a small backpack and are hunted by pythons, eagles, and leopards. Cheney and Seyfarth documented something remarkable: one recorded vervet vocalization made vervets look up, presumably for eagles; another made them look down, presumably for pythons; and a third sent them running up into the trees, a good defense against approaching leopards. Young vervets sometimes use these calls faultily, perhaps sounding a leopard alarm for a warthog. But they get better as they grow up. They learn.</p><p>A newer generation of scientists has been trying to understand bird vocalizations. The alarm calls of Siberian jays can be said to have been partially translated. One of their screeches indicates a sitting hawk (which prompts other jays to come together in a group), another a flying hawk (jays hide, which makes them difficult to spot), and a third a hawk actively attacking (jays fly to the treetops to search for the attacker, and possibly flee). When cheery birds known as tufted titmice make a piercing sound, other titmice may respond by collectively harrying an invading predator. Some birds even lie. Fork-tailed drongos—common, innocuous-looking little dark birds that live in Africa—sometimes mimic the alarm calls of starlings or meerkats. Duped listeners flee the nonexistent threat, leaving behind a buffet for the drongo.</p><p>Upon seeing an owl, a chickadee might sound a loud <em>chick-a-dee-dee-dee</em>, adding <em>dees</em> in relation to how dangerous the predator is perceived to be. This call is also understood by nuthatches, which will join in to mob and harass the predator, forming a kind of defensive alliance. If you record an Australian bird warning of a nearby cuckoo—cuckoos leave their eggs in the nests of other species and often kill their step-siblings—birds in China will understand the call.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Kleindorfer considers Cheney and Seyfarth, the primatologists, to be important sources of inspiration. After she moved to Australia, she and her colleagues built up a sound library of Australian songbirds. They also made recordings of quieter, familial bird sounds, such as the incubation calls. Each family unit, they discovered, had its own “familect,” a system of sounds that chicks learn from their parents. Curiously, chicks seemed to adopt sounds sung either by their mother or by their father—but they avoided the sounds used by both parents. If the mother sings ABCXYZ and the father sings ABCGHI, then the chicks tend to sing the sound units X, Y, Z, G, H, and I. It’s as if the young birds separate themselves from their parents by not speaking the shared sounds, but also stay close to their parents by learning what’s unique to Mom and unique to Dad. When female chicks grow up, they are attracted to mates whose repertoire is familiar (he’s one of us!), but&nbsp;not too familiar (he’s not my brother or dad).</p><p>Birds in general are turning out to have intellectual abilities far greater than most people had imagined. It’s not just that parrots and crows can do math as ably as young children, or that scrub jays cleverly cache and then uncache their food to fool other jays. Even inconspicuous and uncelebrated birds are capable of learning, and of sharing their learning with others. In the nineteen-twenties, tits from Swaythling, England, figured out how to open the caps of milk bottles, and by the late forties tits across Ireland, Wales, and England had learned the trick. If language is more a capacity than it is a speech act, it seems possible that birds possess it.</p><p>In 1889, Ludwig Paul Koch, an eight-year-old boy in Frankfurt, Germany, received a present from his father: an Edison phonograph and some wax cylinders for recording sounds. The oldest known audio of birdsong is young Koch’s recording of his pet white-rumped shama, a smallish songbird with a dark head, an orange body, and feathers that resemble a white bustle on its glossy black tail. A shama sings like a small chamber orchestra, with slippery, percussive, and sweet sounds in phrases of varying lengths. Many similar recordings followed. In 1929, the Cornell Library of Natural Sounds—now the Macaulay Library—was started with a few hard-won recordings of a sparrow, a wren, and a grosbeak. (Cornell is to ornithology what the Juilliard School is to music.)</p><p>Koch, who was Jewish, became a professional musician but fled Germany in the nineteen-thirties. In England, he became a beloved presence on BBC radio. Sounding like a singsong, sanguine sibling of Werner Herzog, he guided Brits through the charms of birdsong. (A yellow icterine warbler, he told listeners, “frequently called me by my Christian name&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;. Ludwig, Ludwig.”) Koch often expressed the hope that such recordings might be used for science. Many years later, they were.</p><p>In 2010, Grant Van Horn was an undergraduate at U.C. San Diego and working in a computer-vision and machine-learning lab led by the computer scientist Serge Belongie. The lab was looking for a good data set to train an image-recognition program. At the time, Van Horn told me, many of the top images on Flickr, the popular photography Web site, were of birds. Van Horn was no birder, but he wanted to see if he and his colleagues could teach a computer program to distinguish between closely related species, such as a house wren and a marsh wren. As it turned out, they could.</p><p>The lab’s work soon attracted the attention of ornithology researchers at Cornell. Van Horn recalls them telling him and his colleagues, “in the nicest possible way, ‘Look, guys—this data set is quaint and poorly constructed, and the species that you chose to study make no sense. Do you want to effectively redo this whole process, but do it in collaboration with us?’&nbsp;” When Van Horn visited Cornell, the scientists took him out birding every morning and evening, and he remembers wishing that he could take their expertise back to California with him. The collaboration eventually helped the Cornell Lab of Ornithology develop Merlin Bird ID, an app that could reliably identify several hundred species of bird from photographs. It proved immensely popular—but the Cornell team had always had larger ambitions. “They kept asking, ‘How can we do this with sound?’&nbsp;” Van Horn recalled. That was what the scientists were most interested in. But he assumed that auditory recognition was outside his expertise—until, out of curiosity, he attended a workshop on audio-related machine learning.</p><p>“I kind of had an epiphany,” Van Horn said. Sound recognition often relied on spectrograms, visual representations of sounds similar to what you see in audio-editing software. Mike Webster, an animal-communication expert at Cornell who directs the Macaulay Library, and who worked on Merlin, told me, “When people figured out how to visualize sound—how to actually take measures of it—that led to just an explosion of research and understanding about how and why birds communicate with each other.” Much of the work in sound recognition, Van Horn realized, was actually visual: “I thought, Let me bring these computer-vision skills to bear.” An early test could differentiate between recordings of alder flycatchers and willow flycatchers.</p><figure><p><span><div data-attr-viewport-monitor=""><a data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/cartoon/a27294&quot;}" href="https://www.newyorker.com/cartoon/a27294" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"><picture></picture></a><p><span>“It’s still too heavy. What if instead of two armrests we just share one?”</span></p><p><span>Cartoon by Edward Steed</span></p></div></span></p></figure><p>In 2021, the number of bird recordings in the Macaulay Library, many of which were submitted by citizen scientists, reached a million. That same year, Cornell released Merlin Sound ID, which was originally trained on around two hundred and fifty hours of bird sounds, as well as on background noises (whistling wind, passing cars), all manually annotated by experts. At first, Sound ID could identify about three hundred different North American birds, with a bias toward those found around Cornell. Three years and a million additional recordings later, Sound ID can now very accurately identify about fourteen hundred species. The lab hopes that number can grow to roughly eight thousand, out of around eleven thousand known bird species.</p><p>Amateurs now have a remarkable ability to recognize the birds that are cooing or chirping—which has generated more interest in birds and directed more citizen-science recordings to the Macaulay Library. But decoding the bird vocalizations is another matter. One problem is that certain sorts of recordings are more plentiful than others. “Most of our database is songs,” Webster said. “We can now understand songs at a level that we couldn’t before.” Alarm calls are also relatively easy to capture. But something like nest chatter, which is quieter and less predictable, is more elusive: “There are whole categories of bird communication that we’ve hardly even started to look at.” Webster isn’t expecting there to be straightforward translations of birds’ sounds into human language; animals live in perceptual worlds that are just too different from our own. Still, he sees machine learning as a powerful new tool. “There are a lot of people who have dreams of using A.I. to allow us to decipher what animals are saying,” he told me.</p><p>After three decades of research, Webster is preparing to retire. When I asked him what he hoped the next generation of scientists might learn, he thought for a moment. “Well, social birds. They are constantly chatting to each other,” he said. “Making little noises. Often very quietly. It’s like they’re having a whisper conversation. What in the hell are they saying to one another? I’d really like to know.”</p><p>Until my eleven-year-old daughter became interested in birds, I barely knew a starling from a sparrow. She once asked me, incredulously, “You’re saying you can’t tell a male sparrow from a female?” For a long time, we lived just east of the Lincoln Tunnel, where “birds” meant pigeons and seagulls, but within weeks of moving to Brooklyn we saw a red-tailed hawk on a lamppost. My daughter began talking about dark-eyed juncos and tufted titmice and peregrine falcons; we started visiting bird sanctuaries, and I eventually outgrew my favoritism toward mammals. Like millions of others, we started to use Merlin Bird ID. Usually, we heard birds before we saw them. Some local sparrows nesting in a hollow pole on our block sounded like Laurel and Hardy bickering.</p><p>“Anthropomorphism” is a familiar term that describes a common error: the assumption that animals have human qualities. A less familiar term, “anthropectomy,” also describes a kind of error—that of baselessly assuming animals <em>don’t</em> share certain qualities with us. Which kind of error is a person more likely to make? Or are these not errors but, rather, starting points, with someone like Jane Goodall starting from the premise that 98.7 per cent of our DNA is shared with chimps, and someone else starting from the fact that we humans have sequenced our own DNA and no other species has even invented pliers? Since we’re still arguing about what language is, it’s difficult to say which assumption about animal language is more presumptuous.</p><p>Toshitaka Suzuki first started to wonder if birds speak their own language during his last year of college, at Toho University, in Tokyo. He was on a hike in the forests of Karuizawa when he witnessed what struck him as a strange drama among some common Japanese tits, birds that resemble chickadees. One tit called out <em>dee-dee-dee</em> near some scattered sunflower seeds; other tits flew over and began to eat. “Then one bird called out <em>hee-hee-hee</em>, and the birds all flew off into nearby bushes,” Suzuki recalled. He could see no reason for them to abandon their feast.</p><p>Seconds later, a sparrow hawk swooped in; all of the tits had escaped safely. “I thought, Maybe <em>hee-hee-hee</em> means ‘Hawk incoming, run away!’&nbsp;” Suzuki said. He already took birds seriously and knew a lot about them; he had studied under Hiroshi Hasegawa, a scientist who was central in bringing the short-tailed albatross back from near-extinction. But Suzuki had thought of bird vocalizations as, for the most part, emotive, like music, or as a kind of beautiful nonsense. He has now devoted eighteen years to researching tits and their communication. “I couldn’t have imagined how long I would be studying tits, because I love other animals as well,” Suzuki told me. Like many researchers, he hopes that the more we understand birds the likelier we are to protect them.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>In April, 2023, at the University of Tokyo, Suzuki founded what he calls the world’s first laboratory specifically devoted to animal linguistics. He argues that more work should be done to explore what cognitive abilities underlie human language—and then to investigate whether these abilities are present in animals. (In many ways, this approach mirrors the work of Berwick and Chomsky, but leads to different conclusions.) Some are skeptical of his push to compare animal communication to human language. “It’s just so far removed from the complexity of human language that it doesn’t make sense to use the same word,” Todd Freeberg, an animal-communication researcher at the University of Tennessee, told me. When a chickadee amplifies a call by adding <em>dees</em>, some researchers might say that they are engaging in referential signalling, by adjusting their call to the seriousness of the threat. But Freeberg points out that extra <em>dees</em> could also be a result of heightened arousal, in general—less a conscious message than a physical response.</p><p>Like Kleindorfer, Suzuki took an interest in nests. Early on, he showed that chicks in nesting boxes respond to a call associated with crow sightings by crouching, and to a call associated with snakes by fleeing the nest altogether. The arc of Suzuki’s research has, to some extent, followed a series of arguments about what qualities are required for communication to rise to the status of language. Humans are noted for their ability to form a mental image—a concept—of what they are communicating. Suzuki designed an experiment in which he played a variety of calls and moved a stick in a variety of ways; only when he played a snake-alarm call and moved a stick in a snakelike way did the birds tend to react as if a snake were present. To him, this suggested that they had some concept of snake-ness. (He said that the experiment was inspired by the way that humans perceive shapes in clouds.)</p><p>In a 2023 study, Suzuki showed that tits responded differently to a recorded ABCD call than they did to a remixed version of the call, such as DABC—a potential challenge to linguists who see sophisticated syntax as being unique to human language. (Studies of southern pied babblers and of chestnut-crowned babblers also have interesting syntax results.) Symbolic gestures—also often considered unique to humans—were addressed in a particularly adorable Suzuki paper, in 2024. His team watched mated pairs of tits as they entered their nest boxes. The opening to each nest box was small, allowing only one bird at a time to pass. But sometimes one bird, usually the female, fluttered its wings in what seemed to be an “after you” gesture. The other bird would then enter the box first. The fluttering didn’t point at the nest box. In Suzuki’s view, this suggested that the flutter was not a simple indication but, instead, a symbolic gesture—another item crossed off on the unique-to-human-language list.</p><p>Perhaps the nest-box study needs to be replicated; perhaps there are alternative interpretations of the results in the concept and syntax studies. Suzuki is open to such critiques. But he is also skeptical of many prominent ideas in linguistics, such as Chomsky and Berwick’s argument that a slight evolutionary change in the brain unlocked a new linguistic capacity in humans: the unique and powerful ability to connect individual units in a hierarchical and expressive way. (Suzuki thinks that language more likely emerged bit by bit.) By Suzuki’s latest count, the tit’s vocal repertoire has more than two hundred distinct calls and phrases. He has many more experiments to conduct.</p><p>Recently, my daughter and I took an early-morning trip to Little Stony Point, in the Hudson Valley, and met up with two people who have no particular need for an app like Merlin Bird ID. Andrew&nbsp;C. Vallely does field-ornithology work for the American Museum of Natural History; he’s become friends, by way of bird-watching, with Jeffrey Yang, an editor at New Directions Publishing. Yang had been seeing a lot of migrating warblers, which had flown well over a thousand miles—did we want to come try our luck? At his suggestion, I warned my daughter that there was no telling whether we’d actually see any.</p><p>About five minutes down the trail, in a not particularly distinguished wood (we could still hear cars and an excavator across the river), we saw a kingfisher diving and an adolescent eagle on a bare tree. As we walked, stopped, walked, stopped, we repeatedly heard what sounded like the call of a red-tailed hawk. But it soon became clear, at least to Vallely and Yang, that it was a jay mimicking a hawk. “They do that sometimes,” Vallely told me.</p><p>“To scare away other predators?”</p><p>“That’s one thought,” he said. “Vocal mimicry can be pretty mysterious.”</p><p>We heard the “tea kettle tea kettle” call of a Carolina wren; it sounded like a game of marbles to me. We saw a warbling vireo, a Cape May warbler, a blackpoll warbler, and a black-and-white warbler—birds so small that it was difficult to fathom how far some of them had travelled to be there. We heard little chips that sounded like a window being cleaned; a crickety decrescendo that was not made by crickets; a sound like a trill running into a wall; a high-pitched three-fast-one-slow, like a child playing Beethoven’s Fifth Symphony. We encountered forty-four species by Yang’s able count, and at the very end we saw a Swainson’s thrush, who apparently wasn’t in the mood to show off. Bird-watching, I thought, is a misleading term. So much of the fleeting, present-tense pleasure of it is bird-listening.</p><p>The quiet of the pandemic brought natural sounds to the foreground for Maddie Cusimano, who was then a graduate researcher of auditory perception at M.I.T.’s Center for Brains, Minds, and Machines. “Like a lot of people, I had the sense of getting to know the birds around me for the first time,” she told me. Two doves were often visible from her window; she read that, in some dove pairs, one bird sings to the other in the mornings, and in the evenings the roles reverse. Cusimano was familiar enough with machine learning that, when she tried out bird-identification apps, she thought, I could help make this kind of thing.</p><p>Cusimano is now a senior scientist specializing in A.I. research at the Earth Species Project (E.S.P.), a nonprofit dedicated to “using artificial intelligence to decode non-human communication.” E.S.P.’s current efforts examine such species as zebra finches, crows, and beluga whales, but its early work has been preoccupied with preliminary challenges: the “cocktail-party problem” of picking up individual sounds in a noisy environment; how to correlate particular noises with the precise contexts in which they occur. “It’s like we want to write the Magna Carta, but first we need to make the quill,” Katie Zacarian, the organization’s co-founder and C.E.O., told me. Zacarian isn’t expecting a Google Translate for animal languages, but she does believe that we can understand animals better. She remembers that, as a kid, people often brought her father, an entomologist, pictures and specimens and asked: What is this? Her mother was a researcher and an administrator of multilingual education programs. “There’s this underlying current, in their work, of decoding,” she told me.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>When I talked to Cusimano, on Zoom, she pulled up a collection of sound files of crows. Her data set comes from Daniela Canestrari and Vittorio Baglione, researchers at the University of León, in Spain, who have been studying Spanish carrion crows for more than twenty-five years. Cusimano has spent countless hours sitting in San Francisco, listening to these birds, and can sometimes guess which one she’s hearing. “This is maybe what you expect a crow to sound like,” she said, playing me two caws. “But then there’s also this,” she said, playing a whispery rasp. “Some sounds are very long.” She played a ghostly <em>oooo</em>. “Then these two sounds, which you would never think were coming from crows.” One sounded like the click of a computer mouse; another sounded froggy. Her favorite recording reminded me of a duck’s quack. “I love these sounds,” she told me.</p><p>One ambition of Cusimano’s work is to find correlations between these varied vocalizations and the precise contexts in which they occurred. Research partners recently identified a quiet grunt that is most often made right when an adult crow returns to a nest—perhaps a way of saying, “Wake up!” A small bio-logger on the back of a crow can provide audio along with other data—a bird’s-tail view. “You hear their wingbeats, you can hear their friends calling, and them calling back to their friends,” Cusimano told me. The data feels intimate: “You hear baby chicks a distance away, then you hear the bird take off, and the chick sounds are getting louder. And then the crow lands in the nest. You’re in the middle of this crow family.”</p><p>Can a machine be trained to distinguish individual birds by the sounds they make? Can it pick up on vocalizations across individuals which share similar functions? Machine learning is excellent at detecting correlations, but some are irrelevant and even misleading. Cusimano developed an algorithm to distinguish among caws made by various crows, which had names such as Naranja, Rosa, and Azul. She seemed to have succeeded. Then she realized that the computer might be categorizing the sounds based on distinctive background noises, which corresponded to the placement of the recording devices. “The algorithms can pick up on tiny little clues that confound the actual problems we want to find answers to,” she said.</p><p>Those who live and work alongside animals, whether they’re scientists or not, often think, as a matter of course, that animals can speak with one another, and in depth. Instead of being surprised by the discovery of each “unexpected” animal ability, maybe we should be surprised that humans have such low expectations. Many of us laugh—or shake our heads sadly—when we read that Descartes supposedly threw a cat out of a window to see if it would show fear, as a sort of test for consciousness. (He believed that nonhuman animals were senseless automatons.) Yet many of us would also consider it a wonder that, according to a recent study, elephants seem to have distinct names for one another, which their elephant friends and family use among themselves.</p><p>When I started researching this story, I was amazed by each additional avian accomplishment that I learned about, especially in small, ordinary birds. It wasn’t only that they communicated this or that to one another but that they were full of concerns—that they were at the center of their own worlds. But shouldn’t I have intuited that this was the case all along? I had baselessly assumed that birds had little on their minds. The other day, my daughter and I were walking to her soccer practice, passing by sparrows and also people. “We know almost nothing about birds,” she told me. “There’s so much we don’t even notice.” She thought for a moment. “I think they have just as much language as we do, but a lot of it is in their mind. So we don’t hear it.”&nbsp;♦</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TikTok owner sacks intern for sabotaging AI project (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c7v62gg49zro</link>
            <guid>41900402</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 03:21:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c7v62gg49zro">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c7v62gg49zro</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41900402">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>TikTok owner, ByteDance, says it has sacked an intern for "maliciously interfering" with the training of one of its artificial intelligence (AI) models.<!-- --></p><p>But the firm rejected claims about the extent of the damage caused by the unnamed individual, saying they "contain some exaggerations and inaccuracies".<!-- --></p><p>It comes after reports about the incident spread over the weekend on social media.<!-- --></p><p>The Chinese technology giant's Doubao ChatGPT-like generative AI model is the country's most popular AI chatbot.<!-- --></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>"The individual was an intern with the [advertising] technology team and has no experience with the AI Lab," ByteDance said in a statement.<!-- --></p><p>"Their social media profile and some media reports contain inaccuracies."<!-- --></p><p>Its commercial online operations, including its large language AI models, were unaffected by the intern's actions, the company added.<!-- --></p><p>ByteDance also denied reports that the incident caused more than $10m (£7.7m) of damage by disrupting an AI training system made up of thousands of powerful graphics processing units (GPU).<!-- --></p><p>As well as firing the person in August, ByteDance said it had informed the intern's university and industry bodies about the incident.<!-- --></p><p>ByteDance operates some of the world's most popular social media apps, including TikTok and its Chinese-equivalent Douyin. <!-- --></p><p>It is widely seen as a leader when it comes to algorithm development due to how appealing its apps are to users.<!-- --></p><p>Like many of its peers in China and around the world, the social media giant is investing heavily in AI.<!-- --></p><p>It uses the technology to power its Doubao chatbot as well as many other applications, including a text-to-video tool called Jimeng.<!-- --></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A step toward fully 3D-printed active electronics (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.mit.edu/2024/mit-team-takes-major-step-toward-fully-3d-printed-active-electronics-1015</link>
            <guid>41899873</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 01:17:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2024/mit-team-takes-major-step-toward-fully-3d-printed-active-electronics-1015">https://news.mit.edu/2024/mit-team-takes-major-step-toward-fully-3d-printed-active-electronics-1015</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41899873">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
          

            <p>Active electronics — components that can control electrical signals — usually contain semiconductor devices that receive, store, and process information. These components, which must be made in a clean room, require advanced fabrication technology that is not widely available outside a few specialized manufacturing centers.</p><p>During the Covid-19 pandemic, the lack of widespread semiconductor fabrication facilities was one cause of a worldwide electronics shortage, which drove up costs for consumers and had implications in everything from&nbsp;<a href="https://news.mit.edu/2022/us-leadership-microelectronics-semiconductors-0119" target="_blank">economic growth to national defense</a>. The ability to 3D print an entire, active electronic device without the need for semiconductors could bring electronics fabrication to businesses, labs, and homes across the globe.</p><p>While this idea is still far off, MIT researchers have taken an important step in that direction by demonstrating fully 3D-printed resettable fuses, which are key components of active electronics that usually require semiconductors.</p><p>The researchers’ semiconductor-free devices, which they produced using standard 3D printing hardware and an inexpensive, biodegradable material, can perform the same switching functions as the semiconductor-based transistors used for processing operations in active electronics.</p><p>Although still far from achieving the performance of semiconductor transistors, the 3D-printed devices could be used for basic control operations like regulating the speed of an electric motor.</p><p>“This technology has real legs. While we cannot compete with silicon as a semiconductor, our idea is not to necessarily replace what is existing, but to push 3D printing technology into uncharted territory. In a nutshell, this is really about democratizing technology. This could allow anyone to create smart hardware far from traditional manufacturing centers,” says Luis Fernando Velásquez-García, a principal research scientist in MIT’s Microsystems Technology Laboratories (MTL) and senior author of a <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/17452759.2024.2404157" target="_blank">paper describing the devices</a>, which appears in <em>Virtual and Physical Prototyping.</em></p><p>He is joined on the paper by lead author Jorge Cañada, an electrical engineering and computer science graduate student.</p><p><strong>An unexpected project</strong></p><p>Semiconductors, including silicon, are materials with electrical properties that can be tailored by adding certain impurities. A silicon device can have conductive and insulating regions, depending on how it is engineered. These properties make silicon ideal for producing transistors, which are a basic building block of modern electronics.</p><p>However, the researchers didn’t set out to 3D-print semiconductor-free devices that could behave like silicon-based transistors.</p><p>This project grew out of another in which they were fabricating magnetic coils using extrusion printing, a process where the printer melts filament and squirts material through a nozzle, fabricating an object layer-by-layer.</p><p>They saw an interesting phenomenon in the material they were using, a polymer filament doped with copper nanoparticles.</p><p>If they passed a large amount of electric current into the material, it would exhibit a huge spike in resistance but would return to its original level shortly after the current flow stopped.</p><p>This property enables engineers to make transistors that can operate as switches, something that is typically only associated with silicon and other semiconductors. Transistors, which switch on and off to process binary data, are used to form logic gates which perform computation.</p><p>“We saw that this was something that could help take 3D printing hardware to the next level. It offers a clear way to provide some degree of ‘smart’ to an electronic device,” Velásquez-García says.</p><p>The researchers tried to replicate the same phenomenon with other 3D printing filaments, testing polymers doped with carbon, carbon nanotubes, and graphene. In the end, they could not find another printable material that could function as a resettable fuse.</p><p>They hypothesize that the copper particles in the material spread out when it is heated by the electric current, which causes a spike in resistance that comes back down when the material cools and the copper particles move closer together. They also think the polymer base of the material changes from crystalline to amorphous when heated, then returns to crystalline when cooled down — a phenomenon known as the polymeric positive temperature coefficient.</p><p>“For now, that is our best explanation, but that is not the full answer because that doesn’t explain why it only happened in this combination of materials. We need to do more research, but there is no doubt that this phenomenon is real,” he says.</p><p><strong>3D-printing active electronics</strong></p><p>The team leveraged the phenomenon to print switches in a single step that could be used to form semiconductor-free logic gates.</p><p>The devices are made from thin, 3D-printed traces of the copper-doped polymer. They contain intersecting conductive regions that enable the researchers to regulate the resistance by controlling the voltage fed into the switch.</p><p>While the devices did not perform as well as silicon-based transistors, they could be used for simpler control and processing functions, such as turning a motor on and off. Their experiments showed that, even after 4,000 cycles of switching, the devices showed no signs of deterioration.</p><p>But there are limits to how small the researchers can make the switches, based on the physics of extrusion printing and the properties of the material. They could print devices that were a few hundred microns, but transistors in state-of-the-art electronics are only few nanometers in diameter.</p><p>“The reality is that there are many engineering situations that don’t require the best chips. At the end of the day, all you care about is whether your device can do the task. This technology is able to satisfy a constraint like that,” he says.</p><p>However, unlike semiconductor fabrication, their technique uses a biodegradable material and the process uses less energy and produces less waste. The polymer filament could also be doped with other materials, like magnetic microparticles that could enable additional functionalities.</p><p>In the future, the researchers want to use this technology to print fully functional electronics. They are striving to fabricate a working magnetic motor using only extrusion 3D printing. They also want to finetune the process so they could build more complex circuits and see how far they can push the performance of these devices.</p><p>“This paper demonstrates that active electronic devices can be made using extruded polymeric conductive materials. This technology enables electronics to be built into 3D printed structures. An intriguing application is on-demand 3D printing of mechatronics on board spacecraft,” says Roger Howe, the William E. Ayer Professor of Engineering, Emeritus, at Stanford University, who was not involved with this work.</p><p>This work is funded, in part, by Empiriko Corporation.</p>        

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Learn Rust the Dangerous Way (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/</link>
            <guid>41899599</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:15:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/">https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41899599">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <header>
    
    
  </header>
  
  
  <p>LRtDW is a series of articles putting Rust features in context for low-level C
programmers who maybe don’t have a formal CS background — the sort of
people who work on firmware, game engines, OS kernels, and the like. Basically,
people like me.</p>
<p>I’ve added Rust to my toolbelt, and I hope to get you excited enough to do the
same.</p>
<ol start="0">
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/0/">Why Learn Rust the Dangerous Way?</a> Introduction and ground rules.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/1/">You can’t write C in just any ol’ language:</a> translating a grungy
optimized C program into grungy optimized unsafe Rust.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/2/">References available upon request:</a> how Rust <em>references</em> are
different from pointers, how they are the same, and why we care.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/3/">Measure what you optimize:</a> taking a hard look at an optimization
based on uninitialized memory, and converting it to safe code that’s just as
fast.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/4/">A more perfect union:</a> considering alternatives to pointer casting,
and how to write safe wrappers for <code>unsafe</code> operations.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/5/">Making safe things from unsafe parts:</a> finally converting most of the
program to safe code, and making sure that the <code>unsafe</code> bits are safe-ish.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><a href="https://cliffle.com/p/dangerust/6/">Let the compiler do the work:</a> a <strong>bonus section</strong> that looks at how
we’d write the program idiomatically in native Rust, and rely on
auto-vectorization to make it fast.</p>
</li>
</ol>

  
    <p><span>
      
        <a href="https://cliffle.com/tags/c/">#c</a>
      
        <a href="https://cliffle.com/tags/optimization/">#optimization</a>
      
        <a href="https://cliffle.com/tags/rust/">#rust</a>
      
        <a href="https://cliffle.com/tags/tutorial/">#tutorial</a>
      
    </span>
  
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Today is Ubuntu's 20th Anniversary (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000003.html</link>
            <guid>41898736</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 21:44:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000003.html">https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000003.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41898736">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
   
    <b>Mark Shuttleworth</b> 
    <a href="mailto:ubuntu-announce%40lists.ubuntu.com?Subject=Announcing%20Ubuntu%204.10%20%22The%20Warty%20Warthog%20Release%22&amp;In-Reply-To=" title="Announcing Ubuntu 4.10 &quot;The Warty Warthog Release&quot;">mark at hbd.com
       </a><br>
    <i>Wed Oct 20 11:06:23 CDT 2004</i>
    <ul>
        <li>Previous message: <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000002.html">Announcing Ubuntu 4.10 (Release Candidate)
</a></li>
        <li>Next message: <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000004.html">Warty Live CD Released
</a></li>
         <li> <b>Messages sorted by:</b> 
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/date.html#3">[ date ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/thread.html#3">[ thread ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/subject.html#3">[ subject ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/author.html#3">[ author ]</a>
         </li>
       </ul>
    <hr>  
<!--beginarticle-->
<pre>=== Announcing Ubuntu 4.10 "The Warty Warthog Release" ===

The warm-hearted Warthogs of the Warty Team are proud to present the
very first release of Ubuntu!

Ubuntu is a new Linux distribution that brings together the extraordinary
breadth of Debian with a fast and easy install, regular releases (every
six months), a tight selection of excellent packages installed by default
and a commitment to security updates with 18 months of security and
technical support for every release.

You get a distribution that is:

  * absolutely committed to free software,  every end-user application 
on the
    CD is free software

  * 100% free of charge, and the Ubuntu team is committed to keeping
    Ubuntu free of charge

  * security updates for the distribution at no charge for 18 months
    for any release

  * updated to the latest desktop and kernel and infrastructure every
    six months with a new release

  * supports x86, amd64 and ppc processors, with additional ports under
    way

If you've heard all about Ubuntu and just want to get the install CD or
test the Release Candidate Live CD, you can download it here immediately:

  <a href="http://www.ubuntulinux.org/download/">http://www.ubuntulinux.org/download/</a>

If you want a shrinkwrapped CD we will gladly ship it to you at no cost.
To receive a complimentary copy of the Warty Warthog CD -- or a handful
to give to your friends, your school or LUG, register online at:

  <a href="http://shipit.ubuntulinux.org/">http://shipit.ubuntulinux.org/</a>

For more information, you can turn to any of the following resources:

Ubuntu Website: <a href="http://www.ubuntulinux.org/">http://www.ubuntulinux.org</a>

  The website contains some basic background on Ubuntu, an
  overview of the project, information on how to get it, and
  some documentation for the software.

Ubuntu Wiki: <a href="http://wiki.ubuntulinux.org/">http://wiki.ubuntulinux.org</a>

  The wiki is a shared web space used by the Ubuntu community to
  develop new ideas for Ubuntu. Anybody is welcome to edit and
  add to the wiki.

Ubuntu IRC Channel: #ubuntu and on irc.freenode.net

  The Ubuntu IRC channel is your best place to start for help and
  discussion about Ubuntu and the Warty Warthog release. We aim
  to keep the signal-to-noise ratio as high as possible on that
  channel, and on all community forums.

Ubuntu Mailing Lists:

  Ubuntu mailing lists are the heart of our community. In addition to the
  announcement list, and lists for users and developers of Ubuntu,
  there are now Ubuntu mailing lists in German, French, Spanish as well
  as lists devoted to Ubuntu security, news, translators, and the
  inevitable lighthearted chitchat list ("the Sounder"). To get more
  information or subscribe, visit:

    <a href="http://lists.ubuntu.com/">http://lists.ubuntu.com</a>


Warty Warthog Features

 * Simple and fast Installation

   Ubuntu comes on one single CD, with thousands of extra packages
   available online. The install is optimised for speed and
   simplicity. Ubuntu has excellent support for laptops (both
   x86 based and Powerbook / iBook PPC based), and can also be
   setup in a minimalist server configuration.

 * GNOME 2.8

   Ubuntu was the first distribution to ship Gnome 2.8, on the day
   of the 2.8 release. Ubuntu is a great way to try out Gnome 2.8 if
   you have not already experienced its speed and simplicity.

 * Firefox 0.9 (with security patches)

 * First class productivity software

   Evolution 2.0 and OpenOffice.org 1.1.2

 * XFree86 4.3 with improved hardware support

   We also worked hard to detect as much hardware as possible,
   simplifying the X install considerably.

Warty can be installed in a minimalist mode for servers, or in full
desktop mode. It works well on laptops and desktops. Warty is secure
by design - a key goal was to ensure that Warty was as safe from attack
over the internet as possible after a default install.

Thanks to the team of professional and volunteer maintainers who have
worked so hard to bring the Warthog to life, and also to our rapidly
growing community, who have provided excellent testing and ideas for
the future of Ubuntu!

"Ubuntu" is an ancient African word for "humanity towards others", and
we think it's a perfect name for an open source community project. In
that spirit we invite you to join, to contribute and to share Ubuntu
with your own community. Our next release, the Hoary Hedgehog, is due
in six months time. You can help to shape it by joining the team
and contributing your own expertise. See you at #ubuntu on
irc.freenode.net.


</pre>


<!--endarticle-->
    <hr>
    <ul>
        <!--threads-->
	<li>Previous message: <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000002.html">Announcing Ubuntu 4.10 (Release Candidate)
</a></li>
	<li>Next message: <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/000004.html">Warty Live CD Released
</a></li>
         <li> <b>Messages sorted by:</b> 
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/date.html#3">[ date ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/thread.html#3">[ thread ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/subject.html#3">[ subject ]</a>
              <a href="https://lists.ubuntu.com/archives/ubuntu-announce/2004-October/author.html#3">[ author ]</a>
         </li>
       </ul>

<hr>
<a href="http://lists.ubuntu.com/mailman/listinfo/ubuntu-announce">More information about the ubuntu-announce
mailing list</a><br>

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft said it lost weeks of security logs for its customers' cloud products (275 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/10/17/microsoft-said-it-lost-weeks-of-security-logs-for-its-customers-cloud-products/</link>
            <guid>41898723</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2024 21:42:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/10/17/microsoft-said-it-lost-weeks-of-security-logs-for-its-customers-cloud-products/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/10/17/microsoft-said-it-lost-weeks-of-security-logs-for-its-customers-cloud-products/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41898723">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">Microsoft has notified customers that it’s missing more than two weeks of security logs for some of its cloud products, leaving network defenders without critical data for detecting possible intrusions.</p>

<p>According to a notification sent to affected customers, Microsoft said that “a bug in one of Microsoft’s internal monitoring agents resulted in a malfunction in some of the agents when uploading log data to our internal logging platform” between September 2 and September 19.&nbsp;</p>







<p>The notification said that the logging outage was not caused by a security incident, and “only affected the collection of log events.”&nbsp;</p>

<p>Business Insider <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/microsoft-tells-customers-it-lost-log-data-key-security-products-2024-10" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">first reported</a> the loss of log data earlier in October. Details of the notification have not been widely reported. As noted by <a href="https://cyberplace.social/@GossiTheDog/113313392062371141" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">security researcher Kevin Beaumont</a>, the notifications that Microsoft sent to affected companies are likely accessible only to a handful of users with tenant admin rights.</p>

<p>Logging helps to keep track of events within a product, such as information about users signing in and failed attempts, which can help network defenders identify suspected intrusions. Missing logs could make it more difficult to identify unauthorized access to the customers’ networks during that two-week window.&nbsp;</p>

<p>The affected products include Microsoft Entra, Sentinel, Defender for Cloud, and Purview, according to the Business Insider report. Affected customers “may have experienced potential gaps in security related logs or events, possibly affecting customers’ ability to analyze data, detect threats, or generate security alerts,” the notification said.</p>

<p>Microsoft would not answer specific questions about the logging outage, but a Microsoft executive confirmed to TechCrunch that the incident was caused by an “operational bug within our internal monitoring agent.”</p>


<p>“We have mitigated the issue by rolling back a service change. We have communicated to all impacted customers and will provide support as needed,” said John Sheehan, a Microsoft corporate vice president.</p>

<p>The logging outage comes a year after Microsoft <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/07/17/microsoft-lost-keys-government-hacked/">came under fire from federal investigators</a> for withholding security logs from certain U.S. federal government departments that host their emails on the company’s hardened, government-only cloud; investigators said having access to those logs could have identified a series of China-backed intrusions far sooner.</p>

<p>The China-backed intruders, referred to as Storm-0558, broke into Microsoft’s network and stole a digital skeleton key that allowed the hackers unfettered access to U.S. government emails stored in Microsoft’s cloud. According to a <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/11/cyber-security-review-board-microsoft-hack-government-emails/">government-issued postmortem of the cyberattack</a>, the State Department identified the intrusions because it paid for a higher-tier Microsoft license that granted access to security logs for its cloud products, which many other hacked U.S. government agencies did not have.</p>







<p>Following the China-backed hacks, Microsoft said <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/microsoft-to-offer-some-cybersecurity-tools-free-after-suspected-china-hack-6db94221" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">it would start providing logs</a> to its lower-paid cloud accounts from September 2023.</p>

<p><em>Carly Page contributed reporting.</em></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>