<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 21:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GPT-4.5 (291 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-4-5/</link>
            <guid>43197872</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 20:01:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-4-5/">https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-4-5/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43197872">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/introducing-gpt-4-5/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EA Open Sources Command and Conquer: Red Alert (480 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/electronicarts/CnC_Red_Alert</link>
            <guid>43197131</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 18:42:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/electronicarts/CnC_Red_Alert">https://github.com/electronicarts/CnC_Red_Alert</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43197131">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Command &amp; Conquer Red Alert</h2><a id="user-content-command--conquer-red-alert" aria-label="Permalink: Command &amp; Conquer Red Alert" href="#command--conquer-red-alert"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository includes source code for Command &amp; Conquer Red Alert. This release provides support to the <a href="https://steamcommunity.com/workshop/browse/?appid=2229840" rel="nofollow">Steam Workshop</a> for the game.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Dependencies</h2><a id="user-content-dependencies" aria-label="Permalink: Dependencies" href="#dependencies"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you wish to rebuild the source code and tools successfully you will need to find or write new replacements (or remove the code using them entirely) for the following libraries;</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>DirectX 5 SDK</li>
<li>DirectX Media 5.1 SDK</li>
<li>Greenleaf Communications Library (GCL)</li>
<li>Human Machine Interface (HMI) “Sound Operating System” (SOS)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Compiling (Win32 Only)</h2><a id="user-content-compiling-win32-only" aria-label="Permalink: Compiling (Win32 Only)" href="#compiling-win32-only"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The current state of the source code does not fully compile and will require some effort to restore it. If you wish to restore the original build environment, the following tools are required;</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Watcom C/C++ (v10.6) for C/C++ source files</li>
<li>Borland Turbo Assembler (TASM v4.0) for assembly files</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To use the compiled binaries, you must own the game. The C&amp;C Ultimate Collection is available for purchase on <a href="https://www.ea.com/en-gb/games/command-and-conquer/command-and-conquer-the-ultimate-collection/buy/pc" rel="nofollow">EA App</a> or <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/bundle/39394/Command__Conquer_The_Ultimate_Collection/" rel="nofollow">Steam</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository will not be accepting contributions (pull requests, issues, etc). If you wish to create changes to the source code and encourage collaboration, please create a fork of the repository under your GitHub user/organization space.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Support</h2><a id="user-content-support" aria-label="Permalink: Support" href="#support"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository is for preservation purposes only and is archived without support.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository and its contents are licensed under the GPL v3 license, with additional terms applied. Please see <a href="https://github.com/electronicarts/CnC_Red_Alert/blob/main/LICENSE.md">LICENSE.md</a> for details.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Goodbye K-9 Mail (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cketti.de/2025/02/26/goodbye-k9mail/</link>
            <guid>43196436</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 17:26:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cketti.de/2025/02/26/goodbye-k9mail/">https://cketti.de/2025/02/26/goodbye-k9mail/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43196436">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article role="main">
        <p><strong>TL;DR:</strong> I quit my job working on <a href="https://www.thunderbird.net/mobile/">Thunderbird for Android</a> and <a href="https://k9mail.app/">K-9 Mail</a> at MZLA.</p>

<p>My personal journey with K-9 Mail started in late 2009, shortly after getting my first Android device<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup>. The pre-installed Email app didn’t work very well with my email provider. When looking for alternatives, I discovered K-9 Mail. It had many of the same issues<sup id="fnref:2" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. But it was an active open source project that accepted contributions. I started fixing the problems I was experiencing and contributed these changes to K-9 Mail. It was a very pleasant experience and so I started fixing bugs reported by other users.</p>

<p>In February 2010, <a href="https://metasocial.com/@jesse">Jesse Vincent</a>, the founder of the K-9 Mail project, offered me commit access to the Subversion<sup id="fnref:3" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> repository. According to my email archive, I replied with the following text:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Thank you! I really enjoyed writing patches for K-9 and gladly accept your offer. But I probably won’t be able to devote as much time to the project as I do right now for a very long time. I hope that’s not a big problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>My prediction turned out to be not quite accurate. I was able to spend a lot of time working on K-9 Mail and quickly became one of the most active contributors.</p>

<p>In 2012, Jesse hired me to work on <a href="https://kaitenmail.com/">Kaiten Mail</a>, a commercial closed-source fork of K-9 Mail. The only real differences between the apps were moderate changes to the user interface. So most of the features and bug fixes we created for Kaiten Mail also went into K-9 Mail. This was important to me and one of the reasons I took the job.</p>

<p>In early 2014, Jesse made me the <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/k-9-mail/c/6OzXyOoksf8/m/xrbvkd1xO8AJ">K-9 Mail project leader</a><sup id="fnref:4" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup>. With Kaiten Mail, end-user support was eating up a lot of time and eventually motivation to work on the app. So we stopped working on it around the same time and the app slowly faded away.</p>

<p>To pay the bills, I started working as a freelancing Android developer<sup id="fnref:5" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup>. Maybe not surprisingly, more often than not I was contracted to work on email clients. Whenever I was working on a closed source fork of K-9 Mail<sup id="fnref:6" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup>, I had a discounted hourly rate that would apply when working on things that were contributed to K-9 Mail. This was mostly bug fixes, but also the odd feature every now and then.</p>

<p>After a contract ended in 2019, I decided to apply for a grant from the <a href="https://prototypefund.de/">Prototype Fund</a> to work on adding JMAP support to K-9 Mail<sup id="fnref:7" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup>. This allowed me to basically work full-time on the project. When the funding period ended in 2020, the COVID-19 pandemic was in full swing. At that time I didn’t feel like looking for a new contract. I filled my days working on K-9 Mail to mute the feeling of despair about the world. I summarized my 2020 in the blog post <a href="https://cketti.de/2021/01/14/my-first-year-as-a-full-time-open-source-developer/">My first year as a full-time open source developer</a>.</p>

<p>Eventually I had to figure out how to finance this full-time open source developer lifestyle. I ended up <a href="https://k9mail.app/2021/02/14/K-9-Mail-is-looking-for-funding">asking</a> K-9 Mail users to donate so I could be paid to dedicate 80% of my time to work on the app. This worked out quite nicely and I wrote about it here: <a href="https://k9mail.app/2022/01/18/2021-in-Review">2021 in Review</a>.</p>

<p>I first learned about plans to create a Thunderbird version for Android in late 2019. I was approached because one of the options considered was basing Thunderbird for Android on K-9 Mail. At the time, I wasn’t really interested in working on Thunderbird for Android. But I was more than happy to help turn the K-9 Mail code base into something that Thunderbird could use as a base for their own app. However, it seemed the times where we had availability to work on such a project never aligned. And so nothing concrete happened. But we stayed in contact.</p>

<p>In December 2021, it seemed to have become a priority to find a solution for the many Thunderbird users asking for an Android app. By that time, I had realized that funding an open source project via donations requires an ongoing fundraising effort. Thunderbird was already doing this for quite some time and getting pretty good at it. I, on the other hand, was not looking forward to the idea of getting better at fundraising.<br>
So, when I was asked again whether I was interested in K-9 Mail and myself joining the Thunderbird project, I said yes. It took another six months for us to figure out the details and <a href="https://k9mail.app/2022/06/13/K-9-Mail-and-Thunderbird">announce</a> the news to the public.</p>

<p>Once under the Thunderbird umbrella, we worked<sup id="fnref:8" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:8" rel="footnote">8</a></sup> on adding features to K-9 Mail that we wanted an initial version of Thunderbird for Android to have. The mobile team slowly grew to include another <a href="https://blog.thunderbird.net/2023/03/thunderbird-for-android-k-9-mail-february-progress-report/">Android developer</a>, then a <a href="https://blog.thunderbird.net/2024/07/thunderbird-for-android-k-9-mail-june-2024-progress-report/">manager</a>. While organizationally the design team was its own group, there was always at least one designer available to work with the mobile team on the Android app. And then there were a bunch of other teams to do the things for which you don’t need Android engineers: support, communication, donations, etc.</p>

<p>In October 2024, we finally released the <a href="https://blog.thunderbird.net/2024/10/thunderbird-for-android-8-0-takes-flight/">first version of Thunderbird for Android</a>. The months leading up to the release were quite stressful for me. All of us were working on many things at the same time to not let the targeted release date slip too much. We never worked overtime, though. And we got additional paid time off after the release ❤️</p>

<p>After a long vacation, we started 2025 with a more comfortable pace. However, the usual joy I felt when working on the app, didn’t return. I finally realized this at the beginning of February, while being sick in bed and having nothing better to do than contemplating life.<br>
I don’t think I was close to a burnout – work wasn’t that much fun anymore, but it was far from being unbearable. I’ve been there before. And in the past it never was a problem to step away from K-9 Mail for a few months. However, it’s different when it’s your job. But since I am in the very fortunate position of being able to afford taking a couple of months off, I decided to do just that. So the question was whether to take a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sabbatical">sabbatical</a> or to quit.<br>
Realistically, permanently walking away from K-9 Mail never was an option in the past. There was no one else to take over as a maintainer. It would have most likely meant the end of the project. K-9 Mail was always too important to me to let that happen.<br>
But this is no longer an issue. There’s now a whole team behind the project and me stepping away no longer is an existential threat to the app.</p>

<p>I want to explore what it feels like to do something else without going back to the project being a foregone conclusion. That is why I quit my job at MZLA.</p>

<p>It was a great job and I had awesome coworkers. I can totally recommend <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/careers/listings/?team=MZLA/Thunderbird">working</a> with these people and will miss doing so 😢</p>

<hr>

<p>I have no idea what I’ll end up doing next. A coworker asked me whether I’ll stick to writing software or do something else entirely. I was quite surprised by this question. Both because in hindsight it felt like an obvious question to ask and because I’ve never even considered doing something else. I guess that means I’m very much still a software person and will be for the foreseeable future.</p>

<p>During my vacation I very much enjoyed being a beginner and learning about technology I haven’t worked with as a developer before (NFC smartcards, USB HID, Bluetooth LE). So I will probably start a lot of personal projects and finish few to none of them 😃</p>

<p>I think there’s a good chance that – after an appropriately sized break – I will return as a volunteer contributor to K-9 Mail/Thunderbird for Android.</p>

<p>But for now, I say: <strong>Goodbye K-9 Mail</strong> 👋</p>

<hr>

<p>This leaves me with saying thank you to everyone who contributed to K-9 Mail and Thunderbird for Android over the years. People wrote code, translated the app, reported bugs, helped other users, gave money, promoted the app, and much more. Thank you all 🙏</p>

<hr>



      </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Turning a Bluetooth device into an Apple AirTag without root privileges (259 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nroottag.github.io/</link>
            <guid>43196207</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 17:03:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nroottag.github.io/">https://nroottag.github.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43196207">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

<div>
                    <h2>Tracking You from a Thousand Miles Away! Turning a
                        Bluetooth Device into an Apple AirTag Without Root Privileges</h2>
                    

                    <p><span>George Mason University<br>USENIX Security 2025</span>
                    </p>

                    
                </div>


<div>
            <p>
                <img src="https://nroottag.github.io/static/images/main.png" alt="Attacking billions of devices">
            </p>
            
            <p>
                A remote attacker can exploit this vulnerability to turn your device—whether it’s a desktop, smartphone,
                or smartwatch—into an AirTag-like tracker, enabling the attacker to track your location.
                How does it work? Over 1.5 billion iPhones could act as free tracking agents for the attacker worldwide.
            </p>
        </div>

<!-- Paper abstract -->
<div>
                <h2>Abstract</h2>
                <p>
                        Apple’s Find My network, leveraging over a billion active Apple devices, is the world’s largest
                        device-locating network.
                        We investigate the potential misuse of this network to maliciously track Bluetooth devices. We
                        present <em>nRootTag</em>,
                        a novel attack method that transforms computers into trackable “AirTags” without requiring root
                        privileges.
                        The attack achieves a success rate of over 90% within minutes at a cost of only a few US
                        dollars.
                        Or, a rainbow table can be built to search keys instantly.
                        Subsequently, it can locate a computer in minutes, posing a substantial risk to user privacy and
                        safety.
                        The attack is effective on Linux, Windows, and Android systems, and can be employed to track
                        desktops, laptops,
                        smartphones, and IoT devices.
                        Our comprehensive evaluation demonstrates nRootTag’s effectiveness and efficiency across various
                        scenarios.
                    </p>
            </div>
<!-- End paper abstract -->


<div>
                    <h2>Overview of Find My Offline Finding</h2>
                    <p>
                        <img src="https://nroottag.github.io/static/images/findmy_overview.jpg" alt="Overview">
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Figure illustrates the overview of Find My offline finding.
                        (1) Through pairing, an AirTag shares the public / private key
                        information with the owner’s device. (2) When the AirTag is
                        separated from the paired device, it advertises its public key
                        via BLE advertisements, known as lost messages. (3) Nearby
                        Apple devices, referred to as finders, generate encrypted lo
                        cation reports and send them, along with the hashed public
                        key, to the Apple Cloud. (4) The Apple Cloud allows anyone
                        to use a hashed public key to retrieve the associated location
                        reports, which can only be decrypted using the correct private
                        key. To ensure anonymity, finders do not authenticate whether
                        a lost message is sent from an Apple device.
                    </p>
                </div>


<div>
                    <h2>Architecture of nRootTag</h2>
                    <div>
                        <p>
                            <img src="https://nroottag.github.io/static/images/architecture.webp" alt="Sizes of model trees">
                        </p>
                        <p>
                            Figure illustrates the architecture of our design.
                            (1) The Trojan code runs on the computer to be tracked. It retrieves the
                            advertising address, acquires the matching public key from our server, and then advertises
                            lost messages.
                            (2) The Server processes requests for acquiring public keys through rainbow table
                            lookup or online key search.
                            (3) The Database system, which contains a rainbow table of key information,
                            provides the corresponding public/private key pair for a given advertising address.
                            (4) The Key Generation and Search serves two purposes: it is used to precompute the
                            rainbow table,
                            and invoked to search for a matching public/private key pair on the fly.
                            Finally, given a public key, the server uses its hash value to query the Apple Cloud for
                            location reports, then decrypts the reports using the private key.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>


<div>
                    <h2>GPU Benchmark</h2>
                    <p>
                        <img src="https://nroottag.github.io/static/images/GridSize_KPS.png" alt="ProbeX Overview">
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        Our study examined several consumer-grade GPUs, such as the RTX 3070, RTX 3080, and RTX 4090,
                        as well as data center-grade GPUs, the A100 (80GB) and H100 (80GB).

                        Although the H100 achieves the highest key generation speed, its prohibitively high cost makes
                        the RTX 3080 a more economical option for performance.
                    </p>

                </div>


<div>
                    <h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
                    <div><p>
                        This work was supported in part by the US National Science Foundation (NSF) under grants
                        CNS-2304720, CNS-2310322, CNS-2309550, and
                        CNS-2309477. It was also supported in part by the Commonwealth Cyber Initiative (CCI).
                        The authors extend their gratitude to the anonymous reviewers and shepherd for their invaluable
                        feedback and suggestions. We also acknowledge Google Earth for the map tiles used in our
                        figures.
                        </p><p>
                        
                        In addition, we appreciate the help from the Apple Security Team for their prompt responses and
                        acknowledgement. Apple recently released patches in
                        iOS 18.2,
                        visionOS 2.2,
                        iPadOS 17.7.3, 18.2,
                        watchOS 11.2,
                        tvOS 18.2,
                        macOS Ventura 13.7.2, Sonoma 14.7.2, Sequoia 15.2 to fix the vulnerability. However, the attack
                        remains effective as long as unpatched iPhones or Apple Watches are in the proximity of the
                        computer running our trojan.
</p><!--                        We extend our gratitude to William Flores-->
<!--                        <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/willlflow/" class="icon">-->
<!--                            <i class="fab fa-linkedin"></i>-->
<!--                        </a>-->
<!--                        for his expert consultancy in CUDA and C++ development.-->
                    </div>

                    <p>
                        <img src="https://nroottag.github.io/static/images/apple_security_update.png" alt="Model retrieval">
                    </p>
                    <p>
                        <img src="https://nroottag.github.io/static/images/apple_acknowledgement.png" alt="Model retrieval">
                    </p>

                </div>


<!--BibTex citation -->
<div id="BibTeX">
        <h2>BibTeX</h2>
        <pre><code>
@inproceedings{chen2025track,
title={Tracking You from a Thousand Miles Away! Turning a Bluetooth Device into an Apple AirTag Without Root Privileges},
author={Chen, Junming and Ma, Xiaoyue and Luo, Lannan and Zeng, Qiang},
booktitle={USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX Security)},
year={2025}
}
        </code></pre>
    </div>
<!--End BibTex citation -->






</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Distributed Systems Programming Has Stalled (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.shadaj.me/writing/distributed-programming-stalled</link>
            <guid>43195702</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 16:12:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.shadaj.me/writing/distributed-programming-stalled">https://www.shadaj.me/writing/distributed-programming-stalled</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43195702">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Over the last decade, we’ve seen great advancements in distributed systems, but the way we program them has seen few fundamental improvements. While we can sometimes abstract away distribution (Spark, Redis, etc.), developers still struggle with challenges like concurrency, fault tolerance, and versioning.</p>
<p>There are lots of people (and startups) working on this. But nearly all focus on tooling to help analyze distributed systems written in classic (sequential) programming languages. Tools like <a href="https://jepsen.io/">Jepsen</a> and <a href="https://antithesis.com/">Antithesis</a> have advanced the state-of-the-art for verifying correctness and fault tolerance, but tooling is no match for programming models that natively surface fundamental concepts. We’ve already seen this with Rust, which provides memory safety guarantees that are far richer than C++ with AddressSanitizer.</p>
<p>If you look online, there are tons of frameworks for writing distributed code. In this blog post, I’ll make the case that they only offer band-aids and sugar over three fixed underlying paradigms: <strong>external-distribution</strong>, <strong>static-location</strong>, and <strong>arbitrary-location</strong>. We’re still missing a programming model that is <em>native</em> to distributed systems. We’ll walk through these paradigms then reflect on what’s missing for a truly distributed programming model.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>External-distribution</strong> architectures are what the vast majority of “distributed” systems look like. In this model, software is written as <em>sequential logic</em> that runs against a state management system with <em>sequential semantics</em>:</p>
<ul>
<li>Stateless Services with a Distributed Database (Aurora DSQL, Cockroach)</li>
<li>Services using gossiped CRDT state (Ditto, ElectricSQL, Redis Enterprise)<sup>1</sup>1<span>1<!-- -->. <!-- -->This may come as a surprise. CRDTs are often marketed as a silver bullet for all distributed systems, but another perspective is they simply <a href="https://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol16/p856-power.pdf">accelerate distributed transactions</a>. Software running over CRDTs is still sequential. <a href="#user-content-fnref-this%20may%20come%20as%20a%20surprise.%20crdts%20are%20often%20marketed%20as%20a%20silver%20bullet%20for%20all%20distributed%20systems,%20but%20another%20perspective%20is%20they%20simply%20accelerate%20distributed%20transactions.%20software%20running%20over%20crdts%20is%20still%20sequential." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></span><span><span>This may come as a surprise. CRDTs are often marketed as a silver bullet for all distributed systems, but another perspective is they simply <a href="https://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol16/p856-power.pdf">accelerate distributed transactions</a>. Software running over CRDTs is still sequential. <a href="#user-content-fnref-this%20may%20come%20as%20a%20surprise.%20crdts%20are%20often%20marketed%20as%20a%20silver%20bullet%20for%20all%20distributed%20systems,%20but%20another%20perspective%20is%20they%20simply%20accelerate%20distributed%20transactions.%20software%20running%20over%20crdts%20is%20still%20sequential." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></span></span></li>
<li>Workflows and Step Functions</li>
</ul>
<p>These architectures are easy to write software in, because none of the underlying distribution is exposed<sup>2</sup>2<span>2<!-- -->. <!-- -->Well that’s the idea, at least. Serializability typically isn’t the default (<a href="https://jepsen.io/consistency/models/snapshot-isolation">snapshot isolation</a> is), so concurrency bugs can sometimes be exposed. <a href="#user-content-fnref-well%20that%E2%80%99s%20the%20idea,%20at%20least.%20serializability%20typically%20isn%E2%80%99t%20the%20default%20(snapshot%20isolation%20is),%20so%20concurrency%20bugs%20can%20sometimes%20be%20exposed." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></span><span><span>Well that’s the idea, at least. Serializability typically isn’t the default (<a href="https://jepsen.io/consistency/models/snapshot-isolation">snapshot isolation</a> is), so concurrency bugs can sometimes be exposed. <a href="#user-content-fnref-well%20that%E2%80%99s%20the%20idea,%20at%20least.%20serializability%20typically%20isn%E2%80%99t%20the%20default%20(snapshot%20isolation%20is),%20so%20concurrency%20bugs%20can%20sometimes%20be%20exposed." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></span></span> to the developer! Although this architecture results in a distributed <em>system</em>, we do not have a distributed <em>programming model</em>.</p>
<p>There is little need to reason about fault-tolerance or concurrency bugs (other than making sure to opt into the right consistency levels for CRDTs). So it’s clear why developers opt for this option, since it hides the distributed chaos under a clean, sequential semantics. But this comes at a clear cost: performance and scalability.</p>
<p>Serializing everything is tantamount to <em>emulating</em> a non-distributed system, but with expensive coordination protocols. The database forms a single point of failure in your system; you either hope that us-east-1 doesn’t go down or switch to a multi-writer system like Cockroach that comes with its own performance implications. Many applications are at sufficiently low scale to tolerate this, but you wouldn’t want to <a href="https://netflixtechblog.com/netflixs-distributed-counter-abstraction-8d0c45eb66b2">implement a counter</a> like this.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Static-location</strong> architectures are the classic way to write distributed code. You compose several units—each written as <em>local (single-machine)</em> code that communicates with other machines using asynchronous network calls:</p>
<ul>
<li>Services communicating with API calls, possibly using async / await (gRPC, REST)</li>
<li>Actors (Akka, Ray, Orleans)</li>
<li>Services polling and pushing to a shared pub/sub (Kafka)</li>
</ul>
<p>These architectures give us full, low-level control. We’re writing a bunch of sequential, single-machine software with network calls. This is great for performance and fault-tolerance because we control what gets run where and when.</p>
<p>But the boundaries between networked units are <strong>rigid and opaque</strong>. Developers must make one-way decisions on how to break up their application. These decisions have a wide impact on correctness; retries and message ordering are controlled by the sender and unknown to the recipient. Furthermore, the language and tooling have limited insight into how units are composed. Jump-to-definition is often unavailable, and serialization mismatches across services can easily creep in.</p>
<p>Most importantly, this approach to distributed systems fundamentally eliminates <strong>semantic co-location and modularity.</strong> In sequential code, things that happen one after the other are <em>textually placed</em> one after the other and function calls encapsulate <em>entire algorithms</em>. But with static-location architectures, developers are coerced to modularize code on machine boundaries, rather than on semantic boundaries. In these architectures there is simply no way to encapsulate a distributed algorithm as a single, unified semantic unit.</p>
<p>Although static-location architectures offer developers the most low-level control over their system, in practice they are difficult to implement robustly without distributed systems expertise. There is a fundamental mismatch between <em>implementation</em> and <em>execution</em>: static-location software is written as single-machine code, but the correctness of the system requires reasoning about the fleet of machines as a whole. Teams building such systems often live in fear of concurrency bugs and failures, leading to mountains of legacy code that are too critical to touch.</p>
<hr>
<p><strong>Arbitrary-location</strong> architectures are the foundation of most “modern” approaches to distributed systems. These architectures simplify distributed systems by letting to write code as if it were running on a single machine, but at runtime the software is <em>dynamically</em> executed <em>across several machines</em><sup>3</sup>3<span>3<!-- -->. <!-- -->Actor frameworks don’t <em>really</em> count even if they support migration, since the developer still has to explicitly define the boundaries of an actor and specify where message passing happens <a href="#user-content-fnref-actor%20frameworks%20don%E2%80%99t%20really%20count%20even%20if%20they%20support%20migration,%20since%20the%20developer%20still%20has%20to%20explicitly%20define%20the%20boundaries%20of%20an%20actor%20and%20specify%20where%20message%20passing%20happens" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></span><span><span>Actor frameworks don’t <em>really</em> count even if they support migration, since the developer still has to explicitly define the boundaries of an actor and specify where message passing happens <a href="#user-content-fnref-actor%20frameworks%20don%E2%80%99t%20really%20count%20even%20if%20they%20support%20migration,%20since%20the%20developer%20still%20has%20to%20explicitly%20define%20the%20boundaries%20of%20an%20actor%20and%20specify%20where%20message%20passing%20happens" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></span></span><strong>:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Distributed SQL Engines</li>
<li>MapReduce Frameworks (Hadoop, Spark)</li>
<li>Stream Processing (Flink, Spark Streaming, Storm)</li>
<li>Durable Execution (Temporal, DBOS, Azure Durable Functions)</li>
</ul>
<p>These architectures elegantly handle the co-location problem since there are no explicit network boundaries in the language/API to split your code across. But this simplicity comes at a significant cost: <strong>control</strong>. By letting the runtime decide how the code is distributed, we lose the ability to make decisions about how the application is scaled, where the fault domains lie, and when data is sent over the network.</p>
<p>Just like the external-distribution model, arbitrary-location architectures often come with a performance cost. Durable execution systems typically snapshot their state to a persistent store between every step<sup>4</sup>4<span>4<!-- -->. <!-- -->With some optimizations when a step is a pure, deterministic function <a href="#user-content-fnref-with%20some%20optimizations%20when%20a%20step%20is%20a%20pure,%20deterministic%20function" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4">↩</a></span><span><span>With some optimizations when a step is a pure, deterministic function <a href="#user-content-fnref-with%20some%20optimizations%20when%20a%20step%20is%20a%20pure,%20deterministic%20function" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4">↩</a></span></span>. Stream processing systems may dynamically persist data and are free to introduce asynchrony across steps. SQL users are at the mercy of the query optimizer, to which they at best can only give “hints” on distribution decisions.</p>
<p>We often need low-level control over where individual logic is placed for performance and correctness. Consider implementing Two-Phase Commit. This protocol has explicit, asymmetric roles for a leader that broadcasts proposals and workers that acknowledge them. To correctly implement such a protocol, we need to explicitly assign specific logic to these roles, since quorums must be determined on a single leader and each worker must atomically decide to accept or reject a proposal. It’s simply not possible to implement such a protocol in an arbitrary-location architecture without introducing unnecessary networking and coordination overhead.</p>
<h2>Obligatory LLM Section</h2>
<p>If you’ve been following the “agentic” LLM space, you might be wondering: “Are any of these issues relevant in a world where my software is being written by an LLM?” If the static-location model is sufficiently rich to express all distributed systems, who cares if it’s painful to program in!</p>
<p>I’d argue that LLMs actually are a great argument why we <em>need</em> a new programming model. These models famously struggle under scenarios where contextually-relevant information is scattered across large bodies of text<sup>5</sup>5<span>5<!-- -->. <!-- -->See the <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/ai-machine-learning/the-needle-in-the-haystack-test-and-how-gemini-pro-solves-it">Needle in a Haystack Test</a>; reasoning about distributed systems is even harder. <a href="#user-content-fnref-see%20the%20needle%20in%20a%20haystack%20test;%20reasoning%20about%20distributed%20systems%20is%20even%20harder." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 5">↩</a></span><span><span>See the <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/ai-machine-learning/the-needle-in-the-haystack-test-and-how-gemini-pro-solves-it">Needle in a Haystack Test</a>; reasoning about distributed systems is even harder. <a href="#user-content-fnref-see%20the%20needle%20in%20a%20haystack%20test;%20reasoning%20about%20distributed%20systems%20is%20even%20harder." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 5">↩</a></span></span>. LLMs do best when semantically-relevant information is co-located.</p>
<p>The static-location model forces us to split up our semantically-connected distributed logic across several modules. LLMs aren’t great yet at correctness on a single machine; it is well beyond their abilities to compose several single-machine programs that work together correctly. Furthermore, LLMs make decisions sequentially; splitting up distributed logic across several networked modules is inherently challenging to the very structure of AI models.</p>
<p>LLMs would do far better with a programming model that retains “semantic locality”. In a hypothetical programming model where code that spans several machines can be co-located, this problem becomes trivial. All the relevant logic for a distributed algorithm would be right next to each other, and the LLM can generate distributed logic in a straight-line manner.</p>
<p>The other piece of the puzzle is correctness. LLMs make mistakes, and our best bet is to combine them with tools that can automatically discover them<sup>6</sup>6<span>6<!-- -->. <!-- -->Lean is a great example of this in action. Teams including <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/ai-solves-imo-problems-at-silver-medal-level/">Google</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.14333">Deepseek</a> have been using it for some time. <a href="#user-content-fnref-lean%20is%20a%20great%20example%20of%20this%20in%20action.%20teams%20including%20google%20and%20deepseek%20have%20been%20using%20it%20for%20some%20time." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 6">↩</a></span><span><span>Lean is a great example of this in action. Teams including <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/ai-solves-imo-problems-at-silver-medal-level/">Google</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.14333">Deepseek</a> have been using it for some time. <a href="#user-content-fnref-lean%20is%20a%20great%20example%20of%20this%20in%20action.%20teams%20including%20google%20and%20deepseek%20have%20been%20using%20it%20for%20some%20time." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 6">↩</a></span></span>. Sequential models have no way to reason about the ways distributed execution might cause trouble. But a sufficiently rich distributed programming model could surface issues arising from network delays and faults (think a borrow-checker, but for distributed systems).</p>
<h2>What can we take from these systems?</h2>
<p>Although the programming models we’ve discussed each have several limitations, they also demonstrate desirable features that a native programming model for distributed systems should support. What can we learn from each model?</p>
<p>I’m going to skip over external-distribution, which as we discussed is not quite distributed. For applications that can tolerate the performance and semantic restrictions of this model, this is the way to go. But for a general distributed programming model, we can’t keep networking and concurrency hidden from the developer.</p>
<p>The static-location model seems like the right place to start, since it is at least capable of <em>expressing</em> all the types of distributed systems we might want to implement, even if the programming model offers us little help in <em>reasoning</em> about the distribution. We were missing two things that the arbitrary-location model offered:</p>
<ul>
<li>Writing logic that spans several machines right next to each other, in a single function</li>
<li>Surfacing semantic information on distributed behavior such as message reordering, retries, and serialization formats across network boundaries</li>
</ul>
<p>Each of these points have a dual, something we don’t want to give up:</p>
<ul>
<li>Explicit control over placement of logic on machines, with the ability to perform local, atomic computations</li>
<li>Rich options for fault tolerance guarantees and network semantics, without the language locking us into global coordination and recovery protocols</li>
</ul>
<p>It’s time for a <em>native</em> programming model—a Rust-for-distributed systems, if you will—that addresses all of these.</p>
<p><em>Thanks to</em> <a href="https://tylerhou.com/"><em>Tyler Hou</em></a><em>,</em> <a href="https://dsf.berkeley.edu/jmh/"><em>Joe Hellerstein</em></a><em>, and</em> <a href="https://www.ramnivas.com/about"><em>Ramnivas Laddad</em></a> <em>for feedback on this post!</em></p>
<section data-footnotes="true">
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-this%20may%20come%20as%20a%20surprise.%20crdts%20are%20often%20marketed%20as%20a%20silver%20bullet%20for%20all%20distributed%20systems,%20but%20another%20perspective%20is%20they%20simply%20accelerate%20distributed%20transactions.%20software%20running%20over%20crdts%20is%20still%20sequential.">
<p>This may come as a surprise. CRDTs are often marketed as a silver bullet for all distributed systems, but another perspective is they simply <a href="https://www.vldb.org/pvldb/vol16/p856-power.pdf">accelerate distributed transactions</a>. Software running over CRDTs is still sequential. <a href="#user-content-fnref-this%20may%20come%20as%20a%20surprise.%20crdts%20are%20often%20marketed%20as%20a%20silver%20bullet%20for%20all%20distributed%20systems,%20but%20another%20perspective%20is%20they%20simply%20accelerate%20distributed%20transactions.%20software%20running%20over%20crdts%20is%20still%20sequential." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-well%20that%E2%80%99s%20the%20idea,%20at%20least.%20serializability%20typically%20isn%E2%80%99t%20the%20default%20(snapshot%20isolation%20is),%20so%20concurrency%20bugs%20can%20sometimes%20be%20exposed.">
<p>Well that’s the idea, at least. Serializability typically isn’t the default (<a href="https://jepsen.io/consistency/models/snapshot-isolation">snapshot isolation</a> is), so concurrency bugs can sometimes be exposed. <a href="#user-content-fnref-well%20that%E2%80%99s%20the%20idea,%20at%20least.%20serializability%20typically%20isn%E2%80%99t%20the%20default%20(snapshot%20isolation%20is),%20so%20concurrency%20bugs%20can%20sometimes%20be%20exposed." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-actor%20frameworks%20don%E2%80%99t%20really%20count%20even%20if%20they%20support%20migration,%20since%20the%20developer%20still%20has%20to%20explicitly%20define%20the%20boundaries%20of%20an%20actor%20and%20specify%20where%20message%20passing%20happens">
<p>Actor frameworks don’t <em>really</em> count even if they support migration, since the developer still has to explicitly define the boundaries of an actor and specify where message passing happens <a href="#user-content-fnref-actor%20frameworks%20don%E2%80%99t%20really%20count%20even%20if%20they%20support%20migration,%20since%20the%20developer%20still%20has%20to%20explicitly%20define%20the%20boundaries%20of%20an%20actor%20and%20specify%20where%20message%20passing%20happens" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 3">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-with%20some%20optimizations%20when%20a%20step%20is%20a%20pure,%20deterministic%20function">
<p>With some optimizations when a step is a pure, deterministic function <a href="#user-content-fnref-with%20some%20optimizations%20when%20a%20step%20is%20a%20pure,%20deterministic%20function" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 4">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-see%20the%20needle%20in%20a%20haystack%20test;%20reasoning%20about%20distributed%20systems%20is%20even%20harder.">
<p>See the <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/ai-machine-learning/the-needle-in-the-haystack-test-and-how-gemini-pro-solves-it">Needle in a Haystack Test</a>; reasoning about distributed systems is even harder. <a href="#user-content-fnref-see%20the%20needle%20in%20a%20haystack%20test;%20reasoning%20about%20distributed%20systems%20is%20even%20harder." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 5">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-lean%20is%20a%20great%20example%20of%20this%20in%20action.%20teams%20including%20google%20and%20deepseek%20have%20been%20using%20it%20for%20some%20time.">
<p>Lean is a great example of this in action. Teams including <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/ai-solves-imo-problems-at-silver-medal-level/">Google</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.14333">Deepseek</a> have been using it for some time. <a href="#user-content-fnref-lean%20is%20a%20great%20example%20of%20this%20in%20action.%20teams%20including%20google%20and%20deepseek%20have%20been%20using%20it%20for%20some%20time." data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 6">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section><!--$!--><template data-dgst="BAILOUT_TO_CLIENT_SIDE_RENDERING"></template><!--/$--></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A $100 DIY muon tomographer (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/diy-muon-tomography</link>
            <guid>43195525</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 15:55:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/diy-muon-tomography">https://spectrum.ieee.org/diy-muon-tomography</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43195525">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="This $100 Muon Detector Lets You Harness the Cosmos"><p>In the mid-1960s, the Nobel Prize–winning physicist Luis Alvarez had a wild idea. He proposed using <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/muons">muons</a>, highly penetrating subatomic particles created when <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/cosmic-rays">cosmic rays</a> strike Earth’s atmosphere, to search for hidden chambers within one of the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/pyramids">pyramids</a> of Giza.</p><p>These muon particles are heavyweight cousins of <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/electrons">electrons</a> that travel close to the speed of light. They can penetrate through many meters of solid rock, including the limestone and granite blocks used to build the pyramids. But some of the muons will be absorbed by this dense material, meaning that they can be used to essentially “X-ray” a pyramid, revealing its inner structure. So in 1968, Alvarez and his colleagues began making muon measurements from a chamber located at the base of the Pyramid of Khafre.</p><p>They didn’t find a hidden chamber, but they did confirm the feasibility of what has come to be called <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Muon_tomography" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">muon tomography</a>. Physicists have since used the technique to discover <a href="https://journals.aps.org/prresearch/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevResearch.2.023017" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">hidden access shafts above tunnels</a>, <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/ncomms4381" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">study magma chambers within volcanos</a>, and even <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/harnessing-cosmic-rays-to-peer-into-fukushimas-deadly-reactors" target="_self">probe the damaged reactors at Fukushima</a>. And, in 2017, muon measurements finally <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/muon-imaging-finds-hidden-chamber-in-great-pyramid-of-giza" target="_self">revealed a hidden chamber in one of the pyramids of Giza</a>—just not the pyramid that Alvarez had chosen to explore.</p><p>You too can perform similar experiments with equipment that you can build yourself for only US $100 or so.</p><p>While some well-documented designs are available for low-cost muon detectors (in particular, the <a href="http://cosmicwatch.lns.mit.edu/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Cosmic Watch</a> project from <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/mit">MIT</a>), I decided to pursue a simpler—and slightly cheaper—approach. I purchased two <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0B45WCBRM/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Geiger-counter kits</a>, each costing only $23. Although it’s called a “kit,” this board in fact comes fully assembled minus the key component: a Geiger-Müller (or <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/gm">GM</a>) tube for detecting ionizing <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/radiation">radiation</a>. It also comes with no documentation.</p><p>The lack of documentation wasn’t a problem once I found <a href="https://www.richardmudhar.com/blog/2023/10/cajoe-ebay-geiger-counter-kit/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">a good source for information about this board</a>—including a pointer to<a href="https://master.dl.sourceforge.net/project/geigerlog/Articles/GeigerLog-Radiation-v1.1%28CAJOE%29-Support-v1.0.pdf" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"> valuable instructions</a> for how to set the tube’s anode voltage.</p><p><img alt="Key components for the muon detector" data-rm-shortcode-id="6d4591bc5cef309c8117827e4543c318" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/key-components-for-the-muon-detector.png?id=56566029&amp;width=980" height="712" id="a9adf" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/key-components-for-the-muon-detector.png?id=56566029&amp;width=980" width="1289"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">The muon detector uses two Geiger-Müller tubes [top], each inserted into a sensor board [bottom right]. Both boards are connected to an <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/arduino">Arduino</a> Nano microcontroller [bottom left].</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">James Provost</small></p><p>For the GM tubes, I decided to buy what I understood to be good ones: Russian-made <a href="https://mightyohm.com/blog/2014/11/a-spotters-guide-to-the-sbm-20-geiger-counter-tube/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">SBM-20 tubes</a>. Many of these are listed on <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/ebay">eBay</a> by sellers in <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/ukraine">Ukraine</a>, but I was able to obtain a pair of such tubes from a supplier in the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/united-states">United States</a> for just <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/225741720104" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">$49</a>.</p><p>“Why two kits and two tubes?” you might ask. It’s because GM tubes don’t react just to muons. Most of the time, they’re triggered by ionizing particles given off by radioactive substances in the environment, such as the daughter products of <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/radon">radon</a> in the air.</p><p><span>Proving that the results reflected the flux of cosmic-ray muons wasn’t difficult.</span></p><p><span></span>To distinguish the high-energy cosmic-ray muons from the other, lower-energy particles isn’t hard, though. Just apply what physicists call the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coincidence_method" target="_blank">coincidence method</a>: Detect only when two nearby tubes are triggered practically simultaneously, meaning one particle has barreled through both tubes. The two tubes in my device are separated by <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B083GNJMXZ" target="_blank">25-millimeter spacers</a>, making it unlikely that a particle coming from a nearby radioactive decay would be energetic enough to pass through both tubes. I reduced the likelihood even more by placing a layer of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B09WDWHK1X/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">fishing-sinker lead</a> between the tubes.</p><p>To turn the stacked pair of GM counters into a coincidence detector, I hooked up the output of each board (oddly labeled VIN, which usually means a pin for a voltage supply input!) to a spare <a href="https://www.arduino.cc/en/Guide/ArduinoNano" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Arduino Nano</a>, programmed to record a hit only when one board registers a count within 1 millisecond of the other. Naturally this means the detector can recognize only muons with trajectories roughly aligned with the plane of the GM tubes so that the muons pass through both tubes.</p><p><img alt="A diagram showing the outlines of two tubes separated by a thin layer of lead. Red lines pass through both tubes and the lead, while green lines stop inside one of the tubes or within the lead. A chart below shows a red line following a curve from 1.1 muon counts per minute at zenith angle of 0 degrees to 0 zero counts per minute at a zenith angle of 90 degrees. Black measurement bars follow the red line closely, except toward 90 degrees where they show a muon flux of 0.1 counts per minute above zero. " data-rm-shortcode-id="60d94e422c1fb04c49c56e1fd6594690" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-diagram-showing-the-outlines-of-two-tubes-separated-by-a-thin-layer-of-lead-red-lines-pass-through-both-tubes-and-the-lead-w.png?id=56566076&amp;width=980" height="2111" id="62974" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-diagram-showing-the-outlines-of-two-tubes-separated-by-a-thin-layer-of-lead-red-lines-pass-through-both-tubes-and-the-lead-w.png?id=56566076&amp;width=980" width="2000"><small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">Geiger-Müller tubes are activated by ionizing radiation, but unlike cosmic-ray muons [red particles], most terrestrial sources [green particles] are not powerful enough to travel through the detector’s two tubes. By registering only activations that occur almost simultaneously, we can plot the muon flux as a function of the angle from vertical of the detector, with the observed data following the predicted model closely</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">James Provost</small></p><p>Proving to myself that the results indeed reflected the flux of cosmic-ray muons wasn’t difficult: I just measured the count rate as a function of how far away from vertical my detector was oriented. You see, the flux of cosmic-ray muons coming in vertically from the sky is greater than the flux of muons traveling horizontally. Between these extremes, the flux should have a cosine-squared dependence on the angle as the detector’s plane rotates from vertical to horizontal.</p><p>So I set about counting events with my device oriented at different angles from vertical, allowing at least 12 hours for each measurement. The results were pretty consistent with the expected cosine-squared variation. For example, when completely horizontal, the detector registered a value that was less than 10 percent of that obtained when vertical, but it wasn’t zero.</p><p>Getting nonzero muon counts even when horizontal isn’t so surprising. With only a 2.5-centimeter separation between the two 1-cm-diameter tubes, my detector’s angular resolution is pretty broad (±22 degrees). So even when I set the unit to sense horizontal flux, it was surely detecting muons coming in from as much as 22 degrees above the horizon.</p><p>With a working muon detector in hand, I set off to probe the Earth—or at least a small part of it—by visiting the <a href="https://historicsites.nc.gov/all-sites/reed-gold-mine" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Reed Gold Mine</a>, in Midland, N.C., the first commercial gold mine in the United States. I spent about two and a half hours in the mine, making five 30-minute measurements. I easily detected the increasingly thick layer of rock above the mine’s main horizontal tunnel. My detector was even able to sense the presence of a vertical shaft at one spot, as the absence of rock allowed more muons to reach me than I measured nearby in the tunnel.</p><p>These measurements take a long time because you need to accumulate enough counts to provide reasonable statistical precision. So you’ll need patience. But it’s not a bad way to harness the power of the cosmos, even deep underground!</p><p><em>This article appears in the March 2025 print issue as “See the World With Muons.”</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Solitaire (320 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://localthunk.com/blog/solitaire</link>
            <guid>43195516</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 15:54:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://localthunk.com/blog/solitaire">https://localthunk.com/blog/solitaire</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43195516">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="item-67bfad0f4671b65dfefb38e0" data-layout-label="Post Body" data-type="item">
  <p>I have cited a few games as inspiration for Balatro in the past, but I wanted to talk about one in particular that hasn’t been mentioned much that arguably is the most important.</p><p>I think if I had some kind of Balatro vision board, solitaire (Klondike) would be right in the middle of it with a big red circle around it. You can probably see some of the similarities between my game and the classic solo card game. I wanted my game to have the same vibe.</p><p>If you’re somehow unfamiliar, solitaire is a group of card games characterized by solo play. Klondike is usually the variant that most people in the west associate with solitaire, but one could argue<em> </em>even Balatro is technically a solitaire game. Traditional solitaire games exist at the peak of game culture for me. These games are so ubiquitous and accepted by society that almost everyone has some memory of playing them. They have transcended gaming culture more than even the biggest IPs (like Tetris or Mario), and they occupy this very interesting <strong><em>wholesome</em></strong> niche. Solitaire is almost viewed as a positive pastime more than a game. That feeling interests me greatly as a game designer.</p><div><p>As Balatro 1.0 development drew nearer to a close in early 2024, I found myself picturing the type of person that might play my game and what a typical play session might look like for them. My fantasy was that I was playing this weird game many years later on a lazy Sunday afternoon; I play a couple of runs, enjoy my time for about an hour, then set it down and continue the rest of my day. I wanted it to feel evergreen, comforting, and enjoyable in a very low-stakes way. I think that’s one of the reasons why there isn’t a player character, health, or classic ‘enemies’ in the game as well. I wanted this game to be as low stakes as a crossword or a sudoku puzzle while still exercising the problem solving part of the brain.</p><p>Essentially I wanted to play Balatro like people play solitaire.</p></div><p>One of the main ways that the vibe of solitaire and my own game differ is in the meta-game Balatro has that solitaire does not. Things like achievements, stake levels, unlocks, and challenges certainly can be looked at as a way to artificially inflate playtime, but those things were added for 2 other reasons I was more concerned about:</p><ol data-rte-list="default"><li><p>To force players to get out of their comfort zone and explore the design of the game in a way they might not if this were a fully unguided gaming experience. In solitaire this probably isn’t super useful because the game has far fewer moving parts, so the player can figure everything out by themselves, but I don’t think that’s the case with a game like Balatro. I feel like even I learned a lot from these guiding goals that I wasn’t anticipating many months after the game launched.</p></li><li><p>To give the players that already enjoy the game loop a sort of checklist to work through if they so choose. They can come up with a list of goals on their own (as I see many from the community have) but I do really appreciate when I play other games and they give me tasks to accomplish and shape my long-form play around while I enjoy the shorter play sessions individually.<br> </p></li></ol><div><p>It’s now been over a year since launch and I am still playing Balatro almost daily. I play a couple runs before I go to bed, and I feel like I just might have accomplished the task of recreating the feeling of playing solitaire for myself. Seeing the discourse around my game has me fairly convinced that this is decidedly not how the average player has been interacting with my game, but I’m still thrilled that people are having a great time with it and I’m even more happy that I feel like this game turned out how I wanted as a player myself.</p><p> This is why you might have seen me refer to this game as ‘jazz solitaire’ in the past. I wanted to bring the old feeling of solitaire into a game with modern design bells and whistles, creating something new and yet familiar. Only time will tell if I actually accomplished that.</p></div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mozilla's New Terms of Use Are Out of Step with Firefox's Direct Competition (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quippd.com/writing/2025/02/26/mozillas-new-terms-of-use-are-out-of-step-with-firefoxs-direct-competition.html</link>
            <guid>43194536</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 14:12:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quippd.com/writing/2025/02/26/mozillas-new-terms-of-use-are-out-of-step-with-firefoxs-direct-competition.html">https://www.quippd.com/writing/2025/02/26/mozillas-new-terms-of-use-are-out-of-step-with-firefoxs-direct-competition.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43194536">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
      <p>On Wednesday, <a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/en/products/firefox/firefox-news/firefox-terms-of-use/">Mozilla introduced legal updates to users of Firefox</a>, and something feels off. I read, and re-read the new <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/about/legal/terms/firefox/">Terms of Use</a> and while much of it reads like standard boilerplate from any tech company, there’s a new section that is unexpected:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you upload or input information through Firefox, you hereby grant us a nonexclusive, royalty-free, worldwide license to use that information to help you navigate, experience, and interact with online content as you indicate with your use of Firefox.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The community <a href="https://mstdn.io/@jomo/114072136787385688">has</a> <a href="https://infosec.exchange/@mttaggart/114071999359445580">also</a> <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/firefox/comments/1iyuvjf/introducing_a_terms_of_use_and_updated_privacy/meyb9e9/">zeroed</a> in on this phrase, with contributors <a href="https://discourse.mozilla.org/t/why-does-mozilla-now-require-a-nonexclusive-royalty-free-worldwide-license-when-entering-information-in-firefox/140700">asking directly</a> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sqpnRyfz_aY">what up with that?</a></p>

<p>While I’m not going to ponder about <em>why</em> Mozilla wants this royalty-free license to my intellectual property, I immediately wondered whether using Microsoft Word also needed this kind of license grant – since it is <em>processing my words</em>.</p>

<p>I was quickly <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-US/servicesagreement">informed</a> by a chatroom interlocutor that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To the extent necessary to provide the Services to you and others, to protect you and the Services, and to improve Microsoft products and services, you grant to Microsoft a worldwide and royalty-free intellectual property license to use Your Content, for example, to make copies of, retain, transmit, reformat, display, and distribute via communication tools Your Content on the Services.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>which seems excessive. However, this copy is part of a section called “Your Content” where Microsoft explicitly disclaims ownership of your content:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Many of our Services allow you to create, store or share Your Content or receive material from others. <strong>We don’t claim ownership of Your Content.</strong> Your Content remains yours and you are responsible for it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If that gives you the ick, or you simply want to avoid the <a href="https://beebom.com/microsoft-free-ad-supported-office-quietly-launched/">ads coming to Office</a>, you may want to try <a href="https://www.libreoffice.org/">LibreOffice</a> - which doesn’t seem to have a terms of service. Just local, open source software.</p>

<p>Ultimately, Microsoft specifically disclaims ownership of your content - something Mozilla does not do.</p>

<p>Is Mozilla an outlier here? Is this as weird as it seems? Mozilla has a <a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/browsers/compare/">browser comparison page</a>, so we can use those as a basis for comparison - let’s look at the data!</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Browser</th>
      <th>Uploaded or input information grants software vendor a nonexclusive, royalty-free, worldwide license</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/about/legal/terms/firefox/">Mozilla Firefox</a></td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>&nbsp;</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://policies.google.com/terms?hl=en-US">Google Chrome</a></td>
      <td>Yes</td>
      <td>Google grants itself a worldwide, non-exclusive, royalty-free license to “host, reproduce, distribute, communicate, and use your content” and to “modify and create derivative works based on your content” for the “limited purpose” of “operating and improving the services” including “using automated systems and algorithms to analyze your content to customize our services for you, such as providing recommendations and personalized search results, content, and ads”. They also retain the right to use “content you’ve shared publicly to promote” their service, such as reviews, and to develop new technologies and services. You also grant these rights to sublicensees. Unsurprisingly, Google grants itself very expansive access to your intellectual property.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-US/servicesagreement">Microsoft Edge</a></td>
      <td>Partial</td>
      <td>Microsoft grants itself a “worldwide and royalty-free intellectual property license to use Your Content, for example, to make copies of, retain, transmit, reformat, display, and distribute via communication tools Your Content on the Services” while explicitly disclaiming ownership of your content.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://www.apple.com/legal/privacy/data/en/safari/">Apple Safari</a></td>
      <td>❌</td>
      <td>No reference to user generated intellectual property. Apple says that they retain “personal data only for so long as necessary to fulfill the purposes for which it was collected”.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://brave.com/terms-of-use/">Brave</a></td>
      <td>❌</td>
      <td>No language about intellectual property licenses of user generated content.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><a href="https://www.opera.com/legal/terms">Opera</a></td>
      <td>❌</td>
      <td>No language about intellectual property licenses of user generated content</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>It would be remiss to not mention that these changes come at the heels of a <a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/en/mozilla/mozilla-leadership-growth-planning-updates/">leadership shakeup</a> at Mozilla, with the exit of its longtime <a href="https://www.politico.com/story/2014/10/getting-there-mozilla-foundations-mitchell-baker-111479">lizard wrangler, Mitchell Baker</a> and a new focus on “<a href="https://www.quippd.com/writing/2024/10/13/protecting-your-privacy-while-eroding-your-democracy-PPAs-considered-harmful.html">privacy-respecting advertising</a>” and “trustworthy, open source AI”.</p>

<p>The initial version of this post concluded that other browser vendors don’t grant themselves the same rights to users’ intellectual property that Mozilla’s new Terms does. Upon further review and discussion, I realize that the exceptions that Google grants itself for usage of people’s content are large enough to drive a truck through - they are expansive. In particular, using people’s intellectual property to serve ads based on that content is exactly the kind of usage that people are creeped out by.</p>

<p>There is something different here, though. Although Google’s ToS is expansive, Mozilla’s is more expansive still. As Google notes, “some of our services are designed to let you upload, submit, store, send, receive, or share your content. You have no obligation to provide any content to our services and you’re free to choose the content that you want to provide. If you choose to upload or share content, please make sure you have the necessary rights to do so and that the content is lawful.” Google grants itself the expansive rights only when users upload or share content to its online services. Mozilla goes beyond this by not limiting the scope of what is covered to what is uploaded to Mozilla services, but more expansively to all “information” input “through” Firefox - that is every website, including ones on your local area network!</p>

<p>Lastly, I think the non-existence of a copyright license grant in the other competing browsers presents a valuable counterexample to claims that users of software programs must explicitly grant copying rights to any software that interacts with user data. What is their exposure to liability?</p>

<p>Clearly, if a license grant isn’t present in the Terms, users aren’t automatically granting <em>expansive</em> rights like letting a print shop republish dozens of copies of their work for free after making a single printout. If such a grant was automatic, vendors wouldn’t need to write it into an agreement that must be clicked through. Vendors that <em>do</em> assert such rights in their Terms can expect them to be operative, as <a href="https://www.mcglinchey.com/insights/split-supreme-judicial-court-issues-important-update-to-clickwrap-arbitration-clause-jurisprudence/">“clickwrap” agreements have been held to be enforceable</a>.</p>

<h2 id="feedback">Feedback</h2>

<p>I received some valuable feedback to this post, so I have further thoughts. At the outset, I’ll note that I am not a lawyer.</p>

<h3 id="this-is-a-prudent-change---it-prevents-lawsuits">This is a prudent change - it prevents lawsuits</h3>

<p>I got feedback that while the new verbiage might not be quite <em>necessary</em>, it clarifies and prevents people and businesses from trying to sue Mozilla for using the software as designed. An example of this might be someone suing Mozilla for uploading a file that they dragged onto Firefox, transmitting the file to a third party website.</p>

<p>It is not clear to me why Mozilla needs a license grant to protect itself from this lawsuit - the software worked as designed, and Mozilla having a license to the data doesn’t indemnify it from transmitting the data to the wrong place - if anything, the indemnification clause does that:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You agree to indemnify and hold Mozilla and its affiliates harmless for any liability or claim from your use of Firefox, to the extent permitted by applicable law.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Lacking a transferable, sub-licensable agreement means that Mozilla can’t escape liability for sending the file to the “wrong” site by granting the “wrong” site the license to the information. The lawsuits that I have come up with in my thought exercises don’t seem coherent to me. It is hard for me to imagine a lawsuit that would be prevented by this phrase.</p>

<p>My interpretation could be totally wrong! If it is, Mozilla can help the community understand why this verbiage is necessary – and what risks forks and other vendors who do not have this language in their ToS harbor. If forks are exposing themselves to legal liability, Mozilla would be performing a community service to non-Mozilla Gecko developers by clarifying their understanding of why copyright law requires users to grant these intellectual property rights to developers.</p>

<h3 id="this-is-how-software-works-the-tos-just-reflects-it">This is how software works, the ToS just reflects it</h3>

<p>Another response I’ve gotten is that computers need to copy data and transform it in order to do valuable things with your data. Thus, Mozilla needs these rights in order to correctly describe how software is working in the background.</p>

<p>This feels ahistorical, like an inversion of how we have always thought about copyright.</p>

<p>Did writing a story in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacWrite">MacWrite</a> give Claris rights to your story?</p>

<p>Remember that to display, edit, transform (underline, italicize, fonts) the documents you write in MacWrite <em>necessarily</em> requires copying your document data from disk to memory to cpu to memory to display – lots of copying. Did Claris need the rights to your copyright to allow you to edit your documents in its software?</p>

<p>I think that we know that it isn’t the case that Claris needed (or had) a legal right to your intellectual property in order to “use” your data in order to let you edit your story.</p>

<p>If that example feels esoteric - since we’re talking about copies, how about copy machines?</p>

<p>If I walk up to a copy machine manufactured by Konica Minolta and copy a proprietary document, am I instantaneously granting Konica Minolta a license to “use” the copy? We know that many industrial copiers have <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/business-guidance/resources/digital-copier-data-security-guide-businesses">hard drives in them</a> - does that mean the next time the disk goes back to Konica Minolta for warranty service, they get to use the documents to train algorithms to more accurately copy those types of documents?</p>

<p>I don’t think that is the case – clearly this is a <em>new</em> right being assigned. We do not assume that mere usage of a copier grants the copier company the right to use your data outside of of what is required to make the copy. We don’t even need the company involved at all! Indeed, I would expect that a responsible company would either destroy hard drives with customer data on them, or to securely wipe them before reuse.</p>

<p>In a more modern software example, guidance on the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl-faq.en.html#CanIUseGPLToolsForNF">GPL specifically clarifies that using open source software to create non-free software</a> is allowed - there is no assumption that using open source software to produce documents similarly grants the rights holders of the software in use rights to your creative work. Artworks created in Inkscape aren’t free to be used by the developers of Inkskape. Clearly, users of open source software aren’t automatically granting developers rights to their work. Why is Firefox different?</p>

<hr>

<p>If you liked this material, please consider <a href="https://ko-fi.com/yoasif">supporting me</a>. You can <a href="https://mastodon.social/@yoasif">message me</a> or follow <a href="https://mastodon.social/@quippdblog">this blog</a> on Mastodon.</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fish 4 (279 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/releases/tag/4.0.0</link>
            <guid>43194024</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 13:06:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/releases/tag/4.0.0">https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/releases/tag/4.0.0</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43194024">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-pjax="true" data-test-selector="body-content" data-view-component="true"><p>fish’s core code has been ported from C++ to Rust (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9512" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9512/hovercard">#9512</a>). This means a large change in dependencies and how to build fish. However, there should be no direct impact on users. Packagers should see the <a href="#rust-packaging">For Distributors</a> section at the end.</p>
<h3>Notable backwards-incompatible changes</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p>As part of a larger binding rework, <code>bind</code> gained a new key notation.<br>
In most cases the old notation should keep working, but in rare cases you may have to change a <code>bind</code> invocation to use the new notation.<br>
See <a href="#changelog-new-bindings">below</a> for details.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><code>ctrl-c</code> now calls a new bind function called <code>clear-commandline</code>. The old behavior, which leaves a “^C” marker, is available as <code>cancel-commandline</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10935" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10935/hovercard">#10935</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><code>random</code> will produce different values from previous versions of fish when used with the same seed, and will work more sensibly with small seed numbers.<br>
The seed was never guaranteed to give the same result across systems,<br>
so we do not expect this to have a large impact (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9593" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9593/hovercard">#9593</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Variables in command position that expand to a subcommand keyword are now forbidden to fix a likely user error.<br>
For example, <code>set editor command emacs; $editor</code> is no longer allowed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10249" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10249/hovercard">#10249</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><code>functions --handlers</code> will now list handlers in a different order.<br>
Now it is definition order, first to last, where before it was last to first.<br>
This was never specifically defined, and we recommend not relying on a specific order (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9944" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9944/hovercard">#9944</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <code>qmark-noglob</code> feature, introduced in fish 3.0, is enabled by default. That means <code>?</code> will no longer act as a single-character glob.<br>
You can, for the time being, turn it back on by adding <code>no-qmark-noglob</code> to <code>fish_features</code> and restarting fish:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="set -Ua fish_features no-qmark-noglob"><pre lang="fish-docs-samples"><code>set -Ua fish_features no-qmark-noglob
</code></pre></div>
<p>The flag will eventually be made read-only, making it impossible to turn off.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Terminals that fail to ignore unrecognized OSC or CSI sequences may display garbage. We know cool-retro-term and emacs’ ansi-term are affected, but most mainstream terminals are not.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>fish no longer searches directories from the Windows system/user <code>$PATH</code> environment variable for Linux executables. To execute Linux binaries by name (i.e. not with a relative or absolute path) from a Windows folder, make sure the <code>/mnt/c/...</code> path is explicitly added to <code>$fish_user_paths</code> and not just automatically appended to <code>$PATH</code> by <code>wsl.exe</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10506" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10506/hovercard">#10506</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Under Microsoft Windows Subsystem for Linux 1 (not WSL 2), backgrounded jobs that have not been disowned and do not terminate on their own after a <code>SIGHUP</code> + <code>SIGCONT</code> sequence will be explicitly killed by fish on exit (after the usual prompt to close or disown them) to work around a WSL 1 deficiency that sees backgrounded processes that run into <code>SIGTTOU</code> remain in a suspended state indefinitely (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5263" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5263/hovercard">#5263</a>). The workaround is to explicitly <code>disown</code> processes you wish to outlive the shell session.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Notable improvements and fixes</h3>

<ul>
<li>
<p>fish now requests XTerm’s <code>modifyOtherKeys</code> keyboard encoding and <a href="https://sw.kovidgoyal.net/kitty/keyboard-protocol/" rel="nofollow">kitty keyboard protocol’s</a> progressive enhancements (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10359" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10359/hovercard">#10359</a>).<br>
Depending on terminal support, this allows to binding more key combinations, including arbitrary combinations of modifiers <code>ctrl</code>, <code>alt</code> and <code>shift</code>, and distinguishing (for example) <code>ctrl-i</code> from <code>tab</code>.</p>
<p>Additionally, <code>bind</code> now supports a human-readable syntax in addition to byte sequences.<br>
This includes modifier names, and names for keys like <code>enter</code> and <code>backspace</code>.<br>
For example</p>
<ul>
<li><code>bind up 'do something'</code> binds the up-arrow key instead of a two-key sequence (“u” and then “p”)</li>
<li><code>bind ctrl-x,alt-c 'do something'</code> binds a sequence of two keys.</li>
</ul>
<p>Any key argument that starts with an ASCII control character (like <code>\e</code> or <code>\cX</code>) or is up to 3 characters long, not a named key, and does not contain <code>,</code> or <code>-</code> will be interpreted in the old syntax to keep compatibility for the majority of bindings.</p>
<p>Keyboard protocols can be turned off by disabling the “keyboard-protocols” feature flag:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="set -Ua fish_features no-keyboard-protocols"><pre lang="fish-docs-samples"><code>set -Ua fish_features no-keyboard-protocols
</code></pre></div>
<p>This is a temporary measure to work around buggy terminals (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/11056" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/11056/hovercard">#11056</a>), which appear to be relatively rare.<br>
Use this if something like “=0” or “=5u” appears in your commandline mysteriously.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>fish can now be built as a self-installing binary (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10367" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10367/hovercard">#10367</a>). That means it can be easily built on one system and copied to another, where it can extract supporting files.<br>
To do this, run:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo install --path . # in a clone of the fish repository
# or `cargo build --release` and copy target/release/fish{,_indent,_key_reader} wherever you want"><pre lang="fish-docs-samples"><code>cargo install --path . # in a clone of the fish repository
# or `cargo build --release` and copy target/release/fish{,_indent,_key_reader} wherever you want
</code></pre></div>
<p>The first time it runs interactively, it will extract all the data files to  <code>~/.local/share/fish/install/</code>. A specific path can be used for the data files with <code>fish --install=PATH</code> To uninstall, remove the fish binaries and that directory.</p>
<p>This build system is experimental; the main build system, using <code>cmake</code>, remains the recommended approach for packaging and installation to a prefix.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A new function <code>fish_should_add_to_history</code> can be overridden to decide whether a command should be added to the history (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10302" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10302/hovercard">#10302</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Bindings can now mix special input functions and shell commands, so <code>bind ctrl-g expand-abbr "commandline -i \n"</code> works as expected (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8186" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8186/hovercard">#8186</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Special input functions run from bindings via <code>commandline -f</code> are now applied immediately, instead of after the currently executing binding (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/3031" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/3031/hovercard">#3031</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10126" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10126/hovercard">#10126</a>).<br>
For example, <code>commandline -i foo; commandline | grep foo</code> succeeds now.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Undo history is no longer truncated after every command, but kept for the lifetime of the shell process.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <code>ctrl-r</code> history search now uses glob syntax (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10131" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10131/hovercard">#10131</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The <code>ctrl-r</code> history search now operates only on the line or command substitution at cursor, making it easier to combine commands from history (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9751" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9751/hovercard">#9751</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Abbreviations can now be restricted to specific commands. For instance:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="abbr --add --command git back 'reset --hard HEAD^'"><pre lang="fish-docs-samples"><code>abbr --add --command git back 'reset --hard HEAD^'
</code></pre></div>
<p>will expand “back” to <code>reset --hard HEAD^</code>, but only when the command is <code>git</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9411" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9411/hovercard">#9411</a>).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Deprecations and removed features</h3>
<ul>
<li>
<p><code>commandline --tokenize</code> (short option <code>-o</code>) has been deprecated in favor of <code>commandline --tokens-expanded</code> (short option <code>-x</code>) which expands variables and other shell syntax, removing the need to use <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/blob/4.0.0/cmds/eval.md">eval</a> in completion scripts (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10212" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10212/hovercard">#10212</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Two new feature flags:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>remove-percent-self</code> (see <code>status features</code>) disables PID expansion of <code>%self</code>, which has been supplanted by <code>$fish_pid</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10262" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10262/hovercard">#10262</a>).</li>
<li><code>test-require-arg</code> disables <code>test</code>’s one-argument mode. That means <code>test -n</code> without an additional argument will return false, <code>test -z</code> will keep returning true. Any other option without an argument, anything that is not an option and no argument will be an error. This also goes for <code>[</code>, test’s alternate name.<br>
This is a frequent source of confusion and so we are breaking with POSIX explicitly in this regard.<br>
In addition to the feature flag, there is a debug category “deprecated-test”. Running fish with <code>fish -d deprecated-test</code> will show warnings whenever a <code>test</code> invocation that would change is used. (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10365" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10365/hovercard">#10365</a>).</li>
</ul>
<p>These can be enabled with:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="set -Ua fish_features remove-percent-self test-require-arg"><pre lang="fish-docs-samples"><code>set -Ua fish_features remove-percent-self test-require-arg
</code></pre></div>
<p>We intend to enable them by default in future, and after that eventually make them read-only.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Specifying key names as terminfo names (using the <code>bind -k</code> syntax) is deprecated and may be removed in a future version.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When a terminal pastes text into fish using bracketed paste, fish used to switch to a special <code>paste</code> bind mode.<br>
This bind mode has been removed. The behavior on paste is no longer configurable.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When an interactive fish is stopped or terminated by a signal that cannot be caught (SIGSTOP or SIGKILL), it may leave the terminal in a state where keypresses with modifiers are sent as CSI u sequences, instead of traditional control characters or escape sequences that are recognized by Readline and compatible programs, such as bash and python.<br>
If this happens, you can use the <code>reset</code> command from <code>ncurses</code> to restore the terminal state.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><code>fish_key_reader --verbose</code> no longer shows timing information.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Terminal information is no longer read from hashed terminfo databases, or termcap databases (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10269" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10269/hovercard">#10269</a>). The vast majority of systems use a non-hashed terminfo database, which is still supported.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><code>source</code> returns an error if used without a filename or pipe/redirection (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10774" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10774/hovercard">#10774</a>).</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h3>Scripting improvements</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>for</code> loops will no longer remember local variables from the previous iteration (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10525" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10525/hovercard">#10525</a>).</li>
<li>A new <code>history append</code> subcommand appends a command to the history, without executing it (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/4506" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/4506/hovercard">#4506</a>).</li>
<li>A new redirection: <code>&lt;? /path/to/file</code> will try opening the file as input, and if it doesn’t succeed silently uses <code>/dev/null</code> instead.<br>
This can help with checks like <code>test -f /path/to/file; and string replace foo bar &lt; /path/to/file</code>. (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10387" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10387/hovercard">#10387</a>)</li>
<li>A new option <code>commandline --tokens-raw</code> prints a list of tokens without any unescaping (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10212" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10212/hovercard">#10212</a>).</li>
<li>A new option <code>commandline --showing-suggestion</code> tests whether an autosuggestion is currently displayed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10586" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10586/hovercard">#10586</a>).</li>
<li><code>functions</code> and <code>type</code> now show that a function was copied and its source, rather than solely <code>Defined interactively</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6575" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6575/hovercard">#6575</a>).</li>
<li>Stack trace now shows line numbers for copied functions (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6575" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6575/hovercard">#6575</a>).</li>
<li><code>foo &amp; &amp;&amp; bar</code> is now a syntax error, like in other shells (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9911" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9911/hovercard">#9911</a>).</li>
<li><code>if -e foo; end</code> now prints a more accurate error (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10000" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10000/hovercard">#10000</a>).</li>
<li><code>cd</code> into a directory that is not readable but accessible (permissions <code>--x</code>) is now possible (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10432" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10432/hovercard">#10432</a>).</li>
<li>An integer overflow in <code>string repeat</code> leading to a near-infinite loop has been fixed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9899" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9899/hovercard">#9899</a>).</li>
<li><code>string shorten</code> behaves better in the presence of non-printable characters, including fixing an integer overflow that shortened strings more than intended (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9854" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9854/hovercard">#9854</a>).</li>
<li><code>string pad</code> no longer allows non-printable characters as padding (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9854" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9854/hovercard">#9854</a>).</li>
<li><code>string repeat</code> now allows omission of <code>-n</code> when the first argument is an integer (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10282" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10282/hovercard">#10282</a>).</li>
<li><code>string match</code> and <code>replace</code> have a new <code>--max-matches</code> option to return as soon as the specified number of matches have been identified, which can improve performance in scripts (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10587" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10587/hovercard">#10587</a>).</li>
<li><code>functions --handlers-type caller-exit</code> once again lists functions defined as <code>function --on-job-exit caller</code>, rather than them being listed by <code>functions --handlers-type process-exit</code>.</li>
<li>A new <code>set --no-event</code> option sets or erases variables without triggering a variable event. This can be useful to change a variable in an event handler (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10480" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10480/hovercard">#10480</a>).</li>
<li>Commas in command substitution output are no longer used as separators in brace expansion, preventing a surprising expansion in some cases (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5048" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5048/hovercard">#5048</a>).</li>
<li>Universal variables can now store strings containing invalid UTF-8 (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10313" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10313/hovercard">#10313</a>).</li>
<li>A new <code>path basename -E</code> option that causes it to return the basename (“filename” with the directory prefix removed) with the final extension (if any) also removed. This is a shorter version of <code>path change-extension "" (path basename $foo)</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10521" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10521/hovercard">#10521</a>).</li>
<li>A new <code>math --scale-mode</code> option to select <code>truncate</code>, <code>round</code>, <code>floor</code>, <code>ceiling</code> as you wish; the default value is <code>truncate</code>. (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9117" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9117/hovercard">#9117</a>).</li>
<li><code>random</code> is now less strict about its arguments, allowing a start larger or equal to the end. (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10879" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10879/hovercard">#10879</a>)</li>
<li><code>function --argument-names</code> now produces an error if a read-only variable name is used, rather than simply ignoring it (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10842" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10842/hovercard">#10842</a>).</li>
<li>Tilde expansion in braces (that is, <code>{~,}</code>) works correctly (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10610" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10610/hovercard">#10610</a>).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Interactive improvements</h3>
<ul>
<li>Autosuggestions were sometimes not shown after recalling a line from history, which has been fixed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10287" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10287/hovercard">#10287</a>).</li>
<li>Up-arrow search matches -- which are highlighted in reverse colors -- are no longer syntax-highlighted, to fix bad contrast with the search match highlighting.</li>
<li>Command abbreviations (those with <code>--position command</code> or without a <code>--position</code>) now also expand after decorators like <code>command</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10396" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10396/hovercard">#10396</a>).</li>
<li>Abbreviations now expand after process separators like <code>;</code> and <code>|</code>. This fixes a regression in version 3.6 (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9730" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9730/hovercard">#9730</a>).</li>
<li>When exporting interactively defined functions (using <code>type</code>, <code>functions</code> or <code>funcsave</code>) the function body is now indented, to match the interactive command line editor (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8603" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/8603/hovercard">#8603</a>).</li>
<li><code>ctrl-x</code> (<code>fish_clipboard_copy</code>) on multiline commands now includes indentation (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10437" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10437/hovercard">#10437</a>).</li>
<li><code>ctrl-v</code> (<code>fish_clipboard_paste</code>) now strips ASCII control characters from the pasted text.<br>
This is consistent with normal keyboard input (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5274" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5274/hovercard">#5274</a>).</li>
<li>When a command like <code>fg %2</code> fails to find the given job, it no longer behaves as if no job spec was given (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9835" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9835/hovercard">#9835</a>).</li>
<li>Redirection in command position like <code>&gt;echo</code> is now highlighted as error (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8877" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8877/hovercard">#8877</a>).</li>
<li><code>fish_vi_cursor</code> now works properly inside the prompt created by builtin <code>read</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10088" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10088/hovercard">#10088</a>).</li>
<li>fish no longer fails to open a FIFO if interrupted by a terminal resize signal (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10250" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10250/hovercard">#10250</a>).</li>
<li><code>read --help</code> and friends no longer ignore redirections. This fixes a regression in version 3.1 (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10274" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10274/hovercard">#10274</a>).</li>
<li>Measuring a command with <code>time</code> now considers the time taken for command substitution (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9100" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9100/hovercard">#9100</a>).</li>
<li><code>fish_add_path</code> now automatically enables verbose mode when used interactively (in the command line), in an effort to be clearer about what it does (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10532" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10532/hovercard">#10532</a>).</li>
<li>fish no longer adopts TTY modes of failed commands (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10603" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10603/hovercard">#10603</a>).</li>
<li><code>complete -e cmd</code> now prevents autoloading completions for <code>cmd</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6716" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6716/hovercard">#6716</a>).</li>
<li>fish’s default color scheme no longer uses the color “blue”, as it has bad contrast against the background in a few terminal’s default palettes (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10758" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10758/hovercard">#10758</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10786" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10786/hovercard">#10786</a>)<br>
The color scheme will not be upgraded for existing installs. If you want, you should select it again via <code>fish_config</code>.</li>
<li>Command lines which are larger than the terminal are now displayed correctly, instead of multiple blank lines being displayed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/7296" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/7296/hovercard">#7296</a>).</li>
<li>Prompts that use external commands will no longer produce an infinite loop if the command crashes (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9796" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9796/hovercard">#9796</a>).</li>
<li>Undo (<code>ctrl-z</code>) restores the cursor position too (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10838" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10838/hovercard">#10838</a>).</li>
<li>The output of <code>jobs</code> shows “-” for jobs that have the same process group ID as the fish process, rather than “-2” (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10833" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10833/hovercard">#10833</a>).</li>
<li>Job expansion (<code>%1</code> syntax) works properly for jobs that are a mixture of external commands and functions (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10832" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10832/hovercard">#10832</a>).</li>
<li>Command lines which have more lines than the terminal can be displayed and edited correctly (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10827" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10827/hovercard">#10827</a>).</li>
<li>Functions that have been erased are no longer highlighted as valid commands (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10866" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10866/hovercard">#10866</a>).</li>
<li><code>not</code>, <code>time</code>, and variable assignments (that is <code>not time a=b env</code>) is correctly recognized as valid syntax (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10890" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10890/hovercard">#10890</a>).</li>
<li>The Web-based configuration removes old right-hand-side prompts again, fixing a regression in fish 3.4.0 (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10675" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10675/hovercard">#10675</a>).</li>
<li>Further protection against programs which crash and leave the terminal in an inconsistent state (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10834" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10834/hovercard">#10834</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/11038" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/11038/hovercard">#11038</a>).</li>
<li>A workaround for git being very slow on macOS has been applied, improving performance after a fresh boot (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10535" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10535/hovercard">#10535</a>).</li>
</ul>
<h4>New or improved bindings</h4>
<ul>
<li>When the cursor is on a command that resolves to an executable script, <code>alt-o</code> will now open that script in your editor (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10266" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10266/hovercard">#10266</a>).</li>
<li>During up-arrow history search, <code>shift-delete</code> will delete the current search item and move to the next older item. Previously this was only supported in the history pager.</li>
<li><code>shift-delete</code> will also remove the currently-displayed autosuggestion from history, and remove it as a suggestion.</li>
<li><code>ctrl-Z</code> (also known as <code>ctrl-shift-z</code>) is now bound to redo.</li>
<li>Some improvements to the <code>alt-e</code> binding which edits the command line in an external editor:
<ul>
<li>The editor’s cursor position is copied back to fish. This is currently supported for Vim and Kakoune.</li>
<li>Cursor position synchronization is only supported for a set of known editors, which are now also detected in aliases which use <code>complete --wraps</code>. For example, use <code>complete --wraps my-vim vim</code> to synchronize cursors when <code>EDITOR=my-vim</code>.</li>
<li>Multiline commands are indented before being sent to the editor, which matches how they are displayed in fish.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The <code>...-path-component</code> bindings, like <code>backward-kill-path-component</code>, now treat <code>#</code> as part of a path component (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10271" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10271/hovercard">#10271</a>).</li>
<li>Bindings like <code>alt-l</code> that print output in between prompts now work correctly with multiline commandlines.</li>
<li><code>alt-d</code> on an empty command line lists the directory history again. This restores the behavior of version 2.1.</li>
<li><code>history-prefix-search-backward</code> and <code>-forward</code> now maintain the cursor position, instead of moving the cursor to the end of the command line (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10430" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10430/hovercard">#10430</a>).</li>
<li>The following keys have refined behavior if the terminal supports <a href="#changelog-new-bindings">the new keyboard encodings</a>:
<ul>
<li><code>shift-enter</code> now inserts a newline instead of executing the command line.</li>
<li><code>ctrl-backspace</code> now deletes the last word instead of only one character (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10741" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10741/hovercard">#10741</a>).</li>
<li><code>ctrl-delete</code> deletes the next word (same as <code>alt-d</code>).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>New special input functions:
<ul>
<li><code>forward-char-passive</code> and <code>backward-char-passive</code> are like their non-passive variants but do not accept autosuggestions or move focus in the completion pager (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10398" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10398/hovercard">#10398</a>).</li>
<li><code>forward-token</code>, <code>backward-token</code>, <code>kill-token</code>, and <code>backward-kill-token</code> are similar to the <code>*-bigword</code> variants but for the whole argument token (which includes escaped spaces) (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/2014" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/2014/hovercard">#2014</a>).</li>
<li><code>clear-commandline</code>, which merely clears the command line, as an alternative to <code>cancel-commandline</code> which prints <code>^C</code> and a new prompt (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10213" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10213/hovercard">#10213</a>).</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The <code>accept-autosuggestion</code> special input function now returns false when there was nothing to accept (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10608" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10608/hovercard">#10608</a>).</li>
<li>Vi mode has seen some improvements but continues to suffer from the lack of people working on it.
<ul>
<li>New default cursor shapes for insert and replace mode.</li>
<li><code>ctrl-n</code> in insert mode accepts autosuggestions (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10339" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10339/hovercard">#10339</a>).</li>
<li>Outside insert mode, the cursor will no longer be placed beyond the last character on the commandline.</li>
<li>When the cursor is at the end of the commandline, a single <code>l</code> will accept an autosuggestion (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10286" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10286/hovercard">#10286</a>).</li>
<li>The cursor position after pasting (<code>p</code>) has been corrected.</li>
<li>Added an additional binding, <code>_</code>, for moving to the beginning of the line (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10720" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10720/hovercard">#10720</a>).</li>
<li>When the cursor is at the start of a line, escaping from insert mode no longer moves the cursor to the previous line.</li>
<li>Added bindings for clipboard interaction, like <code>",+,p</code> and <code>",+,y,y</code>.</li>
<li>Deleting in visual mode now moves the cursor back, matching vi (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10394" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10394/hovercard">#10394</a>).</li>
<li>The <code>;</code>, <code>,</code>, <code>v</code>, <code>V</code>, <code>I</code>, and <code>gU</code> bindings work in visual mode (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10601" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10601/hovercard">#10601</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10648" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10648/hovercard">#10648</a>).</li>
<li>Support <code>%</code> motion (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10593" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10593/hovercard">#10593</a>).</li>
<li><code>ctrl-k</code> to remove the contents of the line beyond the cursor in all modes (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10648" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10648/hovercard">#10648</a>).</li>
<li>Support ab and ib vi text objects. New input functions are introduced <code>jump-{to,till}-matching-bracket</code> (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/1842" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/1842/hovercard">#1842</a>).</li>
<li>The <code>E</code> binding now correctly handles the last character of the word, by jumping to the next word (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9700" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9700/hovercard">#9700</a>).</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>Completions</h4>
<ul>
<li>Command-specific tab completions may now offer results whose first character is a period. For example, it is now possible to tab-complete <code>git add</code> for files with leading periods. The default file completions hide these files, unless the token itself has a leading period (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/3707" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/3707/hovercard">#3707</a>).</li>
<li>Option completion now uses fuzzy subsequence filtering, just like non-option completion (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/830" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/830/hovercard">#830</a>).<br>
This means that <code>--fb</code> may be completed to <code>--foobar</code> if there is no better match.</li>
<li>Completions that insert an entire token now use quotes instead of backslashes to escape special characters (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5433" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/5433/hovercard">#5433</a>).</li>
<li>Normally, file name completions start after the last <code>:</code>  or <code>=</code> in a token.<br>
This helps commands like <code>rsync --files-from=</code>.<br>
This special meaning can now disabled by escaping these separators as <code>\:</code> and <code>\=</code>.<br>
This matches Bash’s behavior.<br>
Note that this escaping is usually not necessary since the completion engine already tries<br>
to guess whether the separator is actually part of a file name.</li>
<li>Various new completion scripts and numerous updates to existing ones.</li>
<li>Completions could hang if the <code>PAGER</code> environment variable was sent to certain editors on macOS, FreeBSD and some other platforms. This has been fixed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10820" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10820/hovercard">#10820</a>).</li>
<li>Generated completions are now stored in <code>$XDG_CACHE_HOME/fish</code> or <code>~/.cache/fish</code> by default (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10369" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10369/hovercard">#10369</a>)</li>
<li>A regression in fish 3.1, where completing a command line could change it completely, has been fixed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10904" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10904/hovercard">#10904</a>).</li>
</ul>
<h4>Improved terminal support</h4>
<ul>
<li>fish now marks the prompt and command-output regions (via OSC 133) to enable terminal shell integration (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10352" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10352/hovercard">#10352</a>).<br>
Shell integration shortcuts can scroll to the next/previous prompt or show the last command output in a pager.</li>
<li>fish now reports the working directory (via OSC 7) unconditionally instead of only for some terminals (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9955" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9955/hovercard">#9955</a>).</li>
<li>fish now sets the terminal window title (via OSC 0) unconditionally instead of only for some terminals (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10037" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10037/hovercard">#10037</a>).</li>
<li>Focus reporting in tmux is no longer disabled on the first prompt.</li>
<li>Focus reporting is now disabled during commands run inside key bindings (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6942" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/6942/hovercard">#6942</a>).</li>
<li>Cursor changes are applied to all terminals that support them, and the list of specifically-supported terminals has been removed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10693" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10693/hovercard">#10693</a>).</li>
<li>If it cannot find the terminfo entry given by <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/blob/4.0.0/language.md#envvar-TERM"><code>TERM</code></a> environment variable, fish will now use an included <code>xterm-256color</code> definition to match the vast majority of current terminal emulators (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10905" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10905/hovercard">#10905</a>). If you need to have a specific terminfo profile for your terminal’s <code>TERM</code> variable, install it into the terminfo database.</li>
<li>Further improvements to the correct display of prompts which fill the width of the terminal (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8164" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/8164/hovercard">#8164</a>).</li>
</ul>
<h3>Other improvements</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>status</code> gained a <code>buildinfo</code> subcommand, to print information on how fish was built, to help with debugging (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10896" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10896/hovercard">#10896</a>).</li>
<li><code>fish_indent</code> will now collapse multiple empty lines into one (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10325" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10325/hovercard">#10325</a>).</li>
<li><code>fish_indent</code> now preserves the modification time of files if there were no changes (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10624" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10624/hovercard">#10624</a>).</li>
<li>Performance in launching external processes has been improved for many cases (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10869" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10869/hovercard">#10869</a>).</li>
<li>Performance and interactivity under Windows Subsystem for Linux has been improved, with a workaround for Windows-specific locations being appended to <code>$PATH</code> by default (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10506" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10506/hovercard">#10506</a>).</li>
<li>On macOS, paths from <code>/etc/paths</code> and <code>/etc/manpaths</code> containing colons are handled correctly (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10684" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10684/hovercard">#10684</a>).</li>
<li>Additional filesystems such as AFS are properly detected as remote, which avoids certain hangs due to expensive filesystem locks (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10818" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10818/hovercard">#10818</a>).</li>
<li>A spurious error when launching multiple instances of fish for the first time has been removed (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10813" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10813/hovercard">#10813</a>).</li>
</ul>

<h3>For distributors</h3>
<p>fish has been ported to Rust. This means a significant change in dependencies, which are listed in the README. In short, Rust 1.70 or greater is required, and a C++ compiler is no longer needed (although a C compiler is still required, for some C glue code and the tests).</p>
<p>CMake remains the recommended build system, because of cargo’s limited support for installing support files. Version 3.5 remains the minimum supported version. The Xcode generator for CMake is not supported any longer (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9924" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9924/hovercard">#9924</a>). CMake builds default to optimized release builds (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/10799" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/10799/hovercard">#10799</a>).</p>
<p>fish no longer depends on the ncurses library, but still uses a terminfo database. When packaging fish, please add a dependency on the package containing your terminfo database instead of curses.</p>
<p>The <code>test</code> target was removed as it can no longer be defined in new CMake versions. Use <code>make fish_run_tests</code>. Any existing test target will not print output if it fails (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/11116" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/11116/hovercard">#11116</a>).</p>
<p>The Web-based configuration has been rewritten to use Alpine.js (<a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/issues/9554" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fish-shell/fish-shell/pull/9554/hovercard">#9554</a>).</p>
<h3>Changes since fish 4.0b1</h3>
<p>A number of improvements were included in fish 4.0.0 following the beta release of 4.0b1. These include fixes for regressions, improvements to completions and documentation, and the removal of a small number of problematic changes.</p>
<p>The full list of fixed issues can be found on the <a href="https://github.com/fish-shell/fish-shell/milestone/43">GitHub milestone page for 4.0-final</a>.</p>
<p><em>Download links: To download the source code for fish, use the file named "fish-4.0.0.tar.xz". The file downloaded from "Source code (tar.gz)" may not build correctly. The SHA-256 sum of this file is <code>2fda5bd970357064d8d4c896e08285ba59965ca2a8c4829ca8a82bf3b89c69f3</code>. A GPG signature from David Adam (key ID <code>0x7A67D962D88A709A</code>) is available  is available as "fish-4.0.0.tar.xz.asc".</em></p>
<p><em>The files called <code>fish-static-*</code> are experimental statically linked builds for any linux with the given architecture. Extract and run, and they will extract their data files as needed</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US Forest Service firings decimate: entire generation of talent and passion lost (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://grist.org/politics/forest-service-firings-decimate-already-understaffed-agency/</link>
            <guid>43193366</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 11:24:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://grist.org/politics/forest-service-firings-decimate-already-understaffed-agency/">https://grist.org/politics/forest-service-firings-decimate-already-understaffed-agency/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43193366">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
    
  
<p><em>This coverage is made possible through a partnership between </em><a href="https://grist.org/"><em>Grist</em></a>, <a href="https://www.bpr.org/"><em>BPR</em></a><em>, a public radio station serving western North Carolina, </em><a href="https://www.wbez.org/"><em>WBEZ</em></a><em>, a public radio station serving the Chicago metropolitan region, and </em><a href="https://www.interlochenpublicradio.org/"><em>Interlochen Public Radio</em></a><em> in Northern Michigan.</em></p>



<p>On a recent Friday afternoon, Marie Richards sat in her living room in northern Michigan. She was having a hard time talking about her job at the U.S. Forest Service in the past tense.</p>



<p>“I absolutely loved my job,” she said. “I didn’t want to go.”</p>



<p>Richards, a citizen of the Sault Ste. Marie Tribe of Chippewa Indians, was a tribal relations specialist at the <a href="https://www.fs.usda.gov/hmnf">Huron-Manistee National Forests</a>. In mid-February, she found out she was one of the some 3,400 workers who had been targeted for layoffs — an estimated 10 percent of the workforce — as part of the Trump administration’s move to cut costs and shrink the federal government.</p>



<p>Richards watched as some of her colleagues were laid off on February 14 — the <a href="https://planetdetroit.org/2025/02/federal-employees-fired-valentine-day-massacre/">so-called</a> Valentine’s Day massacre, when the Trump administration laid off thousands of probationary employees, generally hired within the past two years. She got a call from her supervisor that Saturday informing her that she had been let go, too. The letter she received cited performance issues, even though she, along with others in a similar position, had received a pay raise less than two months earlier.</p>



<p>“None of us deserved this,” Richards said. “We all work hard and we’re dedicated to taking care of the land.”</p>



<p>The U.S. Forest Service, which&nbsp;stewards 193 million acres of public lands from Alaska to Florida, was in trouble even before Trump took office. Chronically understaffed, the service was already under a <a href="https://www.hcn.org/articles/the-forest-service-is-cutting-its-seasonal-workforce-and-public-lands-will-suffer/">Biden-era hiring freeze</a>, all the while on the front lines of fighting and recovering from back-to-back climate disasters across the country.</p>



<figure><div><p><img decoding="async" src="https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" srcset="https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1200 1200w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=330 330w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=768 768w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1200 1200w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1536 1536w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=160&amp;h=90&amp;crop=1 160w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=640&amp;h=853&amp;crop=1 640w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=96&amp;h=96&amp;crop=1 96w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all&amp;w=150 150w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Marie-Richards-inline.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all 1024w" alt="A woman points to the horizon in a snowy field." data-caption="Marie Richards loved her job as a tribal relations specialist for the U.S. National Forest Service. She was one of 3,400 workers targeted for layoffs.
" data-credit="Izzy Ross / Grist"></p><figcaption>Marie Richards loved her job as a tribal relations specialist for the U.S. National Forest Service. She was one of 3,400 workers targeted for layoffs.
 <cite>Izzy Ross / Grist</cite></figcaption></div></figure>



<p>For now, workers with the Forest Service fear this isn’t just the end of the line for their dream careers, but also a turning point for public lands and what they mean in the United States.</p>



<p>“It’s catastrophic,” said Anders Reynolds with the Southern Environmental Law Center, a nonprofit that litigates environmental issues in the southeastern U.S. “We are losing an entire generation of talent and passion.”</p>



<p>The federal agency does more than ensure that Americans have a place to hunt, hike, fish, or paddle. In the South, forest workers played a key role in helping western North Carolina and other communities recover from impacts of Hurricane Helene. In the West, they’re taking on fire risk mitigation and fighting wildfires. They’re also involved in fisheries management in places like Alaska. Across the country, agency biologists and foresters are busy working to strengthen the over 150 national forests and 20 grasslands it monitors in the face of changing climate.</p>



<p>Increasingly, the service is getting spread thin.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The agency has experienced a steady decrease in staffing over the last decade and the workers that remain are often overworked and underpaid, according to Reynolds.</p>



<p>“That means you’re going to see those campgrounds close, the trails go unmaintained, roads closed, you’re going to feel the effects of wildfire and hurricane recovery work that’s just going to remain undone,” said Reynolds. “Communities are going to struggle.”</p>



<p>The Forest Service has reduced its capacity over many years, causing headaches for staff.</p>



<p>A <a href="https://nafsr.org/advocacy/2019/072619%20Workforce%20Capacity%20Study.pdf">report</a> from the National Association of Forest Service Retirees showed the agency losing a little over half of staff who supported specialty ecological restoration projects — meaning a whole range of jobs, from botanists to foresters to wildlife and fisheries biologists — between 1992 and 2018. As a result, understaffed Forest Service ranger districts, hemorrhaging staff positions, <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/GAOREPORTS-GAO-01-53R/html/GAOREPORTS-GAO-01-53R.htm">have consolidated</a>.</p>



<p>Former employees report they saw serious financial and staffing shortages during their time. Bryan Box, a former timber sale administrator with the Forest Service who took some time out of the agency to care for his aging mother, said he found the working conditions unsuitable for a stable, normal life. Box worked for the Chequamegon-Nicolet National Forest in Wisconsin, where he said he made so little he biked around on his off days rather than wasting money on gas. While he was working, multiple national forests around him consolidated, causing a downward spiral on organizational capacity.</p>


<div>
  <article>
    <span>Read Next</span>
    <div>

      
      
                    
            <a href="https://grist.org/wildfires/federal-funding-hiring-freezes-wildfire/">
        <figure>
          <img src="https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all" alt="A wildland firefighter in a helicopter looks down on a fire in Everglades National Park" srcset="https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all 1600w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 1200w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?resize=330%2C220&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 330w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 768w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 1536w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/helicopter-firefighter.jpg?resize=150%2C100&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" height="1067" width="1600" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
        </figure>
      </a>
            
    </div>
  </article>
</div>



<p>“We decommissioned buildings, we decommissioned the infrastructure that we had back in the ‘80s and ‘90s when we had this huge staff,” Box said. “And that put us into a position where we couldn’t hire seasonal employees anymore because we didn’t have housing for them. In rural northern Wisconsin, you know, just there’s not any housing available really. I think at one point our firefighters were all living above a bar.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Other foresters he knew failed to make rent and were evicted or lived itinerantly, couch-surfing, for the love of the work they did. For Box, the financial realities became untenable. So, too, had the restrictions on his work, which grew as budgets failed to grow.</p>



<p>Box’s program was expensive to run and required travel, often to reduce fire fuels by harvesting timber after an emergency. The program he worked for, Box said, ended up needing to reduce costs by cutting travel funds and ending overtime, making it difficult for him to do his job well.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Much of their work involves emergency response, not only fighting fires but also picking up the pieces after conflagrations and hurricanes leave potentially thousands of acres of dead timber.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Matthew Brossard works as the current business representative and organizer for the National Federation of Federal Employees, and was formerly the general vice president for the National Federation of Federal Employees’ Forest Service Council, which represents around 18,000 employees of the Forest Service, 6,000 of whom are probationary, meaning they have either recently been hired or moved to a new position within the agency. Typically, probation — a part of every federal hiring process — is one or two years. Probationary employees were primarily targeted in the layoffs, meaning a generation of hires is potentially interrupted.&nbsp;Brossard said even though the administration maintains they have not fired positions essential to public safety, there’s more to fighting fires than just the firefighters. Support and logistical personnel are essential. “Extra dispatchers, security to close off roads, food unit leaders, base camp managers, all these very important, 100 percent-needed positions. Those people are getting terminated right now,” Brossard said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In another instance recounted by Brossard, someone on assignment to help with long-term hurricane recovery in Louisiana was fired while he was there. The employee lived in Oregon and reported having no financial support for his trip home.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The loss of a seasonal workforce will also be felt, Brossard added. “Without that influx of seasonal workforce, it puts a huge amount of work onto the permanent staff if they’re still employed to do all the work,” he said, meaning not only trailwork and campground maintenance, but also research and other essential work. “So the work that in the summer that should have been done by 15 or 20 people are now going to be done by five or six.”</p>



<p>As workers continue to struggle with the fallout of their abrupt firings, their union is jumping in to protect them, Brossard said. The NFFE-FSC has joined in multiple lawsuits to challenge the firings, including one filed February 12, provided to Grist, that aims to put a stop to the firings and reverse the ones that have already happened, on grounds that the terminations are unlawful. A decision on the lawsuit is still to come, with more potential legal action following, Brossard said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“You’re not reducing, you know,&nbsp;the stereotypical bureaucrats,” Brossard said. “You’re reducing the boots on the ground that are going out and doing work.”&nbsp;</p>


<div>
  <article>
    <span>Read Next</span>
    <div>

      
      
                    
            <a href="https://grist.org/extreme-weather/rural-water-utilities-in-north-carolina-are-still-reeling-from-helene/">
        <figure>
          <img src="https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all" alt="Bottled water and a toilet paper roll sit on a small box near a house" srcset="https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?quality=75&amp;strip=all 2000w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?resize=1200%2C800&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 1200w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?resize=330%2C220&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 330w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?resize=768%2C512&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 768w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?resize=1536%2C1024&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 1536w, https://grist.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Western-North-Carolina-water-jug-toilet-paper.jpg?resize=150%2C100&amp;quality=75&amp;strip=all 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" height="1333" width="2000" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
        </figure>
      </a>
            
    </div>
  </article>
</div>



<p>In an emailed statement to Grist, a spokesperson with the U.S. Department of Agriculture said the new agricultural secretary, Brooke Rollins, supported Trump’s directive to cut spending and inefficiencies while strengthening the department’s services. “As part of this effort, USDA has made the difficult decision to release about 2,000 probationary, non-firefighting employees from the Forest Service. To be clear, none of these individuals were operational firefighters.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>The statement continued, “Released employees were probationary in status, many of whom were compensated by temporary IRA funding. It’s unfortunate that the Biden administration hired thousands of people with no plan in place to pay them long term. Secretary Rollins is committed to preserving essential safety positions and will ensure that critical services remain uninterrupted.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>Back in northern Michigan, Marie Richards, the former tribal relations specialist, crunched down the snowy driveway, pointing toward the Huron-Manistee National Forests where she worked. It spans nearly 1 million acres and covers land tribal nations ceded in two treaties, which the federal government has a responsibility to keep in trust.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Richards said workers like her are also a vital part of pushing the federal government to meet its trust responsibility to tribal nations. She helped connect the region’s federally recognized tribes with officials and staff at the forest service, set up meetings, and ensured work was being carried out responsibly.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“It’s not just the damage to that trust relationship with the Forest Service,” said Richards, who left her job as a repatriation and historic preservation specialist for the Sault Ste. Marie Tribe of Chippewa Indians to work at the agency. “It’s across the board for so many things, and tribes trying to work through that freeze, and making people understand that this isn’t DEI — that this is governmental affairs.”</p>



<p>Richards doesn’t know what’s next; she wants to finish her dissertation (about the impact of the lumber industry on traditional cultural landscapes and Anishinaabe bands and communities) and continue her work.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“It still really hurts that this dream of mine is kind of shattered, and we’ll see, and find a new dream,” she said. “But ultimately, my career, my livelihood, is in tribal relations for our heritage and I will find a home somewhere.”</p>



<p><em>Lilly Knoepp contributed reporting to this story.</em></p>

  
  
  <hr>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[RoboPianist: Dexterous Piano Playing with Deep Reinforcement Learning (2023) (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kzakka.com/robopianist/#demo</link>
            <guid>43192751</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 09:41:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/#demo">https://kzakka.com/robopianist/#demo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43192751">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
  

  <p>@ Conference on Robot Learning (CoRL) 2023</p>
  

  <!-- Authors -->
  
  

  <!-- Affiliations -->
  <div>
    <p><sup>1</sup>UC Berkeley</p>
    <p><sup>2</sup>Google DeepMind</p>
    <p><sup>3</sup>Stanford University</p>
    <p><sup>4</sup>Simon Fraser University</p>
  </div>
  

  <!-- Links -->
  

  
  

  <!-- tldr -->
  <p>
    <strong>TLDR</strong>
    <em>
      We train anthropomorphic robot hands to play the piano using deep RL<br>
      and release a simulated benchmark and dataset to advance high-dimensional control.
    </em>
  </p>
  

  <!-- wasm demo -->
  <section>
    <h2>Interactive Demo</h2>
    <p>
      This is a demo of our simulated piano playing agent trained with reinforcement learning. It runs
      MuJoCo natively in your browser thanks to <a href="https://github.com/zalo/mujoco_wasm/">WebAssembly</a>.
      You can use your mouse to interact with it, for example by dragging down the piano keys to generate sound
      or pushing the hands to perturb them. The controls section in the top right corner can be used to
      change songs and the simulation section to pause or reset the agent. Make sure you click the
      demo at least once to enable sound.
    </p>
    
  </section>

  <section>
    <h2>Overview</h2>
    <h3>Simulation</h3>
    <p>
      We build our simulated piano-playing environment using the open-source <a href="https://mujoco.org/">MuJoCo</a>
      physics engine.
      It consists in a full-size 88-key digital keyboard and two <a href="https://www.shadowrobot.com/">Shadow Dexterous
        Hands</a>,
      each with 24 degrees of freedom.
    </p>
    
    <img src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/environment.png" id="robopianist-env">
    
    <h3>Musical representation</h3>
    <p>
      We use the Musical Instrument Digital Interface (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MIDI">MIDI</a>) standard
      to represent
      a musical piece as a sequence of time-stamped messages corresponding to "note-on" or "note-off" events. A message
      carries
      additional pieces of information such as the pitch of a note and its velocity.
    </p>
    <p>
      We convert the MIDI file into a time-indexed note trajectory (also known as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Piano_roll">piano roll</a>),
      where each note is represented as a one-hot vector of length 88 (the number of keys on a piano). This trajectory
      is used as the goal
      representation for our agent, informing it which keys to press at each time step.
    </p>
    <p>
      The interactive plot below shows the song Twinkle Twinkle Little Star encoded as a piano roll. The x-axis
      represents
      time in seconds, and the y-axis represents musical pitch as a number between 1 and 88. You can hover over each
      note to
      see what additional information it carries.
    </p>
    
    <p>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synthesizer">synthesizer</a> can be used to convert MIDI files to raw
      audio:</p>
    <audio controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/twinkle_twinkle.wav"></audio>
    <h3>Musical evaluation</h3>
    <p>
      We use precision, recall and F1 scores to evaluate the proficiency of our agent. If at a given instance of time
      there are keys that should be "on"
      and keys that should be "off", precision measures how good the agent is at not hitting any of the keys that should
      be "off", while recall measures
      how good the agent is at hitting all the keys that should be "on". The F1 score combines the precision and recall
      into a single metric, and ranges
      from 0 (if either precision or recall is 0) to 1 (perfect precision and recall).
    </p>
    <h3>Piano fingering and dataset</h3>
    <p>
      Piano fingering refers to the assignment of fingers to notes in a piano piece (see figure below).
      Sheet music will typically provide sparse fingering labels for the tricky sections of a piece to
      help guide pianists, and pianists will often develop their own fingering preferences for a given
      piece.
    </p>
    <p>
      In RoboPianist, we found that the agent struggled to learn to play the piano with a sparse reward signal
      due to the exploration challenge associated with the high-dimensional action space. To overcome this issue,
      we added human priors in the form of the fingering labels to the reward function to guide its exploration.
    </p>
    <p>
      Since fingering labels aren't available in MIDI files by default, we used annotations from the Piano Fingering
      Dataset (<a href="https://beam.kisarazu.ac.jp/~saito/research/PianoFingeringDataset/">PIG</a>) to create 150
      labeled MIDI files, which we call Repertoire-150 and release as part of our environment.
    </p>
    <div>
      <p><img src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/fingering.png"></p><figcaption>Finger numbers (1 to 9) annotated above each note. Source: <a href="https://github.com/marcomusy/pianoplayer">PianoPlayer</a></figcaption>
    </div>
    <h3>MDP Formulation</h3>
    <p>
      We model piano-playing as a finite-horizon Markov Decision Process (MDP) defined by a tuple \( (\mathcal{S},
      \mathcal{A}, \mathcal{\rho}, \mathcal{p}, r, \gamma, H) \),
      where \( \mathcal{S} \) is the state space, \( \mathcal{A} \) is the action space, \( \mathcal{\rho}(\cdot) \) is
      the initial state distribution, \( \mathcal{p} (\cdot | s, a) \)
      governs the dynamics, \( r(s, a) \) is the reward function, \( \gamma \) is the discount factor, and \( H \) is
      the horizon. The goal of the agent is to
      maximize its total expected discounted reward over the horizon \( \mathbb{E}\left[\sum_{t=0}^{H} \gamma^t r(s_t,
      a_t) \right] \).
    </p>
    <p>
      At every time step, the agent receives proprioceptive (i.e, hand joint angles), exteroceptive (i.e., piano
      key states) and goal observations (i.e., piano roll) and outputs 22 target joint angles for each hand. These
      are fed to proportional-position actuators which convert them to torques at each joint. The agent then
      receives a weighted sum of reward terms, including a reward for hitting the correct keys, a reward for
      minimizing energy consumption, and a shaping reward for adhering to the fingering labels.
    </p>
    <p>
      For our policy optimizer, we use a state-of-the-art model-free RL algorithm <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.02034">DroQ</a>
      and train our agent for 5 million steps with a control frequency of 20 Hz.
    </p>
  </section>

  <!-- quantitative results -->
  <section>
    <h2>Quantitative Results</h2>
    <p>
      With careful system design, we improve our agent's performance significantly. Specifically,
      adding an energy cost to the reward formulation, providing a few seconds worth of future goals
      rather than just the current goal, and constraining the action space helped the agent learn
      faster and achieve a higher F1 score. The plot below shows the additive effect of each of
      these design choices on three different songs of increasing difficulty.
    </p>
    <p><img src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/design_considerations.png">
    </p>
    <p>
      When compared to a strong derivative-free model predictive control (MPC) baseline, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.00541">Predictive Sampling</a>,
      our agent achieves a much higher F1 score, averaging 0.79 across Etude-12 versus 0.43 for Predictive Sampling.
    </p>
    <p><img src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/etude_12.jpg">
    </p>
  </section>

  <!-- qualitative results -->
  <section>
    <h2>Qualitative Results</h2>
    <p>
      Each video below is playing real-time and shows our agent playing every song in the Etude-12 subset.
      In each video frame, we display the fingering labels by coloring the keys according to the
      corresponding finger color. When a key is pressed, it is colored green.
    </p>
    <h3>Debug dataset</h3>
    <p>
      This dataset contains "entry-level" songs (e.g., scales) and is useful for sanity checking an agent's performance.
      Fingering labels in this dataset were manually annotated by the authors of this paper. It is not part of the
      Repertoire-150 dataset.
    </p>
    <div>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/simple/c_major.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>C Major Scale</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/simple/d_major.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>D Major Scale</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/simple/twinkle_twinkle.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Twinkle Twinkle Little Star</figcaption>
      </p>
    </div>
    <h3>Etude-12 subset</h3>
    <p>
      Etude-12 is a subset of the full 150-large dataset and consists of 12 songs of varying difficulty.
      It is a subset of the full benchmark reserved for more moderate compute budgets.
    </p>
    <div>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Piano%20Sonata%20D845%201st%20Mov.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Piano Sonata D845 1st Mov (F1=0.72)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Partita%20No.%202%206th%20Mov.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Partita No. 2 6th Mov (F1=0.73)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Bagatelle%20Op.%203%20No.%204.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Bagatelle Op. 3 No. 4 (F1=0.75)</figcaption>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/French%20Suite%20No.%205%20Sarabande.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>French Suite No. 5 Sarabande (F1=0.89)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Waltz%20Op.%2064%20No.%201.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Waltz Op. 64 No. 1 (F1=0.78)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/French%20Suite%20No.%201%20Allemande.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>French Suite No. 1 Allemande (F1=0.78)</figcaption>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Piano%20Sonata%20No.%202%201st%20Mov.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Piano Sonata No. 2 1st Mov (F1=0.79)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Kreisleriana%20Op.%2016%20No.%208.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Kreisleriana Op. 16 No. 8 (F1=0.84)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Golliwoggs%20Cakewalk.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Golliwoggs Cakewalk (F1=0.85)</figcaption>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Piano%20Sonata%20No.%2023%202nd%20Mov.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Piano Sonata No. 23 2nd Mov (F1=0.87)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/French%20Suite%20No.%205%20Gavotte.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>French Suite No. 5 Gavotte (F1=0.77)</figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/etude/Piano%20Sonata%20K279%201st%20Mov.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>Piano Sonata K279 1st Mov (F1=0.78)</figcaption>
      </p>
    </div>
  </section>

  <!-- failures -->
  <section>
    <h2>Common failure modes</h2>
    <div>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/failures/close_together.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>
          Since the Shadow Hand forearms are thicker than a human's, the agent sometimes struggles to nail down notes
          that are really close together. Adding full rotational and translational degrees of freedom to the hands could
          give them the ability to overcome this limitation, but would pose additional challenges for learning.
        </figcaption>
      </p>
      <p>
        <video controls="" src="https://kzakka.com/robopianist/assets/videos/failures/large_stretches.mp4"></video>
        <figcaption>
          The agent struggles with songs that require stretching the fingers over many notes, sometimes more than 1
          octave.
        </figcaption>
      </p>
    </div>
  </section>

  <section>
    <h2>Acknowledgments</h2>
    <p>
      This work is supported in part by ONR #N00014-22-1-2121 under the Science of Autonomy program.
    </p>
    <p>
      This website was heavily inspired by <a href="https://brentyi.github.io/tilted/"> Brent Yi's</a>.
    </p>
  </section>




</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gene Hackman has died (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/27/obituaries/gene-hackman-dead.html</link>
            <guid>43192500</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 08:46:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/27/obituaries/gene-hackman-dead.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/27/obituaries/gene-hackman-dead.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43192500">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/27/obituaries/gene-hackman-dead.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Teslas monitor everything – including you [video] from WIRED (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7VHsDODU7E</link>
            <guid>43192079</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 07:12:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7VHsDODU7E">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l7VHsDODU7E</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43192079">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DualPipe: Bidirectional pipeline parallelism algorithm (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DualPipe</link>
            <guid>43190533</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2025 02:08:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DualPipe">https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DualPipe</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43190533">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">DualPipe</h2><a id="user-content-dualpipe" aria-label="Permalink: DualPipe" href="#dualpipe"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">DualPipe is an innovative bidirectional pipeline parallelism algorithm introduced in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2412.19437" rel="nofollow">DeepSeek-V3 Technical Report</a>. It achieves full overlap of forward and backward computation-communication phases, also reducing pipeline bubbles. For detailed information on computation-communication overlap, please refer to the <a href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/profile-data">profile data</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Schedules</h3><a id="user-content-schedules" aria-label="Permalink: Schedules" href="#schedules"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DualPipe/blob/main/images/schedules.png"><img src="https://github.com/deepseek-ai/DualPipe/raw/main/images/schedules.png" alt="schedules"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Example DualPipe scheduling for 8 PP ranks and 20 micro-batches in two directions.
The micro-batches in the reverse direction are symmetric to those in the forward direction, so
we omit their batch ID for illustration simplicity. Two cells enclosed by a shared black border
have mutually overlapped computation and communication</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pipeline Bubbles and Memory Usage Comparison</h3><a id="user-content-pipeline-bubbles-and-memory-usage-comparison" aria-label="Permalink: Pipeline Bubbles and Memory Usage Comparison" href="#pipeline-bubbles-and-memory-usage-comparison"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Method</th>
<th>Bubble</th>
<th>Parameter</th>
<th>Activation</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>1F1B</td>
<td>(PP-1)(𝐹+𝐵)</td>
<td>1×</td>
<td>PP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ZB1P</td>
<td>(PP-1)(𝐹+𝐵-2𝑊)</td>
<td>1×</td>
<td>PP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>DualPipe</td>
<td>(PP/2-1)(𝐹&amp;𝐵+𝐵-3𝑊)</td>
<td>2×</td>
<td>PP+1</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto">𝐹 denotes the execution time of a forward chunk, 𝐵 denotes the execution time of a
full backward chunk, 𝑊 denotes the execution time of a "backward for weights" chunk, and 𝐹&amp;𝐵
denotes the execution time of two mutually overlapped forward and backward chunks.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick Start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick Start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The usage is shown in the following example:</p>

<p dir="auto">Note: For real-world applications, you will need to implement a custom <code>overlapped_forward_backward</code> method tailored to your specific module.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Requirements</h2><a id="user-content-requirements" aria-label="Permalink: Requirements" href="#requirements"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>PyTorch 2.0 and above</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Developers</h2><a id="user-content-developers" aria-label="Permalink: Developers" href="#developers"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">DualPipe was created and developed by Jiashi Li and Chengqi Deng and Wenfeng Liang.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Citation</h2><a id="user-content-citation" aria-label="Permalink: Citation" href="#citation"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@misc{deepseekai2024deepseekv3technicalreport,
      title={DeepSeek-V3 Technical Report}, 
      author={DeepSeek-AI},
      year={2024},
      eprint={2412.19437},
      archivePrefix={arXiv},
      primaryClass={cs.CL},
      url={https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19437}, 
}"><pre><span>@misc</span>{<span>deepseekai2024deepseekv3technicalreport</span>,
      <span>title</span>=<span><span>{</span>DeepSeek-V3 Technical Report<span>}</span></span>, 
      <span>author</span>=<span><span>{</span>DeepSeek-AI<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>year</span>=<span><span>{</span>2024<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>eprint</span>=<span><span>{</span>2412.19437<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>archivePrefix</span>=<span><span>{</span>arXiv<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>primaryClass</span>=<span><span>{</span>cs.CL<span>}</span></span>,
      <span>url</span>=<span><span>{</span>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19437<span>}</span></span>, 
}</pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Geometric Algebra (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bivector.net/</link>
            <guid>43189703</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 23:54:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bivector.net/">https://bivector.net/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43189703">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

		<!-- Header -->
			

		<!-- Banner -->
			
<!--
<div class="inner" style="padding-top:30px; padding-bottom:30px"><center>
<IMG SRC="GAME_LOGO_TRANS.png" style="float:left" style="object-fit:contain;" height=210><BR>
 <A HREF="game2023.html" style="color:black; font-size:120%">GAME2023 - Geometric Algebra Mini Event. </A><BR>
                                From the 19th to the 21st of April, Kortrijk (Belgium) is transformed into a true temple of geometry !<BR>
                                Join us for talks and workshops from leading researchers in the field ! <BR>
                                <A HREF="game2023.html" style="color:#444"> Click here for more information ! </A><BR><BR>
</center></div>
-->		

	
<!--div class="inner" style="padding-top:30px; padding-bottom:30px"><center>
 <A  TARGET="blank" STYLE='font-size:160%; color:orange; font-family:Source Sans Pro, Arial, Helvetica, sans-serif; font-weight:500' HREF="https://staff.science.uva.nl/l.dorst/AGACSE2024/" style="color:black; font-size:120%">AGACSE2024 - Applied Geometric Algebras in Computer Science and Engineering. </A><BR>
The 9th conference on Applied Geometric Algebras in Computer Science and Engineering will be held <B>27 to 29 August 2024,</B> in the Doelenzaal at Singel 425, which is part of the University of Amsterdam Library and situated in central Amsterdam.               
                                <A TARGET="blank" HREF="https://staff.science.uva.nl/l.dorst/AGACSE2024/" style="color:#444"> Click here for more information ! </A><BR><BR>
</center></div-->
			
			
			<div id="twoandahalf"><center>
  
  <h3>Featured Introductions</h3>
  <div>
  <iframe width="350" height="200" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Fc5rlZ3Malw" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe><p>  
  Geometric Numbers
  </p></div>
  <!--div style="max-width:350px; display:inline-block; margin:10px">
  <iframe width="350" height="200" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ikCIUzX9myY" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
  Applications of Geometric Algebra
  </div-->
  <div>
  <iframe width="350" height="200" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/tX4H_ctggYo?start=1084" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
  <!--iframe width="350" height="200" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ichOiuBoBoQ" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe--><p>
  SIGGRAPH 2019 Geometric Algebra
  </p></div>
  <div>
  <iframe width="350" height="200" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/60z_hpEAtD8" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe><p>
  Geometric Algebra
  </p></div>
</center></div>



<!--                                <div style="display:inline-block; text-align:center">

                                <A HREF="game2020.html" style="color:black; font-size:120%"> GAME2020 - Geometric Algebra Mini Event. </A><BR>
                                From the 26th to the 28th of February, Kortrijk (Belgium) is transformed into a true temple of geometry !<BR>
                                Join us for talks and workshops from leading researchers in the field ! <BR>
                                <A HREF="game2020.html" style="color:#444"> Click here for more information ! </A>
                                
				</div> -->

			<!--section id="three" class="wrapper align-center" style="background-color:#6cc091; color:white">
				<div class="inner align-center" style="display: flex;align-items: center;justify-content: center;">
                                <div class="conference" style="display:inline-block;"><a title="SIGGRAPH Conference" href="https://www.siggraph.org/current-conference" href="https://www.siggraph.org/current-conference"><img style="border: none;" src="https://media.siggraph.org/promo/siggraph-badge.gif" src="https://media.siggraph.org/promo/siggraph-badge.gif" alt="SIGGRAPH" width="160" height="64" /></a></div>
                                <div style="padding-left:20px; display:inline-block; text-align:center">
                                Don't miss out on this years Siggraph Course <A HREF="https://s2019.siggraph.org/presentation/?id=gensub_345&sess=sess346" TARGET="blank" STYLE="color:white">"Geometric Algebra for Computer Graphics"</A>!<BR>
                                <A HREF="siggraph.zip" download="siggraph.zip" STYLE="color:white">Download the course notes and code here</A>
                                or check out <A  style="color:white" HREF="https://slides.com/enkimute/siggraph"
                                target="blank">the presentation slides</A>
				</div>
			</section-->

		<!-- Three -->
			<div id="three">
				        <!--
				        <p>We may always depend on it that algebra, which cannot be translated into good English and sound common sense, is bad algebra.<br>
				        <span style="padding-left:400px">William Kingdon Clifford</span>
				        </p>
				        -->
				        <p>
				        Clifford's <b>Geometric Algebra</b> enables a unified, intuitive and fresh perspective
				        on vector spaces, giving elements of arbitrary dimensionality a natural home.
				        </p>
					<div>
						<article>
							
							
							<header>
								<h3>The Vector</h3>
								<p>
							The <b>Vector</b> is an oriented, <b>one dimensional</b><br>
							quantity. Two $\parallel$ <b>Vectors</b> multiply to a <b>Scalar</b> ($\mathbb R$).<br>
							Two $\perp$ vectors <b>anti-commute</b> ($e_1e_2=-e_2e_1$)
							</p>
							</header>
							<!--footer>
								<a href="doc.html" class="button">Learn More</a>
							</footer-->
						</article>
						<article>
							
							
							<header>
								<h3>The Bivector</h3>
								<p>
							The <b>Bivector</b> is an oriented, <b>two dimensional</b><br>
							quantity. <b>Bivectors</b> naturally represent<br> <b>transformations</b>.
							Similarly, $n$ vectors combine into an $n$-vector.
							</p>
							</header>
							<!--footer>
								<a href="doc.html" class="button">Learn More</a>
							</footer-->
						</article>
					</div>
                                </div>
                        <div id="four">
					<p>
					The $n$-dimensional <b>geometric algebra</b> $\mathbb R_{p,q,r}$ is constructed
					from $p$ <b>positive</b>, $q$ <b>negative</b> and $r$ <b>null</b> vectors
					called <b>generators</b>, written $\bf e_i$  
					</p>	
					<div>
						<article>
							
							<header>
								<h3>The Scalar</h3>
								<p>
							The <b>Scalars $\mathbb R$</b> are included in <br>
							the algebras. every basis <b>$n$-vector</b><br> squares
							to a Real Number.<br>
							</p>
							</header>
							<!--footer>
								<a href="doc.html" class="button">Learn More</a>
							</footer-->
						</article>
						<article>
							
							<header>
								<h3>The Rotor</h3>
								<p>
							The product of two <b>vectors</b>, or the<br>
							<b>exponentiation</b> of a  <b>bivector</b> creates<br>
							a rotor. (rotation, translation, ..)
							</p>
							</header>
							<!--footer>
								<a href="doc.html" class="button">Learn More</a>
							</footer-->
						</article>
					</div>
					<p>
					A generic element of the algebra is called a <b>multivector</b> and is
					a linear combination of <b>scalar</b>, <b>vector</b> and <b>$n$-vector</b> parts.<b>
					$$\mathbf X = \alpha_0 + \alpha_1 \mathbf e_1 + .. + \alpha_i \mathbf e_{12} + .. + \alpha_n \mathbf e_{12..n} $$
					</b>
					</p>	
					
					
				</div>
			<div id="four">
				        <h3>Vectorspace Geometric Algebra</h3>
					<p>
					The Geometric Algebras for the 2D and 3D vectors naturally
					include 2D and 3D rotations.
					</p>	
					<div>
						<article>
							<div id="scalar">
							   <p>$\mathbb R_2^+ \cong \mathbb C$</p>
							</div>
							<header>
								<h3>2D Vectors</h3>
								<p>
							The geometric algebra $\mathbb R_2$ of the <br>
							<b>2D Vectors</b> has the <b>complex numbers</b><br>
							as its even subalgebra.
							</p>
							</header>
							<!--footer>
								<a href="doc.html" class="button">Learn More</a>
							</footer-->
						</article>
						<article>
							<div id="scalar">
							   <p>$\mathbb R_3^+ \cong \mathbb H$</p>
							</div>
							<header>
								<h3>3D Vectors</h3>
								<p>
							The geometric algebra $\mathbb R_3$ of the <br>
							<b>3D Vectors</b> has the <b>quaternions</b><br>
							as its even subalgebra.
							</p>
							</header>
							<!--footer>
								<a href="doc.html" class="button">Learn More</a>
							</footer-->
						</article>
					</div>
				</div>
			<div id="five">
				        <h3>Projective Geometric Algebra</h3>
					<p>
					Using one extra dimension, we obtain the plane-based <b>Projective Geometric Algebra</b>
					for 2 and 3 dimensions. Its elements are <b>points</b>, <b>lines</b> and <b>planes</b>. It
					includes elements at <b>infinity</b> and has exception free <b>join</b> and <b>meet</b> operations.
					Its even subalgebra provides in rotations &amp; translations and is isomorphic to the <b>dual quaternions</b>
					</p>	
					<div>
						<article>
							
							
						
							<header>
								<h3>$\mathbb R^*_{2,0,1}$ : 2D PGA</h3>
								<p>
							In <b>2D PGA</b> points <b>join</b> $\vee$ into <br \="">
							lines and lines <b>meet</b> $\wedge$ into points.<br \="">
							<b>Rotations</b> and <b>translations</b> are unified,<br \="">
							with bivectors isomorphic to $\mathfrak{SE}(2)$
							</p>
							</header>
							
						</article>
						<article>
							
							
							<header>
								<h3>$\mathbb R^*_{3,0,1}$ : 3D PGA</h3>
								<p>
							In <b>3D PGA</b> points and lines <b>join</b> $\vee$ into <br \="">
							lines and planes, while lines and planes <b>meet</b> $\wedge$<br \="">
							into points and lines. The bivectors are isomorphic<br \="">
							to $\mathfrak{SE}(3)$, the <b>dual quaternions</b>
							</p>
							</header>
							
						</article>
					</div>
				</div>
			<div id="sox">
				        <h3>Conformal Geometric Algebra</h3>
					<p>
					Using two extra dimensions, we obtain the point-based <b>Conformal Geometric Algebra</b>
					for 2 and 3 dimensions. Its elements are <b>points</b>, <b>point pairs</b>, <b>lines</b>, <b>circles</b>, <b>spheres</b> and <b>planes</b>. It
					includes an infinite point and has exception free <b>join</b> and <b>meet</b> operations.
					Its even subalgebra provides in <b>conformal transformations</b>.
					</p>	
					<div>
						<article>
							
							
						
							<header>
								<h3>$\mathbb R_{3,1}$ : 2D CGA</h3>
								<p>
							In <b>2D CGA</b>, points <b>join</b> ($\wedge$) into lines<br>
							and circles, and lines and circles <b>meet</b> ($\vee$) in points.<br>
							<b>Rotations</b>, <b>Translations</b> and <b>Dilations</b> all <br>
							come in versor form.	
							</p>
							</header>
							
						</article>
						<article>
							
							
							<header>
								<h3>$\mathbb R_{4,1}$ : 3D CGA</h3>
								<p>
							In <b>3D CGA</b>, points <b>join</b> ($\wedge$) into pairs, lines,<br>
							circles, planes and spheres, which <b>meet</b> ($\vee$) in points,<br>
							pairs, circles and lines. <b>Rotations</b>, <b>Translations</b><br>
							and <b>Dilations</b> all come in versor form.	
							</p>
							</header>
							
						</article>
					</div>
				</div>

		<!-- Footer -->
			

		<!-- Scripts -->
			<!--script src="assets/js/jquery.min.js"></script>
			<script src="assets/js/skel.min.js"></script>
			<script src="assets/js/util.js"></script>
			<script src="assets/js/main.js"></script-->
         
	
</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[iMac G4(K) (398 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jcs.org/2025/02/26/imacg4k</link>
            <guid>43188971</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 22:25:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jcs.org/2025/02/26/imacg4k">https://jcs.org/2025/02/26/imacg4k</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43188971">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
					<header>
						
						
					</header>
					<p>A year ago I tried using an M1 iMac for work duty but its 21" screen took up too
						much room on my desk.
						After seeing
						<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hJKcwH7tMW4">Sean's video on Action Retro</a>
						about putting an M4 Mac Mini inside an
						<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IMac_G4">iMac G4</a>,
						I thought I'd give it a try.</p>
					<figure></figure>
					<div>
						<h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of Contents</h2>
						<ol start="0">
							<li><a href="#">Top</a></li>
						</ol>
						<ol id="markdown-toc">
							<li><a href="#juicy-crumb-docklite-g4" id="markdown-toc-juicy-crumb-docklite-g4">Juicy Crumb DockLite G4</a>    
								<ol>
									<li><a href="#color-banding" id="markdown-toc-color-banding">Color Banding</a></li>
									<li><a href="#imac-screen-resolution" id="markdown-toc-imac-screen-resolution">iMac Screen Resolution</a></li>
									<li><a href="#exposed-ports" id="markdown-toc-exposed-ports">Exposed Ports</a></li>
									<li><a href="#screen-blanking" id="markdown-toc-screen-blanking">Screen Blanking</a></li>
								</ol>
							</li>
							<li><a href="#upgrading-the-screen" id="markdown-toc-upgrading-the-screen">Upgrading the Screen</a></li>
							<li><a href="#imac-neck" id="markdown-toc-imac-neck">iMac Neck</a></li>
							<li><a href="#mac-mini-mouting" id="markdown-toc-mac-mini-mouting">Mac Mini Mouting</a></li>
							<li><a href="#remaining-issues" id="markdown-toc-remaining-issues">Remaining Issues</a></li>
						</ol>
					</div>
					<h2 id="juicy-crumb-docklite-g4">Juicy Crumb DockLite G4</h2>
					<p>The
						<a href="https://juicycrumb.com/product/docklite-g4/">Juicy Crumb DockLite G4</a>
						replaces the main logic board in a 17" or 20" iMac G4 and turns its built-in LCD
						into an HDMI monitor.
						It also uses the iMac's custom power supply and has a built-in audio amplifier
						to be able to drive the
						<a href="https://apple.fandom.com/wiki/Apple_Pro_Speakers">Apple Pro speakers</a>
						that were available for the iMac G4.
						Swapping the boards is easy and completely reversible.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_board-1500x821.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_board-680x372.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_board-680x372.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_board-1360x744@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="372"></a>
						<figcaption>iMac G4 1GHz logic board and DockLite G4</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>I ordered the DockLite G4 but it was going to take a few weeks to get.
						In the mean time, I needed to find a 17" iMac G4 in good condition but not fully
						working so that I wouldn't be sacrificing a working machine.
						I eventually found one on eBay and I paid nearly as much for shipping as the
						machine itself.
						The iMac uses a lot of thick steel inside the dome which makes it quite heavy.</p>
					<p><em>Pro tip: there are a bunch of 17" G4 iMacs on eBay that are listed as 15".
							I don't know if it's because eBay fills this in by default or if people are
							confused by the screen size since it measures about 15" horizontally but the 17"
							refers to its diagonal size.
							It's usually possible to tell which size it is by the photos since the 15" looks
							much more square, but if you can get the serial number on the bottom,
							<a href="https://everymac.com/ultimate-mac-lookup/">looking it up</a>
							will confirm whether it's 15" or 17".</em></p>
					<p>Once the dead iMac arrived, a power-on test produced a happy chime but showed
						nothing on the screen.
						At this point I wasn't sure if the LCD was busted or if the problem was with the
						iMac's logic board, so I had to get a
						<a href="https://www.ebay.com/sch/i.html?_nkw=mini-vga+to+vga">Mini VGA to VGA adapter</a>
						to test its video output.
						This also failed to show any video so I was pretty sure the logic board was
						faulty but I still had no idea whether the LCD worked.</p>
					<p>Eventually the DockLite arrived from Australia and after a few minutes of
						swapping things, I was able to confirm that the LCD worked fine and was
						displaying the Mac Mini's desktop over HDMI.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite-m4-1125x1500.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite-m4-505x673.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite-m4-505x673.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite-m4-1010x1346@2x.jpg 2x" width="505" height="673"></a>
							<figcaption>iMac G4 with DockLite G4 connected to M4 Mac Mini</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>Unfortunately after using the iMac for a little while, I noticed a few issues
						that soured my experience with the DockLite.</p>
					<h3 id="color-banding">Color Banding</h3>
					<p>I'm not sure whether the DockLite or the 20-year old LCD screen is to blame for
						this, but there is noticeable color banding on the screen, especially with macOS
						window shadows.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-banding-1500x518.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-banding-680x235.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-banding-680x235.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-banding-1360x470@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="235"></a>
						<figcaption>Color banding in window shadow</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>I wasn't able to test native Mac OS with the iMac's logic board so I can't be
						sure the problem isn't with the LCD, but I've seen this same problem with some
						other generic
						<a href="https://www.ebay.com/sch/i.html?_nkw=lvds+to+hdmi">LVDS/eDP to HDMI</a>
						boards.</p>
					<h3 id="imac-screen-resolution">iMac Screen Resolution</h3>
					<p>My other issue with using the iMac G4 was that its 17" screen has a resolution
						of only 1440x900.
						This isn't terrible but having used 1.5x or 2x resolution screens on my
						<a href="https://jcs.org/openbsd-laptops">laptops</a>
						for many years, the small resolution was not ideal and modern macOS is
						definitely not tuned for 1x resolutions anymore.</p>
					<h3 id="exposed-ports">Exposed Ports</h3>
					<p>It's a very minor gripe, but I would have liked some sort of covers to fill in
						the space between the DockLite's new ports (or lack thereof) and the iMac's
						bottom case cutouts.
						No one's going to see them anyway but for the money, it would have been nice to
						have that included.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_ports-1500x678.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_ports-680x307.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_ports-680x307.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-docklite_ports-1360x614@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="307"></a>
						<figcaption>DockLite ports</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<h3 id="screen-blanking">Screen Blanking</h3>
					<p>However, my biggest issue with the DockLite is that it doesn't support turning
						off the display via HDMI (DPMS or CEC or whatever this is).
						When the Mac Mini tries to blank the screen after inactivity, the DockLite keeps
						the backlight on showing a black screen.
						Juicy Crumb warns about this in the documentation saying to tap the power button
						on the back of the iMac (which pushes the power button on the DockLite board)
						to turn off the screen since leaving it on all the time will damage it.
						This was going to get pretty annoying since I would like to leave the machine on
						all the time but I wouldn't be using it very often, so I would like the display
						to turn off and back on automatically when I need it.</p>
					<p>On the upside, the DockLite <em>does</em> support adjusting the LCD's backlight level
						via USB through a
						<a href="https://juicycrumb.com/juicy-link/">custom macOS application</a>
						rather than having to press the buttons on the back of the iMac.</p>
					<h2 id="upgrading-the-screen">Upgrading the Screen</h2>
					<p>With these faults in mind, I decided to ditch the DockLite and go with a custom
						screen upgrade.
						With a different LCD and appropriate driver board, I could get a higher
						resolution with better color and gain screen blanking.
						By eliminating the DockLite, I could then remove the iMac's internal power
						supply which otherwise takes up a large portion of the upper part of the dome.
						That would then free up enough room inside the iMac to store the Mac Mini
						without modifying it (as Sean had to in his YouTube video).</p>
					<p>Browsing eBay, I found the
						<a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/295880001215">Sharp LQ170R1JX42</a>,
						a 4K 3840x2400 17" LCD originally used in the Dell XPS 17.
						This would provide a 2x resolution of 1920x1200 in the same outer footprint of
						the iMac's original LCD and fit behind the screen bezel.
						An appropriate
						<a href="https://www.aliexpress.us/item/3256807092859241.html">eDP driver board</a>
						would connect the LCD to the Mac Mini over HDMI or USB-C.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-lcd_and_controller-1500x764.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-lcd_and_controller-680x346.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-lcd_and_controller-680x346.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-lcd_and_controller-1360x692@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="346"></a>
						<figcaption>LQ170R1JX42 with eDP driver</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>Once I confirmed the new LCD and driver worked with the Mac Mini, I disassembled
						the iMac to swap its screen.
						The original LCD is quite heavy and is about 1/2" thick due to its CCFL
						backlight.
						The new LCD with its LED backlight is so light and thin, I didn't even bother
						making a frame to attach it to the bezel, I just secured it with tape and then
						mounted the controller to the back of it.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-original_lcd-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-original_lcd-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-original_lcd-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-original_lcd-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>iMac screen with original LCD</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-screen_removed-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-screen_removed-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-screen_removed-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-screen_removed-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>Bezel with screen removed</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-new_lcd-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-new_lcd-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-new_lcd-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-new_lcd-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>New LCD mounted in bezel</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-controller_mounted-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-controller_mounted-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-controller_mounted-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-controller_mounted-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>Controller on the back of the LCD</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>Running at its native 3840x2400 resolution shows how fine its dot-pitch is,
						though I am now running it at 2x:</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-high_resolution-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-high_resolution-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-high_resolution-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-high_resolution-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>3840x2400</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-2x_resolution-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-2x_resolution-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-2x_resolution-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-2x_resolution-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>1920x1200 @ 2x</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>Using the
						<a href="https://github.com/MonitorControl/MonitorControl">MonitorControl</a>
						utility, I could change the LCD backlight level from software, and the eDP board
						automatically powers off the LCD when the Mac Mini tells it to sleep, unlike the
						DockLite.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-monitorcontrol-1500x550.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-monitorcontrol-680x249.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-monitorcontrol-680x249.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-monitorcontrol-1360x498@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="249"></a>
							<figcaption>MonitorControl</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<h2 id="imac-neck">iMac Neck</h2>
					<p>Once the new LCD was working over USB-C, I ran into the problem of having to get
						the new cable run inside of the iMac's articulating neck.
						The cables connecting to the original LCD are run inside the neck assembly
						during manufacturing and then connectors are added afterward since they are too
						large to fit through the small openings at the top and bottom of the neck.
						Unfortunately this meant I had to cut these original cables to get them out, and
						it also made it difficult to run a USB-C cable through it.</p>
					<p>The smallest diameter of the neck hinge is about 9mm where it meets the dome,
						but most USB-C/Thunderbolt cables I tried had at least a width of about 12mm.
						Even after trimming off the rubber/silicone of some of them, they often had a
						PCB or other stuff inside that was wider than the connector.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-imac_neck-1125x1500.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-imac_neck-335x446.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-imac_neck-335x446.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-imac_neck-670x892@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="446"></a>
							<figcaption>Open iMac neck with original cables</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-choke_point-1125x1500.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-choke_point-335x446.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-choke_point-335x446.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-choke_point-670x892@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="446"></a>
							<figcaption>Smallest opening at the neck base</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>The 9mm opening is on a flange that slides inside the base of the neck and is
						where the dome attaches to the neck with 5 screws.
						It tapers to a smaller opening at the top because there is usually a sleeve that
						goes around it to make rotating smoother, though it's not really needed in my
						experience.
						I figured I could make a new piece like it and make it not taper, allowing the
						inner wall to be thinner and its opening wider, ultimately allowing the USB-C
						cable to pass through it.</p>
					<p>I took some measurements and
						<a href="https://jcs.org/notes/2025/01/27/3lgqyqymzrk2x">modeled</a>
						the flange in Tinkercad, then did a bunch of 3D prints making tiny adjustments
						each time.
						I suppose I'm more of a "measure once, cut 14 times" person.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-prototypes-1500x793.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-prototypes-335x177.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-prototypes-335x177.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-prototypes-670x354@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="177"></a>
							<figcaption>3D-printed prototypes</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-wider_neck-1500x793.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-wider_neck-335x177.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-wider_neck-335x177.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-wider_neck-670x354@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="177"></a>
							<figcaption>Final prototype</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>Although it's not load bearing (it is sandwiched between the steel openings at
						the top of the dome and bottom of the neck assembly), I wanted the new flange to
						be made out of something stronger than my 3D printer could produce.
						Once my prototyping was done, I sent the design off to
						<a href="https://jlccnc.com/">JLCCNC</a>
						to get it machined out of 6061 aluminum.
						Their engineer said the thin wall of the vertical tube had to be thicker to get
						safely machined, so although the opening ended up not being as wide as I
						wanted, it still allowed a USB-C cable to pass through.</p>
					<p>It took a few weeks to machine since I was doing this during Chinese New Year.
						Although I didn't like the bead-blasted finish which immediately scuffed up, it
						fit perfectly and the dome could securely attach to the neck.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-tinkercad-1318x793.png"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-tinkercad-221x132.png" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-tinkercad-221x132.png 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-tinkercad-442x264@2x.png 2x" width="221" height="132"></a>
							<figcaption>My final design in Tinkercad</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-machined-1500x902.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-machined-221x132.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-machined-221x132.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-machined-442x264@2x.jpg 2x" width="221" height="132"></a>
							<figcaption>Machined flange vs. original</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-flange_diameters-1500x902.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-flange_diameters-221x132.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-flange_diameters-221x132.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-flange_diameters-442x264@2x.jpg 2x" width="221" height="132"></a>
							<figcaption>Larger inner wall on my flange</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>Once I trimmed off some excess rubber from the end of a Thunderbolt cable, I was
						able to route it through the opening in the rear of the screen housing, down the
						neck, through the new flange, and into the dome.
						I then added some shrink tubing to the connector to replace the removed rubber.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_top-1125x1500.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_top-335x446.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_top-335x446.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_top-670x892@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="446"></a>
							<figcaption>Into the screen housing...</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_through_neck-1125x1500.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_through_neck-335x446.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_through_neck-335x446.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-usb_c_through_neck-670x892@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="446"></a>
							<figcaption>down the neck...</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-through-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-through-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-through-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-through-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>through the flange...</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-into_dome-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-into_dome-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-into_dome-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-into_dome-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>to grandmother's house we go</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>It was important to keep a bit of slack in the cable through the neck to make
						sure its articulation still worked.</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-upright-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-upright-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-upright-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-upright-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>Screen upright</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-extended-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-extended-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-extended-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-extended-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>Screen extended</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<h2 id="mac-mini-mouting">Mac Mini Mouting</h2>
					<p>Once the top was all put back together, I could now focus on mounting the Mac
						Mini inside the dome.</p>
					<p>I modeled a new circular piece to replace the Juicy Crumb DockLite board and
						then added a cross piece to secure the Mac Mini.
						I was limited by my 3D-printer's build plate dimensions so I had to chop off the
						bottom of the circle, but there were no mounting holes in that area anyway.
						I 3D-printed it, inserted heatserts into the cross piece, and bolted down the
						Mac Mini:</p>
					<center>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mount-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mount-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mount-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mount-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>Mac Mini mount (with heatserts)</figcaption>
						</figure>
						<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mounted-1500x1125.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mounted-335x251.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mounted-335x251.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-mac_mounted-670x502@2x.jpg 2x" width="335" height="251"></a>
							<figcaption>Mac Mini mounted</figcaption>
						</figure>
					</center>
					<p>While every tech reviewer complained about the M4 Mac Mini's power button being
						moved to the bottom, it was actually beneficial to me when putting it inside the
						iMac.  Underneath the iMac is a removable panel that originally gave access to
						the upgradeable RAM and AirPort slots, but I no longer need it.</p>
					<p>By mounting the Mac Mini rotated a bit, the power button is now accessible from
						the bottom of the iMac and can be pressed just by tilting up the left side of
						the iMac a bit.
						Since I would only need to press this button on rare occasions, I figured this
						would be easier than having to disassemble the Mac Mini to solder an external
						power button to it.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-power_button-1500x869.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-power_button-680x394.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-power_button-680x394.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-power_button-1360x788@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="394"></a>
						<figcaption>Mac Mini power button</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<p>I didn't want to have to open the iMac to reach certain ports, so I bought some
						short extension cables for the IEC C7/C8 power port, ethernet, and one
						Thunderbolt port.
						For now they are just slightly hanging out the back but I'd like to 3D print
						some sort of bracket to hold them all in place just behind the port openings and
						fill in the voids.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-pigtails-1500x852.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-pigtails-680x386.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-pigtails-680x386.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-pigtails-1360x772@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="386"></a>
						<figcaption>Pigtail cables</figcaption>
					</figure>
					<h2 id="remaining-issues">Remaining Issues</h2>
					<p>Aside from having to make the rear port bracket, I thought it also might be neat
						to make use of the flip-down optical drive door to put some USB ports behind it.</p>
					<p>The eDP LCD controller currently has an annoying "feature" where once the
						display goes to sleep, it shows a blue screen with "No Signal" shown for about
						10 seconds before completely shutting off.
						From what I've read, it's possible to disable this in the firmware but I'm
						still trying to figure out how to modify that.</p>
					<figure><a href="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-done-1500x967.jpg"><img src="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-done-680x438.jpg" srcset="https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-done-680x438.jpg 1x, https://jcs.org/images/2025-02-26-done-1360x876@2x.jpg 2x" width="680" height="438"></a>
						<figcaption>My iMac G4(K) next to my Mac Plus</figcaption>
					</figure>
				</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jeff Bezos' revamp of 'Washington Post' opinions leads editor to quit (281 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.npr.org/2025/02/26/nx-s1-5309725/jeff-bezos-washington-post-opinion-section</link>
            <guid>43188749</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 22:02:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/02/26/nx-s1-5309725/jeff-bezos-washington-post-opinion-section">https://www.npr.org/2025/02/26/nx-s1-5309725/jeff-bezos-washington-post-opinion-section</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43188749">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="storytext">
      <div id="resg-s1-50827">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/400/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 400w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/600/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/800/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 800w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/900/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 900w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1200/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 1200w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1600/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 1600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1800/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 1800w" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/400/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 400w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/600/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/800/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 800w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/900/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 900w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1200/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 1200w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1600/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 1600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1800/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg 1800w" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/1100/quality/50/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/5965x3977+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F14%2Ff3%2Fc083c8ac4248ba39f24e335ce4a9%2Fgettyimages-2194958315.jpg" alt="The Washington Post owner Jeff Bezos attends a luncheon following the inauguration of President Trump in January. Bezos says the newspaper's editorial section will publish only &quot;in support and defense of two pillars: personal liberties and free markets.&quot;" fetchpriority="high">
        </picture>
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                <em>The Washington Post</em> owner Jeff Bezos attends a luncheon following the inauguration of President Trump in January. Bezos says the newspaper's editorial section will publish only "in support and defense of two pillars: personal liberties and free markets."
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    Kevin Dietsch/Getty Images/Getty Images North America
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        Kevin Dietsch/Getty Images/Getty Images North America
        
    </span>
</p></div>
   </div>
   <p>The <em>Washington Post</em>'s billionaire owner, Jeff Bezos, announced a sweeping new libertarian vision for the paper's opinion sections on Wednesday, just four months after his decision to kill a presidential endorsement of Kamala Harris triggered hundreds of thousands of subscribers to cancel.</p>   <p><em>Post</em> Opinions Editor David Shipley, whom Bezos recruited from Bloomberg Opinions in 2022, chose to resign rather than stay to oversee the paper's revamped sections.</p>   <p>"We are going to be writing every day in support and defense of two pillars: personal liberties and free markets," Bezos <a href="https://x.com/JeffBezos/status/1894757287052362088" target="_blank"><u>wrote in a memo to staffers</u></a> announcing the changes. "We'll cover other topics too of course, but viewpoints opposing those pillars will be left to be published by others."</p>   
   <p>Newspaper op-ed sections have incorporated opposing views for years. The term "op-ed" is literally an abbreviation for pieces running "opposite the editorial pages" that often conflicted with a publisher's editorial line. But Bezos characterized that practice as outdated.</p>   <p>"There was a time when a newspaper, especially one that was a local monopoly, might have seen it as a service to bring to the reader's doorstep every morning a broad-based opinion section that sought to cover all views," Bezos said. "Today, the internet does that job."</p>   <h3>Shock inside the newsroom</h3>   <p>At an hour-long meeting with opinion writers, Shipley said he did not know what lay ahead, according to an attendee who spoke on condition of anonymity because they did not have permission to speak publicly.</p>   <p>Shipley said he had wanted a "broader, pluralistic place," but that Bezos sought "a focused [opinion] report."</p>   <p>Bezos justified his decision in the memo to staffers. "I am of America and for America, and proud to be so," he wrote. "And a big part of America's success has been freedom in the economic realm and everywhere else."</p>   <p>The decision sparked fresh shock and dismay at the paper. After senior news editors raised concerns at a meeting Wednesday, Executive Editor Matt Murray reassured them that Bezos had given no indication that he wanted to interfere with news coverage, according to two people with direct knowledge. A spokesperson for the <em>Post</em> confirmed his remarks.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5309725-100" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>Later in the day, Murray sent a memo to the newsroom to underscore the point: "The independent and unbiased work of The Post's newsroom remains unchanged, and we will continue to pursue engaging impactful journalism without fear or favor." (Murray and Bezos did not reply to requests for comment.)</p>   <p><em>Post</em> Associate Editor David Maraniss, a legendary journalist whose association with the newspaper stretches back more than four decades, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/davidmaraniss.bsky.social/post/3lj3o3ozerc2d" target="_blank"><u>wrote on Bluesky</u></a> that he would never write for it again as long as Bezos owns it.</p>   
   <p>"One pernicious step after another, Bezos encroached on the <em>Post</em> editorial policy," Maraniss wrote. "Today he seized it fully. The old <em>Washington Post</em> is gone."</p>   <p>Former senior managing editor Cameron Barr, who had been editing projects for the paper, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/cameron-barr-72093bb0_today-i-am-ending-my-professional-association-activity-7300598172819546112-TjW-?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAAB91b0BakuuTKmXlgSzUTCFIqDVZDWUq6o" target="_blank">announced on LinkedIn that he was severing ties with the <em>Post</em></a>. He wrote that Bezos's changes amount to "an unacceptable erosion of its commitment to publishing a healthy diversity of opinion and argument."</p>   <p>One writer for the opinions section told NPR he was "heartsick," adding, "leadership matters."</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5309725-101" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>NPR spoke to six people with direct knowledge of events for this article. They were given the ability to speak anonymously because they were not authorized to speak about internal matters at the paper.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5309725-102" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>Shipley did not respond to requests for comment. According to a person with direct knowledge, Shipley told Bezos that the new approach would violate the <em>Post</em>'s promise of holding power to account.</p>   <h3>Bezos new approach differs dramatically  from first Trump term</h3>   <p>Bezos stood by the newspaper's dogged reporting on the first Trump administration. In that period, the <em>Post </em>adopted the motto "Democracy Dies in Darkness." It won Pulitzer Prizes for coverage of the <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/pr/2022/05/09/pulitzer-prize-public-service/" target="_blank">Jan. 6 attack on the U.S. Capitol</a> and, earlier, of <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/national/wp/2018/04/16/feature/washington-post-wins-pulitzer-prizes-for-roy-moore-investigation-russia-reporting/" target="_blank">Russian interference</a> in the 2016 presidential election.</p>   <p>His business interests, however, have billions of dollars in dealings with the federal government. And Trump's regulators have made clear they intend to take an active role. </p>   <p>Bezos' decision in October to <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/10/25/nx-s1-5165353/washington-post-presidential-endorsement-trump-harris" target="_blank">kill the Harris editorial</a> sparked a furor inside and outside the paper, leading editorial writers to resign and <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/01/04/nx-s1-5248299/cartoonist-quits-wapo-over-bezos-trump-cartoon-washingtonpost" target="_blank">more than 300,000</a> people to cancel their digital subscriptions in a matter of days. (The <em>Post </em>says it has been able to win some subscribers back and garner some new subscribers in the opening weeks of Trump's second term.)</p>   <div id="resg-s1-50914">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/400/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 400w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/600/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/800/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 800w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/900/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 900w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 1200w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1600/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 1600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1800/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 1800w" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/400/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 400w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/600/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/800/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 800w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/900/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 900w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1200/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 1200w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1600/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 1600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1800/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg 1800w" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1300px) 763px, (min-width: 1025px) calc(100vw - 496px), (min-width: 768px) calc(100vw - 171px), calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/1100/quality/50/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/6000x4000+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fa3%2F16%2F46dd3dcf4d5dbd6d68d69e7392ca%2Fgettyimages-2151301000.jpg" alt="David Shipley resigned as opinions editor of The Washington Post after owner Jeff Bezos declared he wanted the section to focus only on supporting &quot;personal liberties and free markets.&quot; In this 2024 photo, Shipley and the newsroom celebrate winning three Pulitzer Prizes." loading="lazy">
        </picture>
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                David Shipley resigned as opinions editor of <em>The Washington Post</em> after owner Jeff Bezos declared he wanted the section to focus only on supporting "personal liberties and free markets." In this 2024 photo, Shipley and the newsroom celebrate winning three Pulitzer Prizes.
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    The Washington Post/The Washington Post via Getty Im/The Washington Post
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        The Washington Post/The Washington Post via Getty Im/The Washington Post
        
    </span>
</p></div>
   </div>
   <p>As a practical matter, Shipley argued to Bezos, the <em>Wall Street Journal</em>'s highly pro-markets pages have had a similar policy for decades. As with the decision not to publish the endorsement of Harris, Shipley's arguments fell on deaf ears.</p>   
   <p>In his memo to staff, Bezos praised Shipley and wrote that he offered the editor the chance to lead the reformed sections. "I suggested to him if the answer wasn't 'hell yes,' then it had to be 'no,'" Bezos wrote.</p>   <p>The <em>Post</em> has aggressively covered the new administration. But Bezos appears to have embraced the president's return to power. Bezos personally paid $1 million toward Trump's inaugural fund. He and his fiancée Lauren Sánchez traveled to Trump's Florida estate, Mar-a-Lago, to socialize with the Trumps. And, along with other digital chieftains, Bezos sat behind the president as he was sworn in for a second term.</p>   <h3>Opinions editor repeatedly in tough spot</h3>   <p>Shipley's two-and-a-half years have brought acclaim for the section, with two Pulitzer Prizes and two Loeb Awards. But his standing was deeply undercut by Bezos's recent decisions, especially over the Harris endorsement.</p>   <p>When Shipley decided to withhold a cartoon from the Pulitzer-winning staffer Ann Telnaes about Bezos from publication, he told colleagues he believed he was making a decision on the merits, not pulling his punches. The cartoon depicted Bezos abasing himself along with other tech titans before Trump.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5309725-103" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>"Not every editorial judgment is a reflection of a malign force," Shipley said in a statement shared at the time with NPR. "My decision was guided by the fact that we had just published a column on the same topic as the cartoon and had already scheduled another column — this one a satire — for publication. The only bias was against repetition."</p>   <p>Shipley told colleagues privately that he understood, given the moment, it might be hard to credit his actual motivations.</p>   <p>The paper <a href="https://www.npr.org/2024/10/26/nx-s1-5166062/washington-post-endorsement-controversy" target="_blank">has bled veteran talent</a> from both the opinion and news sides since the news broke about the killed editorial. <em>Post</em> journalists left for the <em>Atlantic</em>, the <em>New York Times</em>, the<em> Wall Street Journal</em>, and CNN among other outlets.</p>   
   <p>But <em>Post </em>Publisher and Chief Executive Will Lewis celebrated the change in direction on Wednesday. Lewis previously served for six years in the same role at the <em>Journal</em>, which is owned by Trump ally and conservative media magnate Rupert Murdoch. He has advocated for a similar approach at the <em>Post</em>. </p>   <p>Bezos hired Lewis, in significant part, due to his belief the British journalist could build better bridges to Trump and to conservatives. As well as serving Murdoch as an executive for a decade, Lewis was previously editor of the conservative <em>Telegraph </em>in the U.K. and later served as a consultant for Tory Prime Minister Boris Johnson.  </p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5309725-104" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>"I am very excited about this new clarity and transparency, and cannot wait to see it brought to life in our opinion section. Every Day," Lewis said in a note to staff. "This is not about siding with any political party. This is about being crystal clear about what we stand for as a newspaper. Doing this is a critical part of serving as a premier news publication across America and for all Americans."</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>