<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 10:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Generate impressive-looking terminal output, look busy when stakeholders walk by (302 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder</link>
            <guid>43376824</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 03:45:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder">https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43376824">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">rust-stakeholder</h2><a id="user-content-rust-stakeholder" aria-label="Permalink: rust-stakeholder" href="#rust-stakeholder"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/928b7efc3d1b0e9e30663663cfacfb717a77c7c0df15609127fd24ffeaa6290f/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f6361726565722d73617665642d73756363657373"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/928b7efc3d1b0e9e30663663cfacfb717a77c7c0df15609127fd24ffeaa6290f/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f6361726565722d73617665642d73756363657373" alt="Career Status" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/career-saved-success"></a> <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f9a73e8084b12756c8e993885fb4ff3e247543ae2e838cb3228c375dc86aabb7/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f7374616b65686f6c646572732d696d707265737365642d79656c6c6f77"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f9a73e8084b12756c8e993885fb4ff3e247543ae2e838cb3228c375dc86aabb7/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f7374616b65686f6c646572732d696d707265737365642d79656c6c6f77" alt="Stakeholders" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/stakeholders-impressed-yellow"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder/blob/master/assets/demo.gif"><img src="https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder/raw/master/assets/demo.gif" alt="til" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Become an irreplaceable 10x developer in 30 seconds flat</h2><a id="user-content-become-an-irreplaceable-10x-developer-in-30-seconds-flat" aria-label="Permalink: Become an irreplaceable 10x developer in 30 seconds flat" href="#become-an-irreplaceable-10x-developer-in-30-seconds-flat"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Why learn actual skills when you can just <em>look</em> impressive instead?</p>
<p dir="auto">Introducing <strong>rust-stakeholder</strong> - a CLI tool that generates absolutely meaningless but impressive-looking terminal output to convince everyone you're a coding genius without writing a single line of useful code.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">"After using rust-stakeholder, my boss stopped asking about my deadlines and started asking for my insights during board meetings." - Developer who still hasn't completed their tickets from last sprint</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Remember, it's not about your actual contribution to the codebase, it's about how complicated your terminal looks when the VP of Engineering walks by. Nothing says "I'm vital to this company" like 15 progress bars, cryptic error messages you seem unfazed by, and technical jargon nobody understands.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features that add zero value but look incredibly important</h2><a id="user-content-features-that-add-zero-value-but-look-incredibly-important" aria-label="Permalink: Features that add zero value but look incredibly important" href="#features-that-add-zero-value-but-look-incredibly-important"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>🖥️ <strong>Dazzling Development Simulations</strong>: Make it look like you're solving CERN-level computing problems when you're actually just refreshing Reddit</li>
<li>🧠 <strong>Meaningless Jargon Generator</strong>: Impress with phrases like "Implemented non-euclidean topology optimization for multi-dimensional data representation" (no, it doesn't mean anything)</li>
<li>📊 <strong>Convincing Progress Bars</strong>: Nothing says "I'm working" like a progress bar slowly advancing while you're in the break room</li>
<li>🌐 <strong>Fake Network Activity</strong>: Simulate mission-critical API requests that are actually just your computer talking to itself</li>
<li>🚨 <strong>Artificial Crisis Mode</strong>: Generate realistic-looking alerts so people think you're heroically averting disasters</li>
<li>👥 <strong>Imaginary Team Activity</strong>: Pretend your invisible friends are sending you important pull requests</li>
<li>🎮 <strong>Domain Chameleon</strong>: Switch between backend, frontend, blockchain and 7 other domains faster than you can say "full-stack developer"</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo install --git https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder.git"><pre><code>cargo install --git https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder.git
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or build from source (warning: might involve actual programming):</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder.git
cd rust-stakeholder
cargo build --release # Look at you doing real developer things!"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/giacomo-b/rust-stakeholder.git
cd rust-stakeholder
cargo build --release # Look at you doing real developer things!
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Docker</h2><a id="user-content-docker" aria-label="Permalink: Docker" href="#docker"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Build image</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="docker build -t rust-stakeholder ."><pre>docker build -t rust-stakeholder <span>.</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Usage</p>
<p dir="auto">Basic usage:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="docker run -t --rm rust-stakeholder"><pre><code>docker run -t --rm rust-stakeholder
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">All commands below can be used through:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="docker run -t --rm rust-stakeholder [arguments]"><pre>docker run -t --rm rust-stakeholder [arguments]</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage for career advancement</h2><a id="user-content-usage-for-career-advancement" aria-label="Permalink: Usage for career advancement" href="#usage-for-career-advancement"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Basic usage (for entry-level imposters):</p>

<p dir="auto">Advanced usage (for senior imposters):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Impress the blockchain VC investors
rust-stakeholder --dev-type blockchain --jargon extreme --alerts

# Look busy during performance review season
rust-stakeholder --complexity extreme --team --duration 1800

# Convince everyone you're a 10x game developer
rust-stakeholder --dev-type game-development --framework &quot;Custom Engine&quot; --jargon high

# For the data science frauds
rust-stakeholder --dev-type data-science --jargon extreme --project &quot;Neural-Quantum-Blockchain-AI&quot;

# Emergency mode: Your project is due tomorrow and you haven't started
rust-stakeholder --dev-type fullstack --complexity extreme --alerts --team"><pre><span><span>#</span> Impress the blockchain VC investors</span>
rust-stakeholder --dev-type blockchain --jargon extreme --alerts

<span><span>#</span> Look busy during performance review season</span>
rust-stakeholder --complexity extreme --team --duration 1800

<span><span>#</span> Convince everyone you're a 10x game developer</span>
rust-stakeholder --dev-type game-development --framework <span><span>"</span>Custom Engine<span>"</span></span> --jargon high

<span><span>#</span> For the data science frauds</span>
rust-stakeholder --dev-type data-science --jargon extreme --project <span><span>"</span>Neural-Quantum-Blockchain-AI<span>"</span></span>

<span><span>#</span> Emergency mode: Your project is due tomorrow and you haven't started</span>
rust-stakeholder --dev-type fullstack --complexity extreme --alerts --team</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Career benefits</h2><a id="user-content-career-benefits" aria-label="Permalink: Career benefits" href="#career-benefits"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Promotion Fast-Track</strong>: Skip the tedious "delivering value" step entirely</li>
<li><strong>Meeting Domination</strong>: Let it run in the background during Zoom calls to seem busy</li>
<li><strong>Deadline Extensions</strong>: "Sorry, still resolving those critical system alerts"</li>
<li><strong>Salary Negotiation Tool</strong>: Just leave it running during your performance review</li>
<li><strong>Job Security</strong>: Become the only person who seems to understand your fictional systems</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Testimonials</h2><a id="user-content-testimonials" aria-label="Permalink: Testimonials" href="#testimonials"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">"I left rust-stakeholder running over the weekend. When I came back on Monday, I had been promoted to Principal Engineer." - Anonymous</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">"My manager doesn't know what I do, and thanks to rust-stakeholder, neither do I." - Satisfied User</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">"Since installing rust-stakeholder, my colleagues have stopped asking me for help because my work 'looks too advanced'." - Senior Imposter Engineer</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tests? What tests?</h2><a id="user-content-tests-what-tests" aria-label="Permalink: Tests? What tests?" href="#tests-what-tests"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Currently, this package has the same amount of test coverage as your excuses for missing deadlines - absolutely none.</p>
<p dir="auto">Much like your actual development skills while using this tool, tests are purely theoretical at this point. But, if you're feeling particularly productive between fake terminal sessions, consider adding some!</p>
<p dir="auto">After all, nothing says "I'm a serious developer with impostor syndrome" like meticulously testing a package designed to help you fake being a developer. It's beautifully recursive.</p>
<p dir="auto">Remember: Red, Green, Refactor...</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Contributing? That would involve actual coding. But if you insist:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Fork the repo (whatever that means)</li>
<li>Add more useless but impressive-looking output</li>
<li>Submit a PR and pretend you understand the codebase</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Disclaimer</h2><a id="user-content-disclaimer" aria-label="Permalink: Disclaimer" href="#disclaimer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">rust-stakeholder is satire. If your entire technical reputation is built on running a fake terminal program, I am not responsible for the inevitable moment when someone asks you to actually, you know, code something.</p>
<p dir="auto">I am also not responsible if you accidentally impress your way into a position you're completely unqualified for. Though if that happens, congratulations on your new career in management.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cloudflare asks browser devs to sign insane NDAs before fixing browser blocking (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://forum.palemoon.org/viewtopic.php?t=32127</link>
            <guid>43376064</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:19:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://forum.palemoon.org/viewtopic.php?t=32127">https://forum.palemoon.org/viewtopic.php?t=32127</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43376064">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Since this seems to be an on-going problem at this time, this topic aims to provide a summary and "current status" regarding CloudFlare and its promise they "aren't in the business of claiming any browser is more legitimate than another" handling of their Captcha/turnstile pages.</p><p>

<span>Start of the issue</span></p><p>

On Jan 31<sup>st</sup>, users reported that, similar to an occurrence in 2022, CloudFlare's captcha/"i'm under attack" mode had started failing and looping instead of passing and letting browser users through. It soon became clear that this time, any UXP browser wasn't the only being denied access to the sites being "protected" by CloudFlare. Even Firefox ESR 115 was affected.<br>
The community was quick to respond, opening a CloudFlare community thread explaining the problem (which is the only communications channel available to end users, see below) and reporting the issue. <br>
Assuming Mozilla applied corporate pressure for Firefox ESR, CloudFlare changed its captcha scripting soon after which, in turn, exposed a crash issue in UXP by triggering a situation that was not initially accounted for in JavaScript and would not normally occur. Despite the crashes, CloudFlare did not respond to reports about it, effectively causing DoS for all UXP browser users. The crash was solved with an accelerated release of Pale Moon 33.6.0.<br>
Shortly after this, CloudFlare made another change which, this time, caused a different kind of denial of service by triggering script hang/out-of-memory issues through what seems to be <span><em>deliberate</em></span> behaviour when the script does not pass a collection of Web API checks (since the same behaviour was observed on their "officially supported browsers" as well if the user-agent was spoofed to Pale Moon!). The worst symptoms were mitigated with an out-of-band release of Pale moon 33.6.0.1, which still suffers from the script hang but can recover after the script termination watchdog kicks in.</p><p>

<span>Limited communication channels available and being ghosted</span></p><p>

CloudFlare has extremely limited communication channels available. End users can only post in the self-help "community", webmasters/clients can only get direct communication with CloudFlare by being on one of the higher tier CloudFlare subscriptions, and third party software vendors (like myself) have no direct channel of communication with CloudFlare at all, despite being directly affected by their hold on many of the Internet's services/availability.<br>
Even more so, attempting to contect them through what channels are available resulted in me being ghosted. A request for contact and opening a dialogue for the on-going issues was opened on Feb 13th 2025, nearly 2 weeks ago, with so far 0 response.
</p><blockquote><p><cite>notifications@cloudflare.com wrote:</cite>Your request (01388216) has been submitted, and we will be contacting you soon.</p></blockquote>

<p><span>Status</span></p><p>

Our current status is and remains that any and all websites that are behind a CloudFlare captcha or having activated their "I'm under attack" mode/turnstile pages, are unreachable from Pale Moon and other browsers. The issue in 2022 lasted approximately 2 weeks. This time we're left dead i the water for nearly a month as of the time of writing, with no view on any of this being resolved, no information from CloudFlare, no official statements (other than their short list of commercial browsers listed on their site that they "support"), and a clear and present discrimination against independent, Open Source projects like ours.<br>
Consequentially, our project is currently losing daily active users, and we're being damaged with our traffic-based income being undermined as a result. The longer this lasts, the greater the damage is. Unfortunately my options are limited.<br>
There are grounds for legal action as a last resort, but international anti-trust litigation is difficult and will likely take the better part of a decade to be resolved if I go by the US legal system.</p></div><p>"The world will not be destroyed by those who do evil, but by those who watch them without doing anything." - <em>Albert Einstein</em><br>
"Seek wisdom, not knowledge. Knowledge is of the past; wisdom is of the future." -- <em>Native American proverb</em><br>
"Linux makes everything difficult." -- <em>Lyceus Anubite</em></p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple's long-lost hidden recovery partition from 1994 has been found (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2025/03/apples-long-lost-hidden-recovery-partition-from-1994-has-been-found/</link>
            <guid>43376033</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Mar 2025 00:07:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2025/03/apples-long-lost-hidden-recovery-partition-from-1994-has-been-found/">https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2025/03/apples-long-lost-hidden-recovery-partition-from-1994-has-been-found/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43376033">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				
<p>In my <a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2025/03/the-gooey-rubber-thats-slowly-ruining-old-hard-drives/" data-type="post" data-id="10245" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">last post about hard drives that go bad over time</a>, I hinted at having rescued a lost piece of obscure Apple software history from an old 160 MB Conner hard drive that had its head stuck in the parked position. This post is going to be all about it. It’s the tale of a tad bit of an obsession, what felt like a hopeless search, and how persistence eventually paid off. There’s still an unsolved mystery too, so I’m hoping others will see this and help to fill in the blanks!</p>



<p>This whole saga starts with a <a href="https://www.journaldulapin.com/2022/01/04/performa-550/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">very interesting blog post written by Pierre Dandumont in 2022</a>. Pierre’s (excellent) blog is in French — Google does a good job of translating it for me. He found a quote in a book referring to special functionality bundled with Apple’s Macintosh Performa 550 computer:</p>



<blockquote>
<p><strong>The LC 550’s Secret Partition</strong></p>



<p>If Apple’s programmers, in creating the Performa series, were aiming to make idiot-proof computers, they were serious about it. The Performa 550 is an amazing case in point. When you run the included Apple Backup program (see Chapter 15), you get a little surprise that you didn’t count on: a <em>hidden partition</em> on your hard drive!</p>



<p>This invisible chunk of hard drive space contains a miniature, invisible System Folder. Apple’s internal memo explains it this way:</p>



<p>“When a system problem (one that prevents the Performa from booting) is detected, a [dialog box] informs the user of a system problem. The user can choose to fix the problem manually or to reinstall software from the backup partition’s Mini System Folder.”</p>



<p>If you choose to reinstall your System software, you get the wristwatch cursor for a moment while the miniature System Folder is silently copied to your main hard-drive partition. The Performa restarts from the restored hard drive, and the invisible system partition disappears once again.</p>



<p>We got a Performa team member to admit that this kind of sneaky save-the-users-from-themselves approach may well be adopted in other Performa models.</p>



<p>Who knows what goodness lurks in the hearts of men?</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Cool! Although I have owned my own copy of this book for decades, I had no recollection of ever reading this little blurb. The book, if you’re curious, is <a href="https://apple.fandom.com/wiki/Macworld_Mac_Secrets" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Macworld Mac Secrets</a> by David Pogue and Joseph Schorr. I found this whole functionality very intriguing, particularly because I had what felt like a very personal connection to it: the very first Mac that my family had when I was growing up was a Performa 550. I don’t think I have any pictures from back then, but in the meantime I’ve acquired one that looks exactly identical, so here’s a (slightly blurry) view of the type of machine I’m talking about in this post:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="837" height="1024" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810-837x1024.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810-837x1024.jpg 837w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810-245x300.jpg 245w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810-768x939.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810-1256x1536.jpg 1256w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4372-e1741235973810.jpg 1357w" sizes="(max-width: 837px) 100vw, 837px"></a></figure>



<p>I know that many people think the LC/Performa 5xx case style is ugly, but I really like it! I’m definitely biased though.</p>



<p>This is an early model manufactured in September of 1993, which came with a caddy-loading CD-ROM drive (AppleCD 300i). Like other Macs from the same era, <a href="https://tidbits.com/1994/01/31/apple-improves-cd-drive/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">newer versions from 1994 came with a tray-loading drive instead</a> (AppleCD 300i Plus). For comparison, here’s a photo of a late-model Performa 550 with a manufacture date of March 1994 that <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/re4mat.bsky.social" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">re4mat</a> kindly gave me permission to share here:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550-1024x768.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/re4mat_550.jpg 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>Pierre asked me if I had a copy of Apple’s software restoration CD for the Performa 550, and if I knew how to get it working in an emulator in order to try out this special functionality. I <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/macintosh-os-71x" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">pointed him to a download link</a> for the Performa CD for the 500 Series, version 7.1P6:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4374-e1741239294824.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="907" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4374-e1741239294824-1024x907.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4374-e1741239294824-1024x907.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4374-e1741239294824-300x266.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4374-e1741239294824-768x680.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4374-e1741239294824.jpg 1103w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>If you weren’t using multimedia computers in the early 1990s, you might not recognize the weird rectangular container that this CD is enclosed inside of. It’s a CD caddy, and it’s what was used for inserting CDs into computers like the first one pictured above. You would open the caddy by squeezing the top right and bottom right ends toward each other, stick the disc into it, close it, and then push it into the slot in the computer, similarly to how you would insert a floppy disk. I really don’t miss these things one bit!</p>



<p>Back to the story, though. I also <a href="https://www.emaculation.com/forum/viewtopic.php?t=8031" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gave Pierre some tips for using the restore CD in an emulator</a>. Nowadays, my advice is outdated because it’s much easier to use Apple restore CDs in at least one emulator — <a href="https://www.mamedev.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MAME</a> has come a long way in the last few years. He figured out a bunch more stuff on his own after that, including trying it in his own Performa 450 (not 550), but the bottom line was that the recovery partition was nowhere to be found.</p>



<p>Well, sort of. He found that the process of restoring from the CD actually did create a recovery partition. Here’s a screenshot of the partitioning from inside of Apple HD SC Setup while booted from the Performa CD, after formatting the hard drive by clicking the Initialize button in the main window:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-2.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="492" height="300" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-2.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-2.png 492w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-2-300x183.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 492px) 100vw, 492px"></a></figure>



<p>As you can see, there’s a 2,560 KB partition of type Apple_Recovery almost at the end of the drive, just after the main partition named “Hard Disk”. This was promising at first glance, but the partition was empty! Further testing revealed that the custom Performa-specific version of Apple HD SC Setup (7.2.2P6) bundled on the CD was responsible for creating it, but didn’t actually populate it with any data. Apple Backup also didn’t put anything onto the partition, despite what the book said. I even looked through <a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2013/06/legacy-apple-backup-file-format-on-floppy-disks/" data-type="post" data-id="457" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">my past disassemblies of the Apple Backup and Apple Restore code</a> and confirmed that there was nothing related to creating a recovery partition.</p>



<p>The conclusion at the time was that someone needed to get ahold of a Performa 550 that still had its original hard drive and had never been reformatted. That’s where this story sat for 3 years. </p>



<p>A few months ago, I remembered this whole situation and decided that I really wanted to try to find this partition. After all, the clock had always been ticking. The longer we waited, the fewer and fewer original Performa 550s would be out there in the wild. Not to mention that hard drives go bad and people throw them out without knowing that it’s usually possible to recover data from drives of this era. I confirmed all of Pierre’s findings in MAME. I even tried using Apple Backup in case I missed something, but no, it didn’t do anything with the hidden recovery partition. An easy way to look at it is to manually edit the partition table in a hex editor and change the type from Apple_Recovery to Apple_HFS.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="152" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1024x152.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-1024x152.png 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-300x45.png 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4-768x114.png 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-4.png 1247w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>After doing this and booting up, I found another hard drive icon on my desktop called Recovery Volume, but it was empty, just like Pierre said:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3.png 640w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-3-300x225.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a></figure>



<p>Taking it a bit further, I tried recreating the recovery functionality myself. I copied a minimal system folder to the Recovery Volume, and then changed its type back to Apple_Recovery. This made it invisible again. Then I screwed up my main system folder and rebooted. Sure enough, it automatically came up with the Recovery Volume as the main boot volume.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-14.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-14.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-14.png 640w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-14-300x225.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a></figure>



<p>This proved that the mechanism for booting from the recovery partition worked; we were just missing the data that was supposed to be on it. I came to the same conclusion that Pierre had already reached: we needed to find a Performa 550 that had never been reformatted. In the meantime, I spent some time digging into archives of Apple’s old tech notes and found several more references to this functionality.</p>



<p><a href="https://ia600306.us.archive.org/view_archive.php?archive=/21/items/APPLE_TIL_ARTICLES/TIL00001_to_TIL60496.zip&amp;file=TIL11150-System_7-Performa_Versions_Compared_9-95_%28TA28741%29.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">System 7: Performa Versions Compared (9/95)</a> — the first bullet point under System Software Version 7.1P6 refers to this feature:</p>



<blockquote>
<p><em>Backup Partition Software-automatically detects corrupted system folders. When a bad System Folder is detected, the user is given the option to re-load another System Folder into their system.</em></p>
</blockquote>



<p><a href="https://ia600306.us.archive.org/view_archive.php?archive=/21/items/APPLE_TIL_ARTICLES/TIL00001_to_TIL60496.zip&amp;file=TIL14970-Performa_550-Description_of_Backup_Partition_3-94_%28TA31408%29.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Performa 550: Description of Backup Partition (3/94)</a> — this note is clearly the “internal memo” that Macworld Mac Secrets was quoting. Some interesting excerpts from this article:</p>



<blockquote>
<p><em>The Apple Backup application creates a backup recovery partition that allows the Performa to boot even when the System Software on the main hard drive has been corrupted. The partition is invisible to the user.</em></p>
</blockquote>



<blockquote>
<p><em>There is no built-in limit to the number of times the backup partition can be used. However, the partition will be lost if the hard drive is re-formatted. At this time the backup partition is used only on the Performa 550.</em></p>
</blockquote>



<p><a href="https://ia600306.us.archive.org/view_archive.php?archive=/21/items/APPLE_TIL_ARTICLES/TIL00001_to_TIL60496.zip&amp;file=TIL16006-Performa_550-System_Folder_Created_w-Dinosaur_Safari_CD_8-94_%28TA32248%29.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Performa 550: System Folder Created w/ Dinosaur Safari CD (8/94)</a> — not that I needed any more proof of the recovery partition’s existence at this point, but I got a kick out of this one. It talks about how launching an educational game about dinosaurs accidentally caused the system to go into recovery mode. It provided a little more info about what would happen when the recovery dialog popped up:</p>



<blockquote>
<p><em>When I launch the Dinosaur Safari CD from Creative Multimedia, a dialog box appears telling me that my Performa computer is having trouble starting up. I only have two options Shutdown or Continue? Why?</em></p>
</blockquote>



<p>After reading these articles, I was very convinced that the recovery partition was a real thing that existed, but I was also pretty confident that Apple Backup wasn’t responsible for creating it, despite Apple claiming otherwise. I had already seen that the special build of Apple HD SC Setup was what actually created it, and plus, like I said earlier, I had looked closely into a disassembly of the version of Apple Backup supplied with the Performa 500 series restore CD. There was nothing that copied any files to another partition on the hard drive, at least not that I could see.</p>



<p>Really, the most important thing I gained from this exercise was that the second tech note confirmed the need to find a Performa 550 that had never been reformatted. Also, if the first tech note was to be believed, it needed to have come with System 7.1P6. This could narrow the search even further — <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.mac.system/c/Wj1dL2xW3XQ/m/rt7YC4t-YzsJ" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">I know for a fact that earlier Performa 550 models came with 7.1P5</a>, including my childhood one. The same tech note also pointed out that 7.1P6 was the first version to support the “AppleCD 300+”, which is referring to the tray-loading CD-ROM drive. Based on this information, it’s reasonable to deduce that all Performa 550s with a tray-loading CD-ROM drive would probably have originally come with at least System 7.1P6.</p>



<p>There was only one thing left to try at this point: asking the Internet for help. I asked people everywhere I could think of: <a href="https://tinkerdifferent.com/threads/performa-550-unpreserved-recovery-partition.4048/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tinker Different</a>, <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/performa-550-and-recovery-partition.39815/#post-551319" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">68kMLA</a> (where <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/performa-550-and-recovery-partition.39815/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pierre had already asked</a>), and <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/VintageApple/comments/1i75ns6/anybody_have_a_performa_550_that_has_never_been/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">various</a> social media <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/downtowndougbrown.com/post/3lconemblks2q" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">sites</a>. I searched Reddit and found people who had posted in the past about having a 550, asking if they still had the hard drive. I think I scared some of them — at least one person deleted their post after I asked! To be honest, I can’t blame them. I can imagine how freaky it would be to hear from someone begging to look at my hard drive’s contents. I’m sure some people might think of it as crossing a line, but it’s not as crazy of an ask if it’s a machine they’ve received second-hand from someone else. Plus, I was very clear about exactly what I was looking for (and why).</p>



<p>I asked a seller of a Performa 550 that had been sitting on eBay for a long time if they would be willing to sell me the hard drive separately. They weren’t interested. I even bought some random hard drives on eBay that definitely went with a 5xx-style case. These were easy to identify because this case style uses a unique adapter for plugging the drive into the chassis wiring harness when you slide it into place.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839-1024x768.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839-300x225.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839-768x576.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_3839.jpg 2000w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>What do I have to show for all of these eBay purchases? Well, after dumping them all with my <a href="https://zuluscsi.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ZuluSCSI</a> in initiator mode, I can say that the one pictured above came from a Macintosh TV. I also found another one from an LC 575. Lastly, I bought yet another drive that the seller said came from a Performa 577. The Performa 577 one was funny — it had all the Mac mounting hardware on it, but when I dumped it, it turned out to be from an Atari TT or Falcon (not sure which). I’d love to hear the story of how it ended up with an LC 5xx drive sled and adapter on it! Needless to say, none of them had the elusive recovery partition. One particularly friendly eBay seller was even nice enough to show me a preview of a drive’s contents in HFSExplorer, which helped me determine that it wasn’t from a Performa.</p>



<p>I almost began questioning my sanity at one point during this search. Multiple people initially told me that they thought I was confused about this whole thing. I pointed them toward Apple’s tech notes describing it. Were Pierre and I imagining this whole thing? Were Apple’s tech notes all a lie?</p>



<p>The thing is, this whole functionality was super obscure. It’s understandable that people weren’t familiar with it. Apple publicly stated it was only included with this one specific Performa model. Their own documentation also said that it would be lost if you reformatted the hard drive. It was hiding in the background, so nobody really knew it was there, let alone thought about saving it. Also, I can say that the first thing a lot of people do when they obtain a classic computer is erase it in order to restore it to the factory state. Little did anyone know, if they reformatted the hard drive on a Performa 550, they could have been wiping out rare data that hadn’t been preserved!</p>



<p>Someone who saw my post on Reddit mentioned that they had a Performa 550 and would check it out. It was a newer tray-loading model with a January 1994 manufacture date. Unfortunately, the Conner hard drive inside of it wouldn’t cooperate, and plus this person didn’t have anything capable of dumping the contents. Luckily for me though, they were totally comfortable with letting me borrow the drive and try to recover the data from it.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="221" height="300" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294-221x300.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294-221x300.jpg 221w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294-755x1024.jpg 755w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294-768x1042.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294-1132x1536.jpg 1132w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/img_4215-e1741321686294.jpg 1310w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 221px) 100vw, 221px"></a></figure>



<p>To tie everything together, we have now reached the point in this story that I covered in <a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2025/03/the-gooey-rubber-thats-slowly-ruining-old-hard-drives/" data-type="post" data-id="10245" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">my last post about hard drives with stuck heads</a>. As I mentioned in that blog, I could not get this drive to do anything. It would just spin up, sit there for a while, spin down, and then make an annoying buzzing sound for a while, repeating that whole process over and over again.</p>



<p>I tried all kinds of things. I nudged the head while the platters were spinning, inspected it with my thermal camera to see if any components were getting hot, and tried it at different temperatures — cold shortly after it arrived, and at room temperature later. The only thing I noticed was that when it was making the buzzing sound, one of the IRFD123 MOSFETs would get much hotter than normal: up near 100 degrees Celsius.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="320" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5.png 240w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-5-225x300.png 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 240px) 100vw, 240px"></a></figure>



<p>I wasn’t really sure what to do with this information though. It just seemed wrong that the head wasn’t moving at all. That’s when I finally decided to inspect everything further inside the drive and noticed the head stack seemed like it was sticking to a rubber/plastic looking piece. The Kapton tape trick I figured out and showed off in the last post finally allowed me to dump the drive contents. If you didn’t catch it last time, here’s a video showing how it was stuck, along with a successful dump with the help of the tape:</p>



<figure><p>
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Conner CP30175E hard drive doesn't stay spun up - fix" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bkI-taoX3sI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p></figure>



<p>As soon as the drive imaging process completed, I powered everything off and anxiously opened the hard drive image file with my favorite hex editor (<a href="https://mh-nexus.de/en/hxd/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">HxD</a>):</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="627" height="214" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6.png 627w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-6-300x102.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 627px) 100vw, 627px"></a></figure>



<p>Boom! This drive had a recovery partition on it! Now, that didn’t necessarily mean anything. After all, I had already seen an empty partition created by Apple HD SC Setup on the Performa CD. Still, though, it was definitely promising. Here’s an interpretation of the data at the beginning of the entry in the partition table:</p>



<p>50 4D = PM = Signature<br>00 00 = Padding<br>00 00 00 05 = 5 total partitions on the drive<br>00 04 E2 60 = starting physical block of the partition (0x4E260 blocks = 0x9C4C000 bytes)<br>00 00 14 00 = size of partition in blocks (0x1400 blocks = 0x280000 bytes = 2560 kilobytes)<br>name = MacOS<br>type = Apple_Recovery</p>



<p>Also, just like in the partition table created by the Performa CD that I had inspected earlier, there were four bytes “msjy” at an offset of 0x9C bytes into the partition table entry. No other partitions had any data at 0x9C. I wonder if these are a couple of developers’ initials hiding in there or something? Is it an acronym? “Make Steve Jobs Yodel”? I even asked ChatGPT to come up with a playful interpretation in the context of Macs in the mid-1990s. It suggested “My System Jammed Yesterday”, explaining it as a playful nod to the “chaotic charm” of the era’s extension conflicts and Sad Mac screens. I didn’t even mention anything about it involving OS recovery. Tell me how you really feel about old Macs, ChatGPT!</p>



<p>Knowing that the partition was there, the next step was to look near the end of the dumped drive image in HxD. If the partition had any actual data stored, it would be very obvious because starting at 0x9C4C000 in the file, there would be actual data and not just a bunch of zeros.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="610" height="454" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7.png 610w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-7-300x223.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 610px) 100vw, 610px"></a></figure>



<p>This is where I started to actually get excited. The partition contained boot blocks! This was obvious because of the starting signature of LK and all of the various system file names plainly visible. On the other hand, the recovery partition created by the Performa CD during testing had zeros at this location — no boot blocks.</p>



<p>These boot blocks are identical to the main partition’s boot blocks, except for one very important difference: at 0x1A, the Pascal string containing the Finder name is “recovery” instead of “Finder” like you’d normally see. This means that if you boot from this partition, it will load a program named recovery instead of the usual Finder app you’d expect on most Mac OS installs.</p>



<p>This was definitely something special that the restore CD was not capable of recreating. As I scrolled further down through the partition, it quickly became obvious that it actually had some files!</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="605" height="466" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8.png 605w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-8-300x231.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 605px) 100vw, 605px"></a></figure>



<p>Okay, now I was totally stoked! I booted up a copy of the imaged drive in MAME and immediately noticed that there was evidence that the recovery partition had definitely activated itself on this machine in the past: there was a folder named <em>Mini System Folder</em> on the desktop with a creation date in 2004, and the trash contained an app called Read Me Mini System Folder with the exact same date.</p>



<p>I wanted to experience the automatic OS recovery process for myself without any customizations from the original owner of the machine this hard drive came from, so I used HxD to copy the entire 2,560 KB recovery partition onto the fresh hard drive image I had created by restoring from the Performa CD. This was easy because the Performa version of Apple HD SC Setup had created an empty recovery partition with the exact same size. Then I booted it up in MAME and dragged the System file out of my System Folder in order to intentionally mess it up. I had to turn off System Folder Protection in the Performa control panel first:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-15.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="272" height="208" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-15.png" alt=""></a></figure>



<p>This is the classic kind of mistake that would have normally left you with an unbootable system showing a floppy disk icon with a flashing question mark. Would Apple’s automatic Performa OS recovery save me from myself? I rebooted to see what would happen. Instead of seeing a flashing question mark, I saw a Happy Mac very briefly before the system rebooted itself again. Then another Happy Mac showed up, and this time, it looked like a normal boot, except no extension icons showed up at the bottom of the screen. It was definitely booting from the recovery partition. Eventually, I was greeted with this screen:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-16.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-16.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-16.png 640w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-16-300x225.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a></figure>



<p>Hooray! This was exactly the dialog box that Macworld Mac Secrets and Apple’s tech note had referred to. The recovery partition had been successfully rescued!</p>



<p>Let’s walk through the rest of this feature. If you click Shut Down, obviously the machine turns itself off. But when it boots back up, the recovery partition doesn’t automatically kick in anymore. So you’re on your own to fix the problem by booting from the Performa CD or the Utilities floppy disk.</p>



<p>On the other hand, clicking OK does exactly what the tech note describes. You get the wristwatch cursor for a few seconds, the system reboots, and then you are greeted with this amazing screen, complete with an ugly yellow desktop pattern. Shall we call it the yellow screen of shame? Notice that the Mini System Folder on the desktop is the active System Folder, because it has the special icon.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22.png 640w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22-300x225.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a></figure>



<p>Here are the rest of the pages in this Read Me Mini System Folder app:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-19.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="493" height="306" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-19.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-19.png 493w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-19-300x186.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 493px) 100vw, 493px"></a></figure>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-20.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="493" height="306" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-20.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-20.png 493w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-20-300x186.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 493px) 100vw, 493px"></a></figure>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-21.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="493" height="306" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-21.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-21.png 493w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-21-300x186.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 493px) 100vw, 493px"></a></figure>



<p>Aha! So it’s not entirely automatic, since you still have to manually drag the System, Finder, and System Enablers from the Mini System Folder back to your original System Folder. Still though, it’s a very handy solution that gives you a bootable machine when something goes wrong with your OS.</p>



<p>If you just ignore these instructions and keep using the computer, you will be nagged with this Read Me on every boot because it lives inside the Startup Items folder of the Mini System Folder. The Read Me also appears on your desktop, but for some reason it doesn’t show up until you open the Hard Disk icon.</p>



<p>Let’s take a deeper look at how it all works by temporarily changing the partition type to Apple_HFS instead of Apple_Recovery and booting up again, so we can inspect the files. After a quick automatic rebuild of the desktop file, the Recovery Volume appears, with actual contents this time!</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-9.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="407" height="209" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-9.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-9.png 407w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-9-300x154.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px"></a></figure>



<p>Inside of the System Folder, there are definitely some interesting things. As expected based on the earlier analysis of the boot blocks, there is an app named “recovery” that contains all of the interesting stuff. The icons are kind of arranged willy-nilly in here.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-10.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="407" height="209" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-10.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-10.png 407w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-10-300x154.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px"></a></figure>



<p>The creator code of the recovery app is msjy — the exact same magic value we saw in the partition table entry.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-28.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="452" height="302" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-28.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-28.png 452w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-28-300x200.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 452px) 100vw, 452px"></a></figure>



<p>Scrolling further down, there is a System file and various enablers. Everything is marked as being part of System Software v7.1P6.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-11.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="407" height="209" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-11.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-11.png 407w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-11-300x154.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px"></a></figure>



<p>It’s interesting to me that although this recovery partition was only available on the 550, it still has a bunch of enablers for other Performa models: the 45x/46x, 47x/57x, and 600. I guess that’s not too crazy considering all of these exact same enablers are included with a fresh copy of System 7.1P6 installed using the Performa CD.</p>



<p>As a quick detour, System Enabler 316 is an interesting one that is hard to find info about on the Internet. I inspected its ‘gbly’ resource and determined that it’s for the Centris 610, Centris 650, and Quadra 800. It’s an older version of the enabler created before <a href="https://512pixels.net/2021/03/the-sad-story-of-the-centris/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the speed-bumped Quadra 610 and Quadra 650 were a thing</a>. I wonder if there was a plan at some point to have a Performa model based on one of those machines? If I had to guess, maybe it would have been a 68040-based successor to the Performa 600, which uses the same case style as the Centris 650. The Performa 650?</p>



<p>Let’s not get too far off track. Back to the Recovery Volume’s System Folder — as expected, the Startup Items folder contains the Read Me application:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-12.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="407" height="209" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-12.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-12.png 407w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-12-300x154.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 407px) 100vw, 407px"></a></figure>



<p>Everything started to become clear. The recovery app was marked as the startup application instead of the Finder. It displayed the dialog giving the user the option to recover. If they clicked OK, it would copy the entire System Folder from the Recovery Volume, omitting itself, to the Desktop Folder of the main hard drive partition. Then, it would “bless” the newly-copied mini System Folder and reboot.</p>



<p>How did all this stuff get into the partition? Did Apple Backup do it, or was it factory-programmed data? I tried to see if I could deduce anything from the dates of the files. In order to preserve the integrity of all of the displayed dates, I performed this analysis with a read-only copy of the original drive image in order to prevent any modification dates from being updated.</p>



<p>All of the files in the partition have a creation date of March 4, 1994 — over 31 years ago! Most of the files have a matching modification date, except for the System suitcase, which was last modified on September 26, 1994. I don’t know exactly what this all means, considering it came from a machine with a January 1994 manufacture date.</p>



<p>The Recovery Volume itself also has a creation date of March 4th, just five minutes before the creation date of all the files. Interestingly, the modification date of the volume is still shown as March 4th in the Get Info window, even though the System suitcase was modified later in September of that year.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-29.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="245" height="238" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-29.png" alt=""></a></figure>



<p>The Master Directory Block of the Recovery Volume says the modification date (drLsMod) is September 26th, matching when the System file was changed. I’m not sure what causes this discrepancy. I guess the date displayed in the Get Info window isn’t simply the date stored in the Master Directory Block.</p>



<p>Similarly, although the main hard drive partition has a creation date of December 5, 1993 according to the Master Directory Block, the Get Info window says it was created on February 3, 1994. I’m not sure which one is more accurate. Either way, it’s pretty clear this drive had not been reformatted. I did find it curious that the recovery partition was created over a month later, though. When you reformat a hard drive using the special version of Apple HD SC Setup on the Performa CD, the recovery partition ends up with a creation date about a minute after the main partition.</p>



<p>The Finder and System Enablers in the recovery partition are identical to the same stock files from a 7.1P6 restore. The only difference I could find in the System file was that the recovery partition’s version was missing a single At Ease ‘INIT’ resource, but the At Ease Startup extension automatically adds it to the System file after you reboot. This leaves you with a System file totally identical to what is restored from the Performa CD. I find it odd that At Ease was stripped out, but the American Heritage Dictionary ‘FKEY’ resource was not.</p>



<p>The best theory that I can come up with is that Apple Backup really was responsible for creating this partition. After all, Apple went out of their way to specifically mention it in their tech note. Maybe March 4th, 1994 was the date when the original owner of the computer backed it up for the first time. September 26th could have been the last time that Apple Backup was run. Perhaps the owner completely uninstalled At Ease from the computer between March and September, so the System file had been changed and the recovery copy needed to be updated accordingly? Unfortunately, most of the Performa-specific software had been deleted from this computer. It was still running System 7.1P6, but Apple Backup was nowhere to be found. So I wasn’t able to confirm whether or not a mysterious, unpreserved newer version of Apple Backup was really responsible for populating the partition.</p>



<p>The other theory floating around in my head is that maybe it came from the factory like this. The March 1994 timeline is consistent with the date of the tech note describing the functionality, so maybe that’s when Apple created it and started bundling it. I don’t know how long the machines sat at Apple’s factory before they were actually sold — does a manufacture date of January 1994 also mean it was shipped to a store in January 1994? Either way, I definitely don’t know how to explain the September 26th, 1994 modification date. Maybe a third-party utility did something to the System file on the secondary partition? The first Apple Backup theory seems like the more likely explanation, especially given that Apple said that’s how it was created.</p>



<p>This whole question is the last piece of the puzzle that hasn’t been solved yet. If anyone else has a Performa 550 and would be willing to dump their hard drive or at least look at Apple Backup, I’d be very interested in finding out A) if it has the recovery partition and B) if there was a special newer version of Apple Backup that didn’t make its way onto the Performa CD. I searched for various strings that show up in the “recovery” and “Read Me Mini System Folder” apps, and they aren’t anywhere on the Performa CD. I guess they could be stored compressed somewhere, but I’m pretty confident based on the actual Apple Backup code that nothing is hiding in there. Here are the various versions (with their exact sizes and dates) of Apple Backup that I have seen on Performa 550 installations. None of these have the recovery partition creation built in:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-31.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="749" height="314" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-31.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-31.png 749w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-31-300x126.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></a></figure>



<p>I also found version 1.3 (June 15, 1994, 163,388 bytes used) by restoring from a Performa 636 restore CD. It, too, does not contain any recovery partition code.</p>



<p>For a demo, I thought it would be fun to replicate the problem that the Apple tech note mentioned about the Dinosaur Safari CD inadvertently activating the recovery partition, so I bought a copy to test it out. To make it even more interesting, I decided to run this test on real hardware. I’m leaning toward believing that a lot of the older caddy-loading models (possibly all of them) didn’t have this recovery partition, so just pretend it’s a newer model that came with System 7.1P6. I copied the recovery partition onto a real Apple-branded IBM 160 MB SCSI hard drive using ZuluSCSI’s USB MSC initiator mode, which allows it to act as a USB-to-SCSI bridge. Sorry about the flickery screen; I couldn’t get my phone camera’s shutter speed to sync up perfectly with the display’s refresh rate.</p>



<figure><p>
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Macintosh Performa 550 Dinosaur Safari bug" width="500" height="375" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/A2qp7W5zarI?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p></figure>



<p>Sure enough, when I opened the game from the CD, the computer did exactly what Apple’s tech note said it would do. The workaround of copying the application to my hard drive worked just fine. If it’s not obvious, I sped up the process of copying it to the hard drive — it took a while! It might be interesting someday to look into why this game accidentally activated the OS recovery, but this blog is already getting way too long!</p>



<p>I want to talk a little more about the yellow screen of shame. When I first saw it, I wasn’t entirely sure if it was really part of the recovery functionality or if the original owner just had terrible taste.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22.png 640w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-22-300x225.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px"></a></figure>



<p>Digging deeper, I found three clues that all made it clear it was an intentional choice by Apple to really make it obvious that something was wrong. First, the yellow pattern is stored as a ‘ppat’ resource in the recovery app.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-23.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="405" height="296" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-23.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-23.png 405w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-23-300x219.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 405px) 100vw, 405px"></a></figure>



<p>Second, the System file in the recovery partition has the default blue-gray Performa background shown in the screenshots above. This makes sense, because it’s the pattern that showed up with the dialog about the Performa having trouble starting up.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-24.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="405" height="296" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-24.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-24.png 405w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-24-300x219.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 405px) 100vw, 405px"></a></figure>



<p>And lastly, page 3 of the Read Me app implies that something may have changed your desktop pattern.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-25.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="468" height="51" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-25.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-25.png 468w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-25-300x33.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 468px) 100vw, 468px"></a></figure>



<p>So clearly, the recovery process, by design, sets up the custom yellow background.</p>



<p>Why did I care so much about finding this lost partition? Well, there are a number of reasons. For one, this is exactly the kind of research project that’s perfect for me because I don’t know how to let things go. It’s also something that, quite frankly, needed to be preserved before it became extinct. The most important reason, though, is that this functionality is historically significant and deserves some attention. How many personal computers in 1994 still had the ability to boot after the OS was trashed? Isn’t this an extremely early example of this type of functionality? Did Windows have anything like this prior to Vista? Did the Mac have anything else like this prior to sometime in the OS X era? I would love to hear more comments about what you think on this. I admittedly don’t know a ton about older machines that weren’t Macs.</p>



<p>I’m not saying this feature is perfect. Since we’ve already seen that the Dinosaur Safari CD was able to accidentally activate it, I wouldn’t be surprised if there were other ways to inadvertently cause it to pop up too. It also required manual intervention after the recovery process, which meant that you needed a fair amount of computer knowledge to finish fixing your OS. The average Joe Schmoe would probably have trouble following these directions to fix the System Folder. But still, it leaves you with a bootable system instead of an unusable computer with a flashing question mark. It’s very cool, especially for 1994.</p>



<p>I wonder why Apple didn’t continue down this path with subsequent models? Or even retroactively adding the functionality to earlier ones after a fresh install of a newer OS. I’m not aware of any other Macs that have this partition. It doesn’t depend on any special ROM support or anything like that, at least as far as I can see. I tried out the recovery functionality on several other machines: a IIci, LC, LC 475, and an emulated Performa 600, and it works great on all of them. Heck, it even works on the Classic II/Performa 200!</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-26.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="512" height="342" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-26.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-26.png 512w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-26-300x200.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px"></a></figure>



<p>It kind of looks like the window size of the Read Me app was a calculated decision to ensure it would fit on the 512×342 screen used in black-and-white compact Macs.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-27.png" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="512" height="342" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-27.png" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-27.png 512w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/image-27-300x200.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px"></a></figure>



<p>Thinking about later models, the Performa 630 series used an internal IDE hard drive instead of SCSI, so the custom version of Apple HD SC Setup was no longer used. I wonder if the Performa 57x series had this partition? You’d think they would have had the exact same software bundle as the tray-loading 550 models. If any readers have a Performa 57x machine, I’d greatly appreciate it if you could check!</p>



<p>How did this functionality actually work under the hood? I haven’t gone too deep into the code (maybe it can be a future post), but I have pieced together a few clues. The “msjy” magic number I talked about earlier definitely plays a part in everything. The special Performa version of Apple HD SC Setup also includes a custom version of Apple’s hard disk driver. This driver contains several references to msjy, so I’m pretty sure that’s what it uses to identify the recovery partition.</p>



<p>I also discovered that the 7.1P4 and 7.1P5 Utilities floppy disks, which were bundled with various Performas, have slightly older custom versions of Apple HD SC Setup: 7.2.1P and 7.2.2P respectively. They also create the recovery partition. The interesting thing about these versions is that it appears Apple accidentally forgot to strip out the debug function names, in both the utility itself and the bundled hard disk driver. They didn’t make this mistake in the original non-Performa 7.2.2 version, and they also didn’t make the mistake in the newer 7.2.2P6 version. Anyway, this is kind of cool, because it tells me the names of functions that look for “msjy” at an offset of 0x9C. Function names in that same area of the driver code include: <em>recvrybootable</em>, <em>confirmminsystem</em>, <em>flushrecoveryflag</em>, <em>recoveryvolexists</em>, and <em>setrecoveryflags</em>. So Apple definitely at least sort of released some of the recovery functionality to the public prior to 7.1P6, despite what their own version history says. And the disk driver is definitely involved in it.</p>



<p>Newer versions of Apple’s disk driver no longer contain the magic number, so at some point they must have abandoned this functionality. In my opinion, it’s a real shame that they ditched it — this could have been very useful going forward on all Macs. They could have even expanded on it and automated more of the recovery process. Sure, it used some of your hard drive space, but it could have been a good trade-off for better reliability.</p>



<p>That’s more than enough technical stuff for one post. I am sharing a download link where you can try this functionality out for yourself if you want. After all, the whole reason I did this was for software preservation purposes, so it makes sense to share it with the world. This is a small piece of Apple software history that, to my knowledge, has not been preserved until now. <a href="https://macintoshgarden.org/apps/system-71p6-performa-550-hidden-recovery-partition" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">I uploaded a drive image to the Macintosh Garden.</a> Don’t worry, I didn’t include any of the original owner’s personal data. I started fresh with a blank hard drive image, restored it using the 7.1P6 Performa CD, and then only copied over the restore partition from the dumped hard drive. So this is a factory-fresh Performa 550 7.1P6 install with the recovery partition also present and populated.</p>



<p>The MAME command that I use to boot from this disk image is:</p>



<pre>mame maclc550 -scsi:0 harddisk -harddisk1 Performa550.hda -window -nomaximize -ramsize 32M</pre>



<p>Of course, you can also test it out on a real machine by copying the hard drive image to a <a href="https://zuluscsi.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ZuluSCSI</a> or <a href="https://bluescsi.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">BlueSCSI</a> and naming it something like HD00.hda.</p>



<p>Winding down this super long post now, the main lessons I learned from this research project are:</p>



<ol>
<li>If you get your hands on a vintage computer, strongly consider backing the hard drive up before erasing it. I know it might contain someone’s personal files, so be mindful of that, and of course respect their privacy. But there might still be something hiding in the background that has been lost to time. You never know — it happened here!</li>



<li>The fact that many hard drives go bad as they age might actually be a good thing for software preservation. If a vintage computer’s hard drive has a stuck head that can easily be bypassed, someone might sell it as non-working with data intact, rather than erasing it and selling it as “fully tested and wiped”.</li>



<li>There are some really awesome people out there in the world!</li>
</ol>



<p>Special thanks to <a href="https://www.journaldulapin.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Pierre</a> for discovering that this functionality even existed in the first place, and getting the word out so we could eventually preserve it. I also have to thank David Pogue and Joseph Schorr for writing about it in their book many decades ago. And of course, huge thanks to the amazing person from Reddit, who asked not to be credited, who gave me the opportunity to borrow and repair the drive that ended up containing the lost partition. You’re seriously the best!</p>



<p>I’m going to repeat this again in case anybody has scrolled all the way to the end. There are still missing pieces of knowledge about how exactly this recovery partition would have been originally created. If you happen to have a Performa 550 with its original hard drive and wouldn’t mind checking for the partition and/or a special version of Apple Backup, please let me know! I would be happy to walk anybody through the process of dumping the drive contents. I’ll send you something if you don’t have the equipment needed to dump a hard drive. Even if the machine has been upgraded to System 7.5 or Mac OS 7.6, it’s still fine — everything could very well still be there, lurking in the background.</p>
			  
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Career Advice in 2025 (177 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lethain.com/career-advice-2025/</link>
            <guid>43375923</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 23:41:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lethain.com/career-advice-2025/">https://lethain.com/career-advice-2025/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43375923">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Yesterday, the tj-actions repository, a popular tool used with Github Actions was compromised (for more background read <a href="https://www.stepsecurity.io/blog/harden-runner-detection-tj-actions-changed-files-action-is-compromised">one</a> of these <a href="https://semgrep.dev/blog/2025/popular-github-action-tj-actionschanged-files-is-compromised/">two</a> articles). Watching the infrastructure and security engineering teams at Carta respond, it highlighted to me just how much LLMs can’t meaningfully replace many essential roles of software professionals. However, I’m also reading Jennifer Palkha’s <a href="https://www.recodingamerica.us/">Recoding America</a>, which makes an important point: decision-makers can remain irrational longer than you can remain solvent. (Or, in this context, remain employed.)</p><p>I’ve been thinking about this a lot lately, as I’ve ended up having more “2025 is not much fun”-themed career discussions with prior colleagues navigating the current job market. I’ve tried to pull together my points from those conversations here:</p><ol><li><p>Many people who first entered senior roles in 2010-2020 are finding current roles a lot less fun. There are a number of reasons for this. First, managers were generally evaluated in that period based on their ability to hire, retain and motivate teams. The current market doesn’t value those skills particularly highly, but instead prioritizes a different set of skills: working in the details, pushing pace, and navigating the technology transition to foundational models / LLMs.</p><p>This means many members of the current crop of senior leaders are either worse at the skills they currently need to succeed, or are less motivated by those activities. Either way, they’re having less fun.</p><p>Similarly, the would-be senior leaders from 2010-2020 era who excelled at working in the details, pushing pace and so on, are viewed as stagnate in their careers so are still finding it difficult to move into senior roles. This means that many folks feel like the current market has left them behind. This is, of course, not universal. It is a <em>general</em> experience that <em>many</em> people are having. Many people are not having this experience.</p></li><li><p>The technology transition to Foundational models / LLMs as a core product and development tool is causing many senior leaders’ hard-earned playbooks to be invalidated. Many companies that were stable, durable market leaders are now in tenuous positions because foundational models threaten to erode their advantage. Whether or not their advantage is truly eroded is uncertain, but it is clear that usefully adopting foundational models into a product requires more than simply shoving an OpenAI/Anthropic API call in somewhere.</p><p>Instead, you have to figure out how to design with progressive validation, with critical data validated via human-in-the-loop techniques before it is used in a critical workflow. It also requires designing for a rapidly improving toolkit: many workflows that were laughably bad in 2023 work surprisingly well with the latest reasoning models. Effective product design requires architecting for both massive improvement, and no improvement at all, of models in 2026-2027.</p><p>This is equally true of writing software itself. There’s so much noise about how to write software, and much of it’s clearly propaganda–this blog’s opening anecdote regarding the tj-actions repository prove that expertise remains essential–but parts of it aren’t. I spent a <a href="https://lethain.com/our-own-agents-our-own-tools/">few weeks in the evenings working on a new side project via Cursor in January</a>, and I was surprised at how much my workflow changed even through Cursor itself was far from perfect. Even since then, Claude has advanced from 3.5 to 3.7 with extended thinking. Again, initial application development might easily be radically different in 2027, or it might be largely unchanged after the scaffolding step in complex codebases. (I’m also curious to see if context window limitations drive another flight from monolithic architectures.)</p><p>Sitting out this transition, when we are relearning how to develop software, feels like a high risk proposition. Your well-honed skills in team development are already devalued today relative to three years ago, and now your other skills are at risk of being devalued as well.</p></li><li><p>Valuations and funding are relatively less accessible to non-AI companies than they were three years ago. Certainly elite companies are doing alright, whether or not they have a clear AI angle, but the cutoff for remaining elite has risen. Simultaneously, the public markets are challenged, which means less willingness for both individuals and companies to purchase products, which slows revenue growth, further challenging valuations and funding.</p><p>The consequence of this if you’re at a private, non-AI company, is that you’re likely to hire less, promote less, see less movement in pay bands, and experience a less predictable path to liquidity. It also means fewer open roles at other companies, so there’s more competition when attempting to trade up into a larger, higher compensated role at another company.</p><p>The major exception to this is joining an AI company, but generally those companies are in extremely competitive markets and are priced more appropriately for investors managing a basket of investments than for employees trying to deliver a predictable return. If you join one of these companies today, you’re probably joining a bit late to experience a big pop, your equity might go to zero, and you’ll be working extremely hard for the next five to seven years. This is the classic startup contract, but not necessarily the contract that folks have expected over the past decade as maximum compensation has generally come from joining a later-stage company or member of the Magnificent Seven.</p></li><li><p>As companies respond to the reduced valuations and funding, they are pushing their teams harder to find growth with their existing team. In the right environment, this can be motivating, but people may have opted into to a more relaxed experience that has become markedly less relaxed without their consent.</p></li></ol><p>If you pull all those things together, you’re essentially in a market where <a href="https://lethain.com/forty-year-career/">profit and pace are fixed</a>, and you have to figure out how you personally want to optimize between people, prestige and learning. Whereas a few years ago, I think these variables were much more decoupled, that is not what I hear from folks today, even if their jobs were quite cozy a few years ago.</p><p>Going a bit further, I know folks who are good at their jobs, and have been struggling to find something meaningful for six-plus months. I know folks who are exceptionally strong candidates, who can find reasonably good jobs, but even they are finding that the sorts of jobs they want simply don’t exist right now. I know folks who are strong candidates but with some oddities in their profile, maybe too many short stints, who are now being filtered out because hiring managers need some way to filter through the higher volume of candidates.</p><p>I can’t give advice on what <em>you</em> should do, but if you’re finding this job market difficult, it’s certainly not personal. My sense is that’s basically the experience that everyone is having when searching for new roles right now. If you are in a role today that’s frustrating you, my advice is to try harder than usual to find a way to make it a rewarding experience, even if it’s not perfect. I also wouldn’t personally try to sit this cycle out unless you’re comfortable with a small risk that reentry is quite difficult: I think it’s more likely that the ecosystem is meaningfully different in five years than that it’s largely unchanged.</p><p>Altogether, this hasn’t really been the advice that anyone wanted when they chatted
with me, but it seems to generally have resonated with them as a realistic appraisal
of the current markets. Hopefully there’s something useful for you in here as well.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sign in as anyone: Bypassing SAML SSO authentication with parser differentials (243 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.blog/security/sign-in-as-anyone-bypassing-saml-sso-authentication-with-parser-differentials/</link>
            <guid>43374519</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 19:06:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.blog/security/sign-in-as-anyone-bypassing-saml-sso-authentication-with-parser-differentials/">https://github.blog/security/sign-in-as-anyone-bypassing-saml-sso-authentication-with-parser-differentials/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43374519">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
	
<blockquote><p>Critical authentication bypass vulnerabilities (CVE-2025-25291 + CVE-2025-25292) were discovered in ruby-saml up to version 1.17.0. Attackers who are in possession of a single valid signature that was created with the key used to validate SAML responses or assertions of the targeted organization can use it to construct SAML assertions themselves and are in turn able to log in as any user. In other words, it could be used for an account takeover attack. Users of ruby-saml should update to version 1.18.0. References to libraries making use of ruby-saml (such as omniauth-saml) need also be updated to a version that reference a fixed version of ruby-saml.</p></blockquote>
<p>In this blog post, we detail newly discovered authentication bypass vulnerabilities in the <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml">ruby-saml</a> library used for single sign-on (SSO) via SAML on the service provider (application) side. GitHub doesn’t currently use ruby-saml for authentication, but began evaluating the use of the library with the intention of using an open source library for SAML authentication once more. This library is, however, used in other popular projects and products. We discovered an exploitable instance of this vulnerability in GitLab, and have notified their security team so they can take necessary actions to protect their users against potential attacks.</p>
<p>GitHub previously used the ruby-saml library up to 2014, but moved to our own SAML implementation due to missing features in ruby-saml at that time. Following bug bounty reports around vulnerabilities in our own implementation (such as <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/enterprise-server@3.13/admin/release-notes#3.13.5-security-fixes">CVE-2024-9487</a>, related to encrypted assertions), GitHub recently decided to explore the use of ruby-saml again. Then in October 2024, a blockbuster vulnerability dropped: an <a href="https://github.com/advisories/GHSA-jw9c-mfg7-9rx2">authentication bypass</a> in ruby-saml (CVE-2024-45409) by <a href="https://hackerone.com/ahacker1">ahacker1</a>. With tangible evidence of exploitable attack surface, GitHub’s switch to ruby-saml had to be evaluated more thoroughly now. As such, GitHub started a <a href="https://hackerone.com/github">private bug bounty engagement</a> to evaluate the security of the ruby-saml library. We gave selected bug bounty researchers access to GitHub test environments using ruby-saml for SAML authentication. In tandem, the GitHub Security Lab also reviewed the attack surface of the ruby-saml library.</p>
<p>As is not uncommon when multiple researchers are looking at the same code, both ahacker1, a participant in the <a href="https://hackerone.com/github">GitHub bug bounty program</a>, and I noticed the same thing during code review: ruby-saml was using two different XML parsers during the code path of signature verification. Namely, REXML and Nokogiri. While REXML is an XML parser implemented in pure Ruby, Nokogiri provides an easy-to-use wrapper API around different libraries like libxml2, libgumbo and Xerces (used for JRuby). Nokogiri supports parsing of XML and HTML. It looks like Nokogiri was added to ruby-saml to support <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonical_XML">canonicalization</a> and potentially other things REXML didn’t support at that time.</p>
<p>We both inspected the same code path in the <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L268"><code>validate_signature</code></a> of <code>xml_security.rb</code> and found that the signature element to be verified is first read via REXML, and then also with Nokogiri’s XML parser. So, if REXML and Nokogiri could be tricked into retrieving different signature elements for the same XPath query it might be possible to trick ruby-saml into verifying the wrong signature. It looked like there could be a potential authentication bypass due to a <strong>parser differential</strong>!</p>
<p>The reality was actually more complicated than this.</p>

<p>Roughly speaking, four stages were involved in the discovery of this authentication bypass:</p>
<ol>
<li>Discovering that two different XML parsers are used during code review.  </li>
<li>Establishing if and how a parser differential could be exploited.  </li>
<li>Finding an actual parser differential for the parsers in use.  </li>
<li>Leveraging the parser differential to create a full-blown exploit.</li>
</ol>
<p>To prove the security impact of this vulnerability, it was necessary to complete all four stages and create a full-blown authentication bypass exploit.</p>
<h2 id="quick-recap-how-saml-responses-are-validated">Quick recap: how SAML responses are validated<a href="#quick-recap-how-saml-responses-are-validated" aria-label="Quick recap: how SAML responses are validated"></a></h2>
<p>Security assertion markup language (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Security_Assertion_Markup_Language">SAML</a>) responses are used to transport information about a signed-in user from the identity provider (IdP) to the service provider (SP) in XML format. Often the only important information transported is a username or an email address. When the HTTP POST binding is used, the SAML response travels from the IdP to the SP via the browser of the end user. This makes it obvious why there has to be some sort of signature verification in play to prevent the user from tampering with the message.</p>
<p>Let’s have a quick look at what a simplified SAML response looks like:<br>
<img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?resize=1024%2C355" alt="A diagram depicting a simplified SAML response on the left and the verification of the digest and the signature on the right." width="1024" height="355" srcset="https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?w=2632 2632w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?w=300 300w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?w=768 768w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?w=1024 1024w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?w=1536 1536w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/goodassertion7_2.png?w=2048 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></p>
<p><em>Note: in the response above the XML namespaces were removed for better readability.</em></p>
<p>As you might have noticed: the main part of a simple SAML response is its assertion element (A), whereas the main information contained in the assertion is the information contained in the <code>Subject</code> element (B) (here the NameID containing the username: admin). A real assertion typically contains more information (e.g. <code>NotBefore</code> and <code>NotOnOrAfter</code> dates as part of a <code>Conditions</code> element.)</p>
<p>Normally, the <code>Assertion</code> (A) (without the whole <code>Signature</code> part) is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonical_XML">canonicalized</a> and then compared against the <code>DigestValue</code> (C) and the <code>SignedInfo</code> (D) is canonicalized and verified against the <code>SignatureValue</code> (E). In this sample, the assertion of the SAML response is signed, and in other cases the whole SAML response is signed.</p>
<h2 id="searching-for-parser-differentials">Searching for parser differentials<a href="#searching-for-parser-differentials" aria-label="Searching for parser differentials"></a></h2>
<p>We learned that ruby-saml used two different XML parsers (REXML and Nokogiri) for validating the SAML response. Now let’s have a look at the verification of the signature and the digest comparison.<br>
The focus of the following explanation lies on the <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L268"><code>validate_signature</code></a> method inside of <code>xml_security.rb</code>.</p>
<p>Inside that method, there’s a broad XPath <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L278C1-L282C8">query</a> with REXML for the first signature element inside the SAML document:</p>
<pre><code>sig_element = REXML::XPath.first(
  @working_copy,
  "//ds:Signature",
  {"ds"=&gt;DSIG}
)
</code></pre>
<p><em>Hint: When reading the code snippets, you can tell the difference between queries for REXML and Nokogiri by looking at how they are called. REXML methods are prefixed with <code>REXML::</code>, whereas Nokogiri methods are called on <code>document</code>.</em></p>
<p>Later, the actual <code>SignatureValue</code> is <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L293C1-L298C92">read</a> from this element:</p>
<pre><code>base64_signature = REXML::XPath.first(
  sig_element,
  "./ds:SignatureValue",
  {"ds" =&gt; DSIG}
)
signature = Base64.decode64(OneLogin::RubySaml::Utils.element_text(base64_signature))
</code></pre>
<p>Note: the name of the <code>Signature</code> element might be a bit confusing. While it contains the actual signature in the <code>SignatureValue</code> node it also contains the part that is actually signed in the <code>SignedInfo</code> node. Most importantly the <code>DigestValue</code> element contains the digest (hash) of the assertion and information about the used key.</p>
<p>So, an actual <code>Signature</code> element could look like this (removed namespace information for better readability):</p>
<pre><code>&lt;Signature&gt;
    &lt;SignedInfo&gt;
        &lt;CanonicalizationMethod Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/xml-exc-c14n#" /&gt;
        &lt;SignatureMethod Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmldsig-more#rsa-sha256" /&gt;
        &lt;Reference URI="#_SAMEID"&gt;
            &lt;Transforms&gt;&lt;Transform Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/10/xml-exc-c14n#" /&gt;&lt;/Transforms&gt;
            &lt;DigestMethod Algorithm="http://www.w3.org/2001/04/xmlenc#sha256" /&gt;
            &lt;DigestValue&gt;Su4v[..]&lt;/DigestValue&gt;
        &lt;/Reference&gt;
    &lt;/SignedInfo&gt;
    &lt;SignatureValue&gt;L8/i[..]&lt;/SignatureValue&gt;
    &lt;KeyInfo&gt;
        &lt;X509Data&gt;
            &lt;X509Certificate&gt;MIID[..]&lt;/X509Certificate&gt;
        &lt;/X509Data&gt;
    &lt;/KeyInfo&gt;
&lt;/Signature&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Later in the same method (<code>validate_signature</code>) there’s again a <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L307">query for the Signature</a>(s)—but this time with Nokogiri.</p>
<pre><code>noko_sig_element = document.at_xpath('//ds:Signature', 'ds' =&gt; DSIG)
</code></pre>
<p>Then the <code>SignedInfo</code> element is taken from that signature and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Canonical_XML">canonicalized</a>:</p>
<pre><code>noko_signed_info_element = noko_sig_element.at_xpath('./ds:SignedInfo', 'ds' =&gt; DSIG)

canon_string = noko_signed_info_element.canonicalize(canon_algorithm)
</code></pre>
<p>Let’s remember this <code>canon_string</code> contains the canonicalized <code>SignedInfo</code> element.</p>
<p>The <code>SignedInfo</code> element is then also <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L314C6-L318C8">extracted</a> with REXML:</p>
<pre><code> signed_info_element = REXML::XPath.first(
        sig_element,
        "./ds:SignedInfo",
        { "ds" =&gt; DSIG }
 )
</code></pre>
<p>From this <code>SignedInfo</code> element the <code>Reference</code> node is <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L324">read</a>:</p>
<pre><code>ref = REXML::XPath.first(signed_info_element, "./ds:Reference", {"ds"=&gt;DSIG})
</code></pre>
<p>Now the code <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L326C1-L327C1">queries for the referenced node</a> by looking for nodes with the signed element id using Nokogiri:</p>
<pre><code>reference_nodes = document.xpath("//*[@ID=$id]", nil, { 'id' =&gt; extract_signed_element_id })
</code></pre>
<p>The method <code>extract_signed_element_id</code> <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L406C9-L406C34">extracts</a> the signed element id with help of REXML. From the previous authentication bypass (CVE-2024-45409), there’s now a <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L328">check</a> that only one element with the same ID can exist.</p>
<p>The first of the <code>reference_nodes</code> is taken and canonicalized:</p>
<pre><code>hashed_element = reference_nodes[0][..]canon_hashed_element = hashed_element.canonicalize(canon_algorithm, inclusive_namespaces)
</code></pre>
<p>The <code>canon_hashed_element</code> is then <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L349C7-L349C59">hashed</a>:</p>
<pre><code>hash = digest_algorithm.digest(canon_hashed_element)
</code></pre>
<p>The <code>DigestValue</code> to compare it against is then <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L350C7-L355C99">extracted</a> with REXML:</p>
<pre><code>encoded_digest_value = REXML::XPath.first(
        ref,
        "./ds:DigestValue",
        { "ds" =&gt; DSIG }
      )
digest_value = Base64.decode64(OneLogin::RubySaml::Utils.element_text(encoded_digest_value))
</code></pre>
<p>Finally, the <code>hash</code> (built from the element extracted by Nokogiri) is <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L357">compared</a> against the <code>digest_value</code> (extracted with REXML):</p>
<pre><code>unless digests_match?(hash, digest_value)
</code></pre>
<p>The <code>canon_string</code> extracted some lines ago (a result of an extraction with Nokogiri) is later <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/blob/21b676bdf55452750d8ee5facd2f6e3c51927315/lib/xml_security.rb#L366C7-L366C86">verified against</a> <code>signature</code> (extracted with REXML).</p>
<pre><code>unless cert.public_key.verify(signature_algorithm.new, signature, canon_string)
</code></pre>
<p>In the end, we have the following constellation:</p>
<ol>
<li>The assertion is extracted and canonicalized with Nokogiri, and then hashed. In contrast, the hash against which it will be compared is extracted with REXML.  </li>
<li>The SignedInfo element is extracted and canonicalized with Nokogiri - it is then verified against the SignatureValue, which was extracted with REXML.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="exploiting-the-parser-differential">Exploiting the parser differential<a href="#exploiting-the-parser-differential" aria-label="Exploiting the parser differential"></a></h2>
<p>The question is: is it possible to create an XML document where REXML sees one signature and Nokogiri sees another?</p>
<p>It turns out, yes.</p>
<p>Ahacker1, participating in the bug bounty, was faster to produce a working exploit using a parser differential. Among other things, ahacker1 was inspired by the <a href="https://mattermost.com/blog/securing-xml-implementations-across-the-web/">XML roundtrips vulnerabilities</a> published by Mattermost’s Juho Forsén in 2021.</p>
<p>Not much later, I produced an exploit using a different parser differential with the help of <a href="https://blog.trailofbits.com/2024/03/29/introducing-ruzzy-a-coverage-guided-ruby-fuzzer/">Trail of Bits’ Ruby fuzzer</a> called ruzzy.</p>
<p>Both exploits result in an authentication bypass. Meaning that an attacker, who is in possession of a single valid signature that was created with the key used to validate SAML responses or assertions of the targeted organization, can use it to construct assertions for any users which will be accepted by ruby-saml. Such a signature can either come from a signed assertion or response from another (unprivileged) user or in certain cases, it can even come from signed metadata of a SAML identity provider (which can be publicly accessible).</p>
<p>An exploit could look like this. Here, an additional Signature was added as part of the <code>StatusDetail</code> element that is only visible to Nokogiri:</p>
<p><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?resize=1024%2C400" alt="A diagram depicting a simplified SAML response on the left and the verification of the digest and the signature on the right. For both the signature and the digest verification one part is extracted using Nokogiri and the other using REXML." width="1024" height="400" srcset="https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=3496 3496w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=300 300w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=768 768w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=1024 1024w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=1536 1536w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=2048 2048w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/rubysaml-parser-diff-simplified8_2.png?w=3000 3000w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></p>
<p>In summary:</p>
<p>The <code>SignedInfo</code> element (A) from the signature that is visible to Nokogiri is canonicalized and verified against the <code>SignatureValue</code> (B) that was extracted from the signature seen by REXML.</p>
<p>The assertion is retrieved via Nokogiri by looking for its ID. This assertion is then canonicalized and hashed (C). The hash is then compared to the hash contained in the <code>DigestValue</code> (D). This DigestValue was retrieved via REXML. This DigestValue has no corresponding signature.</p>
<p>So, two things take place:</p>
<ul>
<li>A valid SignedInfo with DigestValue is verified against a valid signature. (which checks out)  </li>
<li>A fabricated canonicalized assertion is compared against its calculated digest. (which checks out as well)</li>
</ul>
<p>This allows an attacker, who is in possession of a valid signed assertion for any (unprivileged) user, to fabricate assertions and as such impersonate any other user.</p>
<h3 id="check-for-errors-when-using-nokogiri">Check for errors when using Nokogiri<a href="#check-for-errors-when-using-nokogiri" aria-label="Check for errors when using Nokogiri"></a></h3>
<p>Parts of the currently known, undisclosed exploits can be stopped by checking for Nokogiri parsing errors on SAML responses. Sadly, those errors do not result in exceptions, but need to be checked on the <a href="https://www.rubydoc.info/github/sparklemotion/nokogiri/Nokogiri%2FXML%2FDocument:errors"><code>errors</code></a> member of the parsed document:</p>
<pre><code>doc = Nokogiri::XML(xml) do |config|
  config.options = Nokogiri::XML::ParseOptions::STRICT | Nokogiri::XML::ParseOptions::NONET
end

raise "XML errors when parsing: " + doc.errors.to_s if doc.errors.any?
</code></pre>
<p>While this is far from a perfect fix for the issues at hand, it renders at least one exploit infeasible.</p>
<h2 id="indicators-of-compromise">Indicators of compromise<a href="#indicators-of-compromise" aria-label="Indicators of compromise"></a></h2>
<p>We are not aware of any reliable indicators of compromise. While we’ve found a potential indicator of compromise, it only works in debug-like environments and to publish it, we would have to reveal too many details about how to implement a working exploit so we’ve decided that it’s better not to publish it. Instead, our best recommendation is to look for suspicious logins via SAML on the service provider side from IP addresses that do not align with the user’s expected location.</p>
<h2 id="saml-and-xml-signaturesas-confusing-as-it-gets">SAML and XML signatures:as confusing as it gets<a href="#saml-and-xml-signaturesas-confusing-as-it-gets" aria-label="SAML and XML signatures:as confusing as it gets"></a></h2>
<p>Some might say it’s hard to integrate systems with SAML. That might be true. However, it’s even harder to write implementations of SAML using XML signatures in a secure way. As others have stated before: it’s probably best to <a href="https://ssoready.com/blog/engineering/ruby-saml-pwned-by-xml-signature-wrapping-attacks/#how-to-fix-this-disregard-the-spec">disregard the specifications</a>, as following them doesn’t help build secure implementations.<br>
To rehash how the validation works if the SAML assertion is signed, let’s have a look at the graphic below,  depicting a simplified SAML response. The assertion, which transports the protected information, contains a signature. Confusing, right?</p>
<p><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/conclusion-combined-saml.png?resize=1024%2C497" alt="A diagram showing a SAML response and its parts: the Assertion containing the Signature and the Signature containing the SignedInfo of which the DigestValue is a part." width="1024" height="497" srcset="https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/conclusion-combined-saml.png?w=1768 1768w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/conclusion-combined-saml.png?w=300 300w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/conclusion-combined-saml.png?w=768 768w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/conclusion-combined-saml.png?w=1024 1024w, https://github.blog/wp-content/uploads/2025/03/conclusion-combined-saml.png?w=1536 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px"></p>
<p>To complicate it even more: What is even signed here? The whole assertion? No!</p>
<p>What’s signed is the <code>SignedInfo</code> element and the <code>SignedInfo</code> element contains a <code>DigestValue</code>. This <code>DigestValue</code> is the hash of the canonicalized assertion with the signature element removed before the canonicalization. This two-stage verification process can lead to implementations that have a disconnect between the verification of the hash and the verification of the signature. This is the case for these Ruby-SAML parser differentials: while the hash and the signature check out on their own, they have no connection. The hash is actually a hash of the assertion, but the signature is a signature of a different <code>SignedInfo</code> element containing another hash. What you actually want is a direct connection between the hashed content, the hash, and the signature. (And once the verification is done you only want to retrieve information from the exact part that was actually verified.) Or, alternatively, use a less complicated standard to transport a cryptographically signed username between two systems - but here we are.</p>
<p>In this case, the library already extracted the <code>SignedInfo</code> and used it to verify the signature of its canonicalized string,<code>canon_string</code>. However, it did not use it to obtain the digest value. If the library had used the content of the already extracted <code>SignedInfo</code> to obtain the digest value, it would have been secure in this case even with two XML parsers in use.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion<a href="#conclusion" aria-label="Conclusion"></a></h2>
<p>As shown once again: relying on two different parsers in a security context can be tricky and error-prone. That being said: exploitability is not automatically guaranteed in such cases. As we have seen in this case, checking for Nokogiri errors could not have prevented the parser differential, but could have stopped at least one practical exploitation of it.</p>
<p>The initial fix for the authentication bypasses does not remove one of the XML parsers to prevent API compatibility problems. As noted, the more fundamental issue was the disconnect between verification of the hash and verification of the signature, which was exploitable via parser differentials. The <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/pull/736">removal of one of the XML</a> parsers was already planned for other reasons, and will likely come as part of a major release in combination with additional improvements to strengthen the library. If your company relies on open source software for business-critical functionality, consider <a href="https://github.com/sponsors">sponsoring</a> them to help fund their future development and bug fix releases.</p>
<p>If you’re a user of ruby-saml library, make sure to update to the latest version, 1.18.0, containing fixes for <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/security/advisories/GHSA-4vc4-m8qh-g8jm">CVE-2025-25291</a> and <a href="https://github.com/SAML-Toolkits/ruby-saml/security/advisories/GHSA-754f-8gm6-c4r2">CVE-2025-25292</a>. References to libraries making use of ruby-saml (such as <a href="https://github.com/omniauth/omniauth-saml">omniauth-saml</a>) need also be updated to a version that reference a fixed version of ruby-saml. We will publish a proof of concept exploit at a later date in the <a href="https://github.com/github/securitylab">GitHub Security Lab repository</a>.</p>
<h3 id="acknowledgments">Acknowledgments<a href="#acknowledgments" aria-label="Acknowledgments"></a></h3>
<p>Special thanks to Sixto Martín, maintainer of ruby-saml, and Jeff Guerra from the GitHub Bug Bounty program.<br>
Special thanks also to ahacker1 for giving inputs to this blog post.</p>
<h3 id="timeline">Timeline<a href="#timeline" aria-label="Timeline"></a></h3>
<ul>
<li>2024-11-04: Bug bounty report demonstrating an authentication bypass was reported against a GitHub test environment evaluating ruby-saml for SAML authentication.  </li>
<li>2024-11-04: Work started to identify and test potential mitigations.  </li>
<li>2024-11-12: A second authentication bypass was found by Peter that renders the planned mitigations for the first useless.  </li>
<li>2024-11-13: Initial contact with Sixto Martín, maintainer of ruby-saml.  </li>
<li>2024-11-14: Both parser differentials are reported to ruby-saml, the maintainer responds immediately.  </li>
<li>2024-11-14: The work on potential patches by the maintainer and ahacker1 begins. (One of the initial ideas was to remove one of the XML parsers, but this was not feasible without breaking backwards compatibility).  </li>
<li>2025-02-04: ahacker1 proposes a non-backwards compatible fix.  </li>
<li>2025-02-06: ahacker1 also proposes a backwards compatible fix.  </li>
<li>2025-02-12: The 90 days deadline of GitHub Security Lab advisories ends.  </li>
<li>2025-02-16: The maintainer starts working on a fix with the idea to be backwards-compatible and easier to understand.  </li>
<li>2025-02-17: Initial contact with GitLab to coordinate a release of their on-prem product with the release of the ruby-saml library.  </li>
<li>2025-03-12: A fixed version of ruby-saml was released.</li>
</ul>

	
<section>
	<hr>
	<div>
		<h2>Tags:</h2>
		<ul>
							<li>
					<a href="https://github.blog/tag/authentication/" rel="tag">
						authentication					</a>
				</li>
							<li>
					<a href="https://github.blog/tag/github-security-lab/" rel="tag">
						GitHub Security Lab					</a>
				</li>
							<li>
					<a href="https://github.blog/tag/ruby/" rel="tag">
						ruby					</a>
				</li>
							<li>
					<a href="https://github.blog/tag/saml/" rel="tag">
						SAML					</a>
				</li>
							<li>
					<a href="https://github.blog/tag/vulnerability/" rel="tag">
						vulnerability					</a>
				</li>
					</ul>
	</div>
</section>
	<div>
	<h2>
		Written by	</h2>
	
			<article>
	<div>
					<div>
				<picture>
					<source srcset="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/176818?v=4&amp;s=200" width="120" height="120" media="(min-width: 768px)">
					<img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/176818?v=4&amp;s=200" alt="Peter Stöckli" width="80" height="80" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
				</picture>
			</div>
				
					<p>Security Researcher at GitHub Security Lab</p>
			</div>
</article>
	</div>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[They're Close to My Body: A Hagiography of Nine Inch Nails and Robin Finck (2020) (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thewhitereview.org/feature/theyre-really-close-to-my-body/</link>
            <guid>43374237</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 18:15:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thewhitereview.org/feature/theyre-really-close-to-my-body/">https://www.thewhitereview.org/feature/theyre-really-close-to-my-body/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43374237">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
						<div>
						
												
							<p>
								‘They’re Really Close To My Body’: A Hagiography of Nine Inch Nails and their resident mystic Robin Finck							</p>
						</div>
						<p>‘We possess nothing in this world other than the power to say “I”. This is what we must yield up to God.’</p>
<p>— Simone Weil</p>

<p>‘God break down the door<br>
You won’t find the answers here Not the ones you came looking for.’</p>
<p>— Nine Inch Nails</p>


<h4>Photosensitivity warning: Many of the hyperlinks in this essay go to live videos, which feature a strobe light.</h4>


<ol>
<li></li>
</ol>
<p>I was 10 years old when <em><strong>The Downward Spiral</strong></em> by Nine Inch Nails was released in 1994, and I listened to it more than any other record for the next six years, when everything I knew about myself was disintegrating and becoming unknowable. It lives in my blood memory, the soundtrack to the most formative part of my life. When I think of that time, my memories resonate with those songs, I can’t imagine myself without them, who I would have been. Since then, twenty-five years, I regularly go through periods where the only thing I listen to for weeks, months at a time is Nine Inch Nails, and this locates me, returns me to myself. When you love a band for more than half your life, something happens as their songs come to live in you, they echo through how you remember the past, and fortify how you are legible to yourself in the present.</p>

<p>NIN was the first band that got me in trouble with grown-ups – for this, they have a special place in my heart that no other band will ever touch. For Christmas vacation in 1996, when I was 12, I brought the <em><strong>Broken</strong></em> EP with me when I went to stay with my Catholic grandparents. <em><strong>Broken</strong></em> was packaged in a cardboard ‘digipak’, so my grandmother, rather than struggle with a plastic jewel case, could open it like a book. The lyrics were printed on the inside, though I was singing them aloud all the time too. I think Grandma had the biggest problem with my favourite lyric – ‘Gotta listen to your big-time, hard-line, bad-luck, fist fuck’ – but there was enough offensive sentiment on that record to compel her to gather my family for an intervention. They asked me how I could listen to this violent, raging, blasphemous music. My answer, ‘Because I like it,’ still seems to be the best response to such a question.</p>

<p><iframe title="Nine Inch Nails: Closer (Uncensored) (1994)" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/3554226?dnt=1&amp;app_id=122963" width="504" height="380" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>The ‘<span><em><strong><a href="https://vimeo.com/3554226"><span>Closer</span></a></strong></em></span>’ video also got me in trouble. It was rarely played on MTV, and since these were the days before YouTubing could satiate fan cravings, I lived in constant, nervous hope that I’d be lucky enough to catch one of its late-night airings, maybe even be able to record it on VHS. One night I did get lucky, but I was at a sleepover birthday party, with giggling girls in pyjama shorts. We were 13, maybe 14 years old. The TV was playing in the background. That electronic beat came on – <em>dum, fft! dum, fft! </em>– animating, via air through tubes, the raw pig heart nailed to the Cherner chair. I squealed, turned up the volume, and sat six inches from the screen. I sang along, knew every word. ‘I wanna fuck you like an animal / I wanna feel you from the inside / I wanna fuck you like an animal / My whole existence is flawed / You get me closer to God.’ I clapped when Trent Reznor, his aquiline profile in silhouette, licked that strange, vintage microphone that looked at once phallic and mammillary. When the shots of him bound and blindfolded came on during the second chorus, I remember swooning and sighing, as if I were watching a boy band. No one joined me. They all hung back. I can imagine this scene now, how they saw me, a person lonely and young and singing to herself, leaning in to that bizarre world on the screen, with its spinning eggs and crucified monkey and apple-mouthed pig and split-open nautilus, the world that summoned something powerful and fundamental in me and told me that, although I felt like it, I was not world-less. Even if the world I’d lived in so far, the very world of this generic, bland, teenaged living room, had been deserted and companionless for me, the world of that video promised that, somewhere, there were people who saw visions like mine, full of nihilism and perversions but also twisted beauty, a kind of gracefulness in all the shit. The birthday girl’s parents called my parents, expressing concern, and banned me from coming over again.</p>

<p>I saved up to buy the VHS tour documentary for <em><strong>The Self Destruct Tour</strong></em>, called <span><span><a href="https://vimeo.com/61998095"><em><strong><span>Closure</span></strong></em></a></span></span>, which was released in 1997, when I was 13. It was the first VHS tape I ever owned, and what it contained, what it revealed, about this band felt like I’d discovered the Gnostic Gospels. The grainy image storms with brown light and shadows, and the music they play, on a stage draped in shrouds and scrolls of loose cassette tape, is brutal and desperate. The band destroy their instruments, each other, and themselves. Keyboards are stomped on until the keys look like ribs that have been cracked off their spines. Multiple band members get injured: Trent throws a microphone stand that lands on the drummer’s head, and, with blood pouring into his eyes, the guy keeps playing. The crowd doesn’t just mosh, it tears itself apart, punching each other, crowd-surfing, and clawing their way toward the stage. <span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=g9elkwmsZZk">They grab for Trent while bouncers fight them off</a></span>. Trent sneers back, ‘Whoever threw that, fuck you.’ It looked like the most exciting live show imaginable. I’d dream of it sitting in class, while the teacher droned on about the quadratic equation. I’d wonder what it felt like to be in that crowd, that room drenched in fury and sweat, with those songs, that music, the most explosive noise I’d ever heard. Around this time, I started playing in bands, and I got to learn for myself how good it feels to turn your amps all the way up and scream until your throat breaks. It instilled a belief in me that I still have to this day: that any spiritual ailment can be cured by playing music at maximum volume in a small, dark room.</p>

<p><iframe title="Nine Inch Nails: &amp;quot;Closure&amp;quot; part one: Self Destruct (1997)" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/61998095?dnt=1&amp;app_id=122963" width="640" height="480" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>The behind-the-scenes shots in <em><strong>Closure</strong></em> are even more infamous than the concert footage. They show the band destroying dressing rooms by heaving couches against walls, staggering around hungover in clothes whose rank funk you can practically smell off the screen. They snigger at Midwest gas stations where they shove oranges up their shirts to look like tits, and howl with laughter during a prank call to a sex worker, where they ask her to ‘Tell me you wanna fuck my nine inch nail’. I remember that there was a lot of ass and genitals on display, most of it male. Jim Rose’s Circus, a BDSM freak show, was one of the opening acts, and we watch one of the performers backstage try to lift an armchair that’s hooked to his limp dick. Marilyn Manson, another opening act, is young and lean and impish, sitting next to a pair of strippers with a look of inebriated glee on his lipstick-smeared face. Buzz Osborne of Melvins is persuaded by a drunken mob of band members to throw a lamp at an EXIT sign that is dripping with beer (this lives on in Tumblr gifsets entitled ‘Buzz, et. al., versus EXIT sign’). NIN begin the tour playing small theatres, and end, two years later, in arenas. Lou Reed comes backstage after a show and says, ‘It was so smart, it was just so fucking smart.’ There is the terrific version of ‘Hurt’ sung with David Bowie and <span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZfV7NLCWiiU">the notorious, mud-covered Woodstock ’94 performance</a></span>. This</span> was the tour where they wore black leather and latex covered in cornstarch, and Trent was in short-shorts with garters, dripping in sweat and blood. He careens around the stage, jerking off his microphone stand, and knocking over his bandmates by roping his mic cable around their feet, or sometimes just outright tackling them.</p>

<p>Some of the most exhilarating scenes – not only in <em><strong>Closure</strong></em> but in most of their live videos from the tours of the 1990s – show how Trent particularly enjoys attacking the lead guitarist, Robin Finck. Trent gropes him, leaps on him, twists him to the ground, shoves him off the stage into the surging crowd, and if it’s not a tackle, it’s an erotically menacing embrace of an arm around Robin’s head, <span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dkLsukaNqeE&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=4m27s">bending his neck back and stroking his forehead</a></span>, or pushing up against him from behind. On YouTube, there are several fan-made compilations, with titles like ‘Trent Reznor vs. Robin Finck (Part 1)’, that give a sense. There is also a sequence on <em><strong>Closure</strong></em>’s ‘bonus materials’ where a nearly-naked Marilyn Manson appears onstage and shoves Trent to the ground while kissing him. Along with the ‘Closer’ video, these scenes constructed a world where sex converged with rage, encapsulating the turgid passions of puberty in a way that no other band at the time did. Gruff, melancholic Pearl Jam could not get close to the feeling that being inside the belly of the beast of lust is warm and wet but also suffocating. More than anything else in his repertoire, Trent has had to account for these boiling, carnal eruptions in interviews. (‘I don’t walk around throwing mic stands when I’m eating dinner,’ he pointed out in an interview with <em><strong>MuchMusic</strong></em>.) In 1995, at age 11, I remember reading a particularly lurid article in the magazine <em><strong>Details</strong></em>, which bloomed in my fantasies for years after. The interviewer asks Trent the five words he associates with sex. Trent replies, ‘Taste, sweat, lick, come, bite,’ and is then asked if he’s into masochism and whether he associates sex with pain. He says yes. As I would experience in the next few years – making out awkwardly in closets and cars, bumping teeth and wincing at too-long fingernails, not to mention being confronted with the banal brutality of young desire – not only were sex and pain linked, but they felt like the same thing. Masochism was not a choice or a kink. It was how sex felt all the time. All you could do was submit. This was especially compounded for someone, as I was, assigned female at birth. Growing up, I was told not just by adults, but by so many depictions of erotic love in movies and TV, that if a boy called you names, insulted you, ignored you, and even (or <em>especially</em>) when he hit you, it was because he liked you. To be wanted was to suffer. And <em>to </em>want was to be monstrous.</p>

<p>The lyrics of Nine Inch Nails, so simple and vulnerable in their angst, in their need, in their defeat, offered articulation and insight into this rough new world. They were embarrassing as hell to sing along to – so bald and filthy! <em>so </em>corny! – but that’s exactly what made them meaningful. They explained the stuff that embarrassed you, gave it shape, cause, and expression, and validated it as true. In that same interview from 1995, Trent says, ‘Every day I’m saying the most personal thing I could ever say… But one of the prices is that there’s an open raw nerve that I’m letting everybody look at. There’s a hole in the back of my pants with a bare asshole showing, and you can see right in there. And sometimes I wish I hadn’t.’ Here, he could be describing having to endure one day of high school when you’ve got a crush on someone who doesn’t know you exist and you’ve just gathered your courage to say hi. NIN was the perfect band, especially for a goth, for an adolescence of gender confusion and the violence of craving. Lain over the harsh, wrathful quality of the music, you could scream and thrash and flail around to the huge sounds, but still be talking about how small you felt. I remember so many days of shuffling through the hallway at school, chewing my own tongue, my body crawling with thirst, and my only relief would come when I got home after school and cranked NIN up on my Walkman. It was transcendent in a basic way that I’ve never experienced since. As an adult I listen to a lot of hardcore, metal, and noise – bands that make angry, desolating music about being angry and desolated – but I keep returning to NIN precisely because of those naked lyrics about want. Let’s be real: you can’t sing along to Merzbow.</p>

<p>Along with satisfying the untamed needs born in that vortex of sex and rage, one of the reasons I’m so unabashedly a NIN fan, and have been for so long, is because they’ve never humiliated me as they’ve gone through the years, like nearly every other mainstream band I loved growing up in the 1990s. I can declare my love for them without having to suffer the scorn that so many of those bands now deserve for selling out in various, pathetic ways. Indeed, it’s recently felt as though all these years of cult devotion are being validated in a populist way, as NIN re-emerged in the late 2010s as a singular bastion of uncompromising artistic vision, the last men standing. <em><strong>Billboard</strong></em> recently declared us to be in the midst of a ‘Reznorssance’. After winning the Oscar for Best Score for <em><strong>The Social Network</strong></em>, and going on to score <em><strong>Waves</strong></em>, <em><strong>Watchmen</strong></em>, and the new Pixar film <em><strong>Soul</strong></em>, a meme went around stating that ‘From now on all good movies will be scored by NIN.’ The band appeared, as ‘The’ Nine Inch Nails, in the new <em><strong>Twin Peaks</strong></em>, and they looked and sounded fucking amazing. Miley Cyrus sang a warped version of ‘Head Like a Hole’ on <em><strong>Black Mirror</strong></em>, turning it into a capitalist nightmare of so-called feminist empowerment, which Reznor celebrated by releasing a T-shirt with the hilariously uncanny lyrics: ‘Head like a hole! I’m on a roll! Riding so high! Achieving my goals!’ At the end of the episode, Miley sang the real lyrics, which were as clarifying and articulate in 2019 as they were in 1989. The many years where the band’s popularity receded from mainstream success are now seen as evidence of their integrity. NIN has always foregrounded politics, not only before it became cool and trendy to do so, but at a time when it was likely to harm one’s career. During the record-industry crisis brought on by the internet – the one that made many artists turn into assholes whining about their bank accounts – Reznor released a new record, not as a pay-what-you-want download, but for free, saying, ‘This one is on me.’ When NIN won the Webby award for it, Trent’s entire speech was, ‘Wait. We didn’t charge anything.’ Last week, in the midst of the COVID-19 crisis, <span><a href="https://store-uk.nin.com/products/ghosts-v-together-and-ghosts-vi-locusts">they released two new albums for free</a></span>, with a statement that read, ‘It made us feel better to make these and it feels good to share them. Music has always had a way of making us feel a little less alone in the world… and hopefully it does for you, too. Remember, everyone is in this thing together and this too shall pass.’&nbsp;After the 2016 US election, Trent declared that if you voted for Trump, he didn’t want you at a NIN concert, and during NIN’s world tour of 2017-18, while playing outside of the States, he consistently apologised for his country. ‘Please, forgive us,’ he said. This during the same year the Smashing Pumpkins staged a ‘reunion tour’ where Billy Corgan monologued every night that he didn’t care who you voted for, what mattered most was that you were here – or, in other words, that you liked his band.</p>

<p>Beyond politics, something elemental about what NIN did for me as a kid has remained central to who I am as an adult. My precious VHS of <em><strong>Closure</strong></em> and the band it depicted represented everything I wanted, and still want, the world to be: chaotic, feverish, ungovernable. It had the power (maybe not literally, although it was thrilling to think so) to blow up the walls around me, the ones that kept me inside those bland generic rooms, lorded over by lifeless adults who insisted I obey rules that had no meaning beyond control. Watching <em><strong>Closure</strong></em> as an adult cracks me up with its childishness, how adolescent all those boys are, snickering at their dicks out and their rowdy tantrums. But I’d be lying if I didn’t admit to some nostalgia.</p>

<p>Adulthood has sobered me on the actual political impact of rebelliousness. I know that flipping off cop cars doesn’t actually <em>do </em>anything to dismantle oppression, but it sure as fuck still <em>feels </em>good. It will always thrill me to shout ‘Fuck you!’ to teachers, parents, bosses. To spit on the door of a bank, to crush a cigarette into the face on a politician’s sign. What a feeling of liberation to go to my high-school campus on a weekend and piss on the office door of the chemistry teacher who was giving me a D-. When I see young goths and punks sitting in piles of each other outside drugstores, smoking their clove cigarettes in their Dr. Martens and writing lyrics on their fragile skin in ballpoint pen, I will always smile and nod and want to lean over and tell them to try to stay romantic about all that acrimony for as long as they can, because the romance of it is what will help the most.</p>

<p>NIN is the purest expression of fury in music that I’ve experienced, and I love them most for how they femme-ed it, made it queer. It wasn’t just that they wore lipstick while they broke themselves. It was the excruciating nakedness of the lyrics paired with the visceral embodiment of their performance. Though their performances proposed the body as something to hope to transcend, they only revealed and articulated this hope as false. Such transcendence was not, in fact, possible: the body was not something from which you could escape, you’ll always have to drag it along behind you. Rather than this feeling like a punishment, however, a live NIN show was a testament to the fact that this embodiment could still feel enraptured, generative, even mystical.</p>

<p>This is because NIN is the band who most corroborate the fact that there can be a mysticism of fury. There are different kinds of mysticism, but all are primarily defined in terms of ecstasy, which comes from the Greek <em>ekstasis</em>, <em>ek </em>meaning ‘out’ and <em>stasis </em>meaning ‘stand’. Ecstasy is the standing outside of oneself, an experience that requires a total transformation of self, one that also transforms where (and through what) it can stand. We usually understand ecstasy as being conjoined with joy, affording an escape by catapulting you in sweet relief outside of your confining, earthly body of pain and frustration. But ecstasy can also be understood in terms of fury, rooted within, and because of, the bounds of your own skin. From this place, and only ever bound to it, implosive rather than explosive, fury mutates those bonds. Think of being throttled with rage: how your body shimmers with it, how you are changed. Think of the Furies, the ancient goddesses of vengeance and justice (which is where we get the word; the Romans invented it to translate the Greek name Erinyes), who are prescribed by their transformations: when an injustice occurs, they morph into human-shaped birds with blood shooting out of their eyes. They torment the perpetrator, shrieking at him, until he is brought to justice, and then they shape-shift again, this time into mourning old women, cloaked and heavy with despair at the fact that they’ve had to metamorphosise at all. Crucially, the centripetal collapse of fury, its core and border within the body itself, can be understood both as feminine and subordinate, because the oppressed – women, slaves, the disabled – have historically been equated with the body, reducible to and by it. Rage at such bondage is both liberation and limitation. Like the Furies, what fury produces is catharsis, a totalising change, but the thing that is altered is not the external world itself, but the bodies of those who are most affected by that world’s perfidy.</p>

<p>Fury can never be asked for more than what it is at its most pure – and the same could be said of joy. Both are primordial, basic materials, the raw stuff of life. Depending on your worldview, either one or the other is what’s required to first kindle anything at all. Obviously, I’m of the mind that fury is the OG ingredient. To begin anything we need a spark, a flame, a big bang, a fist punching through a wall. Although joy extends outward (to stand outside of one’s self), fury expands what is interior. It tunnels into the deepest redoubt of your being, excavating a violent, primordial place made of need and want. A definition of fury could be that it is the near-unbearable reckoning with how you didn’t get what you needed or wanted. This, necessarily, must take place at your tender, wounded pith, which means that the transformation fury offers, though it uncovers an infinite space within yourself, stops at the edges of your own skin. NIN’s fury, especially onstage, reaches this limit quickly. It produces a storm of ferocity, throwing the band members against themselves and the crowd, hurling the music forward in rapture and rupture. But if this storm was all their performance contained, the band would not be as powerfully purgative as they are. If they began and ended at fury only, the transcendent capacity delivered at a NIN show would stay grounded within the material perimeter of the body, circumscribing how lonely it is to live there, that place, that thing, which is all, in the end, that one has. But it doesn’t stop at this – because NIN has, as its touring guitarist, an actual ecstatic mystic on their stage: Robin Finck.</p>

<ol start="2">
<li></li>
</ol>
<p>Robin Finck. He is the biggest reason I am a NIN fan, but he is also something more, someone I’ve followed for 25 years, who has shown me the way to places I never thought existed, let alone imagined that I’d one day go to. It’s not enough to say that he is my favourite guitar player, or one of the first rock stars who I wanted to be. What he’s revealed to me has felt less like a veneration and closer to a kind of communion with another world. First it was how he looked, which was unlike anything I’d ever seen before, not entirely man, or woman, and which revealed the way to a world beyond gender and the regime it imposes on the body – making his kind of ecstasy the sort that stands <em>outside</em>. As a dreamy queer kid on the brink of puberty, such a guide was life-changing and life-saving. But then, it was so much more: it was how he played his instrument, which is signatory for its refusal to conform to the context in which he exists, and his performance while playing, whose fundamental characteristic is of someone with bottomless presence who is also entirely gone from this world. He is the strangest guitarist I can think of, not because his style of playing is the strangest, but because of the choices he makes for the kinds of stages he plays on. What he does – or perhaps it’s more accurate to say, what he refuses to do – produces a kind of radical negation of presence. Such a negation deviates from the world of rock, which is almost ontologically about the exaltation of the performers’ presence. Robin never does what you think he will, what you’d expect from someone in his place. Robin’s also the strangest celebrity I can think of: he’s played on some of the biggest stages in the world with NIN, and for a decade as Slash’s replacement in Guns N’ Roses, but his career is a demonstration of the refusal of celebrity. He’s given only a handful of interviews in twenty-five years – the first on-camera interview focusing on only him just appeared in 2018 – and when he does speak, he is extremely self-effacing. When asked to introduce himself in a feature on NIN, he said, ‘I’m Robin Finck, one of the guitarists in Nine Inch Nails.’ This, from <em>the </em>guitarist in Nine Inch Nails. (There have been other guitarists in Nine Inch Nails when Robin didn’t play with them, but, no matter how good they are, I consider them interlopers next to Robin Finck.) I’ve heard from a fan who waited for him outside the venue for hours after a concert that when he appeared, he introduced himself to her. ‘Hi, I’m Robin,’ he said. ‘Yes,’ she said. ‘I know very well who you are.’ It took many years for all of this to synthesise into something that made sense, and only now in my mid-30s, after watching him for more than two decades, do I understand that he has been a role model for me, not in terms of how to be a musician, or a performer, or an artist, or even a person. Rather, Robin Finck showed me how to be a mystic.</p>

<p>Despite its reliance on ecstasy, I can’t explain what exactly mysticism <em>is </em>– no one can, that’s the point. Mysticism is a state, an experience, where language can’t go, and this ineffability is precisely what defines it. Another way of saying this is: if you can define it in words, it’s not mysticism. The root of the words ‘mysticism’ and ‘mystery’, <em>myst</em>, comes from a Latin word for ‘secret rite, worship, or secret thing’, which originated in a Greek word that meant ‘to close, shut’, as in, closing one’s lips in secrecy, or shutting one’s eyes so as not to see. The secret, unknowable-ness of it is the only way to define it. What this means is that mystics as such are ultimately unknowable. The closest we can get to them is some sort of reading and writing that cannot be hermeneutical, cannot be oriented toward definition. An explanation of mysticism will only ever fail, so a circumscription of that failure, an account of the unknowing, must be the point.</p>

<p>It took me a year into writing this essay to understand that I am actually writing a <em>hagiography</em>: a writing of the lives of the saints. ‘Hagio’ is a Greek word that means sacred, holy, and devoted to the gods. Hagiography was, during the Middle Ages and into the Medieval period, the primary literary genre of Western civilisation, because it was the kind produced by the Christian Church. For several centuries, the only literate people were priests, and so they wrote for each other the stories they deemed worthy of being written, and the ones they wanted to read. Before I was able to articulate that I was following this lineage, I explained why I was writing this essay by saying that I’m just a really, really big fan. But fandom, which is perhaps one of the primary literary genres of <em>our </em>current time, is different to hagiography in that, for the latter, your subject might as well be dead. In fact, for hagiography it’s better if your subject <em>is </em>dead, because it requires idealisation, a certain amount of romance and fantasy. It asks both writer and reader to devote their time to that which is no longer alive, proposing that through the hagiography the subject can live on, an eternal life. It also insists, since the text’s subject is dead, on making an account of someone who can no longer account for themselves. Amy Hollywood, in <em><strong>Sensible&nbsp;</strong><strong>Ecstasy</strong></em>, writes how the task of the hagiographer is to interpret not only the life, but the very body, of that which is beyond interpretation. This is especially true with women saints, and has significant political consequences: to write their lives, literate male priests attempted to clarify behaviours that they found incomprehensible. The result of this was that so many Medieval women saints were said, by their hagiographers, to do bizarre things as expressions of their mysticism: some can fly, some weep until they Biblically flood the village, St. Catherina of Siena was said to have worn Christ’s foreskin as her wedding ring when they married. The list goes on. If one cannot hope to know the unknowable, then hagiography is perhaps a coming-to-terms with this. People cope with unknowability and that which cannot be known in different ways; sometimes I think mysticism is simply the experience of living for, because of, and within this coping.</p>

<p>Crucially, hagiography is a solitary genre, both to read and to write, but it is necessarily and fathomlessly solitary for the writer. To write a hagiography is to bear the knowledge of just how small you are, a small thing reaching out to a vast, unknowable heaven. My hagiography began as an email to a friend: I’d invited them to a NIN show, and they said they’d of course love to join, but they never got into NIN, what was it that I liked about them? I started typing bits of answer, as if I were a priest hunched over my scroll, writing by candlelight, to say, let me show you what has given my life purpose. After my email swelled past 2,000 words, I thought, maybe I ought to move this to a Word document and take it seriously as a piece of writing. This felt strange; I’ve never before been compelled to write from a place of enthusiasm. It was hard to justify, I’m so used to needing critique – or fury! – to be my reason. Eventually, I turned in a 7,000-word version to my agent, who, a little bewildered (all year, I’d been turning down paying gigs in order to write this thing that no one had asked for), told me I’d probably need to cut it by several thousand words for publication. I took all of her other edits, but not the one about the length; instead, I added 8,000 more words. It wasn’t that I was obsessed with Robin Finck: it was that I was obsessed with <em>writing </em>about Robin Finck, which kept seeming like an impossible task. As my essay’s word count still climbed, I understood that a part of me was surrendering to something I couldn’t explain at all, and although an essay, etymologically, is an attempt at some sort of explanation, I realised that as I got close to definitions, I simultaneously got close to paradoxes, that as I made my way towards the shore of perceptibility, I was also becoming drenched in the incommunicable. This, then, was how I realised that I was writing about mysticism.</p>

<p>For me, the way mysticism feels in practice has to do with a paradox: it’s where you can feel the edges of your body as they are being annihilated by, and into, something greater than you. In order to encounter anything, you first need a body to experience it. The enigma comes at this place of simultaneous existence and obliteration: to feel something being destroyed, you first have to feel its intactness. How else will you feel your edges burning away? Don’t they have to remain, somehow, as edges? But how? It’s so illegible a feeling, and yet it still happens inside your skin, or very, very close to it. It opens up an alien world, and yet that world seems to still be located in your body. It troubles the understanding of ecstasy as something that forces you outside of yourself – in a way, it asks if the transformation that mysticism produces is happening to you, or the world, or both. Or, something else that neither of those two are – yet.</p>

<p>Music, perhaps more than any other art, produces this simultaneous feeling of something happening very close to you, alongside, or within, while feeling something much bigger than yourself, which you can’t see or touch, overwhelm and engulf you. At least this is where I’ve experienced mysticism, when playing my own music and being in the audience of others. There are plenty of musicians I like who seem like mystics in more obvious ways than Robin Finck, but it’s precisely because he doesn’t seem like one – that paradox – that pronounces it for me. From a hagiographical point of view, Robin Finck is not dead, but – with his unknowable-ness, with how he mystifies me – he might as well be.</p>

<p>Like most frontmen and lead guitarists, Trent Reznor is a god, but Robin Finck is a demon. Reznor is plenty diabolical, but Finck has a serpentine energy, Medusa hair, and it feels plausible that, at some point in his life, he made a deal with the devil for the superhuman ability to excel at a wordless, subterranean language. On stage, he <span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=m0L_zDV2VI8&amp;">moves</a></span></span> as if no one’s watching him, as if he’s conferring with an oracular force that feels as interior and intimate as it does radically extrinsic. I can’t say this about any other lead guitarist of Robin’s stature. He’s definitely classifiable as a rock guitar god – a category whose tautology is its ostentatious flamboyance – but because he refuses to perform the choreography attendant to this category, something important is revealed about how he positions himself on these rock-star stages, what he takes from them, what he gives. Despite this rejection of the spotlight, or maybe because of it, he is one of the most captivating performers I’ve ever seen, and this is saying something, since he’s sharing the stage with Trent Reznor. My friend, who knew nothing about NIN, grabbed me about halfway through the show to shout, ‘I can<em>not stop </em>watching the guitar player!’ At that moment, Robin’s head and shoulders were bent over as if in a pillory, and he was trembling, almost motionless, like a Butoh performer. When he performs, I mainly feel as if I <em>shouldn’t </em>be watching him, that I’m invading his privacy, bearing witness to a secret act that just happens to be taking place on a stage in front of 20,000 people.</p>

<p>He most resembles one of those inflatable, dancing tube-bodies in front of car dealerships, whose limbs unfurl and elongate, keeping a time that seems like breathing. He convulses hypnotically, as if in a trance, lifting his arms up and away. He often falls. He is very <span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ilQhPeSBAI8&amp;"><span><span>awkward</span></span></a></span>. When he steps in time, he lifts his knees high, like a marionette puppet. He’ll hook his neck around his microphone stand and rock back and forth with it, or grind against his amp, not in a sexual way, but as if it’s a door he wants to go through. At the end of playing the bar, his spine often curls over, guitar touching the ground, like he’s exhaling his whole being. He does a lot of crouching at the side of the stage, hidden behind the speakers. He’s the only one other than Trent who leaves his designated area, climbing up the platform where the amps are, lurching back and forth in front of the drums, though this never has the practised sweep that Trent’s has. Robin looks more like Frankenstein lumbering around. When not in a swoony reverie, his expression is set to a haunted, grimacing frown. Sometimes he’ll stop playing his instrument altogether, stand eerily still, and peer out into the audience, as though looking beyond but also through them, into some other depth. In bzarektah36’s description of a YouTube video where this is featured, we are warned: ‘Be on the lookout for Robin’s death stare.’ The entranced inelegance of his movement is interrupted by the moments when he explodes with violence, though he never harms anyone else as Trent does, and this makes it seem less like violence and more like a part of himself is breaking open. There are fan videos online of Robin smashing, breaking or throwing his guitar, <span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TaPQX5YX-M4&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=2m13s">knocking over</a></span></span> microphone stands, and leaving the stage in the middle of the song <span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tLD2A9BE6V4&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=14s">if something doesn’t sound right</a></span></span>. But perhaps because his entire affect is of someone not entirely in or of this world, you get the sense that when he exits the stage, he is exiting this plane of reality, going to a place no one can follow. In many songs, when it’s not his turn to play, he disappears from his spot on stage left completely, reappearing only when it is – often, magically, from stage right. I don’t know where he goes.</p>

<p><iframe title="Nine Inch Nails: March Of The Pigs (1994)" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/3554852?dnt=1&amp;app_id=122963" width="640" height="480" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<ol start="3">
<li></li>
</ol>
<p>I first saw him in the ‘<span><span><em><strong><a href="https://vimeo.com/3554852">March of the Pigs</a></strong></em></span></span>’ video, from 1994, when I was 10. I somehow managed to download it – over dial-up! – and would watch and rewatch the 200-pixels-wide file because it felt like it contained clues for how to live. This first encounter with Robin Finck changed my world. It was how he looked, how he moved, and what that seemed to mean – or, maybe it’s more accurate to say, the meaning it resisted. He was different from anything I’d ever seen, and also different from the video itself, a tension that dilated the world of what NIN promised. Standing next to the other guitarist, Danny Lohner, who had the goatee and unmistakable aggression of a straight white boy, Robin looked alien, femme, a future gender. His face was childlike and open, Caravaggio beautiful, with pouty lips, shaved eyebrows, and big, moony eyes. He seemed possessed, swinging his feet around in graceless arcs and grimacing in time to the harsh sounds. He didn’t have a recognisable gender, but it was more than that: maybe he wasn’t even human. ‘You can <em>do </em>that?!’ I remember thinking, which was another way of saying, ‘You can <em>be </em>that?’</p>

<p>About every great rock band ever, it has been said, as a high compliment, that girls want to fuck the singer and boys want to be the lead guitarist. Categorically, I’ve always been in the boys’ camp – I never wanted to fuck Trent Reznor, I wanted to be Robin Finck. I could understand the sex appeal of these frontmen, but it absolutely diminished when compared to what the guitarists represented. Frontmen embody a kind of divine charisma, strutting across the stage and mesmerising the crowd with their god-like powers, like preachers who can open up the kingdom of heaven for you. They are the ones front and centre, their hearts on their sleeve, spreading their arms up and out and singing the lines that will lift everyone into the sky. How clichéd, but still, how you want to go there. Off to the side are the guitarists. They don’t smile at the crowd, or talk, or sing, and if they do, it’s backup, turned down in the mix. They hold their instrument close, intertwining their bodies around it. They seem to have gained access to a place hidden from our world, ferrymen on the river Styx.</p>

<p>The <em>fuck vs. be </em>configuration of rock-star fandom has never made much sense to me. Rock music elementally is about how wanting to fuck someone converges dangerously and deliciously with wanting to be someone. The maxim is meant to explain how much desire has accumulated around the band, not only in terms of how we lust after them, but in terms of something that cuts closer to how we desire ourselves. Audiences, as much as they are fans of particular figures, want to see themselves reflected back through those figures. All good rock stars have a bewitching power that goes straight through the sternum and touches something quivering and central in the gut. It’s the feeling that you can find yourself, or who you want to be, in one of the musicians onstage. In psychoanalysis, this would be called projection, the transfer of your desires on to another person. But a more ancient way of explaining it is through the spiritual idea of communion, which has to do with an unspeakable sense of connection with something that both lives in your body and beyond it.</p>

<p>Watching a rock star onstage, using their body and face to express something interior now made into flesh and sound, can show you all kinds of things: where the edges of your body are, and how they can be dissolved; how you can feel connected to other bodies around you, and also to something you can’t see or touch, but which you can hear and feel. It can help you understand <em>what </em>you feel, by affording you the sense of recognition: you can hear your feelings and thoughts emerge from someone else. But it also shows you what is <em>possible </em>to feel, by letting you see what someone else has done with those same feelings. This is what connects you to that thing that is both in your own body and beyond it. Because connection has to do with desire, all of this can point toward how you <em>want </em>to feel, which is to say, how to get to the self you want to become. You can do that. You can be that.</p>

<p>But upon first seeing Robin in the ‘Pigs’ video, he confused me: he was as delicate and lissom and ethereal as he was scraggy and agitated and wild. There was his long, lithe, snaky body and narrow hips, and his soft, feminine face. There was his grimace, that mesmerised look of being taken over, and the wrecked sound of his guitar. He seemed at once lost, out of place, and exactly, perfectly fitted to where he was. Although the camera, in one charged take, fixates on Trent, who pummels around the sound stage and rubs the crotch of his oxblood-red leather pants, it is Robin who is a personification of the song itself, which goes from its thrashing 7/8 time signature and hammering screams – ‘Bite! Chew! Suck! Away the tender parts!’ – to a major-key piano breakdown where the melody lilts and the vocals entreat, ‘And doesn’t it make you feel better?’ Robin stands behind Trent and the camera only catches him in the frame sometimes. He curves his neck and tosses his hair and plays his guitar as if he’s in a different room, and even world, to the rest of the band. This air of displacement, of existing somewhere else while you are also right here, which has continued to mark his stage presence, reached into me as an explanation for the strange dislocation I’d felt in my body and its place in the world so far. I’d never felt comfortable in my own skin, not because of the skin itself, but because of what the world said it signified. When I looked at myself, I saw one thing – I was a dragon, I had snakes for hair! – but when the world looked back, it insisted that it saw another, something that was supposed to be docile, pretty, manageable. You’re a girl, it said. A <em>what</em>? I said.</p>

<p>The confusion Robin instigated felt somehow familiar, and at some point, it made me wonder if I was looking at something queer. ‘Queer’ was a term I’d heard about but not known exactly what it meant – it was thrown around by kids my age as well as adults, along with ‘gay’, as both an insult about a deviant form of desire and a marker of something consummately strange. When I saw this person, embodied it seemed in multiple worlds, some made of the recognisable world around me, some from nowhere I’d known before, I understood how the word ‘queer’ means things that are not articulable, that cannot be contained according to conventional laws of meaning. It made me realise not only that ‘queer’ could describe me too, but that I <em>wanted </em>it to. It activated that experience of communion. There was a reverberation of recognition that told me the quivering thing in my gut was not alone – this is what I could be, what I was – but also that there was a place beyond what I knew so far about myself, outside it, and maybe it was populated with others who felt the same way, and this was how to get there.</p>

<p>On the surface, Robin was an exemplary figure of the 1990s era of rock-star gender-fuckery, especially the goth section of it, when Kurt Cobain wore dresses, Marilyn Manson looked like a woman, and PJ Harvey’s voice sounded like a man’s. It was fabulous. All that mesh and black lipstick was our generation’s Bowie-inspired glam moment, and Robin embodied it perfectly. Robin’s squirming presence during the muddy Woodstock performance is the one people remember next to Trent’s. (One of the first sentences of his entry on the NIN Wiki reads, ‘His appearance, particularly during <em><strong>The Downward Spiral</strong> </em>era… has arguably made him one of the most iconic members of NIN other than Trent Reznor.’) At the time, being 10 years old, my identification with his look as something queer had less to do with sexuality, per se, and&nbsp;more to do with the way a body looked and moved, and how it did those things by either conforming to or breaking the rules. Encountering Robin Finck was a concurrence with someone whose embodiment was capacious enough to contain many seemingly disparate parts, and it appeared that, despite this (or maybe, perhaps, <em>because </em>of it?), he lived in his skin comfortably, which was the first time I’d ever seen that such a state could be possible for someone who looked the way I wanted to. But even as a child, before I’d started to think about mysticism and what, exactly, it was, something about seeing Robin Finck had more in it that pointed me towards a standing outside of myself, which was an order of magnitude bigger than the usual celebrity worship and the feeling of being a fan. The feeling of my own body compelled me toward thinking about mysticism because, for the mystic, the body has to be simultaneously felt and exploded. The feeling that dominated me, and still does, is that I wanted to live outside of my body, without and beyond it. I didn’t know how to do this, or if it was even possible, but watching Robin Finck, slipping out of the roles that the world tried to put him in, showed me a way.</p>

<p>Despite being in two of the biggest rock bands of all time, very few people, even fans of those bands, can tell you who Robin Finck is. Trust me, I’ve asked. He’s perhaps of the same species as Blixa Bargeld, whose own band is the magnificent Einstürzende Neubauten, but who’s most well known for playing guitar and singing backup with Nick Cave and The Bad Seeds in the 1980s. Blixa has currency among Bad Seeds fans as much for his bulging, insectoid eyes and ur-punk mullet hair as for his brutal scream and guitar sound – but what makes him so beloved is the very fact of his sidekick status. Similarly, because Robin Finck has stood to the left of Trent Reznor and Axl Rose, some of the greatest frontmen of all time, he attracts the attention of those who prefer to look towards the liminal rather than at what’s at the centre.</p>

<p>Born in 1971 in New Jersey and raised in Georgia, most of Robin Finck’s biography is unknown. He’s given few interviews and, when he does do press events with NIN, he sits silently at the edge of the band. He is especially committed to maintaining his anonymity, even for&nbsp;public work. In my research for this article, I encountered more stories of him intentionally removing his name from projects than projects themselves. When I interviewed Kelly Kalman, who runs the Facebook fan page <span><span><a href="https://www.facebook.com/FinckYourself">Finck Yourself </a></span></span>(which currently has 305 likes), she told me that she started the page specifically to keep track of him, but it’s been slow going. The only public performance he did in 2019 was as one of a dozen performers at a charity ball for an animal shelter in Sonoma County. Following his hashtags on the internet, Kelly learned when tickets went on sale and bought two, travelling across the country for the concert. She said she had no idea that it would be as intimate as it was until the event organisers emailed her to ask what she’d like for dinner. It was set up in a tent outside a farm for 300 people; she said the stage was about as large as a king-sized mattress. Sitting at her table, she was literally bumped into by Robin Finck as he walked past. She described how he recognised her (she’s the same fan who waits for him outside venues), how his eyes darkened. He gently led her and her friend outside, and said he was happy to take photos and sign autographs there but that, once inside, they had to promise that they wouldn’t draw attention to him in any way. ‘I’m here to support my family,’ he explained. (The performance was directed by his wife.) Kelly said her stomach dropped then, worrying she’d overstepped some boundary, despite it being a public performance for which she’d bought tickets. In general, she said, she worries about being creepy, since following him demands a certain persistence, as there is hardly any trace of him in the world.</p>

<p>In 1989, he briefly attended the Berklee College of Music, and we can confirm this because a photo of his student ID card exists on a fan’s Tumblr. In the 1990s, between NIN and GNR, he toured as a guitarist with Cirque du Soleil, where he met Bianca Sapetto, a choreographer, acrobat and trapeze artist, who became his wife. They have two children together, and have collaborated on projects like LedZAerial, where he plays in a Led Zeppelin cover band while she and other performers dance suspended from the ceiling. For most of his career he has worked as a touring musician, and since NIN and GNR don’t tour often, he is out of the spotlight for years at a time. The only music of his own that he’s released was a collaboration in 2015 with a Portuguese electronic artist named Wordclock, for the instrumental soundtrack of a horror video game called <em><strong>NOCT</strong></em>. Occasionally he’s released a collaborative track, and by occasionally, I mean a total of three times, and these have been for the trailers of video games or films. He has appeared on several NIN and GNR records, but not all of them, and only on certain tracks. Kelly pointed out that Robin refuses credit for his work on the GNR album, <em><strong>Chinese Democracy</strong></em>, which is notable because Axl Rose, who Kelly says is ‘the man who loves to take credit for everything’, insists on citing Robin’s contribution.</p>

<p>For a short time he maintained a web presence by answering fan questions via his website’s message board in terse, enigmatic sentences. When asked, ‘Robin, do you think time will end?’ he replied, ‘with every blink’. When he has had accounts on social media, they’ve been similarly short and baffling, as in 2010 when he tweeted 126 times to say things like, ‘A course amid the smoke and silt, is there if look for finding wilt.’ At the start of NIN’s <em><strong>Cold and Black and Infinite</strong></em> tour of 2018, he began an Instagram account, but mainly posts collages of the sky with no captions; if he posts a selfie, he edits it to make his face look deformed. In 2018, he gave his first of two video interviews ever, one of them a <span><span><a href="https://youtu.be/ntIDyFx2Co0">rig rundown with <em><strong>Premier Guitar</strong></em></a></span></span>, where his long silences and awkward rhythm with the interviewer compelled YouTube comments like, ‘Oof…brutal! I’d rather hear gunshots coming from my Grandma’s bedroom then continue watching this,’ and ‘I had a root canal on Wednesday and that was easier to get through.’ (When asked what he likes about a particular guitar, the silence hangs until he can muster, ‘I just like the way it feels.’) Some comments defended him, with suggestions like, ‘This is a great unintentional ASMR video!’ and ‘David Lynch directed this rig rundown. Love it!’</p>

<p>Until 2018, the <em><strong>Closure</strong></em> documentary from 1997 was the longest screen time he’s ever had. In it we get only a glimpse, but in that glimpse, his archetype was established. He wears black nail polish, a leather slave collar, and fingerless metallic silver gloves. This look, more than any other, comprises the Patronus of my gender identity as a teenager. In a black unitard thing with booty shorts and ripped stockings, he could be mistaken for a tall, broad-shouldered woman, though once or twice he wears a codpiece made of glittering chain mail. (Before NIN, he had a brief stint in a band called Impotent Sea Snakes, which performed in drag; Robin’s persona with them was ‘Queenie’.) He’s 23, 24. He’s quiet and aloof, not one who throws couches. He has shaved eyebrows and paints white Kabuki-style slashes in their place, and we watch him carefully draw lines on his nostrils with black eyeliner and put a dot at his third eye, for reasons we shall never know. He opens his make-up box and compact, saying proudly to the camera, ‘See how fast I can do that?’ He has a reedy, gentle, almost girlish voice, which clashes with the shredded-sounding screams that come out of him onstage. In almost every backstage shot of him, he’s doing his make-up in the background or briefly pushing his face into the camera (if I were that pretty I would too), and his ass, in those booty shorts, is one of the ones on display. As always, he rarely speaks. Another fan-made compilation is ‘<span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C9zwrCH7Zbk"><span><span>Robin Finck Talking</span></span></a></span>’, only two-and-a-half minutes long. An article once strutted the title, ‘CONFIRMED: Robin Finck Has a Speaking Voice.’</p>

<p>And of course, there is that hair, that <em>Robin Finck hair</em>. The first suggestion Google offers when you type in ‘Robin Finck’ is ‘hair’. Shaved to the scalp on the sides of the skull to accentuate the long wisps of sideburns, the creation’s focal point is the mullet-y back-patch of dreads that go past his shoulders. In the ‘Pigs’ video, <em><strong>Closure</strong></em> documentary, and Woodstock show, a kind of half-ponytail sprouts from the crown of his head. It looks like a rotting palm tree. It could be said to be a precursor to Ariana Grande’s signature half-ponytail, in the way that the dire wolf is the prehistoric mother to the Chihuahua. Over the years, Robin’s mullet-dreads would be topped with various arrangements: a Mohawk- shaped stripe, a widow’s-peaky spike, and, sometimes, incongruously soft bangs. On the <em><strong>Fragility</strong></em> tour he is shaved bald or Mohawked, the sideburns fluffy curls at his ears, with make-up reminiscent of Kembra Pfahler’s The Voluptuous Horror of Karen Black. When Robin toured with GNR, his hair was remarkable too. First, in 2002, he wore a monk-like tonsure, the front half of the crown shaved, with the hair long and loose in the back, as if he’d dipped his bald head into half a wig. In 2006 and 2007, he grew out his mane and beard to look like a homeless beach bum (completing the look with a shirt made of garbage bags). Around 2013, with NIN again, the dreads left, replaced by a rat-tail-looking swatch, but the long sideburns, shaved sides and top-spikes are still there, and in any live video you watch of NIN since then, someone in the YouTube comments section is going apeshit for Robin’s hair (YouTube user LetsGetHighonMorris regrets: ‘Too bad I’m not man enough to wear my hair like he does.’).</p>

<p>In one of <em><strong>Closure</strong></em>’s most memorable<span> <a href="https://youtu.be/hPKo29PLItI?t=162"><span><span>scenes</span></span></a></span>, Robin shaves his trademark hair. Trent helps, leaning over him and asking, ‘You wanna leave the little sideburns?’ As they head to the stage, Robin tosses on a long black wig, and calls ‘Trent!’, then hurries to follow him. It’s a moment that feels slightly erotic, but more companionably intimate, with a whiff of care. In a film that rejoices in self-destructive delirium, here we have a moment of trust. Anyone getting their head shaved to the skin by someone else is in a vulnerable position, but there’s something deeper here about what Robin incites people to do, to feel. Trent and the camera, and us by extension, are all helping this young man achieve the odd vision for how he wants to look, though what that exactly is, we can’t say.</p>

<p>Any witch will tell you that hair is everything, the container of your power. If your hair is right, your confidence, your command and your sense of self are secured and definite and indestructible. Your hair is who you are – and, as any queer kid will tell you, if it’s not yet, you can get it cut to be that way. Getting your hair cut is a sacred ceremony, and when it goes wrong, the results are disastrous. I once wound up in the hospital with suicidal depression after a particularly atrocious haircut, and I’m only half-joking. Rock stars live and die by their hair. In <em><strong>Just Kids</strong></em>, Patti Smith acknowledges that the minute she got her iconic cut, the world started to notice her and her career began. It’s certain that Robin Finck wouldn’t be where he is today without that hair. There’s never been a sustained review of Robin as a musician, but in nearly every article where he is mentioned, this one included, the writer will remark on his hair. Robin’s hair seems to signify everything notable about him: his strange-ness and out-of-place-ness, something only he can pull off.</p>

<p>Offstage (and sometimes on) Robin has a penchant for wearing feather jewellery, chokers, shawls and clogs, and this also makes NIN that much more voluminous for his inclusion in a band of guys dressed in black jeans and T-shirts. In every candid and behind-the-scenes photo and video I’ve ever found of him, he’s wearing clogs with notable socks (pink stripes are a favourite). It appears he has several well-loved pairs of clogs, including white ones. My friends must be quite tired by now of me sending them photos of Robin in his clogs, and I’ve heard Trent give him shit for it, in videos of soundchecks. ‘Robin’s out here… he’s got clogs, he’s got red socks,’ Trent laments. During performances, Robin replaces his clogs with sneakers, which is sensible, it’s easy to sprain an ankle by jumping around in clogs.</p>

<p>These fashion choices may seem superficial things to dote on, but they substantiate for me why Robin’s presence is so amplifying to NIN, and so noteworthy in the world of rock stars. It’s not just his queer – in all senses of the word – comportment, but how indecipherable he is. The most common word I’ve seen used to describe him is ‘weirdo’, and that’s by <em>fans. </em>His only mention in the fan-made NIN Drinking Game, to be played during concerts or while watching live footage, is to drink ‘when Robin does something weird’. Robin himself remarked upon this in the only interview of substance he’s given about his background, which was with <em><strong>Ultimate Guitar</strong></em> in 2014. When discussing his audition with NIN in 1992, he said, ‘My kneejerk reaction was, “Nine Inch Nails? Isn’t that a lot of black hair and synthesisers? I’m really not sure where I’d fit in.”’</p>

<p>This inexplicability of how he managed to have a place in the world of mainstream rock, and the way he occupies that place, is why I care about him so much. I don’t pay much attention to mainstream rock, other than to know that almost all of it is not for me. And I sometimes hesitate to call Robin Finck my favourite guitarist over Japanese musician Keiji Haino, because Haino-San’s music is the kind I listen to on a daily basis and go to see live and try to make in my own work, and Robin’s is not. (And if we’re talking hair, I’m definitely going for Haino-San’s.) But despite the fact that Haino-San is an unearthly, shamanistic creature who conjures new universes of the strangest sounds I’ve ever heard (in 2018, NPR called him the ‘dark wizard of the avant-garde’), I find Robin the more perplexing of the two. Haino-San is the premier experimental guitarist and, in my opinion, has the best hair of any musician of all time. He is also absolutely otherworldly – but he is legible as being of this otherworldly world. When I say that Keiji Haino is a mystic, it’s obvious. Of course he is.</p>

<p>Calling Robin a mystic, however, is not at all explicit, and it’s taken me years to realise that this was the role he played in my life, that by watching him slip in and out of legibility, I was not necessarily watching an individual, but what was coming <em>through </em>that individual. Sometimes he seems made of flesh and bone, within grasp, sometimes he’s on another planet. Here he is onstage with NIN as Trent blasts around the stage and breaks shit, but Robin is off crouching in a corner with his head down. Here he is listed as performing at a public, ticketed show, but he is disturbed when a fan actually comes to see him there. Here he is playing the beloved guitar solo in ‘Sweet Child O’ Mine’, but he’s doing it while wearing a white satin Pagliacci suit and standing motionless, looking with a blank face, not at the sea of screaming fans before him, but off into another dimension. This incongruity is more intense in GNR than NIN. Where GNR glories in its hyper-masculine instrument-stroking, Robin seems to glory in nursing an oddly beating heart to aural life. In every video I’ve seen of Robin onstage next to Axl Rose, I think, who let this poetic, sonic-seamstress freak on to the same stage as a bunch of goons?</p>

<ol start="4">
<li></li>
</ol>
<p>The thing about playing the guitar is that it <em>is </em>a body, in and of itself, and so you have to meet and understand it with your own. As with any lover, it requires that you invent and share a language together, which only the two of you speak. To play it, you have to hold it close, carry it on your shoulder, use your whole body, both hands, you feel it vibrate through your bones, the skin of it rubs against yours. It has its own smell that mixes with your sweat, and you have to wipe it off when you’re done.</p>

<p>Robin has said that he plays an instrument ‘you can carry’, and this is key to understanding his role in a band like NIN, whose catalogue is constructed out of synthesiser-based sounds, the ‘only constant’ of which, Trent’s said, ‘has been [the archetypal synthesiser] Moog’. In one of those two interviews of 2018, Robin<span> <a href="https://youtu.be/qTx3gpSZJ6c?t=591"><span><span>explained</span></span></a> </span>why he chose the guitar, ‘I just like the push and pull of it. That’s one thing I like about the guitar, is this, is this thing here.’ He moves his left hand up and his right hand down. ‘There’s not a lot of instruments where you have a push and pull, with such a nuanced articulation, of both hands hitting the same string, but in all these different distances, but at the same time… It’s all right here, it’s the strings, and it’s the chords, and – they’re really <em>close </em>to my <em>body</em>.’</p>

<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="Ernie Ball: String Theory featuring Robin Finck of Nine Inch Nails" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/qTx3gpSZJ6c?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>The reason why guitarists seem more likely than singers to have made deals with the devil is because the devil and the power he possesses, what he’s selling, can’t be contained in an ordinary human body part like the throat, and it can’t be something as democratic as words, these common things used by so many people to communicate boring shit like what you need to buy from the store. And yet, for all its transcendent power, sound is material. It needs matter to exist, it needs ears and a brain and a heart to hear it, flesh to resonate through, a body to hold it. In the case of the guitar, though, this flesh has been possessed by something else. Singers inevitably lose their mojo because the throat ages, but guitarists, as if propelled by a kind of sorcery, get better with time (just look at Keith Richards). If you play the guitar, you’ve consented to let this magical, unworldly force burrow into your soul, claim it, coil up in your gut, that place that quivers, it lives there now. It changes you, from the inside out. As Robin says:</p>

<p>It’s a superpower. It’s an invisible cape. It’s a magic trick. It’s a tenuous operation of unfathomable nuance. It’s an ever-evolving stream of happy accidents. It’s a culture made up of weirdos and rule breakers and geniuses of design and beach freaks and brainiacs and cavemen and crooked little flowers. And it’s been a huge part of my identity for as long as I can remember.</p>

<p>This is why it’s so disquieting to watch a guitarist destroy his guitar; it’s like watching someone break his own arm.</p>

<p>I prefer the live versions of many NIN songs just for Robin’s guitar. Unlike the albums, it gets to snarl and growl, and in the mix, the guitar is pushed forward, loud, abrasive, the highs right on the edge of making you wince. NIN songs build for a while, with a heavy groove, a bass line that anchors as it throbs, layered soundscapes of noise, and Trent’s singing, always more melodic than you expect. By the time the guitar comes in you’re a little hypnotised, lulled into submission and singing along. <span><span><a href="https://youtu.be/B1QQi22CWYc?t=236">The guitar cracks the song open</a></span></span>. But it doesn’t wail with masturbatory rock-guitar-god moves. The way Robin plays, how he encounters this other body with his own, can be heard in his choices. There are hardly any guitar solos, in a traditional sense, in Nine Inch Nails. (This is borne in the songwriting: Trent has remarked that it matters more to him that his songs make people feel seen rather than incite a few nerds to go, ‘Cool guitar solo.’) Instead, the guitar cycles through orchestral chord progressions, bent, strident, or one riff, repeated over and over, which Robin plays with more upstrokes than down.</p>

<p>When I talk about Robin to other guitarists, I get my whole point across by describing him as ‘the motherfucker who upstrokes his way through ‘<span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=724LmPamC2A&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=118">Wish</a></span></span>.’ That song – thrashing, belligerent, with my favourite ‘fist fuck’ lyric, and one of the most hostile riffs there is – is the last place you’d think an upstroke would work, but Robin bobs his hand through it with the pluck of a polka. Josh Homme, of Queens of the Stone Age, has described upstrokes as ‘like yanking a feather out of a chicken’, noting that ‘you can’t upstroke your way to toughness’. Upstrokes are not common in rock, because downstrokes feel so good to play. They’re like stepping down hard on the gas pedal, or punctuating a sentence with an exclamation mark. (Punk is an entire genre played in downstrokes; while funk flourishes with ups, mainly because they fit so well in the pocket of the downbeat, those little breaths between the kick.) If you’ve never played guitar, I don’t know how well I can communicate the feeling of playing down. It’s orgiastic, it stomps and punches, as gratifying (I would imagine, and, O, how I love to imagine it!) as breaking the windshield of a cop car with a baseball bat. But where downstrokes are a declaration, upstrokes are an inquiry, which makes them more interesting because they complicate, rather than simplify, what you’re playing. If you think of each bar as a sentence made up of words, strung together by a series of commas, and gathering momentum as the sequence starts to coalesce into an idea, upstrokes are like a colon, setting up the thought of the downstroke to be conclusive: <em>bam</em>, <em>this </em>is what <em>that </em>means. Or, they can be a question mark, opening the sentence upward, a petition to the heavens. They ask – what goes up – and then they wait for the answer, needing the next stroke to bring it – must come down. It’s like an inhale waiting for its release.</p>

<p>Robin is a master of the upstroke in a field of players who tend toward the down, and this disregard for what is considered acceptably tough in rock music is a hallmark of his playing. He often starts the riff up, making the whole thing feel catapulted upward by its own velocity, as though he’s stepped on a landmine (like the verse riff in ‘<span><span><a href="https://youtu.be/xXksJZ7gqOg?t=7">Head Down</a></span></span>’). Even when the other musicians, including Trent, play the same riff alongside Robin with only downstrokes, <span><span><a href="https://vimeo.com/390225625">Robin goes up</a></span></span>, slapping at the strings, flicking his hand away and sideways and around his head. He often wields his whole right arm like a violin bow, tapping the strings and letting them reverberate while his left hand does hammers-on and pull-offs (<span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fJao0Mnp-20&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=3m29s">here’s a good example of this</a></span>). I guess it makes sense, if you already live in the underworld, to make moves that pull you skyward.</p>

<p>It’s not just upstrokes that make his playing what it is, though: it’s the entire universe he conjures with his right hand. The left hand is often the star for guitarists, how their value is measured. Bring up any YouTube video of a ‘best guitar solo’ and watch the camera pull a tight focus on the left as its fingers dance around the fretboard, and not stray once to the right, as though the player were one-handed. But a guitarist is only as good as his right hand, because that is where the notes being played by the left find their voice. You’re playing an E chord with your left, but is your right hand chugga-chugga-ing because you’re in a speed metal band, or is it oompa-oompa-ing because you’re in a bluegrass band? Are you screaming the phrase ‘I want to die’, or are you moaning it, mewling it, weeping? Are you saying ‘I love you’ as a plea or as a threat?</p>

<p>I can’t think of another rock guitar god of Robin’s calibre who smuggles in such weird shit with his right hand. It’s like he’s carrying a little bomb of subversive sound, letting it explode within the verse-chorus structure of a pop song. He has cited more textural guitar players as influences, with, as he puts it, ‘lots of right-hand funny business’, and says that he’s ‘always liked guitar players that play in phrases, maybe like a horn player who needs to take a breath.’ Similar to wearing clogs in an aggressive industrial rock band, playing lead guitar in terms of texture and breath situates him askance. Yep, he’s a weirdo. This could make him one of those arrogant noise boys, flagrantly displaying his skill with weird chord voicings, and drawing attention to himself via obnoxious clamours from a colossal pedal board. But I’ve never heard him cited by, or claim, this crew, and I don’t think he really fits there, simply because he doesn’t permit himself to go on too long. On the other end of the spectrum, conventional rock fans complain online that he is ‘untalented’ because he ‘cannot phrase licks properly’. In a way, these complaints can be forgiven, because he doesn’t, say, arpeggiate his way into bombastic lead guitar land with gasconading wailing. This makes it impossible to locate him in one place – he’s neither all the way in the land of avant-garde guitar-noisemaker, nor is he reigning over the territory of the rock guitar god. He has the dexterity and range to take him to both those places, but he doesn’t linger in either one. He’s here, he’s there, but then, he’s not, he’s somewhere else.</p>

<p>There are plenty of adroit, eclectic guitarists out there, but what’s different about Robin is the stages he plays on. It’s not hard to find a trickster guitarist playing in a math rock band at your local art bar. It is hard to find one, however, on a stage in front of 80,000 people, playing in a band not known for being weird. Those kinds of stages are the places where you find guitarists whose rock licks and screaming solos communicate just a couple of ideas, and almost all of them have to do with ego. When I interviewed Kelly Kalman (who runs the Facebook fan page), I asked her if she could explain her devotion to Robin. She said, when people ask, she accounts for herself by playing a four-minute live video she took of him on the 2018 tour, playing the song ‘<span><span><a href="https://vimeo.com/305404030">The Background World</a></span></span>’. This is remarkable because practically nothing happens in this video. Robin plays just a few sustained notes and hardly moves, only swaying a little. His eyes are closed and his mouth is open; sometimes he winces. He even plays a wrong note. Kelly said, ‘He’s expressing a different part of his ability than speed. It’s not, “Look at this sick solo this guy can do, no one can do that.” Maybe someone else <em>can </em>do this, but no one does.’</p>

<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="The Background World - NIN - 12/8/18" src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/305404030?dnt=1&amp;app_id=122963" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p>You can also tell a lot about a musician’s personality, or, if you will, his soul, by how he moves as he plays his instrument – the meeting of these two bodies together produces a specific sound, their shared language, as well as a specific way of being embodied within the sound. Watching how a musician moves is similar to witnessing what gets displayed when a person dances: you can guess how he fucks, how he rages, how he cries and laughs, how he sees himself and his place in the world, what he’s like when he needs something. A good guitarist will move his whole self, not just his body, while playing. Or, let his whole self be moved. Think of Jimi Hendrix’s knee-bends while he strangles the neck with hammers and pulls, almost as if standing were too strong a stance to take in the presence of such sound. Think of Prince, at the end of the bar, shooting his thumb all the way down the E string, as though he were resetting the fretboard in a kind of ablution before attacking it again. If someone moves as if they think no one’s watching, especially someone onstage in front of tens of thousands of adoring fans, something integral gets revealed about how they envision themselves in relationship to the world. It’s about what they think they deserve from it, and what, if anything, they think they ought to give it. Watching Robin play, he doesn’t bend the guitar to his will or use it as a means to showcase his talent. Instead, he makes his whole body writhe with it, like they are breathing into each other’s mouths. At, for, the guitar, he keeps vigil. A guitarist who’s consented to be possessed by the guitar is, in a way, consenting to let his entire body become the throat for the guitar’s voice. This is why his body’s movement is so important in carrying the sound, because it lets the guitar sing.</p>

<p>As guitar nerds know, the best guitarists are identifiable by their guitar tone, which is as specific and individuated as a singer’s voice. And speaking of guitar tones, oh mama (when Robin finally did that <em><strong>Rig Rundown</strong></em> interview, in 2018, it propelled me to spend hundreds of nerd hours in Reddit forum holes, not to mention hundreds of dollars, in order to mod my Tele to sound like his, but that story is for another hagiography). Robin’s tone is created by technical wizardry but shaped with an ear for the visceral; he often removes pickups from his guitars, playing only through the bridge pickup, which, rather than thinning the sound to be emaciated, hones and sharpens it, like a shaved spike of metal. He gets his guitar to sound like a rusty zipper being opened and closed (‘<span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8Lqsx2Jn4hE&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=6">Discipline</a></span>’), or a big-toothed saw scraping to life (the verse of ‘<span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mWZzEZsx66A&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=39">Letting You</a></span></span>’), or a deranged voice howling through a wire (take your pick, but <span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JKf90HrlPMM&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=5402"><span><span>the live version of ‘31 Ghosts </span><span>IV</span></span></a></span><span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JKf90HrlPMM&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=5402">’</a> </span></span>is a good one). And when he <span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4Ak15PpPX1c&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=2m57s">wahs</a></span></span>, my god – it’s like what comes through satellites in sci-fi movies when the aliens attempt communication. The distorted fuzz that Robin gets from his guitar tone feels less garage rock and more corroded, like the signal is being pumped through an old computer, spitting out digital decay. It’s partly the Les Paul, his main model, which always sounds a bit shimmery, with bright high- and mid-tones, but lots of guitarists play this guitar and none of them sound as damaged, as gone, as Robin.</p>

<p>In 2009, NIN played <em><strong>The Downward Spiral</strong></em> in its entirety to a flabbergasted crowd at NYC’s Webster Hall, two shows of the first song to the last, the only time they’ve ever done this (you can watch it on YouTube, or download it from the long-running fan website <a href="http://ninlive.com/"><span><span>NINlive.com</span></span></a>; worthy of mention is the fact that NIN are officially okay with fans audio- and video-recording their concerts, which has meant nearly every concert they’ve played since 1988 is archived). People shout at each other: ‘Oh my GOD!’ ‘I’m amazed! I’m <em>amazed</em>!’ ‘I’ve died and gone to hell!’ The version of ‘Ruiner’ at these shows, rarely played live, has one of the closest instances we get to an epic guitar solo, albeit a defiantly NIN guitar solo. After the second blasting chorus, all the sound diminishes except for the bass. <span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iooA2DPKsOw&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=165">Then Robin’s guitar comes in like a drill</a></span></span> and makes a ragged, tearing sound. He has the stage for a full minute. His body twitches like an eel, and he stretches each note out for what always feels like a few beats too long. Online wimps would gripe about the improper lick-phrasing, no doubt. He swings his feet around in stomps and kicks, just like he did fifteen years before in the ‘Pigs’ video, though they seem to be off time, swinging during silences. Toward the end, he lets the distortion deflate, muting the strings with his right hand while his left goes up the neck – a deft, if unusual, choice, which punctuates how this was not really a rock guitar solo, but something that, instead of dominating with his own control, he let slither away.</p>

<p>It has long been said by musicians that you can tell a good one by what he doesn’t play, by the notes he chooses to leave out. It reveals his understanding of the song as a structure, and how his decisions not only hold it up but give it space to breathe, let it live its own life without him. It also shows how self-confident he is as a player, knowing that he doesn’t have to blow his load over everything to leave a mark. Of all the rock gods, Robin is the only one I can think of who lets one or two notes do for him what the rest of the guys use dozens for.</p>

<p>Look at the video of GNR guitarist Richard Fortus and Robin playing an instrumental cover of Christina Aguilera’s ‘<span><span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=CnETMH1TPGU&amp;feature=youtu.be&amp;t=99">Beautiful</a></span></span>’.&nbsp;Fortus starts with a cascade of noodling. He’s a fine player, and I have nothing against him, but when Robin starts playing, you can see what is soul, and what is not. It has to do with Robin’s timing, his choices about what <i>not </i>to play. Remember that he thinks of the breaths between phrases, like a horn player, so he doesn’t fill all the space with wiggly notes, showing off how quickly he can go through scales. He lets one note sing, really sing, and there are as many soundless pauses as there are notes. At around two minutes, he starts to play rhythm so Fortus can have his turn to solo. Listen to the difference. The spacing becomes rapid and crowded, which indicates rock-guitar expertise, and draws the focus to Fortus as a player, but pulls the focus away from the song. It’s like Fortus has something to prove about himself that doesn’t include the song, whereas Robin is content to let the song be bigger than he is, which it is.</p>

<ol start="5">
<li></li>
</ol>
<p>Because he seems driven to let himself be annihilated so as to make space for something bigger, I think of the Medieval women mystics (many of whom, notably, were <em>auto</em>hagiographers), like Marguerite Porete, Julian of Norwich, and Hildegard von Bingen, who spoke of letting themselves become nothing so as to let God in. I think of Anne Carson’s essay ‘Decreation’, where she quotes Simone Weil: ‘We possess nothing in this world other than the power to say “I”. This is what we must yield up to God.’ Mysticism is different from spirituality and most religious practices in its insistence on this radical yielding. Religions, the institutions of them, are structured as hierarchies, with a divine force being worshipped and served by its disciples. Mysticism, on the other hand, is the total inverse of hierarchy: it’s structured by nothingness, and, if there is a hierarchy, it’s the idea that the first thing that needs to be obliterated is your self. But this kind of obliteration is not a harmful one. What happens during mysticism, as Anne Carson’s essay suggests, is <em>decreation</em>, rather than destruction. It has to do with love, the most daring kind of it: ‘For when an ecstatic is asked the question, <em>What is it that love dares the self to do? </em>she will answer: <em>Love dares the self to leave itself behind</em>.’</p>

<p>This yielding is what I see when I watch Robin perform. It’s not just that he yields the centre of the stage to the frontmen, and it’s not just that he plays fewer notes so as to yield to the song. It’s that, in his hermeticism, his demeanour onstage and in the press, and his choices about what and when and where to play, he seems to yield his entire self toward the goal of making music with what he can, and no more. The humbleness of him is so absolute it feels an order of magnitude bigger than someone being modest. (I’ve heard some compare him to Jonny Greenwood, another famously reclusive, brilliant guitarist standing to the side of the stage. But Greenwood’s prolific career as co-songwriter of Radiohead, not to mention all his solo film scores, and the ample adoration he enjoys among fans, put him in an arena of visibility, and choices made in favour of that visibility, that Robin is definitely not in.) A note of this yielding of the self can be found in Robin Finck’s few public statements, as when he wrote on his website, ‘i’m not interested in saving music. i’m here to serve music.’ When asked what kind of music he enjoys, Robin replied: ‘an open window. two hawks circling out there up there somewhere. the white blue sky. ana’s piano in my kitchen. early mornings. the rush of a freeway in the distance.’</p>

<p>While writing this essay, my agent urged me to contact Robin for an interview. But that’s not what I want from him, or what this essay is about. (I did email his manager, asking for his birth time, to cast his natal chart, but, obviously, never heard back.) So much of fandom is about belonging to a community of fans, but meeting Kelly was the first time in my life I’d ever met another Robin Finck fan. No, this is a hagiography, a profoundly solitary genre: I am trying to account for someone who is unaccountable. He showed me how to get to a world where language made of words can’t go; I can only report back about how he first guided me toward the gate. I can’t explain what happens once you pass through the gate, and I doubt Robin could either; here I am, coping with the unknowable. When I considered which questions I’d ask if I were given the chance, I first thought I should ask about how he gets to this other place. ‘Where do you go?’ I thought would be a good one. But then I realised that no one who’s been to that other place is able to answer such a question. If there were an answer, it would be something like, ‘Nowhere.’ A better question might be, ‘How do you stay? What ways do you manage to inhabit this material plane, with the rest of us?’ Although I imagine the answer to this would be, ‘I don’t know.’ After our interview, I sent Kelly a draft of this essay, and she highlighted this point, writing: ‘There’s not much to ask him – because that’s like asking somebody to interview music. What would you say to music if you could? I can’t think of a thing; I just have to let music be what it is, and that is what Robin is.’</p>

<p>When I suggested that he might be from another dimension, she agreed instantly, and told me how she’d once asked a friend of hers, who is a spiritual medium, to read him. The friend said, ‘I don’t mean that his body is extraterrestrial, although it is quite unusual, but his soul energy.’ (I told Kelly that I explain it by the fact that Robin shares a very specific astrological signature with Simone Weil.) Kelly pointed out that every Robin Finck fan she’s met (‘there are few of us but we’re all like this’), including me, has no sexual interest in him. She said this after I’d explained my mysticism argument, and it reminded me that mysticism, despite its deep enmeshment with the body, is often thought of as asexual. But then, I think of the queerness of communion: the desire to eat your god.</p>

<p>I worry that by writing this, I’m going to anger Robin, or make him uncomfortable. I’m certain I will never meet him, never hear from him. That’s not why I’m doing this. As a hagiographer, my task, my work, is one of devotion. Here I am, a small thing, hunched over my text, hours and hours and hours, trying to cope with the unknowability of someone who has meant this much to me. I think of another Simone Weil quote: ‘We cannot take a step toward the heavens. God crosses the universe and comes to us.’ I hope my labour, this text, this time I’ve spent, is a small gesture of care to him, and for something so much bigger than me, music itself. I’ve only ever wanted to be a humble servant to a craft: Robin, more than any other guide, has shown me how. I think of how Kelly works as a nurse. In astrology, nurses are ruled by the house of care, which is also the house of devotion and service, and includes nuns. Also known as the house of ritual and work, some astrologers, including myself, explain it as the house of magic – the ritual labour that one must do every day in order to make the most powerful magic there is, staying alive.</p>

<p>Sometimes I think there’s no difference between mysticism and magic. Both have to do with that paradoxical convergence of materiality and immateriality, when one transforms into the other, and yet, somehow, both stay intact. That disintegration I felt as a teenager, when NIN first rescued me, it transformed me totally, but my body didn’t disappear, my materiality didn’t cease to exist. It had just changed form. As death does to life. As communion does with your god. This is how magic works and how mysticism works. It’s also how music works. Without logic or language, it takes you somewhere not here, not on earth, maybe above it, maybe below, a place, or a state, where the rules and bounds of your materiality no longer hold. It defies gravity, and time, and space, and words. It gets you out of your head, your body, your self, and lets you feel, if only for a moment, somewhere, someone, some<em>thing </em>else. But despite whatever transcendence it offers, it still happens here, in your bedroom, your kitchen, your little life, within the bounds of your skin, and it changes those material conditions. It lives in your body, but then it also becomes your body. This is why it helps so much. It’s got enough magic to bring you through the gate to that other dimension, but more than that, it’s what makes being here bearable because it is ultimately your companion in this world. Take me away, for where I’m going and how I will get there, but also, for where I live, for where I always am, here, right here. Give me something I can use to feel the scintillating spark of what it means to be changed.</p>


<h4>*A version of this essay was delivered<span><span> <a href="http://davidrobertsartfoundation.com/live/curators-series-12-a-performance-by-johanna-hedva/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=http://davidrobertsartfoundation.com/live/curators-series-12-a-performance-by-johanna-hedva/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1585836512697000&amp;usg=AFQjCNExBBegPXio2q5RWIYcXXppIbZUZA">as a lecture</a></span></span>, in collaboration with DRAF, in November 2019.</h4>
						
						
							<br>
							

							<div>
								<p><h3>ABOUT THE CONTRIBUTOR</h3></p><div><p><a href="http://johannahedva.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-saferedirecturl="https://www.google.com/url?q=http://johannahedva.com/&amp;source=gmail&amp;ust=1585748300986000&amp;usg=AFQjCNHJWeRvt7V7TkjZjRVj7PHS2gzhoQ">JOHANNA HEDVA</a> is the author of the novel, <em><strong>ON HELL</strong></em>. Their collection of poems and essays, <em><strong>MINERVA THE MISCARRIAGE OF THE BRAIN</strong></em>, will be published in September 2020. Their essay, ‘Sick Woman Theory,’ published in <em><strong>MASK</strong></em> in 2016, has been translated into six languages, and their writing has appeared in <em><strong>TRIPLE CANOPY</strong></em>, <em><strong>FRIEZE</strong></em>, <em><strong>BLACK WARRIOR REVIEW</strong></em>, and <em><strong>ASIAN AMERICAN LITERARY REVIEW</strong></em>. Their work has been shown at The Institute of Contemporary Arts in London, Performance Space New York, the LA Architecture and Design Museum, and the Museum of Contemporary Art on the Moon. Their album, <em><strong>THE SUN AND THE MOON</strong></em>, was released in March 2019, and they’re currently touring <em><strong>BLACK MOON LILITH IN PISCES IN THE 4TH HOUSE</strong></em>, a doom metal guitar and voice performance influenced by Korean shamanist ritual. Their novel, <em><strong><a href="https://www.andotherstories.org/your-love-is-not-good/">YOUR LOVE IS NO GOOD</a></strong></em>&nbsp;is out in May 2023 from And Other Stories.

&nbsp;</p></div>
							




					</div>
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How many artists' careers did the Beatles kill? (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cantgetmuchhigher.com/p/how-many-artists-did-the-beatles</link>
            <guid>43373765</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 17:05:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cantgetmuchhigher.com/p/how-many-artists-did-the-beatles">https://www.cantgetmuchhigher.com/p/how-many-artists-did-the-beatles</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43373765">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.cantgetmuchhigher.com/p/how-many-artists-did-the-beatles: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: A personal YouTube frontend based on yt-dlp (250 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt</link>
            <guid>43373242</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 15:45:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt">https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43373242">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">my-yt</h2><a id="user-content-my-yt" aria-label="Permalink: my-yt" href="#my-yt"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">MYGA - make <em>you</em>tube <strong>great</strong> again</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">A clean and minimal youtube frontend, without all the ads and whistles.
Supported by yt-dlp, and optionally your local AI model, to make your youtube experience local, mindful, succint and ad free.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/preview.png"><img src="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/raw/main/preview.png" alt="preview my-yt"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Channel management/Subscriptions</li>
<li>Download videos from YouTube, using <code>yt-dlp</code> behind the scenes</li>
<li>Summarize video content using your local AI model</li>
<li>Ignore videos you don't want to watch</li>
<li>Play videos in background</li>
<li>Offline media playback</li>
<li>No dependencies (except for <code>nano-spawn</code>), HTML/CSS only, no JS frameworks on client/server side</li>
<li>Host it in your home network to playback videos on all your devices</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why?</h2><a id="user-content-why" aria-label="Permalink: Why?" href="#why"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Why not??</strong></li>
<li>wanted to get back my chronological feed, instead of a "algorithmically curated" one</li>
<li>no distractions, no ads, just videos and a clean UI</li>
<li>wanted to try integrate the so much hyped AI in a personal project</li>
<li>wanted to try out <code>yt-dlp</code></li>
<li>I am even paying for YouTube Premium, so it's not a matter of money, but a matter of control over my attention and offline experience</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Application runs on <a href="http://localhost:3000/" rel="nofollow">http://localhost:3000</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation (node.js)</h2><a id="user-content-installation-nodejs" aria-label="Permalink: Installation (node.js)" href="#installation-nodejs"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt.git
cd my-yt
npm i
# install yt-dlp, please see https://github.com/yt-dlp/yt-dlp

npm start"><pre>git clone https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt.git
<span>cd</span> my-yt
npm i
<span><span>#</span> install yt-dlp, please see https://github.com/yt-dlp/yt-dlp</span>

npm start</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation (docker)</h2><a id="user-content-installation-docker" aria-label="Permalink: Installation (docker)" href="#installation-docker"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt.git
cd my-yt
docker compose up --build -d"><pre>git clone https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt.git
<span>cd</span> my-yt
docker compose up --build -d</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Project</h2><a id="user-content-project" aria-label="Permalink: Project" href="#project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Here are some links to help you understand the project better:</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/lib/server.js">server.js</a></h3><a id="user-content-serverjs" aria-label="Permalink: server.js" href="#serverjs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Bare HTTP server</p>
<p dir="auto">Handles SSE for client updates</p>
<p dir="auto">Implements HTTP Ranged requests for video playback</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/lib/llm.js">llm.js</a></h3><a id="user-content-llmjs" aria-label="Permalink: llm.js" href="#llmjs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Makes requests using the chat completions API of LMStudio.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/lib/sse.js">sse.js</a></h3><a id="user-content-ssejs" aria-label="Permalink: sse.js" href="#ssejs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Utility functions for Server-sent events</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/lib/subtitles-summary.js">subtitles-summary.js</a></h3><a id="user-content-subtitles-summaryjs" aria-label="Permalink: subtitles-summary.js" href="#subtitles-summaryjs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Summarizes video transcript using LMStudio API</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/lib/youtube.js">youtube.js</a></h3><a id="user-content-youtubejs" aria-label="Permalink: youtube.js" href="#youtubejs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">yt-dlp wrapper to download videos, get channel videos and video information and transcript</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/blob/main/lib/repository.js">repository.js</a></h3><a id="user-content-repositoryjs" aria-label="Permalink: repository.js" href="#repositoryjs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Handles persistence of video information (set video as downloaded, summary, ignored, upserting videos, etc.)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/christian-fei/my-yt/tree/main/client">client</a></h3><a id="user-content-client" aria-label="Permalink: client" href="#client"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">dependency less, bare HTML5, CSS3 and JS for a basic frontend</p>
<p dir="auto">Handles SSE updates, interacting with the API</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">General information</h2><a id="user-content-general-information" aria-label="Permalink: General information" href="#general-information"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Currently, on the LLM side of things:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>supports basic chat completions API (LMStudio right now)
<ul dir="auto">
<li>expects <code>lms server</code> to be running on <code>http://localhost:1234</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>works with <code>meta-llama-3.1-8b-instruct</code> model</li>
<li>customization will come in the future if there's enough interest (let me know by opening an issue or pull-request)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">Download the project while you can before I get striked with a DMCA takedown request</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lemma for the Fundamental Theorem of Galois Theory (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://susam.net/lemma-for-ftgt.html</link>
            <guid>43373196</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 15:38:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://susam.net/lemma-for-ftgt.html">https://susam.net/lemma-for-ftgt.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43373196">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>By <b>Susam Pal</b> on 09 Mar 2025</p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction<a href="#introduction"></a></h2>
<p>
  This post illustrates a key lemma that is used in proving
  the <em>fundamental theorem of Galois theory</em> (FTGT).  Note that
  FTGT is not covered in this post.  The focus of this post is on
  understanding and proving this lemma only.  Here is the lemma from
  the book <em>Galois Theory</em>, 5th ed. by Stewart (2023):
</p>
<p>
    <strong>Lemma 12.1.</strong>
    <em>
      Suppose that \( L/K \) is a field extension, \( M \) is an
      intermediate field, and \( \tau \) is a \( K \)-automorphism of \(
      L.  \)  Then \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} = \tau(M)^{*}.  \)
    </em>
  </p>
<p>
  The notation \( M^* \) denotes the group of all
  \( M \)-automorphisms of \( L \) with composition as the group
  operation.  Note that Stewart writes \( \tau(M)^{*} = \tau M^*
  \tau^{-1} \) while stating the lemma but I have reversed the LHS and
  RHS to maintain consistency with the equations that appear in the
  discussion below.
</p>
<p>
  To build intuition for this lemma, I'll first present an
  illustration, followed by a proof.  The discussion below assumes
  familiarity with field extensions and field automorphisms, as
  several notations and results from these areas will be used
  implicitly without detailed justification.  This post is meant to
  serve as a set of notes on the lemma, not a comprehensive tutorial.
</p>
<h2 id="contents">Contents<a href="#contents"></a></h2>
<ul>
  <li><a href="#introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#illustration">Illustration</a>
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#concrete-example">Concrete Example</a></li>
      <li><a href="#lhs-subset-of-rhs">LHS ⊆ RHS</a></li>
      <li><a href="#lhs-superset-of-rhs">LHS ⊇ RHS</a></li>
      <li><a href="#lhs-equals-rhs">LHS = RHS</a></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="#proof">Proof</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="illustration">Illustration<a href="#illustration"></a></h2>
<h3 id="concrete-example">Concrete Example<a href="#concrete-example"></a></h3>
<p>
  Let \( L = \mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{2}, \sqrt{3}), \) \( K = \mathbb{Q}, \)
  and \( M = \mathbb{Q}(\sqrt{2}).  \)  Note that

  \begin{align*}
    L &amp;= \{ a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6} : a, b, c, d \in \mathbb{Q} \}, \\
    M &amp;= \{ k + l \sqrt{2} : k, l \in \mathbb{Q} \}.
  \end{align*}

  Now the group of \( K \)-automorphisms of \( L \) is

  \[
    K^* = \{\phi_1, \phi_2, \phi_3, \phi_4 \}
  \]

  where each \( \phi_i \) is given by

  \begin{align*}
    \phi_1 &amp;:
    a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6} \mapsto
    a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6}, \\

    \phi_2 &amp;:
    a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6} \mapsto
    a - b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} - d \sqrt{6}, \\

    \phi_3 &amp;:
    a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6} \mapsto
    a + b \sqrt{2} - c \sqrt{3} - d \sqrt{6}, \\

    \phi_4 &amp;:
    a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6} \mapsto
    a - b \sqrt{2} - c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6}.
  \end{align*}

  Then \( M^* = \{ \phi_1, \phi_3 \}.  \)  Let \( \tau = \phi_2.  \)
  Then

  \begin{align*}
  \tau(M)
    &amp;= \{ \tau(x) : x \in \mathbb{M} \} \\
    &amp;= \{ \tau(k + l \sqrt{2}) : k, l \in \mathbb{Q} \} \\
    &amp;= \{ k - l \sqrt{2} : k, l \in \mathbb{Q} \}.
  \end{align*}

  Note that in this case we ended up with \( \tau(M) = M \) but we
  will be careful not to utilise this fact.  We will ensure that the
  steps below work without assuming \( \tau(M) = M.  \)  Next we find

  \begin{equation}
    \tau(M)^* = \{ \phi_1, \phi_3 \}.
    \label{eq-tau-m-ast}
  \end{equation}

  Now

  \begin{align*}
    \tau M^* \tau^{-1}
    &amp;= \{ \tau \gamma \tau^{-1} : \gamma \in {M^*} \} \\
    &amp;= \{ \tau \phi_1 \tau^{-1}, \tau \phi_3 \tau^{-1} \}.
  \end{align*}

  Let us now find out how each element of \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \)
  transforms the elements of \( L.  \)  For all \( a + b \sqrt{2} + c
  \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6} \in L, \) we get

  \begin{align*}
    (\tau \phi_1 \tau^{-1})(a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6})
    &amp;= (\tau \phi_1)(a - b\sqrt{2} + c\sqrt{3} - d\sqrt{6}) \\
    &amp;= \tau (a - b\sqrt{2} + c\sqrt{3} - d\sqrt{6}) \\
    &amp;= a + b\sqrt{2} + c\sqrt{3} + d\sqrt{6}).
  \end{align*}

  Therefore

  \[
    \tau \phi_1 \tau^{-1} = \phi_1.
  \]

  Similarly,

  \begin{align*}
    (\tau \phi_3 \tau^{-1})(a + b \sqrt{2} + c \sqrt{3} + d \sqrt{6})
    &amp;= (\tau \phi_3)(a - b\sqrt{2} + c\sqrt{3} - d\sqrt{6}) \\
    &amp;= \tau (a - b\sqrt{2} - c\sqrt{3} + d\sqrt{6}) \\
    &amp;= a + b\sqrt{2} - c\sqrt{3} - d\sqrt{6}.
  \end{align*}

  Therefore

  \[
    \tau \phi_3 \tau^{-1} = \phi_3.
  \]

  We have shown that

  \begin{equation}
    \tau M^* \tau^{-1} = \{ \phi_1, \phi_3 \}.
    \label{eq-tau-coset}
  \end{equation}

  From \eqref{eq-tau-m-ast} and \eqref{eq-tau-coset} we see that

  \[
     \tau M^* \tau^{-1} = \tau(M)^*.
  \]

  Since we are working with a concrete example of \( \tau \) here, we
  know exactly how it behaves, so we succeeded in demonstrating the
  above equality.  However, in a general proof, \( \tau \) is going to
  be an arbitrary \( K \)-automorphism of \( L, \) so we cannot know
  exactly how it behaves and as a result, we cannot obtain the above
  equation directly.  Therefore, in a general proof, we we will first
  show that \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \subseteq \tau(M)^* \) and then we
  will show that \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \supseteq \tau(M)^* \) in order
  to prove the above equation.
</p>
<h3 id="lhs-subset-of-rhs">LHS ⊆ RHS<a href="#lhs-subset-of-rhs"></a></h3>
<p>
  Once again, let us see how each element of \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \)
  transforms the elements of \( \tau(M).  \)  Note that this time we
  are not going to examine how they transform arbitrary elements of \(
  L.  \)  We are only going to see how they transform the elements of
  \( \tau(M).  \)  For all \( k - l \sqrt{2} \in \tau(M), \) we get

  \begin{align*}
    (\tau \phi_1 \tau^{-1})(k - l \sqrt{2})
    &amp;= (\tau \phi_1)(k + l \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= \tau(k + l \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= k - l \sqrt{2}.
  \end{align*}

  Similarly, for all \( k - l \sqrt{2} \in \tau(M), \) we get

  \begin{align*}
    (\tau \phi_3 \tau^{-1})(k - l \sqrt{2})
    &amp;= (\tau \phi_3)(k + l \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= \tau(k + l \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= k - l \sqrt{2}.
  \end{align*}

  Note above that both \( \phi_1 \) and \( \phi_3 \) fix \( k + l
  \sqrt{2} \in M \) because \( \phi_1, \phi_2 \in M^*, \) the set of
  \( M \)-automorphisms of \( L.  \)  This detail will be used in the
  general proof.
</p>
<p>
  Since both \( \tau \phi_1 \tau^{-1} \) and
  \( \tau \phi_3 \tau^{-1} \) fix the elements of \( \tau(M), \) they
  are both \( \tau(M) \)-automorphisms of \( L.  \)  Therefore \( \tau
  M^* \tau^{-1} \subseteq \tau(M)^{*}.  \)
</p>
<h3 id="lhs-superset-of-rhs">LHS ⊇ RHS<a href="#lhs-superset-of-rhs"></a></h3>
<p>
  Consider the set \( \tau^{-1} \tau(M)^* \tau \) and examine how its
  elements transform the elements of \( M.  \)  For all \( k + l
  \sqrt{2} \in M, \) we get

  \begin{align*}
    (\tau^{-1} \phi_1 \tau)(k + l \sqrt{2})
    &amp;= (\tau^{-1} \phi_1)(k - \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= \tau^{-1}(k - \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= k + l \sqrt{2}.
  \end{align*}

  Similarly, for all \( k + l \sqrt{2} \in M, \) we get

  \begin{align*}
    (\tau^{-1} \phi_3 \tau)(k + l \sqrt{2})
    &amp;= (\tau^{-1} \phi_3)(k - \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= \tau^{-1}(k - \sqrt{2}) \\
    &amp;= k + l \sqrt{2}.
  \end{align*}

  Here both \( \phi_1 \) and \( \phi_3 \) fix \( k - l \sqrt{2} \in
  \tau(M) \) because \( \phi_1, \phi_2 \in \tau(M)^*, \) the set of \(
  \tau(M) \)-automorphisms of \( L.  \)
</p>
<p>
  Since both \( \tau^{-1} \phi_1 \tau \) and
  \( \tau^{-1} \phi_3 \tau \) fix the elements of \( M, \) they are
  both \( M \)-automorphisms of \( L.  \)  Therefore \( \tau^{-1}
  \tau(M)^* \tau \subseteq M^* \) which implies \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1}
  \supseteq \tau(M)^*.  \)
</p>
<h3 id="lhs-equals-rhs">LHS = RHS<a href="#lhs-equals-rhs"></a></h3>
<p>
  The previous two sections complete the illustration of the lemma
  with the chosen example.  We have shown that \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1}
  \subseteq \tau(M)^{*} \) and \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \supseteq
  \tau(M)^*.  \)  Therefore \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} = \tau(M)^*.  \)
</p>
<h2 id="proof">Proof<a href="#proof"></a></h2>
<p>
  The ideas presented in the previous sections will now be extended to
  formulate a general proof.  For clarity, the lemma is stated once
  again below before proceeding with the proof.
</p>
<p>
  <strong>Lemma 12.1.</strong>
  <em>
    Suppose that \( L/K \) is a field extension, \( M \) is an
    intermediate field, and \( \tau \) is a \( K \)-automorphism of \(
    L.  \)  Then \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} = \tau(M)^{*}.  \)
  </em>
</p>
<p>
  <em>Proof.</em>

  For all \( \gamma \in M^*, \) \( x' \in \tau(M), \) we use the
  notation \( x = \tau^{-1}(x') \in M \) and get

  \[
    (\tau \gamma \tau^{-1})(x') = (\tau \gamma)(x) = \tau(x) = x'.
  \]

  In the second equality above, we have used the fact that \( \gamma
  \in M^* \) which implies that \( \gamma \) is an
  \( M \)-automorphism of \( L \) which allows us to conclude that \(
  \gamma(x) = x.  \)  Since every \( \tau \gamma \tau^{-1} \in \tau M^*
  \tau^{-1} \) fixes all elements \( x' \in \tau(M), \) each \( \tau
  \gamma \tau^{-1} \) must be a \( \tau(M) \)-automorphism of \( L.  \)
  Thus \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \subseteq \tau(M)^*.  \)
</p>
<p>
  Similarly, for all \( \gamma' \in \tau(M)^*, \) \( x \in M, \) we
  use the notation \( x' = \tau(x) \in \tau(M) \) and get

  \[
  (\tau^{-1} \gamma' \tau)(x) = (\tau^{-1} \gamma')(x') = \tau^{-1}(x') = x.
  \]

  In the second equality above, we have used the fact that \( \gamma'
  \in \tau(M)^* \) which implies that \( \gamma' \) is an
  \( \tau(M) \)-automorphism of \( L \) which allows us to conclude
  that \( \gamma'(x') = x'.  \)  Since every \( \tau^{-1} \gamma' \tau
  \in \tau^{-1} \tau(M)^* \tau \) fixes all elements \( x \in M, \)
  each \( \tau^{-1} \gamma' \tau \) must be an \( M \)-automorphism of
  \( L.  \)  Thus \( \tau^{-1} \tau(M)^* \tau \subseteq M^*.  \)  This
  implies \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \supseteq \tau(M)^*.  \)
</p>
<p>
  We have shown that \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \subseteq \tau(M)^* \) and
  \( \tau M^* \tau^{-1} \supseteq \tau(M)^*.  \)  Therefore \( \tau M^*
  \tau^{-1} = \tau(M)^*.  \)
</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Milk Kanban (363 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://brodzinski.com/2025/03/milk-kanban.html</link>
            <guid>43373157</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 15:32:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://brodzinski.com/2025/03/milk-kanban.html">https://brodzinski.com/2025/03/milk-kanban.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43373157">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">

<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="580" src="https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/kanban-1-1024x580.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/kanban-1-1024x580.jpg 1024w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/kanban-1-400x227.jpg 400w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/kanban-1-768x435.jpg 768w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/kanban-1-1536x870.jpg 1536w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/kanban-1-2048x1161.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>When people say Kanban, they tend to think of a specific set of practices. Whiteboards &amp; sticky notes (both almost universally virtual). Tasks moving through columns that represent workflow. Every now and then, WIP limits even.</p>



<p>As often as we do it with other things, it reduces a broader principle to a set of oversimplified techniques, which, in turn, tend to underdeliver in many contexts.</p>



<h2>Kanban</h2>



<p>In its original meaning, Kanban represented a visual signal. The thing that communicated, well, something. It might have been a need, option, availability, capacity, request, etc.</p>



<p>In our Kanban systems, the actual Kanban is a sticky note.</p>



<p>It represents work, and given its closest environment (board, columns, other stickies, visual decorators), it communicates what needs, or needs not, to be done.</p>



<p>If it’s yellow, it’s a regular feature. If there’s a blocker on it, it requests focus. If there’s a long queue of neighbors, it suggests flow inefficiency. If it’s a column named “ready for…” it communicates available work and/or handoff.</p>



<p>A visual signal all the way.</p>



<h2>Visual Signals</h2>



<p>Let’s decouple ourselves from the most standard Kanban board design. Let’s forget columns, sticky notes, and all that jazz.</p>



<p>Enters Kasia, our office manager at Lunar. One of the many things Kasia takes care of is making sure we don’t run out of kitchen supplies. The tricky part is that when you don’t drink milk yourself, it becomes a pain to check the cupboard with milk reserves every now and then to ensure we’re stocked.</p>



<p>Then, one day, I found this.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="681" src="https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/milk-kanban-1-1024x681.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/milk-kanban-1-1024x681.jpg 1024w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/milk-kanban-1-400x266.jpg 400w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/milk-kanban-1-768x510.jpg 768w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/milk-kanban-1-1536x1021.jpg 1536w, https://brodzinski.com/wp-content/uploads/milk-kanban-1-2048x1361.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>A simple index card taped to the last milk carton in a row stating, “Bring me to Kasia.” That’s it.</p>



<p>In the context, it really says that:</p>



<ul>
<li>we’re running out of (specific kind of) milk</li>



<li>we want to restock soon</li>



<li>there’s enough time to make an order (we don’t drink that much of cappuccinos and macchiatos)</li>
</ul>



<p>But it’s just a visual signal. Kanban at its very core.</p>



<h2>Simplicity is the King</h2>



<p>What Kasia designed is a perfect Kanban system. It relies on visual signals, which are put in the context. Even better, unlike most Kanban boards I see across teams, the system is self-explanatory. Everything one needs to know is written on the index card.</p>



<p>That’s, by the way, another characteristic of a good Kanban system. It should be as simple as possible (but not simpler). Our workflow representations <a href="https://brodzinski.com/2011/01/kanban-board-keep-it-simple.html">tend to get more and more complex over time by themselves</a>; we don’t need to make them so from the outset.</p>



<p>It’s a safe assumption that, almost always, there’s a simpler visualization that would work just as well. We, process designers, often fall into the trap of overengineering our tools.</p>



<p>And it’s a healthy wake-up call when someone who knows close to nothing about our fancy stuff designs a system that we would unlikely think of. One that is a perfect implementation of the original spirit, even if it doesn’t follow any of the common techniques.</p>



<p>Because it’s all about <a href="https://brodzinski.com/2014/08/practices-principles-values.html">principles, not practices</a>.</p>



<p>That’s what we can learn from Milk Kanban.</p>




				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[For climate and livelihoods, Africa bets big on solar mini-grids (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://knowablemagazine.org/content/article/technology/2025/nigeria-bets-on-solar-minigrids-for-climate-livelihood</link>
            <guid>43372729</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 14:24:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://knowablemagazine.org/content/article/technology/2025/nigeria-bets-on-solar-minigrids-for-climate-livelihood">https://knowablemagazine.org/content/article/technology/2025/nigeria-bets-on-solar-minigrids-for-climate-livelihood</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43372729">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<h2>Republish</h2>
<div>
<p>Thank you for your interest in republishing! This HTML is pre-formatted to adhere to our <a href="https://knowablemagazine.org/page/republish">guidelines</a>, which include: Crediting both the author and Knowable Magazine; preserving all hyperlinks; including the canonical link to the original article in the article metadata. Article text (including the headline) may not be edited without prior permission from Knowable Magazine staff. Photographs and illustrations are not included in this license. Please see our <a href="https://knowablemagazine.org/republish">full guidelines</a> for more information.</p>
</div>

<p><a href="#">close</a>
</p></div><p>http://instance.metastore.ingenta.com/content/article/technology/2025/nigeria-bets-on-solar-minigrids-for-climate-livelihood</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Arbitrary-Scale Super-Resolution with Neural Heat Fields (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://therasr.github.io/</link>
            <guid>43371583</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Mar 2025 10:39:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://therasr.github.io/">https://therasr.github.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43371583">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://therasr.github.io/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>