<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 23:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Godot founders had desperately hoped Unity wouldn't 'blow up' (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.gamedeveloper.com/programming/godot-founders-had-desperately-hoped-unity-wouldn-t-blow-up-</link>
            <guid>41468667</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 18:41:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.gamedeveloper.com/programming/godot-founders-had-desperately-hoped-unity-wouldn-t-blow-up-">https://www.gamedeveloper.com/programming/godot-founders-had-desperately-hoped-unity-wouldn-t-blow-up-</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41468667">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.gamedeveloper.com/programming/godot-founders-had-desperately-hoped-unity-wouldn-t-blow-up-: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Show HN: Infinity – Realistic AI characters that can speak (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41467704</link>
            <guid>41467704</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 16:47:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41467704">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41467704: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nginx has moved to GitHub (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/ITL3AOQSAJANFJXMM3VOVOIGOUADWFFK.html</link>
            <guid>41466963</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 15:17:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/ITL3AOQSAJANFJXMM3VOVOIGOUADWFFK.html">https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/ITL3AOQSAJANFJXMM3VOVOIGOUADWFFK.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41466963">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
   
    <b>Roman Arutyunyan</b> 
    <a href="mailto:nginx-announce%40nginx.org?Subject=Re%3A%20%5Bnginx-announce%5D%20NGINX%20has%20moved%20to%20Github%21&amp;In-Reply-To=%3CF7C066E5-1C8C-4E86-B936-273C9F67E8AB%40nginx.com%3E" title="[nginx-announce] NGINX has moved to Github!">arut at nginx.com
       </a><br>
    <i>Fri Sep  6 15:11:21 UTC 2024</i>
    <ul>
        <li>Previous message (by thread): <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/UUOCLLONPR6244YQYU65PO5LB7JDYCWM.html">[nginx-announce] nginx security advisory (CVE-2024-7347)
</a></li>
        
         <li> <b>Messages sorted by:</b> 
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/date.html#357">[ date ]</a>
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/thread.html#357">[ thread ]</a>
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/subject.html#357">[ subject ]</a>
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/author.html#357">[ author ]</a>
         </li>
       </ul>
    <hr>  
<!--beginarticle-->
<pre>Hello from NGINX!

Today we're thrilled to announce that the official NGINX Open Source development
repository has moved from Mercurial to GitHub [1][2][3], where we will now start
accepting contributions in the form of Pull Requests. Additionally, starting
today, we will begin accepting bugs reports, feature requests and enhancements
directly through GitHub, under the "Issues" tab. Moreover, we've moved our
community forums to the GitHub "Discussions" area, where you will now be able
to engage in conversation, ask, and answer questions.

Important: to report a security vulnerability, please follow our security
policy [4].

We understand that changes like these may require adjustment, so to give you
more time, we will continue accepting patches and provide community support
via mailing lists until December 31st, 2024.

We believe these changes will serve to centralize, modernize and expand access
to NGINX development and communities. They represent our continued commitment
to open source, as outlined in the blog post [5]. Most of all, we can't wait to
see all of your contributions, discussions and feedback, as we move into this
next chapter for NGINX.

[1] <a href="https://github.com/nginx/nginx">https://github.com/nginx/nginx</a>
[2] <a href="https://github.com/nginx/nginx-tests">https://github.com/nginx/nginx-tests</a>
[3] <a href="https://github.com/nginx/nginx.org">https://github.com/nginx/nginx.org</a>
[4] <a href="https://github.com/nginx/nginx/blob/master/SECURITY.md">https://github.com/nginx/nginx/blob/master/SECURITY.md</a>
[5] <a href="https://www.f5.com/company/blog/nginx/meetup-recap-nginxs-commitments-to-the-open-source-community">https://www.f5.com/company/blog/nginx/meetup-recap-nginxs-commitments-to-the-open-source-community</a>


On behalf of the NGINX Team,

Roman Arutyunyan
<a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/mailman/listinfo/nginx-announce">arut at nginx.com</a>
</pre>

<!--endarticle-->
    <hr>
    <ul>
        <!--threads-->
	<li>Previous message (by thread): <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/UUOCLLONPR6244YQYU65PO5LB7JDYCWM.html">[nginx-announce] nginx security advisory (CVE-2024-7347)
</a></li>
	
         <li> <b>Messages sorted by:</b> 
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/date.html#357">[ date ]</a>
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/thread.html#357">[ thread ]</a>
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/subject.html#357">[ subject ]</a>
              <a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/pipermail/nginx-announce/2024/author.html#357">[ author ]</a>
         </li>
       </ul>

<hr>
<a href="https://mailman.nginx.org/mailman/listinfo/nginx-announce">More information about the nginx-announce
mailing list</a><br>

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Wealthfolio: A Private, Open-Source Investment Tracker (589 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://wealthfolio.app</link>
            <guid>41465735</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 12:56:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://wealthfolio.app">https://wealthfolio.app</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41465735">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://wealthfolio.app: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Effects of Gen AI on High Skilled Work: Experiments with Software Developers (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4945566</link>
            <guid>41465081</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 11:21:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4945566">https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=4945566</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41465081">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

	
	
		
	

	
	
		
		
	

	
	

	
	
	
	
	
    
        
    
	

	
	<p>
		
		
			<span>22 Pages</span>
		
		

		<span>Posted: 5 Sep 2024</span>
		
		
		
	</p>
	
		
	
	
	
	
	



	
	
	
	
		
		
	
	
		
			<p>Date Written: September 03, 2024</p>
		
	

	
	
		
		
	

	
	
		
	
	<div>
		<h3>Abstract</h3>
		<p>This study evaluates the impact of generative AI on software developer productivity by analyzing data from three randomized controlled trials conducted at Microsoft, Accenture, and an anonymous Fortune 100 electronics manufacturing company. These field experiments, which were run by the companies as part of their ordinary course of business, provided a randomly selected subset of developers with access to GitHub Copilot, an AI-based coding assistant that suggests intelligent code completions. Though each separate experiment is noisy, combined across all three experiments and 4,867 software developers, our analysis reveals a 26.08% increase (SE: 10.3%) in the number of completed tasks among developers using the AI tool. Notably, less experienced developers showed higher adoption rates and greater productivity gains. </p>
	</div>
	

	<center>
		
		


	

	
	

		
		

	
	


	</center>

	
	
	
		
	
	
	

	
	
	

	
    
    
	

	
	
		<p><strong>JEL Classification:</strong> J24, O32, O33</p>
	
	

	
	

























    	
	
	
	
   	
	
	
	
	
	            
	















	











    
    










    
    
    
    
















	



    




	<p>
		<strong>Suggested Citation:</strong>
		<a href="#">Suggested Citation<i></i></a>
	</p>
	<p>
		
			Cui,  Zheyuan and Demirer,  Mert and Jaffe,  Sonia and Musolff,  Leon and Peng,  Sida and Salz,  Tobias, The Effects of Generative AI on High Skilled Work: Evidence from Three Field Experiments with Software Developers (September 03, 2024).  Available at SSRN: <a href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=4945566" target="_blank">https://ssrn.com/abstract=4945566</a> or <a href="https://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4945566" target="_blank">http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.4945566 </a>
		
	</p>
	

	
	
	

	
	

	
	
		
	

	
	
	
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Swift is a more convenient Rust (226 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://blog.namangoel.com/swift-is-the-more-convenient-rust</link>
            <guid>41464371</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 09:10:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://blog.namangoel.com/swift-is-the-more-convenient-rust">http://blog.namangoel.com/swift-is-the-more-convenient-rust</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41464371">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="container">
  <article id="kf5pNR8Jwc8n6dk7svFLSk">
	<time datetime="2023-10-02">October  2, 2023</time>
  <h2>
    <a href="http://blog.namangoel.com/swift-is-the-more-convenient-rust">Swift is a more convenient Rust</a>
  </h2>
	<p>I’ve been learning Rust lately. </p>

<p>Rust is one of the most loved languages out there, is fast, and has an amazing community. Rust invented the concept of ownership as a solution memory management issues without resorting to something slower like Garbage Collection or Reference Counting. But, when you don’t need to be quite as low level, it gives you utilities such as <code>Rc</code>, <code>Arc</code> and <code>Cow</code> to do reference counting and “clone-on-right” in your code. And, when you need to go lower-level still, you can use the <code>unsafe</code> system  and access raw C pointers.</p>

<p>Rust also has a bunch of awesome features from functional languages like tagged enums, match expressions, first class functions and a powerful type system with generics.</p>

<p>Rust has an LLVM-based compiler which lets it compile to native code and WASM.</p>

<p>I’ve also been doing a bit of Swift programming for a couple of years now. And the more I learn Rust, the more I see a reflection of Swift. (I know that Swift stole a lot of ideas from Rust, I’m talking about my own perspective here).</p>

<p>Swift, too, has awesome features from functional languages like tagged enums, match expressions and first-class functions. It too has a very powerful type system with generics.</p>

<p>Swift too gives you complete type-safety without a garbage collector. By default, everything is a value type with “copy-on-write” semantics. But when you need extra speed you can opt into an ownership system and “move” values to avoid copying. And if you need to go even lower level, you can use the unsafe system and access raw C pointers.</p>

<p>Swift has an LLVM-based compiler which lets it compile to native code and WASM.</p>
<h2 id="deja-vu_2">Deja Vu? <a href="#deja-vu_2">#</a></h2>
<p>You’re probably feeling like you just read the same paragraphs twice. This is no accident. Swift is extremely similar to Rust and has most of the same feature-set. But there is a very big difference is <em>perspective</em>. If you consider the default memory model, this will start to make a lot of sense.</p>
<h2 id="rust-is-bottomup-swift-is-topdown_2">Rust is bottom-up, Swift is top-down. <a href="#rust-is-bottomup-swift-is-topdown_2">#</a></h2>
<p>Rust is a low-level systems language at heart, but it gives you the tools to go higher level. Swift starts at a high level and gives you the ability to go low-level.</p>

<p>The most obvious example of this is the memory management model. Swift use value-types by default with <code>copy-on-write</code> semantics. This is the equivalent of using <code>Cow&lt;&gt;</code> for all your values in Rust. But defaults matter. Rust makes it easy to use “moved” and “borrowed” values but requires extra ceremony to use <code>Cow&lt;&gt;</code> values as you need to “unwrap” them <code>.as_mutable()</code> to actually use the value within. Swift makes these Copy-on-Write values easy to use and instead requires extra ceremony to use borrowing and moving instead. Rust is faster by default, Swift is simpler and easier by default.</p>
<h2 id="swift-takes-rust39s-ideas-and-hides-them-in-c_2">Swift takes Rust’s ideas and hides them in C-like syntax. <a href="#swift-takes-rust39s-ideas-and-hides-them-in-c_2">#</a></h2>
<p>Swift’s syntax is a masterclass in taking awesome functional language concepts and hiding them in C-like syntax to trick the developers into accepting them.</p>

<p>Consider <code>match</code> statements. This is what a match statement looks like in Rust:</p>

<pre><code>enum Coin {
    Penny,
    Nickel,
    Dime,
    Quarter,
}

fn value_in_cents(coin: Coin) -&gt; u8 {
    match coin {
        Coin::Penny =&gt; 1,
        Coin::Nickel =&gt; 5,
        Coin::Dime =&gt; 10,
        Coin::Quarter =&gt; 25,
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Here’s how that same code would be written in Swift:</p>

<pre><code>enum Coin {
    case penny
    case nickel
    case dime
    case quarter
}
func valueInCents(coin: Coin) -&gt; Int {
    switch coin {
    case .penny: 1
    case .nickel: 5
    case .dime: 10
    case .quarter: 25
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Swift doesn’t have a <code>match</code> statement or expression. It has a <code>switch</code> statement that developers are already familiar with. Except this <code>switch</code> statement is actually not a <code>switch</code> statement at all. It’s an expression. It doesn’t “fallthrough”. It does pattern matching. It’s just a <code>match</code> expression with a different name and syntax.</p>

<p>In fact, Swift treats <code>enums</code> as more than <em>just</em> types and lets you put methods directly on it:</p>

<pre><code>enum Coin {
    case penny
    case nickel
    case dime
    case quarter

    func valueInCents() -&gt; Int {
        switch self {
        case .penny: 1
        case .nickel: 5
        case .dime: 10
        case .quarter: 25
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>
<h3 id="optional-types_3">Optional Types <a href="#optional-types_3">#</a></h3>
<p>Rust doesn’t have <code>null</code>, but it does have <code>None</code>. Swift has a <code>nil</code>, but it’s really just a <code>None</code> in hiding. Instead of an <code>Option&lt;T&gt;</code>, Swift let’s you use <code>T?</code>, but the compiler still forces you to check that the value is not <code>nil</code> before you can use it.</p>

<p>You get the same safety with more convenience since you can do this in Swift with an optional type:</p>

<pre><code>let val: T?

if let val {
  // val is now of type `T`.
}
</code></pre>

<p>Also, you’re not forced to wrap every value with a <code>Some(val)</code> before returning it. The Swift compiler takes care of that for you. A <code>T</code> will transparently be converted into a <code>T?</code> when needed.</p>
<h3 id="error-handling_3">Error Handling <a href="#error-handling_3">#</a></h3>
<p>Rust doesn’t have <code>try-catch</code>. Instead it has a <code>Result</code> type which contains the success and error types.</p>

<p>Swift doesn’t have a <code>try-catch</code> either, but it does have <code>do-catch</code> and you have to use <code>try</code> before calling a function that could throw. Again, this is just deception for those developers coming from C-like languages. Swift’s error handling works exactly like Rust’s behind the scenes, but it is hidden in a clever, familiar syntax. </p>

<pre><code>func usesErrorThrowingFunction() throws {
  let x = try thisFnCanThrow()
}

func handlesErrors() {
  do {
    let x = try thisFnCanThrow()
  } catch err {
    // handle the `err` here.
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is very similar to how Rust let’s you use <code>?</code> at the end of statements to automatically forward errors, but you don’t have to wrap your success values in <code>Ok()</code>.</p>
<h2 id="rust39s-compiler-catches-problems-swift39s-co_2">Rust’s compiler catches problems. Swift’s compiler solves some of them <a href="#rust39s-compiler-catches-problems-swift39s-co_2">#</a></h2>
<p>There are many common problems that Rust’s compiler will catch at compile time and even suggest solutions for you. The example that portrays this well is self-referencing enums.</p>

<p>Consider an enum that represents a tree. Since, it is a recursive type, Rust will force you to use something like <code>Box&lt;&gt;</code> for referencing a type within itself.</p>

<pre><code>enum TreeNode&lt;T&gt; {
    Leaf(T),
    Branch(Vec&lt;Box&lt;TreeNode&lt;T&gt;&gt;&gt;),
}
</code></pre>

<p>(You could also us <code>Box&lt;Vec&lt;TreeNode&lt;T&gt;&gt;&gt;</code> instead)</p>

<p>This makes the problem explicit and forces you to deal with it directly. Swift is a little more, <em>automatic</em>.</p>

<pre><code>indirect enum TreeNode&lt;T&gt; {
    case leaf(T)
    case branch([TreeNode&lt;T&gt;])
}
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Note</strong>: that you still have to annotate this <code>enum</code> with the <code>indirect</code> keyword to indicate that it is recursive. But once you’ve done that, Swift’s compiler takes care of the rest. You don’t have to think about <code>Box&lt;&gt;</code> or <code>Rc&lt;&gt;</code>. The values just work normally.</p>
<h2 id="swift-is-less-quotpurequot_2">Swift is less “pure” <a href="#swift-is-less-quotpurequot_2">#</a></h2>
<p>Swift was designed to replace Objective-C and needed to be able to interface with existing code. So, it has made a lot of pragmatic choices that makes it a much less “pure” and “minimalist” language. Swift is a pretty big language compared to Rust and has many more features built-in. However, Swift is designed with “progressive disclosure” in mind which means that just as soon as you think you’ve learned the language a little more of the iceberg pops out of the water.</p>

<p>Here are just <em>some</em> of the language features:</p>

<ul>
<li>Classes / Inhertence</li>
<li>async-await</li>
<li>async-sequences</li>
<li>actors</li>
<li>getters and setters</li>
<li>lazy properties</li>
<li>property wrappers</li>
<li>Result Builders (for building tree-like structures. e.g. HTML / SwiftUI)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="convenience-has-its-costs_2">Convenience has its costs <a href="#convenience-has-its-costs_2">#</a></h2>
<p>Swift is a far easier language to get started and productive with. The syntax is more familiar and a lot more is done for you automatically. But this really just makes Swift a higher-level language and it comes with the same tradeoffs.</p>

<p>By default, a Rust program is much faster than a Swift program. This is because Rust is fast by default, and <em>lets</em> you be slow, while Swift is easy by default and <em>lets</em> you be fast.</p>

<p>Based on this, I would say both languages have their uses. Rust is better for systems and embedded programming. It’s better for writing compilers and browser engines (Servo) and it’s better for writing entire operating systems.</p>

<p>Swift is better for writing UI and servers and some parts of compilers and operating systems. Over time I expect to see the overlap get bigger.</p>

  <figure id="kudo_kf5pNR8Jwc8n6dk7svFLSk">
    <a href="#kudo">
      
    </a>
    <p>198</p>
    <p>Kudos</p>
  </figure>
  <figure id="kudo_side_kf5pNR8Jwc8n6dk7svFLSk">
    <a href="#kudo">
      
    </a>
    <p>198</p>
    <p>Kudos</p>
  </figure>
</article>

</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Study: Playing D&D helps autistic players in social interactions (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/science/2024/09/study-playing-dungeons-dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions/</link>
            <guid>41464347</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 09:05:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/science/2024/09/study-playing-dungeons-dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions/">https://arstechnica.com/science/2024/09/study-playing-dungeons-dragons-helps-autistic-players-in-social-interactions/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41464347">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <header>
            <h4>
      We can be heroes    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">"I can make a character quite different from how I interact with people in real life."</h2>
                    </header>
        <div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/dungeons1-800x543.jpg" alt="A Dungeons &amp; Dragons game session featuring a map, miniatures, dice, and character sheets">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/dungeons1.jpg" data-height="815" data-width="1200">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Researchers say that <em>Dungeons &amp; Dragons</em> can give autistic players a way to engage in low-risk social interactions.</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 5:single/related:04b3d803d4cd1281478d87cb93ce04f4 --><!-- empty -->
<p>Since its introduction in the 1970s, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dungeons_%26_Dragons"><em>Dungeons &amp; Dragons</em></a> has become one of the most influential <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tabletop_role-playing_game">tabletop role-playing games</a> (TRPGs) in popular culture, featuring heavily in <em>Stranger Things</em>, for example, and spawning <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2023/03/review-dd-honor-among-thieves-is-a-worthy-homage-to-the-classic-rpg/">a blockbuster movie</a> released last year. Over the last decade or so, researchers have turned their focus more heavily to the ways in which <em>D&amp;D</em> and other TRPGs <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10803-024-06408-0">can help</a> people with autism form healthy social connections, in part because the gaming environment offers clear rules around social interactions. According to the authors of a <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/10.1177/13623613241275260">new paper</a> published in the journal Autism, <em>D&amp;D</em> helped boost players' confidence with autism, giving them a strong sense of kinship or belonging, among other benefits.</p>
<p>“There are many myths and misconceptions about autism, with some of the biggest suggesting that those with it aren’t socially motivated, or don’t have any imagination," <a href="https://www.plymouth.ac.uk/news/dungeons-and-dragons-can-help-autistic-people-gain-confidence-and-find-their-inner-hero">said co-author Gray Atherton</a>, a psychologist at the University of Plymouth. "<em>Dungeons &amp; Dragons</em> goes against all that, centering around working together in a team, all of which takes place in a completely imaginary environment. Those taking part in our study saw the game as a breath of fresh air, a chance to take on a different persona and share experiences outside of an often challenging reality. That sense of escapism made them feel incredibly comfortable, and many of them said they were now trying to apply aspects of it in their daily lives.”</p>
<p>Prior research has shown that autistic people are more likely to feel lonely, have smaller social networks, and often experience anxiety in social settings. Their desire for social connection leads many to "mask" their neurodivergent traits in public for fear of being rejected as a result of social gaffes. "I think every autistic person has had multiple instances of social rejection and loss of relationships," one of the study participants said when Atherton et al. interviewed them about their experiences. "You've done something wrong. You don't know what it is. They don't tell you, and you find out when you've been just, you know, left shunned in relationships, left out.... It's traumatic."</p>                                                                        
                                                                                
<p>TPRGs like <em>D&amp;D</em> can serve as a social lubricant for autistic players, according to a <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/381885971_We've_All_Come_Together_A_Board-Gaming_Approach_for_Working_with_Autistic_People">year-long study</a> published earlier this year co-authored by Atherton, because there is less uncertainty around how to behave in-game—unlike the plethora of unwritten social rules that make navigating social settings so anxiety-inducing. Such games immerse players in a fantastical world where they create their characters with unique backstories, strengths, and weaknesses and cooperate with others to complete campaigns. A game master guides the overall campaign, but the game itself evolves according to the various choices different players make throughout.</p>
<h2>A critical hit</h2>
<p>Small wonder, then, that there tend to be <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/10468781231189493">higher percentages</a> of autistic TRPG players than in the general populace. For this latest study. Atherton et al. wanted to specifically investigate how autistic players experience <em>D&amp;D</em> when playing in groups with other autistic players. It's essentially a case study with a small sample size—just eight participants—and qualitative in nature, since the post-play analysis focused on semistructured interviews with each player after the conclusion of the online campaign, the better to highlight their individual voices.</p>
<p>The players were recruited through social media advertisements within the <em>D&amp;D</em>, Reddit and Discord online communities; all had received an autism diagnosis by a medical professional. They were split into two groups of four players, with one of the researchers (who's been playing <em>D&amp;D</em> for years) acting as the dungeon master. The online sessions featured in the study was the <a href="https://forgottenrealms.fandom.com/wiki/Waterdeep:_Dragon_Heist">Waterdeep: Dragonheist</a> campaign. The campaign ran for six weeks, with sessions lasting between two and four hours (including breaks).</p>
<p>Participants spoke repeatedly about the positive benefits they received from playing <em>D&amp;D</em>, providing a friendly environment that helped them relax about social pressures. "When you're interacting with people over <em>D&amp;D</em>, you're more likely to understand what's going on," one participant said in their study interview. "That's because the method you'll use to interact is written out. You can see what you're meant to do. There's an actual sort of reference sheet for some social interactions." That, in turn, helped foster a sense of belonging and kinship with their fellow players.</p>                                                                        
                                                                                
<p>Participants also reported feeling emotionally invested and close to their characters, with some preferring to separate themselves from their character in order to explore other aspects of their personality or even an entirely new persona, thus broadening their perspectives. "I can make a character quite different from how I interact with people in real-life interactions," one participant said. "It helps you put yourself in the other person's perspective because you are technically entering a persona that is your character. You can then try to see how it feels to be in that interaction or in that scenario through another lens." And some participants said they were able to "rewrite" their own personal stories outside the game by adopting some of their characters' traits—a psychological phenomenon known as "bleed."</p>
<p>“Autism comes with several stigmas, and that can lead to people being met with judgment or disdain," <a href="https://www.plymouth.ac.uk/news/dungeons-and-dragons-can-help-autistic-people-gain-confidence-and-find-their-inner-hero">said co-author Liam Cross</a>, also of the University of Plymouth. "We also hear from lots of families who have concerns about whether teenagers with autism are spending too much time playing things like video games. A lot of the time that is because people have a picture in their minds of how a person with autism should behave, but that is based on neurotypical experiences. Our studies have shown that there are everyday games and hobbies that autistic people do not simply enjoy but also gain confidence and other skills from. It might not be the case for everyone with autism, but our work suggests it can enable people to have positive experiences that are worth celebrating.”</p>
<p>Autism, 2024. DOI: <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1177/13623613241275260">10.1177/13623613241275260</a> &nbsp;(<a href="http://arstechnica.com/science/news/2010/03/dois-and-their-discontents-1.ars">About DOIs</a>).</p>

                                                </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intent to unship: HTTP/2 Push (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://groups.google.com/a/mozilla.org/g/dev-platform/c/vU9hJg343U8/m/4cZsHz7TAQAJ</link>
            <guid>41464334</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 09:03:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://groups.google.com/a/mozilla.org/g/dev-platform/c/vU9hJg343U8/m/4cZsHz7TAQAJ">https://groups.google.com/a/mozilla.org/g/dev-platform/c/vU9hJg343U8/m/4cZsHz7TAQAJ</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41464334">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://groups.google.com/a/mozilla.org/g/dev-platform/c/vU9hJg343U8/m/4cZsHz7TAQAJ: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Did Sandia use a thermonuclear secondary in a product logo? (556 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/</link>
            <guid>41463809</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 07:27:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/">https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41463809">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p>I happened to look at a slide deck from Sandia National Laboratories from 2007 that someone had posted on Reddit late last night (you know, as one does, instead of <em>sleeping</em>), and one particular slide jumped out at me:&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635-600x450.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="450" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635-600x450.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635-1024x769.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635-768x576.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635-1536x1153.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sandia-Sierra-Mechanics-Package-Logo-Slide-1716635.jpg 2044w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>It’s a little graphic advertising the different kinds of modeling software that are part of something called the SIERRA framework, as part of a pretty standard “overview” presentation on computer modeling at Sandia that was given at a meeting in Luxembourg.<sup><a href="#footnote_0_7400" id="identifier_0_7400" title="Harold Morgan, “Sandia National Laboratories and Engineering Sciences Overview,” SAND2007-6636P, Presentation to Goodyear/Sandia CRADA Meeting Colmar-Berg, Luxembourg (22 October 2007).">1</a></sup></p>
<p>Did you catch the part that made me stop and audibly say, “<em>uhhhhh</em>“? Look at the lower right:</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail-600x323.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="323" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail-600x323.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail-1024x552.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail-768x414.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail-1536x828.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-detail-2048x1104.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>So, that looks an&nbsp;<em>awful lot</em> like the cutaway of a compact thermonuclear weapon design. I immediately wondered if I couldn’t find a better resolution version of the same graphic, so I went onto OSTI.gov and starting plugging in terms that seemed relevant. Searching for “Sierra” and “Salinas” and restricting to “Conference presentations” turned up a bunch of other instances of it from the 2007-2011 or so timeframe. The one with the highest resolution came from another presentation, from 2008:<sup><a href="#footnote_1_7400" id="identifier_1_7400" title="Heidi Ammerlahn, Richard Griffith, and Paul Nielan, “Modeling and Simulation at Sandia: An Overview,” SAND2008-3315P (23 April 2008).">2</a></sup></p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail-600x387.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="387" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail-600x387.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail-1024x660.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail-768x495.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail-1536x991.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2008-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1709042-detail.jpg 1814w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>So this is <em>awfully strange</em>. We’ve got something here that looks like a plausible reentry vehicle for a nuclear warhead. The bits in red, yellow, perhaps fuscia at the “tip” are in the position (and about the right size) to be the arming, fuzing, and firing system. The bits below that — the green, the blue, etc. — look like a thermonuclear warhead. The green part looks like it is meant to represent the location of the “primary,” while the the cylinders-within-cylinders are a classic representation of a thermonuclear “secondary.” One could debate about the exact identity of each color, but it looks a lot like it is meant to represent a radiation case, an interstage medium, a tamper, fusion fuel, and a “sparkplug.” You’ve even got an interesting little “dip” into the central cylinder which looks like a channel to get neutrons into the “sparkplug.”&nbsp;</p>
<p>By comparison, this image from later in the presentation looks a lot more like what one would expect them to release about a reentry vehicle in a public document — just the arming, fuzing, and firing system (the top part, with the detail at right), and then the “warhead” section depicted as a featureless blank:</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23-600x407.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="407" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23-600x407.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23-1024x694.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23-768x521.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23-1536x1041.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2007-Sierra-Salinas-warhead-1716635-page-23.jpg 1720w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>Even&nbsp;<em>that</em> is a little more revealing than usual, as it gives pretty precise dimensions. So seeing something that looks like it is meant to represent the warhead itself is… <em>pretty</em> <em>surprising</em>!<sup><a href="#footnote_2_7400" id="identifier_2_7400" title="And, just to be very clear about it, that complicated set of machinery in the render is the arming, fuzing, and firing (AFF) system. The basic shapes of such systems have been declassified for a long time. It is the system that causes the warhead firing signal to be sent if the right conditions are met. It is not the warhead itself and is a separate component.">3</a></sup></p>
<p>This isn’t some one-off slip up kind of thing. This particular graphic is present in at least half-a-dozen conference presentations on OSTI.gov, and even some on a few other government websites (like <a href="https://tfaws.nasa.gov/TFAWS11/Proceedings/TFAWS2011-IN-002.pdf">this presentation given to NASA</a>). It’s literally the logo they use for this particular software package. And it’s not some kind of redaction error, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2021/05/17/how-not-to-redact-a-warhead/">like the ones I wrote about previously</a>, in which things <em>not dissimilar from the above</em> were very clearly <em>intended</em> to be redacted, but were done so poorly that you could in fact see some aspects of them. This is literally the logo for this particular software framework, and it has been used in lots of presentations (including those done overseas), and is posted all over unclassified, public-facing databases hosted by the federal government.</p>
<p>It took me a little more searching, but I eventually tracked down an isolated version of the image from yet another Sandia presentation:</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model-600x265.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="265" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model-600x265.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model-1024x452.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model-768x339.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model-1536x678.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/SAND2007-6128P-Model-2048x904.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>The slide doesn’t give any clarification as to what we’re looking at, here, other than indicating that it part of modeling work for the purposes of structural dynamics, and is clearly part of a nuclear weapons context.<sup><a href="#footnote_3_7400" id="identifier_3_7400" title="Thomas M. Baca, “1523 General Capability Overview,” SAND2007-6128P (1 September 2007).">4</a></sup></p>
<p>The SIERRA software framework, I gather, is a simulation/modeling toolkit that allowed scientists to basically simulate a relatively “full spectrum” of weapons safety issues. This is Sandia’s bread and butter: making sure that your weapon won’t go off if, say, you drop it, or set it on fire, or let it get hit by lightning. Things which have happened <em>a number of times</em> over the years.<sup><a href="#footnote_4_7400" id="identifier_4_7400" title="Sandia made (and has since put online) a very informative, well-produced, three-part documentary about their work on the technical side of “command and control” of nuclear weapons, titled Always/Never: The Quest for Safety, Control, and Survivability. It’s worth a watch if you haven’t seen it. Separately, one of my favorite bits of weapons jargon is the term “mechanical insult,” which means denting your warhead in some way.">5</a></sup> The “Salinas” package in particular seems to be about modeling mechanical aspects of materials. Which is to say, this demonstration of its “capabilities” is not about showing you that it is modeling how a nuclear weapon would detonate. It is showing you, “look, we can model a lot of different materials — steel, uranium, lithium, etc. — and could probably tell you whether they would crack or strain or shatter or whatever if you, say, dropped this weapon.” That’s my quick gloss on the various presentations, anyway.</p>
<p>To give a sense of how strange this is, here is the only “officially sanctioned” way to represent a multistage thermonuclear weapon, according to US Department of Energy guidance since the 1990s:</p>

<p>Two circles in a box, maybe inside of a reentry vehicle. That’s it. Nothing that gives any actual sense of size, location, materials, <em>physicality</em>. One can compare this with the images of more speculative thermonuclear weapon designs in the public domain for a sense of how&nbsp;<em>limited</em> the official release is compared with what is “believed to be known” about such things:</p>

<p>Incidentally, I submitted a FOIA request on that particular guidance document (TCG-NAS-2) some time back, and the document that I got back was hilariously redacted to the point that even&nbsp;<em>terms</em> like “gun-type” and “implosion” were redacted, much less&nbsp;<em>any and all images</em>, despite that document apparently containing examples of what actually <em>could</em> be said publicly about these things.<sup><a href="#footnote_5_7400" id="identifier_5_7400" title="U.S. Department of Energy, “Joint DOE/DoD Topical Classification Guide for Nuclear Assembly Systems,” TCG-NAS-2 (March 1997), received in 2021 in response to FOIA request HQ-2020-00067-F.">6</a></sup> Which is just to emphasize, it’s not like the DOE is particularly <em>loose</em> about even as vaguely representational an image as is that one — if anything, the err in the other direction.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Why are they so uptight about thermonuclear weapon design “shapes”? The official reason, of course, is because of proliferation concerns. But there’s another reason: even the&nbsp;<em>appearance</em> of giving away “secrets” can generate unwanted publicity and political scandal.&nbsp;</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos-600x496.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="496" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos-600x496.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos-1024x846.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos-768x634.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos-1536x1269.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1999-Cox-Report-Los-Alamos.jpg 1666w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>In 1999, the <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/GPO-CRPT-105hrpt851/pdf/GPO-CRPT-105hrpt851.pdf">Cox Committee’s report</a> on Chinese nuclear espionage made some hay out of publicly-available depictions of H-bombs, and featured an entire spread dedicated to the fact that “visitors to Los Alamos National Laboratory are provided a 72-page publication that provides, among other things, a primer on the design of thermonuclear weapons.” It sensationalized that very two-circles-in-a-box image that I showed above, and weaponized it. How dare Los Alamos give that away! Despite it being unclassified. But that’s what I mean by unwanted political scandal — lots of scandals about the release of “secrets” involve non-secrets. (There’s a lot on this sort of thing <a href="https://book.nuclearsecrecy.com/">in my book</a>, of course.)</p>
<p>Which leads us to an interesting puzzle: why would the censors <em>repeatedly </em>allow Sandia to use what appears to be a thermonuclear weapon cutaway as part of a promotional diagram for a software package? There are a few possibilities that come to my mind.</p>
<div id="attachment_7408"><p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-scaled.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-7408" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-600x384.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="384" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-600x384.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-1024x655.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-768x491.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-1536x982.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Sandia-UNCLEARED-badge-2048x1310.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-7408">I gave a talk at Sandia this summer, and they made me wear this badge (and another one with my face on it, which I wasn’t allowed to photograph or keep) everywhere I went. Presumably so nobody would tell me secrets, but also, perhaps, to indicate my willingness to play Checkers.</p></div>
<p>One is the idea that this is an accident, a leak, an <em>oopsie</em>. I find this unlikely to the point of near impossibility. Not because the classification officers are perfect. But this is <em>so obviously not something you would authorize for release</em> if you thought it was representing something classified. To have approved&nbsp;<em>many</em> presentations with this graphic in it to go out into the world, to be posted on the websites of multiple government agencies… they’re not <em>perfect</em>, but&nbsp;they’re not<em> fools</em>. Again, if anything, they tend to err on the side&nbsp;not releasing&nbsp;<em>enough</em>. So I find it hard to believe that they’d have messed this up, again and again, when it is the most&nbsp;<em>blatant thing in the world</em>. This isn’t some subtle technical thing. Anyone who thinks about weapons information and secrecy is going to know what a cylindrical secondary looks like. I mean, this thing&nbsp;<em>jumps off the page</em> if you are that kind of person. Which I am, of course, but so are redactors. If this were the case, it would be an&nbsp;<em>incredible</em> and <em>repeat </em>failure of the classification system at many points, in the&nbsp;<em>same way</em>, over several years. One can’t say such a thing is&nbsp;<em>impossible</em> but I find that&nbsp;<em>extremely unlikely.</em></p>
<p>Another easily dismissible possibility is that this is some kind of deliberate release of classified information. Again, there is an entire infrastructure devoted to&nbsp;<em>not</em> letting this happen. With peoples’ jobs, security clearances, and personal freedoms on the line. Plus the fact that the people who tend to work in these jobs take for granted that secrecy translates to security. Even actual spies wouldn’t do it this way — they’re not about releasing secrets to the public, they’re about channeling them to the people they are spying to, quiet-like.&nbsp;</p>
<p>So we’re left with much more plausible conclusion that <em>they consider this to be unclassifiable and benign.</em> But <em>why</em> would they think that, given what we know about how sensitive they are to anything that comes even <em>remotely</em> close to representing internal weapon components?&nbsp;</p>
<div id="attachment_7418"><p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-7418" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object-600x414.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="414" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object-600x414.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object-1024x707.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object-768x530.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object-1536x1060.jpg 1536w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-DOE-Multipurpose-Test-Object.jpg 1828w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-7418">This “multipurpose test object” (taken from the aforementioned TGC-NAS-2 report from 1997) is an example of what I mean by a deliberately “unclassified shape”: something specified by the DOE as being <em>evocative</em> of the kinds of physical shapes and materials that are involved in nuclear weapons designs, but are <em>explicitly</em> indicated as being not actually relevant to weapons design. So this kind of “shape” is something you could use to validate simulation codes on which would probably work with actual weapons materials/designs, but would not actually reveal any weapons materials/designs information other than what has already been declassified.</p></div>
<p>The “obvious” answer, if my above assertions are true, is that it <em>must not actually represent a thermonuclear secondary</em>. What else could it be? It could be some kind of pre-approved “unclassified shape” which is used for diagnostics and model verification, for example. There are other examples of this kind of thing that the labs have used over time. That is entirely a possibility. What would be bizarre about this being the answer is that a) “unclassified shapes” generally don’t look like actual, plausible weapon designs, and this thing looks “close-enough”; b) it still gives off <em>the appearance</em> of a classified shape, which as noted, is dangerous in and of itself from a political standpoint; and c) if the goal is just to show off modeling capabilities in a very superficial way (this is essentially an advertising logo) they surely could have picked a million&nbsp;<em>less provocative</em> (from a classification standpoint) examples.&nbsp;</p>
<p>It’s also possible that it isn’t even meant to be a nuclear weapon at all. Sure, it looks like a reentry vehicle. Yeah… it seems awfully nuke-shaped. But there are other things that can look like nukes but at really meant to be something else. Maybe I’m seeing a “secondary” because I’m primed to see one, by the context? It’s… possible. Neither spheres-within-sphere nor cylinders-within-cylinders are <em>inherently</em> related to nuclear weapons components. But when you place them like that, in a reentry vehicle, in that order… it looks <em>very much</em> like a fusing system, a primary, a secondary… It would be quite surprising to me if it was <em>not</em> meant to be representative of those things, but something totally different. And, again, the original context of that model appears to be very firmly rooted in nuclear weapons development.<sup><a href="#footnote_6_7400" id="identifier_6_7400" title="For example, I don’t know exactly what this is meant to be — an example used in a Los Alamos presentation on computer modeling — but it’s not a nuclear weapon.">7</a></sup></p>
<p>Another possibility is that it is some kind of “deliberate disinformation” or “misinformation.” This is the kind of thing that I think people assume the government labs might do, but in my experience, is pretty unusual and pretty unlikely. In general, you have to remember that the national laboratories are pretty, well, <em>boring</em>, when it comes to classified information. They&nbsp;<em>want</em> to be boring in this respect. They are not doing cloak-and-dagger stuff on the regular. They’re scientists and engineers for the most part. These are not James Bond-wannabes. They don’t parachute behind enemy lines to set up palace coups. They are&nbsp;<em>extremely rule-abiding</em> for the most part. There are lots of social and historical reasons for this (again, <a href="https://book.nuclearsecrecy.com/">my book</a> goes into the historical ones — the anxiety about “nuclear secrets” always made the Atomic Energy Commission and its successor organizations very anxious about being accused of being lax about them).&nbsp;</p>
<p>And beyond the institutional culture aspects, the idea that a bunch of engineers at Sandia are going to be using a software package logo to deliberate leak out misinformation, just&nbsp;<em>waiting</em> for someone to notice it, seems a little unlikely to me on the face of it. I mean, really. What is the “operation” here? Who is meant to be “fooled”? Me? You? The North&nbsp; Koreans? It doesn’t feel very realistic.<sup><a href="#footnote_7_7400" id="identifier_7_7400" title="And nor does taking it one level “deeper”: the idea that they’d put out real information to make us think it must be fake information, because why else would they put it out? This is an amusing idea but, I assure you, is not how bureaucrats think, and we are talking, for better or worse, about bureaucrats here.">8</a></sup></p>
<p>And one can add to the above the fact that, at least historically, the Atomic Energy Commission and its successor organizations have frowned on disinformation and misinformation for other very practical reasons. If you release a lie, you run the risk of someone noticing it is a lie, which can draw more attention to the reality. And even misinformation/inaccuracy <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2011/12/28/weekly-document-7-is-inaccuracy-classified-1963/">can put “brackets” around the possibilities of truth</a>. The goal of these organizations is to leave a&nbsp;<em>total blank</em> in the areas that they don’t want people to know about, and misinformation/disinformation/inaccuracy is something other than a <em>total blank</em>.&nbsp;</p>
<p>That’s where I’ve ended up, in thinking about what this “means” and what possibly accounts for it. But it’s still bizarre that anyone would allow something that looks so&nbsp;<em>suggestive</em>, even if it is not&nbsp;<em>accurate</em>, to be released as an official product of a national laboratory. It seems like a bad idea, anyway. And yet — I can’t come up with an explanation for this that isn’t one kind of bad idea or another. But I think this is the “most plausible bad idea” of the set.</p>
<p>One last thing. In more recent presentations on the SIERRA Mechanics framework, they changed the diagram somewhat:<sup><a href="#footnote_8_7400" id="identifier_8_7400" title="E.g., Timothy Walsh, Greg Bunting, Andrew Kurzawski, Ellen Le, and Kevin Dowding, “Large-Scale Inverse Capabilities in Sierra Mechanics,” SAND2019-6059C (May 29, 2019).">9</a></sup></p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2019-Sierra-Mechanics-logo-1640699.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2019-Sierra-Mechanics-logo-1640699-600x472.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="472" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2019-Sierra-Mechanics-logo-1640699-600x472.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2019-Sierra-Mechanics-logo-1640699-1024x806.jpg 1024w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2019-Sierra-Mechanics-logo-1640699-768x604.jpg 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/2019-Sierra-Mechanics-logo-1640699.jpg 1416w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>The resolution isn’t great, but you can see that the potentially problematic part is much more obscured. But <em>it’s still there</em>, so I don’t think that is really an attempt to draw attention from it, so much as it is an artifact of somewhat careless graphic design. In general, it’s not a <em>great logo</em> by any means — too busy, too complicated, too much information, does not reproduce well at small sizes or low resolutions, etc. — but, as discussed, that is not even close to the most potentially problematic aspect of it!</p>
<p>I saw this and couldn’t resist quickly writing something up about it. That’s all I’ve got. If you’ve got thoughts on it, let me know. And if you haven’t already signed up for it, I am much more active on my other blog, <a href="http://doomsdaymachines.net/"><em>Doomsday Machines</em></a>, as of late!</p>
<hr>
<p>I’ve updated this post a few times since I first put it up this afternoon, but just stumbled across something even more helpful. Here’s an image from a 2014 article about computational science at Sandia that looks awfully similar to the one above:<sup><a href="#footnote_9_7400" id="identifier_9_7400" title="Monte Basgall, “Joint venture,” DEIXIS Magazine (September 2014).">10</a></sup></p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/LargeRvMesh.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/LargeRvMesh-600x409.png" alt="" width="600" height="409" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/LargeRvMesh-600x409.png 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/LargeRvMesh-768x524.png 768w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/LargeRvMesh.png 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>Unlike the others, it comes with a caption: “The multiple components of a nuclear weapon body are highlighted in this intentionally simplified mesh. Each part is comprised of numerous subcomponents, fastened together with screws, nuts, bolts, jar-lid-like fittings and more.” Which is just to say, it is pretty clearly saying that this “thing” is meant to be some kind of representation of a nuclear weapon, albeit “intentionally simplified.” Which doesn’t really solve the mystery — if anything, it just highlights why I still find it so odd that this thing got approved for released at all! Not in the sense that it contains “secrets” — but in the sense that it is just not the kind of image the national labs tend to release.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Someone reminded me of something I had seen years ago: the British nuclear program at Aldermaston, when it has published on its own computer modeling in the past, used a sort of “bomb mockup” that looks far more deliberately “fake” than this Sandia one. I offer this up as what I would think is a more&nbsp; “safe”&nbsp; approach than something that looks, even superficially, like a “real” secondary design:</p>
<p><a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Aldermaston-test-object.jpg"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Aldermaston-test-object-600x520.jpg" alt="" width="600" height="520" srcset="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Aldermaston-test-object-600x520.jpg 600w, https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Aldermaston-test-object.jpg 621w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>This is called the MACE (Modal Analysis Correlation Exercise) assembly, and was created by the UK Atomic Weapons Research Establishment in the 1990s to serve as a sort of a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Utah_teapot">Utah Teapot</a> of weapons structural modeling: a benign shape that could be used to test aspects of the code that would nonetheless tell you if the code would work for real weapons assemblies.<sup><a href="#footnote_10_7400" id="identifier_10_7400" title="Some more info on the MACE assembly can be found in this PhD thesis from 2004: Philip Ind, “The Non-Intrusive Model Testing of Delicate and Critical Structures” (Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine, University of London, 2004). The screen cap image comes from an in-house AWRE publication (Discovery) from 2000.">11</a></sup></p>
<p>Anyway, I’m just surprised the DOE would release&nbsp;<em>any</em> image that gave really&nbsp;<em>any</em> implied graphical structure of a thermonuclear secondary, even if it is clearly schematic and meant to be only somewhat representative. It’s more than they usually allow!</p>
<ol><li id="footnote_0_7400">Harold Morgan, “<a href="https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1716635">Sandia National Laboratories and Engineering Sciences Overview</a>,” SAND2007-6636P, Presentation to Goodyear/Sandia CRADA Meeting Colmar-Berg, Luxembourg (22 October 2007).<span> [<a href="#identifier_0_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_1_7400">Heidi Ammerlahn, Richard Griffith, and Paul Nielan, “<a href="https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1709042">Modeling and Simulation at Sandia: An Overview</a>,” SAND2008-3315P (23 April 2008).<span> [<a href="#identifier_1_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_2_7400">And, just to be very clear about it, that complicated set of machinery in the render is the arming, fuzing, and firing (AFF) system. The basic shapes of such systems have been declassified for a long time. It is the system that causes the warhead firing signal to be sent if the right conditions are met. It is not the warhead itself and is a separate component.<span> [<a href="#identifier_2_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_3_7400">Thomas M. Baca, “<a href="https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1719007">1523 General Capability Overview</a>,” SAND2007-6128P (1 September 2007).<span> [<a href="#identifier_3_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_4_7400">Sandia made (and has since put online) a very informative, well-produced, three-part documentary about their work on the technical side of “command and control” of nuclear weapons, titled <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DQEB3LJ5psk"><em>Always/Never: The Quest for Safety, Control, and Survivability</em></a>. It’s worth a watch if you haven’t seen it. Separately, one of my favorite bits of weapons jargon is the term “mechanical insult,” which means denting your warhead in some way.<span> [<a href="#identifier_4_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_5_7400">U.S. Department of Energy, “<a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/1997-TCG-NAS-2-Joint-DOE-DOD-Topical-Classi%EF%AC%81cation-Classification-Guide-for-Nuclear-Assembly-Systems-FOIA-HQ-2020-00067-F.pdf">Joint DOE/DoD Topical Classification Guide for Nuclear Assembly Systems</a>,” TCG-NAS-2 (March 1997), received in 2021 in response to FOIA request HQ-2020-00067-F.<span> [<a href="#identifier_5_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_6_7400">For example, I don’t know exactly what <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Los-Alamos-odd-device.jpg">this</a> is meant to be — an example used in <a href="https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1983836">a Los Alamos presentation on computer modeling</a> — but it’s not a nuclear weapon.<span> [<a href="#identifier_6_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_7_7400">And nor does taking it one level “deeper”: the idea that they’d put out <em>real</em> information to make us think it must be <em>fake</em> information, because why else would they put it out? This is an amusing idea but, I assure you, is not how bureaucrats think, and we are talking, for better or worse, about bureaucrats here.<span> [<a href="#identifier_7_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_8_7400">E.g., <span>Timothy Walsh, Greg Bunting, Andrew Kurzawski, Ellen Le, and Kevin Dowding, “<a href="https://www.osti.gov/servlets/purl/1640699">Large-Scale Inverse Capabilities in Sierra Mechanics</a>,” SAND2019-6059C (May 29, 2019).<span> [<a href="#identifier_8_7400">↩</a>]</span></span></li><li id="footnote_9_7400">Monte Basgall, “<a href="https://deixismagazine.org/2014/09/joint-venture/">Joint venture</a>,” <em>DEIXIS Magazine</em> (September 2014).<span> [<a href="#identifier_9_7400">↩</a>]</span></li><li id="footnote_10_7400">Some more info on the MACE assembly can be found in this PhD thesis from 2004: Philip Ind, “<a href="https://www.imperial.ac.uk/media/imperial-college/research-centres-and-groups/dynamics/7289238.PDF">The Non-Intrusive Model Testing of Delicate and Critical Structures</a>” (Imperial College of Science, Technology, and Medicine, University of London, 2004). The screen cap image comes from <a href="http://web.archive.org/web/20060314131511/http://www.awe.co.uk/Images/joint_test_prog_tcm6-1953.pdf">an in-house AWRE publication (<em>Discovery</em>) from 2000</a>.<span> [<a href="#identifier_10_7400">↩</a>]</span></li></ol>
				

								<p>Tags: <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/2000s/" rel="tag">2000s</a>, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/2010s/" rel="tag">2010s</a>, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/bad-ideas/" rel="tag">Bad ideas</a>, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/bomb-design/" rel="tag">Bomb design</a>, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/graphic-design/" rel="tag">Graphic design</a>, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/hydrogen-bomb/" rel="tag">Hydrogen bomb</a>, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/tag/sandia-national-laboratories/" rel="tag">Sandia National Laboratories</a></p>
				<p>
					<small>
						This entry was posted
												on Wednesday, September 4th, 2024 at 1:21 pm						and is filed under <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/category/redactions/" rel="category tag">Redactions</a>.
						You can follow any responses to this entry through the <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/feed/">RSS 2.0</a> feed.

													You can <a href="#respond">leave a response</a>, or <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/trackback/" rel="trackback">trackback</a> from your own site.

						 <p>
<b>Citation:</b> Alex Wellerstein, "Did Sandia use a thermonuclear secondary in a product logo?," <em>Restricted Data: A Nuclear History Blog</em>, September 4, 2024, accessed September 6, 2024, <a href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/">https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2024/09/04/did-sandia-use-a-thermonuclear-secondary-in-a-product-logo/</a>.

					</p></small>
				</p>

		<br>


			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Exercise has 2M users but no money in the bank (391 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://exercism.org/blog/september-2024-restructure</link>
            <guid>41463734</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 07:16:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://exercism.org/blog/september-2024-restructure">https://exercism.org/blog/september-2024-restructure</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41463734">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>Hi everyone!</p>
<p>Last week we hit the huge milestone of <strong>two million users</strong>.
Within a few hours, we also hit <strong>45 million exercise submissions</strong>.</p>
<p>A day later, I paid the <strong>final payroll</strong> for me, Erik and Aron, and our bank account reduced down to the point we can't afford to pay another.</p>
<p>I think this sums up Exercism's story pretty well.
Over <strong>1,200 people per day sign up</strong> to Exercism.
Tens of thousands solve exercises each day.
But we don't have enough money to continue to work on the platform.</p>
<p>We've tried a lot of things to change that.
We've spoken to hundreds of funders and companies, but Exercism isn't the right fit for their support.
It doesn't fit a niche that makes sense for them.
By serving people everywhere, it seems we don't serve a narrow enough demographic that we align to funders' often narrow missions!</p>
<p>The one area we have had some promising success is in advertising on the site.
But the effort it takes to find advertisers and manage them, and my general desire not to flood Exercism with adverts, has meant that I feel this isn't a very sustainable strategy.</p>
<p>I think it's fair to say that at this stage <strong>I've lost faith in the nonprofit business model</strong> working in a way that allows Exercism to reach any of its potential.
Keeping something free for everyone relies on either the user being the product, or on significant donations, and without either, it's very hard to grow.</p>
<h2 id="h-erik-oss-restructure">Erik + OSS Restructure</h2>
<p>Probably the hardest thing about the situation right now, is that <strong>we can no longer afford to pay Erik</strong>, so he's leaving as an employee at the end of this week.</p>
<p>Erik has been an absolute critical part of Exercism's growth and success over the last few years.
He's also been a wonderful colleague and friend, and I'll really miss working alongside him.
It goes without saying that I'm incredibly grateful to Erik for all his hard work and support.
And I know many of you will feel the same (if so, please reach out and tell him!)</p>
<p>Erik's a die-hard Exercism fan, and he's going to continue as a senior maintainer of a few tracks, and he'll hold onto his super-admin privileges, but the plethora of hidden (and often a bit boring) things that he does day-to-day need to get spread across the organisation.</p>
<p>The one key thing we're enforcing is that <strong>every PR in a live Exercism repository should get a review before it can be merged</strong> (with only one exception outlined below).
This has generally been the case anyway for a long time, but there are places where it's fallen through the cracks, so we've now scripted things to ensure this is always the case.</p>
<p>To do this, we've come up with a new classification system for repos, and specific rules for each type:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<code>maintained</code>: A repo that has multiple maintainers. All PRs require reviews from a track maintainer.</li>
<li>
<code>maintained-solitary</code>: A repo that has one maintainer. A new cross-track-maintainers team will get pinged to review all PRs.</li>
<li>
<code>unmaintained</code>: A repo that has no maintainers. The cross-track-maintainers team will get pinged here too.</li>
<li>
<code>maintained-autonomous</code>: A repo where all maintainers are also in the cross-track-maintainer team. This is the exception, where they can merge their own PRs.</li>
<li>
<code>wip-track</code>: An unlaunched track. As it's not "live" yet, it doesn't have restrictions.</li>
</ul>
<p>We've created two new GitHub teams that enforce this.</p>
<ul>
<li>
<code>@exercism/guardians</code>: A team to check the safety of PRs to tooling repositories (test runners, analyzers, etc). Made up of a few longstanding polyglots.</li>
<li>
<code>@exercism/cross-track-maintainers</code>: A new team made up of longstanding polyglots who are active on the site on a day-to-day basis, and who have the same level of reviewing-pedanticism that I do (ie they're not more strict or more flexible than me). This is important, as I want a consistent, responsive experience from this team.</li>
</ul>
<p>Both teams are invite-only.
I'll review them sporadically.</p>
<p>We've also invited new maintainers and "pruned" a lot of inactive maintainers as part of this.
To those people who have been removed - thank you for all you've done, and please know you're very welcome back if you find the time/desire to contribute in earnest to Exercism again!</p>
<h2 id="h-so-what-s-next">So what's next?</h2>
<p>So this has all been a bit gloom and doom so far.
Things don't always go as you hope in life, but you have to make lemonade from the lemons!</p>
<p>Right now, we have about 800 monthly donors and about $7,500 in monthly donations.
That <strong>covers our server costs</strong> pretty much exactly.
So if you're donating right now, thank you.
You are literally keeping our servers on.
Our donor base is generally quite stable, so I'm not too worried about Exercism's existential prospects.</p>
<p>(It would be really good to build a bit of a financial buffer, so if you can afford it, please consider making a <a href="https://exercism.org/donate">recurring or one-off donation</a> 💙)</p>
<p>We also have an <strong>amazing community, maintainer team, and group of mentors</strong> who keep adding new exercises (and tracks!), helping students, and numerous other things.
Exercism has probably never been healthier as an organisation.
It's <strong>growing faster than ever</strong>, more people are using it than ever, and I think the product and educational experience is better than ever.
So I'm still deeply dedicated to growing and nurturing Exercism.</p>
<p>For the last few months, I've been working on a new educational product teaching coding fundamentals that I'm going to launch in 2025.
96% of people who try to learn coding give up - which I find unacceptable, so I'm aiming to change that.
My plan is to give beginners a rock-solid base, then funnel them into Exercism.
I'm creating a new for-profit company for the new company, and going to use proceeds from that to keep Exercism growing.
I've raised a little investment for this, which means I can continue to pay Aron's salary, so he'll be staying around, working on that with me, and tweaking Exercism as needed.</p>
<p>I'm also planning (probably 90% certain) of running <strong>a dedicated learn-to-code course</strong> from Jan-March 2025, where I can test out some of what we've been building, and I can get my hands dirty working with the students who existing platforms don't serve.
So keep out for an announcement about this soon.</p>
<p>I'm exploring launching <strong>a basic version of Exercism Teams</strong>, as a way of making some extra revenue.
There's <a href="https://forum.exercism.org/t/exercism-teams-coming-soon/12667" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">a forum post</a> here where you can leave thoughts.
I'd really appreciate any you have!</p>
<p>But first, <strong>I need a breather!</strong>
I'll be taking the next two weeks off, unplugging and recovering a little.</p>
<p>Thanks for all your support - emotional and financial.
Exercism's community is phenomenal and <strong>I'm deeply grateful</strong> to everyone involved in the project.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The expected value of the game is positive regardless of Ballmer’s strategy (185 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gukov.dev/puzzles/math/2024/09/05/steve-ballmer-was-wrong.html</link>
            <guid>41463330</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 06:08:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gukov.dev/puzzles/math/2024/09/05/steve-ballmer-was-wrong.html">https://gukov.dev/puzzles/math/2024/09/05/steve-ballmer-was-wrong.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41463330">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>A few days ago John Graham-Cumming posted about <a href="https://blog.jgc.org/2024/09/steve-ballmers-binary-search-interview.html">“Steve Ballmer’s incorrect binary search interview question”</a> which <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41434637">drew a lot of attention</a> on Hacker News. The Ballmer’s favorite brain teaser goes like this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I’m thinking of a number between 1 and 100. You can guess, after each guess I’ll tell you whether you’re high or low. You get it the first guess - I’ll give you five bucks. Four bucks, three, two, one, zero, you pay me a buck, you pay me two, you pay me three</em>.</p>

  <p><em>Should you accept to play this game?</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Steve Ballmer argues in <a href="https://youtu.be/svCYbkS0Sjk?si=89kJu8Ukkr9QpkFX&amp;t=34">this YouTube interview</a> that there are two reasons why you should not play this game:</p>

<ol>
  <li>There are many numbers that would result in a loss, making the expected value negative even if he randomly picks numbers between 1 and 100.</li>
  <li>He can strategically pick numbers that would require the longest time for you to find using binary search.</li>
</ol>

<p>However, John counters Ballmer’s first point in his <a href="https://blog.jgc.org/2024/09/steve-ballmers-binary-search-interview.html">blog post</a> by demonstrating that if Ballmer selects the number randomly, the expected value of the game is actually positive: <strong>$0.20</strong>.</p>

<p>I will refute the second point and demonstrate that the expected value of the game is positive regardless of Ballmer’s strategy.</p>

<h2 id="how-can-ballmer-pick-numbers-adversarially">How can Ballmer pick numbers adversarially?</h2>

<p>Let’s assume you always employ the binary search strategy to find the number. Out of the 100 numbers, there are 37 that would require you to ask 6 questions to make a guess.</p>

<p>If Ballmer is aware of your strategy, he can always select one of these “losing” numbers, resulting in a loss for you in every game.</p>

<p>This holds true for any “fixed” search pattern. There will always be at least 37 numbers that would result in a loss, and Ballmer can choose one of them.</p>

<h2 id="how-can-you-counter">How can you counter?</h2>

<p>Here we’re getting into the <strong>game theory</strong> territory.</p>

<p>Instead of using a single fixed search pattern, you can prepare a set of different search patterns. Then at the beginning of the game, draw one of these patterns with some probability and stick to it during the game.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strategy_(game_theory)#Pure_and_mixed_strategies">In game theory</a>, you call it a <strong>mixed strategy</strong> based on the <strong>strategy set</strong> of multiple <strong>pure strategies</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Because the same number could be “winning” for one search pattern and “losing” for another, such a mixed strategy could “even out” the expected winnings for each number.</p>

<p>Potentially, a mixed strategy could even make every number “winning”, i.e. have a positive expected value of the win for every number.</p>

<p>And this is exactly what we’re looking for!</p>

<h2 id="how-to-find-the-winning-mixed-strategy">How to find the winning mixed strategy?</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note: We are looking for <em>any</em> winning strategy, not the <em>best</em> winning strategy that has the maximum expected value in the worst case, i.e., the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nash_equilibrium">Nash equilibrium</a>. If you are curious about the Nash equilibrium, Arthur O’Dwyer explored it for the game <a href="https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2024/09/04/the-game-is-flawed/">up to 5 numbers</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Finding the mixed strategy that wins on every number can be viewed as a mathematical optimization problem.</p>

<p>Every strategy can be described as a “win” vector $V = (v_1, .., v_{100})$, where $v_k$ is the expected win if Ballmer picks the number $k$. For example, the binary search could correspond to a vector with $v_{50} = 5$, $v_{25} = 4$, and $v_{0} = -1$.</p>

<p>Suppose we have a set of pure strategies ${V_1, V_2, …, V_n}$, and our mixed strategy chooses the strategy $V_k$ with probability $p_k$.</p>

<p>Then the corresponding “win” vector for the mixed strategy is just a linear combination: $V_{mixed}=\sum_{i=1}^{n}{p_iV_i}$.</p>

<p>In this interpretation, finding the winning strategy means finding some linear combination of the given vectors with two constraints:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Each element of the linear combination is positive (the strategy wins money, on average, for each number).</li>
  <li>The coefficients of this linear combination are non-negative (as they correspond to probabilities).</li>
</ul>

<p>This is a typical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linear_programming">linear programming</a> problem, and scipy <a href="https://docs.scipy.org/doc/scipy/reference/generated/scipy.optimize.linprog.html">has an efficient solver</a> for it.</p>

<p>To find a mixed strategy, I thought of a set of pure strategies (various binary searches), <a href="https://github.com/gukoff/ballmer_puzzle/blob/main/main.py#L98">fed it</a> into <code>scipy.linprog()</code>, and voilà - the solver came up with a winning strategy!</p>

<h2 id="example-winning-strategy">Example winning strategy</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p>Full code is at <a href="https://github.com/gukoff/ballmer_puzzle#winning-strategy">gukoff/ballmer_puzzle</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<ul>
  <li>Average win if Ballmer chooses randomly: <strong>$0.12</strong></li>
  <li>Worst win if Ballmer chooses adversarially: <strong>$0.07</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>The resulting mixed strategy goes like this:</p>

<div><pre><code>- With probability 0.2120%: Binary search, first guess is 29. On each step, guess the middle element in the interval, in case of tie guess the left one.
- With probability 0.0450%: Binary search, first guess is 33. On each step, guess the middle element in the interval, in case of tie guess the left one.
- With probability 0.9843%: Binary search, first guess is 26. On each step, guess the middle element in the interval, in case of tie guess the right one.
- With probability 0.6910%: Binary search, first guess is 28. On each step, guess the middle element in the interval, in case of tie guess the right one.
- With probability 0.9686%: Binary search, first guess is 1. On each step, guess the rightmost element in the interval that won't increase the worst-case complexity.
- With probability 0.7134%: Binary search, first guess is 18. On each step, guess the rightmost element in the interval that won't increase the worst-case complexity.
- With probability 2.7288%: Binary search, first guess is 46. On each step, guess the rightmost element in the interval that won't increase the worst-case complexity.
- With probability 2.6411%: Binary search, first guess is 36. On each step, guess the leftmost element in the interval that won't increase the worst-case complexity.
- With probability 5.2209%: Binary search, first guess is 40. On each step, guess the leftmost element in the interval that won't increase the worst-case complexity.

...
</code></pre></div>

<p>The complete strategy consists of 60 lines, which I have omitted for brevity. If you are interested, you can <a href="https://github.com/gukoff/ballmer_puzzle?tab=readme-ov-file#winning-strategy">view it on GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>If you find winning (on average) 7 cents per game worth your time, then you should definitely play this game with Steve Ballmer the next time he offers.</p>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What happens when you touch a pickle to an AM radio tower (335 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/what-happens-when-you-touch-pickle-am-radio-tower</link>
            <guid>41462574</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 03:16:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/what-happens-when-you-touch-pickle-am-radio-tower">https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/what-happens-when-you-touch-pickle-am-radio-tower</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41462574">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A few months ago, our <a href="https://www.instagram.com/insights/media/3333127873529510767/">AM radio hot dog experiment</a> went mildly viral. That was a result of me asking my Dad 'what would happen if you ground a hot dog to one of your AM radio towers?' He didn't know, so one night on the way to my son's volleyball practice, we tested it. And it was <em>awesome</em>.</p>

<p>There's a video and some pictures in my <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/talking-hot-dog-gives-new-meaning-ham-radio">hot dog radio blog post</a> from back in March.</p>

<p>
<video preload="" autoplay="" loop="" playsinline="" muted="">
  <source src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/bratwurst-am-tower.mp4" type="video/mp4">
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
</p>

<p>Fast forward a few months and one Open Sauce later, and Jay from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@PlasmaChannel">Plasma Channel</a> visited us in St. Charles, MO, for round two—where my Dad and I were prepared to measure (almost) everything: SWR, RF forward power, SDR on site, AM field intensity 25km (16mi) away, meat thermals, and—courtesy of Jay—some taste testing!</p>

<p>Our full experience is documented in today's Geerling Engineering video:</p>

<div>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/wzDEIBpbLRk" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div>

<p>But I'll also summarize all our test results in this blog post, for easier reference:</p>

<h2>Test Setup and Safety Precautions</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-hotdog.jpg" alt="RF Safety - Hot Dog AM radio tower"></p>

<p><strong>DO NOT ATTEMPT</strong>. Don't mess with towers, especially AM broadcast towers.</p>

<p>We consulted with an experienced broadcast antenna designer before any testing. Using <a href="https://transition.fcc.gov/Bureaus/Engineering_Technology/Documents/bulletins/oet65/oet65.pdf">conservative FCC guidelines</a> (also see <a href="https://transition.fcc.gov/oet/info/documents/bulletins/oet65/oet65a.pdf">Supplement A</a>), we determined a safe exposure distance <em>for the tower and transmitter at this single tower site</em>. Every tower, station, and frequency will be different, so again, <em>do not attempt</em> what we did. It was for educational purposes only. And science.</p>

<h2>Experiment 1 - Hot Dog</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-hotdog-measurements.jpg" alt="RF Safety - Hot Dog device measurements"></p>

<p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: Well, we already knew the hot dog would make some noise. This time, we brought all our instrumentation, and measured how it affected the signal.</p>

<p><strong>Observations</strong>: The hot dog did, indeed, produce copious noise through plasma-air interaction. It did an excellent job demodulating the AM signal into audible sound, and the entire hot dog was heated to around 80°C—which is luckily a safe internal temperature for eating.</p>

<p>What may be <em>less</em> safe is eating whatever charred remains were left on the end of the hot dog. The transmitter RF output (as measured on the control panel) rose to 14 kW (from a nominal 12) briefly, before the internal <a href="https://electronics.stackexchange.com/a/2936/9952">foldback protection</a> cut power to around 6 kW (until we stopped shorting the hot dog to ground, after which the Nautel XR12 raised power back to 12 kW).</p>

<h2>Experiment 2 - Pickle (Gherkin)</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-pickle-plasma-shockwave.jpg" alt="RF Safety - Plasma shockwave coming off gherkin pickle on AM tower"></p>

<p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: Some commenters believed the salt content of a fresh gherkin would cause the arc to change from orange-ish (hot dog) to green-ish (pickle). We speculated it may turn more reddish...</p>

<p><strong>Observations</strong>: The gherkin was quite a pickle. While testing, there was a loud spark, then the transmitter quickly got <em>very</em> quiet. We originally thought it cauterized itself and caused less conduction, but were very wrong. As it turns out, the pickle was an <em>excellent</em> conductor, with much lower internal resistance than any of the meats we tested. The salt-saturated watery interior provided an excellent path from tower to ground!</p>

<p>This was the only object we tested which caused the transmitter to completely disable its RF output, if only momentarily. The end of the pickle glowed orange, and we also observed a plasma <em>shockwave</em> (pictured above) in a few frames. Would love to see this with a high-speed camera!</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-jay-pickle-eat.jpg" alt="Jay from Plasma Channel Taste-Tests a Pickle"></p>

<p>In the category of 'what-were-you-thinking' comes Jay from the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@PlasmaChannel">Plasma Channel</a>. He decided to taste-test the pickle, and immediately spat it out as he said it tasted strongly of copper. He speculates the taste may have resulted from the electrolysis of the copper we used to ground the pickle. We speculate he may be a little crazy—our kind of crazy. Jay has his own video on the experience here: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NowhPAMDOTo">Creating A Plasma Shockwave Using Wireless Energy</a>.</p>

<h2>Experiment 3 - Bratwurst</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-bratwurst.jpg" alt="RF Safety - Bratwurst on AM radio tower"></p>

<p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: Many commenters speculated a bratwurst would translate the normally-English radio signal into German. We had our doubts.</p>

<p><strong>Observations</strong>: The bratwurst did indeed translate the signal into German! Or, well... it broadcast the german phrases the <a href="https://adamwrightstl.com/about/">on-air talent</a> spoke during his morning show.</p>

<p>The bratwurst was the floppiest of the tested meats, and had a rather phallic look as it was hanging off the end of our probe. The 'droop' resulted in a large contact patch, which produced more smoke than the hot dog, but not any perceptible difference in sound. The transmitter reacted about the same as it did with the hot dog.</p>

<h2>Experiment 4 - Vegan Hot Dog</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-vegan-hot-dog.jpg" alt="RF Safety - vegan hot dot"></p>

<p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: We expected the vegan hot dog to perform similarly to the all-beef hot dog, though were wondering if it could surprise us. <a href="https://lightlife.com/product/jumbo-smart-dogs/">Soybeans and sugar</a> may react differently than beef or turkey!</p>

<p><strong>Observations</strong>: The sound was a bit louder, the vegan hot dog was a bit cooler, and the end burned off a bit more quickly. The more disgusting bit was the end near the copper insertion point—some white substance oozed out the backside and did not look very appetizing (see photo above).</p>

<p>Jay taste-tested the cooked vegan hot dog (this time biting off a section from the middle, not a part that came in contact with the copper) and described the taste as 'pretty good'.</p>

<h2>Experiment 5 - Corn Dog</h2>

<p>
<video preload="" autoplay="" loop="" playsinline="" muted="">
  <source src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/corn-dog-am-tower-shrunk.mp4" type="video/mp4">
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>
</p>

<p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: We speculated the corn layer surrounding the hot dog may provide enough insulation to prevent a serious reaction with the tower. This item also was a physical manifestation of our sometimes 'corny' dad jokes.</p>

<p><strong>Observations</strong>: Copious amounts of smoke, followed by large bursts of flame. Honestly, this was the most surprising of the bunch. The smoke seemed to follow the leg of the tower at a fairly large distance from the point of contact!</p>

<p>Unlike the other meats, the smell of the burnt corn dog was pleasant–almost sugary. The sound was not that loud, and apparently the corn layer provided enough resistance the transmitter's foldback protection circuit never activated; the transmitter continued at 12 kW power throughout our corn dog test.</p>

<p>Nobody was brave enough to taste-test the corn dog.</p>

<h2>Experiment 6 - Breakfast Sausage</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-breakfast-sausage.jpg" alt="RF Safety - AM breakfast sausage"></p>

<p><strong>Hypothesis</strong>: Will a meat meant for the 'a.m.' perform any better on an AM radio tower?</p>

<p><strong>Observations</strong>: Yes, in fact—this smaller bit of meat was louder than the rest, and seemed to burn <em>very</em> evenly. The breakfast sausage stayed under 70°C, and it quickly kicked the transmitter back to 6 kW (half) output, but was stable at that power output.</p>

<p>The end was quite crispy.</p>

<h2>Experiment 7 - Hot Dog Warmer</h2>

<p>We also tested holding a hot dog on the stick within about 1" of the base of the tower for approximately 60 seconds, but found there to be no significant heating at that distance. Part of the hot dog had to be touching the tower, creating the plasma arcs, to heat the hot dog at the 1460 kHz frequency of this broadcast station. At least at the 7 kW or so this tower was putting out.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/rf-safety-transmitter-status-display.jpg" alt="RF Safety - transmitter status log"></p>

<p>If we ran the tests again, I would very much like to bring a sound pressure level meter. It would be interesting to more quantitatively measure the sound of each object.</p>

<p>Some have also suggested using a better insulating rod—something like <a href="https://amzn.to/3z41UKv">this $300 fiberglass rod</a>. It would be an improvement over our wooden stick, though with the power at <em>this</em> antenna, the risk is extremely small that RF would arc through the stick, into a human holding it (especially with our thick rubber gloves), versus through the copper in the end. The bigger risk is heating and near-field RF exposure, which follows the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inverse-square_law">inverse-square law</a>. Distance is safety.</p>

<p>I would love to get a high speed camera (capable of at least 10,000 fps) to capture the plasma interaction between the tower and the meat to see if we could visualize the amplitude modulation in plasma. Maybe also repeating the experiment at dusk, so the plasma is brighter.</p>

<p>As it is, there are just lots of bright bursts of plasma that look interesting but mask the hidden modulation causing them! (If you're a Slow Mo Guy and you're reading this... DMs are open, lol.)</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LwIP – Lightweight IP Stack (167 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nongnu.org/lwip/2_1_x/index.html</link>
            <guid>41461850</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 01:00:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nongnu.org/lwip/2_1_x/index.html">https://www.nongnu.org/lwip/2_1_x/index.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461850">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nongnu.org/lwip/2_1_x/index.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Don't Tech Companies Pay Their Engineers to Stay? (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.goethena.com/post/why-dont-tech-companies-pay-engineers-more-to-stay/</link>
            <guid>41461747</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 06 Sep 2024 00:41:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.goethena.com/post/why-dont-tech-companies-pay-engineers-more-to-stay/">https://www.goethena.com/post/why-dont-tech-companies-pay-engineers-more-to-stay/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461747">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
                    
<p><em>Staying in a role builds valuable, company-specific domain knowledge. Leaving often results in a payday—so, why aren’t tech companies paying more for their engineers to stay?</em></p>



<p id="viewer-3sprm"><em>This article was originally published to </em><a href="https://marker.medium.com/why-dont-tech-companies-pay-their-engineers-to-stay-b9c7e4b751e9" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em><u>Marker</u></em></a><em>.</em></p>



<h2 id="viewer-eutfd"><strong>Why don’t companies pay engineers more?</strong></h2>



<p id="viewer-tnit">When news broke that breakout star Regé-Jean Page was <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/entertainment/tv/2021/04/02/bridgerton-rege-jean-page-wont-return-simon-basset-season-2/7063065002/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><u>leaving Bridgerton after only one season</u></a>, my initial reaction was that of shock and heartbreak. I couldn’t fathom why Netflix and The Duke of Hastings weren’t able to come to <em>some </em>sort of agreement.</p>



<p id="viewer-16onb">But then it hit me: my entire career, I’ve watched talented engineers leave companies for greener pastures after painfully short tenures. I’m even guilty of this myself — I left an amazing company after less than two years to join <a href="https://www.goethena.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><u>Ethena</u></a> as VP of Engineering.</p>



<p id="viewer-296pr">My example aside, I think the larger phenomena is a problem with organizations, not individuals. When hiring someone new, companies are forced to play in the open market, competing for top talent. But internally, they create opaque and informationally asymmetric compensation structures designed to minimize growth for existing employees to save the company’s bottom line.</p>



<p id="viewer-4lru8">That’s not the type of company I want to be a part of, so at Ethena, I’m working to create career paths and compensation structures that encourage long and happy tenures by <strong>paying our engineers generously and in proportion to their impact</strong>.</p>



<p id="viewer-4sd7n">Additionally, I’ll be working with our not yet hired <a href="https://jobs.lever.co/ethena/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><u>Head of People</u></a> to <strong>publish our compensation formula publically</strong>.</p>



<p id="viewer-ncd7">Let’s break down why this strategy makes sense, and why I believe it will be fundamental to Ethena Engineering’s long-term success.</p>







<h2 id="viewer-2qgeg"><strong>Tech compensation is all wrong</strong></h2>



<p id="viewer-9it7m">With a market this hot, software developers are hopping between companies and raking in enormous pay raises in the process. But let’s think like economists for a second — in a perfect market, this shouldn’t be possible! If a developer of a certain caliber is able to demand a given salary on the open market, why isn’t their existing company paying them that very same amount? In our imperfect world, engineers join a company at a certain level of expertise, spend time learning and growing that expertise within that company, and then for whatever reason find that it’s much easier to get recognition for that growth <em>outside</em> that company.</p>



<p id="viewer-f9b2u">A graph or two might help illustrate the problem. First, market salary increases with years of experience, assuming an engineer is improving their skills of course!</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="712" height="424" src="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_7eb09b3b3db64c38b017a22f173c9088_mv2.webp" alt="" srcset="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_7eb09b3b3db64c38b017a22f173c9088_mv2.webp 712w, https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_7eb09b3b3db64c38b017a22f173c9088_mv2-300x179.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px"></figure>



<p id="viewer-fhu06">That one is a bit obvious, huh? Okay, well, let’s look at an engineer’s salary in their job at Acme Corp. Notice the slope of the line is a bit less . . . exciting? In my opinion, it’s likely the short-sighted desire to save money that defines the slope of this line at many companies.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="712" height="406" src="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_b7f90219012d4bf4be4f863dd68ea6c7_mv2.webp" alt="" srcset="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_b7f90219012d4bf4be4f863dd68ea6c7_mv2.webp 712w, https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_b7f90219012d4bf4be4f863dd68ea6c7_mv2-300x171.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 712px) 100vw, 712px"></figure>



<p id="viewer-faf14">Well, if we’re talking about tech compensation over time, what about impact? Check out this steep angle!</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="708" height="374" src="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_ab652db952a44b3d89397224345b2e81_mv2.webp" alt="" srcset="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_ab652db952a44b3d89397224345b2e81_mv2.webp 708w, https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_ab652db952a44b3d89397224345b2e81_mv2-300x158.webp 300w" sizes="(max-width: 708px) 100vw, 708px"></figure>



<p id="viewer-9e72g">See, developers don’t just improve their transferable skills while working at their company—they gain domain knowledge that is<em> specific to that company</em>, and that stuff is incredibly valuable. The wild thing is that it’s only valuable to that one company! Let’s put it all together in one graph, and please don’t judge my blending of the units here . . .</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="925" height="380" src="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_56a1342296554847826f31397da0d476_mv2.webp" alt="" srcset="https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_56a1342296554847826f31397da0d476_mv2.webp 925w, https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_56a1342296554847826f31397da0d476_mv2-300x123.webp 300w, https://www.goethena.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/4d2dc5_56a1342296554847826f31397da0d476_mv2-768x316.webp 768w" sizes="(max-width: 925px) 100vw, 925px"></figure>



<p id="viewer-f39g5">The hard truth that many companies struggle to wrap their heads around is that they should be paying their long-tenured engineers <em>above market</em> <em>rate</em>. This is because an engineer that’s been working at a company for a long time will be more impactful <em>specifically at that company than at any other company</em>. Bridgerton casting aside, a company like Netflix <a href="https://hbr.org/2014/01/how-netflix-reinvented-hr" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><u>understands this</u></a>, and will always outbid the competition for their top talent.</p>



<h2 id="viewer-36kfk"><strong>Paying engineers more is easier said than done…</strong></h2>



<p id="viewer-ak6jm">It’s easy to say “pay your developers more,” but it’s never that simple. For one thing, this type of compensation structure is unrealistic for very early-stage startups where paying your first few engineers a market salary is usually impossible.</p>



<p id="viewer-evo0q">Additionally, without an HR infrastructure in place, simplicity and equality can help early-stage companies thrive. This is why, so far at Ethena, the entire engineering team, including myself, has made the same salary.</p>



<p id="viewer-bvn89">The other challenge with a compensation strategy like I’m proposing is measuring everyone’s unique impact accurately and without bias. What happens when the new hotshot junior engineer suddenly starts outperforming the old guard? With an impact-based compensation structure, she would deserve a sizeable raise, but is the company willing to go through with it and risk upsetting the other team members?</p>



<p id="viewer-2gqd9">Plus, not all engineers necessarily increase their level of impact over time. How are these engineers, who still add value every day, compensated in this type of structure? I believe the key to navigating these hard problems is organizational maturity.</p>



<p id="viewer-dq9d3">At Ethena, our track record of transparency, open feedback channels, and an experienced management team put us in a position to make these types of bold policies that other companies may struggle to operationalize.</p>



<h2 id="viewer-1din5"><strong>So, what’s the plan for compensating engineers?</strong></h2>



<p id="viewer-d3elk">With the help of our soon-to-be Head of People, we intend to create a formula that takes into account title, years of tenure, and performance to create a compensation graph that scales with company impact as closely as possible. By making it predictable and public, both existing team members and potential hires can know in advance what they should expect to make at Ethena in the short- and long-term.</p>



<p id="viewer-fdnj">It also means being comfortable with hard truths — not everyone’s impact grows in the same way and at the same time scale and maintaining talent density means being willing to part ways with underperformers. At the end of the day, if any engineer at Ethena demonstrates they are performing at a certain level, regardless of how many years of experience they have in or outside of the company, they should be rewarded with a title and base salary that matches their impact (in addition to their tenure and performance multipliers!).</p>



<p id="viewer-dqi34">So stay tuned for more! I hope the future Head of People knows what they’ll be getting themselves into . . .</p>



<hr>



<p id="viewer-dmngh">Speaking of compensating engineers, <a href="https://jobs.lever.co/ethena?team=Software%20Development" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><u>we’re hiring</u></a>!</p>
                </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Tell HN: Burnout is bad to your brain, take care (628 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461499</link>
            <guid>41461499</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 23:59:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461499">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><td><table>
        <tbody><tr id="41461499">
      <td><span></span></td>      <td><center><a id="up_41461499" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41461499&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41461499"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461499">Tell HN: Burnout is bad to your brain, take care</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span>
          <span id="score_41461499">165 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=tuyguntn">tuyguntn</a> <span title="2024-09-05T23:59:02.000000Z"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461499">1 hour ago</a></span> <span id="unv_41461499"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=41461499&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41461499">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Tell%20HN%3A%20Burnout%20is%20bad%20to%20your%20brain%2C%20take%20care&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=41461499&amp;auth=65296f0963350844d44e2445b8720b797b03478f">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41461499">77&nbsp;comments</a>        </span>
              </td></tr>
    <tr><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>I am depressed and burned out for quite some time already, unfortunately my brain still couldn't recover from it.</p><p>If I summarize the impact of burnout to my brain:</p><p>- Before: I could learn things pretty quickly, come up with solutions to the problems, even be able to see common patterns and see bigger underlying problems</p><p>- After: can't learn, can't work, can't remember, can't see solutions for trivial problems (e.g. if your shirt is wet, you can change it, but I stare at it thinking when it is going to get dried up)</p><p>Take care of your mental health</p></div></td></tr>        <tr><td></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr>  </tbody></table>
  </td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>