<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 11:00:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sleep apnea: Mouthguards less invasive, just as effective as CPAP (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://newatlas.com/medical/sleep-apnea-mouthguard-cpap-blood-pressure/</link>
            <guid>40037046</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2024 04:20:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://newatlas.com/medical/sleep-apnea-mouthguard-cpap-blood-pressure/">https://newatlas.com/medical/sleep-apnea-mouthguard-cpap-blood-pressure/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40037046">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Obstructive sleep apnea can cause or contribute to high blood pressure, so a new study examined which sleep apnea treatments – a CPAP machine or a mouthguard that keeps the airways open – was more effective at lowering blood pressure.</p><p>Medications are the first-line treatment for high blood pressure, otherwise known as hypertension. However, <a href="https://newatlas.com/medical/nasal-spray-sleep-apnea/" data-cms-ai="0">obstructive sleep apnea</a> (OSA), which can cause and/or exacerbate <a href="https://newatlas.com/medical/new-drug-two-for-one-treatment-heart-failure-sleep-apnea/" data-cms-ai="0">hypertension</a>, is being recognized as an underdiagnosed and modifiable risk factor. The most common sleep-rated breathing disorder, OSA is caused by the collapse of the upper airway during sleep, which leads to frequent sleep interruptions, up to 30 times an hour, all night long.</p><p>Continuous positive airway pressure (<a href="https://newatlas.com/medical/health-benefits-cpap-acid-reflux/" data-cms-ai="0">CPAP</a>) delivered via a face or nasal mask is often used to treat OSA. An alternative treatment is a mandibular advancement device or MAD. Similar to a bite guard, a MAD holds the lower jaw (mandible) and tongue forward, keeping the airway open. There are pros and cons for both. CPAP, while effective, tends to be uncomfortable, so it’s poorly tolerated. MADs are less intrusive, but studies have shown they’re outperformed by CPAP when it comes to the apnea-hypopnea index (AHI), the number of times airflow fully (apnea) or partially (hypopnea) stops per hour during sleep.</p><div data-align-center="">
                
                    <figure>
    
    
    
    


<p><img alt="A nasal CPAP device" width="1440" height="960" data-image-size="articleImage" loading="lazy" data-srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/7de242b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/440x293!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/cc06e61/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/800x533!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/cf76a17/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/08dd39e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/1920x1280!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 1920w" data-src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/7f9ee6e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/1440x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1240px) 800px, (min-width: 1024px) 95vw, 100vw" srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/7de242b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/440x293!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/cc06e61/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/800x533!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/cf76a17/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/08dd39e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/1920x1280!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg 1920w" src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/7f9ee6e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/1999x1333+0+0/resize/1440x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F7a%2F92%2Fe6f848074e3c8e1bae05c03062e6%2Fdepositphotos-227915398-l.jpg">
</p>



    
    

    
        <div><figcaption itemprop="caption">A nasal CPAP device</figcaption></div>
    
</figure>

                
            </div><p>Researchers from the National University of Singapore (NUS) and the University of Sydney conducted a randomized controlled trial to compare the effectiveness of MAD and CPAP in reducing hypertension in patients with moderate-to-severe OSA.</p><p>“Looking at the totality of evidence available in all the literature, it is still reasonable to say that CPAP is the first-line treatment until we have more data on the MAD,” said Ronald Lee Chi-Hang, professor of medicine at NUS’ Yong Loo Lin School of Medicine and corresponding author of the study. “However, for patients who cannot truly tolerate or accept using a CPAP, we should be more open-minded in looking for an alternative therapy such as a MAD, which, based on our study, numerically had a better blood pressure reduction in patients compared with a CPAP.”</p><p>Being a non-inferiority trial, the study tested whether a new treatment (MAD) is not worse than an established one (CPAP). The researchers recruited 220 participants with moderate-to-severe OSA and randomized them to either CPAP or MAD. Of the participants, 44.5% were overweight, and 49.5% were obese. The most prevalent high cardiovascular risk factors were coronary artery disease (60.9%) and diabetes (59.1%), with 44.1% of participants having had hypertension for more than 10 years.</p><p>At baseline and six-month follow-up, both groups underwent 24-hour ambulatory blood pressure (BP) monitoring, completed a questionnaire on sleepiness, and had blood tests for cardiovascular markers. Both devices tracked use. The primary outcome was the difference in 24-hour mean BP between baseline and follow-up.</p><p>MADs significantly reduced 24-hour mean BP from baseline to six-month follow-up, which was not significant in the CPAP group. The decrease in the MAD group was, on average, 1.64 mmHg larger than the CPAP group. Compared to the CPAP group, the MAD group also showed a larger between-group reduction in all ambulatory BP measures, especially nighttime BP, and more participants achieved a systolic BP (the top number) below 120 mmHg. None of the participants experienced symptomatic low BP or hypotension. From these data, the researchers ascertained that a MAD was non-inferior to CPAP.</p><div data-align-center="">
                
                    <figure>
    
    
    
    


<p><img alt="An oral device like this SomnoDent Flex® is just as effective as CPAP in reduced sleep apnea-related high blood pressure" width="1440" height="960" data-image-size="articleImage" loading="lazy" data-srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/f916740/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/440x293!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/fe3e66e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/800x533!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/7ce7a4b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/fdcbafb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/1920x1280!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 1920w" data-src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/8d25768/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/1440x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1240px) 800px, (min-width: 1024px) 95vw, 100vw" srcset="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/f916740/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/440x293!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 440w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/fe3e66e/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/800x533!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 800w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/7ce7a4b/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/1200x800!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 1200w,https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/fdcbafb/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/1920x1280!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg 1920w" src="https://assets.newatlas.com/dims4/default/8d25768/2147483647/strip/true/crop/2000x1333+0+0/resize/1440x960!/quality/90/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnewatlas-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F75%2F06%2Fff6a49e14c9ab197914227746ef6%2Fsomnodent.jpg">
</p>



    
    

    
        <div><figcaption itemprop="caption">An oral device like this SomnoDent Flex® is just as effective as CPAP in reduced sleep apnea-related high blood pressure</figcaption></div>
    
</figure>

                
            </div><p>The researchers also looked at differences in adherence between the two devices; that is, how long participants stuck with their allocated treatment. Over half (56.5%) assigned to the MAD used it for six or more hours each night on average over the study period, while 23.2% of CPAP users did the same.</p><p>“The MAD patients simply used the device longer,” Chi-Hang said. “That also might explain why the blood pressure reduction at nighttime, when the patients are actually using it, had a better reduction in the MAD arm.”</p><p>Adherence to the <a href="https://aasm.org/" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">American Academy of Sleep Medicine</a>’s (AASM) recommendation of four or more hours of use in at least 70% of nights overall was similar between groups, with 69.4% of the MAD group and 64.3% of the CPAP group meeting this recommendation. Both groups had reduced daytime sleepiness, and there were no between-group differences in cardiovascular biomarkers.</p><p>“People should be aware that over 400 million people globally have moderate-to-severe obstructive sleep apnea, and it is underdiagnosed and may be a contributing factor to their high blood pressure,” said Chi-Hang. “Especially for patients whose blood pressure is hard to control or who have a lot of excessive daytime sleepiness, go see a physician about sleep apnea and get treated if necessary.”</p><p>The study participants were of East Asian descent, and 85.5% were male. Although ethnic Chinese make up about 17.3% of the world’s population, further research on more diverse populations is needed to determine whether the results are generalizable. Further, the researchers note that adherence may have been higher because the study was conducted during COVID-19 travel lockdowns.</p><p>Further studies are planned to examine the impacts of the devices on cognition.</p><p>The study, funded by the Singapore Ministry of Health, was published in the <i><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0735109724009069?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">Journal of the American College of Cardiology</a></i>.</p><p>Source: <a href="https://nus.edu.sg/" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">NUS</a> via <a href="https://www.scimex.org/newsfeed/sleep-apnoea-mouthguard-could-be-just-as-effective-for-lowering-blood-pressure-as-a-cpap-machine" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">Scimex</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Spectral Ray Tracing (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://larswander.com/writing/spectral-ray-tracing/</link>
            <guid>40035552</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 23:45:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://larswander.com/writing/spectral-ray-tracing/">https://larswander.com/writing/spectral-ray-tracing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40035552">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
  
  <blockquote>
<p>I’m sharing this to give some background on my recent artworks exploring light, color, and perception through spectral ray tracing. This ray tracer that I’ve written has shown up in a few of my series, and I wanted to explain what “spectral ray tracing” even is. I have shared some outputs at the <a href="#spectral-ray-tracing-and-computer-art">end of this writeup</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In computer art, the artist builds both a scene and a camera to capture it out of code. The system being visualized, and process to render it into an array of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/RGB_color_spaces">RGB</a> values are both made of the same 1s and 0s, pure abstraction turned into light. In much the same way, our eyes and brains are made of the same <em>stuff</em> as the universe they exist within and observe. This self-referential perspective on our awareness is both eerie and profound, obvious yet unsettling.</p>
<p>For this reason, this idea of building cameras out of code has stuck with me. Now there are countless ways to do so, but one very literal and well-known process is “ray tracing”. In its essence, ray tracing models the path light travels between a simulated camera and light source, bouncing rays between virtual objects in to “illuminate” the scene.</p>
<h2 id="ray-tracing">Ray Tracing</h2>
<p>Ray tracing takes many shortcuts in the process to render an image in the name of performance. For example: ray tracing traverses the path from the light source to the camera in reverse (though there are exceptions), with the idea being that the vast majority of rays emitted from the light source never make it to the camera. By instead starting the ray at the camera’s perspective and traveling backwards, we know that the ray already “made it” to the camera. This is physically sound under our current model of the universe, as we assume the laws governing light transport are symmetric with respect to the direction of time (a.k.a. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/T-symmetry">T-symmetry</a>).</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/8/83/Ray_trace_diagram.svg" alt="Diagram showing ray tracing on a simple scene">
  <figcaption>A simple scene being rendered via ray tracing. Each "pixel" on the left-hand grid has its color determined by the object it intersects in the scene, and how much light that object receives from the light source. Source: <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Ray_trace_diagram.svg">wikimedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Another major shortcut that’s typically taken, but is far less physically sound, involves treating each light ray as a particle carrying the RGB vector corresponding to its “color”, ignoring any <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wave%E2%80%93particle_duality">wave-like properties light has</a>. Rather remarkably, this shortcut produces physically-realistic scenes in a wide range of scenarios. The reason why this works so well has quite a long explanation, but is in large part due to how our eyes work: simply put, we have three types of color-sensitive cells in our eyes, sensitive to short (blue), medium (green), and long (red) wavelengths of light.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/1/1e/Cones_SMJ2_E.svg" alt="Diagram showing cone cell sensitivies">
  <figcaption>This diagram shows the sensitivity of the SML (short, medium, long) cone cells as a function of light's wavelength. The color we see is a result of how much the incoming light stimulates each of those cone cells. Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Cones_SMJ2_E.svg">wikimedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>However, our eyes don’t just receive red, green, and blue light (unless they’re very close to a computer screen or wearing a VR headset); our eyes are receiving a continuous spectrum of light, and converting that into the perception of color.</p>
<h2 id="seeing-the-spectrum">Seeing the Spectrum</h2>
<figure>
  <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d9/Linear_visible_spectrum.svg" alt="Diagram showing the full spectrum of single-wavelength colors">
  <figcaption>The full visible spectrum of single-wavelength colors. Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Linear_visible_spectrum.svg">wikimedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Color that we see in the physical world is rarely made of just a single wavelength, instead, it’s a collection of many wavelengths forming what we call an SPD (spectral power distribution). For every color we can see, there are countless spectral power distributions that could correspond to that color. The fact that a single color can have many different SPDs is known as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metamerism_(color)">metamerism</a>, and is a fascinating concept in its own right. For example: yellow has a corresponding wavelength as seen in the above visible spectrum at around 580nm, but it can also be reproduced with a mix of red and green light (as it must be, given that the diagram itself is being rendered using only RGB values on a computer monitor).</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/e/e7/Solar_spectrum_en.svg" alt="The SPD corresponding to daylight. Wavelength is on the x-axis, and the normalized intensity is on the y-axis">
  <figcaption>The SPD for daylight, extending past the visible spectrum into ultraviolet and infrared. It's no coincidence that the intensity peaks around the part of the spectrum visible to us, as this is clearly an evolutionary adaptation to our environment. Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Solar_spectrum_en.svg">wikimedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Another consequence of how our eyes see color from a distribution of wavelengths is the existence of non-spectral colors, like magenta. These colors can’t be reproduced by any single wavelength, and require multiple wavelengths of light to reproduce. Notice there is no magenta in that spectrum above, as it requires a mix of high and low-wavelength light (blue and red) to be seen.</p>
<p>What’s most remarkable about this conversion from SPD to color is that it is possible to do so purely mathematically. The fact that such a link exists, bridging physics, physiology, and our subjective experience is honestly surreal. What’s even more remarkable is that this quantitative link was made back in 1931 with the creation of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CIE_1931_color_space#">CIE 1931 color spaces</a>, at a time before the Turing machine (let alone a computer) was even invented, and access to electricity hadn’t even made it across America.</p>
<p>If you want to implement this conversion yourself, I recommend reading <a href="https://pbr-book.org/4ed/Radiometry,_Spectra,_and_Color/Color">this chapter of Physically Based Rendering</a>, which gives a very thorough treatment of the subject.</p>
<h2 id="when-wavelength-matters">When Wavelength Matters</h2>
<p>As mentioned above, when ray tracing it’s often unnecessary to account for the full spectrum of light, let alone each ray’s “wavelength”. However, there are cases where a ray’s wave-like properties directly influence its path through a scene, and as a result effects the colors we see. The classic example is dispersion, when the path light takes is “bent” according to its wavelength.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/f5/Light_dispersion_conceptual_waves.gif" alt="An animation showing light being split by a triangular prism according to its wavelength">
  <figcaption>An optical prism showing white light being split into its component frequencies via dispersion. Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Light_dispersion_conceptual_waves.gif">wikimedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Another fascinating example you’ve probably seen in person is called “thin film interference”, and it explains the rainbow-like patterns visible on soap bubbles. These patterns are formed by the constructive and destructive interference patterns generated by the reflections off of the upper and lower layers of the soap boundary. Since this doesn’t involve splitting the spectrum into single wavelengths, but rather increasing or decreasing the contribution of parts of the spectrum the colors generated are often non-spectral colors, like turquoises, teals, magentas, browns…</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/55/Thin_film_interference_phase_2.svg" alt="An image showing destructive interference on a thin film boundary.">
  <figcaption>Destructive interference happening at a thin film boundary (in blue). The two incoming rays (labeled A and B) have the same wavelength, yet opposite phase after reflection due to traveling different distances before overlapping. The resulting ray (labeled C) is attenuated as a result. Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Thin_film_interference_phase_2.svg">wikimedia</a></figcaption>
</figure>
<h2 id="spectral-ray-tracing-and-computer-art">Spectral Ray Tracing and Computer Art</h2>
<p>To summarize, spectral ray tracing is just ray tracing that takes into account the wave-like properties of light. Instead of viewing the world through the lens of RGB color, spectral ray tracing generates spectral power distributions for every pixel in the scene, leveraging the wavelength and phase of rays to better estimate color in scenarios where this extra information matters.</p>
<p>I’ve been curious what happens when some of the laws dictating how light moves are deliberately broken, building cameras out of code in a universe just a little unlike our own. Working with the richness of the full spectrum of light, spectral ray tracing has allowed me to break the rules governing light transport in otherworldly ways.</p>
<p>Here are a few selected outputs from the past year. All of these were generated using my hand-written, no-dependency JavaScript and GLSL spectral ray tracer.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://larswander.com/img/art/light-painting/high-res/ldbtw-01.webp">
  <figcaption><i>Light Doesn't Bend That Way #1</i>, 2023</figcaption>
</figure>
<br>
<figure>
  <img src="https://larswander.com/img/art/light-painting/high-res/reflect0422.webp">
  <figcaption>This was generated by making the angle of reflection a function of wavelength. Note this process only seems to generate spectral colors. 
    <p><i>Untitled</i>, 2023</p></figcaption>
</figure>
<br>
<figure>
  <img src="https://larswander.com/img/art/light-painting/high-res/reflect_fs_0053.webp">
  <figcaption>An WIP piece made for the series <a href="https://larswander.com/art/full-spectrum">FULL_SPECTRUM</a>, released in Tokyo 2023. 
    <p><i>Untitled</i>, 2023</p></figcaption>
</figure>
<br>
<figure>
  <video width="100%" loop="true" autoplay="true" controls="" src="https://larswander.com/img/art/light-painting/high-res/rotate0099.mp4"></video>
  <figcaption>Putting these pieces into motion has been my favorite part of this system so far.
    <p>
  <i>Untitled</i>, 2024</p></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>I hope this has given you a little more insight into my practice and the works I’ve created. I hope to keep exploring this medium, and if this excites you, you can find more pieces like these on my <a href="https://twitter.com/larswander">twitter</a> or <a href="https://instagram.com/larswander">instagram</a>.</p>


        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Visualizing Attention, a Transformer's Heart [video] (586 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.3blue1brown.com/lessons/attention</link>
            <guid>40035514</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 23:38:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/lessons/attention">https://www.3blue1brown.com/lessons/attention</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40035514">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__next"><main><div data-dark="false" data-width="normal"><h2 id="thanks">Thanks</h2><p>Special thanks to those below for supporting the original video behind this post, and to<!-- --> <a href="https://www.3blue1brown.com/thanks">current patrons</a> <!-- -->for funding ongoing projects. If you find these lessons valuable,<!-- --> <a href="https://www.patreon.com/3blue1brown">consider joining</a>.</p><p><span>.chance</span><span>A Zook</span><span>Aaron Binns</span><span>Ada Cohen</span><span>Adam Cedrone</span><span>Adam Dřínek</span><span>aeroeng15</span><span>Alan Stein</span><span>Albin Egasse</span><span>Alex </span><span>Alex Hackman</span><span>Alexandru Irimiea</span><span>Alexis Olson</span><span>Ali Yahya</span><span>Aljoscha Schulze</span><span>Alon Amit</span><span>Alvin Khaled</span><span>Aman Karunakaran</span><span>Andrea Di Biagio</span><span>Andrew Busey</span><span>Andrew Poelstra</span><span>Andrew Villagran</span><span>Andrew Wyld</span><span>Andrey Chursin</span><span>Anthony Eufemio</span><span>Aravind C V</span><span>Arkajyoti Misra</span><span>Arthur Zey</span><span>Arto Bendiken</span><span>Arun Kulshreshtha</span><span>Avi Bryant</span><span>Axel Ericsson</span><span>Barry Fam</span><span>Barry McLaurin</span><span>Beckett Madden-Woods</span><span>Ben Delo</span><span>Benjamin Bailey</span><span>Bigyan Bhar</span><span>Blake Byers</span><span>Boris Veselinovich</span><span>Bpendragon </span><span>Bradley Pirtle</span><span>Bren </span><span>Brian Cloutier</span><span>Brian King</span><span>Brian Staroselsky</span><span>Britt Selvitelle</span><span>bruce oberg</span><span>Burt Humburg</span><span>Carlos Iriarte</span><span>Carolus Reinecke</span><span>Charles Southerland</span><span>Chris Alexiuk</span><span>Chris Connett</span><span>Chris Mabee</span><span>Chris Seaby</span><span>Christian Broß</span><span>Constantine Goltsev</span><span>Cooper Jones</span><span>Corey Ogburn</span><span>Craig Schwandt</span><span>Cristi Cobzarenco</span><span>Cristian Amitroaie</span><span>Cy 'kkm' K'Nelson</span><span>D. Sivakumar</span><span>d5b</span><span>Dallas De Atley</span><span>Dan Davison</span><span>Dan Herbatschek </span><span>Dan Kinch</span><span>Dan Lawrence</span><span>Dan Martin</span><span>Daniel Badgio</span><span>Daniel Rolandsgard Kjellevold</span><span>Dave Kester</span><span>dave nicponski</span><span>David Bar-On</span><span>David Barker</span><span>David Gow</span><span>David J Wu</span><span>David Johnston</span><span>Deep Kalra</span><span>Deepak Devjani</span><span>Delton Ding</span><span>Dominik Wagner</span><span>Donal Botkin</span><span>Eddy Lazzarin</span><span>Eduardo M Chumbes</span><span>emptymachine</span><span>Eric Koslow</span><span>Eric Younge</span><span>Ero Carrera</span><span>Eryq Ouithaqueue</span><span>Eugene Pakhomov</span><span>Evan Miyazono</span><span>Filip Rolenec</span><span>Frank R. Brown, Jr.</span><span>Gabriele Siino</span><span>Garbanarba</span><span>George Maged Botros</span><span>Gerardo Ubaghs</span><span>gonezoomy</span><span>Gordon Gould</span><span>Gregory Hopper</span><span>gregostras</span><span>Guillaume Sartoretti</span><span>Harris Hoke</span><span>Henry Reich</span><span>Hitoshi Yamauchi</span><span>Holger Flier</span><span>Igor Bogetić</span><span>Infinite Flite</span><span>Ivan</span><span>J. Dmitri Gallow</span><span>Jacob Harmon</span><span>Jaewon Jung</span><span>James Golab</span><span>Jamie Winterton</span><span>Jan-Hendrik Prinz</span><span>Janak Ramakrishnan</span><span>Jason Arkens</span><span>Jason Hise</span><span>Jean-Manuel Izaret</span><span>Jed Yeiser</span><span>Jeff Butterworth</span><span>Jeff Linse</span><span>Jeff R</span><span>Jeff Straathof</span><span>Jeremy </span><span>Jeremy Cole</span><span>Jeremy Smith</span><span>Jerris Heaton</span><span>Jimmy Yang</span><span>jml</span><span>Joe kraus</span><span>Joe Pregracke</span><span>John</span><span>John C. Vesey</span><span>John Camp</span><span>John Haley</span><span>John Le</span><span>John Luttig</span><span>John McClaskey</span><span>Jon Adams</span><span>Jonathan </span><span>Jonathan M.</span><span>Jonathan Whitmore</span><span>Jonathan Wilson</span><span>Jonathon  Krall</span><span>José Breijo</span><span>Joseph John Cox</span><span>JosephG</span><span>Josh Wiley</span><span>Joshua Ouellette</span><span>Juan Benet</span><span>Julian Parmar</span><span>Julien Dubois</span><span>Justin Chandler</span><span>Karim Safin</span><span>Karma Shi</span><span>Keith Tyson</span><span>Kenneth Larsen</span><span>Kevin </span><span>Kieryn </span><span>Killian McGuinness</span><span>Konstantin Belotserkovets</span><span>Krishanu Sankar</span><span>Lambda GPU Workstations</span><span>lardysoft</span><span>leafyleaf</span><span>Lee Burnette</span><span>Lee Redden</span><span>Linda Xie</span><span>Lukas Biewald</span><span>Majid Alfifi</span><span>Maksim Stepanenko</span><span>Mano Prime</span><span>Mara Cating-Subramanian</span><span>Marco</span><span>Marek Gluszczuk</span><span>Mark Steitz</span><span>MarkM</span><span>Marshall McQuillen</span><span>Martin Mauersberg</span><span>Matt Parlmer</span><span>Matthew Bouchard</span><span>Matthew Piziak</span><span>Mauricio Sánchez-Bella</span><span>Max Anderson</span><span>Max Li</span><span>Max Welz</span><span>Maxim Kuzmich</span><span>Maxim Nitsche</span><span>Meni Rosenfeld</span><span>Merl</span><span>Michael Dunworth</span><span>Michael Kokosenski</span><span>Michael Liuzzi</span><span>Mike </span><span>Mike Dour</span><span>Mike Dussault</span><span>Mohammad Hosseini</span><span>Mohsen Hejrati</span><span>Molly Mackinlay</span><span>MR. FANTASTIC</span><span>Mukul Ram</span><span>Mutual Information</span><span>namewithheld </span><span>Nate Glissmeyer</span><span>Nate Pinsky</span><span>Nick</span><span>Nick Rubino</span><span>Nick Valverde</span><span>Nikhil Abraham</span><span>Nipun Ramakrishnan</span><span>noname</span><span>nothings</span><span>Octavian Voicu</span><span>Oleksandr Kuvshynov</span><span>Oliver Steele</span><span>Orb Li</span><span>otavio good</span><span>Patch Kessler</span><span>Patrick Lucas</span><span>Paul Pluzhnikov</span><span>Paul Wolfgang</span><span>Pavel Dubov</span><span>Pāvils Jurjāns</span><span>Person</span><span>Peter Freese</span><span>Peter Mcinerney</span><span>Philipp Legner</span><span>Pierre Lancien</span><span>Pradeep Gollakota</span><span>Prathap Sridharan</span><span>Rami Maalouf</span><span>Randy C. Will</span><span>Randy True</span><span>Raymond Fowkes</span><span>Rebecca Lin</span><span>rehmi post</span><span>Ripta Pasay</span><span>Rob</span><span>Rob Granieri</span><span>Rod S</span><span>Ron Capelli</span><span>Ronnie Cheng</span><span>Ronny</span><span>Roy Velich</span><span>Ruslan Abdikeev</span><span>Russel Simmons</span><span>Ryan Atallah</span><span>Ryan Mahuron</span><span>Scott Gorlick</span><span>Scott Gray</span><span>Sean Chittenden</span><span>Sergey Ovchinnikov</span><span>Seth Kaufman</span><span>Shardul Heda</span><span>Siddhesh Vichare</span><span>Sinan Taifour</span><span>Smarter Every Day</span><span>Stefan Korntreff</span><span>Stephen Palazola</span><span>Steve Huynh</span><span>Steve Muench</span><span>Steven Siddals</span><span>Tal Einav</span><span>Tanmayan Pande</span><span>Taras Bobrovytsky</span><span>Terry Hayes</span><span>The 1111 Code</span><span>Thomas Peter Berntsen</span><span>Timothy Chklovski</span><span>Todd Wang</span><span>tril zerobyte</span><span>Tristan Saldanha</span><span>Tyler Herrmann</span><span>Tyler Parcell</span><span>Tyler Veness</span><span>Ubiquity Ventures</span><span>Vai-Lam Mui</span><span>Vignan Velivela</span><span>Vignesh Valliappan</span><span>Vijay </span><span>Vikram Paralkar</span><span>Vince Gabor</span><span>Xierumeng </span><span>Yana Chernobilsky</span><span>Yoon Suk Oh</span><span>you say long names are tricky but all I hear is sempai noticed me</span><span>Yurii Monastyrshyn</span><span>Yushi Wang</span><span>Zachariah Rosenberg</span><span>Zachary Walton</span><span>Антон Кочков</span><span>Олександр Горленко</span><span>昊 陈</span></p></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WireViz: Easily document cables and wiring harnesses (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz</link>
            <guid>40035414</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 23:22:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz">https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40035414">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">WireViz</h2><a id="user-content-wireviz" aria-label="Permalink: WireViz" href="#wireviz"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://pypi.org/project/wireviz/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/3f7384c3f8367c2a55d891a6a2ae09e67a4d486b7aea9b0a18d4d67bd36d6ebe/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f7769726576697a2e7376673f636f6c6f72423d626c7565" alt="PyPI - Version" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/wireviz.svg?colorB=blue"></a>
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/wireviz/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/068f00edc963607b667132b13eaf6d4e319ad04344d486b70fb165b41f81c698/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f707976657273696f6e732f7769726576697a2e7376673f" alt="PyPI - Python Version" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/pyversions/wireviz.svg?"></a>
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/wireviz/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/bd49c664acece1166f020cd199b501efa066fbbd6d019d4267677433dff757e9/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f646d2f7769726576697a" alt="PyPI - Downloads" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/dm/wireviz"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Summary</h2><a id="user-content-summary" aria-label="Permalink: Summary" href="#summary"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">WireViz is a tool for easily documenting cables, wiring harnesses and connector pinouts. It takes plain text, YAML-formatted files as input and produces beautiful graphical output (SVG, PNG, ...) thanks to <a href="https://www.graphviz.org/" rel="nofollow">GraphViz</a>. It handles automatic BOM (Bill of Materials) creation and has a lot of extra features.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>WireViz input files are fully text based
<ul dir="auto">
<li>No special editor required</li>
<li>Human readable</li>
<li>Easy version control</li>
<li>YAML syntax</li>
<li>UTF-8 input and output files for special character support</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Understands and uses color abbreviations as per <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_color_code#Color_band_system" rel="nofollow">IEC 60757</a> (black=BK, red=RD, ...)

</li>
<li>Auto-generates standard wire color schemes and allows custom ones if needed
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/DIN_47100" rel="nofollow">DIN 47100</a> (WT/BN/GN/YE/GY/PK/BU/RD/BK/VT/...)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_color_code#Color_band_system" rel="nofollow">IEC 60757</a>   (BN/RD/OR/YE/GN/BU/VT/GY/WT/BK/...)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/25-pair_color_code#Color_coding" rel="nofollow">25 Pair Color Code</a> (BUWH/WHBU/OGWH/WHOG/GNWH/WHGN/BNWH/...)</li>
<li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TIA/EIA-568#Wiring" rel="nofollow">TIA/EIA 568 A/B</a>  (Subset of 25-Pair, used in CAT-5/6/...)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Understands wire gauge in mm² or AWG
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Optionally auto-calculates equivalent gauge between mm² and AWG</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Is suitable for both very simple cables, and more complex harnesses.</li>
<li>Allows for easy-autorouting for 1-to-1 wiring</li>
<li>Generates BOM (Bill of Materials)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note</em>: WireViz is not designed to represent the complete wiring of a system. Its main aim is to document the construction of individual wires and harnesses.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h2><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo 01</h3><a id="user-content-demo-01" aria-label="Permalink: Demo 01" href="#demo-01"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/demo01.yml">WireViz input file</a>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="connectors:
  X1:
    type: D-Sub
    subtype: female
    pinlabels: [DCD, RX, TX, DTR, GND, DSR, RTS, CTS, RI]
  X2:
    type: Molex KK 254
    subtype: female
    pinlabels: [GND, RX, TX]

cables:
  W1:
    gauge: 0.25 mm2
    length: 0.2
    color_code: DIN
    wirecount: 3
    shield: true

connections:
  -
    - X1: [5,2,3]
    - W1: [1,2,3]
    - X2: [1,3,2]
  -
    - X1: 5
    - W1: s"><pre><span>connectors</span>:
  <span>X1</span>:
    <span>type</span>: <span>D-Sub</span>
    <span>subtype</span>: <span>female</span>
    <span>pinlabels</span>: <span>[DCD, RX, TX, DTR, GND, DSR, RTS, CTS, RI]</span>
  <span>X2</span>:
    <span>type</span>: <span>Molex KK 254</span>
    <span>subtype</span>: <span>female</span>
    <span>pinlabels</span>: <span>[GND, RX, TX]</span>

<span>cables</span>:
  <span>W1</span>:
    <span>gauge</span>: <span>0.25 mm2</span>
    <span>length</span>: <span>0.2</span>
    <span>color_code</span>: <span>DIN</span>
    <span>wirecount</span>: <span>3</span>
    <span>shield</span>: <span>true</span>

<span>connections</span>:
  -
    - <span>X1</span>: <span>[5,2,3]</span>
    - <span>W1</span>: <span>[1,2,3]</span>
    - <span>X2</span>: <span>[1,3,2]</span>
  -
    - <span>X1</span>: <span>5</span>
    - <span>W1</span>: <span>s</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Output file:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/demo01.png"><img src="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/raw/master/examples/demo01.png" alt="Sample output diagram"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/demo01.bom.tsv">Bill of Materials</a> (auto-generated)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo 02</h3><a id="user-content-demo-02" aria-label="Permalink: Demo 02" href="#demo-02"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/demo02.png"><img src="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/raw/master/examples/demo02.png" alt=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/demo02.yml">Source</a> - <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/demo02.bom.tsv">Bill of Materials</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tutorial and example gallery</h3><a id="user-content-tutorial-and-example-gallery" aria-label="Permalink: Tutorial and example gallery" href="#tutorial-and-example-gallery"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/tutorial/readme.md">tutorial page</a> for sample code,
as well as the <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/examples/readme.md">example gallery</a> to see more of what WireViz can do.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h3><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Requirements</h4><a id="user-content-requirements" aria-label="Permalink: Requirements" href="#requirements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">WireViz requires Python 3.7 or later.</p>
<p dir="auto">WireWiz requires GraphViz to be installed in order to work. See the <a href="https://graphviz.org/download/" rel="nofollow">GraphViz download page</a> for OS-specific instructions.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note</em>: Ubuntu 18.04 LTS users in particular may need to separately install Python 3.7 or above, as that comes with Python 3.6 as the included system Python install.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installing the latest release</h4><a id="user-content-installing-the-latest-release" aria-label="Permalink: Installing the latest release" href="#installing-the-latest-release"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The latest WireViz release can be downloaded from <a href="https://pypi.org/project/wireviz/" rel="nofollow">PyPI</a> with the following command:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installing the development version</h4><a id="user-content-installing-the-development-version" aria-label="Permalink: Installing the development version" href="#installing-the-development-version"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Access to the current state of the development branch can be gained by cloning the repo and installing manually:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone <repo url>
cd <working copy>
git checkout dev
pip3 install -e ."><pre><code>git clone &lt;repo url&gt;
cd &lt;working copy&gt;
git checkout dev
pip3 install -e .
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you would like to contribute to this project, make sure you read the <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/docs/CONTRIBUTING.md">contribution guidelines</a>!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to run</h3><a id="user-content-how-to-run" aria-label="Permalink: How to run" href="#how-to-run"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ wireviz ~/path/to/file/mywire.yml"><pre><code>$ wireviz ~/path/to/file/mywire.yml
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This will output the following files</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="mywire.gv         GraphViz output
mywire.svg        Wiring diagram as vector image
mywire.png        Wiring diagram as raster image
mywire.bom.tsv    BOM (bill of materials) as tab-separated text file
mywire.html       HTML page with wiring diagram and BOM embedded"><pre><code>mywire.gv         GraphViz output
mywire.svg        Wiring diagram as vector image
mywire.png        Wiring diagram as raster image
mywire.bom.tsv    BOM (bill of materials) as tab-separated text file
mywire.html       HTML page with wiring diagram and BOM embedded
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Command line options</h4><a id="user-content-command-line-options" aria-label="Permalink: Command line options" href="#command-line-options"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>--prepend-file &lt;FILE&gt;</code> to prepend an additional YAML file. Useful for part libraries and templates shared among multiple cables/harnesses.</li>
<li><code>-o &lt;OUTPUT&gt;</code> or <code>--output_file &lt;OUTPUT&gt;</code> to generate output files with a name different from the input file.</li>
<li><code>-V</code> or <code>--version</code> to display the WireViz version.</li>
<li><code>-h</code> or <code>--help</code> to see a summary of the usage help text.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Syntax description</h3><a id="user-content-syntax-description" aria-label="Permalink: Syntax description" href="#syntax-description"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A description of the WireViz YAML input syntax can be found <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/docs/syntax.md">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">(Re-)Building the example projects</h3><a id="user-content-re-building-the-example-projects" aria-label="Permalink: (Re-)Building the example projects" href="#re-building-the-example-projects"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please see the <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/docs/buildscript.md">documentation</a> of the <code>build_examples.py</code> script for info on building the demos, examples and tutorial.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Changelog</h2><a id="user-content-changelog" aria-label="Permalink: Changelog" href="#changelog"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/docs/CHANGELOG.md">CHANGELOG.md</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Status</h2><a id="user-content-status" aria-label="Permalink: Status" href="#status"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is very much a work in progress. Source code, API, syntax and functionality may change wildly at any time.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/wireviz/WireViz/blob/master/LICENSE">GPL-3.0</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Airship to Orbit Project (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jpaerospace.com/ATO/ATO.html</link>
            <guid>40034140</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 20:24:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jpaerospace.com/ATO/ATO.html">https://www.jpaerospace.com/ATO/ATO.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40034140">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>If you want to get to
space you climb on top of a giant fuel tank and light it on
fire. There has got to be a better way.<p>

The idea is simple. Use an airship to float on the top of the
airmosphere, then the craft slowly accelerates using electric/chemical
hybrid rocket engines over days until it reaches orbital velocity.</p><p>

The details are complicated. For one, for an airship to fly at the edge of
space it will need to be big. I mean really big, over a mile long. It
would also need to be very light, a gossomer hypersonic airship. Such a
vehicle is not suited for flight in the lower atmopshere. This and other
factors create the need to a three stage approach.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My cat alerted me to a DDoS attack (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.dannyguo.com/blog/my-cat-alerted-me-to-a-ddos-attack</link>
            <guid>40034045</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 20:12:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.dannyguo.com/blog/my-cat-alerted-me-to-a-ddos-attack">https://www.dannyguo.com/blog/my-cat-alerted-me-to-a-ddos-attack</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40034045">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
        

        

        <p>A few years ago, my cat gave me my most memorable middle of the night software
engineering incident. I was working at a startup, and we didn’t have a formal
on-call rotation yet. That was a deliberate decision, since being on-call is
painful, and the team was good about just collectively keeping an eye out for
urgent alerts. We eventually set up an on-call rotation, but before that
happened, I had a fun night.</p>
<p>Around 3 a.m., I woke up because my cat was grooming my hair. The grooming
itself wasn’t unusual. She did it occasionally, and I optimistically took it as
a sign that she actually liked me and didn’t just tolerate me. Here’s the <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Cat%20Tax">cat
tax</a>:</p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/DM89U2s.jpg" alt="my cat in a Fancy Feast box"></p>
<p><img src="https://i.imgur.com/jDwIABh.jpg" alt="my cat grooming my hair"></p>
<p>But in 9 years, that was the only time she did it while I was sleeping. I
checked my phone to see what time it was, and I noticed that an <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/cloudwatch/">AWS
CloudWatch</a> alert had gone off a couple
minutes ago because of <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/networking-and-content-delivery/identifying-unhealthy-targets-of-elastic-load-balancer/">unhealthy targets for our load
balancer</a>.</p>
<p>I tried to go to our website, but it didn’t load. I groaned and went to log onto
my work laptop. Our monitoring dashboard showed a massive number of requests
coming from many IP addresses that were associated with different countries. And
international traffic wasn’t typical for us anyway since our products were only
available to people in the United States. It was a <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ddos/what-is-a-ddos-attack/">distributed
denial-of-service (DDoS)
attack</a>.</p>
<p>My first and not great thought was to block IP addresses at the server level,
which would have been tedious and possibly ineffective if the attacker had
significantly more source IP addresses to use. But then I remembered that we had
already set up <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/waf/">AWS Web Application Firewall</a>. To
deal with the immediate outage, I set up a rule to <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/waf/latest/developerguide/waf-rule-statement-type-geo-match.html">block requests from other
countries</a>.
It took effect and blocked hundreds of thousands of requests over the next hour
or so. Our website started working again, and the flood of requests stopped.</p>
<p>Later that morning, we noticed that we had received an email to our customer
support inbox around when the attack started. With horrible grammar, the sender
claimed to have found a vulnerability with our website that crashed
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apache_HTTP_Server">Apache</a>, which we didn’t even
use. They said they stopped all traffic to our website and could keep it that
way for months. They generously offered to give us a “solution file” if we sent
them $5,000 in Bitcoin. We didn’t reply, though in retrospect, it could have
been fun to try to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dWzz3NeDz3E">troll them</a>.</p>
<p>I still find it hard to believe the perfect timing of my cat waking me up. You
might guess that the AWS alert caused my phone to vibrate or make a sound,
waking my cat up first. But I keep my phone in do not disturb mode during the
night. So I just like to think that somehow, she sensed something was wrong that
couldn’t wait until the morning. It was certainly a more pleasant way to be
woken up than by a blaring <a href="https://www.pagerduty.com/">PagerDuty</a> alarm.</p>
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI made these movies sharper – critics say it ruined them (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/13/movies/ai-blu-ray-true-lies.html</link>
            <guid>40033646</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 19:25:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/13/movies/ai-blu-ray-true-lies.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/13/movies/ai-blu-ray-true-lies.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033646">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/13/movies/ai-blu-ray-true-lies.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Personal VPN services are snake oil (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://httpscolonforwardslashforwardslashwwwdotzoltanbalazsdotcom.com/2024/03/01/VPN-Snakeoil.html</link>
            <guid>40033522</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 19:08:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://httpscolonforwardslashforwardslashwwwdotzoltanbalazsdotcom.com/2024/03/01/VPN-Snakeoil.html">https://httpscolonforwardslashforwardslashwwwdotzoltanbalazsdotcom.com/2024/03/01/VPN-Snakeoil.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033522">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  
  
  
  
  <p>
    Published on 01 Mar 2024
    
  </p>
  
  <h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>Personal VPN services are a multi-million dollar business. But is it worth your money?</p>

<p><img src="https://httpscolonforwardslashforwardslashwwwdotzoltanbalazsdotcom.com/_img/VPN-1.png" alt="NordVPN"><br>
If they can <a href="https://www.thoughtleaders.io/blog/how-much-money-does-pewdiepie-make">afford to sponsor Pewdiepie</a>, they should do something right, right? Fifty million flies can’t be wrong!</p>

<p>This is going to be a complex topic, so bear with me.</p>

<p>The statement I would like to prove:<br>
There are only a few problems for a few people worldwide where the answer is using a personal VPN service. 
You don’t need a personal VPN service if you are an average Internet user. 
If you are a tech-savvy user, you can do much better than using a VPN.<br>
Personal VPNs are the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Homeopathy#Evidence_and_efficacy">homeopathic medicines</a> of the tech industry. Also known as a scam.</p>

<h2 id="glossary">Glossary</h2>
<p>By personal/commercial VPN service, I mean NordVPN, Tunnelbear, Mullvad VPN, etc. Company VPNs, or a VPN to phone into your home network, are out of the scope of this article.<br>
By public Wi-Fi, I mean Wi-Fi services where it is either open or the WPA key is shared with everyone. From a security point of view, there is not much difference between the two.</p>

<p>Let’s break down the problem of privacy and security. Let’s start with …</p>

<h2 id="security">Security</h2>
<p>Fifteen years ago, it was common malpractice that even though websites used HTTPS for the login page, the rest of the communication was over HTTP. One could steal the authentication cookie from the unencrypted Wi-Fi stream and use that to log in to that service. Tools like Surfjack and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=etyCbkOKHsc">Firesheep</a> were popular tools for wannabe hackers. Back then, using a personal VPN service at public Wi-Fi made sense. Also, many email clients checked their email using unencrypted POP3 or IMAP protocols.</p>

<p>But nowadays, there <a href="https://transparencyreport.google.com/https/overview">is practically no vital service on the Internet</a>, which does not run on HTTPS.</p>

<p>OK, but what about tools like <a href="https://github.com/moxie0/sslstrip">SSLStrip?</a>
SSLStrip works like this:</p>
<ol>
  <li>User types www.mybanklogin.com</li>
  <li>The browser connects to clear-text, unprotected http://www.mybanklogin.com</li>
  <li>Attacker having active man-in-the-middle (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man-in-the-middle_attack">MiTM</a>) capability sees this traffic</li>
  <li>The web server notifies the user’s browser that it should use the secure https://www.mybanklogin.com site</li>
  <li>The attacker removes this notification</li>
  <li>The user continues the login process over the insecure, unencrypted http://www.mybanklogin.com</li>
</ol>

<p>So, can hackers steal my username and password? First, for accounts that matter, you should use 2FA (short for multi-factor authentication). It would be best to use unphisable 2FA like FIDO2/webauthn (e.g. Yubikey) for accounts that matter. 
Nowadays, most browsers implement <a href="https://therecord.media/eff-to-deprecate-https-everywhere-extension-as-https-is-becoming-ubiquitous">“HTTPS only mode”</a>. Next time, instead of turning on your VPN, you should check if your browser already uses HTTPS only mode, and if not, turn that on. For example, Safari does that by default.<br>
Ask your service provider to implement <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_Strict_Transport_Security">HSTS</a>.
It is excellent about HSTS that the user cannot bypass certificate errors. And the browser will auto-connect to HTTPS by default. 
The good news is that if you use mobile apps, almost all are secure already. Just keep your mobile OS and apps up-to-date. No one will spoil a precious <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-day_(computing)">0-day</a> to attack you. 
If you are worried about DNS MiTM, use <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/dns-over-https">DNS over HTTP</a> in your browser. 
OK, but what about tools like <a href="https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/2015/07/15/the-new-metasploit-browser-autopwn-strikes-faster-and-smarter-part-1/">Metasploit browser autopwn</a>? 
Well, the good news is that it is much easier to keep your browser up-to-date compared to ~ ten years ago. Nowadays, however, it is rare that recent browser exploits are openly available for any hacker to use. If you are a target of a government, spy agency, or hacker-for-hire services, yes, they may have the resources to hack your browser, but chances are you are not that important. Sorry. And if you are that important, VPNs will not decrease your risks.</p>

<p>One massive problem with personal VPN services is that they are working to fail open. If the connection fails, your connection is not “protected” anymore. Some premium VPN providers sell “kill switch” functionality, but I am sure less than 1% of the users use this properly.</p>

<p>Looking at the practical side, how many legit stories do you know where someone lost money that could have been avoided just by using a VPN? I have never heard such a story. The “ Darkhotel “ attacker group could have been such an example, except that a VPN would not protect you against their attack, as they used fake Wi-Fi captive portals to deliver the exploit/malware. And before logging into a hotel Wi-Fi portal, you can’t start your VPN …</p>

<p>And before I forget, let’s quickly discuss free VPNs. Never, ever install a free VPN solution. They will abuse your network connectivity, and other malicious or non-malicious users will use it to do whatever they want. It is like inviting one thousand unknown people to your house to have a party and leave them unattended. You can find many stories where free VPNs are actually malware.</p>

<p><img src="https://httpscolonforwardslashforwardslashwwwdotzoltanbalazsdotcom.com/_img/vpn-2.webp" alt="VPN_ads"></p>

<h2 id="privacy-concerns">Privacy concerns</h2>
<p>OK, but what about my DNS and TLS records being exposed to everyone so they can follow what I am doing? In a public place, anyone can look at your display already. Or, if you are worried about your ISP selling your traffic data, there are better options for you. 
Use <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/1.1.1.1/encryption/dns-over-https/encrypted-dns-browsers/">DNS over HTTPS</a>, for example. 
You have to use a VPN provider you trust better than your ISP/Wi-Fi provider.
Also, as <a href="https://support.mozilla.org/en-US/kb/understand-encrypted-client-hello">Encrypted Client Hello</a> is about to start soon, it will be exponentially harder for eavesdroppers to figure out which sites you are trying to visit.</p>

<p>But if you care about privacy, the answer is always ToR, ToR browser or Tails, and never VPN. Except in cases where you first have to hide your ToR usage using a VPN, which is a rare exception among users. If you don’t understand why you would need that, you probably don’t need that complexity. 
Tor Browser uses uncountable techniques that prevent tracking your browser. And if your privacy is essential against local Wi-Fi attackers, your ISP, why is the ad industry not in scope? Adblockers are only half the solution against tracking.</p>

<h2 id="when-to-use-a-personal-vpn">When to use a personal VPN?</h2>
<ol>
  <li>Geofence bypass for region-locked content.</li>
  <li>Piracy. Not that you should not support your artists/musicians/content creators, filmmakers, actors, … but I agree that there are situations in life when piracy is the only ethical option.</li>
  <li>Soft network block/censorship. Do your own research. Don’t end up in jail.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Claims made by VPN companies:</p>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>VPNs reduce the risk of “getting hacked,” whatever that means. 
This is not true. Additional services provided by VPNs, like URL filtering, can reduce your risk. However, it is more effective to use URL filtering on the endpoint level, not the network level, as most VPN companies do.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>VPNs protect your privacy<br>
Even though they increase your privacy, it is still far from what ToR can do for you.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Suppose you want to increase your privacy and security. Instead of watching VPN reviews on YouTube, I recommend that you patch your operating system and your browser and configure always HTTPS and DoH in your browser. Use an ad blocker or, even better, a <a href="https://www.privacytools.io/private-browser">browser built with privacy in mind</a>. If you frequently install new applications, use antivirus/endpoint protection on your non-mobile OS. For Windows, the built-in default Microsoft Defender is a good option. Congratulations, you are in a better position compared to using a VPN, and you don’t have to pay for it, and you don’t have to enable it all the time.</p>

<p><img src="https://httpscolonforwardslashforwardslashwwwdotzoltanbalazsdotcom.com/_img/vpn-3.jpg" alt="Change-my-mind"></p>

<h2 id="what-to-read">What to read?</h2>
<p>I found these articles also useful. As this is a complex topic, with different aspects, if you want to read more, this is where I recommend to start:<br>
<a href="https://overengineer.dev/blog/2019/04/08/very-precarious-narrative.html">overengineer.dev</a><br>
<a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2017/03/post-fcc-privacy-rules-should-you-vpn/">krebsonsecurity.com</a><br>
<a href="https://gist.github.com/joepie91/5a9909939e6ce7d09e29">gist.github.com/joepie91</a><br>
<a href="https://www.spacebar.news/you-dont-need-a-vpn/">www.spacebar.news</a><br>
<a href="https://www.forbes.com/advisor/business/vpn-statistics/">www.forbes.com</a><br>
<a href="https://it.slashdot.org/story/22/01/02/2143256/nbc-you-probably-dont-need-to-rely-on-a-vpn-anymore">it.slashdot.org</a></p>

<h2 id="ps">PS</h2>
<p>Yes, some of these VPN products provide extra services/functions/protections. And some of these extras make sense. But that does not mean that VPN is the answer to your problems overall.</p>

<h2 id="ps-2">PS 2</h2>
<p>WPA3 can support encryption and privacy on open, non-password-protected networks. I have not seen it anywhere in the wild, but the future is bright. If you operate open Wi-Fi networks, please, please, upgrade to WPA3.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sandboxing all the things with Flatpak and BubbleBox (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ralfj.de/blog/2024/04/14/bubblebox.html</link>
            <guid>40033497</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 19:04:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ralfj.de/blog/2024/04/14/bubblebox.html">https://www.ralfj.de/blog/2024/04/14/bubblebox.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033497">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="-content">
      <header>
    
    
</header>

<p>A few years ago, I have <a href="https://www.ralfj.de/blog/2019/03/09/firejail.html">blogged</a> about my approach to sandboxing less-trusted applications that I have to or want to run on my main machine.
The approach has changed since then, so it is time for an update.</p>

<!-- MORE -->

<p>Over time I grew increasingly frustrated with Firejail: configurations would frequently break on updates,
and debugging Firejail profiles is extremely hard. When considering all the included files, we are talking
about many hundred lines of configuration with a subtle interplay of allowlists and blocklists.
Even when I knew which folder I wanted to give access to, it was often non-trivial to ensure that
this access would actually be possible.</p>

<p>Now I am instead using a combination of two different approaches: Flatpak and BubbleBox.</p>

<h2 id="flatpak">Flatpak</h2>

<p>The easiest sandbox to maintain is the sandbox maintained by someone else.
So when a Flatpak exists for software I want to or have to use, such as Signal or Zoom, that is generally my preferred approach.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, Flatpaks can come with extremely liberal default profiles that make the sandbox mostly pointless.
The following global overrides help ensure that this does not happen:</p>
<div><pre><code>[Context]
sockets=!gpg-agent;!pcsc;!ssh-auth;!system-bus;!session-bus
filesystems=~/.XCompose:ro;xdg-config/fontconfig:ro;!~/.gnupg;!~/.ssh;!xdg-documents;!home;!host

[Session Bus Policy]
org.freedesktop.Flatpak=none
org.freedesktop.secrets=none
</code></pre></div>

<h2 id="bubblebox">BubbleBox</h2>

<p>However, not all software exists as Flatpak.
Also, sometimes I want software to run basically on my host system (i.e., to use the regular <code>/usr</code>), just without access to literally <em>everything</em> in my home directory.
Examples of this are Factorio and VSCodium.
The latter doesn’t work in Flatpak as I want to use it with LaTeX, and realistically this means it needs to run the LaTeX installed via <code>apt</code>.
The official recommendation is to effectively disable the Flatpak sandbox, but that entirely defeats the point, so I went looking for alternatives.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/containers/bubblewrap">bubblewrap</a> provides a very convenient solution: it can start an application in its own private filesystem namespace with full control over which part of the host file system is accessible from inside the sandbox.
I wrote a small wrapper around bubblewrap to make this configuration a bit more convenient to write and manage;
this project is called <a href="https://www.ralfj.de/projects/bubblebox">BubbleBox</a>.
This week-end I finally got around to adding support for <a href="https://github.com/flatpak/xdg-dbus-proxy">xdg-dbus-proxy</a> so that sandboxed applications can now access particular D-Bus functions without having access to the entire bus (which is in general not safe to expose to a sandboxed application).
That means it’s finally time to blog about this project, so here we go – if you are interested, check out <a href="https://www.ralfj.de/projects/bubblebox">BubbleBox</a>;
the project page explains how you can use it to set up your own sandboxing.<sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I should also note that this is not the only bubblewrap-based sandboxing solution.
<a href="https://github.com/igo95862/bubblejail">bubblejail</a> is fairly similar but provides a configuration GUI and a good set of default provides;
it was a very useful resource when figuring out the right bubblewrap flags to make complex GUI applications work properly.
(Incidentally, “bubblejail” is also how I called my own script originally, but then I realized that the name is already taken.)
Joachim Breitner also recently <a href="https://www.joachim-breitner.de/blog/812-Convenient_sandboxed_development_environment">blogged</a> about his own bubblewrap-based sandboxing script.
There are many ways to do this, and it was fun to figure out my own solution.</p>

<p>Using bubblewrap and xdg-dbus-proxy for this was an absolute joy.
Both of these components came out of the Flatpak project, but the authors realized that they could be independently useful,
so in best Unix tradition they turned them into tools that provide all the required mechanism without hard-coding any sort of policy.
Despite doing highly non-trivial tasks, they are both pretty easy to use and compose and very well-documented.
Thanks a lot to everyone involved!</p>






    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I made a tool to clean and convert any webpage to Markdown (373 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://markdowndown.vercel.app/</link>
            <guid>40033490</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 19:03:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://markdowndown.vercel.app/">https://markdowndown.vercel.app/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033490">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>Convert any webpage to a clean markdown<br> w/ images downloaded.</p></div><div><p><h3>Options</h3></p><div><p><label for="remove-noncontent">Remove non-content elements</label></p><p><label for="remove-images">Download images locally and link them</label></p><p><label for="apply-gpt">Apply GPT Filter on Markdown</label></p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Good news against dengue (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/content/blog-post/good-news-against-dengue</link>
            <guid>40033268</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 18:36:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/content/blog-post/good-news-against-dengue">https://www.science.org/content/blog-post/good-news-against-dengue</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033268">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/content/blog-post/good-news-against-dengue: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Phanpy: A minimalistic opinionated Mastodon web client (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://phanpy.social</link>
            <guid>40033039</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 18:06:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://phanpy.social">https://phanpy.social</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033039">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Discovering My Roommate's Death on Facebook (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://medium.com/the-wind-phone/discovering-my-roommates-death-on-facebook-3a060fc477ec</link>
            <guid>40033033</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 18:06:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://medium.com/the-wind-phone/discovering-my-roommates-death-on-facebook-3a060fc477ec">https://medium.com/the-wind-phone/discovering-my-roommates-death-on-facebook-3a060fc477ec</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40033033">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><h2 id="9b51" data-testid="storyTitle">Discovering My Roommate’s Death on Facebook</h2></p><div><h2 id="8795">A Journey of loss and reflection</h2><div><a rel="noopener follow" href="https://medium.com/@mohaboelez?source=post_page-----3a060fc477ec--------------------------------"><div aria-hidden="false"><p><img alt="Mohamed Aboelez" src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fill:88:88/1*RjJNbQcqhgVZyJC_Aq3gUA.png" width="44" height="44" loading="lazy" data-testid="authorPhoto"></p></div></a><a href="https://medium.com/the-wind-phone?source=post_page-----3a060fc477ec--------------------------------" rel="noopener follow"><div aria-hidden="false"><p><img alt="The Wind Phone" src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fill:48:48/1*l3U4oGLVdqpfO2nGLFDioQ.png" width="24" height="24" loading="lazy" data-testid="publicationPhoto"></p></div></a></div></div><figure><figcaption>Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@sandym10?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">Sandy Millar</a> on <a href="https://unsplash.com/?utm_source=medium&amp;utm_medium=referral" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">Unsplash</a></figcaption></figure><p id="211f">I found out on Facebook that my new roommate was dead.</p><p id="f52c">I was sitting at my kitchen table around lunchtime, scrolling through clever status updates and cute baby photos, when I saw it. Someone had tagged a recent photo of him grinning in a plaid shirt and had written: “Taken far too soon. RIP Paul.”</p><p id="a051">I froze. I hadn’t seen Paul in about two days. I had assumed he’d been with his friend. But not dead. Of course not dead.</p><p id="cb00">As similar messages began to flood my news feed, irrational thoughts wrestled for control of my confused brain.</p><p id="987e">I looked over at the Mexican ingredients he had stacked in our pantry. “No one buys that much salsa verde and then dies, right? Facebook is lying.”</p><p id="c9b7">Leaping up from the table, I ran through the living room and down the hallway to Paul’s bedroom door. I even knocked and called his name, half-expecting him to answer, and sheepishly apologized for that silliness about Facebook pronouncing him dead.</p><p id="68f7">Silence. I swung the door open. The room was quiet; the carpet still had the tracks of a vacuum from days earlier.</p><p id="2463">Denial turned to panic. Surely there is a series of very important things you’re supposed to do immediately when Facebook announces your roommate’s death. I couldn’t think of one.</p><p id="14ca">Several hours and a handful of frantic Facebook messages later, details emerged. Paul — a cheerful 35-year-old Irish guy who worked for a nonprofit and melted at the sight of a Dachshund — had been hit and killed by a car not far from our apartment two nights earlier. While I had assumed he was spending time with his friend, his body had been in the city morgue.</p><p id="4429">Paul had moved into our flat in San Francisco’s Cow Hollow neighborhood just a month earlier, and during most of that time, I had been overseas for work. We exchanged emails and talked on the phone a bit. The day after I came home, we sat in the window of a crowded Starbucks and laughed about how we would burn sage through the apartment — or whatever it is you’re supposed to do to expel the bad energy of departing roommates.</p><p id="4f8b">We talked about his upcoming trip to Ecuador and promised to speak only Spanish at home. I asked if he’d walked up to the marina to watch our stunning pink-sky sunsets, and his face lit up like I’d just cut his rent in half.</p><p id="41a1">“Oh my gosh, I have to do that!” he said.</p><p id="8ca7">Paul was an almost stranger who was becoming a friend. I was completely unprepared for how his sudden death would unravel and reshape my life.</p><p id="9ed9">For weeks following the crash, it felt like my world revolved around the dead roommate who no longer lived on the other side of my bedroom wall.</p><p id="e96c">I helped his friends sift through his things in search of a funeral suit. I walked up to his open casket and said goodbye to this wax-figure version of a guy whose face I’d last seen in my bathroom mirror a few days earlier. I sat wedged in the corner of a wooden pew as the chapel emptied and tried to compose myself before standing up to be introduced to Paul’s friend. How could I cry in front of someone who had lost so much more?</p><p id="dd4c">Exhausted from sleepless nights in an apartment that suddenly felt like a shrine to my dead roommate, I declined sincere invitations to join his friends at a pub after the funeral. Instead, I clicked down the street, left a message for a friend who didn’t pick up, and took the bus home to sit in Paul’s room and stare at a throw pillow with a Dachshund on it. The next day, his friend came over and tearfully asked if he could have the pillow, saying they had bought it at a flea market together.</p><p id="3cf1">I didn’t know what to do with the rest of Paul’s things, so for weeks I did nothing. His electric shaver stayed in the medicine cabinet, the cans of chipotle peppers on his shelf in the pantry. I watered the chiles he was growing in a green plastic container on a shelf in his room. On top of his dresser sat the tin of hair pomade he had been grabbing out of the medicine cabinet the last time I saw him.</p><p id="1e7f">Instead of working at the kitchen table, I went to coffee shops and generally stayed out of the house-slash-death-shrine as much as possible. But there was no escape. My heart pounded every time I waited to cross the street where he’d died. Our conversations played in my head like a movie — or perhaps a short film. An imaginary clock ticked down the remaining seconds of his life as we naively chatted about the best websites for plane tickets and how he was definitely going to start going to the gym again.</p><p id="5d15">If my reaction to the death of an almost stranger seems dramatic, perhaps it’s because Paul wasn’t supposed to be one more Craigslist roommate through the revolving door. He was a piece of a life that I was determined to deconstruct and rebuild from the ground up.</p><p id="427b">My rapidly approaching 30th birthday had prompted a determination to sculpt my existence into everything I wished my 20s had been. That meant reconnecting and disconnecting, thinking about the space between who I was and who I wanted to be. It meant surrounding myself with people who cared about the world, who woke up every day and did things that mattered. Whatever that meant.</p><p id="31af">A language interpreter supporting a nonprofit dedicated to empowering small business owners in developing nations, Paul relocated in pursuit of a new beginning following a breakup. Amidst mastering his fourth language, he shared aspirations of rekindling neglected friendships. Our lives, much alike, were undergoing reconstruction.</p><p id="c3cf">Until he died, of course.</p><p id="3fd8">Paul was 35, about five years older than me when he stepped off the curb at the wrong moment. Watching tearful friends approach his coffin one by one, I imagined myself lying in that varnished box with wax skin. Did I have five years? Two? A week? Was I living the way I would if I knew that the ticking clock was closer to zero than I wanted?</p><p id="c9ac">A few days after the funeral, I walked to the marina to watch that pink-sky sunset. As the sun bled fuchsia through the sky and the Golden Gate Bridge reflected in the tide, I thought about Paul’s body buried in the ground in Northern Ireland while his belongings were just as he had left them in our apartment a few blocks away. I imagined a parallel existence where he had never stepped off the curb that night, where I would come home and find him studying his Russian notes in a kitchen that smelled like chipotle.</p><p id="13da">Weeks later, I finally summoned the will to clear out Paul’s room. As I carefully packed away the roommate who was gone almost as soon as he arrived, I came across a dresser drawer stuffed with crumpled, recently worn clothes. I pulled out a T-shirt. It read: “All we have is now.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Kate Editor on the different supported operating systems (262 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/</link>
            <guid>40032869</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 17:47:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/">https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40032869">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<article>
   
  <div><h2 id="unix-like-systems-with-x11-or-wayland">Unix like systems with X11 or Wayland</h2>
<p>All <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix">Unix like systems</a> with either <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_Window_System">X11</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wayland_(protocol)">Wayland</a> are well supported since ever.</p>
<p>Linux with X11 and now Wayland is for a long time the primary system on that Kate work happens.</p>
<p>Over the years it was, like most of the <a href="https://apps.kde.org/">KDE applications</a>, ported to various <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Berkeley_Software_Distribution">BSD</a> variants.</p>
<p>Be it some mainstream Linux distribution like <a href="https://fedoraproject.org/">Fedora</a> or a niche one like <a href="http://nixos.org/">NixOS</a>, Kate is available as binary package.
You love BSD?
From <a href="https://freebsd.org/">FreeBSD</a> to <a href="https://openbsd.org/">OpenBSD</a>, you can get a Kate package via your normal package system.</p>
<p>And in the normal case, you can just build it from source on your own, all needed patches should be in our repositories upstream.
If that is not the case for your system, please help to upstream them.</p>
<p>Below the current state of the master branch compiled on NixOS unstable with Wayland.</p>
<center><a href="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/images/2024-kate-linux-wayland.png" target="_blank"><img width="700" src="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/images/2024-kate-linux-wayland-small.png"></a></center>
<p>How to compile Kate on your own on a Unix like system and start to help to develop it can be found out <a href="https://kate-editor.org/build-it/">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id="windows">Windows</h2>
<p>Since several years there are activities in the KDE community to provide our libraries and applications for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Microsoft_Windows">Windows</a>.</p>
<p>Even if that is a non-free platform, we can reach out to new users and developers that might later be then even interested to switch a full open platform.</p>
<p>Progress is slow, but steady.
We have Kate and some other applications in the official <a href="https://apps.microsoft.com/search/publisher?name=KDE+e.V.">Windows Store</a> and nightly build for more of them.
With reasonable effort you can develop Kate on Windows with <a href="https://community.kde.org/Get_Involved/development/Windows">Craft</a>.</p>
<p>Below the current state of the master branch running on Windows 11 inside VirtualBox.</p>
<center><a href="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/images/2024-kate-windows.png" target="_blank"><img width="700" src="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/images/2024-kate-windows-small.png"></a></center>
<p>If you like to try that, use the nighly installer linked on the <a href="https://kate-editor.org/get-it/">Kate website</a>.</p>
<h2 id="macos">macOS</h2>
<p>Beside Windows, the major other non-free platform Kate tries to support is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MacOS">macOS</a>.</p>
<p>We have nighly build available for that and you can, like on Windows, develop Kate with the help of <a href="https://community.kde.org/Get_Involved/development/Mac">Craft</a>.</p>
<p>Below the current state of the master branch running native on my M2 ARM Mac Mini.</p>
<center><a href="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/images/2024-kate-macos.png" target="_blank"><img width="700" src="https://cullmann.io/posts/kate-on-all-platforms-2024/images/2024-kate-macos-small.png"></a></center>
<p>Same as for Windows, if you like to try that, use the nighly installer for either ARM or Intel Macs linked on the <a href="https://kate-editor.org/get-it/">Kate website</a>.</p>
<h2 id="other-platforms">Other Platforms</h2>
<p>Naturally there are more than the above mentioned operating systems around.</p>
<p>Beside the mobile ones like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IOS">iOS</a> that are not that interesting for Kate, many other desktop operating systems exist.</p>
<p>Even if the Kate team itself doesn’t put active work it them, that doesn’t mean Kate can’t run there.</p>
<p>Without any active work on our side, for example a Kate port for <a href="https://www.haiku-os.org/">Haiku</a> was done.
Some one-liner patches for that got even upstreamed.</p>
<p>If you work on some port of our stuff and need to upstream stuff, please contact us.
Even if you work on a non-mainstream system, as long as the patches are not too intrusive, we are interested to have them.</p>
<h2 id="help-us">Help us!</h2>
<p>Naturally the most of our developers are working on the Linux or some BSD.</p>
<p>That means the other systems are always in need of more people to help out, both on the programming and testing side.</p>
<p>For Kate, testing should be easy, grab a nighly build for Windows or macOS on the <a href="https://kate-editor.org/get-it/">Kate website</a>.
Or even better, get <a href="https://community.kde.org/Craft">Craft</a> running, that will make it easier to contribute, too.</p>
<p>One recent topic that needs love is the removal of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/D-Bus">DBus</a> for Windows/macOS/Android and other systems that don’t use it normally.</p>
<p>If you are up to help with that, <a href="https://invent.kde.org/packaging/craft-blueprints-kde/-/issues/17">here</a> that is coordinated.
The current state is already sufficient that the nightly builds of Kate no longer hang on e.g. macOS, but still some frameworks like KIO will need more work.</p>
<p>Just don’t get that wrong, DBus is great on the Linux or BSD systems that use it natively, but it is a pain on systems that have no notion of DBus and leads there to hangs or the spawning of unwanted processes.
Beside that, the usefulness is low there, as there are no services on the bus to communicate with anyways.</p>
<h2 id="feedback">Feedback</h2>
<p>You can provide feedback on the matching <a href="https://lemmy.kde.social/post/1121189">KDE Social</a> or <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/kde/comments/1c3z0g4/kate_on_all_platforms_2024/">reddit</a> post.</p>


  </div>

  
</article>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hidden dependencies in Linux binaries (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://thelittleengineerthatcould.blogspot.com/2024/04/hidden-dependencies-in-linux-binaries.html</link>
            <guid>40032750</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 17:33:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://thelittleengineerthatcould.blogspot.com/2024/04/hidden-dependencies-in-linux-binaries.html">http://thelittleengineerthatcould.blogspot.com/2024/04/hidden-dependencies-in-linux-binaries.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40032750">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-8484368653625039763" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p>
  I have recently released an open source tool called <a href="https://github.com/stolk/sotrace">sotrace</a>.
  It maps out the .so dependencies for a binary or library, and presents them in a nice graph.
</p>

<p>
  When I run it on my lean, mean, simple test program that runs a Vulkan Compute shader, I get this graph of dynamically linked libraries.
</p>

<p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiR9Q-0XTbsdCjFOxtrB_ls_eUT1EojYisOJyXmBBfj9DIHufcbkPuH12SVVORF3btQFOTYc5MUgLMgFtK860xwOCp63Xjb_b48DcUZ11UK340GEJgsYveD8bewIE276gvPTZyaH0zun2bMzCv3YRd68hha9ohGSknKCspmzx0_avNehLUruKrMJ_PAf-Ux/s1600/out-static.png"><img alt="" data-original-height="355" data-original-width="836" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiR9Q-0XTbsdCjFOxtrB_ls_eUT1EojYisOJyXmBBfj9DIHufcbkPuH12SVVORF3btQFOTYc5MUgLMgFtK860xwOCp63Xjb_b48DcUZ11UK340GEJgsYveD8bewIE276gvPTZyaH0zun2bMzCv3YRd68hha9ohGSknKCspmzx0_avNehLUruKrMJ_PAf-Ux/s1600/out-static.png"></a></p>

<p>
  So tidy!
</p>

<p>
  Because I also wanted run-time loaded dependencies, I added a mode where you can run sotool on a process-id instead.
  Running it on a process of the exact same binary, I gaze into the chasm of complexity with despair:
</p>

<p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg_DzGRHat-SIpBGSehMtc6zRiBTeQBRK6VlkpjvC7kdXDPNg17uowukUyKXxPr22OgNz5w0inOGG2OWyPCKCevn03szlCECa6iDVSri5pICUzpUn_T3p7ZeLOHKdWeaOkiVqKq5urI4dVSNI5ZjwquRuiF-0gw0VEBp2zQq85MD0VtEKkH5NvOUArvdWId/s4540/out-dynamic.png"><img alt="" data-original-height="4540" data-original-width="1745" height="600" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg_DzGRHat-SIpBGSehMtc6zRiBTeQBRK6VlkpjvC7kdXDPNg17uowukUyKXxPr22OgNz5w0inOGG2OWyPCKCevn03szlCECa6iDVSri5pICUzpUn_T3p7ZeLOHKdWeaOkiVqKq5urI4dVSNI5ZjwquRuiF-0gw0VEBp2zQq85MD0VtEKkH5NvOUArvdWId/s600/out-dynamic.png"></a></p>

<p>
  Sweet Mother of Isaac Newton! What is this abomination?
</p>

<p>
  This runs a compute kernel on a GPU, with no graphics output at all.
  Why is X11 pulled in? And even some wayland stuff? Ugh.
  This is what I've come to see as hidden dependencies.
  My program depends on them, even though it does not link against them.
</p>

<p>
  Meanwhile, when I use CUDA instead of Vulkan, I get serenity back. CUDA FTW!
</p>

<p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg9dyXUDF9u4E2k4ebgxP-E34Oin035IOevzjmu1izVuuS2xsxPsNLlNb4AzXusBAVbemJLJ-aUyhM7nwqVbFzR_IrY_R1LXxqLacb7Cwfg7IjnBgltNm6It7PYvDJMX9J41oIhFLc5nMZk8Bk3FsMQSUR9Tzdwnc_bbE5ouPvYTtNSlgTRCgqmWUSy4RKz/s714/out-cuda.png"><img alt="" data-original-height="570" data-original-width="714" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEg9dyXUDF9u4E2k4ebgxP-E34Oin035IOevzjmu1izVuuS2xsxPsNLlNb4AzXusBAVbemJLJ-aUyhM7nwqVbFzR_IrY_R1LXxqLacb7Cwfg7IjnBgltNm6It7PYvDJMX9J41oIhFLc5nMZk8Bk3FsMQSUR9Tzdwnc_bbE5ouPvYTtNSlgTRCgqmWUSy4RKz/s600/out-cuda.png" width="600"></a></p>

<p>
  And for completeness, when I run the OpenCL version of my compute kernel:
</p>

<p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjBBlDr109u0cavMF1-zTkiMq_HXdnGZvk35KdW8Fzw1HHjqBRE54P4hyH9FwAX2sYG7ZwNtDwS8Mp4HhYfHgYe8BBHAh3Y-3yRS6J5ZC1eJRmn0xtXHExESTfrmzSerjRa5OhJoJZZ60h0AQG4GIptbZNEkYKYQErG2J_UU5lkf3d108AYU5AaPmD_YxgK/s3316/out-cl.png"><img alt="" data-original-height="3316" data-original-width="1773" height="600" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjBBlDr109u0cavMF1-zTkiMq_HXdnGZvk35KdW8Fzw1HHjqBRE54P4hyH9FwAX2sYG7ZwNtDwS8Mp4HhYfHgYe8BBHAh3Y-3yRS6J5ZC1eJRmn0xtXHExESTfrmzSerjRa5OhJoJZZ60h0AQG4GIptbZNEkYKYQErG2J_UU5lkf3d108AYU5AaPmD_YxgK/s600/out-cl.png"></a></p>

<p>
  So, if you are a developer on Linux, give it a try and be amazed at what you dredge up.
  Let me know your findings!
</p>

<p><i> "Yours Truly, Bram, fighting complexity wherever he finds it.</i></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Interview with Senior JavaScript Developer 2024 [video] (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aWfYxg-Ypm4</link>
            <guid>40032363</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 16:38:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aWfYxg-Ypm4">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aWfYxg-Ypm4</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40032363">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hospitals that make profits should pay taxes (246 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.statnews.com/2024/04/14/nonprofit-hospitals-turn-profit-charity-care-tax-exempt-status/</link>
            <guid>40032233</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 16:23:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2024/04/14/nonprofit-hospitals-turn-profit-charity-care-tax-exempt-status/">https://www.statnews.com/2024/04/14/nonprofit-hospitals-turn-profit-charity-care-tax-exempt-status/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40032233">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
	<p><span><span>A</span></span>s diligent taxpayers breathe a sigh of relief that the hassle of filing their tax forms is over for another year, the Internal Revenue Service continues to let most U.S. hospitals <a href="https://kffhealthnews.org/news/article/nonprofit-hospitals-tax-breaks-community-benefit/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">pay nothing</a> in federal taxes. It’s time for Congress to take a hard look at the IRS’s hand in health care.</p>
<p>The agency uses a vague “community benefit” standard to liberally grant tax-exempt status to so-called nonprofit hospitals even as many of them are financially taking advantage of sick Americans with inflated medical bills. Several of my Johns Hopkins colleagues and I <a href="https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jama/fullarticle/2737183" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published</a> a study in the Journal of the American Medical Association showing that some nonprofit hospitals sue and garnish the wages of low-income patients who can’t afford to pay their medical bills. Where’s the community benefit in that? Nonprofit hospitals are supposed to be compassionate and merciful, not predatory and ruthless.</p>
<p>Many hospitals force people who are suffering and seeking care in earnest to sign their financial life away as a condition of treatment. Some make <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2022/06/30/well/live/surprise-medical-bills.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contesting a bill</a> difficult and others <a href="https://thehill.com/policy/healthcare/4107837-just-over-a-third-of-hospitals-are-complying-with-price-transparency-rules-report/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">do not comply</a> with the federal <a href="https://www.cms.gov/priorities/key-initiatives/hospital-price-transparency/hospitals" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hospital transparency rule</a> which requires hospitals to post prices for common shoppable services. The most recent money game that nonprofit hospitals are dialing up is adding billions of dollars in <a href="https://www.wsj.com/health/healthcare/hidden-hospital-fees-cost-patients-hundreds-of-dollars-0024cd95" target="_blank" rel="noopener">“facility fees”</a> for routine care. These billing tricks are fleecing everyday Americans. Congress could make them disappear overnight if it passed a law disqualifying hospitals that use them from getting the coveted tax-exempt benefit.</p>
<p>Many tax-exempt hospitals argue that they provide millions of dollars in free care. But here’s what’s really going on: Much of what they call free care is emergency care that hospitals are required to provide by law (the 1986 <a href="https://www.cms.gov/medicare/regulations-guidance/legislation/emergency-medical-treatment-labor-act" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emergency Medical Treatment and Labor Act</a> requires hospitals to care for anyone who walks in with an emergent condition). But after the care has been provided, patients are often hounded for payment, often at an artificially inflated price. Hospitals then report the difference between their high sticker price and what they actually collect after shaking down a patient as charity care.</p>
<p>But that’s not charity. In a twist of irony, a 2021 study <a href="https://www.healthaffairs.org/doi/abs/10.1377/hlthaff.2020.01627" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published in Health Affairs</a> found that for-profit hospitals provided 65% <em>more</em> charity care than nonprofit ones.</p>
<p>The bar for receiving tax-exempt status should not be simply abiding by the law.</p>
		
		
<p>Hospitals leaders across the nation have told me that they need to avoid federal taxes in order to survive. But the way taxes work, businesses are taxed only on their profits. Some hospitals hide their profits in cost-shift accounting and loan refinancing, even engaging in aggressive real estate and venture capital investing. According to <a href="https://projects.propublica.org/nonprofits/organizations/951644600" target="_blank" rel="noopener">public tax records</a>, Cedars Sinai in Beverly Hills had an income surplus of $750 million in 2022 and paid no federal taxes. Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center in New York had $400 million and also paid no federal taxes. The top three hospital administrators there made nearly $20 million in salaries.</p>
<p>Try booking an appointment at these or any nonprofit hospital and see if you can do it without insurance or cash up front. It’s nearly impossible. Most nonprofit hospitals will refuse to schedule appointments, even cancer care, unless you financially qualify by showing your ability to pay.</p>
<p>If hospitals schedule appointments and operations only for people who financially qualify, arguing that they are a business, they should pay their fair share of taxes like every other American business. A Kaiser Family Foundation <a href="https://www.kff.org/health-costs/issue-brief/the-estimated-value-of-tax-exemption-for-nonprofit-hospitals-was-about-28-billion-in-2020/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">study</a> estimated the total value of tax exemptions for nonprofit hospitals was $28 billion in 2020 alone. By my calculation, that’s equivalent to a $107 tax credit for every American who filed a return that year.</p>
<p>Momentum to stop this gaming of the system is growing. In August, a bipartisan group of U.S. senators including Bill Cassidy and Elizabeth Warren <a href="https://www.cassidy.senate.gov/newsroom/press-releases/cassidy-colleagues-probe-potential-abuse-of-tax-exempt-status-by-nonprofit-hospitals/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">demanded more transparency</a> from the IRS on the issue after a <a href="https://www.gao.gov/assets/gao-23-106777.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">General Accountability Office report</a> found that the agency “did not have a well-documented process” to ensure that hospitals met tax-exempt criteria.</p>
			
		
<p>In October, Bernie Sanders, the chair of the Senate Health, Education, Labor and Pensions committee stressed the need to address the problem. “Many nonprofit hospital systems across the country are failing to provide low-income Americans with the affordable medical care required by their nonprofit status — despite receiving billions in tax benefits and providing exorbitant compensation packages to their senior executives,” he said in a <a href="https://www.help.senate.gov/chair/newsroom/press/news-chairman-sanders-releases-new-report-showing-major-nonprofit-hospital-systems-exploiting-tax-breaks-and-prioritizing-ceo-pay-over-helping-patients-afford-medical-care" target="_blank" rel="noopener">statement</a>.</p>
<p>In another sign that government officials are getting fed up with hospitals paying no taxes, in 2023 a Pennsylvania judge revoked a hospital’s property tax exemption. This action came after the Pottstown school district sued the hospital, arguing that its special tax treatment resulted in <a href="https://whyy.org/articles/pa-hospitals-revoked-property-tax-exemption/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">$900,000 less revenue</a> for the school each year.</p>
<p>It’s not just the IRS’s lackadaisical approach to hospitals that’s mind-boggling. It’s also the agency’s hostility to direct primary care and other creative strategies developed by doctors to address chronic diseases. The IRS does not allow individuals or families who subscribe to direct primary care — a type of intensive primary care that takes extra time to focus on prevention — to include that cost as a tax-deductible health savings account expense. A <a href="https://trumpwhitehouse.archives.gov/presidential-actions/executive-order-improving-price-quality-transparency-american-healthcare-put-patients-first/#:~:text=potentially%20including%20direct%20primary%20care%20arrangements%20and%20healthcare%20sharing%20ministries%2C%20as%20eligible%20medical%20expenses" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2019 White House executive order</a> challenged this position to no avail. Last month, the IRS sternly <a href="https://www.irs.gov/newsroom/irs-alert-beware-of-companies-misrepresenting-nutrition-wellness-and-general-health-expenses-as-medical-care-for-fsas-hsas-hras-and-msas" target="_blank" rel="noopener">warned</a> Americans that they cannot use their own health savings account to buy healthy foods as directed by their doctors.</p>
<p>The IRS continues to propagate a reactionary approach to sickness rather than a proactive approach to health. Chronic diseases are the leading cause of death in the U.S. and consume a majority of the $4.5 trillion Americans <a href="https://www.cms.gov/data-research/statistics-trends-and-reports/national-health-expenditure-data/nhe-fact-sheet" target="_blank" rel="noopener">spend on health care</a>. The current Whac-a-Mole system isn’t working. Most American adults take <a href="https://www.consumerreports.org/prescription-drugs/too-many-meds-americas-love-affair-with-prescription-medication/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">4 or more prescription medications</a> regularly, making the U.S. the most medicated population in the world. The country needs to try <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7023959/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new approaches</a> to health.</p>
<p>Instead of scolding Americans who sign up for direct primary care or want to eat healthier foods, the IRS should hold hospitals accountable for the taxes they should be paying.</p>
<p><em>Marty Makary, M.D., M.P.H., is a professor at the Johns Hopkins School of Medicine and Carey Business School and author of the forthcoming book </em><a href="https://www.bloomsbury.com/us/blind-spots-9781639735310/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>“Blind Spots: When medicine gets it wrong and what it means for our health”</em></a><em> (Bloomsbury Press, Sept. 2024).</em></p>
<p>
<h2>LETTER TO THE EDITOR</h2>
<h4>Have an opinion on this essay? <a href="https://statnews.com/submit-a-letter-to-the-editor/?subject=Hospitals%20that%20make%20profits%20should%20pay%20taxes" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submit a letter to the editor here</a>.</h4>
</p>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A day in the life of a Walmart manager (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-walmart-manager-who-makes-240-000-a-year-3248037f</link>
            <guid>40031365</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 14:35:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-walmart-manager-who-makes-240-000-a-year-3248037f">https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-walmart-manager-who-makes-240-000-a-year-3248037f</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40031365">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/business/retail/a-day-in-the-life-of-a-walmart-manager-who-makes-240-000-a-year-3248037f: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Roku says hackers gained access to 576k accounts in latest data-breach incident (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/tech/roku-says-hackers-gained-access-to-576-000-accounts-in-latest-data-breach-incident-8f73ab15</link>
            <guid>40031256</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 14:23:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/roku-says-hackers-gained-access-to-576-000-accounts-in-latest-data-breach-incident-8f73ab15">https://www.wsj.com/tech/roku-says-hackers-gained-access-to-576-000-accounts-in-latest-data-breach-incident-8f73ab15</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40031256">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/tech/roku-says-hackers-gained-access-to-576-000-accounts-in-latest-data-breach-incident-8f73ab15: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Stack, an open-source Clerk/Firebase Auth alternative (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stack-auth.com/blog/introducing-stack</link>
            <guid>40031090</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 14:00:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stack-auth.com/blog/introducing-stack">https://stack-auth.com/blog/introducing-stack</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40031090">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><p>If you build lots of projects, it's likely that you've spent a significant amount of time on working with user logins. Despite how crucial it is, it's hard to find a service that has the features you need to get started quickly while remaining open-source.</p>
<p>That's why we built Stack. It has components to get you started within minutes, such as <code>&lt;SignIn /&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;ForgotPassword /&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;AccountSettings /&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;EmailVerification /&gt;</code>, <code>&lt;UserButton /&gt;</code>, and hooks like <code>useUser()</code>. We are starting with support for Next.js and React components (RSC or RCC), but are going to expand soon.</p>
<p>What's cool about Stack is that if you use a design system like MUI or shadcn, its components will automatically adapt to your theme. For example, below is a screenshot of the same sign-in page with Radix UI, and then with Joy UI.</p>
<p><img src="https://stack-auth.com/assets/images/radix-account-settings.png" alt="Stack account settings with Radix UI"><img src="https://stack-auth.com/assets/images/joy-account-settings.png" alt="Stack account settings with Joy UI"></p>
<p>And for the developers, you probably want an interface to manage your users, too. We provide you with a handy admin dashboard that shows an overview of your users and lets you edit or delete them.</p>
<p><img src="https://stack-auth.com/assets/images/dashboard.png" alt="Stack Dashboard"></p><p>It really is that simple. The best part is that Stack is 100% open-source &amp; self-hostable. You wouldn't want to grow your company with sweat and tears only to see that your proprietary authentication vendor locked you in to raise prices.</p>
<p>That's not where it ends, of course. On our roadmap for the next few weeks, we have the following items:</p>
<ul>
<li>Support for more frameworks</li>
<li>SSO/SAML</li>
<li>Passkeys, TOTP and two-factor authentication</li>
<li>AuthZ and permission management</li>
<li>Analytics integrations</li>
<li>etc. etc.</li>
</ul>
<p>We are on <a href="https://github.com/stackframe-projects/stack" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a>, please leave a star if you like the project. We also have a <a href="https://discord.stack-auth.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord server</a>, where we're more than happy to answer questions. If you'd like to get started in just 10 minutes, sign up on <a href="https://app.stack-auth.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">our dashboard</a>.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Redis Re-Implemented with SQLite (373 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/nalgeon/redka</link>
            <guid>40030746</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 12:51:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka">https://github.com/nalgeon/redka</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40030746">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/blob/main/logo.svg"><img alt="Redka" src="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/raw/main/logo.svg" height="80"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka aims to reimplement the good parts of Redis with SQLite, while remaining compatible with Redis API.</p>
<p dir="auto">Notable features:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Data does not have to fit in RAM.</li>
<li>ACID transactions.</li>
<li>SQL views for better introspection and reporting.</li>
<li>Both in-process (Go API) and standalone (RESP) servers.</li>
<li>Redis-compatible commands and wire protocol.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">This is a work in progress. See below for the current status and roadmap.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="#commands">Commands</a> •
<a href="#installation">Installation</a> •
<a href="#usage">Usage</a> •
<a href="#persistence">Persistence</a> •
<a href="#performance">Performance</a> •
<a href="#roadmap">Roadmap</a> •
<a href="#more-information">More</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Commands</h2><a id="user-content-commands" aria-label="Permalink: Commands" href="#commands"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka aims to support five core Redis data types: strings, lists, sets, hashes, and sorted sets.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Strings</h3><a id="user-content-strings" aria-label="Permalink: Strings" href="#strings"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Strings are the most basic Redis type, representing a sequence of bytes. Redka supports the following string-related commands:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Command</th>
<th>Go API</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>DECR</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().Incr</code></td>
<td>Decrements the integer value of a key by one.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>DECRBY</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().Incr</code></td>
<td>Decrements a number from the integer value of a key.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>GET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().Get</code></td>
<td>Returns the value of a key.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>GETSET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().GetSet</code></td>
<td>Sets the key to a new value and returns the prev value.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>INCR</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().Incr</code></td>
<td>Increments the integer value of a key by one.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>INCRBY</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().Incr</code></td>
<td>Increments the integer value of a key by a number.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>INCRBYFLOAT</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().IncrFloat</code></td>
<td>Increments the float value of a key by a number.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>MGET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().GetMany</code></td>
<td>Returns the values of one or more keys.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>MSET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().SetMany</code></td>
<td>Sets the values of one or more keys.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>MSETNX</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().SetManyNX</code></td>
<td>Sets the values of one or more keys when all keys don't exist.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>PSETEX</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().SetExpires</code></td>
<td>Sets the value and expiration time (in ms) of a key.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>SET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().Set</code></td>
<td>Sets the value of a key.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>SETEX</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().SetExpires</code></td>
<td>Sets the value and expiration (in sec) time of a key.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>SETNX</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Str().SetNotExists</code></td>
<td>Sets the value of a key when the key doesn't exist.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p dir="auto">The following string-related commands are not planned for 1.0:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="APPEND  GETDEL  GETEX  GETRANGE  LCS  SETRANGE  STRLEN  SUBSTR"><pre><code>APPEND  GETDEL  GETEX  GETRANGE  LCS  SETRANGE  STRLEN  SUBSTR
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Lists</h3><a id="user-content-lists" aria-label="Permalink: Lists" href="#lists"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Lists are lists of strings sorted by insertion order. Redka aims to support the following list-related commands in 1.0:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="LINDEX  LINSERT  LLEN  LPOP  LPUSHX  LRANGE  LREM  LSET
LTRIM  RPOP  RPOPLPUSH  RPUSH  RPUSHX"><pre><code>LINDEX  LINSERT  LLEN  LPOP  LPUSHX  LRANGE  LREM  LSET
LTRIM  RPOP  RPOPLPUSH  RPUSH  RPUSHX
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sets</h3><a id="user-content-sets" aria-label="Permalink: Sets" href="#sets"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Sets are unordered collections of unique strings. Redka aims to support the following set-related commands in 1.0:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SADD  SCARD  SDIFF  SDIFFSTORE  SINTER  SINTERSTORE
SISMEMBER  SMEMBERS  SMOVE  SPOP  SRANDMEMBER  SREM
SUNION  SUNIONSTORE"><pre><code>SADD  SCARD  SDIFF  SDIFFSTORE  SINTER  SINTERSTORE
SISMEMBER  SMEMBERS  SMOVE  SPOP  SRANDMEMBER  SREM
SUNION  SUNIONSTORE
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hashes</h3><a id="user-content-hashes" aria-label="Permalink: Hashes" href="#hashes"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Hashes are field-value (hash)maps. Redka supports the following hash-related commands:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Command</th>
<th>Go API</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>HDEL</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Delete</code></td>
<td>Deletes one or more fields and their values.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HEXISTS</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Exists</code></td>
<td>Determines whether a field exists.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HGET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Get</code></td>
<td>Returns the value of a field.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HGETALL</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Items</code></td>
<td>Returns all fields and values.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HINCRBY</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Incr</code></td>
<td>Increments the integer value of a field.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HINCRBYFLOAT</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().IncrFloat</code></td>
<td>Increments the float value of a field.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HKEYS</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Keys</code></td>
<td>Returns all fields.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HLEN</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Len</code></td>
<td>Returns the number of fields.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HMGET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().GetMany</code></td>
<td>Returns the values of multiple fields.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HMSET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().SetMany</code></td>
<td>Sets the values of multiple fields.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HSCAN</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Scanner</code></td>
<td>Iterates over fields and values.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HSET</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().SetMany</code></td>
<td>Sets the values of one ore more fields.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HSETNX</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().SetNotExists</code></td>
<td>Sets the value of a field when it doesn't exist.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>HVALS</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Hash().Exists</code></td>
<td>Returns all values.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p dir="auto">The following hash-related commands are not planned for 1.0:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sorted sets</h3><a id="user-content-sorted-sets" aria-label="Permalink: Sorted sets" href="#sorted-sets"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Sorted sets are collections of unique strings ordered by each string's associated score. Redka aims to support the following sorted set related commands in 1.0:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ZADD  ZCARD  ZCOUNT  ZINCRBY  ZINTERSTORE  ZRANGE
ZRANK  ZREM  ZSCORE"><pre><code>ZADD  ZCARD  ZCOUNT  ZINCRBY  ZINTERSTORE  ZRANGE
ZRANK  ZREM  ZSCORE
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Key management</h3><a id="user-content-key-management" aria-label="Permalink: Key management" href="#key-management"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka supports the following key management (generic) commands:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Command</th>
<th>Go API</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>DEL</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Delete</code></td>
<td>Deletes one or more keys.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EXISTS</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Count</code></td>
<td>Determines whether one or more keys exist.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EXPIRE</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Expire</code></td>
<td>Sets the expiration time of a key (in seconds).</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EXPIREAT</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().ExpireAt</code></td>
<td>Sets the expiration time of a key to a Unix timestamp.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>KEYS</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Keys</code></td>
<td>Returns all key names that match a pattern.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>PERSIST</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Persist</code></td>
<td>Removes the expiration time of a key.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>PEXPIRE</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Expire</code></td>
<td>Sets the expiration time of a key in ms.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>PEXPIREAT</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().ExpireAt</code></td>
<td>Sets the expiration time of a key to a Unix ms timestamp.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>RANDOMKEY</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Random</code></td>
<td>Returns a random key name from the database.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>RENAME</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Rename</code></td>
<td>Renames a key and overwrites the destination.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>RENAMENX</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().RenameNotExists</code></td>
<td>Renames a key only when the target key name doesn't exist.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>SCAN</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().Scanner</code></td>
<td>Iterates over the key names in the database.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p dir="auto">The following generic commands are not planned for 1.0:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="COPY  DUMP  EXPIRETIME  MIGRATE  MOVE  OBJECT  PEXPIRETIME
PTTL  RESTORE  SORT  SORT_RO  TOUCH  TTL  TYPE  UNLINK
WAIT  WAITAOF"><pre><code>COPY  DUMP  EXPIRETIME  MIGRATE  MOVE  OBJECT  PEXPIRETIME
PTTL  RESTORE  SORT  SORT_RO  TOUCH  TTL  TYPE  UNLINK
WAIT  WAITAOF
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Transactions</h3><a id="user-content-transactions" aria-label="Permalink: Transactions" href="#transactions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka supports the following transaction commands:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Command</th>
<th>Go API</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>DISCARD</code></td>
<td><code>DB.View</code> / <code>DB.Update</code></td>
<td>Discards a transaction.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EXEC</code></td>
<td><code>DB.View</code> / <code>DB.Update</code></td>
<td>Executes all commands in a transaction.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>MULTI</code></td>
<td><code>DB.View</code> / <code>DB.Update</code></td>
<td>Starts a transaction.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p dir="auto">Unlike Redis, Redka's transactions are fully ACID, providing automatic rollback in case of failure.</p>
<p dir="auto">The following transaction commands are not planned for 1.0:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Server/connection management</h3><a id="user-content-serverconnection-management" aria-label="Permalink: Server/connection management" href="#serverconnection-management"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka supports only a couple of server and connection management commands:</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Command</th>
<th>Go API</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>ECHO</code></td>
<td>—</td>
<td>Returns the given string.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>FLUSHDB</code></td>
<td><code>DB.Key().DeleteAll</code></td>
<td>Remove all keys from the database.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p dir="auto">The rest of the server and connection management commands are not planned for 1.0.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka can be installed as a standalone Redis-compatible server, or as a Go module for in-process use.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Standalone server</h2><a id="user-content-standalone-server" aria-label="Permalink: Standalone server" href="#standalone-server"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka server is a single-file binary. Download it from the <a href="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/releases">releases</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Linux (x86 CPU only):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl -L -O &quot;https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/releases/download/v0.2.0/redka_linux_amd64.zip&quot;
unzip redka_linux_amd64.zip
chmod +x redka"><pre>curl -L -O <span><span>"</span>https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/releases/download/v0.2.0/redka_linux_amd64.zip<span>"</span></span>
unzip redka_linux_amd64.zip
chmod +x redka</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">macOS (both x86 and ARM/Apple Silicon CPU):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl -L -O &quot;https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/releases/download/v0.2.0/redka_darwin_amd64.zip&quot;
unzip redka_darwin_amd64.zip
# remove the build from quarantine
# (macOS disables unsigned binaries)
xattr -d com.apple.quarantine redka
chmod +x redka"><pre>curl -L -O <span><span>"</span>https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/releases/download/v0.2.0/redka_darwin_amd64.zip<span>"</span></span>
unzip redka_darwin_amd64.zip
<span><span>#</span> remove the build from quarantine</span>
<span><span>#</span> (macOS disables unsigned binaries)</span>
xattr -d com.apple.quarantine redka
chmod +x redka</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or pull with Docker as follows (x86/ARM):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="docker pull nalgeon/redka"><pre>docker pull nalgeon/redka</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or build from source (requires Go 1.22 and GCC):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/nalgeon/redka.git
cd redka
make setup build
# the path to the binary after the build
# will be ./build/redka"><pre>git clone https://github.com/nalgeon/redka.git
<span>cd</span> redka
make setup build
<span><span>#</span> the path to the binary after the build</span>
<span><span>#</span> will be ./build/redka</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Go module</h2><a id="user-content-go-module" aria-label="Permalink: Go module" href="#go-module"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Install the module as follows:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="go get github.com/nalgeon/redka"><pre>go get github.com/nalgeon/redka</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You'll also need an SQLite driver. Use <code>github.com/mattn/go-sqlite3</code> if you don't mind CGO. Otherwise use a pure Go driver <code>modernc.org/sqlite</code>. Install either with <code>go get</code> like this:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="go get github.com/mattn/go-sqlite3"><pre>go get github.com/mattn/go-sqlite3</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka can be used as a standalone Redis-compatible server, or as an embeddable in-process server with Go API.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Standalone server</h3><a id="user-content-standalone-server-1" aria-label="Permalink: Standalone server" href="#standalone-server-1"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka server is a single-file binary. After downloading and unpacking the release asset, run it as follows:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="redka [-h host] [-p port] [db-path]"><pre><code>redka [-h host] [-p port] [db-path]
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For example:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="./redka
./redka data.db
./redka -h 0.0.0.0 -p 6379 data.db"><pre>./redka
./redka data.db
./redka -h 0.0.0.0 -p 6379 data.db</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Server defaults are host <code>localhost</code>, port <code>6379</code> and empty DB path.</p>
<p dir="auto">Running without a DB path creates an in-memory database. The data is not persisted in this case, and will be gone when the server is stopped.</p>
<p dir="auto">You can also run Redka with Docker as follows:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# database inside the container
# will be lost when the container stops
docker run --rm -p 6379:6379 nalgeon/redka

# persistent database
# using the /path/to/data host directory
docker run --rm -p 6379:6379 -v /path/to/data:/data nalgeon/redka

# in-memory database, custom post
docker run --rm -p 6380:6380 nalgeon/redka redka -h 0.0.0.0 -p 6380"><pre><span><span>#</span> database inside the container</span>
<span><span>#</span> will be lost when the container stops</span>
docker run --rm -p 6379:6379 nalgeon/redka

<span><span>#</span> persistent database</span>
<span><span>#</span> using the /path/to/data host directory</span>
docker run --rm -p 6379:6379 -v /path/to/data:/data nalgeon/redka

<span><span>#</span> in-memory database, custom post</span>
docker run --rm -p 6380:6380 nalgeon/redka redka -h 0.0.0.0 -p 6380</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Server defaults in Docker are host <code>0.0.0.0</code>, port <code>6379</code> and DB path <code>/data/redka.db</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Once the server is running, connect to it using <code>redis-cli</code> or an API client like <code>redis-py</code> or <code>go-redis</code> — just as you would with Redis.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="redis-cli -h localhost -p 6379"><pre>redis-cli -h localhost -p 6379</pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="127.0.0.1:6379> echo hello
&quot;hello&quot;
127.0.0.1:6379> set name alice
OK
127.0.0.1:6379> get name
&quot;alice&quot;"><pre><code>127.0.0.1:6379&gt; echo hello
"hello"
127.0.0.1:6379&gt; set name alice
OK
127.0.0.1:6379&gt; get name
"alice"
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">In-process server</h3><a id="user-content-in-process-server" aria-label="Permalink: In-process server" href="#in-process-server"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The primary object in Redka is the <code>DB</code>. To open or create your database, use the <code>redka.Open()</code> function:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="package main

import (
    &quot;log&quot;

    _ &quot;github.com/mattn/go-sqlite3&quot;
    &quot;github.com/nalgeon/redka&quot;
)

func main() {
    // Open or create the data.db file.
    db, err := redka.Open(&quot;data.db&quot;, nil)
    if err != nil {
        log.Fatal(err)
    }
    // Always close the database when you are finished.
    defer db.Close()
    // ...
}"><pre><span>package</span> main

<span>import</span> (
    <span>"log"</span>

    _ <span>"github.com/mattn/go-sqlite3"</span>
    <span>"github.com/nalgeon/redka"</span>
)

<span>func</span> <span>main</span>() {
    <span>// Open or create the data.db file.</span>
    <span>db</span>, <span>err</span> <span>:=</span> <span>redka</span>.<span>Open</span>(<span>"data.db"</span>, <span>nil</span>)
    <span>if</span> <span>err</span> <span>!=</span> <span>nil</span> {
        <span>log</span>.<span>Fatal</span>(<span>err</span>)
    }
    <span>// Always close the database when you are finished.</span>
    <span>defer</span> <span>db</span>.<span>Close</span>()
    <span>// ...</span>
}</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Don't forget to import the driver (here I use <code>github.com/mattn/go-sqlite3</code>). Using <code>modernc.org/sqlite</code> is slightly different, see <a href="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/blob/main/example/modernc/main.go">example/modernc/main.go</a> for details.</p>
<p dir="auto">To open an in-memory database that doesn't persist to disk, use the following path:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="// All data is lost when the database is closed.
redka.Open(&quot;file:redka?mode=memory&amp;cache=shared&quot;)"><pre><span>// All data is lost when the database is closed.</span>
<span>redka</span>.<span>Open</span>(<span>"file:redka?mode=memory&amp;cache=shared"</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">After opening the database, call <code>redka.DB</code> methods to run individual commands:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="db.Str().Set(&quot;name&quot;, &quot;alice&quot;)
db.Str().Set(&quot;age&quot;, 25)

count, err := db.Key().Count(&quot;name&quot;, &quot;age&quot;, &quot;city&quot;)
slog.Info(&quot;count&quot;, &quot;count&quot;, count, &quot;err&quot;, err)

name, err := db.Str().Get(&quot;name&quot;)
slog.Info(&quot;get&quot;, &quot;name&quot;, name, &quot;err&quot;, err)"><pre><span>db</span>.<span>Str</span>().<span>Set</span>(<span>"name"</span>, <span>"alice"</span>)
<span>db</span>.<span>Str</span>().<span>Set</span>(<span>"age"</span>, <span>25</span>)

<span>count</span>, <span>err</span> <span>:=</span> <span>db</span>.<span>Key</span>().<span>Count</span>(<span>"name"</span>, <span>"age"</span>, <span>"city"</span>)
<span>slog</span>.<span>Info</span>(<span>"count"</span>, <span>"count"</span>, <span>count</span>, <span>"err"</span>, <span>err</span>)

<span>name</span>, <span>err</span> <span>:=</span> <span>db</span>.<span>Str</span>().<span>Get</span>(<span>"name"</span>)
<span>slog</span>.<span>Info</span>(<span>"get"</span>, <span>"name"</span>, <span>name</span>, <span>"err"</span>, <span>err</span>)</pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="count count=2 err=<nil>
get name=&quot;alice&quot; err=<nil>"><pre><code>count count=2 err=&lt;nil&gt;
get name="alice" err=&lt;nil&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See the full example in <a href="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/blob/main/example/simple/main.go">example/simple/main.go</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Use transactions to batch commands. There are <code>View</code> (read-only transaction) and <code>Update</code> (writable transaction) methods for this:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="updCount := 0
err := db.Update(func(tx *redka.Tx) error {
    err := tx.Str().Set(&quot;name&quot;, &quot;bob&quot;)
    if err != nil {
        return err
    }
    updCount++

    err = tx.Str().Set(&quot;age&quot;, 50)
    if err != nil {
        return err
    }
    updCount++
    return nil
})
slog.Info(&quot;updated&quot;, &quot;count&quot;, updCount, &quot;err&quot;, err)"><pre><span>updCount</span> <span>:=</span> <span>0</span>
<span>err</span> <span>:=</span> <span>db</span>.<span>Update</span>(<span>func</span>(<span>tx</span> <span>*</span>redka.<span>Tx</span>) <span>error</span> {
    <span>err</span> <span>:=</span> <span>tx</span>.<span>Str</span>().<span>Set</span>(<span>"name"</span>, <span>"bob"</span>)
    <span>if</span> <span>err</span> <span>!=</span> <span>nil</span> {
        <span>return</span> <span>err</span>
    }
    <span>updCount</span><span>++</span>

    <span>err</span> <span>=</span> <span>tx</span>.<span>Str</span>().<span>Set</span>(<span>"age"</span>, <span>50</span>)
    <span>if</span> <span>err</span> <span>!=</span> <span>nil</span> {
        <span>return</span> <span>err</span>
    }
    <span>updCount</span><span>++</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>nil</span>
})
<span>slog</span>.<span>Info</span>(<span>"updated"</span>, <span>"count"</span>, <span>updCount</span>, <span>"err"</span>, <span>err</span>)</pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="updated count=2 err=<nil>"><pre><code>updated count=2 err=&lt;nil&gt;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">See the full example in <a href="https://github.com/nalgeon/redka/blob/main/example/tx/main.go">example/tx/main.go</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://pkg.go.dev/github.com/nalgeon/redka" rel="nofollow">package documentation</a> for API reference.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Persistence</h2><a id="user-content-persistence" aria-label="Permalink: Persistence" href="#persistence"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka stores data in a SQLite database using the following tables:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="rkey
---
id       integer primary key
key      text not null
type     integer not null    -- 1 string, 2 list, 3 set, 4 hash, 5 sorted set
version  integer not null    -- incremented when the key value is updated
etime    integer             -- expiration timestamp in unix milliseconds
mtime    integer not null    -- modification timestamp in unix milliseconds

rstring
---
key_id   integer not null    -- FK -> rkey.id
value    blob not null

rhash
---
key_id   integer not null    -- FK -> rkey.id
field    text not null
value    blob not null"><pre><code>rkey
---
id       integer primary key
key      text not null
type     integer not null    -- 1 string, 2 list, 3 set, 4 hash, 5 sorted set
version  integer not null    -- incremented when the key value is updated
etime    integer             -- expiration timestamp in unix milliseconds
mtime    integer not null    -- modification timestamp in unix milliseconds

rstring
---
key_id   integer not null    -- FK -&gt; rkey.id
value    blob not null

rhash
---
key_id   integer not null    -- FK -&gt; rkey.id
field    text not null
value    blob not null
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">To access the data with SQL, use views instead of tables:</p>

<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="┌────────┬──────┬───────┬───────┬─────────────────────┐
│ key_id │ key  │ value │ etime │        mtime        │
├────────┼──────┼───────┼───────┼─────────────────────┤
│ 1      │ name │ alice │       │ 2024-04-03 16:58:14 │
│ 2      │ age  │ 50    │       │ 2024-04-03 16:34:52 │
└────────┴──────┴───────┴───────┴─────────────────────┘"><pre><code>┌────────┬──────┬───────┬───────┬─────────────────────┐
│ key_id │ key  │ value │ etime │        mtime        │
├────────┼──────┼───────┼───────┼─────────────────────┤
│ 1      │ name │ alice │       │ 2024-04-03 16:58:14 │
│ 2      │ age  │ 50    │       │ 2024-04-03 16:34:52 │
└────────┴──────┴───────┴───────┴─────────────────────┘
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><code>etime</code> and <code>mtime</code> are in UTC.</p>
<p dir="auto">There is a separate view for every data type:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Performance</h2><a id="user-content-performance" aria-label="Permalink: Performance" href="#performance"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I've compared Redka with Redis using <a href="https://redis.io/docs/management/optimization/benchmarks/" rel="nofollow">redis-benchmark</a> with the following parameters:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>10 parallel connections</li>
<li>1000000 requests</li>
<li>10000 randomized keys</li>
<li>GET/SET commands</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">SQLite settings:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pragma journal_mode = wal;
pragma synchronous = normal;
pragma temp_store = memory;
pragma mmap_size = 268435456;
pragma foreign_keys = on;"><pre><code>pragma journal_mode = wal;
pragma synchronous = normal;
pragma temp_store = memory;
pragma mmap_size = 268435456;
pragma foreign_keys = on;
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Hardware: Apple M1 8-core CPU, 16GB RAM</p>
<p dir="auto">Results:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="redis-server --appendonly no
redis-benchmark -p 6379 -q -c 10 -n 1000000 -r 10000 -t get,set

SET: 133262.25 requests per second, p50=0.055 msec
GET: 139217.59 requests per second, p50=0.055 msec"><pre><code>redis-server --appendonly no
redis-benchmark -p 6379 -q -c 10 -n 1000000 -r 10000 -t get,set

SET: 133262.25 requests per second, p50=0.055 msec
GET: 139217.59 requests per second, p50=0.055 msec
</code></pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="./redka -p 6380 data.db
redis-benchmark -p 6380 -q -c 10 -n 1000000 -r 10000 -t get,set

SET: 22551.47 requests per second, p50=0.255 msec
GET: 56802.05 requests per second, p50=0.119 msec"><pre><code>./redka -p 6380 data.db
redis-benchmark -p 6380 -q -c 10 -n 1000000 -r 10000 -t get,set

SET: 22551.47 requests per second, p50=0.255 msec
GET: 56802.05 requests per second, p50=0.119 msec
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">So while Redka is 2-6 times slower than Redis (not surprising, since we are comparing a relational database to a key-value data store), it can still do 23K writes/sec and 57K reads/sec, which is pretty good if you ask me.</p>
<p dir="auto">Note that running in a container may result in poorer performance.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Roadmap</h2><a id="user-content-roadmap" aria-label="Permalink: Roadmap" href="#roadmap"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The project is on its way to 1.0.</p>
<p dir="auto">The 1.0 release will include the following features from Redis 2.x (which I consider the "golden age" of the Redis API):</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>✅ Strings.</li>
<li>⬜ Lists.</li>
<li>⬜ Sets.</li>
<li>✅ Hashes.</li>
<li>⏳ Sorted sets.</li>
<li>✅ Key management.</li>
<li>✅ Transactions.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">✅ = done, ⏳ = in progress, ⬜ = next in line</p>
<p dir="auto">Future versions may include additional data types (such as streams, HyperLogLog or geo), features like publish/subscribe, and more commands for existing types.</p>
<p dir="auto">Features I'd rather not implement even in future versions:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Lua scripting.</li>
<li>Authentication and ACLs.</li>
<li>Multiple databases.</li>
<li>Watch/unwatch.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Features I definitely don't want to implement:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Cluster.</li>
<li>Sentinel.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">More information</h2><a id="user-content-more-information" aria-label="Permalink: More information" href="#more-information"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h3><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Contributions are welcome. For anything other than bugfixes, please first open an issue to discuss what you want to change.</p>
<p dir="auto">Be sure to add or update tests as appropriate.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgements</h3><a id="user-content-acknowledgements" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgements" href="#acknowledgements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Redka would not be possible without these great projects and their creators:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://redis.io/" rel="nofollow">Redis</a> (<a href="https://github.com/antirez">Salvatore Sanfilippo</a>). It's such an amazing idea to go beyond the get-set paradigm and provide a convenient API for more complex data structures.</li>
<li><a href="https://sqlite.org/" rel="nofollow">SQLite</a> (<a href="https://www.sqlite.org/crew.html" rel="nofollow">D. Richard Hipp</a>). The in-process database powering the world.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tidwall/redcon">Redcon</a> (<a href="https://github.com/tidwall">Josh Baker</a>). A very clean and convenient implementation of a RESP server.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Logo font by <a href="https://ektype.in/" rel="nofollow">Ek Type</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h3><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Copyright 2024 <a href="https://antonz.org/" rel="nofollow">Anton Zhiyanov</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">The software is available under the BSD-3-Clause license.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Stay tuned</h3><a id="user-content-stay-tuned" aria-label="Permalink: Stay tuned" href="#stay-tuned"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">★ <a href="https://antonz.org/subscribe/" rel="nofollow">Subscribe</a> to stay on top of new features.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Guide to Stock Options Conversations (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://zaidesanton.substack.com/p/the-guide-to-stock-options-conversations</link>
            <guid>40030721</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2024 12:45:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://zaidesanton.substack.com/p/the-guide-to-stock-options-conversations">https://zaidesanton.substack.com/p/the-guide-to-stock-options-conversations</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40030721">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>TLDR: you should help your employees make sense of their stock options. </p><p><strong>When they start</strong><span>, help them understand how different scenarios will play out for them.</span></p><p><span>If they </span><strong>stay for a long time or are promoted</strong><span> - make sure they get additional grants. </span></p><p><strong>When they leave</strong><span> - help them gather the information they need to make a decision. Explain the 3 different scenarios, and how it’ll affect them - the company going bankrupt, being sold for the current valuation, and being sold for 10X. </span></p><p><span>Stock options help you </span><strong>align the employees' interests with the company's success.</strong></p><p>People don’t talk about stock options for multiple reasons:</p><ol><li><p><span>The “Assume your equity will be worth nothing” mantra. Especially in 2024, people prefer to treat stock options as</span><strong> a lottery ticket and not as an investment.</strong><span> </span></p></li><li><p><span>All the (unneeded) </span><strong>secrecy</strong><span> around the compensation package - you are not allowed to talk about your salary and stock options with other employees, and in some places not even with your manager.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Companies make it hard to understand</strong><span> the value of your stock options. </span></p></li></ol><p><span> and </span><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marcorogers/" rel="">Marco Rogers</a><span> had </span><a href="https://safeforwork.substack.com/p/023-startup-equity-the-obvious-yet" rel="">a great discussion about that topic</a><span>, which inspired me to write this article.</span></p><p>They mentioned that it’s our role as managers to:</p><blockquote><p><span>…</span><strong>Give people the info they need to think critically about equity.</strong><span> That means thinking about the probability of options being worth a lot vs. nothing vs. somewhere in the middle.</span></p><p><strong>Without equity, a startup job is just another job!</strong><span> Companies may see employees walking away from equity as letting them keep more for themselves. But this is terribly short-sighted, it takes away a major motivational factor for employees to work hard and stick with the company.&nbsp;</span></p></blockquote><p>I’m going to try to help you do that. You can also do your employees a favor, and just forward them this article :)</p><p>But first, a basic explanation of stock options:</p><p><em><span>For a deeper explanation,</span><a href="https://www.mystockoptions.com/articles/stock-options-101-the-essentials" rel=""> read this article.</a></em></p><p>Every company, including private ones like startups, is divided into parts called shares. These shares represent ownership in the company. For example, if a company has 1,000 shares in total and you own 200 of them, you own 20% of the company.</p><p>Stock options are a special deal companies offer to their employees, giving them the right to buy shares at a specific price, known as the exercise price (or grant price/strike price), after a certain period has passed. This is a way for companies to reward employees and encourage them to stay longer and work towards making the company more successful. </p><p>If the company's value increases, so does the value of its shares. This allows employees to buy shares at the lower exercise price and potentially sell them at a higher market price, making a profit.</p><p><strong>Stock options align the employees' interests with the company's success.</strong></p><p><span>The sad truth is that companies </span><a href="https://safeforwork.substack.com/p/023-startup-equity-the-obvious-yet" rel="">make it very hard for people to understand</a><span> the numbers behind stock options:</span></p><blockquote><p><strong>Marco: </strong><span>When employees try to learn more about equity, they can end up feeling like they’re not smart enough to understand the value of their equity and I think that's on purpose.</span></p><p><strong>Jen: </strong><span>I know for a fact that recruiters at many companies don’t want you to ask too many questions.&nbsp;</span></p><p><strong>Marco:</strong><span> I would go even further than that – the information imbalance has the deck stacked against employees. </span><strong>Companies don’t provide all the information</strong><span> that employees need to make informed decisions. So that’s one reason people simply opt out of the conversation altogether. </span></p></blockquote><p><span>When starting at a startup, an engineer usually gets a stock options grant, with a </span><a href="https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/09/what-is-cliff-vesting.asp" rel="">4-year vesting period, with 1-year cliff</a><span>. What they don’t know, is what they’ve actually got. </span><strong>What’s the worth of those options?</strong></p><p>You can help them with 3 simple questions:</p><p>This is the basic value they’ll need for any future discussion. What is the price they’ll need to pay to buy the share? </p><p>In some companies, the initial job contracts are misleading, and mention a nominal price of $0.01. In reality, when you get the option grant contract (usually after the next board meeting), it’s a higher value. </p><p>In my opinion, this should be discussed during the contract phase, but this is rarely the case, as companies deem it private information. </p><p><span>The crazy part is that even after you join - </span><strong>if you don’t ask, nobody will tell you. </strong></p><p>This information can help you understand if you are ‘in the money’ - meaning the exercise price is lower than the current share price.</p><p>A liquidation event = an Acquisition / Merge / IPO / Secondary sale. </p><p>You can play out a hypothetical scenario with them, just to explain the concept: “Let’s you got 1000 options, with an exercise price of $10, and the current share price is $15.”</p><ul><li><p><span>What can they gain if they sell for the </span><strong>current</strong><span> share price? - They’ll need to pay $10K, and will get $15K - a $5K profit.</span></p></li><li><p><span>What will they gain in the </span><strong>10X scenario? - </strong><span>They’ll pay the same $10K, but will get $150K - a $140K profit. Note that the bigger the company grows, the less impact the exercise price has. </span><br><em>This calculation doesn’t take into account the dilution during future funding rounds.</em></p></li></ul><p>If after having this conversation, the employee is left with the feeling: ”hmmm, even in the 10X scenario that’s not too much, I thought I’d make more” - you need to discuss it with your manager. Maybe you need to offer better packages.</p><p><a href="https://review.firstround.com/the-right-way-to-grant-equity-to-your-employees/" rel="">This article offers a valuable perspective</a><span> to see if your company is good at incentivizing employees:</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png" width="594" height="387.97297297297297" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:435,&quot;width&quot;:666,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:594,&quot;bytes&quot;:97317,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5043275f-8ef4-439c-afcc-d296fffc1674_666x435.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>I’ll not get too deep into that, if you want to read about the best practices of additional stock options grants, </span><a href="https://review.firstround.com/the-right-way-to-grant-equity-to-your-employees/" rel="">go read the article mentioned above.</a></p><p>Just make sure you have a grasp of how it works in your company. You’ll be surprised how much you can affect those things. </p><p><a href="https://safeforwork.substack.com/p/023-startup-equity-the-obvious-yet" rel="">Marco shared his story in the article:</a></p><blockquote><p>After Yammer, I joined another startup as the first engineer, and I ended up vesting quite a bit of equity. When it was time to leave, I had some very serious conversations with my family. We made the bet and put down a lot of money to exercise, then spent 3.5 years waiting. Finally, the news came that the company was going public, and I got an even bigger check than I had from Yammer. I started reconnecting with coworkers and it was… heartbreaking.</p><p><span>Just heartbreaking. People told me, </span><strong>“I didn't understand equity, it seemed too expensive to exercise, so I didn’t do anything.”</strong><span> It’s tough, because the period I worked for that company was pretty grueling, but I can tell you what makes up for it: money. Money makes up for a lot of regret. It really solidified the stance that I'm laying out right now, which is that you can't ignore the value of equity.</span></p></blockquote><p>Do NOT take this story as advice that you should tell your employees to always exercise their options! That is definitely not the case. </p><p><span>The lesson is that </span><strong>most people approach this decision in ignorance</strong><span>. They think something along the lines of: “I need to pay $30K to exercise my options. The chances of actually seeing money from it are very low, so it’s not worth that money”.</span></p><p>Let’s say your employee vested 1000 shares, with an exercise price of $30 for each. So to exercise (=buy) all of them, they’ll need to spend $30K, not a small sum. </p><p><span>In my opinion, it’s our job as managers to help them </span><strong>make the right decision, for THEM.</strong></p><p>What do they need to consider before making the decision:</p><p>Similar to the question in the first section - this is the most critical question, it is the value the investors in the last round paid for their shares. </p><p>There is a HUGE difference between these 2 cases:</p><ul><li><p>A current share price of $50, which prices your shares at $50K. In this case, if you don’t buy the shares, you are leaving $20K ‘on the table’.</p></li><li><p><span>A current share price of $300. In this case, your shares are priced at $300K </span><strong>right now</strong><span>, and you’ll be leaving $270K ‘on the table’. </span></p></li></ul><p>As an insider, people think they have better knowledge, but usually, they just get emotionally involved in the decision. I don’t have data to back that up, but I’m sure that employees that were fired, are much less likely to exercise their options. Their logic could be “If this company chose to fire a great employee like me, there is no chance they’ll succeed”.</p><p>It’s much better to use cold data and take into account the stage of the company. This is just an example, you don’t really need exact numbers:</p><p>Buying your shares is NOT a bet, but an investment. The employee needs to decide if they want to make it, and how much to spend on it.</p><p><span>It’s not all-or-nothing! They can buy just some of their shares. If they are not willing to spend any money, they can use companies such as </span><a href="https://join.equitybee.com/" rel="">Equitybee</a><span>, which lets “you exercise your stock options with no out-of-pocket cost so you can profit from a future IPO.” [Not sponsored, and I’ve never tried them]. </span></p><p>Once they have the information, they need to consider 3 options:</p><ol><li><p><strong>You will lose 100% of your investment</strong><span> - the most likely option. Will you be angry at yourself for spending that money? Will it create a conflict in the family? Or will you be able to brush it off?</span></p></li><li><p><span>The company will be sold </span><strong>close to the current value - </strong><span>how much will you make? </span></p></li><li><p><span>The company will be sold for </span><strong>10x the current value</strong><span> - </span><strong>how will you feel if won’t be a part of it? </strong><span>Is it a life-changing event, and you will regret it your whole life? </span></p></li></ol><p>In the end, only the employee can make that decision, but you can provide A LOT of help in gathering the information and laying out the facts.</p><p><span>It’s important to understand that this could be one of the </span><strong>most critical investment decisions</strong><span> the employee will make their whole life. And as such, it needs to be considered carefully. I would even go as far as to recommend talking to a financial advisor for personalized advice.</span></p><p>I know that most people think that I went a little overboard with the guidance to employees. Until the companies do a better job of it, and there will be better education and common knowledge - I think it’s our job as managers to fill the gaps. </p><p><span>If the subjects of stocks, VCs, and money interest you, I recommend you subscribe to </span></p><p><span> and </span></p><p><span>.</span></p><ul><li><p><a href="https://randsinrepose.com/archives/the-update-the-vent-and-the-disaster" rel="">This is BY FAR the best article I’ve read on 1:1 meetings</a><span>, by </span></p><span> </span></li><li><p><a href="https://read.perspectiveship.com/p/inversion" rel="">What we should do to make our teams miserable</a><span> (the inversion mental model) by </span></p><span> </span></li><li><p><a href="https://enginuity.substack.com/p/manager-leader-mentor" rel="">The multiple forms of leadership - Manager, Leader, Mentor,</a><span> by </span></p><span> </span></li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>