<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 02:30:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X's new country-of-origin feature reveals many 'US' accounts to be foreign-run (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news/xs-new-country-of-origin-feature-shakes-maga-and-democrat-circles-as-many-us-accounts-revealed-to-be-foreignrun-101763857104296.html</link>
            <guid>46028422</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 23:25:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news/xs-new-country-of-origin-feature-shakes-maga-and-democrat-circles-as-many-us-accounts-revealed-to-be-foreignrun-101763857104296.html">https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news/xs-new-country-of-origin-feature-shakes-maga-and-democrat-circles-as-many-us-accounts-revealed-to-be-foreignrun-101763857104296.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46028422">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="dataHolder" data-vars-storyid="101763857104296" data-story-section="world news" data-story-subsection="us news" data-vars-author="Shuvrajit Das Biswas" data-premium-story="false" data-performance-type="not-set" data-story-title="X's new country-of-origin feature shakes MAGA and Democrat circles as many 'US' accounts revealed to be foreign-run" data-collapse-article="true" data-type="story" data-title="US News: Stay Updated with the Latest US News on Politics, Crime, and Local Stories of today| Hindustan Times" data-url="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news" data-story-id="101763857104296" data-story-sectionid="101606302270901" data-story-subsectionid="101697094809307" data-containaffiliate-embed="false" data-disable-poll="false" data-disable-quiz="false" data-published-date="11232025-07:22:10" data-created-by="Shuvrajit Das Biswas" data-author-name="Shuvrajit Das Biswas">      <div> <p>Published on: Nov 23, 2025 07:22 am IST </p>   </div> <h2>Elon Musk's X, formerly Twitter, has rolled out a feature where going to the ‘Joined’ tab on one's profile, displays the country of origin for that account.</h2>  <div> <div dataid="/world-news/us-news/xs-new-country-of-origin-feature-shakes-maga-and-democrat-circles-as-many-us-accounts-revealed-to-be-foreignrun-101763857104296.html"> <div> <p>Elon Musk's X, formerly Twitter, has introduced the country of origin feature that seems to have thrown both the <a target="_blank" href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/trending/us/donald-trump-looks-diplomatic-zohran-mamdani-seems-nervous-maga-fans-react-to-viral-fascist-remark-video-101763778824813-amp.html" data-vars-page-type="story" data-vars-link-type="Manual" data-vars-anchor-text="MAGA">MAGA</a> and Democrats' worlds online into chaos. Several profiles online, that had pushed certain narratives are now being found to have been operating from outside the US.</p> <figure> <span> <picture> <source media="(max-width:767px)" srcset="https://www.hindustantimes.com/ht-img/img/2025/11/23/550x309/X-OUTAGES--0_1763858923898_1763858955787.JPG" alt="X has introduced a feature that lets people see where an account is based out of. (REUTERS)" title="X has introduced a feature that lets people see where an account is based out of. (REUTERS)"> <img src="https://www.hindustantimes.com/ht-img/img/2025/11/23/550x309/X-OUTAGES--0_1763858923898_1763858955787.JPG" alt="X has introduced a feature that lets people see where an account is based out of. (REUTERS)" title="X has introduced a feature that lets people see where an account is based out of. (REUTERS)"> </picture> </span> <figcaption>X has introduced a feature that lets people see where an account is based out of. (REUTERS)</figcaption> </figure> </div>  <p>The social media platform introduced a feature where one can see the country the account is based in. One has to head to an account and click on the date joined tab, which opens up onto a new page. This shows the country where that particular account is being operated from. While the feature was briefly removed after its introduction, it has now been added again, and both sides of the political spectrum are having a field day, calling out each other online.</p>     <h3>What to know about ‘American’ accounts based out of US</h3><p>The accounts being discussed here have pushed agendas within the US, and commented on US politics regularly. Many are also named to echo political movements, like some MAGA accounts.</p> <h2>Also Read | <a target="_blank" href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/technology/x-unveils-chat-a-new-messaging-platform-with-video-calls-and-privacy-controls-to-rival-whatsapp-101763436921864.html" data-vars-page-type="story" data-vars-link-type="Manual" data-vars-anchor-text="X unveils ‘Chat’: A new messaging platform with video calls and privacy controls to rival WhatsApp">X unveils ‘Chat’: A new messaging platform with video calls and privacy controls to rival WhatsApp</a></h2><p>However, these ‘political influencers’ have been found to be based outside the US, raising questions about the motives.</p> <p>One profile going by 'MAGA NATION' with a follower count of over 392,000, is based out of eastern Europe. Similarly, ‘Dark Maga’ a page with over 15,000 followers is based out of Thailand. ‘MAGA Scope’ which boasts over 51,000 followers is actually operated out of Nigeria, and ‘America First’, an account with over 67,000 followers is based out of Bangladesh.</p>   <p>“At this time thousands of MAGA-aligned influencer accounts and large political pages that claim to be based in the U.S. are now being investigated and exposed with many of them traced to India, Nigeria, and other countries,” a news aggregator page on X noted.</p> <p>It wasn't just on the MAGA side. An account going by ‘Ron Smith’ whose bio claims he's a ‘Proud Democrat’ and ‘Professional MAGA hunter’ is operated out of <a target="_blank" href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/kenya-uses-u-s-funded-antiterrorism-courts-for-political-crackdown-101757413804786.html" data-vars-page-type="story" data-vars-link-type="Manual" data-vars-anchor-text="Kenya">Kenya</a>. The account has over 52,000 followers.</p>   <p>‘Republicans against Trump’ an anti-<a target="_blank" href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/topic/donald-trump" data-vars-page-type="story" data-vars-link-type="Manual" data-vars-anchor-text="Donald Trump">Donald Trump</a> page on X, which tries to push politics against MAGA, was reportedly operating out of Austria. While the location now shows US, X notes that the account location might not be accurate due to use of VPN. “The Anti-Trump account “Republicans Against Trump” which 1M followed has been identified as a non-American from Austria and is currently using a VPN to hide their location,” a page said, making note of this.</p> <p>‘Republicans against Trump’ has over 978,000 followers.</p>   <p>On a side note, an account going by ‘Mariana Times’, with over 78,000 followers, which posts pro-Israel content has been found to be based out of India. </p> <p>People within the MAGA orbit have also reacted to this new feature. Congresswoman Anna Paulina Luna wrote on X from her personal account, “All of these pretend “pro-America” accounts that were pushing infighting within Maga are literally foreign grifters. I’m telling you, the foreign opp is real and so are the bot accounts.” </p> <p>Alexis Wilkins, FBI director Kash Patel's girlfriend, also added, “I hope that everyone sees, regardless of their specific reason, that the enemy is outside of the house. The people posing as Americans with big American opinions but are actually operating from a basement across the world have one common goal - to destroy the United States. We have our issues, but we really can’t allow them to succeed.”</p>  </div>  <div>  <p> Stay updated with <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news">US News</a> covering politics, crime, weather, local events, and sports highlights. Get the latest on <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/topic/donald-trump">Donald Trump</a> and American politics also realtime updates on <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news/indonesia-ferry-fire-passenger-livestreams-horror-at-sea-while-holding-baby-watch-101753022743487.html">Indonesia ferry fire</a>. <label for="trendTopsSHow-101763857104296"></label> </p> </div> <div>  <div> <p>Stay updated with <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news">US News</a> covering politics, crime, weather, local events, and sports highlights. Get the latest on <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/topic/donald-trump">Donald Trump</a> and American politics also realtime updates on <a href="https://www.hindustantimes.com/world-news/us-news/indonesia-ferry-fire-passenger-livestreams-horror-at-sea-while-holding-baby-watch-101753022743487.html">Indonesia ferry fire</a>.</p> </div>  <p><label for="trendTopsSHow-101763857104296" id="spanSeeLessEcho">See Less</label> </p>  </div>     </div>     </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Iowa City made its buses free. traffic cleared, and so did the air (184 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/18/climate/iowa-city-free-buses.html</link>
            <guid>46027833</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 22:06:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/18/climate/iowa-city-free-buses.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/18/climate/iowa-city-free-buses.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027833">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/18/climate/iowa-city-free-buses.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Several core problems with Rust (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bykozy.me/blog/rust-is-a-disappointment/</link>
            <guid>46027709</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 21:52:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bykozy.me/blog/rust-is-a-disappointment/">https://bykozy.me/blog/rust-is-a-disappointment/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46027709">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
    
    

    <div>
      <p>I used to call myself a Rust hater, but really I was doing it just to compensate for the perceivable fanboyism e.g. Rust tops on stackoverflow surveys as most-loved language. There are many reasons to hate C++, and I hate C++ too. Lots of people were waiting for a better programming language, but got Rust instead.</p>
<p>There are several core problems with Rust:</p>
<ol>
<li>Its compilation is slow. I mean SLOW. Slower than C++. <span id="continue-reading"></span> I know over years Rust became several times faster, but objectively we need it to be two orders of magnitude faster, not just two times.</li>
<li>It’s complex. Just as complex as C++. But C++ had legacy and Rust had not. The complexity of forcing your way through the jungle of <code>Arc&lt;Mutex&lt;Box&lt;T&gt;&gt;&gt;</code> on every single step directly impacts the quality of the logic being implemented i.e. you can’t see the forest for the trees. Once again, C++ has the same problem, so what’s the point of the language switch in the end?</li>
<li>Memory safety is not that sacred. In fact, for many applications malfunctioning is better than crashing — particulary in the embedded world where Rust wants to be present. You cannot get 99.999% reliability with Rust — it crashes all the time.</li>
<li>When handling lots of mutable shared state (GUI, DB, stateful services, OS/hardware), the performance of native Rust memory model is subpar, and non-native unsafes just leave you with slow compilation, high complexity, and no memory safety in the end — which makes Rust practically meaningless for heavy mutable state jobs.</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="c-actually-sucks">C++ actually sucks</h2>
<p>There is no doubt about it. Undefined behavior (UB) is a fundamental aspec of the language, you don’t simply encounter UB — the whole language is built on UB. You do array indexing and you immediately encounter UB because the language just does not check out of bound access. I want to emphasize that lots of UB-s are not even justified by performance matters — it’s an outright sloppy design of C carried over and amplified in C++. I can go all day long about how C++ sucks:</p>
<ul>
<li>implicit type conversions, implicit copies, implicit constructors, implicit object slicing, and pretty much everything implicit;</li>
<li>function overloading (implicit), particulary considering its omnipresence in STL;</li>
<li>non-uniform error handling with exceptions as afterthought;</li>
<li>still #include-ing text files 40 years after C and One Definition Rule barely checked by compilers;</li>
<li>unsound combination of paradigms (good luck overriding a generic function in descendant classes);</li>
<li>SFINAE nuisance as a core mechanism of generic programming;</li>
<li>T, T&amp;, T*, std::optional<t>, std::unique_ptr<t> to describe similar things, each broken in its own way. Put a const cherry on top of it.</t></t></li>
</ul>
<p>So C++ is complex, unsafe, and it’s compiler is slow. How does the Rust (not) fix those issues?</p>
<h2 id="1-slow-compilation">1. Slow compilation</h2>
<p>It’s not a temporary problem — it’s by design. Here one of the designers explains why the Rust development team sacrificed the compilation speed every time:<br>
<a href="https://pingcap.medium.com/the-rust-compilation-model-calamity-1a8ce781cf6c">https://pingcap.medium.com/the-rust-compilation-model-calamity-1a8ce781cf6c</a></p>
<p><a href="https://prev.rust-lang.org/en-US/faq.html#why-is-rustc-slow">Rust FAQ</a> explains that there are many efforts to optimize it, like better frontend, MIR, and so on. But MIR effort was started at 2015 and it still fails to significantly quicken the compilation (although it speeds up compiler checks).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, it’s impossible to make Rust compile fast. The problem is inherent to all similar generics-heavy languages, like Haskell. Arguably, Rust is closer to Haskell than it is to C++. You can also say it’s close to a template-heavy C++ — and template-heavy C++ code exhibits the same problem of slow compilation.<br>
When you do <code>for i in 0..limit {}</code> — you don’t just iterate, you create a range, you create an iterator, you iterate over it — all of it monomorphized to your concrete types and have to be optimized individually (non-optimized Rust code is insanely slow, it’s mostly unusable even for debugging).<br>
Put a non-optional borrow-checker on top of it — and there you have your insanely slow compiler. And you WILL recompile a lot, because borrow checker is relentless.</p>
<h2 id="2-complexity">2. Complexity</h2>
<p>You just cannot avoid it. You cannot go along like “I’m writing a cold path high-level code, I don’t need performance, I don’t need to go deeper into lifetime handling, I just want to write a high level logic”. You will be forced into the low level nuances every time you write a single line of Rust. There is no garbage collector for Rust and will never be — you will have to semi-manually pack all your data into a tree of ownership. You have to be fluent in ownership, borrowing, traits to write just a few lines of code.</p>
<p>As I’ve already mentioned, this makes it very hard to write high-level logic in Rust. That’s why many of early Rust adopters actually revert to Node.js and Go for less performance-sensitive services — high complexity combined with slow compilation makes it impractical to write anything complex in sole Rust.</p>
<h2 id="3-memory-safety">3. Memory safety</h2>
<p>There are two uncompromising things in the Rust fundament: performance and memory safety. I have to argue that Rust designers went wa-a-ay overboard with memory safety. You know the containers are actually implemented with <code>unsafe</code> functions, because there is just no perfect correctness possible in the Turing machine model — you have to build safe programs from carefully arranged unsafe building blocks. Node.js and Go are considered practically safe language. Rust sacrificed sanity and practicality for memory safety — and gets none of them at the end of the day, it’s still not 100% memory safe.</p>
<p>Now speaking about practicality — lots of use cases just don’t need perfect memory safety. There are ways to implement unsafe programs that still don’t execute remote code or leak secret — they only corrupt user data and act sporadically. If a pacemaker stops — telling a victim “but the memory was not corrupted in the crash” is a weak consolation. We actually had a recent Cloudflare outage caused by a crash on <code>unwrap()</code> function:<br>
<a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/18-november-2025-outage/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/18-november-2025-outage/</a></p>
<p>It’s probably the strongest point of my whining: <strong>Rust is memory safe and unreliable. The price of memory safety was reliability</strong> in addition to the developer’s sanity ­— that’s why I’m telling the language designers went overboard. They sacrificied core practical quality for an abstract principle of memory safety. Just like Haskell designers sacrificed practicality for purity — that’s why I reiterate on parallels between Rust and Haskell.</p>

<p>It’s possible, but employing mutable shared state in Rust just makes no sense. You lose most of advantages and are left with all the deficiencies of Rust. Pretty much all of the successful Rust projects are employing shared read-only state, one way data flow, acyclic data structures: rustc compiler, mdbook and pulldown-cmark Markdown tools, Actix and Axum for stateless handlers, append-only blockchains, single-threaded WASM. The model is, once again, very similar to Haskell, which also excels in parsers, stateless handler, mostly-non-interactive CLI tools, and was employed in blockchains.</p>
<p>Early prototypes of Rust actually had Software Transactional Memory (STM) as an option for safe concurrency, however, STM has performance penalties and it requires simple but significant runtime support.</p>
<p>Step into the shared mutable state — and there a memory corruption is not an exception, it’s a rule. You have to handle the corruptions, you cannot simply crash. Borrow checker, ownership? Just useless, you cannot analyze ownership in a cyclic graph without GC-like algorithm.</p>
<p>Sync/Send, Mutex and reference counting (Arc)? Unfortuantely, those lock or simply mess with CPU caches badly, so they are inefficient for multithreaded communication, at least an intensive one. They are safe, but inefficient. Which kinda destroys the first uncompromising thing in Rust — performance. So, to reiterate, the second you step into the shared mutable state you lose every single advantage of Rust. Which is kinda rational considering that the main concept of Rust was to never employ a shared mutable state.</p>
<p>Particulary, GUI is a mutable shared state. Hence we don’t see any big GUI projects in Rust. <a href="https://zed.dev/">Zed IDE</a> is still beta for so many years — I can almost feel the pain of the developers hacking their way through the borrow checker jungle just to realize their logic is bug-ridden, and they are yet to implement dozens of other features.<br>
Big databases, scalable stateful services, operating systems, at least significant Linux modules? Yet to be seen.</p>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<p>So, is the Rust bad or good? It’s neither. It’s a mediocre programming language with thousands of man-month put into its development — this fact alone makes Rust a viable tool, just because you can pick it from the shelf and employ as-is. This blog was generated with Zola, written in Rust — I did not have to write a single line of Rust code to use it. And the Rust is a good fit for Zola SSG because of its non-interactive nature with one-way flow of immutable data. Just, please, don’t run around screaming “we should all switch our development to Rust because it’s the best programming language”.</p>

    </div>

    
    

    

    
    
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA["Good engineering management" is a fad (158 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lethain.com/good-eng-mgmt-is-a-fad/</link>
            <guid>46026939</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 20:16:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lethain.com/good-eng-mgmt-is-a-fad/">https://lethain.com/good-eng-mgmt-is-a-fad/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46026939">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>As I get older, I increasingly think about
whether I’m spending my time the right way
to advance my career and my life.
This is also a question that your company
asks about you every performance cycle:
is this engineering manager spending their
time effectively to advance the company or their organization?</p><p>Confusingly, in my experience, answering these nominally similar questions
has surprisingly little in common.
This piece spends some time exploring both questions in the particularly
odd moment we live in today, where managers are being told they’ve
spent the last decade doing the wrong things, and need to engage
with a new model of engineering management in order to be
valued by the latest iteration of the industry.</p><div><p>If you’d be more interested in a video version of this,
here is the recording of a practice run I gave for a talk
centered on these same ideas
(<a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/17lTreuVdYMNOr7k2XLzrshEJnB-StaNUzAyh9tE0b5w/edit?slide=id.g39f551c2725_0_0#slide=id.g39f551c2725_0_0">slides from talk</a>).</p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/IJlrX4Z4QWs?si=m9HgL7y0AvdOSUq6" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div><h2 id="good-leadership-is-a-fad">Good leadership is a fad</h2><p>When I started my software career at Yahoo in the late 2000s, I had two 1:1s with my manager over the course of two
years. The first one came a few months after I started, and he mostly asked me about a colleague’s work quality.
The second came when I gave notice that I was leaving to <a href="https://lethain.com/digg-v4/">join Digg</a>.
A modern evaluation of this manager would be scathing, but his management style closely resembled that of the
team leader in <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Soul-New-Machine-Tracy-Kidder/dp/0316491977"><em>The Soul of A New Machine</em></a>:
identifying an important opportunity for the team, and navigating the broader organization that might impede progress
towards that goal.
He was, in the context we were working in, an effective manager.</p><p>Compare that leadership style to the expectations of the 2010s, where attracting, retaining, and motivating engineers
was emphasized as the most important leadership criteria in many organizations.
This made sense in <a href="https://lethain.com/productivity-in-the-age-of-hypergrowth/">the era of hypergrowth</a>, where budgets were uncapped
and many companies viewed hiring strong engineers as their constraint on growth.
This was an era where managers were explicitly told to stop writing software as the first step of their transition into management,
and it was good advice! Looking back we can argue it was bad guidance by today’s standards, but it aligned the managers with the leadership expectations
of the moment.</p><p>Then think about our current era, that started in late 2022, where higher interest rates killed <a href="https://www.readmargins.com/p/zirp-explains-the-world">zero-interest-rate-policy (ZIRP)</a>
and productized large language models are positioned as killing deep Engineering organizations.
We’ve flattened Engineering organizations where many roles that previously focused on coordination
are now expected to be hands-on keyboard, working deep in the details.
Once again, the best managers of the prior era–who did exactly what the industry asked them to do–are now reframed as bureaucrats
rather than integral leaders.</p><p>In each of these transitions, the business environment shifted, leading to a new formulation of ideal leadership.
That makes a lot of sense: of course we want leaders to fit the necessary patterns of today.
Where things get weird is that in each case a morality tale was subsequently superimposed on top of the transition:</p><ul><li>In the 2010s, the morality tale was that it was all about empowering engineers as a fundamental good.
Sure, I can get excited for that, but I don’t really believe that narrative: it happened because hiring was competitive.</li><li>In the 2020s, the morality tale is that bureaucratic middle management have made organizations stale and inefficient.
The lack of experts has crippled organizational efficiency.
Once again, I can get behind that–there’s truth here–but the much larger drivers aren’t about morality,
it’s about ZIRP-ending and optimism about productivity gains from AI tooling.</li></ul><p>The conclusion here is clear: the industry will want different things from you as it evolves,
and it will tell you that each of those shifts is because of some complex moral change,
but it’s pretty much always about business realities changing.
If you take any current morality tale as true, then you’re setting yourself up
to be severely out of position when the industry shifts again in a few years,
because “good leadership” is just a fad.</p><h2 id="self-development-across-leadership-fads">Self-development across leadership fads</h2><p>If you accept the argument that the specifically desired leadership skills of today
are the result of fads that frequently shift, then it leads to an important followup question:
what are the right skills to develop in to be effective today and to be impactful across fads?</p><p>Having been and worked with engineering managers for some time, I think there are
<a href="https://lethain.com/categories-engineering-leadership/">eight foundational engineering management skills</a>,
which I want to personally group into two clusters: core skills that are essential to operate in all roles
(including entry-level management roles), and growth skills whose presence–or absence–determines
how far you can go in your career.</p><p>The core skills are:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Execution</strong>: lead team to deliver expected tangible and intangible work.
Fundamentally, management is about getting things done, and you’ll neither
get an opportunity to begin managing, nor stay long as a manager, if your
teams don’t execute.</p><p><em>Examples</em>: ship projects, manage on-call rotation, sprint planning, manage incidents</p></li><li><p><strong>Team</strong>: shape the team and the environment such that they succeed.
This is <em>not</em> working for the team, nor is it working for your leadership, it is
finding the balance between the two that works for both.</p><p><em>Examples</em>: hiring, coaching, performance management, advocate with your management</p></li><li><p><strong>Ownership</strong>: navigate reality to make consistent progress, even when reality is difficult
Finding a way to get things done, rather than finding a way that it not getting done is someone else’s fault.</p><p><em>Examples</em>: doing hard things, showing up when it’s uncomfortable, being accountable despite systemic issues</p></li><li><p><strong>Alignment</strong>: build shared understanding across leadership, stakeholders, your team, and the problem space.
Finding a realistic plan that meets the moment, without surprising or being surprised by those around you.</p><p><em>Examples</em>: document and share top problems, and updates during crises</p></li></ol><p>The growth skills are:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Taste</strong>: exercise discerning judgment about what “good” looks like—technically, in business terms, and in process/strategy.
Taste is a broadchurch, and my experience is that broad taste is an somewhat universal criteria for truly senior roles.
In some ways, taste is a prerequisite to Amazon’s <a href="https://www.amazon.jobs/content/en/our-workplace/leadership-principles">Are Right, A Lot</a>.</p><p><em>Examples</em>: refine proposed product concept,
avoid high-risk rewrite,
find usability issues in team’s work</p></li><li><p><strong>Clarity</strong>: your team, stakeholders, and leadership know what you’re doing and why, and agree that it makes sense.
In particular, they understand how you are overcoming your biggest problems. So clarity is not, “Struggling with scalability issues”
but instead “Sharding the user logins database in a new cluster to reduce load.”</p><p><em>Examples</em>: identify levers to progress,
create plan to exit a crisis,
show progress on implementing that plan</p></li><li><p><strong>Navigating ambiguity</strong>: work from complex problem to opinionated, viable approach.
If you’re given an extremely messy, open-ended problem, can you still find a way to make progress?
(I’ve <a href="https://lethain.com/navigating-ambiguity/">written previously about this topic</a>.)</p><p><em>Examples</em>: launching a new business line,
improving developer experience,
going from 1 to N cloud regions</p></li><li><p><strong>Working across timescales</strong>: ensure your areas of responsibility make progress across both the short and long term.
There are many ways to appear successful by cutting corners today, that end in disaster tomorrow.
Success requires understanding, and being accountable for, how different timescales interact.</p><p><em>Examples</em>: have an explicit destination,
ensure short-term work steers towards it,
be long-term rigid and short-term flexible</p></li></ol><p>Having spent a fair amount of time pressure testing these, I’m pretty sure most effective managers, and manager archetypes, can be fit into these boxes.</p><h3 id="self-assessing-on-these-skills">Self-assessing on these skills</h3><p>There’s no perfect way to measure anything complex, but here are some thinking
questions for you to spend time with as you assess where you stand on each of these skills:</p><ol><li><strong>Execution</strong><ul><li>When did your team last have friction delivering work? Is that a recurring issue?</li><li>What’s something hard you shipped that went really, really well?</li><li>When were you last pulled onto solving a time-sensitive, executive-visible project?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Team</strong><ul><li>Who was the last strong performer you hired?</li><li>Have you retained your strongest performers?</li><li>What strong performers want to join your team?</li><li>Which peers consider your team highly effective?</li><li>When did an executive describe your team as exceptional?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Ownership</strong><ul><li>When did you or your team overcome the odds to deliver something important? (Would your stakeholders agree?)</li><li>What’s the last difficult problem you solved that stayed solved (rather than reoccurring)?</li><li>When did you last solve the problem first before addressing cross-team gaps?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Alignment</strong><ul><li>When was the last time you were surprised by a stakeholder? What could you do to prevent that reoccuring?</li><li>How does a new stakeholder understand your prioritization tradeoffs (incl rationale)?</li><li>When did you last disappoint a stakeholder without damaging your relationship?</li><li>What stakeholders would join your company because they trust you?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Taste</strong><ul><li>What’s a recent decision that is meaningfully better because you were present?</li><li>If your product counterpart left, what decisions would you struggle to make?</li><li>Where’s a subtle clarification that significantly changed a design or launch?</li><li>How have you inflected team’s outcomes by seeing around corners?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Clarity</strong><ul><li>What’s a difficult trade-off you recently helped your team make?</li><li>How could you enable them to make that same trade-off without your direct participation?</li><li>What’s a recent decision you made that was undone? How?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Navigating ambiguity</strong><ul><li>What problem have you worked on that was stuck before assisted, and unstuck afterwards?</li><li>How did you unstick it?</li><li>Do senior leaders bring ambiguous problems to you? Why?</li></ul></li><li><strong>Working across timescales</strong><ul><li>What’s a recent trade off you made between short and long-term priorities?</li><li>How do you inform these tradeoffs across timescales?</li><li>What long-term goals are you protecting at significant short-term cost?</li></ul></li></ol><p>Most of these questions stand on their own, but it’s worth briefly explaining
the “Have you ever been pulled into a SpecificSortOfProject by an executive?” questions.
My experience is that in most companies, executives will try to poach you onto their most
important problems that correspond to your strengths.
So if they’re never attempting to pull you in then either you’re not considered as particularly
strong on that dimensions, or you’re already very saturated with other work such that it doesn’t
seem possible to pull you in.</p><h3 id="are-core-skills-the-same-over-time">Are “core skills” the same over time?</h3><p>While those groupings of “core” and “growth” skills are obvious groupings to me,
what I came to appreciate while writing this is that some skills swap between core to growth
as the fads evolve.
Where <em>execution</em> is a foundational skill today, it was less of a core skill in the hypergrowth era,
and even less in the investor era.</p><p>This is the fundamentally tricky part of succeeding as an engineering manager across fads:
you need a sufficiently broad base across each of these skills to be successful, otherwise
you’re very likely to be viewed as a weak manager when the eras unpredictably end.</p><h2 id="stay-energized-to-stay-engaged">Stay energized to stay engaged</h2><p>The “<a href="https://lethain.com/frameworks-decision-making/">Manage your priorities and energy</a>” chapter in
<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Engineering-Executives-Primer-Impactful-Leadership/dp/1098149483/"><em>The Engineering Executive’s Primer</em></a>
captures an important reality that took me too long to understand:
the perfect allocation of work is not the mathematically ideal allocation that maximizes impact.
Instead, it’s the balance between that mathematical ideal and doing
things that energize you enough to stay motivated over the long haul.
If you’re someone who loves writing software, that might involve writing a bit more than helpful to your team.
If you’re someone who loves streamlining an organization, it might be improving a friction-filled process that is a personal affront, even if it’s not causing <em>that much</em> overall inefficiency.</p><h2 id="forty-year-career">Forty-year career</h2><p>Similarly to the question of prioritizing activities to stay energized, there’s also understanding
where you are in your career, an idea I explored in <a href="https://lethain.com/forty-year-career/">A forty-year career</a>.</p><p><img src="https://lethain.com/static/blog/2019/40-year-hero.png" alt="Diagram of different ways to prioritize roles across your career"></p><p>For each role, you have the chance to prioritize across different dimensions like pace, people, prestige, profit, or learning.
There’s no “right decision,” and there are always tradeoffs.
The decisions you make early in your career will compound over the following forty years.
You also have to operate within the constraints of your life today and your possible lives tomorrow.
Early in my career, I had few responsibilities to others, and had the opportunity to work extremely hard
at places like Uber. Today, with more family responsibilities, I am unwilling to make the tradeoffs to
consistently work that way, which has real implications on how I think about which roles to prioritize
over time.</p><p>Recognizing these tradeoffs, and making them deliberately, is one of the highest value things you can do
to shape your career. Most importantly, it’s extremely hard to have a career at all if you don’t think about
these dimensions and have a healthy amount of self-awareness to understand the tradeoffs that will allow you
to stay engaged over half a lifetime.</p><p><time datetime="2025-10-26T04:00:00-07:00">Published on October 26, 2025.</time></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[780k Windows Users Downloaded Linux Distro Zorin OS in the Last 5 Weeks (217 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.zorin.com/2025/11/18/test-the-upgrade-from-zorin-os-17-to-18-and-celebrating-1-million-downloads-of-zorin-os-18/</link>
            <guid>46026579</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 19:38:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.zorin.com/2025/11/18/test-the-upgrade-from-zorin-os-17-to-18-and-celebrating-1-million-downloads-of-zorin-os-18/">https://blog.zorin.com/2025/11/18/test-the-upgrade-from-zorin-os-17-to-18-and-celebrating-1-million-downloads-of-zorin-os-18/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46026579">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <p>Upgrade directly and keep your existing files, apps, and settings. Available for testing today.</p>
          
            
              <p><img src="https://assets.zorincdn.com/images/releases/upgrader/18-upgrader-testing-banner.jpg" alt="Zorin OS 18 banner image with 1 million downloads label and upgrade icon"></p><p>We’re thrilled to announce that Zorin OS 18 has amassed <strong>1 million downloads</strong> in just over a month since its release, breaking all previous records.</p>
<p>The response from users, tech reviewers, and creators around the world has been incredible:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“Zorin OS 18 is very polished indeed and an excellent choice for those seeking to migrate from Windows…”</em></p>
<p><em><strong>– ExplainingComputers</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“All-in-all, the ZorinOS team has taken a great Linux desktop OS and made it even better.”</em></p>
<p><em><strong>– ZDNET</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“I really, really like Zorin Appearance… I thought this was an excellent feature for people coming over from Windows.”</em></p>
<p><em><strong>– XDA Developers</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“Zorin OS is a standout choice for ex-Windows users… It’s one of the best free Linux variants that actually feels like Windows”</em></p>
<p><em><strong>– PC World</strong></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://blog.zorin.com/2025/10/14/zorin-os-18-has-arrived/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Learn about what’s new in Zorin OS 18 ›</a></p>
<p>What’s even more encouraging is that <strong>over 78% of these downloads came from Windows</strong>. This influx of new users reflects our mission to provide a better alternative to the incumbent PC operating systems from Big Tech.</p>
<p>We would like to take this moment to extend a massive thank you to everyone who has downloaded, shared, and supported our biggest release ever. Your enthusiasm is what drives us to make Zorin OS even better!</p>
<h2 id="upgrades-from-zorin-os-17-to-18">Upgrades from Zorin OS 17 to 18</h2>
<p>We’re also excited to announce that we’re officially launching upgrades from Zorin OS 17 to 18 today.</p>
<p>This upgrade path is in early testing and is currently only available to users of the <strong>Zorin OS 17 Core, Education, and Pro</strong> editions. Upgrading now will allow us to collect feedback and fix bugs to improve the user experience before its full stable launch in the coming weeks.</p>
<p>This upgrade path is designed to allow existing Zorin OS 17 users to upgrade their computers to Zorin OS 18 directly, without needing to re-install the operating system. This means you’ll be able to keep your files, apps, and settings, all while taking advantage of the new features and improvements in Zorin OS 18.</p>
<h3 id="how-to-upgrade-from-zorin-os-17-to-18-in-testing">How to upgrade from Zorin OS 17 to 18 (in testing)</h3>
<p><em><strong>Warning:</strong> This upgrade path is not recommended for production machines yet. Upgrading during the testing period may cause stability issues or breakages on your system.</em></p>
<ol>
<li>
<p>To avoid data loss, please back up the important files on your computer to an external drive or cloud storage service. <a href="https://help.zorin.com/docs/getting-started/back-up-files/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">View how to back up your files ›</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Install the latest software updates by opening the Zorin Menu → System Tools → Software Updater and following the on-screen instructions.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Open the Zorin Menu → Utilities → Terminal and enter this command:<br>
<code>gsettings set com.zorin.desktop.upgrader show-test-upgrades true</code></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Follow the instructions in stage 3 of <a href="https://help.zorin.com/docs/getting-started/upgrade-zorin-os/#3-start-the-upgrade" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this guide</a> to complete the upgrade process.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<figure><a href="https://help.zorin.com/docs/getting-started/upgrade-zorin-os/#3-start-the-upgrade" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img src="https://assets.zorincdn.com/images/releases/upgrader/upgrading-to-18.png" alt="Upgrader">
</a></figure>
<p>After the testing period is completed in the coming weeks, this upgrade option will be available to all Zorin OS 17 users through the <strong>Upgrade Zorin OS</strong> app. Stay tuned to our newsletter to be the first to know when upgrades are enabled for everyone.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://zorin.com/newsletter/">Subscribe to the Zorin Newsletter</a>
</p>


        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fran Sans – font inspired by San Francisco light rail displays (607 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://emilysneddon.com/fran-sans-essay</link>
            <guid>46025942</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 18:20:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://emilysneddon.com/fran-sans-essay">https://emilysneddon.com/fran-sans-essay</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46025942">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><bodycopy>Written by EMILY SNEDDON<br>
Published on 6TH NOVEMBER 2025
<p>


<span>










<a href="https://www.emilysneddon.com/fransans" target="_blank">Fran Sans</a> is a display font in every sense of the term. It’s an interpretation of the destination displays found on some of the light rail vehicles that service the city of San Francisco.<media-item autoplay="true" disable-zoom="true" hash="J2600265671666234692990740506745" loop="true" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" muted="true" uses="inline-part-styles"><figcaption slot="caption">SFMTA Photo Department</figcaption></media-item><p>

I say <i>some</i> because destination displays aren’t consistently used across the city’s transit system. In fact, SF has an unusually high number of independent public transit agencies. Unlike New York, Chicago or L.A., which each have one, maybe two, San Francisco and the greater Bay Area have over two dozen. Each agency, with its own models of buses and trains, use different destination displays, creating an eclectic patchwork of typography across the city.</p><p>

Among them, one display in particular has always stood out to me: the LCD panel displays inside Muni’s Breda Light Rail Vehicles. I remember first noticing them on a Saturday in October on the N-Judah, heading to the Outer Sunset for a shrimp hoagie. This context is important, as anyone who’s spent an October weekend in SF knows this is the optimal vibe to really take in the beauty of the city.&nbsp;</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="Y2571762958662850480571347675257" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" uses="inline-part-styles"></media-item><p>
What caught my eye was how the displays look mechanical and yet distinctly personal. Constructed on a 3×5 grid, the characters are made up of geometric modules: squares, quarter-circles, and angled forms. Combined, these modules create imperfect, almost primitive letterforms, revealing a utility and charm that feels distinctly like the San Francisco I’ve come to know.</p><p>


This balance of utility and charm seems to show up everywhere in San Francisco and its history. The Golden Gate’s “International Orange” started as nothing more than a rust-proof primer, yet is now the city’s defining colour. The Painted Ladies became multicoloured icons after the 1960s Colourist movement covered decades of grey paint. Even the steepness of the streets was once an oversight in city planning but has since been romanticised in films and on postcards. So perhaps it is unsurprising that I would find this same utility and charm in a place as small and functional as a train sign.</p><p>
To learn more about these displays, I visited the San Francisco Municipal Transportation Agency’s (SFMTA) Electronics Shop at Balboa Park. There, technician Armando Lumbad had set up one of the signs. They each feature one large LCD panel which displays the line name, and twenty-four smaller ones to display the destination. The loose spacing of the letters and fluorescent backlighting gives the sign a raw, analogue quality. Modern LED dot-matrix displays are far more efficient and flexible, but to me, they lack the awkwardness that makes these Breda signs so delightful.</p><media-item autoplay="true" browser-default="false" disable-zoom="true" hash="A2571773420420157235690484312185" limit-by="width" loop="true" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" muted="true" scale="100" uses="inline-part-styles"></media-item><p>

Armando showed me how the signs work. He handed me a printed matrix table listing every line and destination, each paired with a three-digit code. On route, train operators punch the code into a control panel at the back of the display, and the LCD blocks light on specific segments of the grid to build each letter. I picked code 119, and Armando entered it for me. A few seconds later the panels revealed my own stop: the N-Judah at Church &amp; Duboce. There in the workshop, devoid of the context of the trains and the commute, the display looked almost monolithic, or sculptural, and I have since fantasised whether it would be possible to ship one of these home to Australia.</p><p>


Looking inside of the display, I found labels identifying the make and model. The signs were designed and manufactured by Trans-Lite, Inc., a company based in Milford, Connecticut that specialised in transport signage from 1959 until its acquisition by the Nordic firm Teknoware in 2012. After lots of amateur detective work, and with the help from an anonymous Reddit user in a Connecticut community group, I was connected with Gary Wallberg, Senior Engineer at Trans-Lite and the person responsible for the design of these very signs back in 1999.</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="E2571778130962277154087875422329" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" uses="inline-part-styles"><figcaption slot="caption">Original drawings of the display, courtesy of William Maley Jnr, former owner and CEO of TRANS-LITE, INC.</figcaption></media-item><p>
Learning that the alphabet came from an engineer really explains its temperament and why I was drawn to it in the first place. The signs were designed for sufficiency: fixed segments, fixed grid, and no extras. Characters were created only as destinations required them, while other characters, like the Q, X, and much of the punctuation, were never programmed into the signs. In reducing everything to its bare essentials, somehow character emerged, and it’s what inspired me to design Fran Sans.</p><p>

I shared some initial drawings with Dave Foster of <a href="https://www.fostertype.com/" target="_blank">Foster Type</a> who encouraged me to get the font software Glyphs and turn it into my first working font. From there, I broke down the anatomy of the letters into modules, then used them like Lego to build out a full set: uppercase A–Z, numerals, core punctuation.&nbsp;</p><media-item hash="Q2572899645280231776139518191737" media-style="border-width: 0rem; border-color: rgba(0, 0, 0, 0.85); border-style: solid;" uses="inline-part-styles"></media-item><p>

Some glyphs remain unsolved in this first version, for example the standard @ symbol refuses to squeeze politely into the 3×5 logic. Lowercase remains a question for the future, and would likely mean reconsidering the grid. But, as with the displays themselves, I am judging Fran Sans as sufficient for now.</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="A2606685398315595430709885708409" scale="100%"><figcaption slot="caption">Grid comparison. Left is a photo of the display, right is Fran Sans.</figcaption></media-item><p>


Getting up close to these signs, you’ll notice Fran Sans’ gridlines are simplified even from its real‑life muse, but my hope is that its character remains. Specifically: the N and the zero, where the unusually thick diagonals close in on the counters; and the Z and 7, whose diagonals can feel uncomfortably thin. I’ve also noticed the centre of the M can scale strangely and read like an H at small sizes, but in fairness, this type was never designed for the kind of technical detail so many monospaced fonts aim for. Throughout the process I tried to protect these unorthodox moments, because to me, they determined the success of this interpretation.</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="U2634632898338157057546050119801"></media-item><p>

Fran Sans comes in three styles: Solid, Tile, and Panel, each building in visual complexity. The decision to include variations, particularly the Solid style, was inspired by my time working at <a href="https://christopherdoyle.co/" target="_blank">Christopher Doyle &amp; Co.</a> There, we worked with Bell Shakespeare, Australia’s national theatre company dedicated to the works of William Shakespeare. The equity of the Bell Shakespeare brand lies in its typography, which is a beautiful custom typeface called Hotspur, designed and produced by none other than Dave Foster.</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="C2633085234643522250621956958329" href="https://christopherdoyle.co/" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" target="_blank" uses="inline-part-styles"><figcaption slot="caption">Hotspur by DAVE FOSTER.</figcaption></media-item><p>

Often, brand fonts are chosen or designed to convey a single feeling. Maybe it’s warmth and friendliness, or a sense of tech and innovation. But what I’ve always loved about the Bell typeface is how one weight could serve both Shakespeare’s comedies and tragedies, simply by shifting scale, spacing, or alignment. Hotspur has the gravity to carry the darkness of <i>Titus Andronicus</i> and the roundness to convey the humour of <i>Much Ado About Nothing</i>. And while Fran Sans Solid is technically no Hotspur, I wanted it to share that same versatility.</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="K2633083737395092763912490494073" href="https://christopherdoyle.co/" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" target="_blank" uses="inline-part-styles"><figcaption slot="caption">Bell Shakespeare by CHRISTOPHER DOYLE &amp; CO.</figcaption></media-item><p>

Further inspiration for Fran Sans came from the <a href="https://letterformarchive.org/" target="_blank">Letterform Archive</a>, the world’s leading typography archive, based in San Francisco. Librarian and archivist <a href="https://www.kateallalong.com/" target="_blank">Kate Long Stellar</a> thoughtfully curated a research visit filled with modular typography spanning most of the past century. On the table were two pieces that had a significant impact on Fran Sans and are now personal must-sees at the archive. First, Joan Trochut’s <i>Tipo Veloz</i> “Fast Type” (1942) was created during the Second World War when resources were scarce. <i>Tipo Veloz</i> gave printers the ability to draw with type, rearranging modular pieces to form letters, ornaments and even illustrations.</p><p>

Second, Zuzana Licko’s process work for <i>Lo-Res</i> (1985), an Emigre typeface, opened new ways of thinking about how ideas move between the physical and the digital and then back again. Seeing how <i>Lo-Res</i> was documented through iterations and variations gave the typeface a depth and richness that changed my understanding of how fonts are built. At some point I want to explore physical applications for Fran Sans out of respect for its origins, since it is impossible to fully capture the display’s charm on screen.</p><media-item disable-zoom="true" hash="Q2572944407798912902336988096633" media-style="border-color: #d02a00; border-width: 0.3rem; border-style: solid;" uses="inline-part-styles"><figcaption slot="caption">Letterform Archive research visit, MAY 2025.</figcaption></media-item><p>

Back at the SFMTA, Armando told me the Breda vehicles are being replaced, and with them their destination displays will be swapped for newer LED dot-matrix units that are more efficient and easier to maintain. By the end of 2025 the signs that inspired Fran Sans will disappear from the city, taking with them a small but distinctive part of the city’s voice. 
That feels like a real loss. San Francisco is always reinventing itself, yet its charm lies in how much of its history still shows through. My hope is that Fran Sans can inspire a deeper appreciation for the imperfections that give our lives and our cities character. Life is so rich when ease and efficiency are not the measure.</p></span><span>For commercial and non-commercial use of FRAN SANS, please get in touch: <a href="mailto:emily@emilysneddon.com" rel="mailto">emily@emilysneddon.com</a><p>WITH THANKS<br>Dave Foster, for being my go-to at every stage of this project.<br>Maria Doreuli, for thoughtfully reviewing Fran Sans.<br>Maddy Carrucan, for the words that always keep me dreamy.<br>Jeremy Menzies, for the photography of the Breda vehicles.<br>Kate Long Stellar, for curating a research visit on modular typography.<br>Angie Wang, for suggesting it and helping to make it happen.<br>Vasiliy Tsurkan, for inviting me into to the SFMTA workshop.<br>Armando Lumbad, for maintaining the signs that I love so much.<br>Rick Laubscher, for putting me in touch with the SFMTA.<br>William Maley Jr, for opening up the TRANS-LITE, INC. archives.<br>Gary Wallberg, for designing and engineering the original signs.<br>Gregory Wallberg, for responding to a very suspicious facebook post.<br>Reddit u/steve31086, for sleuthing the details of William Maley Jr.</p></span><span></span><span><span>OUTSIDE MY LIFE,<br>INSIDE THE DREAM.<p>

FALLING UP THE STAIRS,<br>INTO THE STREET.</p><p>

LET THE CABLE CAR<br>CARRY ME.</p><p>

STRAIGHT OUT OF TOWN,<br>INTO THE SEA.</p><p>

PAST THE DAHLIAS AND<br>THE SELF-DRIVING CARS.</p><p>

THE CHURCH OF 8 WHEELS.<br>THE LOWER HAIGHT BARS.</p><p>

THE PEAK HOUR SPRAWL.<br>THE KIDS IN THE PARK.</p><p>

THE SLANTING HOUSES.<br>THE BAY AFTER DARK.</p><p>

MY WINDOW, MY OWN<br>SILVER SCREEN.</p><p>

I FOLLOW WHERE THE<br>FOG TAKES ME.</p><p><span>By
<a href="https://www.instagram.com/okheymaddy" target="_blank">MADDY CARRUCAN</a></span></p></span></span><span></span><span></span></p></bodycopy></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Native Secure Enclave backed SSH keys on macOS (320 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gist.github.com/arianvp/5f59f1783e3eaf1a2d4cd8e952bb4acf</link>
            <guid>46025721</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 17:55:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gist.github.com/arianvp/5f59f1783e3eaf1a2d4cd8e952bb4acf">https://gist.github.com/arianvp/5f59f1783e3eaf1a2d4cd8e952bb4acf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46025721">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="file-ssh_macos_secure_enclaves-md" tabindex="0" role="region" aria-label="SSH_MACOS_SECURE_ENCLAVES.md content, created by arianvp on 05:53PM today.">
    <article itemprop="text">
<p dir="auto">It turns out that MacOS Tahoe can generate and use secure-enclave backed SSH keys! This replaces projects like <a href="https://github.com/maxgoedjen/secretive">https://github.com/maxgoedjen/secretive</a></p>
<p dir="auto">There is a shared library <code>/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib</code> that traditionally has been used to add smartcard support
to ssh by implementing <code>PKCS11Provider</code> interface. However since recently it also implements <code>SecurityKeyProivder</code>
which supports loading keys directly from the secure enclave! <code>SecurityKeyProvider</code> is what is normally used to talk to FIDO2 devices (e.g. <code>libfido2</code> can be used to talk to your Yubikey). However you can now use it to talk to your Secure Enclave instead!</p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span>recording.mov</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/628387/517875041-ff033694-13e1-454e-b42b-b5c19e0fb2a0.mov?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjM5MjY1MDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2MzkyNjIwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii82MjgzODcvNTE3ODc1MDQxLWZmMDMzNjk0LTEzZTEtNDU0ZS1iNDJiLWI1YzE5ZTBmYjJhMC5tb3Y_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMTIzJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTEyM1QxOTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT05NjE1Y2I3ZTU4MTJhZTJjYmRjZWU4ZWJkM2VhZDQ5OThlM2QwYjE0NzQ0MmI3MDAwZmUwNTdlYjUyMDA3NTVjJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.CTlxpHcd3krcgxNbq4CAYVk9dXiFV53_mHbAsMiDYKE" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/628387/517875041-ff033694-13e1-454e-b42b-b5c19e0fb2a0.mov?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjM5MjY1MDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2MzkyNjIwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii82MjgzODcvNTE3ODc1MDQxLWZmMDMzNjk0LTEzZTEtNDU0ZS1iNDJiLWI1YzE5ZTBmYjJhMC5tb3Y_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMTIzJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTEyM1QxOTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT05NjE1Y2I3ZTU4MTJhZTJjYmRjZWU4ZWJkM2VhZDQ5OThlM2QwYjE0NzQ0MmI3MDAwZmUwNTdlYjUyMDA3NTVjJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.CTlxpHcd3krcgxNbq4CAYVk9dXiFV53_mHbAsMiDYKE" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">Key setup</h2><a id="user-content-key-setup" aria-label="Permalink: Key setup" href="#key-setup"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <code>man sc_auth</code> and <code>man ssh-keychain</code> for all the options</p>
<p dir="auto">To create a Secure Enclave backed key that requires biometrics, run the
following command and press TouchID:</p>
<pre><code>% sc_auth create-ctk-identity -l ssh -k p-256-ne -t bio
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">You can confirm that the key was create with the <code>list-ctk-identities</code> command:</p>
<pre><code>arian@Mac ssh-keychain % sc_auth  list-ctk-identities       
Key Type Public Key Hash                          Prot Label Common Name Email Address Valid To        Valid 
p-256-ne A71277F0BC5825A7B3576D014F31282A866EF3BC bio  ssh   ssh                       23.11.26, 17:09 YES
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">It also supports listing the ssh key fingerprints instead:</p>
<pre><code>% sc_auth  list-ctk-identities -t ssh
Key Type Public Key Hash                                    Prot Label Common Name Email Address Valid To        Valid 
p-256-ne SHA256:vs4ByYo+T9M3V8iiDYONMSvx2k5Fj2ujVBWt1j6yzis bio  ssh   ssh                       23.11.26, 17:09 YES 
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">Keys can be deleted with</p>
<pre><code>% sc_auth delete-ctk-identity -h &lt;Public Key Hash&gt;
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">Usage with <code>ssh</code></h2><a id="user-content-usage-with-ssh" aria-label="Permalink: Usage with ssh" href="#usage-with-ssh"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can "download" the public / private keypair from the secure enclave using the following command:</p>
<pre><code>% ssh-keygen -w /usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib -K -N ""
Enter PIN for authenticator: 
You may need to touch your authenticator to authorize key download.
Saved ECDSA-SK key to id_ecdsa_sk_rk
% cat id_ecdsa_sk_rk.pub 
sk-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256@openssh.com AAAAInNrLWVjZHNhLXNoYTItbmlzdHAyNTZAb3BlbnNzaC5jb20AAAAIbmlzdHAyNTYAAABBBKiHAiAZhcsZ95n85dkNGs9GnbDt0aNOia2gnuknYV2wKL3y0u+d3QrE9cFkmWXIymHZMglL+uJA+6mShY8SeykAAAAEc3NoOg== ssh:
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">You can just use the empty string for PIN. For some reason <code>openssh</code> always asks for
it even if the authenticator in question does not use a PIN but a biometric.
Note that the "private" key here is just a reference to the FIDO credential. It does
not contain any secret key material. Hence I'm specifiyng <code>-N ""</code> to skip an encryption
passphrase.</p>
<p dir="auto">Now if you copy this public key to your authorized keys file, it should work!</p>
<pre><code>% ssh-copy-id -i id_ecdsa_sk_rk localhost
% ssh -o SecurityKeyProvider=/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib localhost
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">Usage with <code>ssh-agent</code></h2><a id="user-content-usage-with-ssh-agent" aria-label="Permalink: Usage with ssh-agent" href="#usage-with-ssh-agent"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Instead of downloading the public/private keypair to a file you can also directly
make the keys available to <code>ssh-agent</code>. For this you can use the following command:</p>
<pre><code>% ssh-add -K -S /usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib
Enter PIN for authenticator: 
Resident identity added: ECDSA-SK SHA256:vs4ByYo+T9M3V8iiDYONMSvx2k5Fj2ujVBWt1j6yzis
% ssh-add -L
sk-ecdsa-sha2-nistp256@openssh.com AAAAInNrLWVjZHNhLXNoYTItbmlzdHAyNTZAb3BlbnNzaC5jb20AAAAIbmlzdHAyNTYAAABBBKiHAiAZhcsZ95n85dkNGs9GnbDt0aNOia2gnuknYV2wKL3y0u+d3QrE9cFkmWXIymHZMglL+uJA+6mShY8SeykAAAAEc3NoOg== 
% ssh-copy-id localhost
% ssh -o SecurityKeyProvider=/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib localhost
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">Using the SecurityKeyProvider by default</h2><a id="user-content-using-the-securitykeyprovider-by-default" aria-label="Permalink: Using the SecurityKeyProvider by default" href="#using-the-securitykeyprovider-by-default"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>SecurityKeyProvider</code> can be configured in <code>.ssh/config</code> but I recommend setting
<code>export SSH_SK_PROVIDER=/usr/lib/ssh-keychain.dylib</code> in your <code>.zprofile</code> instead as
that environment variable gets picked up by <code>ssh</code>, <code>ssh-add</code> and <code>ssh-keygen</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">This means you can just do:</p>
<pre><code>ssh-add -K
ssh my-server
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">or</p>
<pre><code>ssh-keygen -K
ssh -i id_ecdsa_rk_sk my-server
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">to ssh into your server</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">Exportable keys</h2><a id="user-content-exportable-keys" aria-label="Permalink: Exportable keys" href="#exportable-keys"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">There's also an exportable variant where the private key is encrypted using the secure enclave as opposed to generated on the secure enclave. This is might be considered secure but is convenient for key backup.</p>
<pre><code>% sc_auth create-ctk-identity -l ssh-exportable -k p-256 -t bio
% sc_auth list-ctk-identities
p-256    A581E5404ED157C4C73FFDBDFC1339E0D873FCAE bio  ssh-exportable ssh-exportable               23.11.26, 19:50 YES  
% sc_auth export-ctk-identity -h A581E5404ED157C4C73FFDBDFC1339E0D873FCAE -f ssh-exportable.pem
Enter a password which will be used to protect the exported items:
Verify password:
</code></pre>
<p dir="auto">You can then re-import it on another device</p>
<pre><code>% sc_auth import-ctk-identities -f ssh-exportable.pem.p12 -t bio
Enter PKCS12 file password:
</code></pre>
</article>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are consumers just tech debt to Microsoft? (219 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://birchtree.me/blog/are-consumers-just-tech-debt-to-microsoft/</link>
            <guid>46025196</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 17:14:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://birchtree.me/blog/are-consumers-just-tech-debt-to-microsoft/">https://birchtree.me/blog/are-consumers-just-tech-debt-to-microsoft/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46025196">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                
<main>

        <article>

        

    <div>
        <p>I’m not saying this will definitely happen, but I think we could be on the cusp of a significant shift in Windows market share for consumer computers. It is not going to drop to 2% in a year or anything, but I feel like a few pieces are coming together that could move the needle in a way we have not seen in several decades. There are three things on my mind .</p><p>Number one is that Microsoft just does not feel like a consumer tech company at all anymore. Yes, they have always been much more corporate than the likes of Apple or Google, but it really shows in the last few years as they seem to only have energy for AI and web services. If you are not a customer who is a major business or a developer creating the next AI-powered app, Microsoft does not seem to care about you.</p><p>I just do not see excitement there. The only thing of note they have added to Windows in the last five years is Copilot, and I have yet to meet a normal human being who enjoys using it. And all the Windows 11 changes seem to have just gone over about as well as a lead balloon. I just do not think they care at all about Windows with consumers.</p><p>The second thing is the affordable MacBook rumored to be coming out in 2026. This will be a meaningfully cheaper MacBook that people can purchase at price points that many Windows computers have been hovering around for many years. Considering Apple’s focus on consumers first and a price point that can get more people in the door, it seems like that could move the needle.</p><p>The third thing is gamers. Gamers use Windows largely because they have to, not because they are passionate about it. Maybe they were passionate about it in the 90s, but any passion has gone away. Now it is just the operating system they use to launch Steam. In early 2026, Valve is going to release the Steam Machine after a few years of success with the Steam Deck. We will see how they do there, but what they are doing is releasing a machine that runs Windows games on Linux. And it runs them really well. The Steam Deck has proven that over the last few years. If someone can package up a version of Linux that is optimized for gamers, then I think there is a meaningful number of PC gamers who would happily run that on their computer instead.</p><p>I do not know if this is going to happen. It is always easy to be cynical and suggest everything will stay the same, and I understand that markets of this size take a long time to change. However, it just feels like there are some things happening right now that are going to move the needle, and I am excited to see what happens.</p>
    </div>
</article>


                    
</main>
                            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dark Mode Sucks (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tomechangosubanana.com/2025/dark-mode-sucks/</link>
            <guid>46024894</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:45:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tomechangosubanana.com/2025/dark-mode-sucks/">https://www.tomechangosubanana.com/2025/dark-mode-sucks/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024894">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
    <p>The fetish modern Internet users have with “dark mode” has to stop, as does the rhetoric they typically use to advance their arguments, stuff like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>blasts my eyeballs with full-beam daylight.</p></blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Every time I open it, I physically recoil like a Victorian child seeing electricity for the first time.</p></blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My retinas and I would be very grateful</p></blockquote>
<p>or</p>
<blockquote>
<p>the light of a thousand suns</p></blockquote>
<p>Give me a break. If normal mode bothers you so much, it says one thing: <em>your ambient lighting is crap</em> . That will kill your eyesight and no, dark mode won’t save you. Fix your lighting instead of bullying the rest of the Internet into eyesight-damaging practices.</p>


    

    

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Calculus for Mathematicians, Computer Scientists, and Physicists [pdf] (236 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mathcs.holycross.edu/~ahwang/print/calc.pdf</link>
            <guid>46024773</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:31:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mathcs.holycross.edu/~ahwang/print/calc.pdf">https://mathcs.holycross.edu/~ahwang/print/calc.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024773">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: Good resources to learn financial systems engineering? (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024753</link>
            <guid>46024753</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:30:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024753">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><tbody><tr id="46025843"><td></td></tr><tr id="46027089"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46027089" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46027089&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p># Books</p><p>## *<i>Trading and Exchanges: Market Microstructure for Practitioners</i> by Larry Harris*</p><p>- comprehensive overview written in an accessible way</p><p>## *<i>The Microstructure of Financial Markets</i> by Frank de Jong and Barbara Rindi*</p><p>- 1st 1/4 of the book is generally useful. Then the math starts. This math is not needed to get a basic overview.</p><p>These are two books I wish someone gave to me when I started my first capital markets software engineering job. I recommend them to all the people I place in financial system engineering roles.</p><p>This is my passion.  Message me if you want to talk more about this — see HN profile for contact info.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46027002"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46027002" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46027002&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I would recommend the Jane Street youtube channel, the ocamal focused ones in my opinion you can skip. But otherwise their engineering videos will give you a good sense of it. When it comes to low latency systems this is a very private ecosystem. There are some open source projects for learning some of the mechanics of trading, market data and the order to settlement lifecycle. I am not aware of any being built for low latency.</p><p>Market data ingest, analysis and resulting order execution is chewing through way more data way faster than any banking transaction system. I have worked on both of them.</p><p>If you want more in the weeds but still high level I gave a talk on the main concepts and systems you need to know to code low latency for markets. <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1HIPJb0XX3JDHEYSrZC8v1HfK8i8eWNLNodkiq4STU7Q/view?slide=id.p#slide=id.p" rel="nofollow">https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1HIPJb0XX3JDHEYSrZC8v...</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46025792"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46025792" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46025792&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I work on low(ish) latency trading systems in FX. FIX is the standard communication protocol and familiarity with it is essential for me. Here you can look up the standard message types and tag values:
<a href="https://fiximate.fixtrading.org/" rel="nofollow">https://fiximate.fixtrading.org/</a></p><p>They also have docs for the standard message flows you can expect during trading. I use it regularly.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46025969"><td></td></tr><tr id="46026229"><td></td></tr><tr id="46025687"><td></td></tr><tr id="46027077"><td></td></tr><tr id="46026629"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46026629" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46026629&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>&gt; Currently most parties there take minutes to process messages and I think there could be a lot to learn from financial systems engineering</p><p>Depends on what you mean by "financial systems". There are plenty of financial systems that takes days or weeks to fully process transactions.</p><p>You're probably referring to stock trading systems (which by their nature have to be extremely low latency). The term to search for is "HFT" (high-frequency trading).</p><p>Here is a recent paper on the topic (focused on C++, though most things you find will tend to be): <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.04259" rel="nofollow">https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.04259</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46025526"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46025526" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46025526&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p><i>Currently most parties there take minutes to process messages</i></p><p>I suspect that the energy market is a bit different from markets where being ruthlessly fast might be a good long term behavior. So there might be good reasons for that way of doing business due to the specific nature of the energy market.</p><p>For example a limited number of counter parties might make stable B2B relationships more valuable. Or regulatory compliance might require extra steps. Or the messaging system might be noisy.</p><p>Or not. I wonder how executives at the trading companies would describe the delay.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46026697"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46026697" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46026697&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>One other thing that comes to mind - the players in the financial markets make so much money off that message-processing speed that it opens up a whole lot of options that may not be available to someone without those kinds of deep pockets. We're all still fighting Einstein, but the ability to just throw resources at the problem can surface some solutions that are out of reach when you manufacture something other than money.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46027337"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46027337" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46027337&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I agree and scale is one of the reasons there's so much money to be made. The NYSE trades over $18 billion a day. A small edge can be exercised many many times.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46025352"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46025352" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46025352&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I've heard from a friend in the energy trading space that they're a bit behind, but your question is still a bit too broad.</p><p>What in the financial space do you want to hear about? Networks, exchanges, settlement?</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46025774"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46025774" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46025774&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I am mainly working on B2B message exchange, e.g. via AS4/EDIFACT/ebix/CIM files and most parties seem to still work with a lot of batch processing. With the ongoing digitization of e.g. metering hardware and faster settlement times in the energy markets (EU-centric) I think this might not cut it anymore in the future.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46026471"><td></td></tr><tr id="46027469"><td></td></tr><tr id="46027293"><td></td></tr><tr id="46026892"><td></td></tr><tr id="46026524"><td></td></tr><tr id="46025591"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46025591" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46025591&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>A lot of settlement in financial markets is still pretty slow. That’s a big reason why there was so much fintech interest in blockchain.</p><p>You may be thinking of high frequency trading. In that case, traders interact directly with an exchange - e.g. via direct market access[1] - so it’s a pre-established two-party interaction. There’s no particular technical difficulty with making that fast. Usually, slow transaction times are a consequence of the structure of the market, not a technical issue particularly.</p><p>[1] <a href="https://corporatefinanceinstitute.com/resources/career-map/sell-side/capital-markets/direct-market-access-dma/" rel="nofollow">https://corporatefinanceinstitute.com/resources/career-map/s...</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46027142"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46027142" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46027142&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>In the broad picture of engineering, I would consider this to be technically difficult. Many pieces of the puzzle need to interact correctly to remove latency, from physical location, network gear, decision about where software runs, removing unnecessary layers of <i>everything</i>, to algos and data structures, and doing razor-tight tradeoff analysis favoring low-latency at every step along the way. It’s also expensive. So it’s hard to agree that this is not hard. On the flip side, if you find this easy and want a job, msg me.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46026722"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46026722" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46026722&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46024753"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I wouldn't look further than asking what happens currently in the processing of these messages. It might turn out for example that the minutes delay is deliberate: high frequency trading can become unstable more easily than low frequency trading. Perhaps there's a human in the loop?</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr></tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[73% of AI startups are just prompt engineering (220 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pub.towardsai.net/i-reverse-engineered-200-ai-startups-73-are-lying-a8610acab0d3</link>
            <guid>46024644</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:17:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pub.towardsai.net/i-reverse-engineered-200-ai-startups-73-are-lying-a8610acab0d3">https://pub.towardsai.net/i-reverse-engineered-200-ai-startups-73-are-lying-a8610acab0d3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024644">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://pub.towardsai.net/i-reverse-engineered-200-ai-startups-73-are-lying-a8610acab0d3: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mount Proton Drive on Linux using rclone and systemd (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/dadtronics/protondrive-linux</link>
            <guid>46024584</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 16:12:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/dadtronics/protondrive-linux">https://github.com/dadtronics/protondrive-linux</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024584">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Mount Proton Drive on Linux using rclone and systemd</h2><a id="user-content-mount-proton-drive-on-linux-using-rclone-and-systemd" aria-label="Permalink: Mount Proton Drive on Linux using rclone and systemd" href="#mount-proton-drive-on-linux-using-rclone-and-systemd"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This guide automates the process of mounting <a href="https://proton.me/drive" rel="nofollow">Proton Drive</a> on a Linux system using <a href="https://rclone.org/" rel="nofollow"><code>rclone</code></a> and <code>systemd</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Tested on <strong>Arch Linux</strong>, but should work on most Linux distributions with minor adjustments.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🔧 Features</h2><a id="user-content--features" aria-label="Permalink: 🔧 Features" href="#-features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Mounts Proton Drive at login via <code>systemd --user</code></li>
<li>Uses <code>rclone</code> with <code>--vfs-cache-mode writes</code> for compatibility</li>
<li>Enables background service with logging</li>
<li>Adds FUSE support for <code>--allow-other</code> mounts</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 Quick Start</h2><a id="user-content--quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: 🚀 Quick Start" href="#-quick-start"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">1. ✅ Install Dependencies</h3><a id="user-content-1--install-dependencies" aria-label="Permalink: 1. ✅ Install Dependencies" href="#1--install-dependencies"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install <code>fuse3</code> (required for mounting):</h4><a id="user-content-install-fuse3-required-for-mounting" aria-label="Permalink: Install fuse3 (required for mounting):" href="#install-fuse3-required-for-mounting"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install <code>rclone</code> (must be v1.64.0 or newer)</h4><a id="user-content-install-rclone-must-be-v1640-or-newer" aria-label="Permalink: Install rclone (must be v1.64.0 or newer)" href="#install-rclone-must-be-v1640-or-newer"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">🔹 <strong>Option 1: Use precompiled binary (recommended)</strong></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl -O https://downloads.rclone.org/rclone-current-linux-amd64.zip
unzip rclone-current-linux-amd64.zip
cd rclone-*-linux-amd64
sudo cp rclone /usr/local/bin/
sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/rclone"><pre>curl -O https://downloads.rclone.org/rclone-current-linux-amd64.zip
unzip rclone-current-linux-amd64.zip
<span>cd</span> rclone-<span>*</span>-linux-amd64
sudo cp rclone /usr/local/bin/
sudo chmod +x /usr/local/bin/rclone</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Verify:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="rclone version
# Must be v1.64.0 or higher"><pre>rclone version
<span><span>#</span> Must be v1.64.0 or higher</span></pre></div>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">2. 🔐 Configure Proton Drive Remote</h3><a id="user-content-2--configure-proton-drive-remote" aria-label="Permalink: 2. 🔐 Configure Proton Drive Remote" href="#2--configure-proton-drive-remote"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Run:</p>

<p dir="auto">Follow prompts:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>n</code> → New remote</li>
<li>Name: <code>proton</code></li>
<li>Type: <code>protondrive</code></li>
<li>Log in via browser when prompted</li>
<li>Accept and save</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">3. 📜 Run Setup Script</h3><a id="user-content-3--run-setup-script" aria-label="Permalink: 3. 📜 Run Setup Script" href="#3--run-setup-script"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Run the provided script:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="chmod +x setup-proton-mount.sh
./setup-proton-mount.sh"><pre>chmod +x setup-proton-mount.sh
./setup-proton-mount.sh</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The script will:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Create the mount point: <code>~/ProtonDrive</code></li>
<li>Write the systemd user service</li>
<li>Add <code>user_allow_other</code> to <code>/etc/fuse.conf</code> (if missing)</li>
<li>Add user to the <code>fuse</code> group (if needed)</li>
<li>Enable and start the mount service</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">4. 🔁 Reboot or Log Out/In</h3><a id="user-content-4--reboot-or-log-outin" aria-label="Permalink: 4. 🔁 Reboot or Log Out/In" href="#4--reboot-or-log-outin"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If the script added you to the <code>fuse</code> group, you must <strong>log out and back in</strong> for the change to take effect.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🔍 Verify Mount</h2><a id="user-content--verify-mount" aria-label="Permalink: 🔍 Verify Mount" href="#-verify-mount"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Check if Proton Drive is mounted:</p>

<p dir="auto">Check systemd service:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="systemctl --user status rclone-proton.mount.service"><pre>systemctl --user status rclone-proton.mount.service</pre></div>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🧼 Uninstall</h2><a id="user-content--uninstall" aria-label="Permalink: 🧼 Uninstall" href="#-uninstall"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To remove the auto-mount setup:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="systemctl --user disable --now rclone-proton.mount.service
rm ~/.config/systemd/user/rclone-proton.mount.service"><pre>systemctl --user disable --now rclone-proton.mount.service
rm <span>~</span>/.config/systemd/user/rclone-proton.mount.service</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">(Optional) Remove <code>~/ProtonDrive</code> if you no longer need the mount point.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📁 Files</h2><a id="user-content--files" aria-label="Permalink: 📁 Files" href="#-files"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>setup-proton-mount.sh</code> — full setup script</li>
<li><code>~/.config/systemd/user/rclone-proton.mount.service</code> — systemd unit</li>
<li><code>~/ProtonDrive</code> — mount location</li>
<li><code>~/.cache/rclone/rclone-proton.log</code> — log output (optional)</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📎 Requirements</h2><a id="user-content--requirements" aria-label="Permalink: 📎 Requirements" href="#-requirements"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>rclone &gt;= 1.64.0</code> with Proton Drive support</li>
<li><code>fuse3</code></li>
<li>A Proton Drive account</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🛟 Troubleshooting</h2><a id="user-content--troubleshooting" aria-label="Permalink: 🛟 Troubleshooting" href="#-troubleshooting"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If the mount isn't working:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="journalctl --user -u rclone-proton.mount.service"><pre>journalctl --user -u rclone-proton.mount.service</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">To restart the service manually:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="systemctl --user restart rclone-proton.mount.service"><pre>systemctl --user restart rclone-proton.mount.service</pre></div>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📚 References</h2><a id="user-content--references" aria-label="Permalink: 📚 References" href="#-references"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://rclone.org/protondrive/" rel="nofollow">rclone Proton Drive Docs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Systemd/User" rel="nofollow">systemd user services</a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Court filings allege Meta downplayed risks to children and misled the public (328 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://time.com/7336204/meta-lawsuit-files-child-safety/</link>
            <guid>46024184</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 15:18:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://time.com/7336204/meta-lawsuit-files-child-safety/">https://time.com/7336204/meta-lawsuit-files-child-safety/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024184">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article id="article-body"><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Sex trafficking on Meta platforms was both difficult to report and widely tolerated, according to a court filing unsealed Friday. In a plaintiffs’ brief filed as part of a major lawsuit against four social media companies, Instagram’s former head of safety and well-being Vaishnavi Jayakumar testified that when she joined Meta in 2020 she was shocked to learn that the company had a “17x” strike policy for accounts that reportedly engaged in the “trafficking of humans for sex.”&nbsp;</p><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">“You could incur 16 violations for prostitution and sexual solicitation, and upon the 17th violation, your account would be suspended,” Jayakumar reportedly testified, adding that “by any measure across the industry, [it was] a very, very high strike threshold.” The plaintiffs claim that this testimony is corroborated by internal company documentation.</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">The brief, filed by plaintiffs in the Northern District of California, alleges that Meta was aware of serious harms on its platform and engaged in a broad pattern of deceit to downplay risks to young users. According to the brief, Meta was aware that millions of adult strangers were contacting minors on its sites; that its products exacerbated mental health issues in teens; and that content related to eating disorders, suicide, and child sexual abuse was frequently detected, yet rarely removed. According to the brief, the company failed to disclose these harms to the public or to Congress, and refused to implement safety fixes that could have protected young users.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">“Meta has designed social media products and platforms that it is aware are addictive to kids, and they’re aware that those addictions lead to a whole host of serious mental health issues,” says Previn Warren, the co-lead attorney for the plaintiffs in the case. “Like tobacco, this is a situation where there are dangerous products that were marketed to kids,” Warren adds. “They did it anyway, because more usage meant more profits for the company.”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">The following allegations against Meta come from the brief filed in an unprecedented multidistrict litigation. More than 1,800 plaintiffs—including children and parents, school districts, and state attorneys general—have joined together in a suit alleging that the parent companies behind Instagram, TikTok, Snapchat, and YouTube “relentlessly pursued a strategy of growth at all costs, recklessly ignoring the impact of their products on children’s mental and physical health,” according to their master complaint. The newly unsealed allegations about Meta are just one small part of the sprawling suit. (TIME filed a motion to intervene in the case to ensure public access to court records; the motion was denied.)</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">The plaintiffs’ brief, first reported by TIME, purports to be based on sworn depositions of current and former Meta executives, internal communications, and company research and presentations obtained during the lawsuit’s discovery process. It includes quotes and excerpts from thousands of pages of testimony and internal company documents. TIME was not able to independently view the underlying testimony or research quoted in the brief, since those documents remain under seal.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content"><strong>Read More:</strong> <em><a href="https://time.com/7334078/matthew-bergman-social-media-victims-lawsuits/">The Lawyer Suing Social Media Companies On Behalf of Kids</a></em></p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">But the brief still paints a damning picture of the company’s internal research and deliberations about issues that have long plagued its platforms. Plaintiffs claim that since 2017, Meta has aggressively pursued young users, even as its internal research suggested its social media products could be addictive and dangerous to kids. Meta employees proposed multiple ways to mitigate these harms, according to the brief, but were repeatedly blocked by executives who feared that new safety features would hamper teen engagement or user growth.</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">“We strongly disagree with these allegations, which rely on cherry-picked quotes and misinformed opinions in an attempt to present a deliberately misleading picture," a Meta spokesperson said in a statement to TIME. "The full record will show that for over a decade, we have listened to parents, researched issues that matter most, and made real changes to protect teens – like introducing Teen Accounts with built-in protections and providing parents with controls to manage their teens’ experiences. We’re proud of the progress we’ve made and we stand by our record.”</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">In the years since the lawsuit was filed, Meta has implemented new safety features designed to address some of the problems described by plaintiffs. In 2024, Meta unveiled Instagram Teen Accounts, which defaults any user between 13 and 18 into an account that is automatically private, limits sensitive content, turns off notifications at night, and doesn’t allow messaging from unconnected adults. “We know parents are worried about their teens having unsafe or inappropriate experiences online, and that’s why we’ve significantly reimagined the Instagram experience for tens of millions of teens with new Teen Accounts,” a Meta spokeswoman told TIME in June. “These accounts provide teens with built-in protections to automatically limit who’s contacting them and the content they’re seeing, and teens under 16 need a parent’s permission to change those settings. We also give parents oversight over their teens’ use of Instagram, with ways to see who their teens are chatting with and block them from using the app for more than 15 minutes a day, or for certain periods of time, like during school or at night.”</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">And yet the plaintiffs’ brief suggests that Meta resisted safety changes like these for years.&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">The brief quotes testimony from Brian Boland, Meta’s former vice president of partnerships who worked at the company for 11 years and resigned in 2020. “My feeling then and my feeling now is that they don’t meaningfully care about user safety,” he allegedly said. “It’s not something that they spend a lot of time on. It’s not something they think about. And I really think they don’t care.”</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">After the plaintiffs’ brief was unsealed late Friday night, Meta did not immediately respond to TIME’s requests for comment.&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Here are some of the most notable allegations from the plaintiffs’ omnibus brief:&nbsp;</p><h2>Allegation: Meta had a high threshold for "sex trafficking" content—and no way to report child sexual content</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Despite Instagram’s “zero tolerance” policy for child sexual abuse material, the platform did not offer users a simple way to report child sexual abuse content, according to the brief. Plaintiffs allege that Jayakumar raised the issue multiple times when she joined Meta in 2020, but was told it would be too difficult to address. Yet Instagram allowed users to easily report far less serious violations, like “spam,” “intellectual property violation” and “promotion of firearms,” according to plaintiffs.</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Jayakumar was even more shocked to learn that Instagram had a disturbingly high tolerance for sex trafficking on the platform. According to the brief, she testified that Meta had a “17x” strike policy for accounts that reportedly engaged in the “trafficking of humans for sex,” meaning it would take at least 16 reports for an account to be deleted.   </p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">“Meta never told parents, the public, or the Districts that it doesn’t delete accounts that have engaged over fifteen times in sex trafficking,” the plaintiffs wrote. </p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">A Meta spokesperson disputed this allegation to TIME, saying the company has for years removed accounts immediately if it suspects them of human trafficking or exploitation and has made it easier over time for users to report content that violates child-exploitation policies. </p><h2>Allegation: Meta "lied to Congress" about its knowledge of harms on the platform</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">For years, plaintiffs allege, Meta’s internal research had found that teenagers who frequently use Instagram and Facebook have higher rates of anxiety and depression.&nbsp;</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">In late 2019, according to the brief, Meta designed a “deactivation study,” which found that users who stopped using Facebook and Instagram for a week showed lower rates of anxiety, depression, and loneliness. Meta halted the study and did not publicly disclose the results, stating that the research study was biased by the “existing media narratives around the company.” (A Meta spokesperson told TIME that the study was initially conceived as a pair of one-weeks pilots, and researchers declined to continue it because it found that the only reductions in feelings of depression, anxiety, and loneliness were among people who already believed Facebook was bad for them.)</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">At least one Meta employee was uncomfortable with the implications of this decision: “If the results are bad and we don’t publish and they leak,” this employee wrote, according to the brief, “is it going to look like tobacco companies doing research and knowing cigs were bad and then keeping that info to themselves?”</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Indeed, in December 2020, when the Senate Judiciary Committee asked the company in a set of written questions whether it was “able to determine whether increased use of its platform among teenage girls has any correlation with increased signs of depression” and “increased signs of anxiety,” the company offered only a one-word answer: “No.”</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">To the plaintiffs in the case, the implication is clear: “The company never publicly disclosed the results of its deactivation study. Instead, Meta lied to Congress about what it knew.”</p><h2>Allegation: The company knew Instagram was letting adult strangers connect with teenagers</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">For years <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2018/10/instagram-has-massive-harassment-problem/572890/">Instagram has had </a>a well-documented problem of adults harassing teens. Around 2019, company researchers recommended making all teen accounts private by default in order to prevent adult strangers from connecting with kids, according to the plaintiffs’ brief. Instead of implementing this recommendation, Meta asked its growth team to study the potential impact of making all teen accounts private. The growth team was pessimistic, according to the brief, and responded that the change would likely reduce engagement.&nbsp;</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">By 2020, the growth team had determined that a private-by-default setting would result in a loss of 1.5 million monthly active teens a year on Instagram. The plaintiffs’ brief quotes an unnamed employee as saying: “taking away unwanted interactions… is likely to lead to a potentially untenable problem with engagement and growth.” Over the next several months, plaintiffs allege, Meta’s policy, legal, communications, privacy, and well-being teams all recommended making teen accounts private by default, arguing that the switch “will increase teen safety” and was in line with expectations from users, parents, and regulators. But Meta did not launch the feature that year.&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Safety researchers were dismayed, according to excerpts of an internal conversation quoted in the filing. One allegedly grumbled: “Isn’t safety the whole point of this team?”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">“Meta knew that placing teens into a default-private setting would have eliminated 5.4 million unwanted interactions a day,” the plaintiffs wrote. Still, Meta didn’t make the fix. Instead, inappropriate interactions between adults and kids on Instagram skyrocketed to 38 times that on Facebook Messenger, according to the brief. The launch of Instagram Reels allegedly compounded the problem. It allowed young teenagers to broadcast short videos to a wide audience, including adult strangers.</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content"><strong>Read More:</strong> <em><a href="https://time.com/7327229/raul-torrez-new-mexico-meta-lawsuit/">The AG Putting Big Tech On Trial</a></em>.</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">An internal 2022 audit allegedly found that Instagram’s Accounts You May Follow feature recommended 1.4 million potentially inappropriate adults to teenage users in a single day. By 2023, according to the plaintiffs, Meta knew that they were recommending minors to potentially suspicious adults and vice versa.&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">It wasn’t until 2024 that Meta rolled out default privacy settings to all teen accounts. In the four years it took the company to implement their own safety recommendations, teens experienced billions of unwanted interactions with strangers online. Inappropriate encounters between teens and adults were common enough, according to the brief, that the company had an acronym for them: “IIC,” or “inappropriate interactions with children.”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">A Meta spokesperson said the company has defaulted teens under 16 to private accounts since 2021, began defaulting teens under 18 into private accounts with the introduction of its Teen Accounts program, and has <a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2023/12/combating-online-predators/">taken steps</a> to protect users from online predators. </p></div><div><h2>Allegation: Meta aggressively targeted young users</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Meta feared young users would abandon Facebook and Instagram for their competitors. Acquiring and keeping young users became a central business goal. Meta CEO Mark Zuckerberg suggested that “teen time spent be our top goal of 2017,” according to a company executive quoted in the brief. That has remained the case, plaintiffs allege; internal company documents from 2024 stated that “acquiring new teen users is mission critical to the success of Instagram.” (A Meta spokesperson said time spent on its platforms is not currently a company goal.)</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Meta launched a campaign to connect with school districts and paid organizations like the National Parent Teacher Association and Scholastic to conduct outreach to schools and families. Meanwhile, according to the brief, Meta used location data to push notifications to students in “school blasts,” presumably as part of an attempt to increase youth engagement during the school day. As one employee allegedly put it: “One of the things we need to optimize for is sneaking a look at your phone under your desk in the middle of Chemistry :)”.</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Though Meta aggressively pursued young users, it may not have known exactly how old those new users were. Whistleblower <a href="https://www.judiciary.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/6ccd5abd-cbb9-5107-d48d-b99e821eb244/2025-09-09%20-%20QFR%20Responses%20-%20Sattizahn.pdf">Jason Sattizahn recently</a> testified to Congress that Meta does not reliably know the age of its users. (Meta pushed back on Sattizahn’s testimony, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/tech/tech-news/meta-whistleblower-research-kids-vr-former-employees-stock-rcna230131">saying in a statement to NBC</a> that his claims were “nonsense” and “based on selectively leaked internal documents that were picked specifically to craft a false narrative.”) In 2022, according to the plaintiffs’ brief, there were 216 million users on Meta platforms whose age was “unknown.”</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Federal law requires social media platforms to observe various data-privacy safeguards for users under 13, and Meta policy states that users under 13 are not allowed on its platforms. Yet the plaintiffs’ court filing claims Meta knew that children under 13 used the company’s products anyway. Internal research cited in the brief suggested there were 4 million users under 13 on Instagram in 2015; by 2018, the plaintiffs claim, Meta knew that roughly 40% of children aged 9 to 12 said they used Instagram daily.</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">The plaintiffs allege that this was a deliberate business strategy. The brief describes a coordinated effort to acquire young users that included studying the psychology and digital behavior of “tweens” and exploring new products designed for “users as young as 5-10.”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Internally, some employees expressed disgust at the attempt to target preteens. “Oh good, we’re going after &lt;13 year olds now?” one wrote, according to the brief. “Zuck has been talking about that for a while...targeting 11 year olds feels like tobacco companies a couple decades ago (and today). Like we’re seriously saying ‘we have to hook them young’ here.”</p><h2>Allegation: Meta's executives initially shelved efforts to make Instagram less toxic for teens</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">To combat toxic “social comparison,” in 2019 Instagram CEO Adam Mosseri announced a new product feature that would “hide” likes on posts. Meta researchers had determined that hiding likes would make users “significantly less likely to feel worse about themselves,” according to the plaintiffs’ brief. The initiative was code-named Project Daisy.&nbsp;</p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">But after a series of tests, Meta backtracked on Project Daisy. It determined the feature was “pretty negative to FB metrics,” including ad revenue, according to the plaintiffs’ brief, which quotes an unnamed employee on the growth team insisting: “It’s a social comparison app, fucking get used to it.”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">A similar debate took place over the app’s beauty filters. Plaintiffs claim that an internal review concluded beauty filters exacerbated the “risk and maintenance of several mental health concerns, including body dissatisfaction, eating disorders, and body dysmorphic disorder,” and that Meta knew that “children are particularly vulnerable.” Meta banned beauty filters in 2019, only to roll them back out the following year after the company realized that banning beauty filters would have a “negative growth impact,” according to the plaintiffs’ brief.&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Other company researchers allegedly built an AI “classifier” to identify content that would lead to negative appearance comparison, so that Meta could avoid recommending it to vulnerable kids. But Mosseri allegedly killed the project, disappointing developers who “felt like they had a solution” to “a big problem.”</p></div><div><h2>Allegation: Meta doesn't automatically remove harmful content, including self-harm content</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">While Meta developed AI tools to monitor the platforms for harmful content, the company didn’t automatically delete that content even when it determined with “100% confidence” that it violated Meta’s policies against child sexual-abuse material or eating-disorder content. Meta’s AI classifiers did not automatically delete posts that glorified self-harm unless they were 94% certain they violated platform policy, according to the plaintiffs’ brief. As a result, most of that content remained on the platform, where teenage users often discovered it. In a 2021 internal company survey cited by plaintiffs, more than 8% of respondents aged 13 to 15 reported having seen someone harm themselves, or threaten to do so, on Instagram during the past week.</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content"><strong>Read More: </strong><em><a href="https://time.com/7310444/instagram-lawsuit-self-harm/">‘Everything I Learned About Suicide, I Learned On Instagram.’</a></em></p></div><div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">A Meta spokesperson said the company reports more child sexual-abuse material than any other service and uses an array of tools to proactively find that content, including photo and video-matching technologies as well as machine learning. The spokesperson said human reviewers assess content flagged before it is deleted to ensure it violates policies, prevent mistakes that could affect users, and maintain the integrity of the company's detection databases. </p><h2>Allegation: Meta knew its products were addictive, but publicly downplayed the harms</h2><p data-testid="paragraph-content">The addictive nature of the company’s products wasn’t a secret internally. “Oh my gosh yall IG is a drug,” one of the company’s user-experience researchers allegedly wrote to a colleague. “We’re basically pushers.”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Meta does not officially study addiction to its products, plaintiffs allege; it studies “problematic use.” In 2018, company researchers surveyed 20,000 Facebook users in the U.S. and found that 58% had some level of “problematic use”—55% mild, and 3.1% severe. But when Meta published an account of this research the following year, only the smaller number of users with “severe” problematic use was mentioned. “We estimate (as an upper bound) that 3.1% of Facebook users in the U.S. experience problematic use,” <a href="https://scontent-sjc6-1.xx.fbcdn.net/v/t39.8562-6/240848801_924166131530538_1308218914254273445_n.pdf?_nc_cat=111&amp;ccb=1-7&amp;_nc_sid=e280be&amp;_nc_ohc=C_tgb_3384YQ7kNvwHuZaN0&amp;_nc_oc=Adm09HFJ1ktJoo9WIE0m4qDw6-OlF_2k7EQF8rnKbmwRLRsOB1cDAsP3XLwyT8q2accez_oKoOZRXzLKpBMUCsHU&amp;_nc_zt=14&amp;_nc_ht=scontent-sjc6-1.xx&amp;_nc_gid=WZWa2peYFXQxwOygthrZ6g&amp;oh=00_AfhNhtKp-IiYwptqBR42Y2exRT2A9v9zp5xlCdNIzxAJ_A&amp;oe=6925C501">wrote the researchers</a>. The other 55% of users are not mentioned anywhere in the public report.&nbsp;</p></div><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Plaintiffs allege that Meta’s safety team proposed features designed to lessen addiction, only to see them set aside or watered down. One employee who helped develop a “quiet mode” feature said it was shelved because Meta was concerned that this feature would negatively impact metrics related to growth and usage.</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Around the same time, another user-experience researcher at Instagram allegedly recommended that Meta inform the public about its research findings: “Because our product exploits weaknesses in the human psychology to promote product engagement and time spent,” the researcher wrote, Meta needed to “alert people to the effect that the product has on their brain.”&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content">Meta did not.&nbsp;</p><p data-testid="paragraph-content"><em>This story has been updated to reflect additional comments from Meta. </em></p></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Editing Code in Emacs (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://redpenguin101.github.io/html/posts/2025_11_23_emacs_for_code_editing.html</link>
            <guid>46024032</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 14:59:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://redpenguin101.github.io/html/posts/2025_11_23_emacs_for_code_editing.html">https://redpenguin101.github.io/html/posts/2025_11_23_emacs_for_code_editing.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46024032">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
<h2 id="editing-code-in-emacs">Editing Code in Emacs</h2>
<p>When you write code, you want to focus on the code, not on the text
of the code. This means a) you have to have a good text editing setup,
and b) you need to have a muscle-memory level instinct for using that
setup. The second comes with practice and with <em>consistency</em>
(i.e.&nbsp;not changing your config too much too quickly). The first is what
I will talk about here.</p>
<p>This document is meant for people who are current users of, or at
least slightly familiar with Emacs. I won’t spend much time explaining
Emacs basics - for example how incremental search, or compilation
buffers work (I would recommend <a href="https://www.masteringemacs.org/book">Mastering Emacs</a> for
that). But I will give rationales for the choices I’ve made in
encouraging or discouraging certain patterns.</p>
<p>You can read this in two ways: The general Emacs commands I use to
try to edit the text of programs efficiently, and the specific keybinds
I use in my modal ‘command’ mode to make those commands as convenient as
possible.</p>
<h2 id="no-mouse-no-arrows">No Mouse, No Arrows</h2>
<p>All text editing practices rely on minimising the work your fingers
do by minimising the number of keystrokes and keeping your fingers as
close to the home row as possible. This means no arrow keys and no
mouse. This can be enforced by remapping your arrow keys to
<code>ignore</code>, and by installing the package
<code>disable-mouse</code>.</p>
<h2 id="modal-editing-command-and-insert-modes">Modal Editing: Command
and Insert Modes</h2>
<p>Editing code is different from writing prose in that you spend a lot
more time moving around the document, and moving things around
<em>in</em> the document, than actually writing text. The actions for
moving are more important than the actions for typing, and should
therefore be closer to hand. This is the premise of <em>modal
editing</em>: the “default” actions of most keyboard keys are to move,
not to type. For example in the default ‘mode’, hitting ‘a’ doesn’t type
the ‘a’ character, it moves the cursor to the start of the line. To
actually type things, you need to hit a special key which puts you in
‘insert’ mode. Then when you are finished typing, you hit another key
which puts you in the default (or ‘command’) mode.</p>
<p>My modal system is <a href="https://github.com/RedPenguin101/dotfiles/blob/main/modal.el">custom
written</a> and very lightweight - about 150 lines, not including the
keybinds themselves. I recommend using <em>a</em> modal system, if not
mine then someone elses, such as Evil or Meow. But if you really dislike
them, you can still do everything I describe here in vanilla emacs, and
most of the commands already have default keybinds. There are only four
‘custom’ functions I use: the half page scrolls, and the
kill-whole-word/sexp. And all are very simple.</p>
<h2 id="a-note-on-defaults">A note on defaults</h2>
<p>A problem with customised setups is that they mean you can’t pick up
your friend’s Emacs setup and use it, because your muscle memory will
cause you to hit all the wrong keys. This effect can be mitigated by
sticking with the ‘language’ of the system. Emacs has pretty clear (if
arguably not very good) conventions for most of it’s keys:
<code>f</code> means forward, <code>n</code> means next,
<code>C-g</code> is always ‘cancel’. My setup tries to stick with these
conventions as much as possible. <code>f</code> in command mode is
‘forward-word’. <code>n</code> is ‘next line’.</p>
<p>Additionally there is basically no remapping <em>for insert
mode</em>. The idea being that editing in a vanilla Emacs is the same as
editing using only insert mode in my setup. I find that you spend a fair
amount of time navigating from <em>within</em> insert mode even in my
setup, so you won’t lose your muscle memory.</p>
<h2 id="leaders">Leaders</h2>
<p>The most common actions for moving around the screen are on a single
keystroke on command mode. For example, to go to the next line, you hit
<code>n</code>. To go forward by a word, press <code>f</code>.</p>
<p>Less common, but still important commands are usually two or three
keystrokes. For example, save file is <code>vs</code>. Kill word is
<code>kf</code>. In these cases, the first key is a ‘leader’ key. I use
a few leader keys:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>v</code>: A general leader key, but mostly for file, buffer
and window operations.</li>
<li><code>k</code>: Kill leader: most of the kill commands are under
this.</li>
<li><code>s</code>: Search leader: most searches are under this</li>
<li><code>vp</code>: Project leader: contains several operations that
are useful when working on a ‘project’ that consists of many files,
which is very common with programming projects.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="getting-in-and-out-of-insert-mode">Getting in and out of insert
mode</h2>
<p>To transition from command to insert mode, press <code>i</code>. To
transition from insert to command mode, press <code>C-j</code>.</p>
<p>There are a few more ways to get into insert mode:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>I</code>: Insert after character</li>
<li><code>O</code>: Insert in overwrite mode (overwrite mode will be
cancelled when you return to command mode)</li>
<li><code>A</code>: Insert at start of (indented) line</li>
<li><code>E</code>: Insert at end of line</li>
<li><code>C-RET</code>: Newline and insert</li>
<li><code>S-RET</code>: Newline above and insert</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="moving-vertically">Moving Vertically</h2>
<p>I recommend you set up relative line numbers, and global-hl-line-mode
so you can clearly see which line your cursor is on and how far away
each line is.</p>
<pre><code>(setq-default display-line-numbers-type 'relative)
(global-display-line-numbers-mode 1)
(global-hl-line-mode +1)</code></pre>
<p>In command mode press <code>n</code> to move to the next line, and
<code>p</code> to move to the previous line. Often they will be used in
conjunction with a numeric prefix: type <code>12n</code> to move down 12
lines. This number-prefix pattern is general: you can do most commands
multiple times by typing digits before typing the command.</p>
<p><code>r</code> moves up by a half page, and <code>t</code> moves down
by a half page while keeping the cursor line in the middle of the
screen. These are used in preference to the usual <code>scroll-up</code>
and <code>scroll-down</code> commands, which move so much you have to
spend a second reorienting.</p>
<p>Two useful and related actions are <code>recenter-top-bottom</code>
and <code>move-to-window-line-top-bottom</code>. These are bound to
<code>l</code> and <code>L</code> respectively. <code>l</code> moves the
screen around the current highlighted line - first centring the screen
around the hl-line, then putting the hl-line at the top of the screen,
then at the bottom. It’s best to just try it out. <code>L</code> is sort
of the opposite, it moves the <em>cursor</em> around the screen, first
to the center, then to the top, then to the bottom.</p>
<p><code>.</code> and <code>,</code> are ‘beginning-of-defun’ and
‘end-of-defun’. You can think of these as moving by a top level ‘block’.
These are usually pretty useful, but depend on your language mode having
a good definition for what a ‘block’ is.</p>
<p>Less often used, but occasionally useful, are <code>&lt;</code> and
<code>&gt;</code> for moving to the beginning and end of the current
buffer.</p>
<h2 id="moving-horizontally">Moving Horizontally</h2>
<p>Moving horizontally is important, but when programming you should
really avoid using these commands too much in favour of moving in larger
syntactic units - see the later sections on moving by expression and
search.</p>
<p>You should turn on subword mode:</p>
<pre><code>(global-subword-mode 1)</code></pre>
<p>When moving horizontally, try to move in as large a unit as you can.
You should almost never move left or right by an individual character.
The smallest general unit is a “word” - similar to how most editors will
use <code>Ctrl-Right</code> to move right by a word. To move forward by
a word, press <code>f</code>. To move backward by a word, press
<code>b</code>.</p>
<p>The definition of a ‘word’ in Emacs can be a bit tricky, especially
when it comes to programming. <code>foo_bar_baz</code> is <em>three</em>
words. <code>fooBarBaz</code> (if you’ve got subword mode turned on) is
also three words. So for either of these, if your cursor is on the
<code>f</code> of <code>foo</code>, pressing <code>f</code> to go
forward will put you before the <code>baz</code> symbol. This is handy
for changing things within a long variable name. But it’s not great for
rapid navigation. Which is why I recommend moving by <em>expression</em>
over moving by <em>word</em>.</p>
<p>If you must move by a single character, use <code>C-f</code> and
<code>C-b</code> respectively.</p>
<p><code>e</code> moves to the end of the current line. <code>a</code>
moves to the start of the current line, but generally you should prefer
<code>m</code>, which moves to the first non-whitespace character of the
line - which is usually what you want when programming. However, if I’m
trying to move to the start or end of a line, it’s usually because I
want to type something there. And for doing that you can use
<code>A</code> and <code>E</code> respectively, which will move to the
start or end of the line and immediately enter insert mode.</p>
<p>This is it for moving strictly within a line. But for the various
reasons outlined above, you really you shouldn’t use these too much.
There are better ways to move within a line: moving by expression and
moving by search.</p>
<h2 id="moving-by-expression">Moving by Expression</h2>
<p>S-Expressions, or Sexps, are a big thing in lisps and therefore in
Emacs. Most programming languages are syntactically ‘blocks’ of symbols
enclosed in different bracket types. Many use curly braces to denote
execution blocks - function bodies, loops, structure definitions -
square brackets to denote arrays, and parentheses to denote
parameter/argument lists. All fit the s-expression definition. When
you’re moving around a program it can be useful to think in terms of
jumping in to, out of, over, or within those blocks. Emacs has lots of
commands for this, and there are extensions which add even more, but I
really only use four.</p>
<p><code>j</code> moves forward by a sexp. If the cursor is over an
opening bracket of any kind, pressing <code>j</code> will jump
<em>over</em> that whole block. <code>h</code> will do the same thing,
but backwards. This can effectively be used as a ‘jump to matching
bracket’ command.</p>
<p>If on a non-bracket character, these will jump forward or back by one
syntactic symbol. This should generally be preferred to moving by
<em>word</em> because in most cases when programming you want to jump
over the symbol, not the word. For example if are at the start of the
variable name <code>foo_bar_baz</code>, unless you want to change
something in that variable, you probably want to jump over the whole
thing. <code>j</code> will do that, whereas <code>f</code> will jump you
to <code>bar</code>.</p>
<p>The other two I use are ‘down-list’ (<code>d</code>) and up list
(<code>u</code>). These jump <em>into</em> and <em>out of</em> a block.
For example if my editor looks like this, where <code>|</code> is the
cursor position: <code>dele|te(state.im_temp_entity_buffer)</code>, and
I hit <code>d</code>, the cursor will be moved into the next block - in
this case the argument list for delete:
<code>delete(|state.im_temp_entity_buffer)</code>. Pressing
<code>u</code> will move the the cursor <em>out</em> of that list:
<code>delete(state.im_temp_entity_buffer)|</code>. This works on any
type of brackets. These can also be used with a negative argument
(e.g.&nbsp;<code>-d</code>) to go <em>back</em> into and <em>back</em> out of
an expression. You can reverse the above sequence with <code>-d</code>,
resulting in <code>delete(state.im_temp_entity_buffer|)</code>, and then
<code>-u</code> resulting in
<code>delete|(state.im_temp_entity_buffer)</code>.</p>
<p>Using these sexp expressions when programming is usually far more
effective than using the horizontal movements like ‘forward-word’, and
you should get into the habit of preferring them.</p>
<h2 id="moving-by-search">Moving by Search</h2>
<p>Sexps are great, but really the best way to move more than a few
words around your buffer is to move by searching for the string of text
you want to jump to. If the location you want to jump to is on the
screen, this creates a sort of ‘look at, jump to’ dynamic, where you
find where your want your cursor to be with your eyes, type some of the
text at that location, and your cursor is now there. But it also works
great if the location you’re looking for is off the screen.</p>
<p>The simplest commands are the usual ‘isearch-forward’ and
‘isearch-backward’. The mappings for these are unchanged from standard
Emacs: <code>C-s</code> and <code>C-r</code>. There are packages which
provide alternative versions of this - ‘jump-char’ and ‘avy’, for
example - but I find these work fine.</p>
<p>Sometimes you’re searching for something that is pretty common, and
using incremental search is a slog. In this case, you can use occur,
with <code>so</code>, which creates a buffer with all the instances of
the search term, hyperlinked so you can easily jump to that
location.</p>
<p>How to use occur not specific to my setup, but is very useful to
learn, so I’ll go into some detail. When you are in an occur buffer:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>M-n</code> and <code>M-p</code> will move up and down, but
<em>won’t</em> jump the original buffer to the relevant line</li>
<li><code>n</code> and <code>p</code> will do the same, but it
<em>will</em> update the original buffer to show the line</li>
<li><code>M-g M-n</code> and <code>M-g M-p</code> will not only update
the original buffer to show the selected line, but it will make the
original buffer active at that location. A bit hard to explain in words,
but it’s very useful, try it out.</li>
</ul>
<p>The other useful thing about occur is that, while it’s read only by
default, you can make it editable with <code>e</code>. And from here you
can edit <em>the original buffers</em> from in the occur window. Huge.
Get back to read-only mode with <code>C-c C-c</code></p>
<p>You can also create an occur window for multiple buffer with
<code>multi-occur-in-matching-buffers</code>. But I find that a bit
fiddly. What I would really like is a ‘project-occur’ which searches for
all instances of a term in a current project. But Emacs doesn’t have
that built in that I’m aware, though I believe it’s in the common
‘projectile’ external package. I use the ‘ag’ package and silver-surfer
search program to search project-wide for terms, but it’s not ideal.</p>
<h2 id="registers-and-the-mark">Registers and the Mark</h2>
<p>Another way to quickly jump around a buffer is to use registers.
These are short lived ‘bookmarks’, which you can set and return to.
Typically I’ll use these when I want to temporarily jump to another
location from a point I’ll want to return to afterwards. For example,
jumping into a function from the calling location, then back out to the
calling location. Typically I’ll hit <code>v SPC a</code> to set my
current location to the register <code>a</code>. Then jump to the other
place. Then when I’m done, <code>vja</code> will take me back to my
original location. If I want to chain these together, I’ll use the
registers <code>a</code>, <code>s</code> <code>d</code> and
<code>f</code> as a sort of ‘stack’ Often I’ll also want to jump between
two locations repeatedly, so I’ll set them up as <code>a</code> and
<code>s</code>.</p>
<p>An alternative way to get the above behaviour is to the use the
‘mark’ as a very transitory, but automatic, register. When you do most
‘jumps’ in emacs, e.g.&nbsp;using isearch, a temporary register called the
‘mark’ is created in the place you jumped from. Or, you can set it
manually using <code>gg</code>.Then, you can jump to that mark
(resetting it to the place you jumped from in the process) with
<code>C-x C-x</code>. This is a like the <code>a</code> and
<code>s</code> pattern I described above, but with the advantage that
you don’t have to set the register yourself. You can also ‘pop’ the mark
by hitting <code>C-u g</code>. And you can do this repeatedly by hitting
<code>C-u g g g</code>. The downside being that the mark is less
permanent than the registers, so you can accidental set it to something
else, and you’ll find your jumps will take you somewhere you don’t
expect, which is disorienting. For that reason I usually use manual
registers.</p>
<h2 id="find-and-replace">Find and replace</h2>
<p>While you can use occur mode to do find-replace, generally it’s
easier to use <code>sq</code> (query-replace). This is both standard
emacs functionality and works basically the same as other editors
find-replace so I won’t go into how it works.</p>
<p>A variant on that is <code>vpq</code>, which is <em>project</em>
query-replace. It works the same way, but runs through every file in
your project, not just the current buffer.</p>
<h2 id="killing-or-cut-copy-paste">Killing, or Cut Copy Paste</h2>
<p>In the hierarchy of importance of operations in program text editing,
moving around the buffer is top, cut/copy/paste is second, and typing is
third.</p>
<p>We’ve seen that there are lots of options for moving around the
screen using different syntactic units. Moving and ‘killing’ (as emacs
called the operation that is usually called cut) are sort of ‘twinned’:
for each move, there is usually an equivalent kill. And in my setup they
are, where possible, on the same keys, just with a <code>k</code>
prefix.</p>
<p>So <code>kf</code> is kill forward word, <code>kj</code> is kill
forward sexp. A full list is below, but if you just think about how you
move by a certain amount, you can usually get the equivalent kill
function this way.</p>
<p>There are a few special cases for kills though. There is
<code>kf</code> for kill forward word and <code>kj</code> for kill
forward sexp, often what you want to do is kill the whole word/sexp
<em>you are currently in</em>. These are the <code>ki</code> (kill whole
word) and <code>kn</code> (kill whole sexp) commands. Similarly,
<code>ke</code> will kill from your point to the end of the line, but
more often you will want to ‘kill whole line’ <code>kl</code>.</p>
<p>A convenient (though often inefficient) thing to do is kill all the
text in a highlighted region. You can do this is <code>kw</code> kill
region. Or you can <em>copy</em> a region with <code>ks</code> kill
save.</p>
<p>You will often find yourself wanting to kill from your cursor up to a
certain character. Emacs calls this a ‘zap’, and you can do it with
<code>kz</code> zap to character.</p>
<p>Finally, if you find yourself wanting to join the current line with
the line above it, <code>k6</code> will do that.</p>
<p>To paste, just hit <code>y</code> (for yank).</p>
<p>Here is the full list of kill commands.</p>
<ul>
<li><code>kf</code> kill word</li>
<li><code>kb</code> kill back</li>
<li><code>kj</code> kill sexp</li>
<li><code>kn</code> kill inner sexp</li>
<li><code>kh</code> kill sexp back</li>
<li><code>ke</code> kill to end of line</li>
<li><code>kl</code> kill whole line</li>
<li><code>kw</code> kill region</li>
<li><code>ks</code> kill ring save</li>
<li><code>k6</code> join line</li>
<li><code>kr</code> kill rectangle</li>
<li><code>kz</code> zap to character</li>
<li><code>ki</code> kill inner word</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="file-and-window-operations">File and window operations</h2>
<p>When programming you spend a lot of time jumping between files and
buffers within the ‘project’. The project usually being defined as the
root of the source repo.</p>
<p>Most of these operations are mapped with the <code>v</code> leader
key, and in the case of commands that operate on the whole project,
<code>vp</code>. None of them are particularly unusual, so I’ll just
list them:</p>
<h3 id="window-commands">Window commands</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>w</code> delete other windows</li>
<li><code>o</code> other window</li>
<li><code>v1</code> delete other window</li>
<li><code>v2</code> split window below</li>
<li><code>v3</code> split window right</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="file-commands">File commands</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>vf</code> find file</li>
<li><code>vpf</code> project find file</li>
<li><code>vs</code> save file</li>
<li><code>vps</code> save project files</li>
<li><code>vr</code> recent files (requires some custom setup)</li>
<li><code>vd</code> dired</li>
<li><code>vpd</code> project root dired</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="buffer-commands">Buffer commands</h3>
<ul>
<li><code>vk</code> kill buffer</li>
<li><code>vpk</code> project kill buffers</li>
<li><code>vb</code> switch buffer</li>
<li><code>vpb</code> project switch to buffer</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="other-useful-things-that-dont-fit-anywhere-else">Other useful
things that don’t fit anywhere else</h2>
<p>Macros are surprisingly usable in Emacs, though they are something of
an art. <code>v[</code> starts defining a macro, <code>v]</code> ends
it. <code>vm</code> applies the macro. You can apply it repeatedly with
<code>vmmmmm...</code></p>
<p>LSPs using Emacs LSP implementation eglot are something of a mixed
blessing in my experience. I usually keep it turned off. But sometimes
being able to use ‘xref-find-definition’ (<code>M-.</code>) and the
improved tab completion is too useful to ignore.</p>
<p>‘comment-line’ <code>;</code> I use all the time. If you have a
region highlighted, it will comment out the region.</p>
<p><code>/</code> for ‘undo’, <code>v\</code> for whitespace cleanup.
<code>q</code> for ‘fill or reindent’ will usually tidy the formatting
of whichever block you’re in. <code>x</code> is ‘execute command’.
<code>z</code> is repeat.</p>
<p>Rectangle editing is often useful. Highlight the region you want to
edit, and then <code>kr</code> to kill it, or <code>vt</code> to replace
the rectangle with the thing you type. I find this works for most cases
I would use multi-cursor in other editors.</p>
<p><code>vv</code> opens the VC interface (magit, in my case).</p>
<p>I tend to use <code>sh</code> to highlight a phrase in a certain
colour when I want something I’m currently working on to show up
clearly.</p>
<p><code>vi</code> for imenu, and <code>vI</code> for imenu-to-buffer
are reasonable ways to browse your code by ‘section’, provided the
major-mode implements it properly.</p>
<p>I disable a bunch of commands I sometimes hit accidentally with
unpleasant consequences, most annoying the two ‘suspend’ shortcuts
<code>C-z</code> and <code>C-x C-z</code>.</p>
<h2 id="non-editing-configuration">Non-editing Configuration</h2>
<p>I have some other stuff in my configuration apart from the above
keybindings. But most of it is either very common (fixing where
temporary files are saved), or very specific to how I like to do things
and not good general advice. For example I turn off transient mark mode,
but I wouldn’t recommend it generally.</p>
<p>Tab completion can be a pain to get it how you like it. I use this,
but it’s not perfect:</p>
<pre><code>(setq-default indent-tabs-mode t)
(setq-default tab-width 4)
(setq tab-always-indent 'complete)
(setq tab-first-completion 'word)</code></pre>
<p>I <em>would</em> recommend relying on as few external packages as
possible. I use, and would recommend, these ones:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>ag</code> an interface to the silver-surfer search program.
This is a way to search for a term across a whole project. grep is a
reasonable alternative, but I prefer the silver surfer. Use it with
<code>sa</code></li>
<li><code>diff-hl</code>: A utility for highlighting lines that have
changed since your last commit.</li>
<li><code>magit</code>: makes using git bearable (or possible, for
things like rebasing)</li>
<li><code>visible-mark</code>: indicate visually where the ‘mark’
is.</li>
</ul>
<p>And a couple of other, language specific ones.</p>
<h2 id="why-not-vim">Why not vim?</h2>
<p>No reason other than I’m used to emacs. There’s nothing here you
couldn’t equally do with vim.</p>
<h2 id="my-init.el">My init.el</h2>
<p>Is here: <a href="https://github.com/RedPenguin101/dotfiles/blob/main/init.el">https://github.com/RedPenguin101/dotfiles/blob/main/init.el</a></p>


</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Racket v9.0 (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.racket-lang.org/2025/11/racket-v9-0.html</link>
            <guid>46023460</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 13:35:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.racket-lang.org/2025/11/racket-v9-0.html">https://blog.racket-lang.org/2025/11/racket-v9-0.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46023460">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <header>
  
  </header>

<p><em>posted by Stephen De Gabrielle and John Clements</em></p>

<hr>

<p>We are pleased to announce Racket v9.0 is now available from <a href="https://download.racket-lang.org/">https://download.racket-lang.org/</a>.</p>

<p><strong>Racket 9.0 is here!</strong></p>

<p>A major release is always exciting and Racket 9.0 is no exception in that it introduces Parallel Threads. While Racket has had green threads for some time, and supports parallelism via futures and places, we feel parallel threads is a major addition.</p>

<h2 id="as-of-this-release">As of this release:</h2>

<ul>
 <li>Racket supports parallel threads. <a href="https://blog.racket-lang.org/2025/11/parallel-threads.html">For more information see the new blog post on the topic.</a>
  <ul>
   <li>Parallel threads can be created using the <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/reference/threads.html#%28def._%28%28lib._racket%2Fprivate%2Fbase..rkt%29._thread%29%29"><code>#:pool</code></a> argument to thread creation.</li>
   <li>Threads created with  <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/reference/threads.html#%28def._%28%28lib._racket%2Fprivate%2Fbase..rkt%29._thread%29%29"><code>#:keep</code></a>  set to <code>'results</code> will record their results for later retrieval  with <code>thread-wait</code>.</li></ul></li>
 <li>The <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/reference/black-box.html#%28def._%28%28quote._~23~25kernel%29._black-box%29%29"><code>black-box</code></a> wrapper prevents the optimizing compiler from optimizing away certain computations entirely. This can be helpful in ensuring that benchmarks are accurate.</li>
 <li>The <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/reference/linklets.html#%28def._%28%28lib._racket%2Flinklet..rkt%29._decompile-linklet%29%29"><code>decompile-linklet</code></a> function can map linklets back to s-expressions.</li>
 <li>When using BC Racket, the <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/reference/places.html#%28def._%28%28lib._racket%2Fplace..rkt%29._processor-count%29%29"><code>processor-count</code></a> function is changed to always return the parallel count.</li>
 <li>We now distribute “natipkg” packages for AArch64, useful for package-build and package-testing infrastructure.</li>
 <li>Check Syntax tracks identifiers more deeply nested in the “origin” field of syntax objects.</li>
 <li>The <code>math</code> library includes <a href="https://docs.racket-lang.org/math/Real_Distribution_Families.html#%28part._.Weibull_.Distributions%29">Weibull distributions</a>.</li>
 <li>There are many other repairs and documentation improvements!</li></ul>

<h2 id="thank-you">Thank you</h2>

<p>The following people contributed to this release:</p>

<p>Alexander Shopov, Anthony Carrico, Bert De Ketelaere, Bogdan Popa, Cadence Ember, David Van Horn, Gustavo Massaccesi, Jade Sailor, Jakub Zalewski, Jens Axel Søgaard, jestarray, John Clements, Jordan Johnson, Matthew Flatt, Matthias Felleisen, Mike Sperber, Philip McGrath, RMOlive, Robby Findler, Ruifeng Xie, Ryan Culpepper, Sam Phillips, Sam Tobin-Hochstadt, Sebastian Rakel, shenleban tongying, Shu-Hung You, Stephen De Gabrielle, Steve Byan, and Wing Hei Chan.</p>

<p><strong>Racket</strong> is a community developed open source project and we welcome new contributors. See <a href="https://github.com/racket/racket/blob/master/README.md#contributing">racket/README.md</a> to learn how you can be a part of this amazing project.</p>

<h2 id="feedback-welcome">Feedback Welcome</h2>

<p>Questions and discussion welcome at the Racket community on <a href="https://racket.discourse.group/invites/VxkBcXY7yL">Discourse</a> or <a href="https://discord.gg/6Zq8sH5">Discord</a>.</p>



<p>If you can - please help get the word out to users and platform specific repo packagers</p>

<pre><code>Racket - the Language-Oriented Programming Language - version 9.0 is now available from https://download.racket-lang.org

See https://blog.racket-lang.org/2025/11/racket-v9-0.html for the release announcement and highlights.</code></pre>

<p><em>Replace this with your post text. Add one or more comma-separated Tags above. The special tag <code>DRAFT</code> will prevent the post from being published.</em></p>
<!-- more-->
<col-2>

</col-2></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Shaders: How to draw high fidelity graphics with just x and y coordinates (346 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.makingsoftware.com/chapters/shaders</link>
            <guid>46023013</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 12:26:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.makingsoftware.com/chapters/shaders">https://www.makingsoftware.com/chapters/shaders</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46023013">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.makingsoftware.com/chapters/shaders: Error: Request failed with status code 429]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Silicon Valley startups: being evil, again and again (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://notesfrombelow.org/article/silicon-valley-startups-doing-evil-again-and-again</link>
            <guid>46022704</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 11:32:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://notesfrombelow.org/article/silicon-valley-startups-doing-evil-again-and-again">https://notesfrombelow.org/article/silicon-valley-startups-doing-evil-again-and-again</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46022704">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p>Google, the Silicon Valley company <em>par excellence</em>, proclaimed to “organise the world’s information” and adopted “don’t be evil” as its corporate motto. And what could possibly be wrong with such aspirations? Indeed, most company leaders and high-tech workers, in the Valley, genuinely believe they are “making the world a better place” while also making money.</p>
<p>Silicon Valley is the progressive face of capitalism. We’ve experienced it, intimately. Billions of people, across the globe, enjoy real benefits from searching the world’s information, connecting with people across time and space, and carrying a supercomputers in their pockets. Silicon Valley doesn’t obviously throw workers into factories and mines for endless hours on low pay; such images are hidden, rendered distant by the supply chain . Instead, the Valley, in our imaginations, is populated by knowledge workers, a diverse and smart workforce that designs, solves, and codes in humane office spaces, with above average wages, ping pong, cafeterias, flexible working hours, sleeping cubicles. What’s not to like?</p>
<p>We could consider the Valley’s hidden workers, those who clean, wait tables, wash cars, nanny, deliver packages, tend gardens, fix infrastructure for poverty wages; we could explore the trailer parks down the road from Google HQ, or document the shootings in the streets, the homeless that push shopping trolleys up and down the El Camino, their world a bundle of rags; or the gun shops that sell semi-automatics, the out-of-control, over-staffed police, armed with military-grade cast-me-downs, that regularly gun down the poor; the families crowded into small apartments, the father who spends his days scouring trash bins for recyclable bottles to trade for cash, the human trafficking of women, the prostitution, coerced to serve a predominately male workforce; or the disciplining and harassment of the undocumented, the deportations, the splitting up and destruction of families; or the local charities that collect food for kids, during seasonal holidays, since outside of school time their families cannot provide; or the extraordinarily high incarceration rates that control the surplus labour force, the armed guards on campuses and in schools, office complexes and shop interiors; or the poverty, the child who cannot concentrate in class since their teeth are rotting in their mouth, the extreme and devastating inequalities in wealth and income, the untreated illnesses and injuries, for lack of medical access, the widespread use of antidepressants, the addictions, the dispossessed, the broken dreams and the crying … </p>
<p>Yet these symptoms of a broken and decaying society are studiously ignored, repressed, unmentioned by Silicon Valley’s middle and upper classes. Psychological repression is widespread amongst the highly paid of the Valley. It’s a defence: it’s just too damn painful to contemplate the full horror of social reality. And life can be organised to avoid it, or deny it. So many don’t even notice.</p>
<p>I could mention all the evil business models, where vast computing power and fancy algorithms trawl our digital footprints to track and surveil, to sell and manipulate, to intensify our addictions; and we might reflect on the Valley’s enormous and continuing contributions to building military  machines that rain down death and destruction. </p>
<p>Instead, here, in this article, I want to point to the root problem, <em>the ultimate source of evil</em>, and explain why Silicon Valley is hypocrisy on a grand scale. The Valley’s movers and shakers believe they are progressive, that entrepreneurial capitalism is the road to utopia. But it’s not. In fact, the opposite is the case: the Valley is a cause of this horror, of the social ills, and the social breakdown that it must repress: it is both responsible and culpable for creating a dystopia.</p>
<p>I want all the talented, hopeful, optimistic high-tech workers, who genuinely want to make the world a better place, who are about to found a new and exciting startup, to just take a short pause, to stop, look around, think, reflect and reconsider: <em>the kind of firm you incorporate, the institutional rules you adopt, is precisely the choice point between doing evil and doing good</em>.</p>
<p>I will try to explain. My apologies if it takes a little while, since if the following facts were readily understood and generally accepted, then Silicon Valley would already be good, not evil, and I wouldn’t need to explain.</p>
<h2 id="silicon-valley-midwife-of-the-capitalist-firm">Silicon Valley: midwife of the capitalist firm</h2>
<p>The Valley is all about startups. They spring up all the time. New exciting and hopeful adventures. It’s like forming a band, but better.</p>
<p>In huge, mature corporations the social relations of production are obscured by layers of hierarchy and absentee ownership. But in a startup the power relations are direct and visible, and often share an office with you. You can observe the basic unit of production in capitalism—the capitalist firm—as if under a microscope.</p>
<p>Let’s lay out the property relations of a (slightly simplified) typical startup. </p>
<p>The startup has owner(s), usually “high net worth” individuals, either directly present or indirectly in the form of venture capital firms. Venture capital provides the initial funds for the new venture. The actual founders, the ones with the ideas and talent, but no money, also part own the firm. The divvying up of the initial share issue between founders and early investors is a detail. The founders, armed with a new injection of capital, then recruit workers by convincing them of “the vision”. These are the first employees. And off we go. </p>
<p>The owner(s) of the startup are in complete control, and their decisions are final. Owners can promote, demote, hire and fire anyone, at any time. Owners set wage levels, which are kept secret (and the workers, being earnest and highly disciplined, avoid this subject with each other—that would break a taboo). Startups are definitely not run on democratic lines: workers don’t get to appoint managers, set strategy, or distribute profits. Instead, the startup is a mini dictatorship: sure, there’s plenty of technical debate, and back-and-forth, and head scratching, but ultimately it’s a dictatorship.</p>
<p>The owners pays all input costs—such as office rental, computers, electricity and heating, labour etc. They own all outputs, such as new software or hardware, and any inventions (which, in the Valley, are aggressively patented). The owners are liable for any profits and losses of the company. The startup’s bank accounts are hidden from the workers, and out of their control.</p>
<p>This basic social relation—between profit-taking capitalist owners and wage-earning workers—is constitutive of capitalism. For example, today you can travel to Shropshire, England, and visit Ironbridge village, one of the birthplaces of the industrial revolution and “the silicon valley of the 1800s”. You can tour an early ironworks and see the great furnaces where workers toiled, the tiny administrative office (to dole out wages, and keep accounts), and nearby, on a large hill overlooking the site, the capitalists’ large and imposing mansions.</p>
<p>The form may have changed, but not the content. In this sense, Silicon Valley is deeply conservative. It proclaims to disrupt everything, and make all fresh, new and shiny—except this basic social relationship.</p>
<p>Almost all Silicon Valley workers accept these social relations as entirely natural, acceptable, and pretty much fair and equitable. The owners fund the company. They therefore “own the firm”. The owners risk a lot of capital, and the workers receive a good wage, based on supply and demand in the marketplace, plus some ramp-up time to try and invent new stuff, which is fun. What’s not to like? What’s the problem?</p>
<h2 id="silicon-valley-its-theft-all-the-way-down">Silicon Valley: it’s theft all the way down</h2>
<p>Startups reproduce, in embryo form, the wage system, where the capitalist owner hires-in labour at a pre-agreed rental price. In a capitalist firm, labour is just an another <em>ex ante</em> cost of production. The workers mix their labour with inputs and produce an output for sale. Normally, firms sell at prices that exceed their costs of production, which includes the cost of used-up inputs, rent, interest on capital loans, and wage costs etc. Any residual income then gets distributed as profit to the owner, or owners, of the firm.</p>
<p>Imagine that you and I agree to exchange something in the marketplace, say a second-hand iPhone on Ebay. You get the money, I get an iPhone. You may get a good deal, or I may get a good deal, depending on our “higgling and haggling” in the marketplace. Whether a fair price is struck, or not, there’s an exchange of something for something: some goods for some money. This social transaction satisfies a “principle of exchange”. We’ve swapped stuff, and no-one forced us to.</p>
<p>But let’s say I just took the iPhone from you. And you received no money at all. This violates the principle of exchange. I got something for nothing: some goods, some resources, for free. That’s theft. Obviously so.</p>
<p><em>All startups in Silicon Valley violate the principle of exchange and institute a system of theft</em>. They are theft-based institutions. If the startup is successful and grows, so does the theft, since theft is baked into the institutional structure of the firm, right from the get go. If the startup goes global, like an Apple, Facebook, or Google, then the cancer spreads and the theft takes place on a global scale.</p>
<p>But the theft is hidden. We need some reflection to really see it.</p>
<p>The workers in a startup are the actual cause of any profits it makes. We can demonstrate this with a simple thought experiment: imagine the workers stopped working. Would the firm have any possibility of making a profit, or if already profitable, continue to make that profit? But we don’t need to imagine. This is called a strike. And owners hate it, since it kills their profit.</p>
<p>So, in any company, including a startup, the workers create the value. </p>
<p>What, then, do the owners contribute or create?</p>
<p>The owners, or venture capitalists, contribute capital. They advance money to fund the startup until it (hopefully) starts making money. And then they expect a return. Since they’ve given something they should definitely get something back, otherwise we violate the principle of exchange. In fact, they should expect repayment of the sums advanced and—let’s be generous here—also a risk premium (since most startups fail without making profit) and, also—in order to be really straight and fair about this—some collateral as security (such as first dibs on any outstanding assets if the venture fails). This seems like a fair exchange.</p>
<p>It is. So far so good. </p>
<p>But if early investors merely did this—that is, simply advance some <em>loan capital</em>—they would not become the owners of the firm. Once the startup made money, the loan would be repaid (by the firm), and the early investors would have no further claims on the fruits of others’ labour (that is the value created by the workers).</p>
<p>The important point is this: loan capital does not violate the principle of exchange.</p>
<p>But Silicon Valley startups are not funded by loan capital. Venture capitalists want, and get, much more than this. They advance capital to a firm, but in addition to being repaid, they demand ownership of the firm, i.e. <em>equity capital</em>, and receive stock (shares in the firm). And so they “own the firm”. In consequence, once their initial loan and risk premium is repaid, they get even more: they retain a claim on the firm’s future income, that is the fruits of others’ labour <em>in perpetuity</em> (or until the firm dissolves, or they sell their shares etc.)</p>
<p>And the mere legal ownership of a firm is <em>sufficient</em> to lay claim on its profit. And, right here, is precisely the moment when the principle of exchange is violated. Once the firm repays its debt then the early investors are now made whole. Beyond this point, we have workers creating profits, and owners appropriating that profit without needing to contribute an hour of their time, or a dime from their pockets. The owners are getting something for nothing. The owners can, as John Stuart Mill put it: “grow richer, as it were in their sleep”. There’s no exchange. Just appropriation. And that is what’s commonly, and accurately, called economic exploitation.</p>
<p>The important point is this: equity capital violates the principle of exchange. </p>
<p>Sometimes the meaning of a social situation can suddenly flip. You notice something new, like an object in the wrong place, or a small inconsistency that points to a secret, or a lie. This is one of those occasions. There’s an enormous difference between <em>advancing</em> capital to a firm, and <em>owning</em> a firm. This vital distinction is conspicuously absent from all the upbeat, world-changing, and progressive chit-chat in the coffee shops, restaurants, offices and homes of Silicon Valley. So let’s pretend they might be listening, that all their chatter stops, just for a moment, and we whisper into each and every individual ear: <em>equity capital is theft</em>. </p>
<p>When you take profits, but contribute <em>nothing</em> to the output of a firm, other than holding a paper claim, you are stealing.</p>
<p>Yet this is how startups in Silicon Valley are organised. Cohort after cohort of “smart” groups of highly educated workers are quite happy to sign up to their own exploitation, and cede control over how they organise their working day, and what they produce. The most effective prison is the one you don’t realise you’re in.</p>
<p>But hold on. Look, we’ve woken the libertarian consciousness of Silicon Valley, and its rationality is strong and terrible: those that were whispered to have been stirred, and they reply, in unison: No-one forces workers to accept these terms, and the wage contract is voluntary, and therefore perfectly OK! Go away, annoying socialist, and stop spoiling our fun!</p>
<h2 id="silicon-valley-forcing-people-to-sell-their-labour">Silicon Valley: forcing people to sell their labour</h2>
<p>Do workers freely enter into the wage contract? Do founders, with great ideas, have the freedom to start new commercial ventures that aren’t based on theft? To answer, let’s first define non-exploitative social relations of production.</p>
<p>In principle, Silicon Valley startups could be incorporated as profit-sharing worker cooperatives. In this type of institution, all working members share the profit, which is democratically distributed. So if you join the co-op, you get a say, and you get profit shares. If you leave, you don’t anymore. The firm is collectively owned by its current working members.</p>
<p>Worker co-ops don’t hire in labour at a pre-agreed rental price. They do the opposite. They hire-in capital at a pre-agreed rental price (i.e., raise loan capital <em>not</em> equity capital). So capital, not labour, is merely another <em>ex ante</em> cost of production with no claim on the residual income of the firm.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1">1</a></sup></p>
<p>In a democratic worker co-op, the principle of exchange is not violated, and no-one systematically exploits others and steals the value they (jointly) created. Clearly, this is a more lucrative deal for workers: profit-sharing is better than a wage. So why doesn’t this happen in the Valley? Why don’t lots of workers incorporate worker co-ops? </p>
<p>There are some carrots and a stick.</p>
<h3 id="the-carrot-join-us-join-us">The carrot: join us, join us!</h3>
<p>High-tech workers, especially those with in-demand skills, get more than wages, they get stock options.</p>
<p>A stock option bestows the right to purchase company shares at a (very low) predefined price. You have to work, normally for many years, before you can exercise that right. The aim is worker retention, and align incentives so workers are motivated to create profits “for the company”. Stock options, in a sense, automatically bestow the material benefits of trade unionism without the need to organise. Any worker is, of course, glad of this potential source of additional income.</p>
<p>But stock options, when exercised, are equity capital and confer (part) ownership of the firm: and, as we’ve seen, that fundamentally means participating in theft. Stock options, therefore, invite a section of the working class to join the elevated ranks of the capitalist class, and start exploiting others’ labour. (In practice, most stock options turn out worthless, since most new ventures fail. But it’s the hope that motivates).</p>
<p>In a small startup, as is common in Silicon Valley, it’s especially clear that the workers create all the added value. But the owner(s) appropriate it. So even the best educated minds start to notice. And this doesn’t seem entirely fair. So stock options function to muddy the waters, and paper over the inconvenient truth of exploitation.</p>
<p>So that’s one carrot, which pushes high-tech workers to sign-up to a capitalist firm. But there are more. If a group of workers decide to incorporate a new venture then, unless they are highly politically conscious and especially moral creatures, they will incorporate a capitalist firm, not a worker co-op. Why? Because you’ll definitely make more money by owning a firm, paying others wages, and keeping the profit to yourself.</p>
<p>Many startup founders in Silicon Valley know they’re ripping off the workers they employ. They might soothe their guilt by pointing out they offer stock options, or throw themselves into libertarianism, which conveniently coincides with their material interests. But it’s a fact that stock is normally heavily concentrated amongst a few early founders and venture capitalists. As time goes on, the founders contributions are eclipsed by the hired workers, and then it’s just exploitation all down the line. The company is bought-out, the founders get their initial advances and more, and therefore cash in, and make their millions. But, in almost all cases, they did not contribute to the creation of that value—they stole it from the workers they hired.</p>
<p>So the wage contract is sweetened by stock options. That works. But the contract is only voluntary if the workers have other options, if they have a choice. Do they?</p>
<h3 id="the-stick-reproduce-capitalism-or-wither-and-die">The stick: reproduce capitalism or wither and die</h3>
<p>But there are sticks too, which remove all choice, and prevent founders from incorporating worker co-operatives, even if they were sufficiently politically conscious to want to. </p>
<p>Silicon Valley is famous for its vibrant and extensive venture capital community. Plenty of capital swills around, continually searching, like Sauron’s great eye, for the latest hit company to fund, and therefore own and exploit the efforts and creativity of hundreds and thousands of workers.</p>
<p>Any venture capitalist, quite naturally, wants to maximise their returns. So, if faced with a choice between funding two companies, A and B, where A is a capitalist firm, and therefore offers equity in return for capital, whereas B is a worker co-op, and only offers interest repayments in return for capital, then the venture capitalist will always opt to fund A. No contest. Equity capital is strictly a better deal than loan capital. (And it’s not just more money, but also top-down dictatorial control of the company’s direction, and the working conditions and wage levels of employees. And being powerful is much more fun than being powerless. It’s great for the ego.)</p>
<p>Hence worker co-ops don’t get funded in Silicon Valley, and never will. So all those talented and creative workers, with good ideas for making things that people want, have no choice but to incorporate a capitalist firm, and begin sorting people into a class of owners, and a class of workers.</p>
<p>I witnessed an especially ugly example at an Silicon Valley business conference. An “Angel Investor” (someone who provides early seed capital) presented a talk about the criteria they apply when deciding which new ventures to invest in, and therefore what aspiring founders should do in order to maximise their chances of raising capital. A big factor, for the Angel, was that founders also raise money from friends and family, since “the desire to not disappoint loved ones is a great stimulant to hard work”. The Angel gave examples of “great stories” about teams they’d funded and the great returns made “by everybody”. At the close the Angel invited any founders in the audience to come and pitch their ideas to him—right there and then.</p>
<p>A line of about twenty or so young people formed in front of the Angel, desperate to get funding for their cherished ideas. And there it was, like a frozen scene from a perverted nativity: an anointed minority of one, with the monopoly on capital, and an unwashed majority, full of aspirations and creativity, lining up, cap-in-hand, to proffer the sacrifice of equity in their newborn, and surrender themselves to exploitation.</p>
<p>There was no choice, there is no choice: either submit to capital or watch your ideas wither and die. There are no other practical ways to raise significant capital. Real Angels don’t exist: those that ask only for their loan to be repaid, and not ownership of the firm; who reject the social relationship of equity capital, and therefore only invest in new ventures that incorporate as democratic worker-owned co-ops, so that all profit is shared, according to actual merit and contribution. If such fabled beings were present, the line before them would have been much, much longer.</p>
<p>There is no choice. Founders must incorporate capitalist firms, and must rent-in labour. And workers, who need income, don’t have the option to join a worker co-op. They must sign the wage contract. This isn’t voluntary, it’s coerced—by those with the monopoly on capital.</p>
<p>Silicon Valley culture celebrates venture capital, the Schumpeterian heroic entrepreneur, the dynamism of capitalism, and the gee-whiz technical and creative ideas of startup founders. But Silicon Valley repeatedly and continually reproduces exploitation, where some members of the firm own it, and others simply rent their labour to it. There’s zero innovation or disruption in this sphere. The Valley is a great engine, churning out new companies, day after day, which reproduce the division between an economic class that wins, and an economic class that loses.</p>

<p>Economic inequality has always been around. But notably, in the last 30 years or so, economic inequality, in the rich countries, has significantly increased. So we find people at the bottom struggling for food and shelter, while those at the top earn many years worth of the average salary while they sleep. The majority in the middle work hard yet lack savings, living their entire lives a few paychecks from destitution.</p>
<p>Things have got so bad that even mainstream discourse has shifted to reflect the new reality. We’re routinely told that millennials face low wages, poor quality jobs, high debt, and worse economic outcomes compared to their parents. People now accept that the political system is rigged by a rich elite who’ve captured the institutions of the nation state. And even the arch conservative world of academic economics talks about inequality. And that simply didn’t happen as recently as ten years ago.</p>
<p>Bourgeois thinkers struggle to explain the major cause of economic inequality, because to do requires thinking deeply about property relations and the issue of systematic exploitation. Instead, they prefer to think about unequal human capital endowments, taxation policies, interest and growth rates, the saving habits of workers, rising costs in child and health care, or the impact of automation. They’ll think about anything and everything except the actual reason for inequality.</p>
<p>Capitalist firms, in an important sense, are social machines, institutions that operate within the context of a market economy to “sort” individuals into different classes by means of the wage system. This sorting produces a very specific income and wealth distribution, which is peculiar to capitalism. Empirically, capitalist societies exhibit two distinct regimes: a lognormal distribution of wage income, and a Pareto distribution of profit income.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2">2</a></sup></p>
<p>In any dynamic society, with a continual reallocation of the division of labour as new skills are demanded and other skills are automated or changed, we should expect some level of wage inequality due to mismatches between supply and demand in the labour market. Also, some jobs are terrible and dangerous, and people should get more for risking more. And some people really do contribute more within the workplace, and its OK if they get additional awards from their peers, if only to make sure they stick around. And some people actually need more, perhaps due to illness or disabilities or additional domestic responsibilities. All this is fine.</p>
<p>But, empirically, we see more than wage inequality. We see two distinct regimes. We see a majority earning wages, at the bottom of the scale, and a minority taking profits, at the top of the scale. Capitalist societies produce extreme inequalities where the top 10% or so take a big and disproportionate slice of the social pie.</p>
<p>And the reason is obvious, for those willing to look: the major cause of economic inequality is the wage system itself. The more workers a capitalist exploits the more profit they make. The more profit they make the more workers they can exploit. And capitalists in the super-rich bracket enjoy positive feedback effects. They can hardly lose. The economic game is entirely rigged in their favour. And, in this elevated state, they fall asleep, wake up the next morning, having earned more than workers do in their entire lifetimes.</p>
<p>In fact, the inequality between capitalists far exceeds the inequality between workers. The super-rich become astronomically rich as we bounce along the power-law tail of the Pareto distribution. The astronomically rich capture ostensibly democratic institutions, a phenomenon that is particularly clear in the USA, so that even mild social reforms are off the table. We’ve seen a collection of post-war policies, that once mitigated economic inequality, ditched in the last thirty years or so. This is why things have got even worse. Economic exploitation has increased.</p>
<p>Extreme economic inequality causes untold misery. At the top we see excessive and wasteful hyper-consumption. At the bottom, countless everyday struggles to live a dignified life. All the social ills of Silicon Valley, many of which are hidden in plain sight, are suffered mostly by the poorly paid, those with the least money. But inequality affects everyone. Societies with high Gini coefficients do worse on almost all measures of social well-being.</p>
<p>But it doesn’t have to be this way. Let’s imagine an impossible event, just for the sake of illustrating a point. Imagine that all the people we whispered to—in the cafes, the offices and homes of Silicon Valley—actually listened, and decided, right there and then, to abolish exploitation, and resolved, with great determination, to only ever incorporate worker co-ops, and only lend capital, and never demand equity, then—with one decisive and unlikely step—Silicon Valley would actually begin to do good. Because it’s at this precise pivotal moment—the birth of a new productive unit—that a society’s social relations of production either get reproduced, or changed. For once you start to abolish the wage contract, and the renting of human beings, you start to abolish economic classes and extreme income inequality. Wealth would then start to be shared more equitably, and fairly, upon the principle of exchange, according to actual contributions to production, and not specious paper claims. The Pareto upper-regime would lose its material basis, would totter and fall, and therewith all the power that goes with it, the ability to capture and corrupt democracies and run them for the benefit of a privileged and undeserving few. The majority of the population would have more, enjoy more, and live better.</p>
<p>You know, perhaps some really gifted entrepreneurs could figure out a way to export this culture, and good social outcomes, to the rest of the world. </p>
<h2 id="silicon-valley-bullshit-progressivism">Silicon Valley: bullshit progressivism</h2>
<p>But sadly, as of today, that is a dream. And it’s not even a dream that’s widely shared. Silicon Valley does not see the connection between the kinds of firms it funds and creates, and the kinds of social ills that surround it.</p>
<p>But why single out Silicon Valley? What I’ve just described applies to capitalism in general.<br>
Silicon Valley deserves especial opprobrium because the contradiction between its self-image and its reality is particularly stark. Silicon Valley desperately, desperately wants to view itself, and be seen as, socially progressive, enlightened, cutting-edge and, yes, utopian.</p>
<p>But despite the explosion of ideas and firms, and the progressive rhetoric, the core propositions of capitalism are completely untouched, inviolate. The coupling of radical technical experimentation, with extreme conservation of capitalist property relations, has been a very successful recipe for the Valley’s elite.</p>
<p>But the very startups that want to “change the world for the better” immediately reproduce economic exploitation: they separate human beings into a class that must rent their labour, and a class that appropriates the fruits of that labour; a class that is disciplined and must do as they are told in the workplace, and a class that disciplines and commands without democratic control. Every time an optimistic and earnest group of workers, with some great ideas, incorporate a startup and issue equity, any progressive content of those ideas are irreparably harmed.</p>
<p>Yet this is the specific evil that Silicon Valley does: it funnels the progressive content of technical utopianism (the increase in the forces of production) into institutions that exploit workers on a global scale, and contribute to extreme economic inequality (the existing social relations of production). Silicon Valley helps produce the dystopia we live in. It doesn’t change the world for the better. It makes it worse, every single day.</p>
<p>The narcissistic self-image of Valley culture contributes to its political backwardness. Some workers celebrate a victory when corporate HR departments commit to diversity in the workplace, or promise to address the gender pay gap. But these are easy concessions for capitalism, softballs, and the owners of your firm will happily accommodate you. Just don’t ask for bottom-up democracy in the workplace, or profit-sharing. Try it. You’ll get a very different response.</p>
<p>But that’s what I do wish for. And I’m talking to you now, fellow workers of the Valley! If you really want to do no evil, to be good, disrupt the status quo and make the world a better place, then <em>don’t create a capitalist firm</em>: it’s a top-down dictatorship, where the dictators steal the money. There’s nothing progressive about this kind of social institution. Founding such a startup is deeply unethical, represents institutionalised theft, and is a prime cause of diverse social ills. </p>
<p>Instead, use your talents to create democratic worker-owned cooperatives, based on equality among its working members; or help think of creative ways to solve the political problem of capitalists’ monopoly on capital.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3">3</a></sup> Abolishing economic exploitation genuinely makes the world a better place. Reproducing it in your startup does not.</p>

            
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Signal knows who you're talking to (2023) (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sanesecurityguy.com/articles/signal-knows-who-youre-talking-to/</link>
            <guid>46022279</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 10:22:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sanesecurityguy.com/articles/signal-knows-who-youre-talking-to/">https://sanesecurityguy.com/articles/signal-knows-who-youre-talking-to/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46022279">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

				
<p>Or, at the very least, they can.</p>



<p>Recently I got a friend to finally join me on Signal. He asked something about whether or not Signal is truly secure and private, like if it was safe from US government surveillance. I told him: <em>“Well, it’s end-to-end encrypted, so they don’t know <strong>what</strong> we’re talking about, but they definitely know that we’re talking to each other.”</em></p>



<p>I said that because Signal uses our phone numbers as ID’s. So, Signal would know that Phone Number A is talking to Phone Number B, and if they can figure out that Phone Number A belongs to me, and Phone Number B belongs to my buddy (usually not too hard to figure out with some OSINT or the assistance of certain governments), then Signal would know that my buddy and I are talking, even if they don’t know what we’re talking about.</p>



<p>This is a limit of end-to-end encryption, which I’ve <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://sanesecurityguy.com/articles/the-limits-of-end-to-end-encryption/" target="_blank">talked about before</a>. End-to-end encryption provides confidentiality of data, but not anonymity or protection from identifying metadata.</p>



<p>However, I was surprised when my friend got back to me saying that, no, Signal actually doesn’t know who’s talking to who because of this feature called “<a href="https://signal.org/blog/sealed-sender/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Sealed Sender</a>“.</p>



<p><em>“Woah! Seriously?! Cool!”</em> I thought. But then I started reading how Sealed Sender actually works, according to none other than Signal themselves, and I found that this feature is very technically complex, and <strong>totally useless</strong>.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ ಠ ᴥಠ ʔ: Woah! Seriously?! Not cool!</p>
</blockquote>



<h2>One-way anonymity for two-way communications</h2>



<p>While Sealed Sender is pretty complicated under the hood, the result of it is one-way anonymity. That means that, when Phone Number A sends a message to Phone Number B, Signal won’t know that the message is coming from Phone Number A and will only know that the message is to be delivered to Phone Number B.</p>



<p>It does this in a way that’s very similar to snail mail without a return address: the letter inside the mail envelope might tell the recipient who the sender is, but the mail envelope itself tells the post office only who the recipient is so that it can be delivered to them. If the post office doesn’t or can’t open the envelope to read the letter itself, then they don’t know who the sender is. Later on, when the recipient wants to send a reply to the sender, they can do the same thing.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ·ᴥ·ʔ: Hm, okay. This kind of sounds like it’s anonymous.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Well, yes, it sort of is, but only when there’s only one message to be sent. The problem comes up when multiple messages are being sent back-and-forth like this.</p>



<p>Sticking with the snail mail analogy, what happens when two pen pals keep sending mail to each other from their homes without including return addresses in their envelopes? The postal service might not know who exactly is sending each piece of mail but, over time, they would know that <strong>Address A in Lower Manhattan</strong>, New York, keeps on getting one-way mail from the post office in 3630 East Tremont Avenue, <strong>the Bronx</strong>, New York; and <strong>Address B in the Bronx</strong> keeps on getting one-way mail from the post office in 350 Canal Street, <strong>Lower Manhattan</strong>.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ´•ᴥ•`ʔ: Oh. Then the postal service would be pretty sure that whoever is living at Address A and Address B are talking to each other.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Exactly. That’s the limitation of one-way anonymity: <strong>it works only one way!</strong> Once you start doing two-way communications, with replies going back-and-forth, then one-way anonymity is useless.</p>



<h2>Two pieces of metadata</h2>



<p>With multiple messages being sent back-and-forth over time, and with Signal knowing <em>only the recipient phone number</em> of each message, it would be pretty hard for Signal to figure out who’s talking to who when their servers are getting thousands of messages every second from different senders, with each message being conveyed to thousands of different recipients. But, Signal doesn’t know <em>only the recipient phone number</em> of each message; they also know the IP address of each sender. And this is where the snail mail analogy fails, because IP addresses are <em>much more specific</em> than post offices.</p>



<p>Signal messages, as we all know, get sent over the internet, and the internet sends data around using IP addresses. Sealed Sender only protects the sender’s phone number; it does not protect the sender’s IP address. So, if you’re sending Signal messages to your super secret pen pal from your house, and you aren’t using a VPN or Tor, then Signal knows that the messages being sent to your pen pal’s phone number are coming from your house’s IP address (not a post office, your house).</p>



<p>Even if you are using some method of masking your real IP address, you still have to use <em>some</em> IP address in order to communicate on the internet, and Signal will see that <em>the same IP address keeps on sending messages to the same phone number</em>. That’s enough to easily figure out that all of these different messages meant for the recipient are coming from the same sender. Sure, maybe you’re using the IP address of a VPN server or Tor exit node that has other Signal users sending messages at the same time, but that’s extremely unlikely. More likely: Even when you use a VPN or Tor, Signal can easily tell that every Sealed Sender message you’re sending to your pen pal are coming from one person: you.</p>



<p>And if your pen pal replies, the reply will have his IP address on it (the same IP address Signal sent your messages to) and your phone number on it. And then, when you want to receive the reply, you have to connect to Signal’s servers using, again, your IP address (the same IP address you used to send your messages to your pen pal earlier). Just like that, with two messages, Signal figured out which phone number (yours) is talking to which other phone number (your pen pal’s). If they ever decide to try and figure out who own these two phone numbers, they could ask your telecoms, or simply search Facebook and Twitter.</p>



<p>You can’t avoid using IP addresses on the internet; they are a necessity on the internet. But you can use a VPN or Tor to mask your real IP address with a fake one that’s not tied to your identity. <strong>But you can’t do that with phone numbers.</strong> A phone number is either tied to your identity or it isn’t; there is no masking possible, unless you use a service like <a href="https://mysudo.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">MySudo</a> which <a href="https://mysudo.com/mysudo-plans/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">isn’t available for most of us</a> (US and Canada only, as of this writing). If you’re fortunate enough to be able to buy a prepaid SIM without ID, then great, all you and your pen pal have to do is buy some SIM cards that aren’t tied to your identities. If buying a prepaid SIM without ID ain’t an option, then your phone number has to be tied to your identity, and Signal can use these unmasked phone numbers, in combination with masked or unmasked IP addresses, to figure out who’s talking to who, <em>despite Sealed Sender’s promises</em>, as long as there’s a two-way conversation going on.</p>



<p>Which brings up an interesting question: <strong>Why does Signal require phone numbers?</strong></p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ´•ᴥ•`ʔ: Hey, that is an interesting question…</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Signal works over the internet, and the internet requires IP (internet protocol) addresses in order to figure out where a message should go. But sending messages over the internet <strong>does not</strong> require phone numbers; that’s a requirement when using SMS or cellular calls or mobile data, <strong>but not for using the internet</strong>. And yet, the “privacy-protecting” Signal app requires you to use a phone number to send and receive messages…</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ⚆ᴥ⚆ʔ: Hmmmm…</p>
</blockquote>



<h2>It’s always a two-way street</h2>



<p>It gets worse. I keep repeating this: <strong>two-way communication</strong>. Sealed Sender doesn’t work with <strong>two-way communication</strong>. But, I’ve kind of been lying. The truth is: <strong>Signal already knows which phone numbers have been talking to which, even with Sealed Sender and only one-way communication.</strong></p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ ಠ ᴥಠ ʔ: What?!</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Do these check marks look familiar to you? (Forgive the pixelation.)</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1035" height="580" src="https://sanesecurityguy.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Delivery-Receipt.png" alt="" srcset="https://sanesecurityguy.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Delivery-Receipt.png 1035w, https://sanesecurityguy.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Delivery-Receipt-300x168.png 300w, https://sanesecurityguy.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Delivery-Receipt-768x430.png 768w, https://sanesecurityguy.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/Delivery-Receipt-600x336.png 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1035px) 100vw, 1035px"></figure>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ·ᴥ·ʔ: Hm, yeah. Aren’t they the check marks that show up for at least a second whenever I send a Signal message? This is what’s shown after the lone check mark, and before they both turn white to indicate that my message was read, right?</p>
</blockquote>



<p>That’s right. The lone check mark indicates that your Signal message was sent to Signal’s servers, these two check marks above indicate that your Signal message has been delivered to the recipient, and the two white check marks indicate that the recipient has read your Signal message.</p>



<p>Now, the thing about the two check marks above is that your Signal app only shows them when your phone has received what’s called a “delivery receipt” from the recipient’s phone. Whenever your pen pal gets a message from you, their Signal app sends a delivery receipt from their phone, through Signal’s servers, to your phone. Their Signal app does this <em>automatically and instantly</em>, and neither of you can turn it off. You can turn off read receipts (the two white check marks) and typing indicators, but you can’t turn off the <em>very first reply</em>: delivery receipts.</p>



<p>The delivery receipt is – <em>ahem</em> – also “protected” using Sealed Sender, but what was it that I’ve been saying this whole time is wrong with Sealed Sender?</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ·ᴥ·ʔ: It works only one-way…</p>
</blockquote>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ&nbsp;&nbsp; • ᴥ • &nbsp;&nbsp;ʔ: It works only one-way…</p>
</blockquote>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ&nbsp;&nbsp; º ᴥ º &nbsp;&nbsp;ʔ: …and the delivery receipt automatically makes it two-way.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Exactly. And you can’t turn it off. Go figure why.</p>



<h2>Some alternatives and a work in progress</h2>



<p>So if you can’t trust Signal, who can you trust? Well, if all you need is a private text-based communication channel that won’t falsely advertise their privacy guarantees to you, <a href="https://proton.me/mail" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Proton Mail</a> and <a href="https://tuta.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tutanota</a> (now called Tuta) are pretty good. But if you want private voice-based communication, then that’s gonna’ be a problem. WhatsApp is even worse than Signal, Telegram is <a href="https://sanesecurityguy.com/articles/the-limits-of-end-to-end-encryption/#end-to-end-apps" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">even worse than WhatsApp</a>, Wire requires an email address to use it (another unnecessary requirement), and most of the rest can’t be trusted because they aren’t open-source.</p>



<p>You could use <a href="https://meet.jit.si/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Jitsi</a> for voice communications, but you’d have to use a separate service for text communications. You could use <a href="https://matrix.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Matrix</a> for both text and voice, but that’s a software and communication protocol, so you’d have to set up your own server running it. You could use <a href="https://element.io/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Element</a>, which runs Matrix servers, but you’d have to <a href="https://element.io/privacy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">trust Amazon and Cloudflare</a> with your metadata, making this a rather messy solution to a privacy problem.</p>



<p>What that leaves us with is a single service that is still a work in progress: <a href="https://simplex.chat/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SimpleX</a>. It asks for no global identifiers like phone numbers or email addresses. It at least tries, unlike Signal, <em>to make sure that it doesn’t know who’s talking to who</em>. It does this with the use of proxies that you randomly send your messages through to get to your recipient (the <a href="https://github.com/simplex-chat/simplexmq/blob/master/protocol/overview-tjr.md#technical-details" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">technical details</a> of which are too complicated to get into here). Of course it is <a href="https://github.com/simplex-chat/simplex-chat" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">open-source</a> and end-to-end encrypted, otherwise I wouldn’t be mentioning it. It even goes so far as to <strong>allow you to use Tor</strong> with it, or any <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SOCKS" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">SOCKS</a> proxy. It’s pretty cool, actually; the most technically amazing communications platform I’ve ever seen.</p>



<p>But, it ain’t perfect. It’s kinda’ slow, and messages sometimes don’t come in in the right order or don’t come in at all. Voice calls are… iffy, particularly when using Tor. It is still a young, developing project, though it has been making great strides in improving itself, including <a href="https://github.com/trailofbits/publications/blob/master/reviews/SimpleXChat.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">getting a security audit</a>.</p>



<p>Time will tell how it turns out, but at least I can say one thing: we’ve got a viable alternative.</p>







<p>Hey, Kuma!</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ •̀ᴥ•́ ʔ: Where have you been for the past 11 months?!</p>
</blockquote>



<p>I actually started writing this article months ago and then got busy again.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ ಠ ᴥಠ ʔ: Well at least visit me with some tips and tricks every once in a while.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>I’ll try, buddy, but real life comes first before imaginary friends.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>ʕ •̀ᴥ•́ ʔ: I know I’m imaginary, but are your subscribers?</p>
</blockquote>



<p>I dunno’. Maybe they should give me a hint by signing up below!</p>



<p>Or don’t; my RSS feed’s in the site menu. Unlike Signal, I don’t need you to sign up with a global identifier.</p>
  
  
  
  

  
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[After my dad died, we found the love letters (801 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jenn.site/after-my-dad-died-we-found-the-love-letters/</link>
            <guid>46021825</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 08:40:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jenn.site/after-my-dad-died-we-found-the-love-letters/">https://www.jenn.site/after-my-dad-died-we-found-the-love-letters/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46021825">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    

    

    
        

        <p>
            <i>
                <time datetime="2025-11-23T05:52Z">
    23 Nov, 2025
</time>
            </i>
        </p>
    

    <p>a few days after <a href="https://jenn.site/my-dad-could-still-be-alive-but-hes-not/">dad died</a>, we found the love letters, hidden away among his things. one of them said, <em>i love dota and i love peaches, but i love you more. i will quit smoking and lose weight for you. the happiest days of my life are the ones that start with you across the breakfast table from me.</em></p>
<p>my parents were not a love match. at 27 and 26, they were embarrassingly old by the standards of their small chinese port town. all four of my grandparents exerted enormous pressure to force them together.</p>
<p>my father fulfilled the familial obligations heaped on his shoulders without complaint. he didn't get along with my mother, or my younger brother, but this wasn't too bad; he often worked away from us (for months and even years on end), mostly in china, more recently in redacted, another canadian city.</p>
<p>the physical distance between us for most of my life has made his passing easier for me to come to terms with. i call him dad here but i didn't lose a dad, i lost someone who was abstractly a father to me. he was more often gone than there, had missed all of my graduations and birthday parties. there was one time he took care of me when i was sick. his hands on me were gentle, and he told me stories from chinese history while i lay feverish in bed. i was seven. this is approximately the only memory i have of him being a dad to me.</p>
<p>still, the two of us were close in our own way. sometimes, the two of us would go on long walks together. after fifteen minutes of silence, or twenty, something would loosen in him and he would start to tell me about the depths of his sadness and the disappointment in the way his life played out. i was good at not taking this personally. i didn't think he ever had a chance to be happy or authentic, his entire life. he sacrificed himself so i could.</p>
<p>i always thought that if he had a chance at happiness, he would be the gentle, funny, and sensitive aesthete that i caught glimpses of sometimes, instead of the bullheaded chinese patriarch others seemed to demand.</p>
<p>except it turns out he did have this chance after all. his lover and i ended up meeting soon after his death. edward lived in redacted, the city that my dad had worked in for the past year and a bit.</p>
<p>edward tells me their story, all in a rush. he and my dad had been seeing each other for three years, and had agreed to go exclusive a year and a half ago. they met while he was in china, and there was an instant spark between them, something special and precious that neither of them had felt before. dad convinced him to apply for a university program here in canada, to eventually get permanent residency in canada. so edward, in his 30s, sold his flourishing business and his house, and came to start over in a foreign land for the sake of being with him.</p>
<p>edward reckons they were engaged, or something like it; they lived together, toured open houses in redacted every weekend with every intent to buy something together, and there was an understanding that dad would soon come out, divorce my mother, and live in the open with edward for the rest of their lives.</p>
<p>edward gave me some photos he had of my dad, and i could scarcely believe that they were of the grim, sad man i knew. he beams in all of them, glowing with joy, his smile more incandescent than i've ever seen in my entire life. i steal glances at edward, the person who took all those impossible photos. the person he was looking at.</p>
<p>my mind keeps stuttering to boskovitch's installation, that single box fan behind plexiglass. i imagine the course of events from edward's point of view: a year living with the love of your life, and then they are suddenly gone in an awful accident and you are too late to see them one last time, to attend the funeral. your own grief is an isolating thing because you are closeted and no one else knew who you were to each other. i wish we had gotten in touch sooner, but edward is grateful to be allowed any affordance, at all.</p>
<p>their life in redacted seemed similarly impossible: a life where my dad splurged on the treats he never did at home (hagen dazs ice cream, honeycrisp apples, nice shoes) and left the house on a regular basis to explore the city with the one he loves. a life where he felt safe enough to ask for kisses and cuddles because he knew they would be provided, even to <em>sa jiao</em> playfully. all i ever knew him to do at home was to sit in a stupor by the television set.</p>
<p>and there was a new hurt, but it was sweet, to imagine the way life could have been in ten years time, a life i've never previously imagined; dad happily with edward in a nice new house where i'd visit every so often, shoulders loose and smiling, and we'd get to talk, <em>actually</em> talk.</p>
<p>according to edward, my dad had known that he had liked men at least since his university years. that makes it almost forty years in the closet, then; just thinking about it makes me feel a sort of dizzying claustrophobia.</p>
<p>i came out to mom years before i came out to dad. when i did, mom told me that coming out to dad was not a good idea, because he was such a traditionalist and she didn't know how he would react. but i came out to him anyways, one quiet afternoon when i visited him in china, because i thought our relationship was good and that he can handle it, and i wanted him to know this about me.</p>
<p>when i did, he took it well. he told me that though the path i am on is a painful one, he would be there for me, and that the most important thing was to find <em>xin fu</em> in life, not to live your life in accordance to the expectations of anyone else. in my staggering relief i did not notice the confusion. i just felt so grateful to have had that understanding, a precious gift that i did not have any expectation of receiving. now, i feel only bereft of the conversations we never managed to have, and grief for the life he never got to live.</p>
<p>dad lives in my living room these days, in a box made of cherry wood, because mom didn't want him in the house after the truth came out. so when edward visited, he got to see him one last time, and say goodbye. he held the box in his arms and wept, spilling more tears and emotions than his biological family managed to, and i escaped to my room for the evening to give them some privacy.</p>
<p>did i mention the shrines? we set them up for the dead in our culture. we had ours, a formal thing in a cabinet, and we had knelt in front of it like we were supposed to, given the correct number of kowtows. edward shared with me pictures of his. it sprawled over the entirety of his dining table. it had packs of playing cards from the brand he liked best and his favourite cuts of meat and the wine he finished off the day with. every morning, he would play my dad's favourite songs to him. i didn't know my dad's favourite cuts of meat. i didn't know he drank wine. i didn't know he listened to music.</p>
<p>so of course i let them say goodbye to each other. when i went out of my room the next morning, he was still fully dressed on my couch, bedding untouched, staring blankly at the box in his lap. it gleamed red in the morning sun. he rose at my approach, put my dad back on the mantle with gentle hands, and then stood quietly at a perfect parade rest in front of him as i managed breakfast for the two of us. his flight back to redacted was that afternoon.</p>
<p>i don't know how to thank you for all this, he says. the chance to say goodbye. he was really proud of you, he spoke about you to me all the time. he never told me that you were gay. edward tells me that dad had plans to go back to redacted in a few weeks time and that he wanted to tell me everything before he left, but he was anxious about how i'd take it. i don't ask edward how many times he'd made the resolution to tell me before.</p>
<p>because you see, my dad was a coward. mom had started asking for divorces by the time i was in my teens, and dad was the one who always said no. he would complain to <em>her</em> mother, a traditionalist, to ensure that she would berate her daughter back into line. his family and his culture had no place for him, so he used her as a shield to make sure that he would be spared the scrutiny. slowly, we found evidence of other affairs, going back decades. of course my mother did not want him in the house.</p>
<p>i sit by my dad sometimes, and i make sure he always has a bowl of fresh fruit. fifty seven years, most of them suffocating and miserable, the last three of them shot through with so much joy his smile absolutely glows.</p>
<div><p><em>he wasted his entire life</em>, my mom said to me, the evening we found the love letters. <em>his entire life, and mine as well.</em></p><p>
(<a href="https://jenn.site/my-dead-deadbeat-gay-dad/">dissolution</a>)</p></div>


    

    
        
            <p>
                
                    <a href="https://www.jenn.site/blog/?q=diary">#diary</a>
                
                    <a href="https://www.jenn.site/blog/?q=longform">#longform</a>
                
            </p>
        

        
            


        

        
            
        
    


  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Revisits JPEG XL in Chromium After Earlier Removal (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://windowsreport.com/google-revisits-jpeg-xl-in-chromium-after-earlier-removal/</link>
            <guid>46021179</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 06:05:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://windowsreport.com/google-revisits-jpeg-xl-in-chromium-after-earlier-removal/">https://windowsreport.com/google-revisits-jpeg-xl-in-chromium-after-earlier-removal/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46021179">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="primary">
							
<div>

<!--googleoff: all-->

<p><span id="close-restoro-download-arrow">X</span>INSTALL BY CLICKING THE DOWNLOAD
    FILE</p>


<!--googleon: all-->

</div>




<p>Three years ago, Google removed JPEG XL support from Chrome, stating there wasn’t enough interest at the time. That position has now changed.</p>



<p>In a recent note to developers, a Chrome team representative <a href="https://groups.google.com/a/chromium.org/g/blink-dev/c/WjCKcBw219k/m/NmOyvMCCBAAJ">confirmed </a>that work has restarted to bring JPEG XL to Chromium and said Google “would ship it in Chrome” once long-term maintenance and the usual launch requirements are met.</p>



<p>The team explained that other platforms moved ahead. Safari supports JPEG XL, and Windows 11 users can add native support through an image extension from Microsoft Store. The format is also confirmed for use in PDF documents. There has been continuous demand from developers and users who ask for its return.</p>



<p>Before Google ships the feature in Chrome, the company wants the integration to be secure and supported over time.</p>



<h2 id="h-chrome-jpeg-xl-implementation-adds-animation-support">Chrome JPEG XL implementation adds animation support</h2>



<p>A developer has submitted new code that reintroduces JPEG XL to Chromium. This version is marked as feature complete. The developer <a href="https://groups.google.com/a/chromium.org/g/blink-dev/c/WjCKcBw219k/m/NeiCV32tBAAJ">said</a> it also “includes animation support,” which earlier implementations did not offer. The code passes most of Chrome’s automated testing, but it remains under review and is not available to users.</p>



<p>The featured image is taken from an unlisted developer demo created for testing purposes.</p>



<p>JPEG XL is a newer image format intended as a replacement for traditional JPEG files. It can reduce file size without loss in visual quality. This may help web pages load faster and reduce data usage.  More details are available on the <a href="https://jpegxl.info/">official JPEG XL website</a>.</p>



<p>Google has not provided a timeline for JPEG XL support in Chrome. Users cannot enable the format today, but development has restarted after years without progress.</p>
<!-- CONTENT END 1 -->
						</div><div>
							<hr>
							<a href="https://windowsreport.com/author/venkat/">
								<div>
									<p><img src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/a9aaee4663a51a684e4cdf06c26cfad27545c87765d6dbdcedd6426dfec1e2eb?s=50&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fwindowsreport.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2024%2F01%2Fwricon.png&amp;r=g" width="50" height="50" alt="Venkat" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%2050%2050'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/a9aaee4663a51a684e4cdf06c26cfad27545c87765d6dbdcedd6426dfec1e2eb?s=50&amp;d=https%3A%2F%2Fwindowsreport.com%2Fwp-content%2Fuploads%2F2024%2F01%2Fwricon.png&amp;r=g">									</p>
									<div>
										<p>
											<strong>Venkat</strong>
											<img width="12" height="12" alt="Shield" src="https://windowsreport.com/wp-content/themes/reflectormedia-universalis/assets/images/shield-icon.svg" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%2012%2012'%3E%3C/svg%3E">
										</p>
																					<p>Tech Journalist</p>
																			</div>
								</div>
							</a>
															<p>
									Venkat is a tech writer with over 15 years of experience, known for spotting new browser features and tech changes before they go public. Based in India, he breaks down under-the-radar browser updates to help readers stay ahead.								</p>
														<hr>
						</div><div>
        <p><span>
            Readers help support Windows Report. We may get a commission if you buy through our links.        </span>
        <img width="8" height="8" alt="Tooltip Icon" src="https://windowsreport.com/wp-content/themes/reflectormedia-universalis/assets/images/info-icon.svg" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%208%208'%3E%3C/svg%3E"></p><p>
                Read our disclosure page to find out how can you help Windows Report sustain the editorial team.                <a href="https://windowsreport.com/affiliate-disclosure/" target="_blank" aria-label="Affiliate Disclosure">Read more</a>
            </p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unusual circuits in the Intel 386's standard cell logic (210 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.righto.com/2025/11/unusual-386-standard-cell-circuits.html</link>
            <guid>46020543</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 03:33:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.righto.com/2025/11/unusual-386-standard-cell-circuits.html">https://www.righto.com/2025/11/unusual-386-standard-cell-circuits.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46020543">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-3467012800646079318" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p>I've been studying the standard cell circuitry in the Intel 386 processor recently.
The 386, introduced in 1985, was Intel's most complex processor at the time, containing 285,000 transistors.
Intel's existing design techniques couldn't handle this complexity and the chip began to fall behind schedule.
To meet the schedule, the 386 team started using a technique called standard cell logic.
Instead of laying out each transistor manually, the layout process was performed by a computer.</p>
<p>The idea behind standard cell logic is to create standardized circuits (standard cells) for each type of logic element, such
as an inverter, NAND gate, or latch.
You feed your circuit description into software that selects the necessary cells, 
positions these cells into columns, and then routes the wiring between the cells.
This "automatic place and route" process creates the chip layout much faster than manual layout.
However, switching to standard cells was a risky decision since if the software couldn't create a
dense enough layout, the chip couldn't be manufactured.
But in the end, the 386 finished ahead of schedule, an almost unheard-of accomplishment.<span id="fnref:oral-history"><a href="#fn:oral-history">1</a></span></p>
<p>The 386's standard cell circuitry contains a few circuits that I didn't expect.
In this blog post, I'll take a quick look at some of these circuits:
surprisingly large multiplexers, a transistor that doesn't fit into the standard cell layout,
and inverters that turned out not to be inverters.
(If you want more background on standard cells in the 386, see my earlier post,
"<a href="https://www.righto.com/2024/01/intel-386-standard-cells.html">Reverse engineering standard cell logic in the Intel 386 processor</a>".)</p>
<p>The photo below shows the 386 die with the automatic-place-and-route regions highlighted; I'm focusing
on the red region in the lower right.
These blocks of logic have cells arranged in rows, giving them a characteristic striped appearance.
The dark stripes are the transistors that make up the logic gates, while the lighter regions between the stripes are the
"routing channels" that hold the wiring that connects the cells.
In comparison,
functional blocks
such as the datapath on the left
and the microcode ROM in the lower right
were designed manually to optimize density and performance, giving them a more solid appearance.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/die-labeled.jpg"><img alt="The 386 die with the standard-cell regions highlighted." height="530" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/die-labeled-w500.jpg" title="The 386 die with the standard-cell regions highlighted." width="500"></a></p><p>The 386 die with the standard-cell regions highlighted.</p>
<p>As for other features on the chip,
the black circles around the border are bond wire connections that go to the chip's external pins.
The chip has two metal layers, a small number by modern
standards, but a jump from the single metal layer of earlier processors such as the 286.
(Providing two layers of metal made automated routing practical: one layer can hold horizontal wires while the other layer
can hold vertical wires.)
The metal appears white in larger areas, but
purplish where circuitry underneath roughens its surface.
The underlying silicon and the polysilicon wiring are obscured by the metal layers.</p>
<h2>The giant multiplexers</h2>
<p>The standard cell circuitry that I'm examining (red box above) is part of the control logic that selects registers
while executing an instruction.
You might think that it is easy to select which registers take part in an instruction, but
due to the complexity of the x86 architecture, it is more difficult.
One problem is that a 32-bit register such as EAX can also be treated as the 16-bit register AX,
or two 8-bit registers AH and AL.
A second problem is that some instructions include a "direction" bit that switches the source and
destination registers.
Moreover, sometimes the register is specified by bits in the instruction, but in other cases,
the register is specified by the microcode.
Due to these factors, selecting the registers for an operation is a complicated process with many
cases, using control bits from the instruction, from the microcode, and from other sources.</p>
<p>Three registers need to be selected for an operation—two source registers and a destination register—and there
are about 17 cases that need to be handled.
Registers are specified with 7-bit control signals that select one of the 30 registers and control
which part of the register is accessed.
With three control signals, each 7 bits wide, and about 17 cases for each, you can see that
the register control logic is large and complicated.
(I wrote more about the 386's registers <a href="https://www.righto.com/2025/05/intel-386-register-circuitry.html">here</a>.)</p>
<p>I'm still reverse engineering the register control logic, so I won't go into details.
Instead, I'll discuss how the register control circuit uses multiplexers, implemented with standard cells.
A multiplexer is a circuit that combines multiple
input signals into a single output by selecting one of the inputs.<span id="fnref:one-hot"><a href="#fn:one-hot">2</a></span>
A multiplexer can be implemented with logic gates, for instance, by ANDing each input with the
corresponding control line, and then ORing the results together.
However, the 386 uses a different approach—CMOS switches—that avoids a large AND/OR gate.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/cmos-switch.jpg"><img alt="Schematic of a CMOS switch." height="169" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/cmos-switch-w200.jpg" title="Schematic of a CMOS switch." width="200"></a></p><p>Schematic of a CMOS switch.</p>
<p>The schematic above shows how a CMOS switch is constructed from two MOS transistors.
When the two transistors are on, the output is connected to the input, but when the two transistors are
off, the output is isolated.
An NMOS transistor is turned on when its input is high, but a PMOS transistor is turned on when its
input is <em>low</em>. Thus, the switch uses two control inputs, one inverted.
The motivation for using two transistors is that an NMOS transistor is better at pulling the output
low, while a PMOS transistor is better at pulling the output high, so combining them yields the best performance.<span id="fnref:6502"><a href="#fn:6502">3</a></span>
Unlike a logic gate, the CMOS switch has no amplification, so a signal is weakened as it passes through the switch.
As will be seen below, inverters can be used to amplify the signal.</p>
<p>The image below shows how CMOS switches appear under the microscope.
This image is very hard to interpret because the two layers of metal on the 386 are packed together densely, but you
can see that some wires run horizontally and others run vertically.
The bottom layer of metal (called M1) runs vertically in the routing area, as well as providing internal
wiring for a cell.
The top layer of metal (M2) runs horizontally; unlike M1, the M2 wires can cross a cell.
The large circles are vias that connect the M1 and M2 layers, while the small circles are connections
between M1 and polysilicon or M1 and silicon.
The central third of the image is a column of standard cells with two CMOS switches outlined in green.
The cells are bordered by the vertical ground rail and
+5V rail that power the cells. 
The routing areas are on either side of the cells, holding the wiring that connects the cells.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/switch-metal.jpg"><img alt="Two CMOS switches, highlighted in green. The lower switch is flipped vertically compared to the upper switch." height="465" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/switch-metal-w400.jpg" title="Two CMOS switches, highlighted in green. The lower switch is flipped vertically compared to the upper switch." width="400"></a></p><p>Two CMOS switches, highlighted in green. The lower switch is flipped vertically compared to the upper switch.</p>
<p>Removing the metal layers reveals the underlying silicon with a layer of polysilicon wiring on top.
The doped silicon regions show up as dark outlines.
I've drawn the polysilicon in green; it forms a transistor (brighter green) when it crosses doped silicon.
The metal ground and power lines are shown in blue and red, respectively, with other metal wiring in purple.
The black dots are vias between layers.
Note how metal wiring (purple) and polysilicon wiring (green) are combined to route signals within
the cell.
Although this standard cell is complicated, the important thing is that it only needs to be designed once.
The standard cells for different functions are all designed to have the same width, so the cells can be arranged in
columns, snapped together like Lego bricks.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/switch-diagram.jpg"><img alt="A diagram showing the silicon for a standard-cell switch. The polysilicon is shown in green. The bottom metal is shown in blue, red, and purple." height="289" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/switch-diagram-w400.jpg" title="A diagram showing the silicon for a standard-cell switch. The polysilicon is shown in green. The bottom metal is shown in blue, red, and purple." width="400"></a></p><p>A diagram showing the silicon for a standard-cell switch. The polysilicon is shown in green. The bottom metal is shown in blue, red, and purple.</p>
<p>To summarize, this switch circuit allows the input to be connected to the output or disconnected, controlled by the select signal.
This switch is more complicated than the earlier schematic because it includes two inverters to amplify
the signal.
The data input and the two select lines are connected to the polysilicon (green); the cell is designed so
these connections can be made on either side.
At the top, the input goes through a standard two-transistor inverter.
The lower left has two transistors, combining the NMOS half of an inverter with the NMOS half of the switch.
A similar circuit on the right combines the PMOS part of an inverter and switch.
However, because PMOS transistors are weaker, this part of the circuit is duplicated.</p>
<p>A multiplexer is constructed by combining multiple switches, one for each input.
Turning on one switch will select the corresponding input.
For instance, a four-to-one multiplexer has four switches, so it can select one of the four inputs.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/mux4.jpg"><img alt="A four-way multiplexer constructed from CMOS switches and individual transistors." height="430" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/mux4-w200.jpg" title="A four-way multiplexer constructed from CMOS switches and individual transistors." width="200"></a></p><p>A four-way multiplexer constructed from CMOS switches and individual transistors.</p>
<p>The schematic above shows a hypothetical multiplexer with four inputs.
One optimization is that if an input is always 0, the PMOS transistor can be omitted. Likewise,
if an input is always 1, the NMOS transistor can be omitted.
One set of select lines is activated at a time to select the corresponding input.
The pink circuit selects 1,
green selects input A, yellow selects input B, and blue selects 0.
The multiplexers in the 386 are similar, but have more inputs.</p>
<p>The diagram below shows how much circuitry is devoted to multiplexers in this block of standard cells.
The green, purple, and red cells correspond to the multiplexers driving the three register control
outputs.
The yellow cells are inverters that generate the inverted control signals for the CMOS switches.
This diagram also shows how the automatic layout of cells results in a layout that appears random.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/muxes.jpg"><img alt="A block of standard-cell logic with multiplexers highlighted. The metal and polysilicon layers were removed for this photo, revealing the silicon transistors." height="452" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/muxes-w400.jpg" title="A block of standard-cell logic with multiplexers highlighted. The metal and polysilicon layers were removed for this photo, revealing the silicon transistors." width="400"></a></p><p>A block of standard-cell logic with multiplexers highlighted. The metal and polysilicon layers were removed for this photo, revealing the silicon transistors.</p>
<h2>The misplaced transistor</h2>
<p>The idea of standard-cell logic is that standardized cells are arranged in columns.
The space between the cells is the "routing channel", holding the wiring that links the cells.
The 386 circuitry follows this layout, except for one single transistor, sitting between two columns
of cells.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/extra-transistor.jpg"><img alt="The &quot;misplaced&quot; transistor, indicated by the arrow. The irregular green regions are oxide that was incompletely removed." height="433" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/extra-transistor-w500.jpg" title="The &quot;misplaced&quot; transistor, indicated by the arrow. The irregular green regions are oxide that was incompletely removed." width="500"></a></p><p>The "misplaced" transistor, indicated by the arrow. The irregular green regions are oxide that was incompletely removed.</p>
<p>I wrote some software tools to help me analyze the standard cells. Unfortunately, my tools
assumed that all the cells were in columns, so this one wayward transistor caused me considerable inconvenience.</p>
<p>The transistor turns out to be a PMOS transistor, pulling a signal high as part of a multiplexer.
But why is this transistor out of place?
My hypothesis is that the transistor is a bug fix.
Regenerating the cell layout was very costly, taking many hours on an IBM mainframe computer.
Presumably, someone found that they could just stick the necessary transistor into an unused spot in the
routing channel, manually add the necessary wiring, and avoid the delay of regenerating all the cells.</p>
<h2>The fake inverter</h2>
<p>The simplest CMOS gate is the inverter, with an NMOS transistor to pull the output low and a
PMOS transistor to pull the output high.
The standard cell circuitry that I examined contains over a hundred inverters of various
sizes.
(Performance is improved by using inverters that aren't too small but also aren't
larger than necessary for a particular circuit. Thus, the standard cell library includes inverters of multiple sizes.)</p>
<p>The image below shows a medium-sized standard-cell inverter under the microscope.
For this image, I removed the two metal layers with acid to show the underlying polysilicon
(bright green) and silicon (gray).
The quality of this image is
poor—it is difficult to remove the metal without destroying the polysilicon—but the diagram below
should clarify the circuit.
The inverter has two transistors: a PMOS transistor connected to +5 volts to pull the output high when
the input is 0, and an NMOS transistor connected to ground to pull the output low when the input is 1.
(The PMOS transistor needs to be larger because PMOS transistors don't function as well as NMOS transistors due to
silicon physics.)</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/inverter-diagram.jpg"><img alt="An inverter as seen on the die. The corresponding standard cell is shown below." height="347" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/inverter-diagram-w450.jpg" title="An inverter as seen on the die. The corresponding standard cell is shown below." width="450"></a></p><p>An inverter as seen on the die. The corresponding standard cell is shown below.</p>
<p>The polysilicon input line plays a key role: where it crosses the doped silicon, a transistor gate is
formed.
To make the standard cell more flexible, the input to the inverter
can be connected on either the left or the right; in this case, the input
is connected on the right and there is no connection on the left.
The inverter's output can be taken from the polysilicon on the upper left or the right, but in this case, it
is taken from the upper metal layer (not shown).
The power, ground, and output lines are in the lower metal layer, which I have represented by
the thin red, blue, and yellow lines. The black circles are connections between the metal layer and
the underlying silicon.</p>
<p>This inverter appears dozens of times in the circuitry.
However, I came across a few inverters that didn't make sense. The problem was
that the inverter's output was connected to the output of a multiplexer.
Since an inverter is either on or off, its value would clobber the output of the multiplexer.<span id="fnref:latch"><a href="#fn:latch">4</a></span>
This didn't make any sense.
I double- and triple-checked the wiring to make sure I hadn't messed up.
After more investigation, I found another problem: the input to a "bad" inverter didn't make sense
either. The input consisted of two signals shorted together, which doesn't work.</p>
<p>Finally, I realized what was going on. A "bad inverter" has the exact silicon layout of an inverter,
but it wasn't an inverter: it was independent NMOS and PMOS transistors with separate inputs.
Now it all made sense.
With two inputs, the input signals were independent, not shorted together.
And since the transistors were controlled separately, the NMOS transistor could pull the output
low in some circumstances, the PMOS transistor could pull the output high in other circumstances,
or both transistors could be off, allowing the multiplexer's output to be used undisturbed.
In other words, the "inverter" was just two more cases for the multiplexer.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/transistors-die.jpg"><img alt="The &quot;bad&quot; inverter. (Image is flipped vertically for comparison with the previous inverter.)" height="177" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-curiosities/transistors-die-w450.jpg" title="The &quot;bad&quot; inverter. (Image is flipped vertically for comparison with the previous inverter.)" width="450"></a></p><p>The "bad" inverter. (Image is flipped vertically for comparison with the previous inverter.)</p>
<p>If you compare the "bad inverter" cell below with the previous cell, they look <em>almost</em> the same, but
there are subtle differences.
First, the gates of the two transistors are connected in the real inverter, but disconnected
by a small gap in the transistor pair.
I've indicated this gap in the photo above; it is hard to tell if the gap is real or just an imaging
artifact, so I didn't spot it.
The second difference is that the "fake" inverter has two input connections, one to each transistor,
while the inverter has a single input connection.
Unfortunately, I assumed that the two connections were just a trick to route the signal across
the inverter without requiring an extra wire.
In total, this cell was used 32 times as a real inverter and 9 times
as independent transistors.</p>
<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p>Standard cell logic and automatic place and route have a long history before the 386,
back to the early 1970s, so this isn't an Intel invention.<span id="fnref:standard-cell-history"><a href="#fn:standard-cell-history">5</a></span>
Nonetheless, the 386 team deserves the credit for deciding to use this technology at a time when it
was a risky decision.
They needed to develop custom software for their placing and routing needs, so this wasn't a trivial undertaking.
This choice paid off and they completed the 386 ahead of schedule.
The 386 ended up being a huge success for Intel, moving the x86 architecture to 32 bits and defining the dominant computer
architecture for the rest of the 20th century.</p>
<p>If you're interested in standard cell logic, I also wrote about <a href="https://www.righto.com/2021/03/reverse-engineering-standard-cell-logic.html">standard cell logic in an IBM chip</a>.
I plan to write more about the 386, so 
follow me on
<a href="https://oldbytes.space/@kenshirriff">Mastodon</a>, <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/righto.com">Bluesky</a>,
or RSS for updates.
Thanks to Pat Gelsinger and Roxanne Koester for providing helpful papers.</p>
<p>For more on the 386 and other chips, follow me on
Mastodon (<a href="https://oldbytes.space/@kenshirriff">@<span data-cfemail="4328262d302b2a31312a2525032c2f27213a3726306d3033222026">[email&nbsp;protected]</span></a>),
Bluesky (<a href="https://bsky.app/profile/righto.com">@righto.com</a>),
or <a href="https://www.righto.com/feeds/posts/default">RSS</a>.  (I've given up on Twitter.)
If you want to read more about the 386, I've written about the <a href="https://www.righto.com/2023/11/intel-386-clock-circuit.html">clock pin</a>,
<a href="https://www.righto.com/2025/05/386-prefetch-circuitry-reverse-engineered.html">prefetch queue</a>, <a href="https://www.righto.com/2023/10/intel-386-die-versions.html">die versions</a>, <a href="https://www.righto.com/2025/08/intel-386-package-ct-scan.html">packaging</a>, and <a href="https://www.righto.com/2025/08/static-latchup-metastability-386.html">I/O circuits</a>.</p>
<h2>Notes and references</h2>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[MCP Apps just dropped (OpenAI and Anthropic collab) and I think this is huge (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://blog.modelcontextprotocol.io/posts/2025-11-21-mcp-apps/</link>
            <guid>46020502</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Nov 2025 03:27:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://blog.modelcontextprotocol.io/posts/2025-11-21-mcp-apps/">http://blog.modelcontextprotocol.io/posts/2025-11-21-mcp-apps/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46020502">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><p>Today we’re introducing the proposal for the <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/ext-apps">MCP Apps Extension</a> (<a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/modelcontextprotocol/pull/1865">SEP-1865</a>) to standardize support for interactive user interfaces in the Model Context Protocol.</p><p>This extension addresses one of the most requested features from the MCP community and builds on proven work from <a href="https://github.com/idosal/mcp-ui">MCP-UI</a> and <a href="https://developers.openai.com/apps-sdk/">OpenAI Apps SDK</a> - the <strong>ability for MCP servers to deliver interactive user interfaces to hosts</strong>.</p><p>MCP Apps Extension introduces a standardized pattern for declaring UI resources, linking them to tools, and enabling bidirectional communication between embedded interfaces and the host application.</p><p><img alt="Example of an inline chat app with interactive UI for permission management" loading="lazy" src="http://blog.modelcontextprotocol.io/posts/images/inline-chat-app.png"></p><p>The SEP was authored by MCP Core Maintainers at OpenAI and Anthropic, together with the MCP-UI creators and lead maintainers of the MCP UI Community Working Group.</p><h2 id="standardization-for-interactive-interfaces">Standardization for interactive interfaces</h2><p>Currently, MCP servers are limited to exchanging text and structured data with hosts. While this works well for many use cases, it creates friction when tools need to present visual information or gather complex user input.</p><p>For example, consider a data visualization MCP server that returns chart data as JSON. The host application must interpret that data and render it. Handling all kinds of specialized data in this scenario translates to a significant burden for client developers, who would need to build their own logic to render the UI. As more UI requirements come up, like the need to collect multiple related settings from users, the complexity balloons. Alternatively, without UI support, these interactions become awkward exchanges of text prompts and responses.</p><p>The MCP community has been creative in working around these limitations, but different implementations using varying conventions and architectures make it harder for servers to work consistently across clients. This lack of standardization creates a real risk of ecosystem fragmentation - something we’re working to proactively prevent.</p><h2 id="building-together">Building together</h2><p>The <a href="https://github.com/MCP-UI-Org/mcp-ui">MCP-UI project</a>, created by <a href="https://github.com/idosal">Ido Salomon</a> and <a href="https://github.com/liady">Liad Yosef</a> and maintained by a dedicated community, spearheaded the vision of agentic apps with interactive interfaces. The project developed patterns for delivering rich user interfaces as first-class MCP resources, proving that agentic apps fit naturally within the MCP architecture. The project is backed by a large community and provides <a href="https://mcpui.dev/guide/client/overview">rich SDKs</a>, adopted at leading companies and projects such as Postman, Shopify, Hugging Face, Goose, and ElevenLabs.</p><p>The <a href="https://developers.openai.com/apps-sdk/">OpenAI Apps SDK</a> further validated the demand for rich UI experiences within conversational AI interfaces. The SDK enables developers to build rich, interactive applications inside ChatGPT using MCP as its backbone. To ensure interoperability and establish consistent security and usage patterns across the ecosystem, Anthropic, OpenAI, and MCP-UI are collaborating to create an official MCP extension for interactive interfaces.</p><p><img alt="Example of a fullscreen app with a rich data table interface" loading="lazy" src="http://blog.modelcontextprotocol.io/posts/images/fullscreen-chat-app.png"></p><h2 id="mcp-apps-extension-specification">MCP Apps Extension specification</h2><p>We’re proposing a specification for UI resources in MCP, but the implications go further than just a set of schema changes. The MCP Apps Extension is starting to look like an agentic app runtime: a foundation for novel interactions between AI models, users, and applications. The proposal is intentionally lean, starting with core patterns that we plan on expanding over time.</p><h3 id="key-design-decisions">Key design decisions</h3><h4 id="pre-declared-resources">Pre-declared resources</h4><p>UI templates are resources with the <code>ui://</code> URI scheme, referenced in tool metadata.</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="ts"><span><span><span>// Server registers UI resource
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>{
</span></span><span><span>  <span>uri</span><span>:</span> <span>"ui://charts/bar-chart"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>  <span>name</span><span>:</span> <span>"Bar Chart Viewer"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>  <span>mimeType</span><span>:</span> <span>"text/html+mcp"</span>
</span></span><span><span>}
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>// Tool references it in metadata
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>{
</span></span><span><span>  <span>name</span><span>:</span> <span>"visualize_data_as_bar_chart"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>  <span>description</span><span>:</span> <span>"Plots some data as a bar chart"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>  <span>inputSchema</span><span>:</span> {
</span></span><span><span>    <span>type</span><span>:</span> <span>"object"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>    <span>properties</span><span>:</span> {
</span></span><span><span>      <span>series</span><span>:</span> { <span>type</span><span>:</span> <span>"array"</span>, <span>items</span>: <span>....</span> }
</span></span><span><span>    }
</span></span><span><span>  },
</span></span><span><span>  <span>_meta</span><span>:</span> {
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"ui/resourceUri"</span><span>:</span> <span>"ui://charts/bar-chart"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>  }
</span></span><span><span>}
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>This approach enables hosts to prefetch and review templates before tool execution, improving both performance and security. It also separates static presentation (the template) from dynamic data (tool results), enabling better caching.</p><h4 id="mcp-transport-for-communication">MCP transport for communication</h4><p>Instead of inventing a custom message protocol, UI components communicate with hosts using existing MCP JSON-RPC base protocol over <code>postMessage</code>. This means that:</p><ul><li>UI developers can use the standard <code>@modelcontextprotocol/sdk</code> to build their applications</li><li>All communication is structured and auditable</li><li>Future MCP features automatically work with the UI extension</li></ul><h4 id="starting-with-html">Starting with HTML</h4><p>The initial extension specification supports only <code>text/html</code> content, rendered in sandboxed <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/docs/Web/HTML/Reference/Elements/iframe">iframes</a>. This provides:</p><ul><li>Universal browser support</li><li>Well-understood security model</li><li>Screenshot and preview generation capabilities</li><li>A clear baseline for future extensions</li></ul><p>Other content types such as external URLs, remote DOM, and native widgets are explicitly deferred to future iterations.</p><h4 id="security-first">Security-first</h4><p>Hosting interactive content from MCP servers requires careful security consideration. The proposal addresses this through multiple layers:</p><ol><li><strong>Iframe sandboxing</strong>: All UI content runs in sandboxed iframes with restricted permissions</li><li><strong>Predeclared templates</strong>: Hosts can review HTML content before rendering</li><li><strong>Auditable messages</strong>: All UI-to-host communication goes through loggable JSON-RPC</li><li><strong>User consent</strong>: Hosts can require explicit approval for UI-initiated tool calls</li></ol><p>These mitigations create defense in depth against malicious servers while preserving the flexibility developers need.</p><h4 id="backward-compatibility">Backward compatibility</h4><p>MCP Apps is an optional extension. Existing implementations continue working without changes, and hosts can gradually adopt UI support at their own pace. Servers should provide text-only fallback for all UI-enabled tools and return meaningful content even when UI is unavailable, so they can serve both UI-capable and text-only hosts.</p><h2 id="whats-next">What’s next</h2><p>The <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol-community/working-groups/issues/35">UI Community Working Group</a> has been instrumental in shaping this proposal through extensive feedback and discussion. We have built an <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/ext-apps">early access SDK</a> to demonstrate the patterns and types described in the specification proposal. The <a href="https://mcpui.dev/">MCP-UI</a> client and server SDKs support these patterns.</p><p>If you are interested in contributing to this effort, we invite you to:</p><ul><li>Review the full specification in <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/modelcontextprotocol/pull/1865">SEP-1865</a></li><li>Share feedback and concerns in <a href="https://github.com/MCP-UI-Org/mcp-ui/issues">GitHub Issues</a></li><li>Join the discussion in the <code>#ui-wg</code> channel in the <a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/community/communication#discord">MCP Contributors Discord</a></li><li>Test prototype implementations and share your experience</li></ul><h2 id="acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</h2><p>This proposal wouldn’t exist without the work of the maintainers at MCP-UI, OpenAI, and Anthropic.</p><p><strong>Ido Salomon</strong> and <strong>Liad Yosef</strong>, through MCP-UI and moderation of <code>#ui-wg</code>, incubated and championed many of the patterns that MCP Apps now standardizes, and together with contributors demonstrated that UI resources can be a natural part of MCP.</p><p><strong>Sean Strong</strong>, <strong>Olivier Chafik</strong>, <strong>Anton Pidkuiko</strong>, and <strong>Jerome Swannack</strong> from Anthropic helped steer the initiative and drive the collaboration.</p><p><strong>Nick Cooper</strong>, <strong>Alexei Christakis</strong>, and <strong>Bryan Ashley</strong> from OpenAI have provided valuable direction from their experience building the Apps SDK.</p><p>Special thanks to the <strong>UI Community Working Group</strong> members and everyone who contributed to the discussions that shaped this proposal.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>