<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 10:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Physical Intelligence's first generalist robotic model (249 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.physicalintelligence.company/blog/pi0?blog</link>
            <guid>42011770</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 21:34:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/blog/pi0?blog">https://www.physicalintelligence.company/blog/pi0?blog</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42011770">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>Published</p><p>October 31, 2024</p><p>Email</p><p><span>research@physicalintelligence.company</span><span>Kevin Black, Noah Brown, Danny Driess, Michael Equi, Adnan Esmail, Chelsea Finn, Nick Fusai, Lachy Groom, Karol Hausman, Brian Ichter, Szymon Jakubczak, Tim Jones, Kay Ke, Sergey Levine, Adrian Li-Bell, Mohith Mothukuri, Suraj Nair, Karl Pertsch, Lucy Shi, James Tanner, Quan Vuong, Anna Walling, Haohuan Wang, Ury Zhilinsky</span></p><p>Paper</p></div>
<video autoplay="" controls="" loop="" muted="" playsinline="" poster="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/images/p0-hero-video-poster.jpg"><source src="https://dnrjl01ydafck.cloudfront.net/v2/upload/PhysicalIntelligence_2min_v2_out.mp4" type="video/mp4"></video>
<div><p>We are living through an AI revolution: the past decade witnessed practically useful AI assistants, AI systems that can generate photorealistic images and videos, and even models that can predict the structure of proteins. But in spite of all these advances, human intelligence dramatically outpaces AI when it comes to the physical world. To paraphrase <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moravec%27s_paradox">Moravec’s paradox</a>, winning a game of chess or discovering a new drug represent “easy” problems for AI to solve, but folding a shirt or cleaning up a table requires solving some of the most difficult engineering problems ever conceived. To build AI systems that have the kind of physically situated versatility that people possess, we need a new approach — we need to make AI systems embodied so that they can acquire physical intelligence.</p><p>Over the past eight months, we’ve developed a general-purpose robot foundation model that we call <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> (pi-zero). We believe this is a first step toward our long-term goal of developing artificial physical intelligence, so that users can simply ask robots to perform any task they want, just like they can ask large language models (LLMs) and chatbot assistants. Like LLMs, our model is trained on broad and diverse data and can follow various text instructions. Unlike LLMs, it spans images, text, and actions and acquires physical intelligence by training on embodied experience from robots, learning to directly output low-level motor commands via a novel architecture. It can control a variety of different robots, and can either be prompted to carry out the desired task, or fine-tuned to specialize it to challenging application scenarios. An extended article on our work can be found <a href="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/download/pi0.pdf">here</a>.</p></div>

<div><h3>The promise of generalist robot policies</h3><p>Today’s robots are narrow specialists. Industrial robots are programmed for repetitive motions in choreographed settings, repeatedly making the same weld in the same spot on an assembly line or dropping the same item into the same box. Even such simple behaviors require extensive manual engineering, and more complex behaviors in messy real-world environments such as homes are simply infeasible. AI could change that, allowing robots to <em>learn</em> and follow user instructions, so that programming a new behavior is as simple as telling the robot what you want done, and the robot can itself figure out how to adapt its behavior to its environment. But this requires data. Language models and other foundation models mine data from the web, utilizing a significant fraction of all available documents. There is no such treasure trove of robot data, so to enable a robot to learn a new skill, large amounts of data need to be collected <em>with that particular robot and for that particular application</em>.</p><p>If we could train a single <em>generalist</em> robot policy that can perform a wide range of different skills and control a wide range of different robots, we would overcome this challenge: such a model would need only a little bit of data from each robot and each application. Just as a person can learn a new skill quickly by drawing on a lifetime’s worth of experience, such a generalist robot policy could be specialized to new tasks with only modest amounts of data. This would not be the first time that a generalist model beat a specialist at the specialist’s own task: language models have superseded more specialized language processing systems precisely because they can better solve those downstream specialist tasks by drawing on their diverse and general purpose pretraining. In the same way that LLMs provide a <em>foundation model</em> for language, these generalist robot policies will provide a robot foundation model for physical intelligence.</p><p>To get there, we will need to solve major technical challenges. Our first step is <span>π<sub>0</sub></span>, a prototype model that combines large-scale multi-task and multi-robot data collection with a new network architecture to enable the most capable and dexterous generalist robot policy to date. While we believe this is only a small early step toward developing truly general-purpose robot models, we think it represents an exciting step that provides a glimpse of what is to come.</p><h3>A cross-embodiment training mixture</h3></div>
<div><p><span>π<sub>0</sub></span> uses Internet-scale vision-language pre-pretraining, open-source robot
manipulation datasets, and our own datasets consisting of dexterous tasks from
8 distinct robots. The model can then perform a wide variety of tasks, via
either zero-shot prompting or fine-tuning.</p></div>
<p>Our first prototype generalist robot policy is trained on the largest robot
interaction dataset to date. The full training mixture includes both
open-source data and a large and diverse dataset of dexterous tasks that we
collected across 8 distinct robots.</p>
<div><p>Our dataset contains diverse tasks, with each task exhibiting a wide variety of motion primitives, many different objects, and various scenes.</p></div>
<div><p>The tasks in this dataset exercise different dimensions of robot dexterity while covering the range of real tasks that these robots might be asked to perform, from bussing dishes to packing items into envelopes, folding clothing, routing cables, assembling boxes, plugging in power plugs, packing food into to-go boxes, and picking up and throwing out trash. Our goal in selecting these tasks is not to solve any particular application, but to start to provide our model with a general understanding of physical interactions — an initial foundation for physical intelligence.</p><h3>Inheriting Internet-scale semantic understanding</h3><p>Beyond training on many different robots, <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> inherits semantic knowledge and visual understanding from Internet-scale pretraining by starting from a pre-trained vision-language model (VLM). VLMs are trained to model text and images on the web — widely used VLMs include GPT-4V and Gemini. We use a smaller 3 billion parameter VLM as a starting point, and adapt it for real-time dexterous robot control.</p><p>VLMs effectively transfer semantic knowledge from the web, but they are trained to output only discrete language tokens. Dexterous robot manipulation requires <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> to output motor commands at a high frequency, up to 50 times per second. To provide this level of dexterity, we developed a novel method to augment pre-trained VLMs with continuous action outputs via flow matching, a variant of diffusion models. Starting from diverse robot data and a VLM pre-trained on Internet-scale data, we train our vision-language-action flow matching model, which we can then post-train on high-quality robot data to solve a range of downstream tasks.</p></div>
<div><p><img alt="Our vision-language-action model uses a novel flow matching formulation, which augments a vision-language model pre-trained on Internet-scale data with continuous outputs. This enables high-frequency dexterous control, making it particularly well-suited for fine-tuning for complex robot manipulation tasks, such as folding laundry or assembling boxes." loading="lazy" width="569" height="414" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/images/blog-03.jpg"></p><p>Our vision-language-action model uses a novel flow matching formulation, which augments a vision-language model pre-trained on Internet-scale data with continuous outputs. This enables high-frequency dexterous control, making it particularly well-suited for fine-tuning for complex robot manipulation tasks, such as folding laundry or assembling boxes.</p></div>
<div><h3>Post-training for dexterous manipulation</h3><p>More complex and dexterous tasks may require the model to be fine-tuned to specialize it to downstream challenges. Fine-tuning the model with high-quality data for a challenging task, such as folding laundry, is analogous to the post-training process employed by LLM designers. Pre-training teaches the model about the physical world, while fine-tuning forces it to perform a particular task <em>well</em>. Let’s take a look at some of these tasks.</p></div>
<div><p>After post-training, the robot can unload the dryer, bring the clothes over to the table, and fold the clothes into a stack. The video is uncut, from a single policy operating fully autonomously.</p></div>
<p><strong>Laundry</strong>. We fine-tuned <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> to fold laundry, using either a mobile robot
or a fixed pair of arms. The goal is to get the clothing into a neat stack.
This task is exceptionally difficult for robots (...and some humans): while a
single t-shirt laid flat on the table can sometimes be folded just by repeating
a pre-scripted set of motions, a pile of tangled laundry can be crumpled in
many different ways, so it is not enough to simply move the arms through the
same motion. To our knowledge, no prior robot system has been demonstrated to
perform this task at this level of complexity.</p>

<p>Notably, by training on diverse data, we find that the robot is able to recover
when someone tries to intervene in a variety of different ways.</p>

<p><strong>Table bussing.</strong> We also fine-tuned the model to bus a table. This requires
the robot to pick up dishes and trash on the table, putting any dishes,
cutlery, or cups into a bussing bin, and putting trash into the trash bin. This
task requires the robot to handle a dizzying variety of items. One of the
exciting consequences of training <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> on large and diverse datasets was the
range of emergent strategies that the robot employed: instead of simply
grasping each item in turn, the model could stack multiple dishes to put them
into the bin together, or shake off trash from a plate into the garbage before
placing the plate into the bussing bin.</p>

<p><strong>Assembling a box.</strong> Here, the robot has to take a flattened cardboard box and
build it, folding the sides and then tucking in the flaps. This is very
difficult, because each fold and tuck might fail in unexpected ways, so the
robot needs to watch its progress and adjust as it goes. It also needs to brace
the box with both arms, even using the table, so that the partially folded box
doesn’t come apart.</p>

<div><h3>Evaluating and comparing <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> to prior models</h3><p>We compared <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> to other robot foundation models that have been proposed in the academic literature on our tasks: <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://openvla.github.io/">OpenVLA</a>, a 7B parameter VLA model that uses discretized actions, and <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://octo-models.github.io/">Octo</a>, a 93M parameter model that uses diffusion outputs. These tasks are very difficult compared to those that are typically used in academic experiments — for example, the tasks in the <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://openvla.github.io/">OpenVLA evaluation</a> typically consist of single stage behaviors (e.g., “put eggplant into pot”), whereas our simplest bussing task consisting of sorting multiple objects into either a garbage bin or a bussing bin, and our more complex tasks might require multiple stages, manipulation of deformable objects, and the ability to deploy one of many possible strategies given the current configuration of the environment. These tasks are evaluated according to a scoring rubric that assigns a score of 1.0 for a fully successful completion, with “partial credit” for partially correct execution (e.g., bussing half the objects leads to a score of 0.5). The average scores across 5 zero-shot evaluation tasks are shown below, comparing the full <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> pre-trained model, <span>π<sub>0</sub></span>-small, which is a 470M parameter model that does not use VLM pre-training, <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://openvla.github.io/">OpenVLA</a>, and <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://octo-models.github.io/">Octo</a>. Although OpenVLA and Octo can attain non-zero performance on the easiest of these tasks (“Bussing Easy”), <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> is by far the best-performing model across all of the tasks. The small version, <span>π<sub>0</sub></span>-small, attains the second best performance, but there is more than a 2x improvement in performance from using our full-size architecture with VLM pre-training.</p></div>
<div><div><p><img alt="Zero-shot Performance Comparison Across Tasks" loading="lazy" width="1390" height="700" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/_next/image?url=%2Fimages%2Fp0-zero-shot-comparison.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.physicalintelligence.company/_next/image?url=%2Fimages%2Fp0-zero-shot-comparison.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/_next/image?url=%2Fimages%2Fp0-zero-shot-comparison.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p></div><p>Average scores for <span>π<sub>0</sub></span>, <span>π<sub>0</sub></span>-small, OpenVLA, and Octo for zero-shot evaluation on 5 test tasks. Across all of the tasks, <span>π<sub>0</sub></span> consistently attains good performance, and outperforms both the small variant and the prior models.</p></div>
<div><p>We include detailed videos from our rigorous empirical evaluation below, with examples of successful and failed episodes for both our zero-shot experiments and the fine-tuning evaluation. Complete results from all experiments can be found in the <a href="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/download/pi0.pdf">full article</a>.</p><h3>Where do we go from here?</h3><p>Our mission at Physical Intelligence is to develop foundation models that can control any robot to perform any task. Our experiments so far show that such models can control a variety of robots and perform tasks that no prior robot learning system has done successfully, such as folding laundry from a hamper or assembling a cardboard box. But generalist robot policies are still in their infancy, and we have a long way to go. The frontiers of robot foundation model research include long-horizon reasoning and planning, autonomous self-improvement, robustness, and safety. We expect that the coming year will see major advances along all of these directions, but the initial results paint a promising picture for the future of robot foundation models: highly capable generalist policies that inherit semantic understanding from Internet-scale pretraining, incorporate data from many different tasks and robot platforms, and enable unprecedented dexterity and physical capability.</p><p>We also think that succeeding at this will require not only new technologies and more data, but a collective effort involving the entire robotics community. We already have collaborations underway with a number of companies and robotics labs, both to refine hardware designs for teleoperation and autonomy, and incorporate data from our partners into our pre-trained models so that we can provide access to models adapted to their specific platforms.</p><p>If you are interested in collaborating, please <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="mailto:collaborate@physicalintelligence.company">reach out</a>. We are particularly excited to work with companies scaling up data collection with robots deployed for real-world applications, who are looking to collaborate on autonomy.</p><p>We are also hiring! If you'd be interested in <a href="https://www.physicalintelligence.company/join-us">joining us</a> please get in touch.</p><p>For researchers interested in our work, collaborations, or other queries, please write to <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="mailto:research@physicalintelligence.company">research@physicalintelligence.company</a>.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An Update on Apple M1/M2 GPU Drivers (432 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/995383/34dc5950cab5e739/</link>
            <guid>42011239</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 20:36:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/995383/34dc5950cab5e739/">https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/995383/34dc5950cab5e739/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42011239">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<blockquote>
<div>
<h3>Welcome to LWN.net</h3>
<p>
The following subscription-only content has been made available to you 
by an LWN subscriber.  Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the 
best news from the Linux and free software communities.  If you enjoy this 
article, please consider <a href="https://lwn.net/subscribe/">subscribing to LWN</a>.  Thank you
for visiting LWN.net!
</p></div>
</blockquote>

<p>
The kernel graphics driver for the Apple M1 and M2 GPUs is, rather
famously, written in Rust, but it has achieved conformance with
various graphics standards, which is also noteworthy.  At the <a href="https://indico.freedesktop.org/event/6/">X.Org Developers Conference
(XDC)&nbsp;2024</a>, Alyssa Rosenzweig gave an update on the status of the
driver, along with some news about the kinds of games it can support (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TtLP5sAXYKo">YouTube video</a>, <a href="https://indico.freedesktop.org/event/6/contributions/284/attachments/230/310/slides.pdf">slides</a>).
There has been lots of progress since her talk at XDC last year (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O36VFNdQHsE">YouTube video</a>),
with, of course, still more to come.
</p>

<p>
It is something of an XDC tradition, since she began it in Montreal in&nbsp;2019
(<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PqAAWzchHvk">YouTube video</a>),
for Rosenzweig to give her presentations dressed like a witch.
This year's edition was no exception, though this time she started her talk in
French, which resulted in some nervous chuckles from attendees. After a few
sentences, she switched to English, "<q>I'm just kidding</q>", and
continued with her talk.
</p>

<h4>Updates and tessellation</h4>

<p>
Last year at XDC, she and Asahi Lina reported that the driver had reached
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenGL_ES">OpenGL ES</a>&nbsp;3.1
conformance.  They also talked about <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opengl/wiki/Geometry_Shader">geometry
shaders</a>, because "<q>that was the next step</q>".  Since then, the
driver has become <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenGL">OpenGL</a>&nbsp;4.6
conformant. That meant she was going to turn to talking about <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opengl/wiki/tessellation">tessellation</a>
shaders, "<q>as I threatened to do at the end of last year's talk</q>".
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tessellation_(computer_graphics)">Tessellation</a>,
which is a technique that "<q>allows detail to be dynamically added and
subtracted</q>" from a scene, is required for OpenGL&nbsp;4.0, and there is
a hardware tessellator on the Apple GPU—but, "<q>we can't use it</q>".  The
hardware is too limited to implement any of the standards; "<q>it is
missing features that are hard required for OpenGL, <a href="https://www.vulkan.org/">Vulkan</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Direct3D">Direct3D</a></q>".  That
makes it "<q>pretty much useless to anybody who is not implementing <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metal_(API)">Metal</a></q>".  Apple
supports OpenGL&nbsp;4.1, though it is not conformant, but if you use any
of the features that the hardware does not support, it simply falls back to
software; "<q>we are not going to do that</q>".
</p>

<p><a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/996249/">
<img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/2024/xdc-rosenzweig-sm.png" alt="[Alyssa Rosenzweig]" title="Alyssa Rosenzweig" width="225" height="280">
</a></p><p>
As far as Rosenzweig is aware, the hardware lacks <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/spec/latest/chapters/tessellation.html#tessellation-point-mode">point mode</a>, where points
are used instead of the usual triangles; it also lacks <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/spec/latest/chapters/tessellation.html#tessellation-isoline-tessellation">isoline</a>
support, but those two things can be emulated. The real problem comes
with <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opengl/wiki/Transform_Feedback">transform
feedback</a> and geometry shaders, neither of which is supported by the
hardware, but the driver emulates them with <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opengl/wiki/Compute_Shader">compute
shaders</a>.  However, the hardware tessellator cannot be used at all when
those are being emulated because minute differences in the tessellation algorithms used
by the hardware and the emulation would result in <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/spec/latest/appendices/invariance.html">invariance</a>
failures.  She is not sure whether that is a problem in practice or not,
"<q>but the spec says not to do it</q>", so she is hoping not to have to go
that route.
</p>

<p>
Instead, "<q>we use software</q>".  In particular, Microsoft released a
reference tessellator a decade or more ago, which was meant to show
hardware vendors what they were supposed to implement when tessellation was
first introduced.  It is "<q>a giant pile of 2000 lines of C++</q>" that
she does not understand, despite trying multiple times; "<q>it is
inscrutable</q>". The code will tessellate a single <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opengl/wiki/tessellation#Patches">patch</a>, which gave the
driver developers an idea: "<q>if we can run that code, we can get the
tessellation outputs and then we can just draw the triangles or the lines
with this <a href="https://vulkan-tutorial.com/Vertex_buffers/Index_buffer">index buffer</a></q>".
</p>

<p>
There are some problems with that approach, however, starting with the fact
that the developers are writing a GPU driver; "<q>famously, GPUs do not like running
2000 lines of C++</q>".  But, she announced, "<q>we have conformant <a href="https://www.khronos.org/opencl/">OpenCL</a>&nbsp;3.0 support</q>"
thanks to Karol Herbst, though it has not yet been released.  OpenCL C is
"<q>pretty much the same as regular CPU C</q>", though it has a few
limitations and some extensions for GPUs.  So the idea would be to turn the
C++ tessellation code into OpenCL C code; "<q>we don't have to understand
any of it, we just need to not break anything when we do the port</q>".
</p>

<p>
That works, but "<q><tt>tessellator.cl</tt> is the most unhinged file of my
career</q>"; doing things that way was also the most unhinged thing she has done in her career
"<q>and I'm standing up here in a witch hat for the fifth year in a
row</q>". The character debuted in the exact same room in&nbsp;2019 when she
was 17 years old, she recalled.
</p>

<p>
The CPU tessellator only operates on a single patch at a time, but a scene
might have 10,000 patches—doing them all serially will be a real problem.
GPUs are massively parallel, though, so having multiple threads each doing
tessellation is "<q>pretty easy to arrange</q>".  There is a problem with
memory allocation; the CPU tessellator just allocates for each operation
sequentially, but that will not work for parallel processing.  Instead, the
driver uses the GPU atomic instructions to manage the allocation of output buffers.
</p>

<p>
In order to draw the output of the tessellators, though, there is a need to
use draw instructions with packed data structures as specified by the GPU.
That is normally done from the C driver code using functions that are <a href="https://gitlab.freedesktop.org/mesa/mesa/-/merge_requests/25498">generated
by the GenXML tool</a>.  Since the tessellators are simply C code,
"<q>thanks to OpenCL</q>", the generated functions can be included into the
code that runs on the GPU.  Rosenzweig went into more detail, which fills
in the holes (and likely inaccuracies) of the above description; those
interested in the details should look at the presentation video and her
slides.
</p>

<p>
"<q>Does it work?  Yes, it does.</q>"
She showed an image of terrain tessellation from a Vulkan demo.  It was run
on an M2 Mac with "<q>entirely OpenCL-based tessellation</q>". There is also
the question of "<q>how is the performance of this abomination?</q>"  The
answer is that it is "<q>okay</q>".  On the system, software-only terrain tessellation runs at
less than one frame-per-second (fps), which "<q>is not very fun for playing
games</q>"; for OpenCL, it runs at 265fps, which is "<q>pretty good</q>"
and is unlikely to be the bottleneck for real games.  The hardware
can do
820fps; "<q>I did wire up the hardware tessellator just to get a number for
this talk.</q>"   There is still room for improvement on the driver's
numbers, she said.
</p>

<h4>Vulkan and gaming</h4>

<p>
She also announced Vulkan&nbsp;1.3 conformance for the Honeykrisp M1/M2 GPU
driver. It <a href="https://rosenzweig.io/blog/vk13-on-the-m1-in-1-month.html">started</a>
by copying the <a href="https://docs.mesa3d.org/drivers/nvk.html">NVK
Vulkan driver for NVIDIA GPUs</a>, "<q>smashed against the [Open]GL&nbsp;4.6
[driver]</q>", which started passing the conformance test suite
"<q>in about a month</q>".  That was six months ago and, since then, she
has added geometry and tessellation shaders, transform feedback, and <a href="https://docs.vulkan.org/spec/latest/chapters/shaders.html#shaders-objects">shader
objects</a>.  The driver now supports every feature needed for multiple
DirectX versions.
</p>

<p>
There are a lot of problems "<q>if we want to run triple-A (AAA) games on
this system</q>", however.  A target game runs on DirectX and Windows on an x86 CPU with
4KB pages, but "<q>our target hardware is running literally none of those
things</q>". What is needed is to somehow translate DirectX to Vulkan,
Windows to Linux, x86 to Arm64, and 4KB pages to 16KB pages.  The first two
have a well-known solution in the form of the <a href="https://github.com/doitsujin/dxvk/wiki">DXVK driver</a> and <a href="https://www.winehq.org/">Wine</a>, which are "<q>generally packaged
into <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Proton_(software)">Proton</a>
for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steam_(service)">Steam</a> gaming</q>".
Going from x86 to Arm64 also has off-the-shelf solutions: <a href="https://fex-emu.com/">FEX-Emu</a> or <a href="https://box86.org/">Box64</a>.  She has a bias toward FEX-Emu;
"<q>when I am not committing <a href="https://www.mesa3d.org/">Mesa</a>
crimes, I am committing FEX-Emulation crimes</q>".  The big problem,
though, is the page-size difference.
</p>

<p>
FEX-Emu requires 4KB pages; Box64 has a "<q>hack to use 16KB pages, but it
doesn't work for Wine, so it doesn't help us here</q>".  MacOS can use 4KB
pages for the x86 emulation, but "<q>this requires very invasive kernel
support</q>";  <a href="https://asahilinux.org/">Asahi Linux</a> already has around 1000 patches that are making
their way toward the mainline kernel, but "<q>every one of those thousand
is a challenge</q>". Making changes like "<q>rewriting the Linux memory
manager</q>" is not a reasonable path.
</p>

<p>
It turns out that, even though Linux does not support heterogeneous page
sizes between different processes, it does support them between different
kernels; "<q>what I mean by that is virtualization</q>".  A KVM guest
kernel can have a different page size than the host kernel.  So, "<q>this
entire mess</q>", consisting of FEX-Emu, Wine, DXVK, Honeykrisp, Steam, and
the game, "<q>we are going to throw that into a virtual machine, which is
running a 4KB guest kernel</q>".
</p>

<p>
There is some overhead, of course, but it is hardware virtualization, so
that should have low CPU overhead.  The problem lies with the peripherals,
she said.  So, instead of having Honeykrisp in the host kernel, it runs in
the guest using <a href="https://indico.freedesktop.org/event/2/contributions/53/attachments/76/121/XDC2022_%20virtgpu%20drm%20native%20context.pdf">virtgpu</a>
native contexts;  all of the work to create the final GPU command buffer is done
in the guest and handed to the host, rather than making all of the Vulkan
calls individually traverse the virtual-machine boundary.  The <a href="https://docs.mesa3d.org/drivers/virgl.html">VirGL</a> renderer on the
host then hands that to the GPU, which "<q>is not 100% native speed, but
definitely well above 90%</q>", Rosenzweig said.
</p>

<p>
The good news is that the overheads for the CPU and GPU do not stack, since
the two run in parallel. "<q>So all the crap overhead we have in the CPU is
actually crap that is running in parallel to the crap overhead on the GPU,
so we only pay the cost once.</q>"
</p>

<p>
"<q>'Does it work?' is the question you all want to know.</q>"  It does,
she said, it runs
games like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portal_(video_game)">Portal</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Portal_2">Portal&nbsp;2</a>. She also listed a number of
others: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Castle_Crashers">Castle Crashers</a>,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Witcher_3:_Wild_Hunt">The
Witcher&nbsp;3</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fallout_4">Fallout&nbsp;4</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Control_(video_game)">Control</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ghostrunner">Ghostrunner</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyberpunk_2077">Cyberpunk&nbsp;2077</a>.
</p>

<p>
All of the different pieces that she mentioned were <a href="https://rosenzweig.io/blog/aaa-gaming-on-m1.html">made available</a>
on October&nbsp;10, the day of the talk.  For those running the <a href="https://asahilinux.org/fedora/">Fedora Asahi Remix</a> distribution,
she suggested immediately updating to pick up the pieces that
she had described.  Before taking questions, she launched Steam, which took
some time to come up, in part because of the virtual machine and the x86
emulation.  Once it came up, she launched Control, which ran at 45fps on an
M1 MAX system.
</p>

<p>
There was a question about resources from someone who has a Mac with 8GB of
RAM.  Rosenzweig said that the high-end gaming titles are only likely to
work on systems with 16GB or more.  She noted that she was playing Castle
Crashers on an 8GB system during the conference, so some games will play;
Portal will also work on that system.  She hopes that the resources
required will drop over time.
</p>

<p>
Another question was about <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ray_tracing_(graphics)">ray-tracing</a>
support, since Control can use that <a href="https://www.khronos.org/blog/ray-tracing-in-vulkan">feature</a>.
Rosenzweig suggested that patches were welcome but that she did not see
that as a high priority ("<q>frankly, I think ray tracing is a bit of a
gimmick feature</q>").  Apple hardware only supports it with the M3 and
the current driver is for M1 and M2 GPUs, though she plans to start working
on M3 before long.  The session concluded soon after that, though
Rosenzweig played Control, admittedly poorly, as time ran down.
</p>

<p>
[ I would like to thank LWN's travel sponsor, the Linux Foundation, for
travel assistance to Montreal for XDC. ]
</p><br clear="all"><table>
           <tbody><tr><th colspan="2">Index entries for this article</th></tr>
           <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/">Conference</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/#X.Org_Developers_Conference-2024">X.Org Developers Conference/2024</a></td></tr>
            </tbody></table><br clear="all">

               <br clear="all">
               <hr>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Wait Until 8th (380 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.waituntil8th.org</link>
            <guid>42011193</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 20:32:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.waituntil8th.org">https://www.waituntil8th.org</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42011193">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-block-type="2" data-border-radii="{&quot;topLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;topRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomLeft&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0},&quot;bottomRight&quot;:{&quot;unit&quot;:&quot;px&quot;,&quot;value&quot;:0.0}}" id="block-20d2d7d07ef691626788">
  <h2>We empower parents to say yes to waiting for the smartphone.</h2><p>The Wait Until 8th pledge empowers parents to rally together to delay giving children a smartphone until at least the end of 8th grade. Let’s protect the elementary and middle school years from the distractions and the dangers of a smartphone. Banding together helps decrease the pressure to have a phone at an early age.&nbsp;Ten years old is the average age children get their first smartphone. You can change this! </p><p>More than 82,000 parents have said yes to waiting on the smartphone for their families. This is making a tremendous difference in communities across the country! </p><p>Smartphones are distracting and potentially dangerous for children yet are widespread in elementary and middle school because of unrealistic social pressure and expectations to have one.</p><p>These devices are quickly changing childhood for children. Playing outdoors, spending time with friends, reading books and hanging out with family is happening a lot less to make room for hours of snap chatting, instagramming, and catching up on YouTube.</p><p>Parents feel powerless in this uphill battle and need community support to help delay the ever-evolving presence of the smartphone in the classroom, social arena and family dinner table. Link arms with other parents to wait until at least the end of eighth grade for a smartphone! </p><p>By signing the online pledge, you promise not to give your child a smartphone until at least the end of 8th grade as long as at least 10 families total from your child’s grade and school pledge. &nbsp;Once 10 families have pledged to delay the smartphone, you will be notified that the pledge is active! You will receive a list of families who are delaying from your child’s grade and emails for the parents. It is helpful to be connected with other families waiting in your child’s grade. Check out our list of schools with <a href="https://www.waituntil8th.org/where-is-the-pledge" target="_blank">active pledges here!</a></p><p>The Wait Until 8th pledge encourages parents to delay the smartphone. If you need to get in touch before the end of 8th grade, we have some great basic phones and smartwatches <a href="https://www.waituntil8th.org/devices" target="_blank">featured here</a>. If you would like your child to have a basic phone or smartwatch to call and text only, you still can sign the pledge! These basic options avoid many of the distractions and dangers of the smartphone.&nbsp;</p><p>Childhood is too short to waste on a smartphone. Take the <a href="https://www.waituntil8th.org/take-the-pledge">pledge</a> today!&nbsp;</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ghost jobs are wreaking havoc on tech workers (184 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sfgate.com/tech/article/ghost-jobs-california-tech-industry-19871249.php</link>
            <guid>42010130</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 18:49:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sfgate.com/tech/article/ghost-jobs-california-tech-industry-19871249.php">https://www.sfgate.com/tech/article/ghost-jobs-california-tech-industry-19871249.php</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42010130">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.sfgate.com/tech/article/ghost-jobs-california-tech-industry-19871249.php: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What sank the Bayesian superyacht in Italy? (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2024/10/31/world/europe/bayesian-yacht-sinking-italy.html</link>
            <guid>42009570</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 18:03:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2024/10/31/world/europe/bayesian-yacht-sinking-italy.html">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2024/10/31/world/europe/bayesian-yacht-sinking-italy.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42009570">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="00italy-yacht"><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->It all happened so fast.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Karsten Borner was planted on the halfdeck of his sailboat in the slanting rain. A grizzled mariner who had survived many storms, he was anchored in the same cove as Mr. Lynch’s yacht, at the same time, as the squall blew in during the early hours of Aug. 19.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Luckily, he was already awake. As the wind picked up, he and his crew scurried around closing hatches, clearing the decks and firing up the engines to keep his boat steady.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->He couldn’t see much, but in flashes of lightning, he kept catching glimpses of Mr. Lynch’s long, sleek sloop bobbing behind him. It was only a few hundred feet away and its super-tall aluminum mast — one of the tallest ever made — was lit up with bright white lights, swaying in the wind.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Then he lost sight of it. The rain fell like gravel, drawing a curtain around his boat. When he looked up again, he was stunned. The Bayesian was disappearing, at a very odd angle, into the sea.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In the weeks since, Mr. Borner, who has sailed for more than half a century, still can’t believe the yacht sank in front of him. There weren’t any big waves that night, he said. Both boats were close to shore. His own sailboat — a converted tugboat built in East Germany 66 years ago — weathered the same squall just fine. And that other craft was a superyacht of the superrich, gleaming blue, 184 feet long and drawing stares wherever it went.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“It’s a mystery,” Mr. Borner said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="media grid">  <div> <figure aria-label="media grid"><div><figure>    </figure> </div><div><figure>    </figure> </div><div><figure>    </figure> </div><div><figure>    </figure> </div> </figure></div> <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The seven victims of the Bayesian sinking, clockwise from top left: Hannah Lynch, Mike Lynch, Judy Bloomer, Jonathan Bloomer, Christopher Morvillo, Neda Nassiri and Recaldo Thomas.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>   <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->via Agence France-Presse — Getty Images; via Reuters; Patrick McMullan, via Getty Images<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->That mystery has rippled around the globe as several investigations into the tragedy unfold. It has vexed maritime experts and compounded the grief of family and friends of the seven people who perished, including Mr. Lynch and his teenage daughter, Hannah, whose bodies were found trapped below deck.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The investigations turn on three central questions: Why did the Bayesian, which now lies 160 feet at the bottom of the Mediterranean, sink so fast? Did the yacht have any design flaws? Did the captain or crew make any fatal mistakes?<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Bayesian was a one-of-a-kind sailboat, built by Perini Navi, a famous Italian yacht maker. The company says the group of 10 superyachts that the Bayesian belonged to was “the most successful series of large sailing yachts ever conceived.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->But the Bayesian was different. Its original buyer — a Dutch businessman, not the Lynches — insisted on a single, striking mast that would be taller than just about any other mast in the world, according to the Italian yacht maker and three people with detailed knowledge of how this boat was built.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->That decision resulted in major engineering consequences that ultimately left the boat significantly more vulnerable than many comparable superyachts, The Times investigation has found.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->— More than a dozen naval architects, engineers and other experts consulted by The Times found glaring weaknesses in the Bayesian’s design that they said could have contributed to the disaster.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->— Basic design choices, like the two tall doors on the side of the deck, increased the Bayesian’s chances of taking on dangerous amounts of water if high winds pushed the boat over toward its side, several naval architects said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->— Witness and survivor accounts revealed how this deadly sequence unfolded in real time: The yacht fell completely on its side and sank within minutes.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="graphic">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Sources: Perini Navi (technical drawing of the yacht) and New York Times reporting.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p></div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Seemingly small details on any boat — like how close air vents are to the waterline, or where a ship’s ballast is placed in the hull — might not sound decisive on their own. But when taken together, experts said, they appear to have compromised this vessel.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Such built-in vulnerabilities may not have been solely responsible for the yacht’s sinking, of course. The storm’s unexpected ferocity definitely played a part in the calamitous stew of events. Italian investigators are also looking hard at the actions of the Bayesian’s captain and crew.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Giovanni Costantino, the chief executive of the Italian Sea Group, the company that owns Perini Navi, said that when operated properly, the Bayesian was “unsinkable.” He maintains that the yacht was carefully engineered to survive bad storms, and he has put the blame for the tragedy squarely on the crew, accusing them of making a chain of fatal errors.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“I know, all the crew knows, that they did not do what they should have done,” he said. (Crew members have not revealed much, saying they are under a “gag order.”)<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Costantino said the design was not at fault and that the towering mast, which stood 237 feet tall, had not created “any kind of problem.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“The ship was an unsinkable ship,” he said. “I say it, I repeat it.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The world of superyachts is incredibly opaque, the exclusive realm of some of the richest people on the planet, and exactly how these multimillion dollar boats are designed, approved and owned remain closely guarded secrets.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Making sure a superyacht is fit for the seas is a job left to a network of private companies and public agencies, and the Bayesian’s design was approved by the American Bureau of Shipping and the British Maritime and Coastguard Agency.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->All the attention this tragedy has received could result in a closer look at yachting regulations. Several naval engineers in different countries who have gained access to the Bayesian’s documents say that as yachts have become more elaborate and subject to owners’ whims, others may be in danger as well.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Bayesian’s technical documents show just how vulnerable it was. Even without major errors by the crew, the ship could have sunk in a storm that other boats survived, engineers say.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“We can look at it in hindsight and say they were in the wrong place at the wrong time. No, that’s not true,” said Tad Roberts, a Canadian naval architect who has nearly 40 years of experience designing boats, including superyachts.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“This boat had definite shortcomings that kind of uniquely made it vulnerable to what happened.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Victory Voyages<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A cruise on the Bayesian was a voyage into luxury. The days were typically warm, sunny and calm, and finished off with plates of fresh langoustine and sumptuous chocolate. Hours would pass lounging on sun chairs, swimming in the sea or maybe taking out a kayak while the Bayesian crew, in branded polo shirts, watched vigilantly from the deck.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“It felt like a beautiful hotel that was floating on water,” remembers Abbie VanSickle, a New York Times reporter who was invited aboard in July because her husband, Jonathan Baum, was part of Mr. Lynch’s legal defense team.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Lynch had been acquitted in June in a criminal case in which he was accused of fraudulently inflating the value of his software company when he sold it to Hewlett-Packard for $11 billion. He could have been sent to prison for years. To celebrate his win — and his freedom — he asked friends and lawyers to cruise the Mediterranean with him.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Lynch seemed proud that his boat had one of the world’s tallest masts — a little booklet in her cabin even said as much, Ms. VanSickle remembered. Whenever they chugged into a harbor, she said, “people would take photos of it constantly because it was so crazy-looking in comparison to other boats.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Most of the time, though, the Bayesian operated like a motorboat, powered by two enormous diesel engines. During her five-day voyage, Ms. VanSickle said they sailed only once, for just a few hours. But when they did, the boat moved through the water so smoothly, she said, it felt like they were “gliding.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="image">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A promotional photo from Perini Navi of the Bayesian, which Mr. Lynch named after an 18th-century theory on probability.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>   <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->EPA, via Shutterstock<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A few weeks after Ms. VanSickle got off and returned to her life as a reporter in Washington, Mr. Lynch welcomed aboard his next batch of guests. This was the second celebratory voyage, beginning in mid-August, and Mr. Lynch had planned to get back to London, where he lived, around Aug. 20.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Among the 12 passengers were Mr. Lynch; his wife, Angela Bacares; their 18-year-old daughter, Hannah, who was soon off to Oxford; one of his lead lawyers, <a href="https://www.cliffordchance.com/people_and_places/people/partners/us/chris_morvillo.html">Chris Morvillo</a>, and his wife, Neda Nassiri, who designed handcrafted jewelry; Jonathan Bloomer, an international banker and trusted adviser, and his wife, Judy, a psychotherapist celebrated for her charity work.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Lynch also invited some younger colleagues, including a couple who brought a baby on board. The crew was led by James Cutfield, an experienced New Zealand sailor, backed up by a first mate, a ship engineer, several deckhands and hostesses, totaling 10 in all.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Lynch was on the rebound, fired up about the possibility of starting a nonprofit to help exonerate people wrongly accused of crimes, said Sir David Davis, a friend and prominent conservative British politician.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Lynch sent Sir David a text message offering the choice of lunch or dinner in London on Aug. 22, when he was back.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->An Unanticipated Storm<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Mediterranean Sea was flat on Aug. 18. But bad weather was moving south, from Naples toward Sicily. The Italian Air Force’s Meteomar forecast warned of scattered thunderstorms, gusts of wind and a rough sea. Several yacht captains said the weather warning was far from specific or extraordinary.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Borner, the captain who for decades has been running cruises and diving excursions on his old sailboat, the <a href="https://sir-robert.com/en/">Sir Robert Baden Powell</a>, was finishing up his own trip, picking his way west along the Sicilian coast.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The wind was blowing from the northwest and Mr. Borner figured that the curvature of Sicily’s rugged coastline at Porticello, a small fishing village built around a cove, would shelter him. He arrived in the cove that afternoon, went ashore with his guests and grabbed some pizza.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“It was a nice evening,” he remembered.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->While they were in town, the Bayesian chugged into the same cove. It dropped anchor at 9:35 p.m., about a third of a mile from land. As Mr. Borner went to sleep around 11, the night was clear. The lights of the Bayesian’s mast glowed behind him.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="image">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Lights illuminating the mast of the Bayseian on Aug. 18.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>   <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Baia Santa Nicolicchia/Fabio La Bianca, via Reuters<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->At midnight on Aug. 19, the Italian Coast Guard put out a warning for a northwesterly Gale Force 8, a serious storm in which winds could reach 46 miles per hour. But the gale was predicted to hit hundreds of miles from Sicily.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Around 3 a.m., Mr. Borner woke up to help some of his passengers catch an early flight from Palermo, Sicily’s biggest city. But as the winds picked up rapidly, whipping the cove into a frothy chop, he scratched his plan to go ashore.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->He and his crew shut the portholes and skylights and started the engine, to keep the bow pointed into the wind and prevent the boat from being hit on its side.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->On the Bayesian, a young deckhand, Matthew Griffiths, later told the authorities that when the wind hit 20 knots, he woke up the captain, according to a person close to the crew (who said that neither of them was allowed to speak publicly). The captain then gave the order to wake up others, the person said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->At 3:51 a.m., the Bayesian started to drift — first 80 meters one way, then 80 meters another, its data transmitter shows. Maritime experts said this meant it was being blown around and probably dragging its anchor. It’s unclear whether the engines had been started.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->At 4:02 a.m., a camera mounted on a boat in Porticello’s cove shows bright blue flashes of lightning. Three minutes later, another at a Porticello cafe captures the wind tearing down deck umbrellas. So much rain hits one of the cameras, it looks as if it’s being blasted with a hose.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure>    </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Borner estimated that the wind gusts reached 60 knots, or nearly 70 miles an hour — just below hurricane strength — and said they had pushed his boat onto its side about 15 degrees, a serious lean but nothing close to capsizing.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Reports immediately after the disaster raised the possibility that the Bayesian had been hit by a tornado-like disturbance called a waterspout, but the authorities don’t think that happened. Still, the wind was doing something dangerous: It was changing direction.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->According to a nearby weather station, it was blowing west-southwest then southwest, then north-northwest. This increased the chances of getting ambushed by a random gust that could slam into the side of a boat, which can tilt even a big vessel.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A third video shows the Bayesian rocking back and forth and beginning to lean. Then the lights on its  giant mast blink out — all but the top one, which was powered by a battery.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->By 4:06 a.m., the rain has turned into a blinding cascade. That same minute, the Bayesian’s location signal cuts out. Mr. Borner’s crew squinted through the nearly impenetrable haze of sea spray and rain and spotted a large object in the water. They first thought it was a reef.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“But I knew there was no reef,” Mr. Borner said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->It was the Bayesian, they now believe, knocked onto its side.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“Two Minutes” to Tragedy<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->At 4:34 a.m., a red emergency flare, bright as a meteor, shot into the sky. The storm had passed, and Mr. Borner and his first mate jumped into a small boat, zooming across the black water.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->First they saw cushions floating. Then a flashing light. Then a life raft built for 12 packed with 15 people, bloodied and soaked to the skin, including a baby.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->One person had a cut on the head, another on his chest. Some had already been bandaged. They were cold, wet and dazed. They were too shocked, Mr. Borner said, to say what happened.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->As he loaded the survivors into his boat and began to head back to the Sir Robert, one woman pleaded with him not to leave.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“Please,” she told him. “Continue searching.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Some people were still missing.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Borner decided to unload the survivors onto the Sir Robert, then send his small boat back. His crew gave them blankets and dry clothes. Some survivors were so shaken they needed to be led below deck by hand.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Nobody said much, Mr. Borner remembered.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->One man told him: “I was the captain of this.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Another said the boat had “sunk in two minutes.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The woman who had begged him to keep searching sat huddled on the deck.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“Are you OK?” Mr. Borner asked her.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“No,” she replied. “I am not OK at all.’’<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="image">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Capt. Karsten Borner, who rescued the survivors of the Bayesian.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>   <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Guglielmo Mangiapane/Reuters<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Borner said he later realized it was Angela Bacares, wife of Mr. Lynch and mother of Hannah Lynch. Neither had made it onto the life raft. (Salamander Davoudi, a spokeswoman for Lynch family, told The Times that Ms. Bacares was not speaking to the media because she was grieving and wanted privacy.)<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A few hours after, a string of ambulances arrived at Palermo’s main hospital. Dr. Domenico Cipolla, the head of pediatric emergency, evaluated the youngest survivor, a 1-year-old girl.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The baby was OK, Dr. Cipolla said, but she had experienced quite an ordeal. She and her mother had been sleeping on a sofa on deck because of the rough sea, Dr. Cipolla said, when the boat suddenly lurched and threw them to the deck.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A moment later the boat turned completely on its side, the baby’s father told the doctor, flipping his hand as he described it. The doctor said the mother told him that she and her baby were hurled into the water and that her baby nearly slipped away. But then she grabbed her and swam to a nearby life raft, which was designed to deploy automatically.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The parents were later identified as Charlotte Golunski, a colleague of Mr. Lynch, and James Emslie. Ms. Golunski did not respond to several messages left for her, and efforts to reach Mr. Emslie were unsuccessful.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="graphic">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Sources: Perini Navi (technical drawing of the yacht) and New York Times reporting.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p></div> </figure><p><h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mistakes by the Crew?<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The biggest question that investigators are focused on is how the Bayesian filled with water so fast.<strong> </strong>To many in the yachting world, it doesn’t make sense.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The boat had been built with several watertight compartments under the deck, to prevent water from spreading from one area to others. And it had been approved as safe by the Maritime and Coastguard Agency, part of Britain’s Department for Transport, and by the American Bureau of Shipping, a private company that reviews boat designs<strong>.</strong><!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->On top of that,<strong> </strong>one Italian official and underwater video footage broadcast on Italian television indicated that there were no holes or other structural damage visible in the hull.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Even so, the Bayesian, like many superyachts, had all kinds of openings in which water could theoretically get in: big air vents for the engines; smaller ones for the kitchen, crew quarters and guest cabins; large glass doors at the back and the sides so that people could walk onto the deck; and various hatches for crew and passenger access.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In interviews with Mr. Costantino, the chief executive of the Italian Sea Group, and his spokeswoman, the company accused the crew of leaving hatches open during the storm, including a doorway-size opening on the left rear of the hull, close to the water line. The spokeswoman claimed that hatch was the only place where so much water could have come gushing in.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The company speculated that the crew did not close a watertight door between this hatch and the engine room. A flooded engine room might explain the sudden blackout that killed the mast lights and then, a few minutes later, the location transmitter.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->But witnesses, an Italian official familiar with the investigation and the underwater video challenged the company’s versions of events. The footage appeared to show the watertight door to the engine room closed, and the Italian official said the divers had not seen any open hatches on the hull.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Borner also said that after rescuing the captain, he asked him if he had shut the hatches. The captain said he had. Mr. Borner shared pictures taken by his guests a few moments before the Bayesian sank that appear to show that hull hatches were closed.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A Compromised Design?<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Bayesian’s origins go back to 2000. That year, Perini hired Ron Holland Design, a premier naval architectural firm, to design a series of 56-meter sailboats, said a person with knowledge of the timeline. As the superrich have become even richer, yachts have grown steadily bigger, and Perini was emerging as one of the world’s best-known builders of superyachts, often defined as motor yachts or sailboats longer than 24 meters, or 79 feet.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Ron Holland firm, based in Ireland at the time, drew up plans for the hull, keel, rudder and, crucially, the placement of the masts — two masts. All other features, like the cabins, decks and vent system, were designed by Perini, according to the person, who did not want to be identified because of the possibility of legal action connected to the sinking.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In 2003, the first yacht in the series hit the water, <a href="https://www.perininavi.it/yacht/2003-burrasca-2/">the Burrasca</a> (which means storm in Italian). Over the next four years, Perini built three more 56-meter superyachts from these blueprints, all with two masts. On <a href="https://www.perininavi.it/yacht/s-y-56m-caoz-14/">Perini’s website</a>, they look nearly identical.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Then came the Bayesian.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Construction on its hull began in 2005 at a shipyard in Tuzla, Turkey, according to the boat’s documents. But the original buyer for this yacht didn’t want the standard two-mast design. Instead, the Italian Sea Group said, he wanted the boat to be built with one large mast for better sailing performance.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->That led to a radically different design, said three people with knowledge of what followed, and a cascade of modifications — some to accommodate the gigantic mast, and some apparently for stylistic or other reasons.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="image">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A promotional photo from Perini Navi showing the Bayesian’s mast and sails.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>   <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->EPA, via Shutterstock<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The most obvious departure from the previous Perini ships was the mast itself. Beyond being exceptionally tall — more than 40 feet higher than the original foremast — it was also very heavy, at least 24 tons of aluminum, possibly more. This alone would have challenged the boat’s stability, because so much weight was high above deck.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Since then, many yacht makers have switched to lighter, carbon-fiber masts.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“Technology moved on,” Mr. Costantino said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Naval engineers pointed out that the heavier a yacht is up high, the more ballast it often needs down low — weight at the bottom of the boat to lower its center of gravity and resist its tendency to lean over.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Small notes on hull diagrams in the Bayesian’s documents show that the Turkish shipyard revised the ballast in July 2006, nearly 10 months after the keel was laid, which is one of the first steps of production.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“Values updated as from information by Yildiz,” the notes say in all caps, naming the shipyard.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->But where this ballast was placed was curious, maritime experts said. Rather than spreading the ballast evenly across the bottom of the boat — which would have guaranteed the best stability — the builders stacked it toward the rear of the ship’s hull.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“When I first saw this, I couldn’t believe it,” said Mr. Roberts, the naval architect. “It made no sense to me.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The ballast seems to have been pushed toward the rear of the boat to offset the single, heavy mast closer toward the front, Mr. Roberts concluded. He said he had never seen the main ballast used in such a design tactic before.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->That was not the only change, experts said. A single mast would have plunged almost directly through the wheelhouse, an interior station where the ship can be controlled, so that was moved, too. A deck lounge was added, along with two tall doors on the sides. None of the other Perini yachts in the 56-meter series have these design elements.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="graphic">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Sources: Perini Navi (technical drawing of the yacht) and New York Times reporting.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p></div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Bayesian sat lower in the water than other yachts in the same Perini series, said Stephen Edwards, the Bayesian’s captain from 2015 to 2020. Naval architects said this by itself would make it easier for water to pour through vents and other openings when the boat leans on its side.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Whenever a boat leans too far and water starts gushing in through open doors or vents, it can set off a dangerous downward spiral that is hard to stop and that can sink a boat in minutes.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Such risks are calculated and laid out in a lengthy, proprietary document — kind of a safety bible — for many vessels certified to ply the seas.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Times has obtained that safety bible, called a stability book, for the Bayesian. Copies of the 88-page book are also sweeping through a global community of experts who are obsessively trying to solve the puzzle of how and why the boat sank. More than a dozen of those experts, including naval architects and engineers, found weaknesses in the Bayesian’s design that they said could have contributed to the disaster.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The stability book obtained by The Times was written before the Lynches bought the boat in 2014, when the yacht was called the Salute and owned by John Groenewoud, a Dutch businessman. In an email, he confirmed signing a contract for “the boat with 1 mast” in 2005, but declined to discuss any safety implications that may have had.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Times obtained the stability book for another 56-meter Perini yacht, with two masts instead of one. A comparison of the boats showed that the Bayesian was significantly less stable.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Specifically, the data shows that the two-masted ship could lean at least 10 degrees farther onto its side before taking on dangerous amounts of water.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The documents also show that the Bayesian could begin taking on some water at angles that appeared to violate the safety threshold set by the British Maritime and Coastguard Agency.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Italian Sea Group responded that the boat was in line with regulations and had been approved. When asked how that happened, an agency spokesman refused to clarify, citing the continuing investigations.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The other boat’s documents also showed that the sister yacht sat a little higher in the water than the Bayesian did, as Mr. Edwards emphasized. And under many circumstances, experts said, the sister ship had a better center of gravity and was more resistant to capsizing, two additional factors that would have made it safer.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“The other boat is, at least on paper, a better boat,” Mr. Roberts said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->To make boats safer, naval architects said they religiously ensured that vent openings are far from the water line. When showed a picture of a 56-meter Perini yacht that, like the Bayesian, had vents built into the hull, Philipp Luke, a Dutch naval architect, started violently shaking his head.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“No, no, no,” he said. “You don’t do that.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In the end, several naval architects said, all these flaws may have come together at the worst time — in a sudden storm.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Two Spanish naval engineers, Guillermo Gefaell and Juan Manuel López, calculated that the sheer size of the Bayesian’s mast and rigging made the yacht a wind catcher, even with the sails down.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Writing for the Association of Naval and Ocean Engineers of Spain, they used a computer model to calculate what would have happened to the Bayesian if a strong gust of roughly 54 knots, around 62 mph, hit its side. Under those conditions, the Spanish engineers estimated, the Bayesian could lean dynamically and take on nearly a ton of water each second through an engine room vent.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In an interview, Mr. Gefaell noted that he, like almost everyone else, did not know everything that happened that night. But if the gusts were as strong as Mr. Borner estimated — 60 knots — the punch would have pushed the boat to an even more severe angle, his calculations showed, very quickly knocking the boat all the way over onto its side, as the witnesses recounted.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->At that point, Mr. Gefaell said, “the boat was certainly lost.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><h2><!-- HTML_TAG_START --><br>A Watery Maze<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h2> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Within hours of the sinking, emergency divers plunged in. Their mission: Find survivors.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Bayesian sat 160 feet below the surface, leaning on its right side on the seabed. The once-gleaming cabins were clogged with chairs, clothes, curtains and the enormous number of seat cushions that Ms. Bacares had brought onboard to make the boat more comfortable. The search was made even more difficult and dangerous, divers said, by the many mirrors installed below deck that now reflected back their lights in a disorienting, watery maze.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->On the first day, divers found the body of the yacht’s chef, Recaldo Thomas, floating near the boat. Over the next three days, they found the bodies of Mr. Lynch and four other passengers in a small cabin near the foot of a narrow staircase leading down from the deck to the passenger’s quarters. Finally, divers discovered the body of the last missing person, Hannah Lynch, trapped behind furniture in a nearby cabin.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->One Italian official said the six passengers might have been trying to climb the main guest staircase when a surge of water poured down the stairs and knocked them back into the cabins. With the boat flipped on its side, water gushing in, and total darkness, it would have been nearly impossible for anyone below deck to escape, experts said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The Italian authorities plan to raise the wreck to inspect it more closely. That could take months. In the meantime, at least two major investigations are unfolding, one by Italian prosecutors and the other by the British Marine Accident Investigation Branch.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><figure aria-label="image">   <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Rescue workers bringing the body of the final Bayesian victim to shore, in Porticello, Italy, on Aug. 23.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>   <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Igor Petyx/EPA, via Shutterstock<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->From the first weeks after the accident, Italian prosecutors said that Mr. Cutfield, the captain, and two of his crew were under investigation.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Cutfield hasn’t said a word publicly and did not respond to messages asking for comment. Several crew members, when approached at a hotel in Sicily in August, said they had all been put under a gag order. When asked who imposed it, they responded: “No comment.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In the yachting world, Mr. Cutfield has some solid references. Turgay Ciner, a Turkish industrial magnate and sailing enthusiast, employed him to run his yacht for 12 years.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“He never made any mistakes,” Mr. Ciner said.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Mr. Ciner, speaking by phone from Istanbul, recounted a bad storm near Capri about 10 years ago that Mr. Cutfield handled. They were sailing on another 56-meter Perini yacht, the Melek, a two-masted boat in the same series as the Bayesian. He said that Mr. Cutfield performed very well and was “one out of a hundred.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Why Mr. Cutfield left in a lifeboat with the other survivors when a half dozen passengers were still missing is a matter Italian prosecutors are looking into.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->But several yacht captains have defended Mr. Cutfield, saying that whatever happened that night, it happened very quickly.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->When a boat sinks fast, said Adam Hauck, an American yacht captain, there’s not much hope for anyone still onboard. The adage of the captain going down with the ship, he said, is antiquated and unrealistic.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“It’s not like a Titanic movie where you’re going through the water and you can just look in the rooms,” Mr. Hauck said. “At some point, you can’t go back for people.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing ChatGPT Search (1160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-search/</link>
            <guid>42008569</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 16:41:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-search/">https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-search/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42008569">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/introducing-chatgpt-search/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Smashing the Limits: Installing Windows XP in DOSBox-X (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/</link>
            <guid>42008499</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 16:32:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/">https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42008499">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p>In my <a href="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-2000-in-dosbox-x/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">previous article</a>
, I described how I managed to install Windows 2000 in DOSBox-X.</p>
<p>Even though this experiment was successful, I was not really happy with the results. While I got Windows 2000 working, I didn’t want to stop there. The final goal for the project was to get Windows XP running instead. However, after multiple attempts I gave up, thinking that Windows XP was impossible to use.</p>
<p>Well - I was wrong. But let’s start at the beginning.</p>

<div>
<p>At the time of writing this article, running Windows XP isn’t officially supported by the DOSBox-X project. Don’t blame the developers for any issues - this is very experimental.</p></div>

<h2 id="previously">Previously…</h2>
<p>Since I wasn’t able to do a clean install of Windows 2000 due to driver and compatibility issues as described in my previous article, I started with the upgrade route right away. Upgrading from Windows 98 to Windows XP is officially supported, so I was pretty confident this would work for me as well.</p>
<p>I created a copy of the hard drive image after each step, so I was able to start the upgrade procedure with a clean installation of Windows 98 (Second Edition).</p>
<p>After mounting the Windows XP ISO image, I was greeted by the Windows XP Setup.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_upgrade_clean_selection.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup: Select between upgrade and clean install" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup: Select between upgrade and clean install</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>Because of the issues I had with the clean installation of Windows 2000, I used the “Upgrade” installation type instead because that’s what worked for Windows 2000 as well.</p>
<p>After typing in the product key, the Setup was about to start the file copy process. In fact, it even started copying the installation files but failed at the very first file.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_98_xp_setup_error.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup failing to copy files during the upgrade" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup failing to copy files during the upgrade</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>“The ISO must be bad!” I said to myself. I obtained this ISO file many years ago, so some silent file corruption was not entirely impossible. To avoid any potential issues caused by bad images, I always create checksum files immediately after obtaining the image. So, I compared the ISO image with the checksums I had - and to my surprise, I got a perfect match. The ISO image itself is absolutely fine since I have used it multiple times before.</p>
<p>To further investigate, I even went ahead and reinstalled Windows 98 from scratch to rule out any possible installation issues, but to my dismay, I encountered the same error message again.</p>
<p>Great. Getting another ISO image or starting with a fresh installation would have been <em>way</em> too easy, right?!</p>
<h2 id="back-to-square-one">Back to square one.</h2>
<p>Since the upgrade didn’t work as planned, I decided to proceed with a clean installation instead. Unfortunately, I encountered difficulties booting DOSBox-X from the ISO image. As a workaround, I launched the Setup from within another fresh Windows 98 installation just like I did for Windows 2000.</p>
<p>After my previous experience with the Windows XP Setup, I mentally prepared myself for yet another potential failure. However, to my surprise, this time the Setup didn’t just throw an error message at me; instead, it smoothly proceeded to copy over the temporary installation files. Crisis averted!</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_98_xp_setup_clean_copy_files.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup copying files, started from Windows 98" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup copying files, started from Windows 98</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>One reboot later, I was greeted by the beloved and very familiar blue hue of the Windows XP Setup.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_text_installer.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup starting at the initial stage" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup starting at the initial stage</figcaption>
</figure>



<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_text_installer_warning.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup: Yes, I know we have a previous version installed" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup: Yes, I know we have a previous version installed</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>And now - the moment of truth. After confirming that we want to overwrite the existing Windows installation, Windows XP Setup started the next step of the installation by copying over the temporary installation files to the Windows directory.</p>
<p>I can’t say that I was surprised when the project stumbled across yet another issue. After copying over some files atrociously slow, it failed. No matter how often I retried, it always failed. I couldn’t track down the issue to one particular file though because on subsequent runs (yes, I tried!), it failed at a <em>different</em> file.</p>
<p>Based on the experience I had with the Windows 2000 installer I <em>think</em> this is related to either the IDE driver or the emulation of the IDE controller and the devices are simply dropping out of the system.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_text_installer_copy_error.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup failing to copy files" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup failing to copy files</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>The next obvious way to solve this issue was to reboot the system and try to run Setup again. Unfortunately, this wasn’t an option either because after a reboot it simply failed to copy the very first file - turns out that Windows Setup already started to overwrite vital parts of the previous installation.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_text_installer_copy_error_after_reboot.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup failing to copy any file after a reboot" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup failing to copy any file after a reboot</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>At this point, I gave up. Running Windows XP in DOSBox-X clearly wasn’t possible. Heck, I couldn’t even get the installation to work!</p>
<h2 id="new-technology-from-1999">New Technology from 1999</h2>
<p>“It is the NT conversion, stupid!”, I yelled at myself a couple of days later.</p>
<p>While Windows 98 is using MS-DOS to bootstrap the system and uses parts of it in its kernel, Windows XP uses the Windows NT platform instead. Just like Windows 2000!</p>
<p>What if swapping out the kernel requires some sort of low-level access I don’t have in DOSBox-X?</p>
<p>So I installed Windows 98 again, updated it to Windows 2000, fixed the missing taskbar, verified the system was working, mounted the Windows XP ISO, and started the installer again.</p>
<p>Because I was afraid that a clean installation would fail again, I went with the upgrade route once more. Not really knowing what to expect, I clicked on the magic button and waited.</p>
<p>And yes - this time, the upgrade seemed to work! No error messages this time!</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_setup_stage_1.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup started from Windows 2000" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup started from Windows 2000</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>One reboot later, I noticed something very promising.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_setup_stage_2.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup: Now with colors!" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup: Now with colors!</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>Instead of starting in the text-based installer again, I got a colorful graphic installer, indicating that Windows Setup was taking a different route this time. And amazingly, the installation ran just fine without any issues.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_setup_stage_3.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup: Installing Windows" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup: Installing Windows!</figcaption>
</figure>



<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_setup_stage_4.webp" alt="Windows XP Setup: Finalizing installation" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP Setup: Finalizing installation</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>With this part of the installation complete, there was one last reboot to survive.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_booting_featured.webp" alt="Windows XP finally booting" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP finally booting</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>Windows XP was bootable and the installation itself was complete!</p>
<p>Soon thereafter, things started to go downhill though. After the first boot, Windows XP is supposed to start the so-called “Out of Box Experience” (OOBE) in order to finalize the installation by setting up some options and the user account.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_oobe.webp" alt="Windows XP OOBE" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP OOBE</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>The OOBE started, but what an experience it was! This wasn’t an experience. This was pure madness!</p>
<p>The <a href="https://soundcloud.com/stanlepard/1996-internet-starter-kit-velkommen-original-mix" target="_blank" rel="noopener">beautiful setup music</a>
 was cluttered with tons of distortion sounding like incredible compression artifacts caused by a <em>very</em> unhappy WMA decoder.</p>
<p>In fact, the performance was so poor that the system completely locked up and I had no other choice than rebooting the system.</p>
<p>Fortunately, Windows XP is able to migrate the user accounts from Windows 2000 because I had no option to create a new account - I guess I avoided yet another dead end.</p>
<p>And <em>yet another</em> reboot later - there it was. In all its glory.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_winver.webp" alt="Windows XP - it’s alive!" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP - it's alive!</figcaption>
</figure>



<p>I did it. Windows XP is running successfully in DOSBox-X.</p>
<p>Obviously, I had to retry the games I tried on Windows 2000. <em>The Sims</em> in the various versions I tried before still failed, but this was expected. <em>Roller Coaster Tycoon</em> improved by a lot. I couldn’t spot any sound issues this time and the game was perfectly playable.</p>
<p>And last but not least: Yes, the iconic <em>3D Pinball: Space Cadet</em> worked flawlessly as well.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_3d_pinball.webp" alt="Windows XP - 3D Pinball Space Cadet" loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>Windows XP - 3D Pinball Space Cadet</figcaption>
</figure>



<h2 id="closing-words">Closing words</h2>
<p>This is what I like about emulation and playing around with those systems so much. Even though some tasks seem to be impossible at first, there are always new routes to explore, helping you to achieve things many people (including yourself!) say are impossible.</p>
<p>I love it.</p>
<figure>
  <img src="https://fabulous.systems/posts/2023/07/installing-windows-xp-in-dosbox-x/windows_xp_turn_off_computer.webp" alt="It is now safe to turn off your computer." loading="lazy">
  <figcaption>It is now safe to turn off your computer.</figcaption>
</figure>



			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Claude for Desktop (268 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://claude.ai/download</link>
            <guid>42007649</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 15:04:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://claude.ai/download">https://claude.ai/download</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42007649">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="region" aria-label="Notifications (F8)" tabindex="-1"><ol tabindex="-1"></ol></div><!--$--><div><p><span>Loading...</span></p></div><!--/$--></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fuzzing between the lines in popular barcode software (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.trailofbits.com/2024/10/31/fuzzing-between-the-lines-in-popular-barcode-software/</link>
            <guid>42006698</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 13:28:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.trailofbits.com/2024/10/31/fuzzing-between-the-lines-in-popular-barcode-software/">https://blog.trailofbits.com/2024/10/31/fuzzing-between-the-lines-in-popular-barcode-software/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42006698">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">

			
				
<article id="post-108489">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		<p><em>By Artur Cygan</em></p>
<p>Fuzzing—one of the most successful techniques for finding security bugs, consistently featured in articles and industry conferences—has become so popular that you may think most important software has already been extensively fuzzed. But that’s not always the case. In this blog post, we show how we fuzzed the ZBar barcode scanning library and why, despite our limited time budget, we found serious bugs: an out-of-bounds stack buffer write that can lead to arbitrary code execution with a malicious barcode, and a memory leak that can be used to perform a denial-of-service attack.</p>
<p>ZBar is an open-source library for reading barcodes written in C. It supports an impressive number of barcode formats, including QR codes. One of our clients used it, so we wanted to quickly assess its security. Given the extensive amount of code, manual review was not an option. Since we noticed no public mention of fuzzing, we decided to give it a shot.</p>
<h3>Assessing the project’s fuzzing state</h3>
<p>You might ask: how do you know whether or not software has been fuzzed? Although there’s no definitive answer to this question, it’s possible to make some educated guesses. First, we can check the repository for any mention of fuzzing, including searching issues, pull requests, and the code itself. For instance, <a href="https://github.com/mchehab/zbar/issues/233">this issue</a> proposes a fuzzing harness, but it was likely never run. Second, we can check <a href="https://github.com/google/oss-fuzz/tree/master/projects">the oss-fuzz projects</a>. If the project is fuzzed with oss-fuzz, it’s worth checking if the fuzzing harnesses are targeting the functionality we’re interested in and whether the project actually works. We observed cases where project builds were failing for months and were not actively fuzzed. Similarly to the project’s repository, oss-fuzz issues and pull requests can contain interesting information. Developers expressed <a href="https://github.com/google/oss-fuzz/issues/3863">some interest</a> in bringing ZBar to oss-fuzz, but this was ultimately abandoned.</p>
<p>By this point we knew two things about ZBar: it was barely fuzzed (or not fuzzed at all), and we identified starting points for creating our own fuzzing campaign.</p>
<h3>Instrumenting the build</h3>
<p>To fuzz ZBar, it has to be built with sanitizer and fuzzer instrumentation. Building an unfamiliar project can be a time-consuming challenge on its own, and adding instrumentation for fuzzing often makes this task even more difficult. For that reason, it’s useful to take an existing build and tweak it. Fortunately, ZBar is already <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/blob/011567f35433879aae5024fc6ec53f2a0568a6c4/pkgs/tools/graphics/zbar/default.nix">packaged in Nixpkgs</a>, so we could quickly modify the build:</p>
<pre>zbar-instrumented = with pkgs; (zbar.override {
  stdenv = clang16Stdenv;
}).overrideAttrs (orig: {
  buildInputs = orig.buildInputs ++ [ llvmPackages_16.openmp ];
  dontStrip = true;
  doCheck = false; # tests started failing with sanitizers
  CFLAGS = "-g -fsanitize=address,fuzzer-no-link";
  LDFLAGS = "-g -fsanitize=address,fuzzer-no-link";
});
</pre>
<p>Figure 1: Instrumenting ZBar for fuzzing</p>
<p>Nix packages are described with the Nix programming language and can be easily manipulated in various ways. In the case above, we use override to modify <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/blob/011567f35433879aae5024fc6ec53f2a0568a6c4/pkgs/tools/graphics/zbar/default.nix#L1-L30">inputs</a> defined by the package where we set the package’s compiler to Clang (otherwise, GCC is used by default). The following <code>overrideAttrs</code> function is a free-form override that allows us to modify anything we want. With <code>overrideAttrs</code>, we add the missing <code>openmp</code> dependency, disable stripping so that debug build works properly, and disable the tests. Finally, we add the instrumentation compiler and linker flags for AddressSanitizer and libFuzzer. (If you’re unfamiliar with the instrumentation flags, our <a href="https://appsec.guide/">AppSec Testing Handbook</a> has excellent <a href="https://appsec.guide/docs/fuzzing/c-cpp/libfuzzer/">guidance</a>.)</p>
<p>Obviously, Nix is not the only answer to this problem. Depending on the software and packaging, tweaking existing packages might be more difficult. However, we highly recommend trying it out, as we found it to be often the quickest way to achieve the goal.</p>
<h3>How to identify the target</h3>
<p>After preparing the instrumentation, we need to identify the fuzzing target. This part heavily depends on the project and can be non-trivial. Luckily, in ZBar the target was quite obvious: the function that takes an image and decodes barcode data from it. At this point there are a few questions to answer. How big should the image be? By default, ZBar tries to read all the known code types. Should we configure the scanner to specific codes or just try them all at once? We think it’s important not to overthink this and start with <em>something</em> to see how it performs. We started with the following harness, based on <a href="https://github.com/ZBar/ZBar/blob/854a5d97059e395807091ac4d80c53f7968abb8f/examples/scan_image.c#L65-L104">the official example</a>:</p>
<pre>#include <span>&lt;stdio.h&gt;</span>
#include <span>&lt;stdlib.h&gt;</span>
#include <span>&lt;zbar.h&gt;</span>

using namespace zbar;

extern "C" int LLVMFuzzerTestOneInput(const uint8_t *data, uint32_t size) {
  int width = 16, height = 16;
  if (size != width*height) return 1;

  zbar_image_t *image = zbar_image_create();
  if(!image)
    return 0;

  zbar_image_set_size(image, width, height);
  zbar_image_set_format(image, zbar_fourcc('Y', '8', '0', '0'));
  zbar_image_set_data(image, data, size, NULL);

  /* create a reader */
  zbar_image_scanner_t *scanner = zbar_image_scanner_create();

  /* configure the reader */
  zbar_image_scanner_set_config(scanner, (zbar_symbol_type_t)0, ZBAR_CFG_ENABLE, 1);
  zbar_scan_image(scanner, image);

  /* clean up */
  zbar_image_destroy(image);
  zbar_image_scanner_destroy(scanner);
  return 0;
}
</pre>
<p>Figure 2: Initial testing harness</p>
<p>In this harness, we essentially modified the sample to take the input image from the fuzzer and locked it down to a 2-by-2 pixel square (8 bits per pixel). Running this harness resulted in one <code>LeakSanitizer</code> crash reporting a memory leak. Because <code>libFuzzer</code> stops at the first crash, we disabled the memory leak detection with <code>-detect_leaks=0</code> and continued fuzzing. After a while, the coverage gains appeared to stall, so we decided to enlarge the input image to 4-by-4 pixels. Surprisingly, libFuzzer struggled to figure out that input should be of size 1024 and couldn’t start fuzzing. Even tweaking the <code>max_len</code> and <code>len_control</code> options didn’t help. we managed to kickstart fuzzing by manually passing a seed input of the right size:</p>
<pre>$ head -c 1024 /dev/zero &gt; seed
$ ./result/bin/zbar-fuzz -detect_leaks=0 -seed_inputs=seed
</pre>
<p>Figure 3: Manually passing the seed input</p>
<p>After this, the fuzzer was able to quickly find another crash from AddressSanitizer caused by a stack buffer overflow. If you paid attention to the ZBar instrumentation code, we mentioned in the comment that its tests are disabled due to sanitizer failure. It turned out the failure during tests wasn’t a false positive and concerned the same bug the fuzzer discovered.</p>
<p>Even with this simple approach, we managed to find some bugs in the library. However, with more time, we could have made a number of improvements to find even more bugs:</p>
<ul>
<li>Initiate the corpus with pictures of code types to help the fuzzer cover the code more quickly</li>
<li>Target specific codes that could help the fuzzer maintain a homogenous corpus and generate more accurate mutations</li>
<li>Check code coverage where it stalls to help the fuzzer get past any difficult branches</li>
</ul>
<h3>Diagnosing crashes</h3>
<p>It turned out that the stack buffer out-of-bounds write bug was independently reported around the same time by another researcher. The vulnerability was assigned <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2023-40890">CVE-2023-40890</a> and was fixed in commit <a href="https://github.com/mchehab/zbar/commit/012a030250a203e5529d09caedea7ad7173dacfd">012a030</a>. The issue lied in the lookup_sequence function, as the fuzzer pointed out:</p>
<pre>==22005==ERROR: AddressSanitizer: stack-buffer-overflow on address 0x7fa297900578 at pc 0x7fa299b84ee2 bp 0x7ffe86531ef0 sp 0x7ffe86531ee8
WRITE of size 4 at 0x7fa297900578 thread T0
    #0 0x7fa299b84ee1 in lookup_sequence /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/decoder/databar.c:698:12
    #1 0x7fa299b84ee1 in match_segment_exp /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/decoder/databar.c:758:21
    #2 0x7fa299b7fc02 in decode_char /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/decoder/databar.c:1081:16
    #3 0x7fa299b7e225 in _zbar_decode_databar /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/decoder/databar.c:1269:11
    #4 0x7fa299b756a6 in zbar_decode_width /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/decoder.c:274:15
    #5 0x7fa299b726c1 in process_edge /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/scanner.c:173:16
    #6 0x7fa299b726c1 in zbar_scanner_flush /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/scanner.c:186:35
    #7 0x7fa299b7088a in quiet_border /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/img_scanner.c:708:5
    #8 0x7fa299b7088a in _zbar_scan_image /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/img_scanner.c:1020:13
    #9 0x7fa299b6e978 in zbar_scan_image /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/img_scanner.c:1146:12
    #10 0x55c5b5f36a0f in LLVMFuzzerTestOneInput /tmp/nix-build-zbar-fuzz-0.23.92.drv-0/zbar/fuzz.cpp:25:3
    ...
    #17 0x55c5b5d192e4 in _start (/nix/store/1lk9b8j92dx5xjfnhwh2g3x2g4d9mvsd-zbar-fuzz-0.23.92/bin/.zbar-fuzz-wrapped+0x352e4)

Address 0x7fa297900578 is located in stack of thread T0 at offset 376 in frame
    #0 0x7fa299b80b8f in match_segment_exp /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/decoder/databar.c:709

  This frame has 4 object(s):
    [32, 120) 'bestsegs' (line 711)
    [160, 248) 'segs' (line 711)
    [288, 376) 'seq' (line 711) &lt;== Memory access at offset 376 overflows this variable
    [416, 544) 'iseg' (line 713)
</pre>
<p>Figure 4: Fuzzer triggered of out-of-bounds write bug</p>
<p>This memory leak bug opens a denial-of-service attack vector, especially since the leak size depends on the input and appears to be the <code>image border size / 2 * 8 * 3 bytes</code>, so for an image with a border of 512, the leak is 6KiB. A program using ZBar to repeatedly scan untrusted codes can eventually exhaust memory and crash. The root issue is in the <a href="https://github.com/mchehab/zbar/blob/a549566ea11eb03622bd4458a1728ffe3f589163/zbar/sqcode.c#L300-L578"><code>_zbar_sq_decode</code></a> function, which fails to free allocated memory under certain error conditions. This is again correctly pointed out by the fuzzer:</p>
<pre>==21815==ERROR: LeakSanitizer: detected memory leaks

Direct leak of 48 byte(s) in 1 object(s) allocated from:
    #0 0x55df498b66ff in __interceptor_malloc (/nix/store/ncb5qgjr6jds4na1iadf5cxgdym6fbl5-zbar-fuzz-0.23.92/bin/.zbar-fuzz-wrapped+0x20b6ff)
    #1 0x7f71e9334cbf in _zbar_sq_decode /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/sqcode.c:397:19
    #2 0x7f71e92d7cf8 in _zbar_scan_image /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/img_scanner.c:1055:5
    #3 0x7f71e92d5978 in zbar_scan_image /tmp/nix-build-zbar-0.23.92.drv-0/source/zbar/img_scanner.c:1146:12
    #4 0x55df498fda0f in LLVMFuzzerTestOneInput /tmp/nix-build-zbar-fuzz-0.23.92.drv-0/zbar/fuzz.cpp:25:3
    ...
    #11 0x7f71e8f8bacd in __libc_start_call_main (/nix/store/46m4xx889wlhsdj72j38fnlyyvvvvbyb-glibc-2.37-8/lib/libc.so.6+0x23acd) (BuildId: 2ed90a3fa8dfeee1e77c301df6ba346580b73e8a)
...
SUMMARY: AddressSanitizer: 144 byte(s) leaked in 3 allocation(s).
</pre>
<p>Figure 5: Fuzzer triggers a memory leak bug</p>
<p>The root cause of the leak is missing memory cleanup in error paths. There are two instances where the <code>_zbar_sq_decode</code> function returns without executing the cleanup code under the <a href="https://github.com/mchehab/zbar/blob/a549566ea11eb03622bd4458a1728ffe3f589163/zbar/sqcode.c#L572-L576"><code>free_borders</code></a> label.</p>
<pre>diff --git a/zbar/sqcode.c b/zbar/sqcode.c
index 422c803d..a5e808fc 100644
--- a/zbar/sqcode.c
+++ b/zbar/sqcode.c
@@ -371,7 +371,7 @@ found_start:;
        border_len = 1;
        top_border = malloc(sizeof(sq_point));
        if (!top_border)
-       return 1;
+       goto free_borders;
        top_border[0] = top_left_dot.center;
    }
     }
@@ -471,7 +471,7 @@ found_start:;
    }
     }
     if (cur_len != border_len || border_len &lt; 6)
-   return 1;
+   goto free_borders;
     inc_x        = right_border[5].x - right_border[3].x;
     inc_y        = right_border[5].y - right_border[3].y;
     right_border[2].x = right_border[3].x - 0.5 * inc_x;
</pre>
<p>Figure 6: _zbar_sq_decode returns without executing cleanup code</p>
<p>We reported this issue along with the patch to the maintainer, however, after an extended period of time we still haven’t heard back. We published <a href="https://github.com/trail-of-forks/zbar/commit/6059b7f2c97595aca5077e6c357617ff132e79fd.patch">this patch on our ZBar fork</a> and opened <a href="https://github.com/mchehab/zbar/pull/294">a pull request</a> in the upstream ZBar repository.</p>
<h3>Putting it all together</h3>
<p>To reproduce the research from this article, save the fuzzing harness shown earlier as <code>zbar_harness.cpp</code> and the following Nix file as <code>zbar-fuzz.nix</code>. The Nix file already contains the instrumented ZBar build and the harness build. Build it with <code>nix-build zbar-fuzz.nix</code> and run <code>./result/bin/zbar-fuzz</code>. The <code>postInstall</code> phase is not strictly required but ensures that the harness has llvm-symbolizer available to show the source locations, which helps in diagnosing the root cause.</p>
<pre>let
  # nixpkgs snapshot from Aug 7, 2023
  pkgs = import (fetchTarball "https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs/archive/011567f35433879aae5024fc6ec53f2a0568a6c4.tar.gz") {};

  zbar-instrumented = with pkgs; (zbar.override {
    stdenv = clang16Stdenv;
  }).overrideAttrs (orig: {
    buildInputs = orig.buildInputs ++ [ llvmPackages_16.openmp ];
    dontStrip = true;
    doCheck = false; # tests fail with sanitizer
    CFLAGS = "-g -fsanitize=address,fuzzer-no-link";
    LDFLAGS = "-g -fsanitize=address,fuzzer-no-link";
  });

in with pkgs; clang16Stdenv.mkDerivation rec {
 pname = "zbar-fuzz";
 version = zbar.version;
 src = ./.;

 nativeBuildInputs = [ makeWrapper ];

 buildInputs = [ zbar-instrumented ];

 dontStrip = true;

 buildPhase = ''
   mkdir -p $out/bin
   clang++ zbar_harness.cpp -fsanitize=address,fuzzer -g -lzbar -o $out/bin/zbar-fuzz
 '';

 postInstall = ''
   wrapProgram $out/bin/zbar-fuzz \
     --prefix PATH : ${lib.getBin llvmPackages_16.llvm}/bin
 '';
}
</pre>
<p>Figure 7: Instrumented ZBar build and the harness build</p>
<h3>Lessons learned</h3>
<p>There are a few takeaways from this experiment. First, it’s important to fuzz the unsafe code even if you don’t have a lot of time to do so. Other researchers can expand on the work by increasing the code coverage of the fuzzer.</p>
<p>Cut out any unnecessary features to limit attack vectors. ZBar by default scans all code types, which means that an attacker can trigger a bug in any of the scanners. If you only need to scan QR codes for instance, then ZBar can be configured to do so in the code:</p>
<pre>zbar_image_scanner_set_config(scanner, (zbar_symbol_type_t)0, ZBAR_CFG_ENABLE, 0);
zbar_image_scanner_set_config(scanner, ZBAR_QRCODE, ZBAR_CFG_ENABLE, 1);
</pre>
<p>Figure 8: Configuring ZBar to scan only QR codes</p>
<p>Or when using the <code>zbarimg</code> CLI program, add the options: <code>--set '*.enable=0' --set 'qr.enable=1'</code>.</p>
<p>Finally, add sanitizer instrumentation to your build. At the bare minimum, you should use AddressSanitizer. As this ZBar example shows, if the test were built with sanitizers, it would have caught a critical memory safety vulnerability. Another benefit is that sanitizers save time and effort for adding fuzzing to a project, as sanitizers are essentially a required step for fuzzing C/C++ code.</p>
<p>We use fuzzing extensively at Trail of Bits. Take a look at our <a href="https://appsec.guide/docs/fuzzing/">Testing Handbook</a> for more resources, and <a href="https://www.trailofbits.com/contact/">contact us</a> if you’re interested in custom fuzzing for your project.</p>

			</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	
</article><!-- #post-108489 -->
						<!-- #nav-below -->
		
					<!-- #comments .comments-area -->

			
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sorry, Gas Companies – Parody Isn't Infringement (Even If It Creeps You Out) (213 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/10/sorry-gas-companies-parody-isnt-infringement-even-if-it-creeps-you-out</link>
            <guid>42006265</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 12:37:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/10/sorry-gas-companies-parody-isnt-infringement-even-if-it-creeps-you-out">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/10/sorry-gas-companies-parody-isnt-infringement-even-if-it-creeps-you-out</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42006265">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <article role="article">
  
  
  <div><p><span data-contrast="auto">Activism comes in many forms. You might </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/09/protestors-nationwide-rally-tell-apple-dont-break-encryption-dont-break-your"><span data-contrast="none">hold a rally</span></a><span data-contrast="auto">, </span><a href="https://act.eff.org/"><span data-contrast="none">write to Congress</span></a><span data-contrast="auto">, or </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/press/releases/diverse-groups-fly-airship-over-nsas-utah-data-center-protest-illegal-internet-spying"><span data-contrast="none">fly a blimp</span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> over the NSA. </span><i><span data-contrast="auto">Or</span></i><span data-contrast="auto"> you might use a </span><a href="https://repaer.earth/"><span data-contrast="none">darkly hilarious parody</span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> to make your point, like our client Modest Proposals recently did.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}"> <br></span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">Modest Proposals is an activist collective that uses parody and culture jamming to advance environmental justice and other social causes. As part of a </span><a href="https://www.themodestproposals.org/life-offsets.html"><span data-contrast="none">campaign</span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> shining a spotlight on the environmental damage and human toll caused by the liquefied natural gas (LNG) industry, Modest Proposals invented a company called Repaer. The fake company’s </span><a href="https://repaer.org/"><span data-contrast="none">website</span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> offers energy companies the opportunity to purchase “life offsets” that balance the human deaths their activities cause by extending the lives of individuals deemed economically valuable. The website also advertises a “Plasma Pals” program that encourages parents to donate their child’s plasma to wealthy recipients. Scroll down on the homepage a bit, and you’ll see the logos for three (real) LNG companies—Repaer’s “Featured Partners.”</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-ccp-props="{}">Believe it or not, the companies didn’t like this. (Shocking!) Two of them—TotalEnergies and Equinor—sent our client stern emails threatening legal action if their names and logos weren’t removed from the website. TotalEnergies also sent a demand to the website’s hosting service, Netlify, that got repaer.earth taken offline. That was our cue to get involved.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}"> <br></span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">We sent&nbsp;<a href="https://www.eff.org/document/eff-letter-totalenergies-re-modest-proposals">letters</a> to both companies, explaining what should be obvious: the website was a noncommercial work of activism, unlikely to confuse any reasonable viewer. Trademark law is about protecting consumers; it’s not a tool for businesses to shut down criticism. We also sent a counternotice to Netlify denying TotalEnergies’ allegations and demanding that repaer.earth be restored.</span><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-ccp-props="{}">&nbsp;We wish this were the first time we’ve had to send letters like that, but EFF regularly helps activists and critics push back on bogus </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/09/climate-has-posse-and-so-does-political-satire"><span data-contrast="none">trademark</span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> and </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/08/copyright-not-tool-silence-critics-religious-education"><span data-contrast="none">copyright</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2024/03/sxsw-tried-silence-critics-bogus-trademark-and-copyright-claims-eff-fought-back"><span data-contrast="none">claims</span></a><span data-contrast="auto">. This incident is also part of a broader and long-standing pattern of the energy industry weaponizing the law to quash dissent by environmental activists. </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/takedowns/landis-gyr-agrees-leave-documents-then-sends-notice-take-them-down"><span data-contrast="none">These</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/press/releases/eff-and-eri-fight-quash-speech-chilling-subpoenas-chevron"><span data-contrast="none">are</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2010/01/and-another-one-takedown-hall-shame-peabody-energy"><span data-contrast="none">just</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2013/08/using-copyright-silence-oil-company-satire-how-crude"><span data-contrast="none">examples</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2011/05/utah-court-strikes-blow-free-speech-dismisses"><span data-contrast="none">EFF</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/04/greenpeace-stands-against-slapps-and-wins"><span data-contrast="none">has</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/press/archives/2010/01/05"><span data-contrast="none">written</span></a> <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/09/its-time-federal-anti-slapp-law-protect-online-speakers"><span data-contrast="none">about</span></a><span data-contrast="auto">. We’ve been fighting these tactics for a long time, both by representing individual activist groups and through supporting legislative efforts like a </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/09/its-time-federal-anti-slapp-law-protect-online-speakers"><span data-contrast="none">federal anti-SLAPP bill</span></a><span data-contrast="auto">.</span><span data-ccp-props="0}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-ccp-props="{}">Frustratingly, Netlify made us go through the full </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/issues/dmca"><span data-contrast="none">DMCA</span></a><span data-contrast="auto"> counternotice process—including a 10-business-day waiting period to have the site restored—even though this was never a DMCA claim. (The DMCA is copyright law, not trademark, and TotalEnergies didn’t even meet the notice requirements that Netlify claims to follow.) Rather than wait around for Netlify to act, Modest Proposals eventually moved the website to a different hosting service.&nbsp; </span><span data-ccp-props="{}"><br></span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="auto">Equinor and TotalEnergies, on the other hand, have remained silent. This is a pretty common result when we help push back against bad trademark and copyright claims: the rights owners slink away once they realize their bullying tactics won’t work, without actually admitting they were wrong. We’re glad these companies seem to have backed off regardless, but victims of bogus claims deserve more certainty than this.</span></p>

</div>

          </article>
    </div><div>
          <h2>Join EFF Lists</h2>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Moving to a World Beyond "p < 0.05" (2019) (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2019.1583913</link>
            <guid>42005635</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 11:16:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2019.1583913">https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2019.1583913</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42005635">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00031305.2019.1583913: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: TikTok Influencers Database with Analyzed Audio (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.topyappers.com/</link>
            <guid>42005516</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 10:56:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.topyappers.com/">https://www.topyappers.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42005516">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><tr><td></td><td><span>Business &amp; Entrepreneurship</span></td><td><span>4.6K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Social Media Marketing Agencies</span><span>Video Production Services</span><span>Digital Marketing Courses</span><span>Personal Branding Coaching</span><span>Small Business Marketing</span></p></td><td><p>TikTok, Instagram, YouTube, Audiobook.com, Fiverr, Mercedes</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Investwithnat | Finance Bestie</p><p>investwithnat</p></div></td><td><span>Finance</span></td><td><span>58.4K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Financial services</span><span>Investment platforms</span><span>Credit card companies</span><span>High-yield savings accounts</span><span>Real estate</span></p></td><td><p>Sofi, S&amp;P 500, Collective, Yelp Elite, Alaska Airlines Visa Signature card, Roth IRA, Apartments.com</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Education and Career</span></td><td><span>491.3K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Tech Education</span><span>Software Development</span><span>Online Learning Platforms</span><span>Career Coaching</span><span>Startups and Entrepreneurship</span></p></td><td><p>Brev</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Education</span></td><td><span>29.6K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Online Learning Platforms</span><span>Financial Services</span><span>Tech Tools for Professionals</span><span>AI Products</span><span>Career Coaching</span></p></td><td><p>Undetectable AI, Servicenow, Nvidia, ChatGBT, GitHub, Numerai, QuantConnect, Olaide</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>courtney johnson</p><p>courtney..johnson</p></div></td><td><span>Career and Personal Development</span></td><td><span>224.4K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Career Coaching</span><span>Resume Services</span><span>Social Media Management Tools</span><span>Online Courses for Professionals</span></p></td><td><p>Tango, Gumroad</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Finance Bro</p><p>youraveragefinancebro</p></div></td><td><span>Finance &amp; Business</span></td><td><span>270.8K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Financial education</span><span>Career advice for finance professionals</span><span>Microsoft Excel tutorials</span><span>Productivity hacks</span><span>Financial technology</span></p></td><td><p>Microsoft Excel, Patagonia, Enron, Taco Bell, Crunch Wraps, Scribe, Carousel, Powerpoint, Kalshe, Taylor Swift, Nvidia, McDonald's, Wendy's, Theranos, JMP, Black Rock, Instagram, LinkedIn, Bitcoin, BTC</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Corporate Steve &amp; Co…</p><p>beyondeducation_</p></div></td><td><span>Career &amp; Business</span></td><td><span>23.7K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Recruitment Agencies</span><span>Diversity &amp; Inclusion Training</span><span>Career Coaching</span><span>Job Search Platforms</span><span>Corporate Culture Consultants</span></p></td><td><p>L’Oréal, Hsbc, GTA 6</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Jerry Chen | MisoDope</p><p>misodope</p></div></td><td><span>Software Development</span></td><td><span>471.3K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Software Development Tools</span><span>Coding Bootcamps</span><span>Career Coaching</span><span>Tech Recruitment</span><span>AI Tools</span></p></td><td><p>Microsoft 365 Copilot, JetBrains, Python, WebStorm, DataGrip, Full Psych Academy, CodeSmith, Code Academy, Free Code Camp, Swift, IntelliJ, VS Code, Neovim, Android Studio, ChatGPT, AWS, Terraform, Teams, Slack, Discord</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Lifestyle</span></td><td><span>226.5K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Running apparel and shoes</span><span>Fitness equipment and supplements</span><span>Travel destinations and experiences</span><span>Fashion brands</span><span>Beauty products</span></p></td><td><p>Nike, Air Max Diane, compression boots, roller, Frozen ex-sandwich, Wii jacket, playera, Abbott, Queen's Butter Wish, New York Rock Runners, Subway, Central Park, calsetas, tennis, gloves, band, socks, jacket, chamaras, bandita</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Macaila | Outdoor Content</p><p>makilllla</p></div></td><td><span>Nature &amp; Outdoors</span></td><td><span>161.5K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Outdoor gear &amp; apparel</span><span>Camping &amp; hiking equipment</span><span>Nature documentaries &amp; educational content</span><span>Sustainable living products</span><span>Travel &amp; adventure companies</span></p></td><td><p>Anchor portable power bank, Best Buy Canada, Usnia (lichen), Old man's beard, Amanita muscaria (fly agaric), Rain pants, Headlamp, Moss, Ferns, Mushrooms, Tinctures, Skin cream, Tea, Fire starter, Solar panels, Box wine</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Fashion</span></td><td><span>70.1K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Streetwear Brands</span><span>Clothing Manufacturers</span><span>Fashion Accessories</span><span>Sneakers</span><span>Men's Fashion</span></p></td><td><p>Hoodie, Watch, Cardigan, Sweats, Joggers, Denim Jacket, Pants, Set, Slides, Shorts, Necklace, Jeans, Tie Top, Shirt Skirt, Bapestas, Shoes, Tote, Sweatshirt, Long Sleeve, Glasses</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Travel</span></td><td><span>9.3K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Travel</span><span>Airlines</span><span>Tourism</span><span>Adventure Gear</span><span>Lifestyle</span></p></td><td><p>China Southern Airlines</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>brooklyn.nfts</p><p>brooklyn.nfts</p></div></td><td><span>NFT</span></td><td><span>67.9K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>NFT marketplaces</span><span>NFT art creation tools</span><span>Crypto wallets</span><span>Web3 platforms</span><span>NFT education resources</span></p></td><td><p>Electra Ladies, NFTs, Opensea, Rarible, Fandefi, Lens Protocol, Drink Cloudwater, Photoshop, Blender</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>ET the Engineer</p><p>no_dilemma</p></div></td><td><span>Engineering</span></td><td><span>70.1K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Construction</span><span>Engineering</span><span>Architecture</span><span>Insurance</span><span>Disaster Preparedness</span></p></td><td><p>Xena Workwear, Dentyne, Hubba Bubba, Fantasy Hike, Bluey, Moxie Trades, Blundstone, Doc Martens, Keens, Redback Boots, Tito's, M&amp;M's, Ugg, Kishigo, Dawson Vest, Louisianan, Ken Costume</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Entrepreneurship</span></td><td><span>96.7K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Ecommerce</span><span>Dropshipping</span><span>Clothing Brands</span><span>Marketing and Advertising</span><span>Business Coaching</span></p></td><td><p>Alibaba, Shopify, Procreate, DJI Osmo Pocket 3, LastPass, Clickfunnels, Stripe, Turo, Tesla, Snag Rag, One Love Clothing, MNML, Durags, Jogging Suits, Hoodies, T-shirts, Track Pants, Big Cartel, Zipfox, Remitly</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Alyssa the TikTok Shop Coach</p><p>thetiktokshopcoach</p></div></td><td><span>Business &amp; Finance</span></td><td><span>52.2K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>E-commerce Platforms</span><span>Affiliate Marketing Tools</span><span>Online Business Courses</span><span>Coaching &amp; Mentorship Programs</span><span>TikTok Marketing Services</span></p></td><td><p>Cadillac, TikTok Shop, BMC Brands Meet Creators, TikTok Shop Accelerator, Foot Massager, Brands Meet Creators Live, BMC Academy, TikTok Shop Creator 1 0 1 Course</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>Grace Roehrenbeck</p><p>graceroehrenbeck</p></div></td><td><span>Education</span></td><td><span>58.6K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Nursing schools</span><span>Nursing supplies</span><span>Healthcare products</span><span>Time management tools</span><span>Educational resources</span></p></td><td><p>Dyson, White Chicken Chili, Tbell, Frosted Flakes, McDonald's, Myers Fall Scented Sprays, Trader Joe's, Incredible Health</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Productivity</span></td><td><span>53.1K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Productivity Apps</span><span>Project Management Software</span><span>Online Learning Platforms</span><span>Microsoft Office Products</span><span>Google Workspace Products</span></p></td><td><p>ClickUp, OneNote, Brain Sensei, MiRo, Plus Docs, Google Slides, Excel</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td></td><td><span>Science &amp; Education</span></td><td><span>54.8K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Space Agencies (NASA, ESA, etc.)</span><span>Science Museums &amp; Planetariums</span><span>Astronomy &amp; Space Photography Equipment</span><span>Educational Technology &amp; Software</span><span>Travel &amp; Adventure</span></p></td><td><p>Moonshine, Aurora, Grand Canyon, Mediterranean Sea, 3D Printer, Magnets, Glasses</p></td><td></td></tr><tr><td><div><p>eoinsrecovery</p><p>eoinsrecovery</p></div></td><td><span>Addiction Recovery</span></td><td><span>16.8K</span></td><td></td><td></td><td><p><span>Addiction Recovery Resources</span><span>Mental Health Apps</span><span>Sobriety Support Groups</span><span>Weight Loss Programs</span><span>Fitness Products</span></p></td><td></td><td></td></tr></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>