<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 22:00:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ex Post Office CEO hands back award after IT failures lead to false convictions (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-67925304</link>
            <guid>38930011</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 18:36:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-67925304">https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-67925304</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38930011">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main id="main-content" data-testid="main-content"><article><header></header><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><picture><source srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg.webp 800w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/976/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg.webp 976w" type="image/webp"><img alt="Paula Vennells" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg 800w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/976/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg 976w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/976/cpsprodpb/4E1B/production/_132259991_vennells2-002.jpg" width="976" height="549" loading="eager"></picture></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Parliament TV</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Paula Vennells said she was "truly sorry for the devastation" caused to sub-postmasters and their families</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p><b>Former Post Office boss Paula Vennells is handing back her CBE with immediate effect after facing mounting pressure over the Horizon IT scandal.</b></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>More than 700 sub-postmasters were prosecuted based on data from faulty Horizon software between 1999 and 2015.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Some people went to prison for false accounting and theft, while many were financially ruined.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>More than a million people signed a petition calling for Ms Vennells to be stripped of her CBE.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Government ministers have promised a plan as soon as later this week to help hundreds of sub-postmasters clear their names.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>One idea being explored is passing a new law that would exonerate hundreds wrongfully convicted.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>In a statement, Ms Vennells, who was Post Office chief executive between 2012 and 2019, said she had "listened" to the sub-postmasters and others calling for her to return her CBE. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>"I am truly sorry for the devastation caused to the sub-postmasters and their families, whose lives were torn apart by being wrongly accused and wrongly prosecuted as a result of the Horizon system." </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Ms Vennells has long faced questions over her role in the scandal, which has been described as one of the most widespread miscarriages of justice the UK has seen.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>While the scandal has been public knowledge for some time with a public inquiry ongoing, an ITV drama - Mr Bates vs The Post Office - which aired last week <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-67894818">thrust the issue back into the spotlight.</a></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>A public inquiry into the scandal has been under way since February 2021, and will resume on Thursday following a break over Christmas.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Fujitsu - the Japanese technology company that manufactured the Horizon system - has been invited to answer questions from MPs next week.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The Business and Trade Select Committee says Post Office minister Kevin Hollinrake has confirmed he will attend the evidence session on 16 January.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Ms Vennells was appointed as CBE for services to the Post Office and to charity in the 2019 New Year's Honours - despite ongoing legal action against Post Office, which was launched by 555 sub-postmasters in 2017.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>During her tenure, the Post Office repeatedly denied there were problems with the Horizon system.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The Post Office said the honour was given for her work on "diversity and inclusion", and her "commitment to the social purpose at the heart of the business and her dedication in putting the customer first".</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>However, despite the offer by Ms Vennells, the only person who can strip someone of an honour is King Charles. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>People can indicate they would like to renounce their honour, as Ms Vennells has now done - but doing so has no formal effect. Until the King is advised by the Forfeiture Committee and acts on its advice, Ms Vennells will continue to hold her CBE.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The Communication Workers Union (CWU), which represents 110,000 employees of Royal Mail (which Post Office used to be part of)<!-- -->said Ms Vennells' decision was "a token gesture". </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>CWU's national officer Andy Furey also called for her to return performance-related bonuses she received during her role at Post Office. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>He said: "Since she received these bonuses while overseeing the most widespread miscarriage of justice in British history, it would only be right to return this money."</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Many victims of the scandal are still fighting to have their convictions overturned or to secure full compensation after being forced to pay out thousands of pounds of their own money for shortfalls that were caused by Horizon accounting software.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Jo Hamilton, a former subpostmistress who was wrongly convicted in 2008 of stealing thousands of pounds from a village shop in Hampshire, said she was glad Ms Vennells had agreed to return the honour. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>"It's a shame it took just a million people to cripple her conscience," she said. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Downing Street has said it is "obviously the right decision" for Ms Vennells to return her CBE. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Former sub-postmaster Michael Rudkin, whose wife Susan was <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-leicestershire-66939587">wrongly accused of stealing £44,000</a>, said he was pleased that Ms Vennells had chosen to return her CBE. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>He said he had written personally to Ms Vennells after his wife's prosecution to ask for a further investigation into her case, and received no help. </p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Michael Rudkin says his family was ostracised by their community</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Mr Rudkin, who lost his job and union position due to the Horizon scandal, said his family had also lost friends due to the allegations.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>A CBE (Commander of the British Empire) is awarded to someone who has gone "above and beyond for the community or country". </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>After a damehood or knighthood, it is the highest level of Order of the British Empire, and is followed by the OBE (Officer of the Order of the British Empire), then the MBE (Member of the Order of the British Empire).</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Number 10 also said it would support "further recognition" of the work of sub-postmaster Alan Bates and others to expose the Horizon scandal.</p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><span></span></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>ITV / Shutterstock</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Will Mellor as former sub-postmaster Lee Castleton and Amy Nuttall as Lisa Castleton in Mr Bates vs the Post Office TV Show</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Until 2012, the Post Office was part of Royal Mail before they were split into two. Between 2003 and 2010, the chief executive of Royal Mail was Adam Crozier who went on to lead ITV and is now chairman of BT.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>He was replaced by Dame Moya Greene who ran Royal Mail for eight years, during which time the company was privatised and listed on the London Stock Exchange in 2013.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The government has been considering options to speed up justice for wrongfully convicted sub-postmasters.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Former minister Nadhim Zahawi has called for a "simple bill" to quash all the remaining convictions based on "bad data". </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>However, others have disagreed, including former attorney general Dominic Grieve who told the BBC that it would amount to "parliamentary interference in the judicial process". </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Instead, he said each case "ought to be considered on its own merits", and sent to the Criminal Cases Review Commission (CCRC), which investigates alleged miscarriages of justice. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The scandal has been described as the most widespread miscarriage of justice in British history, but to date only 93 convictions have been overturned and of them, just 30 people have agreed "full and final" compensation settlements, meaning many victims are still fighting to clear their names.</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Some 54 cases have resulted in either a conviction being upheld, people being refused permission to appeal, or the person appealing having withdrawn from the process.</p></div></article></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Study Finds Microplastics in Nearly 90% of Proteins Sampled (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://oceanconservancy.org/news/its-not-just-seafood-new-study-finds-microplastics-in-nearly-90-of-proteins-sampled-including-plant-based-meat-alternatives/</link>
            <guid>38929967</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 18:33:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://oceanconservancy.org/news/its-not-just-seafood-new-study-finds-microplastics-in-nearly-90-of-proteins-sampled-including-plant-based-meat-alternatives/">https://oceanconservancy.org/news/its-not-just-seafood-new-study-finds-microplastics-in-nearly-90-of-proteins-sampled-including-plant-based-meat-alternatives/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38929967">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          

                      <h3>Researchers at Ocean Conservancy and University of Toronto estimate that American adults could be consuming up to 3.8 million microplastics per year from protein alone</h3>
          
          
        </div><div>
          
<p>Portland, Ore. – A <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0269749123022352?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">new study</a> led by researchers at Ocean Conservancy and the University of Toronto and published today in the journal <em>Environmental Pollution</em> found microplastic particles in 88% of protein food samples tested. The samples were drawn from 16 different protein types* destined for U.S. consumers, including seafood, pork, beef, chicken, tofu, and three different plant-based meat alternatives.</p>



<p>While scientists have long documented the presence of microplastics in the digestive tracts of commercial fish and shellfish like salmon, halibut and oysters, there has been little research into whether these microplastics are entering the filets of the fish – the parts that are actually eaten by people; and little research into terrestrial protein sources like beef and chicken that make up a large part of the American diet. In this study, microplastics were found in all 16 protein types tested, suggesting that humans are likely eating microplastics no matter the source of protein they choose. Furthermore, there were no statistical differences in microplastic concentrations between land- and ocean-sourced proteins.</p>



<p>“This is a startling reminder of just how prolific plastic pollution has become – humans live on land and yet seafood samples are just as likely to be contaminated with plastics as are terrestrial derived proteins,” said study co-author Dr. Britta Baechler, a marine biologist and Associate Director of Plastics Science at Ocean Conservancy. “And there’s no escaping them no matter what you eat, it seems. The plastic pollution crisis is impacting all of us, and we need to take action to address its many forms.”</p>



<p>The study found evidence that food processing is a likely source of microplastic contamination, as highly processed protein products (like fish sticks, chicken nuggets, tofu, and plant-based burgers, among others) contained significantly more microplastics per gram than minimally processed products (items like packaged wild Alaska pollock, raw chicken breast, and others). However, no statistical difference was found between high-processed products and fresh-caught products, suggesting that food processing is not the only source of microplastic contamination and opening avenues for further research.</p>



<p>“It’s tempting to want to draw conclusions like ‘eat less of this and more of that’ to avoid microplastics in your diet; but right now we still know very little about the microplastic burdens in commonly consumed foods. Our study adds to this knowledge but also demonstrates the need for further research to better understand the bigger picture, including where these microplastics are coming from and the potential human health risks<a>,</a>” said primary co-author Madeleine Milne, who conducted the research while at the Rochman Lab at the University of Toronto in 2022.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Notably, across all samples, nearly half (44%) of the identified microplastics were fibers, which is consistent with other studies suggesting that fibers are the most prevalent form of microplastic in the environment. About a third of the microplastics (30%) were plastic fragments.</p>



<p>Using survey data from <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fmars.2023.1323477/abstract" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a separate study</a> by Ocean Conservancy and the University of Toronto (to be published in <em>Frontiers in Marine Science)</em> the authors estimate an American adult will consume, on average, 11,500 microplastics per year. Annual exposure could be as high as 3.8 million microplastics per year if calculated using the highest levels of microplastics found in each individual protein type and the average reported protein consumption rates.</p>



<p>“As ocean scientists, my co-authors and I are deeply concerned about the growing plastics crisis in the world’s ocean,” said Dr. George Leonard, Ocean Conservancy’s Chief Scientist and a co-author of the study. “But our study shows that plastics in our food goes well beyond fish and shellfish to a wide variety of other protein sources, as well.&nbsp; Our work is a call to action to reduce plastic pollution in its many forms to ensure a safe and healthy food supply for all consumers.”&nbsp;</p>



<p>###</p>



<p>*Protein types included store-purchased breaded shrimp, minced pollock, fish sticks, white Gulf shrimp (headless/shell-on), Key West pink shrimp (headless/shell-on), Alaska Pollock fillets (skinless), chicken nuggets, top sirloin steaks, pork loin chops, chicken breasts, plant-based nuggets, plant-based fish sticks, plant-based ground beef, and tofu blocks.</p>



<p><strong>Note:</strong> Photos of the experiment are available <a href="https://oceanconservancy.mediavalet.com/portals/microplasticsinproteins" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">here</a>. The location and photographer’s name are indicated in the file names.</p>



<p><strong>About Ocean Conservancy</strong></p>



<p>Ocean Conservancy is working to protect the ocean from today’s greatest global challenges. Together with our partners, we create evidence-based solutions for a healthy ocean and the wildlife and communities that depend on it. For more information, visit oceanconservancy.org, or follow us on <a href="https://www.facebook.com/oceanconservancy" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Facebook</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/ourocean" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">X (formerly known as Twitter)</a> or <a href="https://www.instagram.com/oceanconservancy">Instagram</a>.</p>



<p><strong>About the Rochman Lab at the University of Toronto</strong></p>



<p>Dr. Chelsea Rochman is an assistant professor in Ecology and Evolutionary Biology at the University of Toronto. The Rochman Lab is home to roughly 20 researchers focused on methods to sample and measure microplastics, and the sources, fate and effects of microplastics in freshwater and marine ecosystems.&nbsp;</p>




        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Ugliest Airplane: An Appreciation of the Transavia AirTruk (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.smithsonianmag.com/air-space-magazine/ugliest-airplane-appreciation-180978708/</link>
            <guid>38928970</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 17:31:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.smithsonianmag.com/air-space-magazine/ugliest-airplane-appreciation-180978708/">https://www.smithsonianmag.com/air-space-magazine/ugliest-airplane-appreciation-180978708/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38928970">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-article-body="">
        
          <figure>
            <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/Et0hpWkc4Dhrs6rrS2hDqMv2IiQ=/1000x750/filters:no_upscale()/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/93/3a/933ad68e-af75-4c6d-8aea-b86cc1b55d5c/11j_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-gavinconroyac3q8790_live.jpg" alt="11J_DJ2022_UgliestShowplane-GavinConroyAC3Q8790_LIVE.jpg" itemprop="image">
            <figcaption>
              
                A rare three-ship formation of TransAvia PL-12 AirTruks led by Ian Bell (in yellow) with Nick Wills (center) and Steve Death (top) departs an October 2018 airshow in Temora, New South Wales, Australia. 


              
            </figcaption>
          </figure>
        

        

        <p>It is one of the most bizarre looking aircraft ever to reach production. Its conception occurred in Australia, its gestation in New Zealand, and its growth and maturation back in Australia. This geography, and unfettered thinking about the TransAvia AirTruk’s mission, drove the airplane’s unusual appearance.</p>

<p>In the mid-1950s, the largely agricultural country of New Zealand found itself in need of new aircraft for “topdressing”—spreading soil enhancers and fertilizers by air—what we on this side of the world call “cropdusting.” The old airplanes they had inherited from the British Commonwealth, mostly converted de Havilland Tiger Moths and Piper Cub-like Austers, were wearing out. A few new American designs were imported, but currency restrictions of the day made them very expensive. New Zealanders needed a locally built airplane specifically designed for the job and sold for an affordable price.</p>


<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/LnyC3ZGUDvgew6EGiln63sH1Avg=/fit-in/1072x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/21/61/2161b7c1-f7eb-421f-a10a-f8422d52dceb/11i_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-aerautoprototypec1950_live.jpg" alt="The Ugliest Airplane: An Appreciation" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      Luigi Pellarini's PL-2C flying car, circa 1950. 

    
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Jack Worthington and Snow Bennett, operators of New Zealand’s Northern Air Services, found a good starting place in the PL-7, built by Kingsford Smith Aviation Service near Sydney, Australia. The PL-7 was the brainchild of Italian aircraft designer Luigi Pellarini. Pellarini was not a man constrained by convention: His previous design, a flying car, was marketed in post-World War II Italy during a time when most Italians couldn’t afford so much as a motor scooter. It failed. (Not entirely his fault. Sixty-five years later, nobody has successfully marketed a flying car.) He sought greener pastures in Australia, where he was engaged to design an agricultural airplane. His solutions made practical sense, even if they didn’t look like anything that had flown before.</p>

<p>Pellarini reasoned that a topdressing aircraft—a cropduster—should carry as much payload as possible and still operate out of any patch of ground close to the worksite. He started with a large, steel, barrel-shaped tank and began adding. Attach points for a set of biplane wings and a tricycle landing gear were welded on. He figured that the rear fuselage—often corroded by chemicals in cropdusters—was there only to provide an attachment for the tail, so he dispensed with it altogether and hung two sets of tail surfaces on narrow booms projecting aft from the wings. This had the added benefit of allowing space for a loading truck to be backed between the tails where it could fill the hopper while the engine was running, keeping turnaround time to a minimum (agricultural airplanes don’t make money when they are on the ground). The pilot was perched on top of the aft end of the tank, giving him a clear view of the ground behind the lower wing. Racks beneath the lower wings could be used for additional payload, fuel, or to airdrop supplies without landing—a useful feature in a rough country where just delivering a bundle of fence posts could take a mounted man with a pack animal a full day.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/MCFDISAwJlwLZaz-PRICtnESkSE=/fit-in/1072x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/bd/be/bdbe40b6-1c75-4b00-97eb-8279e8484c36/11d_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-img_3640_live.jpg" alt="The Ugliest Airplane: An Appreciation" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      Nick Wills taxis at Temora Airport last September.

    
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The PL-7 was not a small airplane. The top wing spanned 41 feet and it weighed 5,000 pounds loaded, so it required a significant amount of power to do its job. The expedient solution for that challenge was the Armstrong Siddeley Cheetah, a British seven-cylinder, 400-horsepower radial engine. The Cheetah powered the Avro Anson, the most common multi-engine trainer in the British empire. Thousands of twin-engine Ansons were built, so Cheetahs were cheap and widely available.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/z_sVZc20DZ_CyV-TE-NiOOyozdo=/fit-in/1072x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/0f/8e/0f8ed2da-9f6d-4285-a55c-b8efab8640e4/11g_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-conroy-ac3q9259_live.jpg" alt="The Ugliest Airplane: An Appreciation" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      Ian Bell banks over Temora Airport, NSW, Australia after a flight display in October 2018. An AirTruk’s widely spaced tail booms allow a farm vehicle to pull between to fill its  hopper.


    
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>The resulting prototype was hard on the eyes but performed well. Northern Air Services could not find the financing they needed to fully develop the airplane and advertised to sell the project, complete with the flying prototype and 200 Cheetah engines. Before they could find a buyer, however, the prototype was lost in a hangar fire in 1958.</p>

<p>Worthington and Bennett enticed Pellarini to New Zealand to design a new airplane based on the same ideas that had worked on the PL-7. To keep costs down, he used as many parts as he could from another military trainer, the North American Harvard (known to Americans as the T-6 or SNJ). The New Zealand air force was putting its fleet of Harvards up for bid, and Bennett Aircraft, based in Te Kuiti, New Zealand, bought 40 of them. A crew stripped off engines, wheels and brakes, control rods, and canopy components, all of which were to be incorporated into Pellarini’s PL-11, dubbed the Airtruck. Like the PL-7, the PL-11 was essentially a flying fertilizer tank, but this one was a monoplane. The cockpit was moved from the rear of the tank to high atop the front of it, almost above the 600-hp Pratt &amp; Whitney radial engine. The signature twin tail booms remained. The PL-11 was New Zealand’s first natively designed and built commercial airplane, but it proved difficult to get government officials to approve it for production. Although the first Airtruck flew in 1960, three years elapsed before it was issued an airworthiness certificate.</p>

<p>The delay effectively killed the project. After two years of struggling with an intransigent bureaucracy, Pellarini left in disgust and returned to Australia. Bennett succeeded in building a second example in 1968, but by then the PL-11’s time had passed.</p>

<figure>
  
    <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/f7nY6cJ-as1C8FMVQXcEJ0O8rXQ=/fit-in/1072x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/34/9b/349b370b-7e97-4399-9389-8348c7065969/11a_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-kingsfordsmithservicepl7tanker_live.jpg" alt="The Ugliest Airplane: An Appreciation" loading="lazy">
  

  <figcaption>
    
      The prototype Kingsford-Smith PL-7 agricultural tanker in its first flight in September 1956 at Bankstown Airport, Sydney, Australia. 
    
    
  </figcaption>
</figure>
<p>Pellarini’s next airplane was the Australian-built PL-12. It was similar to the PL-11, but this time there was no call to use parts from old military airplanes. Splitting the difference between the biplane PL-7 and the monoplane PL-11, the PL-12 was a sesquiplane, with a small lower wing mounting the main landing gear. An American flat-six Continental engine of 285-horsepower was fitted, lowering the thrust line to the point that the pilot, perched at the crest of the stubby fuselage, looked through the very top of the prop arc. Down in the depths of the fuselage, behind the hopper, a tiny cabin could be outfitted with a pair of seats so the airplane could ferry a complete working crew—pilot, loader driver, and helper—to remote strips. (It would have been a nasty trip. Australian Sam Richards remembers a short trip in the lower “cabin” as being very noisy and cramped. “As a bonus,” he says, “when the flaps come down for landing the only exit is blocked. You can’t see a thing so you’re left hoping the pilot gets it right and you’re not trapped in the wreckage.”)</p>

<p>The result was a sturdy workhorse that could lift its own empty weight over again, even with the small, economical engine. In 1965, the TransAvia Corporation formed to develop and produce the PL-12 “AirTruk” (spelling changed to avoid a conflict with the Bennett airplane). TransAvia tried to get Australian government support while they developed an aircraft construction industry that could compete in world markets. Demonstrator AirTruks flew to Southeast Asia, India, and Europe; and one was shipped to the United States.</p>

<p>Pilot reaction was positive, despite the decidedly weird appearance. Stephen Death’s first agricultural flying job was piloting an AirTruk for his father’s air spraying service in Albury, New South Wales. “My father Keith adopted AirTruks when they first appeared in 1967 and I started flying them in 1983, fresh from my agricultural rating,” Death remembers. “I quickly learnt that it was not a fast aircraft, especially with spray booms and a wind-driven pump attached. The dual outlet doors on the bottom gave a very good pattern when spreading superphosphate. They were slow in the climb and sluggish when they were heavy, but still gave great feedback to the pilot.</p>

<p>“I am sure that the forgiving nature of the AirTruk saved me during my early [agricultural] flying career. Our company still operates a pair of AirTruks, using them as backup aircraft for busy periods. Even after 4,000 hours in type, I still enjoy flying them, either for work or just for fun.”</p>


    
        
  
    <div>
            
              
                
                  <div>
                    <figure>
                      <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/Is-YuQO91uxAbmyRNmSN_29ryv0=/fit-in/1072x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/ce/79/ce792768-df90-41c1-a92a-f62f5bf173df/11c_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-ian_eaa102da-e371-4487-8018_live.jpg" alt="">

                      <div>
                        <p><span></span> / <span></span></p>

                        
                      </div>
                      
                      <figcaption>
                        Ian Bell bought AirTruk tail number VH-TRJ not for work but for fun.
                        
                      </figcaption>
                      
                    </figure>
                  </div>
                
              
                
                  <div>
                    <figure>
                      <img src="https://th-thumbnailer.cdn-si-edu.com/ayg4w_BXdQZ6dpeeePNk-05MywQ=/fit-in/1072x0/https://tf-cmsv2-smithsonianmag-media.s3.amazonaws.com/filer/c2/5e/c25e4bef-5952-48ee-bf59-5924a05c068b/11f_dj2022_ugliestshowplane-_conroy-ac3q9573_live.jpg" alt="">

                      <div>
                        <p><span></span> / <span></span></p>

                        
                      </div>
                      
                      <figcaption>
                        In 2018 at Temora, Stephen Death flies a 1983 AirTruk used for spreading superphosphate fertilizer.
                        
                      </figcaption>
                      
                    </figure>
                  </div>
                
              
            
          </div>
  

    

<p>But the airplane never became popular—although it became briefly famous when a heavily made-up example starred in 1985’s <em>Mad Max Beyond Thunderdome</em>. In the end, neither government funding nor significant foreign sales developed. Proposals for air ambulance and armed, forward-air-control versions also came to naught. With increasing competition from American designs, AirTruk production ceased in 1988 after a 120-strong production run. Agricultural airplanes are flown hard and thus tend to have short lives, and today the AirTruk has almost vanished.</p>

<p>Almost. Besides the pair Death operates, rancher and vineyard owner Ian Bell owns another that he flies just for the pleasure of flying it.</p>

<p>“The AirTruk first attracted my attention when I was a young boy,” Bell says. “Our family farm had an airstrip we used for weed spraying and fertilizer applications. Among the many types of aircraft being used was the AirTruk. [It] took my eye because it was so different. Ten years ago I had the chance to buy a well-maintained example, and I have enjoyed flying and showing it ever since.”</p>

<p>The AirTruk has a few strange features, Bell explains, but flying it is not so different from conventional designs. “One of the biggest differences is the unique view from the cockpit. There is literally nothing in front of you. The pilot is above both the engine and the load, and is surrounded by a steel tube truss for maximum safety. In the air, control response, despite the unusual configuration, is entirely orthodox. Landings, with that rugged landing gear and unlimited visibility, are easy.”</p>

<p>Death’s airplanes are the last AirTruks spraying fertilizer, but the ugly duckling has found a new role: airshow performer. Along with fellow pilot Nick Wills, Death teams with Bell to perform as a three-ship airshow act. Bell has another AirTruk in Death’s shop undergoing restoration, so they hope to soon show off a four-ship diamond formation.</p>

<p>Today at age 50-plus, the AirTruk lives the life a lot of us could envy: a little work, a little play, and a lot of pleasure for those who use it for either purpose.</p>



<p><em>Ken Scott lives on an airpark in Oregon where, with help from his wife Camilla and hangar poodle FoPaw, he builds, flies, and writes about airplanes.</em></p>

        

        

        
          
  <div>
      <p>Get the latest stories in your inbox every weekday.</p>
      
    </div>


        

        

        
          


  

  


        

         
        

        
          
        

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is my plane a 737 Max? (446 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ismyplanea737max.com/</link>
            <guid>38928951</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 17:30:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ismyplanea737max.com/">https://www.ismyplanea737max.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38928951">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p><span>​</span></p><p>Flight Number</p></div><p><span>Nearest flight (live, scheduled or landed) with a given flight number. Schedules change and equipment swaps are common. Double check your reservation for the latest aircraft type running on your route.</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Building an e-ink picture frame that displays an iCloud photo album (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ben.page/eink</link>
            <guid>38928277</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 16:45:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ben.page/eink">https://ben.page/eink</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38928277">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>  <p>For Christmas, I gave my parents this e-ink picture frame (built from an old e-reader) that cycles through photos from a shared iCloud photo album:</p><div><article><p><span>Wrote a blog post about reverse-engineering iCloud photo albums and rooting the Nook! </span><a href="https://ben.page/eink" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ben.page/eink</a></p><div><article><p><span>Made an e-ink picture frame for my parents using an old e-reader! It auto-updates with pictures from a shared iCloud photo album:</span></p></article></div></article></div><p>It's a re-worked version of a gift that I gave to my girlfriend in October, except that one was in a smaller frame that fell apart pretty quickly:</p><p><img src="https://ben.page/posts/eink/IMG_9398%20Large.jpeg" alt="" title=""></p><p>I rebuilt hers to be more solid, and built one for my parents at the same time. Here's how I did it:</p><h2>The e-reader</h2><p>For this project I went with a Nook Simple Touch Reader. You can find them on eBay or Facebook Marketplace for $10-$30 used.</p><p><img src="https://ben.page/posts/eink/image.png" alt="" title=""></p><p>The reason to go with a Nook instead of a Kindle or another e-reader is that Nooks run Android under the hood. That means they're far easier to root and to run Android apps on.</p><p>For that part, I followed <a href="https://shkspr.mobi/blog/2020/02/turn-an-old-ereader-into-an-information-screen-nook-str/">this wonderful post by Terence Eden</a>. The process was quite straightforward; the only thing to note is that you'll need a microSD card.</p><p>After you get it running Android, as the post describes, you can run an ancient Android app called Electric Sign. This app allows you to put any website on the Nook's screen and have it refresh at a given interval, with a catch: the Nook doesn't support SSL. Therefore I had to set up a website that uses <code>http://</code> instead of <code>https://</code>, which is remarkably difficult in this day and age. (I had to set up a custom Nginx server, because you can't use something like Vercel.)</p><p>But once that part was done, I just had to put the website URL into the Electric Sign app on the Nook and I was all set!</p><h2>The frame</h2><p>I bought <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09ZQ9GQ95">this pack of 8x10 frames off Amazon</a>, but in general what I was looking for was a frame that was large but could hold a 5x7 picture with a matte. That's because the Nook's display was more or less 5x7, but I needed a big frame (8x10) to hold the sides and charging cable coming out the bottom.</p><p>I simply jammed the Nook into the frame and forced the latches on the back shut, with the cable sticking out the bottom. It surprisingly fits the Nook, albeit with some bulging in the back.</p><p>If you look closely, the black bezels at the top and bottom of the Nook would show through the 5x7 hole, so I added some white card stock to have them blend in a bit better.</p><h2>iCloud photo album</h2><p>I wanted to source the images from a shared iCloud photo album. That way, I could share the album with my parents, and they could add new photos that would show up on the frame right from their Photos app.</p><p>iCloud photo albums have no API. However, if you share an iCloud photo album to a public link, you can use the Developer Tools to inspect the API requests Apple is making to get the photos. If you replicate those requests, you too can load the photos from the shared iCloud album (as long as the album stays publicly shared).</p><p>Here's my <a href="https://laravel.com/">Laravel</a> code that I used, for reference:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>$webstream </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Http</span><span>::</span><span>post</span><span>(</span><span>'</span><span>https://p01-sharedstreams.icloud.com/12345678/sharedstreams/webstream</span><span>'</span><span>, [</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>'</span><span>streamCtag</span><span>'</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>null</span></span>
<span><span>]);</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>$photoGuids </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>collect</span><span>($webstream</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>json</span><span>()[</span><span>'</span><span>photos</span><span>'</span><span>])</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>pluck</span><span>(</span><span>'</span><span>photoGuid</span><span>'</span><span>);</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>// I wanted the highest quality versions, so those are the checksums I collected for later. </span></span>
<span><span>$checksums </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>collect</span><span>($webstream</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>json</span><span>()[</span><span>'</span><span>photos</span><span>'</span><span>])</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>function</span><span> ($photo) {</span></span>
<span><span>    $maxFileSize </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>;</span></span>
<span><span>    $maxFileSizeChecksum </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>null</span><span>;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>foreach</span><span> ($photo[</span><span>'</span><span>derivatives</span><span>'</span><span>] </span><span>as</span><span> $derivative) {</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>if</span><span> ($derivative[</span><span>'</span><span>fileSize</span><span>'</span><span>] </span><span>&gt;</span><span> $maxFileSize) {</span></span>
<span><span>            $maxFileSize </span><span>=</span><span> $derivative[</span><span>'</span><span>fileSize</span><span>'</span><span>];</span></span>
<span><span>            $maxFileSizeChecksum </span><span>=</span><span> $derivative[</span><span>'</span><span>checksum</span><span>'</span><span>];</span></span>
<span><span>        }</span></span>
<span><span>    }</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>return</span><span> $maxFileSizeChecksum;</span></span>
<span><span>});</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>$assets </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>Http</span><span>::</span><span>post</span><span>(</span><span>'</span><span>https://p01-sharedstreams.icloud.com/12345678/sharedstreams/webasseturls</span><span>'</span><span>, [</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>'</span><span>photoGuids</span><span>'</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> $photoGuids,</span></span>
<span><span>]);</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>$urls </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>collect</span><span>($assets</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>json</span><span>()[</span><span>'</span><span>items</span><span>'</span><span>])</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>-&gt;</span><span>filter</span><span>(</span><span>function</span><span> ($item, $key) </span><span>use</span><span> ($checksums) {</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>return</span><span> $checksums</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>contains</span><span>($key);</span></span>
<span><span>    })</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>-&gt;</span><span>map</span><span>(</span><span>function</span><span> ($item) {</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>return</span><span> </span><span>'</span><span>https://</span><span>'</span><span> </span><span>.</span><span> $item[</span><span>'</span><span>url_location</span><span>'</span><span>] </span><span>.</span><span> $item[</span><span>'</span><span>url_path</span><span>'</span><span>];</span></span>
<span><span>    })</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>-&gt;</span><span>values</span><span>();</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>$url </span><span>=</span><span> $urls</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>random</span><span>(); </span><span>// Pick a random photo from the album. </span></span></code></pre></div><p>From this, I just inserted the image into a very simple HTML page, using the <a href="https://wsrv.nl/">wsrv.nl</a> API to crop the photo to the exact dimensions of the Nook (600x800 pixels):</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>img</span><span> </span><span>src</span><span>=</span><span>"</span><span>{{</span><span> </span><span>route</span><span>(</span><span>'</span><span>image</span><span>'</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>'</span><span>url</span><span>'</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://wsrv.nl/?url=</span><span>{$encodedUrl}</span><span>&amp;w=600&amp;h=800&amp;fit=cover&amp;mod=1.2</span><span>"</span><span>],</span><span> </span><span>false</span><span>)</span><span> </span><span>}}</span><span>"</span><span> /&gt;</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I did brighten the images a little (using <code>mod=1.2</code>) so they'd look better on the e-ink screen, and also you'll notice that I'm going through an <code>image</code> route — that's a route that proxies Apple's images because those images would normally use <code>https</code> and I need them going through my <code>http</code>-only server so the Nook can load the image.</p><h2>Putting it all together</h2><p>I mounted the Nook in the frame, set the website with the photo from the shared album, and closed it all up with a charging cable so it can stay plugged in all the time. It's been working beautifully so far!</p>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You Don't Need More Resilience. You Need Friends. and Money (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2024-01-09/what-you-ve-heard-about-resilience-is-probably-wrong</link>
            <guid>38928265</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 16:45:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2024-01-09/what-you-ve-heard-about-resilience-is-probably-wrong">https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2024-01-09/what-you-ve-heard-about-resilience-is-probably-wrong</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38928265">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
    <section>
        <h3>Why did this happen?</h3>
        <p>Please make sure your browser supports JavaScript and cookies and that you are not
            blocking them from loading.
            For more information you can review our <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Terms of
                Service</a> and <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Cookie Policy</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <h3>Need Help?</h3>
        <p>For inquiries related to this message please <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/feedback">contact
            our support team</a> and provide the reference ID below.</p>
        <p>Block reference ID:</p>
    </section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Samsung forecasts 85% drop in profit as chip sales falter (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://koreajoongangdaily.joins.com/news/2024-01-09/business/industry/Samsung-forecasts-85-drop-in-profit-for-last-year-amid-chip-slump/1954130</link>
            <guid>38928182</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 16:40:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://koreajoongangdaily.joins.com/news/2024-01-09/business/industry/Samsung-forecasts-85-drop-in-profit-for-last-year-amid-chip-slump/1954130">https://koreajoongangdaily.joins.com/news/2024-01-09/business/industry/Samsung-forecasts-85-drop-in-profit-for-last-year-amid-chip-slump/1954130</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38928182">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="doc">
                    
                    
                                            <div>              <p><img alt="A worker waters a flower bed beside the logo of Samsung Electronics at the company's headquarters in Suwon, Gyeonggi. [REUTERS]" src="https://koreajoongangdaily.joins.com/data/photo/2024/01/09/88a7357d-4603-4a5b-b3e8-953222f43174.jpg">          <span></span>                  </p>                  <p>A worker waters a flower bed beside the logo of Samsung Electronics at the company's headquarters in Suwon, Gyeonggi. [REUTERS]</p>              </div>        &nbsp;  <p>   Samsung Electronics forecast an 84.9 percent yearly decline in operating profit last year as a severe cyclical downturn in the semiconductor industry eroded its profitability.   </p><p>   &nbsp;     The Suwon, Gyeonggi-based tech giant announced in a preliminary earnings report Tuesday that expects to post an operating profit of 6.5 trillion won ($5 billion), a number that is the lowest since 2008 and below the market consensus of 7.5 trillion won.  </p><p>   &nbsp;     The company projects an annual sales figure of 258.2 trillion won, down 14.6 percent on year. That forecast falls short of the market estimate of 262 trillion won.  </p><p>   &nbsp;     The preliminary forecast did not include detailed breakdowns.   <br>   <b>&nbsp;</b>  <br>   But Kim Dong-won, an analyst at KB Securities, estimates that Samsung’s memory chip business generated a combined 15 trillion won of operating losses throughout the year, though profits in the smartphone and panel-making businesses helped the company remain in the black.  <br>   <b>&nbsp;</b>  <br>   Experts and market analysts both in Korea and abroad believe the current downturn hit its bottom last year and will rebound this year with robust demand expected in the advanced AI segment.   <br>   <b><br></b>  <br>   “The memory chip business generated 15 trillion won of operating losses in 2023, but it will likely post 14 trillion won of profit in 2024 by adding 29 trillion won in total,” Kim said.   </p><p>   &nbsp;     The market changes reflect progress that Samsung made in reducing inventory and increasing shipments in the fourth quarter.&nbsp;  </p><p>   &nbsp;     Shipments of dynamic random-access memory and NAND flash memory chips increased by 30 percent based on bit growth, and inventory levels had fallen by more than 50 percent by the end of last year compared to the beginning, according to Kim.   </p><p>   &nbsp;     In the fourth quarter alone, Samsung Electronics' operating profit dropped by 35 percent to 2.8 trillion won, while sales dropped 4.9 percent to 67 trillion won, according to the early earnings result.   </p><p>   &nbsp;     Kim Young-gun, an analyst at Mirae Asset Securities, estimates that Samsung’s semiconductor business recorded 2.2 trillion won in operating loss during the quarter, while the smartphone and network equipment division posted 2.5 trillion won in profit. The panel-making business brought in 1.9 trillion won of profit, while consumer electronics made 400 billion won, according to Kim of Mirae Asset Securities.   <br>   <b>&nbsp;</b>  <br>   He noted that the chip sector is recovering at a slower-than-expected pace because the growth of shipment and prices centers around a few high-performing semiconductors at a time when overall demand for electronic devices remains weak.   <br>   <b><br></b>  <br>   “There have been improvements in shipments and average selling prices, but the scale was weaker than expected, since a batch of high-end products had been shipped first,” Kim said.   </p><p>   &nbsp;     The final result will be announced by the end of this month.  </p><p> BY PARK EUN-JEE [park.eunjee@joongang.co.kr]</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X Purges Prominent Journalists, Leftists with No Explanation (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.vice.com/en/article/5d948x/x-purges-prominent-journalists-leftists-with-no-explanation</link>
            <guid>38927699</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 16:07:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.vice.com/en/article/5d948x/x-purges-prominent-journalists-leftists-with-no-explanation">https://www.vice.com/en/article/5d948x/x-purges-prominent-journalists-leftists-with-no-explanation</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38927699">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="BodyComponentRenderer"><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p><strong>UPDATE 1/9/24: </strong>Hours after reporting out this initial story, some of the suspended X accounts returned. X has not explained what happened and the affected account owners have no idea why they were briefly suspended. The reinstatement came after notable users such as <a href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1744766353494376749?s=20" target="_blank">George Galloway</a>, a former member of the British Parliament, called out Musk for banning the accounts.</p></span></p><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>Suspended journalist Steven Monacelli told Motherboard that he wasn’t able to contact X. “The only message I received from Twitter was this buggy response to my appeal,” he said. “I think this is the reason I was unbanned. Elon Musk playing customer service rep to a far right misinfo and conspiracy theory poster.” Musk responded to far-right conspiracy theorist Jackson Hinkle’s X post calling out the suspensions before accounts were reinstated. </p></span></p><div data-component="ImageBlock"><div><picture><source media="(min-width: 1000px)" srcset="https://video-images.vice.com/_uncategorized/1704821851398-screenshot20240109-112301.png?resize=20:*"><source media="(min-width: 700px)" srcset="https://video-images.vice.com/_uncategorized/1704821851398-screenshot20240109-112301.png?resize=20:*"><source media="(min-width: 0px)" srcset="https://video-images.vice.com/_uncategorized/1704821851398-screenshot20240109-112301.png?resize=20:*"><img alt="Screenshot_20240109-112301.png" decoding="async" loading="eager" width="1440" height="10115" src="https://www.vice.com/en/article/5d948x/Screenshot_20240109-112301.png"></picture></div><p>Image via Monacelli.</p></div><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The original story follows.</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The X accounts of several prominent journalists and leftist pundits were suspended from the site, formerly known as Twitter, on Tuesday morning with no clear explanation.</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The suspensions affected several journalists and commentators, including <em>Texas Observer</em> journalist Steven Monacelli, Ken Klippensten of The Intercept, podcaster Rob Rousseau, and Alan MacLeod of MintPress News. The landing page for their accounts says it’s been suspended, but does not give any explanation as to why. A message on the profiles simply states “X suspends accounts which violate the X rules.”</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The ban didn’t just hit journalists either. Several prominent-left leaning accounts were also purged from the website, including the account for the TrueAnon podcast and @zei_squirrel, a cartoon squirrel that tweets media criticism of figures like Glenn Greenwald.&nbsp;</p></span></p><p><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>The ban was carried out with no overarching explanation; suspended accounts link to the X terms of service, which cover a wide range of possible violations.&nbsp;</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>“I haven't received any communications from Twitter/X about why I have been suspended,” Monacelli told Motherboard in an email. “I can't think of anything I've posted lately that would be worthy of suspensions. Although I have written multiple critical reports about Twitter/X and Elon Musk.”</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>MacLeod posted a brief explanation of events on his Telegram and Instagram accounts. “Today, without warning or explanation, Twitter suspended my account,” he said. “They told me to check my email for a reason, but no email has been forthcoming. I have never even remotely been involved in any controversy/ been reported/ been stuck in Twitter jail before, so I assume the real reason is political, especially as high-profile leftist accounts like Rob Rousseau and Ze_Squirrel were also targeted today.”</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>This isn't the first time the site has banned reporters. In April, it permanently suspended Wired reporter Dell Cameron after he spoke with a hacker who accessed conservative pundit Matt Walsh’s emails. In December of 2022, it suspended the accounts of ten journalists who’d been critical of site owner Elon Musk.</p></span><span data-component="TextBlock"><p>Motherboard could not reach X for comment, and instead received an automatic email response saying, "Busy now, please check back later."</p></span></p></div><div><p><h3>ORIGINAL REPORTING ON EVERYTHING THAT MATTERS IN YOUR INBOX.</h3></p><p>By signing up, you agree to the<!-- --> <a href="https://vice-web-statics-cdn.vice.com/privacy-policy/en_us/page/terms-of-use.html">Terms of Use</a> <!-- -->and<!-- --> <a href="https://vice-web-statics-cdn.vice.com/privacy-policy/en_us/page/privacy-policy.html">Privacy Policy</a> <!-- -->&amp; to receive electronic communications from Vice Media Group, which may include marketing promotions, advertisements and sponsored content.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GE Vernova announces order of 674 wind turbines, providing 2.4 GW of power (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ge.com/news/press-releases/ge-vernova-announces-2point4-gw-order-for-pattern-energy-sunzia-wind-project</link>
            <guid>38926978</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 15:05:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ge.com/news/press-releases/ge-vernova-announces-2point4-gw-order-for-pattern-energy-sunzia-wind-project">https://www.ge.com/news/press-releases/ge-vernova-announces-2point4-gw-order-for-pattern-energy-sunzia-wind-project</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38926978">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article_description" data-history-node-id="143328" about="/news/press-releases/ge-vernova-announces-2point4-gw-order-for-pattern-energy-sunzia-wind-project">
              <ul><li><em>Expected to be the largest wind project in US history, powered by GE’s next generation workhorse turbine 3.6-154</em></li><li><em>Record order for GE wind with 674 turbines, providing 2.4 GW of power generation, bringing GE Vernova installed base with Pattern Energy to 4.3 GW</em></li><li><em>Reinforces GE Vernova’s commitment to revitalize and enhance American manufacturing – with growth fueled by the IRA</em></li><li><em>GE Vernova bringing expertise across energy transition to project, from turbine technology &amp; services to grid technology/modelling and financial services</em></li></ul><p><strong>Schenectady, New York: January 9, 2024</strong> – GE Vernova’s Onshore Wind business (NYSE: GE) today announced a new equipment and long-term services deal with Pattern Energy to supply 674 3.6-154<sup>1</sup> wind turbines that will provide more than 2.4 gigawatts (GW) of power at the SunZia Wind project in New Mexico.</p><p>SunZia Wind, which is expected to be the largest wind project in the Western Hemisphere at over 3.5 GW total project size, will bring GE Vernova’s installed base with Pattern Energy in North America to approximately 4.3 GW upon completion. The order, which was received in the fourth quarter of 2023, is the largest single onshore wind turbine order ever received by GE Vernova, both in terms of quantity of turbines and gigawatts of power generation, upon completion.</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/scott-strazik/" target="_blank"><strong>Scott Strazik</strong></a><strong>, CEO of GE Vernova</strong>, said, “<em>We are pleased to support Pattern Energy on this monumental project that reinforces the key role wind power has in delivering renewable energy to meet the growing demand for power in the Western U.S. and in accelerating the energy transition. The project is a great example of how the policy certainty created by the IRA is helping to drive significant investments in the U.S. wind power market. I want to congratulate our teams across GE Vernova for all the work that has and will go into bringing a project of this scale and magnitude to life.</em>”</p><p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/vicabate/" target="_blank"><strong>Vic Abate</strong></a><strong>, Chief Technology Officer, GE and CEO, GE Vernova’s Wind business</strong>, said, “<em>This project demonstrates GE Vernova’s ability to deliver on our workhorse strategy in Onshore Wind – producing fewer variants in large quantities at scale to drive quality and reliability across the fleet for our customers. We are proud to partner with our customer, Pattern Energy, on this historic project that will deliver the critical renewable energy required to meet the growing demand for power in the Western U.S.</em>”</p><p>The 3.6-154 turbine is one of GE’s next generation workhorse products. Designed specifically for the U.S., the 3.6-154 delivers the highest efficiency in the market, with an optimized size for ease of logistics and installation. The 3.6-154 is built on the back of the 2.8-127 – the #1 turbine in the world over the last two years, according to the Woodmac 2022 OEM report, with more than 200 million operating hours of experience. The result of three years of research and development, this product is expected to bring recent innovations in turbine and blade design, including the digital blade certificate, an AI-trained blade manufacturing process designed to produce industry leading quality. The 3.6-154 launches as the most tested and validated turbine in GE’s history – a robust turbine to power the domestic energy transition.</p><p>GE Vernova and Pattern Energy’s collaboration on SunZia spans the last 18 months and includes collaborative development and supply chain work to optimize site layouts and performance while minimizing unnecessary variants – following GE Vernova’s workhorse philosophy.</p><p>“<em>We are proud to expand on our mutual installed base with GE in North America to more than 4 GW,</em>” said <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/hunter-armistead-0502a313/" target="_blank"><strong>Hunter Armistead</strong></a><strong>, CEO of Pattern Energy</strong>. “<em>From the beginning this was a truly collaborative approach with GE to design an optimal site that maximizes turbine performance and optimizes fleet consistency. Nacelles and towers for the GE turbine are being domestically produced right here in the United States, helping SunZia create thousands of new jobs in manufacturing and construction. We’re proud to be building this milestone project together with GE that will bring clean energy to 3 million Americans.</em>”</p><p>The project will be supplied through GE Vernova’s nacelle facility in Pensacola, Florida, as well as tower manufacturing facilities in Belen, New Mexico, Pueblo, Colorado, and Amarillo, Texas, reinforcing GE Vernova’s focus on taking full advantage of the Inflation Reduction Act to revitalize and enhance American manufacturing. GE Vernova announced in <a href="https://www.ge.com/news/press-releases/ge-vernova-announces-50-million-investment-200-wind-manufacturing-jobs-in-new-york" target="_blank">May of 2023</a> that it plans to invest $50 million and add 200 additional union jobs as part of creating a new manufacturing assembly line for its Onshore Wind business in Schenectady, New York, and announced that the first turbine was produced by that facility in <a href="https://www.ge.com/news/press-releases/ge-vernova-produces-first-onshore-wind-turbine-at-new-york-facility" target="_blank">November of 2023</a>.</p><p><strong>Abate </strong>said, “<em>Mega projects like SunZia, coupled with the IRA, are enabling our continued investments in wind technology, domestic manufacturing, and product quality. These investments are aiding the country’s efforts to decarbonize the electric grid in support of climate change goals</em>.”</p><p>In support of this wind turbine mega deal, GE Vernova was able to provide Pattern Energy with both high tech consulting services (Consulting Services), and <a href="https://patternenergy.com/pattern-energy-closes-11-billion-financing-of-largest-clean-energy-infrastructure-project-in-u-s-history/" target="_blank">financial services</a> (Financial Services) that contributed to the project’s launch.</p><p>GE Vernova’s 3.6-154 turbine is one of several workhorse products that bring together focused design, efficient supply, reduced complexity, improved reliability, and bankability to offer best-in-class products. GE Vernova’s Onshore Wind business has been the number one provider of onshore wind turbine installs in the U.S. for the last five years according to the American Clean Power Association, and currently has a fleet of more than 55,000 wind turbines installed around the world.</p><p><em>1 – GE's 3.6 MW turbine with a 154-meter rotor is what we refer to as the 3.6-154.</em></p><p>###</p><p><strong>About GE Vernova</strong><br>GE Vernova is a planned, purpose-built global energy company that includes Power, Wind, and Electrification businesses and is supported by its accelerator businesses of Advanced Research, Consulting Services, and Financial Services. Building on over 130 years of experience tackling the world’s challenges, GE Vernova is uniquely positioned to help lead the energy transition by continuing to electrify the world while simultaneously working to decarbonize it. GE Vernova helps customers power economies and deliver electricity that is vital to health, safety, security, and improved quality of life. GE Vernova is headquartered in Cambridge, Massachusetts, U.S., with more than 80,000 employees across 100+ countries around the world. GE Vernova’s <strong>Onshore Wind</strong> business is a world leader in onshore wind technology. With an installed base of approximately 55,000 turbines around the world, it offers a high-tech product portfolio of turbines for a broad range of site conditions.</p><p>GE Vernova’s mission is embedded in its name – it retains its legacy, “GE,” as an enduring and hard-earned badge of quality and ingenuity. “Ver” / “verde” signal Earth’s verdant and lush ecosystems. “Nova,” from the Latin “novus,” nods to a new, innovative era of lower carbon energy. Supported by the Company Purpose, <em>The Energy to Change the World</em>, GE Vernova will help deliver a more affordable, reliable, sustainable, and secure energy future. Learn more: <a href="https://www.gevernova.com/" target="_blank">GE Vernova</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/gevernova/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a>.</p>

              
                            <p>For media inquiries, please contact: </p>
                            <address>
            Tim Brown
                          <br>
              Media Relations, Wind
                                      <br>
              GE Vernova
                                      <br>
              +1 302 509 9352
                                                  <br>
              <a href="https://www.ge.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#73071a1e5d11011c041d3314165d101c1e"><span data-cfemail="681c0105460a1a071f06280f0d460b0705">[email&nbsp;protected]</span></a>
                                  </address>
                          <hr>

                                                  <h6>business unit</h6>
                  
              
                        
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple tells EU it has five different App Stores, not just one (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://9to5mac.com/2024/01/09/five-different-app-stores/</link>
            <guid>38926476</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 14:21:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/01/09/five-different-app-stores/">https://9to5mac.com/2024/01/09/five-different-app-stores/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38926476">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
			<img src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/01/five-different-App-Stores.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/01/five-different-App-Stores.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/01/five-different-App-Stores.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/01/five-different-App-Stores.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/01/five-different-App-Stores.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" width="1600" height="800" alt="Five different App Stores | App icons depicted as physical building blocks" fetchpriority="high">
	
	</figure>

<p>While <a href="https://9to5mac.com/guides/aapl/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a> is <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/12/13/apple-alternative-app-stores-iphone/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">making behind-the-scenes preparations</a> for allowing third-party app stores to comply with Europe’s <a href="https://9to5mac.com/guides/antitrust/">antitrust</a> requirements, the company is continuing to make arguments about why it shouldn’t have to.</p>



<p>Latest among these is the suggestion that the <a href="https://9to5mac.com/guides/app-store/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">App Store</a> shouldn’t be viewed as a ‘platform’ as the company actually operates five different app stores … </p>



<h2 id="h-a-quick-recap">A quick recap</h2>



<p>Antitrust regulators have long been eyeing Apple’s exclusive control over the sale of third-party iPhone apps. Whether you’re a consumer wanting to buy an iPhone app, or a developer wanting to sell one, there’s only one place you can do so: the App Store.</p>



<p>Apple has complete control over which apps it allows into the&nbsp;App Store, and the company sets its own terms – including its 15% or 30% commission – which developers and consumers alike have to accept. Many regulators, including the European Union, consider this a breach of competition law.</p>



<p>The Digital Markets Act (DMA) specifically states that the App Store is covered by the law. This means that&nbsp;<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/09/06/digital-markets-act-antitrust-law/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple must permit competition in the iPhone app market</a>, and it’s most likely that the only way the company can fully comply with this legislation is to allow competing app stores on the iPhone. The deadline for compliance is April of this year, and Apple has long been <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/12/13/apple-alternative-app-stores-iphone/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">working on plans to meet this requirement</a>.</p>



<h2 id="h-apple-says-it-has-five-different-app-stores">Apple says it has five different app stores</h2>



<p>The DMA applies to what are described as technology “platforms,” and the EU separately defines which company’s products and services fall within this term. Apple’s App Store is one of them.</p>



<p>Not so, said Apple, as the App Store isn’t a single entity. <em><a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/apple-disputes-eu-rules-labelling-its-5-app-stores-one-service-2024-01-08/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Reuters</a></em> reports on the argument the iPhone maker yesterday made in a European court hearing.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The European Commission made “material factual errors, in concluding that the applicant’s five App Stores are a single core platform service,” Apple said in its plea to the Luxembourg-based General Court, Europe’s second-highest.</p>



<p>The company in its argument to the EU competition enforcer said it operates five App Stores on iPhones, iPads, Mac computers, Apple TVs and Apple Watches, with each designed to distribute apps for a specific operating system and Apple device.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>While iMessage has <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/12/06/eus-imessage-antitrust-investigation-looks-set-to-rule-in-apples-favor/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">so far not been deemed a platform</a> – as <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/09/04/imessage-app-store-gatekeeper-not-big-enough/">it doesn’t have enough regular users</a> in Europe (WhatsApp is far more popular there, even among iPhone users) – Apple continues to make precautionary arguments against this changing in future.</p>



<p><em>Reuters’</em> summary makes it sound like Apple’s case here is rather sketchier!</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The company contends that iMessage [doesn’t fall within the scope of the DMA] as it is not a fee-based service and it does not monetise it via the sale of hardware devices nor via the processing of personal data.</p>
</blockquote>



<h2 id="h-9to5mac-s-take">9to5Mac’s Take</h2>



<p>The plurality of app stores probably ultimately makes little difference, as the iPhone App Store would itself be large enough to quality as a platform. But Apple <em>may</em> succeed in arguing that its app stores for other devices should be excluded. (The Mac App Store should already be safe, as users are free to download and install apps direct from developers.)</p>



<p>The argument that Apple doesn’t monetize iMessage “via the sale of hardware devices” seems more of a stretch, since the company is <a href="https://9to5google.com/2021/04/08/apple-imessage-android/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">on record as knowing the power of iMessage to sell iPhones</a> and keep users locked into the Apple ecosystem.</p>



<p>The Cupertino company likely wants to throw as many arguments as possible onto the table, however, in case its usage numbers are questioned. Personally, I suspect <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/16/apple-rcs-coming-to-iphone/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">its U-turn on RCS support</a> is <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/17/apples-rcs-announcement/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">probably enough to protect it here</a>.</p>



<p><em>Photo by&nbsp;<a href="https://unsplash.com/@ilgmyzin?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Ilgmyzin</a>&nbsp;on&nbsp;<a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/a-pile-of-colorful-dice-Xe21OFRpqvk?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Unsplash</a></em></p>
	<p>
		<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBggKMLOFATDAGg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add 9to5Mac to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
	</p>
	<p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://9to5mac.com/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nebula is an open-source and free-to-use modern C++ game engine (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/gscept/nebula</link>
            <guid>38925928</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 13:29:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/gscept/nebula">https://github.com/gscept/nebula</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38925928">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:gscept/nebula" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="EvGTDpNBGiPRQV01DwsT_f_ZAEmAPNcyjaAWswTT5p46qR6lbE-IRR0bFtzhQaL8qe5AFb_L9XCCOeoHpHn1Gg" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="gscept/nebula" data-current-org="gscept" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=fQXz%2BtVXUkwsRGqwRj8%2FYaoIcxQnPpCNLXLK0D%2BtalSVoeIyncDHZEtI9hxCKhajKyfr9AQ%2BozOAHRGmW7%2Bc3Ai5MRtj6gOzj3z7EM99%2BOp4NmmAnZ4vujaYSekxkNkWLxdIb0cdzq6Ls4l%2FoLl0xWttT8INK03wiKfCOoqHIrc%2B2o4jkNHTNddSXB%2Fn4pd3UQUVksmiCMz2a6SLIM7CBIgTeEKn%2BHnO5%2Fkp3QLkgfuivMiGqxtbN3vwt45prJ9xa28Jo8ANDGabChyqRXfpaNNHHFM8ded%2F%2Fw6jsUcjXjl%2B1wQad1sYWnAILhMhLvs0HoNETSm2R3dXBXmDhsjBkq%2BzZEzA4DnTdOVU8bSUP05XA4Mtxlhvq2V5sGugFan6%2FPcvn6oRtovCXsV8d6Gf5Kuo6ET0MEgfJEmsJh63mL%2B3IvYld%2BlfV%2BWkhHFiNDHliC3VeTCJX%2Fzd6ILzQD0yasdCTGfJ5se5QZ4N1ldX6BoE07d2qZirAO9Ru5%2FqLblhpSmD46Ssebmtsw%3D%3D--YmT34zkcUKKfmIfG--BMcB3VSYFbuJUi%2BtzMtwUg%3D%3D&quot; />">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=gscept%2Fnebula" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/gscept/nebula&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="40736aa90cf5c6a420eb0284bdbb5946abba20af746f217dd7d3331cacc85b21" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
              Sign up
            </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GitHub Having Issues Today (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.githubstatus.com/incidents/pxg3dz4yg7lp</link>
            <guid>38925704</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 13:05:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.githubstatus.com/incidents/pxg3dz4yg7lp">https://www.githubstatus.com/incidents/pxg3dz4yg7lp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38925704">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <div>
      <p>Incident with Issues, API Requests, Pull Requests, Actions, Pages, Git Operations, Webhooks, Packages and Codespaces</p>
      
    </div>

    <div>
      <!-- postmortem if it's published -->

      <!-- incident updates in reverse order -->
        <div>
          <p>
            Resolved
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>This incident has been resolved.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704811245000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:40</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Pull Requests is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704811137000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:38</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Packages is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704811038000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:37</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Git Operations is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704810773000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:32</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Codespaces is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704810474000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:27</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Actions is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704810351000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:25</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>API Requests is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704810253000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:24</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Issues is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704810242000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:24</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Webhooks is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704810001000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:20</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Pages is operating normally.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704809788000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:16</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>API Requests is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704809755000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:15</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>5xx error rates remain elevated but are seeing a downward trend with many services fully recovered. We will continue monitoring the situation and keep users updated on progress toward full recovery.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704809737000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:15</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Actions is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704809498000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">14:11</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>We are experiencing an elevated rate of 5xx errors on the order of 1-5% being returned from numerous APIs across the site. The issue has been isolated to one datacenter. We will continue to keep users updated on progress towards mitigation.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704807555000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:39</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Codespaces is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704807354000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:35</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Packages is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704807245000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:34</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Webhooks is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704807095000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:31</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Git Operations is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704806671000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:24</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Pages is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704806617000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:23</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>API Requests is experiencing degraded availability. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704805634000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:07</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>We are an increase in the rate of 5xx errors on the order of 1-3% being returned from numerous APIs across the site. We will continue to keep users updated on progress towards mitigation.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704805558000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:05</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Actions is experiencing degraded availability. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704805540000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:05</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Update
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>Pull Requests is experiencing degraded performance. We are continuing to investigate.</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704805447000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:04</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <p>
            Investigating
          </p>
          <div>
            <p><span>We are investigating reports of degraded performance for Issues and API Requests</span>
            </p>
            <p>
              Posted <span data-datetime-unix="1704805352000"></span>Jan <var data-var="date">09</var>, <var data-var="year">2024</var> - <var data-var="time">13:02</var> UTC
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>

      <!-- affected components -->
        <p>
          This incident affected: Git Operations, API Requests, Webhooks, Issues, Pull Requests, Actions, Packages, Pages, and Codespaces.
        </p>
    </div>

    
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Turing Complete is a game about computer science (259 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://turingcomplete.game/</link>
            <guid>38925307</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 12:22:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://turingcomplete.game/">https://turingcomplete.game/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38925307">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://turingcomplete.game/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google breaks search for Firefox users because of bad UA string sniffing (414 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/webcompat/web-bugs/issues/131916</link>
            <guid>38924300</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 10:04:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/webcompat/web-bugs/issues/131916">https://github.com/webcompat/web-bugs/issues/131916</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38924300">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-view-component="true" id="discussion_bucket">                  <h2>Comments</h2>
<div data-hpc="" data-quote-markdown=".js-comment-body" data-discussion-hovercards-enabled="" data-issue-and-pr-hovercards-enabled="" data-team-hovercards-enabled="">
      <div data-gid="I_kwDOARFbIc57bFPy" data-url="/webcompat/web-bugs/issues/131916/partials/body?issue=131916" data-channel="eyJjIjoiaXNzdWU6MjA3MDY5Njk0NiIsInQiOjE3MDQ4MDUyMDZ9--b6b67f6e6ad5eaa4133933d4bfab59a4a67669268c6ff895fa2f438359103367">

  <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/webcompat-bot/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/webcompat-bot"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/8862693?s=80&amp;u=8ade6e002d8150934377da08d3542b68c20d2682&amp;v=4" width="40" height="40" alt="@webcompat-bot"></a>

</p>

  <div data-body-version="75f369ebb1b0d8aabbaac22e8c2d0ef96ddff93b4cd3f83ffba226defb4c74dd" id="issue-2070696946">

        <task-lists disabled="" sortable="">
<div>
          




<p dir="auto"><strong>URL</strong>: <a href="https://www.google.com/" rel="nofollow">https://www.google.com/</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Browser / Version</strong>: Firefox Mobile 121.0<br>
<strong>Operating System</strong>: Android 13<br>
<strong>Tested Another Browser</strong>: Yes Other</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Problem type</strong>: Site is not usable<br>
<strong>Description</strong>: Page not loading correctly<br>
<strong>Steps to Reproduce</strong>:<br>
The page is blank. The page is blank the page is blank.</p>
<details>
      <summary>View the screenshot</summary>
      <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/16a554571b3cea973d2b7346457a351fa2f31266874ab72e8e3e14ff39ba73b1/68747470733a2f2f776562636f6d7061742e636f6d2f75706c6f6164732f323032342f312f36646264356165652d396339612d346338352d383739342d3564336435626334323336612e6a706567"><img alt="Screenshot" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/16a554571b3cea973d2b7346457a351fa2f31266874ab72e8e3e14ff39ba73b1/68747470733a2f2f776562636f6d7061742e636f6d2f75706c6f6164732f323032342f312f36646264356165652d396339612d346338352d383739342d3564336435626334323336612e6a706567" data-canonical-src="https://webcompat.com/uploads/2024/1/6dbd5aee-9c9a-4c85-8794-5d3d5bc4236a.jpeg"></a>
      </details>
<details>
<summary>Browser Configuration</summary>
<ul dir="auto">
  <li>gfx.webrender.all: false</li><li>gfx.webrender.blob-images: true</li><li>gfx.webrender.enabled: false</li><li>buildID: 20231230165955</li><li>channel: release</li><li>hasTouchScreen: true</li><li>mixed active content blocked: false</li><li>mixed passive content blocked: false</li><li>tracking content blocked: false</li>
</ul>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://webcompat.com/console_logs/2024/1/8c27f8a1-2d2b-455b-9762-9a9686c49bf0" rel="nofollow">View console log messages</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>From <a href="https://webcompat.com/" rel="nofollow">webcompat.com</a> with ❤️</em></p>
      </div>
</task-lists>


        
      </div>

</div>


      <div>
    


      <div data-team-hovercards-enabled="" id="event-11426134262" data-gid="LE_lADOARFbIc57bFPyzwAAAAKoor6U">

    

        <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/webcompat-bot/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/webcompat-bot"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/8862693?s=40&amp;u=8ade6e002d8150934377da08d3542b68c20d2682&amp;v=4" width="20" height="20" alt="@webcompat-bot"></a>
<a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/webcompat-bot/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/webcompat-bot">webcompat-bot</a>




      changed the title
<del>In the moderation queue.</del>

<ins>www.google.com - site is not usable</ins></p><a href="#event-11426134262"><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T07:09:17Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time></a>

  </div>

      <div data-gid="IC_kwDOARFbIc5wNPu2" data-url="/webcompat/web-bugs/comments/IC_kwDOARFbIc5wNPu2/partials/timeline_issue_comment">

  <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/sv-calin/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/sv-calin"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/107036654?s=80&amp;u=ab638d5508e713f1438ae3428d05da7e917001a0&amp;v=4" width="40" height="40" alt="@sv-calin"></a>

</p>


  <div data-body-version="938a20dadbc3cdd6b785f546541cb2cefaf1417123858bc5eb158daf6a0b0be4" id="issuecomment-1882520502">

        <task-lists disabled="" sortable="">
<div>
          <p dir="auto">Thank you for reporting this issue, I was able to reproduce it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/107036654/295126671-843ea799-a12f-4118-91ee-d0c5cb261927.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDQ4MDU1MDUsIm5iZiI6MTcwNDgwNTIwNSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDcwMzY2NTQvMjk1MTI2NjcxLTg0M2VhNzk5LWExMmYtNDExOC05MWVlLWQwYzVjYjI2MTkyNy5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwMTA5JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDEwOVQxMzAwMDVaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1jZjQ2NjJmNDMzZGU5NTFhMjUwYTNlZGU5OGE5ZGM1YTA5MzgyMTRjNGQzOTJmZDlhNGYxNTYxOWY5M2FjMWVlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.xnKo4XcXDLxSFX8JyV06BX9a5sCyFan8lByCDO5NGZo"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/107036654/295126671-843ea799-a12f-4118-91ee-d0c5cb261927.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDQ4MDU1MDUsIm5iZiI6MTcwNDgwNTIwNSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDcwMzY2NTQvMjk1MTI2NjcxLTg0M2VhNzk5LWExMmYtNDExOC05MWVlLWQwYzVjYjI2MTkyNy5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwMTA5JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDEwOVQxMzAwMDVaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1jZjQ2NjJmNDMzZGU5NTFhMjUwYTNlZGU5OGE5ZGM1YTA5MzgyMTRjNGQzOTJmZDlhNGYxNTYxOWY5M2FjMWVlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.xnKo4XcXDLxSFX8JyV06BX9a5sCyFan8lByCDO5NGZo" alt="image"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/107036654/295126702-28a13a90-ad88-4cae-b117-e673b1e53acd.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDQ4MDU1MDUsIm5iZiI6MTcwNDgwNTIwNSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDcwMzY2NTQvMjk1MTI2NzAyLTI4YTEzYTkwLWFkODgtNGNhZS1iMTE3LWU2NzNiMWU1M2FjZC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwMTA5JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDEwOVQxMzAwMDVaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT04ZGFiOTMxZGJkZDkxM2ZkZThjYzU1OTQ3MDdjMTIxNWJmMjU0NTY3YjY5ZjVmNGJlNGE4OGJmNWJhYmFlNGY3JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.9yZNLAb3go_enV2SXIQb0M1AtU2hKN4HbXlAIzJYmbU"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/107036654/295126702-28a13a90-ad88-4cae-b117-e673b1e53acd.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDQ4MDU1MDUsIm5iZiI6MTcwNDgwNTIwNSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDcwMzY2NTQvMjk1MTI2NzAyLTI4YTEzYTkwLWFkODgtNGNhZS1iMTE3LWU2NzNiMWU1M2FjZC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwMTA5JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDEwOVQxMzAwMDVaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT04ZGFiOTMxZGJkZDkxM2ZkZThjYzU1OTQ3MDdjMTIxNWJmMjU0NTY3YjY5ZjVmNGJlNGE4OGJmNWJhYmFlNGY3JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.9yZNLAb3go_enV2SXIQb0M1AtU2hKN4HbXlAIzJYmbU" alt="image"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Tested on:</strong><br>
• Browser / Version: Firefox Nightly 123.0a1-20240108213208 / Firefox Release 121.0.1-20231230165955 / Chrome 120.0.6099.43<br>
• Operating System: OnePlus 6 A6000 (Android 11) - 1080 x 2280 pixels, 19:9 ratio (~402 ppi pixel density)</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Notes:</strong></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Reproducible on both Firefox Release and Nightly</li>
<li>Disabling the ETP makes the cookie banner appear but accepting it doesn't result in the page showing, it is still blank</li>
<li>Not reproducible on Chrome</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Moving to Needsdiagnosis.</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">[qa_02/2024]</p>
      </div>
</task-lists>


        
      </div>

</div>


      <div data-gid="UNLE_lADOARFbIc57bFPyzwAAAAKpDXLx">
  
          


  <div data-team-hovercards-enabled="" id="event-11426168277">

    

        <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/sv-calin/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/sv-calin"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/107036654?s=40&amp;u=ab638d5508e713f1438ae3428d05da7e917001a0&amp;v=4" width="20" height="20" alt="@sv-calin"></a>
<a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/sv-calin/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/sv-calin">sv-calin</a>




      changed the title
<del>www.google.com - site is not usable</del>

<ins>www.google.com - The page is blank when accessed</ins></p><a href="#event-11426168277"><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T07:13:09Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time></a>

  </div>


  


  <div><p>
  This was referenced </p><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T07:30:23Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time>
</div>



</div>


  

        <div data-gid="CRE_kwDOARFbIc5QLrTD"><p>
  This was referenced </p><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T07:39:21Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time>
</div>

        <div data-gid="IC_kwDOARFbIc5wNYtC" data-url="/webcompat/web-bugs/comments/IC_kwDOARFbIc5wNYtC/partials/timeline_issue_comment">

  <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/denschub/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/denschub"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/344777?s=80&amp;u=cc785c96d962a238392ed1b263bf8d66f951a874&amp;v=4" width="40" height="40" alt="@denschub"></a>

</p>


  

</div>


        <div data-gid="LE_lADOARFbIc57bFPyzwAAAAKpElSV"><p>
  This was referenced </p><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T07:48:49Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time>
</div>

        <div data-gid="IC_kwDOARFbIc5wNpyp" data-url="/webcompat/web-bugs/comments/IC_kwDOARFbIc5wNpyp/partials/timeline_issue_comment">

  <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/denschub/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/denschub"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/344777?s=80&amp;u=cc785c96d962a238392ed1b263bf8d66f951a874&amp;v=4" width="40" height="40" alt="@denschub"></a>

</p>


  <div data-body-version="7380172e2f1bc048b1dbf70dec263ad0feb9119c2ddf069d0a8dcd6724dbfc7a" id="issuecomment-1882627241">

        <task-lists disabled="" sortable="">
<div>
          <p dir="auto">This is entirely server-side UA sniffing going wrong. You get an empty HTML doc, only a doctype, with a Firefox Android UA. You can reproduce this with curl,</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ curl -H &quot;User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Android 10; Mobile; rv:123.0) Gecko/123.0 Firefox/123.0&quot; https://www.google.com
<!DOCTYPE html>%"><pre lang="plain"><code>$ curl -H "User-Agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Android 10; Mobile; rv:123.0) Gecko/123.0 Firefox/123.0" https://www.google.com
&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;%
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">and it seems that this affects all UA strings with versions &gt;= 65. &lt;=64 work.</p>
      </div>
</task-lists>


        
      </div>

</div>


        <div data-gid="CRE_kwDOARFbIc5QLwaF">
  
          <div><p>
  This was referenced </p><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T08:53:43Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time>
</div>

  <div><p>
  This was referenced </p><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T10:31:56Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time>
</div>



</div>

        <div data-gid="IC_kwDOARFbIc5wOf5R" data-url="/webcompat/web-bugs/comments/IC_kwDOARFbIc5wOf5R/partials/timeline_issue_comment">

  <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/robertsdotpm/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/robertsdotpm"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/7320766?s=80&amp;u=97eabf632048c609c759fac825512a4b000f312f&amp;v=4" width="40" height="40" alt="@robertsdotpm"></a>

</p>


  <div id="issuecomment-1882848849">
      
  
  <details data-body-version="1621dfd3aa394a2e14c7aa8d7cd08e2d03378df73bb327f19a59d3f841248956">
    <summary>
      <div>
        <h3>
              This comment was marked as off-topic.

        </h3>
        
      </div>
    </summary>
  </details>


    </div>

</div>


        <div data-gid="IC_kwDOARFbIc5wOgdX" data-url="/webcompat/web-bugs/comments/IC_kwDOARFbIc5wOgdX/partials/timeline_issue_comment">

  <p><a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/denschub/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/denschub"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/344777?s=80&amp;u=cc785c96d962a238392ed1b263bf8d66f951a874&amp;v=4" width="40" height="40" alt="@denschub"></a>

</p>


  <div data-body-version="c59a70ab1ec93c0ed607e39af0009a1c25399af73294ffd5694eeba9eab6532d" id="issuecomment-1882851159">

        <task-lists disabled="" sortable="">
<div>
          <p dir="auto">Since this has now been posted to HN, I'll be locking this thread. This bugtracker is a work place, not a discussion forum.</p>
      </div>
</task-lists>


        
      </div>

</div>


        <div data-team-hovercards-enabled="" id="event-11428732439" data-gid="LOE_lADOARFbIc57bFPyzwAAAAKpNJ4X">

    

        <p><a data-hovercard-type="organization" data-hovercard-url="/orgs/webcompat/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/webcompat"><img src="https://avatars.githubusercontent.com/u/6175168?s=40&amp;v=4" width="20" height="20" alt="@webcompat"></a>
<a data-hovercard-type="organization" data-hovercard-url="/orgs/webcompat/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/webcompat">webcompat</a>




      locked and limited conversation to collaborators


    </p><a href="#event-11428732439"><relative-time datetime="2024-01-09T10:55:23Z">Jan 9, 2024</relative-time></a>

  </div>



  <!-- Rendered timeline since 2024-01-09 02:55:23 -->
  
</div>


  </div>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Using Git Offline (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.gibbard.me/using_git_offline/</link>
            <guid>38924159</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 09:44:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.gibbard.me/using_git_offline/">https://www.gibbard.me/using_git_offline/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38924159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
        <p>Some companies use an isolated network or even the complete lack of a network as a security measure to protect from unauthorized access. Working on these systems can be a struggle but it is still possible, and perhaps even more important, to use a proper version control tool like Git.</p>
<p>By design Git works quite happily with no remote repository. You can branch, stage, and commit files just like normal.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>mkdir testRepo
<span>cd</span> testRepo
git init
touch test.txt
git add --all
git commit -m <span>"Initial Commit"</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>This works great if just a single machine is used for development, but this is often not the case.</p>
<h2>Working with multiple machines — Using a USB memory stick/HDD</h2>
<p>When security policy allows read/write access to a memory stick or portable hard drive a remote repository can be created on this device.</p>
<p>On one development machine mount the memory stick.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>cd</span> /path/to/memory/stick
mkdir repoName.git
<span>cd</span> repoName.git
git init --bare
</code></pre></div>

<p>Navigate to the repository that is to be shared, add the remote repository on the memory stick, and push the changes.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>cd</span> /path/to/local/repo/
git remote add origin /path/to/memory/stick/repoName.git
git push origin master
</code></pre></div>

<p>NB. The remote can be called anything. It doesn’t have to be called “origin”.</p>
<p>Unmount the memory stick and mount it on another development machine.</p>
<p>If the development machine does not have a copy of the repository on it already then git clone can be used.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git clone /path/to/memory/stick/repoName.git
</code></pre></div>

<p>If there is a copy of the repository already on the machine add the memory stick as a remote and fetch/pull the changes.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>cd</span> /path/to/local/repo/
git remote add origin /path/to/memory/stick/repoName.git
git pull origin
</code></pre></div>

<p>From now on use Git as normal but make sure that whenever a git pull, fetch, or push is performed the memory stick is mounted on the machine.</p>
<p>Ensure the memory stick is part of your backup routine.</p>
<h2>Working with multiple machines — Using&nbsp;CD/DVDs</h2>
<p>In locked down development environments memory sticks may be blocked. Using Git is still possible, but a little be more inconvenient.</p>
<p>Git will happily fetch changes from one copy of a local repository to another. One option then is to simply copy the directory containing the local Git repository to another computer via CD or other media and make changes and commits like normal on both machines. When you want to combine changes select one machine to perform the merge and copy the other repository over to this machine. To pull all the changes into the current branch use:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git pull /path/to/other/repo
</code></pre></div>

<p>Alternatively you can fetch the changes and create a new branch to store them:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git fetch /path/to/other/repo
git checkout -b new_branch FETCH_HEAD
</code></pre></div>

<p>At this point create a new copy of the repository complete with merges and move it over to the other machine/s. Pull the latest changes into the other repositories or if desired simply replace the whole repository with the new copy.</p>
<p>Obviously this is far from optimal. Copying the whole repository directory will include personal settings and files excluded in the&nbsp;.gitignore file. To mitigate this Git clone could be used to duplicate the repository rather than just copying it, but a much better option is to use git bundle.</p>
<h3>Git bundle</h3>
<p>A git bundle allows for part or all of a repository to be compressed into a single file in a format that git is able to clone and fetch from.</p>
<p>The workflow works very similar to before, but instead of copying the whole repository directory a git bundle is created. On the first machine create a bundle using:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git bundle create repoName.bundle --all
</code></pre></div>

<p>The <code>-- all</code> option bundles the entire repository including all branches and tags. Specific branches or tags can be selected using <code>-b branchName</code> or <code>-t tagName</code>.</p>
<p>Copy the repoName.bundle file to another computer. To clone the repository simply use:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git clone repoName.bundle
</code></pre></div>

<p>Changes and commits can be made on any of the computers then like before one machine must be selected to perform the merge. On the non-merging machine make sure all changes are committed and create a bundle using:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git bundle create repoName.bundle --all
</code></pre></div>

<p>For larger repositories it is a good idea to only bundle part of the repository to avoid transferring more data than needed. For example to only include the last 5 commits on the master branch use:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git bundle create repoName.bundle -5 master
</code></pre></div>

<p>It is important that there are no gaps between the commits in the bundle and the commits on the repository where the merging will occur or the process will fail.</p>
<p>Copy the bundle to the computer where the merge will occur and pull the changes using:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git pull /path/to/repoName.bundle
</code></pre></div>

<p>Once the merging/rebasing is done create another bundle using:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git bundle create repoName.bundle --all
</code></pre></div>

<p>In the above command <code>--all</code> can be replaced with the desired subset of repos/commits.</p>
<p>Move the bundle file to the other machine/s and update the changes there using:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git pull /path/to/repoName.bundle
</code></pre></div>

<h3>Creating a local remote repository</h3>
<p>Bundles solve the problem of synchronising Git repositories without a network, but we are still left with multiple computers all likely to be slightly out of sync with each other. If a new developer joins the team who do they copy the repository from? The best option is to select one development machine that will act as the “server”. A bare Git repository can be created on this development machine in addition to a local clone of the repository where the developer will actually work.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>cd</span> /path/to/store/main/repo
mkdir remoteRepoName.git
<span>cd</span> remoteRepoName.git
git init --bare
</code></pre></div>

<p>Next navigate to the local git repository or create a new one and add the remoteRepoName.git repository as a remote repository.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>cd</span> /path/to/local/repo/
git remote add origin /path/to/store/main/repo/remoteRepoName.git
git push origin branchName
</code></pre></div>

<p>Changes can then be made in the local repository, or pulled from bundles created on other development machines. Whenever changes are made they can be pushed to the remote using:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code>git push origin branchName
</code></pre></div>

<h2>Summary</h2>
<p>The distributed nature of Git allows it to work well without a central server. While the options presented will never be as convenient as just pushing to github they certainly beat the alternative of: <code>main_v1_final version_with_bobs_extra_patch finalfinal_version</code>.</p>
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Heat pumps, more than you wanted to know (2023) (217 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://calv.info/heat-pumps</link>
            <guid>38923969</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 09:18:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://calv.info/heat-pumps">https://calv.info/heat-pumps</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38923969">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Over the last few months, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bakershogry/">Baker</a> and I have been digging in deep on <a href="https://heatpumpshooray.com/">Heat Pumps</a>. I'm putting my explorations here on pause but wanted to write up everything we've learned over the last few months.</p>
<p>Heat pumps are unique in that they are a tool for fighting climate change, where <strong>we have the technology <em>today</em></strong>. It's the same tech that we've been using in refrigerators and AC units for decades. Switching to heat pumps would reduce <a href="https://www.epa.gov/ghgemissions/sources-greenhouse-gas-emissions">hundreds of MT of CO2 emissions per year</a>. And yet, they are only present in <a href="https://www.eia.gov/consumption/residential/data/2020/hc/pdf/HC%206.1.pdf">15% of US single-family homes</a>.</p>
<p>Unlike more speculative areas of climate tech, adopting heat pumps en-masse is more a question of <strong>deployment</strong>. There are barriers with <strong>financing</strong>, the <strong>purchase journey</strong>, the <strong>large up-front install cost</strong>, and the <strong>lack of differentiated outcomes</strong>. I'll get to all of these down below.</p>
<p>Overall, it feels like a space which is ripe for disruption, which is why you see a lot of startup founders starting to investigate this space. Every step in the process today is broken, which means that there is a lot to improve.</p>
<p><em>Author's note: I'm not a grizzled heat pump or HVAC expert, so it's certainly possible I got some stuff wrong. What follows is the result of about six months of research. If you have a correction, please reach out.</em></p>
<h2>Types of heat pumps</h2>
<p>If you're totally new to the space: <strong>heat pumps are a high-efficiency, climate-friendly option to heat and cool your home</strong>. They run on pure electricity, and are 3-4x more efficient than existing electric options. They are one of our best tools in the fight against climate change, and should be deployed in every home in America.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://calv.info/heat-pumps/heat-pump-cycle.jpg"></p><p><span>The heat pump cycle. Via https://airteamltd.com/</span></p></div>
<p>Heat pumps consist of the same set of components...</p>
<p><strong>An outdoor unit</strong> which either collects heat from the outdoors to be brought inside, or releases heat collected from indoors. It will typically have a fan to move air across a set of coils (metal) which conduct heat from the refrigerant. there are two primary styles of these: "barrel-style" which look more like a traditional AC unit and "box-style" which are the boxes you see on <a href="http://heatpumpshooray.com/">Heat Pumps, Hooray!</a>.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://calv.info/heat-pumps/mitsubishi-unit.jpg"></p><p><span>An outdoor unit</span></p></div>
<p><strong>An indoor unit (or indoor heads)</strong> which either pulls heat in from inside the home or disperses it out. think of it as functionally the same thing as the outdoor unit, but it sits <em>inside</em> your house and looks different based on how heat is distributed throughout the home (see below)</p>
<p><strong>Refrigerant lines</strong> which exchange heat between the indoors and outdoors. these are metal tubes that carry a substance known as refrigerant which has an extremely low boiling point.</p>
<p><strong>A compressor</strong> which is used to modulate pressure of the refrigerant</p>
<p><strong>A reversing-valve</strong> which changes the directional flow of refrigerant to either heat or cool your home. when you adjust the thermostat 'mode', it is effectively changing the direction of the reversing-valve.</p>
<p><strong>Sometimes: heat strips / resistive heating</strong>: in <em>very</em> cold climates below -5 degrees F, heat pump capacity will go down to the point where it may have trouble meeting the heating load. To combat this, certain heat pumps ship with resistive elements (imagine a toaster oven that generates heat by running through a wire).</p>
<p>Additionally, there are a few other 'flavors' of heat pumps depending on your home setup, but all of these consist of the same core parts.</p>
<h4>Heat pump flavors: how heat is distributed</h4>
<p>If you want to install a heat pump in your home, you have several options for how that process works.</p>
<p><strong>Option 1: Central-ducted</strong> - most US homes have duct-work to move heat (and air!) throughout the house. In these systems, there's a central set of tubes which run air throughout the house, kind of like blood vessels will carry blood throughout the body. Centrally ducted heat pumps are the most popular, since about 60% of US homes already have ducts. If you have ducts, using that ductwork is typically the cheapest and most effective way to distribute heat.</p>
<p><strong>Option 2: Mini-split aka ductless</strong> - for homes without duct-work, or cases where you want to condition a specific room (e.g. think of a garage), you can use a mini-split unit. This works in the same way as the central units, but instead of hiding the indoor unit in a basement or closet, they are instead mounted visibly on the walls. Refrigerant lines will run directly from an outdoor unit to an indoor one. Because these can't heat the whole home, they are typically smaller. In some cases, you can route refrigerant to multiple 'heads' inside the home.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://calv.info/heat-pumps/mini-split.jpg"></p><p><span>Mini-split units don't use central ducts and instead sit on your wall</span></p></div>
<p><strong>Option 3: Mono-block or 'packaged'</strong> - there's one other type of heat pump which is generally less popular because it's not as flexible or performant for many housing configurations, the 'mono-block' unit. These combine indoor and outdoor units into a single form factor that sits outside the house, and then moves air inside. It benefits from simplicity of install (no refrigerant lines), but won't be nearly as efficient as a split system and has a bigger outdoor footprint.</p>
<p><strong>Option 4: Air-to-water</strong> - for households who have radiant heating, heat pumps (or heat pump water heaters) can exchange heat with water. This is less popular in the US, but a popular way to heat in Europe.</p>
<h4>Heat pump flavors: heating sources</h4>
<p>In addition to how heat is distributed inside, there are also differences in how heat pumps.</p>
<p><strong>Air-source heat pumps</strong> are the most common heat pump variety, that you see everywhere. These exchange heat with the outside air, just like an AC Unit.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://calv.info/heat-pumps/air-source-heat-pump.jpg"></p><p><span>Air-source heat pumps sit outside your home</span></p></div>
<p><strong>Dual-fuel</strong> - a dual fuel heat pump setup is basically the same as centrally ducted, but it just means that you <em>don't</em> replace your existing furnace, and have the heat pump installed alongside it. This is a popular route for homeowners looking to gradually transition. With dual-fuel, the heat pump and the gas furnace can never run simultaneously, so it won't save much money on heating. But it can be useful for gradually moving to electric heating.</p>
<p><strong>Air-to-ground (aka ground-source)</strong> - in extreme climates (think the northeast), heat pump heating and cooling both become lower efficiency. pulling heat out of the very cold air is hard to do, as is pushing heat into hot humid days. it turns out that if you <a href="https://www.energy.gov/energysaver/geothermal-heat-pumps">drill down ~30-40 feet, the soil temperature will remain more or less constant throughout the year</a>. this gives a heat pump much better efficiency.</p>
<h2>The market</h2>
<p>Today's market participants are split into a few different layers: <strong>consumers, contractors and technicians, wholesalers, and manufacturers</strong>.</p>
<p>Let's start with <strong>consumers</strong>. Furnace equipment typically has a lifetime of 20 years, while AC equipment has a lifetime of more like 15 years. When your furnace or AC dies (or perhaps you want to get an AC for the first time), you have a magical window of opportunity to upgrade to a heat pump.</p>
<p>Today, most consumers will either call the number on the side of the unit left by the original installer (an ingenious and basically zero-cost lead-flow technique), or will search on Yelp, Angie's List, or Google to find a contractor. Typically these lead-flow businesses will get ~$60-80 per lead.</p>
<p>Typically the breakdown is...</p>
<ul>
<li>2-4k equipment cost (pure hardware)</li>
<li>4-15k labor cost (removing old equipment, running refrigerant lines, install)</li>
<li>10-20k (maybe) duct upgrades, panel upgrades</li>
</ul>
<p>That labor cost has a wide variance. It's mostly a function of supply and demand. In areas where many people have AC, it's relatively easy to retrofit a heat pump and it happens all the time</p>
<p>Most of the time, heat pump upgrades will be done under <em>duress</em>. About 80% of furnace replacements happen during a "break-fix" scenario, where the existing equipment has stopped working and new equipment needs to be installed. It's much more difficult to ask for a bigger replacement (both in terms of time and cost) when the heating is out and your family is cold! Homeowners will call a <strong>contractor</strong> (also referred to as an HVAC technician) who comes in to investigate the issue.</p>
<p><strong>Contracting firms</strong> are typically both small and fragmented. There are <a href="https://www.bls.gov/oes/current/oes499021.htm">300,000 HVAC technicians in the US</a>, but <a href="https://www.ibisworld.com/industry-statistics/number-of-businesses/heating-air-conditioning-contractors-united-states/">145,000 companies</a>! That means many of them are either sole proprietors, or just a few individuals with a truck.</p>
<p>It's a good business to be in, generally speaking. Individual shops may be making anywhere from $500k to $10m per year depending on the size of operations. The <a href="https://www.bls.gov/oes/current/oes499021.htm">mean hourly wage for a technician is $26/hour</a>.</p>
<p>Most contractors that we've talked with indicate that there's a severe labor shortage. Contractors have to be experts at system design, understanding heating and cooling loads, some electrical work, pressure variations, and construction. It’s a skilled trade that takes a long time to master.</p>
<p>New contractors typically learn via the <a href="https://en.wikibooks.org/wiki/Mentor_teacher/Apprenticeship_model"><strong>apprenticeship model</strong></a>, but in the last few years, fewer individuals have entered these trades. In some cases, contractors aren't even taking new jobs for months. Demand for contractors spikes twice per year; the first hot day in summer, and the first cold day of the winter.</p>
<p>Over the last few years, there's been an increase in private equity roll-up vehicles buying up these firms. Many of them are trying to centralize and bring technology to key functions (scheduling, financing, invoicing) and allow the technicians to spend more time on their specialized work.</p>
<p>Contractors have not historically adopted a lot of software, though there are companies trying to serve them (<a href="https://www.servicetitan.com/">ServiceTitan</a>).</p>
<p>Finally there are the <strong>manufacturers</strong>. These are the only large players in the market, they are a handful of publicly traded companies, like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrier_Global">Carrier</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trane">Trane</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lennox">Lennox</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mitsubishi_Group">Mitsubishi</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daikin">Daikin</a>. Each of them bring in <a href="https://d18rn0p25nwr6d.cloudfront.net/CIK-0001466258/45e3cbd7-53cc-416d-9ed7-6e84d9b7c7ce.pdf#page=3">$1b+ in hardware, and typically maintain a 20% margin</a>.</p>
<div><p><img src="https://calv.info/heat-pumps/trane-finances.png"></p><p><span>Trane's financials from their 10-K filing. 4.3b in revenue, 20% margin</span></p></div>
<p>Many technicians have agreements directly with wholesalers or the manufacturer. As a result, it's tough to buy a heat pump unit <em>even if you really wanted to</em>. Similar to the way car dealerships worked 20 years ago, you have to go through the dealer (aka the contractor or wholesaler) who is a licensed retailer for the manufacturer.</p>
<p>These manufacturers are slightly disincentivized from pushing heat pump adoption for two reasons: 1) many of them <em>also</em> sell furnaces and A/C units, and have whole divisions responsible for those P&amp;L statements 2) they want to maintain a margin on equipment. Rather than provide equipment that is higher-cost but easier to install, they will try and ship the lowest possible cost, and then pass the labor costs on to the end consumer.</p>
<p>There are <a href="https://www.eia.gov/consumption/residential/data/2020/hc/pdf/HC%202.1.pdf"><strong>77 million single-family homes in the US</strong></a>, and roughly <a href="https://rpsc.energy.gov/tech-solutions/hvac"><strong>3 million</strong> furnace or AC units installed per year</a>.</p>
<h2>Installing a heat pump</h2>
<p>Okay, so what's a heat pump install look like? There's a few different pieces..</p>
<p><strong>On-site visit</strong>: the purpose of this is two-fold. One part of it is to actually assess the quote and ensure that there aren't any issues. The second is to help sell the homeowner on the desired solution. As part of this on-site visit, the contractor will want to do some initial system sizing to determine what sort of system you need.</p>
<p>In repair cases, the first visit ends up being the most important. When a technician says that the existing equipment is and needs to be replaced, they set the framing for the entire journey.</p>
<p>The output of the system design should include a <strong>load sizing report for the home</strong>. It should indicate how many BTUs you need to heat your home in the winter, and how many tons of cooling you need in the summer.</p>
<p>As it turns out, load sizing is a surprisingly tricky problem to get right. Design will depend on your room configuration, insulation, and even position of the home relative to the sun. The “gold standard” way to do this is by running a <a href="https://www.acca.org/standards/technical-manuals/manual-j"><strong>Manual J calculation</strong></a> on the home, and doing a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Blower_door"><strong>blower door test</strong></a> which assesses the actual leakiness of the home.</p>
<p>Many contractors will skip this step if replacing the existing equipment with a newer version of the same equipment. This is another reason that contractors will prefer to stick with replacing existing systems vs swapping out for a heat pump.</p>
<p>There's a few things that will blow up a quote...</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>new ductwork</strong> - if you live in a climate where it doesn't get too hot, you might have small ductwork. The ducts don't need to be very big because gas furnaces heat at a high temperature (140F). Heat pumps heat at a much lower temperature (100-110F), which means they need to move more volume of air to work. Getting to this increased volume requires increasing the duct size, which tends to add 10-20k to the up-front cost. In practice, if existing ductwork is insufficient, the installer will instead recommend a ductless system, which also tends to be more expensive (remember, if you have ducts, they are the cheapest way to deliver heat).</li>
<li><strong>panel upgrade / and new 240v outlets</strong> - older homes were wired in a time before we had all these electric appliances (solar panels, evs, etc). A heat pump might require upgrading your panel to accommodate increased amperage. Doing a panel upgrade isn't terribly expensive, but it might add 2-3k to rewire the home. It also increases the end-to-end time for the job, as the utility may have to upgrade service to the home.</li>
<li><strong>new insulation</strong> - insulating a home is expensive, but probably the thing you should do before making any other upgrades. in most cases, insulation will be the #1 thing you can do to make your home more efficient.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Install</strong>: a heat pump should be able to be installed in about a day. The technicians will have to remove any old units, and run any new refrigerant lines (aka drilling holes in the walls of your home). If you have an existing AC, the technicians can likely re-use the refrigerant lines already in your walls. The technicians will install the outdoor unit by placing it on a concrete slab and hooking it up to the electrical outlets, as well as the different indoor units. Often, technicians will recommend installing new thermostats as part of this process. Finally, they'll need to "charge" the refrigerants, filling the lines with R-410A (or another refrigerant).</p>
<p><strong>Follow-up / maintenance:</strong> most installers offer a 1-year warranty on any work that they do. Callbacks with heat pumps are most frequently due to leaking refrigerant (which also is bad from a climate-perspective, more on that below).</p>
<h2>Utilities</h2>
<p>There's one other player in this market who we didn't talk about yet: <strong>utilities</strong> and <strong>government funding</strong>.</p>
<p>The government has set aside budgets to help consumers drive the adoption of green technology. Typically these budgets are set at the federal level, and then flow down to the 'state energy office'. Each state energy office then works with local utilities (<a href="https://www.coned.com/en/">ConEd</a>, <a href="https://www.pge.com/">PG&amp;E</a>) or NGOs (<a href="https://www.bayren.org/">BayRen</a>) to provide programs for consumers to adopt high-efficiency devices.</p>
<p>While the large budget numbers are set at the federal level, actually dispersing that money is very much a local issue.</p>
<p>I've personally found the way utilities work to be a hard thing to reason about, but in general, here's how people have described their incentives to me...</p>
<ul>
<li>utilities charge each consumer a <strong>'fixed service fee</strong>' which is something like $20/mo. this costs them basically nothing to service (think of it like the gym membership)</li>
<li>utilities generally <strong>want to decrease peak demand</strong> on their systems, while simultaneously keeping customers connected and paying the service fee. the higher the demand, the more expensive it is for a utility to deliver that energy, so utilities will minimize spike and lower-margin "peak load"</li>
<li>utilities are <strong>'procurement engines',</strong> they are very good at funding new capital improvements, if they can show a return on those projects. they tend to build little in-house</li>
<li><strong>electric</strong> utilities will incentivize <strong>switching to all-electric</strong>. <strong>gas</strong> utilities will incentivize <strong>high-efficiency devices</strong>. in some cases, utilities which do both will figure out the cost to serve individual homes, and try and switch load to whatever method is cheapest to serve.</li>
</ul>
<p>Despite all this, the software and data utilities provide is an area that is ripe for startups to dig into. It's also a slog, the most well-known company here is <a href="https://www.oracle.com/industries/utilities/opower-energy-efficiency/">Opower</a>, but there aren't many others willing to brave the high-touch sales cycle.</p>
<h2>Incentives and rebates</h2>
<p>A key result of that government funding is that utilities often offer $2k-3k <em>per heat pump install</em> to bring higher-efficiency devices into the home. With the <a href="https://www.rewiringamerica.org/app/ira-calculator">Inflation Reduction Act this number has expanded dramatically for low and middle income families</a>.</p>
<p>There's a lot of problems that exist with these incentives...</p>
<p><strong>Discovery</strong> - before they can apply for incentives, homeowners have to know about them! The unfortunate thing is that these incentives are spread across many different sites. In many cases, incentives are "good until the money runs out", which means a consumer might be expecting <em>more</em> money back.</p>
<p><strong>Eligibility</strong> - woof, incentive eligibility is a complex thing. Often it depends on a multitude of factors: the exact unit which was installed, the sizing vs existing equipment, the household income, and more. It is difficult for homeowners and contractors alike to wade through to know how much money they are eligible for.</p>
<p><strong>Application</strong> - applying for rebates requires an annoying amount of paperwork. In cases of things like EV chargers, consumers can fill out the applications themselves. For a heat pump, it will probably require 2-3 hours of contractor time... which is why many contractors just don't bother!</p>
<p><strong>Financing</strong> - the biggest incentives have historically come in the form of tax credits that you can claim off your tax bill at the end of the year. This means that the consumer has to 'float' the cost of the install up-front, until they can claim the rebate months later. More progressive utilities will partner with banks to <a href="https://www.velocitycu.com/loans/austin-energy/">provide interest-free loans</a>, but there's still a big gap here.</p>
<h2>Heat pump economics (am I getting ripped off?)</h2>
<p>You might be wondering how money flows as part of this process...</p>
<ul>
<li>the <strong>wholesalers</strong> will typically charge <strong>3-5k</strong> per heat pump unit. Higher efficiency units will be more expensive (<strong>6-8k</strong>). The manufacturer will try and maintain a <strong>30% margin</strong>, with higher-efficiency units having a greater margin.</li>
<li>the <strong>installers</strong> will pass that cost onto the consumer, and then typically <em>double the cost of the unit for labor</em>. For a 5k system, there will be minimum 5k in labor costs. In certain geos with a more competitive labor market (SF, Seattle), we've even seen labor account for <strong>70-90% of the bill</strong>.</li>
<li>the average consumer with a high-efficiency gas furnace will save something like <strong>~$200/year on fuel costs</strong>. the consumers using more expensive forms of energy (e.g. fuel oil) will save closer to <strong>$2,000 per year</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>contractors</strong> will usually include some buffer room</li>
</ul>
<p>The net-result is that <strong>in a heat-pump popular market with many AC units</strong> and mild climate (think Austin, TX), the cost will be something like <strong>$8-10k to switch to a heat pump</strong>. In a market where AC usage is much rarer (SF), or the climate is more extreme (e.g. Seattle, Boston), <strong>a heat pump install might run you $20k.</strong></p>
<h2>A word on Refrigerants</h2>
<p>While I'm generally bullish on heat pumps and convinced that we must adopt them to prevent climate change, today's heat pumps aren't <em>all</em> sunshine and rainbows. There's one big problem with rolling them out: <strong>refrigerants</strong>.</p>
<p>Remember, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Refrigerant">refrigerants are substances which transfer heat from outside in (or vice versa)</a>. Refrigerants have a very low boiling point (think -40 degrees F). The low boiling point makes it easy to change the pressure to adjust whether a refrigerant is liquid or gas, which is good for heating transfer, but can create problems elsewhere.</p>
<p>Notably, many refrigerants have a high<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming_potential"> <strong>global-warming-potential</strong> (GWP)</a>. This number is measured relative to CO2 (which has a GWP of 1), and expresses how much worse a molecule of refrigerant is when it comes to global warming.</p>
<p>There have been thousands of refrigerants categorized over time. They are typically numbered by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_refrigerants">R-{Ccount - 1}{Hcount + 1}{Fcount}</a> when viewed as pure chains, but when they are combined the numbering scheme changes to be more sequential.</p>
<p>Today's most popular refrigerant is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R-410A">R-410A</a>. It is a mixture of CHF<sub>2</sub>CF<sub>3</sub> and CH<sub>2</sub>F<sub>2</sub> has a GWP of 1,400. (It should be noted that even with some refrigerant leakage, <a href="https://heatpumpshooray.com/">we still see that heat pumps come out ahead when it comes to GWP</a>)</p>
<p>Over time, we've been steadily outlawing high global-warming-potential refrigerants (remember CFCs and HFCs?). <a href="https://www.epa.gov/newsreleases/us-will-dramatically-cut-climate-damaging-greenhouse-gases-new-program-aimed-chemicals">And in 2024, the industry is gearing up to phase out R-410A</a>.</p>
<p>The one problem is that there aren't a lot of other <em>good</em> alternatives that exist. Refrigerants fall into two classes...</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>flammable</strong>: these are refrigerants like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Propane_refrigeration">Propane (R-290)</a> or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Isobutane">Isobutane</a>. We can't roll them out without updating a bunch of building codes. <em>As an aside, it's sort of crazy to me that we decide to limit propane in building codes, when we pipe natural gas into homes all the time to literally light it on fire.</em></li>
<li><strong>high-pressure</strong>: among the leading non-flammable refrigerants is <a href="https://www.danfoss.com/en/about-danfoss/our-businesses/cooling/refrigerants-and-energy-efficiency/refrigerants-for-lowering-the-gwp/carbon-dioxide-co2/">CO2</a>. It's not flammable (good!) has a GWP of 1 (also good!) but requires a <em>lot</em> more pressure to turn from vapor to liquid (bad!). This means more expensive compressors.</li>
</ul>
<p>Finding new refrigerants is an active area of research, and will probably require a sea change. Most of the big manufacturers seem to be heavily investigating this area of research.</p>
<h2>Buckets of problems</h2>
<p><strong>Consumer awareness</strong> - most consumers don't know (or care much) about how they get their heat. Despite being available for many years, heat pumps have only recently entered the popular discourse. Unlike solar or EVs, heat pumps are pretty much invisible, and it's not yet a status symbol in any dimension.</p>
<p><strong>Urgency of problem</strong> - most HVAC systems are replaced when the old system has broken. Consumers typically don't have a ton of appetite to do a lengthy heat pump install when they can't keep their home warm! On the flip side, when an HVAC system is working smoothly, consumers have little desire to switch it out and add risk to the process.</p>
<p><strong>Contractor incentives</strong> - contractors typically want to avoid any sort of callback. The easiest way to do this is to replace the existing equipment. It minimizes risk, and additional labor hours. You don't have to worry about running into issues which might lead to a drastically higher quote (duct sizing or panel upgrades).</p>
<p><strong>Regional markets</strong> - one reason HVAC is tricky for startups to tackle is that it's a highly fragmented, very regional market. The pitch for consumers is actually different depending on geo. In SF or Seattle, heat pumps might be viewed as 'adding an AC for the first time'. In the southeast, it's a way of reducing your electricity bill by 2-3x. In the northeast, heat pumps are best positioned to replace expensive sources of fuel like fuel oil.</p>
<h2>Areas of opportunity</h2>
<p><strong>Financing</strong>. Solar has a rich set of options for financing the big up-front cost. These largely do not exist with heat pumps today (though local utilities may sometimes run 0% APR loan programs). Applying for rebates and incentives is an arduous process, and often <em>still</em> requires that you spend money up-front.</p>
<p><strong>System design</strong>. Designing a system for a home is tricky, and often involves a visit to the home. This is both annoying for consumers, and costs the contractor as it requires an extra 2-3h of transit time to prepare a quote that they may not even be paid for! The holy grail here would be working in the same way that solar does: going directly from address -&gt; design. We've built a lot of this modeling into <a href="http://heatpumpshooray.com/">Heat Pumps, Hooray!</a>, but there's still internals of the system which require more work to surface (ductwork, panel, refrigerant lines). There are some companies focused exclusively on system design (<a href="https://www.coolcalc.com/">CoolCalc</a>, <a href="https://www.getarch.com/">Arch</a>, <a href="https://www.getconduit.com/">Conduit</a>).</p>
<p><strong>New heat pumps and refrigerants</strong>. There's a number of startups trying to build new heat pumps: <a href="https://www.gradientcomfort.com/">Gradient</a>, <a href="https://stow.energy/">Stow</a>, <a href="https://dandelionenergy.com/">Dandelion Energy</a>, and others. A system like Gradient's window unit doesn't require any sort of contractor install and works for multi-family apartment buildings. Dandelion takes a differentiated approach by focusing on ground-source heat pumps, which are more difficult to purchase.</p>
<p><strong>Purchase journey.</strong> Right now, it's fairly difficult to get a heat pump even if you are highly motivated and not budget constrained. There's a number of companies trying to help the purchase journey: <a href="https://www.woltair.com/">Woltair</a> in Poland, <a href="https://lun.energy/">Lun</a> in the EU. Each of them are working to make buying a heat pump more similar to buying a dishwasher or washer/dryer online.</p>
<p>Additionally there are some other pathways that folks are trying to explore that I'm a little less bullish on, but I thought are worth mentioning here.</p>
<p><strong>Luxury products?</strong> A number of folks are investigating whether heat pumps might become a luxury product. I'm personally skeptical here. Heating and cooling are a lot less tangible than an EV or having solar on your roof. That said, if you could find a way to turn a heat pump into a futuristic technological device or a high-status symbol, I think you'd have a lot of luck. <a href="https://www.quilt.com/">Quilt</a> is one such company, applying high industrial design to an antiquated market. For products like an induction stove where you use it daily, I think this approach can work much better (a la <a href="https://www.impulselabs.com/">Impulse</a>).</p>
<p><strong>Whole-home electrification</strong>. It's far more common to upgrade a single component at a time. But there are a few companies trying to do whole-home electrification by providing better hardware and software: <a href="https://www.lunarenergy.com/">Lunar Energy</a>, <a href="https://www.elephantenergy.org/">Elephant Energy</a>.</p>
<h2>Thanks</h2>
<p>First and foremost, I wanted to thank <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/bakershogry/">Baker</a> for being an incredible thought partner throughout all of this and building something really cool and useful.</p>
<p>Additionally, there have been a handful of folks we've had conversations with who fundamentally changed my understanding of the Heat Pump market: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/shaylekann/">Shayle</a> (if you have not checked out <a href="https://www.canarymedia.com/podcasts/catalyst-with-shayle-kann">his podcast</a>, you owe it to yourself to do so), <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andy-lubershane-0ab3bb24/">Andy</a>, and Gregory from EIP, <a href="https://www.innovationendeavors.com/team/sam-smith-eppsteiner/">Sam</a> and <a href="https://www.innovationendeavors.com/team/josh-rapperport/">Josh</a> from Innovation Endeavors, <a href="https://fiftyyears.com/team/seth-bannon">Seth</a> and <a href="https://fiftyyears.com/team/alex-teng">Alex</a> from 50y, and <a href="https://twitter.com/KVibhor">Vibhor</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-cahn-60150793/">David</a> from Coatue, <a href="https://erikareinhardt.com/">Erika Reinhardt</a></p>
<p>Thank you demo crew: <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/kevin-niparko-5ab86b54/">Kevin Niparko</a> and <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/people/lauren-reeder/">Lauren Reeder</a> for keeping us going with feedback and encouragement throughout.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Python 3.13 Gets a JIT (832 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tonybaloney.github.io/posts/python-gets-a-jit.html</link>
            <guid>38923741</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 08:35:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tonybaloney.github.io/posts/python-gets-a-jit.html">https://tonybaloney.github.io/posts/python-gets-a-jit.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38923741">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                <p>Happy New Year everyone! In late December 2023 (Christmas Day to be precise), CPython core developer <a href="https://github.com/brandtbucher">Brandt Bucher</a> submitted a <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/pull/113465">little pull-request to the Python 3.13</a> branch adding a JIT compiler.</p>
<p>This change, once accepted would be one of the biggest changes to the CPython Interpreter since the Specializing Adaptive Interpreter added in Python 3.11 (which was also from Brandt).</p>
<p>In this blog post, we’re going to have a look at this JIT, what it is, how it works and what the benefits are.</p>
<h2>What is a JIT?</h2>
<p>JIT, or “Just in Time” is a compilation design that implies that compilation happens on demand when the code is run the first time. It’s a very broad term that could mean many things. I guess, technically the Python compiler is already a JIT because it compiles from Python code into Bytecode.</p>
<p>What people <em>tend</em> to mean when they say a JIT compiler, is a compiler that emits <strong>machine code</strong>. This is in contrast to an AOT (Ahead of Time) compiler, like the GNU C compiler, GCC or the Rust compiler rustc which generates the machine code once and distributes as a binary executable.</p>
<p>When you run Python code, it is first compiled into bytecodes. There are plenty of talks and videos about this process online so I don’t want to rehash this too much, but what is important to note about Python bytecodes is:</p>
<ol>
<li>They mean nothing to the CPU and require a special bytecode interpreter loop to execute</li>
<li>They are high level and can equate to 1000’s of machine instructions</li>
<li>They are type agnostic</li>
<li>They are cross-platform</li>
</ol>
<p>For a very simple Python function <code>f()</code> that defines a variable <code>a</code> and assigns the value <code>1</code>:</p>
<pre><code>def func():
    a = 1
    return a
</code></pre>

<p>It compiles to 5 bytecode instructions, which you can see by running <code>dis.dis</code>:</p>
<pre><code>&gt;&gt;&gt; import dis
&gt;&gt;&gt; dis.dis(f)
 34           0 RESUME                   0

 35           2 LOAD_CONST               1 (1)
              4 STORE_FAST               0 (a)

 36           6 LOAD_FAST                0 (a)
              8 RETURN_VALUE
</code></pre>

<p>I have a more interactive disassembler called <a href="https://github.com/tonybaloney/dissy">dissy</a> as well if you want to try something more complicated.</p>
<p>For this function, Python 3.11 compiled into the instructions <code>LOAD_CONST</code>, <code>STORE_FAST</code>, <code>LOAD_CONST</code>, and <code>RETURN_VALUE</code>. These instructions are interpreted when the function is run by a massive loop written in C.</p>
<p>If you were to write a very crude Python evaluation loop in Python equivalent to the one in C, it would look something like this:</p>
<pre><code>import dis

def interpret(func):
    stack = []
    variables = {}
    for instruction in dis.get_instructions(func):
        if instruction.opname == "LOAD_CONST":
            stack.append(instruction.argval)
        elif instruction.opname == "LOAD_FAST":
            stack.append(variables[instruction.argval])
        elif instruction.opname == "STORE_FAST":
            variables[instruction.argval] = stack.pop()
        elif instruction.opname == "RETURN_VALUE":
            return stack.pop()


def func():
    a = 1
    return a
</code></pre>

<p>If you gave this interpreter our test function, it would execute them and print the results:</p>
<pre><code>print(interpret(func))
</code></pre>

<p>This loop with a big switch/if-else statement is an equivalent, albeit simplified version of how CPython’s interpreter loop works. CPython is written in C and compiled by a C compiler. For the sake of simplicity I’ll build out this example in Python.</p>
<p>For our interpreter, everytime you want to run the function, <code>func</code> it has to loop through each instruction and compare the bytecode name (called the opcode) with each if-statement. Both this comparison and the loop itself add an overhead to the execution. That overhead seems redundant if you run the function 10,000 times and the bytecodes never change (because they are immutable). It would be more efficient to instead generate the code in a sequence instead of a evaluating this loop every time you call the function.</p>
<p>This is what a JIT does. There are many types of JIT compiler. Numba is a JIT. PyPy has a JIT. Java has lots of JITs. Pyston and Pyjion are JITs.</p>
<p>The JIT that is proposed for Python 3.13 is a copy-any-patch JIT.</p>
<h2>What is a copy-and-patch JIT?</h2>
<p>Never heard of a copy-and-patch JIT? Don’t worry, nor had I and nor have most people. It’s an idea <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3485513">only proposed recently in 2021</a> and designed as a fast algorithm for dynamic language runtimes.</p>
<p>I’ll try and explain what a copy-and-patch JIT is by expanding our interpreter loop and rewriting it as a JIT. Before, the interpreter loop did two things, first it interpreted (looked at the bytecode) then it executed (ran the instruction). What we can do instead is to seperate those tasks and have the interpreter output the instructions and not execute them.</p>
<p>A <strong>copy-and-patch</strong> JIT is the idea that you <strong>copy</strong> the instructions for each command and fill-in-the-blanks for that bytecode arguments (or <strong>patch</strong>). Here’s a rewritten example, I keep the loop very similar but each time I append a code string with the Python code to execute:</p>
<pre><code>def copy_and_patch_interpret(func):
    code = 'def f():\n'
    code += '  stack = []\n'
    code += '  variables = {}\n'
    for instruction in dis.get_instructions(func):
        if instruction.opname == "LOAD_CONST":
            code += f'  stack.append({instruction.argval})\n'
        elif instruction.opname == "LOAD_FAST":
            code += f'  stack.append(variables["{instruction.argval}"])\n'
        elif instruction.opname == "STORE_FAST":
            code += f'  variables["{instruction.argval}"] = stack.pop()\n'
        elif instruction.opname == "RETURN_VALUE":
            code += '  return stack.pop()\n'
    code += 'f()'
    return code
</code></pre>

<p>This result for the original function is:</p>
<pre><code>def f():
  stack = []
  variables = {}
  stack.append(1)
  variables["a"] = stack.pop()
  stack.append(None)
  return stack.pop()
f()
</code></pre>

<p>This time, the code is <strong>sequential</strong> and doesn’t require the loop to execute. We can store the resulting string and run it as many times as we like:</p>
<pre><code>compiled_function = compile(copy_and_patch_interpret(func), filename="&lt;string&gt;", mode="exec")

print(exec(compiled_function))
print(exec(compiled_function))
print(exec(compiled_function))
</code></pre>

<p>What was the point in that? Well the resulting code does the same thing, but it should run faster. I gave the two implementations to <a href="https://pypi.org/project/richbench/">rich bench</a> and the copy-and-patch method runs faster <em>(Keep in mind though that loops in Python are very slow compared to C.)</em></p>
<h2>Why a copy-and-patch JIT?</h2>
<p>This technique of writing out the instructions for each bytecode and patching the values has upsides and downsides compared to a “full” JIT compiler. A full JIT compiler would normally compile high-level bytecodes like <code>LOAD_FAST</code> into lower level instructions in an IL (Intermediate Language). Because every CPU architecture has different instructions and features, it would be monumentally-complicated to write a compiler that converts high-level code directly to machine code and supports 32-bit and 64-bit CPUs, as well as Apple’s ARM architecture as well as all the other flavours of ARM. Instead most JIT’s compile first to an IL that is a generic machine-code-like instruction set. Those instructions are things like “PUSH A 64-bit integer”, “POP a 64-bit float”, “MULTIPLY the values on the stack”. The JIT can then compile IL into machine-code at runtime by emitting CPU-specific instructions and storing them in memory to be later executed (similar to how we did in our example).</p>
<p>Once you have IL, you can run all sorts of fun optimizations on the code like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Constant_folding">constant propagation</a> and loop hoisting. You can see an example of this in <a href="https://live.trypyjion.com/">Pyjion’s live compiler UI</a>.</p>
<p>The big downside with a “full” JIT is that the process of compiling once into IL and then again into machine code is <strong>slow</strong>. Not only is it slow, but it is memory intensive. To illustrate this, data from recent research <a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/spe.3267">“Python meets JIT compilers: A simple implementation and a comparative evaluation”</a> showed that Java-based JITs for Python like GraalPy, and Jython can take up to 100 times longer to start than normal CPython and consume up to an additional Gigabyte of RAM to compile. There are already full JIT implementations for Python.</p>
<p>Copy-and-patch was selected because the compilation from bytecodes to machine code is done as a set of “templates” that are then stitched together and patched at runtime with the correct values. This means that your average Python user isn’t running this complex JIT compiler architecture inside their Python runtime. Python writing it’s own IL and JIT would also be unreasonable since so many are available off-the-shelf like LLVMs and ryuJIT. But a full-JIT would require those being bundled with Python and all the added overheads. A copy-and-patch JIT only requires the LLVM JIT tools be installed on the machine where CPython is compiled from source, and for most people that means the machines of the CI that builds and packages CPython for python.org.</p>
<h2>So how does this JIT work?</h2>
<p>The copy-and-patch compiler for Python works by extending some new (and honestly not widely known about) APIs to Python 3.13’s API. These changes enable pluggable optimizers to be discoverable at runtime in CPython and control how code is executed. This new JIT is an optional optimizer for this new architecture. I assume that it will be the default in future versions once the major bugs have been squashed. </p>
<p>When you compile CPython from source, you can provide a flag <code>--enable-experimental-jit</code> to the configure script. This will generate machine-code templates for the Python bytecodes. This happens by first copying the C code for each bytecode, for example for LOAD_CONST, the simplest:</p>
<pre><code>frame-&gt;instr_ptr = next_instr;
next_instr += 1;
INSTRUCTION_STATS(LOAD_CONST); // Not used unless compiled with instrumentation
PyObject *value;
value = GETITEM(FRAME_CO_CONSTS, oparg);
Py_INCREF(value);
stack_pointer[0] = value;
stack_pointer += 1;
DISPATCH();
</code></pre>

<p>The instructions for this bytecode are first compiled by the C compiled into a little shared library and then stored as machine code. Because there are some variables normally determined at runtime, like <code>oparg</code>, the C code is compiled with those parameters left as <code>0</code>. There is then a list of the 0 values that need to be filled in, called holes. For <code>LOAD_CONST</code>, there are 2 holes to be filled , the oparg and the next instruction:</p>
<pre><code>static const Hole _LOAD_CONST_code_holes[3] = {
    {0xd, HoleKind_X86_64_RELOC_UNSIGNED, HoleValue_OPARG, NULL, 0x0},
    {0x46, HoleKind_X86_64_RELOC_UNSIGNED, HoleValue_CONTINUE, NULL, 0x0},
};
</code></pre>

<p>All of the machine code is then stored as a sequence of bytes in the file <code>jit_stencil.h</code> which is automatically generated by a new build stage. The disassembled code is stored as a comment above each bytecode template, where <code>JIT_OPARG</code> and <code>JIT_CONTINUE</code> are the holes to be filled:</p>
<pre><code>0000000000000000 &lt;__JIT_ENTRY&gt;:
pushq   %rbp
movq    %rsp, %rbp
movq    (%rdi), %rax
movq    0x28(%rax), %rax
movabsq $0x0, %rcx
000000000000000d:  X86_64_RELOC_UNSIGNED        __JIT_OPARG
movzwl  %cx, %ecx
movq    0x28(%rax,%rcx,8), %rax
movl    0xc(%rax), %ecx
incl    %ecx
je      0x3d &lt;__JIT_ENTRY+0x3d&gt;
movq    %gs:0x0, %r8
cmpq    (%rax), %r8
jne     0x37 &lt;__JIT_ENTRY+0x37&gt;
movl    %ecx, 0xc(%rax)
jmp     0x3d &lt;__JIT_ENTRY+0x3d&gt;
lock
addq    $0x4, 0x10(%rax)
movq    %rax, (%rsi)
addq    $0x8, %rsi
movabsq $0x0, %rax
0000000000000046:  X86_64_RELOC_UNSIGNED        __JIT_CONTINUE
popq    %rbp
jmpq    *%rax
</code></pre>

<p>The new JIT compiler, will when activated copy the machine-code instructions for each bytecode into a sequence and replace the values for each template with the arguments for that bytecode in the code object. The resulting machine code is stored in memory and then each time the Python function is run, that machine-code is executed directly.</p>
<p>You can see the JITted code if you compile <a href="https://github.com/brandtbucher/cpython/pull/32">my branch</a> and try it on this <a href="https://gist.github.com/tonybaloney/7e12e416ad69968e297547498f7bcde1">test script</a> then give it to a disassembler like Ada Pro or Hopper. At the moment,  the JIT is only used if the function contains the <code>JUMP_BACKWARD</code> opcode which is used in the <code>while</code> statement but that will change in the future.</p>
<h2>Is it faster?</h2>
<p>The initial benchmarks show something of <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/pull/113465#issuecomment-1876225775">a 2-9% performance improvement</a>. You might be disappointed by this number, especially since this blog post has been talking about assembly and machine code and nothing is faster than that right? Well, remember that CPython is already written in C and that was already compiled to machine-code by the C compiler. In most cases, this JIT will be executing almost the same machine-code instructions as it was before.</p>
<p><strong>However</strong>, think of this JIT as being the cornerstone of a series of much larger optimizations. None of which are possible without it. For this change to be accepted, understood and maintained in an open-source project it needs to start simple.</p>
<h2>The future is bright, the future is JIT compiled</h2>
<p>The challenges with the existing interpreter being compiled ahead-of-time are that there are fewer opportunities for serious optimizations. Python 3.11’s adaptive interpreter was a step in the right direction, but it needs to go a lot further for Python to see a step-change in performance. </p>
<p>I think that whilst the first version of this JIT isn’t going to seriously dent any benchmarks (yet), it opens the door to some huge optimizations and not just ones that benefit the toy benchmark programs in the standard benchmark suite. </p>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Where Have All the Websites Gone? (356 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fromjason.xyz/p/notebook/where-have-all-the-websites-gone/</link>
            <guid>38923627</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 08:13:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fromjason.xyz/p/notebook/where-have-all-the-websites-gone/">https://www.fromjason.xyz/p/notebook/where-have-all-the-websites-gone/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38923627">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>   

<p>It’s Tuesday morning. The year is 2009. You’re just waking up after a long and boozy New Year’s Eve with friends. Your head rings, and your mouth is the type of dry that makes you question your adulthood. You feel something scratch against your arm. Did you take a lover last night? Sort of. It’s a pizza box. Meat lovers.</p>
<p>You reach for your phone. There’s no TikTok or Snapchat yet. Facebook and Instagram are a thing, but they exist as a type of social syndicator— a place to see what your friends were up to last night. You already know as much. The occasional whiff of rank vodka keeps your memory jogged. You tap the browser icon and start typing a web￼ address, perhaps appending <code>www</code> as a precautionary ￼relic. <em>Who got drunker than me</em>, you wonder. After a brief page load, you arrive at textsfromlastnight.com. “<em>I cant get the smell of ass out of my nose</em>,” reads the top post.</p>
<p>You scroll, pausing only for the occasional forward to your best friend, who undoubtedly hurts as much as you. You both laugh at the crass misfortunes of others and quietly hope you hadn’t somehow made it onto the front page yourself.</p>
<p>You copy the link to the best of the bunch, the story that made you laugh the hardest, and post it to your Facebook.</p>
<h2 id="for-you-but-not-by-us" tabindex="-1">For you, but not by us. <a href="#for-you-but-not-by-us">#</a></h2>
<p>For better or worse, the web doesn’t work like that anymore. No one clicks a webpage hoping to learn which cat <em>can haz cheeseburger</em>. Weirdos, maybe. <em>Sickos</em>.</p>
<p>No, we get our content from a For You Page now— algorithmically selected videos and images made by our favorite creators, produced explicitly for our preferred platform. Which platform doesn’t matter much. So long as it’s one of the big five. Creators churn out content for all of them.</p>
<p>It’s a technical marvel, that internet. Something so mindblowingly impressive that if you showed it to someone even thirty years ago, their face would melt the fuck off. So why does it feel like something’s missing? Why are we all so collectively unhappy with the state of the web?</p>
<h2 id="where-did-all-the-websites-go" tabindex="-1">Where <em>did</em> all the websites go? <a href="#where-did-all-the-websites-go">#</a></h2>
<p>A tweet went viral this Thanksgiving when a Twitter user posed a question to their followers. A peek at the comments, and I could only assume the tweet struck a nerve. It certainly did with me. It's why I wrote this piece.</p>
<p><img src="https://fromjason.xyz/img/image-wheredidallthewebsitesgo.jpg" alt="tweet"></p>
<p>Everyone had their own answer. Some comments blamed the app-ification of the web. "<em>Everything is an app now!</em>," one user replied. Others point to the death of Adobe Flash and how so many sites and games died along with it. Everyone agrees that websites have indeed vanished, and we all miss the days we were free to visit them.</p>
<p>I have good news and bad news.</p>
<p>The good news is that websites didn’t go anywhere. There are currently one billion websites on the World Wide Web. Here’s a few from my bookmarks that are <em>amazing</em>.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://anthonybourdain.tumblr.com/">Anthony Bourdain’s Tumblr</a></li>
<li><a href="https://yesterweb.org/">Yesterweb.org</a></li>
<li><a href="https://grumpy.website/">Grumpy Website</a></li>
<li><a href="https://solar.lowtechmagazine.com/">Low-Tech Magazine</a></li>
<li><a href="http://www.lostparks.com/">Florida’s Lost Tourist Attractions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.abandonedamerica.us/abandoned-theaters">Abandoned America</a></li>
<li><a href="https://letterboxd.tools/Film_taste_compatibility_test">Letterbox Compatibility Test</a></li>
<li><a href="https://everynoise.com/">Every Noise</a></li>
<li><a href="https://designmanifestos.org/">Design Manifestos</a></li>
<li><a href="https://amtrakexplorer.com/">Amtrak Explorer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/archive/">The Atlantic Archive</a></li>
<li><a href="https://cari.institute/aesthetics">CARI Aesthetics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://potato.cheap/">The Cheap Web</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Cool, right? So here’s the bad news— <em>we</em> are the ones who vanished, and I suspect what we really miss are the joys of discovery.</p>
<h2 id="we-miss-curation" tabindex="-1">We miss curation <a href="#we-miss-curation">#</a></h2>
<p>We used to know how to do this. Not long ago, we were good at separating the signal from noise. Granted, there’s a lot more noise these days, but most of it comes from and is encouraged by the silos we dwell in.</p>
<p>Somewhere between the late 2000’s aggregator sites and the contemporary For You Page, we lost our ability to <em>curate</em> the web. Worse still, we’ve outsourced our discovery to corporate algorithms. Most of us did it in exchange for an endless content feed. By most, I mean upwards of 90% who don’t make content on a platform as understood by the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1%25_rule">90/9/1 rule</a>. And that’s okay! Or, at least, it makes total sense to me. Who wouldn’t want a steady stream of dopamine shots?</p>
<p>The rest of us, <a href="https://www.fromjason.xyz/p/notebook/how-do-we-stop-meta-in-2024-we-fix-the-information-loop/">posters, amplifiers, and aggregators</a>, traded our discovery autonomy for a chance at fame and fortune. Not all, but enough to change the social web landscape.</p>
<p>But that gold at the end of the rainbow isn’t for us. “Creator funds” pull from a fixed pot. It’s a line item in a budget that doesn’t change, whether one hundred or one million hands dip inside it. Executives in polished cement floor offices, who you’ll never meet, <em>choose</em> their winners and losers. And I’m guessing it’s not a meritocracy-based system. They pick their tokens, round up their shills, and stuff Apple Watch ads between them.</p>
<p>So when we wonder where all the websites have gone, know it’s the <em>curators</em> we’re nostalgic for because the curators showed us the best the web had to offer once upon a time. And the curators— the tenders, aggregators, collectors, and connectors— can bring us back to something better. Because it’s still out there, we just have to find it.</p>
<p>Here’s the best part. You can be that curator right now, at this very moment. You can start to rebuild the interconnectivity that made the web fun to explore. And you don’t need to be a computer scientist to do it.</p>
<p>Open a Linktree account or whatever. And instead of adding your other social media accounts, add three links to your favorite blog posts. Or, add links to a few artists with their own sites. Or your favorite aggregator sites. It doesn’t matter what you include, so long as we make portals to other digital green spaces that exist outside of Instagram.</p>
<p><strong>Then, throw that list into your link-in-bio</strong>. I just <a href="https://www.instagram.com/jasondotgov/">swapped my IG link</a> from my home page to a post listing my favorite blogging platforms. Most, if not all, are from “indie” developers. And who knows, maybe someone clicks on it and the web gains a new writer. How cool would that be?</p>
<p>So what do ya say? Let's make a bunch of open web <em>portals</em> for 2024! I guess I set this up for a two-parter, haven’t I? I’ll see you at the next post.</p>

 </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DARPA Moves Forward on X-65: Plane with no moving control surfaces (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.darpa.mil/news-events/2024-01-03</link>
            <guid>38922657</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 05:22:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.darpa.mil/news-events/2024-01-03">https://www.darpa.mil/news-events/2024-01-03</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38922657">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ContentPane" role="main">

						

						<div>
							<h2>Tags</h2>
						</div>
						<!-- need a horizontal datalist control so that tag values can be bound to the anchor tag with the id of the tag -->

						<p><span>|</span>

						</p>


						







						<div id="myRelatedContent_dRelated">
								<h2>Similarly&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Tagged&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Content</h2>
								
							</div>

						<div id="divMedia">
							<p>
								<h2>Images</h2>
							</p>
							<ul id="ulMedia">
							</ul>
						</div>

					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bit-Banging Bluetooth Low Energy (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dmitry.gr/?r=05.Projects&amp;proj=11.%20Bluetooth%20LE%20fakery</link>
            <guid>38922040</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 03:43:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dmitry.gr/?r=05.Projects&#x26;proj=11.%20Bluetooth%20LE%20fakery">https://dmitry.gr/?r=05.Projects&#x26;proj=11.%20Bluetooth%20LE%20fakery</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38922040">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<h2>Faking Bluetooth LE</h2>
<p><b>Bluetooth LE</b> is a new technology, introduced in the Bluetooth 4.0 spec. It has <i>absolutely nothing</i> to do with bluetooth besides the name. Now that we have that out of the way, why is it cool? Well, it was made for low power, and the design shows. Unlike real bluetooth that does frequency hoppping on a precise schedule, regardless of anything, LE hops after some number of packets are sent, and thus one does not need to be awake to keep a running clock to know where to hop to next. In fact, LE allows a device to completely shut down its radio for large periods of time while maintaining a connection. This makes it awesome for keyboards and mice and all kinds of other such things. Another cool feature in LE is that devices can send unsolicited broadcasts of small chunks of data. Unlike real bluetooth, scanning for devices in the LE world can be passive - you just listen for advertisement packets on the right channels and you hear all the advertisements.
</p>
<p><b>The simple channel hopping behaviour</b> of LE means that we can probably pretend to be an LE device without the complex radio that normal bluetoth requires. The frequency is 2.4GHz, chanels are 1MHz apart, modulation is GFSK, datarate is 1MBps, preamble is 10101010 or 01010101 based on first data byte, and addressing is done using a 32-bit address. Gee, don't we know a device that can do all that? Of course we do! The ever-popular <a href="http://www.semiconductorstore.com/cart/pc/viewPrd.asp?idproduct=41939">Nordic nRF24L01+</a>. So let's look at the differences between what LE needs and what we have:</p><ul><li><b>CRC:</b> BTLE uses a 24-bit CRC that is not something nRF24 can do. Luckily for us, nRF24 allows us to disable the CRC, and then we can send our own and check received ones manually. Unpleasant? Sure, but doable.</li><li><b>Frequency Hopping:</b> BTLE needs ut to be able to hop quickly - 150us or faster. Sadly here nRF24 fails us. After every transmission it shuts down its PLL, and then restarts it on every transmit or receive command. This takes 130us. We are left with too little time to do anything here, sadly. Luckily this is not the major issue.</li><li><b>Packet Length:</b> BTLE packets are of various sizes, up to 39 bytes of payload in fact. But the one packet we would really want to support is the CONNECT_REQ packet, which is in fact 34 bytes of payload + 3 of CRC, meaning we'd need to receive 37 bytes if we want to check CRCs, and even if we were willing to throw caution to the wind and ignore them, we need to receive 34. nRF24 will not handle packets over 32 bytes. Sadly the last two bytes are kind of important (hop size and a part of the channel map). This is where we lose.</li></ul>

<p><b>So... we cannot accept connections,</b> but not all is lost... BTLE allows unsolicited advertisements, so we can still do some cool things by making them broadcast data to anyone who'll listen. Let's work out just how much data we can send... Out of our 32-byte budget: 3 go into CRC, 2 go into the ADV_NONCONN_IND packet header,  and 6 go into the MAC address, leaving us with 21 bytes of payload. This payload, however, must have structure. Assuming minimum required headers, we can get away with sending 19 bytes of data if we do not want our device to broadcast a name. If we do want a name, we have 17 bytes to split between the name (in UTF-8) and our data. And if we want to comply with the spec better and broadcast device attributes, we'll have 14 bytes to split between name and data or 16 bytes of pure data - not too bad.
</p>
<p><b>Let's sort out the details</b> then... first of all, BTLE and nRF24 send data bits in the air in opposite order, so we'll have to reverse all our bits. Second, BTLE uses data whitening, and nRF24 does not, so we'll need to do that by hand too. Lastly, there is the previously-mentioned 24-bit CRC. All LE broadcasts get sent to the same "address": 0x8E89BED6, also known as "bed six." Of course, for us it'll be bit-reversed. BTLE applies CRC to the whole payload but not the address. Whitening is applied to the payload and the CRC. Knowing this, thus, gives us the ordering of events needed to assemble a complete working packet. Advertisement packets are sent on 3 channels: 37, 38, and 39, which are 2.402HGz, 2.426GHz, and 2.480GHz respectively. We'll alternate between them, spewing our broadcast everywhere methodically.
</p>
<p><b>BTLE CRC</b> is not too hard to implement in C, uses the initial value of 0x555555, and looks something like this: </p><div><pre>void btLeCrc(const uint8_t* data, uint8_t len, uint8_t* dst){

	uint8_t v, t, d;

	while(len--){
		d = *data++;
		for(v = 0; v &lt; 8; v++, d &gt;&gt;= 1){
		
			t = dst[0] &gt;&gt; 7;
			dst[0] &lt;&lt;= 1;
			if(dst[1] &amp; 0x80) dst[0] |= 1;
			dst[1] &lt;&lt;= 1;
			if(dst[2] &amp; 0x80) dst[1] |= 1;
			dst[2] &lt;&lt;= 1;
			
			if(t != (d &amp; 1)){
			
				dst[2] ^= 0x5B;
				dst[1] ^= 0x06;
			}
		}	
	}
}</pre></div>

<p><b>The data whitening function</b> is also not too complicated. It is a 7-bit linear-shift feedback style and is initialized by the value that is equal to (channelNum &lt;&lt; 1) + 1. The code goes something like this: </p><div><pre>void btLeWhiten(uint8_t* data, uint8_t len, uint8_t whitenCoeff){
	uint8_t  m;
	
	while(len--){
	
		for(m = 1; m; m &lt;&lt;= 1){
		
			if(whitenCoeff &amp; 0x80){
				
				whitenCoeff ^= 0x11;
				(*data) ^= m;
			}
			whitenCoeff &lt;&lt;= 1;
		}
		data++;
	}
}</pre></div>

<p><b>The advertisement packet payload</b> looks like this:</p><div><pre>struct adv_hdr{
	uint8_t header; //we use 0x40 to say it is a non-connectable undirected
			//advertisement and address we're sending is random (not assigned)
	uint8_t dataLen; //length of following data (including MAC addr)
	uint8_t MAC[6]; //the mac address
}</pre></div>

<p><b>So if we lump all this together,</b> we'll end up with a packet with the above header. We then CRC it using the above CRC function. We then whiten it using the above whitening function. After this we send it. Let's see... yup, it works. An iPad3 running BTLExplorer shows that our device is visible and is a BTLE device. Cool! One caveat: if you do not broadcast a device name, BTLExplorer will crash - this is their bug, so do not worry.
</p>
<p><b>What is the payload data format?</b> you may ask. Well, data is made of chunks, each of which has a 2-byte header: length and type (in that order, length includes the length of the type byte). Types you care about are:</p><ul><li><b>2:</b> Flags - length will be 2 and the lone byte's value you want is 5 - this means a single-mode (not BTLE/BT combo) device in limited discovery mode.</li><li><b>8 or 9:</b> Name - length is the length of the name in UTF-8 without NULL-termination. 8 is for "shortened name" and 9 is for "complete name."</li><li><b>255:</b> Custom data. This is where you can shove your custom data. On iPhone you'll have complete access to this.</li></ul>

<p><b>Why all this?</b> Well, if you know a simpler way for an embedded project to communicate data to an iPhone, let me know. WiFi is power hungry and messy. Real bluetooth is locked down in iPhone, as are serial ports. This method works. If and when Android gets a BTLE API, I am sure broadcast data will be available to you too - it just makes sense.
</p>
<p><b>Future work:</b> I just got some non-nordic 2.4GHz parts that support packets up to 64 bytes and can keep their PPLs on, meaning that a full BTLE stack may be possible on them. I am working on this as you read this.
</p>
<p>All the code as well as the research that went into this and is published here is under this license: you may use it in any way you please if and only if it is for non-commercial purposes, you must provide a link to this page as well. Any commercial use must be discussed with me.
</p>
<p><b>Full sample code</b>, that will run on the nordic-fob from Sparkfun looks <b>approximately</b> like this:</p><div><pre>#include &lt;stdio.h&gt;
#include &lt;avr/io.h&gt;
#include &lt;avr/interrupt.h&gt;
#include &lt;avr/sleep.h&gt;
#define F_CPU	8000000
#include &lt;avr/delay.h&gt;


#define PIN_CE	1 //Output
#define PIN_nCS	2 //Output


#define MY_MAC_0	0xEF
#define MY_MAC_1	0xFF
#define MY_MAC_2	0xC0
#define MY_MAC_3	0xAA
#define MY_MAC_4	0x18
#define MY_MAC_5	0x00


ISR(PCINT0_vect)
{
	//useless
}

void btLeCrc(const uint8_t* data, uint8_t len, uint8_t* dst){

	uint8_t v, t, d;

	while(len--){
	
		d = *data++;
		for(v = 0; v &lt; 8; v++, d &gt;&gt;= 1){
		
			t = dst[0] &gt;&gt; 7;
			
			dst[0] &lt;&lt;= 1;
			if(dst[1] &amp; 0x80) dst[0] |= 1;
			dst[1] &lt;&lt;= 1;
			if(dst[2] &amp; 0x80) dst[1] |= 1;
			dst[2] &lt;&lt;= 1;
			
		
			if(t != (d &amp; 1)){
			
				dst[2] ^= 0x5B;
				dst[1] ^= 0x06;
			}
		}	
	}
}

uint8_t  swapbits(uint8_t a){

	uint8 v = 0;
	
	if(a &amp; 0x80) v |= 0x01;
	if(a &amp; 0x40) v |= 0x02;
	if(a &amp; 0x20) v |= 0x04;
	if(a &amp; 0x10) v |= 0x08;
	if(a &amp; 0x08) v |= 0x10;
	if(a &amp; 0x04) v |= 0x20;
	if(a &amp; 0x02) v |= 0x40;
	if(a &amp; 0x01) v |= 0x80;

	return v;
}

void btLeWhiten(uint8_t* data, uint8_t len, uint8_t whitenCoeff){

	uint8_t  m;
	
	while(len--){
	
		for(m = 1; m; m &lt;&lt;= 1){
		
			if(whitenCoeff &amp; 0x80){
				
				whitenCoeff ^= 0x11;
				(*data) ^= m;
			}
			whitenCoeff &lt;&lt;= 1;
		}
		data++;
	}
}

static inline uint8_t btLeWhitenStart(uint8_t chan){
	//the value we actually use is what BT'd use left shifted one...makes our life easier

	return swapbits(chan) | 2;	
}

void btLePacketEncode(uint8_t* packet, uint8_t len, uint8_t chan){
	//length is of packet, including crc. pre-populate crc in packet with initial crc value!

	uint8_t i, dataLen = len - 3;
	
	btLeCrc(packet, dataLen, packet + dataLen);
	for(i = 0; i &lt; 3; i++, dataLen++) packet[dataLen] = swapbits(packet[dataLen]);
	btLeWhiten(packet, len, btLeWhitenStart(chan));
	for(i = 0; i &lt; len; i++) packet[i] = swapbits(packet[i]);
	
}

uint8_t spi_byte(uint8_t byte){

	uint8_t i = 0;
	
	do{
		PORTB &amp;=~ (uint8_t)(1 &lt;&lt; 6);
		if(byte &amp; 0x80) PORTB |= (uint8_t)(1 &lt;&lt; 6);
		CLK |= (uint8_t)(1 &lt;&lt; 4);
		byte &lt;&lt;= 1;
		if(PINA &amp; (uint8_t)32) byte++;
		CLK &amp;=~ (uint8_t)(1 &lt;&lt; 4);
	
	}while(--i);

	return byte;
}

void nrf_cmd(uint8_t cmd, uint8_t data)
{
	cbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
	spi_byte(cmd);
	spi_byte(data);
	sbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS); //Deselect chip
}

void nrf_simplebyte(uint8_t cmd)
{
	cbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
	spi_byte(cmd);
	sbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
}

void nrf_manybytes(uint8_t* data, uint8_t len){

	cbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
	do{
	
		spi_byte(*data++);
	
	}while(--len);
	sbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
}

void fob_init (void)
{
	DDRA = (uint8_t)~(1&lt;&lt;5);
	DDRB = 0b00000110;
	PORTA = 0b10001111;
	cbi(PORTB, PIN_CE);
	TCCR0B = (1&lt;&lt;CS00);
	MCUCR = (1&lt;&lt;SM1)|(1&lt;&lt;SE);
	sei();
}

int main (void)
{
	static const uint8_t chRf[] = {2, 26,80};
	static const uint8_t chLe[] = {37,38,39};
	uint8_t i, L, ch = 0;
	uint8_t buf[32];
	
	fob_init();
	
	DDRA |= 4;
	PORTA |= 4;
	
	nrf_cmd(0x20, 0x12);	//on, no crc, int on RX/TX done
	nrf_cmd(0x21, 0x00);	//no auto-acknowledge
	nrf_cmd(0x22, 0x00);	//no RX
	nrf_cmd(0x23, 0x02);	//5-byte address
	nrf_cmd(0x24, 0x00);	//no auto-retransmit
	nrf_cmd(0x26, 0x06);	//1MBps at 0dBm
	nrf_cmd(0x27, 0x3E);	//clear various flags
	nrf_cmd(0x3C, 0x00);	//no dynamic payloads
	nrf_cmd(0x3D, 0x00);	//no features
	nrf_cmd(0x31, 32);	//always RX 32 bytes
	nrf_cmd(0x22, 0x01);	//RX on pipe 0
	
	buf[0] = 0x30;			//set addresses
	buf[1] = swapbits(0x8E);
	buf[2] = swapbits(0x89);
	buf[3] = swapbits(0xBE);
	buf[4] = swapbits(0xD6);
	nrf_manybytes(buf, 5);
	buf[0] = 0x2A;
	nrf_manybytes(buf, 5);

	
	
	while(1){
		
		L = 0;
		
		buf[L++] = 0x40;	//PDU type, given address is random
�Xbuf[L++] = 11;X�//17 bytes of payload
		
		buf[L++] = MY_MAC_0;
		buf[L++] = MY_MAC_1;
		buf[L++] = MY_MAC_2;
		buf[L++] = MY_MAC_3;
		buf[L++] = MY_MAC_4;
		buf[L++] = MY_MAC_5;
		
		buf[L++] = 2;		//flags (LE-only, limited discovery mode)
		buf[L++] = 0x01;
		buf[L++] = 0x05;
		
		buf[L++] = 7;
		buf[L++] = 0x08;
		buf[L++] = 'n';
		buf[L++] = 'R';
		buf[L++] = 'F';
		buf[L++] = ' ';
		buf[L++] = 'L';
		buf[L++] = 'E';
		
		buf[L++] = 0x55;	//CRC start value: 0x555555
		buf[L++] = 0x55;
		buf[L++] = 0x55;
		
		
		if(++ch == sizeof(chRf)) ch = 0;
		
		nrf_cmd(0x25, chRf[ch]);
		nrf_cmd(0x27, 0x6E);	//clear flags

		btLePacketEncode(buf, L, chLe[ch]);
		
		nrf_simplebyte(0xE2); //Clear RX Fifo
		nrf_simplebyte(0xE1); //Clear TX Fifo
	
		cbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
		spi_byte(0xA0);
		for(i = 0 ; i &lt; L ; i++) spi_byte(buf[i]);
		sbi(PORTB, PIN_nCS);
	
		nrf_cmd(0x20, 0x12);	//tx on
		sbi(PORTB, PIN_CE);	 //do tx
		delay_ms(10);
		cbi(PORTB, PIN_CE);	(in preparation of switching to RX quickly)
	}
	
	
	return 0;
}
</pre></div>


					
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mixtral 8x7B: A Sparse Mixture of Experts language model (325 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04088</link>
            <guid>38921668</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 02:53:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04088">https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04088</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38921668">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
    <div><p><span>Authors:</span><a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Jiang,+A+Q">Albert Q. Jiang</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Sablayrolles,+A">Alexandre Sablayrolles</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Roux,+A">Antoine Roux</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Mensch,+A">Arthur Mensch</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Savary,+B">Blanche Savary</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Bamford,+C">Chris Bamford</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Chaplot,+D+S">Devendra Singh Chaplot</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=de+las+Casas,+D">Diego de las Casas</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Hanna,+E+B">Emma Bou Hanna</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Bressand,+F">Florian Bressand</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lengyel,+G">Gianna Lengyel</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Bour,+G">Guillaume Bour</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lample,+G">Guillaume Lample</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lavaud,+L+R">Lélio Renard Lavaud</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Saulnier,+L">Lucile Saulnier</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lachaux,+M">Marie-Anne Lachaux</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Stock,+P">Pierre Stock</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Subramanian,+S">Sandeep Subramanian</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Yang,+S">Sophia Yang</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Antoniak,+S">Szymon Antoniak</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Scao,+T+L">Teven Le Scao</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Gervet,+T">Théophile Gervet</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lavril,+T">Thibaut Lavril</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Wang,+T">Thomas Wang</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lacroix,+T">Timothée Lacroix</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Sayed,+W+E">William El Sayed</a></p></div>            
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2401.04088.pdf">Download PDF</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>We introduce Mixtral 8x7B, a Sparse Mixture of Experts (SMoE) language model. Mixtral has the same architecture as Mistral 7B, with the difference that each layer is composed of 8 feedforward blocks (i.e. experts). For every token, at each layer, a router network selects two experts to process the current state and combine their outputs. Even though each token only sees two experts, the selected experts can be different at each timestep. As a result, each token has access to 47B parameters, but only uses 13B active parameters during inference. Mixtral was trained with a context size of 32k tokens and it outperforms or matches Llama 2 70B and GPT-3.5 across all evaluated benchmarks. In particular, Mixtral vastly outperforms Llama 2 70B on mathematics, code generation, and multilingual benchmarks. We also provide a model fine-tuned to follow instructions, Mixtral 8x7B - Instruct, that surpasses GPT-3.5 Turbo, Claude-2.1, Gemini Pro, and Llama 2 70B - chat model on human benchmarks. Both the base and instruct models are released under the Apache 2.0 license.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Devendra Singh Chaplot [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/d382fa4f/2401.04088">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Mon, 8 Jan 2024 18:47:34 UTC (2,811 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mode7 Graphics Library for Playdate (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/risolvipro/playdate-mode7</link>
            <guid>38921518</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 02:31:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/risolvipro/playdate-mode7">https://github.com/risolvipro/playdate-mode7</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38921518">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:risolvipro/playdate-mode7" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="VSDdCHhZZGFlmSuNggHuegGHtTc-yk1y4ZhnmxAMR8pI9g0-MH394XIwlPeEFZX_AA45ds4OupWDD-tGsmrOqQ" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="risolvipro/playdate-mode7" data-current-org="" data-current-owner="risolvipro" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=qfs56yFFXBspFgEzeLF27tVWNf%2BsZ4zCLJqtqUI8h5%2FPcsj7afM421e1Iw4fkpKKaouxhaQK81FsAX089c%2FqJilcoWp%2FRhOyRRq7Dmx9WVVMRrjzN6ctJaU9WN%2BOrdTl%2BIPDcMc2%2BQqFZvo50iCHX3z3MO6gCYWYtWOczTZLwy1FVFvEVpjVcMbVwngPsWSP9QKECZLN2rRPn8dRfOMnuPkS39MbyneJyxM0hyUtz6s6B6oM8KrIP9KWdaClcNL2PbtfrICBr6dgcIPMim2w%2FuaoYKRT3fjcthb64bC9Gpn2AZR8Yl9iX6G%2FQi4AlGPX%2BVSLWdqrtXck4SJi6oAsglX9bfanDSXnasM5alCMuPd5gydL2Hay%2FD%2Fe%2BAwYMBFnk1OQjp5%2FiUGhtVOIT4mL338skMdPOLhW9JsT8AIPphyyfux%2Bd6Y0RkIda9IW4oVq5AKlvuRh7Z8jIKlOEwlLsiqOmwf9JMb7hPhcGukJJHfL24caTBWuoyMKOgFW934WcXydirwnhWHp6GOg06hAu%2FfvuXdyJ3wShIU%3D--mMNtYq2IefiX%2B2Mr--%2FOdWSGiOnYwdyyndhV1zvw%3D%3D&quot; />">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<div data-modal-dialog-overlay="">
  <modal-dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" role="dialog" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-disabled="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</modal-dialog></div>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=risolvipro%2Fplaydate-mode7" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/risolvipro/playdate-mode7&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="af5c9f22b2da516de4c895803a8e3644c2f7d80f3e9654c3755961a8f013e3c0" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
              Sign up
            </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why does holding a key fob to your head increase its range? (499 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/101913/why-does-a-remote-car-key-work-when-held-to-your-head-body</link>
            <guid>38921441</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 02:23:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/101913/why-does-a-remote-car-key-work-when-held-to-your-head-body">https://physics.stackexchange.com/questions/101913/why-does-a-remote-car-key-work-when-held-to-your-head-body</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38921441">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<p>Are you <em>sure</em> holding it to your head really makes it better? Your experiment is very poorly designed because you have only sampled instances where the remote wasn't working when your head wasn't in the picture. This is blatant <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Selection_bias" rel="nofollow noreferrer">selection bias</a>.</p>

<p>No doubt, putting the remote near your head (or anything else conductive) will significantly <em>alter</em> the electromagnetic radiations of the remote. But is it <em>better</em>, or just <em>different</em>? If it wasn't working to start, then you changed something, then it worked, that doesn't mean it's better. You need to also try holding it to your head, then find instances where that doesn't work, then try using the remote normally.</p>

<p>It's a common flaw in human reasoning at work here. People like to attribute success in some random or complex process to some ritual (in this case, putting the remote on your head) rather than simply realizing the success was due to an unrelated perturbation of the system, or simply another trial. Here's a familiar (at least, to people of the right age) instance of this flaw:</p>

<p><a href="http://xkcd.com/218/" rel="nofollow noreferrer"><img src="https://i.stack.imgur.com/Voo3d.png" alt="XKCD comic"></a></p>

<p>The <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nintendo_Entertainment_System" rel="nofollow noreferrer">NES</a> had game cartridges that were notoriously unreliable. The culprit was a cheaply designed electrical contact. Child wisdom had it that taking the cartridge out, vigorously blowing into the cartridge, and putting it back in would fix it. Each clan of children probably had some variation on this ritual, with important details, such as pushing the cartridge up and down a couple times, shaking the cartridge, leaving the door open, pressing the reset button multiple times, and so on. In reality, removing and re-inserting the cartridge and rebooting the NES just introduced another trial, and eventually it worked. The rest is insignificant ritual and superstition. (But don't tell any kids from the 80's that -- they won't believe you!)</p>

<p>That's not to say it's not <em>possible</em> your head does improve the remote's range. Indeed, your head will be inductively and capacitively coupled to the antenna. Significant RF currents will exist in your head, and some of this energy will be radiated, and your head will radiate differently than the antenna in the remote.</p>

<p>Perhaps, by virtue of your head's increased size, it makes a more efficient antenna. It's also possible, by virtue of your head's lower conductivity compared to copper, that it's a <em>less</em> effective antenna. It's also possible your head will act as a reflector, directing more of the radio's energy at the car. It's also possible your head will refract the waves away from the car.</p>

<p>The point is <em>we don't know</em>. All the research I've done turns up anecdotal evidence at best, by people who are not RF engineers performing similarly poorly designed experiments, or people who have talked to "an expert". I've never seen data collected by a qualified engineer with proper test equipment.</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Carta to exit secondary trading business (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://henrysward.medium.com/should-carta-facilitate-secondary-trading-c319e0c9f080</link>
            <guid>38921343</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 02:11:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://henrysward.medium.com/should-carta-facilitate-secondary-trading-c319e0c9f080">https://henrysward.medium.com/should-carta-facilitate-secondary-trading-c319e0c9f080</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38921343">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p id="e784">For those interested, let me provide more context below.</p><figure><figcaption><em>Liquidity has been a problem I wanted to solve for almost a decade. From our </em><a href="https://carta.com/blog/carta-series-a/" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank"><em>Series A deck</em></a><em> back in 2014.</em></figcaption></figure><p id="c81e"><strong>Nasdaq for Private Markets?</strong></p><p id="0306">We started eShares 10 years ago as the “Nasdaq for Private Markets” (we were not “the captable company”) because I wanted to solve the liquidity problem for founders, employees, and angel investors. The percentage of startups that get to IPO is so small that 99% of founders never receive liquidity and spend a decade or more paper rich but cash poor. That seemed a problem worth solving.</p><p id="9853">Fast forward to today, our business is broken down as follows: the captable business is about $250M/year, fund administration is about $100M, private equity is about $20M, and the secondary trading business is about $3M. We have done a decent job at building the captable business, an ok job at fund admin (but feeling the growing pains), and an abysmal job at the secondary business.</p><p id="03c1">It is my greatest failure and disappointment. Some of my other ideas have worked — like captables, 409As, fund administration, private equity. But ALL of my ideas around liquidity — auctions, investor matching, secondary trading, open tender offers, have not worked. I might not be the entrepreneur that can solve this problem.</p><p id="bf4c"><strong>Because We Have the Data, We Can’t Use It</strong></p><p id="4f4c">But I am learning something else — Carta might not be <em>the company</em> that can solve this problem. Many people think we are best poised to solve liquidity because we have captable data. But that same argument is used for data products. People say “You have all the data so you should put Pitchbook out of business!” But it is precisely <em>because </em>we have the data, that we can’t use it. It is our customers’ data, not ours. That’s why in ten years Carta has never released a data product. I use Pitchbook and Techcrunch when I research a company before I meet the CEO.</p><p id="efbe">Having ground truth data is not an advantage if we can’t use it. And it is a disadvantage if people think we use it. For example, if we send emails to prospects through publicly available information, how do customers know if we sourced it publicly or internally? Will they believe us if we tell them? And does it matter? Just the appearance of impropriety is damning.</p><p id="8c84"><strong>Founders Come First</strong></p><p id="ced6">From the beginning, we have always built for founders. Even in our liquidity business, the northstar has been to create systematic founder liquidity, that they control, which they can extend to everyone else on the captable. Historically, liquidity has not been founder friendly and our goal was to change that. But we have not succeeded.</p><p id="2441">We won’t do anything that threatens the trust of our founders. And so we will exit the secondary trading business to eliminate any concern that we are not acting in our founders’ best interests. We will focus on what we do best, which is cap table and fund administration software. There are many many talented people working on the private market liquidity problem. We will enthusiastically cheer for them from the sidelines. It is an important problem. I hope someone solves it.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I cut GTA Online loading times by 70% (2021) (197 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nee.lv/2021/02/28/How-I-cut-GTA-Online-loading-times-by-70/</link>
            <guid>38921237</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 01:55:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nee.lv/2021/02/28/How-I-cut-GTA-Online-loading-times-by-70/">https://nee.lv/2021/02/28/How-I-cut-GTA-Online-loading-times-by-70/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38921237">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>GTA Online. <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gtaonline/comments/9vgo0g/how_the_fuck_are_20_minute_load_times_acceptable/">Infamous</a> for its slow loading times. Having picked up the game again to finish some of the newer heists I was <em>shocked</em> (/s) to discover that it still loads just as slow as the day it was released 7 years ago.</p>
<p>It was time. Time to get to the bottom of this.</p>
<h2 id="Recon"><a href="#Recon" title="Recon"></a>Recon</h2><p>First I wanted to check if someone had already solved this problem. Most of the results I found pointed towards anecdata about <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://metro.co.uk/2017/11/01/why-does-gta-v-take-so-long-to-load-7041927/">how the game is so sophisticated</a> that it needs to load so long, stories on how the <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://steamcommunity.com/app/271590/discussions/0/217690940938819317/">p2p network architecture</a> is rubbish (not saying that it isn’t), some elaborate ways of <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://gtaforums.com/topic/908000-fastest-way-to-load-into-gtao-single-player-first-or-straight-in/">loading into story mode and a solo session after that</a> and a couple of mods that allowed skipping the startup R* logo video. Some more reading told me we could save a whopping 10-30 seconds with these combined!</p>
<p>Meanwhile on my PC…</p>
<h2 id="Benchmark"><a href="#Benchmark" title="Benchmark"></a>Benchmark</h2><figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br><span>8</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>Story mode load time:  ~1m 10s</span><br><span>Online mode load time: ~6m flat</span><br><span>Startup menu disabled, time from R* logo until in-game (social club login time isn't counted).</span><br><span></span><br><span>Old but decent CPU:   AMD FX-8350</span><br><span>Cheap-o SSD:          KINGSTON SA400S37120G</span><br><span>We have to have RAM:  2x Kingston 8192 MB (DDR3-1337) 99U5471</span><br><span>Good-ish GPU:         NVIDIA GeForce GTX 1070</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>I know my setup is dated but what on <em>earth</em> could take 6x longer to load into online mode? I couldn’t measure any difference using the story-to-online loading technique <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gtaonline/comments/kycy7a/gtao_loading_times_using_different_methods/">as others have found before me</a>. Even if it did work the results would be down in the noise.</p>
<h2 id="I-Am-Not-Alone"><a href="#I-Am-Not-Alone" title="I Am (Not) Alone"></a>I Am (Not) Alone</h2><p>If <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gtaonline/comments/ht4i56/your_average_online_loading_time/">this poll</a> is to be trusted then the issue is widespread enough to mildly annoy more than 80% of the player base. It’s been 7 years R*!</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-0.png" alt="🎵What does the poll say?🎵"></p>
<p>Looking around a bit to find who are the lucky ~20% that get sub 3 minute load times I came across <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RdCqDdjp6iU">a</a> <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pJzr3qfyCyg">few</a> <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RK7BUFx_NGk">benchmarks</a> with high-end gaming PCs and an online mode load time of about 2 minutes. I would <del>kill</del> <em>hack</em> for a 2 minute load time! It does seem to be hardware-dependent but something doesn’t add up here…</p>
<p>How come their story mode still takes near a minute to load? (The M.2 one didn’t count the startup logos btw.) Also, loading story to online takes them only a minute more while I’m getting about five more. I know that their hardware specs are a lot better but surely not 5x better.</p>
<h2 id="Highly-accurate-measurements"><a href="#Highly-accurate-measurements" title="Highly accurate measurements"></a>Highly accurate measurements</h2><p>Armed with such powerful tools as <em>the Task Manager</em> I began to investigate what resources could be the bottleneck.</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-1.png" alt="Can you smell it?"></p>
<p>After taking a minute to load the common resources used for both story and online modes (which is near on par with high-end PCs) GTA decides to max out a single core on my machine for four minutes and do nothing else.</p>
<p>Disk usage? None! Network usage? There’s a bit, but it drops basically to zero after a few seconds (apart from loading the rotating info banners). GPU usage? Zero. Memory usage? Completely flat…</p>
<p>What, is it mining crypto or something? I smell code. <em>Really bad code</em>.</p>
<h2 id="Single-thread-bound"><a href="#Single-thread-bound" title="Single thread-bound"></a>Single thread-bound</h2><p>While my old AMD CPU has 8 cores and it does pack a punch, it was made in the olden days. Back when AMD’s <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="http://valid.x86.fr/bench/6u7sdy/1">single-thread performance</a> was <em>way</em> behind Intel’s. This might not explain all of the load time differences but it should explain most of it.</p>
<p>What’s odd is that it’s using up <em>just</em> the CPU. I was expecting vast amounts of disk reads loading up resources or loads of network requests trying to negotiate a session in the p2p network. But this? This is probably a bug.</p>
<h2 id="Profiling"><a href="#Profiling" title="Profiling"></a>Profiling</h2><p>Profilers are a great way of finding CPU bottlenecks. There’s only one problem - most of them rely on instrumenting the source code to get a perfect picture of what’s happening in the process. And I don’t have the source code. Nor do I need microsecond-perfect readings - I have 4 minutes’ worth of a bottleneck.</p>
<p>Enter stack sampling: for closed source applications there’s only one option. Dump the running process’ stack and current instruction pointer’s location to build a calling tree in set intervals. Then add them up to get statistics on what’s going on. There’s only one profiler that I know of (might be ignorant here) that can do this on Windows. And it hasn’t been updated in over 10 years. It’s <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="http://lukestackwalker.sourceforge.net/">Luke Stackwalker</a>! Someone, please give this project some love :)</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-2.png" alt="The power of statistics compels you!"></p>
<p>Normally Luke would group the same functions together but since I don’t have debugging symbols I had to eyeball nearby addresses to guess if it’s the same place. And what do we see? Not one bottleneck but two of them!</p>
<h2 id="Down-the-rabbit-hole"><a href="#Down-the-rabbit-hole" title="Down the rabbit hole"></a>Down the rabbit hole</h2><p>Having borrowed <em>my friend’s</em> completely legitimate copy of <em>the industry-standard disassembler</em> (no, I really can’t afford the thing… gonna learn to <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://ghidra-sre.org/">ghidra</a> one of these days) I went to take GTA apart.</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-3.png" alt="Gibberish Galore"></p>
<p>That doesn’t look right at all. Most high-profile games come with built-in protection against reverse engineering to keep away pirates, cheaters, and modders. Not that it has ever stopped them.</p>
<p>There seems to be some sort of an obfuscation/encryption at play here that has replaced most instructions with gibberish. Not to worry, we simply need to dump the game’s memory while it’s executing the part we want to look at. The instructions have to be de-obfuscated before running one way or another. I had <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://github.com/glmcdona/Process-Dump">Process Dump</a> lying around, so I used that, but there are plenty of other tools available to do this sort of thing.</p>
<h2 id="Problem-one-It’s…-strlen"><a href="#Problem-one-It’s…-strlen" title="Problem one: It’s… strlen?!"></a>Problem one: It’s… strlen?!</h2><p>Disassembling the now-less-obfuscated dump reveals that one of the addresses has a label pulled out of somewhere! It’s <code>strlen</code>? Going down the call stack the next one is labeled <code>vscan_fn</code> and after that the labels end, tho I’m fairly confident it’s <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://github.com/chakra-core/ChakraCore/blob/master/pal/src/safecrt/sscanf.c#L47"><code>sscanf</code></a>.</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-4.png" alt="A graph a day keeps the skeptics away"></p>
<p>It’s parsing something. Parsing what? Untangling the disassembly would take forever so I decided to dump some samples from the running process using <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://x64dbg.com/">x64dbg</a>. Some debug-stepping later it turns out it’s… JSON! They’re parsing JSON. A whopping <strong>10 megabytes</strong> worth of JSON with some <strong>63k item entries</strong>.</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br><span>8</span><br><span>9</span><br><span>10</span><br><span>11</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>...,</span><br><span>{</span><br><span>    <span>"key"</span>: <span>"WP_WCT_TINT_21_t2_v9_n2"</span>,</span><br><span>    <span>"price"</span>: <span>45000</span>,</span><br><span>    <span>"statName"</span>: <span>"CHAR_KIT_FM_PURCHASE20"</span>,</span><br><span>    <span>"storageType"</span>: <span>"BITFIELD"</span>,</span><br><span>    <span>"bitShift"</span>: <span>7</span>,</span><br><span>    <span>"bitSize"</span>: <span>1</span>,</span><br><span>    <span>"category"</span>: [<span>"CATEGORY_WEAPON_MOD"</span>]</span><br><span>},</span><br><span>...</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>What is it? It appears to be data for a “net shop catalog” according to some references. I assume it contains a list of all the possible items and upgrades you can buy in GTA Online.</p>
<p>But 10 megs? That’s nothing! And using <code>sscanf</code> may not be optimal but surely it’s not that bad? Well…</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-5.png" alt="Ouch!"></p>
<p>Yeah, that’s gonna take a while… To be fair I had no idea most <code>sscanf</code> implementations called <code>strlen</code> so I can’t blame the developer who wrote this. I would assume it just scanned byte by byte and could stop on a <code>NULL</code>.</p>
<h2 id="Problem-two-Let’s-use-a-Hash-…-Array"><a href="#Problem-two-Let’s-use-a-Hash-…-Array" title="Problem two: Let’s use a Hash- … Array?"></a>Problem two: Let’s use a Hash- … Array?</h2><p>Turns out the second offender is called right next to the first one. They’re both even called in the same <code>if</code> statement as seen in this ugly decompilation:</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-6.png" alt="Beggar thy neighbour"></p>
<p>All labels are mine, no idea what the functions/parameters are actually called.</p>
<p>The second problem? Right after parsing an item, it’s stored in an array (or an inlined C++ list? not sure). Each entry looks something like this:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span><span>struct</span> {</span></span><br><span>    <span>uint64_t</span> *hash;</span><br><span>    <span>item_t</span>   *item;</span><br><span>} entry;</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>But before it’s stored? It checks the <em>entire</em> array, one by one, comparing the hash of the item to see if it’s in the list or not. With ~63k entries that’s <code>(n^2+n)/2 = (63000^2+63000)/2 = 1984531500</code> checks if my math is right. Most of them useless. You have unique <em>hashes</em> why not use a <em>hash map</em>.</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-7.png" alt="Oof!"></p>
<p>I named it <code>hashmap</code> while reversing but it’s clearly <code>not_a_hashmap</code>. And it gets even better. The hash-array-list-thing is empty before loading the JSON. And all of the items in the JSON are unique! They don’t even <em>need</em> to check if it’s in the list or not! They even have a function to directly insert the items! Just use that! Srsly, WAT!?</p>
<h2 id="PoC"><a href="#PoC" title="PoC"></a>PoC</h2><p>Now that’s nice and all, but no one is going to take me seriously unless I test this so I can write a clickbait title for the post.</p>
<p>The plan? Write a <code>.dll</code>, inject it in GTA, <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://github.com/TsudaKageyu/minhook">hook</a> some functions, ???, profit.</p>
<p>The JSON problem is hairy, I can’t realistically replace their parser. Replacing <code>sscanf</code> with one that doesn’t depend on <code>strlen</code> would be more realistic. But there’s an even easier way.</p>
<ul>
<li>hook strlen</li>
<li>wait for a long string</li>
<li>“cache” the start and length of it</li>
<li>if it’s called again within the string’s range, return cached value</li>
</ul>
<p>Something like:</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br><span>8</span><br><span>9</span><br><span>10</span><br><span>11</span><br><span>12</span><br><span>13</span><br><span>14</span><br><span>15</span><br><span>16</span><br><span>17</span><br><span>18</span><br><span>19</span><br><span>20</span><br><span>21</span><br><span>22</span><br><span>23</span><br><span>24</span><br><span>25</span><br><span>26</span><br><span>27</span><br><span>28</span><br><span>29</span><br><span>30</span><br><span>31</span><br><span>32</span><br><span>33</span><br><span>34</span><br><span>35</span><br><span>36</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span><span>size_t</span> <span>strlen_cacher</span><span>(<span>char</span>* str)</span></span></span><br><span><span></span>{</span><br><span>  <span>static</span> <span>char</span>* start;</span><br><span>  <span>static</span> <span>char</span>* end;</span><br><span>  <span>size_t</span> len;</span><br><span>  <span>const</span> <span>size_t</span> cap = <span>20000</span>;</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  <span>if</span> (start &amp;&amp; str &gt;= start &amp;&amp; str &lt;= end) {</span><br><span>    </span><br><span>    len = end - str;</span><br><span></span><br><span>    </span><br><span>    </span><br><span>    <span>if</span> (len &lt; cap / <span>2</span>)</span><br><span>      MH_DisableHook((LPVOID)strlen_addr);</span><br><span></span><br><span>    </span><br><span>    <span>return</span> len;</span><br><span>  }</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  len = builtin_strlen(str);</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  <span>if</span> (len &gt; cap) {</span><br><span>    start = str;</span><br><span>    end = str + len;</span><br><span>  }</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  <span>return</span> len;</span><br><span>}</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>And as for the hash-array problem, it’s more straightforward - just skip the duplicate checks entirely and insert the items directly since we know the values are unique.</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br><span>7</span><br><span>8</span><br><span>9</span><br><span>10</span><br><span>11</span><br><span>12</span><br><span>13</span><br><span>14</span><br><span>15</span><br><span>16</span><br><span>17</span><br><span>18</span><br><span>19</span><br><span>20</span><br><span>21</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span><span><span>char</span> __fastcall <span>netcat_insert_dedupe_hooked</span><span>(<span>uint64_t</span> catalog, <span>uint64_t</span>* key, <span>uint64_t</span>* item)</span></span></span><br><span><span></span>{</span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  <span>uint64_t</span> not_a_hashmap = catalog + <span>88</span>;</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  <span>if</span> (!(*(<span>uint8_t</span>(__fastcall**)(<span>uint64_t</span>*))(*item + <span>48</span>))(item))</span><br><span>    <span>return</span> <span>0</span>;</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  netcat_insert_direct(not_a_hashmap, key, &amp;item);</span><br><span></span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  </span><br><span>  <span>if</span> (*key == <span>0x7FFFD6BE</span>) {</span><br><span>    MH_DisableHook((LPVOID)netcat_insert_dedupe_addr);</span><br><span>    unload();</span><br><span>  }</span><br><span></span><br><span>  <span>return</span> <span>1</span>;</span><br><span>}</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>Full source of PoC <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://github.com/tostercx/GTAO_Booster_PoC">here</a>.</p>
<h2 id="Results"><a href="#Results" title="Results"></a>Results</h2><p>Well, did it work then?</p>
<figure><table><tbody><tr><td><pre><span>1</span><br><span>2</span><br><span>3</span><br><span>4</span><br><span>5</span><br><span>6</span><br></pre></td><td><pre><span>Original online mode load time:        ~6m flat</span><br><span>Time with only duplication check patch: 4m 30s</span><br><span>Time with only JSON parser patch:       2m 50s</span><br><span>Time with both issues patched:          1m 50s</span><br><span></span><br><span>(6*60 - (1*60+50)) / (6*60) = 69.4% load time improvement (nice!)</span><br></pre></td></tr></tbody></table></figure>

<p>Hell yes, it did! :))</p>
<p>Most likely, this won’t solve everyone’s load times - there might be other bottlenecks on different systems, but it’s such a gaping hole that I have no idea how R* has missed it all these years.</p>
<h2 id="tl-dr"><a href="#tl-dr" title="tl;dr"></a>tl;dr</h2><ul>
<li>There’s a single thread CPU bottleneck while starting up GTA Online</li>
<li>It turns out GTA struggles to parse a 10MB JSON file</li>
<li>The JSON parser itself is poorly built / naive and</li>
<li>After parsing there’s a slow item de-duplication routine</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="R-please-fix"><a href="#R-please-fix" title="R* please fix"></a>R* please fix</h2><p>If this somehow reaches Rockstar: the problems shouldn’t take more than a day for a single dev to solve. Please do something about it :&lt;</p>
<p>You could either switch to a hashmap for the de-duplication or completely skip it on startup as a faster fix. For the JSON parser - just swap out the library for a more performant one. I don’t think there’s any easier way out.</p>
<p>ty &lt;3</p>
<h2 id="Small-update"><a href="#Small-update" title="Small update"></a>Small update</h2><p>I was expecting to get some attention but nowhere near this much! After reaching the top of <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=26296339">HN</a> this post has spread like wildfire! <strong>Thank you for the overwhelming response :)</strong></p>
<p>I’ll do more writing if something interesting comes along, but don’t expect anything of this scale soon - there was a lot of luck involved.</p>
<p>A few people suggested spamming this post to Rockstar’s support - please don’t! I’m sure they’ve seen this by now. Continuing would only bog down support tickets for everyone else. Social media is fair game in my book tho.</p>
<p>Several HN comments suggested I add a donate button, as they would like to buy me a beer (thank you!) so I’m <del>placing a link in the footer</del>.</p>
<p>Thank you for reading and all the support :)</p>
<h2 id="Update-2021-03-15"><a href="#Update-2021-03-15" title="Update 2021-03-15"></a>Update 2021-03-15</h2><ul>
<li>Got confirmation from R* that this is getting a fix soon</li>
<li>Just got awarded $10k through their H1 in-game bounty as an exception :)) (usually only for security issues)</li>
<li>Trying to figure out what’s a W8 and how to fill it (lol)</li>
<li>I did try asking for more technical details but they couldn’t say anything</li>
<li>Will do another  benchmark on my same old setup as soon as the update is out, I’m sure their engineers won’t disappoint :)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="Update-2021-03-16"><a href="#Update-2021-03-16" title="Update 2021-03-16"></a>Update 2021-03-16</h2><p>R* <a target="_blank" rel="noopener" href="https://support.rockstargames.com/articles/360061161574/">released the update</a>! Downloaded it and got my first run results - same hardware, same measurement - from R* logo to fully online.</p>
<p><img src="https://nee.lv/images/pasted-8.png" alt="upload successful"></p>
<p>Fully fixed! t0st approves!</p>
<p>Thanks again for all the coffees, and thanks to R* for taking the time to look into this and the generous bounty!</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Macs can now inform Apple if any liquids have been detected in the USB-C ports (198 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/03/macs-liquids-detected-in-usb-c-ports/</link>
            <guid>38920738</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jan 2024 00:46:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/03/macs-liquids-detected-in-usb-c-ports/">https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/03/macs-liquids-detected-in-usb-c-ports/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38920738">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
			<img src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/MacBook-USB-C-MagSafe-ports.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/MacBook-USB-C-MagSafe-ports.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/MacBook-USB-C-MagSafe-ports.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/MacBook-USB-C-MagSafe-ports.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/MacBook-USB-C-MagSafe-ports.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" width="1600" height="800" alt="MacBook USB-C MagSafe ports" fetchpriority="high">
	
	</figure>

<p>Apple’s limited warranty doesn’t cover damage caused by liquids, even for water-resistant products like the iPhone, Apple Watch, and some AirPods models. Because of this, Apple has different methods to detect if the device has been exposed to liquids. And on the latest Macs, Apple now has a way of knowing if liquids have been detected in the USB-C ports.</p>







<p>As noted by <em>9to5Mac</em>, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/10/25/macos-sonoma-14-1/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">macOS Sonoma 14.1</a> includes a new system daemon named “liquiddetectiond,” which, as the name suggests, can identify when the computer has been exposed to liquids. More specifically, this daemon runs in the background to collect liquid detection analysis from each USB-C port on the Mac.</p>



<p>This daemon is described as a “Liquid Detection and Corrosion Mitigation Daemon.” iPhones and iPads have a similar daemon, which is used to alert users when liquid is detected in the connector so that they immediately unplug the charging cable to prevent damage.</p>



<p>On the Mac, however, the code suggests that the daemon is only used for “analytics” and is not associated with end-user features. While Apple may eventually implement an alert similar to the one that already exists in iOS, it seems more likely that the data collected by this daemon will be used for technicians to determine whether a Mac is eligible for free repair.</p>



<p>Of course, that’s just one more way for Apple to know if the Mac has been exposed to liquids. As <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT201880" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple’s website describes</a>, “Mac laptop computers and some Apple wired and wireless keyboards have Liquid Contact Indicators (LCI) to help determine if these products have been exposed to liquid.”</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="2000" height="1000" src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all" alt="Latest Macs can now inform Apple if any liquids have been detected in the USB-C ports" srcset="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg 2000w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=155,78 155w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=655,328 655w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=768,384 768w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=1024,512 1024w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=1536,768 1536w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=350,175 350w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=140,70 140w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=1600,800 1600w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=290,145 290w, https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/Apple-iPhone-liquid.jpg?resize=150,75 150w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px"></figure>



<p>These indicators are strategically placed inside the devices and change color when they come into contact with liquids. Putting a digital liquid detector on USB-C ports is just another way to ensure that technicians are right about claiming that a Mac has been exposed to liquids.</p>



<p>It’s unclear at this point whether the new daemon works with any Macs running the latest version of macOS or only with <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/10/30/new-m3-imac/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">M3 Macs</a> due to some extra hardware requirement.</p>



<h2 id="h-read-also">Read also</h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/10/26/ios-17-2-update-sealed-iphones/">iOS 17.2 confirms the existence of a new system to update sealed iPhones at Apple Stores</a></li>



<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/01/new-macos-sonoma-build-m3-macs/">Buying one of the new M3 Macs? There’s a new macOS Sonoma build waiting for you</a></li>
</ul>
	<p>
		<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBggKMLOFATDAGg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add 9to5Mac to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
	</p>
	<div><p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://9to5mac.com/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p><p><a href="https://bit.ly/3shtH6M"><img src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/10/integration_1.webp" alt="" width="750" height="150"></a></p></div>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Polars (843 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pola.rs/</link>
            <guid>38920043</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 23:32:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pola.rs/">https://pola.rs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38920043">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><section data-astro-cid-bbe6dxrz=""><div data-astro-cid-bbe6dxrz=""><h2 data-astro-cid-bbe6dxrz="">DataFrames for<br> the new <u>era</u></h2><p><a href="https://docs.pola.rs/user-guide/" target="_blank" data-astro-cid-bbe6dxrz="">Get Started</a></p></div><img src="https://pola.rs/_astro/hero-bg.446f3be5_GUTeu.svg" alt="Data swooshes" data-astro-cid-bbe6dxrz="" width="1440" height="558" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></section><div data-astro-cid-6yr37or7=""><div data-astro-cid-n45p2yly=""><p><img src="https://pola.rs/_astro/icon-1.4d3edfea_1C80PW.webp" alt="Fast" data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="" width="280" height="280" loading="lazy" decoding="async"><span data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="">01</span><span data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="">Fast</span></p><p data-astro-cid-6yr37or7="">Polars is written from the ground up with performance in mind. Its multi-threaded query engine is written in Rust and designed for effective paralellism. Its vectorized and columnar processing enable cache-coherent algorithms and high performance on modern processors. </p></div><div data-astro-cid-n45p2yly=""><p><img src="https://pola.rs/_astro/icon-2.dc0bfc10_285k5H.svg" alt="Easy to use" data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="" width="168" height="141" loading="lazy" decoding="async"><span data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="">02</span><span data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="">Easy to use</span></p><p data-astro-cid-6yr37or7="">You will feel right at home with Polars if you are familiar with data wrangling. Its expressions are intuitive and empower you to write readable and performant code at the same time.</p></div><div data-astro-cid-n45p2yly=""><p><img src="https://pola.rs/_astro/icon-3.a539d0ef_Z1ISJxs.svg" alt="Open Source" data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="" width="162" height="140" loading="lazy" decoding="async"><span data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="">03</span><span data-astro-cid-n45p2yly="">Open Source</span></p><p data-astro-cid-6yr37or7="">Polars is and always will be open source. Driven by an active community of developers. Everyone is encouraged to add new features and contribute. It is free to use under the MIT license.</p></div></div><div><div><p><h2>Built by developers for developers to achieve up to <span>50x Performance</span></h2></p></div><div><p>Why use Polars</p><p>Polars was benchmarked against several other solutions on the independent TPCH Benchmark. This benchmark aims to replicate data wrangling operations used in practice. Polars easily trumps other solutions due to its parallel execution engine, efficient algorithms and use of vectorization with SIMD (Single Instruction, Multiple Data). Compared to pandas, it can achieve more than 30x performance gains.</p><p><a href="https://pola.rs/posts/benchmarks">Learn more →</a></p><p>The benchmark was performed on a <a href="https://cloud.google.com/compute/docs/general-purpose-machines#n2-high-mem">n2-highmem-16</a> with scale factor 10 including IO. The queries are <a href="https://github.com/pola-rs/tpch">open source</a>.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://pola.rs/_astro/perf-illustration.842c8328_2dRYyE.svg" alt="Performance illustration" width="566" height="570" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></p></div></div><div><h3>Quick install</h3><p>Polars is written from the ground up making it easy to install. Select your programming language and get started!</p><div><div data-tab="2"><p><code>[dependencies]<br>polars = { version = "x", features = ["lazy", ...]}</code></p></div><div data-tab="3"><p><code>const pl = require('nodejs-polars');</code></p></div></div></div><div><p>Support</p><h3>Support for all common data formats</h3><p>Polars supports reading and writing to all common data formats. This allows you to easily integrate Polars into your existing data stack.</p><ul><li>Text: CSV &amp; JSON</li><li>Binary: Parquet, Delta Lake, AVRO &amp; Excel</li><li>IPC: Feather, Arrow</li><li>Databases: MySQL, Postgres, SQL Server, Sqlite, Redshift &amp; Oracle</li><li>Cloud Storage: S3, Azure Blob &amp; Azure File</li></ul></div><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><h2 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
How <u data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Polars</u> will<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
make your life <u data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">easier</u></h2></p><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">01</p><h4 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Easy<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">to use</h4><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Write your queries the way they were intended. Polars, internally, will determine the most efficient way to execute using its query optimiser.</p></div><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">02</p><h4 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Embarrassingly<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Parallel</h4><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Complete your queries faster! Polars fully utilises the power of your machine by dividing the workload among the available CPU cores without any additional configuration, nor serialization overhead.</p></div><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">03</p><h4 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
Apache<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
Arrow
</h4><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Polars utilises the Apache Arrow memory model allowing you to easily integrate with existing tools in the data landscape. It supports zero-copy data sharing for efficient collaboration. </p></div><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">04</p><h4 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
Close to<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
the metal
</h4><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Polars is written from the ground up, designed close to the machine and without external dependencies. This allows for full control of the ecosystem (API, memory &amp; execution).</p></div><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">05</p><h4 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
Written<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
in Rust
</h4><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">The core of Polars is written in Rust, one of the fastest growing programming languages in the world. Rust allows for high performance with fine grained control over memory.</p></div><div data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn=""><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">06</p><h4 data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
Out<br data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">
of core
</h4><p data-astro-cid-ty2zxhyn="">Want to process large data sets that are bigger than your memory? Our streaming API allows you to process your results efficiently skipping the need to keep all the data in memory.</p></div></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Turing Complete Transformers: Two Transformers Are More Powerful Than One (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openreview.net/forum?id=MGWsPGogLH</link>
            <guid>38919884</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2024 23:20:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openreview.net/forum?id=MGWsPGogLH">https://openreview.net/forum?id=MGWsPGogLH</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38919884">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>Keywords<!-- -->:</strong> <span>transformers, computational complexity, computation, generalization, agents, multi-model</span></p><p><strong>TL;DR<!-- -->:</strong> <span>We prove transformers are not Turing complete, propose a new architecture that is Turing complete, and empirically demonstrate that the new architecture can generalize more effectively than transformers.</span></p><p><strong>Abstract<!-- -->:</strong> <span>This paper presents Find+Replace transformers, a family of multi-transformer architectures that can provably do things no single transformer can, and which outperforms GPT-4 on several challenging tasks. We first establish that traditional transformers and similar architectures are not Turing Complete, while Find+Replace transformers are. Using this fact, we show how arbitrary programs can be compiled into Find+Replace transformers, potentially aiding interpretability research. We also demonstrate the superior performance of Find+Replace transformers over GPT-4 on a set of composition challenge problems. This work aims to provide a theoretical basis for multi-transformer architectures, and to encourage their further exploration.</span></p><p><strong>Primary Area<!-- -->:</strong> <span>general machine learning (i.e., none of the above)</span></p><p><strong>Code Of Ethics<!-- -->:</strong> <span>I acknowledge that I and all co-authors of this work have read and commit to adhering to the ICLR Code of Ethics.</span></p><p><strong>Submission Guidelines<!-- -->:</strong> <span>I certify that this submission complies with the submission instructions as described on https://iclr.cc/Conferences/2024/AuthorGuide.</span></p><p><strong>Anonymous Url<!-- -->:</strong> <span>I certify that there is no URL (e.g., github page) that could be used to find authors' identity.</span></p><p><strong>No Acknowledgement Section<!-- -->:</strong> <span>I certify that there is no acknowledgement section in this submission for double blind review.</span></p><p><strong>Submission Number<!-- -->:</strong> <span>8781</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>