<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 22:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Parody site ClownStrike refused to bow to CrowdStrike's bogus DMCA takedown (357 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/08/parody-site-clownstrike-refused-to-bow-to-crowdstrikes-bogus-dmca-takedown/</link>
            <guid>41173486</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 18:07:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/08/parody-site-clownstrike-refused-to-bow-to-crowdstrikes-bogus-dmca-takedown/">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/08/parody-site-clownstrike-refused-to-bow-to-crowdstrikes-bogus-dmca-takedown/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173486">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/GettyImages-1349097864-800x534.jpg" alt="Parody site ClownStrike refused to bow to CrowdStrike’s bogus DMCA takedown">
      <figcaption></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 112:single/related:a77b1b9f108bd31cda2402047b36fe7c --><!-- empty -->
<p>Doesn't CrowdStrike have more important things to do right now than try to take down a parody site?</p>
<p>That's what IT consultant David Senk wondered when CrowdStrike sent a Digital Millennium Copyright Act (DMCA)&nbsp;takedown notice targeting his <a href="https://clownstrike.lol/">parody site ClownStrike</a>.</p>
<p>Senk created ClownStrike in the aftermath of the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/07/major-outages-at-crowdstrike-microsoft-leave-the-world-with-bsods-and-confusion/">largest IT outage</a> the world has ever seen—which CrowdStrike blamed on a <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/07/crowdstrike-blames-testing-bugs-for-security-update-that-took-down-8-5m-windows-pcs/">buggy security update</a> that shut down systems and incited prolonged chaos in airports, hospitals, and businesses worldwide.</p>
<p>Although Senk wasn't personally impacted by the outage, he told Ars he is "a proponent of decentralization." He seized the opportunity to mock "CrowdStrike's ability to cause literal billions of dollars of damage" because he viewed this as "collateral from the incredible amount of 'centralization' in the tech industry."</p>
<p>Setting up the parody site at clownstrike.lol on July 24, Senk's site design is simple. It shows the CrowdStrike logo fading into a cartoon clown, with circus music blasting throughout the transition. For the first 48 hours of its existence, the site used an unaltered version of CrowdStrike's Falcon logo, which is used for its cybersecurity platform, but Senk later added a rainbow propeller hat to the falcon's head.</p>
<p>"I put the site up initially just to be silly," Senk told Ars, noting that he's a bit "old-school" and has "always loved parody sites" (like <a href="http://toastytech.com/evil/index.html">this one</a>).</p>
<p>It was all fun and games, but on July 31, Senk received a DMCA notice from Cloudflare's trust and safety team, which was then hosting the parody site. The notice informed Senk that CSC Digital Brand Services' global anti-fraud team, on behalf of CrowdStrike, was requesting the immediate removal of the CrowdStrike logo from the parody site, or else Senk risked Cloudflare taking down the whole site.</p>                                                                        
                                                                                
<p>Senk immediately felt the takedown was bogus. His site was obviously parody, which he felt should have made his use of the CrowdStrike logos—altered or not—fair use. He immediately responded to Cloudflare to contest the notice, but Cloudflare did not respond to or even acknowledge receipt of his counter notice. Instead, Cloudflare sent a second email warning Senk of the alleged infringement, but once again, Cloudflare failed to respond to his counter notice.</p>
<p>This left Senk little choice but to relocate his parody site to "somewhere less-susceptible to DMCA takedown requests," Senk told Ars, which ended up being a Hetzner server in Finland.</p>
<p>Currently on the ClownStrike site, when you click a CSC logo altered with a clown wig, you can find Senk <a href="https://clownstrike.lol/crowdmad/">venting</a> about "corporate cyberbullies" taking down "content that they disagree with" and calling Cloudflare's counter notice system "hilariously ineffective."</p>
<p>"The DMCA requires service providers to 'act expeditiously to remove or disable access to the infringing material,' yet it gives those same 'service providers' 14 days to restore access in the event of a counternotice!" Senk complained. "The DMCA, like much American legislation, is heavily biased towards corporations instead of the actual living, breathing citizens of the country."</p>
<p>Reached for comment, CrowdStrike declined to comment on ClownStrike's takedown directly. But it seems like the takedown notice probably never should have been sent to Senk. His parody site likely got swept up in CrowdStrike's anti-fraud efforts to stop bad actors attempting to take advantage of the global IT outage by deceptively using CrowdStrike's logo on malicious sites.</p>
<p>“As part of our proactive fraud management activities, CrowdStrike’s anti-fraud partners have issued more than 500 takedown notices in the last two weeks to help prevent bad actors from exploiting current events," CrowdStrike's statement said. "These actions are taken to help protect customers and the industry from phishing sites and malicious activity. While parody sites are not the intended target of these efforts, it’s possible for such sites to be inadvertently impacted. We will review the process and, where appropriate, evolve ongoing anti-fraud activities.”</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Actual Wolf of Wallstreet Cold Call Script (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jointhefollowup.com/p/the-actual-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script</link>
            <guid>41173377</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 17:56:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jointhefollowup.com/p/the-actual-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script">https://www.jointhefollowup.com/p/the-actual-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173377">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-blocks"><p><i><b>Happy </b></i><b>S’mores Day</b><i><b>! </b></i>Don’t you wish you had s’more opportunities in your pipeline 🥁… <i>sorry, I know that was bad</i>. Back to business. </p><p><b>In today’s Follow Up:</b></p><div><ul><li><p> The real Wolf of Wall Street cold call script 📞&nbsp; </p></li><li><p> Sales in the news 🗞️ </p></li><li><p> Sales weapon of the day 🛠️ </p></li><li><p> Chart of the Day &amp; Memes 🖼️&nbsp; </p></li></ul></div><p id="sales-fact-of-the-day"><h3><b>Sales Fact of The Day</b></h3></p><div><p>On average, sellers spend 23.8 hours (or 52%) of their week creating messaging.</p><p><small> Source: Gartner </small></p></div><p> No one’s influenced more millennial sales reps than <i><b>The Wolf of Wall Street </b></i>and <i><b>Jordan Belfort</b></i>. </p><p> He’s the younger generation’s Glengarry Glen Ross, except better looking and criminally charged… </p><p> While the movie is wild and hilarious, it’s also based on the true story of Stratton Oakmont and their sales team. </p><p> The firm was founded in 1989 as an “over-the-counter” brokerage house and became one of the<span>&nbsp;</span>largest OTC firms in the US during the late 80s and 90s. </p><p> If you can look past the $200M they defrauded from 1,500 investors… they were actually a pretty successful sales team. </p><p> Today, we’re going under the hood to dissect the Stratton Oakmont sales scripts. </p><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/c4c3935d-8dd0-48e7-a77a-5e912ac5ec97/Please_respect_my_decision.png"></p><p id="the-holy-grail-of-sales-scripts-str"><h3><b>The holy grail of sales scripts, straight from the Stratton Oakmont playbook:</b></h3></p><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/ac1fbf78-68b8-4bb8-88de-d4558fde2e96/Starton_Oakmont_Script_1.png"></p><p> Pretty standard introduction. (<i>Hard to read without using the Jordan Belfort voice in your head</i>&nbsp;😂 ) </p><p> Next, we get straight to the point of why you’re calling. </p><p> Like most sales scripts, it features a pattern interrupt. In this case, it’s “<i>I know you’re busy, I’ll get straight to the point</i>”. </p><p> A pattern interrupt changes someone’s natural pattern of thought. It’s important in every sales script because it gets the prospect to pay attention and let down their guard. </p><p><b>Ex</b>: “<i>Hey John, I know you don’t know me and weren’t expecting my call</i>”. </p><p> Next, it gives us two paths for the two possible responses. </p><p> The “<b>yes</b>” response is pretty standard, but the first “<b>no</b>” response is most important. This is the opportunity to educate the prospect in the way you want. </p><p> The final line is your classic call to action. For many sales reps, this will be your request to get the prospect on another call. </p><p> Although this script asks to send the prospect more information, your goal should always be to get something on the calendar. </p><p> In most cases, <b>sending info via email</b> = <b>never hearing from them again</b>. </p><p> And at last, we have the secret weapon: “<i><b>Fair enough</b></i><b>?</b>”. </p><p> This is one of the most powerful words in selling. </p><p> Chris Voss (<i>hostage negotiator</i>) has said “<i><b>fair</b></i>” is the “<i>single most powerful word in any negotiation</i>”. </p><p> It worked in sales back then and still works in sales today. </p><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/952782d0-49a8-4b20-8e0b-6469edbe1958/Stratton_Oakmont_script_2.png"></p><p> Stratton trained their reps to qualify prospects as early as possible. </p><p> One of the biggest mistakes you can make is spending too much time with an unqualified prospect. Find out your prospect has no chance of buying now, rather than later. </p><p> Next, we have the <b>objection handling</b>. Responses to objections are one of the most important features of your script. Without them, <b>sales reps will fail</b>. </p><p> The goal is simply to get the prospect to say the word “<b>yes</b>”. </p><p> You can also add probing questions like, “<i>I’m assuming you’re already satisfied with their results, am I right</i>?” or “<i>We have clients who used your same brokers, but after they saw our historical returns they change their strategy. Would it make sense to take a look?</i>” </p><p> And again, we’ve got the secret weapon…“<i><b>fair enough?</b></i><i>”</i></p><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/d4461dbc-30fe-4960-ba43-ad9fbd4298f0/Strattonn_Oakmont_3.png"></p><p> Some popular tactics Stratton used before they became trendy on Instagram: </p><div><ul><li><p><b>Qualifying: </b>“I’m sure you…” </p></li><li><p><b>Scarcity: </b>“Only a handful of…” </p></li><li><p><b>Secret weapon: </b>“Fair enough?’ </p></li><li><p><b>Anti-selling: “</b>I’m not trying to sell anything…” and our favorite “Believe me we’re not looking to run your portfolio” (<i>then what are you trying to do…?</i>) </p></li></ul></div><div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/2a3be46f-1d97-44a9-b2df-28f664f11acc/image.png"></p></div><p> Lastly, we have the section that may be our favorite. </p><p> In this case “<b>he</b>” = <b>your prospect</b>. </p><p> If your prospect is up, you should be too. And you should be on the phone with them. </p><p> This is all about that mindset-grind set. 🙃&nbsp; </p><div><p> ❝ </p><p>"The Only Thing Standing Between You And Your Goal Is The Bulls**t Story You Keep Telling Yourself As To Why You Can't Achieve It."</p><p><small> Jordan Belfort </small></p></div><p id="now-we-know-what-youre-all-thinking"><h4><b>Now, we know what you’re all thinking…</b></h4></p><p> Did Stratton Oakmont do very illegal things? <b>Yes</b>. </p><p> Should you use this same sale script? <b>Nope</b>. </p><p> Do we all kind of wish we worked at Stratton Oakmont for a year and made tons of money….? <b>Probably. </b>🤷&nbsp; </p><div><p><h3><span><b>Sales Tip of The Day</b></span></h3></p><p><span>Are you opening up your cold calls with:</span></p><p><span> “</span><span><i>Hi This is {name}, can I have 15 seconds to tell you why I called”</i></span><span>. </span></p><p><span>Although this line is taught by many sales trainers, it’s becoming overused and immediately lets prospects know it’s a sales call. </span></p><p><span>Instead, try opening with something like: </span></p><p><span>“</span><span><i>Hi this is {name}, and I work with other {their job title} to help with xyx… and I came across your LinkedIn. Do you have a sec to talk? </i></span><span>”</span></p><p><span>This opener feels less </span><span><i>salesy, </i></span><span>and is actually the reason why you called. It’s best to build a relationship with your prospect from an honest place from the start.</span></p></div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/e477fff2-0d90-4219-92e6-3dac7700c4f0/_004AAD__1_.png"></p><div><p><span><b>Sales in the News</b></span></p><div><ul><li><p><span>Why salespeople who are </span><span><a href="https://www.securityinfowatch.com/integrators/article/53066447/modern-selling-are-you-down-with-followup?utm_source=www.jointhefollowup.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=the-real-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">great at follow-up</a></span><span> will succeed even if they aren’t the best.</span></p></li><li><p><span>“Salesperson” remains Linkedin's </span><span><a href="https://www.inc.com/jessica-stillman/hiring-top-10-most-in-demand-jobs-right-now-per-linkedin-data.html?utm_source=www.jointhefollowup.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=the-real-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">second most in-demand job</a></span><span> this quarter. </span></p></li><li><p><span>Sent a cold email to a prospect and they replied "</span><span><i>But I am in prison</i></span><span>". </span><span><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/sales/comments/15mp4qk/how_do_i_respond_to_but_i_am_in_prison/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">How do I respond</a></span><span>?</span></p></li><li><p><span>Even at 38,000 ft, a </span><span><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/corporatebro_sales-activity-7094698856126251008-6Vo3?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">sales bro can’t miss an opportunity</a></span><span> to win friends and influence people…</span></p></li></ul></div></div><div><p><span><b>Sales Weapon of The Day </b></span></p><p><span><a href="https://www.voicenotes.org/?utm_source=www.jointhefollowup.com&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=the-real-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Voice Notes</a></span><span>: Create emails, sales pitches, and summaries from your voice notes. Just hit record, start talking, and let AI turn your voice into writing. </span></p></div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/e477fff2-0d90-4219-92e6-3dac7700c4f0/_004AAD__1_.png"></p><p id="chart-of-the-day"><h2><b>Chart of The Day:</b></h2></p><p id="esg-software-sales"><h2>ESG Software Sales 👀&nbsp;</h2></p><div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/266395c6-6bc1-478b-a47b-fd18f2133660/Screenshot_2023-08-09_at_10.26.34_AM.png"></p><p><small><p>Source: exploding topics </p></small></p></div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/28a75f3b-2e68-4db0-8a6f-266486396fb2/_004AAD.png"></p><p id="sales-meme-of-the-day"><h2><b>Sales Meme of the Day</b></h2></p><div><blockquote><p>“The name of the company, Blackberry. It is a cutting edge intelligent security software company out of Waterloo, Canada awaiting imminent patent approval on the next generation of 5G smartphone devices that have both huge military and civilian applications now.”</p><a data-skip-tracking="true" href="https://twitter.com/RampCapitalLLC/status/1353716875457417216?s=20&amp;utm_source=www.jointhefollowup.com&amp;utm_medium=newsletter&amp;utm_campaign=the-real-wolf-of-wall-street-sales-script"><p> — Ramp Capital Guy (@RampCapitalLLC) <br> 2:50 PM • Jan 25, 2021 </p></a></blockquote></div><p> And that’s a wrap! </p><p><span>Want to advertise in The Follow Up? </span><span><a href="https://www.jointhefollowup.com/c/advertise" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow">Click Here</a></span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tracking supermarket prices with Playwright (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/</link>
            <guid>41173335</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 17:52:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/">https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173335">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
<h2>Tracking supermarket prices with playwright<br>
  <small>Aug  6, 2024 • 2126 words • 11 min read </small>
</h2>

<p>Back in Dec 2022, when inflation was running high, I built a
<a href="https://pricewatcher.gr/en">website</a> for tracking price changes in the three largest
supermarkets of my home country, Greece.</p>
<p>
<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024-08-pricewatcher-1.png">
    <img src="https://www.sakisv.net/2024-08-pricewatcher-1.png" alt="Screenshot of pricewatcher.gr showing a summary of the last 30 days of price changes across 3 supermarkets">
</a>
</p>

<p>In the process I ran into a few interesting hurdles that I had to clear before being able
to "go live". There were also several lessons I learned and faulty assumptions that I
made.</p>
<p>In this post I will talk about scraping: What I use, where it runs, how I got around some
restrictions and how I got it to the point that it can run for months without
intervention.</p>


<h2 id="table-of-contents"> Table of contents </h2>
<ul>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#scraping-js-sites">Scraping js sites</a>
  
  </li>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#automating">Automating</a>
  
    <ul>
      
        <li>
        <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#use-an-old-laptop">Use an old laptop?</a>
          <ul>
          
          </ul>
        </li>
      
        <li>
        <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#use-the-cloud">Use the cloud?</a>
          <ul>
          
          </ul>
        </li>
      
        <li>
        <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#use-an-old-laptop-and-the-cloud">Use an old laptop AND the cloud!</a>
          <ul>
          
          </ul>
        </li>
      
    </ul>
  
  </li>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#avoiding-ip-restrictions">Avoiding IP restrictions</a>
  
  </li>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#how-and-when-does-it-fail">How and when does it fail?</a>
  
  </li>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#optimising">Optimising</a>
  
    <ul>
      
        <li>
        <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#use-a-bigger-server">Use a bigger server</a>
          <ul>
          
          </ul>
        </li>
      
        <li>
        <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#fetch-fewer-things">Fetch fewer things</a>
          <ul>
          
          </ul>
        </li>
      
    </ul>
  
  </li>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#cost">Cost</a>
  
  </li>

  <li>
  <a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024/08/tracking-supermarket-prices-playwright/#conclusion">Conclusion</a>
  
  </li>

</ul>


<h2 id="scraping-js-sites">Scraping js sites</h2>
<p>The main problem was, what else? Javascript.</p>
<p>All three eshops are rendered with js and even in the few spots where they don't, they
still rely on js to load products as you scroll, similar to infinite scrolling in social
media. This means that using plain simple <code>curl</code> or <code>requests.get()</code> was out of the
question; I needed something that could run js.</p>
<p>Enter <a href="https://playwright.dev/">Playwright</a>.</p>
<p>Playwright allows you to programmatically control a web browser, providing an API to
handle almost everything, from opening a new tab and navigating to a URL, to inspecting
the DOM, retrieving element details, and intercepting and inspecting requests.</p>
<p>It also supports Chromium, Safari and Firefox browsers and you can use it with <a href="https://playwright.dev/docs/intro">Node</a>, <a href="https://playwright.dev/java/docs/intro">Java</a>,
<a href="https://playwright.dev/dotnet/docs/intro">.NET</a> and, most importantly, <a href="https://playwright.dev/python/docs/intro">Python</a>.</p>
<p>With this in my belt, doing the scrolling and the loading of the products looked like
this:</p>
<pre data-lang="python"><code data-lang="python"><span>
</span><span>def </span><span>visit_links</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>):
</span><span>    </span><span>#
</span><span>    </span><span># &lt;truncated&gt;
</span><span>    </span><span>#
</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span># do the infinite scrolling
</span><span>    load_more_locator </span><span>= </span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>page</span><span>.</span><span>get_by_test_id</span><span>(
</span><span>        </span><span>"vertical-load-more-wrapper"
</span><span>    )</span><span>.</span><span>all</span><span>()
</span><span>    </span><span>while </span><span>len</span><span>(load_more_locator) </span><span>== </span><span>1</span><span>:
</span><span>        load_more_locator[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>scroll_into_view_if_needed</span><span>()
</span><span>        load_more_locator </span><span>= </span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>page</span><span>.</span><span>get_by_test_id</span><span>(
</span><span>            </span><span>"vertical-load-more-wrapper"
</span><span>        )</span><span>.</span><span>all</span><span>()
</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span># once the infinite scroll is finished, load all the products
</span><span>    products </span><span>= </span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>page</span><span>.</span><span>locator</span><span>(</span><span>"li.product-item"</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>all</span><span>()
</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span># and then ensure that we only keep products that don't have the "unavailable" text
</span><span>    products </span><span>= </span><span>[
</span><span>        p
</span><span>        </span><span>for </span><span>p </span><span>in </span><span>products
</span><span>        </span><span>if </span><span>len</span><span>(p</span><span>.</span><span>get_by_test_id</span><span>(</span><span>"product-block-unavailable-text"</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>all</span><span>()) </span><span>== </span><span>0
</span><span>    ]
</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span>#
</span><span>    </span><span># &lt;truncated&gt;
</span><span>    </span><span>#
</span></code></pre>
<p>By the end of this method, I have a list of product <code>&lt;div&gt;</code>s, each containing the
product's name, price, photo, link, etc, that I get to parse to extract this information.
Then I do the same for the next product category, and so on.</p>
<p>Once I wrote the scrapers for all 3 supermarkets, the next step was to run it in an
automated way, so that every day I will have the new prices and I can compare with the day
before.</p>
<h2 id="automating">Automating</h2>
<p>Running this whole process for an entire supermarket on my M1 MBP would take anywhere from
50m to 2h 30m, depending on the supermarket. I could also run all 3 scrapers in
parallel with no noticeable difference.</p>
<p>However using my laptop was good for development and testing, but I needed a more
permanent solution.</p>
<h3 id="use-an-old-laptop">Use an old laptop?</h3>
<p>The first attempt to a solution came in the form of an old laptop, dating all the way back
to 2013.</p>
<p>It had dual core M-family processor clocked @ 2.20GHz and 4GB of RAM, which are on the low side
especially by today's standards, but then again I only needed to open a single tab in a
headless browser and navigate to a bunch of different URLs. Surely a dual core CPU with
4GB of RAM could handle that, right?</p>
<p>Well, not quite.</p>
<p>Even after bumping its memory to 12GB, the performance was far too disappointing,
measuring in more than 2h even for the "fast" supermarket.<sup><a href="#1">1</a></sup></p>
<h3 id="use-the-cloud">Use the cloud?</h3>
<p>So the next option was to use the cloud ☁️</p>
<p>My first thought was to use AWS, since that's what I'm most familiar with, but looking at
the prices for a moderately-powerful EC2 instance (i.e. 4 cores and 8GB of RAM) it was
going to cost much more than I was comfortable to spend for a side project.</p>
<p>At the time of writing, a <code>c5a.xlarge</code> instance is at <a href="https://instances.vantage.sh/aws/ec2/c5a.xlarge?region=eu-north-1&amp;os=linux&amp;cost_duration=hourly&amp;reserved_term=Standard.noUpfront">$0.1640 per hour</a> in
<code>eu-north-1</code>. That comes to a nice $118.08 per month, or $1,416.96 per year. Not so cheap.</p>
<p>So I turned to <a href="https://www.hetzner.com/">Hetzner</a>.</p>
<p>The equivalent server there is <code>cpx31</code>, which is at $17.22 (€15.72) per month, or $206.64
per year, which is ~7 times cheaper than AWS, which makes it a no-brainer for my use case.</p>
<p>So Hetzner it is.</p>
<h3 id="use-an-old-laptop-and-the-cloud">Use an old laptop AND the cloud!</h3>
<p>Having settled on the cloud provider to run the scraping from, next step was to finally
automate it and run it once per day.</p>
<p>The old laptop may not be powerful enough to run the scraping itself, but it was more than
capable of running a CI server that just delegates scraping to the much beefier server
from Hetzner.</p>
<p>My CI of choice is <a href="https://concourse-ci.org/">Concourse</a> which describes itself as "a continuous
thing-doer". While it has a bit of a learning curve, I appreciate its declarative model
for the pipelines and how it versions every single input to ensure reproducible builds as
much as it can.</p>
<p>Here's what the scraping pipeline looks like:</p>
<p>
<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/2024-08-pricewatcher-scrape-pipeline.png">
    <img src="https://www.sakisv.net/2024-08-pricewatcher-scrape-pipeline.png" alt="screenshot of pricewatcher scraping pipeline in concourse">
</a>
<small>The scraping pipeline in concourse</small>
</p>

<p>It has a nightly trigger which creates the scraping server and then triggers the three
scraping jobs in parallel. When all of them are finished, it tears down the server to keep
the costs down, and the raw output of each scraper is passed onto a job that transforms it
to a format which is then loaded into <a href="https://pricewatcher.gr/en">pricewatcher.gr</a>. Last,
but definitely not least, when any of these steps fails I get an email alert.</p>
<h2 id="avoiding-ip-restrictions">Avoiding IP restrictions</h2>
<p>But of course nothing is ever that simple.</p>
<p>While the supermarket that I was using to test things every step of the way worked fine,
one of them didn't. The reason? It was behind Akamai and they had enabled a firewall rule
which was blocking requests originating from non-residential IP addresses.</p>
<p>I had to find a way to do a "reverse vpn"<sup><a href="#2">2</a></sup> kind of thing, so that the requests would
appear to originate from my home IP.</p>
<p>Enter <a href="https://tailscale.com/">tailscale</a>.</p>
<p>Tailscale allows you to put your devices on the same network even if, in
reality, they are all over the place.</p>
<p>Once they are in the same network, then you can designate one of them to act as an "exit
node". You can then tell the other devices to use the designated exit node and, from that
point on, all their requests flow through there.</p>
<p>And if you're lucky like me, your ISP is using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carrier-grade_NAT">CGNAT</a>, which basically means that
your public IP address is not tied to you specifically, but it is shared with other
customers of the ISP. This allows some flexibility and peace of mind that your IP won't be
blindly blocked because that wouldn't affect just you.</p>
<p>So after all that, my good ol' laptop just got one more duty for itself:</p>
<p>Acting as an exit node for the scraping traffic.</p>
<h2 id="how-and-when-does-it-fail">How and when does it fail?</h2>
<p>I've been running this setup for a year and a half now, and it has proved to be quite
reliable.</p>
<p>Of course, as with any scraping project, you're always at the mercy of the developers of the website
you're scraping, and <a href="https://pricewatcher.gr/en">pricewatcher</a> is no exception.</p>
<p>There are 2 kinds of failures that I've faced: breaking changes and non-breaking changes.</p>
<p>The first one is easy: They changed something and your scraper failed. It may be something
simple as running a survey so you have to click one more button, or something more complex
where they completely change the layout and you have to make a larger refactor of your
scraper.</p>
<p>The second kind is nastier.</p>
<p>They change things in a way that doesn't make your scraper fail. Instead the scraping
continues as before, visiting all the links and scraping all the products. However the way
they write the prices has changed and now a bag of chips doesn't cost €1.99 but €199,
because they now use <code>&lt;sup&gt;</code> to separate the decimal part:</p>

<p>
<img src="https://www.sakisv.net/2024-08-pricewatcher-ruffles.png" alt="screenshot of a ruffles chips bag">
</p>
<p>
<img src="https://www.sakisv.net/2024-08-pricewatcher-ruffles-sup.png" alt="screenshot of the html showing <sup>
tag being used">
</p>

<p>To catch these changes I rely on my transformation step being as strict as possible with
its inputs.</p>
<p>In both cases however, the crucial part is to get feedback as soon as possible. Because
this runs daily, it gives me some flexibility to look at it when I have time. It can also
be a source of anxiety in case something breaks when I'm off for 2 weeks for holidays.
(Luckily they don't change their sites that often and that dramatically)</p>
<h2 id="optimising">Optimising</h2>
<p>While the overall architecture has remained pretty much the same since day 1,
I've made several changes to almost all other aspects of how scraping works, to improve
its reliability and to reduce the amount of work I had to do.</p>
<p>I configured email alerts for when things fail, heuristics that alert me when a
scraping yields too many or too few products for that supermarket, timeouts, retries that don't
start from the beginning, etc.</p>
<p>All of these could be a post of their own, and maybe they will (write a comment if you
want!), but I want to highlight two other optimisations here.</p>
<p>The main bottleneck in this entire process is the duration of the scraping. The longer it
takes, the more I end up paying and the more annoying it is if something fails and it
needs to be retried from the beginning.</p>
<p>After lots of trial and error, two changes improved the times significantly: A bigger server and
reducing the amount of data that I fetch.</p>
<h3 id="use-a-bigger-server">Use a bigger server</h3>
<p>I went from 4vCPUs and 16GB of RAM to 8vCPUs and 16GB of RAM, which reduced
the duration by about ~20%, making it comparable to the performance I get on my MBP.
Also, because I'm only using the scraping server for ~2h the difference in price is negligible.</p>
<h3 id="fetch-fewer-things">Fetch fewer things</h3>
<p>Part of the truncated snippet above is this bit, taken straight from the <a href="https://playwright.dev/python/docs/api/class-page#page-route">playwright
docs</a>:</p>
<pre data-lang="python"><code data-lang="python"><span>def </span><span>visit_links</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>):
</span><span>        images_regexp </span><span>= </span><span>re</span><span>.</span><span>compile</span><span>(</span><span>r</span><span>"(</span><span>\.</span><span>png</span><span>?</span><span>.</span><span>*</span><span>$</span><span>)</span><span>|</span><span>(</span><span>\.</span><span>jpg</span><span>.</span><span>*</span><span>$</span><span>)"</span><span>)
</span><span>        </span><span>for </span><span>index</span><span>, </span><span>link </span><span>in </span><span>enumerate</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>links):
</span><span>            </span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>page</span><span>.</span><span>goto</span><span>(link)
</span><span>            </span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>page</span><span>.</span><span>route</span><span>(images_regexp</span><span>, </span><span>lambda </span><span>route</span><span>: route</span><span>.</span><span>abort</span><span>())
</span><span>        </span><span>#
</span><span>        </span><span># &lt;truncated&gt;
</span><span>        </span><span>#
</span></code></pre>
<p>This aborts all requests to fetch images when I'm loading products. This not only makes
the scraping quicker, but also saves bandwidth and, presumably, a few cents, for the
websites.</p>
<p>While both of these are obvious in hindsight, sometimes it takes conscious effort to take
a step back and re-examine the problem at hand. It also helps to talk about it out loud,
either to a friend who knows or, even better, to a friend who doesn't know, for some
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubber_duck_debugging">rubber-duck debugging</a>.</p>
<h2 id="cost">Cost</h2>
<p>So how much does the scraping cost?</p>
<p>Accoring to the last invoice from Hetzner: €4.94 for the 31 servers I spinned up and €0.09 for the 31
IPv4 addresses they received.</p>
<p>The data from the scraping are saved in <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/en-gb/developer-platform/r2/">Cloudflare's R2</a> where they have a
pretty generous 10GB free tier which I have not hit yet, so that's another €0.00 there.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>These are the main building blocks of how I built a scraping pipeline for
<a href="https://pricewatcher.gr/en">pricewatcher</a> in order to keep track of how supermarkets change their
prices.</p>
<p>Leave a comment below if it piqued your interest and/or you'd like me to dive a bit
deeper in any area.</p>






<p>


<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/tags/playwright">/playwright/</a>

<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/tags/python">/python/</a>

<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/tags/concourse">/concourse/</a>

<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/tags/pricewatcher">/pricewatcher/</a>

<a href="https://www.sakisv.net/tags/tailscale">/tailscale/</a>


</p>








      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Full text search over Postgres: Elasticsearch vs. alternatives (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.paradedb.com/pages/elasticsearch_vs_postgres</link>
            <guid>41173288</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 17:48:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.paradedb.com/pages/elasticsearch_vs_postgres">https://blog.paradedb.com/pages/elasticsearch_vs_postgres</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173288">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Written by Ming Ying on July 31, 2024</p>
<p><img src="https://mintlify.s3-us-west-1.amazonaws.com/paradedb-blog/images/elastic_vs_postgres.png"></p><p>Over the past six months, we’ve spoken to 50+ companies who are looking for a full text search (FTS) solution over data stored
in Postgres. For many of these companies, the decision boils down to Elasticsearch vs. native Postgres full text search.</p>
<p>By working with these companies, we’ve identified the areas where each solution shines. Here’s what we’ve learned.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-full-text-search-fts"><span>What is Full Text Search (FTS)?</span></h2>
<p>Full text search is a technique that finds entries in a collection of text based on the presence of specific keywords and phrases.
Most search engines like Elasticsearch use the BM25 algorithm to rank search results. BM25 considers how often a term appears and how unique that term is across all documents.</p>
<p>Full text search is different from similarity search, also known as vector search, which searches for and ranks results by semantic meaning.
Many modern applications use a combination of full text and similarity search. This practice is called hybrid search and can yield more accurate results.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.postgresql.org/docs/current/textsearch-intro.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Postgres FTS</a> is a native functionality available to all Postgres
databases. It leverages the <code>tsvector</code> data type, which stores text as searchable tokens, and the GIN index, which improves search
speeds.</p>
<h3 id="the-good"><span>The Good</span></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Simplicity</strong>. Postgres FTS requires no additional infrastructure and is available on all managed Postgres services like AWS RDS. In the long run, not having to orchestrate and manage an external search engine saves significant time and headache.</li>
<li><strong>Real-Time Search</strong>. With Postgres FTS, data is searchable immediately upon commit. This can be incredibly useful to companies building user-facing or latency-sensitive search experiences — for instance, e-commerce sites or fintechs.</li>
<li><strong>Postgres Transactions and MVCC</strong>. Postgres’ ACID transactions and multi-version concurrency control (MVCC) ensure that FTS results are reliable under concurrent access and frequent updates.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-bad"><span>The Bad</span></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Feature Incomplete</strong>. The limited feature set of Postgres FTS may be a deal breaker for some companies. Missing features include BM25 scoring, relevance tuning, custom tokenizers, and faceting.</li>
<li><strong>Poor Performance Over Large Datasets</strong>. While Postgres FTS performs well over tables with a few million rows, performance degrades considerably over tables with tens of millions of rows.</li>
<li><strong>Transactional Overhead</strong>. Creating a GIN index over a column adds a small amount (usually milliseconds) of latency to transactions that affect that column.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="key-takeaway"><span>Key Takeaway</span></h3>
<p>Postgres FTS is ideal for search over small to medium-sized tables that do not require sophisticated FTS queries. We’re being intentionally vague about what “medium-sized” and “sophisticated” entail — the specifics vary depending on your performance requirements. Luckily, testing and migrating to/from Postgres FTS is fairly straightforward.</p>
<h2 id="elasticsearch"><span>Elasticsearch</span></h2>
<p>While Elastic today offers a wide variety of products, its core product, Elasticsearch, is a data store and full text search engine.</p>
<h3 id="the-good-2"><span>The Good</span></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Comprehensive Feature Set</strong>. Elasticsearch is capable of handling almost any FTS query. The Elastic Query DSL (domain-specific language) is the gold standard for full text search capabilities.</li>
<li><strong>Performant</strong>. Our <a href="https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb/tree/dev/benchmarks#results" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">benchmarks</a> show that Elasticsearch can query billions of rows in milliseconds thanks to its underlying battle-tested Lucene search engine and distributed architecture.</li>
<li><strong>More than Search</strong>. Beyond FTS, Elasticsearch is also an analytical query engine, vector database, security and observability platform. Many organizations enjoy the simplicity of consolidating several services within Elasticsearch.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="the-bad-2"><span>The Bad</span></h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Not a Reliable Data Store</strong>. We’ve talked to many companies who have tried and regretted their decision to use Elasticsearch as their primary data store. This is not a practice we recommend — Elasticsearch’s lack of ACID transactions and MVCC can lead to data inconsistencies and loss, while its lack of relational properties and real-time consistency makes many database queries challenging.</li>
<li><strong>Requires ETL Pipelines</strong>. Because Elasticsearch is not a reliable data store, organizations that use Postgres typically extract, transform, and load (ETL) data from Postgres to Elasticsearch. Because failures in ETL pipelines can lead to all sorts of production outages, these pipelines need to be carefully maintained to avoid breaking changes in the underlying Postgres schema.</li>
<li><strong>Loss of Data Freshness</strong>. ETL jobs are time-consuming and run at periodic intervals. Data that reaches Elasticsearch often lags several hours behind Postgres, which may be prohibitive for applications that perform real-time search over Postgres tables.</li>
<li><strong>Expensive</strong>. We were surprised to hear from several enterprises that Elasticsearch had grown to become their largest software expense. As the cost of their Elasticsearch clusters ballooned, many of these enterprises switched from Elasticsearch Cloud to self-managed. While this reduced their cloud spend, it introduced a new problem: Elasticsearch is notoriously difficult to run, tune, and manage. These organizations then hired (expensive) engineers to manage their Elasticsearch clusters.</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="key-takeaway-2"><span>Key Takeaway</span></h3>
<p>Elasticsearch delivers excellent search performance at the price of operational overhead and data freshness. We recommend Elasticsearch if more lightweight alternatives cannot get the job done or if you intend on using other Elasticsearch services.</p>
<h2 id="alternative-search-engines"><span>Alternative Search Engines</span></h2>
<p>Over the years, a modern breed of search engines like Algolia, Meilisearch, and Typesense has emerged. These engines are commonly used to build user-facing search experiences. <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Hacker News search</a>, for instance, is built on Algolia.</p>
<p>While each service differentiates around the edges, there’s an important caveat for developers looking for search over Postgres: none of these solutions are built specifically for Postgres. Users of Postgres will likely experience many of the same problems with these services as they would with Elasticsearch.</p>
<h2 id="is-the-best-of-both-worlds-possible"><span>Is the Best of Both Worlds Possible?</span></h2>
<p>ParadeDB is a full text search engine built for Postgres. Powered by an extension called <code>pg_search</code>, ParadeDB embeds Tantivy, a Rust-based Lucene alternative, inside Postgres. Like native Postgres FTS, ParadeDB plugs into any existing, self-managed Postgres database with no additional infrastructure. Like Elasticsearch, ParadeDB provides the capabilities of an advanced full text search engine.</p>
<p>Compatibility with managed Postgres services like Amazon RDS is coming soon. To get notified when it’s ready, we invite you to fill out our <a href="https://form.typeform.com/to/jHkLmIzx?typeform-source=paradedb.typeform.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">interest form</a>.
In the meantime, you can follow our <a href="https://github.com/paradedb/paradedb" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">GitHub repository</a> and give us a star!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Structured Outputs in the API (360 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/introducing-structured-outputs-in-the-api/</link>
            <guid>41173223</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 17:41:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/introducing-structured-outputs-in-the-api/">https://openai.com/index/introducing-structured-outputs-in-the-api/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173223">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/introducing-structured-outputs-in-the-api/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: 1-FPS encrypted screen sharing for introverts (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://1fps.video/</link>
            <guid>41173161</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 17:36:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://1fps.video/">https://1fps.video/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173161">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    <h2>1fps.video - Encrypted Screen Sharing</h2>
    
    <h2>Quick Start</h2>
    <p>You need Golang installed for this command to work. If you don't have Golang, you can install it using one of these methods:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>For Mac, Linux, or Windows, use this one-line command to install Go Runtime: <a href="https://webinstall.dev/golang/" target="_blank">https://webinstall.dev/golang/</a></li>
        <li>Or visit the official Go website for installation instructions: <a href="https://go.dev/doc/install" target="_blank">https://go.dev/doc/install</a></li>
    </ul>
    <p><code id="commandText">go run github.com/1fpsvideo/1fps@v0.1.1</code>
        
    </p>
    <p>
        <a href="https://github.com/1fpsvideo/1fps" target="_blank">
            🔒 Check out our secure, open-source client app
        </a>
    </p>

    
    <ul>
        <li>Developers</li>
        <li>IT teams</li>
        <li>Security professionals</li>
        <li>Meeting-free collaboration enthusiasts</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Why 1 FPS?</h2>
    <p>We've discovered that low FPS video sharing is often sufficient for most collaborative tasks, especially for developers who spend most of their time writing code. Our approach offers several benefits:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>Promotes a <span>meeting-free culture</span> by eliminating the need for audio</li>
        <li>Significantly reduces CPU, memory, and network consumption</li>
        <li>Allows older laptops to perform better during screen sharing</li>
        <li>More environmentally friendly due to lower resource usage</li>
    </ul>

    <h2>Is 1 FPS enough?</h2>
    <p>For most coding and development work, absolutely! Plus, we use WebSocket-based cursor tracking, providing smooth, near 30 FPS pointer movement for precise demonstrations.</p>

    <h2>Why choose our service?</h2>
    <p>1fps.video is perfect for introverts and remote workers who prefer sharing their screen without the pressure of audio or video calls. It's a versatile solution that works alongside any team chat application you're already using.</p>

    <h2>Privacy and Security</h2>
    <p>We take your privacy seriously:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>All data is <span>end-to-end encrypted</span></li>
        <li>Encryption keys are generated client-side and never sent to our servers</li>
        <li>The key is part of the URL (after the # symbol), which is never transmitted to the backend</li>
        <li>Only those with the full link can access your shared screen</li>
    </ul>
    <p><strong>Note:</strong> We're currently working on encrypting cursor coordinates for even greater privacy.</p>

    <p>Start sharing your screen effortlessly and securely with 1fps.video today!</p>

    

		
		

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Proton announces release of a new VPN protocol, "Stealth" (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://protonvpn.com/blog/stealth-vpn-protocol</link>
            <guid>41173089</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 17:30:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://protonvpn.com/blog/stealth-vpn-protocol">https://protonvpn.com/blog/stealth-vpn-protocol</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41173089">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <p><time datetime="2024-08-06T11:55:39">Published on August 6, 2024</time> </p> 
<p><strong>We’ve developed a new VPN protocol, Stealth, that can avoid detection and let you bypass internet censorship and VPN blocks.</strong></p>



<p>We’re pleased to announce Stealth, a new, undetectable VPN protocol that can bypass most firewalls and VPN blocking methods. You’ll be able to bypass advanced VPN blocks, access censored sites, and communicate with people on social media, even if your government is trying to restrict access.</p>



<h2>Why is Stealth needed?</h2>



<p>In 2017, we launched Proton VPN because there was no trustworthy, reliable, and freely available VPN service. Our motivation was simple. Because our services, such as Proton Mail, play a crucial role in ensuring freedom and privacy worldwide, we knew authoritarian governments would eventually try to block them. </p>



<p>But with Proton VPN, people can bypass those blocks and continue using Proton Mail. Over the past few years, Proton VPN has become an essential tool, helping ensure the free flow of information for tens of millions of people during crises and wars around the world.</p>



<p>Since we launched Proton VPN, we’ve continuously worked on technology to bypass surveillance and censorship. For example, in 2017, we launched <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://protonvpn.com/support/secure-core-vpn/">Secure Core VPN</a>, which provides greater privacy than typical VPN services. </p>



<p>In 2020, we launched <a rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank" href="https://proton.me/blog/anti-censorship-alternative-routing">alternative routing<span>(new window)</span></a>, which bypasses VPN blocks by re-routing our connections over other hard-to-trace paths. Finally, in 2021, we released <a href="https://protonvpn.com/secure-vpn/vpn-accelerator">VPN Accelerator</a>, a unique technology that provides connection speeds that are up to 400% faster, which is critically important for users in far-flung regions with slower internet.</p>



<p>As we have stepped up our efforts to build a more censorship-resistant VPN, authoritarian governments have also stepped up their efforts to block VPNs. Traditional <a rel="" target="_self" href="https://protonvpn.com/blog/whats-the-best-vpn-protocol/">VPN protocols</a> (such as OpenVPN, IKEv2, and WireGuard) are relatively easy to recognize on a network. And as deep packet inspection (DPI) technology becomes more widespread, it will be easier and easier for authoritarian governments to detect and block VPNs using these protocols. </p>



<p>For years there have been various projects to try to obfuscate existing VPN protocols, but many of them are hacks on top of existing protocols that unfortunately no longer work very well.</p>



<p>We designed our Stealth protocol from the ground up to not have these issues. With Stealth enabled, your Proton VPN connection will be almost completely undetectable.</p>



<p>Stealth is available on all Proton VPN plans, including our Free plan, because everyone deserves online freedom. For now, you can use Stealth on our Android, Windows, macOS, and iOS apps.</p>











<h2 id="Blog-HowdoIuseStealth?">How do I use Stealth?</h2>



<p>To activate Stealth, open the Proton VPN app on your device.</p>



<ul>
<li>On Android,  tap <strong>☰</strong> →  <strong>Settings</strong> → <strong>Advanced</strong> → <strong>Protocol</strong> and choose <strong>Stealth</strong>.</li>



<li> On Windows, tap<strong> ☰</strong> <strong>Settings → Connection → Protocol and choose Stealth.</strong></li>



<li>On iOS and iPadOS, tap&nbsp;<strong>Settings</strong>&nbsp;→<strong>&nbsp;Security options</strong>&nbsp;→&nbsp;<strong>Protocol</strong>&nbsp;and choose&nbsp;<strong>Stealth</strong>.</li>



<li>On macOS,&nbsp;<strong>ProtonVPN</strong>&nbsp;in the macOS taskbar →&nbsp;<strong>Preferences</strong>&nbsp;→&nbsp;<strong>Connection</strong>&nbsp;→&nbsp;<strong>Protocol</strong>&nbsp;and select&nbsp;<strong>Stealth</strong>&nbsp;from the dropdown menu.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>Stealth is not yet available on our Linux app.</p>



<p><a rel="" target="_self" href="https://protonvpn.com/support/how-to-change-vpn-protocols/"><strong>Learn more about changing VPN protocols</strong></a></p>



<h2 id="Blog-HowdoestheStealthVPNprotocolwork?">How does the Stealth VPN protocol work?</h2>



<p>Stealth uses obfuscation to hide your VPN connection from censors. The general idea is to make VPN traffic look like “normal” traffic&nbsp;—&nbsp;or common HTTPS connections. Stealth does this by using obfuscated TLS tunneling over TCP. This is different from most popular VPN protocols that typically use UDP, making them easier to detect and block. Without going into too much detail, Stealth also establishes VPN connections in a specific and unique way that avoids alerting internet filters.</p>



<p>Despite these obfuscation features, the Stealth VPN protocol is also optimized for high performance and is compatible with our VPN Accelerator technology. Coupled with our lightweight internals, Stealth can achieve higher performance than older obfuscated VPN protocols that are generally built on top of OpenVPN over TCP.</p>



<h2 id="Blog-Thefightcontinues"><strong>The fight continues</strong></h2>



<p>We want to thank the members of the Proton community who helped us test the Stealth VPN protocol over the last couple of months. They live under restrictive censorship regimes, and Stealth would have been impossible to develop without their assistance. Thank you.</p>



<p>However, in the constantly evolving battle for online freedom, our work is not finished. Accordingly, we designed Stealth to be an extensible and adaptable VPN protocol that is flexible enough to meet new challenges.</p>



<p>The cause of freedom has no borders, and we must stand together for it to succeed. Tools like Proton VPN play a vital role in keeping the internet free.&nbsp;Our investment in technologies like Stealth is part of our commitment to provide internet privacy to everyone, regardless of their ability to pay.</p>



<p>Proton VPN will always be free, but if you would like to support our mission to keep the internet free and open to all, you can subscribe to a paid plan which offers even faster speeds and premium features.</p>











<p>P.S. We want to say thanks to the hundreds of Proton VPN community members who suggested names for our new protocol. Your top choice was Neutrino, which we liked a lot because of the connection to physics.&nbsp;And neutrinos can pass through all matter, making it even more appropriate.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Unfortunately, we felt this name might cause confusion with a Web3 project, so we picked Stealth instead. This was another popular community suggestion, and its meaning is more obvious to those less familiar with physics.</p>
 </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dell lays off 12,500 people (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/06/dell_layoffs/</link>
            <guid>41172399</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 16:28:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/06/dell_layoffs/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/06/dell_layoffs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41172399">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Dell has made another round of layoffs, which <em>The Register</em> understands have cut deep and seen even company veterans let go.</p>
<p>HR exit meetings kicked off on Tuesday morning, spurring a wave of LinkedIn status changes, while others found comfort venting or trading information in <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/dell">online forums</a>.</p>
<p>Dell confirmed the layoffs to <em>The Register</em>.</p>

    

<p>"Through a reorganization of our go-to-market teams and an ongoing series of actions, we are becoming a leaner company. We are combining teams and prioritizing where we invest across the company. We continually evolve our business, so we're set up to deliver the best innovation, value and service to our customers and partners," Dell told <i>The Register</i> by email.</p>

        


        

<p>The sentiment was also <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-08-05/dell-layoffs-hit-sales-team-with-new-unit-focused-on-ai">reportedly</a>expressed in a memo sent to some employees as they watched colleagues pack up their belongings.</p>
<p>In the memo, president of global sales and customer operations Bill Scannell and global channels president John Byrne used the term "streamlining layers of management."</p>

        

<p>According to Scannell and Byrne, Dell aims to grow faster than the market by unlocking "the value of modern IT and AI" for customer organizations.</p>
<p>Implied was that they would be doing this without the help of an undisclosed number of newly former employees. That number has been <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://x.com/WhatLayoff/status/1820595751849693413">guesstimated</a> at around ten percent of the workforce – about 12,500 people – as part of an effort to get the overall workforce from 120,000 to <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/03/dell_return_to_work/">below 100,000</a>.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/20/dell_rto_mandate/">Staff say Dell's return to office mandate is a stealth layoff, especially for women</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/02/10/tech_job_cuts_gitlab_microsoft/">Tech job bonfire rages on as Microsoft, GitLab and others join in</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/06/20/half_of_dell_us_staff_wfh/">Half of Dell US staff reportedly opted for remote work</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/12/15/ai_implementation_challenges/">Everyone's talking about AI but industry reps say few are ready to implement</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/05/stock_market_outages/">Stock-trading apps fall under the feet of stampeding panicking investors</a></li>
</ul>
<p>It is unknown if this round of cuts met that target, or if further firings will follow – particularly as many suspicious 1:1 meetings scheduled for Tuesday were <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tSY0Var">allegedly</a> moved.</p>
<p>As one employee <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tRHybgc">put it</a>: "There are only so many HR reps to go around." A prophetic musing, as Dell's Human Resources department was <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tRJUooS">allegedly</a> too swamped to even show up for some terminations – leaving the job instead to line managers.</p>
<p>Severance for most will likely <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tRdSXcr">involve</a> a payout of two months wages plus a week per year served up to a max of 26 weeks, and potential partial bonus payouts. Loyal Dell graybeards have <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tRJ8ZuF">grumbled</a> about losing long-term incentives and <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tRIaBSr">stock options</a>.</p>

        

<p>Some employees have reported seeing the workforce reduction writing on the wall. "I work in advertising and recently learned that Dell's fall print budgets were cut two weeks ago, which makes sense. Additionally, Intel had issued a major RFP that they withdrew last week, just before the news broke about their mass layoffs and stock decline," claimed <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tSaEMwD">one employee</a>.</p>
<p>"With how frequent the layoffs have been I can't trust there won't be more in the future. I've survived so far but almost half my team is gone now versus two years ago," <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.thelayoff.com/t/1tSrZvnR">pondered</a> another Dell-ite who has decided to seek employment elsewhere.</p>
<p>One Redditor <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Austin/comments/1ekwl3n/comment/lgnq3za/">referred</a> to the regular layoffs endured by Dell employees as the yearly "rank and yank."</p>
<p>Last year was special – much like this year – when it came to the numbers seen in its rank and yank. The PC giant <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/02/06/dell_job_cuts/">announced</a> a reduction of around five percent of its workforce, but ended up with double that – cutting 13,000 over the 2023 fiscal year, according to <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-03-26/dell-layoffs-hit-13-000-employees-over-the-past-year">reports</a>.</p>
<p>The same year, Dell <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/05/10/dell_remote_work_revision/">called</a> its workforce back to the office after previously promising the workplace would forever stay primarily remote or hybrid. Many saw the mandate to return as a <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/02/20/dell_rto_mandate/">stealth layoff</a> that disproportionately harmed women.</p>
<p>Dell's layoffs come one week after Intel <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/01/intel_to_ax_headcount/">announced</a> it will shed 15 percent of its payroll as the x86 giant scrambles to get its finances under control. That could be tricky as it is occupied with damage control having missed the AI market, suffered a revenue slump, confronted additional competition in the PC space, and admitted its Raptor Lake chips are <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/23/intel_raptor_lake_instability_fix/">frying systems</a>.</p>
<p>The next day, Intel stock took a 26 percent hit.</p>
<p>Dell was also <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://seekingalpha.com/news/4134242-dell-reduces-sales-team-as-it-prioritizes-ai-report">reportedly</a> down three percent during afternoon trading on Monday – which, in comparison to this week's <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/05/stock_market_outages/">stock market wobble</a>, seemed par for the course.</p>
<p>The decreased need for employees could also be sign that Dell is engaging more with partners and less with in-house sales. Many of the positions eliminated appear to come from the sales division. Last August Dell announced its <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.delltechnologies.com/partner/en-sg/partner/partner-first-storage.htm">Partner First For Storage</a> strategy – an initiative aimed at boosting sales through the channel. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Is Ending Production of Chromecast (541 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.google/products/google-nest/chromecast-history/</link>
            <guid>41171060</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 14:15:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.google/products/google-nest/chromecast-history/">https://blog.google/products/google-nest/chromecast-history/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41171060">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article ng-init="drawerToggle = {'open': true}">

    
    





    

    
      

<div data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Hero Menu&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;7 memorable moments in Chromecast\u0027s history&quot;
  }">
  <div>
      <div>
          <p>Aug 06, 2024</p>
          
            <p data-reading-time-render="">[[read-time]] min read</p>
          
        </div>
      
        <p>
          Take a look back at Chromecast’s evolution over the past 11 years — and learn about the future of streaming TV with Google.
        </p>
      
    </div>
  <div data-component="uni-ai-generated-summary" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;event&quot;: &quot;module_impression&quot;,
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;ai_summary&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;CTA&quot;
  }">
      
        <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_1">
          <h2>General summary</h2>
          <p>Chromecast, the popular streaming device, is bidding farewell after 11 years and over 100 million devices sold. Chromecast revolutionized TV streaming by offering an easy and affordable way to cast online content onto TVs. As technology advanced, Google invested in embedding Chromecast technology into millions of TV devices, including Android TV, making streaming more accessible than ever. To mark this transition, Google is introducing Google TV Streamer, a premium device designed for the modern era of entertainment and smart home needs.</p>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
      
        <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_2">
          <h2>Bullet points</h2>
          <ul>
<li>Chromecast, with over 100 million devices sold, is ending production after 11 years.<ul>
<li>Chromecast revolutionized streaming by offering an affordable and simple way to cast online content onto TVs.</li>
<li>Technology advancements and the rise of smart TVs with built-in streaming capabilities have changed the landscape.</li>
<li>Google is introducing Google TV Streamer, a more advanced device for entertainment and smart home needs.</li>
<li>Chromecast's legacy is celebrated with a look back at some of its memorable moments.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
      
        <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_3">
          <h2>Basic explainer</h2>
          <p>Chromecast, a device that lets you watch online content on your TV, is ending production after 11 years.</p>
<p>Chromecast was a simple and affordable way to stream content from your phone or tablet to your TV.</p>
<p>Since then, streaming and smart TVs have become more common, and Chromecast technology has been built into millions of TV devices.</p>
<p>Google is introducing Google TV Streamer, a new device that builds on Chromecast technology and offers more features for entertainment and smart home needs.</p>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
      

      
      <div>
        <h4>
          Explore other styles:
        </h4>
        
      </div>
      

      </div>
</div>

    

    
      







<div>
    <figure>
      <div>
  <p><img srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_Hero-B.width-600.format-webp.webp 600w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_Hero-B.width-1200.format-webp.webp 1200w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_Hero-B.width-1600.format-webp.webp 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, (max-width: 1023px) 600px, 1024px" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_Hero-B.width-1200.format-webp.webp" fetchpriority="high" alt="Illustration of three people sitting in front of a TV. Four iterations of Chromecast devices surround them in bubbles.">
  </p>
</div>

      
    </figure>
  </div>


    

    
    <div data-reading-time="true" data-component="uni-drop-cap|uni-tombstone">

            
              


<google-read-aloud-player data-analytics-module="{
        &quot;event&quot;: &quot;module_impression&quot;,
        &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;ai_audio&quot;,
        &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;7 memorable moments in Chromecast\u0027s history&quot;
    }" data-date-modified="2024-08-06T13:38:05.338177+00:00" data-progress-bar-style="half-wave" data-api-key="AIzaSyBLT6VkYe-x7sWLZI2Ep26-fNkBKgND-Ac" data-article-style="style9" data-tracking-ids="G-HGNBTNCHCQ,G-6NKTLKV14N" data-voice-list="en.ioh-pngnat:Cyan,en.usb-pngnat:Lime" data-layout-style="style1" data-highlight-mode="word-over-paragraph" data-highlight-text-color="#000000" data-highlight-word-background="#8AB4F8" data-highlight-paragraph-background="#D2E3FC" data-background="linear-gradient(180deg, #F1F3F4 0%, #F8F9FA 100%)" data-foreground-color="#202124" data-font="600 16px Google Sans, sans-serif" data-box-shadow="0px 1px 3px 1px rgba(60, 64, 67, 0.15)">
</google-read-aloud-player>




            

            
            
<!--article text-->

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;7 memorable moments in Chromecast\u0027s history&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="r562r">After 11 years and over 100 million devices sold, we're ending production of Chromecast, which will now only be available while supplies last. The time has now come to evolve the smart TV streaming device category — primed for the new area of AI, entertainment and smart homes. With this, there are <a href="https://safety.google/nest/" rt-link-type="external">no changes to our support policy</a> for existing Chromecast devices, with continued software and security updates to the latest devices.</p><p data-block-key="456hn">When we launched Chromecast, most TVs had few (if any) apps, streaming was unreliable and complicated and connecting your TV to your phone, tablet or laptop was clunky and hard. Chromecast was our answer to this problem, a simple and affordable way to cast your favorite online content right on your TV screen. It was as easy as plugging in the device and hitting play. Chromecast’s small dongle form factor made it easy to hide behind a TV, and the affordable price made it accessible to millions and the perfect gift for many.</p><p data-block-key="bq3db">Since then, technology has evolved dramatically. Streaming and smart TVs abound. We invested heavily in embedding Google Cast technology into millions of TV devices, including Android TV. Android TV has <a href="https://blog.google/products/android/android-anniversary-tv-auto-wear/" rt-link-type="external">expanded to 220 million devices</a> worldwide and we are continuing to bring Google Cast to other TV devices, like LG TVs. Thousands of apps support casting, making it easier than ever to watch your content from your phone and tablet on the big screen. So we are taking the next step in evolving how streaming TV devices can add even more capabilities to your smart TV, built on top of the same Chromecast technology.</p><p data-block-key="59n5t">Today, we’re <a href="https://blog.google/products/google-nest/google-tv-streamer" rt-link-type="external">introducing Google TV Streamer</a>, a more premium device built for the new era of entertainment and smart home needs. With Google TV Streamer, you can not only indulge your entertainment needs, but also have a hub for your whole smart home.</p><p data-block-key="ej1jt">Still, Google TV Streamer wouldn't exist without Chromecast paving the way. To honor the end of this era, here is a trip down memory lane of some of Chromecast's biggest moments.</p></div>
  

  
    

<div data-component="uni-image-carousel" data-analytics-module="{ &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Article Carousel&quot;, &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;7 memorable moments in Chromecast\u0027s history&quot; }">
    
    <ul>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A small, black HDMI stick with the Chrome logo" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_1st_gen.max-200x200.format-webp.webp" data-loading="{ &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_1st_gen.max-1000x1000.format-webp.webp&quot;, &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_1st_gen.max-1086x1086.format-webp.webp&quot; }">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="8dlct">2013: This tiny device brought the experience of casting content from your phone to the biggest screen in your house. <a href="https://blog.google/products/chromecast/from-tvs-to-tablets-everything-you-love/" rt-link-type="external">Chromecast (1st gen)</a> was a small, portable stick that plugged right into the HDMI port of your TV. You could then use your phone, tablet or computer to wirelessly cast content from apps like YouTube.</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A yellow, round disc with the Chrome logo in the center and a black cable attached" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_2nd_gen_rXPC2vI.max-1196x1196.format-webp.webp">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="1273z">2015: The <a href="https://blog.google/products/android/smore-to-love-across-all-your-screens/" rt-link-type="external">second-generation Chromecast</a> had a new dongle design, plus new color options (yellow and red, in addition to black). Switching to a dongle made it easier to tuck Chromecast behind your TV. And with a magnetized back and HDMI plug, it attached perfectly to TVs and wall mounts.</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A small, black, puck-shaped device with textured concentric rings around a Chrome logo with a yellow cable attached" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_Audio.max-1198x1198.format-webp.webp">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="1273z">2015: We launched <a href="https://blog.google/products/chromecast/how-love-chromecast-lot/" rt-link-type="external">Chromecast Audio</a>, a streaming music player, which could plug directly into speakers or home theater systems for easy audio streaming. It transformed any speaker into a modern streaming audio system. It also featured a headphone jack and grooved design to resemble a vinyl record.</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A black, puck-shaped device with an ethernet port and a Google G logo with a black, flat HDMI cord attached" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_Ultra.max-936x936.format-webp.webp">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="1273z">2016: <a href="https://blog.google/products/chromecast/fastest-chromecast-yet-4k-and-hdr-support/" rt-link-type="external">Chromecast Ultra</a> was the first Chromecast device to provide 4K streaming and an ethernet port for uninterrupted viewing. It was also the first to support Dolby Vision.</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A white, circular device with the Google G logo in the center and a black, flat HDMI cord attached" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_3rd_gen.max-1210x1210.format-webp.webp">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="1273z">2018: <a href="https://blog.google/products/chromecast/five-reasons-and-two-colors-why-we-love-new-chromecast/" rt-link-type="external">The third generation of Chromecast</a> leveled up with smoother playback support and 15% faster speeds than its predecessor. We also added support for Dolby Digital PlusTM and fully integrated Chromecast with Nest smart speakers, so you could control your TV with a quick “Hey Google.”</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A pink, oval-shaped dongle with attached HDMI cord. Next to it is a pink, curved remote with eight buttons and a circular d-pad." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Chromecast_with_Google_TV_4k.max-772x772.format-webp.webp">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="1273z">2020: <a href="https://blog.google/products/chromecast/best-chromecast-google-tv/" rt-link-type="external">Chromecast with Google TV (4K)</a> came onto the scene to organize all your entertainment in one place with tailored recommendations, a personal watchlist and the ability to search across all your apps at once using your voice. We also introduced our most-requested feature: a voice remote.</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
        <li>
          <figure>
            <p><img alt="A white, oval-shaped dongle with an attached HDMI cord and pink. Next to it is a curved remote with eight buttons and a circular d-pad." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/Google_with_Chromecast_TV_HD.max-1274x1274.format-webp.webp">
            
            </p>
            
              <figcaption><p data-block-key="1273z">2022: We launched <a href="https://blog.google/products/chromecast/chromecast-google-tv-hd/" rt-link-type="external">Chromecast with Google TV (HD)</a>, built with affordability in mind, to bring the Google TV experience — including access to over 10,000 apps in 1080p — to even more people.</p></figcaption>
            
          </figure>
        </li>
      
    </ul>
    <ul role="tablist">
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
        <li>
          
        </li>
      
    </ul>
  </div>

  


            
            

            
              




            
          </div>
  </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I built a simple, open-source tool to manage servers and SSH keys (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/d3witt/viking</link>
            <guid>41170925</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 13:58:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/d3witt/viking">https://github.com/d3witt/viking</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41170925">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Viking 🗺️</h2><a id="user-content-viking-️" aria-label="Permalink: Viking 🗺️" href="#viking-️"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Simple way to manage your remote machines</h3><a id="user-content-simple-way-to-manage-your-remote-machines" aria-label="Permalink: Simple way to manage your remote machines" href="#simple-way-to-manage-your-remote-machines"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Bare metal servers are awesome. They let you pick where to run your software and how to deploy it. You get full control to make the most of the server's resources. No limits, no compromises. That's real freedom.</p>
<p dir="auto">Viking makes it easier to work with them.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="NAME:
   viking - Manage your SSH keys and remote machines

USAGE:
   viking [global options] command [command options]

VERSION:
   v1.0

COMMANDS:
   exec     Execute shell command on machine
   key      Manage SSH keys
   machine  Manage your machines
   config   Get config directory path
   help, h  Shows a list of commands or help for one command

GLOBAL OPTIONS:
   --help, -h     show help
   --version, -v  print the version"><pre><code>NAME:
   viking - Manage your SSH keys and remote machines

USAGE:
   viking [global options] command [command options]

VERSION:
   v1.0

COMMANDS:
   exec     Execute shell command on machine
   key      Manage SSH keys
   machine  Manage your machines
   config   Get config directory path
   help, h  Shows a list of commands or help for one command

GLOBAL OPTIONS:
   --help, -h     show help
   --version, -v  print the version
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 Installation</h2><a id="user-content--installation" aria-label="Permalink: 🚀 Installation" href="#-installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/d3witt/viking/releases">releases</a> for pre-built binaries.</p>
<p dir="auto">On Unix:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="env CGO_ENABLED=0 go install -ldflags=&quot;-s -w&quot; github.com/d3witt/viking@latest"><pre><code>env CGO_ENABLED=0 go install -ldflags="-s -w" github.com/d3witt/viking@latest
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">On Windows cmd:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="set CGO_ENABLED=0
go install -ldflags=&quot;-s -w&quot; github.com/d3witt/viking@latest"><pre><code>set CGO_ENABLED=0
go install -ldflags="-s -w" github.com/d3witt/viking@latest
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">On Windows powershell:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$env:CGO_ENABLED = '0'
go install -ldflags=&quot;-s -w&quot; github.com/d3witt/viking@latest"><pre><code>$env:CGO_ENABLED = '0'
go install -ldflags="-s -w" github.com/d3witt/viking@latest
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📄 Usage</h2><a id="user-content--usage" aria-label="Permalink: 📄 Usage" href="#-usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🛰️ Add machine:</h4><a id="user-content-️-add-machine" aria-label="Permalink: 🛰️ Add machine:" href="#️-add-machine"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ viking machine add --name deathstar --key starkey 168.112.216.50
Machine deathstar added."><pre><code>$ viking machine add --name deathstar --key starkey 168.112.216.50
Machine deathstar added.
</code></pre></div>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">The key flag is not required. If a key is not specified, SSH Agent will be used to connect to the server.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📡 Exec command:</h4><a id="user-content--exec-command" aria-label="Permalink: 📡 Exec command:" href="#-exec-command"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ viking exec deathstar echo 1234
1234"><pre><code>$ viking exec deathstar echo 1234
1234
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📺 Connect to the machine:</h4><a id="user-content--connect-to-the-machine" aria-label="Permalink: 📺 Connect to the machine:" href="#-connect-to-the-machine"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ viking exec --tty deathstar /bin/bash
root@deathstar:~$"><pre><code>$ viking exec --tty deathstar /bin/bash
root@deathstar:~$
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🔑 Add SSH key from a file</h4><a id="user-content--add-ssh-key-from-a-file" aria-label="Permalink: 🔑 Add SSH key from a file" href="#-add-ssh-key-from-a-file"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ viking key add --name starkey --passphrase dart ./id_rsa_star
Key starkey added."><pre><code>$ viking key add --name starkey --passphrase dart ./id_rsa_star
Key starkey added.
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🆕 Generate SSH Key</h4><a id="user-content--generate-ssh-key" aria-label="Permalink: 🆕 Generate SSH Key" href="#-generate-ssh-key"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ viking key generate --name starkey2
Key starkey2 added."><pre><code>$ viking key generate --name starkey2
Key starkey2 added.
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📋 Copy public SSH Key</h4><a id="user-content--copy-public-ssh-key" aria-label="Permalink: 📋 Copy public SSH Key" href="#-copy-public-ssh-key"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ viking key copy starkey2
Public key copied to your clipboard."><pre><code>$ viking key copy starkey2
Public key copied to your clipboard.
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">⚙️ Custom config directory</h4><a id="user-content-️-custom-config-directory" aria-label="Permalink: ⚙️ Custom config directory" href="#️-custom-config-directory"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Viking saves data locally. Set <code>VIKING_CONFIG_DIR</code> env variable for a custom directory. Use <code>viking config</code> to check the current config folder.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🤝  Missing a Feature?</h2><a id="user-content---missing-a-feature" aria-label="Permalink: 🤝  Missing a Feature?" href="#--missing-a-feature"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Feel free to open a new issue, or contact me.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📘  License</h2><a id="user-content---license" aria-label="Permalink: 📘  License" href="#--license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Viking is provided under the <a href="https://github.com/d3witt/viking/blob/main/LICENSE">MIT License</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WordStar 7, the last ever DOS version, is re-released for free (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/06/wordstar_7_the_last_ever/</link>
            <guid>41169195</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 09:47:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/06/wordstar_7_the_last_ever/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/06/wordstar_7_the_last_ever/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41169195">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Before WordPerfect, the most popular work processor was WordStar. Now, the last ever DOS version has been bundled and set free by one of its biggest fans.</p>
<div><p><a href="https://regmedia.co.uk/2024/08/05/wordstar-7-on-macos.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://regmedia.co.uk/2024/08/05/wordstar-7-on-macos.png?x=648&amp;y=375&amp;infer_y=1" alt="wordstar 7 on macos" title="wordstar 7 on macos" height="375" width="648"></a></p><p>Wordstar 7 on macOS - click to enlarge</p>
</div>
<p>WordStar 7.0d was the last-ever DOS release of <em>the</em> classic word processor, and it still has admirers today. A <a href="https://sfwriter.com/wordstar.htm" rel="nofollow">notable enthusiast</a> is Canadian SF writer Robert J Sawyer, who wrote the book that became the <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1441135/" rel="nofollow">TV series <em>Flashforward</em></a>.</p>
<p>Thanks to his efforts you can now try out this pinnacle of pre-Windows PC programs for professional prose-smiths. Sawyer has taken the final release, packaged it up along with some useful tools — including DOS emulators for modern Windows – and <a href="https://sfwriter.com/blog/?p=5806" rel="nofollow">shared the result</a>. Now you, too, can revel in the sheer unbridled power of this powerful app.</p>
<p>Sawyer says:</p>

<p>The download is 680MB, but as well as the app itself, full documentation, and some tools to help translate WordStar documents to more modern formats, it also includes copies of two FOSS tools that will let you run this MS-DOS application on modern Windows: <a href="https://dosbox-x.com/" rel="nofollow">DOSbox-X</a> and <a href="http://vdosplus.org/" rel="nofollow">vDosPlus</a>. Regular <em>Register</em> readers may recognize both from our story on <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/06/28/friday_foss_fest_running_dos/">how to run DOS on a 64-bit OS</a> from last year. Sawyer also offers a <a href="https://www.sfwriter.com/wordstar-command-summary.pdf" rel="nofollow">handy command reference</a> [PDF].</p>
<p>WordStar has a long and exceptionally involved history, as the Wordstar.org fan site <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240525080009/https:/www.wordstar.org/index.php/wordstar-history" rel="nofollow">used to chronicle</a>. It started out on CP/M, was ported to DOS, multiple incompatible programs of the same name launched, and later still <a href="https://winworldpc.com/product/wordstar/20-for-windows" rel="nofollow">ported to Windows</a>. The last ever release was part of an <a href="https://winworldpc.com/product/xoom-office-suite/97" rel="nofollow">obscure office suite</a>. Sawyer is correct: the final DOS version really is the true classic.</p>
<p>MicroPro, the company behind WordStar, was repeatedly acquired. At one point it was part of SoftKey, which was acquired and became <a href="https://www.theregister.com/1999/05/04/fears_grow_over_web_perverting/">the Learning Company</a>, which was <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2000/02/08/was_mattel_ceo_pushed/">bought by Mattel</a> in what <a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/report-on-business/rob-magazine/kevin-oleary-hes-not-a-billionaire-he-just-plays-one-on-tv/article4564334/?page=all" rel="nofollow">BusinessWeek called</a> "the worst acquisition of all time." As a result, the software business was spun off again and bought by <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2007/10/19/ireland_mergers_acquisitions/">Houghton Mifflin Riverdeep</a>. Sawyer says:</p>

<p>While it certainly has been abandoned since the end of the 20th century, the term "abandonware" isn't a legal one. It's not clear to us who owns the intellectual property. We doubt it's one of the surviving offshoots, today's <a href="https://www.hmhco.com/about-us" rel="nofollow">Houghton Mifflin Harcourt</a>, but it could be another offshoot, <a href="https://www.mackiev.com/" rel="nofollow">Software MacKiev</a>. Either way, it's very unlikely that the owners will care.</p>
<p>If the many changes&nbsp;of ownership weren't enough, the program itself had many offshoots. A rewrite in C became the incompatible <a href="https://winworldpc.com/product/wordstar/2000" rel="nofollow">Wordstar 2000</a>, that abandoned the keyboard-centric UI which was WordStar's hallmark. MicroPro also acquired a student's Modula-2 project and rebadged it WordStar Express, which Amstrad PC 1512 owners may remember: Amstrad got a licence cheaply and bundled it as "WordStar 1512". Even WordStar 7 isn't based on the original code: MicroPro bought a rival clone of the program called NewWord, and made it the official WordStar 4 – as still <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/technology-27407502" rel="nofollow">used by George R R Martin</a>.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/03/wordperfect_bruce_bastian/">RIP: WordPerfect co-founder Bruce Bastian dies at 76</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/10/25/microsoft_word_40/">Word turns 40: From 'new kid on the block' to 'I can't believe it's not bloatware'</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/03/04/on_call/">Saving a loved one from a document disaster</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2021/12/17/tilde_text_editor/">Fans of original gangster editors, look away now: It's Tilde, a text editor that doesn't work like it's 1976</a></li>
</ul>
<p>While many folks in the Unix world have Vi keystrokes engraved in their muscle memory, those for WordStar are the equivalent for CP/M and MS-DOS users&nbsp;of a certain age. <code>Ctrl+S/ E/D/X</code> for navigation, <code>Ctrl+K, B</code> to mark the start of a block, <code>Ctrl+K, K</code> to mark the end, then <code>Ctrl+K, C</code> to copy it or <code>Ctrl+K, V</code> to move it; and <code>Ctrl+K+S</code> to Save. The modern <a href="https://joe-editor.sourceforge.io/" rel="nofollow">Joe text editor</a> still uses them, for instance. It hasn't got all the functionality, but if you don't want to struggle with an emulator to run a DOS app, the FOSS clone <a href="http://wordtsar.ca/" rel="nofollow">WordTsar</a> comes close, and has <a href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/wordtsar/files/Releases/" rel="nofollow">versions for Windows, Linux and macOS</a>.</p>
<p>By modern standards, WordStar doesn't do much, but it does everything many writers want. The <em>Reg</em> FOSS desk is rather fond of Robert Sawyer's novels, as well as George R R Martin's come to that, but those less given to genre fiction may recognize William F Buckley Jr and Ralph Ellison, both&nbsp;keen users. ®</p>

    
                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI co-founder John Schulman says he will leave and join rival Anthropic (365 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/08/06/openai-co-founder-john-schulman-says-he-will-join-rival-anthropic.html</link>
            <guid>41168904</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 08:39:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/08/06/openai-co-founder-john-schulman-says-he-will-join-rival-anthropic.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/08/06/openai-co-founder-john-schulman-says-he-will-join-rival-anthropic.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41168904">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-108016585" data-test="InlineImage"><p>The ChatGPT chat screen on a smartphone arranged in the Brooklyn borough of New York, US, on Thursday, March 9, 2023. ChatGPT has made writing computer code and cheating on homework easier. Soon, it could make email scams a cinch. That's the warning from Darktrace Plc, the British cybersecurity firm.</p><p>Gabby Jones | Bloomberg | Getty Images</p></div><div><p>OpenAI co-founder John Schulman said in a Monday X post that he would leave the <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/MSFT/">Microsoft</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>-backed company and join Anthropic, an artificial intelligence startup with funding from <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-2"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/AMZN/">Amazon</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span>.</p><p>The move comes less than three months after OpenAI <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/17/openai-superalignment-sutskever-leike.html">disbanded a superalignment team</a> that focused on trying to ensure that people can control AI systems that exceed human capability at many tasks.</p><p>Schulman had been a co-leader of OpenAI's post-training team that refined AI models for the ChatGPT chatbot and a programming interface for third-party developers, according to a biography on his <a href="http://joschu.net/" target="_blank">website</a>. In June, OpenAI <a href="https://openai.com/index/openai-board-forms-safety-and-security-committee/" target="_blank">said</a> Schulman, as head of alignment science, would join a safety and security committee that would provide advice to the board. Schulman has only worked at OpenAI since receiving a Ph.D. in computer science in 2016 from the University of California, Berkeley.</p><p>"This choice stems from my desire to deepen my focus on AI alignment, and to start a new chapter of my career where I can return to hands-on technical work," Schulman wrote in the <a href="https://x.com/johnschulman2/status/1820610863499509855" target="_blank">social media post</a>.</p><p>He said he wasn't leaving because of a lack of support for new work on the topic at OpenAI.</p><p>"On the contrary, company leaders have been very committed to investing in this area," he said.</p><p>The leaders of the superalignment team, Jan Leike and company co-founder Ilya Sutskever, both left this year. Leike <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/05/28/openai-safety-leader-jan-leike-joins-amazon-backed-anthropic.html">joined Anthropic</a>, while Sutskever said he was <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/06/19/openai-co-founder-ilya-sutskever-announces-safe-superintelligence.html">helping to start</a> a new company, Safe Superintelligence Inc.</p><p>Since OpenAI staff members established Anthropic in 2021, the two young San Francisco-based businesses have been battling to have the most performant generative AI models that can come up with human-like text. Amazon, Google and Meta have also developed large language models.</p><p>"Very excited to be working together again!" Leike wrote <a href="https://x.com/janleike/status/1820613953350959504" target="_blank">in reply</a> to Schulman's message.</p><p>Sam Altman, OpenAI's co-founder and CEO, said in a <a href="https://x.com/sama/status/1820617107354083611" target="_blank">post</a> of his own that Schulman's perspective informed the startup's early strategy.</p><p>Schulman and others chose to leave after the board pushed out Altman as chief last November. Employees protested the decision, prompting Sutskever and two other board members, Tasha McCauley and Helen Toner, to resign. <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/11/22/openai-brings-sam-altman-back-as-ceo-days-after-ouster.html">Altman was reinstated</a> and OpenAI took on additional board members.</p><p>Toner said on a<a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/former-openai-board-member-helen-toner-dishes-on-reasons-why-they-ousted-sam-altman" target="_blank"> podcast</a> that Altman had given the board incorrect information about the "small number of formal safety processes that the company did have in place."</p><p>The law firm WilmerHale found in an independent <a href="https://openai.com/index/review-completed-altman-brockman-to-continue-to-lead-openai/" target="_blank">review</a> that the board wasn't concerned about product safety when it pushed out Altman.</p><p>Last week, Altman <a href="https://x.com/sama/status/1818867964369928387" target="_blank">said on X</a> that OpenAI "has been working with the US AI Safety Institute on an agreement where we would provide early access to our next foundation model so that we can work together to push forward the science of AI evaluations." Altman said OpenAI is still committed to keeping 20% of its computing resources for safety initiatives.</p><p>Also on Monday, Greg Brockman, another co-founder of OpenAI and its president, announced that he was taking a <a href="https://x.com/gdb/status/1820644694264791459" target="_blank">sabbatical for the rest of the year</a>.</p><p><strong>WATCH:</strong> <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/video/2024/07/25/openai-announces-a-search-engine-called-searchgpt.html">OpenAI announces a search engine called SearchGPT</a></p></div><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-108011950" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000346800" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-108011950"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/108011951-17219321001721932097-35516808318-1080pnbcnews.jpg?v=1721932099&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="OpenAI announces a search engine called SearchGPT"><span></span><span></span></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X is closing San Francisco HQ and relocating staffers to San Jose (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2024/08/05/x-closing-san-francisco-hq-relocating-staffers-san-jose-palo-alto-shared-space-with-x-ai-linda-yaccarino-leaked-email/</link>
            <guid>41168889</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 08:37:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/08/05/x-closing-san-francisco-hq-relocating-staffers-san-jose-palo-alto-shared-space-with-x-ai-linda-yaccarino-leaked-email/">https://fortune.com/2024/08/05/x-closing-san-francisco-hq-relocating-staffers-san-jose-palo-alto-shared-space-with-x-ai-linda-yaccarino-leaked-email/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41168889">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-cy="article-content" id="article-content"><p>X, the social media company formerly known as <a href="https://fortune.com/company/twitter/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/twitter/">Twitter</a>, is set to leave San Francisco in the coming weeks.</p><div>



<p>In a Monday email from Linda Yaccarino, the<a href="https://fortune.com/2023/11/20/inside-elon-musk-twitter-44-billion-takeover-x-oral-history/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2023/11/20/inside-elon-musk-twitter-44-billion-takeover-x-oral-history/"> CEO of X appointed last year by owner Elon Musk</a>, X staffers were briefly informed of the company’s plans to shutter the office that has served as Twitter headquarters for more than a decade.</p>



<p>“After much thought, we have made the decision to close our San Francisco office over the next few weeks,” Yaccarino wrote in the email viewed by <em>Fortune</em>. “This is an important decision that impacts many of you, but it is the right one for our company in the long term.”</p>



<p>Musk abruptly&nbsp;<a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1813295489032622586?lang=en" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1813295489032622586?lang=en" rel="noopener">stated on X</a>&nbsp;about three weeks ago that the company’s headquarters would move to Texas, where his other companies <a href="https://fortune.com/company/spacex/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/spacex/">SpaceX</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/tesla/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/tesla/">Tesla</a> and The Boring Company, are also located. Musk and X were sued earlier this year by the owner of the Market Street building, for allegedly failing to pay rent after Musk took over Twitter in late 2022. The building owner&nbsp;<a href="https://www.reuters.com/legal/litigation/xs-san-francisco-landlord-dismisses-lawsuit-claiming-unpaid-rent-2024-03-19/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://www.reuters.com/legal/litigation/xs-san-francisco-landlord-dismisses-lawsuit-claiming-unpaid-rent-2024-03-19/" rel="noopener">dismissed</a>&nbsp;the lawsuit in March.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Yaccarino’s note to X staff said nothing of a move to Texas, as Musk claimed last month. Instead, she said that X staff located in San Francisco would be moved to existing office space in San Jose and Palo Alto.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“We will work to transition to our new primary locations in the Bay Area,” she wrote.</p>



<p>The move comes as San Francisco is struggling to revive its downtown district and its commercial real estate market. And it marks a setback to the city’s efforts to turn the gritty mid-Market Street area into a thriving tech hub. </p>



<p><a href="https://www.sfgate.com/business/article/twitter-signs-lease-for-headquarters-in-mid-market-2374112.php" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://www.sfgate.com/business/article/twitter-signs-lease-for-headquarters-in-mid-market-2374112.php" rel="noopener">Twitter took over the San Francisco space</a>—an expansive, 1-million square foot Art Deco building that once served as a furniture showroom—and made it its global headquarters in 2012. Soon after Musk became Twitter’s owner, firing thousands of employees, several floors of the building were effectively closed; and when the company was renamed X, the famous <a href="https://fortune.com/2023/07/26/passionate-elon-musk-employees-are-coating-the-twitter-offices-in-black-paint-and-boasting-about-hunting-and-eradicating-remnants-of-the-twitter-bird/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2023/07/26/passionate-elon-musk-employees-are-coating-the-twitter-offices-in-black-paint-and-boasting-about-hunting-and-eradicating-remnants-of-the-twitter-bird/">Twitter sign (along with all other vestiges of the company’s pre-Musk era) were summarily removed</a>. More than a dozen&nbsp;<a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/elon-musk-twitter-layoffs-closing-international-offices-singapore-europe-2023-1#:~:text=Twitter%20is%20leaving%20at%20least,Twitter's%20new%20owner%2C%20Elon%20Musk." target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://www.businessinsider.com/elon-musk-twitter-layoffs-closing-international-offices-singapore-europe-2023-1#:~:text=Twitter%20is%20leaving%20at%20least,Twitter's%20new%20owner%2C%20Elon%20Musk." rel="noopener">global offices were closed as well.</a>&nbsp;Musk also ended the company’s flexible work from home policy, requiring all employees to work in the office every day.&nbsp;</p>



<p>X representatives did not respond to an email seeking comment. Details of Yaccarino’s email was first <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/08/05/technology/x-twitter-san-francisco-office.html" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://www.nytimes.com/2024/08/05/technology/x-twitter-san-francisco-office.html" rel="noopener">reported by the New York Times</a>. </p>



<p>Below is the full note that Yaccarino sent staffers on Monday:</p>



<p>Title:<em>&nbsp;SF Office Closing</em></p>



<p><em>All,</em></p>



<p><em>After much thought, we have made the decision to close our San Francisco office over the next few weeks. This is an important decision that impacts many of you, but it is the right one for our company in the long term.</em></p>



<p><em>We will work to transition to our new primary locations in the Bay Area including the existing office in San Jose and a new engineering focused shared space with XAl in Palo Alto.</em></p>



<p><em>For those based in San Francisco, I know this will impact you all in different ways. Leadership is actively working on plans, including transportation options, for those directly impacted.</em></p>



<p><em>Further information and next steps will be communicated in the coming weeks.</em></p></div><p><strong>Recommended Newsletter:</strong> The Fortune Next to Lead newsletter is a must-read for the next generation of C-suite leaders. Every Monday, the newsletter provides the strategies, resources, and expert insight needed to claim the most coveted positions in business. <a href="https://fortune.com/newsletters/next-to-lead?&amp;itm_source=fortune&amp;itm_medium=article_tout&amp;itm_campaign=next_to_lead_v2&amp;itm_content=elon_amazon_google" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/newsletters/next-to-lead?&amp;itm_source=fortune&amp;itm_medium=article_tout&amp;itm_campaign=next_to_lead_v2&amp;itm_content=elon_amazon_google">Subscribe now</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Writing a tile server in Python (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.grulic.org.ar/~mdione/glob/posts/writing-a-tile-server-in-python/</link>
            <guid>41168033</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 05:25:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.grulic.org.ar/~mdione/glob/posts/writing-a-tile-server-in-python/">https://www.grulic.org.ar/~mdione/glob/posts/writing-a-tile-server-in-python/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41168033">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody text">
    <p>Another dictated post<sup id="fnref:0"><a href="#fn:0">1</a></sup><sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13">11</a></sup>, but heavily edited. Buyer beware.</p>
<p>I developed a tileset based on OpenStreetMap data and style and elevation information, but I don't have a render server.
What I have been doing is using <a href="https://github.com/StyXman/osm-tile-tools">my own version</a> of an old script from the
<code>mapnik</code> version of the OSM style. This
script is called <code>generate_tiles</code>, and I made big modifications to it and now it's capable of doing many things,
including spawning several processes for handling the rendering. You can define regions that you want to render, or you
can just provide a bbox or a set of tiles or just coordinates. You can change the size of the meta tile, and it handles
empty tiles. If you find a sea tile, most probably you will not need to render its children<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10">9</a></sup>, where children are the
four tiles that are just under it in the next zoom level. For instance, in zoom level zero we have only one tile (0,0,0),
and it's children are (1,0,0), (1,0,1), (1,1,0) and (1,1,1). 75% of the planet's surface is water, and with Mercator
projection and the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Southern_Ocean">Antartic Ocean</a>, the percent of tiles
could be bigger, so this optimization cuts a lot of useless rendering time.</p>
<p>Another optimization is that it assumes that when you render zoom level N, you will be using
at least the same data for zoom level N+1. Of course, I am
not catching that data because <code>mapnik</code> does not allow this, but the operating system does the catching. So if
you have enough RAM, then you should be able to reuse all the data that's already in buffers and cache, instead of
having to fetch them again from disk. This in theory should accelerate rendering and probably it is<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11">10</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The script works very well, and I've been using it for years already for rendering tiles in batches for several zoom
levels. Because my personal computer is way more powerful than
my server (and younger; 2018 vs 2011), I render in my computer and <code>rsync</code> to my server.</p>
<p>So now I wanted to make a tile server based on
this. Why do I want to make my own and not use <code>renderd</code>? I think my main issue with <code>renderd</code> is that it does not store
the individual tiles, but keeps metatiles of 8x8 tiles and serve the individual tiles from there. This saves inode usage
and internal fragmentation. Since my main usage so far has been (and probably will continue to be) rendering regions by
hand, and since my current (static) tile server stores all the latest versions of the tiles I have rendered since I
started doing this some 15 years ago, I want updating the server in a fast way. Most tile storage methods I know
fail terribly at update time (<a href="https://en.osm.town/@mdione/111069567039016636">see here</a>); most of the time it means
sending the whole file over the wire. Also, individual
tiles are easier to convert to anything else, like creating a MBTiles file, push it to my phone, and have a offline
tile service I can carry with me on treks where there is no signal. Also, serving the tiles can be as easy as
<code>python -m http.server</code> from the tileset root directory. So <code>renderd</code> is not useful for me. Another reason is, well, I
already have the rendering engine working. So how does it work?</p>
<p>The rendering engine consists
of one main thread, which I call Master, and rendering threads<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2">3</a></sup>. These rendering threads load the style and wait for
work to do. The current style file is 6MiB+ and takes <code>mapnik</code> 4s+ to load it and generate all its structures, which
means these threads have to be created once per service lifetime. I have one queue that can send commands from the
Master to the renderer pool asking for rendering a metatile, which is faster than rendering the individual tiles. Then
one of the rendering threads picks the request from this queue, calls <code>mapnik</code>, generates the metatile, cuts it into
the subtiles and saves them to disk. The rendering thread posts in another queue, telling the Master about the children
metatiles that must be rendered, which due to emptiness can be between 0 and 4.</p>
<p>To implement the caching optimization I mentioned before, I use a third structure to maintain a stack. At the beginning
I push into it the initial work; later I pop one element from it, and when a rendered returns the list of children to be
rendered, I push them on top of the rest. This is what tries to guarantee that a metatile's children will be rendered
before moving to another region that would trash the cache. And because the children can inspect the tiles being written,
they can figure out when a child is all sea tiles and not returning it for rendering.</p>
<p>At the beginning I thought that, because the multiprocessing queues are implemented with pipes, I could use <code>select()</code><sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3">4</a></sup> to
see whether the queue was ready for writing or reading and use a typical non-blocking loop. When you're trying
to write, these queues will block when the queue is full, and when you're trying to read, they will block when the queue
is empty. But these two conditions, full and empty, are actually handled by semaphores, not by the size of the pipe.
That means that selecting on those pipes, even if I could reach all the way down into the structures of the
<code>multiprocessing.Queue</code> all the way down. and add them to a selector, yes, the read queue will not be selected if it's
empty (nothing to read), but the write queue will not, since availability of space in the pipe does not mean the queue
is not full.</p>
<p>So instead I'm peeking into these queues. For the work queue, I know that the Master thread<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9">8</a></sup> is the only writer, so I can peek to
see if it is full. If it is, I am not going to send any new work to be done, because it means that all the renders are
busy, and the only work queued to be done has not been picked up yet. For the reading side it's the same, Master is the
only reader. so, I can peek if it's empty, and if it is, I am not going to try to read any information from it. So, I
have a loop, peeking first into the work queue and then into the info queue. If nothing has been done, I sleep a
fraction of a second.</p>
<p>Now let's try to think about how to replace this main loop with a web frontend. What is the web frontend going to do?
It's going to be getting queries by different clients. It could be just a slippy map in a web page, so we have a browser
as a client, or it could be any of the applications that can also render slippy maps. For instance, on Linux, we have
<code>marble</code>; on Android, I use MyTrails, and OsmAnd.</p>
<p>One of the things about these clients is that they have timeouts. Why
am I mentioning this? Because rendering a metatile for me can take between 3 to 120 seconds, depending on the zoom level.
There are zoom levels that are really, really expensive, like between 7 and 10. If a client is going to be asking
directly a rendering service for a tile, and the tile takes too long to render, the
client will timeout and close the connection. How do we handle this on the server side? Well, instead of the work stack,
the server will have request queue, which will be collecting the requests from the clients, and the Master will be
sending these  requests to the render pool.</p>
<p>So if the client closes the connection, I want to be able to react to that, removing any lingering requests made by that
client from the request queue. If I don't do that, the request queue will start piling up more and more requests,
creating a denial of service. This is not possible in multiprocessing queues, you cannot remove an element. The only
container that can do that is a dequeue<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5">5</a></sup>, which also is optimized for putting and popping things from both ends (it's
probably implemented using a circular buffer), which is perfect for a queue. As for the info queue, I will not be caring
anymore about children metatiles, because I will not be doing any work that the clients are not requesting.</p>
<p>What framework that would allow me to do this? Let's recap the requirements:</p>
<ul>
<li>Results are computed, and take several seconds.</li>
<li>The library that generates the results is not async, nor thread safe, so I need to use subprocesses to achieve
  parallelization.</li>
<li>A current batch implementation uses 2 queues to send and retrieve computations to a pool of subprocesses; my idea is
  to "just" add a web frontend to this.</li>
<li>Each subprocess spends some seconds warming up, son I can't spawn a new process for each request.</li>
<li>Since I will have a queue of requested computations, if a client dies, if its query is being processed, then I let
  it finish; if not, I should remove it from the waiting queue.</li>
</ul>
<p>I started with FastAPI, but it doesn't have the support that I need. At first I just implemented a tile server; the idea
was to grow from there<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6">6</a></sup>, but reading the docs it only allows doing long running async stuff <em>after</em> the response has
been sent.</p>
<p>Next was Flask. Flask is not async unless you want to use <code>sendfile()</code>. <code>sendfile()</code> is a way to make the
kernel read a file and write it directly on a socket without intervention from the process requesting that. The
alternative is to to open the file, read a block, write it on the socket, repeat. This definitely makes your code more
complex, you have to handle lots of cases. So <code>sendfile()</code> is very, very handy, but it's also faster because it's
0-copy. But Flask does not give control of what happens when the client suddenly closes the connection. I can
instruct it to cancel the tasks in flight, but as per all the previous explanation, that's not what I want.</p>
<p>This same problem seems to affect all async frameworks I looked into. <code>asyncio</code>, <code>aiohttp</code>, <code>tornado</code>. Except, of course,
<code>twisted</code>, but its API for that is with callbacks, and TBH, I was starting to get tired of all this, and the prospect
of callback hell, even when all the rest of the system could be developed in a more async way, was too much. And this is
not counting the fact that I need to hook into the main loop to step the Master. This could be implemented with timed
callbacks, such as <code>twisted</code>'s <code>callLater()</code>, but another thought started to form in my head.</p>
<p>Why did I go directly for frameworks? Because they're supposed to make our lives easier, but from the beginning I had
the impression that this would not be a run of the mill service. The main issue came down to beign able to send things
to render, return the rendered data to the right clients, associate several clients to a single job before it finished
(more than one client might request the same tile or several tiles that belong to the same metatile), and handle client
and job cancellation when clients disappear. The more frameworks' documentation I read, the more I started to fear that
the only solution was to implement an non-blocking<sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14">12</a></sup> loop myself.</p>
<p>I gotta be honest, I dusted
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/UNIX_Network_Programming?useskin=vector">an old Unix Network Programming book</a>, 2nd Ed.,
1998 (!!!), read half a chapter, and I was ready to do it. And thanks to the simple <code>selector</code> API, it's a breeze:</p>
<ol>
<li>Create a listening socket.</li>
<li>Register it for read events (connections).</li>
<li>On connection, accept the client and wait for read events in that one too.</li>
<li>We were not registering for write before because the client is always ready for write before we start sending
     anything, which lead to tight loops.</li>
<li>On client read, read the request and send the job to Master. Unregister for read.</li>
<li>But if there's nothing to read, the client disconnected. Send an empty.response, unregister for read and register
     for write.</li>
<li>Step Master.</li>
<li>If anything came back, generate the responses and queue them for sending. Register the right clients for write.</li>
<li>On client write (almost always), send the response and the file with <code>sendfile()</code> if any.</li>
<li>Then close the connection and unregister.</li>
<li>Loop to #3.</li>
</ol>
<p>Initially all this, including reimplementing fake Master and render threads, took less than 200 lines of code, some 11h
of on-and-off work. Now that I have finished I have a better idea of how to implement this at least with <code>twisted</code>,
which I think I will have to do, since step 4 assumes the whole query can be <code>recv()</code>'ed in one go and step 7 similarly
for <code>send()</code>'ing; luckily I don't need to do any handholding for <code>sendfile()</code>, even when the socket is non blocking.
A more production ready service needs to handle short reads and writes. Also, the HTTP/1.1 protocol all clients are
using allows me to assume that once a query is received, the client will be waiting for an answer before trying anything
else, and that I can close the connection once a response has been send and assume the client will open a new connection
for more tiles. And even then, supporting keep alive should not be that hard (instead of closing the client, unregister
for write, register for read, and only do the close dance when the response is empty). And because I can simply step
Master in the main loop, I don't have to worry about blocking queues.</p>
<p>Of course, now it's more complex, because it's implementing support for multiple clients with different
queries requiring rendering the same metatile. This is due that applications will open several clients for fetching
tiles when showing a region, and unless it's only 4 and they fall in the corner of 4 adjacent metatiles, they will always mean
more than one client per metatile. Also, I could have several clients looking at the same region.
<a href="https://github.com/StyXman/osm-tile-tools/blob/master/rendering_tile_server-sockets.py">The current code</a> is
approaching the 500 lines, but all that should also be present in any other implementation.</p>
<p>I'm pretty happy about how fast I could make it work and how easy it was. Soon I'll be finishing integrating a real
render thread with saving the tiles and implement the fact that if one metatile's tile is not present, we can assume
it's OK, but if all are not present, I have to find out if they were all empty or never rendered. A last step would be
how to make all this testable. And of course, the <code>twisted</code> port.
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                       </p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Soul of Maintaining a New Machine (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://books.worksinprogress.co/book/maintenance-of-everything/communities-of-practice/the-soul-of-maintaining-a-new-machine/1</link>
            <guid>41167615</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 03:49:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://books.worksinprogress.co/book/maintenance-of-everything/communities-of-practice/the-soul-of-maintaining-a-new-machine/1">https://books.worksinprogress.co/book/maintenance-of-everything/communities-of-practice/the-soul-of-maintaining-a-new-machine/1</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41167615">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main><p data-block-index="0"><span>T</span>THEY ATE TOGETHER every chance they could.&nbsp; They had to.&nbsp; The enormous photocopiers they were responsible for maintaining were so complex, temperamental, and variable between models and upgrades that it was difficult to keep the machines functioning without frequent conversations with their peers about the ever-shifting nuances of repair and care.&nbsp; The core of their operational knowledge was social.&nbsp; That’s the subject of this chapter.</p><p data-block-index="1">It was the mid-1980s.&nbsp; They were the technician teams charged with servicing the Xerox machines that suddenly were providing all of America’s offices with vast quantities of photocopies and frustration.&nbsp; The machines were so large, noisy, and busy that most offices kept them in a separate room.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="2">An inquisitive anthropologist discovered that what the technicians did all day with those machines was grotesquely different from what Xerox corporation thought they did, and the divergence was hampering the company unnecessarily.&nbsp; The saga that followed his revelation is worth recounting in detail because of what it shows about the ingenuity of professional maintainers at work in a high-ambiguity environment, the harm caused by an institutionalized wrong theory of their work, and the invincible power of an institutionalized wrong theory to resist change.</p><figure><p><img sizes="(max-width: 1050px) 100vw, 800px" loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/wnul3lsbpisc9bau28qa"></p><figcaption><p>The cover of Julian Orr’s influential <em>Talking About Machines </em>shows technicians working on the Xerox 5090 photocopier, introduced in 1990.&nbsp; Though they were doing messy blue-collar work, Xerox required the technicians to act and dress white-collar.&nbsp; They carried their tools in a briefcase.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Talking-about-Machines-Ethnography-Collection/dp/0801432979/ref=sr_1_1" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><p data-block-index="4">The anthropologist was Julian Orr.&nbsp; In 1979, he was hired by Xerox PARC (Palo Alto Research Center) in northern California to provide technical support for two machines being developed there—the Alto computer and a color laser printer.&nbsp; By 1984 he had migrated to studying Xerox service technicians, encouraged by John Seely Brown, then a lab manager, later director of PARC.&nbsp; Orr’s research culminated in <sub><strong>a remarkable book titled </strong></sub><sub><em><strong>Talking About Machines</strong></em></sub><em>: An Ethnography of a Modern Job</em>, published in 1996.&nbsp; His book shows that the most baffling problems the technicians faced in their machines were solved by <em>discussion</em>, and the most instructive element in their conversation was what Orr calls “war stories”—narratives the technicians told each other about how they worked through a bewildering problem in a machine to arrive at a satisfying solution.</p><p data-block-index="5">The stories also establish the teller’s contribution to the local community of technicians.&nbsp; Orr writes:</p><blockquote data-block-index="6">Given that the only status within the community is that of competent practitioner, fame can only be based on a reputation for extraordinarily competent practice, the ability to solve newer and harder problems.&nbsp; Since technicians normally work alone, achievements will only be known if the person responsible tells them.&nbsp; Moreover, technicians want the information to circulate, so that others can address similar problems.&nbsp; A team shares responsibility for its calls, so there is incentive to have all members competent for as many problems as possible.<sup>1</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="7">Often, the issue was not with the copier but with unintentionally destructive behavior by the users.&nbsp; That, too, was considered fixable.&nbsp; Orr declares that the technicians’</p><blockquote data-block-index="8">practice is a continuous, highly skilled improvisation within a triangular relationship of technician, customer, and machine…. Narrative forms a primary element of this practice.&nbsp; The actual process of diagnosis involves the creation of a coherent account of the troubled state of the machine from available pieces of unintegrated information…. A coherent diagnostic narrative constitutes a technician’s mastery of the problematic situation.</blockquote><blockquote data-block-index="9">Narrative preserves such diagnoses as they are told to colleagues…. The circulation of stories among the community of technicians is the principal means by which the technicians stay informed of the developing subtleties of machine behavior in the field.<sup>2</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="10">By the mid-1980s, Xerox copiers had reached such a degree of complexity that “individual machines,” Orr writes, “are quite idiosyncratic, new failure modes appear continuously, and rote procedure cannot address unknown problems.”<sup>3</sup></p><figure><p><img sizes="(max-width: 1050px) 100vw, 1000px" loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/doq9sgdspwlb35zxjmum"></p><figcaption><p>A Xerox 9400 with its panel open for technicians to get at the guts of the machine.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://xeroxnostalgia.com/wp-content/uploads/2013/10/9400_front_cover_open.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><figure><p><img sizes="(max-width: 1050px) 100vw, 1000px" loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/kbmbbdvwtbbijqkwsluu"></p><figcaption><p>Specifying the exact features for a copying job on the 9400’s control panel was not for the faint of heart.  Users varied in their sophistication.  When the machine had a problem, some customers could communicate helpfully with the repair technicians.  Many could not.  Some were, in fact, the cause of the problem.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://xeroxnostalgia.com/2013/10/27/xerox-9500/?_gallery=gg-18-134" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><figure><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/yianyfxrscau6apzn4mz"></p><figcaption><p>Jane Fonda’s first-day-on-the-job character is overwhelmed by a Xerox 9400 belching copies at her in the feminist comedy <em>9 to 5</em>, made in 1980, co-starring Dolly Parton and Lily Tomlin.  Her humiliating defeat by the copy machine was a common experience for office workers in those years.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WxDKgQuehMY&amp;t=178s" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><p data-block-index="14">For example,<strong> </strong><sub><strong>the famous Xerox 9400 that was introduced in 1977</strong></sub><sub> </sub><sub><strong>weighed one and a half tons and took up floor space measuring nine by fifteen feet.</strong></sub>&nbsp; It cost $85,000 ($430,000 in 2024).&nbsp; Automatically feeding up to 3,000 sheets of paper, it made copies at a rate of two per second and collated them into 50 separate bins.&nbsp; It could read and write two-sided sheets, and the image size was adjustable.&nbsp; Every stage of the process required extreme precision—from imaging to paper handling to managing the sequence of electric fields that transferred the image-bearing toner onto the paper, then pressing and baking the toner into the paper, and cleaning everything to be ready for the next image a half-second later.&nbsp; A fault anywhere in that sequence or in the control system could cause degraded copies or take down the whole machine.</p><p data-block-index="15">A technician who serviced 9400s in the 1980s recalls:</p><blockquote data-block-index="16">This machine was the main method of information distribution for the entire Federal Government for quite a while… I took service calls on these machines coming from the Pentagon, the CIA, the State Department, the Defense Mapping Agency, the Nuclear Regulatory Agency, Pax River Naval Research Center, the National Institutes of Health, the Uniformed Services University of the Health Sciences, and the National Bureau of Standards…. Xerox must have made an unbelievably enormous amount of money from that product—and spent an almost equally unbelievable amount maintaining them, because I also remember the nearly endless field retrofits we had to perform to keep them running…. Oh, those were the days!<sup>4</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="17">The technicians were organized into regional teams, servicing all the machines within a geographic area.&nbsp; Each team member had sole responsibility for a group of customer offices and machines.&nbsp; Orr emphasizes that all their attention was focused on the work, with little to spare for the corporation that paid them.&nbsp; Indeed, they “shared few cultural values” with the rest of Xerox and did not seek to rise within it.<sup>5</sup>&nbsp; They relished working within the technician-customer-machine triangle, where their competence was tested and rewarded daily.</p><p data-block-index="18">Since half of the problems they had to fix were caused by misuse of the machines, they had an adage: “Don’t fix the machine, fix the customer.”&nbsp; The copiers were so sensitive that users could screw things up by using toner from a different machine or a cheap knock-off supplier. &nbsp; Or they could mistakenly put paper in the feeder tray curl-side-up instead of curl-side-down (it was vice-versa in other copiers).</p><figure><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/qv4xtciegyjnxgcpl3dr"></p><figcaption><p>In 1983, PARC intern Lucy Suchman conducted a famously diabolical experiment with the supposedly user-friendly Xerox 8200 copier.&nbsp; She made videos of PARC people using it.&nbsp; Tech historian John Tinnell recounts what happened when PARC director John Seely Brown (who was a long-time motorcycle buddy of Xerox CEO Paul Allaire) took one of the videos to corporate headquarters:&nbsp; “[Brown] played the video for a room of Xerox managers.&nbsp; It featured two men struggling and failing to produce a copy of an article [Ronald] Kaplan had written.&nbsp; Everyone back at PARC knew [that] Kaplan was a world-renowned computational linguist, and [Allan] Newell was revered as a founding father of AI.&nbsp; The video showed Newell peering over Kaplan’s shoulder, oscillating between curiosity and confusion as the pair exhausted the full arsenal of their joint expertise, to no avail, for over an hour and a half.&nbsp; One of the Rochester men slammed his fist on the table and hollered, ‘Goddammit, Brown! What did you do, get those guys off the goddamn loading dock?’&nbsp; Brown looked at him and smiled, ‘Well, actually, let me introduce these two stooges to you,’ He revealed Kaplan’s and Newell’s pedigrees, and the Xerox execs sat speechless.”<sup>9</sup></p><p>Lucy Suchman later became the manager of the “Work Practice and Technology” research group at PARC, which was composed of all the anthropologists at PARC plus a few computer scientists.&nbsp; Julian Orr was a member from the beginning.&nbsp; Suchman’s 1987 book, <em>Plans and Situated Actions: The Problem of Human-Machine Communication</em>, became a classic text.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DUwXN01ARYg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><p data-block-index="20"><sub><strong>The machines were so complex that even sophisticated customers could lose their way</strong></sub>—for example by failing to replace a baffle after clearing a paper jam (which would affect the paper’s temperature and cause further jams) or rashly re-using paper that had been through the machine once and was, therefore, oily (which would make rollers so oily that they could no longer feed properly).</p><p data-block-index="21">Even when the problem was purely mechanical, the customer was a primary source of important diagnostic information about when and how the breakdown had occurred.&nbsp; That meant, says Orr, that “the customer must be initiated into the technicians’ community of discourse,”<sup>6</sup> complete with an understanding of how the machine worked, how to recognize the noises it made at the various stages of copying, and the correct language to describe its many failure modes.&nbsp; Some customers resisted learning any such thing, and the technicians had to find a way to jolly them into learning it anyway.&nbsp; Orr writes that users were</p><blockquote data-block-index="22">taught by the technicians how to talk about the machine. They know what to observe—the state of the originals, where the machine leaves paper when it stops, and where in the cycle trouble occurs—and they know most of the terms to describe these phenomena.<sup>7</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="23">As a consequence, the technicians became protective of the nuanced social relationship they built with each customer. &nbsp; Orr notes: “Technicians worry more about the social damage another technician can do in their territory than about what might happen with the machine, perhaps because the machine would be easier to repair than the delicate social equilibrium.<sup>8</sup>”</p><p data-block-index="24">Ethnographer Orr had a sharp eye for detail.&nbsp; He noticed when a technician on a call began by examining copies that had been thrown in the trash and deduced from them that the problem with the machine was different from what the customer had reported.&nbsp; “The trashcan is a filter between good copies and bad,” one technician explained&nbsp; “Just go to the trashcan to find the bad copies and then… interpret what connects them all.”<sup>10</sup></p><p data-block-index="25">Another time, Orr observed a technician joking with a customer about the need to keep any engineers in the building away from a machine that needed fixing, because “engineers believe they have a right to fiddle with any machine they encounter, whether they know anything about it or not.”<sup>11</sup> Orr recalls, “Engineers would go in and change adjustments, which offers limitless possibilities for disaster.”<sup>12</sup></p><p data-block-index="26">Orr noted that many of the technicians came from rural backgrounds, and nearly all—women as well as men—grew up as inveterate tinkerers.&nbsp; Half had studied technical subjects at junior colleges.&nbsp; A fifth learned their technical skills in the military, as had Orr.&nbsp; All received training at Xerox Document University in Leesburg, Virginia, and Orr did the same before undertaking his research on their behavior in the field.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><figure><p><img sizes="(max-width: 1050px) 100vw, 600px" loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/reuywbbacbhrqoamup84"></p><figcaption><p>In 1982, the Xerox 1075 inaugurated the 10 Series, which became known as “the most successful line of copiers in Xerox history and served to restore the company’s finances and morale.”<sup>16</sup>  The technicians Orr studied were primarily responsible for servicing this machine.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://xeroxnostalgia.com/2018/01/28/xerox-1075/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><p data-block-index="28">The machine he studied for three weeks in Virginia was the then-new Xerox 1075, introduced in 1982 with a $55,000 price tag ($180,000 in 2024 dollars).&nbsp; It was a medium-sized copier that could churn out 70 copies a minute and featured an advanced level of electronics that performed onboard diagnostics and kept error and use logs.&nbsp; Orr writes, “Designed for a monthly volume of less than 40,000 copies, it was placed in situations demanding six and seven times that, which quickly produced unanticipated problems.”<sup>13</sup></p><figure><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/e5wpzr5tphueo7a2zzaa"></p><figcaption><p>The notorious 1970s Xerox 4000 copier.&nbsp; On the “Xerox Nostalgia” website, technicians remember it as “a dog in terms of reliability,” “a beast,” “an electromechanical monster, and dirty,”&nbsp; “a nightmare to keep it working,” “I hated this product!” “I still suffer from two 4000-induced medical conditions: ‘4000 knees’ and ‘A-transport replacement lower back pain’!” and “I got quite proficient on the 4000/4500 and was once told by a Leesburg trainer that <em>an experienced 4000 rep could fix anything.</em>”&nbsp; This photo of the back of the 4000 was taken by a hobbyist who set about restoring the machine in 2019, showing some of the tips he got from battle-scarred technicians on how to get it going.&nbsp; With their help, he succeeded.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://xeroxnostalgia.com/2020/11/23/restoration-of-a-xerox-4000-copier/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><p data-block-index="30">Orr notes that<strong> </strong><sub><strong>the technicians</strong></sub><sub> </sub><sub><strong>he studied</strong></sub><sub> </sub><sub><strong>were accustomed to dealing with unanticipated problems because of their years of experience with Xerox’s worst copier, the infamous 4000</strong></sub>, first released in 1970 and kept in use far past its expected lifespan.&nbsp; “Consequently,” Orr writes, “successful 4000 technicians developed considerable resourcefulness and a propensity for pooling their information with their fellows.”<sup>14</sup></p><p data-block-index="31">Thanks to his training, Orr could blend in with the technicians as a colleague and decipher the cryptic technical language of their war stories, which were always told with extreme brevity.&nbsp; “This brevity,” he explains, “is a matter of cultural propriety and competent practice; it would be inappropriate to waste everyone’s time with the superfluous.”<sup>15</sup>&nbsp; Specialists talking to fellow specialists speak in dense jargon, not to exclude outsiders but to honor their listeners’ expertise and engage it.&nbsp; “Story-telling is an interactive practice,” Orr adds.&nbsp; “You tell the story concisely, but if you notice one of your listeners looking confused, you back up and provide as much detail as necessary so they understand.”<sup>17</sup></p><p data-block-index="32">The war stories were never about routine maintenance or standard problems that everyone knew how to fix.&nbsp; Instead, Orr says,</p><blockquote data-block-index="33">Technicians like new manifestations of the extremes of machine behavior or of human behavior with machines.&nbsp; Problems that require consideration of the chains of cause and effect in the machines and that shed new light on those chains are interesting to talk about…. The stranger the sequence of events and interactions producing the machine behavior, the better the story is, and the more fun it is to tell.<sup>18</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="34">Orr recites the exact wording of one war story told by a senior technician to his peers.&nbsp; (The language is characteristically dense and technical; I’ll explain in a moment what the technician’s peers heard and understood in the story.)&nbsp; The man said:</p><blockquote data-block-index="35">When you have a shorted dicorotron, you can’t even get the machine to run—it’ll cycle about twice and then shut down and give you an E053.&nbsp; First time with the new boards—the new XER board configuration—it wouldn't cook the board if you had an arcing dicorotron.&nbsp; Instead, now it trips the 24-Volt Interlock in the Low Voltage Power Supply, the machine will crash, and when it comes back up, it'll give you an E053.&nbsp; It may or may not give you an F066 that tells you the short is in—you know, check the xerographics. That's exactly what I had down here, at the end of the hall, and Weber and I ran for four hours trying to chase that thing.&nbsp; All it was was a bad dicorotron.&nbsp; We finally got it, ... run it long enough so that we got an E053 with an F066, and the minute we checked the dicorotrons, we had one that was totally dead.&nbsp; Put a new dicorotron in it, and it ran fine.&nbsp; Yeah, that was a fun one.<sup>19</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="36">His peers understood that this story concerned an upgrade to the 1075 copier that, in the process of solving one problem, created a more difficult new one, which combined a meaningless error code with a maddeningly intermittent correct error code.&nbsp; The upgrade was an improved “XER” circuit board that no longer burned out when there was a short in one of the four “dicorotrons” that managed the electrical fields that did the copying (“the xerographics”).&nbsp; Instead, the machine now shut down and displayed a misleading error code—“E053”—indicating a blown circuit breaker, which could be caused by any number of things.&nbsp; The documentation for that error code advised that the problem would go away if certain specific components were replaced—but it never mentioned dicorotrons.&nbsp; Technicians would spend hours replacing components, and the machine just kept on crashing.&nbsp; It turned out that if you ran the process to failure enough times, every now and then, a seemingly spurious “F066” error code would show up, and the documentation for <em>that</em> error code led straight to the dicorotrons.</p><p data-block-index="37">For anyone to solve that problem in the future, they had to know and remember the whole sequence.&nbsp; That was the point of telling a rousing war story about it.&nbsp; (I prefer to call them detective stories.&nbsp; They are all about teasing out the crucial clues from a confusing excess of potentially relevant information.)&nbsp; Other PARC researchers later wrote that the technicians have a</p><blockquote data-block-index="38">strong preference for building up a story of what might be wrong with a particular machine by gleaning information from many sources, including other people in their work group, artifacts (e.g. the machine itself), and formal and informal documents.<sup>20</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="39">Clever word, “gleaning.”&nbsp; It means “to frugally accumulate resources from low-yield contexts.”&nbsp; You peruse a mess of ambiguous data points and get some of them to disambiguate each other.</p><p data-block-index="40">Orr notes that tracking down the cause of a problem is often best done jointly with another technician:</p><blockquote data-block-index="41">In most of the hard diagnoses observed, solution was discovered through re-interpretation of known facts and following the new interpretation with new investigations.&nbsp; This is one of the reasons that consultations and joint trouble-shooting are so popular and effective.&nbsp; The presence of another guarantees another perspective and makes it easier to experiment with new interpretations.&nbsp; It also provides someone to whom to tell stories, who will tell stories in return…. The consideration of the present with reference to known diagnoses of the past, is an essential part of diagnosis.<sup>21</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="42">Orr has a withering critique of the diagnostic “Fault Isolation Procedures” in the documentation—the service manuals—issued to the technicians:</p><blockquote data-block-index="43"><sub><strong>This directive documentation is designed </strong></sub><sub><em><strong>not</strong></em></sub><sub><strong> to provide information for thinking about the machine and its problems but to direct the technician to the solution through a minimal decision tree</strong></sub>…. A system that fixes the machine without either customer or technician knowing how or why is unlikely to be acceptable.&nbsp; Consequently, when the technicians use the directive documentation, they try to determine the <em>purpose</em> of the various tests, to understand what the documentation is testing, to know what they are doing.<sup>22</sup></blockquote><figure><p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_640,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_750,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_828,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_960,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1080,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1280,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1668,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 1668w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_1920,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 1920w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2048,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 2048w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_2560,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 2560w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3200,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 3200w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_3840,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 3840w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_4480,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 4480w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_5120,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 5120w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/w_6016,c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s 6016w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/books-in-progress/image/upload/c_lfill,f_auto/v1/bip/lefviwz5qaukanafmk2s"></p><figcaption><p>A typical diagnostic decision tree in the service manual for the Xerox 1075 copier.  It is a “Fault Isolation Prodedure” (FIP) to correct “High Background/High Density” in copies.  The tests mostly lead to other FIPs on other pages of the manual.  They are entirely directive—do this, then do that.  They do not invite understanding or suggest clues to look for outside the decision tree.  They contain nothing learned by technicians in the field.  They can offer nothing about problems that emerged after the manual was written.</p></figcaption><figcaption><a href="https://apps.dtic.mil/sti/tr/pdf/ADA194403.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Source</a></figcaption></figure><p data-block-index="45">“The documentation,” Orr writes, “is designed not to enable deduction.”<sup>23</sup>&nbsp; Sometimes the manual would suggest something insane, such as solving a particular problem by replacing—at vast expense—all the circuit boards in the entire machine.&nbsp; No one would ever do that.&nbsp; John Seely Brown, the Director of PARC from 1990 to 2000, recalls:&nbsp;</p><blockquote data-block-index="46">Xerox had these beautifully produced instruction manuals for the technicians.&nbsp; They were big.&nbsp; There was a sort of social prestige in leaving them behind on a call.&nbsp; I mean: A, they were useless; and B, you looked like a fool walking in to fix a copier carrying a big encyclopedia.<sup>24</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="47">The field technicians had no part in writing the manuals.&nbsp; They were written by the engineers who had designed the machine and by management, who, Orr says, “[seek] control over their employees, through control of the knowledge necessary to do the job, and can hire cheaper employees, since they do not need skilled labor.”<sup>25</sup>&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="48">At one point, Orr states explicitly what his entire book proves: “<em>Repair and maintenance are not in any sense unskilled work</em>.”<sup>26</sup>&nbsp; He observed that the technicians operated with far more extensive knowledge than the documentation could provide.&nbsp; (An important exception was the schematics.&nbsp; Because the schematic diagrams showed how the machine’s electrical, electronic, mechanical, and pneumatic systems were connected, the technicians considered them accurate and helpful for tracing possible sequences of cause and effect in a machine’s misbehavior.)</p><p data-block-index="49">The technicians were dismayed when—sometimes encouraged by the documentation, as in the dicorotron war story—they had to resort to “shotgunning,” which meant just swapping new parts into the machine until a problem went away.&nbsp; Evaporating a problem rather than solving it meant that nothing was learned that might be helpful next time.&nbsp; The cause remained a mystery, and so did the remedy, along with any hint of how to prevent the problem from recurring.&nbsp; Orr emphasizes the effort the technicians made to earn and maintain the customer’s confidence:</p><blockquote data-block-index="50">The point of telling the customer what has happened is to establish that the problem was addressed in a professional manner, and this requires being able to tell what the machine is doing and being able to say what was done to fix it.<sup>27</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="51">&nbsp;Nevertheless, shotgunning was preferable to failing to fix the customer’s machine.&nbsp; That was unacceptable.&nbsp; Service techs felt obliged to live up to what Orr calls their “gun-slinger mystique” of “the lone technician walking into the customer site to cope with whatever troubles lie therein.”<sup>28</sup>&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="52">To be effective, Orr concludes, the technicians had to “become connoisseurs of the variations in machine misbehavior and of new shades of misunderstanding displayed and practiced by customers.”<sup>29</sup>&nbsp; The enemy of all technicians is chaos, he says.&nbsp; The service techs he studied insisted on carefully tuned reliability in the machines they serviced and valued tidiness at the worksite—no mess of tools, parts, and toner stains all over the place.&nbsp; This was, Orr says, core to “their identity as technicians—defined as those who fix the world and make it right.”<sup>30</sup></p><p data-block-index="53">That might do as a description of maintainers in general: Those who fix the world and make it right.</p><p data-block-index="55"><sub><strong>O</strong></sub>rr’s study quickly became famous and infamous throughout Xerox.&nbsp; A few, mostly Orr’s colleagues at PARC in California, thought it showed a revolutionary path to the future for the company.&nbsp; The many, especially at Xerox headquarters back east in Rochester, New York, thought the study revealed how much time—and company money!—the technicians were wasting just chatting with each other instead of doing what they were paid to do: working with customers.&nbsp; Since customer service was treated primarily as a cost center, some managers suggested the company could save serious money by cutting back on the socializing by the technicians.</p><p data-block-index="56">In April 2000, the <em>Harvard Business Review</em> published a piece by PARC researchers John Seely Brown and Paul Duguid titled “Balancing Act: How to Capture Knowledge Without Killing It.”&nbsp; Referring to the technicians as “reps” (short for “customer service representatives”), the paper summarizes Orr’s research this way:</p><blockquote data-block-index="57">Orr… studied what reps actually did, not what they were assumed to do…. They succeed primarily by departing from formal processes…. Orr found that a quick breakfast can be worth hours of training. While eating, playing cribbage, and gossiping, the reps talked work, and talked it continually. They posed questions, raised problems, offered solutions, constructed answers, laughed at mistakes, and discussed changes in their work, the machines, and customer relations.</blockquote><blockquote data-block-index="58">Orr showed that the reps use one another as their most critical resources. In the course of socializing, the reps develop a collective pool of practical knowledge that any one of them can draw upon. That pool transcends any individual member’s knowledge, and it certainly transcends the corporation’s documentation. Each rep contributes to the pool, drawing from his or her own particular strengths, which the others recognize and rely on. Collectively, the local groups constitute a community of practice.<sup>31</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="59">Some researchers at PARC noted that many of the technician team’s important insights could be applied throughout Xerox globally but were confined within that team.&nbsp; Since engineers at PARC specialized in computer networks—Ethernet was invented there—Orr’s colleagues imagined a company-wide system linking all of Xerox’s 25,000 technicians via the Internet in a global “network of practice” where, to the edification of all, they could share their best solutions and workarounds.&nbsp; The idea was named the Eureka project.</p><p data-block-index="60">It began with a failure.&nbsp; The culmination of a multi-year PARC project to develop a state-of-the-art, artificial-intelligence-driven expert system to help the technicians diagnose problems was finally shown in 1991 to some technicians for comment.&nbsp; They said the system was ingenious, but it wouldn’t be much use because it covered nothing but common faults that everyone already knew how to detect and correct.&nbsp; Confronted by Orr’s observations, the project’s developers realized they had to focus on</p><blockquote data-block-index="61">the importance of <em>non-</em>canonical knowledge generated and shared within the service community.&nbsp; It suggested to us that we could stand the artificial intelligence approach on its head, so to speak; the work community itself could become the expert system, and ideas could flow up from the people engaged in work on the organization’s frontlines.<sup>32</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="62">They resolved to replace the expert system with “a system for experts.”&nbsp; The hard-won knowledge that each technician team developed would instantly be available to all the other teams.&nbsp; “The project,” Brown writes, “set out to create a database to preserve resourceful ideas over time and deliver them over space.”<sup>33</sup><br></p><p data-block-index="64"><sub><strong>I</strong></sub>n 1991, a Xerox district manager in Colorado got wind of Orr’s research and invited him to a meeting in Denver to help develop an idea.&nbsp; Orr recalls:</p><blockquote data-block-index="65">The most significant moment of the meeting occurred when the District Service Manager told a story.&nbsp; He had recently had his furnace repaired.&nbsp; The technician doing the repair had been carrying a portable radio, with which he maintained a continuous conversation with his colleagues, other technicians repairing other furnaces elsewhere.&nbsp; This use of the radio for constant communications struck the manager as something which technicians in his organization could use.<sup>34</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="66">The participants in the meeting noted that Xerox service technicians are “one of the lowest levels of the corporate hierarchy,” and yet they “have more contact with the corporation's customers than any other member of the corporation and so should be valued.”<sup>35</sup>&nbsp; They further noted that customers’ machines were spread so widely all over Colorado that many technicians spent most of their time driving alone, unable to meet very often with other technicians.</p><p data-block-index="67">The first order of business, they decided, was to involve technicians directly in building the scheme, or the whole thing would look like just another unwelcome intervention by management in their work lives.&nbsp; Ethnography to the rescue.&nbsp; Conspicuously non-management Julian Orr was funded to study four teams for three weeks to find out if they wanted portable radios and to pique their interest in helping design the project.&nbsp; The technicians told Orr they would love to have two-way radios that could be used like portable telephones to communicate with their families, co-workers, and customers—but <em>not</em> with their managers, thank you.</p><p data-block-index="68">Accordingly, radios were distributed to five work groups.&nbsp; Orr was invited to study the radio system in use for six months and to work with the technicians on improving the system.&nbsp; (Cell phones were not considered because they couldn’t be group-oriented the way logic-trunked radios could.)&nbsp; The technicians insisted that their communications must be “free from interference or even monitoring,” and the district manager supported them in this.&nbsp; Orr recalls, “On many occasions during the fieldwork, [I] found it necessary to assure other technicians that managers were not <em>allowed</em> to use the radios.”<sup>36</sup>&nbsp; Orr praises the Colorado district for honoring the privacy of the technician teams:</p><blockquote data-block-index="69">This relinquishment underscores a dilemma of modern managers: If they are not controlling, what then is their function?&nbsp; Given these pressures, the managerial decision to let the information remain available only to the technicians is a remarkable event and an achievement for those involved.<sup>37</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="70">The radio project was a roaring success.&nbsp; Orr observes that the technicians “mostly work alone in other people's offices and rarely spoke to any colleagues; now they spend part of their time on the air supporting each other and often converse while driving home at the end of the day, unwinding and getting the day's events in perspective.”&nbsp; Also they “find it easier to share parts or to coordinate trips to the warehouse when necessary.&nbsp; They exchange information about weather or traffic.”&nbsp; When Orr asked them if a message system wouldn’t work just as well, he was told “that the stress in someone's voice cannot be conveyed in a typed message.”&nbsp; “The workgroups have become real through this tool,” they said.&nbsp; “The groups now are based on real and continuing relationships which could not be achieved with weekly meetings.”<sup>38</sup></p><p data-block-index="71">Outside of the enlightened Colorado district, however, perspective on the radio-empowered technicians shifted.&nbsp; Orr writes:</p><blockquote data-block-index="72">After six months of experience, the technicians were quite clear that the radios helped them with diagnosis, with coordination, with morale, with parts supply problems, and with the training of new technicians, but these were not acceptable benefits from the corporation's perspective, which required demonstrable dollar savings.<sup>39</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="73">Xerox corporate decided that since radios made the service reps more efficient, the company could save money by employing fewer reps.&nbsp; To lower the cost of the radios, Xerox reduced their power and range and thus their ability to connect all of the technicians in the district.&nbsp; “The original desire to help the technicians enhance their own practice,” Orr writes, “disappeared from managerial discourse.”<sup>40</sup>&nbsp; For Xerox corporate, the issue was simple.&nbsp; The whole point of any improvement in customer service was to reduce its cost, period.</p><p data-block-index="74">Nevertheless, within a few years, all 25,000 Xerox service reps worldwide were furnished with portable radios to enrich the peer-to-peer discourse that made their work go better.</p><p data-block-index="76"><sub><strong>T</strong></sub>he radio breakthrough in Colorado was a relatively quick win.&nbsp; Getting the Eureka project from vision to reality, it became clear, would require a much longer slog because the concept violated Xerox’s deeply embedded views of how to run a company—from the top down.&nbsp; The lowly technicians should be guided solely by their superiors, not by each other.</p><p data-block-index="77">(I can tell this story in some detail thanks to the profusion of papers published about Xerox service practice and Eureka between 1986 and 2011.&nbsp; Julian Orr wrote 11 of them, including his book and the 1990 PhD thesis it was expanded from.&nbsp; Other authors I’ve relied on are John Seely Brown &amp; Paul Duguid, Daniel Bobrow &amp; Jack Whalen, plus Olivier Rainman, David Bell, Mark Shirley, Cindy Gordon, Robert Cheslow, Norman Crowfoot, Steve Barth, Yutaka Yamauchi, and Andrew Cox.)</p><p data-block-index="78">Eureka’s primary designer and champion at PARC was a French national named Olivier Raiman.&nbsp; One of his colleagues, Cindy Gordon, later wrote of him: “Olivier Raiman was visionary, and his passion, energy, and commitment helped create momentum for the Eureka project.”<sup>41</sup>&nbsp; Establishing some kind of momentum was surely needed, because the managers in Worldwide Customer Services who had oversight of the technicians saw no value in the project and took every opportunity to block it.</p><p data-block-index="79">Their view was partly the product of an earlier effort to “de-skill” the technicians.&nbsp; After the Vietnam War ended in 1975, the supply of technicians trained by the military dried up.&nbsp; “Xerox decided,” writes one of the PARC researchers, “to use less skilled, less experienced service people. It moved away from the documentation and training that described the principles of product operation…, and moved toward ‘directive’ repair and adjustment procedures.”<sup>42</sup> &nbsp; These were the simplistic Fault Isolation Procedures that the technicians struggled to penetrate, trying to discern their purpose.&nbsp; The procedures were all “how” and no “why.”&nbsp; The idea of hiring less skilled technicians quickly died, but the documentation-for-dummies remained unchanged.</p><p data-block-index="80">The managers were so adamant that the directive procedures were sufficient that the technicians had to pretend that was so in order to keep their jobs.&nbsp; The formula was: “Quality service meant uniform service, and uniform service meant following the instructions in the manual.”<sup>43</sup>&nbsp; One service rep told a PARC researcher that he never made private annotations in the manual because that might suggest he was giving nonstandard service.&nbsp; Then, the researcher reports,</p><blockquote data-block-index="81">he showed his "cheat sheet" with recent tips for difficult service problems that he used as an augmentation to the manual.&nbsp; In essence, he was keeping two sets of books: one to show quality inspectors, and one to use for a quality job!<sup>44</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="82">What would have happened if the technicians dutifully never ventured outside the manual?&nbsp; The opinion at PARC was:</p><blockquote data-block-index="83">If the technicians had abandoned diagnosis when the directive documentation did and followed the catch-all rule, which was to replace the machine, they would have drained Xerox of customers.<sup>45</sup>&nbsp;</blockquote><p data-block-index="84">Fortunately for the company, the technicians were more loyal to their customers than to their managers.&nbsp; They would quietly defy Xerox policy to fulfill their professional imperative to fix their customers’ Xerox machines, no matter what.&nbsp; In Julian Orr’s view, “The corporate use of information for leverage and control contrasts with the technicians' attitude of sharing it among those who can use it.”<sup>46</sup>&nbsp; While the managers wanted to suppress improvisation, the technicians celebrated it—and had to keep it secret.&nbsp; Orr adds in disgust:</p><blockquote data-block-index="85">During the 1990s,… the corporation created mandatory structures of meta-work, work about belonging to the organization, which both kept the technicians away from their work with machines and customers and was used to judge them for their performance reviews.<sup>47</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="86">The result, writes Orr, was that the technicians “do less work now servicing customers and more servicing Xerox.”<sup>48</sup></p><p data-block-index="87">Consequently, while the technicians were intrigued by the idea of Eureka sharing their knowledge globally, they had reason to doubt it would go anywhere.&nbsp; One old-timer among the technicians remembered how</p><blockquote data-block-index="88">decades ago when he started at Xerox, he submitted a suggestion on how to install a machine more efficiently.&nbsp; For six months he did not receive any feedback about the suggestion.&nbsp; Then he saw a published bulletin with his idea, attributed to the person who received the suggestion over the phone.&nbsp; After that, the service engineer did not submit any ideas.<sup>49</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="89">Furthermore, Orr was told, other technicians might pay no attention to Eureka because it would look like just another lame offering from on high.&nbsp; In their experience,</p><blockquote data-block-index="90">Information which is distributed to the technicians… is often so fragmentary that the technicians do not perceive it to be of any use at all, and information from the corporation is usually regarded as suspect until confirmed through community experience.<sup>50</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="91">Eureka’s lead champion, Olivier Raiman, describes the resistance this way:</p><blockquote data-block-index="92">Eureka was about a commitment to constant listening and adaptation….&nbsp; In fact, it required an acceptance of what many companies consider a radical concept—the person who does the job is in the best position to know how it can and should be done.&nbsp; This is a scary proposition for middle managers because it fundamentally changes their job description and takes away their role as the residential expert on operational functions.<sup>51</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="93">Orr concluded that the asymmetry between the managers and the technicians was stark: “Management has most of the money and power.”<sup>52</sup>&nbsp; The heavyweights at Worldwide Customer Service said to the PARC researchers, essentially, “The service representatives work for us, not you.&nbsp; The system we have is working just fine.&nbsp; You are not welcome to screw it up with one of your harebrained academic theories.”</p><p data-block-index="95"><sub><strong>T</strong></sub>he emphatic “No” to Eureka from headquarters made Olivier Raiman search for a fragment of the company that might say “Maybe.”&nbsp; He found one in his native France.&nbsp; With permission to immerse himself in the work-life of French service technicians, he set about designing Eureka around their needs.&nbsp; Xerox corporate refused to provide any money for the work, so PARC and Xerox France funded it.&nbsp; Eureka’s designers remember:</p><blockquote data-block-index="96">In the initial stages, we sometimes had to operate like a guerrilla group because opposition was enough to kill the project…. We conducted our first experiment in France partly because it was out of sight of the central Xerox organization.<sup>53</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="97">In 1994, France had the world’s first national computerized communication system--French Minitel, with five million terminals in use.&nbsp; It would provide the infrastructure for the technicians to connect with the Eureka database.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="98">In their <em>Harvard Business Review </em>paper, Brown and Duguid summarized how the database of tips was assembled:</p><blockquote data-block-index="99">Reps, not the organization, supply the tips.&nbsp; But reps also vet the tips.&nbsp; A rep submits a suggestion first to a local expert on the topic.&nbsp; Together, they refine the tip.&nbsp; It’s then submitted to a centralized review process, organized according to business units.&nbsp; Here reps and engineers again vet the tips, accepting some, rejecting others, eliminating duplicates, and calling in experts on the particular product line to resolve doubts and disputes.&nbsp; If a tip survives this process, it becomes available to reps… who have access to the tips database…. So reps using the system know that the tips… are relevant, reliable, and probably not redundant.</blockquote><blockquote data-block-index="100">[Xerox France] offered to pay for the tips, but the pilot group of reps who helped design the system thought that would be a mistake, worrying… that payment for submissions would lead people to focus on quantity rather than quality in making submissions.&nbsp; Instead, the reps chose to have their names attached to tips.&nbsp; Those who submit good tips earn positive recognition. Because even good tips vary in quality, reps, like scientists, build social capital through the quality of their input.<sup>54</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="101">The process relied in particular on the most experienced technician specialists known as “tigers.”&nbsp; France’s leading tiger, Eric Delanchy, joined Raiman in championing the idea with technicians nationwide.&nbsp; Because the tigers were “consultants to other technicians with a mandate to teach and share expertise,”<sup>55</sup> they were best equipped to frame the tips in the most helpful way.&nbsp; The researchers from PARC remember: “We worked interactively with the tigers in France to improve the software, often responding overnight; this transformed [Eureka] from our idea to their tool.”<sup>56</sup>&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="102">Each tip had a three-part structure: Problem, Cause, Solution.&nbsp; That made the tips easy to scan quickly.&nbsp; Here’s an example:</p><blockquote data-block-index="103"><em>Problem</em>: When running Xerox coated stock from Tray 3, customer gets jammed PO8- 19X, and message on copier indicated: ”Paper width is too narrow.”</blockquote><blockquote data-block-index="104"><em>Cause</em>: Xerox coated stock in Tray 3 is too flat or loaded with the curl the wrong way, causing the sheet to be fed skewed. The sheet is still skewed at the registration sensor.&nbsp;</blockquote><blockquote data-block-index="105"><em>Solution</em>: Contrary to what we have been taught, with this stock, load curl <em>down</em> in Tray 3. Instruct customer how to check for curl in paper and flatness. Totally flat stock seems to jam right away. Last resort is to coat the registration transport with antistatic fluid. The fluid will hold up for approximately 10,000 to 15,000 copies. Any question, feel free to contact Employee #930124 — Michael Posus, CST Twin Cities District<sup>57</sup>&nbsp;</blockquote><p data-block-index="106">Eureka was still in rudimentary form in France when the designers first tested it for efficacy.&nbsp; They picked 40 technicians to be trained on Eureka and matched them with 40 similar but Eureka-less technicians to act as the control group.&nbsp; Their work was measured with the standard Xerox metrics, including:</p><blockquote data-block-index="107">cost of parts, service time, number of unscheduled maintenance calls, interrupted calls, and callbacks….&nbsp; The metrics after two months were startling.&nbsp; The experimental group had an approximately 10% lower parts cost and 10% lower average service time than did the control group, without differing significantly in the other service metrics.<sup>58</sup>&nbsp;</blockquote><p data-block-index="108">That convinced the leaders of Xerox France.&nbsp; They rolled out the system to all 1,300 technicians in the country.&nbsp; Within a year, new validated tips were being added at a rate of one a day, coming from 20 percent of the technicians.&nbsp; On average, the technicians were consulting the system more than twice a week.&nbsp; “Xerox France, compared to the rest of Europe,” the PARC researchers report, “went from being an average or below average performer in service to being a benchmark performer.&nbsp; The French service metrics were soon better than the European average by 5-20%, depending on the product.”<sup>59</sup>&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="109">Back in the US, Xerox corporate was <em>still </em>not persuaded, but a senior manager in Canada named Mark Hill was.&nbsp; In 1996, he invited the Eureka team to build a Canadian version. &nbsp; Once again, a leading tiger was essential to championing the project.&nbsp; There was no Minitel platform to work with, but the tiger, Michel Boucher, said some service technicians were already using a networked bulletin board system accessed via laptop and modem.&nbsp; Why not convert Eureka to work on the bulletin board?&nbsp; The database of tips would now be conveniently searchable thanks to new software developed at Xerox called SeachLite.</p><p data-block-index="110">Boucher trained all the other tigers on how to use the system so they could then train the rest of Canada’s 1,200 technicians.&nbsp; They had to do it all in their spare time because, as the PARC developers recall, “Xerox expected technicians to author tips and validators to provide rapid turnaround and validation of submitted tips without any relief from their current workloads.”<sup>60</sup>&nbsp; Along with expecting the work to be done for free, management required that it be done to schedule.&nbsp; The PARC researchers explain how well that worked:</p><blockquote data-block-index="111">Management had never dealt with a program in which the requirements emerged from experiments with pilot users, iterated until the users felt the program warranted large-scale deployment.&nbsp; Managers would try to set deadlines for us to get things done, independent of our process for rapid prototyping and debugging with extensive community involvement.&nbsp; The clash of these two different design and deployment methods had negative results.&nbsp; Some higher-level managers lost some faith in the ability of the Eureka team to deliver.<sup>61</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="112">But they did deliver.&nbsp; After six months of intense work, Eureka launched in Canada in early 1997 with support for 20 Xerox products.&nbsp; Soon, there were 1,900 validated tips for 76 products, and the cost savings for product maintenance were 5 to 8 percent, the same as in France.&nbsp; Cindy Gordon, who was responsible for overseeing the project, writes: “Eureka is a great example of what might be called vernacular knowledge sharing — that is harvesting, organizing and passing around insights that come from the grassroots of an organization.”<sup>62</sup>&nbsp; She notes that the Canadian experiment was so successful, “Some technicians in Minneapolis actually stole the software and access to Eureka and started using it on their own.”<sup>63</sup></p><p data-block-index="114"><sub><strong>A</strong></sub>t last, Xerox’s Worldwide Customer Service was compelled to pay attention, although, as one of their officers, Tom Ruddy, recalls,</p><blockquote data-block-index="115">What it really took was testimonial video clips of old-school, hard-nosed, 25-years-of-experience service technicians telling their personal stories of how Eureka made a difference to them.<sup>64</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="116">The project developers quickly learned that expanding to all 10,000 technicians in the US would meet new hindrances from the “much more bureaucratic and hierarchical” organization in America.&nbsp; They observed that</p><blockquote data-block-index="117">we were constantly trying to balance our belief that simpler was better with corporate managers’ beliefs that if Eureka was the answer, they wanted to be the one to generate the question.<sup>65</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="118">One manager, for instance, insisted that accessing the whole project through Microsoft’s web browser, Internet Explorer, would simplify everything.&nbsp; In fact it complicated everything, just as the developers had predicted.&nbsp; Cascading versions of the browser, operating systems, and other software often failed to work together and had to be constantly updated on 10,000 laptops, which delayed the project for months.</p><p data-block-index="119">Worse was management’s failure to understand that Eureka only spread successfully through direct contact among technicians, as proven in Canada and France.&nbsp; The developers recall:</p><blockquote data-block-index="120">We had originally suggested to… management an alternative ‘‘participatory deployment’’ strategy in which the pilot champions, technicians, and managers most knowledgeable about Eureka would go to other locations in the US service community and talk about their experiences and ideas.&nbsp; Because these people were peers, the technicians would trust them.&nbsp; During a relatively short time, Eureka would have spread across the entire country.<sup>66</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="121">Instead, Xerox employed its customary “spray and pray” distribution mode.&nbsp; For the June 1998 launch, the company</p><blockquote data-block-index="122">distributed Eureka CD-ROMs to the field managers, who were then expected to distribute them to technicians in their work groups.&nbsp; The CD included a computer-based training module; no hands-on training or direct engagement with technicians around the program was planned.<sup>67</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="123">Use of the system spread very slowly.</p><p data-block-index="124">Yet spread it did.&nbsp; The technicians who loved it gradually infected their peers with comments like “In all my years in Xerox, the two best things ever given to us are the radios and Eureka.’’<sup>68</sup> &nbsp;The original plan was to install the system throughout the US before going overseas, but, as the system developers later reported, “demand from technicians in Europe, Latin America, and Asia was so intense that the corporation had to begin distributing Eureka worldwide.”<sup>69</sup>&nbsp; Soon, it reached all 25,000 service reps in the whole company.</p><p data-block-index="125">Eureka was run by PARC, deploying its extensive computer and connectivity resources.&nbsp; When researchers examined how the scaled-up system was being used, they found some surprises.&nbsp; They had assumed that Eureka would be consulted mainly as a last resort, when all routine solutions to a problem had been exhausted.&nbsp; Instead, they discovered that many technicians “use it as a tool of <em>first</em> rather than last resort.”<sup>70</sup>&nbsp; One user reported:</p><blockquote data-block-index="126">I check Eureka before I go to a site, that way when I get there I already know what parts to bring in. The customer is always impressed when you show up and already have an idea on how to fix the machine, and have the part with you. They just love it.<sup>71</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="127">Another said: “Eureka is almost like having another technician with you because you can bounce your ideas or your thought processes off the Eureka database.”<sup>72</sup>&nbsp; Another said he studied Eureka’s problems and solutions because “attending to how others found workarounds has helped him develop his own skills.”<sup>73</sup>&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="128">Best of all, Eureka gave the technicians a way to build their reputation for competence and generosity within the global fellowship of their peers—and with the company at large.&nbsp; In their <em>Harvard Business Review</em> paper, Brown and Duguid report, “At a meeting of Xerox reps in Canada, one individual was surprised by a spontaneous standing ovation from coworkers expressing their respect for his tips.”<sup>74</sup></p><p data-block-index="129">The whole of Xerox received accolades.&nbsp; At the time, many corporations were trying to build sophisticated “Knowledge Management Systems,” and Eureka was a rare success story.&nbsp; &nbsp; In 2002, Cindy Gordon reported that</p><blockquote data-block-index="130">funding for Eureka has steadily increased in the range of 60 percent year over year.…Return on investment has been in the range of tenfold, but, most important, management has supported Eureka at all levels in the organization.<sup>75</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="131">Xerox announced that Eureka was transforming the company and henceforth, “Knowledge Management is our culture.”&nbsp; The company’s Worldwide Customer Service division, which had fought Olivier Raiman for so long, honored him with a plaque praising him for building Eureka “despite resistance from us.”<sup>76</sup>&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="132">Apparently, Julian Orr’s study really had revealed a revolutionary path to the future for Xerox, just as his colleagues at PARC had hoped and lobbied for a decade earlier.&nbsp; Or had it?&nbsp; How deep did the revolution go?&nbsp; As Cindy Gordon noted in 2002, “The Eureka project also had pockets of resistance, and some remain.&nbsp; Some of the biggest opposition came from company strategists.”<sup>77</sup></p><p data-block-index="133">The company’s 25,000 technicians—comprising a fourth of Xerox’s entire workforce—had their titles elevated to “customer service engineer,” but they were still not paid for the time they spent on generating tips, validating them, and constantly pruning and updating the Eureka database.&nbsp; The system’s developers also noted that the technicians and their lore remained oddly isolated from the rest of the company.&nbsp; They wrote, “No formal process incorporates Eureka’s information back into the documentation.”<sup>78</sup>&nbsp; And:</p><blockquote data-block-index="134">One type of tip content was suggestions for better ways of doing things, including proposing modifications to the machines.&nbsp; Technicians are in a good position to notice when a machine was being overused for its purpose, and to suggest to a sales person that the customer might be ready for an upgrade.&nbsp; Viewing field service as the frontline to your customers dramatically changes the perspective on their role, and could engender new strategies for the service force.<sup>79</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="135">To my eye, Xerox never got past viewing customer service as a cost center.&nbsp; The dense lore in the Eureka database proved that the company was ignoring a priceless <em>value</em> center.&nbsp; The service technicians were Xerox’s primary interface with its customers.&nbsp; The techs knew everything about the customers’ real use behavior.&nbsp; They knew exactly what made the machines fail and what made customers unhappy—crucial data for any company.&nbsp; They really were engineers: They solved emergent problems in the machines with a high degree of creativity. &nbsp; More thoroughly than the most adept salesperson, they routinely figured out how to shape their customers’ experience toward satisfaction.</p><p data-block-index="136">(“In their frenzy to earn their bonuses,” Orr recalls, “Xerox salespeople would tell the customer that the machine would do whatever the customer wanted.&nbsp; The technician could later explain what it would really do.”)<sup>80</sup></p><p data-block-index="137">If Xerox had deeply reoriented itself toward service, the best technicians—the tigers—might have been considered for promotion paths into sales, design engineering, and manufacturing.&nbsp; Xerox’s salespeople could have been required to go on occasional repair calls to learn the perspective of the actual users of the machines, not just the account managers they sold to.&nbsp; Ditto the company’s design engineers: Let them watch their brilliant machines fail in mysterious ways.&nbsp; Let them study the myriad paths to destructive misuse by the customers and figure out ways to design around them.&nbsp; The company’s mid-level high-fliers slated for senior management could, in preparation for promotion, get trained up on a current machine at Xerox Document University and then go on some service calls for that machine, ideally in the company of a savvy tiger.&nbsp; Take <em>that</em> knowledge to the top of the corporation.</p><p data-block-index="138">None of that happened, of course. Xerox declined after 2000, and the company’s glory years and Xerox PARC faded into history.</p><p data-block-index="140"><sub><strong>A</strong></sub> byproduct of the Eureka success story was popularization of the term “community of practice.”&nbsp; The concept was developed at the PARC-adjacent Institute for Research on Learning in Palo Alto and published as the core idea of a 1991 book on apprenticeship titled <em>Situated Learning: Legitimate Peripheral Participation, </em>by Jean Lave and Etienne Wenger.&nbsp; Their investigation of apprenticeships among butchers, navy quartermasters, tailors in Liberia, and midwives in Yucután showed that potential recruits to a practice were allowed to hover at the edge of the work, observing.&nbsp; Then they were given simple, routine tasks, and if they showed promise, gradually they were granted more complex tasks.&nbsp; It was not a course of study; it was the stepwise joining of a work community, with all of its skills, values, lingo, jokes, friendships, and tricks of the trade.&nbsp; “The community,” Wenger notes, “is the living curriculum for the apprentice.”<sup>81</sup></p><p data-block-index="141">Brown and Duguid draw an important distinction between the communities of practice embodied in the technician teams and the “network of practice” that Eureka became:</p><blockquote data-block-index="142">People in such networks have practice and knowledge in common, [but they] don’t interact with one another directly to any significant degree…. It produces very loosely coupled systems.”<sup>82</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="143">One thing lost in Eureka was most of the wisdom that the service teams developed about dealing with customer issues, perhaps because, while all 25,000 technicians had the same machines in common, each local team had unique customers.</p><p data-block-index="144">As years went by and social media like Facebook, Reddit, and YouTube proliferated online, all manner of <em>virtual</em> communities of practice emerged that did encourage interaction.&nbsp; You may recall my informant on Twitter who told me about rebuilding his 1996 Toyota guided by Timmy the Toolman YouTube videos and about the “robust community of people that love Toyota 4Runners” he found on Facebook.&nbsp; (He’s @idlebell on Twitter.)&nbsp; When I asked him about the nature of interaction in the group, he wrote:</p><blockquote data-block-index="145">I could post a video or picture of different problems.&nbsp; Or ponder possible solutions and have ten different people debating.&nbsp; Very specific advice.&nbsp; And now I jump in when relevant.&nbsp; For example, I contributed a trick to remove a difficult-to-reach bolt.&nbsp; Imagine.&nbsp; After 26 years discovering a new way to replace a bolt.<sup>83</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="146">Over the years, a considerable literature has emerged espousing communities of practice.&nbsp; Oddly, nearly all of it leaves out something that Orr emphasized: the importance of honoring skill.&nbsp; Who are the best among us?&nbsp; What will it take for me to become one of them?&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p data-block-index="147">A major attraction of a community of practice is its role as an arena for recognition and endorsement by one’s peers.&nbsp; Orr showed how amicable competition among Xerox technicians built competence and spurred achieving mastery.&nbsp; That’s how the tigers were made.&nbsp; The communities discover best practices mainly by paying attention to their best practitioners.</p><p data-block-index="148">I like what Wikipedia has to say about the “social capital” aspect of communities of practice.&nbsp; It says the communities create—and operate—through</p><blockquote data-block-index="149">a shared sense of identity, a shared understanding, shared norms, shared values, trust, cooperation, and reciprocity….&nbsp;</blockquote><blockquote data-block-index="150">Unlike financial forms of capital, social capital is not depleted by use; it is depleted by non-use.<sup>84</sup></blockquote><p data-block-index="152">_________________________________</p></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Twitter kills its San Francisco headquarters, will relocate to South Bay (286 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sfstandard.com/2024/08/05/x-officially-kills-its-san-francisco-headquarters-will-relocate-workers-to-south-bay/</link>
            <guid>41167561</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 03:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2024/08/05/x-officially-kills-its-san-francisco-headquarters-will-relocate-workers-to-south-bay/">https://sfstandard.com/2024/08/05/x-officially-kills-its-san-francisco-headquarters-will-relocate-workers-to-south-bay/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41167561">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>It is officially the end of an era for Mid-Market. Thirteen years after the city <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2022/10/24/as-twitter-goes-so-goes-a-revival-of-the-neighborhood-it-helped-transform/">carved out a special tax break</a> to attract tech companies to its beleaguered downtown corridor, X has confirmed plans to shut its San Francisco headquarters.&nbsp;</p><p>In an internal email reviewed by The Standard, CEO Linda Yaccarino announced Monday that X will close the offices “over the next few weeks” and will relocate San Francisco-based employees to the South Bay.&nbsp;</p><p>Once the move is complete, X’s engineering workers will share an office in Palo Alto with xAI, another company owned by Elon Musk, while the remaining employees will be routed to existing offices in Santana Row, San Jose’s popular residential, retail and business thoroughfare. The New York Times <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/08/05/technology/x-twitter-san-francisco-office.html">first reported</a> the news.</p><p>Yaccarino said in the email titled “SF Office Closure” that the company “is actively working on plans, including transportation options, for those directly impacted” but did not say if X will provide shuttle services or commuter benefits.</p></div><figure id=""><div><p><span><span></span><img alt="Woman wearing glasses speaks into microphone" loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="responsive" sizes="(min-width: 1001px) 600px, (min-width: 768px) 700px, 100vw" srcset="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=768&amp;q=75 768w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=1024&amp;q=75 1024w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/ap24031617163369.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div><figcaption>X CEO Linda Yaccarino informed San Francisco employees via email that they would be transferred to either Palo Alto or San Jose. | <span>Source: </span>Mark Schiefelbein/AP Photo</figcaption></figure><div><p>“This is an important decision that impacts many of you, but it is the right one for our company in the long term,” Yaccarino said.</p><p>X did not respond to a request for comment.&nbsp;</p><p>When the company was acquired by Musk in late 2022, the mercurial tech mogul immediately called all local employees back into the office full time. Sources inside the company, who do not have permission to speak to the media, confirmed that more than half the space at X’s headquarters, located at 1355 Market St., is vacant or unused after multiple rounds of layoffs.&nbsp;</p></div><div><p>Last month, the company began <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2024/07/12/twitter-sheds-most-of-its-san-francisco-office/">marketing the offices for sublease</a>. Shortly thereafter, Musk took to the social media platform to <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2024/07/16/angered-by-a-trans-protection-law-elon-musk-says-x-will-leave-san-francisco-for-austin/">announce</a> that X would relocate to Austin, Texas, due to his fury over a California transgender protection law. Yaccarino’s email made no mention of that move.&nbsp;</p><p>Altogether, X is on the hook for roughly 800,000 square feet of office space at the near-century-old Art Deco building in Mid-Market, with deals that expire in 2026 and 2028.&nbsp;</p></div><figure id=""><div><p><span><span></span><img alt="A man in a dark suit and white shirt sits with fingers interlaced, looking intently at the camera against a black background." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="responsive" sizes="(min-width: 1001px) 600px, (min-width: 768px) 700px, 100vw" srcset="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=768&amp;q=75 768w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=1024&amp;q=75 1024w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/Screenshot-2023-10-03-at-7.18.20-PM.png?w=3840&amp;q=75" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div><figcaption>After acquiring Twitter in late 2022, Elon Musk initiated mass layoffs while ordering local employees back to the office. Last month, he said the company, now known as X, would move to Austin, Texas. | <span>Source: </span>Chesnot/Getty Images</figcaption></figure><div><p>In 2011, <a href="https://sfcontroller.org/sites/default/files/FileCenter/Documents/1865-PDF108.pdf">the city said</a> it would pause its 1.5% payroll tax for companies that moved into the area for up to six years. Companies would have to pay only their first year’s payroll tax, and if headcount swelled later, the tax amount would stay the same. City officials hoped the policy — and Twitter’s arrival — would make the area more attractive to other businesses. And to some extent, it did.&nbsp;</p><p>Certain buildings in the area, such as 1455 Market St., were not eligible for the tax break but still attracted tech companies that opted to cluster around other fast-growing startups. Among the businesses that took the tax break, in addition to Twitter, were the dating app Zoosk, the home decor site One Kings Lane and David Sacks’ <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/david-sacks-yammer-los-angeles-versus-san-francisco-2012-9">Yammer</a>.</p></div><div><p>Twitter — which at the time was threatening to move to Brisbane — became the face and symbol of this incentive to attract companies and construction to the neighborhood.</p><p>A city <a href="https://sfcontroller.org/sites/default/files/FileCenter/Documents/5914-CMPTE%203%20year%20review_final.pdf">report</a> assessing the impact of the tax break, published in 2014, three years after it took effect, said it was likely “the primary reason for the relatively greater growth of businesses” in that area. In 2013, 15 businesses benefited from the tax break, saving a collective $4.2 million, according to the report. The report estimated that the city raked in $7.1 million more in payroll tax from the area than it would have otherwise, painting the policy as a victory.</p><p>However, since the 2019 expiration of the tax breaks and the wide shift to remote work, that exuberance appears firmly in the rearview mirror.&nbsp;</p><p>X’s latest announcement is yet another nail in the coffin.&nbsp;</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Salt (479 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/05/no-salt/</link>
            <guid>41167467</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 03:03:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/05/no-salt/">https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/05/no-salt/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41167467">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
						
<p><em>This is by my brother, Sam. </em></p>



<p>I arrived to Arizona late Saturday, after learning that my brother <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/04/starting-hospice-the-end/">has only a few days left</a> before cancer <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2023/07/22/i-am-dying-of-squamous-cell-carcinoma-and-the-treatments-that-might-save-me-are-just-out-of-reach/">ends him</a>. Jake’s wife, <a href="https://bessstillman.substack.com/">Bess</a>, confessed that she had neither the willpower or the energy to take care of the post-death rituals—in this case, cremation, followed by a celebration of life at some point in the future. Likely at <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2023/08/21/i-know-what-happens-to-me-after-i-die-but-what-about-those-left-behind/">a memorial bench at Stuyvesant Park in New York City</a>, where he and Bess built their life together, met their core group of friends, and made their fondest memories.</p>



<p>I do a lot of research, and finding a funeral home for my brother’s remains was and is quite a bit different than looking for, say, a great sushi restaurant. What should I look for out of a funeral home? Do they have five stars on Yelp? Do they seem “nice?”</p>



<p>Several funeral homes that had good reviews online. The folks on the other end of the line seemed nice. They said the right things, which makes sense because they’ve got a sales funnel. And then they asked for a credit card. I get that funeral homes are businesses that need to make money, just as most of us do. It still feels callous and transactional. Send me an agreement, or something. I’ll DocuSign it. You’ll get your money. I’m barely functional at the moment—sleepwalking through my days as if I will somehow wake from this nightmare, watching my brother and his wonderful wife fall into despair.</p>



<p><strong>Prior to his illness</strong>, Jake and I had been at odds for many years. I didn’t understand him, and neither did he. Both of us lacked the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Adult-Children-Emotionally-Immature-Parents/dp/1626251703?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=thstsst-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957">emotional maturity</a> to form deep, meaningful relationships with other people. In my case, this manifested in self-destructive behaviors like drinking, partying, womanizing, and things of that nature. For Jake, he withdrew from most of society, finding more comfort from the pages of a novel or the many works he himself has written. He eventually found meaning in teaching, and focused on his relationship with Bess.</p>



<p>In turn, I eventually found a partner and a wife who made me a better person. Somehow, both of us <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2023/09/25/strange-trip-psychedelics-and-confronting-the-fear-of-death/">found our way to psychedelics</a> as a way of dealing with reality and exploring the deeper, more esoteric corners of the world. Over the last two years, Jake and I have talked extensively about our experiences with these substances. Therapy has never worked for me. <a href="https://www.wired.com/2000/05/mckenna/">As Terrence McKenna once said</a>, “The real truth, that dare not speak itself, is that no one is in control. Absolutely no one.”</p>



<p>This is not meant to disparage therapists, advocates, or grief counselors. Each person must find their own way to deal with the reality that we perceive: what works for one may not work for others. Changing your life is difficult. It requires hard work. But your life may depend on it, so stop procrastinating and find something that works.</p>



<p><strong><a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2023/08/21/i-know-what-happens-to-me-after-i-die-but-what-about-those-left-behind/">Besides psychedelics</a>, Jake</strong> and I have discovered over the past year that we share a love of cooking, particularly using modern gadgets like Instant Pots, sous vide, and interesting spices. Jake loves his <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B01G5MZZ5Q?ie=UTF8&amp;tag=thstsst-20&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957">plug-in induction stovetop</a>, and thinks it worthwhile despite its cost. At one point I was supposed to go to the final auditions for a show called <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1694423/">MasterChef</a>, which pits amateur cooks against each other behind the gentle coaching of Gordon Ramsay. I foolishly accepted a job offer instead, but perhaps I’ll try again someday in honor of my brother.</p>



<p>Which brings me to the title of this essay. When I arrived at their home yesterday, I observed Jake in the worst condition I’ve ever seen: emaciated, with obvious tumors rampaging throughout his neck and jaw. Bess is seven months pregnant, worrying about the impending death of her soulmate, clinging to what seems like an irrational hope of a miracle turnaround.</p>



<p>I noticed an extremely uncharacteristic lack of food in their home—usually, when I walk in, Jake offers something to eat even when he knows I just ate—so I immediately went to the store to at least ensure that Bess had some food. Jake can scarcely take a sip of water, but says that “normal” food feels more wholesome going through his PEG tube than the brown, yet nutritious, <a href="https://www.functionalformularies.com/product/liquid-hope/">Liquid Hope</a> that gives him most of his daily calories.</p>



<p>Jake still has a larder of dried goods, spices, and gadgets that would be the envy of even a professional chef. Fenugreek sourced directly from Egypt. Fermented locust beans from Nigeria. More forms of masala and curry than most Indian restaurants. I had ambitions to use these spices for what Jake labeled as “possibly his final real meal,”<sup data-fn="f8512c1c-7cae-4665-b5ba-b76a84e5b6e9"><a href="#f8512c1c-7cae-4665-b5ba-b76a84e5b6e9" id="f8512c1c-7cae-4665-b5ba-b76a84e5b6e9-link">1</a></sup> only to realize that antibiotics have ruined his gastrointestinal system to the point that making anything exotic might bug his stomach.</p>



<p>So I opted for something simple: a shakshuka. Tomatoes, vegetables, sauce, and mild flavorings, topped with feta cheese, eggs, and basil. I reached for the salt, and found the bottle empty. I’m not sure why, but I started weeping. No salt. No salt means that he’s not cooking. He’ll never cook again. Salt is the most basic ingredient. <a href="https://jakeseliger.com/2024/02/26/food-and-friends-part-i-food-is-social-life/">Food is (was, I guess) so important to him.</a> He cooked for Bess throughout the summer of 2023, when he couldn’t eat anything except by PEG tube.</p>



<p>I’ll go over to their house again later today, and make sure I cook enough food at least for Bess to be able to eat, and hopefully for Jake to eat via the tube. I’ll stop for more salt on my way.</p>



<p>If the salt is gone, then Jake is too.</p>



<figure><a href="https://jakeseliger.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/dsc00635.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9024" data-permalink="https://jakeseliger.com/2024/08/05/no-salt/dsc00635/" data-orig-file="https://jakeseliger.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/dsc00635.jpg" data-orig-size="2048,1365" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="DSC00635" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://jakeseliger.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/dsc00635.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://jakeseliger.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/dsc00635.jpg?w=550" tabindex="0" role="button" width="1024" height="682" src="https://jakeseliger.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/dsc00635.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a></figure>


<ol><li id="f8512c1c-7cae-4665-b5ba-b76a84e5b6e9">Jake’s wonderful friend <a href="https://www.yelp.com/biz/tracy-dempsey-originals-tempe">Tracey Dempsey</a> also dropped off a plethora of baked goods. Everything she makes is incredible, but I’m partial to the cheesecake. <a href="#f8512c1c-7cae-4665-b5ba-b76a84e5b6e9-link">↩︎</a></li></ol>					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Building rqlite 9.0: Cutting disk usage by half (171 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.philipotoole.com/building-rqlite-9-0-cutting-disk-usage-by-half/</link>
            <guid>41167060</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 01:20:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.philipotoole.com/building-rqlite-9-0-cutting-disk-usage-by-half/">https://www.philipotoole.com/building-rqlite-9-0-cutting-disk-usage-by-half/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41167060">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">

	<div id="primary" role="main">
			
<article id="post-6737">
	
	<!-- .entry-header -->

		<div>
		<p><a href="https://rqlite.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="https://www.philipotoole.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/04/j.png" alt="" width="131" height="126"></a><a href="https://www.rqlite.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">rqlite</a> is a lightweight, <a href="https://github.com/rqlite/rqlite" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open-source</a>, distributed relational database written in <a href="https://golang.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Go</a>, that uses <a href="http://sqlite.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SQLite</a> as its storage engine.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/rqlite/rqlite/tree/referential-snapshot" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Development for 9.0 has started</a>, with the main goal of reducing disk usage by approximately 50%. This goal will be achieved through a high-level design overhaul targeting the primary causes of disk consumption in rqlite.</p>

<h2>What drives current disk usage?</h2>
<p>Today, rqlite’s disk space usage is driven by three main factors:</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Raft Log:</strong> The log of all changes made to the system. This log is at the core of the <a href="https://raft.github.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raft consensus protocol</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Working SQLite Database:</strong> The live database that rqlite uses to serve reads and writes.</li>
<li><strong>A snapshot of the SQLite Database:</strong> <a href="https://support.hashicorp.com/hc/en-us/articles/4408853527059-What-are-the-snapshot-entries-in-the-consul-data-raft-snapshot-directory" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Periodically generated by the Raft system</a> as part of the Raft log truncation process. Log truncation prevents the Raft log from growing indefinitely and is a key component of Raft. This <em>snapshotted</em> copy is used by Raft to restore a node when it restarts, or when a second node needs to “catch up” with the state of an existing cluster.</li>
</ol>
<h2>High-Level Design for rqlite 9.0</h2>
<p>The key strategy for reducing disk usage involves removing the need to store the <em>snapshotted</em> copy of the working SQLite database in the Raft system. While the Raft log is periodically truncated and stops growing after a certain point due to snapshotting, the SQLite database does not have this limitation and continues to grow as more data is written to it. Since the snapshot SQLite database is roughly the same size as the working SQLite database, eliminating this duplicate copy can reduce disk usage by about 50%.</p>
<p><img src="https://www.philipotoole.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/rqlite-snapshot.png" alt="" width="150" height="140" srcset="https://www.philipotoole.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/rqlite-snapshot.png 360w, https://www.philipotoole.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/rqlite-snapshot-300x281.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"></p>
<p>However, an rqlite node still needs a snapshotted copy — this cannot be avoided. So how do we avoid the copy, but still meet the needs of <em>Snapshot and Restore</em>? <strong>The key thing to understand is that the working SQLite database file — ignoring its associated WAL file — and the snapshotted copy in the Raft system are logically the same thing.</strong></p>
<h3>Step-by-step</h3>
<p>Let’s look at how snapshotting will work in 9.0.</p>
<ol>
<li><strong>Snapshot and WAL Checkpointing:</strong> At snapshot time, rqlite will checkpoint the Write-Ahead Log (WAL) of the working SQLite database. All subsequent writes will then be directed to a newly-created WAL file, leaving the main SQLite file unchanged (until the next snapshot is triggered). <strong>It is this key insight</strong> that allows us to use the working SQLite file to serve reads and writes, as well as contain the point-in-time state that the Raft Snapshot store requires.</li>
<li><strong>Write a <em>Reference</em> to Snapshot Store:</strong> Instead of copying the entire SQLite file, rqlite will write a <em>Reference</em>, such as a checksum, to the Snapshot store. This avoids the need to store a duplicate copy of the SQLite data. This reference can be used to validate that the main SQLite file matches what the Snapshot store references, whenever snapshot data is needed. (This check protects against bugs, operational mistakes, or disk corruption but isn’t strictly needed.)</li>
<li><strong>Restoration from Snapshot:</strong> Because all writes after the snapshot process are written to the WAL file, the main SQLite file remains ready for use by the <em>Restore-from-Snapshot</em> process if needed (e.g., during a node restart or when transferring the snapshot to another node). In other words the main SQLite file (again, ignoring its associated WAL file) remains logically the same as that written to the Raft snapshot store.</li>
</ol>
<p>This is why I call this process <em>Referential Snapshotting</em>.</p>
<h3>Bonus Enhancements</h3>
<p>This design change will actually result in a couple of other high-impact improvements.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Faster Snapshotting:</strong> By writing minimal data to the Raft Snapshot store, the snapshotting process will be much faster. It should consist of the SQLite WAL checkpointing time (which is usually very short) and the checksum computation time.&nbsp; There will be no need to copy large amounts of SQLite data to the Snapshot store on every snapshot. When one realises that writes to rqlite are blocked during the Snapshot process, the advantages of faster snapshotting are clear.</li>
<li><strong>Improved Node Restart Times:</strong> Nodes, <a href="https://github.com/rqlite/rqlite/issues/1798" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">even those with multiple gigabytes of SQLite data</a>, will restart much, much faster. Currently, at restart, rqlite has to restore the working SQLite database file from the copy in Raft Snapshot Store. But with this new design, the working SQLite database file will already be in the correct place at start-up. At most, rqlite will only need to compare the checksum in the Snapshot store to the checksum of the working SQLite database. Multi-GB systems should restart within a few seconds.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Next Steps</h3>
<p>The move to rqlite 9.0 should make a significant step forward in optimizing the efficiency of rqlite. By implementing <em>Referential Snapshotting</em>, I expect to achieve significant reductions in disk usage, faster snapshotting, and improved node restart times.</p>
<p>There are many details to get right, including SQLite WAL management, seamless upgrades from earlier releases, and checksum choice. So stay tuned for further updates as we progress towards this major release.</p>
<p><em>If you’re interested in learning more about Raft and how all this works, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8XbxQ1Epi5w" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">check out my recent talk at GopherCon</a> on building Distributed Systems.<br>
</em></p>
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->
	
	</article><!-- #post-6737 -->
		<!-- .navigation -->
		
<!-- #comments -->
		</div><!-- #primary -->

<div id="secondary">
		<h2>Philip O'Toole</h2>
	
	
		<!-- #primary-sidebar -->
	</div><!-- #secondary -->

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>