<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 18:00:09 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Harmful 5G Fast Lanes Are Coming; the FCC Needs to Stop Them (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2024/04/harmful-5g-fast-lanes-are-coming-fcc-needs-stop-them</link>
            <guid>40024062</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 16:09:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2024/04/harmful-5g-fast-lanes-are-coming-fcc-needs-stop-them">https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2024/04/harmful-5g-fast-lanes-are-coming-fcc-needs-stop-them</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40024062">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div property="content:encoded"><p dir="ltr">The FCC is <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/april-2024-open-commission-meeting">set to vote on April 25</a> to restore its authority over the companies we pay to get online, and reinstate federal net neutrality protections that were jettisoned by the Trump administration in 2017.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Net neutrality protections are supposed to ensure that we, not the internet service providers (ISPs) we pay to get online, get to decide what we do online.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC released <a href="http://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/DOC-401676A1.pdf">its draft rules</a> early in April and there’s much to celebrate in them. Mobile carriers like T-Mobile, AT&amp;T and Verizon that have been degrading video quality for mobile users will have to stop. The FCC kept in place state neutrality protections like California’s net neutrality law, allowing for layers of enforcement. The FCC also made it harder for ISPs to evade net neutrality at the point where data enters their networks.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>However, there’s a huge problem: the proposed rules make it possible for mobile ISPs to start picking applications and putting them in a fast lane - where they’ll perform better generally and much better if the network gets congested.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.t-mobile.com/news/network/t-mobile-expands-worlds-first-network-slicing-beta-nationwide">T-Mobile</a>, <a href="https://www.lightreading.com/oss-bss-cx/at-t-tests-gaming-traffic-prioritization-amid-net-neutrality-debate">AT&amp;T</a> and <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/carriers-look-to-offer-fast-lane-access-on-5g-networks-0ab57bcc">Verizon</a> are all testing ways to create these 5G fast lanes for apps such as video conferencing, games, and video where the ISP chooses and controls what gets boosted. They use a technical feature in 5G called network slicing, where part of their radio spectrum gets used as a special lane for the chosen app or apps, separated from the usual internet traffic.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>The FCC’s draft order opens the door to these fast lanes, so long as the app provider isn’t charged for them.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">That means we could soon see fast lane offerings like this:</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img alt="" src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile2.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">Or we could see add-ons like Enhanced Video Conferencing for $10 a month, or one-time 24-hour passes to have Prioritized Online Gaming.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile1.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">This isn't imagination.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The ISPs write about this in their blogs and press releases. They talk about these efforts and dreams openly at conferences, and their equipment vendors plainly lay out how ISPs can chop up internet service into all manner of fast lanes.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>These kinds of ISP-controlled fast lanes violate core net neutrality principles and would limit user choice, distort competition, hamper startups, and help cement platform dominance.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Net neutrality means that we, the people who use the internet, get to decide what we do online, without interference from ISPs. ISPs do not get to interfere with our choices by blocking, speeding up or slowing down apps or kinds of apps. Apps compete on a level playing field, and users, not ISPs, determine which apps are successful.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Letting ISPs decide which apps get to be in a fast lane violates these principles. Apps that are in a fast lane work better than those that are not, especially when the network is busy and apps in the regular lane start suffering. If HBO Max is in a fast lane, it will continue to work well even if the network is busy, while all other video is buffering.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Differences in performance, including relative differences in performance, matter. Even small differences in load times affect how long people stay on a site, how much they pay, and whether they’ll come back. Those differences also affect how high up sites show in search results.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Thus, letting ISPs choose which apps get to be in a fast lane lets them, not users, pick winners and losers online.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">And <a href="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2022/05/facebook-google-big-telecoms-want-keep-violating-net-neutrality-europe-regulators">as we’ve seen in the past</a>, programs like this favor the most popular apps, even when the program is supposedly open to all apps in a category and no apps are paying the ISP. So the biggest apps will end up in all the fast lanes, while most others would be left out. The ones left out would likely include messaging apps like Signal, local news sites, decentralized Fediverse apps like Mastodon and PeerTube, niche video sites like Dropout, indie music sites like Bandcamp, and the millions of other sites and apps in the long tail.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Legislators, government agencies, attorneys general in states both red and blue, public interest groups, startups, and open-source technologists are all working to reduce the power and dominance of the biggest platforms. The FCC should be working to help that effort by creating a level playing field and banning these ISP-controlled 5G fast lanes.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Meaningful net neutrality protections prohibit ISPs from speeding up and slowing down apps and kinds of apps.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">ISPs can pick winners and losers by putting winners in a fast lane or losers in a slow lane.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This is a what it would look like if an ISP put everything except YouTube and TikTok in a slow lane.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile4.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">This is what it would look like if an ISP put YouTube and TikTok in a fast lane.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><img p="" src="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/20240411-mobile4.png"></p>
<p dir="ltr">It’s the same picture. The effect is the same. In either case, disfavored apps will find it harder to compete.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Meaningful net neutrality protections need to protect against both.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>This is not controversial.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">President Obama’s <a href="https://obamawhitehouse.archives.gov/net-neutrality">November 2014 net neutrality proposal</a> included this protection:</p>
<p dir="ltr">“The rules I am asking for are simple, common-sense steps that reflect the Internet you and I use every day.” That included, he said, a brightline ban on ISPs “intentionally slow[ing] down some content or speed[ing] up others — through a process often called “throttling” — based on the type of service or your ISP’s preferences.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">Even proposed <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/115th-congress/house-bill/6393">Republican</a> <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/116th-congress/house-bill/1101/text?s=1&amp;r=98">net neutrality</a> <a href="https://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/sites/default/files/publication/files/RepublicanNetworkNeutralityBill-BILLS-114hr-PIH-OpenInternet.pdf">bills</a> prohibited ISPs from speeding up and slowing down apps and kinds of apps.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Many, including me, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/104020490613577/2">thought the 2015 Order did so</a>, too.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Almost certainly, the millions of Americans who celebrated the 2015 Open Internet Order and fought the 2017 repeal think that net neutrality protections ban fast lanes and slow lanes.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>The draft order takes a different approach.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">The no-throttling rule that the FCC proposed in October explicitly prohibited ISPs from slowing down apps and classes of apps; it was silent on whether the rule also applies to speeding up.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Given the mobile ISPs’ public statements about their plans for 5G fast lanes, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10328020156846/1">public</a> <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10401332717347/1">interest</a> <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/10330745507976/1">groups</a>, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/1215041660232/1">startups</a>, and <a href="https://www.markey.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/letter_to_fcc_title_ii_4224.pdf">members of Congress</a> asked the FCC to clarify in the Order that the no-throttling rule also prohibits ISPs from speeding up apps and classes of apps.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>The draft order did not do that.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">While <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/DOC-401676A1.pdf">draft order</a> acknowledges that some speeding up of apps could violate the no-throttling rule, it added some unclear, nebulous language suggesting that the FCC would review any fast lanes case-by-case, without explaining how it would do that.<sup><a href="#one">1</a></sup> This language gives the FCC maximum flexibility to accept or reject specific fast lanes in the future as it sees fit.</p>
<p dir="ltr">According to the draft order, the agency “could” find a violation of the no-throttling rule, if:&nbsp;</p>
<ol>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">an ISP speeds up specific apps (but not necessarily classes of apps), and</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">the decision to speed up is “unreasonably discriminatory,” and</p>
</li>
<li dir="ltr">
<p dir="ltr">the speeding up has the effect of “‘impair[ing] or degrad[ing]’ other … apps not given the same treatment.”&nbsp;</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>In other words, the proposed no-throttling rule is a bright line rule for slow lanes – ISPs can’t slow down apps or kinds of apps; but for fast lanes, it’s a fuzzy, unclear case-by-case standard.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">For example, would it be “unreasonably discriminatory” to create a 5G fast lane that includes the most popular apps in a category since it responds to consumer preferences? Does an unreasonably discriminatory fast lane need to technically degrade or impair the apps that are not in the fast lane for the FCC to find a violation of the no-throttling rule?&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>There is no way to predict which kinds of fast lanes the FCC might ultimately find to violate the no-throttling rule. This gives ISPs cover to flood the market with various fast-lane offerings, arguing that their version does not violate the no-throttling rule and daring the FCC to enforce its rule.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">And if the mobile ISPs do this, the cable companies will soon follow. Cable companies have the tech to build their own fast lanes, and increasingly they compete with 5G to the Home services. If T-Mobile and Verizon start selling home plans that have “enhanced streaming video,” you can bet the cable companies will launch their own version.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC would then investigate these offerings case-by-case in lengthy and costly proceedings. In the meantime, apps that are not in the fast lane will suffer.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Entrepreneurs and application providers that are not included in a fast lane will have to decide whether to try to get into the fast lane, file an FCC complaint, or just silently suffer.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">Companies that do file complaints will waste years litigating the meaning of “unreasonably discriminatory,” all the while going up against giant telecoms that stockpile lawyers and lobbyists.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Unless you are a high-paid telecom lawyer who bills by the hour, the proposed test for what’s a good or bad fast lane is a nightmare.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Not all 5G slices are harmful.&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">Just to be clear, net neutrality proponents are not asking the FCC to ban network slicing. There’s lots of ways for ISPs to use slices for things that are not normal internet service such as a dedicated slice for a farming operation using remote controlled tractors, slices for telemetry data and oversight of autonomous cars, or providing a slice for a stadium’s video system at a crowded game.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">There are good reasons to isolate this kind of traffic, and it can be done without reducing user choice or tilting the online playing field. Under the FCC’s draft order, such services would be so-called enterprise service offerings, to which the Open Internet protections don’t apply.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">But the 5G fast lanes ISPs are imagining for regular internet access – where ISPs decide which apps or kind of apps get a fast lane – would cause real harm and violate the core tenets of net neutrality.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">We don’t need our ISP deciding for us what’s important and what’s not; we want our ISP to let us decide and stick to the job of connecting our devices to the services we want to use.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">It’s not even clear why such fast lanes are necessary for consumer internet access. As one industry analyst noted, isn’t 5G already supposed to be the fast lane for everything?&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr"><strong>Luckily, there’s still time to fix this.</strong></p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC can and should edit the draft order ahead of the vote on April 24 and clarify in the Order that the no-throttling rule also prohibits ISPs from creating fast lanes for select apps or kinds of apps.&nbsp;</p>
<p dir="ltr">The FCC just needs to put this fix in the fast lane to get it done before it votes on April 25.</p>
<hr>

<p><sup>1</sup> <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/document/promoting-fast-open-and-fair-internet">2024 Draft Order</a>, para. 492 (“Our interpretation of “throttling” encompasses a wide variety of conduct that could impair or degrade an end user’s ability to access content of their choosing; thus, we decline commenters’ request to modify the rule to explicitly include positive and negative discrimination of content. We agree, however, with Free Press that a BIAS provider’s “unreasonably discriminatory” decision to speed up specific content, applications, or services could “impair or degrade” other content, applications, or services not given the same treatment.” (footnotes omitted)).</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is .NET just miles ahead or am I delusional? (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/dotnet/comments/18gpl24/is_net_just_miles_ahead_or_am_i_delusional/</link>
            <guid>40021758</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 09:29:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/dotnet/comments/18gpl24/is_net_just_miles_ahead_or_am_i_delusional/">https://old.reddit.com/r/dotnet/comments/18gpl24/is_net_just_miles_ahead_or_am_i_delusional/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40021758">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Professionally I've only ever worked in c# code bases. Obviously a lot of projects had a js SPA frontend attached, but I wasnt on that side.</p>

<p>I'm branching out into other languages, I'm pretty involved in reading newest tech twitter stuff, articles, youtube videos etc.</p>

<p>I get hit by incredible "what is going on, I had this in .net for  years, i dont even know how any ecosystem exists without it" more and more recently. How do others feel about this?</p>

<p>Some examples: </p>

<p>I just watched this video <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zB9tEQYLPL4">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zB9tEQYLPL4</a>. Appearantly go + htmx have managed to recreate razor or blazor templates and people are gushing about how insane it is that they ALMOST make it typesafe. Its not really typesafe, more like typescript where its autocomplete, but not real.</p>

<p>I remember reading about one of the top javascript ORMs. Drizzle? People realized that it actually queried the entire database in the background and then did in memory query operations in its rust engine??? Generally I have to ignore any "ORM bad" comments people make, because I know their ORMs are actually bad. Its l ike using the original ef at best.</p>

<p>Build stuff and configuration in javascript specifically. In .net its so easy I don't even know what happens. It just works. I press F5 locally and I put it in whatever pipeline for production.Javascript mains just go babel webpack, they have conflicts, c make, i dont know whats going on...</p>

<p>The react server component meme a couple of months back where everyone was freaking out about either how insane it is or how insanely unsafe it is for sql injection. We had it in blazor for years.</p>

<p>Debugging... do I even need to say anything? There are unironic articles out there advocating for print debugging over attaching a debugger. Probably because it has actually some validity in other languages where you not just click the line number and smash F5.</p>

<p>I do like some things from other languages. I think just writing UIs in react, pressing strg s and instantly seeing the result is amazing. Much better than the blazor or razor dev experience.I like ... "hardcoded string options" as actual types. Its like enums but nicer I think. Dont know what that feature is actually called.</p>

<p>I also really like the typescript type magic. Autogenerating a type based on one object. Extending that type with 2 properties in 1 line and using that one. I miss that in c#. But in general these are small nice to haves, not "bro how do you even exist? How can some smart people not just steal ef core 1:1 for rust, go or js?"</p>

<p>I dont really know if I have a question. It just seems to me that these devs with a supposed breadth of knowledge are all missing the .net part. It feels like a weird island. It really feels like a waste.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ubisoft is stripping people's licences for The Crew weeks after its shutdown (171 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pcgamer.com/games/racing/ubisoft-is-stripping-peoples-licences-for-the-crew-weeks-after-its-shutdown-nearly-squandering-hopes-of-private-servers-and-acting-as-a-stark-reminder-of-how-volatile-digital-ownership-is/</link>
            <guid>40020961</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 06:23:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pcgamer.com/games/racing/ubisoft-is-stripping-peoples-licences-for-the-crew-weeks-after-its-shutdown-nearly-squandering-hopes-of-private-servers-and-acting-as-a-stark-reminder-of-how-volatile-digital-ownership-is/">https://www.pcgamer.com/games/racing/ubisoft-is-stripping-peoples-licences-for-the-crew-weeks-after-its-shutdown-nearly-squandering-hopes-of-private-servers-and-acting-as-a-stark-reminder-of-how-volatile-digital-ownership-is/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40020961">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">

<section>
<div itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1920-80.jpg.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-320-80.jpg" alt="Image for Ubisoft is stripping people's licences for The Crew weeks after its shutdown, nearly squandering hopes of fan servers and acting as a stark reminder of how volatile digital ownership is" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296.jpg"></picture>
</div>
<meta itemprop="url" content="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ANB2t95cqBMQe4baprP296.jpg">
<meta itemprop="height" content="600">
<meta itemprop="width" content="338">
<figcaption itemprop="caption description">
<span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Ubisoft)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<p>The downside of digital ownership has reared its ugly head for enjoyers of <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/ubisoft/" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/ubisoft/">Ubisoft</a>'s open-world multiplayer racer The Crew. The publisher has revoked its licence for those who owned it on Ubisoft Connect, almost destroying fan ambitions to revive the game in both an offline and online format.</p><p><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/the-crew-removed-from-sale-will-become-unplayable-after-april-1-we-understand-this-may-be-disappointing-for-players-still-enjoying-the-game/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/the-crew-removed-from-sale-will-become-unplayable-after-april-1-we-understand-this-may-be-disappointing-for-players-still-enjoying-the-game/">The Crew was pulled from sale</a> back in December, with Ubisoft revealing that the servers would be shut down at the beginning of April. Frustratingly, despite a large portion of the game being doable in singleplayer, The Crew remained an online-only endeavour throughout its decade-long lifespan. That had already rendered the game unplayable, but it seems Ubisoft is determined to take things one step further to stamp out any attempts to continue playing it past its expiry date.</p><p>Fans began to notice earlier in the week that the licence to the game had been snatched away from them. A message at the top of the game's library page reads, "You no longer have access to this game. Why not check the Store to pursue your adventures?" It's also been moved to its own individual section in player libraries, listed under "inactive games". Apparently booting the game directly from the installation directory will still launch the game, but only in a demo mode.</p><p>The news has, unsurprisingly, gone down very poorly. "This was the saddest and most ruthless decision I've ever seen in gaming history," one Redditor <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz59uec/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz59uec/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">commented</a> after a screenshot began circulating on the site. "I will always fight for digital media, I love all the advantages it gives to users all around the world. But this… we need protection on the national or European level, that when we purchase something, we need to have lifetime access to it. No matter what."</p><figure data-bordeaux-image-check=""><div><p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-320-80.jpg" alt="Ubisoft Connect's store which shows that the licence for The Crew has been revoked." srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi-1200-80.jpg 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/WwZW7q7tmf8uJ4BXNCcnoi.jpg"></picture></p></div><figcaption itemprop="caption description"><span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Ubisoft)</span></figcaption></figure><p>A further Reddit user <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4rn3d/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4rn3d/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">called it</a> "really abhorrent behavior that needs to stop being legal," with another <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4q9er/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/Games/comments/1c1la9j/comment/kz4q9er/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web2x&amp;context=3">writing</a>, "In an ideal world, revoking a license like this should entitle the buyer to a refund. I'm not sure why they're even bothering doing this. The game isn't playable anymore, so what exactly is the harm in keeping the game available for download for those who have purchased it? Server space? Is Ubisoft really that cheap?"</p><p>It's worth noting that it appears you can technically still download the game on Steam, but any attempt to play is followed-up with <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://imgur.com/WPOWIPc" target="_blank" data-url="https://imgur.com/WPOWIPc">a request to input a game key</a></p><p>Now it's one thing to just delist a game and still allow owners to download and boot it up if they want—even if the game is technically dead—but it's another thing to revoke the licence to the files entirely. It came very close to putting a dent in plans to bring fan servers to the game, but one project appears to still be chugging along.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-gMmpoeneCkWpxZH3cWJFGS"><section><p>Sign up to get the best content of the week, and great gaming deals, as picked by the editors.</p></section></div><blockquote><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/1c1y7h3/ubisoft_revoking_licenses_for_the_crew_preventing" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming/comments/1c1y7h3/ubisoft_revoking_licenses_for_the_crew_preventing">Ubisoft revoking licenses for The Crew, preventing owners who paid for the game from installing it.</a> from <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming" data-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/gaming">r/gaming</a></blockquote><p>The Crew Unlimited Discord server is housing a project called The Crew Offline+Online Server Emulation, intended to bring the game back to a playable state "both offline locally and online" via a community server—no cracking or pirating involved. I asked project member ChemicalFlood how it had impacted their plans:</p><p><em>"We are deeply saddened by Ubisoft's choice to start revoking licences to this game when people have paid hard-earned cash for it," he told me. "In regard to the project, yes! We are currently working on a Server Emulator as opposed to cracking the game. Before the shutdown of the servers, we took the precaution of capturing Network Communications Data. Had we not done this, the project would [have] sadly fallen over and this game would [have] been lost forever.</em></p><p><em>"Thankfully, a server emulation is still possible. But no other patch is possible due to the high amount of DRM placed into the game by Ubisoft, which sadly has restricted our ability to work on a fix, but not impossible!"</em></p><p>I also asked ChemicalFlood how the news had gone down with fans and The Crew Unlimited Discord:&nbsp;</p><p><em>"Obviously, Ubisoft pulling the game licences has left a sour taste in every gamer's mouth and it has unfortunately made it so the game cannot even be launched without it turning into a restricted trial mode. However, we can bypass this new change made by them without having to modify the existing game files, so the project is still on track!</em></p><p><em>"It should go without saying that, by any means, the fact that the community has to implement something like this to continue playing something we all paid for is abysmal, especially something of this magnitude. We of course love the game and want it to be played for generations to come (my own son loved playing this on the <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/playstation/" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/uk/tag/playstation/">PlayStation</a>, 'loved' being the keyword!) But Ubisoft should [have] implemented an offline mode and they could [have]! The offline mode already exists in the files, we just can't turn it on because of the DRM in place.</em></p><p><em>"We hope that the </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.stopkillinggames.com/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.stopkillinggames.com/"><em>Stopkillinggames</em></a><em> campaign will mean that the communities and fans of these games will not be expected to be able to restore every single online-only game like this."</em></p><figure data-bordeaux-image-check=""><div><p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-320-80.jpg" alt="Ubisoft Connect's store which shows that the licence for The Crew has been revoked." srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui-1200-80.jpg 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/YgYXE9WrSfSCZwKiVbFWui.jpg"></picture></p></div><figcaption itemprop="caption description"><span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Ubisoft)</span></figcaption></figure><p>I've requested comment from Ubisoft regarding the situation and will update if I hear back. I'll be interested to know if the publisher provides any solid reason for being extra thorough with its shutdown process. There's a good chance it has something to do with licensing—there are a good deal of licensed songs in The Crew, not to mention all of the real-world car manufacturers present, too. It could make for a sticky situation keeping the files around, and perhaps it was easier to try and kill the whole thing instead.&nbsp;</p><p>Regardless of the reason, it's an ever-looming reminder of how fragile digital ownership can be. A study by the Video Game History Foundation last year found that around <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/study-finds-over-87-percent-of-games-are-unplayable-without-resorting-to-piracy-scavenger-hunts-or-travelling-to-an-archive/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/study-finds-over-87-percent-of-games-are-unplayable-without-resorting-to-piracy-scavenger-hunts-or-travelling-to-an-archive/">87% of games are unplayable</a> without diving into some kind of piracy or fan-created archive, and that number could even worsen as physical discs slowly die out. But preservation is becoming a bigger topic, one that's <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/events-conferences/preserving-old-games-was-seen-as-a-non-commercial-art-project-until-recently-says-nightdive-director-they-were-great-then-and-theyre-great-now-and-companies-have-begun-to-realize-that/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/events-conferences/preserving-old-games-was-seen-as-a-non-commercial-art-project-until-recently-says-nightdive-director-they-were-great-then-and-theyre-great-now-and-companies-have-begun-to-realize-that/">now being taken more seriously</a> as a means of conserving the medium.</p><p>Earlier this month, YouTuber Ross Scott <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/stop-killing-games-campaign/" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/stop-killing-games-campaign/">launched a campaign</a> called "Stop Killing Games" with The Crew as its primary example. His hope is to eventually win a legal victory that would require publishers to keep their live service games playable in some form after they end support, such as by releasing private servers.</p>
</div>
<div id="slice-container-authorBio-gMmpoeneCkWpxZH3cWJFGS"><p>Mollie spent her early childhood deeply invested in games like Killer Instinct, Toontown and Audition Online, which continue to form the pillars of her personality today. She joined PC Gamer in 2020 as a news writer and now lends her expertise to write a wealth of features, guides and reviews with a dash of chaos. She can often be found causing mischief in Final Fantasy 14, using those experiences to write neat things about her favourite MMO. When she's not staring at her bunny girl she can be found sweating out rhythm games, pretending to be good at fighting games or spending far too much money at her local arcade. &nbsp;</p></div>




</section>


<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h5>Most Popular</h5></p></div>







</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Your LLM Is a Capable Regressor When Given In-Context Examples (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07544</link>
            <guid>40019217</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:39:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07544">https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07544</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40019217">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.07544">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2404.07544v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>We analyze how well pre-trained large language models (e.g., Llama2, GPT-4, Claude 3, etc) can do linear and non-linear regression when given in-context examples, without any additional training or gradient updates. Our findings reveal that several large language models (e.g., GPT-4, Claude 3) are able to perform regression tasks with a performance rivaling (or even outperforming) that of traditional supervised methods such as Random Forest, Bagging, or Gradient Boosting. For example, on the challenging Friedman #2 regression dataset, Claude 3 outperforms many supervised methods such as AdaBoost, SVM, Random Forest, KNN, or Gradient Boosting. We then investigate how well the performance of large language models scales with the number of in-context exemplars. We borrow from the notion of regret from online learning and empirically show that LLMs are capable of obtaining a sub-linear regret.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Robert Vacareanu [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/459a9057/2404.07544">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Thu, 11 Apr 2024 08:12:43 UTC (10,436 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Japanese police arrest man for tampering with Pokémon Violet save data (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ign.com/articles/japanese-police-arrest-36-year-old-man-on-suspicion-of-tampering-with-pokemon-violet-save-data</link>
            <guid>40019124</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:27:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/japanese-police-arrest-36-year-old-man-on-suspicion-of-tampering-with-pokemon-violet-save-data">https://www.ign.com/articles/japanese-police-arrest-36-year-old-man-on-suspicion-of-tampering-with-pokemon-violet-save-data</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40019124">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p>Police in Japan have arrested a 36-year-old man on suspicion of selling illegally modified Pokémon save data to customers online — a practice which is banned under the country’s <a href="https://www.japaneselawtranslation.go.jp/en/laws/view/3629" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">2019 Unfair Competition Prevention Act</a>.</p><p>As reported by the <a href="https://www3.nhk.or.jp/lnews/kochi/20240410/8010020207.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Japanese website NHK News</a>, and translated by <a href="https://automaton-media.com/en/news/hacked-pokemon-seller-arrested-by-japanese-police/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Automaton</a>, the suspect was apprehended by police on April 9 after a ‘police cyber patrol’ discovered evidence that the individual had used special tools to illegally modify save data for <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/pokemon-violet">Pokémon Violet</a> in order to change Pokémon move sets.A 36-year-old man was arrest for selling illegally modified Pokemon save data.</p><p>The 36-year-old allegedly took custom orders for rare Pokémon, and sold the resulting tampered data between December 2022 to March 2023, for up to 13,000 yen ($84) a time on a website that served as a marketplace for video game assets and items. He also offered deals in which six Pokémon would be created for the equivalent of roughly $30 in yen.</p><p>The 36-year-old has reportedly admitted to committing the crimes at the heart of the ongoing investigation, while providing the justification that he did it to earn a living. According to Automaton, the suspect could face up to five years imprisonment, and/or a fine of up to 5 million yen (over $32,600).</p><p>This isn’t the first time that criminals have sought to make money off of Game Freak’s wildly popular franchise. For example, In 2021 an ill-fated Pokemon card heist saw one desperate man <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/man-arrested-after-literal-pokemon-card-heist?_gl=1*17zenfa*_up*MQ..*_ga*MTg2MzE0MTUzOC4xNzEyODUwNTk0*_ga_736S6FVMCL*MTcxMjg1MDU5My4xLjAuMTcxMjg1MDU5My4wLjAuMA..">attempt to descend from a six-story building in order to steal a treasure trove of trading cards</a> and cash from a Tokyo store. </p><p>2022 saw the trend continue, with criminals in Tokyo committing a series of high-value Pokemon burglaries, <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/pokmon-and-other-trading-cards-targets-of-unprecedent-number-of-robberies-in-japan">including one instance in which theives made off with a haul of cards worth over $60,000</a>. Its worth noting that the raw last for Pokemon — and the trouble it can land you in — is felt well beyond the criminal fraternity. As a case in point January 2022 saw two Los Angeles police officers fired <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/lapd-officers-fired-for-chasing-snorlax-in-pokemon-go-instead-of-robbers">after they ignored a call to attend a burglary in order to chase down a Snorlax</a> in <a href="https://www.ign.com/games/pokemon-go">Pokemon Go</a>.</p><p>While you’re here why not take a moment to check out IGN’s ranking of the top 10 best pokemon video games of all time, or discover <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/pokemon-face-off-ign-readers-have-chosen-which-pocket-monster-is-the-very-best">which Pokemon our readers have crowned as the very best of all time in our 2021 face off</a>.</p><p><em>Anthony is a freelance contributor covering science and video gaming news for IGN. He has over eight years experience of covering breaking developments in multiple scientific fields and absolutely no time for your shenanigans. Follow him on Twitter @BeardConGamer</em></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I continue to no longer attend vintage computer festivals (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/5591</link>
            <guid>40018990</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:09:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/5591">http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/5591</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40018990">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
	
			<article id="post-5591">
				
				<header>
				  
		    	</header>
		
				<section>
		
				
<div><p>As should be expected, a number of individuals have come forward with responses to the <a href="http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/5587" data-type="link" data-id="http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/5587">initial blog post</a>. While I do not expect everyone to take even a passing interest in the rabbit-hole of the situation or the context, I figured it was worth writing a few quick addendums.</p><p>Naturally, as is the case when you post anything anywhere in public, I am called a liar. I’ll simply say that everything I describe in the blog entry happened. I contacted a VCF administrator and was told it was all disposed of, and that they kept the bins. I am fine with people claiming that disposal was not what happened, but this is what I was told, directly, in human words. The fact that I am seeing contradictory and confusing descriptions of what happened is not a checkmark destined for the Win column.</p></div>



<p>A few people have rushed to indicate that I need to be more careful describing “which” VCF entity is at fault. I am sad to report to them all that the Byzantine VCF structure of name licensing, geographic branding, and internal corporate entity is meaningless to anyone six inches away. You all know each other and you all interchangeably use nomenclature. If you are part of an organization that calls itself some form of “VCF” and need an opportunity to write a statement about how your organization in a solitary/separate entity and should be considered more worthy or ethical than others, feel absolutely free.</p>



<p>A small sliver of people were concerned I was saying that I was never going to go to any computer history conference or event again. I am a free person with the freedom to attend whatever is open to the public. As it stood, however, VCF East was the easiest event for me to attend, so it was where I saw people the most. A minor point is that I considered attendance a form of endorsement, but that is my own personal choice. The chances of me attending other events is, like death by cow, low but never zero.</p>



<p>The rest of the discussions I have seen from the blog entry, raging in the usual stages of social media and posting forums, have failed to require any further response or thought from me personally.</p>



<p>Finally, this is all relatively minor in terms of the work I do and projects I focus on, an event that brought me some fury but which has mostly played the part of filed under “life lessons”. I just got tired of having quiet inward emotion when I was reminded of the event, specifically when VCF announcements would pass by my screen, followed by nice folks asking if they would be seeing me at the event. Now I have made a statement, and rather than the beginning of a saga, I consider it the end of one. My conversations with people and organizations I shift materials to are much longer, much more involved, and with much more contingencies as a result of this event, and things are better for it.</p>



<figure><a href="http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k.jpg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" data-attachment-id="5592" data-permalink="http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/5591/36430499261_7910e3d229_k" data-orig-file="http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k.jpg" data-orig-size="2048,1152" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="36430499261_7910e3d229_k" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-300x169.jpg" data-large-file="http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-1024x576.jpg" src="http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-1024x576.jpg" alt="" srcset="http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-1024x576.jpg 1024w, http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-300x169.jpg 300w, http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-768x432.jpg 768w, http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k-1536x864.jpg 1536w, http://ascii.textfiles.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/36430499261_7910e3d229_k.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>

					<hr>

        			
			        <p><mark>Categorised as:</mark> <a href="http://ascii.textfiles.com/archives/category/uncategorized" rel="category tag">Uncategorized</a> </p>
					    				  				
					<hr>

			        
				</section>

			</article>

			
<!-- You can start editing here. -->

  


	

  		</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Microsoft starts testing ads in the Windows 11 Start menu (177 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/12/24128640/microsoft-windows-11-start-menu-ads-app-recommendations</link>
            <guid>40018948</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2024 00:02:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/12/24128640/microsoft-windows-11-start-menu-ads-app-recommendations">https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/12/24128640/microsoft-windows-11-start-menu-ads-app-recommendations</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40018948">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Microsoft says it’s starting to test ads inside the Start menu on Windows 11. The software maker will use the Recommended section of the Start menu, which usually shows file recommendations, to suggest apps from the Microsoft Store.  </p><p>“This will appear only for Windows Insiders in the Beta Channel in the US and will not apply to commercial devices (devices managed by organizations),” says <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2024/04/12/announcing-windows-11-insider-preview-build-22635-3495-beta-channel/">Microsoft in a blog post</a>. </p><p>The app promotions can be disabled in the Settings section of Windows 11, but it appears that Microsoft will enable these by default. Microsoft is seeking feedback on the changes, so it’s possible the company could decide to ditch these ads in development builds of Windows 11 if there’s enough feedback that suggests they’re not going to be a popular addition.</p><div><div role="button" aria-label="Zoom" tabindex="0"><figure><div><p><span><img alt="An image of the Windows 11 start menu. 1Password is highlighted with a red box indicating that it is an ad and not currently installed." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 744px" srcset="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/376x208/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 376w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/384x212/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 384w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/415x229/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 415w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/480x265/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 480w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/540x298/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 540w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/640x353/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 640w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/750x414/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 750w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/828x457/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 828w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/1080x596/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 1080w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/1200x663/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 1200w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/1440x795/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 1440w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/1920x1060/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 1920w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/2048x1131/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 2048w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/2400x1325/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg 2400w" src="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:670x370/2400x1325/filters:focal(335x185:336x186):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25391279/Capto_Capture_2024_04_12_02_21_43_PM.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div></figure></div><div><figcaption><em>The ad is the one Microsoft highlighted with a red box.</em></figcaption> <p><cite>Image: Microsoft</cite></p></div></div><p>Microsoft started testing <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/3/15/22979251/microsoft-file-explorer-ads-windows-11-testing">ads inside the File Explorer of Windows 11</a> last year before disabling the experiment in beta versions of Windows 11. Microsoft has been experimenting with ads inside Windows for more than 10 years. There are already promotional spots&nbsp;<a href="http://www.theverge.com/2015/4/29/8514345/windows-spotlight-lock-screen-with-ads">on the Windows 10 lock screen</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="http://www.theverge.com/2016/5/16/11682164/microsoft-windows-10-promoted-apps-start-menu-anniversary-update">in the Start menu</a>, so it’s not exactly surprising to see them appear in Windows 11, too. </p><p>Now, it’s up to Windows testers to file feedback on these changes to see whether Microsoft might be forced to not include these ads on shipping versions of Windows 11. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Defeated CEOs are now conceding hybrid working is here to stay (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2024/04/12/kpmg-study-us-ceos-accept-hybrid-working-employee-return-to-office/</link>
            <guid>40018087</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 21:54:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/04/12/kpmg-study-us-ceos-accept-hybrid-working-employee-return-to-office/">https://fortune.com/2024/04/12/kpmg-study-us-ceos-accept-hybrid-working-employee-return-to-office/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40018087">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Good news for those hoping to cling on to working from home: After a year of cracking down with rigid return-to-office mandates—and instilling fear in those who upheaved their life during the pandemic—defeated CEOs are now finally accepting that hybrid working is here to stay.&nbsp;</p><div>



<p><a href="https://fortune.com/company/kpmg/" target="_blank" rel="">KPMG</a> surveyed U.S. CEOs of companies turning over at least $500 million and found that <a href="https://kpmg.com/kpmg-us/content/dam/kpmg/pdf/2024/KPMG-2024-US-CEO-Outlook-Pulse-Survey.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">just one-third expect a full return to the office</a> in the next three years.</p>



<p>So it’s official: Leaders who believe that office workers will be back at their desks five days a week in the near future are now in the small minority.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It’s a complete 360 on their stance last year, when 62% of CEOs surveyed predicted that <a href="https://fortune.com/2023/10/05/ceo-rto-kpmg-research-return-to-work-full-time-5-days/" target="_self" rel="">working from home would end by 2026.</a></p>



<p>At the time, 90% of CEOs even admitted that they were so steadfast on summoning staff back to their vertical towers that they were sweetening the pot with salary raises, promotions, and favorable assignments to those who showed face more.</p>



<p>But now, bosses are backtracking: Nearly half of CEOs have concluded that the future of work is hybrid—up from 34% last year.&nbsp;</p>



<p>What’s more, a sizable chunk of CEOs aren’t just embracing working from home on Fridays, they’re going one step further and ditching the workday altogether.</p>



<p>KPMG found that a third of CEOs are exploring the feasibility of a four-day week at their firm.</p>



<h2>Why the change of heart?</h2>



<p>Many CEOs have dedicated the last year to shaking off pandemic-era habits of working from home and calling staff back to the office, but their mandates have been met with resistance.</p>



<p>Deutsche Bank’s decision to outright <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/02/22/four-day-weekends-from-home-over-fridays-increasingly-just-another-office-day-data/" target="_self" rel="">ban staff from working at home on a Friday</a> and the following Monday has not been taken lightly by staff—a large number of its 90,000-strong workforce have reportedly <a href="https://fortune.com/europe/2024/02/27/deutsche-bank-remote-work-return-to-office-enormous-resistance/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks" target="_self" rel="">started posting critical remarks</a> on the company’s internal messaging board to make their distaste for the new set-up known.</p>



<p><a href="https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/" target="_blank" rel="">Amazon</a> is perhaps the most documented example of how ugly the RTO battle can get: Around 30,000 employees <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/amazons-hr-boss-rejects-employee-remote-work-petition-2023-3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signed a petition</a> protesting the company’s in-office mandate, and more than 1,800 <a href="https://fortune.com/2023/05/31/amazon-headquarters-workers-walkout-layoffs-return-to-office-mandate/?utm_source=search&amp;utm_medium=suggested_search&amp;utm_campaign=search_link_clicks" target="_self" rel="">pledged to walk out</a> from their jobs to take a stand.</p>



<p><a href="https://fortune.com/europe/2023/08/01/research-damaging-results-mandated-return-to-office-worse-than-we-thought-rto-remote-work-careers-leadership-gleb-tsipursky/" target="_self" rel="">Research has echoed</a> that nearly half of companies with return-to-office mandates witnessed a higher level of employee attrition than they had anticipated, and 29% of companies enforcing office returns are struggling with recruitment.</p>



<p>It perhaps explains why, as KPMG’s data shows, CEOs are now waking up to the fact that the future of work is probably the happy medium of hybrid.</p>



<p>“CEOs have realized that forcing people back into the office can only go on for so long,” Amrit Sandhar, CEO of &amp;Evolve an employee engagement consultancy tells <em>Fortune.</em> </p>



<p>“With Gen Z over the next few years making up, in some cases the majority of the workforce, how long can CEOs insist people come into the office, when people are choosing to work remotely?</p>



<p>“We are at the threshold of a new dawn and trying to hold on to past mindsets will have a direct impact on the caliber of people you attract going forward.”</p>



<p>Lewis Maleh, CEO of the global executive recruitment agency Bentley Lewis, has already witnessed a U-turn to more flexible job ads.</p>



<p>“I’ve noticed a definite rise in job postings advertising remote or hybrid work,”&nbsp; Maleh tells <em>Fortune</em>. </p>



<p>“We haven’t worked on any searches that require the candidate to be in the office five days per week in the past six months globally.”</p>



<p>“The shift demonstrates the cementing of hybrid work models, as CEOs increasingly recognize flexibility as a key factor in attracting and retaining top talent.”</p></div><p>Subscribe to CHRO Daily, our newsletter focusing on helping HR executive navigate the changing needs of the workplace. <a href="https://www.fortune.com/newsletters/chro-daily?&amp;itm_source=fortune&amp;itm_medium=article_tout&amp;itm_campaign=chro_daily" target="_self" rel="">Sign up</a> for free.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[XZ backdoor story – Initial analysis (360 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://securelist.com/xz-backdoor-story-part-1/112354/</link>
            <guid>40017310</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 20:28:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://securelist.com/xz-backdoor-story-part-1/112354/">https://securelist.com/xz-backdoor-story-part-1/112354/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40017310">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
													<p>On March 29, 2024, a single <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/03/29/4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">message</a> on the Openwall OSS-security mailing list marked an important discovery for the information security, open source and Linux communities: the discovery of a malicious backdoor in <strong>XZ</strong>. <strong>XZ </strong>is a compression utility integrated into many popular distributions of Linux.</p>
<p>The particular danger of the backdoored library lies in its use by the OpenSSH server process <strong>sshd</strong>. On several systemd-based distributions, including Ubuntu, Debian and RedHat/Fedora Linux, OpenSSH is patched to use systemd features, and as a result has a dependency on this library (note that Arch Linux and Gentoo are unaffected). The ultimate goal of the attackers was most likely to introduce a remote code execution capability to <strong>sshd</strong> that no one else could use.</p>
<p>Unlike other supply chain attacks we have seen in Node.js, <a href="https://securelist.com/two-more-malicious-python-packages-in-the-pypi/107218/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PyPI</a>, <a href="https://social.librem.one/@eighthave/112194828562355097" target="_blank" rel="noopener">FDroid</a>, and the Linux <a href="https://lore.kernel.org/lkml/20210421130105.1226686-1-gregkh@linuxfoundation.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kernel</a> that mostly consisted of atomic malicious patches, fake packages and typosquatted package names, this incident was a multi-stage operation that almost succeeded in compromising SSH servers on a global scale.</p>
<p>The backdoor in the liblzma library was introduced at two levels. The source code of the build infrastructure that generated the final packages was slightly modified (by introducing an additional file <strong>build-to-host.m4</strong>) to extract the next stage script that was hidden in a test case file (<strong>bad-3-corrupt_lzma2.xz</strong>). These scripts in turn extracted a malicious binary component from another test case file (<strong>good-large_compressed.lzma</strong>) that was linked with the legitimate library during the compilation process to be shipped to Linux repositories. Major vendors in turn shipped the malicious component in beta and experimental builds. The compromise of XZ Utils is assigned <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2024-3094" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CVE-2024–3094</a> with the maximum severity score of 10.</p>
<h2 id="the-timeline-of-events">The timeline of events</h2>
<p>2024.01.19 XZ website moved to GitHub pages by a new maintainer (<a href="https://github.com/JiaT75" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jiaT75</a>)<br>
2024.02.15 “build-to-host.m4” is <a href="https://git.tukaani.org/?p=xz.git;a=commitdiff;h=4323bc3e0c1e1d2037d5e670a3bf6633e8a3031e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">added</a> to .gitignore<br>
2024.02.23 two “test files” that contained the stages of the malicious script are <a href="https://git.tukaani.org/?p=xz.git;a=commit;h=cf44e4b7f5dfdbf8c78aef377c10f71e274f63c0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">introduced</a><br>
<u>2024.02.24 XZ 5.6.0 is released</u><br>
2024.02.26 <a href="https://git.tukaani.org/?p=xz.git;a=commitdiff;h=328c52da8a2bbb81307644efdb58db2c422d9ba7" target="_blank" rel="noopener">commit</a> in CMakeLists.txt that sabotages the <a href="https://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man7/landlock.7.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Landlock</a> security feature<br>
2024.03.04 the backdoor leads to <a href="https://bugzilla.redhat.com/show_bug.cgi?id=2267598" target="_blank" rel="noopener">issues</a> with Valgrind<br>
2024.03.09 two “test files” are updated, CRC functions are modified, Valgrind issue is “fixed”<br>
<u>2024.03.09 XZ 5.6.1 is released</u><br>
2024.03.28 bug is discovered, Debian and RedHat notified<br>
2024.03.28 Debian <a href="https://tracker.debian.org/news/1515519/accepted-xz-utils-561really545-1-source-into-unstable/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">rolls back</a> XZ 5.6.1 to 5.4.5-0.2 version<br>
2024.03.29 an email is <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/03/29/4" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published</a> on the OSS-security mailing list<br>
2024.03.29 RedHat confirms backdoored XZ was <a href="https://www.redhat.com/en/blog/urgent-security-alert-fedora-41-and-rawhide-users" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shipped</a> in Fedora Rawhide and Fedora Linux 40 beta<br>
2024.03.30 Debian <a href="https://fulda.social/@Ganneff/112184975950858403" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shuts down</a> builds and starts process to rebuild it<br>
2024.04.02 XZ main developer <a href="https://tukaani.org/xz-backdoor/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recognizes </a>the backdoor incident</p>
<h2 id="backdoored-source-distributions">Backdoored source distributions</h2>
<p><strong>xz-5.6.0</strong></p>

<p><strong>xz-5.6.1</strong></p>

<h2 id="initial-infection-analysis">Initial infection analysis</h2>
<p>The XZ git repository contains a set of test files that are used when testing the compressor/decompressor code to verify that it’s working properly. The account named Jia Tan or “<a href="https://github.com/JiaT75" target="_blank" rel="noopener">jiaT75</a>“, <a href="https://github.com/tukaani-project/xz/commit/cf44e4b7f5dfdbf8c78aef377c10f71e274f63c0" target="_blank" rel="noopener">committed</a> two test files that initially appeared harmless, but served as the bootstrap to implant backdoor.</p>
<p>The associated files were:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>bad-3-corrupt_lzma2.xz</strong> (<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/86fc2c94f8fa3938e3261d0b9eb4836be289f8ae/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">86fc2c94f8fa3938e3261d0b9eb4836be289f8ae</a>)</li>
<li><strong>good-large_compressed.lzma</strong> (<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/540c665dfcd4e5cfba5b72b4787fec4f/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">50941ad9fd99db6fca5debc3c89b3e899a9527d7</a>)</li>
</ul>
<p>These files were intended to contain shell scripts and the backdoor binary object itself. However, they were hidden within the malformed data, and the attacker knew how to properly extract them when needed.</p>
<h3>Stage 1 – The modified <strong>build-to-host</strong> script</h3>
<p>When the XZ release is ready, the official Github repository distributes the project’s source files. Initially, these releases on the repository, aside from containing the malicious test files, were harmless because they don’t get the chance to execute. However, the attacker appears to have only added the malicious code that bootstrap the infection when the releases were sourced from <strong>https://xz[.]tukaani.org</strong>, which was under the control of Jia Tan.</p>
<p>This URL is used by most distributions, and, when downloaded, it comes with a file named <strong>build-to-host.m4</strong> that contains malicious code.</p>
<p><strong>build-to-host.m4 </strong>(<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/b4dd2661a7c69e85f19216a6dbbb1664/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">c86c8f8a69c07fbec8dd650c6604bf0c9876261f</a>) is executed during the build process and executes a line of code that fixes and decompresses the first file added to the tests folder:</p>
<div id="attachment_112357"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112357" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09-1024x167.png" alt="Deobfuscated line of code in build-to-host.m4" width="1024" height="167" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09-1024x167.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09-300x49.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09-768x125.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09-740x121.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09-800x130.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145102/XZ_backdoor_analysis_09.png 1246w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112357">Deobfuscated line of code in build-to-host.m4</p></div>
<p>This line of code replaces the “broken” data from <strong>bad-3-corrupt_lzma2.xz</strong> using the <strong>tr</strong> command, and pipes the output to the <strong>xz -d</strong> command, which decompresses the data. The decompressed data contains a shell script that will be executed later using <strong>/bin/bash</strong>, triggered by this <strong>.m4</strong> file.</p>
<h3 id="stage-2-the-injected-shell-script">Stage 2 – The injected shell script</h3>
<p>The malicious script injected by the malicious <strong>.m4</strong> file verifies that it’s running on a Linux machine and also that it’s running inside the intended build process.</p>
<div id="attachment_112358"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112358" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-1024x229.png" alt="Injected script contents" width="1024" height="229" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-1024x229.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-300x67.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-768x171.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-1536x343.png 1536w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-1568x350.png 1568w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-740x165.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-1255x280.png 1255w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10-800x179.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_10.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112358">Injected script contents</p></div>
<p>To execute the next stage, it uses <strong>good-large_compressed.lzma</strong>, which is indeed compressed correctly with XZ, but contains junk data inside the decompressed data.</p>
<p>The junk data removal procedure is as follows: the <strong>eval</strong> function executes the head pipeline, with each <strong>head</strong> command either ignoring the next 1024 bytes or extracting the next 2048 or 724 bytes.</p>
<p>In total, these commands extracted <strong>33,492 </strong>bytes (<strong>2048*16 + 724 </strong>bytes). The <strong>tail</strong> command then retains the final <strong>31,265 </strong>bytes of the file and ignores the rest.</p>
<p>Then, the <strong>tr</strong> command applies a basic substitution to the output to deobfuscate it. The second XZ command decompresses the transformed bytes as a raw <strong>lzma </strong>stream, after which the result is piped into shell.</p>

<p>The last stage shell script performs many checks to ensure that it is running in the expected environment, such as whether the project is configured to use <a href="https://sourceware.org/glibc/wiki/GNU_IFUNC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IFUNC</a> (which will be discussed in the next sections).</p>
<p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13-1024x83.png" alt="" width="1024" height="83" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13-1024x83.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13-300x24.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13-768x62.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13-740x60.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13-800x65.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145253/XZ_backdoor_analysis_13.png 1110w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p>
<p>Many of the other checks performed by this stage include determining whether GCC is used for compilation or if the project contains specific files that will be used by the script later on.</p>
<p>In this stage, it extracts the backdoor binary code itself, an <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/guile/manual/html_node/Object-File-Format.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">object file</a> that is currently hidden in the same <strong>good-large_compressed.lzma</strong> file, but at a different offset.</p>
<p>The following code handles this:</p>
<div id="attachment_112360"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112360" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12-1024x160.png" alt="Partial command used by the last script stage" width="1024" height="160" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12-1024x160.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12-300x47.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12-768x120.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12-740x115.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12-800x125.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_12.png 1392w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112360">Partial command used by the last script stage</p></div>
<p>The extraction process operates through a sequence of commands, with the result of each command serving as the input for the next one. The formatted one-liner code is shown below:</p>
<div id="attachment_112361"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112361" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-1024x742.png" alt="Formatted backdoor extraction one-liner" width="1024" height="742" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-1024x742.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-300x217.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-768x556.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-483x350.png 483w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-740x536.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-387x280.png 387w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04-800x580.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145406/XZ_backdoor_analysis_04.png 1397w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112361">Formatted backdoor extraction one-liner</p></div>
<p>Initially, the file <strong>good-large_compressed.lzma</strong> is extracted using the <strong>XZ</strong> tool itself. The subsequent steps involve calling a chain of <strong>head</strong> calls with the “<strong>eval $i”</strong> function (same as the stage 3 extraction).</p>
<p>Then a custom RC4-like algorithm is used to decrypt the binary data, which contains another compressed file. This compressed file is also extracted using the XZ utility. The script then removes some bytes from the beginning of the decompressed data using predefined values and saves the result to disk as <strong>liblzma_la-crc64-fast.o</strong>, which is the backdoor file used in the linking process.</p>
<p>Finally, the script modifies the function <strong>is_arch_extension_supported</strong> from the <strong>crc_x86_clmul.h</strong> file in <strong>liblzma</strong>, to replace the call to the <strong>__get_cpuid</strong> function with <strong>_get_cpuid</strong>, removing one underscore character.</p>
<p>This modification allows it to be linked into the library (we’ll discuss this in more detail in the next section). The whole build infection chain can be summarized in the following scheme:</p>
<p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-1024x531.png" alt="" width="1024" height="531" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-1024x531.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-300x156.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-768x398.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-1536x796.png 1536w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-675x350.png 675w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-740x384.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-540x280.png 540w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14-800x415.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145446/XZ_backdoor_analysis_14.png 1645w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p>
<h2 id="binary-backdoor-analysis">Binary backdoor analysis</h2>
<h3 id="a-stealth-loading-scenario">A stealth loading scenario</h3>
<p>In the original XZ code, there are two special functions used to calculate the CRC of the given data: <strong>lzma_crc32 </strong>and <strong>lzma_crc64</strong>. Both of these functions are stored in the ELF symbol table with type <a href="https://sourceware.org/glibc/wiki/GNU_IFUNC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IFUNC</a>, a feature provided by the GNU C Library (GLIBC). IFUNC allows developers to dynamically select the correct function to use. This selection takes place when the dynamic linker loads the shared library.</p>
<p>The reason XZ uses this is that it allows for determining whether an optimized version of the <strong>lzma_crcX </strong>function should be used or not. The optimized version requires special features from modern processors (CLMUL, SSSE3, SSE4.1). These special features need to be verified by issuing the <strong>cpuid </strong>instruction, which is called using the <a href="https://github.com/gcc-mirror/gcc/blob/6f9ba3ea55477cf1bd3d37e40ad116150c06a75e/gcc/config/i386/cpuid.h#L324" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>__get_cpuid</strong></a> wrapper/intrinsic provided by GLIBC, and it’s at this point the backdoor takes advantage to load itself.</p>
<p>The backdoor is stored as an object file, and its primary goal is to be linked to the main executable during compilation. The object file contains the <strong>_get_cpuid</strong> symbol, as the injected shell scripts remove one underscore symbol from the original source code, which means that when the code calls <strong>_get_cpuid</strong>, it actually calls the backdoor’s version of it.</p>
<div id="attachment_112363"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112363" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-1024x392.png" alt="Backdoor code entry point" width="1024" height="392" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-1024x392.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-300x115.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-768x294.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-915x350.png 915w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-740x283.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-732x280.png 732w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07-800x306.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145548/XZ_backdoor_analysis_07.png 1302w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112363">Backdoor code entry point</p></div>
<h3 id="backdoor-code-analysis">Backdoor code analysis</h3>
<p>The initial backdoor code is invoked twice, as both <strong>lzma_crc32</strong> and <strong>lzma_crc64</strong> use the same modified function (<strong>_get_cpuid</strong>). To ensure control over this, a simple counter is created to verify that the code has already been executed. The actual malicious activity starts when the <strong>lzma_crc64</strong> IFUNC invokes <strong>_get_cpuid</strong>, sees the counter value 1 indicating that that the function has already been accessed, and initiates one final step to redirect to the true entry point of this malware.</p>
<div id="attachment_112364"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112364" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-854x1024.png" alt="Backdoor initialization" width="854" height="1024" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-854x1024.png 854w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-250x300.png 250w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-768x921.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-168x200.png 168w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-292x350.png 292w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-740x887.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-233x280.png 233w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01-751x900.png 751w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145625/XZ_backdoor_analysis_01.png 964w" sizes="(max-width: 854px) 100vw, 854px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112364">Backdoor initialization</p></div>
<p>To initialize the malicious code, the backdoor first initializes a couple of structures that hold core information about the current running process. Primarily, it locates the Global Offset Table (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_Offset_Table">GOT</a>) address using hardcoded offsets, and uses this information to find the <strong>cpuid</strong> pointer inside it.</p>
<div id="attachment_112365"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112365" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-1024x381.png" alt="GOT modification code" width="1024" height="381" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-1024x381.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-300x112.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-768x286.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-1536x572.png 1536w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-940x350.png 940w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-740x276.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-752x280.png 752w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03-800x298.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11145711/XZ_backdoor_analysis_03.png 1678w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112365">GOT modification code</p></div>
<p>The GOT contains the offsets of symbols, including the <strong>cpuid</strong> wrapper. The backdoor then swaps the pointers to the main malware function, and calls it as if it were calling <strong>cpuid</strong>.</p>
<h3 id="core-behavior">Core behavior</h3>
<p>The main goal of the backdoor is to successfully hook specific functions that will allow it to monitor every connection to the infected machine. The targeted functions include:</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><strong>Targeted function</strong></td>
<td><strong>Description</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>RSA_public_decrypt</strong></td>
<td>Used by <strong>libcrypto</strong> to decrypt a ciphertext signed by a private key</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>EVP_PKEY_set1_RSA</strong></td>
<td>Used by <strong>libcrypto</strong> to set the RSA key of a given context</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>RSA_get0_key</strong></td>
<td>Used by <strong>libcrypto</strong> to retrieve an RSA key</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>However, hooking all these functions is not a simple and straightforward task for the backdoor. It involves accessing many internal structures and manipulating process-specific structures until it achieves its goal, and it also needs to be as stealthy as possible, which means that the malicious code contains multiple checks to avoid being analyzed.</p>
<h3 id="execution-environment-check">Execution environment check</h3>
<p>It first parses <strong>ld-linux</strong> (dynamic linker), which is primarily responsible for dynamically resolving symbol addresses in memory. It also extracts various information about the environment and verifies that the current process the backdoor is running in matches its execution criteria, which are:</p>
<ul>
<li>The current process is <strong>/usr/bin/sshd</strong></li>
<li>Check if the kill switch is present</li>
</ul>
<p>It extracts the name of the current process from <strong>argv[0]</strong> and also parses all the process environment variables to see if any of them are present in its internal string table. If a match is found, or the process is not <strong>sshd</strong>, the malware halts its execution.</p>
<div id="attachment_112366"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112366" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-1024x864.png" alt="Process environment check" width="1024" height="864" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-1024x864.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-300x253.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-768x648.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-415x350.png 415w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-740x624.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-332x280.png 332w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15-800x675.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150105/XZ_backdoor_analysis_15.png 1299w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112366">Process environment check</p></div>
<p>The only variable inside its own table is <strong>yolAbejyiejuvnup=Evjtgvsh5okmkAvj</strong>, which in this context serves as a <strong>kill switch</strong>.</p>
<h3 id="the-trie-structure">The trie structure</h3>
<p>One of the distinctive features of the backdoor is the use of a single <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trie" target="_blank" rel="noopener">trie</a> structure for string operations. Instead of directly comparing strings or using string hashes to match a particular constant (for example, the name of a library function), the code performs a trie lookup, and checks if the result is equal to a certain constant number. For example, the magic value for the ELF header results in the trie returning <strong>0x300</strong>, and the name of the <strong>system</strong> function is matched with a return value of <strong>0x9F8</strong>. Trie is not just used for comparisons: certain functions that use pointers to strings (for example, <strong>ssh-2.0</strong>) search for these strings in the host binary using the trie, so there will be no suspicious data in the backdoor’s body.</p>
<p>The implementation of the trie uses 16-byte bitmasks, each half corresponding to the byte input ranges <strong>0x00-0x3F</strong> and <strong>0x40-0x7F</strong>, and 2-byte trie leaf nodes, 3 bits of which are flags (direction, termination) and the rest is reserved for the value (or the location of the next node).</p>
<div id="attachment_112367"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_16.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112367" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_16.png" alt="Part of the trie lookup function that performs the bitmap match" width="648" height="275" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_16.png 648w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150150/XZ_backdoor_analysis_16-300x127.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 648px) 100vw, 648px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112367">Part of the trie lookup function that performs the bitmap match</p></div>
<h3 id="symbol-resolver">Symbol resolver</h3>
<p>There are at least three symbol resolver-related routines used by the backdoor to locate the ELF Symbol structure, which holds information such as the symbol name and its offset. All symbol resolver functions receive a key to be searched in the trie.</p>
<div id="attachment_112368"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112368" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05-1024x195.png" alt="Symbol resolver example" width="1024" height="195" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05-1024x195.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05-300x57.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05-768x146.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05-740x141.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05-800x153.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150247/XZ_backdoor_analysis_05.png 1028w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112368">Symbol resolver example</p></div>
<p>One of the backdoor resolver functions iterates through all symbols and verifies which one has the desired key. If it is found, it returns the <strong>Elf64_Sym</strong> structure, which will later be used to populate an internal structure of the backdoor that holds all the necessary function pointers. This process is similar to that commonly seen in Windows threats with API hashing routines.</p>
<p>The backdoor searches many functions from the libcrypto (OpenSSL) library, as these will be used in later encryption routines. It also keeps track of how many functions it was able to find and resolve; this determines whether it is executing properly or should stop.</p>
<p>Another interesting symbol resolver abuses the <strong>lzma_alloc</strong> function, which is part of the liblzma library itself. This function serves as a helper for developers to allocate memory efficiently using the default allocator (malloc) or a custom one. In the case of the XZ backdoor, this function is abused to make use of a fake allocator. In reality, it functions as another symbol resolver. The parameter intended for “allocation size” is, in fact, the symbol key inside the trie. This trick is meant to complicate backdoor analysis.</p>
<div id="attachment_112369"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112369" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06.png" alt="Symbol resolver using a fake allocator structure" width="997" height="98" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06.png 997w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06-300x29.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06-768x75.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06-990x98.png 990w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06-740x73.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150335/XZ_backdoor_analysis_06-800x79.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 997px) 100vw, 997px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112369">Symbol resolver using a fake allocator structure</p></div>
<p>The backdoor dynamically resolves its symbols while executing; it doesn’t necessarily do so all at once or only when it needs to use them. The resolved symbols/functions range from legitimate OpenSSL functions to functions such as <strong>system</strong>, which is used to execute commands on the machine.</p>
<h3 id="the-symbind-hook">The Symbind hook</h3>
<p>As mentioned earlier, the primary objective of the backdoor initialization is to successfully hook functions. To do so, the backdoor makes use of <a href="https://www.man7.org/linux/man-pages/man7/rtld-audit.7.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>rtdl-audit</strong></a>, a feature of the dynamic linker that enables the creation of custom shared libraries to be notified when certain events occur within the linker, such as symbol resolution. In a typical scenario, a developer would create a shared library following the <a href="https://www.man7.org/linux/man-pages/man7/rtld-audit.7.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>rtdl-audit</strong> manual</a>. However, the XZ backdoor opts to perform a runtime patch on the already registered (default) interfaces loaded in memory, thereby hijacking the symbol-resolving routine.</p>
<div id="attachment_112370"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112370" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11-1024x194.png" alt="dl-audit runtime patch" width="1024" height="194" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11-1024x194.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11-300x57.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11-768x146.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11-740x141.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11-800x152.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150425/XZ_backdoor_analysis_11.png 1385w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112370">dl-audit runtime patch</p></div>
<p>The maliciously crafted structure <a href="https://elixir.bootlin.com/glibc/latest/source/sysdeps/generic/ldsodefs.h#L237" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>audit_iface</strong></a>, stored in the <strong>dl_audit</strong> global variable within the dynamic linker’s memory area, contains the <strong>symbind64</strong> callback address, which is invoked by the dynamic linker. It sends all the symbol information to the backdoor control, which is then used to obtain a malicious address for the target functions, thus achieving hooking.</p>
<div id="attachment_112371"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112371" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-1024x308.png" alt="Hooking placement inside the Symbind modified callback" width="1024" height="308" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-1024x308.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-300x90.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-768x231.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-740x222.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-932x280.png 932w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08-800x240.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150507/XZ_backdoor_analysis_08.png 1085w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112371">Hooking placement inside the Symbind modified callback</p></div>
<p>The addresses for <strong>dl_audit</strong> and <strong>dl_naudit</strong>, which holds the number of audit interfaces available, are obtained by disassembling both the <strong>dl_main</strong> and <strong>dl_audit_symbind_alt</strong> functions. The backdoor contains an internal minimalistic <strong>disassembler </strong>used for instruction decoding. It makes extensive use of it, especially when hunting for specific values like the <strong>*audit</strong> addresses.</p>
<div id="attachment_112372"><p><a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-112372" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-1024x492.png" alt="dl_naudit hunting code" width="1024" height="492" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-1024x492.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-300x144.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-768x369.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-728x350.png 728w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-740x356.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-582x280.png 582w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02-800x385.png 800w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2024/04/11150611/XZ_backdoor_analysis_02.png 1504w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-112372">dl_naudit hunting code</p></div>
<p>The <strong>dl_naudit</strong> address is found by one of the <strong>mov </strong>instructions within the <strong>dl_main</strong> function code that accesses it. With that information, the backdoor hunts for access to a memory address and saves it.</p>
<p>It also verifies if the memory address acquired is the same address as the one accessed by the <strong>dl_audit_symbind_alt</strong> function on a given offset. This allows it to safely assume that it has indeed found the correct address. After it finds the <strong>dl_naudit </strong>address, it can easily calculate where <strong>dl_audit </strong>is, since the two are stored next to each other in memory.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In this article, we covered the entire process of backdooring <strong>liblzma (XZ)</strong>, and delved into a detailed analysis of the binary backdoor code, up to achieving its principal goal: hooking.</p>
<p>It’s evident that this backdoor is highly complex and employs sophisticated methods to evade detection. These include the multi-stage implantation in the <strong>XZ</strong> repository, as well as the complex code contained within the binary itself.</p>
<p>There is still much more to explore about the backdoor’s internals, which is why we have decided to present this as <strong>Part I</strong> of the <strong>XZ</strong> backdoor series.</p>
<p>Kaspersky products detect malicious objects related to the attack as <strong>HEUR:Trojan.Script.XZ</strong> and <strong>Trojan.Shell.XZ</strong>. In addition, Kaspersky Endpoint Security for Linux detects malicious code in SSHD process memory as <strong>MEM:Trojan.Linux.XZ</strong> (as part of the Critical Areas Scan task).</p>
<h2 id="indicators-of-compromise">Indicators of compromise</h2>
<h3 id="yara-rules">Yara rules</h3>

		<div id="crayon-6618f13a6f6f7190783011" data-settings=" minimize scroll-mouseover">
				<table>
					<tbody><tr>
				<td data-settings="hide">
					
				</td>
						<td><div><p><span>rule</span><span> </span><span>liblzma_get_cpuid_function</span><span> </span><span>{</span></p><p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>meta</span><span>:</span></p><p><span>	</span><span>description</span><span> </span>=<span> </span><span>"Rule to find the malicious get_cpuid function CVE-2024-3094"</span></p><p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span><span>author</span><span> </span>=<span> </span><span>"Kaspersky Lab"</span></p><p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp; </span><span>strings</span><span>:</span></p><p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span><span>$</span><span>a</span><span> </span>=<span> </span><span>{</span><span> </span><span>F3</span><span> </span><span>0F</span><span> </span><span>1E</span><span> </span><span>FA</span><span> </span><span>55</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>F5</span><span> </span><span>4C</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>CE</span><span> </span><span>53</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>FB</span><span> </span><span>81</span><span> </span><span>E7</span><span> </span><span>00</span><span> </span><span>00</span><span> </span><span>00</span><span> </span><span>80</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>83</span><span> </span><span>EC</span><span> </span><span>28</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>54</span><span> </span><span>24</span><span> </span><span>18</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>4C</span><span> </span><span>24</span><span> </span><span>10</span><span> </span><span>4C</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>44</span><span> </span><span>24</span><span> </span><span>08</span><span> </span><span>E8</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>85</span><span> </span><span>C0</span><span> </span><span>74</span><span> </span><span>27</span><span> </span><span>39</span><span> </span><span>D8</span><span> </span><span>72</span><span> </span><span>23</span><span> </span><span>4C</span><span> </span><span>8B</span><span> </span><span>44</span><span> </span><span>24</span><span> </span><span>08</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>8B</span><span> </span><span>4C</span><span> </span><span>24</span><span> </span><span>10</span><span> </span><span>45</span><span> </span><span>31</span><span> </span><span>C9</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>EE</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>8B</span><span> </span><span>54</span><span> </span><span>24</span><span> </span><span>18</span><span> </span><span>89</span><span> </span><span>DF </span><span>E8</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>?</span><span>?</span><span> </span><span>B8</span><span> </span><span>01</span><span> </span><span>00</span><span> </span><span>00</span><span> </span><span>00</span><span> </span><span>EB</span><span> </span><span>02</span><span> </span><span>31</span><span> </span><span>C0</span><span> </span><span>48</span><span> </span><span>83</span><span> </span><span>C4</span><span> </span><span>28</span><span> </span><span>5B</span><span> </span><span>5D</span><span> </span><span>C3</span><span> </span><span>}</span><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span><span>condition</span><span>:</span></p><p><span>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</span><span>$</span><span>a</span></p><p><span>}</span></p></div></td>
					</tr>
				</tbody></table>
			</div>
<h3 id="known-backdoored-libraries">Known backdoored libraries</h3>
<p><strong>Debian Sid liblzma.so.5.6.0</strong><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/4f0cf1d2a2d44b75079b3ea5ed28fe54/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">4f0cf1d2a2d44b75079b3ea5ed28fe54</a><br>
72e8163734d586b6360b24167a3aff2a3c961efb<br>
319feb5a9cddd81955d915b5632b4a5f8f9080281fb46e2f6d69d53f693c23ae</p>
<p><strong>Debian Sid liblzma.so.5.6.1</strong><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/53d82bb511b71a5d4794cf2d8a2072c1/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">53d82bb511b71a5d4794cf2d8a2072c1</a><br>
8a75968834fc11ba774d7bbdc566d272ff45476c<br>
605861f833fc181c7cdcabd5577ddb8989bea332648a8f498b4eef89b8f85ad4</p>
<p><strong>Related files</strong><br>
d302c6cb2fa1c03c710fa5285651530f, liblzma.so.5<br>
4f0cf1d2a2d44b75079b3ea5ed28fe54, liblzma.so.5.6.0<br>
153df9727a2729879a26c1995007ffbc, liblzma.so.5.6.0.patch<br>
53d82bb511b71a5d4794cf2d8a2072c1, liblzma.so.5.6.1<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/212ffa0b24bb7d749532425a46764433/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">212ffa0b24bb7d749532425a46764433</a>, liblzma_la-crc64-fast.o</p>
<p><strong>Analyzed artefacts</strong><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/86fc2c94f8fa3938e3261d0b9eb4836be289f8ae/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">35028f4b5c6673d6f2e1a80f02944fb2</a>, bad-3-corrupt_lzma2.xz<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/b4dd2661a7c69e85f19216a6dbbb1664/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">b4dd2661a7c69e85f19216a6dbbb1664</a>, build-to-host.m4<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/540c665dfcd4e5cfba5b72b4787fec4f/?utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank" rel="noopener">540c665dfcd4e5cfba5b72b4787fec4f</a>, good-large_compressed.lzma</p>
												</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[House Votes to Extend–and Expand–A Major US Spy Program (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/house-section-702-vote/</link>
            <guid>40017199</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 20:18:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/house-section-702-vote/">https://www.wired.com/story/house-section-702-vote/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40017199">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>A controversial US <a href="https://www.wired.com/live/section-702-reauthorization-congress-2024/?id=6615b9e20bc16967abadab74">wiretap program</a> days from expiration cleared a major hurdle on its way to being reauthorized.</p><p>After months of delays, false starts, and interventions by lawmakers working to preserve and expand the US intelligence community’s spy powers, the House of Representatives voted on Friday to extend Section 702 of the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Act (FISA) for two years.</p><p>Legislation extending the program—controversial for being abused by the government—passed in the House in a <a href="https://clerk.house.gov/Votes/2024119">273–147 vote</a>. The Senate has yet to pass its own bill.</p><p>Section 702 permits the US government to wiretap communications between Americans and foreigners overseas. Hundreds of millions of calls, texts, and emails are intercepted by government spies each with the “compelled assistance” of US communications providers.</p><p>The government may strictly target foreigners believed to possess “foreign intelligence information,” but it also eavesdrops on the conversations of an untold number of Americans each year. (The government claims it is impossible to determine how many Americans get swept up by the program.) The government argues that Americans are not themselves being targeted and thus the wiretaps are legal. Nevertheless, their calls, texts, and emails may be stored by the government for years, and can later be accessed by law enforcement without a judge’s permission.</p><p>The House bill also dramatically expands the statutory definition for communication service providers, something FISA experts, <a data-offer-url="https://www.zwillgen.com/law-enforcement/fisa-702-reauthorization-amendments-second-time-not-charm/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.zwillgen.com/law-enforcement/fisa-702-reauthorization-amendments-second-time-not-charm/&quot;}" href="https://www.zwillgen.com/law-enforcement/fisa-702-reauthorization-amendments-second-time-not-charm/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">including Marc Zwillinger</a>—one of the few people to advise the Foreign Intelligence Surveillance Court (FISC)—have publicly warned against.</p><p>“Anti-reformers not only are refusing common-sense reforms to FISA, they’re pushing for a major expansion of warrantless spying on Americans,” US senator Ron Wyden tells WIRED. “Their amendment would force your cable guy to be a government spy and assist in monitoring Americans’ communications without a warrant.”</p><p>The FBI’s <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/national-security/2023/05/19/fbi-digital-surveillance-misuse-jan6-blm/">track record of abusing the program</a> kicked off a rare détente last fall between progressive Democrats and pro-Trump Republicans—both bothered equally by the FBI’s targeting of activists, journalists, and <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/darin-lahood-fbi-backdoor-search/">a sitting member of Congress</a>. But in a major victory for the Biden administration, House members voted down an amendment earlier in the day that would’ve imposed new warrant requirements on federal agencies accessing Americans’ 702 data.</p><p>“Many members who tanked this vote have long histories of voting for this specific privacy protection,” says Sean Vitka, policy director at the civil-liberties-focused nonprofit Demand Progress, “including former speaker Pelosi, Representative Lieu, and Representative Neguse.”</p><p>The warrant amendment was passed earlier this year by the House Judiciary Committee, whose long-held jurisdiction over FISA has been challenged by friends of the intelligence community. Analysis by the Brennan Center this week found that 80 percent of the base text of the FISA reauthorization bill had been authored by intelligence committee members.</p><p>“Three million Americans' data was searched in this database of information,” says Representative Jim Jordan, chair of the House Judiciary Committee. “The FBI wasn't even following its own rules when they conducted those searches. That's why we need a warrant.”</p><p>Representative Mike Turner, who chairs the House Intelligence Committee, campaigned alongside top spy agency officials for months to defeat the warrant amendment, arguing they’d cost the bureau precious time and impede national security investigations. The communications are legally collected and already in the government's possession, Turner argued; no further approval should be required to inspect them.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>“The United States is at its greatest risk of terrorism in more than a decade following the horrific October 7th attack on Israel, and the [intelligence community] must focus attention and resources on that threat while continuing to stay ahead of China,” Turner and Jim Himes, the top Democrat on the House Intelligence Committee, said in a joint statement after the vote, adding that 702 remains one of the country's most effective national security tools.</p><p>“It allows the United States to counter our adversaries, like China and Russia, thwart potential terrorist attacks from ISIS, Al-Qaeda, Hamas, and Hezbollah, and disrupt international drug cartels who are looking to smuggle fentanyl into our nation,” they said.</p><p>The FBI introduced a slate of new internal policies to clamp down on the abuse itself, changes that the Biden administration argues are sufficient to ward off future abuse. Knowingly searching the database for information about Americans requires analysts—who must now submit to annual training sessions—to seek approval from higher up the chain of command than before. Running batch queries targeting Americans’ communications now requires a consultation with a government attorney.</p><p>While opposing the search warrants, Turner backed a ban on searches of 702 data for criminal cases that lack any foreign element. While that amendment has been welcomed by members on both sides of the issue, privacy hawks say the ban is not quite the major reform that Turner has proclaimed. Data on the program made public by the FISC suggests the ban will in reality affect less than a handful of cases each year.</p><p>Critics of the program say that relying on the FBI to internally police against its own constitutional violations is a tactic that has failed in the past, and that the bureau can no longer be trusted not to spy on Americans without cause.</p><p>“Section 702 has been abused under presidents from both political parties, and it has been used to unlawfully surveil the communications of Americans across the political spectrum,” says Kia Hamadanchy, senior policy counsel at the American Civil Liberties Union. “The Senate must add a warrant requirement and rein in this out-of-control government spying.”</p><p>Judiciary members had also sought to include an amendment banning the government from buying Americans' geolocation data from private companies. At Turner’s behest, House speaker Mike Johnson killed the amendment earlier in the week.</p><p>The US Supreme Court has recognized geolocation data as protected from seizure by the “probable cause” standard. Rather than begin applying for warrants, the government has circumvented the ruling in many cases, buying up GPS data from companies that consumers largely believe are tracking them purely for advertising purposes.</p><p>“They’re buying data. That’s what they’re doing,” says Warren Davidson, a Republican congressperson from Ohio. “They’re structuring markets to collect the data and they’re circumventing the Fourth Amendment. We need to turn that off.”</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Show HN: Mazelit - My wife and I released our first game (456 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40017180</link>
            <guid>40017180</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 20:16:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40017180">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Hey folks,</p><p>About a year ago my wife and I, both closing in on 40, quit our jobs at Red Hat to start a games company and learn game development. Many things happened along the road, and about a week ago we released our first (small) game on Steam.</p><p><a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/2816120/Mazelit/" rel="nofollow">https://store.steampowered.com/app/2816120/Mazelit/</a></p><p>The demo is free to play up to level 8 (the final game plays up to level 80) and we'd appreciate any feedback you have, whether it's for the store page or the game itself.</p><p>We made the game in Godot 4.2 in roughly 3 months and I was working full time next to it. Since we ran into a bunch of roadblocks, we decided to also offer the entire source code up as a DLC in case someone wants to go look how we implemented the game, mod the game, or compile it for a different platform. The only thing we can't redistribute with the game code is the Steamworks SDK, which is available for download from Steam. (The game minus integration is fully runnable without the SDK, though.)</p><p>Cheers and happy weekend!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Green's Dictionary of Slang (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://greensdictofslang.com/</link>
            <guid>40016888</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 19:45:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://greensdictofslang.com/">https://greensdictofslang.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40016888">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<h2>Five hundred years of the vulgar&nbsp;tongue</h2>

<p>‘Quite simply the best historical dictionary of English slang there is, ever has been […] or&nbsp;is&nbsp;ever&nbsp;likely to&nbsp;be’​ —&nbsp;<cite>Journal&nbsp;of&nbsp;English&nbsp;Language&nbsp;and&nbsp;Linguistics</cite>

</p>

<p><small><a href="https://greensdictofslang.com/search/advanced">Advanced search</a></small>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ford's battery flagship socked by mold sickness, workers say (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://labornotes.org/2024/02/fords-battery-flagship-socked-mold-sickness-workers-say</link>
            <guid>40016243</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 18:38:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://labornotes.org/2024/02/fords-battery-flagship-socked-mold-sickness-workers-say">https://labornotes.org/2024/02/fords-battery-flagship-socked-mold-sickness-workers-say</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40016243">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div property="content:encoded"><p>The smell of mold hit James “Lucky” Dugan the moment he walked into the plant.</p>
<p>Last fall, Dugan was one of thousands of union construction workers to arrive in small-town Glendale, Kentucky, to build a vast factory for Ford and SK On, a South Korean company. The plant, when completed, will make batteries for nearly a million electric pickup trucks each year. </p>
<p>When Dugan walked in, huge wooden boxes containing battery-making machines, largely shipped from overseas, were laid across the mile-long factory floor. Black streaks on those wooden boxes, plus the smell, immediately raised alarm bells for workers. But for months, those concerns were met with little remedy from the contractors hired by BlueOval to oversee construction. </p>
<p>Dugan and scores of others now believe they are in the midst of a health crisis at the site. “We don’t get sick pay,” Dugan said. “You’re sick, you’re out of luck.”</p>
<p>The BlueOval SK Battery Park, billed to open in 2025, is a banner project for President Joe Biden’s Inflation Reduction Act, a program of public subsidies and financing to companies moving away from fossil fuels. The Department of Energy has pledged to support the construction of three BlueOval plants in Tennessee and Kentucky with a $9.2 billion low-cost loan. </p>
<p>But under all the high-tech green fanfare, several construction workers, including some who wished to be anonymous, say the site has been gripped by mold and respiratory illness—medieval hazards that workers feel managers neglected in the pressure to quickly open the plant. </p>

<p>Jason Shaffer, a fellow member with Dugan of the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers, was tasked with setting electrical wiring right above laborers breaking down wooden crates. He believes that mold exposure led to the illness that knocked him out of work for over a week. </p>
<p>“Three nights ago, I couldn’t get air in my lungs," Shaffer said in early February. “I was seeing fireflies, coughing up chunks like white leather all night, crawling across the floor.” A nearby clinic diagnosed Shaffer with a bacterial infection of the lungs, but he has yet to get a diagnosis and care for his mold exposure. </p>
<p>Amid contractor companies’ rush to build the plant for Ford, many have required their union workers to build on 12-hour shifts, seven days a week. Despite months of worker concerns, managers waited until early February to take basic precautions against the mold—precautions that might slow construction. </p>
<p>Three months after workers first brought their complaints to management, the Kentucky Education and Labor Cabinet is now investigating the issue. That state agency, along with managers at BlueOval and two contracting companies, did not respond to requests for comment. But the president of an electrical contractor at BlueOval, in an email to a site manager which workers obtained and shared on Facebook, wrote he considers it “inevitable” that contractors will finally shut down the site for a mold cleanup for “most of March.”  </p>
<p>The start of this Kentucky green jobs boom reminds Shaffer of what workers faced in the years before unions: “It’s production supersedes all, even life.”</p>
<h3>HIGH-TECH, OLD FOE</h3>
<p>Since construction began on the Kentucky BlueOval factory in early 2022, workers have raised safety issues. </p>
<p>Electrical workers complained to foremen about the scarce, unheated outdoor portajohns that contractors often left uncleaned and overflowing. The day before a state safety agency inspection last month, Shaffer says, contractors rolled in new portajohns. Another worker sent extensive photos to management of structural concerns in the building, where he had circled joints and supports he considered deeply unsafe. </p>
<p>The building structure was largely in place by spring 2023. Soon after, workers say the sub-contractor Lesco began directing laborers to haul the heavy equipment crates inside and break them down on the factory floor.</p>
<p>Although Shaffer raised concerns about the black streaks and smell from the boxes early in the fall, contractors didn’t shift procedure. In November, with a cold and wet winter rolling in, the general contractor Abel decided to close the huge bay doors on the building, which had previously helped keep the area ventilated.</p>
<h3>MOUNTING ILLNESSES</h3>
<p>That’s when workers say they started to fall sick with respiratory illnesses that kept coming back. At least a few have been diagnosed with Covid or flu. But others who are sick said they have tested negative for those viruses, while struggling to get mold tests. Far from their homes in this sparse stretch of Kentucky, on breaks between marathon shifts, many have struggled to get health care at all. </p>
<p>In December, Dugan drove to a clinic and a distant hospital where he was “told I had the flu, then told I had a pulmonary condition. Finally I had to go to the ER in an ambulance, I couldn’t breathe, and got an X ray, which found something in my lungs.”</p>
<p>Worker complaints piled up until, on December 8, Abel management hired the firm Environmental Testing &amp; Consulting of Kentucky to take “limited samples” for mold. Their report, sent to Abel less than one week later, found seven types of mold inside the wooden crates, including three in “heavy” concentrations. It also noted an “intense mold odor” inside the containers. </p>
<p>To limit exposure, the report included a recommendation for handling the wooden boxes: “DO NOT PUT INSIDE.”</p>
<p>Workers say they first saw the report in early January, and Lesco management continued to bring crates inside and break them down there until early February. In that time, Shaffer said, another 15 workers he knows on site have been ill. “Basically everybody I know on the job says they’ve been sick repeatedly since they started here.” An electrical worker, who wanted to remain anonymous due to concerns about his employment, said he knew 10 co-workers who had taken mold spit tests in recent weeks, with five returning positive. </p>
<h3> ‘SLIGHT ODOR’</h3>
<p>A January 19 notice from Abel addresses the mold concerns but seems to downplay the situation, casting the odor as “slight” and stating that reports by two environmental testing agencies found the mold to be non-hazardous. The company instructed workers with pre-existing conditions or those who are “overly sensitive to molds/dust” to wear a disposable mask. </p>
<p>Paula Schenck, environmental specialist at the University of Connecticut, said that mold exposure, particularly indoors and over a long period of time, could cause health issues. </p>
<p>“Moldy smells and evidence of water damage does correlate with respiratory symptoms in some people, irrespective of what sampling you do,” she said, noting that anyone who thinks they are having mold-induced respiratory issues should see their doctor. “Equally important, the moldy smell is an indication that there are other things—dust mites, critters, bacteria. There’s a whole biological soup that can then be aerosolized that can cause respiratory symptoms.”</p>
<p>Schenck cautioned that workers’ positive mold tests could only prove they’d been exposed, not that mold was causing their illness. But the confirmed presence of mold on-site, she said, indicated the need for serious precautions.</p>
<p>With over a 1,000 electrical workers on the BlueOval site, many spread the word about mounting illnesses on their breaks and over Facebook. Dugan organized a weekly “Brotherhood Night” for IBEW members to gather at a bar or restaurant. Recently, that gathering became a fundraiser to help the family members of “sparkies” laid out by illness, or who needed car repairs to move to a new job. </p>
<p>Although Dugan, Shaffer, and other members say their union stewards on site helped press their concerns to management, they say that local and international IBEW officers who visited the facility scoffed at their concerns. Dugan says a local officer refused to file a grievance on his behalf about the mold in January. One worker requested to stay anonymous out of concern that union officials might withhold his future job placements if he spoke out. Officers with the IBEW local and district did not return requests for comment.</p>
<p>While the federal Occupational Safety and Health Administration has no specific standard for mold, Debbie Berkowitz, former OSHA chief of staff and fellow at Georgetown University’s Kalmanovitz Initiative, said that OSHA could still cite employers for failing to protect workers’ health. OSHA recommends that workers handling mold-contaminated materials be provided with an N-95 mask, at a minimum.</p>
<p>Kentucky, however, runs its own worker safety program—one that is notorious for taking a more lenient and pro-industry approach to enforcement than OSHA. The state’s labor cabinet is now <a href="https://www.wdrb.com/news/business/mold-rampant-at-fords-kentucky-ev-battery-site-workers-say/article_5111bbfe-c14f-11ee-8658-03bf99040de7.html">investigating</a> the situation and visited the construction site in late January after receiving complaints from workers.  </p>
<p><a href="https://www.osha.gov/ords/imis/establishment.search?p_logger=1&amp;establishment=&amp;State=KY&amp;officetype=all&amp;Office=all&amp;sitezip=42740&amp;p_case=all&amp;p_violations_exist=all&amp;startmonth=02&amp;startday=06&amp;startyear=2019&amp;endmonth=02&amp;endday=06&amp;endyear=2024">Records show</a> that, in the past 11 months, the Kentucky agency has opened 12 investigations into contractors over health or safety complaints at the BlueOval site. Half of those cases were closed without any penalty or finding of wrongdoing, and at least two were accidents that resulted in the companies changing procedures; the other six investigations are still ongoing.</p>
<p>Penalties for violations in Kentucky are lower than at the federal level, and the state will only accept complaints from the workers themselves, meaning a wealth of non-employee complaints go ignored. In 2018, the Kentucky Center for Investigative Reporting <a href="https://publicintegrity.org/inequality-poverty-opportunity/workers-rights/fatal-flaws-how-kentucky-fails-its-workers/">found</a> that the agency had “failed to properly investigate nearly every single worksite death in two years,” and OSHA’s audit that year found that the state-run agency was investigating fewer workplaces.</p>
<p>On February 1, local TV channel WDRB aired a story about worker mold concerns and illnesses at the BlueOval site. In the days after, Shaffer says, Abel management finally started making changes. “They’re handing out masks, trying to get more people to wear them. They say they’re going to bring in a third party contractor to open the boxes outside.” A notice from Abel dated February 3 says that the company will start providing workers with suits, goggles, dust masks, and gloves, as well as spraying the wooden crates with a bleach solution.</p>
<p>But according to the Environmental Testing &amp; Consulting report, mold issues in BlueOval’s supply chain “are not going to change any time soon.”</p>
<p>“Roughly 1,500 out of 12,000 seaworthy metal containers are on-site as of now. It may not be possible to stop this contamination from happening considering the many years of planning taken to begin the construction of the battery plant,” inspectors wrote.</p>
<p>Along with dozens of other workers they know, Dugan and Shaffer have volunteered for layoffs and plan to move to new jobs. They expect less-seasoned workers will fill their shoes.</p>
<p>A looming shortage of skilled hands has at least one contractor considering dirty tricks. In the internal email where Lighthouse Electric president Anton Mikec said a March BlueOval shutdown looked “inevitable” for mold cleanup, he also asked for a list of BlueOval workers. His goal: make sure to “turn them around at the door” at his company’s Indiana jobsite, so they’d be more likely to stay laid off and hungry to work at BlueOval in April. </p>
<p>To stop that kind of opportunistic blacklisting by construction bosses, IBEW and many building trades have won contract rights to a union hiring hall that handles worker dispatch. In the new manufacturing building boom, it may take union pressure to enforce that hard-won right.</p>
<h3>CANARY IN THE BATTERY PLANT</h3>
<p>Since it passed in August 2022, the Biden administration has trumpeted the Inflation Reduction Act as a crowning achievement, allocating a landmark $369 billion to climate and clean energy programs. At $9.2 billion, the BlueOval loan is not only the largest IRA incentive, but also the <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2023-ford-ev-battery-plant-funding-biden-green-technology/">largest</a> financial backing offered by the federal government to an automaker since the 2009 financial crisis.</p>
<p>The state of Kentucky has also shown unprecedented support for the project in the form of a $250 million upfront forgivable loan. <a href="https://goodjobsfirst.org/kentuckys-ev-battery-deals-carry-big-costs-for-taxpayers/">According to</a> the non-profit government watchdog Good Jobs First, the loan is the “biggest economic development deal in Kentucky history,” as well as “likely the most generous corporate subsidy the state has ever offered.”</p>
<p>These public subsidies have gently encouraged union labor, but not mandated it. Ford has not committed to bring BlueOval manufacturing workers under its master contract with the United Auto Workers, even after the union’s 2023 strike <a href="https://labornotes.org/2023/11/auto-workers-ratify-new-contracts-big-3">won unionization</a> of similar battery plants at GM and Stellantis.</p>
<p>But even with fully union construction at the BlueOval Kentucky site, workers said the grueling shifts and outbreak of illness left them worried about the direction of the building boom.</p>
<p>“We’re all scared because we know we could be carrying mold on our clothes back to our families, exposing the community,” said Dugan. “This is corporate America walking all over us.”</p>
<p><i>Schuyler Mitchell is an investigative reporter and editor based in Brooklyn. Keith Brower Brown is Labor Notes' Labor-Climate organizer.</i></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Bypass Paywalls repository is gone (303 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40015961</link>
            <guid>40015961</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 18:14:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40015961">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="40017822"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017734"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40017734" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40017734&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>This extension works remarkably well. But it requires frequent updates to stay working as sites change. I sure hope there's some statement on what's up soon.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017584"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017913"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017992"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40018028"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="40017521"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40017521" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40017521&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Do bypasses like this, which I assume just do things like deleting "uncloseable" client-side modals and spoofing UA/referrer headers, count as copy-protection circumvention technology under the DMCA?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017995"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40017995" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40017995&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Does the thing being bypassed prevent you from saving the page, or from making in any other way a copy of any content you've already fetched?<p>If not, how could it be classed as copy-protection?</p><p>Edit: One other thing: if spoofing UA headers was a problem, all the browsers in the world would fall foul of it - because non-Mozilla browsers all say that they're Mozilla, and Opera said it was IE, and Chrome said it was Safari, and now a bunch of browsers say they're Chrome - at the same time as saying they're Mozilla. Except it's more complicated than that.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40018068"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40017564"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017900"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40016612"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40016612" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40016612&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Weird, someone said something about that earlier today but then it got restored and now it's gone again?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017503"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017611"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017707"><td></td></tr>
                            <tr id="40017059"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017459"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017511"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40017511" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40017511&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>It's good that there are forks, but I was under the impression that the head person running the project was the one keeping all the paywall bypasses up to date. Even if these forks work, if no one is actively keeping track of each site that is being bypassed as it breaks or changes, they won't be working for long.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017577"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017731"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017767"><td></td></tr>
                                          <tr id="40017129"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40016918"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40016993"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40016993" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40016993&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The Gitlab one is actually maintained. They haven't been using GitHub for a while now. (Plenty of updates to the extension have occurred within the past 6 months, the date of the last commit on GitHub)</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017016"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40017016" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40017016&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The "clean" version is a fork made by someone else, non-clean version has/had Google Analytics in it, and the fork is more actively maintained</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017033"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40017013"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40017013" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40017013&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The gitlab one is "clean". But i don't remember the exact details regarding what it means. Just not to use the "dirty" one.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017104"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017205"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40017988"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40018032"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40018032" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40018032&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40015961"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>If you look at the source code in any of the mirrors people have linked, you'll find that the "clean" one that was taken down today does not have Google Analytics.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                          <tr id="40017572"><td></td></tr>
            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA["Strong focus on aesthetics" contributed to collapse of Norway timber bridge (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.dezeen.com/2024/04/11/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-timber/</link>
            <guid>40015851</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Apr 2024 18:06:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/2024/04/11/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-timber/">https://www.dezeen.com/2024/04/11/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-timber/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40015851">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<article id="post-2056395" data-article-id="2056395">
<header>

<figure data-lightboximage="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-hero_dezeen_2364_col_0-1.jpg" id="preload-hero">
<img width="852" height="479" src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-hero_dezeen_2364_col_0-1-852x479.jpg" alt="Aftermath of the Tretten Bridge collapse seen from above" decoding="async" srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-hero_dezeen_2364_col_0-1-852x479.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway-hero_dezeen_2364_col_0-1-1704x959.jpg 2x" data-pin-nopin="true"> </figure>



</header>
<section>

<p>An official report into the <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/2022/08/17/norway-timber-tretten-bridge-collapse/">collapse of a 10-year-old</a> mass-timber <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/bridges/">bridge</a> in <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/norway/">Norway</a> in August 2022 has criticised the structure's design and construction.<span id="more-2056395"></span></p>


<p>Two drivers had to be rescued after the Tretten Bridge, over the Gudbrandsdalslågen river in the Øyer area of southern Norway, <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/2022/08/17/norway-timber-tretten-bridge-collapse/">gave way as a heavy goods vehicle was crossing</a>.</p>
<p>Completed in only 2012, the <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/glued-laminated-timber/">glulam</a>-and-steel <a href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/truss-bridges/">truss bridge</a> was designed by Norwegian architecture studio <a href="https://plan.no/">Plan Arkitekter</a> and engineering firm <a href="https://www.norconsult.com/">Norconsult</a> for the Norwegian Public Roads Administration (NPRA).</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nsia.no/Road/Published-reports/2024-03">A recent report by the Norwegian Safety Investigation Authority (NSIA)</a> was critical of parties involved in the bridge's construction and management.</p>
<figure id="preload-0" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2056404" data-lightboximage="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2.jpg" data-orientation="landscape"><img decoding="async" src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2-852x568.jpg" alt="Norway bridge collapse" width="2364" height="1576" srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2-852x568.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2-1704x1136.jpg 2x" sizes="(max-width: 2364px) 100vw, 2364px" data-srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2-852x568.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2-1704x1136.jpg 2x" data-src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_2-852x568.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="><figcaption id="caption-attachment-2056404">Tretten Bridge collapsed in August 2022 as a lorry was crossing</figcaption></figure><p>"The investigation has shown that inadequate caution was exercised in the planning, design, inspection and approval of Tretten Bridge, with respect to the risk factors linked to its unconventional design," the report said.</p>

<p>"A short construction period, span lengths and reuse of existing foundation were framework conditions for the planning of the bridge," it continued.</p>
<p>"These framework conditions, combined with the choice of material and a strong focus on aesthetics, contributed to the structure not being robust."</p>
<p><strong>Failings over 2016 bridge collapse</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.nsia.no/Road/Published-reports/2023-03">An earlier report</a> concluded that the bridge most likely collapsed as a result of block shear failure – a type of fracture – in one of its timber diagonal members that had become weak over time.</p>
<p>Tretten Bridge was designed while building regulations in Norway were in transition from a national system to European codes.</p>
<p>Provisions for this transitional period enabled the project to follow the older national standards, which unlike the Eurocodes did not account for block shear failure.</p>
<p>"In retrospect, all the involved parties can be criticised for selecting and accepting regulations that proved to have a serious shortcoming (block shear failure)," the NSIA said.</p>
<figure id="preload-1" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2056405" data-lightboximage="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3.jpg" data-orientation="landscape"><img decoding="async" src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3-852x568.jpg" alt="Tretten Bridge collapse aftermath" width="2364" height="1576" srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3-852x568.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3-1704x1136.jpg 2x" sizes="(max-width: 2364px) 100vw, 2364px" data-srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3-852x568.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3-1704x1136.jpg 2x" data-src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_3-852x568.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="><figcaption id="caption-attachment-2056405">Made from glued laminated timber and steel, the bridge had a main span of 70 metres</figcaption></figure><p>The report also dealt with investigations of Tretten Bridge carried out after the collapse of the similarly constructed Perkolo Bridge in 2016.</p>
<p>It found that despite "serious faults" being identified at Tretten Bridge around that time, little action was taken by the Norwegian roads authority.</p>
<p>"This represents a system failure in the NPRA, reflecting a lack of knowledge about block shear failure, as well as shortcomings in the bridge management system and risk management," the report said.</p>
<p>"The NSIA believes that Tretten Bridge should either immediately have been closed or traffic restrictions imposed in 2016 when finding over-utilisation in relation to block shear in several of the bridge's connections," it added.</p>
<p>Six safety recommendations have been issued based on the investigation, which the NSIA said provide lessons for relevant organisations in Norway and abroad.</p>
<p>These include reviewing the process for regulating and approving road-related structures and their materials in Norway and clarification of building regulations.</p>
<figure id="preload-2" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-2056402" data-lightboximage="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0.jpg" data-orientation="landscape"><img decoding="async" src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0-852x568.jpg" alt="Collapse mass timber bridge" width="2364" height="1576" srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0-852x568.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0-1704x1136.jpg 2x" sizes="(max-width: 2364px) 100vw, 2364px" data-srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0-852x568.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0-1704x1136.jpg 2x" data-src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2024/04/tretten-bridge-collapse-norway_dezeen_2364_col_0-852x568.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="><figcaption id="caption-attachment-2056402">An official investigation has criticised the design and management of the bridge</figcaption></figure><p>Tretten Bridge was 148 metres long and 10.5 metres wide, with a main span of 70 metres. <a href="https://intrans.iastate.edu/app/uploads/sites/12/2019/03/ID_100_Harstad-Evjen.pdf">A report produced by Plan Arkitekter and Norconsult in 2013</a> gave the bridge a life expectancy of 100 years.</p>
<p>"As far as the Accident Investigation Board is aware, there are no wooden and steel truss bridges in the world that are comparable to Tretten Bridge," said the NSIA report (translated from Norwegian).</p>
<p>"The bridge was special both in terms of span length and asymmetry, trusses in the same direction and the combination of wood and steel."</p>
<p><strong>Aesthetics "not a governing topic"</strong></p>
<p>The NPRA is currently undertaking steps to improve bridge safety. Four similar bridges to Tretten Bridge <a href="https://www.tu.no/artikler/halvannet-ar-etter-tretten-kollapsen-10-av-14-bruer-stengt-eller-delvis-stengt/544644">will reportedly be rebuilt following inspections carried out after its collapse</a>.</p>
<p>Nine of 14 timber bridges that were closed following the incident remained shut or still had restrictions in place as of last month.</p>
<p>Plan Arkitetker has designed many of Norway's wooden bridges.</p>
<p>"If you read the conclusion from NSIA you will see that the collapse of the Tretten Bridge was caused by deficient regulations (national code) for building timber structures at the time of planning/construction," the studio's Yngve Aartun told Dezeen in a statement.</p>
<figure id="preload-3" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-1832201" data-lightboximage="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0.jpg" data-orientation="landscape"><img decoding="async" src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0-852x475.jpg" alt="Tretten Bridge in Norway before it collapsed" width="1704" height="949" srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0-852x475.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0.jpg 2x" sizes="(max-width: 1704px) 100vw, 1704px" data-srcset="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0-852x475.jpg 1x, https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0.jpg 2x" data-src="https://static.dezeen.com/uploads/2022/08/tretten-bridge-norway_dezeen_1704_col_0-852x475.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="><figcaption id="caption-attachment-1832201">Tretten Bridge stood for just 10 years before it collapsed. Photo by Jan-Tore Egge</figcaption></figure><p>"When new regulations (Eurocode) in 2016 revealed a few critical weak joints nothing was done to improve these joints," he continued.</p>
<p>"The bridge had a normal time schedule for engineering and construction. The aesthetics was decided by structural and constructional considerations and not a governing topic to decide the structure in the planning process."</p>
<p>NPRA director general Ingrid Dahl Hovland said the authority is "well underway" with measures to address bridge safety.</p>
<p>"We are in the process of signing off on the first measures," she said. "We want to ensure that any nuances between the safety recommendations from NSIA and the package of measures are captured. This work has top priority."</p>
<p>Norconsult did not respond to a request for comment.</p>
<p><em>The photography is courtesy of the NSIA unless otherwise stated.</em></p>
<div>
<p><span>Read more: </span></p><ul>
<li><a data-id="9172" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/wooden-architecture/">Wooden architecture</a></li>
<li><a data-id="16993" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/truss-bridges/">Truss bridges</a></li>
<li><a data-id="17077" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/mass-timber/">Mass timber</a></li>
<li><a data-id="17446" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/glued-laminated-timber/">Glued laminated timber</a></li>
<li><a data-id="18050" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/building-regulations/">Building regulations</a></li>
<li><a data-id="4" href="https://www.dezeen.com/architecture/">Architecture</a></li>
<li><a data-id="1064" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/norway/">Norway</a></li>
<li><a data-id="4094" href="https://www.dezeen.com/tag/bridges/">Bridges</a></li>
<li><a data-id="6040" href="https://www.dezeen.com/architecture/infrastructure/">Infrastructure</a></li>
<li><a data-id="3067" href="https://www.dezeen.com/news/">News</a></li>
</ul> </div>
</section>



</article>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>