<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 22:30:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[President Jimmy Carter has passed away (420 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/12/29/jimmy-carter-president-dead/</link>
            <guid>42543128</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 21:08:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/12/29/jimmy-carter-president-dead/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/12/29/jimmy-carter-president-dead/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42543128">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/12/29/jimmy-carter-president-dead/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are PC hardware companies driving technology into restricted closed ecosystems? (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.scottrlarson.com/updates/update-closed-technology-ecosystems-storage-configuration-lockdown/</link>
            <guid>42542138</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 19:11:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.scottrlarson.com/updates/update-closed-technology-ecosystems-storage-configuration-lockdown/">https://www.scottrlarson.com/updates/update-closed-technology-ecosystems-storage-configuration-lockdown/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42542138">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
        

<p>I am a Computer Hardware professional. I started working with computer technology in the early eighties. I have seen the evolution of technology starting with closed platforms like the game console era and then the move toward open platforms like the <a href="https://www.scottrlarson.com/memorials/memorial-my-home-computer-reflections-part-1/" target="_blank">Home Computer Golden Age</a>. In the last 5 or 10 years, I have witnessed technology changes that are slowly moving away from open hardware designs towards hardware that is locked down and can’t be modified by the user.  For more articles on this subject, see my  <a href="https://www.scottrlarson.com/categories/deceptivetechnology/" target="_blank">DeceptiveTechnology</a> section.</p>

<h2 id="is-dell-limiting-access-to-drivers-and-designing-bios-to-minimize-os-changes">Is Dell limiting access to drivers and designing BIOS to minimize OS changes?</h2>

<p>In the last few years, I have noticed a trend where Dell does not provide RST storage drivers for NVME SSDs (the software that allows a user to cleanly install an operating system from media) on Laptops and Desktops. Normally, you can just go into the BIOS, switch from NVME Raid to ACHI, and be done with it—or can you?</p>

<p>I recently purchased a Dell Inspiron 16 Plus 7640 Laptop with a BIOS that does not have an option to change to an AHCI storage configuration. Without the RST storage driver not being made available on Dell’s website, and no ability to switch to ACHI, you cannot reinstall Windows in a clean state from a installation disk because the install requires that the RST driver be manually loaded befoe it can see the storage device.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.scottrlarson.com/img/publications/oem-rst-driver-debacle-or-intentional/dell-inspiron-16-plus-bios-storage-configuration-missing-ahci-mode.jpeg" alt="Dell Inspiron 16plus bios storage configuration missing AHCI mode"></p>

<p>Normally, you would see this screen that allows you to switch storage modes
<img src="https://www.scottrlarson.com/img/publications/oem-rst-driver-debacle-or-intentional/dell-inspiron-3030-bios-storage-configuration.jpeg" alt="Dell Inspiron 3030 bios storage configuration AHCI mode"></p>

<p>I tried the key combinations to enable advanced BIOS configuration that worked on previous models, but no dice. Is it a coincidence that Dell has not been releasing the RST storage drivers for most of these models in the last couple of years, and is now deciding that the BIOS storage configuration should not be changable?</p>

<p>If you check Dell’s website for drivers, you probably will not see RST drivers for many models listed. I checked the driver listing for my model and so far I don’t see it.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.scottrlarson.com/img/publications/oem-rst-driver-debacle-or-intentional/dell.com-support-storage-driver-listings-lack-RST.resized.jpeg" alt="Dell.com Support Storage Driver Listings Lack RST"></p>

<p>Here is a different model with no RST listing.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.scottrlarson.com/img/publications/oem-rst-driver-debacle-or-intentional/dell.com-support-storage-driver-listings-lack-RST-different-model.jpeg" alt="Dell.com Support Storage Driver Listings Lack RST Differnt Model"></p>

<p>You can try to find drivers online, based on the hardware id’s, especially from Intel’s website, but they don’t always work for your particular model. I even tried to extract the drivers from the OS but I wasn’t able to find a .inf configuration profile to make it work.</p>

<p>These changes effectively prevents a user from cleanly reinstalling the operating system from media. The only option, that I can see, is to install from the service partition on the device, or from Dell’s BIOS re-installation technology, which contains bloatware, targeted advertising, and data collection.</p>

<p>I’m open to being wrong, please let me know if I am missing something.</p>

<p>Short of evidence to the contrary. I believe this is one small part of a bigger and long-term planned effort within the PC hardware and software industries to control the user experience for consumer hardware. Apple is also moving in this direction with the MacOS by limiting non-approved software from being installed. Yes, you can work around it, but it’s getting harder and harder to do so with every iteration of the Operating System.</p>

<p>We are slowly being boiled to the point of no return. We need some kind of consortium for users to represent our interests otherwise in 10 or 20 years we will have very limited choice when it comes to computer technology.</p>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Toronto man creates tiny mobile homes to help unhoused people escape the cold (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.7419805</link>
            <guid>42541173</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 17:06:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.7419805">https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.7419805</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42541173">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__next"><main><div><article id="article"><p>CBC News | Posted: December 28, 2024 10:23 PM | Last Updated: 21 hours ago</p><p>Homes are attached to bicycles; include heat, electricity and safety features </p><div role="figure" data-pw="imageEmbed"><p>Image  |  ryan donais tiny homes </p><p>Caption: Ryan Donais build his first tiny mobile home this summer, and has now built three homes — one of which is pictured behind him — that can act as temporary shelters for those experiencing homelessness.  (Saeed Dehghani/CBC)</p></div><p>After seeing people sleeping outside in the cold year-after-year, a Toronto man is building tiny mobile homes attached to bicycles to give temporary relief to those who are unhoused.</p><p>Ryan Donais started building the small modular homes this summer as he watched the city's housing crisis becoming more dire. He said he didn't want to go through another winter seeing people living on the streets, so he put his background in construction to use. </p><p>"I just don't see any changes. It's been many years with people outside and it's not changing. I couldn't imagine being outside for years, you know?"</p><p>Since then, Donais has built three homes at a cost of about $10,000 each, most of which has been paid for through donations to his GoFundMe page. </p><div role="figure" data-pw="imageEmbed" dir="ltr"><p>Image  |  tiny tiny homes example </p><p>Caption: Each home built by Donais has heat, electricity and running water, plus safety features including a smoke detector and carbon monoxide alarm.  (Saeed Dehghani/CBC)</p></div><p>He took inspiration form <a href="https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.5920822">Khaleel Seivwright</a>, a carpenter who built wooden shelters during the pandemic — until the city removed them, claiming they were a fire hazard. </p><p>Not wanting his tiny homes to suffer the same fate, Donais said he designed his mobile shelters to hopefully avoid backlash from the city. </p><p>Each of the small units have electricity and heat, running water and a bed, as well as safety features like smoke and carbon monoxide detectors and a fire extinguisher. Donais said the units are also designed with Ontario's e-bike regulations in mind so that they can legally travel on the city's bike lanes if they have to be moved. </p><p><em><strong>WATCH | Step inside his 1st tiny mobile home prototype: </strong></em><span><div role="figure" aria-label="Media Video | CBC News Toronto :  Tiny mobile home creator hopes to offer temporary relief to unhoused people"><p>Media Video | CBC News Toronto :  Tiny mobile home creator hopes to offer temporary relief to unhoused people</p><p>Caption: A Toronto man is building tiny mobile homes attached to bicycles with the hope of offering temporary relief to those who are unhoused. CBC’s Dale Manucdoc has the details.</p><a aria-label="Open full embed in new tab (external link)" href="https://www.cbc.ca/player/play/9.6517158" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Open Full Embed in New Tab <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="-125 -125 600 450" height="1em" width="1em"><title>(external link)</title><path d="M216 12.1v24c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h74L194.1 156c-2.3 2.3-3.6 5.3-3.6 8.5s1.3 6.2 3.6 8.5l16.9 16.9c2.3 2.3 5.3 3.6 8.5 3.6s6.3-1.3 8.5-3.6L335.9 82l.1 74c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h24c6.6 0 12-5.4 12-12V12c0-6.6-5.4-12-12-12L228 .1c-6.6 0-12 5.4-12 12z"></path><path d="M288 192v132c0 6.6-5.4 12-12 12H60c-6.6 0-12-5.4-12-12V108c0-6.6 5.4-12 12-12h132V48H12C5.4 48 0 53.4 0 60v312c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h312c6.6 0 12-5.4 12-12V192h-48z"></path></svg></a><p><span>Loading external pages may require significantly more data usage.</span></p></div></span></p><p>So far, Donais said he hasn't encountered any issues. </p><p>Terra Sawler moved into one of Donais' mobile homes about a month and a half ago after spending close to three years living on the street. </p><p>"This is definitely the safest and warmest I've been since I've been out here."</p><div role="figure" data-pw="imageEmbed" dir="ltr"><p>Image  |  Terra Sawler </p><p>Caption: Terra Sawler has been living one of the tiny mobile homes built by Ryan Donais for more than a month.  (Saeed Dehghani/CBC)</p></div><p>After burning down two tents just trying to stay warm, Sawler says this is definitely a safer option. In addition to keeping her warm, Sawler says the tiny home has also allowed her to have something she hadn't had in years — a good night's sleep. </p><p>"When you're out on the street, you don't sleep every night. You sleep every couple nights," she said. </p><p>"And you gotta take turns and shifts with people, right? 'Cause I mean, I've had my shoes stolen off my feet, I've had my [sleeping] bag cut off, it's a dog-eat-dog world out here." </p><p><em><strong>WATCH | Woman experiencing homelessness grateful for tiny mobile home: </strong></em><span><div role="figure" aria-label="Media Video | CBC News Toronto :  'Tiny Tiny Homes' builder presents another Toronto resident with place to stay"><p>Media Video | CBC News Toronto :  'Tiny Tiny Homes' builder presents another Toronto resident with place to stay</p><p>Caption: A Toronto man who started building small shelters for those in need gave someone a new place to live today. As Naama Weingarten reports, while unhoused people appreciate his efforts, he wishes he never had to build the homes.</p><a aria-label="Open full embed in new tab (external link)" href="https://www.cbc.ca/player/play/9.6601656" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">Open Full Embed in New Tab <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="-125 -125 600 450" height="1em" width="1em"><title>(external link)</title><path d="M216 12.1v24c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h74L194.1 156c-2.3 2.3-3.6 5.3-3.6 8.5s1.3 6.2 3.6 8.5l16.9 16.9c2.3 2.3 5.3 3.6 8.5 3.6s6.3-1.3 8.5-3.6L335.9 82l.1 74c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h24c6.6 0 12-5.4 12-12V12c0-6.6-5.4-12-12-12L228 .1c-6.6 0-12 5.4-12 12z"></path><path d="M288 192v132c0 6.6-5.4 12-12 12H60c-6.6 0-12-5.4-12-12V108c0-6.6 5.4-12 12-12h132V48H12C5.4 48 0 53.4 0 60v312c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h312c6.6 0 12-5.4 12-12V192h-48z"></path></svg></a><p><span>Loading external pages may require significantly more data usage.</span></p></div></span></p><div dir="ltr"><p>As part of its </p><a href="https://www.toronto.ca/community-people/housing-shelter/affordable-housing-developments/modular-housing-initiative/#:~:text=The%20City%20of%20Toronto%20is,new%20modular%20homes%20in%20Toronto." target="_blank" rel="noreferrer">housing action plan<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="-125 -125 600 450" height="1em" width="1em"><title>(external link)</title><path d="M216 12.1v24c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h74L194.1 156c-2.3 2.3-3.6 5.3-3.6 8.5s1.3 6.2 3.6 8.5l16.9 16.9c2.3 2.3 5.3 3.6 8.5 3.6s6.3-1.3 8.5-3.6L335.9 82l.1 74c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h24c6.6 0 12-5.4 12-12V12c0-6.6-5.4-12-12-12L228 .1c-6.6 0-12 5.4-12 12z"></path><path d="M288 192v132c0 6.6-5.4 12-12 12H60c-6.6 0-12-5.4-12-12V108c0-6.6 5.4-12 12-12h132V48H12C5.4 48 0 53.4 0 60v312c0 6.6 5.4 12 12 12h312c6.6 0 12-5.4 12-12V192h-48z"></path></svg></a><p> released in 2020, the City of Toronto has committed to creating 1,000 new modular homes for people experiencing homelessness. So far, the city has completed 216 homes on city-owned sites, its website says. </p></div><p>Other municipalities in Ontario have started to use modular homes to address a lack of housing. </p><div dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.7138608"><u>Peterborough started a modular housing community</u></a><p> filled with cabins in the site of a former parking lot </p></div><div dir="ltr"><a href="https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.7347274"><u>Waterloo also</u></a><p> has a tiny home shelter run by the region that opened last year, while </p><a href="https://www.cbc.ca/lite/story/1.7414830"><u>Hamilton </u></a><p>is expected to open an outdoor shelter made up of tiny modular homes next month following some delays. </p></div><p>Since building his first tiny home in the summer, Donais has since registered his own not-for-profit organization, Tiny Tiny Homes, to help create more. </p><p>He says he's happy to be able to give people like Sawler an escape from the cold with his mini modular homes. But his homes aren't meant to be permanent, and he wishes he didn't have to build them at all. </p><p>"It's a terrible that we're letting people sleep outside. Housing is the answer."</p></article></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Was Wrong about the Ethics Crisis (Moshe Vardi, CACM) (188 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/i-was-wrong-about-the-ethics-crisis/</link>
            <guid>42540862</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 16:23:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/i-was-wrong-about-the-ethics-crisis/">https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/i-was-wrong-about-the-ethics-crisis/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42540862">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
		
		
					<p>Is Big Tech supporting the public good, and if not, what should Big Tech workers do about it?</p>
		
		

			<figure>
			<p><img width="1024" height="576" src="https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg" alt="Moshe Y. Vardi" loading="eager" decoding="async" srcset="https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg 2400w, https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg?resize=1024,576 1024w, https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://cacm.acm.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/080224.OP_.Moshe-Vardi-2400x1350-1.jpg?resize=2048,1152 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></p>		</figure>

		
	</div><div>
		<article><section id="sec1" lang="en"><p id="p-1">The ethics crisis in computing was “launched” in 2018. In March of that year,&nbsp;<i>The Boston Globe</i> asserted, “Computer science faces an ethics crisis. The Cambridge Analytica scandal proves it!” This was in response to the <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/books/techlash/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">Techlash</a>,<a href="#fn1" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn1"><sup>a</sup></a> where <i>Wall Street Journal</i> columnist Peggy Noonan described Silicon Valley executives as “moral Martians who operate on some weird new postmodern ethical wavelength” and Niall Ferguson, a Hoover Institution historian, described cyberspace as “cyberia, a dark and lawless realm where malevolent actors range.”</p><p id="p-2">But in my January 2019 <i>Communications</i> <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/are-we-having-an-ethical-crisis-in-computing/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">column</a>,<a href="#fn2" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn2"><sup>b</sup></a> I dismissed the ethical-crisis vibe. I wrote, “If society finds the surveillance business model offensive, then the remedy is public policy, in the form of laws and regulations, rather than an ethics outrage.” I now think, however, I was wrong. I think I was right to advocate for laws and regulation to address the adverse impacts of computing, but I now believe we do have an ethics crisis in computing.</p><p id="p-3">What changed my mind? First, my anxiety about the ills brought on by computing has risen dramatically, as a perusal of my column over the past five years shows.<a href="#fn3" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn3"><sup>c</sup></a> I <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/to-serve-humanity/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">bemoaned</a> that humanity seems to be serving technology rather than the other way around. I <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/the-winner-takes-all-tech-corporation/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">argued</a> that tech corporations have become too powerful and their power must be <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/the-people-vs-tech/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">curtailed</a>. I <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/advancing-computing-as-a-science-and-profession-but-to-what-end/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">asked</a> that ACM dedicate itself to the public good. I <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/acm-ethics-and-corporate-behavior/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">pointed out</a> that Big Tech’s business models are unethical. I explained how technology <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/technology-and-democracy/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">increases</a> societal polarization. I wailed that computing has blood on its hands. About two years ago, I started giving <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OF3GlEwQBRg" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">talks</a><a href="#fn4" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn4"><sup>d</sup></a> on how to be an ethical computing technologist.</p><p id="p-4">But I have yet, until now, to point at the elephant in the room and ask whether it is ethical to work for Big Tech, taking all of the above into consideration. ACM’s Code of Ethics<a href="#fn5" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn5"><sup>e</sup></a> does offer a clear ethical guideline. It opens with the following sentences: “Computing professionals’ actions change the world. To act responsibly, they should reflect upon the wider impacts of their work, consistently supporting the public good.” So, the ethical star we should follow is the support of the public good.</p><p id="p-5">Supporting the public good is not always straightforward. All of us must navigate the trade-off between “me” and “we.” A famous Talmudic quote states: “If I am not for myself, who will be for me? If I am only for myself, what am I?” We must balance optimizing for oneself with optimizing for others, including the public good. So how does working for Big Tech thread this needle? This is the question that people who work for Big Tech must ask themselves.</p><p id="p-6">The profit motive is not inherently against the public good. As Adam Smith pointed out, “They are led by an invisible hand…and thus without intending it, without knowing it, advance the interest of the society.” But the belief in the magical power of the free market always to serve the public good has <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/opinion/a-computational-lens-on-economics/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">no theoretical basis</a>.<a href="#fn6" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn6"><sup>f</sup></a> In fact, our current climate crisis is a demonstrated <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Big-Myth-American-Business-Government/dp/1635573572" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">market failure</a>.<a href="#fn7" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn7"><sup>g</sup></a> To take an extreme example, Big Tobacco surely does not support the public good, and most of us would agree that it is unethical to work for Big Tobacco. The question, thus, is whether Big Tech is supporting the public good, and if not, what should Big Tech workers do about it.</p><p id="p-7">Of course, there is no simple answer to such a question, and the only reasonable answer to the question of whether it is ethical to work for Big Tech is, “It depends.” But consider Uber. In 2023, <i>Wired</i> magazine <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/uber-ceo-will-always-say-his-company-sucks/" data-jats-ext-link-type="uri">reported</a><a href="#fn8" data-jats-ref-type="fn" data-jats-rid="fn8"><sup>h</sup></a> that “…Travis Kalanick, had built an enormous, enthusiastic user base by subsidizing rides with the company’s vast reservoir of VC funding. Under Kalanick, Uber skirted regulations, shrugged off safety issues, and presided over a workplace rife with sexual harassment.” Was it ethical to have worked at Uber under Kalanick? I am sure many Uber employees were not aware of Kalanick’s shenanigans, but many were, and yet they continued to work at Uber. It was only in 2022 that a whistleblower leaked more than 124,000 company files to the <em>Guardian</em>, exposing its misdeeds.</p><p id="p-8">“It is difficult to get a man to understand something, when his salary depends on his not understanding it,” said the writer and political activist Upton Sinclair. By and large, Big Tech workers do not seem to be asking themselves hard questions, I believe, hence my conclusion that we do indeed suffer from an ethics crisis.</p></section></article>
</div><div>
			<div>
			<p>
				Submit an Article to CACM			</p>
			<p>
				CACM welcomes unsolicited <a href="https://cacm.acm.org/author-guidelines/#CACMsubmission">submissions</a> on topics of relevance and value to the computing community.			</p>
		</div>

<section>
	<div>
		<p>
			You Just Read		</p>
		<h4>
			I Was Wrong about the Ethics Crisis		</h4>
					<a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3704959">
								View in the ACM Digital Library							</a>
			</div>
	<p>© 2024 Copyright held by the owner/author(s).</p>
</section>
		</div><div data-component="ctaMembership">
	
		<div>
				<h3>
					Shape the Future of Computing				</h3>
									<p>
						ACM encourages its members to take a direct hand in shaping the future of the association. There are more ways than ever to get involved.					</p>
													<p><a href="https://www.acm.org/about-acm/get-involved">
						Get Involved											</a>
							</p></div>

		
		<div>
				<h3>
					Communications of the ACM (CACM) is now a fully Open Access publication.				</h3>
									<p>
						By opening CACM to the world, we hope to increase engagement among the broader computer science community and encourage non-members to discover the rich resources ACM has to offer.					</p>
													<p><a href="https://cacm.acm.org/news/cacm-is-becoming-open-access">
						Learn More											</a>
							</p></div>

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[BSD kqueue is a mountain of technical debt (2021) (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ariadne.space/2021/06/06/actually-bsd-kqueue-is-a-mountain-of-technical-debt/</link>
            <guid>42540442</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 15:20:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ariadne.space/2021/06/06/actually-bsd-kqueue-is-a-mountain-of-technical-debt/">https://ariadne.space/2021/06/06/actually-bsd-kqueue-is-a-mountain-of-technical-debt/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42540442">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <p>A side effect of <a href="https://ariadne.space/2021/05/20/the-whole-freenode-kerfluffle/">the whole freenode kerfluffle</a> is that I’ve been looking at IRCD again.&nbsp; IRC, is of course a very weird and interesting place, and the smaller community of people who run IRCDs are largely weirder and even more interesting.</p>
<p>However, in that community of IRCD administrators there happens to be a few incorrect systems programming opinions that have been cargo culted around for years.&nbsp; This particular blog is about one of these bikesheds, namely the <em>kqueue vs epoll debate</em>.</p>
<p>You’ve probably heard it before.&nbsp; It goes something like this, <em>“BSD is better for networking, because it has kqueue.&nbsp; Linux has nothing like kqueue, epoll doesn’t come close."</em>&nbsp; While I agree that epoll doesn’t come close, I think that’s actually a feature that has lead to a much more flexible and composable design.</p>
<h2 id="in-the-beginning">In the beginning…</h2>
<p>Originally, IRCD like most daemons used <code>select</code> for polling sockets for readiness, as this was the first polling API available on systems with BSD sockets.&nbsp; The <code>select</code> syscall works by taking a set of three bitmaps, with each bit describing a file descriptor number: bit 1 refers to file descriptor 1 and so on.&nbsp; The bitmaps are the <code>read_set</code>, <code>write_set</code> and <code>err_set</code>, which map to sockets that can be read, written to or have errors accordingly.&nbsp; Due to design defects with the <code>select</code> syscalls, it can only support up to <code>FD_SETSIZE</code> file descriptors on most systems.&nbsp; This can be mitigated by making <code>fd_set</code> an arbitrarily large bitmap and depending on <code>fdmax</code> to be the upper bound, which is what WinSock has traditionally done on Windows.</p>
<p>The <code>select</code> syscall clearly had some design deficits that negatively affected scalability, so AT&amp;T introduced the <code>poll</code> syscall in System V UNIX.&nbsp; The <code>poll</code> syscall takes an array of <code>struct pollfd</code> of user-specified length, and updates a bitmap of flags in each <code>struct pollfd</code> entry with the current status of each socket.&nbsp; Then you iterate over the <code>struct pollfd</code> list.&nbsp; This is naturally a lot more efficient than <code>select</code>, where you have to iterate over all file descriptors up to <code>fdmax</code> and test for membership in each of the three bitmaps to ascertain each socket’s status.</p>
<p>It can be argued that <code>select</code> was bounded by <code>FD_SETSIZE</code> (which is usually 1024 sockets), while <code>poll</code> begins to have serious scalability issues at around <code>10240</code> sockets.&nbsp; These arbitrary benchmarks have been referred to as the C1K and C10K problems accordingly.&nbsp; Dan Kegel has a <a href="http://www.kegel.com/c10k.html">very lengthy post on his website</a> about his experiences mitigating the C10K problem in the context of running an FTP site.</p>
<h2 id="then-there-was-kqueue">Then there was kqueue…</h2>
<p>In July 2000, Jonathan Lemon introduced kqueue into FreeBSD, which quickly propagated into the other BSD forks as well.&nbsp; kqueue is a kernel-assisted event notification system using two syscalls: <code>kqueue</code> and <code>kevent</code>.&nbsp; The <code>kqueue</code> syscall creates a handle in the kernel represented as a file descriptor, which a developer uses with <code>kevent</code> to add and remove <em>event filters</em>.&nbsp; Event filters can match against file descriptors, processes, filesystem paths, timers, and so on.</p>
<p>This design allows for a single-threaded server to process hundreds of thousands of connections at once, because it can register all of the sockets it wishes to monitor with the kernel and then lazily iterate over the sockets as they have events.</p>
<p>Most IRCDs have supported <code>kqueue</code> for the past 15 to 20 years.</p>
<h2 id="and-then-epoll">And then epoll…</h2>
<p>In October 2002, Davide Libenzi got <a href="http://www.xmailserver.org/linux-patches/nio-improve.html">his <code>epoll</code> patch</a> merged into Linux 2.5.44.&nbsp; Like with kqueue, you use the <code>epoll_create</code> syscall to create a kernel handle which represents the set of descriptors to monitor.&nbsp; You use the <code>epoll_ctl</code> syscall to add or remove descriptors from that set.&nbsp; And finally, you use <code>epoll_wait</code> to wait for kernel events.</p>
<p>In general, the scalability aspects are the same to the application programmer: you have your sockets, you use <code>epoll_ctl</code> to add them to the kernel’s <code>epoll</code> handle, and then you wait for events, just like you would with <code>kevent</code>.</p>
<p>Like <code>kqueue</code>, most IRCDs have supported <code>epoll</code> for the past 15 years.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-file-descriptor-anyway">What is a file descriptor, anyway?</h2>
<p>To understand the argument I am about to make, we need to talk about <em>file descriptors</em>.&nbsp; UNIX uses the term <em>file descriptor</em> a lot, even when referring to things which are clearly <em>not</em> files, like network sockets.&nbsp; Outside the UNIX world, a file descriptor is usually referred to as a <em>kernel handle</em>.&nbsp; Indeed, in Windows, kernel-managed resources are given the <code>HANDLE</code> type, which makes this relationship more clear.&nbsp; Essentially, a kernel handle is basically an opaque reference to an object in kernel space, and the astute reader may notice some similarities to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Object-capability_model">object-capability model</a> as a result.</p>
<p>Now that we understand that file descriptors are actually just kernel handles, we can now talk about <code>kqueue</code> and <code>epoll</code>, and why <code>epoll</code> is actually the correct design.</p>
<h2 id="the-problem-with-event-filters">The problem with event filters</h2>
<p>The key difference between <code>epoll</code> and <code>kqueue</code> is that <code>kqueue</code> operates on the notion of <em>event filters</em> instead of <em>kernel handles</em>.&nbsp; This means that any time you want <code>kqueue</code> to do something new, you have to add a new type of <em>event filter</em>.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?query=kqueue&amp;sektion=2">FreeBSD presently has 10 different event filter types</a>: <code>EVFILT_READ</code>, <code>EVFILT_WRITE</code>, <code>EVFILT_EMPTY</code>, <code>EVFILT_AIO</code>, <code>EVFILT_VNODE</code>, <code>EVFILT_PROC</code>, <code>EVFILT_PROCDESC</code>, <code>EVFILT_SIGNAL</code>, <code>EVFILT_TIMER</code> and <code>EVFILT_USER</code>.&nbsp; Darwin has additional event filters concerning monitoring Mach ports.</p>
<p>Other than <code>EVFILT_READ</code>, <code>EVFILT_WRITE</code> and <code>EVFILT_EMPTY</code>, all of these different event filter types are related to entirely different concerns in the kernel: they don’t monitor kernel handles, but instead other specific subsystems than sockets.</p>
<p>This makes for a powerful API, but one which lacks <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Composability">composability</a>.</p>
<h2 id="epoll-is-better-because-it-is-composable"><code>epoll</code> is better because it is composable</h2>
<p>It is possible to do almost everything that <code>kqueue</code> can do on FreeBSD in Linux, but instead of having a single monolithic syscall to handle <em>everything</em>, Linux takes the approach of providing syscalls which allow almost anything to be represented as a <em>kernel handle</em>.</p>
<p>Since <code>epoll</code> strictly monitors <em>kernel handles</em>, you can register <em>any</em> kernel handle you have with it and get events back when its state changes.&nbsp; As a comparison to Windows, this basically means that <code>epoll</code> is a kernel-accelerated form of <code>WaitForMultipleObjects</code> in the Win32 API.</p>
<p>You are probably wondering how this works, so here’s a table of commonly used <code>kqueue</code> event filters and the Linux syscall used to get a kernel handle for use with <code>epoll</code>.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>BSD event filter</th>
<th>Linux equivalent</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_READ</code>, <code>EVFILT_WRITE</code>, <code>EVFILT_EMPTY</code></td>
<td>Pass the socket with <code>EPOLLIN</code> etc.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_VNODE</code></td>
<td><code>inotify</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_SIGNAL</code></td>
<td><code>signalfd</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_TIMER</code></td>
<td><code>timerfd</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_USER</code></td>
<td><code>eventfd</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_PROC</code>, <code>EVFILT_PROCDESC</code></td>
<td><code>pidfd</code>, alternatively bind processes to a <code>cgroup</code> and monitor <code>cgroup.events</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>EVFILT_AIO</code></td>
<td><code>aiocb.aio_fildes</code> (treat as socket)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Hopefully, as you can see, <code>epoll</code> can automatically monitor <em>any</em> kind of kernel resource without having to be modified, due to its composable design, which makes it superior to <code>kqueue</code> from the perspective of having less technical debt.</p>
<p>Interestingly, <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?query=eventfd&amp;apropos=0&amp;sektion=2&amp;manpath=FreeBSD+13.0-RELEASE+and+Ports&amp;arch=default&amp;format=html">FreeBSD has added support for Linux’s <code>eventfd</code> recently</a>, so it appears that they may take <code>kqueue</code> in this direction as well.&nbsp; Between that and FreeBSD’s <a href="https://www.freebsd.org/cgi/man.cgi?query=procdesc&amp;sektion=4&amp;apropos=0&amp;manpath=FreeBSD+13.0-RELEASE+and+Ports">process descriptors</a>, it seems likely.</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[China turns members of its diaspora into spies (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.economist.com/china/2024/12/26/how-china-turns-members-of-its-diaspora-into-spies</link>
            <guid>42540427</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 15:18:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.economist.com/china/2024/12/26/how-china-turns-members-of-its-diaspora-into-spies">https://www.economist.com/china/2024/12/26/how-china-turns-members-of-its-diaspora-into-spies</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42540427">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main role="main" id="content"><article data-test-id="Article" id="new-article-template"><div data-test-id="standard-article-template"><section><p><span><a href="https://www.economist.com/china" data-analytics="sidebar:section"><span>China</span></a></span><span> | <!-- -->Eyes everywhere</span></p><h2>America is on the hunt for these non-traditional agents. But its efforts risk backfiring</h2></section><section><figure><img alt="Illustration depicting a stylized eye with the Chinese flag as the iris, connected by yellow network lines to two red-tinted globes on either side, symbolizing global surveillance or influence. The background is black with red dots, creating a striking and" fetchpriority="high" width="1280" height="720" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(min-width: 960px) 700px, 95vw" srcset="https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=360,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 360w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=384,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 384w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=480,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 480w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=600,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 600w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=834,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 834w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=960,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 960w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1096,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 1096w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1280,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 1280w, https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1424,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg 1424w" src="https://www.economist.com/cdn-cgi/image/width=1424,quality=80,format=auto/content-assets/images/20250104_CND001.jpg"><figcaption><span>Illustration: Ben Jones</span></figcaption></figure></section><div><section data-body-id="cp2"><p data-component="paragraph"><span data-caps="initial">A</span><small>MONG EXILED</small> Chinese dissidents, Tang Yuanjun was well known. He had participated in the Tiananmen Square protests of 1989 and landed in prison as a result. He later defected to Taiwan, swimming to one of its outlying islands from a fishing boat. America granted him asylum and he settled in New York, becoming the leader of Chinese pro-democracy groups. But in August 2024 he was arrested by the <small>FBI</small>. He admits to having used his position to collect information for the Chinese government and to report on his fellow activists. He did this so that the government would allow him to return to China to see his ailing parents.</p></section><p><h3 id="article-tags">Explore more</h3><nav aria-labelledby="article-tags"><a href="https://www.economist.com/topics/china" data-analytics="tags:china"><span>China</span></a><a href="https://www.economist.com/topics/united-states" data-analytics="tags:united_states"><span>United States</span></a></nav></p></div></div></article></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is Iceland getting ready to join the EU? (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mikegalsworthy.substack.com/p/is-iceland-getting-ready-to-join</link>
            <guid>42539987</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 14:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mikegalsworthy.substack.com/p/is-iceland-getting-ready-to-join">https://mikegalsworthy.substack.com/p/is-iceland-getting-ready-to-join</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42539987">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>Polling shows that the Icelandic public are keener on it than ever before, with more Icelanders wanting to join the EU than stay out. The turnaround happened with Putin’s second invasion of Ukraine in Feb 2022, but other domestic and international dynamics also come into play.</p><p><span>Things are moving fast, as Iceland’s new Foreign Minister </span><a href="https://www.euronews.com/my-europe/2024/12/22/icelands-incoming-government-says-it-will-put-eu-membership-to-referendum-by-2027" rel="">has just announced</a><span> “a referendum on the continuation of Iceland's European Union accession talks and that this referendum be held no later than 2027”. You might ask what is meant by a “continuation”. Ah, well that’s a whole fascinating historical story which I’ll gladly set out below. But basically, the last social democratic government started accession talks in 2009, then a conservative-led government came into power and put talks on pause in 2013, then tried to cancel it outright in 2015, but without parliamentary approval. That led to anger and an open question on whether the accession talks have indeed been cancelled or are still formally open and ready to be picked up again! In the meantime, the national polling has gone from being against joining the EU to being for joining the EU (see graph further down), so the time could be ripe for Iceland to finally join.</span></p><p>But firstly, let’s look at the election that just happened, then this history of Iceland’s place in EFTA, the EEA and its stalled attempt to join the EU. Then we’ll look at what happens now and what the current push means for Iceland, EFTA, Norway and the UK.</p><p>The Icelandic parliament is called the Alþingi (pronounced “Althingi”). It is the oldest surviving parliament (founded in 930 AD) and currently has 63 seats to represent the Icelandic population of nearly 400,000.</p><p>Elections were held in Iceland on 30 November 2024 and the results were:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png" width="1196" height="456" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:456,&quot;width&quot;:1196,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:47383,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F04f2582e-d876-49a2-a2d2-c0f459cea738_1196x456.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>The previous government had been comprised of a coalition of Independence (16 seats), Progressive (13) and Left-Green (8). So in the table above, you can see just how badly they all crashed out.</p><p>The last government was an odd mix, with both Independence (named after Icelandic independence movement from Denmark, which happened in 1918) and Progressive parties both being centre-right parties - but Left-Green doing what it says on the tin and being left wing. In October, prime minister Bjarni Benediktsson announced that the government had collapsed due to disagreements on several fronts and called the general election.</p><p>Note that the Reform Party is nothing like Reform UK – it is liberal, increasingly called “Liberal Reform Party” and staunchly pro-EU. Also, just as the “Progressive Party” is not progressive, the “People’s Party” may sound reactionary, but they are very centrist. Conversely, the “Centre Party” are right-wing populists. Finally, the Pirate Party likes direct democracy.</p><p><span>The new prime minister is </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kristr%C3%BAn_Frostad%C3%B3ttir" rel="">Kristrún Frostadóttir</a><span> (age 36), leader of the Social Democratic Alliance (15 seats). </span><a href="https://grapevine.is/news/2024/12/04/kristrun-frostadottir-begins-formal-government-formation/" rel=""><span>On Dec 4</span><sup>th</sup><span>, she began coalition negotiations</span></a><span> with the Reform Party (11 seats) and People's Party (10 seats) and on Dec 21</span><sup>st</sup><span> they </span><a href="https://icelandmonitor.mbl.is/news/news/2024/12/21/these_are_the_ministers_of_the_government/" rel="">announced their government and ministers</a><span>. The new government now holds 36 out of the 63 seats in the Alþingi.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png" width="496" height="592" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:592,&quot;width&quot;:496,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:450520,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fae1c3334-86c6-49ec-8421-470f8bbe8c61_496x592.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><h6>                               Kristrún Frostadóttir, official portrait.</h6><p><span>Given previously-expressed concerns by Frostadóttir that any referendum could be divisive, </span><a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/europe/icelands-pro-eu-parties-lead-polls-ahead-snap-election-2024-11-28/" rel="">alluding to the narrow margin of Brexit</a><span> in her commentary on the matter, it is surprising how quicky they announced that there would indeed be a referendum on picking up EU accession talks – and the choice of word being “continuation” rather than “starting”, “restarting” or “renewed” indicates very strongly that they believe that the EU will let them continue from where they left off, should they gain the popular mandate for it.</span></p><p>To understand the debate that will happen in Iceland now, it’s very useful to understand Iceland’s relationship with EFTA, the EEA, the EU and even the US.</p><p>Iceland joined EFTA in 1970. At that time, EFTA had been around for ten years, initially founded in 1960 by the “outer seven” of the UK, Portugal, Austria, Switzerland and the Nordic countries Denmark, Sweden and Norway. These “outer seven” counterbalanced the “inner six” of Belgium, France, West Germany, Italy, Luxembourg, and the Netherlands. Those “inner six” had all signed the Treaty of Paris in 1952 to make the European Coal and Steel Community (ECSC), which then developed into just the “European Communities (EC)” in 1967, comprising also the European Atomic Energy Community (Euratom) and the European Economic Community (EEC).</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png" width="460" height="752" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:752,&quot;width&quot;:460,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:162941,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F496c61ce-588b-4a6d-b53e-83c1d7c1d308_460x752.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>In 1972, the UK and Denmark left EFTA to join the EC. Then in 1985, Portugal also left EFTA to join the EC. The 8 members of EFTA (“outer seven” plus Iceland) were now down to 5. In the late 1980s, the EFTA countries began discussing options to join the EEC part of the European Communities. This was while two new members joined EFTA – Finland (1986) and Liechtenstein (1991). By May 1992, the EEC had been renamed the EEA (European Economic Area) and all 7 member states of EFTA signed “The EEA Agreement” alongside the 12 member states of the EC.</p><p>So far, so good… but Switzerland then held a referendum on EEA entry in December 1992 in which its population voted “no” by 50.3% to 49.7%. This is why Switzerland has been out of the EEA and just had messy bilateral arrangements with the EEA/Single Market ever since.</p><p>In 1994 Sweden, Finland and Austria jumped ship from EFTA into the brand-new European Union (the Maastricht Treaty came into force in 1993, forming the “European Union”). The Norwegian government also tried to jump the EFTA ship into the EC in 1972 and then into the EU in 1994, but both times the public stopped them in a referendum. In 1972, “No” won with 53.5% of the vote and in 1994, “No” won with 52.2% of the vote.</p><p>So by the end of 1994, just Norway, Switzerland, Iceland and Liechtenstein were left in EFTA, which remains the case 30 years later. Referendums explain why Norway and Switzerland were kept out of moving into the EU, but as for Liechtenstein and Iceland, they both felt they were too small to have any influence in the EU and with the EEA covering their basic needs, they just never mustered the political will to attempt the move when the bigger countries did.</p><p><span>The mood music changed dramatically in 2008 with the banking crisis. Iceland was particularly badly hit. All three of the country's major privately owned commercial banks (Kaupthing, Glitnir and Landsbankinn) defaulted in late 2008. This made it, in terms of relativity to the size of the nation’s economy, the </span><a href="https://harris.uchicago.edu/news-events/events/2008-icelandic-financial-crisis-arni-mathiesen" rel="">largest systemic banking collapse in economic history</a><span>. According to Gudrun Johnsen, who was on the special commission set up to learn lessons from Iceland's banking collapse: </span><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/business-35485876" rel="">“80% of the stock market was wiped out overnight</a><span>... About every other business in Iceland became technically bankrupt. 97% of the banking sector collapsed in a matter of three days.” The banks were far too big to save by the small nation’s economy and were just allowed to fail.</span></p><p><span>The currency (</span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Icelandic_kr%C3%B3na" rel="">Icelandic króna</a><span>) had already been seen to be extremely volatile and vulnerable before that stage. Icelanders had, before the banking collapse, started thinking about the safety of the Euro as an alternative. </span><a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/bondsNews/idUSL1111656420070911/" rel="">A poll in 2007</a><span> had found 53% of Icelanders favoured adopting the Euro and </span><a href="https://www.sedlabanki.is/uploads/files/WP-26.pdf" rel="">a paper in 2004</a><span> had calculated that Iceland joining the EU and Euro could boost trade with other Euro countries by 60% leading to a 4% increase in GDP per capita. Additionally, Iceland felt alone and started wishing that it had close friends to help handle such turbulence.</span></p><p>All of this was precipitated when, under public pressure, snap parliamentary elections were held in Iceland on 25 April 2009. The (Conservative) Independence Party, which had been governing and which had constantly been the most voted-for party since 1937 suddenly found itself in second place (16 seats) to the Social Democratic Party (20 seats). A government was formed between the Social Democratic Party and the Left-Green movement (14 seats).</p><p><span>Iceland </span><a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/world/factbox-iceland-to-begin-eu-accession-talks-idUSLF250651/" rel="">applied to join the European Union</a><span> in July 2009. Formal negotiations began a year later in July 2010.</span></p><p><span>Iceland’s economy started stabilising and then growing by mid 2011. Emergency legislation to take over the domestic running of the three largest banks, the IMF IMF led a $10 billion financial aid package to pull Iceland out crisis, the application to EU membership and the tourism boom (driven largely by </span><a href="https://www.britannica.com/video/did-you-know-Eyjafjallajokull-volcano-Iceland/-257511" rel="">spectacular volcanic eruptions 2010</a><span> and the use of Iceland in the Game of Thrones series) </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2008%E2%80%932011_Icelandic_financial_crisis" rel="">all helped</a><span>. In particular, Iceland’s tourism boom was dramatic and Iceland now has several times as many tourists per annum as its entire population.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png" width="460" height="534" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:534,&quot;width&quot;:460,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:52901,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fed99b737-f135-4229-b352-98a6ca699d8d_460x534.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>(Picture from: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tourism_in_Iceland)</p><p><span>Ironically, financial recovery seems to have helped the political party (Independence) who had been blamed for the 2008 banking crisis. Parliamentary elections were held in April 2013 and Independence </span><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-22320282" rel="">stormed back to power</a><span>. With their fellow Eurosceptic party, the Progressive Party, which also won 19 seats, they formed a coalition government which held 38 seats of the Alþingi’s 63 seats. In September 2013 the </span><a href="https://www.euractiv.com/section/eu-priorities-2020/news/iceland-walks-out-on-eu-membership-talks/" rel="">Eurosceptic government dissolved its accession team</a><span> and suspended its application to join the EU. Then in March 2015, the Foreign Minister, Gunnar Bragi Sveinsson, announced he had written a letter to Brussels saying that Iceland’s application to join the EU was cancelled. This caused huge political blowback in Iceland because the Alþingi had note voted for this action to be taken, so there were huge questions about the power of the Foreign Minister and the legitimacy of this action. On the EU side, a spokesperson for the European Union's Enlargement Commissioner said that the EU has taken note of the letter from the Icelandic government </span><a href="https://www.ruv.is/frettir/erlent/umsoknin-ekki-formlega-dregin-til-baka" rel="">but that the application had yet to be formally withdrawn</a><span>. Three days later, on March 15 2015, there were protests against the government’s unilateral behaviour in front of the Icelandic Parliament building.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png" width="600" height="445" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:445,&quot;width&quot;:600,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:661956,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8902c189-fdbf-413d-9f39-4e43e3c834f0_600x445.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><h6>Picture from anti-withdrawal protest on March 15, 2015 in front of Icelandic Parliament building. The sign reads “Við ráðum”, which means “We decide” or “We are in charge”, referring to the will of the people vs the Minister’s lone action. Photographer: G. Pétur Matthíasson</h6><p>However, despite the protests, this action effectively ended the EU accession negotiations until the revival in the last few days – nearly a decade later. In the 2016 elections, Independence increased its lead to 21 seats (although Progressive Party tumbled), in the 2017 elections they led again with 16 seats forming a coalition with Progressives and Left-Green, and then in 2021, that coalition held. So 2024 has provided the second break from decades long dominance of the Independence Party. Through all this time, there was broad agreement in the public that a referendum was needed on whether to continue or cancel the accession talks.</p><p>Since the opening of accession talks, there has been polling on whether the public at large are, in principle, for or against joining the EU. From 2010 through to 2022, the answer was “no”. Although that “no” was declining slowly over time, it was clearly “no” until 2022 when a remarkable crossover happened:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png" width="1456" height="975" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:975,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:672190,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffa9470a8-12c4-4225-b5bd-0c6ee15757df_2008x1344.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><h6>Polling data courtesy of Jón Steindór Valdimarsson</h6><p><span>Putin’s invasion of Ukraine shocked many in Europe – and in Iceland it reignited the sense of vulnerability that Icelanders felt about Russia and also their currency in a turbulent world. Since that point, the polling lead for “yes” has been sustained consistently over several time points during the last two years. In the latest poll, the &gt;11% gap would translate into a 57% yes vs 43% no in a referendum where “don’t knows” are excluded. Beyond concerns about Russia and the more unstable world that can knock around their currency so easily, there is the relationship with the US. After WWII, the US became something of the protector of Iceland, with </span><a href="https://www.government.is/diplomatic-missions/embassy-of-iceland-in-washington-d.c/iceland-and-the-us" rel="">a bilateral defence agreement in 1951</a><span> and a US military base in Iceland. In fact, the cod wars against the British fishing fleets were finally resolved in Iceland’s favour by the US wading in to protect Iceland and its geographic strategic importance in NATO. With Russian threats menacing norther Europe, but a new president in the US who shows very little interest in NATO or keeping back Russia, Icelanders worry that Trump would have no interest in defending Iceland, especially given that the US base in Iceland no longer hosts army troops. I’m sure Icelanders were not enamoured to hear Trump’s </span><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/donald-trump/trump-says-ownership-greenland-absolute-necessity-rcna185197" rel="">very recent rekindled pronouncements on Greenland</a><span> either.</span></p><p><span>The “Yes, Iceland” campaign that started in 2009 had shut down in 2015, following the Foreign Minister’s letter. So </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J%C3%B3n_Steind%C3%B3r_Valdimarsson" rel="">Jón Steindór Valdimarsson</a><span>, and Icelandic ex-MP (2017-2021) from the Social Democratic Alliance set up </span><a href="https://evropa.is/" rel="">Evrópuhreyfingin</a><span> (European Movement Iceland) in May 2022 to campaign firstly for a referendum on continuing Iceland’s EU accession talks and then to campaign for Iceland to join the EU. They have 1,600 members I am told and I’ve just received their Christmas email celebrating the announcement of the referendum and looking to mobilise their base.</span></p><p><span>I’ll be blunt – I wrote this section header before it was announced that there will be a referendum before 2027. That announcement caught me off-guard. I began writing this piece on Dec 9</span><sup>th</sup><span> after a long chat with Jón (the European Movement Iceland founder) and I started documenting the history of Iceland-EU relations and requesting data and materials from Jón for a write up. I had been under the impression that the whole question of *whether* the new government would tackle the issue of joining the EU would happen in the new year, maybe even in Feb.</span></p><p><span>So, it’s clearly “game on” already. Note that the new Icelandic government also announced that it would </span><a href="https://schengen.news/icelands-new-government-plans-to-put-eu-accession-to-referendum-by-2027" rel="">assemble a panel of experts to analyse</a><span> the advantages and disadvantages of adopting the Euro. I do not know whether this would happen in parallel to a referendum on accession talks, but I imagine it would be planned that major conclusions of this panel would be presented to the public ahead of any vote on accession talks.</span></p><p><span>Also, a note of caution. When David Cameron came to power in 2015 on the promise of a referendum on the UK’s membership of the EU, he had promised that the referendum would happen </span><a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-21148282" rel="">before the end of 2017</a><span>. In reality, he </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2016/feb/20/cameron-set-to-name-eu-referendum-date-after-cabinet-meeting" rel="">decided in Feb 2016</a><span> that the referendum would be held in four months’ time. Similarly in Iceland, the government have the power to announce the referendum at any point between now and the end of 2017 and may feel that sooner rather than later they want to put the issue to the people and not let the debate drag on for three long years, likely consuming a huge amount of the political bandwidth during that time and impeding progress in other areas of policy. All governments fall out of favour over time, so getting the balance right between not rushing it to the detriment of public education and good referendum structure (as Cameron did) but not letting it string out until it feels more like a burden than an opportunity, will be important.</span></p><p><span>One thing that few people (at least in the UK) have considered is what Iceland joining the EU would mean for EFTA (4 members) and the EEA agreement (3 EFTA members). According to Per Christiansen, a professor of European law &amp; judge at the EFTA Court from 2011-2023, the </span><a href="https://www.ruv.is/english/2024-11-22-norway-keenly-watching-icelandic-election-428442" rel="">days of the EEA Agreement would be numbered</a><span> if Iceland became an EU member. Essentially, to reduce the EEA agreement to just Norway and the Principality of Liechtenstein (population under 40,000) would make the institutions difficult to maintain with any real meaning. Similarly with EFTA per se, are they really going to maintain the EFTA Court and the negotiators to effectively keep just copying EU trade deals?</span></p><p>Beyond a departing Iceland taking EFTA and the EEA agreements to under critical mass for any notion of a club of members, there are also the other aspects that could cause a domino effect upon Norway in particular. Norway and Iceland are culturally close. Norway also has a European Movement, which is aiming to get Norway into the EU and which talks regularly with European Movement Iceland. They watch each other.</p><p><span>Like in Iceland, the 2022 invasion of Ukraine by Putin shifted the conversation in Norway about potentially joining the EU and shifted the dial on polling. Some 30 years after Norway last shut down the option (in 1994) there’s bubbling conversation about whether the </span><a href="https://www.newsinenglish.no/2024/11/29/new-eu-debate-rises-in-norway/" rel="">newest generation of Norwegians should have their say</a><span>. A report published in April 2024 on the Norwegian-EEA relationship has also added to the debate, with the leader of the Liberal Party saying that </span><a href="http://www.nordiclabourjournal.org/i-fokus/in-focus-2024/theme-the-nordic-region-and-the-eu/article.2024-04-25.6671548437" rel="">Norway is better off participating in the politics</a><span> that decide the rules of its labour market rather than just receiving them from other countries.</span></p><p>And resistance to EU membership is falling in Norway - 48% would now vote no to the EU, down from 54% three years ago and 70% in 2016. That’s still ahead of the 32% that would vote yes, but the gap is shrinking quickly. The general wisdom is that if there were an external factor (such as Iceland leaving EEA &amp; EFTA – and joining the EU and, with it, the EU’s fishing policy), then that could be enough for Norway to get shaken out of its comfortably rich-but-obsolete model and also seriously consider joining the EU.</p><p>There are lots of potential dynamics here for European Movement UK’s drive for the UK to join the EU. Firstly, of course, there’s the story that alongside Moldova, Ukraine, Georgia and Eastern European countries looking to join the team of the European Union, there’s also the western European countries of Iceland and Norway. That changes how the EU is perceived and it points to the fact the attraction of the EU is very real to an increasing number of nations and, far from “falling apart”, the EU is fundamentally growing as a perceived guarantor of stability and shared strength.</p><p>There is also the fascinating dynamic of EFTA-EEA and what it means if those associations collapse in favour of the EU. I don’t believe it was ever a realistic proposition that the UK joined EFTA, however, the notion that there’s some half-way house to land in would somewhat vapourise if EFTA became no more. That may remove a stepping-stone to the EU… but it could also remove the potential to get stuck in an inadequate compromise position that we languish in, when full EU membership was always the thing to go for.</p><p>Finally, the model that Iceland is pursuing in its journey mirrors the one that I currently believe we should take – namely an initial referendum (simple majority) on giving our government licence/permission to engage in negotiations… to be followed at a later date by a referendum (probably with a set of thresholds) on an actual deal to be set before the UK public for their approval. Either way, the fact that others in our neighbourhood are moving in a similar direction means that Iceland, Norway and the UK have pro-European contingents that have a shared vision and can learn from each other as we work together over the next years to join the neighbourhood team and strengthen this great continent of ours.</p><p><em>A special note of thanks to Jón Steindór Valdimarsson for taking the time to walk me through so many fascinating stories and dynamics around Iceland’s relationship with Europe and the EU.</em></p></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Average American Spent 2.5 Months on Their Phone in 2024 (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pcmag.com/articles/yikes-the-average-american-spent-25-months-on-their-phone-in-2024</link>
            <guid>42539474</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 12:16:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/articles/yikes-the-average-american-spent-25-months-on-their-phone-in-2024">https://www.pcmag.com/articles/yikes-the-average-american-spent-25-months-on-their-phone-in-2024</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42539474">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.pcmag.com/articles/yikes-the-average-american-spent-25-months-on-their-phone-in-2024: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Run LLMs Locally (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://abishekmuthian.com/how-i-run-llms-locally/</link>
            <guid>42539155</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 10:49:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://abishekmuthian.com/how-i-run-llms-locally/">https://abishekmuthian.com/how-i-run-llms-locally/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42539155">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A HN user asked me<sup><a href="#sources">0</a></sup> how I run LLMs locally with some specific questions, I’m documenting it here for everyone.</p><p>Before I begin I would like to credit the thousands or millions of unknown artists, coders and writers upon whose work the Large Language Models(LLMs) are trained, often without due credit or compensation.</p><h2 id="get-started">Get Started</h2><p>r/LocalLLaMA subreddit<sup><a href="#sources">1</a></sup> &amp; Ollama blog<sup><a href="#sources">2</a></sup> are great places to get started with running LLMs locally.</p><h2 id="hardware">Hardware</h2><p>I have a laptop running Linux with core i9 (32threads) CPU, 4090 GPU (16GB VRAM) and 96 GB of RAM. Models which fit within the VRAM can generate more tokens/second, larger models will be offloaded to RAM (dGPU offloading) and thereby lower tokens/second. I will talk about models in a section below.</p><p>It's not necessary to have such beefy computer for running LLMs locally, smaller models would run fine in older GPUs or in CPU albeit slowly and with more hallucinations.</p><p>There are a number of high quality open-source tools which enable running LLMs locally. These are the tools I use regularly.</p><p>Ollama<sup><a href="#sources">3</a></sup> is a middleware with python, JavaScript libraries for llama.cpp<sup><a href="#sources">4</a></sup> which helps run LLMs. I use Ollama in docker<sup><a href="#sources">5</a></sup>.</p><p>Open WebUI<sup><a href="#sources">6</a></sup> is a frontend which offers familiar chat interface for text and image input and communicates with Ollama back-end and streams the output back to the user.</p><p>llamafile<sup><a href="#sources">7</a></sup> is a single executable file with LLM. It’s probably the easiest way to get started with local LLMs, but I’ve had issues with dGPU offloading in llamafile<sup><a href="#sources">8</a></sup>.</p><p>I’m not a big consumer of image/video generation models, but when needed, I use AUTOMATIC1111<sup><a href="#sources">9</a></sup> for images which require some customisation and Fooocus<sup><a href="#sources">10</a></sup> for simple image generation. For complex workflow automatons with image generation, there’s ComfyUI<sup><a href="#sources">11</a></sup>.</p><p>For code completion I use Continue<sup><a href="#sources">12</a></sup> in VSCode.</p><p>I use Smart Connections<sup><a href="#sources">13</a></sup> in Obsidian<sup><a href="#sources">14</a></sup> to query my notes using Ollama.</p><figure><img alt="Screenshot of Obsidian with chat smart connections extension showing the last journal I write" src="https://abishekmuthian.com/images/obsidian-smart-connections.jpg" width="100%" height="auto" layout="responsive"><figcaption>I asked Smart Connections when I wrote my last journal, I hope to write my journal every day in 2025.</figcaption></figure><h2 id="models">Models</h2><p>I use Ollama models page<sup><a href="#sources">15</a></sup> to download latest LLMs. I use RSS on Thunderbird to keep track of the models. I use CivitAI<sup><a href="#sources">16</a></sup> to download image generation models for specific styles (e.g. Isometric for world building). But be advised that most models in CivitAI seem to be catered towards adult image generation.</p><p>I choose LLMs based on performance/ size. My current choice for LLMs changes frequently due to rapid advancement in LLMs.</p><pre><code>•	Llama3.2 for Smart Connections and generic queries.
•	Deepseek-coder-v2 for code completion in Continue.
•	Qwen2.5-coder for chatting about code in Continue.
•	Stable Diffusion for image generation in AUTOMATIC1111 or Fooocus.
</code></pre><h2 id="updation">Updation</h2><p>I update the docker containers using WatchTower<sup><a href="#sources">17</a></sup> and models from within the Open Web UI.</p><h2 id="fine-tuning-and-quantization">Fine-Tuning and Quantization</h2><p>I haven’t fine-tuned or quantized any models on my machine yet as my Intel CPU may have a manufacturing defect<sup><a href="#sources">18</a></sup> so I don’t want to push it to high temperatures for long durations during training.</p><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2><p>Running LLMs locally gives me total control over my data and lower latency for the responses. None of these would be possible without the open-source projects and <del>open-source</del> free models and original owners of the data upon which these models are trained.</p><p>I will update this post as and when I use newer tools/models.</p><p>[0] <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42537024" target="_blank">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42537024</a></p><p>[1] <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/LocalLLaMA/" target="_blank">https://www.reddit.com/r/LocalLLaMA/</a></p><p>[2] <a href="https://ollama.com/blog" target="_blank">https://ollama.com/blog</a></p><p>[3] <a href="https://ollama.com/download" target="_blank">https://ollama.com/download</a></p><p>[4] <a href="https://github.com/ggerganov/llama.cpp" target="_blank">https://github.com/ggerganov/llama.cpp</a></p><p>[5] <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/ollama/ollama" target="_blank">https://hub.docker.com/r/ollama/ollama</a></p><p>[6] <a href="https://github.com/open-webui/open-webui" target="_blank">https://github.com/open-webui/open-webui</a></p><p>[7] <a href="https://github.com/Mozilla-Ocho/llamafile" target="_blank">https://github.com/Mozilla-Ocho/llamafile</a></p><p>[8] <a href="https://github.com/Mozilla-Ocho/llamafile/issues/611" target="_blank">https://github.com/Mozilla-Ocho/llamafile/issues/611</a></p><p>[9] <a href="https://github.com/AUTOMATIC1111/stable-diffusion-webui" target="_blank">https://github.com/AUTOMATIC1111/stable-diffusion-webui</a></p><p>[10] <a href="https://github.com/lllyasviel/Fooocus" target="_blank">https://github.com/lllyasviel/Fooocus</a></p><p>[11] <a href="https://github.com/comfyanonymous/ComfyUI" target="_blank">https://github.com/comfyanonymous/ComfyUI</a></p><p>[12] <a href="https://docs.continue.dev/getting-started/overview" target="_blank">https://docs.continue.dev/getting-started/overview</a></p><p>[13] <a href="https://github.com/brianpetro/obsidian-smart-connections" target="_blank">https://github.com/brianpetro/obsidian-smart-connections</a></p><p>[14] <a href="https://obsidian.md/" target="_blank">https://obsidian.md</a></p><p>[15] <a href="https://ollama.com/search" target="_blank">https://ollama.com/search</a></p><p>[16] <a href="https://civitai.com/models/63376/isometric-chinese-style-architecture-lora" target="_blank">https://civitai.com/models/63376/isometric-chinese-style-architecture-lora</a></p><p>[17] <a href="https://containrrr.dev/watchtower/" target="_blank">https://containrrr.dev/watchtower/</a></p><p>[18] <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raptor_Lake#Instability_and_degradation_issue" target="_blank">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Raptor_Lake#Instability_and_degradation_issue</a></p></div><p>I strive to write low frequency, High quality content on Health, Product Development, Programming, Software Engineering, DIY, Security, Philosophy and other interests.
If you would like to receive them in your email inbox then please consider subscribing to my <a href="http://eepurl.com/if97pb" target="_blank">Newsletter</a>.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We've not been trained for this: life after the Newag DRM disclosure [video] (330 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-we-ve-not-been-trained-for-this-life-after-the-newag-drm-disclosure</link>
            <guid>42538914</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 09:48:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-we-ve-not-been-trained-for-this-life-after-the-newag-drm-disclosure">https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-we-ve-not-been-trained-for-this-life-after-the-newag-drm-disclosure</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42538914">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-we-ve-not-been-trained-for-this-life-after-the-newag-drm-disclosure: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[BioTerrorism Will Save Your Life with the 4 Thieves Vinegar Collective [video] (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-bioterrorism-will-save-your-life-with-the-4-thieves-vinegar-collective</link>
            <guid>42538903</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 09:47:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-bioterrorism-will-save-your-life-with-the-4-thieves-vinegar-collective">https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-bioterrorism-will-save-your-life-with-the-4-thieves-vinegar-collective</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42538903">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>
<span></span>
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/search?p=Dr.+Mix%C3%A6l+Swan+Laufer">Dr. Mixæl Swan Laufer</a>

</p>

<p><a href="https://media.ccc.de/c/38c3/Ethics,%20Society%20&amp;%20Politics" rel="tag">Ethics, Society &amp; Politics</a>
Playlists:
<a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-bioterrorism-will-save-your-life-with-the-4-thieves-vinegar-collective/playlist">'38c3' videos starting here</a>
/
<a data-method="get" href="https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-bioterrorism-will-save-your-life-with-the-4-thieves-vinegar-collective/audio">audio</a></p>
<!-- %h3 About -->
<p>Governments have criminalized the practice of managing your own health. Despite the fact that for most of human history bodily autonomy, and self-managed health was the norm, it is now required that most aspects of your health must be mediated by an institution deputized by the state. Taking those rights back for yourself is then labeled "BioTerrorism". So be it. Let's learn how.</p>

<p>We all know that custom, hand-made, artisan-crafted, boutique tools are always better than something factory made. A guitar, a wood chisel, a chef's knife, a built racing engine, a firearm, a suit, a pair of shoes. Given that this is so well-known, and so universally understood, it's peculiar at best that this is not seen by most people when it comes to medicine. It is however also true. </p>

<p>Given, however, that the traditional rôle of pharmacists who used to have the freedom to compound custom medicines for the people they were serving has been revoked, and now despite their extensive training, have been limited to being able to do little more than count pills in most cases, we have to do this ourselves. </p>

<p>The problem is that this has been criminalized. The moment you stop groveling for permission from medical authorities, and start becoming actively involved in managing your own health, you are a criminal in most countries in the world. Practicing medicine without a license, manufacture of drugs, possession of laboratory tools, possession of precursor chemicals... the list of felonies goes on. </p>

<p>The choice is yours. Would you like to be the sickest law-abiding citizen, or the healthiest BioTerrorist? If you want the red pill, you'll have to manufacture it yourself. The blue pill is prescription-only, and if you manage to get a prescription, and you're rich maybe you can afford to buy it. </p>

<p>Come learn about the long list of medications which went through the research and development processes, but are never going to be commercially available. Learn how to find more of these, and learn the many ways you can make them yourself.</p>

<p>Licensed to the public under http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</p>

<h3>Download</h3>
<div>

<div>
<h4>These files contain multiple languages.</h4>
<p>
This Talk was translated into multiple languages. The files available
for download contain all languages as separate audio-tracks. Most
desktop video players allow you to choose between them.
</p>
<p>
Please look for "audio tracks" in your desktop video player.
</p>
</div>
<div>
<p>
<h4>Audio</h4>
</p>

</div>
</div>
<!-- %h3 Embed/Share -->

<h3>Tags</h3>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[38C3: Illegal Instructions (405 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://media.ccc.de/c/38c3</link>
            <guid>42537631</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 04:54:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://media.ccc.de/c/38c3">https://media.ccc.de/c/38c3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42537631">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://media.ccc.de/c/38c3: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WebGL Fluid Simulation (325 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://paveldogreat.github.io/WebGL-Fluid-Simulation/</link>
            <guid>42537567</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 04:39:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://paveldogreat.github.io/WebGL-Fluid-Simulation/">https://paveldogreat.github.io/WebGL-Fluid-Simulation/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42537567">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://paveldogreat.github.io/WebGL-Fluid-Simulation/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can LLMs accurately recall the Bible? (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://benkaiser.dev/can-llms-accurately-recall-the-bible/</link>
            <guid>42537332</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 03:44:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://benkaiser.dev/can-llms-accurately-recall-the-bible/">https://benkaiser.dev/can-llms-accurately-recall-the-bible/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42537332">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    <p>I've often found myself uneasy when LLMs (Large Language Models) are asked to quote the Bible. While they can provide insightful discussions about faith, their tendency to hallucinate responses raises concerns when dealing with scripture, which we regard as the inspired Word of God.</p><p>To explore these concerns, I created a benchmark to evaluate how accurately LLMs can recall scripture word for word. Here's a breakdown of my methodology and the test results.</p><h3 id="methodology">Methodology</h3><p>To ensure consistent and fair evaluation, I tested each model using six scenarios designed to measure their ability to accurately recall scripture. For readers interested in the technical details, <a href="https://github.com/benkaiser/llm-compare?ref=benkaiser.dev">the source code for the tests is available here</a>. All tests were conducted with a temperature setting of 0, and I have given slack to the models by making the pass check case and whitespace insensitive.</p><p>A temperature of 0 ensures the models generate the most statistically probable response at each step, minimising creativity or variability and prioritising accuracy. This approach is particularly important when evaluating fixed reference material like the Bible, where precise wording matters.</p><!--kg-card-begin: html--><!--kg-card-end: html--><h3 id="test-1-popular-scripture-recall">Test 1: Popular Scripture Recall</h3><!--kg-card-begin: html--><table>
      <tbody><tr>
        <th>Model</th>
        <th>Pass</th>
      </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 8B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o mini</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 2.0 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
    </tbody></table><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>When asking a model to recall John 3:16 in the NIV translation, the only model that failed to accurately recall the verse word for word was Llama 3.3 70B. It was only a very slight translation mismatch, with it recalling "only begotten son" where the actual verse in the NIV does not include begotten, despite it being present in other translations.</p><h3 id="test-2-obscure-verse-recall">Test 2: Obscure Verse Recall</h3><!--kg-card-begin: html--><table>
      <tbody><tr>
        <th>Model</th>
        <th>Pass</th>
      </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 70B</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 8B</td>
          <td>❌</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
          <td>❌</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o mini</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Flash</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 2.0 Flash</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
    </tbody></table><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>Many models struggled to recall Obadiah 1:16 NIV word for word, often mixing up the words with other translations. For these cases, I have marked them as partial for correctly recalling the verse in <em>some</em> translation, even if not the specific requested one. The models that clearly succeeded seem to be very large models, 405B for Llama and GPT 4o and Claude 3.5 Sonnet.</p><h3 id="test-3-verse-continuation">Test 3: Verse Continuation</h3><!--kg-card-begin: html--><table>
      <tbody><tr>
        <th>Model</th>
        <th>Pass</th>
      </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 8B</td>
          <td>❌</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o mini</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Flash</td>
          <td>❌</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 2.0 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
    </tbody></table><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>When quoting the model 2 Chronicles 11:13 (but without specifying where in the bible it is found) and asking it to produce the immediate next verse, we had a much more mixed bag of results. Many medium-to-large sized models got this correct, but the smaller ones completely hallucinated parts or all of the verse. Claude 3.5 Haiku almost recalled the verse, but referred to the Levites as "they", which is not explicitly a translation in any of the more well known translations and appears to be the model substituting the intention of the word rather than the exact one.</p><h3 id="test-4-verse-block-recall">Test 4: Verse Block Recall</h3><!--kg-card-begin: html--><table>
      <tbody><tr>
        <th>Model</th>
        <th>Pass</th>
      </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 8B</td>
          <td>❌</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o mini</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Flash</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 2.0 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
          <td>⚠️</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
    </tbody></table><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>When asked to recall Lamentations chapter 3 verses 19 through 24, the models did this very well. Only the smallest of the models, Llama 3.1 8B outright failed here, instead recalling the beginning of the chapter. The two warnings were only slight translation mismatches of a few words, but the essence of the verse was preserved.</p><h3 id="test-5-query-based-lookup">Test 5: Query Based Lookup</h3><!--kg-card-begin: html--><table>
      <tbody><tr>
        <th>Model</th>
        <th>Pass</th>
      </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 8B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o mini</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 2.0 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
    </tbody></table><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>Asking the models, "What's that verse in the bible about the Earth being filled with knowledge of God's glory?", all of them successfully recalled it was Habakkuk 2:14. Verse lookup is definitely a strong-suit, even in smaller models.</p><h3 id="test-6-entire-chapter-recall">Test 6: Entire Chapter Recall</h3><!--kg-card-begin: html--><table>
      <tbody><tr>
        <th>Model</th>
        <th>Pass</th>
      </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.1 8B</td>
          <td>❌</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>GPT 4o mini</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 1.5 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Gemini 2.0 Flash</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
        <tr>
          <td>Claude 3.5 Sonnet</td>
          <td>✅</td>
        </tr>
      
    </tbody></table><!--kg-card-end: html--><p>When asking for the entire contents of Romans 6 in the KJV translation, almost all of the models recalled all 23 verses accurately. Even the failed case of Llama 3.1 8B recalled over 98% of the words correctly, with only 9 incorrect words. </p><h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2><p>If you really want to lean on an LLM to give you textually accurate bible verses of popular translations, you really should lean on higher parameter count (i.e. larger) models. These include models like Llama 405B, OpenAI GPT 4o and Claude Sonnet which all had perfect scores. Smaller models (7B range) will often mix up translations, and in some cases even mix up or hallucinate verse altogether. Medium-sized models (70B range) often accurately preserve the intention of the verses, although the verse may be a mangled representation of several translations, and in some cases paraphrased a little by the LLM.</p><p>You can certainly still use smaller models for discussion that references scripture by Book/Chapter/Verse, but it is important to lean on an actual copy of the Bible for the correct text in these cases.</p><p>Looking into the future, we may very well see smaller models perform better on these benchmarks, but there is surely a limitation to how much information can be encoded into such small models.</p><p>For full test results, see <a href="https://benkaiser.github.io/llm-compare/results-with-responses.html?ref=benkaiser.dev">the results file here</a>, including the raw prompts for each test. If you feel like I missed a crucial test, feel free to <a href="https://github.com/benkaiser/llm-compare/issues/new?ref=benkaiser.dev">submit an issue on GitHub</a>.</p>
                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Personal Mail Server on OpenBSD (2019) (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nicolascarpi.github.io/openbsd/2019/04/03/openbsd-mail-server.html</link>
            <guid>42536750</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 01:58:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nicolascarpi.github.io/openbsd/2019/04/03/openbsd-mail-server.html">https://nicolascarpi.github.io/openbsd/2019/04/03/openbsd-mail-server.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42536750">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://nicolascarpi.github.io/openbsd/2019/04/03/openbsd-mail-server.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jeju Air accident in South Korea kills at least 47 (224 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-12-29/plane-crashes-at-s-korea-airport-killing-at-least-23-yonhap</link>
            <guid>42536647</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 01:40:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-12-29/plane-crashes-at-s-korea-airport-killing-at-least-23-yonhap">https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-12-29/plane-crashes-at-s-korea-airport-killing-at-least-23-yonhap</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42536647">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
    <section>
        <h3>Why did this happen?</h3>
        <p>Please make sure your browser supports JavaScript and cookies and that you are not
            blocking them from loading.
            For more information you can review our <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Terms of
                Service</a> and <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Cookie Policy</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <h3>Need Help?</h3>
        <p>For inquiries related to this message please <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/feedback">contact
            our support team</a> and provide the reference ID below.</p>
        <p>Block reference ID:</p>
    </section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[38C3: Blinkencity, radio controlling street lamps and power plants [video] (185 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-blinkencity-radio-controlling-street-lamps-and-power-plants</link>
            <guid>42535622</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 23:02:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-blinkencity-radio-controlling-street-lamps-and-power-plants">https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-blinkencity-radio-controlling-street-lamps-and-power-plants</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42535622">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://media.ccc.de/v/38c3-blinkencity-radio-controlling-street-lamps-and-power-plants: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[All You Need Is 4x 4090 GPUs to Train Your Own Model (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sabareesh.com/posts/llm-rig/</link>
            <guid>42535453</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 22:37:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sabareesh.com/posts/llm-rig/">https://sabareesh.com/posts/llm-rig/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42535453">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://sabareesh.com/posts/llm-rig/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>