<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 13:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You'll regret using natural keys (503 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.ploeh.dk/2024/06/03/youll-regret-using-natural-keys/</link>
            <guid>40580549</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 01:25:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.ploeh.dk/2024/06/03/youll-regret-using-natural-keys/">https://blog.ploeh.dk/2024/06/03/youll-regret-using-natural-keys/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40580549">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post">
    <p>
        <em>Beating another dead horse.</em>
    </p>
    <p>
        Although I live in Copenhagen and mostly walk or ride my bicycle in order to get around town, I do own an old car for getting around the rest of the country. In Denmark, cars go through mandatory official inspection every other year, and I've been through a few of these in my life. A few years ago, the mechanic doing the inspection informed me that my car's <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vehicle_identification_number">chassis number</a> was incorrect.
    </p>
    <p>
        This did make me a bit nervous, because I'd bought the car used, and I was suddenly concerned that things weren't really as I thought. Had I unwittingly bought a stolen car?
    </p>
    <p>
        But the mechanic just walked over to his computer in order to correct the error. That's when a different kind of unease hit me. When you've programmed for some decades, you learn to foresee various typical failure modes. Since a chassis number is an obvious candidate for a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Natural_key">natural key</a>, I already predicted that changing the number would prove to be either impossible, or have all sorts of cascading effects, ultimately terminating in official records no longer recognizing that the car is mine.
    </p>
    <p>
        As it turned out, though, whoever made that piece of software knew what they were doing, because the mechanic just changed the chassis number, and that was that. This is now five or six years ago, and I still own the same car, and I've never had any problems with the official ownership records.
    </p>
    <h3 id="8a38dcbfae1146f8868fe8a408ffe5d8">
        Uniqueness <a href="#8a38dcbfae1146f8868fe8a408ffe5d8">#</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
        The reason I related this story is that I'm currently following an undergraduate course in databases and information systems. Since this course is aimed at students with no real-world experience, it wisely moves forward in a pedagogical progression. In order to teach database keys, it starts with natural keys. From a didactic perspective, this makes sense, but the result, so far, is that the young people I work with now propose database designs with natural keys.
    </p>
    <p>
        I'm not blaming anyone. You have to learn to crawl before you can walk.
    </p>
    <p>
        Still, this situation made me reflect on the following question: <em>Are natural keys ever a good idea?</em>
    </p>
    <p>
        Let's consider an example. For a little project we're doing, we've created a database of <a href="https://www.theworlds50best.com/">the World's 50 best restaurants</a>. My fellow students suggest a table design like this:
    </p>
    <pre><span>CREATE</span>&nbsp;<span>TABLE</span>&nbsp;Restaurants<span>&nbsp;</span><span>(</span>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>year</span>&nbsp;<span>TEXT</span>&nbsp;<span>NOT</span>&nbsp;<span>NULL,</span>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span>rank</span>&nbsp;<span>TEXT</span>&nbsp;<span>NOT</span>&nbsp;<span>NULL,</span>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;restaurantName&nbsp;<span>TEXT</span>&nbsp;<span>NOT</span>&nbsp;<span>NULL,</span>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;cityName&nbsp;<span>TEXT</span>&nbsp;<span>NOT</span>&nbsp;<span>NULL</span>
<span>);</span></pre>
    
    <p>
        Granted, at this point, this table definition defines no key at all. I'm not complaining about that. After all, a month ago, the students probably hadn't seen a database table.
    </p>
    <p>
        From following the course curriculum, it'd be natural, however, to define a key for the <code>Restaurants</code> table as the combination of <code>restaurantName</code>, <code>cityName</code>, and <code>year</code>. The assumption is that name and city uniquely identifies a restaurant.
    </p>
    <p>
        In this particular example, this assumption may actually turn out to hold. So far. After all, the data set isn't that big, and it's important for restaurants in that league to have recognizable names. If I had to guess, I'd say that there's probably only one <a href="https://www.nobelhartundschmutzig.com/">Nobelhart &amp; Schmutzig</a> in the world.
    </p>
    <p>
        Still, a good software architect should challenge the underlying assumptions. Is name and city a <em>natural</em> key? It's easy to imagine that it's not. What if we expand the key to include the country as well? Okay, but what if we had a restaurant named <em>China Wok</em> in Springfield, USA? Hardly unique. Add the state, you say? Probably still not unique.
    </p>
    <h3 id="778bd217e62d4ffca25f487a39d34c1a">
        Identity <a href="#778bd217e62d4ffca25f487a39d34c1a">#</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
        Ensuring uniqueness is only the first of many problems with natural keys. You may quickly reach the conclusion that for a restaurant database, a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Surrogate_key">synthetic key</a> is probably the best choice.
    </p>
    <p>
        But what about 'natural' natural keys, so to speak? An example may be a car's chassis number. This is already an opaque number, and it probably originates from a database somewhere. Or how about a personal identification number? In Denmark we have the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Personal_identification_number_(Denmark)">CPR number</a>, and I understand that the US <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_Security_number">Social Security Number</a> is vaguely analogous.
    </p>
    <p>
        If you're designing a database that already includes such a personal identification number, you might be tempted to use it as a natural key. After all, it's already a key somewhere else, so it's guaranteed to be unique, right?
    </p>
    <p>
        Yes, the number may uniquely identify a person, but the converse may not be true. A person may have more than one identification number. At least when time is a factor.
    </p>
    <p>
        As an example, for technical-historical reasons, the Danish CPR number carries information (which keys shouldn't do), such as a person's date of birth and sex. Since 2014 a new law enables transsexual citizens to get a new CPR number that reflects their perceived gender. The consequence is that the same person may have more than one CPR number. Perhaps not more than one at the same time, but definitely two during a lifetime.
    </p>
    <p>
        Even if existing keys are guaranteed to be unique, you can't assume that the uniqueness gives rise to a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bijection">bijection</a>. If you use an external unique key, you may lose track of the entities that you're trying to keep track of.
    </p>
    <p>
        This is true not only for people, but cars, bicycles (which also have chassis numbers), network cards, etc.
    </p>
    <h3 id="93d43ca6c76a4c6c83e9542bb671f39c">
        Clerical errors <a href="#93d43ca6c76a4c6c83e9542bb671f39c">#</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
        Finally, even if you've found a natural key that is guaranteed to be unique <em>and</em> track the actual entity that you want to keep track of, there's a final argument against using an externally defined key in your system: Data-entry errors.
    </p>
    <p>
        Take the story about my car's chassis number. The mechanic who spotted the discrepancy clearly interpreted it as a clerical error.
    </p>
    <p>
        After a few decades of programming, I've learned that sooner or later, there <em>will</em> be errors in your data. Either it's a clerical error, or the end-user mistyped, or there was a data conversion error when importing from an external system. Or even data conversion errors within the <em>same</em> system, as it goes through upgrades and migrations.
    </p>
    <p>
        Your system should be designed to allow corrections to data. This includes corrections of external keys, such as chassis numbers, government IDs, etc. This means that you can't use such keys as database keys in your own system.
    </p>
    <h3 id="ca9efd721698452f856b089fc3f69ad1">
        Heuristic <a href="#ca9efd721698452f856b089fc3f69ad1">#</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
        Many were the times, earlier in my career, when I decided to use a 'natural key' as a key in my own database. As far as I recall, I've regretted it every single time.
    </p>
    <p>
        These days I follow a hard heuristic: Always use synthetic keys for database tables.
    </p>
    <h3 id="c174062e2ad14b6a9ff4056b1de80a0f">
        Conclusion <a href="#c174062e2ad14b6a9ff4056b1de80a0f">#</a>
    </h3>
    <p>
        Is it ever a good idea to use natural keys in a database design? My experience tells me that it's not. Ultimately, regardless of how certain you can be that the natural key is stable and correctly tracks the entity that it's supposed to keep track of, data errors will occur. This includes errors in those natural keys.
    </p>
    <p>
        You should be able to correct such errors without losing track of the involved entities. You'll regret using natural keys. Use synthetic keys.
    </p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[macOS Bartender Auto-Update Signed by Unknown New Owner (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/04/bartender-mac-app-new-owner/</link>
            <guid>40579660</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 22:34:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/04/bartender-mac-app-new-owner/">https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/04/bartender-mac-app-new-owner/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40579660">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" id="maincontent"><article expanded="true"><div data-io-article-url="/2024/06/04/bartender-mac-app-new-owner/"><p>Popular Mac app Bartender appears to have been quietly sold approximately two months ago, with neither the prior owner nor the current owner providing customers or potential customers with information on the sale.</p>
<p><img src="https://images.macrumors.com/t/sWndGhdSp0x_oZUMjyWjfXgMI4M=/400x0/article-new/2024/06/bartender-app.jpg?lossy" srcset="https://images.macrumors.com/t/sWndGhdSp0x_oZUMjyWjfXgMI4M=/400x0/article-new/2024/06/bartender-app.jpg?lossy 400w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/Pb_br6hlCBm9ECgSrDK3mIGBCpk=/800x0/article-new/2024/06/bartender-app.jpg?lossy 800w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/e7MJBthJKSGVCHXe4f_AqqA34mI=/1600x0/article-new/2024/06/bartender-app.jpg 1600w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/uFa-g-GLLTYO9mTXVRqgh_iTn94=/2500x0/filters:no_upscale()/article-new/2024/06/bartender-app.jpg 2500w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 697px" alt="bartender app" width="2128" height="1197"><br>The transaction came to light after some Reddit users saw a <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/macapps/comments/1d7zjv8/bartender_5_not_safe_anymore_warning_from/">warning from MacUpdater</a> letting them know that the company behind Bartender had been silently replaced. MacUpdater warned users that updates to the app from version 5.0.52 could be potentially unsafe due to the lack of transparency surrounding the situation.</p>
<p>Bartender's new owners replied to the Reddit thread and confirmed that Bartender had been acquired, but did not explain why customers had not been notified nor why there had been a certificate change without said explanation.<br>
</p>
<blockquote><p>Hey everyone, new owners of Bartender here! Our team acquired Bartender from Ben S, the original developer, two months ago. As we prepare to roll out updates for Bartender, we needed to re-sign the app with Apple using our company's information, replacing Ben's. This led to a one-time certificate change.</p>
<p>Truth be told, we should have notated it on the release notes but, since we could not update them retroactively, we included this fact on our blog &amp; shared it with users as they emailed us. We've collaborated closely with Ben to understand his vision for Bartender. Our goal is to implement many of the improvements he had planned and address any reported bugs from the past few months to enhance Bartender's performance.</p></blockquote>
<p>Reddit users asked Bartender's owners for more information on their identity, but there was no response. The Bartender website was updated with information about the certificate change after users began seeing popups asking for new permissions, and while the blog post calls the new certificate request "expected and valid," no background information is provided on the purchase. In the Reddit thread, the owners claim to have posted information about the sale on the website, but that has turned out to be untrue.</p>
<p>At this point, it does not appear that Bartender's new owners plan to inform customers about the change in ownership, but users should be aware that the app has been sold and is no longer being updated by the original developer. The new owner's intentions are not clear, but as Reddit users have pointed out, the situation raises some red flags.</p>
</div></article><p><h2>Popular Stories</h2></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/04/us-carriers-call-outage/">Some AT&amp;T, T-Mobile and Verizon Customers Report Issues With Calls [Update: Fixed]</a></h3><p>Tuesday June 4, 2024 10:51 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>There appears to be an outage with at least one U.S. cellular carrier, with customers unable to place or receive calls. AT&amp;T, T-Mobile, and Verizon customers have been complaining about the issue on social networks, and there are also reports of outages on the Down Detector website. According to a statement from AT&amp;T, the outage is affecting calls between carriers in the United States. All...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/02/gurman-no-new-hardware-at-wwdc-2024/">Gurman: No Hardware at WWDC, Next Apple TV No Longer Coming Soon</a></h3><p>Bloomberg's Mark Gurman does not expect Apple to announce any new hardware during its WWDC 2024 keynote on June 10. "There's no hardware slated to be announced at WWDC, unless Apple unexpectedly previews a new device launching later (to be clear: I don't expect that)," said Gurman, in his Power On newsletter today. Notably, Gurman now says a new Apple TV model "isn't imminent," despite...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/03/sonos-ace-vs-airpods-max/">Sonos Ace Headphones vs. AirPods Max</a></h3><p>Monday June 3, 2024 6:01 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>Sonos in May decided to get into the headphone market with the launch of the Sonos Ace headphones. The $449 Sonos Ace headphones have some enticing design elements and features you won't see in Apple's headphones, so we thought we'd compare them to the $549 AirPods Max to see which is ultimately better. Subscribe to the MacRumors YouTube channel for more videos. In terms of design, both the...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/04/ios-18-these-iphones-wont-support-ai/">iOS 18: These iPhones Likely Won't Support Some AI Features</a></h3><p>Apple is planning a major AI overhaul in iOS 18, but some new features are unlikely to work on older iPhones, even if they do appear on the new operating system's device compatibility list. Apple's initial AI roadmap for iOS 18 is said to come in two parts: Basic AI features that will be processed on-device, and more advanced capabilities that will require communication with Apple's servers. ...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/06/03/iphone-16-pro-thinnest-bezels-smartphone/">iPhone 16 Pro Could Break Record for Thinnest Bezels on a Smartphone</a></h3><p>Apple's upcoming iPhone 16 Pro models will have the thinnest bezels of any smartphone, beating the screen border thinness of even its latest iPhone 15 Pro devices. That's according to the leaker known as "Ice Universe," who has divulged accurate information about Apple's plans in the past. According to multiple sources, despite minimal design changes, both iPhone 16 Pro models will increase...</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[An animated introduction to Fourier series (436 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.andreinc.net/2024/04/24/from-the-circle-to-epicycles</link>
            <guid>40578705</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 20:39:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.andreinc.net/2024/04/24/from-the-circle-to-epicycles">https://www.andreinc.net/2024/04/24/from-the-circle-to-epicycles</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40578705">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section itemprop="text">
        
        <p>This article will be part of a more extended series in which I plan to explore various aspects of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourier_analysis">Fourier Mathematics</a>. I will take notes, create some visuals (a good pretext to learn more about graphics), and hope that it will be useful to someone other than me.</p>

<p>The article has yet to be thoroughly reviewed by anyone other than me, so I put it online, hoping to get some feedback before bringing it to a final state.</p>

<h2 id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>

<p>In this series, we will start with a brief recap of some of the math concepts related to the circle, including trigonometric functions like sine and cosine. We’ll also discuss Euler’s identity, introduce the concept of a sinusoid (and complex sinusoid), and finally, we’ll introduce the concept of Fourier Series.</p>

<p>The animations used in this series are original, although I drew inspiration from some existing materials found on the web. Please keep in mind that this is not a comprehensive course on the topic, so if you’re really interested in learning more, I recommend taking a full course on the subject.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="#the-circle">The Circle</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-number-pi">The number \(\pi\)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#radians">Radians</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-sine-and-the-cosine">The sine and the cosine</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-cos-leads-the-sin">The \(\cos\) leads the \(\sin\)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-parity-of-cos-and-sin">The parity of \(\cos\) and \(\sin\)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#complex-numbers-and-the-unit-circle">Complex Numbers and the Unit Circle</a></li>
  <li><a href="#multiplying-with-i-means-a-rotation-with-fracpi2">Multiplying with \(i\) means a rotation with \(\frac{\pi}{2}\)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#eulers-identity">Euler’s identity</a></li>
  <li><a href="#eulers-formula-the-connection-between-e-pi-and-i">Euler’s formula, the connection between \(e\), \(\pi\) and \(i\)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-sin-and-cos-in-their-exponential-form">The \(\sin\) and \(\cos\) in their exponential form</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-sinusoid">The sinusoid</a></li>
  <li><a href="#sinusoids-are-flexible">Sinusoids are <em>flexible</em></a></li>
  <li><a href="#sinusoids-can-be-complex">Sinusoids can be complex</a></li>
  <li><a href="#sinusoids-can-nullify-themselves">Sinusoids can nullify themselves</a></li>
  <li><a href="#adding-sinusoids-leads-to-complexity">Adding sinusoids leads to complexity</a></li>
  <li><a href="#adding-random-sinusoids-for-fun">Adding random sinusoids for fun</a></li>
  <li><a href="#playing-sinusoidal-tetris-for-fun">Playing Sinusoidal tetris for fun</a></li>
  <li><a href="#a-square-wave-and-sinusoids">A square wave and sinusoids</a></li>
  <li><a href="#epicycles-first-encounter">Epicycles - First Encounter</a></li>
  <li><a href="#epicycles-an-intuitive-understanding">Epicycles - An intuitive understanding</a></li>
  <li><a href="#epicycles-a-flower">Epicycles - A flower </a></li>
  <li><a href="#fourier-series">Fourier Series</a></li>
  <li><a href="#fourier-series-in-exponential-form">Fourier Series in Exponential Form</a></li>
  <li><a href="#example-the-fourier-series-for-the-box-function">Example: The Fourier Series for the Box Function</a></li>
  <li><a href="#example-the-fourier-series-of-the-triangle-wave">Example - The Fourier Series of the Triangle wave</a></li>
  <li><a href="#example-the-fourier-series-of-a-sawtooth-function">Example - The Fourier Series of a Sawtooth Function</a></li>
  <li><a href="#the-fourier-series-machinery">The Fourier Series Machinery</a></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>to be continued</strong></p>

<hr>

<h2 id="the-circle">The Circle</h2>

<p>It all starts with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Circle"><em>The Circle</em></a>:</p>



<p>The Circle is a geometrical figure with a center \(P(a, b)\), and a radius \(r\).</p>

<p>It has the following associated equation:</p>

\[(x-a)^{2} + (y-b)^{2} = r^2\]

<p>If \(a=0, b=0\) and \(r=1\), the circle becomes less generic, so we call it <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unit_circle"><em>The Unit Circle</em></a>:</p>



<p>The equation for <em>The Unit Circle</em> is:</p>

\[x^2+y^2=1\]

<p>One could argue <em>The Circle</em> is the epitome of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symmetry">symmetry</a>.</p>

<p>Pick one point, \(A\), then its reflection <em>on the other side</em>, \(A^{'}\), and start rotating:</p>



<p>What happens on <em>The Circle</em>, stays on <em>The Circle</em>.</p>

<h2 id="the-number-pi">The number \(\pi\)</h2>

<p>We rarely see angles expressed in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Degree_(angle)">degrees</a>; usually, we represent them in relation to the number <a href="https://www.andreinc.net/2024/04/24/(https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pi)">PI</a> \(\pi\): \(\pi\), \(\frac{\pi}{2}\), \(\frac{\pi}{3}\), \(\frac{\pi}{4}\), etc.;</p>

<p>\(\pi\) is the ratio of a circle’s circumference to its diameter. <code>π ≈ 3.14</code>.</p>



<p>If \(r \neq 1\), the circle’s perimeter is \(P=2\pi r\), while the area is \(A=\pi r^2\). Both \(A\) and \(P\) depend on \(\pi\).</p>

<p>\(\pi\) is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number">irrational</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcendental_number">transcendental</a>.</p>

<h2 id="radians">Radians</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radian"><code>radian</code></a> (or <code>rad</code>) is the <em>actual</em> unit we use to measure angles. An intimate relationship exists between the <code>radian</code> and the number \(\pi\).</p>



<p>To transform an angle measured in degrees (\(360°\)) to radians, the algorithm is simple: we multiply the angle by \(\pi\), then divide the result by \(180\).</p>

<h2 id="the-sine-and-the-cosine">The sine and the cosine</h2>

<p>We can define \(\sin\) and \(\cos\) in relationship to <em>The Unit Circle</em>:</p>



<ul>
  <li>\(\theta\) is the angle formed by the radius, \(r\) and the \(x\) axis, at every given point.</li>
  <li>The \(\sin\) function represents the \(y\)-coordinate of a point on the <em>Unit Circle</em>;</li>
  <li>The \(\cos\) function is the \(x\)-coordinate of the same point on the <em>Unit Circle</em>.</li>
</ul>

<p>\(\sin\) and \(\cos\) are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Periodic_function"><em>periodic functions</em></a> with the period \(2\pi\).</p>



<p>At this point, it will be unfair for \(\cos\) not to plot it on the same graph:</p>



<h2 id="the-cos-leads-the-sin">The \(\cos\) leads the \(\sin\)</h2>

<p>Putting \(\cos\) and \(\sin\) side by side, we observe that they are not that different:</p>

\[\sin(x+\frac{\pi}{2})=\cos(x)\]

<p>We say that \(\cos\) leads the \(\sin\) with \(\frac{\pi}{2}\):</p>



<h2 id="the-parity-of-cos-and-sin">The parity of \(\cos\) and \(\sin\)</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Even_and_odd_functions"><em>parity</em> of mathematical functions</a> generally refers to whether a function is <em>even</em>, <em>odd</em>, or <em>neither</em>.</p>

<p>The <em>cosine</em> is <em>even</em>, meaning \(\cos(x)=\cos(-x)\):</p>



<p>And the <em>sine</em> is odd, meaning \(\sin(-x)=-\sin(x)\), or \(\sin(x)=-\sin(-x)\):</p>



<h2 id="complex-numbers-and-the-unit-circle">Complex Numbers and the Unit Circle</h2>

<p>In the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complex_plane">Complex Plane</a>, the points on the circle are defined by the following equation:</p>

\[z=\cos(\theta)+i*\sin(\theta)\]



<h2 id="multiplying-with-i-means-a-rotation-with-fracpi2">Multiplying with \(i\) means a rotation with \(\frac{\pi}{2}\)</h2>

<p>Multiplying a <em>complex number</em> with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Imaginary_unit">imaginary unit</a> \(i\) is the equivalent of rotating the number counterclockwise with \(\frac{\pi}{2}\) on an “imaginary circle” with the radius: \(r=\mid a + b*i \mid=\sqrt{a^2 + b^2}\)</p>

<p>For example, if we take \(z_{1} \in \mathbb{C}\) and we multiply it three times with \(i\) we will have it <em>rotated</em> into the all 4 quadrants of the circle:</p>



<h2 id="eulers-identity">Euler’s identity</h2>

<p>The natural exponential function, often denoted as \(f(x)=e^{x}\), is a particular case of the exponential function where the base is \(e\), also known as <em>Euler’s Number</em> (\(e \approx 2.71828\)).</p>

<p>\(e\), just like \(\pi\), <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Irrational_number">irrational</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transcendental_number">transcendental</a>.</p>

<p>We normally define \(e\) as:</p>

\[e=\sum_{n=0}^{\infty}(\frac{1}{n!})=\frac{1}{0!} + \frac{1}{1!}+\frac{1}{2!}+...\]

\[e=\lim_{x \to \infty}(1+\frac{1}{x})^x\]

\[e=\lim_{x \to 0}(x+1)^{\frac{1}{x}}\]

<p>Even if not obvious, there’s a strong connection between \(e\) and the circle.</p>

<p>The <em>natural exponentiation</em> function is an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eigenfunction"><em>eigenfunction</em></a> for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Derivative">differentiation</a>.</p>

<p>An eigenfunction in this context is a function that, when differentiated, yields a constant multiple of itself:</p>

\[\frac{d}{dx} e^{ax} = a * e^{x}\]

<p>If we substitute \(a \rightarrow e\), by subsequently differentiating \(f(x) = e^{ix}\), we obtain:</p>

\[\frac{d}{dx}f(x) = \frac{d}{dx} (e^{ix}) = i * e^{ix}\]

\[\frac{d^2}{dx^2}f(x) = \frac{d^2}{dx^2} (e^{ix}) = \frac{d}{dx} (i * e^{ix}) = -e^{ix}\]

\[\frac{d^3}{dx^3}f(x) = \frac{d^3}{dx^3} (e^{ix}) = \frac{d}{dx} (-e^{ix}) = -i * e^{ix}\]

\[\frac{d^4}{dx^4}f(x) = \frac{d^4}{dx^4} (e^{ix}) = \frac{d}{dx} (-i*e^{ix}) = e^{ix} = f(x)\]

<p>In simple terms, after we differentiate \(f(x)\) four times (\(f'(x), f''(x), f'''(x), f''''(x)\)), our function does a <em>full circle</em>.</p>

<p>It’s the same pattern described in the previous section when we multiplied our \(z_{1}\) with \(i\).</p>

<p>Subsequently deriving \(e^{ix}\) is the equivalent of subsequently multiplying \(e^{ix}\) with \(i\). Multiplying a complex number with \(i\) means <em>rotating</em> that number in the <em>Complex Plane</em> with \(\frac{\pi}{2}\).</p>

<p>But what is a derivative of a function at a certain point?</p>

<p>It’s the rate of change of that function at that particular point. But we’ve just said that the derivative of \(e^{ix}\) is equivalent to a <em>rotation</em>.</p>

<p>So, the rate of change is rotational.</p>

<p>We can intuitively <em>feel</em> that the function \(e^{ix}\) describes an actual circle.</p>

<p>There’s no other possible solution. So we can boldly affirm that \(e^{ix} = \cos(x) + i*\sin(x)\) (which is the formula discovered by Euler).</p>

<p>Of course, this is not a rigorous demonstration. One can prove Euler’s identity using <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Taylor_series">Taylor Series</a>.</p>

<h2 id="eulers-formula-the-connection-between-e-pi-and-i">Euler’s formula, the connection between \(e\), \(\pi\) and \(i\)</h2>

<p>Euler’s formula is a thing of marvel:</p>

\[e^{ix}=\cos(x) + i * \sin(x)\]

<p>Or, if we choose \(x=\pi\):</p>

\[e^{i\pi}+1=0\]

<h2 id="the-sin-and-cos-in-their-exponential-form">The \(\sin\) and \(\cos\) in their exponential form</h2>

<p>By substituting \(x \rightarrow -x\) into Euler’s identity we obtain:</p>

\[e^{-ix}=\cos(x)-i*\sin(x)\]

<p>If we add/subtract the two equalities, we will obtain the definition of the sine and cosine functions in their exponential form:</p>

\[\cos(x) = \frac{e^{ix} + e^{-ix}}{2}\]

\[\sin(x) = \frac{e^{ix} - e^{-ix}}{2*i}\]

<p>All points of the circle are determined by a functon \(z(x)\), where:</p>

\[z(x)=e^{ix}=\underbrace{\cos(x)}_{Re(x)}+\underbrace{i*\sin(x)}_{Im(x)}\]

<p>\(x\) represents the actual angle \(\theta \in \mathbb{R}\), so \(z(\theta)=e^{i\theta}=cos(\theta)+i*sin(\theta)\).</p>

<p>You’ve seen that we’ve interchanged \(x\) with \(t\) and \(\theta\) throughout the article. It’s confusing, but don’t get confused. We are the ones to decide how to look at \(x\), as an angle or as time.</p>

<h2 id="the-sinusoid">The sinusoid</h2>

<p>A <em>sinusoid</em>, or a <em>sine wave</em>, is a smooth, repetitive curve defined by following function:</p>

\[y(t) = A * \sin(2\pi ft + \varphi) = A * \sin(\omega t + \varphi)\]

<ul>
  <li>\(A\) is called the <em>amplitude</em>, representing the maximum deviation of the function from zero.</li>
  <li>\(f\) is called <em>ordinary frequency</em> and denotes the number of oscillations (the radius moving inside the circle) occurring each second.</li>
  <li>\(\omega=2\pi f\) is called the <em>angular frequency</em>; it’s the same thing as <em>ordinary frequency</em>, but we measure it \(\frac{radians}{second}\);</li>
  <li>\(\varphi\) is called <em>phase offset</em>; it’s measured in radians.</li>
</ul>

<p>If we consider <em>time</em> to be the \(x\)-axis, and \(y(t)\) the \(y\)-axis, the sinusoid becomes:</p>

\[y=f(x)=A * \sin(\omega x + \varphi)\]

<p>The \(\sin\) and \(\cos\) are just particular cases of sinusoids.</p>

<h2 id="sinusoids-are-flexible">Sinusoids are <em>flexible</em></h2>

<p>The following animation is interactive. You can choose the values of \(A=\) 
    
    , \(\omega=\)
         
    and \(\varphi=\) 
     
    to plot the sinusoid (if you pick \(\varphi=\frac{\pi}{2}\) a cosine is plotted):</p>



<h2 id="sinusoids-can-be-complex">Sinusoids can be complex</h2>

<p>Starting with the definition of a sinusoid:</p>

\[y(t) = A * sin(2\pi ft + \varphi) = A * sin(\omega t + \varphi)\]

<p>If we multiply each side with \(A\):</p>

\[A*e^{i\theta}=A*(\cos(\theta)+i*\sin(\theta))\]

<p>If we substitute \(\theta\) with \(\theta=\omega t + \varphi\) we obtain the complex sinusoid:</p>

\[s(t)=A*e^{i(\omega t + \varphi)} = A * \cos(\underbrace{\omega t + \varphi}_{\theta}) + i * A * \sin(\underbrace{\omega t + \varphi}_{\theta})\]

<p>A <em>complex sinusoid</em> captures the behavior of two sinusoids (one cosine and one sine) on both its axes; on the real part, it behaves like a cosine, while on its imaginary part, it behaves like a sine.</p>

<p>The two are <em>in sync</em> as they both depend on the free variable \(\theta\), expressed as \(\theta=\omega t + \varphi\).</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/threedcomplex.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>Two interesting observations:</p>
<ul>
  <li>If we project the complex sinusoid on the plane determined by the Y-axis and Z-axis, we will plot a <em>sine</em> (the Imaginary part);</li>
  <li>If we project the complex sinusoid on the plane determined by the X-axis and Z-axis, we will plot a <em>cosine</em> (the Real part);</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="sinusoids-can-nullify-themselves">Sinusoids can nullify themselves</h2>

<p>Two sinusoids in phase and sharing the same amplitude but with opposite frequencies nullify themselves.</p>



<h2 id="adding-sinusoids-leads-to-complexity">Adding sinusoids leads to complexity</h2>

<p>Let’s plot two arbitrary selected sinusoids \(y_{1}(x)\) and \(y_{2}(x)\), where:</p>
<ul>
  <li>\(y_{1}(x) = \frac{9}{10} * sin(7x + \frac{\pi}{2})\), and</li>
  <li>\(y_{2}(x) = \frac{12}{10} * sin(3x - 2)\) .</li>
</ul>

<p>The sum \(y(x)=y_{1}(x) + y_{2}(x)\) shows an interesting pattern</p>



<h2 id="adding-random-sinusoids-for-fun">Adding random sinusoids for fun</h2>

<p>Adding more sinusoids to an existing one (\(A=1\), \(\omega=1\), \(\varphi=1\)) generate more complex patterns:</p>



<h2 id="playing-sinusoidal-tetris-for-fun">Playing Sinusoidal tetris for fun</h2>

<p>Not so long ago, <a href="https://www.andreinc.net/2024/02/06/the-sinusoidal-tetris">I’ve re-imagined the game of Tetris</a>.</p>

<p>It’s now possible to play Tetris with Sinusoids:</p>

<p><a href="https://www.andreinc.net/2024/02/06/the-sinusoidal-tetris"><img src="https://www.andreinc.net/assets/images/2024-04-08-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/sinusoida-tetris.png" alt="img"></a></p>

<h2 id="a-square-wave-and-sinusoids">A square wave and sinusoids</h2>

<p>If we carefully choose the sinusoids, we can create <em>predictable</em> patterns:</p>

<p>Let’s take, for example, use the following formula:</p>

\[y(x) = \frac{4}{\pi}\sum_{k=1}^{\infty}\frac{\sin(2\pi(2k-1)fx)}{2k-1}\]

<p>Through expansion, the formula becomes:</p>

\[y(x) =  \underbrace{\frac{4}{\pi}\sin(\omega x)}_{y_{1}(x)} + \underbrace{\frac{4}{3\pi}\sin(3\omega x)}_{y_{2}(x)} + ... + \underbrace{\frac{4}{(2k-1)\pi}{\sin((2k-1)\omega x)}}_{y_k(x)} + ...\]

<p>\(y_1(x), y_2(x), y_3(x), ..., y_k(x), ...\) are all the individual sinusoids.</p>

<p>If we perform the sum, we will create a <em>square wave</em>. The more sinusoids we pick, the better the approximation.</p>

<p>Please choose how many sinusoids you want to use, and let’s see how the functions look like for  (and \(\omega\)=):</p>



<h2 id="epicycles---first-encounter">Epicycles - First Encounter</h2>

<p>One sinusoid has a corresponding circle that <em>spins</em>. So, the above animation can be re-imagined like this:</p>

<p>Pick  and \(\omega\)= to plot the circles and the corresponding \(y_k(x)\) functions:</p>



<h2 id="epicycles---an-intuitive-understanding">Epicycles - An intuitive understanding</h2>

<p>There’s an intuitive proof to this: each epicycle corresponds to a specific sinusoid; when we talk about combining the sinusoids, we are talking about summing their positions at each point in time, and eventually, this operation reduces to subsequent vector additions.</p>

<p>Let’s take a simple example by introducing three arbitrarily picked sinusoids and their associated <em>point vectors</em> (or <em>position vectors</em>):</p>
<ul>
  <li>\(y_{1}(x)=1.4sin(x + 1)\), with the associated position vector \(\vec{u_{1}}\);</li>
  <li>\(y_{2}(x)=0.8sin(2*x)\), with the associated position vector \(\vec{u_{2}}\);</li>
  <li>\(y_{3}(x)=0.5sin(3*x)\), with the associated position vector \(\vec{u_{3}}\).</li>
</ul>

<p>Their sum is \(y(x) = y_{1}(x) + y_{2}(x) + y_{3}(x) = 1.4sin(x + 1) + =0.8sin(2*x) + 0.5sin(3*x)\).</p>

<p>A position vector represents the displacement from the origin \((0, 0)\) to a specific point in space. In our case, the vector \((x, y_{k}(x))\) represents the position or location of a point on the graph of the function(s) \(y_{k}(x)\) at a particular \(x\) value.</p>

<p>If we plot \(y(x)\) on the cartesian grid we obtain something like:</p>



<p>At each given point \(x\), we can say for certain that \(\vec{u} = \vec{u_{1}} + \vec{u_{2}} + \vec{u_{3}}\).</p>

<h2 id="epicycles---a-flower">Epicycles - A flower</h2>

<p>If we carefully pick the <em>right sinusoids</em> the moving circles can describe (approximate) any shape we want.</p>

<p>Here is a flower for example:</p>



<p>Can you guess the individual sinusoids working together to draw the flower?</p>

<p>You probably can’t unless you apply methods from a branch of mathematics called <em>Fourier Analysis</em>.</p>

<h2 id="fourier-series">Fourier Series</h2>

<p><em>Fourier Series</em> is the mathematical process through which we expand a periodic function of period \(P\) as a sum of trigonometric functions.</p>

<p>Do you remember the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pink_Floyd">Pink Floyd’s</a> album cover for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Dark_Side_of_the_Moon"><em>Dark Side of The Moon</em></a>:</p>

<p><img src="https://www.andreinc.net/assets/images/2023-07-02-painting-with-circles/darksideofthemoon.jpg" alt="img"></p>

<p>Imagine our function \(f(x)\) is the light itself, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Prism_(optics)">the prism</a> is essentially <em>Fourier Mathematics</em>, and the spectral colors emanating from the prism are the sinusoids.</p>

<p>Following the analogy the formula looks like this:</p>

\[\underbrace{f(x)}_{\text{ light itself}}=\underbrace{A_{0} + \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} [A_{n} cos(\frac{2\pi nx}{P}) + B_{n} sin(\frac{2\pi nx}{P})]}_{\text{the spectral components}}\]

<p>Where \(A_{n}\) and \(B_{n}\) are called <em>Fourier Coefficients</em> are defined by the following integrals:</p>

\[A_{0} = \frac{1}{P} \int_{- \frac{P}{2}}^{+\frac{P}{2}} f(x) dx\]

\[A_{n} = \frac{2}{P} \int_{- \frac{P}{2}}^{+ \frac{P}{2}} f(x) * \cos(\frac{2\pi nx}{P}) dx\]

\[B_{n} = \frac{2}{P} \int_{- \frac{P}{2}}^{+ \frac{P}{2}} f(x) * \sin(\frac{2\pi nx}{P}) dx\]

<h2 id="fourier-series-in-exponential-form">Fourier Series in Exponential Form</h2>

<p>With the help of Euler’s Formula and by changing the sine and cosine functions in their exponential forms, we can also express the Fourier Series of a function as a sum of <em>Complex Sinusoids</em>:</p>

\[f(x) = \sum_{n=-N}^{N} C_{n} e ^ {i2\pi \frac{n}{P}x}\]

<p>Where:</p>

\[C_{n} = \begin{cases}
            A_{0} &amp; \text{if } n = 0 \\
            \frac{1}{2} (A_{n} - i * B_{n}) &amp;  \text{if } n &gt; 0 \\
            \frac{1}{2} (A_{n} + i * B_{n}) &amp; \text{if } n &lt; 0 \\
        \end{cases}\]

<p>If we do additional substitutions, the final form of \(C_{n}\) is:</p>

\[C_{n} = \frac{1}{P} \int_{-\frac{P}{2}}^{\frac{P}{2}} e^{-i2\pi\frac{n}{P}x} f(x) dx\]

<h2 id="example-the-fourier-series-for-the-box-function">Example: The Fourier Series for the Box Function</h2>

<p>Remember the <em>Square Wave</em> we’ve approximated with sinusoids <a href="#adding-sinusoids">in this section</a>? At that point, we used the following formula to express the <em>Square</em> as a sum of sinusoidal components:</p>

\[y(x) = \frac{4}{\pi}\sum_{k=1}^{\infty}\frac{\sin(2\pi(2k-1)fx)}{2k-1}\]

<p>Or, to keep things simpler, by substituting \(\omega=2\pi f\) (\(\omega\) is the angular frequency):</p>

\[y(x) = \frac{4}{\pi}\sum_{k=1}^{\infty}\frac{\sin((2k-1)\omega x)}{2k-1}\]

<p>It’s time to understand how we’ve devised such an approximation.</p>

<p>In <em>isolation</em>, the <em>Square Wave</em>, \(f(x)\) looks like this:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/squarewavef.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>Throughout the interval  <code>[0, 2L]</code>, \(f(x)\) can be written as:</p>

\[f(x) = 2 [H(\frac{x}{L})-H(\frac{x}{L}-1)] - 1\]

<p>Where \(H(x)\) is called the <a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/HeavisideStepFunction.html"><em>Heavisde Step Function</em></a> and has the following definition:</p>

\[H(x) =  \begin{cases}
        0 &amp; \text{if } x \lt 0 \\
        1 &amp; \text{if } x \ge 0 \\
        \end{cases}\]

<p>First of all, let’s look at \(A_{0} = \frac{1}{2L} \int_{0}^{2L} f(x) dx\). Notice how we’ve changed the interval from \([-\frac{P}{2}, \frac{P}{2}]\) to \([0, 2L]\) to match our example. This will be reflected in the formulas.</p>

<p>Well, this coefficient (\(A_{0}\)) is a fancy way to express the average of \(f(x)\) over the interval (in our case <code>[0, 2L]</code>). In the same time \(A_{0}\) is the area determined by \(f(x)\) over <code>[0, 2L]</code> then divided by \(2L\). But if you look at the plot again, you will see that the net area is  \(0\), because the green area (S1) nullifies the red area (S2), regardless of \(L\).</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/squarewavefa0.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>Secondly, let’s compute the \(A_{n} = \frac{1}{L} \int_{0}^{2L} f(x) * \cos(\frac{\pi nx}{L}) dx\) coefficients. An important observation is that \(f(n)\) is odd, and its average value on the interval is \(0\); we can safely say all the coefficients \(A_{n}\) also vanish.</p>

<p>Visually speaking, regardless of how you pick \(n\) or \(L\), the net area determined by the \(A_{n}\) integral will always be zero. It’s visually obvious if we <em>plot</em> \(A_n\). For example plotting \(A_{1}\), \(A_{2}\), \(A_{3}\), \(A_{4}\) looks like this:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/squarewavean.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>Similar symmetrical patterns will emerge if you increase the \(n\) in \(A_{n}\) and plot them.</p>

<p>Thirdly, we need to compute:</p>

\[B_{n} = \frac{1}{L} \int_{0}^{2L} f(x) * \sin(\frac{\pi nx}{L}) dx\]

<p>If we plot a \(B_{1}\), \(B_{2}\), \(B_{3}\) and, let’s say, \(B_{4}\) we can intuitively <em>feel</em> what’s happening with \(B_{n}\):</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/squarewavebn.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>If you have a keen eye for geometrical representations, you will notice that every even \(B_{n}\) is also 0. The red and green areas nullify, so the net area described by the integral is \(0\). The odd terms will be \(2 * \text{something}\), so let’s calculate that \(\text{something}\).</p>

<p>We will need to split the integral on two sub-intervals \([0, L]\) and \([L, 2L]\) (there’s a <em>chasm</em> at \(L\)), but given the fact \(f(x)\) and \(sin(x)\) are odd, \(B_{n}\) can we written as:</p>

\[B_{n} = 2 * [\frac{1}{L} \int_{0}^{L} f(x) * \sin(\frac{\pi nx}{L}) dx]\]

<p>We can now perform <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Integration_by_substitution">u-substition</a>, so we can write:</p>

\[B_{n} = \frac{2}{L} \int_{0}^{nL\pi} \frac{\sin(\frac{u}{L})}{n\pi}du\]

<p>After we take the constant out, we compute the integral, use the intervals, and take into consideration the periodicity of cosine:</p>

\[B_{n} = \frac{2}{n\pi}(1-(-1)^n)\]

<p>And now we see it, \(B_{n}\) is exactly \(0\) if \(n\) is even, and \(B_{n}=2 * \frac{2}{n\pi}\) is \(n\) is odd.</p>

<p>Putting all back into the master formula of the <em>Fourier Series</em>:</p>

\[f(x)=\underbrace{A_{0}}_{0} + \sum_{n=1}^{\infty} [\underbrace{A_{n} \cos(\frac{\pi nx}{L})}_{0} + B_{n} \sin(\frac{\pi nx}{L})]\]

<p>Things become:</p>

\[f(x)=\frac{4}{\pi} \sum_{n=1,3,5...}^{+\infty} (\frac{1}{n} * \sin(\frac{\pi nx}{L}))\]

<p>If we substitute \(n \rightarrow 2k-1\) and consider, we obtain the initial formula:</p>

\[f(x)=\frac{4}{\pi} \sum_{k=1}^{+\infty} (\frac{\sin(\frac{\pi (2k-1)x}{L})}{(2k-1)})\]

<p>To obtain the initial formula, we substitute \(L \rightarrow \frac{1}{2f}\), and \(2\pi f \rightarrow \omega\), basically we create an interdependence between \(L\) (half of the interval) and \(\omega\), \(L=\frac{\pi}{\omega}\):</p>

\[f(x) = \frac{4}{\pi}\sum_{k=1}^{\infty}\frac{\sin((2k-1)\omega x)}{2k-1}\]

<p>Unfortunately, there’s no way we can go to \(+\infty\), so let’s consider \(s(x)\) as an approximation of \(f(x)\) that depends on \(n\).</p>

\[s(x) = \frac{4}{\pi}\sum_{k=1}^{n}\frac{\sin((2k-1)\omega x)}{2k-1} \approx f(x)\]

<p>In the next animation, you will see that by increasing \(n\), the accuracy of our approximation gets better and better, and the <em>gaps</em> are slowly closed:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/tightfourier.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>To understand how adding more coefficients improves the approximation, let’s look back again at a few of our coefficients \(s_{1}(x)\), \(s_{2}(x)\), \(s_{3}(x)\), \(s_{4}(x)\) and \(s_{5}(x)\) (we will pick \(\omega=\frac{\pi}{2}\), so that \(2L=1\)):</p>

\[s_{1}(x) = \frac{4}{\pi} \sin(\frac{\pi x}{2})\]

\[s_{2}(x) = \frac{4}{3\pi} \sin(\frac{3\pi x}{2})\]

\[s_{3}(x) = \frac{4}{5\pi} \sin(\frac{5\pi x}{2})\]

\[s_{4}(x) = \frac{4}{7\pi} \sin(\frac{7\pi x}{2})\]

\[s_{5}(x) = \frac{4}{9\pi} \sin(\frac{9\pi x}{2})\]

<p>Each of the 5 terms is a sinusoid, with \(\frac{4}{\pi}\), \(\frac{4}{3\pi}\), etc. amplitudes, and \(\frac{\pi}{2}\), \(\frac{3\pi}{2}\), etc. frequencies.</p>

<p>So, if we were to approximate a <em>Square Wave</em> with its fifth partial sum (the red dot), we would obtain something like this:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/tightfourieravg.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>Notice how <em>obsessed</em> the <em>red dot</em> is with the <em>blue dot</em> (the actual function) and how closely it follows it.</p>

<p>We can always add more terms to the partial sum to help the <em>red dot</em> in its <em>holy mission</em>, improving the approximation until nobody cares anymore.</p>

<h2 id="example---the-fourier-series-of-the-triangle-wave">Example - The Fourier Series of the Triangle wave</h2>

<p>Without dealing with all the associated math, the <em>Fourier Series</em> decomposition for a triangle-wave is:</p>

\[s(x)=\frac{8}{\pi^2}\sum_{k=1}^{N}\frac{(-1)^{k-1}}{(2k-1)^2}*\sin((2k-1)x)\]

<p>Plotting the function \(s(x)\), we will see that things converge smoothly and fast. As soon as \(n\) approaches \(6\), we can already observe the triangle:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/tighttriangle.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>Let’s compute the first terms six terms of the \(\sum\), so that:</p>

\[s(x) \approx s_1(x) + s_2(x) + s_3(x) + s_4(x) + s_5(x) + s_6(x)\]

<p>Where:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The first term is \(s_1(x)=\frac{8}{\pi^2}*\sin(x)\), where \(A=\frac{8}{\pi^2}\), \(\omega=1\), \(\varphi=0\);</li>
  <li>The second term is \(s_2(x)=-\frac{8}{3^2\pi^2}*\sin(3x)\), where \(A=-\frac{8}{3^2\pi^2}\), \(\omega=3\), \(\varphi=0\);</li>
  <li>The third term is \(s_3(x)=\frac{8}{5^2\pi^2}*\sin(5x)\), where \(A=\frac{8}{5^2\pi^2}\), \(\omega=5\), \(\varphi=0\);</li>
  <li>The fourth term is \(s_4(x)=-\frac{8}{7^2\pi^2}*\sin(7x)\), where \(A=-\frac{8}{7^2\pi^2}\), \(\omega=7\), \(\varphi=0\);</li>
  <li>The fifth term is \(s_5(x)=\frac{8}{9^2\pi^2}*\sin(9x)\), where \(A=\frac{8}{9^2\pi^2}\), \(\omega=9\), \(\varphi=0\);</li>
  <li>The sixth term is \(s_6(x)=-\frac{8}{11^2\pi^2}*\sin(11x)\), where \(A=-\frac{8}{11^2\pi^2}\), \(\omega=11\), \(\varphi=0\);</li>
</ul>

<p>A keen eye will see will observe the that \(s_2(x)\), \(s_4(x)\), \(s_6(x)\) and all the even terms are <em>negative</em>.</p>

<p>A negative amplitude doesn’t make too much sense, at least not in a physical sense. What are we going to do with the <em>minus sign</em>?</p>

<p>We have two options:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Because \(\sin(-x)=-\sin(x)\), nobody stops us to make the <em>frequency</em> negative. For example, \(s_2(x)=\frac{8}{3^2\pi^2}*\sin(-3x)\), so that the \(\omega=-3\). But again, why would we want a <em>negative frequency</em>? This also doesn’t make sense in a physical sense.</li>
  <li>We can use \(\vert A \vert\) and shift the signal with \(\pi\), so that \(\varphi=\pi\).</li>
</ol>

<p>In practice, we will go with 2. as it’s more practical and gives us more control, but the two options are equivalent so that we can write \(s_2(x)\) in both ways:</p>

\[s_2(x)=-\frac{8}{3^2\pi^2}*\sin(3x)\]

\[s_2(x)=\frac{8}{3^2\pi^2}*\sin(3x + \pi)\]

<p>Visually speaking, the results will not be surprising if we plot \(sin(-x)\) and \(sin(x+\pi)\) side by side; the two are equivalent:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/pishift.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>If we consider this, the even terms of \(s(x)\) will become:</p>

<ul>
  <li>\(s_2(x)=\frac{8}{3^2\pi^2}*sin(3x+\pi)\) ;</li>
  <li>\(s_4(x)=\frac{8}{7^2\pi^2}*sin(7x+\pi)\) ;</li>
  <li>\(s_6(x)=\frac{8}{11^2\pi^2}*sin(11x+\pi)\) ;</li>
  <li>…and so on</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="example---the-fourier-series-of-a-sawtooth-function">Example - The Fourier Series of a Sawtooth Function</h2>

<p>Shamelessly skipping the math demonstration, a reverse-sawtooth function has the following form:</p>

\[s(x)=\frac{2}{\pi}\sum_{k=1}^{N}(-1)^k*\frac{\sin(kx)}{k}\]

<p>Plotting \(s(x)\), while increasing \(n\), things look like this:</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/tightsawtooth.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<h2 id="the-fourier-series-machinery">The Fourier Series Machinery</h2>

<p>To better visualize what’s happening, let’s look at a <em>Fourier Series Machinery</em> and how the <em>circles move</em> to create <em><del>beautiful</del> practical patterns</em>.</p>

<p>You can pick the shape of the desired signal from here:  and the sketch will change accordingly.</p>


<p><sup><sup><a href="https://assets/js/2024-04-24-from-the-circle-to-epicycles/fmachinery.js">(Source code)</a></sup></sup></p>

<p>…A bunch of spinning circles on a stick, where each circle corresponds to exactly one term of the series - this is the marvelous <em>Fourier Series Machinery</em>.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.andreinc.net/assets/images/2023-07-02-painting-with-circles/fmachinery.jpg" alt="img"></p>

<p>If we run our signal through the <em>Fourier Series Machinery</em>, we will obtain <em>The Amplitude</em> (\(A\)) and <em>The Phase</em> (\(\varphi\)) for each Frequency (\(\omega\)) from \(1\) to \(N\). Isn’t it amazing? And it all comes down to a bunch of spinning circles… on a stick.</p>

<p><strong>to be continued</strong></p>

        
      </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Some notes on influenceering (212 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/some-notes-on-influenceering</link>
            <guid>40578668</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 20:34:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/some-notes-on-influenceering">https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/some-notes-on-influenceering</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40578668">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p><span>I’ve been putting content on the internet for all of my adult life. The works ranged from security research, to open-source projects, to long-term writing on a variety of topics. In an </span><a href="https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/you-should-write-more" rel="">earlier article</a><span>, I extolled the virtues of publishing just for the sake of it:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>“The concepts in our heads are nebulous and ever-shifting. Putting them on paper forces us to pressure-test our assumptions and address gaps.</em></p><p><em>You don’t need to be the world’s leading expert to write about a particular topic. Experts are often busy and struggle to explain concepts in an accessible way. You should be honest with yourself and with your readers about what you know and don’t know — but otherwise, it’s OK to write about what excites you, and to do it as you learn.”</em></p></blockquote><p>For over two decades, I resisted the desire to monetize my side projects. Part of it was pragmatic: my career paid better than what I could realistically make by cramming ads into articles or selling geeky books. But just as important, I didn’t want to turn a hobby into yet another chore.</p><p>Today, I’d like to share some of the less obvious takeaways from the journey so far.</p><p>By refusing to monetize, you give up most of the tangible upsides of online publishing — but the downsides stay with you either way. In the long haul, you should expect to spend as much time putting out fires and wrangling the technology as you spend on creative pursuits.</p><p>To give you a taste, I had my website randomly delisted by Google, hijacked by SEO spammers in Bing, repeatedly flagged by antivirus tools, and hit with bogus abuse and copyright claims; in each case, it took weeks to get it sorted out, often having to lean on informal connections to get through.</p><p>When I self-hosted, I had to deal with endless configuration and maintenance tasks — and at one point, an outright server compromise. Third-party hosting is easier until it isn’t. For example, it took me nearly a year to get this rendering issue fixed by Substack:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg" width="1168" height="520" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:520,&quot;width&quot;:1168,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:180087,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd99ae74d-3a0c-4895-974d-d0698eb15bed_1168x520.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>How Substack used to display math on this blog.</em></figcaption></figure></div><p>Their support was of no help; what finally worked was a “cold” email to one of the site’s founders. In other words, it took perseverance and luck.</p><p><span>Even with free hosting, you need a job to pay the bills. I poured thousands of dollars into this craft, and I’m sure the same goes for most other habitual content producers you come across. The costs range from photo and video gear, to software licenses, to the procurement of </span><a href="https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/a-brief-history-of-counting-stuff" rel="">antique calculating machines</a><span> and </span><a href="https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/comparing-hobby-pcb-vendors" rel="">random PCBs</a><span>.</span></p><p>Unless you’re a pop star, you are unlikely to gain devoted fans who follow you around. Most of the time, when we come across helpful content on the internet, we don’t think much of the stranger who put it out there. We just take the experience for granted and move on.</p><p>Online hate isn’t so fleeting. Sooner or later, you come across a heckler who follows you around and makes it their life’s mission to “debunk” your claims — or simply hurl insults in your general direction without any pretense of being constructive.</p><p>This seems worse than it really is. Putting others down on the internet is a pretty miserable hobby — often just a way for the other person to cope with their own insecurities and stress.  But still, early on, it plays tricks with your mind — what if I’m really as clueless as they say?</p><p><span>If your content upsets another person, it still means you have an audience. More often than not, the controversy pulls in bystanders and lets them make up their own minds. There </span><em>is</em><span> such a thing as bad press, but on the internet, the threshold is pretty high.</span></p><p><span>What stings far more is when you get no reaction whatsoever: all of sudden, the content’s most important </span><em>raison d'etre</em><span> is lost. Few bloggers or vloggers quit because of the occasional snide remark; many give up when their metrics don’t budge post after post.</span></p><p><span>The process of building an online audience is slow and unpredictable, so my best advice is to pick a platform that doesn’t rub your nose in it. I’ve previously written about my </span><a href="https://lcamtuf.substack.com/p/youtube-is-hell" rel="">special dislike of YouTube</a><span>, where the entire creator experience revolves around view counts:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>“The complexity of the medium is not YouTube’s fault. What I fault them for, however, is that they deliberately thrust authors into a global popularity contest — and offer no reprieve. You can use Reddit, Twitter, or Facebook to hang out with friends without knowing who’s the highest-ranking influencer of the week. On YouTube, view counts are all there is — inescapable and in-your-face.</em></p><p><em><strong>[A thumbnail of a woman flipping off an Alaskan malamute, 82M views]</strong></em></p><p><em>Even in the privacy of your own channel, you’re being compared: to the right of your video, you see similar clips from strangers, along with their scores. The takeaway is simple: there must be something wrong with you if you can’t compete with a person flipping off their dog.”</em></p></blockquote><p><span>Most social media platforms use </span><em>algorithmic feeds</em><span> — that is, they decide what to show not based on their users’ explicit preferences, but on what’s most likely to elicit a response and keep the user engaged. Because of this, follower counts are fairly meaningless: just because a person follows you on Instagram or Facebook, it doesn’t mean they will ever see your posts.</span></p><p>To be fair, the platform you’re reading this on — Substack — is a bit of an outlier. They deliver every post via email, so if a subscriber is still alive and the mails are not ending up in spam, they will see what you have to say. But for a more typical data point, let’s have a look at Twitter: I have 35k+ followers over there, but this translates to just about 1,000 to 2,000 impressions on a typical post. YouTube is the same: I notionally have 1,100 followers there, but a video that isn’t promoted elsewhere tends to get 50-100 views.</p><p>I’m not sure there’s any special takeaway to this — except, if you want to build an audience around subscriptions, make sure they are real. And don’t assume that people with 100k or 1M followers have anything resembling this kind of reach.</p><p>If you ask an average person what’s corrupting the internet, they will probably point to monetization. But it’s not just about money; non-commercial content creators are getting comically distorted signals too.</p><p><span>For example, did you know that my Substack audience is telling me I should stop writing? It’s true: whenever I post a new article, I reliably lose subscribers. If you have a sufficiently large audience, there’s always someone who expected something different, and your new post nudges them to finally unsubscribe. But when I’m </span><strong>not</strong><span> posting, I quickly make up the losses with sign-ups driven through Google search. Clearly, the best growth strategy is to post nothing at all.</span></p><p>More seriously, the sheer randomness of internet’s attention, and its heavy bias toward low-effort content, will drive you nuts. Some of my most popular posts are throwaway quips and memes that went viral on social media. One of my life’s crowning achievements is this:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png" width="1456" height="762" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:762,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:80342,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd2bc890d-6b37-4e2e-8551-af62b7a91600_1485x777.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em>Just asking questions.</em></figcaption></figure></div><p><span>In contrast, some of the work I put weeks or months into essentially lost the SEO game and gets nearly zero traffic. A while ago, I put together an impassioned, contrarian </span><a href="https://lcamtuf.coredump.cx/photo_basics/" rel="">guide to photography</a><span>, illustrated with a number of interactive shots. The only traffic it’s getting today are confused searches for a porn performer with a vaguely similar name. Even though I don’t write for money, there is an immense pressure to produce clickbait — even if simply to add </span><em>“hey, since you’re here, check out this serious thing”.</em></p><p><em><span>For a categorized list of posts on this Substack, </span><a href="https://lcamtuf.coredump.cx/offsite.shtml" rel="">click here</a><span>.</span></em></p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Things the guys who stole my phone have texted me to try to get me to unlock it (421 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gothamist.com/news/things-the-guys-who-stole-my-phone-have-texted-me-to-try-to-get-me-to-unlock-it</link>
            <guid>40578460</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 20:10:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gothamist.com/news/things-the-guys-who-stole-my-phone-have-texted-me-to-try-to-get-me-to-unlock-it">https://gothamist.com/news/things-the-guys-who-stole-my-phone-have-texted-me-to-try-to-get-me-to-unlock-it</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40578460">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><!--[--><!--[--><div><p><i>A version of this story originally appeared in</i> <a href="https://maxread.substack.com/p/iphone-thieves-copypasta" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><i>Read Max</i></a><i>, a twice-weekly newsletter about tech, politics, culture, and media.</i></p><p>My phone was stolen in early March, most likely while I was standing on the platform at the York Street station waiting for the F train. Fifteen minutes later, in a food hall under the movie theater where my boyfriend and I were supposed to see “Dune 2,” I reached into my pocket and realized it was gone. He looked at the Find My app on his phone: My phone was “last seen” at York Street but wasn’t registering a current location. Someone had turned it off.</p><p>As quickly as possible, I did <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/101593" rel="noopener" target="_blank">all the things you’re supposed to do when your phone is lost or stolen</a> —- mark it as lost, cut off service, and remotely erase it. I spent the rest of the night anxiously refreshing the Find My app, watching my phone move around Manhattan before it finally stopped at Rockefeller Center. I didn’t bother confronting the thief. Worst of all, we didn't even see “Dune 2.”</p><p>After two hours in the Williamsburg Apple Store the next morning, I had a new iPhone 15 and I stopped stressing. As long as I didn’t remove the phone from my Apple account or the Find My app, the phone was essentially bricked to anyone without the passcode <i>and</i> my iCloud password — unusable by the thieves, or the fences who I assume bought it from them. Now my phone was their problem.</p><p>Where had my phone gone? I learned (from Reddit comments – where else?) that stolen iPhones usually end up sold in bulk online, either directly by the thief or by a fence who buys stolen phones individually and <i>then</i> sells them in bulk. The purchasers are either <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Flipping/comments/fw7s3v/my_experience_with_liquidationcom/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">looking for parts</a> or think they can crack into the phones, wipe and resell them. This teenager on YouTube, for example, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=26bdjJqWdCo" rel="noopener" target="_blank">bought a box of stolen iPhones</a> for $1,300 on Liquidation.com:</p></div><!--]--><!--[--><div><p>
    <iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/26bdjJqWdCo?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="I Bought STOLEN iPhones for CHEAP"></iframe>
</p>
</div><!--]--><!--[--><div><p>As you can see, most of the phones she tried didn’t have passcodes but were still linked to iCloud accounts, which meant she (or anyone buying the phones) still had access to all of the original owners’ texts, emails and photos. She sent a message to each iCloud email offering to give people their phones back, but only one guy replied.</p><p>I, sadly, did not get a message from a teenage YouTuber earnestly offering to return my stolen phone. Instead I received a series of texts from someone cycling through a number of different strategies for engaging, convincing, tricking or scaring me into unlocking the phone for them.</p><p>Rather than being engaged, convinced, tricked or scared, however, I was delighted. The experience managed to combine the internet's promises of international communion and international crime.</p><p>There was something oddly soothing about being in touch with the people who’d stolen my phone. Instead of it disappearing into the ether, I knew more or less where it was, and thanks to these texts, I knew that it was a source of frustration to the people who’d gotten their hands on it. As the texts escalated in complexity and rage, I sympathized with their plight. I mean, not enough to unlock my phone. But we’ve all been there – sometimes you get stuck with a difficult project at work.</p><p>In case you find yourself in a similar situation, here are some things the guys who stole (or later purchased) my iPhone have told me to try to get me to unlock it.</p></div><!--]--><!--[--><p><h5><b>1) “Your iPhone 14 Pro is trying to pay with Apple Pay in China.”</b></h5></p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>The first text I received from the scammers.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>The first text I got from my new friends was sent on April 28, a few weeks after the phone was stolen, and I have to be honest … it kind of got me, at least for a second. It helped that, even though this text came from a clearly bogus iCloud email address, Apple’s own “helpful” iMessage feature was sort of fooled: the auto-filled contact name said “Maybe: Apple Pay.” Maybe!</p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>Apple’s own “helpful” iMessage feature was sort of fooled: the auto-filled contact name said “Maybe: Apple Pay.” Maybe!</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>At this point, my phone was in Sunnyside, Queens:</p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>My phone was camped out in Sunnyside, Queens for a bit.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>My old phone's new owners persisted with this tactic for a while. I later got the same message again, but from a different iCloud address. Two weeks after that, on May 12, I got an identical message in which “USA” had been replaced with “China.” I'm guessing it was intended to dial up the panic, but instead it made me feel cosmopolitan and sophisticated.</p><!--]--><!--[--><p><h5><b>2) “Iv'e bought an iPhone 14 Pro I'm using, it have your messages, emails, cards, bank, notes and personal information on it”</b></h5></p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>Posing as the unwitting new owners of a stolen iPhone, the scammer continued to try to get me to unlock the phone.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>On May 13, my pen pals reached out from a Filipino phone number. They'd switched from the impersonal "Apple Pay warning" texts to claiming that they were the unwitting new owners of a stolen iPhone. I appreciated this more intimate approach – the message even came from a phone number rather than email address, which was a nice touch – and I was glad to hear they were concerned about my insurance claim. “Best of luck!” I texted back.</p><!--]--><!--[--><p><h5><b>3) “Your old iPhone 14 Pro is recycled by us, we are just recycling merchants, we are not the ones who steal your phone”</b></h5></p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>This was my favorite text. Who am I to say no to recycling?</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>The next day, I was kindly contacted by a U.K. phone number notifying me that the people in possession of my phone simply wanted to recycle it. This was one of my favorites: Sure, there’s an implicit threat (“hackers” might “contact my family” to, what, send them thousands of photos of my dog??), but it's not just some poor sap I'm supposed to help, it's the <i>planet</i>. Who am I to stand in the way of recycling? I replied:</p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>I loved lying to the scammers.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p><h5><b>4) “The phone is going be auctioned on the black market with your personal information and everything about you that you had on it.”</b></h5></p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>I appreciated the use of CAPS in this one.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>I got this one on the same day (May 14), from the Filipino number, which had previously claimed to be some guy who’d accidentally bought my phone.</p><!--]--><!--[--><p><h5><b>5) “Your old iPhone has been disassembled… you do not want to take it back, because it does not belong to the law of the United States”</b></h5></p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>This is where things started escalating.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><div><p>At the same time, I got this nearly identical message from the U.K. number. Thanks to Reddit, I discovered that most of the messages I was getting were <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/iphone/comments/1abu8ec/my_phone_got_stolen_and_this_is_what_they_texted/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">scammer copypasta</a>: English phrases and texts that were passed around between thieves, fences and jailbreakers to entice bereft phone owners like me.</p><p>In the end I think these two texts provide a lesson in the importance of great openers. While the previous message didn’t move me much, it’s hard not to admire the arresting visuals of the detailed iPhone breakdown, the reference to “the law of the United States,” the mocking “you’ll never catch me.” It’s an incredible intro that really elevates the literary value of what would otherwise be a rote bit of vaguely threatening text! ! ! ! ! !</p><p>In any event, I will credit them with being honest: I checked Find My and my phone was indeed in China. It looked like it was in an office building conveniently located around the corner from an Adidas store, about 8,000 miles from me.</p></div><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>My iPhone took a little trip!</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p><h5><b>6) “Listen! I'm going to harassed, wreck and ruin your sad, stupid low pathetic life if its not removed you mindless peasant.”</b></h5></p><!--]--><!--[--><figure><figcaption><!----><p>This was the final (and most threatening) message I received from my scammer friends.</p><p>Veronica de Souza/Gothamist</p></figcaption></figure><!--]--><!--[--><p>I did not like this tone from my best pal! This text (more <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/copypasta/comments/13tv0r3/someone_who_got_their_iphone_stolen_got_this/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">scammer copypasta</a>) was accompanied by two videos. One video showed a “hacker” breaking into someone’s iPhone and going through their camera roll, which was a mix of selfies and graphic videos. Another appeared to be a screen recording of a social video of a man showing off his gun. I guess this is supposed to be the guy named “Miami” who is going to come kill me and my whole family “on Monday.” I haven’t heard from them since.</p><!--]--><!--]--></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Debian's /tmpest in a teapot (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/975565/bcce68a68d82d63a/</link>
            <guid>40578414</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 20:05:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/975565/bcce68a68d82d63a/">https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/975565/bcce68a68d82d63a/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40578414">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<!-- $Id: slink-trial,v 1.1 2005-11-04 21:27:01 corbet Exp $ -->
<center>
<table>
<tbody><tr><td>
<h3>Welcome to LWN.net</h3>
<p>
The following subscription-only content has been made available to you 
by an LWN subscriber.  Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the 
best news from the Linux and free software communities.  If you enjoy this 
article, please consider accepting the trial offer on the right.  Thank you
for visiting LWN.net!
</p></td><td>
<div>
<h3>Free trial subscription</h3>
           <p>
           Try LWN for free for 1 month: no payment
           or credit card required.  <a href="https://lwn.net/Promo/slink-trial2-3/claim">Activate
           your trial subscription now</a> and see why thousands of
           readers subscribe to LWN.net.
           
</p></div>
</td>
</tr>

</tbody></table>
</center>

<p>Debian had a major <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/499410/">discussion</a>
about mounting <tt>/tmp</tt> as a RAM-based tmpfs in 2012 but inertia
won out in the end. Debian systems have continued to
store temporary files on disk by default. Until now. A mere 
12 years later, the project will be switching to a RAM-based <tt>/tmp</tt> in the Debian
13 ("Trixie") release. Additionally, starting with Trixie, the
default will be to periodically clean up temporary files automatically in
<tt><nobr>/tmp</nobr></tt> and <tt><nobr>/var/tmp</nobr></tt>. Naturally, it involved a lengthy discussion first.</p>

<h4>Join the party</h4>

<p>By now, using tmpfs for the <tt>/tmp</tt>
directory is a road well-traveled. Many Linux distributions have already switched to mounting
<tt>/tmp</tt> as a tmpfs. Arch Linux, Fedora, openSUSE
Tumbleweed, and many others have all made the switch. Red Hat Enterprise Linux (RHEL) and its
clones, as well as SUSE Linux Enterprise Server (SLES) and openSUSE Leap, still default to <tt>/tmp</tt> on
disk. Ubuntu, following Debian, also continues to have a disk-based
<tt>/tmp</tt> rather than using tmpfs.</p>

<p>The knobs to control how <tt>/tmp</tt> is mounted, and the handling
of temporary files, <a href="https://systemd.io/TEMPORARY_DIRECTORIES/">are part of
systemd</a>. (On systems where systemd is used, of course.) The
upstream defaults for systemd are to mount <tt>/tmp</tt> as a tmpfs
and delete files that have not been read or changed after ten days in
<tt>/tmp</tt> and 30 days for those stored in <tt>/var/tmp</tt>.
Debian Developer and systemd contributor Luca Boccassi recently
decided it was time to revisit the topic of <tt>/tmp</tt> as a tmpfs,
and start deleting temporary files in <tt>/tmp</tt> and
<tt>/var/tmp</tt>.</p>

<p>On May 6 Boccassi
<a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/ebee234c6f72eb7dfe55809821c038491bfea542.camel@debian.org/">resurrected</a> a discussion from Debian's bug
tracker that started in 2020 and that had trailed off in July 2022 without resolution. The bug
was submitted by Eric Desrochers, who <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=966621#5">complained</a> that
Debian's systemd implementation did not clean <tt>/var/tmp</tt> by
default. Michael Biebl <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=966621#10">wrote</a>
that this was a deliberate choice to match Debian's pre-systemd
behavior. After a long period of inactivity, Biebl <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=966621#35">suggested</a>
in October 2021 (and <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=966621#40">again</a> in July 2022) that Desrochers raise the topic on the Debian devel
mailing list. That never happened.</p>

<p>In reviving the topic, Boccassi declared that it was time to bring Debian's defaults in
line with upstream and other Linux distributions by making
<tt>/tmp</tt> a tmpfs, and cleaning up <tt>/tmp</tt> and <tt>/var/tmp</tt> on a
timer. He planned to apply those changes in the next systemd upload to
Debian unstable within a week, with instructions in the <tt>NEWS</tt> file on
how to override the changes for any users who wanted to keep the
current behavior. That, in turn, sparked quite a discussion.</p>

<h4>The case for and against</h4>

<p>Biebl <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/abb5af73-7b68-4880-b0fc-622112bf4403@debian.org/">worried</a>
about the effect of cleaning up temporary files by default. Currently,
he said, Debian only cleans <tt>/tmp</tt> on boot (which is
unnecessary if <tt>/tmp</tt> is a RAM-based tmpfs) and to never clean
up files in <tt>/var/tmp</tt>. Boccassi <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnQuCfngAWSrZrJCXxru61EVtfsOMjw-5fFHrPQ11U4L9Q@mail.gmail.com/">answered</a>:
"<q>Defaults are defaults, they are trivially and fully overridable
where needed if needed.</q>" Biebl <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/4b514ecf-d6b1-4208-9be3-ffa3f988da32@debian.org/">replied</a>
that there is value in aligning defaults across Linux distributions,
but argued that Debian has "<q>a larger scope</q>" than a desktop
distribution like Fedora. He suggested that it was necessary to "<q>gather feedback from all affected parties 
to make an informed decision</q>". Boccassi <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnRzXjern5wD60Gb+uUmxyTk_duK8jGNND16EA3xpDPVNw@mail.gmail.com/">responded</a>
that it was impossible to have defaults that would make everyone
happy, and he was not looking for hypothetical arguments or
philosophical discussions, he wanted facts: "<q>what would
break where, and how to fix it?</q>"</p>

<p>Sam Hartman <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/tsla5l1d1kh.fsf@suchdamage.org/">noted</a>
that <tt>ssh-agent</tt> created its socket under <tt>/tmp</tt>, but it would be
better if it respected the <tt>$XDG_RUNTIME_DIR</tt> setting and
created its socket under <tt>/run/user</tt>. Boccassi
<a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnQ9TedkhqkAv-+SYV9+_rRwnxc8H7y=mUS1DgY2oV7wkw@mail.gmail.com/">agreed</a>
and said that he had <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1070725">filed a bug</a> for <tt>ssh-agent</tt>. Richard Lewis
<a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/86seyuk41q.fsf@simplex.rtf.org.uk/">pointed
out</a> that tmux stores its sockets in <tt>/tmp/tmux-$UID</tt>, and
deleting those files might mean users could not reattach to a tmux
session that had been idle a long time. Boccassi <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnSYrqwd5s6u1fhT1dx+W2E1Ti3Y84eWAKs9iKZN_O5=OA@mail.gmail.com/">suggested</a>
that using <a href="https://manpages.debian.org/testing/manpages-dev/flock.2.en.html"><tt>flock()</tt></a>
would be the right solution to stop the deletion, and <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnRT3OeZwZ6M=X_fLdWo5Saf6Xgn04UnS_9yywCbfjhGfg@mail.gmail.com/">said</a>
he had <a href="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=1070724">filed a bug</a> on that as well.</p>

<p>Lewis <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/86ikzpjq8k.fsf@simplex.rtf.org.uk/">questioned</a>
whether files downloaded with <tt>apt&nbsp;source</tt> might be
considered "old" when they were extracted under <tt>/tmp</tt> and
immediately flagged to be deleted. Russ Allbery <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/87cypxfgi9.fsf@hope.eyrie.org/">said</a>
that <tt>systemd-tmpfiles</tt> would respect the access timestamp (atime)
and changed timestamp (ctime), not just the modified timestamp
(mtime), "<q>so I think this would only be a problem on file systems that didn't support
those attributes</q>". Allbery said he believed tmpfs supports all three.</p>

<p>Some users store information in <tt>/var/tmp</tt> for long-running
jobs, because they want it preserved without being backed up, <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CANa01B+C2Z6o=QEv33Ovd8pDM4+MqmCZ2L4T2g4nNY4Gj13-dg@mail.gmail.com/">said</a>
Barak A. Pearlmutter. Boccassi <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnT_bYrBRm7j3iU5sN=dtzvHcf0vaRH=Xxc7xEVjQ=txWA@mail.gmail.com/">dismissed</a>
that, saying that those users "<q>assuming they actually exist</q>",
can customize the system defaults according to their needs.</p>

<p>Those users do exist, <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/D14DPA7WSVOK.2LV6HCA1DS4F5@debian.org/">wrote</a>
Jonathan Dowland, "<q>[I've] been one of them, I've worked with many of
them, it's an incredibly common pattern in academic
computing</q>". Making a change to how these files are handled,
"<q>should be a very carefully explored decision</q>". He also
asked for arguments in favor of the change, and to hold off the change
to allow the discussion to continue.</p>

<p>Hartman <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/tsla5l11xl6.fsf@suchdamage.org/">wished</a>
that it was possible to specify that directories under
<tt>/var/tmp</tt> should be deleted entirely or left alone. Boccassi
said that was a reasonable enhancement request, and that it had
already been <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnRbG9EJgu1VDYCwxDYAtmwDj+UrxgxiXkxWgyqOY8UZtw@mail.gmail.com/">filed
upstream</a> for systemd.</p>

<p>Allbery eventually <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/87h6f9hev0.fsf@hope.eyrie.org/">admitted
surprise</a> at the number of people who reported using
<tt>/var/tmp</tt> "<q>for things that are clearly not temporary
files in the traditional UNIX sense</q>". Periodically deleting files
in <tt>/var/tmp</tt>, he said, has been common UNIX practice for at
least 30 years:</p>

<blockquote>
Whatever we do with /var/tmp retention, I beg people to stop using
/var/tmp for data you're keeping for longer than a few days and care about
losing.  That's not what it's for, and you *will* be bitten by this
someday, somewhere, because even with existing Debian configuration many
people run tmpreaper or similar programs.  If you are running a
long-running task that produces data that you care about, make a directory
for it to use, whether in your home directory, /opt, /srv, whatever.
</blockquote>

<p>Hakan Bayındır <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/812a6293-c157-484e-9fc0-002692ad733a@bayindir.org/">said</a>
that he did not use <tt>/var/tmp</tt>, but applications that
other people use do. He cited a high-end scientific application that was
not under his or other users' control. Allbery argued that this
was "<q>not a good design decision</q>" but conceded that may not be
helpful if a user or admin does not have control over the
application's design. However, he said, it was "<q>playing with fire</q>"
to use <tt>/var/tmp</tt> that way "<q>and it's
going to result in someone getting their data deleted at some point,
regardless of what Debian does</q>".</p>

<p>Lewis <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/86h6f9jop1.fsf@simplex.rtf.org.uk/">said</a>
he still did not understand the rationale for the change. Was there,
he asked, "<q>perhaps something more compelling than 'other
distributions and upstream already do this'?</q>" That sounded like
the original rationale, <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/878r0lffbs.fsf@hope.eyrie.org/">Allbery
said</a>, but he added that moving <tt>/tmp</tt> to tmpfs should make
applications run faster, and reaping files under <tt>/var/tmp</tt>
could help to avoid filling up a partition. Allowing the partition to
fill up, he noted, could
cause bounced mail, unstable services, and other problems. It may not
be a problem for desktop systems, which tend to have enough disk space
not to be affected, but for virtual machines that have <tt>/var/tmp</tt>
contained within a small root partition, it is still a concern.</p>

<h4>Rolling out changes</h4>

<p>In the end, none of the arguments for maintaining Debian's status
quo managed to persuade Boccassi to stay his hand. On May 28, Boccassi <a href="https://lwn.net/ml/debian-devel/CAMw=ZnTPEbA7uZ4Cg2sx7PBZS2_Z_8-ZD7UDqoVWq6UasAcUxA@mail.gmail.com/">announced</a>
the changes that he had made and uploaded to unstable. As expected, <tt>/tmp</tt> will become a
tmpfs by default, for both new and existing installations. New
installs will use the systemd default behavior. The
<tt>openssh</tt> and <tt>tmux</tt> packages, he said, had been fixed
to provide exceptions to retain their temporary files. A description has been added
to the Debian installer to inform users that <tt>/tmp</tt> is a tmpfs
by default, and the changes have been noted in the <tt>NEWS</tt>
file. He also offered
to review and merge any changes to the Debian installer that would let
users customize those options during installation.
Users who want <tt>/tmp</tt> to remain on disk can override the
upstream default with <tt>systemctl&nbsp;mask&nbsp;tmp.mount</tt>. To
stop periodic cleanups of <tt>/tmp</tt> and <tt>/var/tmp</tt> users
can run <tt>touch&nbsp;/etc/tmpfiles.d/tmp.conf</tt>.</p>

<p>None of the changes, it should be noted, will affect Debian
versions prior to Trixie. Users of Debian stable and oldstable will
only encounter these changes on upgrade.</p>

<p>As noted, many distributions have already made these changes
without catastrophe. Debian, and its users, should be able to adapt to
the new defaults or override them if they are unsuitable for the
workloads to be run. At worst, it promises to be a temporary
inconvenience.</p><br clear="all">
               <br clear="all">
               <blockquote>
<p>
<b>Did you like this article?</b>  Please accept our 
<a href="https://lwn.net/Promo/slink-trial2-3/claim">trial subscription offer</a> to be
able to see more content like it and to participate in the discussion.
</p>
</blockquote>
<hr><p>
           (<a href="https://lwn.net/Login/?target=/Articles/975565/">Log in</a> to post comments)
           </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Entropy, a CLI that scans files to find high entropy lines (might be secrets) (194 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/EwenQuim/entropy</link>
            <guid>40578060</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 19:25:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/EwenQuim/entropy">https://github.com/EwenQuim/entropy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40578060">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/EwenQuim/entropy/blob/master/entropy.png"><img src="https://github.com/EwenQuim/entropy/raw/master/entropy.png" alt="Entropy logo"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Paranoïd about having secrets leaked in your huge codebase? Entropy is here to help you find them!</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Entropy</h2><a id="user-content-entropy" aria-label="Permalink: Entropy" href="#entropy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://pkg.go.dev/github.com/EwenQuim/entropy" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/93a15bfa5bcb59ef604062700f0a52593262f3e80e675dda2021f2528f6c36aa/68747470733a2f2f706b672e676f2e6465762f62616467652f6769746875622e636f6d2f4577656e5175696d2f656e74726f70792e737667" alt="Go Reference" data-canonical-src="https://pkg.go.dev/badge/github.com/EwenQuim/entropy.svg"></a>
<a href="https://goreportcard.com/report/github.com/EwenQuim/entropy" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/7c76b6a208333f52e7b975ed9ae0e183f446aba3b96a63663b41d2a8354f9045/68747470733a2f2f676f7265706f7274636172642e636f6d2f62616467652f6769746875622e636f6d2f4577656e5175696d2f656e74726f7079" alt="Go Report Card" data-canonical-src="https://goreportcard.com/badge/github.com/EwenQuim/entropy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Entropy is a CLI tool that will <strong>scan your codebase for high entropy lines</strong>, which are often secrets.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you have Go installed</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="go install github.com/EwenQuim/entropy@latest
entropy"><pre>go install github.com/EwenQuim/entropy@latest
entropy</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">or in one line</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="go run github.com/EwenQuim/entropy@latest"><pre>go run github.com/EwenQuim/entropy@latest</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">With brew</h3><a id="user-content-with-brew" aria-label="Permalink: With brew" href="#with-brew"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">WIP</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I don't want to maintain a documentation here, so just run</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="entropy -h"><pre>entropy -h</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">as it will always be up to date.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Influencer cartels manipulate social media (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/how-influencer-cartels-manipulate-social-media-fraudulent-behaviour-hidden-plain</link>
            <guid>40577726</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 18:51:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/how-influencer-cartels-manipulate-social-media-fraudulent-behaviour-hidden-plain">https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/how-influencer-cartels-manipulate-social-media-fraudulent-behaviour-hidden-plain</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40577726">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
      

      <article>
        
              <div>
                
                  <p>Imagine a university that rewards professors based on the number of citations to their research. In response, a group of colleagues might agree to cite each other’s work in every paper they write. What would be the positive and negative effects of our imaginary citation cartel? Economists are not known for excessive citations, which could be explained by positive externalities: the citing author bears all the costs, while the cited author reaps the benefits. As citing authors can’t internalise this positive externality, we end up with fewer citations than is socially optimal.</p>

<p>A citation cartel could solve this issue via reciprocal behaviour: by the cartel agreement, members would receive as many citations as they give. However, this can go too far. If this agreement requires citing unrelated papers, it might be good for group members but lead to meaningless literature reviews. Thus, the benefit of such agreements depends on their nature: making more effort to cite related papers could be good, while citing unrelated papers is probably bad.</p>

<p>Such academic citation cartels are not purely hypothetical. Academic journals have been found to form agreements to boost each other’s journals in the rankings (Van Noorden 2013). Similarly, universities have boosted their colleagues’ citation counts to advance in university rankings (Catanzaro 2024). Due to such citation patterns, Clarivate (Thomson Reuters) has excluded journals from Impact Factor listings, and most recently excluded the entire field of mathematics (Van Noorden 2013, Catanzaro 2024).</p>

<p>Academic citation cartels are difficult to study because there is no data on explicit cartel agreements. But in influencer marketing, cartel agreements are observable. In our new paper (Hinnosaar and Hinnosaar 2024), we study how influencers collude to inflate engagement and the conditions under which influencer cartels can be welfare-improving.</p>

<h2>Distorted incentives and fraudulent behaviour in influencer marketing</h2>

<p>Influencer marketing has become a key part of modern advertising. In 2023, spending on influencer marketing reached $31 billion, already rivalling the entirety of print newspaper advertising. Influencer marketing allows advertisers fine targeting based on consumer interests by choosing a good product-influencer-consumer match.</p>

<p>Many non-celebrity influencers are not paid based on the success of their marketing campaigns. In fact, less than 20% of companies track the sales induced by their influencer marketing campaigns. Instead, influencers’ pay is based on impact measures such as the number of followers and engagement (likes and comments), furnishing an incentive for fraudulent behaviour – for inflating their influence. Inflating influence is a form of advertising fraud that causes market inefficiencies by directing ads to the wrong audience. An estimated 15% of influencer marketing spending is misused due to exaggerated influence. To address this issue, the US Federal Trade Commission proposed a rule in 2023 to ban the sale and purchase of false indicators of social media influence. Cartels provide a way of obtaining fake engagement that does not fall directly under the proposed rule – because no money changes hands – but is still in the same spirit. While there is substantial literature on fake consumer reviews (Mayzlin et al. 2014, Luca and Zervas 2016) and other forms of advertising fraud (Zinman and Zitzewitz 2016), the literature on influencer marketing has focused mostly on advertising disclosure (Ershov and Mitchell 2023, Pei and Mayzlin 2022, Mitchell 2021, Fainmesser and Galeotti 2021), leaving the fraudulent behaviour unstudied.</p>

<h2>How do Instagram cartels work?</h2>

<p>An influencer cartel is a group of influencers who collude to boost their advertising fees by inflating engagement metrics. As in traditional industries (Steen et al. 2013), influencer cartels involve a formal agreement to manipulate the market for the members’ benefit. The cartels operate in online chatrooms. The screenshots below show how one such cartel operates in practice. The image on the left is from an online chat room, where cartel members submit links to their content for extra engagement. Before submitting a link, they must reciprocate by liking and commenting on other members’ posts. An algorithm enforces these rules. The image on the right shows these cartel-induced comments on Instagram. The cartel history and rules make it possible to observe which engagement (comments) originate from the cartel.</p>

<p><strong>Figure 1</strong> Left panel shows posts in online chatroom submitted for cartel engagement; right panel shows Instagram comments originating from the cartel</p>

  


<h6><em>Source</em>: Left panel is a screenshot of a Telegram group; right panel is a screenshot from Instagram. To preserve anonymity, account identifiers are blurred and the photo is replaced with an analogous photo by an AI image generator.</h6>

<h2>What distinguishes ‘bad’ from ‘not-so-bad’ cartels?</h2>

<p>Our theoretical model formalises the main trade-offs in this setting, in the spirit of the imaginary citation group discussed earlier. The model focuses on strategic engagement, a decision that affects social media content distribution and consumption (Aridor et al. 2024) but has been underexplored (with the exception of Filippas et al. 2023, who studied attention bartering in Twitter). Engaging with other influencers’ content has a positive externality, leading to too little engagement in equilibrium. Forming a cartel to reciprocally engage with each other’s content can internalise this externality and might be socially desirable. However, it can also result in low-value engagement, especially when advertisers pay based on quantity rather than quality.</p>

<p>The key dimension to differentiating ‘bad’ from ‘not-so-bad’ cartels is the quality of cartel engagement. By ‘high quality’, we mean engagement coming from influencers with similar interests. The idea is that influencers provide value to advertisers by promoting a product among the target audience: people with similar interests, such as vegan burgers to vegans. If a cartel generates engagement from influencers with other interests (meat lovers), this hurts consumers and advertisers. It hurts consumers because the platform will show them irrelevant content, and advertisers are hurt because their ads are shown to the wrong audience. Whether or not a particular cartel is welfare-reducing or welfare-improving is an empirical question.</p>

<h2>Evaluating engagement quality using machine-learning methods</h2>

<p>To answer this empirical question, we use novel data from influencer cartels and machine learning to analyse Instagram text and photos. The cartel data allows us to directly observe which Instagram posts are included in the cartel and which engagement originates from the cartel (via cartel rules). Our dataset includes two types of cartels, differentiated by cartel entry rules: topic cartels (which only accept influencers posting on specific topics) and general cartels (with unrestricted topics).</p>

<p>Our goal is to compare the quality of natural engagement to that originating from the cartel. We measure the quality by the topic match between the cartel member and the Instagram user who engages. To quantify the similarity of Instagram users, we generate numeric vectors (embeddings) from the text and photos in Instagram posts using a large language model (Language-agnostic BERT Sentence Embedding) and an analogous large neural network (Contrastive Language Image Pre-training model). Then we calculate cosine similarity between the Instagram users based on these numeric vectors.</p>

<h2>Are the cartels likely to be welfare-improving?</h2>

<p>We find that engagement from general cartels is significantly lower in quality compared to natural engagement. Specifically, the quality of engagement from these cartels is nearly as low as that from a counterfactual engagement from a random Instagram user. In contrast, engagement from topic cartels is much closer to the quality of natural engagement.</p>

<p>The figure below illustrates these effects using raw data (see the paper for regression estimates, robustness checks, and additional analysis). It presents distributions of cosine similarity between the author and commenter, separately for general (left panel) and topic (right panel) cartels. It shows that non-cartel commenters (natural engagement) have the highest similarity with the author of the content, and random users have the lowest. Match quality from general cartels is similar to random engagement (left panel). In contrast, topic cartel engagement is much closer to natural engagement (right panel).</p>

<p><strong>Figure 2</strong> Probability density of authors’ similarity to commenters and random users in general cartels (left) and topic cartels (right)</p>

  


<p>Back-of-the-envelope calculations (based on regression analysis) show that if advertisers pay for cartel engagement as if it were natural engagement, they receive only 3–18% of the value with general cartels, and 60–85% with topic cartels. In other words, general cartels provide nearly worthless engagement for advertisers, while topic cartels cause less distortion.</p>

<h2>Conclusions and policy implications</h2>

<p>Our findings lead to three policy implications. First, since general cartels are likely to reduce welfare, stronger regulation of their activities would benefit society. Second, regulations that prohibit buying and selling fake social media indicators should also cover in-kind transfers, such as paying for engagement with reciprocal engagement. Third, the current practice of rewarding engagement quantity encourages harmful collusion. A better approach would be to compensate influencers based on the actual value they provide. Luckily, many advertisers are already moving in this direction. Until they get there, platforms could improve outcomes by reporting match-quality-weighted engagement.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<p>Aridor, G, R Jiménez-Durán, R Levy and L Song (2024), “<a href="https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/economics-social-media">The economics of social media</a>,” VoxEU.org, 20 May.</p>

<p>Catanzaro, M (2024), “Citation Manipulation Found to be Rife in Math”, <em>Science</em> 383 (6682): 470.</p>

<p>Ershov, D and M Mitchell (2023), “The Effects of Influencer Advertising Disclosure Regulations: Evidence from Instagram”, <em>RAND Journal of Economics,</em> forthcoming.</p>

<p>Fainmesser, I P and A Galeotti (2021), “The Market for Online Influence”, <em>American Economic Journal: Microeconomics </em>13(4): 332–72.</p>

<p>Filippas, A, J J Horton and E Lipnowski (2023), “The Production and Consumption of Social Media”, manuscript.</p>

<p>Hinnosaar, M and T Hinnosaar (2024), “<a href="https://cepr.org/publications/dp19079">Influencer Cartels</a>”, CEPR Discussion Paper 19079.</p>

<p>Luca, M and G Zervas (2016), “Fake It Till You Make It: Reputation, Competition, and Yelp Review Fraud”, M<em>anagement Science </em>62(12): 3412–27.</p>

<p>Mayzlin, D, Y Dover and J Chevalier (2014), “Promotional Reviews: An Empirical Investigation of Online Review Manipulation”, <em>American Economic Review </em>104(8): 2421–55.</p>

<p>Mitchell, M (2021), “Free Ad(vice): Internet Influencers and Disclosure Regulation”, <em>RAND Journal of Economics</em> 52(1): 3–21.</p>

<p>Pei, A and D Mayzlin (2022), “Influencing Social Media Influencers Through Affiliation”,<em> Marketing Science</em> 41(3): 593–615.</p>

<p>Steen, F, O Toivanen and A Hyytinen (2013), “<a href="https://cepr.org/voxeu/columns/anatomy-cartel-contracts">Anatomy of cartel contracts</a>”, VoxEU.org, 14 June.</p>

<p>Van Noorden, R (2013), “Brazilian Citation Scheme Outed”, Nature 500(7464): 510–11.</p>

<p>Zinman, J and E Zitzewitz (2016), “Wintertime for Deceptive Advertising?”, American Economic Journal: Applied Economics 8(1): 177–92.</p>

              </div>

              
                                          </article>
    </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why do electronic components have such odd values? (2021) (395 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://digilent.com/blog/why-do-electronic-components-have-such-odd-values/</link>
            <guid>40576132</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 16:20:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://digilent.com/blog/why-do-electronic-components-have-such-odd-values/">https://digilent.com/blog/why-do-electronic-components-have-such-odd-values/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40576132">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-4381">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		<p>If you’ve been around electronics for a while, you’ve probably noticed that components like resistors, capacitors, zener diodes, and inductors come in some odd values. Looking at the chart below, there seems to be no clear rationale&nbsp;behind the values, but there is a pattern. 47kΩ resistors and 22μF capacitors are everywhere, but not 40kΩ or 50kΩ resistors, or 20μF or 30μF capacitors. So what’s the deal? It all has to do with <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Preferred_number" target="_blank" rel="noopener">preferred numbers</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/resistor-color-codes.png"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/resistor-color-codes-600x600.png" alt="resistor-color-codes" width="600" height="600" srcset="https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/resistor-color-codes.png 600w, https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/resistor-color-codes-150x150.png 150w, https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/resistor-color-codes-225x225.png 225w, https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/resistor-color-codes-300x300-cropped.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"></a></p>
<p>We have to go back a few years to 1877 France. The French military used balloons for various purposes and of various sizes, and they had to be anchored using cables. Over time, they ended up with 425 different sizes of mooring cables that had to be individually ordered and inventoried. Talk about a nightmare.</p>
<p>Enter Charles Renard. He was tasked with improving the balloons, but discovered this rat’s nest of cables in the inventory closet instead. He spent some time thinking about it and came up with a series of 17 cable sizes that would allow for every type of balloon to be properly moored. Each size of cable had a max/min rating that just overlapped it’s neighbor above and below, so every required value was covered by one or more cable. This system of numbers became known as the “Renard numbers” and was later included in the&nbsp;“preferred numbers” when the concept was expanded for other applications and became an international standard with ISO (International Organization for Standards) 3 in 1952.</p>
<p>Since then, numerous international standards have been adopted by ISO for countless things, but one of those is how we identify&nbsp;certain electronic components. Using the same idea that Renard developed, these components are labeled with what are known as E-series values within the preferred number system. The lowest value is E6, which enumerates six&nbsp;values between&nbsp;two consecutive powers of 10, i.e., between 10 and 100 or between 10k and 100k. Starting with 10, we increase that value by roughly half and we get 15. Increase by roughly half again and we get 22. Continuing this trend, rounding as needed, and we end up with the series 10, 15, 22, 33, 47, and 68. Components built to the E6 standard have a 20% relative error tolerance, and if we look at the values again we’ll see a trend. Starting with 10 again and adding 20% error we end up with 12. Moving to 15 and subtracting 20% we get… wait for it… 12. Moving up from 15 we get 15 + 20% = 18 and 22 – 20% = 17.6. This trend repeats no matter what range of powers of 10 you use, as long as they are consecutive. So 47kΩ&nbsp;+ 20% = 56400, while 68kΩ – 20% = 54400.</p>
<p>Look again at the values 47 and 68. The max/min values overlap right about 56, don’t they? That sounds familiar. The E12 standard uses all of the same values as E6, but with 6 more values mixed in. These 6 additional values are roughly where the E6 values overlap, and now in order to cover the entire range our %-error is reduced to 10%. Starting again at 10, we have 10, 12, 15, 18, 22, 27, 33, 39, 47, 56, 68, and 82. The math holds true here as well, with the error values just slightly overlapping.</p>
<p>There are four&nbsp;more E-series as well, namely E24, E48, E96, and E192. The image above lists all values included in the E6/E12/E24 standards. With each doubling of&nbsp;values between consecutive powers of 10, there is an associated halving of the %-error allowance as well. So E24 values have a +/- %-error of 5%, E48 is set at 2%, and so on. The values associated with E192 are also available with 0.25% and 0.1% tolerances, and E24 and E96 are also available with 1% tolerances.</p>
<p>Below is a simple graphical view of how the E12 values relate to one another. Along the bottom of the graph you will see the first 13 terms&nbsp;of an ideal geometric sequence as well. (The sequence is given by y=10^(<em>i</em>/<em>b</em>), where <em>b</em> is the value of the series (e.g. 12) and <em>i</em> is the term desired (e.g. the 8th term would yield 10^(8/12)=4.64).) Notice how closely the values are related.</p>
<figure id="attachment_4382" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-4382"><a href="https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/E12_series_tolerance.svg_.png"><img decoding="async" src="https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/E12_series_tolerance.svg_-343x600.png" alt="E12_series_tolerance.svg" width="343" height="600" srcset="https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/E12_series_tolerance.svg_.png 343w, https://digilent.com/blog/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/E12_series_tolerance.svg_-129x225.png 129w" sizes="(max-width: 343px) 100vw, 343px"></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-4382">This graph shows how any value between 1 and 10 is within ±10% of an E12 series value, and its difference from the ideal value in a geometric sequence. By Anders Andersson from <a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File%3AE12_series_tolerance.svg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wikimedia Commons</a>.</figcaption></figure>
<p>While it is possible to have a 3.3kΩ resistor with 20% tolerance test out between 2.64kΩ and 3.96kΩ, I would be hesitant to use it. I want 3.3kΩ, so I tend to use resistors with a higher tolerance, usually 5%, so I can just reach in my bin and know that I’m reasonably close. Looking back at the table in the beginning,&nbsp;we see that there are values of 68 and 75 listed. If I’m looking for a value of 70 (or some multiple power of 10, like 700), what can I do to achieve it? I can certainly start testing every 68 valued resistor I can find (75 is just out of range of 5% tolerance), hoping to find one that is just right, but just because it says 5%, doesn’t mean it is. That is a maximum allowance, and my experience has been that the tolerances are much tighter than that. I could go up to an E96 (681 0r 715) or even E192 (698!), but resistors with that level of %-error tolerance are not common and cost more. I just want something simple that I already have in my bin! The answer is actually quite simple. Just add a 33 and a 47 and call it good. You get your 70 +/- whatever tolerance you want since 33 and 47 are preferred numbers in every E-series. The point is that any value can be made for any circuit requirement simply by adding components together. When you throw in the rules for calculating components in series and parallel, the combinations are endless.</p>

         
        
                    <!--begin code -->

                    
                    <div data-post_id="30055" data-instance_id="1" data-additional_class="pp-multiple-authors-layout-boxed.multiple-authors-target-the-content" data-original_class="pp-multiple-authors-boxes-wrapper pp-multiple-authors-wrapper box-post-id-30055 box-instance-id-1">
                                                                                                                                    <p><span>
                                                                                                                        <ul>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    
                                                                                                                    <li>
                                                                                                                                                                                    <div>
                                                                    <p><img alt="Brandon Marcum" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/759a6fe8a05fd65a78b981319973577c?s=80&amp;d=mm&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/759a6fe8a05fd65a78b981319973577c?s=160&amp;d=mm&amp;r=g 2x" height="80" width="80">                                                                                                                                                                                                            </p>
                                                                                                                                    </div>
                                                            
                                                            
                                                                                                                                                                                                                        </li>
                                                                                                                                                                                                                                    </ul>
                                                                            </span>
                                                                                                                        </p></div>
                    <!--end code -->
                    
                
                                
                
        	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CO2 helps viruses stay alive longer in the air (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.statnews.com/2024/06/04/co2-ventilation-research-virus-airborne-life-haddrell-celebs/</link>
            <guid>40575081</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 14:36:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2024/06/04/co2-ventilation-research-virus-airborne-life-haddrell-celebs/">https://www.statnews.com/2024/06/04/co2-ventilation-research-virus-airborne-life-haddrell-celebs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40575081">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
	<p><span><span>C</span></span>arbon dioxide monitors have been around for decades. But in 2020, they became, almost overnight, a hot commodity. All of a sudden, people wanted them to help assess the safety of indoor spaces — to gauge the likelihood of breathing in coronavirus-laced particles that until very recently had been in someone else’s lungs.</p>
<p>No sensor can monitor how many infectious aerosols are swirling around us in real time. But carbon dioxide, or CO2, can act as a convenient proxy. People exhale it when they breathe, and in spaces that aren’t well ventilated, the gas accumulates. High CO2 concentrations can provide a warning sign that a lot of the air you’re inhaling is coming out of other people’s respiratory tracts.</p>
<p>For decades, that’s how aerosol scientists and ventilation engineers have mostly thought about CO2 — as a sort of indicator for the health of indoor environments. But over the last three years, researchers in the U.K. working with next-generation bioaerosol technologies have discovered that CO2 is more than a useful bystander. In fact, it plays a critical role in determining how long viruses can stay alive in the air: The more CO2 there is, the more virus-friendly the air becomes.</p>
<p>It’s a revelation that is already transforming the way scientists study airborne pathogens. But on a planet where burning fossil fuels and other industrial activities inject 37 billion metric tons of CO2 into the atmosphere each year, it could also have huge implications for human health.</p>
		
		
<p>“By increasing the CO2 in the air, we’re getting rid of a natural means by which viruses become inactivated,” said Allen Haddrell, an environmental chemist at the University of Bristol Aerosol Research Center, who led the new work. “It’s fascinating, but it’s also horrifying.”</p>
<p><span><span>H</span></span>addrell has spent his career designing instruments to better understand the complex chemical reactions that take place in the violent moments after someone coughs, sneezes, or breathes respiratory particles out. The reactions within those flecks determine how far they can float and how long they can linger in the air. In 2013, Haddrell was approached by the U.K.’s Defense Science and Technology Laboratory about making a machine to study how long bacteria can live inside these particles.</p>
<p>For the better part of a century, scientists have done those experiments with an instrument called a nebulizer, which creates a cloud of aerosols from liquids and releases them into a rotating drum. Then they wait and take time-stamped samples of the air inside the drum to calculate a given pathogen’s half-life: how long it can stay alive and aloft.</p>
<p>The trouble is, these nebulizers create complex plumes of particles, with different sizes and ages, so it can be difficult to know exactly what’s being measured. All the tumbling can give microbes a beating, too, making it difficult to interpret data about their viability. The British government’s military research arm wanted better information to help it prepare for a potential bioterrorism attack.</p>
<p>Making an instrument that could provide such information would turn into a six-year slog. Initially, Haddrell tried to adapt a technology known as “optical tweezers,” developed by a colleague of his at Bristol named Jonathan Reid. It uses lasers to trap particles in a microscope for extended periods of time, allowing researchers to measure the light scattering off of them to determine their physical and chemical properties. But bacteria — with all their proteins, fats, and other biomolecules — created patterns too complicated to fully understand.</p>
<p>Eventually, Haddrell, Reid, and a small team of Ph.D. students and postdocs turned to piezoelectronics. They could harness tiny charges of electricity to force fluid out under carefully controlled pressure, forming a perfect liquid bead — each with exactly the same chemical composition, size, and number of viral particles.</p>
<p>Instead of a rotating drum, Haddrell’s team built an electrodynamic force field to trap each tiny particle in mid-air at the moment of its creation. Using a laser and a camera, they could watch each hovering particle move and change as they exposed it to different environmental conditions. Once they’d measured the particles’ size and chemical composition, they could turn off the electrodynamic field, sending the beads plummeting into a Petri dish to be cultured.</p>
<p>The researchers called the contraption CELEBS, for “controlled electrodynamic levitation and extraction of bioaerosols onto a substrate,” and by 2019, they’d <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsif.2018.0779" target="_blank" rel="noopener">shown it could work quite well</a> for benchmark bacteria like E. coli. The plan was to move on to other, more concerning airborne bacterial threats.</p>
<p>Then, a novel coronavirus emerged in China and began sickening millions of people all over the world.</p>
		
		
<p><span><span>O</span></span>n March 23, 2020, the same day Prime Minister Boris Johnson announced a nationwide lockdown to curb the widening outbreak of SARS-CoV-2, Haddrell got an email from a colleague at Bristol’s veterinary school, located on a farm about a 40-minute drive south. They were standing up a Containment Level 3 laboratory there and assembling a multidisciplinary rapid response team to study the virus. Could he get his CELEBS system working there, so they could learn more about how it behaved in respiratory particles?</p>
<p>“It was wild,” recalled Haddrell. “I went from thinking I would be home for the next three to six months to driving down there the next day.”</p>
<figure id="attachment_1165502"><a href="https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1.jpeg"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-328x437.jpeg" alt="Portrait of Allen Haddrell wearing a green shirt, with yellowish/green bushes behind him. -- infectious disease coverage from STAT" width="328" height="437" srcset="https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-328x437.jpeg 328w, https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-1024x1365.jpeg 1024w, https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-768x1024.jpeg 768w, https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-500x667.jpeg 500w, https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-640x853.jpeg 640w, https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1-432x576.jpeg 432w, https://www.statnews.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/IMG_5044-1.jpeg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 328px) 100vw, 328px"></a><figcaption><span>Allen Haddrell</span> <cite>Courtesy Hannah Craven</cite></figcaption></figure>
<p>As the country shut down and the roads emptied of cars, Haddrell began building a high-containment version of his machine. While he did that, a postdoc named Henry Oswin took an existing CELEBS and got it calibrated to work with a mouse virus so they’d be ready to move on to SARS-CoV-2 as soon as the lab opened.</p>
<p>Around that time, researchers using traditional rotating drums began to report <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2020/03/16/coronavirus-can-become-aerosol-doesnt-mean-doomed/">the first survivability data for the new coronavirus</a>. One group, at the National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases, found <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/10.1056/NEJMc2004973" target="_blank" rel="noopener">SARS-CoV-2 could stay viable in aerosols for up to three hours</a>. Another, from Tulane University, found it could live in the air for <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.04.13.20063784v1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">over 16 hours</a>. The divergent findings added to the confusion as officials crafted public health policies in those first months of the pandemic — when Americans were encouraged first not to wear medical-grade masks, <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2020/04/03/white-house-urges-masks-coronavirus/">then to wear homemade cloth coverings</a>.</p>
<p>But when Haddrell’s team finally began their own experiments with SARS-CoV-2 in the fall of that year, they found the virus lost 90% of its ability to infect people within 20 minutes — with most of the loss occurring within the first five minutes.</p>
<p>Haddrell knew that going public with this information was going to be tricky. Because it had come from a totally novel technology, it would be easy to disregard the data as an artifact of an untested method. He wanted to make sure they had an explanation for why, in their hands, the coronavirus decayed much more quickly. So his team spent another year doing experiments and arguing over hypotheses on the daily drives to and from the new lab. Finally, they settled on a possible answer.</p>
<p>In biology labs, viruses are kept alive inside of cell cultures, where the byproducts of eating and growing can drive up the pH to dangerously alkaline levels. To keep that from happening, most culture media contains dissolved bicarbonate, which together with the carbon dioxide gas inside an incubator creates a buffering system.</p>
		
		
<p>Inside a nebulizer, though, these virus-laced bicarbonate solutions become aerosolized, releasing CO2 that builds up if it’s in a confined space. Haddrell’s team found that a standard nebulizer spraying cell culture media could raise the concentration of CO2 in a 7-liter box from 700 parts per million to over 1,100 over the course of 10 minutes. That extra CO2 acted like a buffer keeping the particles closer to a neutral pH, where respiratory viruses are quite content.</p>
<p>In the CELEBS system, that didn’t happen. As particles lost water through evaporation, they rapidly became more basic, which killed any SARS-CoV-2 viruses inside. Haddrell and his team proposed that pH, more than temperature and humidity, was the driving force behind viral decay in respiratory particles. And the method most widely used to study that had been incidentally altering pH without anyone realizing it.</p>
<p><span><span>I</span></span>f they were right, it would call into question decades of data produced by virology research groups around the world. So when Haddrell’s team posted their own results as <a href="https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.01.08.22268944v1.full.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a preprint </a>in January 2022, they expected a bit of blowback. What they got was a hurricane.</p>
<p>“The headline is VERY convenient for people in power” tweeted Jose-Luis Jimenez, an atmospheric chemist at the University of Colorado, referencing <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/jan/11/covid-loses-90-of-ability-to-infect-within-five-minutes-in-air-study" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a Guardian article about the research</a>. “Now they can quote an aerosol preprint to keep doing nothing… [Wonder if they’ll forget not reviewed?]” Other leading aerosol scientists <a href="https://twitter.com/jljcolorado/status/1480927297926479884" target="_blank" rel="noopener">quickly piled on</a>.</p>
<p>Haddrell, who wasn’t active on the social media site at the time, had unknowingly waded into a blistering online feud among researchers <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/the-teeny-tiny-scientific-screwup-that-helped-covid-kill/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">about the extent to which SARS-CoV-2 was airborne</a>. If it could travel through the air and infect people via inhalation, even over short distances, then social distancing and handwashing wasn’t going to be enough to curb its spread — masking and ventilation would also be required.</p>
<p>The controversy hinged on differences in how aerosol scientists and medical professionals used words like “aerosol” and “airborne,” <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2024/04/18/covid-airborne-transmission-disease-who-expanded-definition/#:~:text=Even%20as%20evidence%20grew%20that,was%20airborne%20until%20late%202021.">differences the World Health Organization only recently resolved</a>. But in 2022, many feared that at the precise time when the Delta variant was filling up hospital wards across the U.K. with Covid patients, Haddrell’s data would be wrongly interpreted as casting doubt on the airborne route of transmission.</p>
<p>“That’s not what we were saying at all,” Haddrell said. “When Fox News emailed us, we knew we had a problem,” he said.</p>
<p>So when his group used CELEBS to systematically tease apart all the fundamental processes that could be causing SARS-CoV-2 to die in respiratory particles — temperature, humidity, salt content — and still found that pH played the biggest role, they didn’t put out the results as a preprint before it was <a href="https://royalsocietypublishing.org/doi/10.1098/rsif.2023.0062" target="_blank" rel="noopener">published</a> last summer. He also took to X, formerly Twitter, to explain what this finding meant in practical, pandemic terms: “Anything that reduces the acid content of the air will lower the aerosolized viral load #ventilation,” he wrote.</p>
<p>That’s because the human body is not unlike those nebulizers. We, too, carry around dissolved CO2 in the form of bicarbonate, which our blood transports from all our remote tissues into our lungs. When we exhale, and the bicarbonate inside our respiratory particles comes into contact with the outside air, it quickly breaks down and escapes as CO2 gas. If we’re in an enclosed space, that CO2 sticks around, limiting how high the pH inside those particles can climb — just like inside the rotating drums.</p>
<p>But that still left the question: How much CO2 is necessary to boost the odds of viral survival? The <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-47777-5" target="_blank" rel="noopener">latest paper</a> from Haddrell’s group, published in Nature Communications in April, found a disconcerting answer: not nearly as much as you might think. Increasing the CO2 concentration to just 800 parts per million, a level widely identified as being a marker of good ventilation, significantly extended the life spans of multiple SARS-CoV-2 variants. At higher concentrations — like those you might expect to find in a crowded, poorly ventilated room — Haddrell’s team found that 10 times as much virus remained infectious after 40 minutes when compared to clean air.</p>
		
		
<p><span><span>T</span></span>ogether, the papers make a case for the need to improve the quality of indoor air, said Josh Santarpia, an expert in aerosol transmission of disease at the University of Nebraska Medical Center who was not involved in the study. “It’s not just that your exposure is higher, but the risk is also higher because there are more things that are staying alive,” he said. “It demonstrates the compounded nature of poor ventilation.”</p>
<p>Jimenez, who had been critical of Haddrell’s 2022 preprint and the subsequent media coverage, described the Bristol group’s latest work as “very important” in the push for stronger policies that regulate indoor air. In March, he and a group of international experts <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.adl0677" target="_blank" rel="noopener">writing in Science</a> presented a blueprint for national indoor air standards in public buildings, aiming to reduce both disease transmission and indoor pollutants.</p>
<p>In its call to action, the group proposed CO2 as one of three key metrics, suggesting ventilation rates that would keep CO2 levels at 800 parts per million or below. Lidia Morawska, an aerosol expert at Queensland University of Technology who was also an author on the Science perspective, told STAT that the Bristol work indicates that number might be too conservative.</p>
<p>“This is another argument for lowering the concentration of CO2 as much as we can,” Morawska said. “It’s moving from a role of being just a proxy to being understood as an enhancer, if we can use this term, for infection.”</p>
<p>Other aerosol experts who have studied SARS-CoV-2 extensively, like Linsey Marr at Virginia Tech, aren’t convinced that CO2 and pH are the whole story. “There are still many details we don’t understand about virus survival in respiratory particles,” she told STAT via email. “Their explanation might be right, but it might not.”</p>
<p>Haddrell agrees that more work needs to be done to understand how widely generalizable the phenomenon is. His team is now gearing up to begin more experiments with influenza A viruses.</p>
<p>But others are also taking up the reins. The Bristol group has now sent CELEBS machines to a handful of other labs, including Morawska’s in Australia and some in the U.S. With the recent spread of <a href="https://www.statnews.com/topic/h5n1-bird-flu/">H5N1 bird flu</a> into many mammal species, including dairy cattle and <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2024/05/30/bird-flu-third-case-human-infection-caused-respiratory-symptoms/">farmworkers who care for them</a>, and the continuing rise in atmospheric CO2 levels, understanding the complex interplay between viruses, human bodies, and the environments where they eat, sleep, and breathe, is only growing more urgent.</p>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>