<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 16:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[62 Minutes could bring your business down (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.crowdstrike.com/en-us/#teaser-79minutes-adversary-1</link>
            <guid>41005378</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 11:55:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/en-us/#teaser-79minutes-adversary-1">https://www.crowdstrike.com/en-us/#teaser-79minutes-adversary-1</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41005378">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="container-0306f2696d" data-cmp-is="simple-container" color-palette-background-color="#F8F8F8" data-padding-top="64" data-padding-top-tablet="64" data-padding-top-mobile="112" data-padding-bottom="120" data-padding-bottom-tablet="56" data-padding-bottom-mobile="56" data-padding-left="0" data-padding-left-tablet="0" data-padding-left-mobile="0" data-padding-right="16" data-is-transparent-header="true">
<p><span><p>CrowdStrike is continually recognized as a leader by 3rd party organizations and customers. Learn more at&nbsp;<a href="https://crowdstrike.com/leader">crowdstrike.com/leader</a>.</p>
<p>1&nbsp;Customer expectations are based on calculations made by CrowdStrike with data provided by customers or prospective customers who conduct a Business Value Realized or Business Value Assessment. Average savings are from the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/resources/reports/total-economic-impact-of-crowdstrike-falcon-complete/">Total Economic Impact™ of CrowdStrike Falcon Complete</a>, commissioned by CrowdStrike, February 2021. Results are for a composite organization as stated in the study. Individual results may vary by customer.</p>
<p>2&nbsp;Gartner, Magic Quadrant for Endpoint Protection Platforms, Peter Firstbrook, Chris Silva, 31 December 2022.</p>
<p>Gartner is a registered trademark and service mark and Magic Quadrant is a registered trademark of Gartner, Inc. and/or its affiliates in the U.S. and internationally and are used herein with permission. All rights reserved. This graphic was published by Gartner, Inc. as part of a larger research document and should be evaluated in the context of the entire document. The Gartner document is available upon request from CrowdStrike. Gartner does not endorse any vendor, product or service depicted in its research publications, and does not advise technology users to select only those vendors with the highest ratings or other designation. Gartner research publications consist of the opinions of Gartner research organization and should not be construed as statements of fact. Gartner disclaims all warranties, express or implied, with respect to this research, including any warranties of merchantability or fitness for a particular purpose.</p>
</span>
</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FCC votes unanimously to dramatically limit prison telecom charges (509 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://worthrises.org/pressreleases/2024/7/18/fcc-votes-unanimously-to-significantly-lower-phone-and-video-communication-costs-after-decades-of-exploitation-by-prison-telecoms</link>
            <guid>41005181</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 11:33:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://worthrises.org/pressreleases/2024/7/18/fcc-votes-unanimously-to-significantly-lower-phone-and-video-communication-costs-after-decades-of-exploitation-by-prison-telecoms">https://worthrises.org/pressreleases/2024/7/18/fcc-votes-unanimously-to-significantly-lower-phone-and-video-communication-costs-after-decades-of-exploitation-by-prison-telecoms</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41005181">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>The new rules&nbsp;will impact the prison telecom industry deeply. Loss of revenue is expected to be in the hundreds of millions of dollars (though not equal to the savings to incarcerated people and their families as the industry's business model shifts and correctional agencies purchase security and surveillance services directly). This&nbsp;comes as the two largest market players, Aventiv and ViaPath, each navigate financial crises. Aventiv recently<a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=79823f19b8&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank"> </a>effectively <a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=2bef16be55&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank">defaulted on its $1.3 billion debt</a> after a year of failed refinancing efforts. ViaPath was reportedly closing in on a $1.5 billion refinancing deal until news of the <a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=2e6d95e517&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank">regulations killed the deal</a>.&nbsp;</p><p>The FCC’s new rules also come as an increasing number of states move to make prison and jail communication free. In 2023, Massachusetts, Minnesota, and Colorado each passed legislation to make prison calls free. California made prison calls free in 2022 and Connecticut in 2021. Campaigns are currently underway in more than a dozen other states.</p><p><strong>Former FCC Acting Chairwoman of the FCC and member of the Board of Directors of the Benton Institute for Broadband &amp; Society Mignon Clyburn </strong>said,<strong>&nbsp;</strong>“Today marks a major milestone on the long road to right a market dysfunction that has wronged incarcerated persons and their loved ones for decades. &nbsp;I have nothing but praise for Chairwoman Rosenworcel and her fellow Commissioners who moved this item forward, and the hard-working FCC staff for crafting forceful rules that are faithful to the goals of the Martha Wright-Reed Just and Reasonable Communications Act.”</p><p>“Today, we cross a major milestone in the decades-long quest to prevent gauging of families when they pay to communicate with their incarcerated loved ones. With the Federal Communications Commission vote today, prices are dropping between 8 and 14 cents per minute from existing voice calling caps, and video communication will benefit from rate protections for the first time. Lower cost communication means more memories and tighter bonds, it means more opportunities to say 'I love you' and 'I miss you' at the moment they can make a huge difference in a child's life. It brings people together instead of breaking them apart under the weight of impossible financial burdens,” said <strong>Cheryl A. Leanza, policy advisor to the United Church of Christ Media Justice Ministry.</strong> “The journey to this day has been decades in the making, from Mrs. Martha Wright-Reed, who was willing to put&nbsp;her name on a lawsuit more than 20 years ago, to bi-partisan champions in Congress, hard-working agency leaders and staff, fellow advocates, and most important: the countless family members and incarcerated people who took the time to tell their stories, write postcards, contact their legislators or attend a Federal Communications Commission listening session. It all really does make a difference.”</p><p>“Today, 18 months from the passage of the Marta Wright-Reed Just and Reasonable Communications Act of 2022, the Federal Communications Commission took action to end predatory prison phone rates. After a decade of advocacy, incarcerated individuals and their loved ones will be able to communicate with each other without the barrier of burdensome fees. The absence of these predatory rates is life-changing, potentially lowering rates of depression, isolation, and loneliness incarcerated individuals experience while in prison and helping them succeed when reentering their communities,” said <strong>Koustubh “K.J.” Bagchi, Vice President of the Center for Civil Rights and Technology at The Leadership Conference on Civil and Human Rights.</strong></p><p>“Incarcerated people and their loved ones have paid an unconscionably high price for the greed of the companies who provide telecom services to prisons, jails and detention centers. Thankfully, that’s about to change,” said <strong>Heather Franklin, Internet Campaign Director at Free Press. </strong>“The ability for incarcerated people to maintain regular communication with loved ones, legal counsel and clergy is a human-rights issue. Incarcerated people should be able to connect and communicate without being subject to extortionate rates. We’re grateful for the work of FCC Chairwoman Jessica Rosenworcel, the other commissioners, agency staff, and decades of work by advocates across the country who’ve made today’s strides possible.”&nbsp;</p><p>“The FCC’s action today will help to ensure that families no longer have to pay inflated, predatory rates to speak to their incarcerated loved ones,” said <strong>Ariel Nelson, staff attorney at the National Consumer Law Center, who leads its Criminal Justice Debt &amp; Reintegration Project.</strong> “We are grateful the Commission has also put a stop to two enduring areas of consumer abuse–outrageous fees and site commissions–bringing meaningful financial relief and connection to families across the country.”</p><p>"With today’s order, the FCC affirmed what our movement has been saying for decades: The families of incarcerated people should not be shouldering the costs of their loved ones’ incarceration," said <strong>Peter Wagner, Executive Director of the Prison Policy Initiative. </strong>"Capping the costs of all phone and video calls, as the FCC has done, will bring relief to millions of families, and other provisions in its order will prevent the exploitation of consumers through fees and deceptive pricing. We are glad to see the FCC take these steps toward true consumer protection for incarcerated people."</p><p>“For years, incarcerated people unable to afford exorbitant call rates have been denied the ability to easily communicate with their loved ones, their communities, and even their attorneys. These excessive communications costs hurt incarcerated people as well as their families and communities. By requiring just and reasonable rates, the FCC is working to keep families together and to ease the return to society of incarcerated people. We commend Chairwoman Rosenworcel for her leadership in keeping incarcerated people connected and applaud the FCC for requiring reasonable rates for these vital communications,”<strong> </strong>said <strong>Al Kramer, senior fellow at Public Knowledge.&nbsp;</strong></p><p>“We applaud the leadership of Chairwoman Rosenworcel and the Federal Communications Commission for taking this important and monumental action. The FCC’s order serves as a transformative win for incarcerated peoples and their loved ones who for far too long have had to grapple with outrageous rates,” said <strong>Rebekah P. Goodheart, Jenner &amp; Block LLP, pro bono counsel to the Wright Petitioners. </strong>“Thanks to the tireless advocacy of various groups and civil rights organizations, much-needed relief will be provided.”</p><p>"It’s exciting to see that the Federal Communications Commission is taking steps to enact the Martha Wright-Reed legislation to lower the cost of prison phone calls," said&nbsp;<strong>Brandon Tucker, Senior Policy Director at Color Of Change.</strong> "This is a major step in prison justice. Phone call costs have been predatory and it has never made sense for families of incarcerated people to pay high amounts of money to stay in contact with their loved ones. The system was rooted in corporate greed and not rehabilitation. It is unacceptable that families have gone into debt accepting phone calls from jails and prison. Thank you to Chairwoman Jessica Rosenworcel and other commissioners for rectifying this misstep in our judicial system."</p></div><p><a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=132d7170b3&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank">Worth Rises</a> is a non-profit advocacy organization dedicated to dismantling the prison industry and ending the exploitation of those it targets. Follow @WorthRises on <a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=d744a8dd14&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=d81a2cfc3d&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank">Instagram</a>, and <a href="https://worthrises.us17.list-manage.com/track/click?u=d5deffca38b8d1f6cd5d6dfc9&amp;id=df14550f86&amp;e=6c5990aeb2" target="_blank">Facebook</a>.</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: What is in C-00000291*.sys? (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41004103</link>
            <guid>41004103</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 09:29:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41004103">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="41005051"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005263"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005263" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005263&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>They might just be encrypted with a customer-specific key. That wouldn't surprise me.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005546"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005546" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005546&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>They weren't last time I looked. They seem to contain a bunch of different things, but you can absolutely download and parse them without needing to decrypt anything.</p><p>If you have a Crowdstrike customer ID (CID) — which you can pull from any device that has the implant — you can request any channel file you want from their file server.</p><p>Ask for metahash+/cfs/channelfiles/0000000291/&lt;YOUR CUSTOMER ID&gt;/C-00000291-00000000-00000001.sys and you should get something that starts with:</p><pre><code>    00000000: aaaa aaaa 0100 2301 0000 0500 0000 0000  ......#.........
    00000010: 0100 0000 4808 0000 2c08 0000 0600 0004  ....H...,.......
</code></pre><p>
That's a channel file, unencrypted.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41004658"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005570"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41004838"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41004838" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41004838&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>It's a crowdstrike update file with a bug in it, from what I gather. This makes your Windows machine go blue screen and stop working as it starts up. If you manage to remove it by various methods, it doesn't run and you're fine.</p><p>More informed people will give you more details, but this kind of AV software often has privileged access to the OS, so it can scan your files. The same privileged access also means it can really mess things up if it's not well tested.</p><p>By contrast your ordinary python or VBA script should not be able to blue screen your machine, especially not during startup.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005857"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005857" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005857&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; By contrast your ordinary python or VBA script should not be able to blue screen your machine, especially not during startup.</p><p>This is misleading. If you run a python or VBA script on startup with elevated permissions to e.g. setup a driver (with a bug) or do hardware configurations (in a way which doesn't work) then it will as much blue screen as a sys file.</p><p>The issue is not that it's a `.sys` file, but that a high privilege administrative task run at startup fails so hard that it blue screens.</p><p>(In windows the sys file extension is basically just a marker that the file is part of the "system" without being clear what it is, it can be anything from a data blob,over a data base, over python/VBA files to a device driver or a blob combining multiple of such things. They mostly contain device drivers and hardware configuration, but there are some which are basically just the equivalent of /etc/hostname)</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41005771"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005771" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005771&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>A malware delivery platform sponsored by the US security state. All customers get customised versions nothing to see here.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41004544"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41004852"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41006523"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005800"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41004555"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41004846"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005167"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005167" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005167&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>These files are apparently just definitions/input for the actual CrowdStroke driver, that presumably someone named .sys so it sounds more scary and important.</p><p>Peak irony then that you can just delete them. Surely an antivirus should recognize when its being rollbacked?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005351"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005751"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005751" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005751&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I don’t have a Windows setup, let alone one with CrowdStrike installed, but for this, you have to be in recovery mode to boot, not necessarily to be able to delete that file. For that, admin access may be enough.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41004897"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41004897" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41004897&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>On another note, I know nothing about cybersec, is there a reason for which antivirus on windows run at ring 0 while I read that on Linux and Mac they don't have kernel level access?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005310"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005310" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005310&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It's not an anti-virus, it's intended to monitor all and everything on the machine. You^WAn attacker might want to hide what you're doing and thus it runs at that level.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41004932"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005183"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41006674"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41006674" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41006674&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I complained specifically about that and they bounced it back to me like this was safe and cannot use the machine as I want.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005225"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005675"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005675" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005675&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This is a management move. IT probably wasn't in the loop, since this effectively reduce the responsibilities of IT in terms of compliance.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005278"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41006121"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41006121" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41006121&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The cyber unit within IT is more likely, those ones are besotted with ticking compliance checkboxes, the delegation of responsibility and a game of musical chairs at any cost.</p><p>It is even more likely that IT was at loggerheads with cyber, but nowadays cyber seems to be able to trump everything and everyone.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41006510"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41006510" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41006510&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I work in a customer-facing role for a similar product.  
The handful of customers that asked about kernel modules / drivers saw it as a plus not a con.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41005251"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41004826"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41004826" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41004826&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Hm, is there any website that explains why C-00000291*.sys caused the widespread BSODs?  For example, was it some kind of definition file that was accessing invalid memory locations?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41004799"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41004799" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41004799&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Specifically, if the file is corrupted, in what way is it corrupt? I’m fascinated by how this issue occurred.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41004974"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41004974" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41004974&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It likely contains a bug but is an uncorrupted file. Corrupted to me means the file was changed or modified in a way from it's intended state and likely won't run anymore.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005042"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005077"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005077" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005077&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Star is part of a command to delete any file matching a wildcard `C-00000291*.sys` meaning "starts with 'C-00000291', has any kind of text after that and ends with '.sys'". Actual files appear to differ for every machine</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005153"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005153" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005153&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>This exchange reminds me of a time many years ago where I was reading a computer magazine and they talked about “Windows 9x” and I thought they were referring to some version of Windows that I had never heard of.</p><p>Only a couple of years later did I understand that it was simply a shorthand for talking about Windows 95 and Windows 98.</p><p>Edit: And looking now at Wikipedia apparently it also covers Windows Me. (The Millennium Edition that came between Windows 98 and Windows XP.) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_9x" rel="nofollow">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Windows_9x</a></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005944"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005944" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005944&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Also the reason that Microsoft skipped from Windows 8 to Windows 10. Too much risk of apps testing the first 8 characters of the Windows version against "Windows 9" and concluding they were running on 95/98 rather than 9.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                    <tr id="41004931"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41004931" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41004931&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Wouldn't want to be the guy who pushed this particular commit. It's ironic that the company that is supposed to prevent this sort of thing causes the biggest worldwide outage ever. Crowdstrike is finished. Let's hope this will result in at least a small increase in desktop Linux market share.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41004982"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41006648"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005035"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005035" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005035&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Yeah, but heads will have to roll for this one, the world will be calling for blood, so who better if not "the guy"?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005509"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005509" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005509&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>When the world calls for blood against your organization, it's a test of the organization's character: will they throw a scapegoat under the bus (even if there is a directly responsible person) or will they defend their staff, accept fault, and demonstratively improve process?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41006138"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41006138" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41006138&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Many major companies have post-mortem reviews for this kind of thing. Most of the big failures we see is a mix of people being rushed, detection processes failing, a miscommunication/misunderstanding of the effects of a small change.</p><p>One analogy is rounding - one rounding makes no difference to a transaction, but multiple systems rounding the same direction can have a large scale impact. It's not always rounding money - it can be error handling. A stops at the error, B goes on, turns out they're not in sync.</p><p>Which guy is it? The person who pressed the button? The manager who gave that person more than one task that day? The people who didn't sufficiently test the detection process? The people who wrote the specs without sufficient understanding of the full impact? The person who decided to layoff the people who knew the impact three months ago?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005130"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005130" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005130&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>the management that enabled the process. And follow the chain to the top, they are paid very well to own the risks</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005370"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005370" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005370&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>More importantly, the companies that enabled auto update from a vendor to production rather than having a validation process. This sort of issue can happen with any vendor, penalising the vendor won't help with the next time this happens.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005426"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005426" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005426&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Was there a way to not enable these channel updates? If so, would you still check all the mandatory security measures when being audited?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41005396"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005396" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005396&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>It’s both. If you’re an engineer and you push out shitty code that takes down 911 systems and ambulances, you f’ed up. Push back against processes that cause harm, or have the potential to cause harm. You are ultimately responsible for your actions. No one else. The excuse of “I was just following orders” has been dead and buried since WW2.</p><p>Yeah, ideally management should know better. But management aren’t usually engineers. Even when they are, they don’t deal with the code on a day to day basis. They usually know much less about the actual processes and risks than the engineers on the ground.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41006358"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41006358" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41006358&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; It’s both. If you’re an engineer and you push out shitty code that takes down 911 systems and ambulances, you f’ed up.</p><p>This is wrong. If a company is developing that kind of software is the responsibility of the company to provide a certain level of QA before they release software. And no, it's not that "engineers are pushing out shitty code", but that the shitty company allows shitty code to be deployed in customers' machines.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005609"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005609" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005609&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>if one of the people i manage is not up to the task the fault is mine. I've hired them. I should setup a system of hard gained trust and automation to avoid or at least minimize them fucking up. When fuckups happen, they are my fuckups. Critical systems don't survive only on trust, obviously. If I don't setup the teams and the systems properly, my bosses will also take the blame for having put me in that position.
I'm not advocating for lower layers to avoid responsabilities. But if an head needs to roll you should look above. That said, peole are hardened by fuckups, so there are better solutions than rolling heads, usually.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                    <tr id="41005032"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005032" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005032&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Crowdstrike is finished</p><p>Unlikely, just as Solarwinds wasn't finished when they distributed malware that got government agencies hacked. You underestimate the slow turning radius of giant company purchasing departments.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005705"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005705" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005705&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>As I posted elsewhere, the SolarWinds stock has never recovered from its high before the hack.  And it is on a downward trend.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41005064"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005702"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005702" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005702&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The SolarWinds stock has never recovered from its high before the hack.  And it is on a downward trend.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005227"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005629"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41006691"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41006691" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41006691&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Why the fuck didn't MSFT just do blue/green canarying? No update should be rolled out to a billion devices at once until it's baked in a million devices for a bit, and that only after baking in 10,000 devices for a bit.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41006770"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41005040"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005040" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005040&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Enterprise Linuxes also employ Crowdstrike or similar "security" products as mandatory part of their IT deployments. Often (always?) this is due to companies wanting certification for their secure processes, in order to sell to government or large corporations that require them.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005174"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005174" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005174&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Crowdstrike in their official statement said "Linux and MacOS not affected". Are there any reports stating otherwise?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005963"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41005963" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41005963&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41004103"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>not affected because the bug is in the windows specific code, not because it works so much different on linux</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41005883"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41005374"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41004997"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005242"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41005324"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41005021"><td></td></tr>
                  </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ryanair – when every page is a dark pattern (277 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hallofshame.design/ryanair-when-every-page-is-a-dark-pattern/</link>
            <guid>41004039</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 09:23:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hallofshame.design/ryanair-when-every-page-is-a-dark-pattern/">https://hallofshame.design/ryanair-when-every-page-is-a-dark-pattern/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41004039">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <main>
        <article>
            
                            <figure>
        <p><a href="https://hallofshame.design/ryanair-when-every-page-is-a-dark-pattern/">
                <img data-srcset="/content/images/size/w400/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 400w, /content/images/size/w750/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 750w, /content/images/size/w960/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 960w, /content/images/size/w1140/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 1140w, /content/images/size/w1920/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 1920w" data-sizes="auto" alt="Ryanair – when every page is a dark pattern" srcset="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w400/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 400w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w750/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 750w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w960/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 960w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1140/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 1140w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1920/2022/07/ryanair-2.png 1920w">
            </a>
        </p>

                <figcaption>Illustration by <strong><strong><a href="https://dribbble.com/lucidblue">Lucid Blue</a></strong></strong></figcaption>
    </figure>
            <div>
                <p>Ryanair is a prime example of a company that employs various manipulative techniques, known as "dark patterns," to increase its profits.</p><p>One such tactic is their default sign-up for promotional materials, which is considered a form of "<a href="https://hallofshame.design/tag/privacy-zuckering/">privacy zuckering.</a>"</p><figure><img src="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image.png" alt="Ryanair Contact Details Form" loading="lazy" width="1612" height="622" srcset="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w600/2022/07/image.png 600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1000/2022/07/image.png 1000w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1600/2022/07/image.png 1600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image.png 1612w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Throughout the booking process, the Ryanair website employs various "misdirection" dark patterns to upsell customers on additional services.</p><p>For example, they use prominent buttons to promote "fast track" options, which can be easily clicked on as they are located in the middle of the page, making it easy to accidentally select them while scrolling down to skip the offer.</p><figure><img src="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-1.png" alt="Ryanair Fast Track Dark Pattern" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1126" srcset="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w600/2022/07/image-1.png 600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1000/2022/07/image-1.png 1000w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1600/2022/07/image-1.png 1600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-1.png 2362w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Even if a customer declines the upsell offer on the previous step, Ryanair will continue to use "<a href="https://hallofshame.design/tag/misdirection/">misdirection</a>" dark patterns by displaying another popup with a prominent button. </p><p>This time, they may even change the color of the button and the title to deceive customers further and make it appear as a different offer, tricking the customer's attention and making it less evident that it's the same page as before.</p><figure><img src="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-2.png" alt="Ryanair Fast Track Dark Pattern 2" loading="lazy" width="1384" height="1292" srcset="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w600/2022/07/image-2.png 600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1000/2022/07/image-2.png 1000w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-2.png 1384w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>The Ryanair website employs various "dark patterns" throughout its booking process to upsell customers on additional services and manipulate their attention. </p><p>One such example is using "misdirection" techniques, such as attempting to upsell customers on additional features and strategically placing primary buttons to encourage accidental clicks. This type of manipulative design is prevalent on nearly every website page.</p><figure><img src="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-3.png" alt="Choose your fare for the trip dark pattern" loading="lazy" width="1074" height="1218" srcset="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w600/2022/07/image-3.png 600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1000/2022/07/image-3.png 1000w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-3.png 1074w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Ryanair repeatedly presents customers with upsell offers for the same features, asking multiple times in case the customer changes their mind or falls for one of the manipulative "dark patterns" prevalent throughout the website. This persistent approach increases the likelihood of the customer making an impulse purchase or accidentally clicking on an offer.</p><figure><img src="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/2022/07/image-4.png" alt="Another example of the fare selection with dark patterns" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="744" srcset="https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w600/2022/07/image-4.png 600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1000/2022/07/image-4.png 1000w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w1600/2022/07/image-4.png 1600w, https://hallofshame.design/content/images/size/w2400/2022/07/image-4.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Ryanair has integrated manipulative "dark patterns" into nearly every aspect of their booking process and it appears that they have no plans to stop using them. </p><p>It is important to be cautious and vigilant when using the Ryanair website, as these techniques are designed to deceive customers and increase profits for the company.</p>
            </div>
            
            
        </article>
        
            
            </main>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[74935 viewing Mass worldwide IT outage affects airlines, media and banks (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et</link>
            <guid>41002730</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 07:07:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41002730">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main id="main-content" data-testid="main-content"><div width="300" role="tabpanel" aria-labelledby="tab-LiveReporting" id="LiveReporting" tabindex="-1"><div id="summaryPoints"><h2 type="section-heading">Summary</h2><div spacing="4" data-testid="test-election-component-editorial-text"><ul role="list"><li><p>IT outages are reported across the world, affecting airlines, media, and banks</p></li><li><p>Many flights have been grounded, with queues and delays at airports</p></li><li><p>American Airlines says none of its flights are taking off and the IT problems are due to an issue with <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et?post=asset%3Ae2113049-9970-434b-b0b0-e9c4c428c234#post">Crowdstrike cybersecurity software</a></p></li><li><p>Microsoft earlier said it was taking <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et?post=asset%3A2424710d-194c-4f7f-a4a4-8ad9da83423d#post">mitigation action</a>, but the cause of the outages hasn't been confirmed</p></li><li><p>In the UK, railway companies report delays and say they're <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et?post=asset%3Aaaba3e5c-a8b0-4d60-bcde-32c1e3a6c2a3#post">experiencing "widespread IT issues"</a></p></li><li><p>Some GP surgeries in England are having <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cnk4jdwp49et?post=asset%3A3b2c6ba2-65bb-4d9e-87ff-f14d0285a6ca#post">issues with booking appointments</a></p></li><li><p>Sky News has not been able to broadcast live, its executive chairman says</p></li></ul></div></div><div><div><h2 type="section-heading">Live Reporting</h2><p>Edited by Owen Amos and Barbara Tasch</p></div><div><ol role="list" spacing="6" tabindex="0" data-testid="postList"><span aria-live="polite"></span><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:7d36e461-a04d-455b-9b8f-2b64936cbaaa"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>CBBC is only BBC channel affected</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:26</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><span></span></span></span><span><strong>Yasmin Rufo</strong><br>Culture, arts &amp; entertainment reporter</span></p><p>The BBC’s channel for children and teenagers, CBBC, has been down
since earlier this morning.</p><p>The channel has a message which reads: "Sorry! Something’s gone wrong. </p><p>"While we fix it, please go to BBC iPlayer."</p><p>BBC channels including BBC One and CBeebies are still on
air. </p><p>Other broadcasters including ITV and Channel 4 have not been
affected, but Sky News has been unable to broadcast. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:5da322ed-c550-474e-b358-682fa4e84001"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Barcodes not working at Gatwick</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:24</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><strong>Aruna Iyengar</strong><br>Reporting from Gatwick airport</span></p><p>Here at Gatwick, barcodes are not working so security checks on boarding passes are being done manually, but  security searches are operating normally.</p><p>I didn't have baggage to check in, so no delays for me there. But I had to use cash to buy coffees at Starbucks in the airport departures lounge. </p><p>I am on an internal flight to Newquay and am on the plane now. It is all on time so far - due to take off at 9.20am. </p><p>But we are being warned that it might take time to take off because of backlogs with air traffic control. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:588ff0a3-6a92-4bca-9230-414465829bee"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Poland's largest container terminal 'struggling'</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:22</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><span></span></span></span><span><strong>Adam Easton</strong><br>Warsaw Correspondent</span></p><p>Poland’s largest container terminal, the Baltic Hub in the northern city of Gdansk, is the latest major infrastructure to be affected.</p><p>"Pleased be advised that we are struggling at the Baltic Hub with a global Microsoft operating system outage that is hampering terminal operations," the company says.</p><p>Baltic Hub has asked companies not to send containers to the port. The hub began operating in 2007 and has the capacity to handle up to 2.9 million containers annually.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:e2113049-9970-434b-b0b0-e9c4c428c234"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>American Airlines blames Crowdstrike for outage</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:20</span><p><span>Breaking</span></p></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><span></span></span></span><span><strong>Jonathan Josephs</strong><br>BBC business reporter</span></p><p>American Airlines, which is the world's biggest by passenger numbers, tells BBC that no flights are being allowed to take off, and that it is in contact with all flights that are currently in the air. </p><p>It says the IT problems are because of a "technical issue with Crowdstrike that is impacting multiple carriers".</p><p>The airline says its working with the IT security firm to fix the problem as quickly as possible.
The airline carries an average of 578,000 passengers a day.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:3b288311-885d-41a0-99c4-f42fb2ce0508"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>GP only seeing most unwell patients</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:14</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><span></span></span></span><span><strong>Hugh Pym</strong><br>Health editor</span></p><p>One GP tells me: "We can see acutely unwell [patients] and handwrite notes/scripts, but for anything else we are asking to call back."</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:3b2c6ba2-65bb-4d9e-87ff-f14d0285a6ca"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Problems reported with NHS GP system</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:13</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>There appears to be issues with booking appointments at some GP surgeries in England.</p><p>There are multiple reports in relation to <b>EMIS Web </b>- which allows GPs to manage appointment bookings, conduct patient consultations, and update, store and share patient records.</p><p>Grimethorpe Surgery in Barnsley <a href="https://x.com/GrimethorpeSur1/status/1814187687978361116">posted on X<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> reporting a "major issue" saying it has "no access" to the clinical system. </p><p>The clinic later posted saying: "We are aware that users are still unable to access EMIS Web."</p><p>The Church Lane Surgery in Brighouse posted on X saying "our clinical system has not been working since 7am this morning".</p><p>
"We have no access to patient clinical records so are unable to book appointments or provide information."</p><p>Central Lakes Medical Group in Ambleside wrote on X saying it has been "impacted by the IT outage". </p><p>Solihull Healthcare Partnership in the West Midlands said there is a "national issue" with "EMIS Web", the clinical computer system. </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:d55c4bde-4c3a-4335-8733-39f8375a1093"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Reports name Crowdstrike as possible cause</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:02</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><span></span></span></span><span><strong>Zoe Kleinman</strong><br>Technology editor</span></p><p>There have been reports suggesting that a cybersecurity company called Crowdstrike, which produces antivirus software, issued a software update that has gone horribly wrong and is bricking Windows devices - prompting the so-called "blue screen of death" on PCs.  </p><p>Now, whether these two issues are the same thing, or whether it's a perfect storm of two big things happening simultaneously - I don't yet know. It certainly sounds like it's going to be causing a lot of havoc. </p><p>We've contacted Crowdstrike for response but haven't heard back yet.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:8af60d51-0df0-4538-8f34-5f9882b1d237"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Outage hits airport and parliament in New Zealand</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 09:02</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>In New Zealand, Christchurch International Airport says it is experiencing IT issues across a number of systems which may affect flight arrivals and departures.</p><p>And a spokesperson for New Zealand's parliament says their computer network is having problems.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:1fcd2f60-51fc-4e3e-8e31-b3725e647a39"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Sky News back on air... briefly</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:59</span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><p><span><img alt="Sky News slate" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/5247882f-fecd-46d6-83bc-c4dcd596bb6d.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/5247882f-fecd-46d6-83bc-c4dcd596bb6d.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/5247882f-fecd-46d6-83bc-c4dcd596bb6d.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/5247882f-fecd-46d6-83bc-c4dcd596bb6d.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/5247882f-fecd-46d6-83bc-c4dcd596bb6d.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/723/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/5247882f-fecd-46d6-83bc-c4dcd596bb6d.jpg 723w" width="723" height="406"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Sky News</span></p></figure><p>A few moments ago Sky News resumed broadcasting after being forced off air.</p><p>But it's now once again displaying a slate apologising "for the interruption to this broadcast".</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:1715952e-66c8-4602-abd2-9ebc8792e835"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>In the UK, Gail's unable to take in-store payments</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:58</span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><p><span><img alt="Picture of a sign on window of bakery" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/4f9fe018-a4f0-4ea5-8be1-e5d34f11112d.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/4f9fe018-a4f0-4ea5-8be1-e5d34f11112d.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/4f9fe018-a4f0-4ea5-8be1-e5d34f11112d.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/4f9fe018-a4f0-4ea5-8be1-e5d34f11112d.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/4f9fe018-a4f0-4ea5-8be1-e5d34f11112d.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/4f9fe018-a4f0-4ea5-8be1-e5d34f11112d.jpg 800w" width="978" height="550"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Clara Wikforss</span></p></figure><p>In the UK, bakery and coffee shop chain Gail's is reporting problems.</p><p>A sign outside the window of its Swain's Lane shop in London says it is unable to take in-store payments. </p><p>Users on social media have also reported being unable to make payments at other Gail's outlets.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:ce0c45e1-c3a8-4170-ae7f-0b9ad14ccc53"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Airports in Japan and India also affected</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:55</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>Japan's Narita airport, around 60km (37miles) from Tokyo, says airlines JetStar, Jeju Air, Qantas, HK Express and Spring Japan are having issues with their systems.</p><p>And in India, Delhi airport says some services have been temporarily impacted.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:04c15440-348e-4453-96fa-d9e298972ee0"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Alaska State Troopers report 911 outage</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:53</span><p><span>Breaking</span></p></span></span></h3></span></header><p>Police in the US state of Alaska have <a href="https://www.facebook.com/AlaskaStateTroopersOfficial/posts/pfbid022K5MYDVWd8fKxJqbYVCm9sKz1UTCd2SB4T9z5s7tRA3ZP5cPupbg4TU6Ev4bxi5Ul?locale=en_GB">reported<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a> an outage of emergency phone lines. </p><p>Posting on Facebook, the state police force says "many 911 and non-emergency call centres are not working correctly across the State of Alaska".</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:c17724c6-209e-4f06-9e4f-ded257f57d58"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Long queues at Stansted airport, but flights operating as normal</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:47</span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><p><span><img alt="Long queues at Stansted Airport" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/ffd33e51-d4b0-4721-ba29-9eb92301d7ee.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/ffd33e51-d4b0-4721-ba29-9eb92301d7ee.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/ffd33e51-d4b0-4721-ba29-9eb92301d7ee.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/ffd33e51-d4b0-4721-ba29-9eb92301d7ee.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/ffd33e51-d4b0-4721-ba29-9eb92301d7ee.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/ffd33e51-d4b0-4721-ba29-9eb92301d7ee.jpg 800w" width="1372" height="772"></span></p></figure><p>Meanwhile at London's Stansted airport, some check-ins are being done manually but "flights are still operating as normal".</p><p>"Our main operational systems are unaffected," a spokesperson says, but "some retail payment machine services have been impacted". </p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:b743e1e3-d12b-4300-af47-89e50c17470d"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Amsterdam's Schiphol airport also affected</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:46</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>Amsterdam's Schiphol airport is the latest to report delays caused by the IT outage.</p><p>"The outage has an impact on flights flying from and to
Schiphol," a spokesperson says, adding it is not yet clear how many
flights are affected.</p></article></div></li><li></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:e31c51ab-de8a-43be-b49a-ffd4a4de9e79"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>London Stock Exchange operating as normal</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:42</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>The London Stock Exchange says it's working as normal - but says there are problems with its RNS (regulatory news service).</p><p>"RNS news service is currently experiencing a third party global technical issue, preventing news from being published on www.londonstockexchange.com," the statement says.</p><p>"Technical teams are working to restore the service. Other services across the group, including London Stock Exchange, continue to operate as normal."</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:f19aad0a-1547-4231-b79d-05c911c5b019"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>IT outages: What is happening?</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:36</span></span></span></h3></span></header><figure><p><span><img alt="A blue error screen on a register is seen at a departmental store affected by a cyber outage in Brisbane, Australia" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/e749d07f-8b5b-4020-89ee-c1b862dad36e.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/e749d07f-8b5b-4020-89ee-c1b862dad36e.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/e749d07f-8b5b-4020-89ee-c1b862dad36e.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/e749d07f-8b5b-4020-89ee-c1b862dad36e.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/e749d07f-8b5b-4020-89ee-c1b862dad36e.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2024/7/19/e749d07f-8b5b-4020-89ee-c1b862dad36e.jpg 800w" width="1000" height="750"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>A blue error screen on a checkout at a department store in Brisbane, Australia</p></figcaption></figure><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      Reports of IT outages are coming in from around the world
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Airlines, broadcasters and banks are affected - including Sky News in the UK, which is off-air
    </li></ul><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      Multiple airports in the UK and across the world are reporting delays, with some flights suspended
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      In the US, major airlines including United and Delta are stopping flights
    </li></ul><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      In Australia, airports, shops, and communications are affected, Australia's National Cyber Security Coordinator described it as a "large-scale technical outage"
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Railway companies in the UK report delays
    </li></ul><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      Microsoft says it is continuing to deal with "the lingering impact" of the outage 
    </li></ul></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:31e4f2be-ba2d-48d4-9216-e769a594964a"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Mild chaos at Sydney Airport</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:33</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><span></span></span></span><span><strong>Simon Atkinson</strong><br>Reporting from Sydney airport</span></p><p>It has been an hour of uncertainty and mild chaos here at
Sydney Airport.</p><p>First departure board information screens went blank - with at
least one airline, Jetstar, announcing it could not check passengers in. </p><p>Its
apology on the public address system firmly blamed Microsoft.</p><p>About half an hour later Virgin Australia said there had
been a “total ground stop” with “no flights going in or out”.</p><p>But things do seem
to be moving again. Virgin Australia has started boarding flights (including mine)
and so it looks like the skies above Australia’s biggest city will soon be
filled with aircraft again.</p><p>Not everyone is thrilled. In perhaps stereotypical Australian fashion, I overheard one passenger say he was a bit disappointed not to be squeezing in a
couple of extra Friday night airport beers.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:18a5d341-b8e2-4c7e-8ea6-cbcf8d150996"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>US airlines issue global ground stop on all flights</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:31</span><p><span>Breaking</span></p></span></span></h3></span></header><p>United, Delta and American Airlines - which are all based in the United States - have issued a "global ground stop" on all of their flights. </p><p>Flights that are currently airborne will continue, but no further flights will take off for now.</p></article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:beca9189-0223-4619-8369-553404a8761b"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Ryanair warns of 'potential disruptions across network'</span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 08:26</span></span></span></h3></span></header><p>Further from that post from Edinburgh, European airline Ryanair says it's experiencing "potential disruptions across the network" - which it says is due to a third party outage. </p><p>The airline is advising that anyone travelling today should check the Ryanair app for updates on their flight.</p></article></div></li></ol></div></div></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Crowdstrike Outage Causing Widespread Issues (732 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.afr.com/technology/businesses-crippled-by-widespread-it-outage-20240719-p5jv2t</link>
            <guid>41002677</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 07:00:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.afr.com/technology/businesses-crippled-by-widespread-it-outage-20240719-p5jv2t">https://www.afr.com/technology/businesses-crippled-by-widespread-it-outage-20240719-p5jv2t</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41002677">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="content"><div><ul data-testid="ArticleBreadcrumb-Links"><li><a href="https://www.afr.com/technology">Technology</a></li><li><a href="https://www.afr.com/topic/it-networks-hqr">IT networks</a></li></ul></div><header></header><section><p><time data-testid="ArticleTimestamp-time">Jul 19, 2024 – 4.50pm</time></p><div data-testid="ArticleTools"><p data-testid="Modal-title">Subscribe to gift this article</p><p data-testid="Modal-description"><span>Gift 5 articles to anyone you choose each month when you subscribe.</span></p><p><a data-testid="Modal-subscribe-button" href="https://subscribe.afr.com/?promote_channel=HI_AGFT_GNL_GIFTCTA&amp;utm_source=ArticleGifting&amp;utm_medium=HouseInventory&amp;utm_campaign=General&amp;utm_content=GiftCTA">Subscribe now</a></p><p>Already a subscriber?<!-- --> </p></div></section><div><div id="endOfArticle"><p>Banks, airlines, miners and media companies have been hit with a global IT outage on Friday afternoon that brought down systems and locked workers out of their devices.</p><p>Several companies appear to be hit, including Nine, Deloitte, Qantas and Woolworths. The fault is thought to be linked to a bad patch update provided by global cybersecurity firm CrowdStrike.</p></div><div data-testid="ArticleFooter"><p data-testid="Modal-title">Subscribe to gift this article</p><p data-testid="Modal-description"><span>Gift 5 articles to anyone you choose each month when you subscribe.</span></p><p><a data-testid="Modal-subscribe-button" href="https://subscribe.afr.com/?promote_channel=HI_AGFT_GNL_GIFTCTA&amp;utm_source=ArticleGifting&amp;utm_medium=HouseInventory&amp;utm_campaign=General&amp;utm_content=GiftCTA">Subscribe now</a></p><p>Already a subscriber?<!-- --> </p></div><div data-testid="ArticleTags"><div data-testid="NewsfeedArticleDriver" role="alert"><header><h2>Introducing your <span>Newsfeed</span></h2></header><div><p>Follow the topics, people and companies that matter to you.</p><a href="https://www.afr.com/newsfeed/about">Find out more</a></div></div><h3 data-testid="ArticleTags-heading">Read More</h3><ul><li data-testid="ArticleTags-li"></li><li data-testid="ArticleTags-li"></li><li data-testid="ArticleTags-li"></li><li data-testid="ArticleTags-li"></li><li data-testid="ArticleTags-li"></li></ul></div></div><div><div><header data-testid="ContentUnitHeading-header"><h2 data-pb-type="hi" data-testid="ContentUnitHeading-heading">Latest In Technology</h2></header><p>Fetching latest articles</p></div><section data-contentunit-id="0"><header data-testid="ContentUnitHeading-header"><h2 data-pb-type="hi" data-testid="ContentUnitHeading-heading">Most Viewed In Technology</h2></header><ol></ol></section></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Foliate: Read e-books in style, navigate with ease (388 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://johnfactotum.github.io/foliate/</link>
            <guid>41002273</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 05:48:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://johnfactotum.github.io/foliate/">https://johnfactotum.github.io/foliate/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41002273">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p><b>Read e-books in style.</b> Open EPUB, Mobipocket, Kindle, FB2, CBZ, and PDF files. Read in paginated or scrolled mode. Adjust the font, spacing, margins, and color scheme. Window controls hide automatically to minimize distraction.
        </p><p><b>Navigate with ease.</b> Turn the page with 1:1 touchpad and touchscreen gestures. View the table of contents, or use the <i>find in book</i> feature in the sidebar. Find your way through the book with the reading progress slider and navigation history.</p>
        <figure>
            <img src="https://johnfactotum.github.io/foliate/screenshot.webp" alt="Screenshot">
            <figcaption>Screenshot of Foliate's main interface, showing the book <cite><a href="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks/herman-melville/moby-dick">Moby Dick</a></cite> from <a href="https://standardebooks.org/">Standard Ebooks</a>.</figcaption>
        </figure>
        <div><p><img src="https://johnfactotum.github.io/foliate/annotation.webp" alt="Cropped screenshot showing Foliate's annotation feature"></p><p><b>Add bookmarks and annotations.</b> Reading progress, bookmarks, and annotations are stored in plain JSON files, so you can export or sync them easily with any tool or storage service. <a href="https://github.com/johnfactotum/foliate/blob/gtk4/docs/faq.md#how-are-notes-and-bookmarks-stored">Learn More →</a>
        </p><p><b>Nifty tools.</b> Look up words in Wiktionary and Wikipedia. Translate passages with Google Translate. Read text aloud with with Speech Dispatcher.
        </p></div>
        <div><p><img src="https://johnfactotum.github.io/foliate/vertical.webp" alt="Cropped screenshot of vertical Japanese text rendered in Foliate"></p><p><b>Advanced rendering.</b> Foliate supports right-to-left text, vertical writing, and fixed layout books. Enjoy features such as auto-hyphenation, popup footnotes, and media overlays.
        </p><p><b>Open source.</b> Foliate is free software: you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the terms of the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/licenses/gpl.html">GNU General Public License</a>.
        </p></div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Windows Bluescreen and Boot Loops (update: caused by a Crowdstrike update) (2687 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41002195</link>
            <guid>41002195</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 05:26:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41002195">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="41002702"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002702" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002702&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I don't understand why this outage and the Azure outage earlier don't make it to the front page.</p><p>I'm getting more up to date technical details from the regular media.</p><p>This outage looks to be huge.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002813"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002732"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002746"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002411"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002411" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002411&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>In terms of analysing risk factors to minimise something like this happening again, what are the factors at play here?</p><p>A Crowdstrike update being able to blue-screen Windows Desktops and Servers.</p><p>Whilst Crowdstrike are going to cop a potentially existential-threatening amount of blame, an application shouldn't be able to do this kind of damage to an operating system. This makes me think that, maybe, Crowdstrike were unlucky enough to have accidentally discovered a bug that affects multiple versions of Windows (ie. it's a Windows bug, maybe more-so than it is a Crowdstrike bug).</p><p>There also seems to have been a ball-dropped in regards to auto-updating all the things. Yes, gotta keep your infrastructure up to date to prevent security incidents, but is this done in test environments before it's put into production?</p><p>Un-audited dependence on an increasingly long chain of third-parties.</p><p>All the answers are difficult, time consuming, and therefore expensive, and are only useful in times like now. And if everyone else is down, then there's safety in the crowd. Just point at "them too", and stay the path. This isn't a profitable differentiation. But it should be! (raised fists towards the sky).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002499"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002499" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002499&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Whilst Crowdstrike are going to cop a potentially existential-threatening amount of blame, an application shouldn't be able to do this kind of damage to an operating system.</p><p>It doesn't operate in user space, they install a kernel driver.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002604"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002703"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002762"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002762" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002762&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>There's a grey area between "kernel drivers are required for crowdstrike" and "windows is not modular enough to expose necessary functionality to userspace". It could be solved differently given enough motivation.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002771"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002771" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002771&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Are they? Apple has pretty much banned kernel drivers (kexts) in macOS on Apple Silicon. When they were still used, they were a common cause of crashes and instability, not to mention potential gaping security holes.</p><p>Most things that third-party kernel drivers used to do (device drivers, file systems, etc) are now done just as well, and much more safely, in userspace. I'm surprised if Microsoft isn't heading in this direction too?</p><p>Presumably, Crowdstrike runs on macOS <i>without</i> a kernel extension?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41002516"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002516" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002516&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>At the end of the day, if you give an application a deep set of permissions, that's on you as an administrator, not the OS. This unchecked global rollout appears to just be a violation of every good software engineering practice we know.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002809"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002809" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002809&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Administrators are to blame because management (and a lot of 'cybersecurity policies') demand there's a virus scanner on the machines?</p><p>While virus scanners might pick up some threats not addressed by OS updates yet every one of them I've seen is a rootkit in disguise wanting full system privileges. There are numerous incidents with security holes and crashes caused by these security products. They also aren't that clever: repeatedly scanning the same files 'on access' over and over again wasting CPU and IO is not going to give you any extra security.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002585"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002585" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002585&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; This unchecked global rollout appears to just be a violation of every good software engineering practice we know.</p><p>Yeah, this is what surprises me. Corporate infrastructure policy seems to have been matched to smart phone default settings.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002447"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002447" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002447&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; an application shouldn't be able to do this kind of damage to an operating system</p><p>Antivirus software by its nature probably needs the kind of access that would let it bluescreen your computer.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002629"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002629" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002629&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This is not the case. There are many possible AV architectures, with or without kernel drivers and/or administrator level permissions.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002518"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002518" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002518&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Wading out my depth here, so forgive any stupidity following.</p><p>And there's a certain amount of sense to that, it has to get "under" the layer that viruses can typically get to, but I still think there should be another layer at which the OS is protected from misbehaving anti-virus software (which has been known to happen).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002547"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002575"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002670"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002670" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002670&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The problem I have with this is that anti-virus software has never felt like the most reliable, well-written, trustworthy software that's deserving of it's place in Ring 0.</p><p>I understand I'm yelling into the storm here, because anti-virus also requires that level of system access due to the nature of what it's trying to detect. But then again, does it only need Ring 0 access for the worst of the worst? Can it run 99% of the time in Ring 1, or user space, and only instantiate it's Ring 0 privileges for regular but infrequent scans or if it detects something else may be 'off'?</p><p>Default Ring 0?  Earn it.</p><p>This turns into a "what's your threat level" discussion.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41002864"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002864" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002864&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>My experience working with Crowdstrike was that they were super arrogant about these risks. I was working on a ~50k enterprise rollout, and our CS guy was super belligerent about how long we were taking to do it, how much testing we wanted to do, the way that we were staggering roll outs and managing rollback plans. He didn’t think any of this was necessary, that we should roll it out in one fell swoop, have everything to auto-update all the time, and constantly yapped about how many bigger enterprises than ours completed their rollouts in just a couple of weeks.</p><p>He actually threatened to fire us as a client because he claimed he didn’t want the CS brand associated with an org that was “fully protected” by CS. By far the worst vendor contact I’ve ever had. I’ve had nicer meetings with Oracle lawyers than I was having with this guy. I hope this sort of thing humbles them a little.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002718"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002854"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002854" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002854&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>maybe they installed crowdstrike because they wanted updated without testing. and crowdstrike failed at testing them in their environment.</p><p>sounds like they didnt test all cases and stumbled on a windows bug</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002878"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002878" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002878&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>OTA update went wrong? How can an update go live without proper testing for the millions of live connected endpoints?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002199"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002776"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002776" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002776&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Right after you enter the bit locker recovery key.</p><p>You do have your bit locker recovery key, right? .....right?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002246"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002264"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002264" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002264&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Someone posted this in the thread, but I also can't log in to verify</p><p>&gt; Summary</p><p>&gt; CrowdStrike is aware of reports of crashes on Windows hosts related to the Falcon Sensor.</p><p>&gt; Details</p><p>&gt; Symptoms include hosts experiencing a bugcheck\blue screen error related to the Falcon Sensor.</p><p>&gt; Current Action</p><p>&gt; Our Engineering teams are actively working to resolve this issue and there is no need to open a support ticket.</p><p>&gt; Status updates will be posted below as we have more information to share, including when the issue is resolved.</p><p>&gt; Latest Updates</p><p>&gt; 2024-07-19 05:30 AM UTC | Tech Alert Published.</p><p>&gt; Support</p><p>&gt; Find answers and contact Support with our Support Portal</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41002552"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002698"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002645"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002645" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002645&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Crowdstrike must have some slick salespeople in New Zealand. Seems like nearly everyone uses it. Single point of failure problem.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002748"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002748" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002748&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>CIO here. They are known to be incredibly pushy. In my company we RFP'd for our endpoint &amp; cyber security. Found the CS salesperson went over me to approach our CEO who is completely non-technical to try and seal a contract because I was on leave for 1 week out of service (and this was known to them). When I found out by our CEO informing me of the approach we were happy to sign with SentinelOne</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002855"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002855" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002855&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>One thing I'm really happy about at my current company is that when a sales person from a vendor (not Crowdstrike) tried that our CEO absolutely ripped them a new one and basically banned that company from being a vendor for a decade.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002840"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41002705"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002845"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002845" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002845&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>You mean you think the update was timed and waves will hit every hour for the next nearly 24h, or it’s just 3AM in NYC right now and under the radar?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002605"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002808"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002808" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002808&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I just landed at SeaTac an hour ago and the rideshare/app pickup was absolutely nutso. Like thousands of people standing around waiting for taxis and Ubers. The one person I asked what was going on said that the computer systems at all the regional hotels are down (not sure how that makes more people need cabs). Wonder if it’s from this</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002463"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002463" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002463&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>My entire emergency department got knocked offline by this. Really scary when you have ambulances coming in and are trying to stabilize a heart attack.</p><p>Update: 911 is down in Oregon too, no more ambulances at least.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002707"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002707" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002707&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>But at least the best instant messaging app in the world Microsoft Teams and the best web browser in the world Microsoft Edge are working fine, right?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002735"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41002593"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002853"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002853" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002853&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Disrespect to every CIO to make their business depend on a single operating system, running automatic updates of system software without any canaries and phased deployments.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002796"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002395"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002395" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002395&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Quick fix that worked for us,
In safe mode:</p><p>1.enter in drive C:
2.system 32 folder
3. Drivers
4. Rename crowdstrike folder to something else doesent matter what.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002852"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002852" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002852&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Use stupid snakeoil, win stupid prizes.</p><p>Maybe the world can finally reconsider their use of dumb software products that cater only to security theater and that fuzzy, warm feeling of "protection". And the politics in companies which lead to things like this being introduced ("nobody gets fired for buying IBM").</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002279"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002652"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002368"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002368" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002368&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Australian news reporting this has hit hospitals, fire and rescue, banking, media, airlines and many other companies worldwide.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002600"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002639"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002829"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002829" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002829&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Go to advance repair option then advanced open cmd. Go to windows/system32/drivers/crowdstrike.   Then list all the file and delete file name having 291 at the end using cmd "del filenameendingwith291"</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002638"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002225"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002225" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002225&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Our company is in panic mode. 15 machines blue screened for no apparent reason and stuck in boot loop. I’m a gloating Linux user :)</p><p>Also in Australia</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002587"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002778"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002835"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002420"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002420" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002420&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This is effecting our company. A colleague visited her local supermarket (Woolworths) and all the self-service checkouts were effected.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002738"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002399"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002399" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002399&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Was just using the energy vic website and thought I'd been rate limited when their API stopped working. Seems like it could be this.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002337"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002337" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002337&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>We have ~50 thousand laptops in reboot loop and ~1.5k servers as well. No resolution yet.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                      <tr id="41002529"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002268"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002268" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002268&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>According to Reddit It's hitting Croatia, Philippines, US, Germany, Mexico, India, Japan. SAP servers dropping like flies, that's Defence,Banks, Payroll all affected. Major Retail Chains like Big W down.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002534"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002534" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002534&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>We have outages across whole APAC and most EMEA. Despite being a very big client of CS, we do not have an official resolution yet, an hour into the incident.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002745"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002449"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002449" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002449&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>c:\system32\drivers\csagent.sys renaming this file on server with safe mode boot fixes the issue but disables agent</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002619"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002619" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002619&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Official CrowdStrike workarround:
1. Boot Windows into Safe Mode or the Windows Recovery Environment
2. Navigate to the C:\Windows\System32\drivers\CrowdStrike directory
3. Locate the file matching “C-00000291*.sys”, and delete it. 
4. Boot the host normally.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002761"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002761" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002761&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Fix: Boot Windows into Safe Mode or the Windows Recovery Environment Navigate to the C:\Windows\System32\drivers\CrowdStrike directory Locate the file matching “C-00000291*.sys”, and delete it. Boot the host normally</p><p>Did it work for you?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002415"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002445"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002445" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002445&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I'd guess that it's related. Azure, OneDrive, and Office 365 were having issues this morning Australian time (about 6 hours ago).</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002473"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002473" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002473&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>If that’s the case I wonder why we’re only now seeing everyone’s systems BSODing. Should be an interesting write up (if they release one)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002470"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41002310"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002310" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002310&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Husband is a deputy in California. His department and many others here are down as well (including PDs, jails, ambulance companies, etc.)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002366"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002482"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002482" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002482&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Aren't they doing canary release? Seems weird this would not have been detected on a smaller scale before with a good release process.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002521"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002521" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002521&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Canary releases aren't a magical bug free fix. They might be doing it, but the conditions that trigger a problem can be sneaky and can happen outside your canary period, rendering it useless. It's a best effort method.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002633"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002633" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002633&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>It depends on how global the issue is.</p><p>But yeah I've seen US companies for example only doing their initial releases in the USA only which has zero value for issues that might appear with different localization/language settings for example.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41002654"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002817"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002504"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002520"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002520" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002520&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>what we do is safemode the PC and then open the run CMD as admin. then issue this command. sc delete csagent. reinstall crowdstrike using previous version.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002686"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002686" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002686&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Not gonna be awesome for an org that has 20,000 laptops out there at home with users who don't have admin...</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002525"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002530"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41002657"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002657" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002657&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>HP laptops are booting and its looping</p><p>DELL laptops are observed, after blue dump . Server is up and running fine</p><p>Temporary workaround leads compliance issue.</p><p>From India</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002296"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002296" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002296&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I assume you have to install "CrowdStrike" yourself (i.e. not bundled with Windows by default)? I have no idea what it is before.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002303"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002198"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002259"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002508"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002508" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002508&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Uninstall the Current Version:</p><p>Open the Command Prompt as an administrator.
Run the following command to uninstall the current version:
shell</p><p>sc delete csagent</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002591"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002305"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002459"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002459" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002459&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Do this at your own risk!!
Apparently there are two NON-OFFICIAL solutions:</p><p>1. Rename csagent.sys ( the file causing the BSOD )
2. Rename c:\windows\System32\Drivers\Crowdstrike</p><p>Again, do this at your own risk.
Both workaround have been reported as "working".
I am Linux user so I cannot tell.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002428"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002428" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002428&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>we will found a troubleshooting , we start in revovery mode and rename the path
C:\windows\system32\drivers\Crowdstrike</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002375"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002375" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002375&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>A system restore helps. But obviously not when you’ve got an environment of ~500 or more clients</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002374"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002576"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002576" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002576&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>We had a few machines come out of the boot loop - only to re-enter it 20 mins later. I am sure CS pulled the patch from their CDNs but ...maybe some cached versions still linger?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002644"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41002689"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41002689" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41002689&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41002195"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Flippant commentary:</p><p>Thank fuck Netflix runs on Linux. I just hope the full chain from my TV to Netflix is immune...</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41002789"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41002427"><td></td></tr>
            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Multiple airlines disrupted due to Microsoft Azure outage (352 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/18/us/frontier-flights-grounded-microsoft.html</link>
            <guid>41001959</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 04:09:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/18/us/frontier-flights-grounded-microsoft.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/18/us/frontier-flights-grounded-microsoft.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41001959">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/18/us/frontier-flights-grounded-microsoft.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Double trouble: ESA's Gaia hit by micrometeoroid and solar storm (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Operations/Double_trouble_Gaia_hit_by_micrometeoroid_and_solar_storm</link>
            <guid>40999928</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 21:27:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Operations/Double_trouble_Gaia_hit_by_micrometeoroid_and_solar_storm">https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Operations/Double_trouble_Gaia_hit_by_micrometeoroid_and_solar_storm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40999928">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<header>
	<span>Enabling &amp; Support</span>
	
	<p><span>17/07/2024</span>
				<span><span id="viewcount">11950</span><small> views</small></span>
										<span><span id="ezsr_total_26232852">101</span><small> likes</small></span>
				
	</p>
</header>





<div>
	<p>Launched in December 2013, <a href="https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/Gaia">ESA’s Gaia</a> spacecraft is on a mission to map the locations and motions of more than a billion stars&nbsp;in the Milky Way with extreme precision.</p><p>But it’s not easy being a satellite: space is a dangerous place. In recent months, hyper-velocity space dust and the strongest solar storm in 20 years have threatened Gaia’s ability to carry out the precise measurements for which it is famous.</p>
</div>


			
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2018/06/Things_that_go_bump_in_the_night">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2018/06/things_that_go_bump_in_the_night/17571526-1-eng-GB/Things_that_go_bump_in_the_night_article.png" alt="Space rocks infographic: things that go bump in the night">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2018/06/Things_that_go_bump_in_the_night">Space rocks infographic: things that go bump in the night</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>In April, a tiny particle smaller than a grain of sand struck Gaia at high speed. Known as a micrometeoroid, millions of these particles burn up in Earth’s atmosphere every day.</p><p>But Gaia is located 1.5 million km from Earth at the second Sun-Earth <a href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Operations/What_are_Lagrange_points#:~:text=is%20positioned%20there.-,L2,-Spacecraft%20on%20L2" target="_blank">Lagrange point</a> (L2). Out here, far from our planet’s protective atmosphere, Gaia is often struck by particles like this. Impacts are expected, and the spacecraft was designed to withstand them.</p><p>This object, however, struck Gaia at a very high speed and at just the wrong angle, damaging the spacecraft’s protective cover.</p><p>The impact created a little gap that allowed stray sunlight – around one billionth of the intensity of direct sunlight felt on Earth – to occasionally disrupt Gaia’s very sensitive sensors.</p><p>Gaia’s engineers were in the middle of dealing with this issue when they were faced with another problem.</p><p>The spacecraft’s&nbsp;‘billion-pixel camera’ relies on a series of 106 charge coupled devices (CCDs) – sensors that convert light into electrical signals.</p><p>In May, the electronics controlling one of these CCDs failed – Gaia’s first CCD issue&nbsp;in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2023/12/Gaia_s_10th_anniversary" target="_blank">more than 10 years in space</a>. Each sensor has a different role, and the affected sensor was vital for Gaia’s ability to confirm the detection of stars.&nbsp;Without this sensor to validate its observations, Gaia began to register thousands of false detections.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																								



							
				
								
						
								
													
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/05/Aurora_near_Frankfurt_Germany_May_2024">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/05/aurora_near_frankfurt_germany_may_2024/26083815-1-eng-GB/Aurora_near_Frankfurt_Germany_May_2024_article.jpg" alt="Aurora near Frankfurt, Germany, May 2024">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/05/Aurora_near_Frankfurt_Germany_May_2024">Aurora near Frankfurt, Germany, May 2024</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>The root cause for the electronics failure is not entirely clear. Gaia was designed to spend up to six years in space but has now survived almost twice as long under harsh conditions.</p><p>Around the time of failure, Gaia was hit by the same <a href="https://www.esa.int/Space_Safety/Space_weather/The_May_2024_solar_storm_your_questions_answered" target="_blank">violent burst of energetic particles from the Sun</a> that triggered spectacular auroral lightshows around the world.</p><p>The spacecraft was built to withstand radiation, but during the current period of high solar activity, it is being pushed to its limits.</p><p>It is possible that the storm was the final straw for this piece of the spacecraft’s aging hardware.</p>	</div>	
    
						
			<p>The Gaia teams at ESA’s <a href="https://www.esa.int/About_Us/ESOC/Where_missions_come_alive" target="_blank">ESOC</a> operations centre, <a href="https://www.esa.int/About_Us/ESTEC/European_Space_Research_and_Technology_Centre_ESTEC2" target="_blank">ESTEC</a> technology centre and <a href="https://www.esa.int/About_Us/ESAC/Overview2" target="_blank">ESAC</a> astronomy centre, together with experts from the spacecraft’s manufacturer, <a href="https://www.airbus.com/en/space" target="_blank">Airbus Defence and Space</a>, and the payload experts of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cosmos.esa.int/web/gaia/dpac" target="_blank">Data Processing and Analysis Consortium</a>, have worked together closely over the past few months to investigate, analyse and, ultimately, solve these problems.</p>	
    
							
														
										



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/06/ESA_s_Malarguee_tracking_station_at_sunrise">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/06/esa_s_malarguee_tracking_station_at_sunrise/26189914-1-eng-GB/ESA_s_Malarguee_tracking_station_at_sunrise_article.jpg" alt="Gaia downlinks data to Earth via the deep space communication antennas in ESA's Estrack network">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/06/ESA_s_Malarguee_tracking_station_at_sunrise">Gaia downlinks data to Earth via the deep space communication antennas in ESA's Estrack network</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>“Gaia typically sends over 25 gigabytes of data&nbsp;to Earth every day, but this amount would be much, much higher if the spacecraft’s onboard software didn’t eliminate false star detections first."</p><p>"Both recent incidents disrupted this process. As a result, the spacecraft began generating a huge number of false detections that overwhelmed our systems,” explains Edmund Serpell, Gaia spacecraft operations engineer at ESOC.</p>	</div>	
    
						
			<p>“We cannot physically repair the spacecraft <a href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Operations/What_are_Lagrange_points#:~:text=is%20positioned%20there.-,L2,-Spacecraft%20on%20L2" target="_blank">from 1.5 million km away</a>.&nbsp;However, by carefully modifying the threshold at which Gaia’s software identifies a faint point of light as a star, we have been able to dramatically reduce the number of false detections generated by both the straylight and CCD issues.”</p>	
    
						
			<div>
				<p>Thanks to the hard work and efficient collaboration of all the teams involved, Gaia was recently returned to routine operations.&nbsp;</p><p>In fact, the engineers took the opportunity of this unscheduled disturbance to refocus the optics of Gaia’s twin telescopes for the final time. As a result, Gaia is now producing some of the best quality data that it ever has.</p>	</div>	
    
						
    
						
    
					



</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[60-year-old German man likely seventh person to be effectively cured from HIV (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.rfi.fr/en/international-news/20240718-seventh-person-likely-cured-of-hiv-doctors-announce</link>
            <guid>40999098</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 19:54:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.rfi.fr/en/international-news/20240718-seventh-person-likely-cured-of-hiv-doctors-announce">https://www.rfi.fr/en/international-news/20240718-seventh-person-likely-cured-of-hiv-doctors-announce</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40999098">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
            <span>Paris (AFP) – </span>            A 60-year-old German man is likely the seventh person to be effectively cured from HIV after receiving a stem cell transplant, doctors announced on Thursday.        </p><div>
                <p><span>Issued on: <time datetime="2024-07-18T14:38:12+0000" pubdate="pubdate">18/07/2024 - 16:38</time></span><span>Modified: <time datetime="2024-07-18T14:36:41+0000">18/07/2024 - 16:36</time></span></p>

    <p><span title="Reading time"></span> 2 min</p>
            </div><div>
            
            <p>The painful and risky procedure is for people who have both HIV and aggressive leukaemia, so is not an option for almost all of the nearly 40 million people living with the deadly virus across the world.</p><p>The German man, whose wished to remain anonymous, was dubbed the "next Berlin patient".</p><p>The original Berlin patient, Timothy Ray Brown, was the first person declared cured of HIV back in 2008. Brown died from cancer in 2020.</p><p>The second man from Berlin to achieve long-term HIV remission was announced ahead of the 25th International AIDS Conference being held in the German city of Munich next week.</p><p>He was first diagnosed with HIV in 2009, according to the research abstract being presented at the conference.</p><p>The man received a bone marrow transplant for his leukaemia in 2015. The procedure, which has a 10 percent risk of death, essentially replaces a person's immune system.</p><p>Then he stopped taking anti-retroviral drugs -- which reduce the amount of HIV in the blood -- in late 2018.</p><p>Nearly six years later, he appears to be both HIV and cancer free, the medical researchers said.</p><p>Christian Gaebler, a doctor-researcher at Berlin's Charite university hospital treating the patient, told AFP that the team cannot be "absolutely certain" every last trace of HIV has been eradicated.</p><p>But "the patient's case is highly suggestive of an HIV cure," Gaebler added. "He feels well and is enthusiastic about contributing to our research efforts."</p><h2>'Promising' for wider cure</h2><p>International AIDS Society President Sharon Lewin said researchers hesitate to use the word "cure" because it is not clear how long they need to follow up such cases.</p><p>But more than five years in remission means the man "would be close" to being considered cured, she told a press conference.</p><p>There is an important difference between the man's case and the other HIV patients who have reached long-term remission, she said.</p><p>All but one of the other patients received stem cells from donors with a rare mutation in which part of their CCR5 gene was missing, blocking HIV from entering their body's cells.</p><p>Those donors had inherited two copies of the mutated CCR5 gene -- one from each parent -- making them "essentially immune" to HIV, Lewin said.</p><p>But the new Berlin patient is the first to have received stem cells from a donor who had inherited only one copy of the mutated gene.</p><p>Around 15 percent of people from European origin have one mutated copy, compared to one percent for both. </p><p>Researchers hope the latest success means there will be a much larger potential donor pool in the future.</p><p>The new case is also "promising" for the wider search for an HIV cure that works for all patients, Lewin said.</p><p>This is "because it suggests that you don't actually have to get rid of every single piece of CCR5 for gene therapy to work," she added.</p><p>The Geneva patient, whose case was announced at last year's AIDS conference, is the other exception among the seven. He received a transplant from a donor without any CCR5 mutations -- yet still achieved long-term remission.</p><p>This showed that the effectiveness of the procedure was not just down to the CCR5 gene, Lewin said.</p>
            <p>© 2024 AFP</p>        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What would it take to recreate Bell Labs? (283 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell</link>
            <guid>40998927</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 19:28:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell">https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40998927">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg" width="1456" height="874" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:874,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;kumar patel CO2 laser cutting&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="kumar patel CO2 laser cutting" title="kumar patel CO2 laser cutting" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9c7ee937-36ec-45b6-9100-da60a38984ed_1600x960.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>For most of the 20th century, AT&amp;T was almost entirely responsible for building and operating America’s telephone infrastructure. It manufactured the phones and electrical equipment, laid hundreds of millions of miles of wire across the country, and built and operated the switchboards and exchanges that made it possible for anyone with a phone to call anyone else.</p><p>This huge network required billions of dollars worth of equipment: telephones, switches, cables, amplifiers, repeaters, and so on. All this equipment was built by AT&amp;T’s manufacturing subsidiary, Western Electric. But it was designed and developed by AT&amp;T’s research arm, Bell Telephone Laboratories, better known as Bell Labs.</p><p>To students of technological progress, Bell Labs is a giant. For decades, Bell Labs was considered not only the best industrial research lab in the world, but arguably the best research lab in the world, period. One Bell Lab alumnus described it as “a parallel organization to almost all the academic institutions put together.” Bell Labs not only developed new telephone equipment but performed novel scientific research, under the assumption that such research would ultimately result in improved communications technology.</p><p><span>Bell Labs is most famous for being the birthplace of the transistor, but that’s just one of dozens of major inventions and discoveries that originated there. Bell Labs also spawned: the silicon solar PV cell, the first active and passive communications satellites, the first videophone, the first cellular telephone system, the first fiber optic telephone cable, the quartz clock, Information Theory, Statistical Process Control, the UNIX computer operating system, and the discovery of Cosmic Microwave Background radiation. Many of Bell Labs' less famous inventions were among its most important: the discovery of compounds that could protect polyethylene from decomposing in sunlight isn’t typically mentioned on lists of Bell Labs’ most impressive achievements, but the patents for them were the most valuable that AT&amp;T ever produced. Among Bell Labs’ awards are 10 Nobel Prizes, 5 Turing Awards (the highest honor in computing), and 5 Draper Prizes (the highest honor in engineering).</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-1-146749385" href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell#footnote-1-146749385" target="_self" rel="">1</a></span><span> 36 Bell Labs staff members have been inducted into the Inventors Hall of Fame (though not all for work they did at Bell Labs).</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png" width="609" height="591" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:591,&quot;width&quot;:609,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe4eb913f-a1c0-4816-a936-17b8251004ae_609x591.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Bell Labs still exists today, as a subsidiary of Nokia, but outside the name it has little relationship to the industrial research powerhouse of the 20th century. Following the breakup of AT&amp;T, Bell Labs was gradually carved apart through constant mergers and spinoffs to different organizations, and it has never achieved the heights it did in the 1950s through the 1980s.</p><p><span>Unsurprisingly, there’s perennial interest in recreating a Bell Labs-style research lab that steadily churns out world-changing inventions and discoveries. In a recent newsletter post, Noah Smith argues that we need an “</span><a href="https://www.noahpinion.blog/p/energy-bell-the-sketch-of-an-idea" rel="">energy Bell Labs</a><span>” that can push U.S. energy technology forward, and he’s far from the only one to dream of recreating a Bell Labs-style organization. The </span><a href="https://pubs.aip.org/physicstoday/article/71/10/10/947998/Commentary-Let-s-re-create-Bell-Labs" rel="">idea</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s42254-022-00426-6" rel="">pops up</a><span> </span><a href="https://x.com/rrana03_/status/1353042869930569729" rel="">repeatedly</a><span>.</span></p><p>Unfortunately, the conditions that made Bell Labs so successful were highly historically contingent and not the sort of thing that could be deliberately recreated. Being a subsidiary of a government-sanctioned, vertically integrated monopoly gave Bell Labs a broad research scope and freedom to pursue long-term research projects unavailable to most other industrial labs. Prior discoveries in quantum mechanics provided a wealth of new phenomena that Bell Labs could harvest for new technology, and WWII both pushed technology forward across the board and turned Bell Labs into an organization poised to capitalize on it. In the end, Bell Labs was ultimately undermined by the very technologies that it had created. The world that Bell Labs thrived in no longer exists: to push technological progress forward, we'll need to understand both why Bell Labs worked and why it no longer could.</p><p>For the first several decades of its existence, AT&amp;T’s scientific and inventing efforts were modest. Though new technology was needed to improve and expand the Bell System, AT&amp;T largely relied on acquiring outside patents and inventions and adapting them to its particular needs. In 1892, Hammond Hayes, the head of the Mechanical Department (which designed and tested new equipment) wrote that he had decided to abandon any “theoretical” efforts, and would focus the department on the “practical developments of instruments and apparatus." Any “theoretical” needs could be obtained by collaborating with students at MIT or Harvard. In 1906, Hayes noted that “every effort in the Department is being executed toward perfecting the engineering methods; no one is employed who as an inventor is capable of originating new apparatus of novel design.”</p><p>But starting in 1907, this technological stance began to shift. AT&amp;T’s financial position had deteriorated as it battled with the thousands of independent phone companies that sprang up after its key patents expired. Between 1902 and 1907, AT&amp;T’s debt tripled, and its stock price fell by more than 50%; it could no longer sell the bonds it needed to finance its expansion.</p><p><span>In response to AT&amp;T’s dire financial straits, the company was taken over by a JP Morgan-led group of bankers, who installed Theodore Vail as president. Vail had been the first general manager of AT&amp;T in 1878, and had shepherded it through its early difficulties with expansion and patent battles, but had left the company in 1887 due to disputes with its ownership.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-2-146749385" href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell#footnote-2-146749385" target="_self" rel="">2</a></span><span> Vail had previously worked at the U.S. Post Office and had absorbed its public service ethos. He believed AT&amp;T should operate with an eye towards the long term, and that it should constantly expand and improve its system with new technology. In fact, Vail had initiated the research project for the first buried telephone cable, to address the problems caused by huge masses of overhead wires. The company’s owners, on the other hand, were far more interested in operating as profitably as possible, and wished to avoid unnecessary capital expenditures, technical improvements, or risky research and development endeavors. Unable to resolve this disagreement, Vail left the company in 1887. But when Vail returned to AT&amp;T in 1907, he was given a nearly free hand to shape its operations as he saw fit.</span></p><p>Vail desired to bring the entire telephone industry under the control of AT&amp;T. His articulated (and likely seriously held) reasons were that the telephone system was a natural monopoly, and that the public interest would be best served by a single, government-regulated company, captured by the oft-repeated motto “one system, one policy, universal service." Vail came to believe that universal service — connecting all telephones into a single network — required not only the steady hand of a single company ensuring each component worked reliably and seamlessly, but also constantly improving technology to overcome distance and the exponential increase in complexity caused by more phones connecting to the network. While prior to his arrival, AT&amp;T had largely eschewed invention or theoretical research, by 1910 Vail could boast that AT&amp;T had “extensive laboratories and experimental departments," and that it was generating its own fundamental innovations.</p><p>The first major success of Vail’s technology-focused strategy was solving the problem of transcontinental transmission. When Vail ascended to the presidency, a telephone signal could travel a maximum distance of roughly 1,800 miles; enough to connect New York to Denver, but no farther. The farther telephone signals were sent, the more they attenuated; without some sort of signal amplifier, connecting phones on the east and west coasts (and Vail’s dream of universal service) would be impossible.</p><p>To tackle this problem, AT&amp;T’s John Carty (who had replaced Hayes as head of all AT&amp;T research) and researcher Frank Jewett began a project to develop a telephone signal repeater in 1909. Over the following year, they investigated several potential methods of amplification, including magnetic and mechanical means. But when none of these proved suitable, Carty and Jewett changed strategies. Jewett, who had a PhD in physics from the University of Chicago, was familiar with physics research on the behavior of (recently discovered) electrons, and thought that such research might offer a path forward to creating a successful amplifier. Carty and Jewett hired physicist Harold Arnold in 1911, who began investigating electronic means of amplification.</p><p><span>Arnold’s initial studies on a potential device, the </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mercury-arc_valve" rel="">mercury vapor tube</a><span>, proved fruitless, but in 1912 he was impressed by a demonstration of the audion, invented by Lee de Forest, which was capable of amplifying an electric signal. De Forest, like Edison, was at heart a tinkerer, and it soon became clear that he didn’t quite understand how his invention worked. But it nevertheless seemed promising, and Arnold spent the next several years building a research team to study its behavior and turn it into an effective telephone amplifier. By 1915, 45 people were working in AT&amp;T’s research division, including 7 PhDs. That year, the first New York-San Francisco telephone line opened, powered by the new vacuum-tube-based telephone amplifier. For the first time, it appeared possible to achieve Vail’s goal of a universal telephone system. Science-based technological development had paved the way.</span></p><p><span>Bell Labs wasn’t technically formed until 1925, when AT&amp;T was reorganized and several different research and engineering organizations were combined under a single roof. But by then Vail’s values — constant improvement of telephone service through science-based technological developments — had been woven deep into the fabric of the company. The year Bell Labs formed, researcher Clinton Davisson </span><a href="https://www.bell-labs.com/about/awards/1937-nobel-prize-physics/" rel="">began the experiments</a><span> that would win Bell Labs its first Nobel Prize. While Vail retired in 1919 and died the following year, he made sure to leave the company in the hands of leadership that believed in his credo of universal service, and that constant innovation was the path to get there. Vail conceived of the telephone network as “an ever-living organism” which required “unceasing effort, continually improving and upbuilding." Thanks to Vail’s efforts, it became an article of faith within AT&amp;T that technical innovation would always be needed, and would be valuable even if it took many years to bear fruit.</span></p><p>In its efforts to constantly improve telephone service, Bell Labs would pursue a wide range of scientific investigations; its research division had departments ranging from physics and chemistry to metallurgy, mathematics, and even physiology and psychology. Though its mandate was to improve communications technology, there were innumerable possible ways that might be achieved. Invention, noted Harold Arnold, “is not to be scheduled or coerced” - who knew what fields of science might yield important, practical developments?</p><p><span>But despite its unusual willingness to engage in fundamental scientific research, Bell Labs was still an industrial research lab at heart, tasked with developing products and technology for its parent company. While it took an expansive view of this mandate, investigating anything related to the field of communications and taking on long-term projects with uncertain payoffs, its focus was nevertheless on new technology of practical use to the Bell System. Eric Gilliam, in his </span><a href="https://www.freaktakes.com/p/how-did-places-like-bell-labs-know" rel="">essay on Bell Labs’ research culture</a><span>, describes this as a “long leash but a narrow fence” — researchers had the freedom to pursue a variety of avenues that might be valuable to the Bell System, but there were mechanisms in place (such as an army of system engineers who kept abreast of both scientific developments and practical needs of the telephone system) to nudge them towards the most promising problems.</span></p><p><span>And while its scientific investigations and groundbreaking inventions — that is, its research — made Bell Labs famous, research was always a comparatively small part of Bell Labs’ efforts. Depending on the period, researchers made up only around 10-20% of Bell Labs’ headcount. The vast majority of efforts were always focused on the less glamorous but important work of product development: taking inventions and discoveries and turning them into manufacturable products, testing materials and components to make sure they functioned properly, and gradually improving AT&amp;T’s telephone equipment and infrastructure. In his </span><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/0143122797?k=the%20idea%20factory&amp;ref_=nb_sb_ss_w_scx-ent-pd-bk-d_l_k0_1_16&amp;crid=YOIHCH6VBW0I&amp;sprefix=the%20idea%20factory" rel="">history of Bell labs</a><span>, Jon Gertner describes this sort of work:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>Some men at West Street specialized in experimenting on springs for switchboard keys, others in improving the metal within the springs. AT&amp;T linemen bet with their lives on the integrity of the leather harnesses that kept them tethered at great heights – so Labs technicians established strength and standards for the two-inch leather belts…and improving the metal rivets and parts. Millions of soldered joints held the system together – so Labs engineers had to spend years investigating which fluxes and compounds were best for reinforcing anything from seams on sheet metal to lead joints to copper wires to brass casings… A Bell Labs engineer named Donald Quarles…wrote a long treatise entitled “Motion of Telephone Wires in the Wind.” His men made rigorous, multiyear tests on the proper spans (how far should the poles be spaced apart?), proper lashing (how tight should the wires be wired together?), proper vertical spacing between horizontal strings of wires… Many of the system’s most important cables, meanwhile, were not strung through the air but ran underground. For burying wire, the men in Chester had to develop new processes involving special tractors they invented and splicing techniques.</em></p></blockquote><p>But despite the relatively small proportion of research and invention work in Bell Labs, it was nevertheless crucial. Only by constantly pushing the boundaries of technology forward could AT&amp;T accommodate the relentless growth of the company and demand for service. By 1939 AT&amp;T controlled 83% of all U.S. telephones, 98% of long-distance wires, and 100% of intercontinental radio telephone links. To meet demand, AT&amp;T was adding 2 million miles of telephone wire each year. Bell Labs inventions like the negative feedback amplifier, the coaxial cable, and the crossbar switch made handling this growth possible.</p><p><span>Because its investigations were so wide-ranging, Bell Labs often found itself inventing technology outside of its telecommunications purview.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-3-146749385" href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell#footnote-3-146749385" target="_self" rel="">3</a></span><span> Bell Labs created the first motion picture with synchronized sound (ie: “talkies”), and the first demonstration of color TV. For a time, AT&amp;T tried to license these non-telephone inventions under a subsidiary, Electrical Research Products Incorporated (ERPI), but it faced constant criticism that it was using its monopoly power to muscle into other industries. AT&amp;T eventually spun off ERPI in 1935 (the company still exists today as </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Altec_Lansing" rel="">Altec Lansing</a><span>), and adopted generous licensing terms for its patents. AT&amp;T was so large that it existed right at the edge of what the government would allow to exist, and this tension of capitalizing on its inventions while avoiding antitrust efforts would plague the company throughout its life.</span></p><p>Though it had many successes in the first 25 years of its life, the crowning achievement of Bell Labs research (and its strategy of leveraging early-stage scientific research to create new products) is undoubtedly its development of the transistor, along with its various derivatives (the MOSFET, the solar PV cell) and associated manufacturing technologies (including crystal pulling, zone melting, and diffusion furnaces). The transistor is a classic case of Bell Labs’ strategy: wide research freedom, circumscribed by the requirement to produce things useful for the Bell System. The telephone network required enormous amounts of vacuum tubes and mechanical relays to act as switches, but these were far from ideal components. Vacuum tubes were delicate, power-hungry, and fragile, and mechanical relays were slow and prone to wearing out. Mervin Kelly, physicist and head of the Bell Labs vacuum tube department in the early 1930s (and later the president of Bell Labs), dreamed of replacing them with solid-state components with no moving parts. Advances in quantum mechanics, and novel materials known as semiconductors, suggested that such components might be possible.&nbsp;</p><p>Bell Labs had studied semiconductors since the early 1930s; Walter Brattain, who would eventually share the Nobel Prize for inventing the transistor, was hired in 1929 and had begun to study an early semiconductor device called the copper oxide rectifier. A Depression hiring freeze stymied more serious semiconductor efforts until 1936, when Mervin Kelly (now Bell Labs’ director of research) was finally able to start building a more robust solid-state physics department and hired physicist William Shockley (the second of the three transistor inventors). While not giving Shockley any specific research tasks (indeed, the entire solid-state group had “unprecedented liberty to follow their own research noses as long as their work dovetailed with general company goals”), Kelly emphasized to Shockley the potential value of a solid-state component to replace tubes and mechanical relays.</p><p>The solid-state physicists continued their research over the next several years, studying the behavior of semiconductors and attempting to create a semiconductor amplifier. This research was interrupted by the war but resumed in 1945, the same year physicist John Bardeen was hired. Bardeen proved to be the catalyst the solid-state group needed, and over the next several years Bardeen, Brattain, and Shockley made progress in understanding semiconductor behavior. In December 1947, they unveiled their semiconductor amplifier: the transistor. By 1950, Western Electric was making 100 transistors a month for use in Bell System equipment. A few years later, in 1954, another Bell Labs solid-state research effort yielded the world’s first silicon solar PV cell.</p><p><span>The invention of the transistor was followed by a series of other inventions that turned it from a laboratory curiosity into a practically useful product: the bipolar junction transistor in 1948 was easier to produce and more reliable than Bardeen and Brattain’s point-contact transistor. Crystal pulling in 1950 and </span><a href="https://www.computerhistory.org/siliconengine/development-of-zone-refining/#:~:text=Chemical%20engineer%20William%20Pfann%20pioneered,and%20allowed%20them%20to%20recrystallize." rel="">zone melting</a><span> techniques in 1951 created the ultrapure silicon required for the silicon transistor, invented in 1954 (the first transistors used germanium). That year, </span><a href="https://www.electrochem.org/dl/interface/fal/fal07/fall07_p30-34.pdf" rel="">diffusion furnaces</a><span> were used to introduce microscopic amounts of impurities to create p-n junctions, and so on.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Bell Labs had a solid reputation for research since Clinton Davisson’s 1937 Nobel Prize, but it was the transistor that cemented its status as the world’s leading industrial research laboratory, and possibly the world’s leading research lab. Bell Labs offered nearly all the freedom of an academic research environment, without the burdens of writing grants or teaching classes. Bell Labs researchers had access to far more technical resources (such as cutting-edge equipment) than their academic counterparts. Its prestige, reputation for excellence, and envious working environment allowed Bell Labs to acquire some of the most talented researchers in the world. Bell Labs Nobel Prize winner Horst Stormer </span><a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/1241381" rel="">noted that</a><span> “Over a very long stretch of time, it was the best place in the world and it attracted — and attracts — the best people.” In his </span><a href="https://quello.msu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2015/08/Memories-Noll.pdf" rel="">short memoir</a><span> about Bell Labs, Michael Noll likewise noted that “it seemed everybody wanted to get a job there”. Of Bell Labs’ 10 Nobel Prizes, 8 came from researchers hired in the ‘50s, ‘60s, and ‘70s following the invention of the transistor.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png" width="1456" height="1121" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/a5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1121,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:536174,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa5ddf83d-4f1f-4bd6-be5d-f53dd9270707_3468x2670.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Bell Labs continued to create important inventions and discoveries right up until the 1982 court-ordered breakup of AT&amp;T. Following the consent decree that required AT&amp;T to divest its local telephone operating companies, there was much concern, inside and outside the company, about what would happen to Bell Labs.</p><p><span>Initially, there was optimism that Bell Labs’ seemingly unique, highly productive research environment might be maintained. In 1983, a year before divestiture, Bell Labs AI researcher Mitchell Marcus stated, “I have a feeling that we are returning to an older spirit at the Laboratories that has been very productive.” Though a portion of Bell Labs was carved off following divestiture to form </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Iconectiv" rel="">Bellcore</a><span>, most of Bell Labs remained intact, and it continued its tradition of world-class research. Indeed, research leading to 5 Nobel prizes occurred after the court mandated the breakup of AT&amp;T.</span></p><p><span>But this optimism proved to be misplaced. Following the divestiture, Bell Labs was repeatedly passed from organization to organization and split into smaller parts. After the 1983 split that created Bellcore, Bell Labs remained part of AT&amp;T until 1996, when Western Electric was spun off to create Lucent Technologies. Bell Labs was split again, with most of the organization (and the name) going to Lucent, and a portion staying with AT&amp;T. Lucent, in turn, would later spin off two smaller companies (Avaya and Agere) which each took a portion of Bell Labs researchers. Lucent was then later acquired by Alcatel, shifting ownership of the labs yet again. In 2015, Nokia acquired Alcatel-Lucent, where Bell Labs continues to exist today as “</span><a href="https://www.bell-labs.com/" rel="">Nokia Bell Labs</a><span>."&nbsp;</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png" width="674" height="754" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/eccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:754,&quot;width&quot;:674,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:55671,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feccb222f-04db-45f6-91da-541904a56dd0_674x754.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>In addition to this organizational whiplash, Bell Labs gradually found itself under more financial pressure. Bell Labs was reorganized along business lines, with separate departments focused on specific customer and product types. Some research areas, such as economics and social psychology, were cut, and the remaining research areas found themselves increasingly pressured to focus on the immediate needs of the business. In the face of these changes, talented employees began to leave for academia or Silicon Valley.</p><p><span>Problems accelerated after Bell Labs was passed to Lucent. Lucent was a far smaller company than AT&amp;T at its peak: AT&amp;T had around 1 million employees at the end of the 1970s, while Lucent had just 140,000 employees when it was formed (and shrunk to just 35,000 employees by 2002). By comparison, Bell Labs employed around 25,000 people and 1,300 researchers at the end of the 1970s. Even after two decades of carve-offs and employee departures, the Labs was a far greater financial burden to Lucent than it had been to the largest corporation in America. Offices began to be closed, and layoffs or requested early retirements began for researchers. By 2002, there were only around 500 Bell Labs researchers left. Financial pressure continued: in 2005, a new Bell Labs president </span><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/nmat1643" rel="">announced his intent</a><span> to “align Bell Labs research with the company’s business activities and provide a much stronger impact on the bottom line.”</span></p><p>Amidst these difficulties, Bell Labs’ research efforts slowed. Though Nobel Prize-winning research continued to be performed in the 1980s and even 1990s, it was almost entirely done by researchers who had been hired prior to divestiture. Only one of Bell Labs’ 10 Nobel Prizes was done by an employee hired following the divestiture. A similar pattern exists for the winners of the Draper Prize and those inducted into the National Inventors Hall of Fame. Research seems to have been increasingly focused on software (one notable Bell Labs software researcher is machine learning expert Yann LeCun, who joined Bell Labs in 1988).</p><p>Today, Nokia Bell Labs employs around 750 people, with research efforts focused on “network fundamentals, automation, semiconductors, and AI." But while it trades on the name of its predecessor, for all intents and purposes the old Bell Labs is gone.</p><p>While Bell Labs was far from the only major industrial research laboratory, no other lab could match the scale or scope of Bell Labs’ achievements. In part, Bell Labs’ success was due to getting the right ‘formula’ for running a productive research organization, but it was also due to a variety of historical circumstances that couldn’t be deliberately recreated.</p><p><span>Most importantly, Bell Labs was a subsidiary of AT&amp;T, a highly vertically integrated, government-sanctioned monopoly provider of telephone service, and by far the largest company in the world. This yielded several key benefits. Its size allowed AT&amp;T to devote incredible resources to research and development: though Bell Labs was a huge research organization, it was a comparatively small fraction of AT&amp;T’s revenue. And AT&amp;T’s monopoly status allowed Bell Labs to undertake long-term projects that might take years to pay off. Even if a research effort took 10 or 20 years to bear fruit, the monopoly would still be there. Many of Bell Labs' most important technological advances — fiber optics, undersea telephone cables, electronic switching — took decades to develop.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-4-146749385" href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/what-would-it-take-to-recreate-bell#footnote-4-146749385" target="_self" rel="">4</a></span></p><p>AT&amp;T’s size also gave it a low bar for what constituted a valuable technical improvement. Even a tiny improvement that saved a few cents on a component or service would be large when multiplied by the enormous scale of the Bell System. This low bar made it far more likely a given research effort would be successful.</p><p><span>Similarly, AT&amp;T’s vertical integration, where it designed, built, and operated all its own telephone equipment, gave it a very large research “surface area." The breadth of its offerings could justify a similarly broad set of research initiatives in a variety of different fields. Any given discovery would likely be useful </span><em>somewhere</em><span> in the Bell System. For instance, a test developed for </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Random_dot_stereogram" rel="">depth perception</a><span> by Bell Labs vision researcher Bela Julesz proved to be useful for quality control inspection of integrated circuits, by weeding out inspectors who lacked depth perception.&nbsp;</span></p><p>Cultivating a broad swath of research activities and expertise also likely made those activities more productive. Other experts could (and did) discuss problems, share insights, and suggest possible approaches. The huge pool of knowledge made it easier to avoid bottlenecks and find solutions to problems encountered during development. Many Bell Labs alumni have noted the value of the huge amount of expertise immediately available to help solve problems:</p><blockquote><p><em>One of the great features of Bell Labs was that there were so many experts in so many different fields within it. Furthermore, they were all accessible and glad to share their experience and knowledge with others. The openness of the intellectual atmosphere was a huge strength - Walter Brown</em></p></blockquote><p><span>The size of AT&amp;T also forced technical progress as a matter of survival. AT&amp;T was so large that it sat right on the edge of what the government would allow to exist. Over its life, AT&amp;T was constantly threatened with antitrust action or with government takeover, and only appeasements — such as agreeing to manage </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandia_National_Laboratories" rel="">Sandia National Laboratories</a><span> for the government — managed to stave them off. The most important appeasement was constant improvements to telephone service: only this way could AT&amp;T continue to justify its existence. As Peter Temin and Louis Galambos note in “The Fall of the Bell System”:</span></p><blockquote><p><em>Only its best behavior could shield the largest regulated monopoly in the world from attack–and even that might not be enough…This record of relentless technological improvement was the glue that held together AT&amp;T’s various accommodations with the state and federal governments</em></p></blockquote><p>Bell Labs also benefited from a strong sense of purpose: its mandate was to improve telephone and communication technology, to make AT&amp;T’s offerings better and cheaper, and to accommodate the constantly rising demand for telephone service. Though Bell Labs gave researchers a large amount of freedom, the researchers nevertheless knew they were there to help build the Bell System, and the Labs had mechanisms in place to ensure research efforts were directed to the most important problems.</p><p>John Pierce, the force behind Bell Labs’ communication satellites, argued that “it's very important for laboratories to have some responsibility and some general goal”: labs operate best when there are people on the work that you’re doing. Pierce argues that Bell Labs and the other great labs of the 20th century “were really needed, and they rose to the need.” Not only did this clearly articulated, strongly felt purpose provide a powerful motivation, but it created a “problem-rich environment," a clear set of problems that can act as a guiding star. Shockley and other researchers in Bell Labs’ solid-state department weren’t assigned any particular research task, but they all knew the potential value and usefulness of a solid-state amplifier, and their efforts coalesced around producing one as their research revealed ways that it might be possible. This focus on turning scientific research into real, physical products also likely improved research efforts, by allowing rapid feedback and iteration; people familiar with ‘on-the-ground’ needs could provide suggestions for in-progress efforts, and test experiments and devices could be quickly fabricated and tried out. The silicon solar PV cell, for instance, was a direct result of Bell Labs maintaining facilities for melting silicon and creating purified silicon ingots.</p><p>Bell Labs also benefited from chance historical circumstances, finding itself in the right place at the right time to make major discoveries and create important inventions. Academic research on quantum mechanics in the 1920s and 1930s yielded a huge collection of physical phenomena, and Hitler’s rise in Europe created a steady stream of talented European physicists immigrating to the U.S. As one of the few organizations able to hire physicists at the tail-end of the Depression, Bell Labs was able to acquire top-tier talent in a field that was ripe for exploitation. William Shockley, for instance, noted that job offers “were not just hanging around on trees”: though he applied for jobs at GE and RCA, only Bell Labs offered him a full-time position.</p><p><span>Similarly, AT&amp;T and Bell Labs would grow enormously during WWII, under pressure to fulfill government contracts and develop new weapons. During the war, Bell Labs added several thousand staff and took on more than 1,000 government contracts to develop tank radio sets, enciphering machines, </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M9_gun_director" rel="">antiaircraft gun directors</a><span>, and most of all radar sets. When the war ended, Bell Labs emerged as “the greatest invention factory in any field of science that the world had ever seen,” poised to capitalize on the huge backlog of scientific discoveries and technical progress that had taken place during the war.</span></p><p>More generally, over its life, Bell Labs probably accumulated inventions that would have been invented somewhere else in its absence. The many cases of simultaneous invention (the telephone itself being a classic example) show that an invention will often “appear” once the conditions are right and the necessary predecessor technologies are in place. Because Bell Labs was the largest developer of telecommunications equipment, and because the existence of AT&amp;T (a near-monopsony purchaser of said equipment) may have discouraged outsiders to try and invent new telephone technology, many new telephone-related inventions ended up being created at Bell Labs by default.</p><p><span>And of course, Bell Labs managed to create a culture within the labs that was highly conducive to creating novel inventions and discoveries. Theodore Vail believed that science-based technological development was the key to AT&amp;T’s success, and he inculcated these values so successfully within the company that they lasted for decades. Bell Labs researchers had many of the benefits of an academic research environment (freedom to pursue whatever research avenues they saw fit, ability to achieve academic prestige, little risk of termination, ability to devote long periods to speculative projects with unclear payoffs) without many of its drawbacks (needing to spend time teaching or applying for grants). And it offered many benefits, such as higher salaries and better equipment, that academic research environments couldn’t. It wasn’t uncommon that Bell Labs researchers would plan a few-year stay, then find the environment so hospitable that they remained their entire careers. As the reputation of the Labs increased, these benefits increasingly allowed it to attract top talent, which further accelerated its achievements. (For a more thorough look at the culture within Bell Labs, see </span><a href="https://www.freaktakes.com/p/how-did-places-like-bell-labs-know" rel="">these</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.freaktakes.com/p/bonus-more-details-on-how-bell-labs" rel="">pieces</a><span> by Eric Gilliam.)</span></p><p>While some of the factors behind Bell Labs’ success seem possible to recreate (though not necessarily easily), others seem impossible, or at best contingent on things outside our control.</p><p>In principle, there’s no reason that you couldn’t create a culture like Bell Labs: goal-directed at a high level but with a lot of freedom in how that goal was pursued, highly interdisciplinary, focused on real, practical problems but open to pursuing more “fundamental” research to solve them, minimizing burdens on researchers and maximizing their flexibility. But in practice, such a culture is likely difficult to create deliberately. Some of the things that helped create it at Bell Labs, such as a huge initial success with a science-based technological development project, can’t be willed into existence. Likewise, having a goal attached to a lab is not the same thing as an overriding, urgent need that infuses its culture; the former can simply be dictated, but the latter is dependent on outside forces (like a constantly rising demand for a product) that can’t necessarily be controlled. Similarly, top talent and making a lab highly prestigious is possible in principle but not completely controllable: much of the Labs’ prestige, for instance, came from the invention of the transistor.</p><p><span>And these are likely the </span><em>easiest</em><span> parts of the problem. Bell Labs was made possible by a large-scale, vertically integrated telephone monopoly that allowed for an unusually long and wide research and development horizon for an industrial lab. Outside of those conditions (not likely to be repeated), funding a Bell Labs-style operation does not appear to be something most companies are willing to do. Even a company like Google, which spends billions on R&amp;D and has displayed a willingness to fund speculative, longer-term </span><a href="https://x.company/" rel="">moonshot</a><span> projects like self-driving cars or </span><a href="https://www.calicolabs.com/" rel="">life extension</a><span>, doesn’t completely bite the Bell Labs bullet. Google’s Moonshot projects absorb billions in funding each year, but they tend to be organized as independent companies that raise money outside Google and get spun off when they seem promising enough. Bell Labs also took advantage of historical circumstances: discoveries in quantum mechanics yielded promising new phenomena, and WWII energized the organization while simultaneously creating scientific and technological progress that could later be capitalized on. These contingencies were the result of pure chance, not anything that could be controlled.</span></p><p><span>And even if all these conditions could be created (or were found to not be critical for success), Bell Labs might have been the product of a particular technological regime that we no longer live in. For much of its existence, AT&amp;T was criticized for adopting technology too slowly (such as automatic dialing and electronic switching), but following WWII it began to face the opposite problem: technology it developed seemed to slip out of its fingers to be exploited by others. In the second half of its life, Bell Labs’ invention machine seemed to be increasingly out of its control. Much of the technology invented at Bell Labs, such as the solar PV cell, the CO2 laser, or the chemistry behind the </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glow_stick" rel="">glow stick</a><span>, had little to no impact on the Bell System, and was developed and commercialized for other purposes. Other research, such as efforts to create computer-generated music, had little to no practical application at all.</span></p><p><span>Even technology that did find use in the Bell System, such as the transistor, often left the parent company behind. Bell Labs invented the transistor and many of the early related inventions, but by the 1960s the center of gravity in microelectronics development had begun to move elsewhere; Bell Labs continued to make important inventions (such as </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Molecular-beam_epitaxy" rel="">molecular-beam epitaxypitaxy</a><span> for transistor fabrication), but many of the most important inventions, such as the integrated circuit and the microprocessor, would be invented elsewhere. And AT&amp;T itself struggled to introduce the transistor into its system. Though Bell Labs had developed the transistor specifically to replace vacuum tubes and mechanical relays, the first electronic switching center wasn’t deployed until 1964, and the technology was still being rolled out in the 1980s.</span></p><p><span>Microwave transmission also quickly escaped AT&amp;T’s control. In 1951 AT&amp;T </span><a href="https://www.historyofinformation.com/detail.php?id=4208" rel="">deployed</a><span> the first microwave transmission telephone system, leveraging work on microwaves it had done during WWII. Less than 20 years later, other companies were challenging AT&amp;T with their own microwave systems, one of which (MCI) would ultimately instigate the downfall of AT&amp;T.</span></p><p>This loss of control was partially due to a 1956 agreement with the Justice Department that forced AT&amp;T to license its patents, but this is at best a partial explanation. After all, AT&amp;T had (eventually) maintained control over the development of its technology after its key patents expired in the 1890s, and after it adopted generous patent licensing terms in the 1930s.</p><p>Another reason for the loss of control was a shifting culture within Bell Labs that gave researchers more freedom, and placed less emphasis on eventually turning their work into practical results. Philip Anderson, Bell Labs researcher and winner of the 1977 Nobel Prize in physics, argues that Bell Labs was forced to adjust its culture to retain its most talented researchers. While previous work had to be justified for its possible relevance to the telephone system (though an expansive view of possible relevance was taken), by the 1970s and ‘80s that seemed to no longer be the case. In his memoir about the later years of Bell Labs, Narain Gehani describes the research department as unwilling to cooperate or justify its existence to the business side of the organization at all.</p><p>And finally, this loss of control also might simply be the nature of technology itself. In his memoir of his experiences at Bell Labs, Alan Chynoweth argues that the technology that Bell Labs developed ultimately created a world where something like Bell Labs no longer made sense:</p><blockquote><p><em>Before the discovery of the transistor, telecommunications… was a rather specialized, even arcane branch of engineering. The transistor was to sow the seeds of change. Though it led to a flowering of solid-state science and technology and would eventually revolutionize telecommunications, it also, once it had evolved into integrated circuits and digital technologies, lent itself to revolutionizing almost every other area of electronic engineering, information technology, and product development. It became everyone’s technology, the genie was out of the bottle… nowadays each step along the chain is populated with numerous competing companies specializing in that step so that a company in the next step has a multiplicity of sources of technology from which to choose. In particular, it has made it relatively easy for new competitors to develop their own versions of telecommunications devices, systems, and services. Perhaps it can be said that with the discovery of the transistor, forces were set in motion that would eventually and inevitably lead to Bell Labs losing its unique status.</em></p></blockquote><p><span>Jon Gertner likewise posits in The</span><em> Idea Factory</em><span> that even in the absence of a justice department lawsuit, the technology that Bell Labs spawned would have ultimately unwound the AT&amp;T monopoly and thus the very thing that allowed Bell Labs to exist.</span></p><p>Bell Labs may thus not only be a product of unique historical circumstances, but unique technological circumstances: telecommunications technology that was best provided and controlled by a single, enormous monopoly, which in turn made Bell Labs possible. The question may not be “How do we recreate Bell Labs?” but “How best can we evolve the technological landscape that we’re faced with today?”</p><p><em><strong><span>If you're interested in reading more about Bell Labs, a reading list of the best and most useful books and other resources I found on the subject is </span><a href="https://www.construction-physics.com/p/bell-labs-reading-list" rel="">available here </a><span>for paid subscribers.</span></strong></em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[USPS shared customer postal addresses with Meta, LinkedIn and Snap (366 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/07/18/usps-shared-customer-postal-addresses-with-meta-linkedin-and-snap/</link>
            <guid>40998647</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 18:56:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/07/18/usps-shared-customer-postal-addresses-with-meta-linkedin-and-snap/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/07/18/usps-shared-customer-postal-addresses-with-meta-linkedin-and-snap/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40998647">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">The U.S. Postal Service was sharing the postal addresses of its online customers with advertising and tech giants Meta, LinkedIn and Snap, TechCrunch has found.</p>

<p>On Wednesday, the USPS said it addressed the issue and stopped the practice, claiming that it was “unaware” of it.</p>

	
	


<p>TechCrunch found USPS was sharing customers’ information by way of hidden data-collecting code (also known as tracking pixels) used across its website. Tech and advertising companies create this kind of code to collect information about the user — such as which pages they visit — every time a webpage containing the code loads in the customer’s browser. </p>

<p>In the case of USPS, some of that collected data included the postal addresses of logged-in USPS Informed Delivery customers, who use the service to see photos of their incoming mail before it arrives.</p>

<p>It’s not clear how many individuals had their information collected or for how long. Informed Delivery had <a href="https://www.usps.com/business/pdf/informed-delivery-year-review.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">more than 62 million users</a> as of March 2024.&nbsp;</p>

<p>In a statement to TechCrunch, USPS spokesperson Jim McKean said: “The Postal Service leverages an analytics platform for our own internal purposes, so that we understand the usage of our products and services and which we use on an aggregated basis to market our products.”</p>

<p>“The Postal Service does not sell or provide any personal information that is collected from this analytics platform to any third party, and we were unaware of any configuration of the platform that collected personal information from the URL and that shared it without our knowledge with social media.”&nbsp;</p>

	
	


	
	


<p>“We have taken immediate action to remediate this issue,” the spokesperson said, without saying what action was taken. The spokesperson declined to comment further.&nbsp;</p>

<p>When reached for comment, Facebook spokesperson Emil Vazquez provided a statement: “We’ve been clear in our policies that advertisers should not send sensitive information about people through our Business Tools. Doing so is against our policies, and we educate advertisers on properly setting up Business Tools to prevent this from occurring. Our system is designed to filter out potentially sensitive data it is able to detect.”</p>

<p>Spokespeople for LinkedIn and Snap did not immediately comment when contacted by TechCrunch.</p>

<p>In our testing, TechCrunch discovered that the USPS website shared the postal address of a logged-in USPS Informed Delivery customer with Meta, LinkedIn and Snap. TechCrunch tested this by inspecting the network traffic using tools baked into most modern browsers.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Our testing showed the data-collecting code on USPS’ website was scraping the customer’s address from the Informed Delivery landing page after customers logged in, and then sending it to the companies.</p>

	
	


<p>The code also collected other data, such as information about the user’s computer type and browser, which appeared as partly pseudonymized — essentially scrambled in a way that makes it more difficult for humans to know where data came from, or who it relates to, by using randomized identifiers in place of real customer names. But researchers have <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2019/07/24/researchers-spotlight-the-lie-of-anonymous-data/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">long warned that pseudonymous data can still be used to re-identify seemingly anonymous individuals</a>.&nbsp;</p>

<p>TechCrunch also found that tracking numbers entered into the USPS website were also shared with advertisers and tech companies, including Bing, Google, LinkedIn, Pinterest and Snap. Some in-transit tracking data was also shared, such as the real-world location of the mail in the postal system, even if the customer was not logged in to USPS’ website.</p>

<p>USPS’ spokesperson declined to say if the postal service will ask the tech companies to delete the data that they collected.&nbsp;</p>

	
	


<p>A spokesperson for the USPS Office of Inspector General, the federal watchdog that provides oversight of the postal service, did not comment at press time.</p>

<p>USPS is the latest organization in recent years to curtail its use of web tracking code.</p>

	
	


<p>In 2023, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/03/10/cerebral-shared-millions-patient-data-advertisers/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">telehealth wellness startup Cerebral</a> and <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/04/04/monument-tempest-alcohol-data-breach/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">alcohol recovery apps Tempest and Monument</a> revealed they had shared private health information, including assessments submitted by their users, with tech and advertising companies, and had since removed the tracking code.</p>

<p>In the same year, the Federal Trade Commission brought enforcement action against healthcare data giant GoodRx, which <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/02/01/ftc-slaps-online-pharmacy-goodrx-for-sharing-users-health-data-with-facebook-and-google/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">agreed to pay $1.5 million for sharing health data of customers</a> with advertisers, and online therapy company BetterHelp, which was <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/03/02/betterhelp-owes-customers-7-8m-after-ftc-alleges-data-mishandling/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ordered to compensate patients to the tune of $7.8 million</a> for also sharing their private health questionnaire responses.</p>

<p><em>Updated with comment from Meta.</em></p>

<figure></figure>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: How we leapfrogged traditional vector based RAG with a 'language map' (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/mutableai/status/1813815706783490055</link>
            <guid>40998497</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 18:40:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/mutableai/status/1813815706783490055">https://twitter.com/mutableai/status/1813815706783490055</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40998497">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Devzat – Chat over SSH, with some nice quality-of-life features (377 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/quackduck/devzat</link>
            <guid>40998158</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 17:58:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/quackduck/devzat">https://github.com/quackduck/devzat</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40998158">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/38882631/257676138-046fbb4d-dff2-41e9-a61c-271d0820473e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjEzMzg1MDMsIm5iZiI6MTcyMTMzODIwMywicGF0aCI6Ii8zODg4MjYzMS8yNTc2NzYxMzgtMDQ2ZmJiNGQtZGZmMi00MWU5LWE2MWMtMjcxZDA4MjA0NzNlLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA3MTglMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNzE4VDIxMzAwM1omWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTJmNjJlYThkMmE0ZmMyMGRmMjQyNGIyN2NhYTYzMTZlMDNlOWZjYzYyYzE1ZDI5ZTAzYTdhYjYyNmY0OTA5YTkmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.44OkGPRAQCGXIoWU2pjDLAzicJAzZEuXgIPPi8gyJSA"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/38882631/257676138-046fbb4d-dff2-41e9-a61c-271d0820473e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjEzMzg1MDMsIm5iZiI6MTcyMTMzODIwMywicGF0aCI6Ii8zODg4MjYzMS8yNTc2NzYxMzgtMDQ2ZmJiNGQtZGZmMi00MWU5LWE2MWMtMjcxZDA4MjA0NzNlLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDA3MTglMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwNzE4VDIxMzAwM1omWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTJmNjJlYThkMmE0ZmMyMGRmMjQyNGIyN2NhYTYzMTZlMDNlOWZjYzYyYzE1ZDI5ZTAzYTdhYjYyNmY0OTA5YTkmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.44OkGPRAQCGXIoWU2pjDLAzicJAzZEuXgIPPi8gyJSA"></a>
</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.producthunt.com/posts/devzat?utm_source=badge-top-post-badge&amp;utm_medium=badge&amp;utm_souce=badge-devzat" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ad5bdc736c3591548b48bcbbfb626e80a2c978ed7d71f1fa4d1f014c777e5203/68747470733a2f2f6170692e70726f6475637468756e742e636f6d2f776964676574732f656d6265642d696d6167652f76312f746f702d706f73742d62616467652e7376673f706f73745f69643d323938363738267468656d653d6c6967687426706572696f643d6461696c79" alt="Devzat - Chat with other devs over SSH in your Terminal | Product Hunt" width="250" height="54" data-canonical-src="https://api.producthunt.com/widgets/embed-image/v1/top-post-badge.svg?post_id=298678&amp;theme=light&amp;period=daily"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Where are the devs at? Devzat!</p>
<p dir="auto">Devzat is a custom SSH server that takes you to a chat instead of a shell prompt. Because there's SSH apps on all platforms (even on phones) you can connect to Devzat on any device!</p>

<p dir="auto">A recording I took one day:
<a href="https://asciinema.org/a/477083?speed=3" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/02aea36c96ffa18a9c0affa4ed44f96e5a11359ac3dd846db5cafb62e4620751/68747470733a2f2f61736369696e656d612e6f72672f612f3437373038332e737667" alt="asciicast" data-canonical-src="https://asciinema.org/a/477083.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Try it out:</p>

<p dir="auto">You can log in with a nickname:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ssh nickname@devzat.hackclub.com"><pre>ssh nickname@devzat.hackclub.com</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you're under a firewall, you can still join on port 443:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ssh devzat.hackclub.com -p 443"><pre>ssh devzat.hackclub.com -p 443</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you add this to <code>~/.ssh/config</code>:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Host chat
    HostName devzat.hackclub.com"><pre lang="ssh"><code>Host chat
    HostName devzat.hackclub.com
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You'll be able to join with just:</p>

<p dir="auto">We also have a Slack bridge! If you're on the <a href="https://hackclub.com/" rel="nofollow">Hack Club</a> Slack, check out the <code>#ssh-chat-bridge</code> channel!</p>
<p dir="auto">Feel free to make a <a href="https://github.com/quackduck/devzat/issues">new issue</a> if something doesn't work.</p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://stats.uptimerobot.com/kxMQqfYk4y" rel="nofollow">status site</a> of the main Devzat server to check if it might be down.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Want to host your own instance?</h3><a id="user-content-want-to-host-your-own-instance" aria-label="Permalink: Want to host your own instance?" href="#want-to-host-your-own-instance"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Quick start:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/quackduck/devzat &amp;&amp; cd devzat
go install # or build, if you want to keep things pwd
ssh-keygen -qN '' -f devzat-sshkey # new ssh host key for the server
devzat # run! the default config is used &amp; written automatically"><pre>git clone https://github.com/quackduck/devzat <span>&amp;&amp;</span> <span>cd</span> devzat
go install <span><span>#</span> or build, if you want to keep things pwd</span>
ssh-keygen -qN <span><span>'</span><span>'</span></span> -f devzat-sshkey <span><span>#</span> new ssh host key for the server</span>
devzat <span><span>#</span> run! the default config is used &amp; written automatically</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">These commands download, build, setup and run a Devzat server listening on port 2221, the default port (change by setting <code>$PORT</code>).</p>
<p dir="auto">Check out the <a href="https://github.com/quackduck/devzat/blob/main/Admin's%20Manual.md">Admin's Manual</a> for complete self-host documentation!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Permission denied?</h3><a id="user-content-permission-denied" aria-label="Permalink: Permission denied?" href="#permission-denied"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Devzat uses public keys to identify users. If you are denied access: <code>foo@devzat.hackclub.com: Permission denied (publickey)</code> try logging in on port 443, which does not require a key, using <code>ssh devzat.hackclub.com -p 443</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">This error may happen because you do not have an SSH key pair. Generate one with the command <code>ssh-keygen</code> if this is the case. (you can usually check if you have a key pair by making sure a file of this form: <code>~/.ssh/id_*</code> exists)</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Help</h3><a id="user-content-help" aria-label="Permalink: Help" href="#help"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Welcome to Devzat! Devzat is chat over SSH: github.com/quackduck/devzat
Because there's SSH apps on all platforms, even on mobile, you can join from anywhere.

Run `cmds` to see a list of commands.

Interesting features:
• Rooms! Run cd to see all rooms and use cd #foo to join a new room.
• Markdown support! Tables, headers, italics and everything. Just use \n in place of newlines.
• Code syntax highlighting. Use Markdown fences to send code. Run eg-code to see an example.
• Direct messages! Send a quick DM using =user <msg> or stay in DMs by running cd @user.
• Timezone support, use tz Continent/City to set your timezone.
• Built in Tic Tac Toe and Hangman! Run tic or hang <word> to start new games.
• Emoji replacements! :rocket: => 🚀  (like on Slack and Discord)

For replacing newlines, I often use bulkseotools.com/add-remove-line-breaks.php.

Made by Ishan Goel with feature ideas from friends.
Thanks to Caleb Denio for lending his server!"><pre lang="text"><code>Welcome to Devzat! Devzat is chat over SSH: github.com/quackduck/devzat
Because there's SSH apps on all platforms, even on mobile, you can join from anywhere.

Run `cmds` to see a list of commands.

Interesting features:
• Rooms! Run cd to see all rooms and use cd #foo to join a new room.
• Markdown support! Tables, headers, italics and everything. Just use \n in place of newlines.
• Code syntax highlighting. Use Markdown fences to send code. Run eg-code to see an example.
• Direct messages! Send a quick DM using =user &lt;msg&gt; or stay in DMs by running cd @user.
• Timezone support, use tz Continent/City to set your timezone.
• Built in Tic Tac Toe and Hangman! Run tic or hang &lt;word&gt; to start new games.
• Emoji replacements! :rocket: =&gt; 🚀  (like on Slack and Discord)

For replacing newlines, I often use bulkseotools.com/add-remove-line-breaks.php.

Made by Ishan Goel with feature ideas from friends.
Thanks to Caleb Denio for lending his server!
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Commands</h3><a id="user-content-commands" aria-label="Permalink: Commands" href="#commands"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Commands
   =<user>   <msg>           DM <user> with <msg>
   users                     List users
   color     <color>         Change your name's color
   exit                      Leave the chat
   help                      Show help
   man       <cmd>           Get help for a specific command
   emojis                    See a list of emojis
   bell      on|off|all      ANSI bell on pings (on), never (off) or for every message (all)
   clear                     Clear the screen
   hang      <char|word>     Play hangman
   tic       <cell num>      Play tic tac toe!
   devmonk                   Test your typing speed
   cd        #room|user      Join #room, DM user or run cd to see a list
   tz        <zone> [24h]    Set your IANA timezone (like tz Asia/Dubai) and optionally set 24h
   nick      <name>          Change your username
   pronouns  @user|pronouns  Set your pronouns or get another user's
   theme     <theme>|list    Change the syntax highlighting theme
   rest                      Uncommon commands list
   cmds                      Show this message"><pre lang="text"><code>Commands
   =&lt;user&gt;   &lt;msg&gt;           DM &lt;user&gt; with &lt;msg&gt;
   users                     List users
   color     &lt;color&gt;         Change your name's color
   exit                      Leave the chat
   help                      Show help
   man       &lt;cmd&gt;           Get help for a specific command
   emojis                    See a list of emojis
   bell      on|off|all      ANSI bell on pings (on), never (off) or for every message (all)
   clear                     Clear the screen
   hang      &lt;char|word&gt;     Play hangman
   tic       &lt;cell num&gt;      Play tic tac toe!
   devmonk                   Test your typing speed
   cd        #room|user      Join #room, DM user or run cd to see a list
   tz        &lt;zone&gt; [24h]    Set your IANA timezone (like tz Asia/Dubai) and optionally set 24h
   nick      &lt;name&gt;          Change your username
   pronouns  @user|pronouns  Set your pronouns or get another user's
   theme     &lt;theme&gt;|list    Change the syntax highlighting theme
   rest                      Uncommon commands list
   cmds                      Show this message
</code></pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="The rest
   people                  See info about nice people who joined
   id       <user>         Get a unique ID for a user (hashed key)
   admins                  Print the ID (hashed key) for all admins
   eg-code  [big]          Example syntax-highlighted code
   lsbans                  List banned IDs
   ban      <user>         Ban <user> (admin)
   unban    <IP|ID> [dur]  Unban a person and optionally, for a duration (admin)
   kick     <user>         Kick <user> (admin)
   art                     Show some panda art
   pwd                     Show your current room
   shrug                   ¯\_(ツ)_/¯"><pre><code>The rest
   people                  See info about nice people who joined
   id       &lt;user&gt;         Get a unique ID for a user (hashed key)
   admins                  Print the ID (hashed key) for all admins
   eg-code  [big]          Example syntax-highlighted code
   lsbans                  List banned IDs
   ban      &lt;user&gt;         Ban &lt;user&gt; (admin)
   unban    &lt;IP|ID&gt; [dur]  Unban a person and optionally, for a duration (admin)
   kick     &lt;user&gt;         Kick &lt;user&gt; (admin)
   art                     Show some panda art
   pwd                     Show your current room
   shrug                   ¯\_(ツ)_/¯
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Integrations</h2><a id="user-content-integrations" aria-label="Permalink: Integrations" href="#integrations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">When self-hosting an instance, Devzat can integrate with Slack and/or Discord to bridge messages, and Twitter to post new-user announcements.
See the <a href="https://github.com/quackduck/devzat/blob/main/Admin's%20Manual.md">Admin's Manual</a> for more info.</p>
<p dir="auto">Devzat has a plugin API you can use to integrate your own services: <a href="https://github.com/quackduck/devzat/blob/main/plugin/README.md">documentation</a>. Feel free to add a plugin to the main instance. Just ask for a token on the server.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Stargazers over time</h2><a id="user-content-stargazers-over-time" aria-label="Permalink: Stargazers over time" href="#stargazers-over-time"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://starchart.cc/quackduck/devzat" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/3d26b60cf346b758d4a8176cc08aa6d8e05383a5263a83b2307849125b95fc4a/68747470733a2f2f7374617263686172742e63632f717561636b6475636b2f6465767a61742e737667" alt="Stargazers over time" data-canonical-src="https://starchart.cc/quackduck/devzat.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">People</h2><a id="user-content-people" aria-label="Permalink: People" href="#people"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">People who you might know who have joined:</p>
<p dir="auto">Zach Latta - Founder of Hack Club: <em>"omg amazing! this is so awesome"</em><br>
Ant Wilson - Co founder, Supabase: <a href="https://twitter.com/AntWilson/status/1396444302721445889" rel="nofollow"><em>"brilliant!"</em></a><br>
Bereket <a href="https://twitter.com/heybereket" rel="nofollow">@heybereket</a>: <em>"this is pretty cool"</em><br>
Ayush <a href="https://twitter.com/ayshptk" rel="nofollow">@ayshptk</a>: <em>"Can I double star the repo somehow 🥺"</em><br>
Sanketh <a href="https://twitter.com/SankethYS" rel="nofollow">@SankethYS</a>: <em>"Heck! How does this work. So cool."</em><br>
Tony Dinh <a href="https://twitter.com/tdinh_me" rel="nofollow">@tdinh_me</a>: <em>"supeer cool, oh, open source as well? yeah"</em><br>
Srushti <a href="https://twitter.com/srushtiuniverse" rel="nofollow">@srushtiuniverse</a>: <em>"Yess it's awesome. I tried it."</em><br>
Surjith <a href="https://twitter.com/surjithctly" rel="nofollow">@surjithctly</a>: <em>"Whoa, who made this?"</em><br>
Arav <a href="https://twitter.com/HeyArav" rel="nofollow">@HeyArav</a>: <a href="https://twitter.com/tregsthedev/status/1384180393893498880" rel="nofollow"><em>"Okay, this is actually super awesome."</em></a><br>
Harsh <a href="https://twitter.com/harshb__" rel="nofollow">@harshb__</a>: <em>"im gonna come here everyday to chill when i get bored of studying lol, this is so cool"</em>
Krish <a href="https://twitter.com/krishnerkar_" rel="nofollow">@krishnerkar_</a>:  <a href="https://twitter.com/krishnerkar_/status/1384173042616573960" rel="nofollow"><em>"SHIT! THIS IS SO DOPE"</em></a><br>
Amrit <a href="https://twitter.com/astro_shenava" rel="nofollow">@astro_shenava</a>: <em>"Super cool man"</em><br>
Mudrank <a href="https://twitter.com/mudrankgupta" rel="nofollow">@mudrankgupta</a>: "🔥🚀🚀"</p>
<p dir="auto">From Hack Club:<br>
<strong><a href="https://calebden.io/" rel="nofollow">Caleb Denio</a>, <a href="https://safin.dev/" rel="nofollow">Safin Singh</a>, <a href="https://github.com/E-Lee-Za">Eleeza</a><br>
<a href="https://github.com/s1ntaxe770r">Jubril</a>, <a href="https://sarthakmohanty.me/" rel="nofollow">Sarthak Mohanty</a><br>
<a href="http://sampoder.com/" rel="nofollow">Sam Poder</a>, <a href="http://rishi.cx/" rel="nofollow">Rishi Kothari</a><br>
<a href="https://amogh.sh/" rel="nofollow">Amogh Chaubey</a>, <a href="https://ella.cx/" rel="nofollow">Ella</a>, <a href="https://github.com/Hugoyhu">Hugo Hu</a>
<a href="https://matthewstanciu.me/" rel="nofollow">Matthew Stanciu</a>, <a href="https://tanishqsoni.me/" rel="nofollow">Tanishq Soni</a></strong></p>
<p dir="auto">Huge thanks to the amazing <a href="https://github.com/cjdenio">Caleb Denio</a> for lending me the original Devzat server 💖</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><em>Made by <a href="https://twitter.com/usrbinishan/" rel="nofollow">Ishan Goel</a> with feature ideas from friends. Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/CalebDenio" rel="nofollow">Caleb Denio</a> for lending his server!</em></h3><a id="user-content-made-by-ishan-goel-with-feature-ideas-from-friends-thanks-to-caleb-denio-for-lending-his-server" aria-label="Permalink: Made by Ishan Goel with feature ideas from friends. Thanks to Caleb Denio for lending his server!" href="#made-by-ishan-goel-with-feature-ideas-from-friends-thanks-to-caleb-denio-for-lending-his-server"></a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Transcribro: On-device Accurate Speech-to-text (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/soupslurpr/Transcribro</link>
            <guid>40997850</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 17:25:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/soupslurpr/Transcribro">https://github.com/soupslurpr/Transcribro</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40997850">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Transcribro</h2><a id="user-content-transcribro" aria-label="Permalink: Transcribro" href="#transcribro"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Transcribro is a private and on-device speech recognition keyboard and service for Android.<br>
It uses whisper.cpp to run the OpenAI Whisper family of models and Silero VAD for voice activity detection.<br>
It features a voice input keyboard, enabling you to type with speech.<br>
It can also be used by other apps either explicitly or when set as the user-selected speech to text app which some apps
may use for speech to text.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Download</h2><a id="user-content-download" aria-label="Permalink: Download" href="#download"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Transcribro is available on the <a href="https://accrescent.app/" rel="nofollow">Accrescent</a> app store and GitHub releases.<br>
<a href="https://accrescent.app/" rel="nofollow">Accrescent</a> is the recommended way to get Transcribro as it is more secure
than GitHub releases.<br>
Click on the badge below to get it on <a href="https://accrescent.app/" rel="nofollow">Accrescent</a>.</p>
<a href="https://accrescent.app/app/dev.soupslurpr.transcribro" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Get it on Accrescent" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8146730bd00bbc28f13f08de93a882e3897911d9962280b12f7966789eeaaef6/68747470733a2f2f61636372657363656e742e6170702f6261646765732f6765742d69742d6f6e2e706e67" height="80" data-canonical-src="https://accrescent.app/badges/get-it-on.png">
</a>
<p dir="auto">The package name and SHA-256 hash of the signing certificate is below, so if you are downloading the APK, you can
verify Transcribro with <a href="https://developer.android.com/studio/command-line/apksigner#usage-verify" rel="nofollow"><code>apksigner</code></a>
using <code>apksigner verify --print-certs Transcribro-X.Y.Z.apk</code> and/or
<a href="https://github.com/soupslurpr/AppVerifier">AppVerifier</a>.
If you are downloading from <a href="https://accrescent.app/" rel="nofollow">Accrescent</a> then you should verify
<a href="https://accrescent.app/" rel="nofollow">Accrescent</a> itself <a href="https://accrescent.app/faq#verifying" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">dev.soupslurpr.transcribro<br>
7D:BC:FB:FA:A1:35:B4:4E:6E:93:91:02:25:DC:B1:4E:05:82:91:DA:8C:2D:36:22:73:49:49:B7:1A:B3:BE:64</p>
<p dir="auto">It can also be found on a <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/soupslurpr.dev/post/3kopox4ffl72t" rel="nofollow">Bluesky post</a>
to distrust the website.
It is encouraged to verify it's the same with other people as well for assurance.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Community</h2><a id="user-content-community" aria-label="Permalink: Community" href="#community"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Join the Matrix space at <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#transcribro:matrix.org" rel="nofollow">https://matrix.to/#/#transcribro:matrix.org</a> for the General, Announcements, and
Testing rooms.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Check <a href="https://github.com/soupslurpr/Transcribro/blob/master/CONTRIBUTING.md">CONTRIBUTING.md</a> for things to know
if you want to contribute.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Donation</h2><a id="user-content-donation" aria-label="Permalink: Donation" href="#donation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Enjoy Transcribro? You can donate to <a href="https://github.com/soupslurpr">soupslurpr</a>, the lead developer of Transcribro to
support their work on Transcribro and their other open source projects. Thank you!</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.getmonero.org/" rel="nofollow">Monero</a> address:<br>
<code>88rAaNowhaC8JG8NJDpcdRWr1gGVmtFPnHWPS9xXvqY44G4XKVi5hZMax2FQ6B8KAcMpzkeJAhNek8qMHZjjwvkEKuiyBKF</code></p>
<p dir="auto">The <a href="https://www.getmonero.org/" rel="nofollow">Monero</a> address and also a QR code can be found in the app's Donate screen.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Branding</h2><a id="user-content-branding" aria-label="Permalink: Branding" href="#branding"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You may not use the name "Transcribro", a name that includes "Transcribro", and the app icon in a derivative work that
has published builds.<br>
This is to prevent confusion of which is the official Transcribro.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Screenshots</h2><a id="user-content-screenshots" aria-label="Permalink: Screenshots" href="#screenshots"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/soupslurpr/Transcribro/blob/master/Screenshot_20240607-005336.png"><img src="https://github.com/soupslurpr/Transcribro/raw/master/Screenshot_20240607-005336.png" alt="Screenshot of the keyboard UI, focused on the search bar of Vanadium's incognito tab."></a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GPT-4o mini: advancing cost-efficient intelligence (212 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-mini-advancing-cost-efficient-intelligence/</link>
            <guid>40997585</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jul 2024 17:02:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-mini-advancing-cost-efficient-intelligence/">https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-mini-advancing-cost-efficient-intelligence/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40997585">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/gpt-4o-mini-advancing-cost-efficient-intelligence/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>