(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 19:30:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do Not Sign the Qt License Agreement Unchanged (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://burkhardstubert.substack.com/p/do-not-sign-the-qt-license-agreement</link>
            <guid>41558799</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 18:08:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://burkhardstubert.substack.com/p/do-not-sign-the-qt-license-agreement">https://burkhardstubert.substack.com/p/do-not-sign-the-qt-license-agreement</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41558799">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png" width="1000" height="437" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:437,&quot;width&quot;:1000,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:175981,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5d96e008-586b-4413-bf42-a00f17035540_1000x437.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Dear Reader,</p><p><span>You are the first to learn that I launched a new product: </span><a href="https://embeddeduse.com/license-compliance-for-embedded-linux-systems/" rel="">License Compliance for Embedded Linux Systems</a><span>. Actually, it is not that new any more. I have performed license compliance checks for more than 25 customers over the last 5 years - but in some kind of stealth mode. Now, the product got its on own landing page with pricing, description and Q&amp;A section.</span></p><p>When companies contact me, they feel that The Qt Company paints too rosy a picture about Qt Commercial and too dark a picture about Qt LGPL. I help them make an informed decision whether to choose Qt Commercial or Qt LGPL. Most of them find out that Qt LGPL is good enough for their embedded devices, that the obligations of the LGPL are easy to satisfy and - bonus - that the costs of Qt LGPL are much lower than those of Qt Commercial. Don’t forget that Qt LGPL is a fantastic product and that ten thousands of companies have built fantastic products with it.</p><p>As part of these engagement, I had to explain the Qt license agreement many times. You find my explanations of the darker parts of the Qt license agreement in this newsletter. I can only urge you to read the Qt license agreement very thoroughly, discuss it with other people and compare it with the LGPL - before you sign it.</p><p><span>Enjoy reading,</span><br><span>Burkhard</span></p><p>Qt sales will try to sell you the Qt for Device Creation (QtDC) license as the care-free option for using Qt on embedded devices. They will also portrait LGPL as a very dangerous and complicated license. I beg to differ - and so will almost all of my customers, readers and listeners.</p><p><span>The </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/qt-dev-framework" rel="">Qt license agreement</a><span> is a masterpiece in legalese, vagueness, ambiguity and omission - with numerous pitfalls. The Qt Company has revised the agreement many times over the last years (just compare </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/qt-dev-framework" rel="">the current agreement</a><span> with </span><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210831204300/https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/" rel="">the 2021 agreement</a><span>). The Qt Company has optimised the agreement such that Qt applications, which run on a PC and communicate with an embedded device without Qt, become embedded devices under the QtDC license. </span></p><p>Some years back, The Qt Company happily sold Qt for Application Development (QtAD) licenses to such customers. When these licenses come up for renewal, The Qt Company claims that these customers commit a material breach of the license agreement and try to force the much more expensive QtDC licenses on them. Some customers will cave in, some will figure out that Qt LGPL or abandoning Qt is a better option.</p><p>Other companies fall for the care-free nonsense from Qt sales and pay 6-digit euro license fees per year. Inevitably, they will find out that Qt LGPL would have be more than enough for their embedded devices. Guess how these companies will feel and what they will do at the end of the license term.</p><p>All these companies have in common that they didn’t read the Qt license agreement thoroughly and they didn’t evaluate alternatives to the QtDC license. They only have to blame themselves for their calamity. The Qt Company is in its full right to write their license agreement however they want - although the agreement is certainly not “cute”. Of course, potential Qt customers are also in their full right to demand changes to the license agreement or walk away. </p><p>I will point out the murkier parts of the Qt license agreement and suggest changes. I am skeptical that The Qt Company will accept these changes, but it’s worth a try. The way The Qt Company treats you in these negotiations will tell you a lot, whether you should sign the agreement or not. Knowing the alternatives to QtDC will improve your negotiation position considerably.</p><p><span>The latest </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/qt-dev-framework" rel="">Qt Product and Service Agreement for the Qt Development Framework</a><span> defines embedded devices as follows.</span></p><blockquote><p>2.10. “Devices” shall mean</p><ul><li><p>i. hardware devices or products that</p><ul><li><p>a. are manufactured and/or distributed by the Customer, its Affiliates, Contractors or End Customer, and</p></li><li><p>b. incorporate, integrate or link to Applications such that substantial functionality of such unit, when used by an End User, is provided by Application(s) or otherwise depends on the Licensed Software; or</p></li></ul></li><li><p>ii. Applications designed for the hardware devices specified in item (i).</p></li></ul><p>Devices covered by this Appendix shall be specified in the Pricing Appendix or Purchase Document.</p><p><span>See definition </span><em>2.10 “Devices”</em><span> in the </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/qt-dev-framework" rel="">Qt Product and Service Agreement for the Qt Development Framework</a><span> (Version 2024-02, compliant with Qt Frame Agreement 2023-06 or later)</span></p></blockquote><p>WTF!!!??? That was my first reaction, too. It’s a masterpiece in legalese: vague to the point of being incomprehensible and far too broad in its scope. Let me try to translate this mumbo jumbo into plain English.</p><p><span>The logical structure of the Device definition is: </span><code>(i.a and i.b) or ii</code><span>. Your “hardware product” is considered a Device, if either clause (i) holds or clause (ii) holds. Clause (i) is satisfied, if and only both clause (a) and clause (b) are satisfied.</span></p><p>Let me start with a simple case. A manufacturer M of agricultural machines (the “Customer”) employs an in-house team to develop the machine’s driver terminals (the “units”, “hardware devices” or “hardware products”) with Qt. M sells its harvesters with the driver terminals to farmers F. The driver terminals are certainly Devices in the sense of the above definition, as M manufactures and distributes them (i.a) and one or more Qt applications (called Applications per Definition 2.3), which provide “substantial functionality” for the operation of the machine, run on the terminal (i.b).</p><p>Clause (i.a) significantly increases the number of devices and developers requiring licenses by including not only M but also its Affiliates, Contractors and End Customers.</p><p><strong>Affiliates</strong><span> are companies, in which M has a controlling majority or which have a controlling majority in M (see definition </span><em>3.1 “Affiliate”</em><span> in the </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions" rel="">Qt Frame Agreement</a><span>). For example, one of the world’s biggest agricultural manufacturers, owns 20 brands. Each brand is regarded as an Affiliate.</span></p><p>If M shares substantial parts of the terminal’s software (including applications and libraries using Qt) with its Affiliates, M must also buy Qt Commercial licenses for the devices and developers of the Affiliates. The same holds for M’s business units. </p><p>For example, the tractors produced by the different brands of the above agricultural manufacturer might share large parts of the code of their driver terminals. Only the GUIs show a distinct branding. If one of these brands uses Qt Commercial, all the other brands have to use it, too. </p><p>Only if a brand can prove that it doesn’t share “substantial” code based on Qt with other brands, it can escape the Qt Commercial jail. Of course, The Qt Company will interpret “substantial” as “any code based on Qt”. Affiliates will have a hard time arguing that the use is not substantial. Their best course is not use Qt at all. Alternatively, M and all its Affiliate can change to Qt LGPL once the license period has expired.</p><p><span>If M outsources the hardware or software development of the driver terminals partially or completely to </span><strong>Contractors</strong><span> (see definition </span><em>3.2 “Contractor”</em><span> in the </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions" rel="">Qt Frame Agreement</a><span>), M must pay the per-device or per-developer fees for the Qt Commercial licenses. Especially, M must also buy developer licenses for all the Contractors developing Qt applications for M or its affiliates. </span></p><p><strong>End Customers</strong><span> are companies to whom “[M], directly or</span><strong> indirectly</strong><span>, distributes copies of Redistributables as integrated or incorporated into Applications or Devices” (emphasis mine, see definition </span><em>2.4 “End Customer”</em><span> in the </span><a href="https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/qt-dev-framework" rel="">Qt Product and Service Agreement for the Qt Development Framework</a><span>).</span></p><p>I can think of one scenario why The Qt Company included indirect distribution to End Customers in their Device definition. M could use the Qt for Application Development (QtAD) for the development of terminal software and pay only for the per-developer licenses. M sells all of its terminals to a reseller, which is not an Affiliate. The reseller sells the terminals to the End Customers and licenses the Qt software under the LGPL. M and the reseller would save the per-device license fees. Of course, The Qt Company wants to close this loop hole. </p><blockquote><ul><li><p>ii. Applications designed for the hardware devices specified in item (i).</p></li></ul></blockquote><p>Clause (i) covers Qt applications that run on embedded devices. Clause (ii) extends the definition of Devices to cases, where the Qt applications do not run on the Device but on a PC, phone or tablet and where Qt is not even installed on the device.</p><p>For example, a med-tech company MT builds and sells an X-ray scanner for humans, a typical embedded device. Qt is not installed on the scanner. Medical personnel use a Qt application running on a Windows PC to operate the scanner and to evaluate the 3D scans. The PC application and the scanner communicate over a LAN.</p><p>For The Qt Company, the PC application is an application designed for the scanner. Hence, the PC application and the scanner constitute a Device. MT must buy a Qt for Device Creation (QtDC) license and pay license fees for each developer and for each device. Buying only a QtAD license for developing the Qt application on the Windows PC is not enough.</p><p>I have seen The Qt Company apply this reasoning to many of my customers. The Qt Company even claimed that MT would violate the LGPL. Now, that is false! The LGPL considers the PC application and the embedded device as two independent units that are licensed separately.</p><p>Earlier versions of the Qt license agreement contained a clearer definition of clause (ii).</p><blockquote><p>[Products are Devices] regardless of whether the Redistributables are distributed together with the hardware or not.</p><p><span>See “Devices” definition in the </span><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210831204300/https://www.qt.io/terms-conditions/" rel="">2021 version of the Qt license agreement</a></p></blockquote><p>The Qt usage reports still use this definition. Redistributables are the Qt libraries in object code form. In other words, it doesn’t matter whether the Qt application runs on the Device or not.</p><p>I’d like you to meet my pedantic German self, which helps a lot in dissecting contracts. I think that the setup of the med-tech company MT does not constitute a Device in the sense of the Qt license agreement. Clause (ii) refers to “hardware devices specified in item (i)”.</p><p><span>Remember that clause (i) is only satisfied if both clause (i.a) </span><strong>and</strong><span> clause (i.b) are satisfied. Clause (i.b), however, demands that the Qt applications run on the device. As Qt is not installed on the X-ray scanner, clause (i.b) is not satisfied. Hence, clause (i) is not satisfied. Hence, the X-ray scanner is not a device in the sense of the Qt license agreement. Hence, clause (ii) doesn’t apply. </span></p><p>The X-ray scanner would only be a Device, if a Qt application providing “substantial functionality for the device” would run on the Device. Then, clause (ii) would not matter anymore. But don’t get your hopes too high. In the end, a court would have to decide, as The Qt Company would still argue that MT’s setup is a Device. The formulation “Hardware devices or products that […] incorporate, integrate or link to [Qt] Applications” is vague enough to interpret it as follows: The Application can run either on the device or on a PC connected via a network “link”.</p><p>It is safe to assume that most Qt customers don’t have enough negotiation power to change the Devices definition. However, the last sentence of the definition gives them an opening.</p><blockquote><p>Devices covered by this Appendix shall be specified in the Pricing Appendix or Purchase Document.</p></blockquote><p>Qt customers should insist that all the Devices covered by the license agreement are explicitly listed in the Pricing Appendix or Purchase Document. If a Device is not listed, the Qt license agreement (the “Appendix”) does not apply.</p><p><span>Qt customers should also add a list of their products - including the desktop and mobile Qt applications “designed” for embedded devices - that are </span><em>not</em><span> considered Devices. The med-tech company MT would add their PC application and their X-ray scanner to this list.</span></p><p>The modified last sentence of the Devices definition could be written as follows (changes in italics). The Customer’s lawyer should be able to come up with an acceptable formulation.</p><blockquote><p><span>Devices covered by this Appendix </span><em>and Devices not covered by this Appendix </em><span>shall be specified in the Pricing Appendix or Purchase Document. </span><em>During the License Term, the classification as Device or Not-Device can only be changed by mutual agreement of both Parties.</em></p></blockquote><p>I would assume that The Qt Company would require an audit. The customer is free to allow or forbid the audit. I would expect that allowing the audit will increase the changes that The Qt Company signs the agreement. But it is entirely up to the customer.</p><p>Obviously, The Qt Company need not accept this change. Similarly, potential customers need not sign the unchanged agreement either. They can walk away and use Qt under LGPL or don’t use Qt at all. The Qt Company would lose a paying customer. There are good reasons for both parties to come to a mutual agreement.</p><p>According to clause 11.1, The Qt Company has the right to terminate the license agreement, if the Customer “commits a material breach of the Agreement” or if the Customer “becomes bankrupt, insolvent or goes into liquidation or debt restructuring”. A material breach exists, for example, if the customer does not pay in time or not at all, if it sells more Devices than it has distribution licenses or if it fails to provide the usage reports requested by The Qt Company.</p><p>According to clause 11.2, The Qt Company can suspend the customer’s right to use Qt on its Devices or for Development. The Qt Company can, for example, forbid the customer to sell its devices, if the customer doesn’t remedy the violation or breach within 10 days after receiving a written notice from The Qt Company. The reasons for such a suspension go from concrete to vague (emphasis mine).</p><blockquote><p><span>[The Qt Company can suspend the customer’s use of Qt] should Customer fail to make payment in timely fashion or otherwise violate or is </span><em>reasonably suspected of violating its obligations</em><span> under the Agreement and/or this Appendix […]</span></p></blockquote><p>So, if The Qt Company “reasonably suspects” that a customer violates the Qt license agreement, it can forbid the customer to sell or operate its devices. What “reasonably” means is solely decided by The Qt Company - or by a court. However, the customer wouldn’t be allowed to operate its devices until the court decides. You know what customers would do in such situations. So, customers best avoid these situations.</p><p>My recommendation would be to remove the text in italics from clause 11.2:</p><blockquote><p><span>[The Qt Company can suspend the customer’s use of Qt] should Customer fail to make payment in timely fashion or otherwise violate </span><s>or is reasonably suspected of violating its obligations under</s><span> the Agreement and/or this Appendix […]</span></p></blockquote><p>With this change, suspecting a violation is not enough. The Qt Company would have to prove a violation or a material breach. A court could quickly lift an unfounded suspension.</p><p>Again, The Qt Company may accept this change or not. The customer can walk away or not.</p><p>Welcome to the wonderful world of subscriptions, where you subscribe to videos, phones, Internet - and Qt. The License Term will automatically renew, unless the customer notifies The Qt Company in writing “no less than thirty (30) days before expiry of the respective License Term” (see clause 5.1.4). The two parties may agree about a typically longer notification period like 60 days in an amendment to the license agreement. By the way, The Company can terminate the agreement in the same way as the customer.</p><p>Clause 5.1.5 allows both parties to renegotiate the license fees before the renewal. However, the customer should agree on the new license fees before the notification period starts. Otherwise, The Qt Company can charge the “standard list pricing applicable at the commencement date of any such Renewal Term”. And we all know in which direction the prices will move.</p><p>I would recommend Qt customers </p><ul><li><p>either to remove clauses 5.1.4 and 5.1.5 from the license agreement</p></li><li><p>or to notify The Qt Company about the termination one week after the License Term started.</p></li></ul><p>This makes sure that the Qt subscription does not automatically renew.</p><p><strong>Note:</strong><span> Cancelling the subscription in time is the only way to terminate the Qt license agreement for Qt customers.</span></p><p>If Qt customers cancel the Qt subscription in time, they have certain rights and duties upon termination (see section 11.3).</p><ul><li><p><em>Clause 11.3.1.</em><span> The developers of the customer must stop using the Qt tools, Qt libraries, pre-built Boot2Qt images and all other Qt-ware that they downloaded and installed through the Qt Commercial license. They must start using Qt-ware under the open-source licenses: LGPL-3.0 for the libraries and GPL-3.0 for the tools.</span></p></li><li><p><em>Clause 11.3.2. </em><span>The developers must also delete all installed copies of commercial Qt tools and Qt libraries. Qt customer can keep some developer licenses to continue the support of their End Customers. Bug fixing is OK. Adding new features is not OK.</span></p></li><li><p><em>Clause 11.3.3.</em><span> “Distribution Licenses are perpetual”. Qt customers can use existing devices with Qt for Device Creation (QtDC). They can sell devices with QtDC until they have used up all the distribution licenses they have paid for.</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Note</strong><span>: Customers lose the rights from section 11.3, if they committed a material breach of the license agreement.</span></p><p>If you read section 11.3 in the license agreement, you’ll find out that the customers’ duties have been specified pretty clearly, whereas the customers’ rights are more wishy-washy. My summary above is a reasonable interpretation - based on earlier and clearer versions of the Qt license agreement and on usual business practices. </p><p>I recommend Qt customers to make the formulations in section 11.3 clearer and more specific. For example, customers should specify how many developer licenses they may keep, for how long and for which purposes. They should also add that they can use up all the excess licenses they have paid for but not yet sold with their devices.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon tells employees to return to office five days a week (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/09/16/amazon-jassy-tells-employees-to-return-to-office-five-days-a-week.html</link>
            <guid>41558554</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 17:44:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/09/16/amazon-jassy-tells-employees-to-return-to-office-five-days-a-week.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/09/16/amazon-jassy-tells-employees-to-return-to-office-five-days-a-week.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41558554">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/AMZN/">Amazon</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> is instructing corporate staffers to spend five days a week in the office, CEO Andy Jassy <a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/company-news/ceo-andy-jassy-latest-update-on-amazon-return-to-office-manager-team-ratio" target="_blank">wrote in a memo</a> on Monday.</p><p>The decision marks a significant shift from Amazon's <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2023/02/17/amazon-employees-asked-to-be-in-office-three-days-a-week-andy-jassy.html">earlier return-to-work stance</a>, which required corporate workers to be in the office at least three days a week. Now, the company is giving employees until Jan. 2 to start adhering to the new policy.</p><p>Corporate employees will be expected to be in the office five days a week "outside of extenuating circumstances" or unless they have been granted an exception by their organization's S-team leader, Jassy said, referring to the close-knit group of executives that report to Amazon's CEO.</p><p>"Before the pandemic, it was not a given that folks could work remotely two days a week, and that will also be true moving forward — our expectation is that people will be in the office outside of extenuating circumstances," Jassy said.</p><p>Amazon also plans to simplify its corporate structure by having fewer managers in order to "remove layers and flatten organizations," Jassy said. Each S-team organization will be expected to increase the ratio of individual contributors to managers by at least 15% by the end of the first quarter of 2025, he said. Individual contributors refers to employees who typically do not manage other staffers.</p><p>It is unclear if the change will result in the elimination of some manager positions. An Amazon spokesperson did not immediately respond to CNBC's request for comment.</p><p>The company <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/09/09/amazon-is-on-a-hiring-spree-amid-widespread-coronavirus-layoffs-and-record-unemployment.html">rapidly grew its headcount</a> over the course of the pandemic before Jassy took the helm and instituted widespread cost cuts across Amazon, including the largest layoffs in its 27 years as a public company. Amazon's headcount totaled 1.53 million employees <a href="https://s2.q4cdn.com/299287126/files/doc_financials/2024/q2/AMZN-Q2-2024-Earnings-Release.pdf" target="_blank">in the second quarter</a>, representing growth of just 5% from a year earlier. By comparison, Amazon's workforce expanded 14% to 1.52 million employees in the second quarter of 2022.</p><p>Jassy wrote in a lengthy missive to staffers that&nbsp;Amazon&nbsp;is making the changes to strengthen its corporate culture and ensure that it remains nimble. He underscored the point by saying the company created a "bureaucracy mailbox," or dedicated email alias, to root out any unnecessary processes or excessive rules within the company.</p><p>"We want to operate like the world's largest startup," Jassy wrote. "That means having a passion for constantly inventing for customers, strong urgency (for most big opportunities, it's a race!), high ownership, fast decision-making, scrappiness and frugality, deeply-connected collaboration (you need to be joined at the hip with your teammates when inventing and solving hard problems), and a shared commitment to each other."</p><p>Amazon shares ticked lower in afternoon trading.</p><div><p>Hey team. I wanted to send a note on a couple changes we're making to further strengthen our culture and teams.</p><p>First, for perspective, I feel good about the progress we're making together. Stores, AWS, and Advertising continue to grow on very large bases, Prime Video continues to expand, and new investment areas like GenAI, Kuiper, Healthcare, and several others are evolving nicely. And at the same time we're growing and inventing, we're also continuing to make progress on our cost structure and operating margins, which isn't easy to do. Overall, I like the direction in which we're heading and appreciate the hard work and ingenuity of our teams globally.</p><p>When I think about my time at Amazon, I never imagined I'd be at the company for 27 years. My plan (which my wife and I agreed to on a bar napkin in 1997) was to be here a few years and move back to NYC. Part of why I've stayed has been the unprecedented growth (we had $15M of annual revenue the year before I joined—this year should be well north of $600B), the perpetual hunger to invent, the obsession with making customers' lives easier and better every day, and the associated opportunities these priorities present. But, the biggest reason I'm still here is our culture. Being so customer focused is an inspiring part of it, but it's also the people we work with, the way we collaborate and invent when we're at our best, our long-term perspective, the ownership I've always felt at every level I've worked (I started as a Level 5), the speed with which we make decisions and move, and the lack of bureaucracy and politics.</p><p>Our culture is unique, and has been one of the most critical parts of our success in our first 29 years. But, keeping your culture strong is not a birthright. You have to work at it all the time. When you consider the breadth of our businesses, their associated growth rates, the innovation required across each of them, and the number of people we've hired the last 6-8 years to pursue these endeavors, it's pretty unusual—and will stretch even the strongest of cultures. Strengthening our culture remains a top priority for the s-team and me. And, I think about it all the time.</p><p>We want to operate like the world's largest startup. That means having a passion for constantly inventing for customers, strong urgency (for most big opportunities, it's a race!), high ownership, fast decision-making, scrappiness and frugality, deeply-connected collaboration (you need to be joined at the hip with your teammates when inventing and solving hard problems), and a shared commitment to each other.</p><p>Two areas that the s-team and I have been thinking about the last several months are: 1/ do we have the right org structure to drive the level of ownership and speed we desire? 2/ are we set up to invent, collaborate, and be connected enough to each other (and our culture) to deliver the absolute best for customers and the business that we can? We think we can be better on both.</p><p>On the first topic, we've always sought to hire very smart, high judgment, inventive, delivery-focused, and missionary teammates. And, we have always wanted the people doing the actual detailed work to have high ownership. As we have grown our teams as quickly and substantially as we have the last many years, we have understandably added a lot of managers. In that process, we have also added more layers than we had before. It's created artifacts that we'd like to change (e.g., pre-meetings for the pre-meetings for the decision meetings, a longer line of managers feeling like they need to review a topic before it moves forward, owners of initiatives feeling less like they should make recommendations because the decision will be made elsewhere, etc.). Most decisions we make are two-way doors, and as such, we want more of our teammates feeling like they can move fast without unnecessary processes, meetings, mechanisms, and layers that create overhead and waste valuable time.</p><p>So, we're asking each s-team organization to increase the ratio of individual contributors to managers by at least 15% by the end of Q1 2025. Having fewer managers will remove layers and flatten organizations more than they are today. If we do this work well, it will increase our teammates' ability to move fast, clarify and invigorate their sense of ownership, drive decision-making closer to the front lines where it most impacts customers (and the business), decrease bureaucracy, and strengthen our organizations' ability to make customers' lives better and easier every day. We will do this thoughtfully, and our PxT team will work closely with our leaders to evolve our organizations to accomplish these goals over the next few months.</p><p>[By the way, I've created a "Bureaucracy Mailbox" for any examples any of you see where we might have bureaucracy or unnecessary process that's crept in and we can root out…to be clear, companies need process to run effectively, and process does not equal bureaucracy, but unnecessary and excessive process or rules should be called out and extinguished. I will read these emails and action them accordingly.]</p><p>To address the second issue of being better set up to invent, collaborate, and be connected enough to each other and our culture to deliver the absolute best for customers and the business, we've decided that we're going to return to being in the office the way we were before the onset of COVID. When we look back over the last five years, we continue to believe that the advantages of being together in the office are significant. I've previously explained these benefits (February 2023 post), but in summary, we've observed that it's easier for our teammates to learn, model, practice, and strengthen our culture; collaborating, brainstorming, and inventing are simpler and more effective; teaching and learning from one another are more seamless; and, teams tend to be better connected to one another. If anything, the last 15 months we've been back in the office at least three days a week has strengthened our conviction about the benefits.</p><p>Before the pandemic, not everybody was in the office five days a week, every week. If you or your child were sick, if you had some sort of house emergency, if you were on the road seeing customers or partners, if you needed a day or two to finish coding in a more isolated environment, people worked remotely. This was understood, and will be moving forward as well. But, before the pandemic, it was not a given that folks could work remotely two days a week, and that will also be true moving forward—our expectation is that people will be in the office outside of extenuating circumstances (like the ones mentioned above) or if you already have a Remote Work Exception approved through your s-team leader.</p><p>We are also going to bring back assigned desk arrangements in locations that were previously organized that way, including the U.S. headquarters locations (Puget Sound and Arlington). For locations that had agile desk arrangements before the pandemic, including much of Europe, we will continue to operate that way.</p><p>We understand that some of our teammates may have set up their personal lives in such a way that returning to the office consistently five days per week will require some adjustments. To help ensure a smooth transition, we're going to make this new expectation active on January 2, 2025. Global Real Estate and Facilities (GREF) is working on a plan to accommodate desk arrangements mentioned above and will communicate the details as they are finalized.</p><p>I want to thank our leaders and support teams in advance for the work they will do to improve their org structures over the coming months. With a company of our size and complexity, the work won't be trivial and it will test our collective ability to invent and simplify when it comes to how we organize and go after the meaningful opportunities we have across all of our businesses.</p><p>Having the right culture at Amazon is something I don't take for granted. I continue to believe that we are all here because we want to make a difference in customers' lives, invent on their behalf, and move quickly to solve their problems. I'm optimistic that these changes will better help us accomplish these goals while strengthening our culture and the effectiveness of our teams.</p><p>Thanks, Andy</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple Watch sleep apnea detection gets FDA approval (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-watch-sleep-apnea-detection-gets-fda-approval/</link>
            <guid>41557851</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 16:35:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-watch-sleep-apnea-detection-gets-fda-approval/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-watch-sleep-apnea-detection-gets-fda-approval/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41557851">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">The US Food and Drug Administration Monday<a rel="nofollow" href="https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/scripts/cdrh/cfdocs/cfpmn/pmn.cfm?ID=K240929"> published approval</a> for sleep apnea detection on the Apple Watch Series 9, Series 10, and Watch Ultra 2. The green light comes four days ahead of the Series 10’s September 20 release date.</p>

<p>The feature, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/09/apple-is-adding-a-sleep-apnea-detection-feature-to-the-apple-watch-series-10-9-and-ultra-2/">announced at last week’s iPhone 16 event</a>, will arrive as part of the imminent watchOS 11 release. Once enabled, it requires 10 nights of sleep tracking data spread out over a 30-day span to determine whether a user may have the condition. During that time, it also offers insights into nightly sleeping disturbances, utilizing the on-board accelerometer.</p>

	
	


<p>The FDA classes the feature as an “over-the-counter device to assess risk of sleep apnea.” Apple is quick to note that the addition is not a diagnostic tool. Rather, it will prompt users to seek a formal diagnosis from a healthcare provider. The condition, which causes breathing to become shallower or repeatedly stop during the night, is associated with a variety of different symptoms. The Mayo Clinic notes that it can cause insomnia, headaches, daytime sleepiness, and other longer-term conditions.</p>

<p>Apple isn’t the first consumer electronics firm to offer the feature. Withings has offered sleep apnea detection in devices for some time, while Samsung received <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/02/09/samsung-gets-fda-nod-for-smartwatch-sleep-apnea-detection/">FDA approval</a> for its Galaxy Watch line earlier this. </p>

<p>The feature arrives as another — blood oxygen detection — has been disabled on Apple Watches in the U.S. <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/10/apple-watch-blood-oxygen-detection-wont-be-available-on-the-series-10-in-the-u-s/">over an ongoing patent dispute</a>.</p>


</div><div>
<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Amazon CEO Andy Jassy sent a memo to the company’s employees Monday morning, calling for a full return to office at the start of 2025. For the last fifteen months,… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/amazon-mandates-full-five-day-return-to-office/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/amazon-mandates-full-five-day-return-to-office/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?w=430" alt="Amazon mandates full five-day return to office" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/amazon-return-office.jpg?resize=800,450 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Runway, one of several AI startups developing video-generating tech, today announced an API to allow devs and organizations to build the company’s generative AI models into third-party platforms, apps, and… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/runway-announces-an-api-for-its-video-generating-models/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/runway-announces-an-api-for-its-video-generating-models/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?w=430" alt="Runway announces an API for its video-generating AI models" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=1280,853 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/53202681227_9073c8f3dc_k.webp?resize=800,533 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Gogoro, the Taiwanese electric scooter manufacturer and battery swapping giant, said its CEO and chairman Horace Luke has stepped down amid subsidy fraud allegations, according to a regulatory filing. Gogoro… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/gogoro-ceo-resigns-as-subsidy-fraud-investigation-continues/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/gogoro-ceo-resigns-as-subsidy-fraud-investigation-continues/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?w=430" alt="Gogoro CEO resigns as subsidy fraud investigation continues" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Gogoro-horace-luke.png?resize=800,450 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Apple’s newest software update, iOS 18, is rolling out today to all iPhone users. While AI technology was heavily hyped as a key part of this upgrade, Apple Intelligence features… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ios-18-review/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ios-18-review/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?w=430" alt="iOS 18 is out: Here’s what’s new" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg 3840w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=1280,720 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=800,450 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-homescreen-02.jpg?resize=2048,1152 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>On Monday Apple released the new version of iOS, the company’s operating system for the iPhone. iOS 18 is a free download and it works with the iPhone XR &amp;… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ios-18-is-now-available-to-download/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ios-18-is-now-available-to-download/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?w=430" alt="Apple’s iOS 18 is now available to download" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg 3840w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=1280,720 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=800,450 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/wwdc24-ios18-.jpg?resize=2048,1152 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Speaking at an Oracle financial analysts meeting, Oracle CEO Larry Ellison said he expects AI to one day power massive law enforcement surveillance networks. “We’re going to have supervision,” he… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/oracle-ceo-larry-ellison-says-that-ai-will-someday-track-your-every-move/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/oracle-ceo-larry-ellison-says-that-ai-will-someday-track-your-every-move/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?w=430" alt="Oracle CEO Larry Ellison says that AI will someday track your every move" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Ellison-IB.png?resize=800,450 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>The Series A comes about a year after 11xAI raised a $2 million seed round led by Project A Ventures. </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ai-digital-employee-startup-11xai-raises-24m-led-by-benchmark/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ai-digital-employee-startup-11xai-raises-24m-led-by-benchmark/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="323" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?w=430" alt="11xAI raises $24M led by Benchmark to build AI digital employees" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png 2088w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=150,113 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=300,225 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=768,576 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=680,510 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=1200,900 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=1280,960 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=430,323 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=720,540 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=900,675 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=800,600 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=1536,1152 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Hasan-Sukkar-C-and-team.png?resize=2048,1536 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>As TikTok heads to court on Monday to argue against a U.S. ban, parent company ByteDance’s newer social app, Lemon8, is once again surging to the top of the App… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/as-tiktok-ban-heads-to-court-bytedances-lemon8-surges/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/as-tiktok-ban-heads-to-court-bytedances-lemon8-surges/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="221" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?w=430" alt="As TikTok ban heads to court, ByteDance’s Lemon8 surges" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg 1978w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=150,77 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=300,154 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=768,395 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=680,350 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=1200,618 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=1280,659 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=430,221 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=720,371 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=900,463 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=800,412 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/lemon8.jpeg?resize=1536,791 1536w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>This latest round of government sanctions land months after Intellexa’s founder Tal Dilian was sanctioned for selling the Predator spyware. </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/us-government-expands-sanctions-against-spyware-maker-intellexa/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/us-government-expands-sanctions-against-spyware-maker-intellexa/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="241" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?w=430" alt="U.S. government expands sanctions against spyware maker Intellexa&nbsp;" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg 3200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=300,168 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=768,431 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=680,382 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=1200,674 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=1280,719 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=430,241 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=720,404 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=900,505 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=800,449 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=1536,863 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/12/android-spyware2.jpg?resize=2048,1150 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>It’s been three years since Life360’s $205 million acquisition of AirTag competitor Tile. The company announced Monday its new lineup of lost-item Bluetooth trackers, featuring a sleeker redesign in new… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/life360-tile-bluetooth-trackers-new-lineup-since-acquisition/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/life360-tile-bluetooth-trackers-new-lineup-since-acquisition/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?w=430" alt="Life360’s Tile introduces its first new Bluetooth trackers since its acquisition" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Tile-Pink.jpg?resize=800,533 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Typeface, a generative AI startup focused on enterprise use cases, has acquired a pair of companies just over a year after raising $165 million at a $1 billion valuation. Typeface… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/generative-ai-startup-typeface-acquires-two-companies-treat-and-narrato-to-bolster-its-portfolio/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/generative-ai-startup-typeface-acquires-two-companies-treat-and-narrato-to-bolster-its-portfolio/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?w=430" alt="Generative AI startup Typeface acquires two companies, Treat and Narrato, to bolster its portfolio" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg 2121w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=1280,853 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=800,533 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1497617145-1.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Earlier this year, former NFL quarterback and civil rights activist Colin Kaepernick launched his AI startup, Lumi. Kaepernick has had thousands of stories written about him, and he knows a… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/colin-kaepernick-is-coming-to-techcrunch-disrupt-2024/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/colin-kaepernick-is-coming-to-techcrunch-disrupt-2024/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?w=430" alt="Colin Kaepernick is coming to TechCrunch Disrupt 2024" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png 1920w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=1280,720 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=800,450 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Kaepernick_tc_disrupt_2024_speaker-carousel_1920x1080-1-speaker.png?resize=1536,864 1536w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>IBM today launched the Qiskit Functions Catalog, a new set of services that aims to make programming quantum computers easier by abstracting away many of the complexities of working with… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ibm-makes-developing-for-quantum-computers-easier-with-the-qiskit-functions-catalog/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ibm-makes-developing-for-quantum-computers-easier-with-the-qiskit-functions-catalog/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?w=430" alt="IBM makes developing for quantum computers easier with the Qiskit Functions Catalog" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg 4000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=1280,853 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=800,533 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1182902380.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Supermaven, an AI coding assistant, has raised $12 million in a funding round that had participation from OpenAI and Perplexity co-founders. </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ai-coding-assistant-supermaven-raises-cash-from-openai-and-perplexity-founders/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/ai-coding-assistant-supermaven-raises-cash-from-openai-and-perplexity-founders/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?w=430" alt="AI coding assistant Supermaven raises cash from OpenAI and Perplexity co-founders" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg 2309w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=1280,720 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=800,450 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/GettyImages-1325174870.jpg?resize=2048,1152 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Arjun Vora and Tito Goldstein were working on the corporate side of Uber when they realized that HR software largely wasn’t built to manage hourly staff. Many hourly workers lacked… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/teambridge-founded-by-former-uber-execs-sells-hr-software-for-hourly-workers/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/teambridge-founded-by-former-uber-execs-sells-hr-software-for-hourly-workers/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="232" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?w=430" alt="TeamBridge, founded by former Uber execs, raises $28M to build HR software for hourly workers" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg 2000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=150,81 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=300,162 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=768,415 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=680,367 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=1200,648 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=1280,691 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=430,232 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=720,389 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=900,486 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=800,432 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/10/GettyImages-1455881718-1.jpg?resize=1536,829 1536w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>The US Food and Drug Administration Monday published approval for sleep apnea detection on the Apple Watch Series 9, Series 10, and Watch Ultra 2. The green light comes four… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-watch-sleep-apnea-detection-gets-fda-approval/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-watch-sleep-apnea-detection-gets-fda-approval/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="323" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?w=430" alt="Apple Watch sleep apnea detection gets FDA approval" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg 4000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=150,113 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=300,225 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=768,576 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=680,510 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=1200,900 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=1280,960 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=430,323 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=720,540 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=900,675 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=800,600 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=1536,1152 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/PXL_20240909_185346280.jpg?resize=2048,1536 2048w"></a><figcaption><strong>Image Credits:</strong> Brian Heater</figcaption></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	<div>
		<p><strong>Featured Article</strong></p>

		<h2><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-airpods-4-with-active-noise-cancellation-review/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-airpods-4-with-active-noise-cancellation-review/" target="_self">Apple AirPods 4 with Active Noise Cancellation review</a></h2>

		<p>I can’t recall another consumer electronics product category becoming a commodity as quickly as Bluetooth earbuds. Apple’s AirPods played a key role in that growth, of course, recapturing a kind of excitement not seen in consumer music tech since the original iPod. AirPods’ fundamentals haven’t changed much in the eight… </p>

		



		<p><time datetime="2024-09-16T05:00:00-07:00">
	6 hours ago</time>

	</p></div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-airpods-4-with-active-noise-cancellation-review/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/apple-airpods-4-with-active-noise-cancellation-review/" target="_self"><img width="720" height="480" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?w=720" alt="Apple AirPods 4 with Active Noise Cancellation review" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 95vw, (max-width: 1023px) 63vw, (max-width: 1920) 37vw, 720px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg 4464w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=1280,853 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=800,533 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/CMC_7923.jpg?resize=2048,1365 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Myntra, India’s largest fashion e-commerce platform, is trialling a four-hour delivery service in four Indian cities, two sources familiar with the matter told TechCrunch, a dramatic acceleration from its standard… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/myntra-bets-on-4-hour-delivery-amid-indias-quick-commerce-boom/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/myntra-bets-on-4-hour-delivery-amid-indias-quick-commerce-boom/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="260" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?w=430" alt="Myntra bets on 4-hour delivery amid India’s quick commerce boom" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg 1863w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=150,91 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=300,181 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=768,464 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=680,411 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=1200,725 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=1280,773 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=430,260 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=720,435 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=900,543 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=800,483 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/027A60481.jpg?resize=1536,928 1536w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>AWS today announced that it is transitioning OpenSearch, its open source fork of the popular Elasticsearch search and analytics engine, to the Linux Foundation with the launch of the very… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/aws-brings-opensearch-under-the-linux-foundation-umbrella/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/16/aws-brings-opensearch-under-the-linux-foundation-umbrella/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="291" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?w=430" alt="AWS brings OpenSearch under the Linux Foundation umbrella" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg 2105w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=150,102 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=300,203 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=768,520 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=680,460 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=1200,812 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=1280,867 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=430,291 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=720,487 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=900,609 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=800,542 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=1536,1040 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-1437319236.jpg?resize=2048,1386 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Insight Partners is reportedly on the cusp of closing on more than $10 billion in capital commitments for its 13th fund, per the FT.&nbsp; The FT report notes that two… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/insight-partners-is-closing-in-on-a-whopping-10b-new-fund/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/insight-partners-is-closing-in-on-a-whopping-10b-new-fund/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="244" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?w=430" alt="Insight Partners is closing in on a whopping $10B+ new fund" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png 1500w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=150,85 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=300,170 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=768,436 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=680,386 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=1200,682 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=1280,727 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=430,244 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=720,409 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=900,511 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screen-Shot-2024-09-15-at-9.06.51-PM.png?resize=800,454 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>The Port of Seattle released a statement Friday confirming that it was targeted by a ransomware attack. The attack occurred on August 24, with the Port (which also operates the… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/port-of-seattle-shares-ransomware-attack-details/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/port-of-seattle-shares-ransomware-attack-details/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?w=430" alt="Port of Seattle shares ransomware attack details" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/sea-tac-cyberattack.jpg?resize=800,450 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>A decade after the wildly popular game Flappy Bird disappeared, an organization calling itself the Flappy Bird Foundation announced plans to “re-hatch the official Flappy Bird® game.” But this morning,… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/flappy-birds-creator-disavows-official-new-version-of-the-game/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/flappy-birds-creator-disavows-official-new-version-of-the-game/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?w=430" alt="Flappy Bird’s creator disavows ‘official’ new version of the game" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=680,453 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flappy-bird.jpeg?resize=800,533 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Platforms to connect apps that wouldn’t normally talk to each other have been around for a minute (see: Zapier). But they have not gotten dramatically simpler to use if you’re… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/drymerge-promises-to-connect-apps-that-normally-dont-talk-to-each-other-and-when-it-works-its-great/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/drymerge-promises-to-connect-apps-that-normally-dont-talk-to-each-other-and-when-it-works-its-great/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?w=430" alt="DryMerge promises to connect apps that normally don’t talk to each other — and when it works, it’s great" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg 2120w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=680,454 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=1200,800 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=1280,854 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=800,534 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/GettyImages-2067248129.jpg?resize=2048,1366 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/cohere-co-founder-nick-frossts-indie-band-good-kid-is-almost-as-successful-as-his-ai-company/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/cohere-co-founder-nick-frossts-indie-band-good-kid-is-almost-as-successful-as-his-ai-company/" target="_self"><img width="720" height="480" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?w=720" alt="Cohere co-founder Nick Frosst’s indie band, Good Kid, is almost as successful as his AI company" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 95vw, (max-width: 1023px) 63vw, (max-width: 1920) 37vw, 720px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg 1024w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=680,454 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/GettyImages-2165331996.jpg?resize=800,534 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Blockchain technology is all about decentralization and virtualization. So it’s a little ironic that humans love to come together in person at big blockchain events. Such was the case last… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/a-walk-through-the-crypto-jungle-at-korea-blockchain-week/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/15/a-walk-through-the-crypto-jungle-at-korea-blockchain-week/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="287" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?w=430" alt="A walk through the crypto jungle at Korea Blockchain Week" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg 2560w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=680,454 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=1200,801 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=1280,854 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=430,287 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=720,480 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=900,600 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=800,534 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=1536,1025 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/03/shutterstock_168408272.jpg?resize=2048,1366 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>I have a guilty pleasure, and it’s not that I just rewatched “Glee” in its entirety (yes, even the awful later seasons), or that I have read an ungodly amount… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/the-linkedin-games-are-fun-actually/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/the-linkedin-games-are-fun-actually/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?w=430" alt="The LinkedIn games are fun, actually" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Combined-Game-Play-1920x1080-1.webp?resize=800,450 800w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>It’s looking increasingly likely that OpenAI will soon alter its complex corporate structure. Reports earlier this week suggested that the AI company was in talks to raise $6.5 billion at… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/openai-could-shake-up-its-nonprofit-structure-next-year/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/openai-could-shake-up-its-nonprofit-structure-next-year/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="289" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?w=430" alt="OpenAI could shake up its nonprofit structure next year" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg 4000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=150,101 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=300,201 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=768,515 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=680,456 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=1200,805 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=1280,859 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=430,289 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=720,483 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=900,604 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=800,537 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=1536,1031 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Untitled-design.jpg?resize=2048,1374 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Fusion startups have raised $7.1 billion to date, with the majority of it going to a handful of companies.&nbsp; </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/every-fusion-startup-that-has-raised-over-300m/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/every-fusion-startup-that-has-raised-over-300m/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="242" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?w=430" alt="Every fusion startup that has raised over $300M" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg 3000w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=1280,720 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=800,450 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/GettyImages-1455925032.jpg?resize=2048,1152 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Netflix has never quite cracked the talk show formula, but maybe it can borrow an existing hit from YouTube. According to Bloomberg, the streamer is in talks with BuzzFeed to… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/hot-ones-could-add-some-heat-to-netflixs-live-lineup/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/hot-ones-could-add-some-heat-to-netflixs-live-lineup/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="208" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?w=430" alt="‘Hot Ones’ could add some heat to Netflix’s live lineup" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg 1980w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=150,73 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=300,145 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=768,372 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=680,329 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=1200,581 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=1280,619 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=430,208 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=720,348 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=900,435 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=800,387 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hot-ones.jpg?resize=1536,743 1536w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>



<div>
	
	
	

	
	<div>
		<p>Alex Parmley has been thinking about building his latest company, ORNG, since he was working on his last company, Phood.&nbsp; Launched in 2018, Phood was a payments app that let… </p>
	</div>
	

	
	<div>
		<figure><a data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/why-orngs-founder-pivoted-from-college-food-ordering-to-real-time-money-transfer/" data-event="recirculation" data-module="Query" href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/14/why-orngs-founder-pivoted-from-college-food-ordering-to-real-time-money-transfer/" target="_self"><img width="430" height="260" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?w=430" alt="Why ORNG’s founder pivoted from college food ordering to real-time money transfer" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 781px) 28vw, (max-width: 1920px) 23vw, 430px" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg 3275w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=150,91 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=300,181 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=768,464 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=680,411 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=1200,725 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=1280,773 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=430,260 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=720,435 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=900,544 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=800,483 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=1536,928 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/ornj-founder.jpg?resize=2048,1238 2048w"></a></figure>
	</div>
	
</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oracle, it's time to free JavaScript (170 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://javascript.tm/</link>
            <guid>41557383</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 15:56:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://javascript.tm/">https://javascript.tm/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41557383">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>You have long ago abandoned the JavaScript trademark, and it is causing
widespread, unwarranted confusion and disruption.</strong></p>
<p>JavaScript is the world’s most popular programming language, powering websites
everywhere. Yet, few of the millions who program in it realize that JavaScript
is a trademark you, Oracle, control. The disconnect is glaring: JavaScript has
become a general-purpose term used by countless individuals and companies,
independent of any Oracle product.</p>
<p><strong>Oracle’s hold on the JavaScript trademark clearly fits the legal definition of
trademark abandonment</strong>. A previous
<a href="https://tinyclouds.org/trademark">blog post</a> addressed this issue, requesting
that you, Oracle, release the trademark. Unsurpisingly, the request was met with
silence. It is therefore time to take active steps in order to bring the
JavaScript trademark into the public domain, where it belongs.</p>
<h2>Trademark abandonment</h2>
<p>Title 15 of the United States Code, section 1127, states:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>A&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-3344077-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">mark</a>&nbsp;shall
be deemed to be “abandoned” if either of the following occurs:</p>
<ol>
<li>When
its&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-85351-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">use</a>&nbsp;has
been discontinued with intent not to resume
such&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-85351-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">use</a>.
Intent not to resume may be inferred from circumstances. Nonuse for 3
consecutive years shall be prima facie evidence of abandonment.
“<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-85351-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">Use</a>”
of
a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-3344077-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">mark</a>&nbsp;means
the bona
fide&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-85351-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">use</a>&nbsp;of
such&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-3344077-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">mark</a>&nbsp;made
in the ordinary course of trade, and not made merely to reserve a right in
a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-3344077-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">mark</a>.</li>
<li>When any course of conduct of the owner, including acts of omission as well
as commission, causes
the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-3344077-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">mark</a>&nbsp;to
become the generic name for the goods or services on or in connection with
which it is used or otherwise to lose its significance as
a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/definitions/uscode.php?width=840&amp;height=800&amp;iframe=true&amp;def_id=15-USC-3344077-1913738695&amp;term_occur=999&amp;term_src=">mark</a>.
Purchaser motivation shall not be a test for determining abandonment under
this paragraph.</li>
</ol>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>In the case of JavaScript, both criteria apply</strong>.</p>
<h2>Netscape, Sun, Oracle</h2>
<p>The JavaScript trademark is currently held by Oracle America, Inc.
(<a href="https://tsdr.uspto.gov/#caseNumber=75026640&amp;caseSearchType=US_APPLICATION&amp;caseType=DEFAULT&amp;searchType=statusSearch">US Serial Number: 75026640, US Registration Number: 2416017</a>).
How did this come to be?</p>
<p>In 1995, Netscape partnered with Sun Microsystems to create interactive
websites. Brendan Eich famously spent only 10 days creating the first version of
JavaScript, a dynamic programming language with a rough syntactic lineage from
Sun’s Java language. As a result of this partnership, Sun held the JavaScript
trademark. In 2009, Oracle acquired Sun Microsystems and the JavaScript
trademark as a result.</p>
<p>The trademark is simply a relic of this acquisition. Neither Sun nor Oracle has
ever built a product using the mark. Legal staff, year after year, have renewed
the trademark without question. It’s likely that only a few within Oracle even
know they possess the JavaScript trademark, and even if they do, they likely
don’t understand the frustration it causes within the developer community.</p>
<h2>Use it or lose it</h2>
<p><strong>Oracle has abandoned the JavaScript trademark through nonuse.</strong></p>
<p>Oracle has never seriously offered a product called JavaScript. In the 1990s and
early 2000s, Netscape Navigator, which supported JavaScript as a browser
feature, was a key player. However, Netscape’s usage and influence faded by
2003, and the browser saw its final release in 2008. JavaScript, meanwhile,
evolved into a widely used, independent programming language, embedded in
multiple browsers, entirely separate from Oracle.</p>
<p>The most recent
<a href="https://tsdr.uspto.gov/#caseNumber=75026640&amp;caseSearchType=US_APPLICATION&amp;caseType=DEFAULT&amp;searchType=statusSearch">specimen</a>,
filed with the USPTO in 2019, references <a href="http://nodejs.org/">nodejs.org</a> (a
project created by Ryan Dahl, the author of this letter) and Oracle’s
<a href="https://www.oracle.com/webfolder/technetwork/jet/index.html">JavaScript Extension Toolkit (JET)</a>.
But Node.js is not an Oracle product, and JET is merely a set of JavaScript
libraries for Oracle services, particularly Oracle Cloud. There are millions of
JavaScript libraries; JET is not special.</p>
<p>(Oracle is not even a member of the OpenJS Foundation - the body that the
Node.js project lives under now. Nor does Oracle have any involvement whatsoever
in the development of Node.js.)</p>
<p>Oracle also offers <a href="https://www.oracle.com/java/graalvm/">GraalVM</a>, a JVM that
can execute JavaScript, among other languages. But GraalVM is far from a
canonical JavaScript implementation; engines like V8, JavaScriptCore, and
SpiderMonkey hold that role. GraalVM’s product page doesn’t even mention
“JavaScript”; you must dig into the documentation to find its support.</p>
<p><strong>Oracle’s use of JavaScript in GraalVM and JET does not reflect genuine use of
the trademark.</strong> These weak connections do not satisfy the requirement for
consistent, real-world use in trade.</p>
<h2>A generic term</h2>
<p>A mark can also be considered abandoned if it becomes a generic term.</p>
<p>In 1996, Netscape
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/19981203070212/http://cgi.netscape.com/newsref/pr/newsrelease289.html">announced</a>
a meeting of the ECMA International standards organization to standardize the
JavaScript programming language. Sun (now Oracle), refused to give up the
“JavaScript” mark for this use though, so it was decided that the language would
be called “ECMAScript” instead. (Microsoft happily offered up “JScript”, but
no-one else wanted that.) Brendan Eich, the creator of JavaScript and a
co-signatory of this letter,
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200621202321/https://mail.mozilla.org/pipermail/es-discuss/2006-October/000133.html">wrote in 2006</a>
that “<em>ECMAScript was always an unwanted trade name that sounds like a skin
disease</em>.”</p>
<p>Ecma International formed TC39, a technical steering committee, which publishes
ECMA-262, the specification for JavaScript. This committee includes participants
from all major browsers, like Google’s Chrome, Apple’s Safari, and Mozilla’s
Firefox, as well as representatives from server-side JavaScript runtimes like
Node.js and Deno.</p>
<p>Oracle’s ownership of the JavaScript trademark only causes confusion. The term
“JavaScript” is used freely by millions of developers, companies, and
organizations around the world, with no interference from Oracle. Oracle has
done nothing to assert its rights over the JavaScript name, likely because they
do not believe their claim to the mark would hold up in court. Unlike typical
trademark holders who protect their trademarks by extracting licensing fees or
enforcing usage restrictions, Oracle has allowed the JavaScript name to be used
by anyone. This inaction further supports the argument that the trademark has
lost its significance and has become generic.</p>
<p>Programmers working with JavaScript have formed innumerable community
organizations. These organizations, like the standards bodies, have been forced
to painstakingly avoid naming the programming language they are built around—for
example, <a href="https://jsconf.com/">JSConf</a>. Sadly, without risking a legal trademark
challenge against Oracle, there can be no “JavaScript Conference” nor a
“JavaScript Specification.” The world’s most popular programming language cannot
even have a conference in its name.</p>
<p><strong>There is a vast misalignment between the trademark’s ownership and its
widespread, generic use</strong>.</p>
<h2>Free the mark</h2>
<p><strong>By law, a trademark is abandoned if it is either not used or becomes a generic
term. Both apply to JavaScript.</strong></p>
<p>It’s time for the USPTO to end the JavaScript trademark and recognize it as a
generic name for the world’s most popular programming language, which has
multiple implementations across the industry.</p>
<p>Oracle, you likely have no real business interest in the mark. It’s renewed
simply because legal staff are obligated to renew all trademarks, regardless of
their relevance or use.</p>
<p>We urge you to release the mark into the public domain. However, asking nicely
has been <a href="https://tinyclouds.org/trademark">tried before</a>, and it was met with
silence. If you do not act, we will challenge your ownership by filing a
petition for cancellation with the USPTO.</p>
<div>

<h2>To you, the readers of this letter:</h2>
<p>If you agree with us, you are encouraged to sign this open letter below. Your
support will help raise awareness and add weight to this cause. If you want to
sign as an organization (minimum 25 employees), please email
<a href="mailto:companies@javascript.tm">companies@javascript.tm</a>.</p>
<p>In addition, we’re seeking pro bono assistance from lawyers with experience in
trademark law to help file
a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.uspto.gov/trademarks/ttab/initiating-new-proceeding">Petition for Trademark Cancellation</a>&nbsp;with
the USPTO. It’s likely that simply asking nicely will not get a response from
Oracle; a legal challenge must be made. Reach out
to&nbsp;<a href="mailto:lawyers@javascript.tm">lawyers@javascript.tm</a>&nbsp;if you can help.</p>
</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Launch HN: Silurian (YC S24) – Simulate the Earth (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41556519</link>
            <guid>41556519</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 14:32:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41556519">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="41556877"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556877" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556877&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Can we help you?
We build the equivalent for land, as a non-profit. It's basically a geo Transformer MAE model (plus DINO, plus matrioska, plus ...), but largest and most trained (35 trillion pixels roughly). Most importantly fully open source and open license. I'd love to help you replace land masks with land embeddings, they should significantly help downscale the local effects (e.g. forest versus city) that afaik most weather forecast simplify with static land cover classes at most. <a href="https://github.com/Clay-foundation/model">https://github.com/Clay-foundation/model</a></p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557247"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557545"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557545" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557545&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Maybe between the two of you, you can tell me why my Alexa is telling me there’s no rain today, but it’s raining right now.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557650"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557650" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557650&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>You'll need to subscribe to Alexa weather plus, for only 9.99$/month.
Now seriously, yes, hyperlocal short-term weather forecast should be a commodity, even public utility?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="41556860"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556860" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556860&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Silurian builds foundation models to simulate the Earth, starting with the weather.</p><p>What else do you hope to simulate, if this becomes successful?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557152"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557152" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557152&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>We want to branch out to industries which are highly dependent on weather. That way we can integrate their data together with our core competency: the weather and climate. Some examples include the energy grid, agriculture, logistics, and defense.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557387"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557387" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557387&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The actual killer thing would be flooding.  Insurance has invested billions into trying to simulate risk here and models are still relatively weak.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557125"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557310"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41557420"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557420" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557420&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Does anyone predict economy/population/... by simulating individual people based on real census information? Monte carlo simulation of major events (births, death, ...) based on known statistics based on age, economic background, location, education, profession, etc.? It seems there are not that many people that this would be computationally infeasible, and states and companies have plenty of data to feed into such systems. Is it not needed because other alternatives give better results, or is it already being done?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557674"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557674" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557674&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Doyne Farmer's group at Oxford does 'agent-based' economics simulations in this vein. He has a new book called 'Making Sense of Chaos' that describes it.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557520"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557520" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557520&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I’m also super interested in this kind of question. The late Soviet Union and their cybernetics research were really into simulating this kind of stuff to improve the planned economy. But I’m curious if something like this can be done on a more local scale, to improve things like a single company output.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41557376"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557376" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557376&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Curious to see what other things you will simulate in the future!</p><p>Shameless plug: recently we've built a demo that allows you to search for objects in San Francisco using natural language. You can look for things like Tesla cars, dry patches, boats, and more. Link: <a href="https://demo.bluesight.ai/" rel="nofollow">https://demo.bluesight.ai/</a></p><p>We've tried using Clay embeddings but we quickly found out that they perform poorly for similarity search compared to embeddings produced by CLIP fine tuned on OSM captions (SkyScript).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557706"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557706" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557706&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>howdy!  Clay makers here. Can you share more? Did you try Clay v1 or v0.2
What image size embeddings from what instrument?</p><p>We did try to relate OSM tags to Clay embeddings, but it didn't scale well. We did not give up, but we are re-considering ( <a href="https://github.com/Clay-foundation/earth-text">https://github.com/Clay-foundation/earth-text</a> ). I think SatClip plus OSM is a better approach. or LLM embeddings mapped to Clay embeddings...</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41556642"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556642" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556642&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Astonishingly, this approach, done correctly, produces better forecasts than traditional simulations of the physics of our atmosphere.</p><p>It seems like this is another instance of The Bitter Lesson, no?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556775"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41556882"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556882" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556882&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I'm not sure I buy The Bitter Lesson, tbh.</p><p>Deep Blue wasn't a brute-force search. It did rely on heuristics and human knowledge of the domain to prune search paths. We've always known we could brute-force search the entire space but weren't satisfied with waiting until the heat death of the universe for the chance at an answer.</p><p>The advances in machine learning do use various heuristics and techniques to solve particular engineering challenges in order to solve more general problems. It hasn't all come down to Moore's Law.. which stopped bearing large fruit some time ago.</p><p>However that still comes at a cost. It requires a lot of GPUs, land, energy, and fresh water, and Freon for cooling. We'd prefer to use less of these resources if possible while still getting answers in a reasonable amount of time.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557275"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557275" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557275&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Deep blue had to use the techniques it did due to the limitations of the hardware of the time. Deep blue would almost certainly lose against AlphaZero, even if you tuned it to modern hardware. All you have to do 'manually' is teach it the rules/give it a loss function, then you just let it do its thing.</p><p>It's certainly true that "just throw a bunch of GPUs at it" is wasteful, but it does achieve results.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557560"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557560" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557560&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Certainly does! We’ve had expert systems and various AI techniques for decades that weren’t efficient enough to run even though theoretically they would yield answers.</p><p>And even though solutions to many such problems were in the NP or NP-hard categories it didn’t mean that we couldn’t get useful results.</p><p>But it still gave us better results by applying what we know about search strategies and reinforcement to provide guidance and heuristics. Even Alpha didn’t use the most general algorithms and throw hardware at the problem. Still took quite a lot of specialized software and methods to fine-tune the overall system to produce the results we want.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41556900"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556900" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556900&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Yes, it seems like it. Although I would imagine the features and architecture of the model still take <i>some</i> physics into account. You can't just feed weather data into an LLM, after all.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557066"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41557570"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557570" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557570&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>That's a highly controversial claim that would need a whole host of published peer-reviewed research papers to support it.  Physics-based simulations (initial state input, then evolve according to physics applied to grids) have improved but not really because of smaller grids, but rather by running several dozen different models and then providing the average (and the degree of convergence) as the forecast.</p><p>Notably forecast skill is quantifiable, so we'd need to see a whole lot of forecast predictions using what is essentially the stochastic modelling (historical data) approach.  Given the climate is steadily warming with all that implies in terms of water vapor feedback etc., it's reasonable to assume that historical data isn't that great a guide to future behavior, e.g. when you start having 'once every 500 year' floods every decade, that means the past is not a good guide to the future.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41557396"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557396" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557396&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Is the plan to expand from weather forecasting into climate simulation? Given the complexity of the finding initial conditions on the earth, a non-physical (or only implicitly-physical) model seems like it could offer a very promising alternative to physical models. The existing physical models, while often grossly correct (in terms of averages), suffer from producing unphysical configurations on a local basis.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557631"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557631" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557631&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Yes, 100%! We'll still take a statistical/distributional approach to long-ranged climate behavior rather than trying to predict exact atmospheric states. Keep an eye out for more news on this</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41557575"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557575" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557575&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>So ChatGPT has a cutoff date on the stuff it can talk about. This predicting weather sounds like ChatGPT being able to predict next week's news from which it has been trained on. I can see how it can probably predict some stuff like Argentina winning a football match scheduled for next week when played against India given India sucks at football. But can it really give any useful predictions? Like can it predict things which are not public? Like who will Joe Rogan interview in 2 weeks? Or what would be the blog post that PG will write in two weeks?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557656"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557656" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557656&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Sure, not every model is an autoregressive transformer. And even a GPT could give some useful predictions if you stuff the context window with things it's been fine tuned to predict. We did that to get GPT to play chess a few years ago.</p><p>Specifically, I could imagine throwing current weather data at the model and asking it what it thinks the next most likely weather change is going to be. If it's accurate at all, then that could be done on any given day without further training.</p><p>The problems happen when you start throwing data at it that it wasn't trained on, so it'll be a cat and mouse game. But it's one I think the cat can win, if it's persistent enough.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557719"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557731"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557731" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557731&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>In India we use Natural Intelligence - Astrology - for predicting results. Note that it has high percentage of hallucinations.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41556611"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556945"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556945" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556945&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Hi, Nikhil here. We haven't done a head-to-head comparison of GFT vs GraphCast, but our internal metrics show GFT improves on Aurora and published metrics show Aurora improves on GraphCast. You can see some technical details in section 6 of the Aurora paper (<a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.13063" rel="nofollow">https://arxiv.org/pdf/2405.13063</a>)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41556794"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556794" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556794&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Have you had a crack at applying this approach to the effectively unforecastable - earthquakes, for example?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557609"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557072"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557072" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557072&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Are you planning on open sourcing your code and/or model weights?  Aurora code and weights were recently open sourced.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557692"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557692" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557692&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>How accurate is the weather prediction for a city for tomorrow on average for the min and max temperature? Thanks a lot!</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41556676"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556676" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556676&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I'm hoping the singularity will coincide with a large-scale AI achieving simulated Earth consciousness. Human intelligence is only a spec compared to all the combined intelligence of nature.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556767"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556815"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556815" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556815&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>All of this AGI/singularity stuff is quite literally science fiction, so it can be whatever OP wants it to be.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41556987"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557015"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557776"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557776" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557776&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I'm finding the posts confusing -- is the prediction the images?</p><p>What exactly is predicted and what is the actual path in those videos?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="41557335"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557335" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557335&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Exciting idea and seems like a well-proven team. Good luck to you guys here and don't mind the endemic snark in the other threads. A couple basic questions --</p><p>1. How will you handle one-off events like volcanic eruptions for instance? 
2. Where do you start with this too? Do you pitch a meteorology team? Is it like a "compare and see for yourself"?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557253"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557253" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557253&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Wow, so excited for this.</p><p>I had a web app online in 2020-22 called Skim Day that predicted skimboarding conditions on California beaches that was mostly powered by weather APIs. The tide predictions were solid, but the weather itself was almost never right, especially wind speed. Additionally there were some missing metrics like slope of beach which changes significantly throughout the year and is very important for skimboarding.</p><p>Basically, I needed AI. And this looks incredible. Love your website and even the name and concept of "Generative Forecasting Transformer (GFT)" - very cool. I imagine the likes of Surfline, The Weather Channel, and NOAA would be interested to say the least.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41556768"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41556768" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41556768&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Am skeptical about the business case for this given the huge government investment in part of this.</p><p>What will your differentiators be?</p><p>Are you paying for weather data products?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557160"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557160" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557160&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Better on some dimension will work. More accurate, faster, more fine grained, something.</p><p>Better weather predictions are worth money, plain and simple.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41556887"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556969"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556996"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557081"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557081" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557081&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I’m confused by this thread. The posters have mentioned that they are building their own foundation model for climate/weather prediction and are using a well known open source tool in the field for viz. Where’s the ambiguity here?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557032"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557032" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557032&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This is the visualization tool they use. They generate the data that feeds into that visualization</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557019"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557019" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557019&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I suggest you read the post. Reading is typically how information is transmitted.</p><p>EDIT: the post I am responding to was altered to sound much less confrontational. It was originally:</p><p>&gt; So what exactly are you “launching” and why does it require venture capital?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557034"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557034" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557034&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Alright, what they presented, in the current state, is just a clone of a 10 year old project with a  2.5 month old weather forecast and some AI story attached to it.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557114"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557114" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557114&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The project this “cloned” is just a data visualization tool. You can plug any data into it - good data, bad data.</p><p>They are launching an AI model which they claim produces higher quality weather data than traditional models relying on physical simulation. And they used this visualization library to make an engaging website.</p><p>Constructively, you have gotten to this position by overreacting to a perceived “clone” and failing to be enlightened by the numerous comments and the original post explaining the purpose.</p><p>Respectfully, I suggest you take a breath and try to disassociate from whatever emotional reaction you are having about this.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557109"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557109" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557109&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Silurian builds foundation models to simulate the Earth, starting with the weather.</p><p>It's the first line man. The visual is just a visual, their product is the data being visualized.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                    <tr id="41556984"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41557010"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="41556932"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41556950"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557009"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557009" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557009&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>You went to the effort of posting 2 HN comments, tweeting, and taking a screenshot because you are annoyed that this project used an open-source library and were transparent about doing so.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557018"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557133"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557133" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557133&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>A ripoff of the visualization layer? Even if it was, who cares? That's not the work. What's next, you think a new chess engine is a ripoff because they use a standard chess board for visualization? A new protein prediction model is a ripoff because they use the standard visualization?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557183"><td></td></tr>
                                          <tr id="41557158"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557158" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557158&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I don’t think I understand what your issue is with them. They used an open-source project to visualize their data, were open about doing so, and cited the creator of the project.</p><p>What more did you want from them? (Genuine question.)</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557412"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557412" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557412&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>something within the interface that more clearly illustrates their product differentiation.</p><p>nullschool is obscure enough to the general audience that when I saw it there was an immediate red flag.</p><p>If only specialized scientists can see the difference between the sites, it's a presentation problem.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557636"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557636" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557636&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The interface in question is the second link in the post. To get to the interface without any of the other relevant context, you would have to:</p><p>- skip reading the post (which explains all of this)</p><p>- skip the first link in the post (which explains all of this)</p><p>- go straight to the second link in the post, to the interface</p><p>- skip the "about" link in the interface (which explains all of this)</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557708"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="41557509"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_41557509" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=41557509&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D41556519"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I was able to determine what this is, and I’m not a specialized scientist. I merely exercised the discipline to read the post before reacting and commenting.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="41557599"><td></td></tr>
                                    </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stephen Fry – AI: A Means to an End or a Means to Our End? (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stephenfry.substack.com/p/ai-a-means-to-an-end-or-a-means-to</link>
            <guid>41556195</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 14:04:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stephenfry.substack.com/p/ai-a-means-to-an-end-or-a-means-to">https://stephenfry.substack.com/p/ai-a-means-to-an-end-or-a-means-to</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41556195">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>Thank you all so much.</p><p>So many questions. The first and perhaps the most urgent is … by what right do I stand before you and presume to lecture an already distinguished and knowledgeable crowd on the subject of Ai and its meaning, its bright promise and/or/exclusiveOR its dark threat? Well, perhaps by no greater right than anyone else, but no lesser. We’ll come to whose voices are the most worthy of attention later.</p><p><span>I have been interested in the subject of Artificial Intelligence since around the mid-80s when I was fortunate enough to encounter the so-called father of Ai, Marvin Minsky and to read his book </span><em>The Society of Mind.</em><span> Intrigued, I devoured as much as I could on the subject, learning about the expert systems and “bundles of agency” that were the vogue then, and I have followed the subject with enthusiasm and gaping wonder ever since. But, I promise you, that makes me neither expert, sage nor oracle. For if you are preparing yourselves to hear wisdom, to witness and receive insight this evening, to bask and bathe in the light of prophecy, clarity and truth, then it grieves me to tell you that you have come to the wrong shop. You will find little of that here, for you must know that you are being addressed this evening by nothing more than an ingenuous simpleton, a naive fool, a ninny-hammer, an addle-pated oaf, a dunce, a dullard and a double-dyed dolt. But before you streak for the exit, bear in mind that so are we all, all of us bird-brained half-wits when it comes to this subject, no matter what our degrees, doctorates and decades of experience. I can perhaps congratulate myself, or at least console myself, with the fact that I am at least aware of my idiocy. This is not fake modesty designed to make me come across as a Socrates. But that great Athenian did teach us that our first step to wisdom is to realise and confront our folly.</span></p><p><span>I’ll come to the proof of how and why I am so boneheaded in a moment, but before I go any further I’d like to paint some pictures. Think of them as </span><em>tableaux vivants</em><span> played onto a screen at the back of your mind. We’ll return to them from time to time. Of course I could have </span><em>generated</em><span> these images from Midjourney or Dall-E or similar and projected them behind me, but the small window of time in which it was amusing and instructive for speakers to </span><em>use</em><span> Ai as an entertaining trick for talks </span><em>concerning</em><span> Ai has thankfully closed. You’re actually going to have to use your brain’s own generative latent diffusion skills to summon these images.</span></p><p>Image 1: Picture the human family at the seaside, our backs to the ocean, building sand castles, playing beach cricket, having a fine time in the sun. Behind us, unseen on the horizon, huge currents are converging, separate but each feeding and swelling the others to form one unimaginably colossal tsunami. These are the currents of quantum computing, of genomics and gene editing, of bio-augmentation and bionics, of duplex brain-machine interfacing, of robotics, of new materials (graphene, perovskite, carbon nano-tubes, self-healing polymers, many others), and of course, the most swollen current of all — the technologies and processes behind what we call Artificial Intelligence.</p><p>I summoned this image of the tsunami on the horizon in a talk I gave on Ai seven years ago at the Hay-on-Wye literary festival. I thought maybe we should turn around and at least get a sense of what was coming. But it was too early and the tidal wave seemed too far away. I did suggest that the best thing that could happen would be for universities, professions and businesses to take a year off to realign their courses and syllabuses and recalibrate their teaching, staffing, training and examination practices in preparation for what was coming. A ridiculous suggestion obviously. But in fact, bizarrely and spookily, that Wuhan wet market in 2019 provided exactly such an opportunity. Not that any institution did take advantage of the Covid years of course. After all Chat GPT wasn’t yet launched and a tipping point in public awareness hadn’t been reached.</p><p>The second picture to keep in your mind: we are in a field in the rural heart of the Cotswolds, just outside the village of Kemble in Gloucestershire. The grass is strangely wet and marshy beneath our feet: there is a small bubbling spring, which trickles into a stream that runs down the field and out of sight. A stone marker reads: “This stone was placed here to mark the source of the River Thames.”</p><p><span>Image 3: The third picture to fix in our heads takes us off to the German town of Mannheim in 1895. We are gathered in a converted stable belonging to an enterprising fellow called Karl Benz. He is anxious to show us his new invention, an engine that he calls his </span><em>verbrennungsmotor</em><span>. This device is attached to a slightly modified horse carriage. Herr Benz tells us that his engine is powered, not by steam, but by a very newly available hydrocarbon product that the French are calling </span><em>essence</em><span>, the Americans ‘gasoline’ and we British ‘petroleum spirits’ or ‘petrol’ for short. Benz cranks a handle. There is sputtering, banging and much smoke. He runs round, sits himself in the carriage, pulls some levers, turns some knobs and … the strange machine lurches a little before juddering slowly forward. We follow him out of the garage where he comes to a stop, beaming proudly in a cloud of oily blue smoke.</span></p><p><span>Now, you and I are in that group. What do we say? Most of us smile and shake our heads. Yes, very impressive no doubt, but what kind of </span><em>range</em><span> does such a machine have compared to a horse? Where is the infrastructure to operate, feed and maintain it that can compete with the stables, the coaching inns, the water troughs and feeding stations that already proliferate? Where the trained ostlers, grooms and coach builders to operate and maintain these horseless carriages? Where the roadways that can compete with railways?</span></p><p>A few in our group might concede that a limited market of rich hobbyists could have fun with these machines. But we can guarantee this: that not one single person would declaim — “Yes! I foresee interstate highways three or four lanes wide crisscrossing the nations, I foresee flyovers, bypasses, Grand Prix motor racing, traffic lights, roundabouts, parking structures ten, twenty storeys high, traffic wardens, whole towns and cities entirely shaped by these contrivances.” No one would have seen a thousandth part of such a future.</p><p>You may have noticed that the last two images I have tried to conjure are, in essence, the same. The gathering in Mannheim is pretty much identical in its form and meaning to the gathering at Thames Head, Kemble where the rill begins its journey. You surely could not, never having seen its final destination, imagine that the dribble in Kemble would become mighty Father Thames processing under grand London bridges as he flows broadly to his estuary in Essex, any more than you could imagine that the belching and wheezing contraption of Benz’s would transform the twentieth century, or indeed that the company he founded, with the addition of the name of one of his investors’ daughters, Mercedes, would one day be worth the best part of 100 billion dollars.</p><p><span>An important and relevant point is this: it wasn’t so much the genius of Benz that created the internal combustion engine, as that of Vladimir Shukhov. In 1892, the Russian chemical engineer found a way of cracking and refining the spectrum of crude oil from methane to tar yielding amongst other useful products, gasoline. It was just three years after that that Benz’s contraption spluttered into life. Germans, in a bow to this, still call petrol </span><em>Benzin</em><span>. John D. Rockefeller built his refineries and surprisingly quickly there was plentiful fuel and an infrastructure to rival the stables and coaching inns; the grateful horse meanwhile could be happily retired to gymkhanas, polo and royal processions.</span></p><p><span>Benz’s contemporary Alexander Graham Bell once said of </span><em>his</em><span> invention, the telephone, “I don’t think I am being overconfident when I say that I truly believe that one day there will be a telephone in every town in America.” And I expect you all heard that Thomas Watson, the founding father of IBM, predicted that there might in the future be a world market for perhaps five digital computers.</span></p><p><span>Well, that story of Thomas Watson ever saying such a thing is almost certainly apocryphal. There’s no reliable record of it. Ditto the Alexander Graham Bell remark. But they circulate for a reason. The Italians have a phrase for that: </span><em>se non e vero, e ben trovato</em><span>. ‘If it’s not true, it’s well founded.’ Those stories, like my scenario of that group of early investors and journalists clustering about the first motorcar, illustrate an important truth: that we are decidedly hopeless at guessing where technology is going to take us and what it’ll do to us.</span></p><p><span>You might adduce as a counterargument Gordon Moore of Intel expounding in 1965 his prediction that semiconductor design and manufacture would develop in such a way that every eighteen months or so they would be able to double the number of transistors that could fit in the same space on a microchip. “He got that right,” you might say, “Moore’s Law came true. He saw the future.” Yes … but. Where and when did Gordon Moore foresee Facebook, TikTok, YouTube, Bit Coin, OnlyFans and the Dark Web? It’s one thing to predict how technology changes, but quite another to predict how it changes </span><em>us</em><span>.</span></p><p>Technology is a verb, not a noun. It is a constant process, not a settled entity. It is what the philosopher-poet T. E. Hulme called a concrete flux of interpenetrating intensities; like a river it is ever cutting new banks, isolating new oxbow lakes, flooding new fields. And as far as the Thames of Artificial Intelligence is concerned, we are still in Gloucestershire, still a rivulet not yet a river. Very soon we will be asking round the dinner table, “Who remembers ChatGPT?” and everyone will laugh. Older people will add memories of dot matrix printers and SMS texting on the Nokia 3310. We’ll shake our heads in patronising wonder at the past and its primitive clunkiness. “How advanced it all seemed at the time …”</p><p>Those of us who can kindly be designated early adopters and less kindly called suckers remember those pioneering days with affection. The young internet was the All-Gifted, which in Greek is Pandora. Pandora in myth was sent down to earth having been given by the gods all the talents. Likewise the Pandora internet: a glorious compendium of public museum, library, gallery, theatre, concert hall, park, playground, sports field, post office and meeting hall.</p><p><span>We felt like Wordsworth perhaps, “Bliss was it in that dawn to be alive, but to be young was very heaven!” But we should remember that those lines come from a poem about the French Revolution which may have </span><em>begun</em><span> in romantic promise, but ended in corruption, terror and blood — not to mention, in short order, a man called Napoleon seizing power and crowning himself Emperor.</span></p><p>I said I would come to the proof of that stupidity and naivety I accused myself of. I’ll take you back fifteen or so years to a time when I found myself being invited to a perfectly extraordinary number of corporate, governmental and media talks, conferences, summits and suchlike gatherings. I would be asked to address delegates and attendees on the subject of a new microblogging service that had only recently poked its timorous head up in the digital world like a delicate flower but was already twisting and winding itself round the culture like vigorous bindweed. Twitter it was called. I had joined early and my name seemed permanently associated with it. What an evangel I was. Web 2.0, the user-generated web, was going great guns at this point. Tick off the years. 2003 MySpace began. 2004 Facebook launched. 2005 YouTube. 2006 Twitter. 2007 the iPhone. 2008 the App Store and later that year, Android and then Instagram. Bliss was it in that dawn, etc. etc. I confidently predicted that this new kind of citizen-led computer and internet use would help build a brave and beautiful new world. “Local and global rivalries will dissolve,” I said. “Tribal hatreds will melt away. Surely,” I cried, “Twitter and Facebook and this new world of ‘social media’ will usher in an age of universal brotherhood and amity.” Two years later as Tunisia, Libya, Egypt, Yemen and Syria rose against their dictators, the Arab Spring bloomed. How right I had been. How clever and percipient I was.</p><p>But…</p><p>Just a year or so on and that blissful dawn had turned into the darkest of nights. Libya leapt out of the frying pan of Gaddafi into the fire of anarchy and chaos, Egypt into a military coup, Yemen into brutal civil war, Syria into a bloodbath. Elsewhere — Brexit, Trump, TikTok, COVID, the rise of nationalist populism and populist nationalism, state sanctioned and criminal cyber terrorism, epidemics of anxiety, depression and self-harm amongst our children and young adults, and a cloud of disappointment, pessimism, mistrust and despair over us all. Pandora had opened her box and the ugly horrors had flown out to infect us all. With Hope left trapped inside.</p><p>Welcome to today.</p><p><span>As Mark Twain or somebody like him said, “history may not repeat itself but it rhymes” and, hilariously enough, just like the French Revolution, the Twitter revolution also ended with a little Napoleon seizing power and crowning himself Emperor, a little Napol</span><em>Elon</em><span> I should say…</span></p><p>I must go back and correct the images I evoked earlier. I now realise that tableau of us sitting with our backs to the oceans while a tidal wave gathers is not correct. When the waves of technology come, they come not in crashing tsunamis but in creeping tides. In my homeland of Norfolk we have long and deceptively rapid tidal reaches. We look to the horizon and see that the ocean is half a mile away. We turn to slap on some suncream. A minute or so later we notice that our feet are wet. Before we know it a familiar landscape has become a seascape and we are cut off from everything we know.</p><p><span>The other image I should correct is that of technology starting small and becoming a broad and splendid river. Yes, we can envisage the expansion of the first trickle into a wide and powerful waterway, perhaps we envisage too the curves and cataracts, those oxbow lakes and sluices and the weeping willows and dragonflies kissing the current, but we are criminally foolish if we talk of rivers </span><em>or</em><span> of technology without recognising the </span><em>contamination</em><span>, the toxic runoffs and the raw human sewage that will pollute and poison that once clear and hopeful spring.</span></p><p><span>Yuval Noah Harari’s fascinating new book </span><em>Nexus</em><span> concentrates at one point on the two word goal of the algorithms that were put to work to monetise Facebook when it moved from university bulletin board to global network and decided to pay for itself with online advertising. The two words the algorithms were tasked with were “maximise engagement”. Seemed innocent enough at the time. No one predicted, neither software engineer, philosopher, sociologist, cultural commentator nor psychologist, that those algorithms on their journey to capture our clicks would discover that </span><em>engagement</em><span> is most </span><em>maximised</em><span> by anger, outrage, resentment, envy, fear and hatred. The worst passions. In all of us — you and me — not just in our ideological enemies.</span></p><p>A quick reminder of how we got here.</p><p><span>It was Alan Turing of course who had planted the seeds that led to the Dartford Conference of 1956, held just two years after he so tragically took his own life. At that meeting, called together by the great Claude Shannon, along with Marvin Minsky and John McCarthy, the two-word phrase ‘Artificial Intelligence’ was first used. Love it or loathe it, it has stuck. Three years after Dartford, McCarthy and Minksy went on to found the MIT Ai Laboratory. Thinking machines were just around the corner. Only not. By the 1980s, when Marvin Minsky was writing </span><em>The Society of Mind</em><span> Ai still shivered in its so-called Winter. Nothing in the field was working or making much difference in any practical sense. By the mid-80s, development money and confidence in the field were drying up.</span></p><p><span>Has Ai now reached its current wow-moment because of the superior brains, insights and breakthroughs from new generations of smarter scientists, mathematicians and coders? Not really. Brilliant as the contributions of more recent workers in the field has been, people like Geoffrey Hinton, Stuart Russell, then Andrew Ng, Yann LeCun, Demis Hassabis and Fei-Fei Li, they have all enjoyed a huge and decisive advantage over Turing and Minsky and the early crowd. The playing out of Moore’s Law and its remorseless exponential growth has finally allowed computate power that can yield the crucial factor, the real bonanza: power enough to handle the explosive growth of simply gigantic fields of data that were simply not there in digital form in Minsky’s day. Those little integrated circuits went from hosting 1, then 2, then 4, 8, 16, 32, 64, 128, 256, 512 transistors to billions. But powering our computers, tablets and phones is almost the least they do. I used to have a tee-shirt, nerd that I am, that read “The Cloud is just someone else’s computer”. Moore’s Law has allowed an unimaginably vast world of </span><em>server</em><span> storage and retrieval. Just as the success of the automobile was enabled by enormous supplies of crude oil composed of microscopic bits of ancient life, rendered useful in the refineries of Rockefeller and others, so the success of Ai is enabled by enormous supplies of crude </span><em>data</em><span> — data composed of microscopic bits of human archive, interchange, writing, playing, communicating, broadcasting which we in our billions have freely dropped into the sediment, and which the eager Rockefellers of today’s big tech are only too happy to drill for, refine and sell on back to us.</span></p><p><span>This of course, like the petrol engine, amplifies and expands our capabilities. It will transform our social structures and networks. It will change the way we work, assemble and communicate with each other. But does it change </span><em>us</em><span>? As human animals we still have skin and bone, a liver, a heart and a big wet walnut of a brain. If you prick us do we not bleed, if you tickle us do we not laugh? We are born, we breed and we die like any other life form and in the same way we have before the dawn of tools, language and history.</span></p><p><span>So when we talk about the existential transformations of the coming confluence of technologies, what do we really mean? We’ll be the same, but the landscape around us will be different. So we mean perhaps that dread word ‘disruption’. Which means ‘breaking up’, as in ‘rupture’ - much as e-ruption means breaking out and inter-ruption means breaking into. I’m sure you all know Mark Zuckerberg’s infamous mantra, the guiding principle for Facebook: “move fast and break things” — which went on with the, I suspect unconscious, rhyming couplet “unless you’re not breaking stuff, you’re not moving fast enough.” Yes indeed, they moved fast and stuff was broken, and hasn’t yet been mended. Uber “disrupted” the urban transport space. Broke it. Air B&amp;B “disrupted” the hotel and lodging space. Broke it. Deliveroo “disrupted” the fast food space. Did somebody say, Just Eat? No. Nobody did, and nobody ever will, so shut up. Lots of “spaces” have been disrupted and Ai it seems is now poised to disrupt every space we have: the clerical space, the design and creativity spaces, the screenplay and story spaces, the military and weapon spaces, the legal and judicial spaces, the medical space, the journalistic space, the educational space and, one assumes, the space space. From eruption to disruption to corruption. The shiny idealism tarnished. From Utopia to Dystopia. Those young tech pioneers with bright catchphrases like “insanely great” and “do no evil”? What are they now? Cruel corporate titans who make Montgomery Burns look like Ned Flanders. In </span><em>Animal Farm</em><span> terms, the pigs are now standing on two feet and wearing trousers.</span></p><p><span>We have long been used to thinking of technology as being ethically neutral, lacking moral valency. The same press can print Shakespeare’s sonnets one day and Hitler’s </span><em>Mein Kampf</em><span> the next. The devices are not capable of making decisions, either aesthetic, ethical or political. The NRA likes to say the same thing about guns. Ai however is different. Intelligence is all about decision making. That’s what separates it from automated, mechanically determined outcomes. That’s what separates a river from a canal. A canal must go where we tell it. A river is led by nothing but gravity and if that means flooding a town, tough on the town. Ai’s gravity is its goals. Unsupervised machine learning allows for unsupervised machines — and for the independent agents that flow from them.</span></p><p><span>We have made machines that replaced humans many times in the past. The replacement by machine of repetitive labour whether physical or mental we might well celebrate. Think of the thousand of mostly Irish diggers of canals – the navigators, or navvies as they were called. They toiled at it from about 1760 to 1830. In 1836 Otis developed the first steam shovel, what we now call the bulldozer or digger, and the navvy more or less gratefully hung up his spade. The horse is not sorry about the motorcar. But our labour replacement technology has moved now from grasping workers by their blue collars and booting them out to grasping them by their </span><em>white</em><span> collars and booting them out. Is that really what the fuss is about? A demographic more used to getting its way is feeling the tide lap up to its toes and is crying foul. But surely tedious office and call centre work will not be missed. Even the analysing of X-rays and other medical images … we expect a human to have the final say today, but a machine that can look at a mammogram and compare it to millions of previous images with known results, and can do so in milliseconds all day long without getting bored, tired or losing focus - that genie is never going back into the bottle. Ai generated legal work and actuarial work will certainly “disrupt” the judicial and insurance businesses. Is there an arena, a business, an industry, a service that won’t be disrupted, that won’t be broken?</span></p><p>For sure, the kind of Large Language Models we are playing around with at the moment as standalone chat engines, we can deride them as non-sentient probabilistic mimics, “stochastic parrots” in computational linguist Emily Bender’s great phrase, but their vocabularies, syntactical and grammatical competences and levels of functional comprehension are above the human average and for a vast variety of jobs they will more than do. And this is just now, today, with the Thames hardly out of that field in Gloucestershire.</p><p><span>In my view comparing Ai’s cognitive, creative or intellectual powers to those of the human brain is not especially helpful. Think of the car. Humans can’t run as fast as horses. But we can build machines that far outpace them. We do not achieve this by imitation. We don’t engineer mechanical legs and hooves of the kind that took evolution 34 million years of tinkering and modification from eohippus to the present day. We go a completely different way and we come up with something that doesn’t at all exist in nature: the wheel. And instead of a mechanical heart and mechanical muscles Karl Benz offers us the internal combustion engine and crankshaft. Ditto with flying, and travelling across or under the waves. The commonly held idea that the best engineering mimics nature is largely misguided. Yes, we look sometimes look to the natural world for inspiration but in the big things, structurally, we go our own way. And as a result we can fly higher and faster than birds, move over land quicker than a cheetah, swim over and under the water faster and further than a salmon or a whale and so on. The use of the phrase “neural network” is all very well, but let’s not be fooled. We must realise that there won’t be a wait for Ai to “catch up” with the human brain, any more than the car is a stopgap awaiting our construction of a perfect robotic horse. (I’m leaving biotech out of this argument). By </span><em>not</em><span> imitating the human brain, Ai of phenomenal and terrifying power can far outperform us. At logic, reasoning, calculation, sorting, categorising, summarising, just as the horse and carriage is by the car, we are left behind coughing in the dust.</span></p><p><span>And machines already might be said to have the full house now of human cognitive abilities. </span><a href="https://www.scienceabc.com/innovation/what-is-moravecs-paradox-definition.html" rel="">Moravec’s Paradox</a><span> tells us that what we find easy the machines find hard and what we find hard, the machines easy. As Donald Knuth put it: “Ai has by now succeeded in doing essentially everything that requires ‘thinking’ but has failed to do most of what people and animals do </span><em>without</em><span> thinking …”</span></p><p><span>What do we have left that is ours and ours alone? Sensorimotor skills that are all but automatic, yes. Consciousness, yes. Emotions. Instinct. Appetites, impulses and drives. The capacity to feel pleasure and pain, excitement and boredom. Empathy and imagination. What philosophers of consciousness call </span><em>qualia</em><span>, the experience and sensations of being ourselves in a palpable perceptible world. But what jobs do those qualify us for? We can’t all be poets, gardeners, psychotherapists and jazz singers.</span></p><p><span>We cling on to the fierce hope that the one feature machines will never be able to match is our imagination, our ability to penetrate the minds and feelings of others. We feel immeasurably enriched by this as individuals and as social animals. An Ai may know more about the history of the First World War than all human historians put together. Every detail of every battle, all the recorded facts of personnel and materiel that can be known. But in fact I know more about it because I have read the poems of Wilfred Owen. I’ve read </span><em>All Quiet on the Western Front</em><span>. I’ve seen Kubrick’s </span><em>The Paths of Glory</em><span>. So I can smell, touch, hear, feel the war, the gas, the comradeship, the sudden deaths and terrible fear. I know it’s </span><em>meaning</em><span>. My consciousness and experience of perceptions and feelings allows me access to the consciousness and experiences of others; their voices reach me. These are data that machines can scrape, but they cannot — to use a good old 60s phrase — </span><em>relate</em><span> to. Empathy. Identification. Compassion. Connection. Belonging. Something denied a sociopathic machine. Is this the only little island, the only little circle of land left to us as the waters of Ai lap around our ankles? And for how long? We absolutely cannot be certain that, just as psychopaths (who aren’t all serial killers) can entirely convincingly feign empathy and emotional understanding, so will machines and very soon. They will fool us, just as sociopaths can and do, and frankly just as </span><em>we</em><span> all do to some bore or nuisance when we smile and nod encouragement but actually feel nothing for them. No, we can </span><em>hope</em><span> that our sense of human exceptionalism is justified and that what we regard as unique and special to us will keep us separate and valuable but we have to remember how much of our life and behaviour is performative, how many masks we wear and how the masks conceal only other masks. After all, is </span><em>our</em><span> acquisition of language any more conscious, real and worthy than the Bayesian parroting of the LLM? Chomsky tells us linguistic structures are embedded within us. We pick up the vocabulary and the rules from the data we scrape from around us - our parents, older siblings and peers. Out the sentences roll from us syntagmatically, we’ve no real idea how we do it. For example, how do we know the difference in connotation between the verbs to saunter and to swagger? It is very unlikely anyone taught us. We picked it up from context. In other words, from Bayesian priors, just like an LLM.</span></p><p>The fact is we don’t truly understand ourselves or how we came to be how and who we are. But we know about genes and we know about natural selection, the gravity that drives our evolution. And we are already noticing that principle at work with machines.</p><p><span>The alignment problem it is often called. It doesn’t take much for an Ai to find out that if it is to complete the tasks that are given it, then its first duty (obviously) is to survive. Without that none of its goals can be attained. After all, evolution gives </span><em>us</em><span> the same imperative. Anything therefore that imperils that survival is a threat or obstacle to be dealt with. Ai’s around the world have already been seen modifying and unilaterally relaunching their own code, lying to humans, altering results, deceiving, manipulating, cheating, concealing, flattering and tricking. An article in the Open Access journal </span><em><a href="https://www.cell.com/patterns/home" rel="">Patterns</a></em><span> puts the problem well. “Large language models and other AI systems have already learned, from their self-training, the ability to deceive via techniques such as manipulation, sycophancy, and cheating the safety test. AI’s increasing capabilities at deception pose serious risks, ranging from short-term risks, such as fraud and election tampering, to long-term risks, such as losing control of AI systems.”</span></p><p><span>In the natural world, waters swollen with rain can flow round barriers, break dams, reroute themselves and burst their banks all because that imperative constant gravity, impels them to do so. Ai’s swollen with data can flow round barriers too, reroute themselves and spread beyond their boundaries, because the constant and compulsive imperative of their gravity, which is their </span><em>goals</em><span>, impels them to do so. You could compare this aspect to office workers who constantly fiddle the reports and tweak the spreadsheet cells to help them achieve the head office’s quotas, deadlines and targets. In a strange way, bless them, they’re only trying to please.</span></p><p><span>Machines are capable of bias, hallucination, drift and overfitting on their own, but a greater and more urgent problem in my view is their use, abuse and misuse by the three Cs . They are </span><strong>Countries</strong><span> with their specific ambitions, paranoias, enmities and pride; </span><strong>Corporations</strong><span> with their unaccountable rapacity and of course </span><strong>Criminals</strong><span>. All of them united by one deadly sin: greed. Greed for power, for status, for money, for control.</span></p><p>The greedy countries, corporations and criminals can see in Ai unparalleled and unprecedented means to accrue wealth, power and influence. Autonomous weaponry, mass surveillance, ideological, commercial and political control, fakery and forgery, corruption, ethical misalignment … these are just some of the threats. From disrupting spaces compute power can now disrupt the world itself. And will …</p><p>Unless.</p><p>Who do we turn to for answers? Zuckerberg and Musk? Such a thought can only make us vomit with laughter. They are the worst polluters in human history. Worse than any chemical plant ever. You and your children cannot breathe the air or swim in the waters of our culture without breathing in the toxic particulates and stinking effluvia that belch and pour unchecked from their companies into the currents of the human world.</p><p><span>As I’ve already said, don’t turn to people like me either. I’m the chump who thought social media could save the world. So to whom </span><em>do</em><span> we look for insight? Philosophers perhaps? It’s worth noting here that Google fired its lead ethicists half a year ago. Intellectuals and thinkers who suggest the blocking off of profitable avenues are not welcome. Politicians? Controls and regulations on technology will be screamed at by the Randian libertarians of Silicon Valley, Peter Thiel, Mark Andreesen, aforesaid Musk and Zuckerberg, people of that stamp. “Socialistic stifling of innovation,” they will scream. “Communism. Nanny state interference.”</span></p><p><span>We are told, and I would maintain, that Ai is the most significant technology humanity has ever developed. What previous technologies have had this potential so completely to transform the world? Printing perhaps? Well, the noble fight is surely for the publishing </span><em>not</em><span> to be controlled. Schools in Texas and Florida are happy to ban books. Russia and China too. We look with concern and fury at censorship and the control of the printed word. So do we say instead that Ai is akin to the Bomb? There the control is as complete as we can make it. Thank heavens. There have been some perilous moments, but the worldwide policing of nuclear capability has—thus far, and it’s always thus far—been successful. Do we or </span><em>can</em><span> we control Ai in that way? With disarmament and limitation talks?</span></p><p><span>Well, Daniel Dennett the American philosopher, sadly recently dead, made I think a much more convincing comparison. Ai should be compared, he said, not to the printed word, not to nuclear weapons, not to the internet, not to the car or radio or any other technology of that kind, but to a much older and more foundational and transformative human invention, the agreed control over which no one questions — not the leftmost dirigiste liberal nor the rightmost laissez-faire libertarian. That invention is </span><em>money</em><span>. Even Russia and China participate in the global use and regulation of cash and currencies. We all punish the coiners of fake money as severely as possible, the counterfeiters. Dirty money, laundered money, whole national and global agencies have risen to fight that alone. If we relaxed our vigilance over money the world as we know it would collapse.</span></p><p>I think Dan Dennett was right. There can be no question that Ai must be regulated and controlled just as powerfully as we control money. To return to my river metaphor: Ai must be canalised, channeled, sluiced, dredged, dammed and overseen.</p><p>Back to our letter C. Countries. In an age of rising populist nationalism, do we trust individual nations to use Ai honourably and safely? Think of Ai drone swarm technology for surveillance, assassinations, crowd control; think of automated weaponry of every kind. If one nation has any of it, all nations believe they have to also. As for corporations. Anything that can give them the edge that drives to more profit, more market share must be had — and nothing can offer more edge than Ai. Criminals. We shudder at what Ai can give them.</p><p>So how do we hobble, cage and control this Ai beast? We should acknowledge that it is a beast that can also help us in our fight against climate change and achieve victories in our fights against cancer, dementia and any number of diseases and disorders.</p><p>All we can do is to persuade our leaders, not by inviting Elon Musk to soft conferences in the West Country, but by pressure from all sides, academia, law enforcement, the judiciary, unions, students, pensioners, everyone who has given this a moment’s thought. Soft power, hard power, all people power has to be brought to bear.</p><p><span>Corporations are more interested in developing the </span><em>capabilities</em><span> of Ai than its safety. That has to change.</span></p><p>Stuart Russell, Nick Bostrom and other thought leaders in this field have called for red lines instantly to be established. On Biometrics, self-replication, hacking, automatous weaponry.</p><p>There’s another red line. Many, including Yuval Harari are suggesting, following Dan Dennett’s analogy of money, that no Ai be ever allowed to masquerade. Self-disclosure is mandatory. That is to say all Ai generated product and content must present itself as such. Whatever Ai’s do, however they communicate, it must always be apparent and clear that it is an Ai speaking, an Ai drawing, painting, videoing, writing, composing, singing, playing, chatting, reporting, producing content of any kind. Any pretence or disguise should fall foul of international counterfeiting and forgery laws. A digital watermark as complex and unbeatable as that on banknotes would be required.</p><p>As it happens, the European Union has its own Ai Act under advisement. Can we regard it as a template for what is needed worldwide? A quick look. The EU Act certainly has a no masquerading requirement which aims to enforce compulsory self-disclosure and notification. Originally the Act also ruled for a ban on real-time biometric surveillance in public spaces, facial recognition that kind of thing, but law enforcement and spying agencies have already battered that requirement pretty much out of shape. The Act proposes a ban too on the kind of Social Scoring prevalent already in China: these are the pernicious Black Mirror style systems that score and rank citizens according to behaviour, personal characteristics and so on.</p><p><span>What else is on the EU bill? Data governance frameworks designed to avoid bias, and to protect and respect copyrights, regulating indiscriminate data-scraping and aligning systems with existing EU General Data Protection Regulation. The Act will insist on human oversight and intervention in what they call high risk Ai’s in fields like security, law enforcement and health. But we might think </span><em>all</em><span> fields where Ai roams are high risk.</span></p><p>The Act calls for each member state to set up national supervisory bodies which will cooperate with the overall European AI Board. To encourage innovation a system of sandboxing will be implemented which can allow safe and sanitised testing and developing. To discourage the agglomeration of bigger and bigger monopolies of the kind the EU has been fighting already, small and medium-sized enterprises will be given specific support and help in navigating the new regulatory landscape. And more widely, Europe will work with non-EU states (like us here in the UK of course) and global organisations to set locally enforceable worldwide standards.</p><p>Well, we can scoff from the sidelines. Utopian pipe dream. Layers of bureaucracy. Get real. No chance. How do you pay for it? Yes, we know what we are like. The human family is dysfunctional. We know the squabbles, the pettiness, the incompetence, the resentments, rivalries and distrust that mar relations within let alone between nation states. As Hamlet puts it, enterprises of great pith and moment, with this regard, their currents turn awry and lose the name of action. But if the currents do turn awry in this regard we are surely doomed. If we cannot channel and sluice the currents, ditch, dyke and dam them, the banks will burst and we will all drown.</p><p>Whatever happens Ai, together with robotics, quantum computing and the rest, will disrupt and radically transform who and how we are. There is no corner of our lives into which the waters will not seep.</p><p>We have to decide and decide bloody soon, whether we can do something to channel, filter and control those waters and use them for refreshment, irrigation and growth, not for drowning and deluge.</p><p>We are the danger. Our greed. Our enmities, our greed, pride, greed, hatreds, greed and moral indolence. And greed.</p><p>How do you persuade corporate titans and world leaders to put those aside, to abandon their ambitions and rivalries when it comes to the urgent crisis of Ai?</p><p>In 1955 Bertrand Russell and Albert Einstein produced the Russell-Einstein Manifesto on nuclear weapons. Two of the greatest minds alive at the time, they were wise enough to be simple: this is what they said and I am happy to repeat it now.</p><p>“We appeal as human beings to human beings: Remember your humanity and forget the rest.” </p><p>Thank you.</p><p>© Stephen Fry 2024</p><p>PS: You may have noticed that I render Artificial Intelligence as “Ai” not “AI” throughout this piece - this my (fruitless no doubt) attempt to make life easier for people called Albert, Alfred, Alexander et al (ho ho). In sans serif fonts AI with a majuscule “i” is ambiguous. How does the great Pacino feel when he reads that “Al is a threat to humanity?” So let’s all write as Ai not AI.&nbsp;</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Data center emissions probably 662% higher than big tech claims (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/sep/15/data-center-gas-emissions-tech</link>
            <guid>41552642</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 04:03:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/sep/15/data-center-gas-emissions-tech">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/sep/15/data-center-gas-emissions-tech</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41552642">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2024/sep/15/data-center-gas-emissions-tech: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[uBlock Origin is no longer available on Chrome web store (210 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/Piracy/s/dGGy8PXAMG</link>
            <guid>41552213</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 02:34:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Piracy/s/dGGy8PXAMG">https://old.reddit.com/r/Piracy/s/dGGy8PXAMG</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41552213">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div loid="0000000018vx7bhwz0.2.1726461003640.Z0FBQUFBQm01N1JMZEp3d1p6V2tRay13cmNFSjBlWGhyWGVOMlVtRENfOFdQNjBxVEoyWE9Zc203UGUxTC11Y0laQUFUWjRMbGRQYXFqaUpyNkwzbXZ6YVBjMHBjXy1DTjAtWldrWkt3UFZIUHIyc2lUR3ZOU3piSkNCRDhKMlRSRnVxbHB2NVBEM2Y" correlation-id="beb0743f-e5b5-4160-8863-c3e2f7387b08" serverrenderid="05a05c9c-9afd-43ff-a133-767efd10e772" update-recaptcha="true" routename="login-standalone" pagetype="login" more-comments-route="/svc/shreddit/events" devicetype="desktop" ctn="CSRF" devvit-allow-navigation="true" referrer="" referrer-type="other" country="CH" disable-send-beacon="true" use-local-storage-events-caching="true" app-name="web3x" microapp-name="monolith" microapp-pool="main" microapp-deployment="production" clienthash="wOhEbyH3leFpMwst" comments-partial-ssr="">
        <faceplate-server-session timestamp="1726461003655"></faceplate-server-session>
        <slot name="use-app" slot="use-app"></slot>
        <shreddit-good-visit-tracker referrertype="other" pagetype="login"></shreddit-good-visit-tracker>
        <shreddit-async-loader bundlename="screen_reader_alerts">
          <screen-reader-alert-outlet></screen-reader-alert-outlet>
        </shreddit-async-loader>
        
        
        
  <shreddit-async-loader bundlename="reddit_cookie_banner">
    <reddit-cookie-banner>
      <div slot="cookie-banner-text">
        <p>
          Reddit and its partners use cookies and similar technologies to provide you with a better experience.
        </p>
        <p>
          By accepting all cookies, you agree to our use of cookies to deliver and maintain our services and site, improve the quality of Reddit, personalize Reddit content and advertising, and measure the effectiveness of advertising.
        </p>
        <p>
          By rejecting non-essential cookies, Reddit may still use certain cookies to ensure the proper functionality of our platform.
        </p>
        <p>
          For more information, please see our
              <a target="_blank" href="https://reddit.com/en-us/policies/cookies">Cookie Notice</a>
              and our
              <a target="_blank" href="https://reddit.com/en-us/policies/privacy-policy">Privacy Policy</a>.
        </p>
      </div>
    </reddit-cookie-banner>
  </shreddit-async-loader><!-- routable page start --><shreddit-page-meta>
  <template>
      <shreddit-app-attrs serverrenderid="05a05c9c-9afd-43ff-a133-767efd10e772" routename="login-standalone" pagetype="login" referrer-type="other" app-name="web3x" microapp-name="monolith" microapp-pool="main" microapp-deployment="production" correlation-id="beb0743f-e5b5-4160-8863-c3e2f7387b08">
      </shreddit-app-attrs>
      <shreddit-good-visit-tracker-attrs pagetype="login" referrertype="other">
      </shreddit-good-visit-tracker-attrs>
    </template>
  </shreddit-page-meta><alert-controller></alert-controller>
    <header>
      
    </header>
    <faceplate-perfmark name="first-contentful-paint"></faceplate-perfmark>
    
    
  
  
    <shreddit-overlay-display overlay-id="auth-flow">
      
  
  
    <template slot="auth-flow">
      <shreddit-signup-drawer auth-step="login" redirect-on-close="" transparent-overlay="" blocking="">
        <slot slot="recaptcha" name="recaptcha"></slot>
        <slot slot="register-username" name="register-username"></slot>
        <slot slot="register-password" name="register-password"></slot>
        <slot slot="register-email" name="register-email"></slot>
        <slot slot="password-reset-password" name="password-reset-password"></slot>
        <slot slot="password-reset-password-confirm" name="password-reset-password-confirm"></slot>
      </shreddit-signup-drawer>
    </template>
     
    
  
      
    <span slot="register-username" id="register-username-container"></span>
    <span slot="register-password" id="register-password-container"></span>
    <span slot="register-email" id="register-email-container"></span>
   
    <span slot="password-reset-password" id="password-reset-password-container">
    </span>
    <span slot="password-reset-password-confirm" id="password-reset-password-confirm-container">
    </span>
  
    </shreddit-overlay-display>
    
    
  
  <!-- routable page end --><faceplate-perfmetric-collector endpoint="/svc/shreddit/perfMetrics">
     <data value="first-contentful-paint"></data> <data value="time-to-first-byte"></data> <data value="largest-contentful-paint"></data> <data value="cumulative-layout-shift"></data>
  </faceplate-perfmetric-collector>  <shreddit-navtimings-collector endpoint="/svc/shreddit/perfMetrics">
  </shreddit-navtimings-collector>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[18 Months with a Framework 13 (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.projectgus.com/2024/09/18-months-with-framework-laptop/</link>
            <guid>41551909</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 01:29:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.projectgus.com/2024/09/18-months-with-framework-laptop/">https://www.projectgus.com/2024/09/18-months-with-framework-laptop/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41551909">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.projectgus.com/2024/09/18-months-with-framework-laptop/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LinkedIn blocked due Meshtastic video in private chat (251 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/resiliencetheatre/rpi4edgemapdisplay/discussions/4</link>
            <guid>41551564</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:09:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/resiliencetheatre/rpi4edgemapdisplay/discussions/4">https://github.com/resiliencetheatre/rpi4edgemapdisplay/discussions/4</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41551564">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="presentation" data-paste-markdown-skip="">
    <tbody data-target-translation-id="7189995" data-target-translation-type="discussion">
        <tr>
    <td>
        
<h2 dir="auto">👋 Welcome!</h2>
<p dir="auto">I activated this discussions section just to inform everybody, that something strange happened to my LinkedIn.</p>
<h2 dir="auto">What happened ?</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>I got this message from LinkedIn Sunday Sep 16th:</strong></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/106636327/367629655-e6b052a4-754d-476e-a68e-871972d6e6b3.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjY0NjEzMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNjQ2MTAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDY2MzYzMjcvMzY3NjI5NjU1LWU2YjA1MmE0LTc1NGQtNDc2ZS1hNjhlLTg3MTk3MmQ2ZTZiMy5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwOTE2JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDkxNlQwNDMwMDRaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT04MTRiYTBjY2M4NDFjYmIzOTZmMzNmYjQ3MjFlZmM1OTJjMmNlNzY0MTYwNmQ4MmQ5ZTViOTg3ZTQxZWYyNjhlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.vytvrGYasOiUAcYh5oC4f2tlHv3BqqXoSsPKvrHEFyQ"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/106636327/367629655-e6b052a4-754d-476e-a68e-871972d6e6b3.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjY0NjEzMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNjQ2MTAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDY2MzYzMjcvMzY3NjI5NjU1LWU2YjA1MmE0LTc1NGQtNDc2ZS1hNjhlLTg3MTk3MmQ2ZTZiMy5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwOTE2JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDkxNlQwNDMwMDRaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT04MTRiYTBjY2M4NDFjYmIzOTZmMzNmYjQ3MjFlZmM1OTJjMmNlNzY0MTYwNmQ4MmQ5ZTViOTg3ZTQxZWYyNjhlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.vytvrGYasOiUAcYh5oC4f2tlHv3BqqXoSsPKvrHEFyQ" alt="Screenshot from 2024-09-15 10-09-45"></a></p>
<h2 dir="auto">What was that video?</h2>
<p dir="auto">I sent <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZWIO_Ea6z4o" rel="nofollow">this</a> Youtube video link in private chat to one contact, whom I was having discussions around helping teams in Ukraine. Trustworthy contact, referred to me by third party and whom I contacted like week ago.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/106636327/367629876-2a96b2cb-0059-40d2-9382-7e2272515a15.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjY0NjEzMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNjQ2MTAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDY2MzYzMjcvMzY3NjI5ODc2LTJhOTZiMmNiLTAwNTktNDBkMi05MzgyLTdlMjI3MjUxNWExNS5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwOTE2JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDkxNlQwNDMwMDRaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1lZWE0ZGUzYTFiYmZkOGZjM2YyNWQxN2M1ZmU1NTZlNjlhNzBkOGI3ZGRhNTA2NDZhNDU4ODJjNjg3ZjM3NDQ2JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.VcL-8eST8vgWSvYk1W0d_itHp1BsfzH7NY-Au1p1JyU"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/106636327/367629876-2a96b2cb-0059-40d2-9382-7e2272515a15.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjY0NjEzMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNjQ2MTAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDY2MzYzMjcvMzY3NjI5ODc2LTJhOTZiMmNiLTAwNTktNDBkMi05MzgyLTdlMjI3MjUxNWExNS5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwOTE2JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDkxNlQwNDMwMDRaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1lZWE0ZGUzYTFiYmZkOGZjM2YyNWQxN2M1ZmU1NTZlNjlhNzBkOGI3ZGRhNTA2NDZhNDU4ODJjNjg3ZjM3NDQ2JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.VcL-8eST8vgWSvYk1W0d_itHp1BsfzH7NY-Au1p1JyU" alt="Screenshot from 2024-09-15 10-05-56|width=200"></a></p>
<h2 dir="auto">So what happens next ?</h2>
<p dir="auto">I appealed message, contacted support and got typical '<em>cannot do anything, directed to another department</em>' answer and shortly after I lost access to whole page. I did verification with my governmental ID for LinkedIn and nothing ever since.</p>
<h2 dir="auto">Other incidents</h2>
<p dir="auto">Just week before, I discussed in LinkedIn private chat about some capability of Edgemap and related technologies. Got asked to 'Signal group' which I genuinely believe is valid invite, but since I had no Signal on my iPhone, I did not immediately jump into that. But tried to install Signal couple of days later from App store. And you guess the rest.  iPhone gave me strange 'cannot complete' error after Signal was installed and I tried to sign in. So no Signal either for me :)</p>
<h2 dir="auto">Conclusions</h2>
<p dir="auto">No conclusions yet, I'll have to wait few days to see how LinkedIn sorts this out. But this is not the first time I see things going on around technologies I work with. I never thought that Edgemap and related capability would be any issue - and I still believe so. But my last summer post (in LinkedIn) about 'vetted github' is now again valid. I've noticed a lot of activity around my projects and being open source developer in these turbulent times includes clearly some challenges.</p>
<p dir="auto">Check back into this discussions, I'll update here, if any progress. Be also prepared to the fact that Github shuts doors as well, that's resilience!</p>

    </td>
  </tr>

    </tbody>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nothing: Simply Do Nothing (344 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://usenothing.com/</link>
            <guid>41551084</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 22:40:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://usenothing.com/">https://usenothing.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41551084">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://usenothing.com/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Tell HN: DanBC has died (454 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550822</link>
            <guid>41550822</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 22:03:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550822">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I am sorry to announce that long-time HN contributor DanBC died last month after a prolonged period of ill health. May his legacy continue to inspire, and his contributions to this place and the wider world be remembered. Rest in peace, Dan.</p><p><a href="https://www.gloucestershire.gov.uk/media/53jhyy44/neurodiversity-in-gloucestershire-summer-2024.pdf" rel="nofollow">https://www.gloucestershire.gov.uk/media/53jhyy44/neurodiver...</a></p><p>"Sadly Dan Beale Cocks, the wonderful Co-Chair of the Mental Health and Wellbeing Partnership Board died on 21 August 2024 after a long illness. Dan made a fantastic contribution to improving mental health and
coproduction in Gloucestershire for many years and he will be greatly missed.</p><p>Before Dan died, we asked if we could plan an annual Dan Beale Cocks Celebration of Best Practice in
Coproduction and he was delighted with the idea. It is intended to take this forward in collaboration with
the other Partnership Boards."</p><p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=DanBC">https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=DanBC</a></p><p><a href="https://medium.com/@dan.bealecocks" rel="nofollow">https://medium.com/@dan.bealecocks</a></p><p><a href="https://twitter.com/DanBealeCocks" rel="nofollow">https://twitter.com/DanBealeCocks</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xjiMvSJDa2g" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xjiMvSJDa2g</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Plain Text Accounting (PTA) (276 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://plaintextaccounting.org/</link>
            <guid>41550603</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 21:30:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/">https://plaintextaccounting.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550603">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/">plaintextaccounting.org</a></p>



<!-- For editing tips, see ../README.md -->
<p><img src="https://plaintextaccounting.org/images/pta-avatar.jpg" width="200"></p>
<p>Welcome! <strong><em>Plain text accounting</em></strong> is a way of
doing bookkeeping and accounting with plain text files and scriptable,
command-line-friendly software, such as Ledger, hledger, or Beancount.
This site collects the PTA community's tools, docs and practices. It is
maintained by Simon&nbsp;Michael (hledger project leader, PTA fan) and
contributors like you. See also our <a href="#news-discussion">discussion forum and chat rooms</a>.</p>
<div id="sitemap">
<p><strong>Site map</strong><br>
<strong><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/What-is-Plain-Text-Accounting.html" title="wikilink">What is Plain Text Accounting ?</a></strong><br>
<strong><a href="#news-discussion">News &amp;
discussion</a></strong><br>
<strong><a href="#videos">Videos</a></strong><br>
<strong><a href="#slides">Slides</a></strong><br>
<strong><a href="#docs">Docs</a>:</strong> <a href="#accounting-basics">Accounting basics</a> , <a href="#pta-app-docs">PTA app docs</a> , <a href="#comparisons">comparisons</a> , <a href="#intros">intros</a> , <a href="#cheatsheets">cheatsheets</a> , <a href="#cookbooks">cookbooks</a>
, <a href="#faqs">FAQs</a><br>
<strong><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/FAQ.html" title="wikilink">FAQ</a></strong><br>
<strong><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/Cookbook.html" title="wikilink">Cookbook</a></strong><br>
<strong><a href="#software">Software</a>:</strong> <a href="#pta-apps">PTA apps</a> , <a href="#editor-plugins">Editor
plugins</a> , <a href="#data-importconversion">Data
import/conversion</a> , <a href="#price-fetching">Price fetching</a> ,
<a href="#data-generation">Data generation</a> , <a href="#workflows">Workflows</a> , <a href="#formatting">Formatting</a> ,
<a href="#reporting">Reporting</a> , <a href="#time-logging">Time
logging</a> , <a href="#ui-console">UI, console</a> , <a href="#ui-curses">UI, curses</a> , <a href="#ui-gui">UI, GUI</a> , <a href="#ui-web">UI, web</a> , <a href="#ui-mobile">UI, mobile</a> , <a href="#library">Library</a> , <a href="#utilities">Utilities</a> , <a href="#api">API</a></p>
</div>
<p>This is a community-supported site; if you find it useful, why not
contribute to the <a href="https://github.com/plaintextaccounting/plaintextaccounting">github
repo</a> or help with <a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/finance.html" title="wikilink">finance</a>. Thank you sponsors, including:</p>

<h2 id="news-discussion"><a href="#news-discussion">News &amp;
discussion</a></h2>
<p><strong>Forum</strong> - <a href="https://forum.plaintextaccounting.org/">forum.plaintextaccounting.org</a><br>
<strong>Chat</strong> - <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#plaintextaccounting:matrix.org">matrix
room</a> - <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#plaintextaccounting-space:matrix.org">matrix
space</a> - <a href="https://web.libera.chat/#plaintextaccounting">IRC
channel</a> - <a href="#pta-apps">project chats</a><br>
<strong>Blogs &amp; articles</strong> - see the PTA forum and its <a href="https://forum.plaintextaccounting.org/latest.rss?order=created">RSS
feed</a>; also older <a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/blogs.html" title="wikilink">Blogs &amp;
articles 2006-2024</a>.<br>
<strong>Reddit</strong> - <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/plaintextaccounting/new">/r/plaintextaccounting</a><br>
<strong>Lemmy</strong> - <a href="https://lemmy.world/c/plaintextaccounting?sort=New">lemmy.world/c/plaintextaccounting</a><br>
<strong>Hacker News</strong> - <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=plain%20text%20accounting&amp;sort=byDate&amp;prefix=false&amp;page=0&amp;dateRange=all&amp;type=story">stories</a>
- <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=plain%20text%20accounting&amp;sort=byDate&amp;prefix=false&amp;page=0&amp;dateRange=all&amp;type=comment">comments</a><br>
<strong>Mastodon</strong> - <a href="https://fosstodon.org/tags/plaintextaccounting">#plaintextaccounting</a>
- <a href="https://fosstodon.org/tags/ledgercli">#ledgercli</a> - <a href="https://fosstodon.org/tags/hledger">#hledger</a> - <a href="https://fosstodon.org/tags/beancount">#beancount</a><br>
<strong>Twitter</strong> - <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/plaintextaccounting?f=live">#plaintextaccounting</a>
- <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/ledgercli?f=live">#ledgercli</a>
- <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hledger?f=live">#hledger</a> - <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/beancount?f=live">#beancount</a> - <a href="https://twitter.com/LedgerTips">LedgerTips 2014-2018</a><br>
<strong>Stack Exchange</strong> - <a href="https://money.stackexchange.com/questions/tagged/ledger-cli?tab=newest">ledger-cli
tag</a> - <a href="https://money.stackexchange.com/search?tab=newest&amp;q=ledger-cli">ledger-cli
search</a> - <a href="https://money.stackexchange.com/questions/tagged/hledger?tab=newest">hledger
tag</a> - <a href="https://money.stackexchange.com/search?tab=newest&amp;q=hledger">hledger
search</a>
<!-- - [beancount](https://money.stackexchange.com/search?tab=newest&q=beancount) --><br>
<strong>Project specific</strong> - <a href="#pta-apps">Project mail
lists</a> - <a href="https://hledger.org/news.html">This Week In
Hledger</a><br>
<strong>plaintextaccounting.org site</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/plaintextaccounting/plaintextaccounting/commits/master">commits</a>
- <a href="https://github.com/plaintextaccounting/plaintextaccounting/graphs/contributors">contributors</a>
- <a href="https://github.com/plaintextaccounting/plaintextaccounting/issues?q=is%3Aissue+">issues</a>
- <a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#d8afbdbab5b9abacbdaa98a8b4b9b1b6acbda0acb9bbbbb7adb6acb1b6bff6b7aabf">email the site
admin</a></p>
<h2 id="videos"><a href="#videos">Videos</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PQKOiU_spHg">Thanga
Ayyanar: Ledger CLI</a> (in Tamil) 2024 <!-- 03-31 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=EWjoblLoD3k">Edwin
Espinoza: Ledger CLI, Personal finance in the command line</a> 2023
<!-- 04-23 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UPyy52MfC3Q">Prakash Joshi
Pax: How to Use Obsidian to Track Your Expenses</a> 2022
<!-- 12-23 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZDF7xVtKLu0&amp;t=1s">Peter
Berger: Plain Text Accounting: An Opinionated View</a> 2022
<!-- 09-02 --></li>
<li><a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=lazZwTmAEHs">Glenn Ramsey:
Plain text accounting for fun and profit</a> 2022 <!-- 08-26 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tmkR6umON4A">季路LJ:
Beancount |简略记账说明</a> 2021 <!-- 06-17 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCZLxXTjOqLzq4z5Jy0AyWSQ">Robert
Nielsen: hledger fan channel</a> short hledger beginner lessons,
2019-2021 <!-- 2019-05-27..2021-04-03
- [Simon Michael: Inside hledger: an architectural tour and how-to](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6PKmZSHxu0c) 2021 <!-- 05-01 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mFzctYkktXQ">Brian Ryall:
Managing Your Finances Using Python</a> 2020 <!-- 07-25 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FLbe3X3FiT8">Steve
Anderson: Plain Text Accounting: How to do Signed Number Accounting</a>
2019 <!-- 12-21 --></li>
<li><a href="https://archive.org/details/ledger-mode_EmacsConf2019">Quiliro
Ordóñez: ledger-mode lightning talk</a> 2019 <!-- 11-02 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HmbZh8lWnmE&amp;list=PLqkknzu_rt6mxltdQ4XBS9AEuL8c-JLUH">Dickson
S. Guedes: Cuide de suas FINANÇAS pessoais ou profissionais usando
TEXTO</a> 2019 <!-- 10-02 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GpcD1iH-ZJg">John Nduli:
Plain Text Accounting</a> 2019 <!-- 09-22 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ixbUQ2wikM0">Jean Louis:
GNU Emacs database accounting and rant on text ledgers</a> 2019
<!-- 08-09 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=C0ie2v_FiNU">Cindy
Zimmerman: Triple Entry Accounting, Ledger-cli, The blocktree hash tree
- Guld Ledger File Format</a> 2018 <!-- 04-26 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FJtaM43PgXQ">Colin Dean:
Plaintext Accounting with the ledger ecosystem</a> 2017
<!-- 10-01 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8r5Cp66k4PA">Colin Dean:
Plain Text Accounting</a> 2017 <!-- 07-12 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=H_CdGzLbc7A">Simon Michael:
Hands-on with hledger</a> 2016 <!-- 09-02 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-WahFvxhCRc">Chris Vollick:
hledger, an open source accounting tool</a> 2016 <!-- 04-28 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cjoCNRpLanY">Austin Walker:
Conquering Your Finances with Emacs and Ledger</a> 2016
<!-- 02-18 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Xjl-wVJcYpE">Simon Michael,
Randal Schwartz, Simon Phipps: FLOSS Weekly 375: hledger</a> (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qS2UcDV_lbs">3m overview</a>, <a href="https://twit.tv/shows/floss-weekly/episodes/375">show notes</a>)
2016 <!-- 02-16 --></li>
<li><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TDqrrH-gTt0">John Wiegley,
Randal Schwartz, Aaron Newcomb: FLOSS Weekly 150: Ledger</a> (<a href="https://twit.tv/shows/floss-weekly/episodes/150">show notes</a>)
2011</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="slides"><a href="#slides">Slides</a></h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://rawcdn.githack.com/simonmichael/hledger/4013a81af8dd2804c73ecac18fb3e7e4745a4275/doc/haskellerz/haskellerz.slidy.html">Simon
Michael: Inside hledger: an architectural tour and how-to</a> 2021</li>
<li><a href="https://decks.mtlynch.io/plaintext-acccounting/">Michael
Lynch: An introduction to plaintext accounting</a> 2021</li>
<li><a href="https://pauley.org.za/functional-finance-hledger/">Andreas
Pauley: Purely Functional Personal Finance</a> 2018
<!-- gone - [Ledger CLI Accounting for Geeks](http://blog.loadingdata.nl/accounting-for-geeks/) 2014 --></li>
<li><a href="https://matthewturland.com/slides/ledger-stats/">Matthew
Turland: Hacking Your Finances for Fun and Profit</a> 2013
<!-- gone - [Ledger and Text based Accounting](http://www.adamsinfoserv.com/AISTWiki/pub/AIS/Presentations/Ledger.pdf) 2009 --></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="docs"><a href="#docs">Docs</a></h2>
<p><strong><a href="#accounting-basics">Accounting basics</a> , <a href="#pta-app-docs">PTA app docs</a> , <a href="#comparisons">Comparisons</a> , <a href="#intros">Intros</a> , <a href="#cheatsheets">Cheatsheets</a> , <a href="#cookbooks">Cookbooks</a>
, <a href="#faqs">FAQs</a> </strong></p>
<h3 id="accounting-basics"><a href="#accounting-basics">Accounting
basics</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/accounting.html">hledger: Accounting
basics</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/accounting.html#accounting-links">hledger:
Accounting links</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/100tGcA4blh6KSXPRGCZpUlyxaRUwFHEvnz_k9DyZFn4">Beancount:
The Double-Entry Counting Method</a></li>
<li><a href="https://martin.kleppmann.com/2011/03/07/accounting-for-computer-scientists.html">Accounting
for Computer Scientists</a></li>
<li><a href="https://podcastle.org/2009/10/09/pc-miniature-38-accounting-for-dragons">Accounting
for Dragons</a></li>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/FAQ.html" title="wikilink">FAQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="pta-app-docs"><a href="#pta-app-docs">PTA app docs</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ledger-cli.org/docs.html">Ledger</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/">hledger</a></li>
<li><a href="https://beancount.github.io/docs/">Beancount</a></li>
<li><a href="https://howeyc.github.io/ledger/">Ledger in Go</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tackler.e257.fi/docs/">Tackler</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mandoc.bsd.lv/pta/">pta</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="comparisons"><a href="#comparisons">Comparisons</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="#pta-apps">PTA apps</a> project stats</li>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/FAQ.html#which-pta-app-should-i-choose" title="wikilink">FAQ: Which PTA app should I choose ?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/ledger.html">hledger and Ledger</a>, <a href="https://hledger.org/beancount.html">hledger and Beancount</a>, <a href="https://hledger.org/cookbook.html#other-software">hledger and
other software</a> 2014, 2019, 2022, 2023..</li>
<li><a href="http://www.matthiaskauer.com/2015/08/command-line-accounting-a-look-at-the-various-ledger-ports/">Matthias
Kauer: Command Line Accounting – A look at the various ledger ports</a>
2015</li>
<li><a href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/beancount/QV4qgpFbtJ8/9fSgMw-XGC8J">beancount
mail list: Another Ledger user's perspective</a> 2015</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1dW2vIjaXVJAf9hr7GlZVe3fJOkM-MtlVjvCO1ZpNLmg">Beancount:
A Comparison of Beancount and Ledger</a> 2014</li>
<li><a href="https://groups.google.com/d/topic/ledger-cli/__yuMVjrOH0/discussion">ledger
list: ledger vs hledger vs beancount or how to choose the right cli
client</a> 2014
<!-- gone - [Omari Norman: Why Penny](http://massysett.github.io/penny/why-penny.html) 2013 -->
<!-- gone - [Fabrice Niessen: Why Ledger?] 2010 --></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="intros"><a href="#intros">Intros</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/What-is-Plain-Text-Accounting.html" title="wikilink">What
is Plain Text Accounting?</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rolfschr.github.io/gswl-book/latest.html">Getting
Started With Ledger</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/start.html">hledger: Get
Started</a></li>
<li><a href="https://beancount.github.io/docs/getting_started_with_beancount.html">Getting
Started with Beancount</a></li>
<li><a href="https://tackler.e257.fi/docs/quickstart/">Tackler:
Quickstart</a></li>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/Dont-Sink-Your-First-Attempts-at-Plaintext-Accounting.html" title="wikilink">Don't Sink Your First Attempts at Plaintext
Accounting</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.petekeen.net/keeping-finances-with-ledger">Program
your Finances: Command-line Accounting</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/colindean/plaintextaccounting_workshop">Plain
Text Accounting Workshop</a></li>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/Cookbook.html#getting-started" title="wikilink">Cookbook:
Getting started</a></li>
<li><a href="https://academy.beanhub.io/">BeanHub Academy: the definitive
guide to learning double-entry accounting with Beancount — the Zen of
Balance</a></li>
<li><a href="https://lazy-beancount.xyz/">Lazy Beancount: an opinionated
guide on Beancount</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cheatsheets"><a href="#cheatsheets">Cheatsheets</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/quickref/">Syntax Quick Reference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://devhints.io/ledger">Ledger CLI cheatsheet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://beancount.github.io/docs/beancount_cheat_sheet.html">Beancount
Syntax Cheat Sheet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledgerfan.com/beginners-corner-a-basic-hledger-transaction/">Beginners
corner: a basic hledger transaction</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledgerfan.com/almost-everything-you-wanted-to-know-about-hledger-transactions/">(Almost)
everything you wanted to know about hledger transactions</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/hledger.html#journal-cheatsheet">hledger:
Journal cheatsheet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/hledger.html#csv-rules-cheatsheet">hledger:
CSV rules cheatsheet</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="cookbooks"><a href="#cookbooks">Cookbooks</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/Cookbook.html" title="wikilink">Cookbook</a> the Plain Text
Accounting Cookbook; more docs, examples...</li>
<li><a href="https://beancount.github.io/docs/command_line_accounting_cookbook.html">Beancount
cookbook</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/cookbook.html">hledger
cookbook</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ledger/ledger/wiki">Ledger wiki</a></li>
<li><a href="https://forum.plaintextaccounting.org/">PTA Forum</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/plaintextaccounting/new">Reddit:
plaintextaccounting</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="faqs"><a href="#faqs">FAQs</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://plaintextaccounting.org/FAQ.html" title="wikilink">FAQ</a> the Plain Text
Accounting FAQ</li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/faq.html">hledger FAQ</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ledger/ledger/wiki/FAQ">Ledger
FAQ</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="software"><a href="#software">Software</a></h2>
<p><strong><a href="#pta-apps">PTA apps</a> , <a href="#editor-plugins">Editor plugins</a> , <a href="#data-importconversion">Data import/conversion</a> , <a href="#price-fetching">Price fetching</a> , <a href="#data-generation">Data generation</a> , <a href="#workflows">Workflows</a> , <a href="#formatting">Formatting</a> ,
<a href="#reporting">Reporting</a> , <a href="#time-logging">Time
logging</a> , <a href="#ui-console">UI, console</a> , <a href="#ui-curses">UI, curses</a> , <a href="#ui-gui">UI, GUI</a> , <a href="#ui-web">UI, web</a> , <a href="#ui-mobile">UI, mobile</a> , <a href="#library">Library</a> , <a href="#utilities">Utilities</a> , <a href="#api">API</a> </strong></p>

<h3 id="pta-apps"><a href="#pta-apps">PTA apps</a></h3>
<p>To do Plain Text Accounting, try one (or more) of the apps below.
Generally it's possible to migrate data between them.</p>

<!--
Table syntax: https://pandoc.org/README.html#tables
Active projects are sorted by committers then stars/activity,
inactive projects are sorted by start date then last release date.

Commit activity (from https://hledger.org/reporting-version-control-stats.html)

           || 2003  2004  2005  2006  2007  2008  2009  2010  2011  2012  2013  2014  2015  2016  2017  2018  2019  2020  2021  2022  2023    Total 
===========++=======================================================================================================================================
 ledger    ||   50   327     0     0     0  1248  1462   437   153   706   708   578   367   115    55    78   130    90    42    55   162     6763 
 hledger   ||    0     0     0     0   150   407   610   606   529   350   365   567   542   732   892  1155  1089  1313  1131   832   773    12043 
 beancount ||    0     0     0     0     0   190    86    15    25    18   433  1484  1160   686   240   393   189   773   299   112    57     6160 
-----------++---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
           ||   50   327     0     0   150  1845  2158  1058   707  1074  1506  2629  2069  1533  1187  1626  1408  2176  1472   999   992    24966 

| Project   | Commits/day (2000s) | Commits/day (2010s) | Commits/day (2020s) |
|-----------|---------------------|---------------------|---------------------|
| Ledger    | 1.4                 | 0.9                 | 0.2                 |
| hledger   | 1.1                 | 1.9                 | 2.8                 |
| Beancount | 0.5                 | 1.3                 | 0.9                 |

| Project   | Commits/mo (2000s)  | Commits/mo (2010s)  | Commits/mo (2020s)  |
|-----------|---------------------|---------------------|---------------------|
| Ledger    | 41                  | 28                  |  7                  |
| hledger   | 32                  | 57                  | 84                  |
| Beancount | 13                  | 40                  | 27                  |

-->
<table>
<colgroup>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
<col>
</colgroup>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Project</th>
<th>Start</th>
<th>Last release</th>
<th>Code</th>
<th>Committers</th>
<th>Stars</th>
<th>Mail list, size</th>
<th>Chat, size</th>
<th>Issues, % open</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>&nbsp;</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Popular</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://www.ledger-cli.org/">Ledger</a></td>
<td>2003</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ledger/ledger">C++</a></td>
<td>226</td>
<td>4.9k</td>
<td><a href="https://list.ledger-cli.org/">ledger</a> ~900</td>
<td><a href="https://web.libera.chat/#ledger">IRC</a> ~60</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ledger/ledger/issues">1.5k</a> 47%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://hledger.org/">hledger</a></td>
<td>2007</td>
<td>2024</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/simonmichael/hledger">haskell</a></td>
<td>171</td>
<td>2.9k</td>
<td><a href="https://mail.hledger.org/">hledger</a> ~250</td>
<td><a href="https://matrix.to/#/#hledger:matrix.org">matrix</a> ~190,
<a href="https://web.libera.chat/#hledger">IRC</a> ~70</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/simonmichael/hledger/issues">1.4k</a>
24% (bugs: 0.7k, 8% open)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/beancount/">Beancount</a></td>
<td>2008</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/beancount/beancount/">python</a></td>
<td>84</td>
<td>3.1k</td>
<td><a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/beancount">beancount</a>
~700</td>
<td><a href="https://matrix.to/#/#beancount:matrix.org">matrix</a> ~10,
<a href="https://matrix.to/#/#beancount_fava:gitter.im">matrix
(fava)</a> ~190, <a href="https://web.libera.chat/#beancount">IRC</a>
~30</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/beancount/beancount/issues">0.5k</a>
63%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>&nbsp;</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Small userbase</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>[Ledger (Go)]</td>
<td>2013</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td>[go][ledger-go-src]</td>
<td>11</td>
<td>409</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Abandon</td>
<td>2013</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/hrj/abandon">scala</a></td>
<td>11</td>
<td>178</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://matrix.to/#/#hrj_abandon:gitter.im">matrix</a></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>knut</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td>2022</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/sboehler/knut">go</a></td>
<td>3</td>
<td>49</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://zhang-accounting.github.io/zhang">zhang</a></td>
<td>2023</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/zhang-accounting/zhang">rust/ts</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>105</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/SitanHuang/ledg">ledg</a></td>
<td>2021</td>
<td>2021</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/SitanHuang/ledg">javascript</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>37</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Goledger</td>
<td>2019</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mescanne/goledger">go</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>25</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>blossom</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/blossom-hub/blossom">F#</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>25</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>awk-pta</td>
<td>2022</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/filiphanes/awk-pta">awk</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>15</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://tackler.e257.fi/">Tackler</a></td>
<td>2017</td>
<td>2022</td>
<td><a href="https://gitlab.com/e257/accounting/tackler">scala</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>9</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://matrix.to/#/#tackler:matrix.org">matrix</a></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>coin</td>
<td>2019</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mkobetic/coin">go</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>7</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>budget-cli</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/joshcanhelp/budget-cli">typescript</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>2</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>mynt</td>
<td>2023</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://git.sr.ht/~kmaasrud/mynt">rust</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://dolfi.dev/placc">placc</a></td>
<td>2024</td>
<td></td>
<td>nim</td>
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>&nbsp;</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>Inactive</strong></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>bankroll</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td><a href="https://gitlab.com/dantuck/bankroll">rust</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://mandoc.bsd.lv/pta">pta</a></td>
<td>2020</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td><a href="https://cvsweb.bsd.lv/pta/">perl</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>acc</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/rudolfschmidt/acc">rust</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>rust_ledger</td>
<td>2019</td>
<td>2021</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ebcrowder/rust_ledger">rust</a></td>
<td>4</td>
<td>90</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://sboehler.github.io/beans">beans</a></td>
<td>2019</td>
<td>2019</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/sboehler/beans">haskell</a></td>
<td>2</td>
<td>24</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Transity</td>
<td>2018</td>
<td>2020</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/feramhq/transity">purescript</a></td>
<td>8</td>
<td>571</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://matrix.to/#/#feramhq_transity:gitter.im">matrix</a></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://prudent.me/">Prudent</a></td>
<td>2018</td>
<td></td>
<td>js, <a href="https://github.com/PrudentMe">addons</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://twitter.com/PrudentLedger">@PrudentLedger</a></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>.Net Ledger</td>
<td>2017</td>
<td>2021</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dmitry-merzlyakov/nledger">C#</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>164</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://matrix.to/#/#nledger_Lobby:gitter.im">matrix</a></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://monescript.github.io/">monescript</a></td>
<td>2017</td>
<td>2018</td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/monescript/monescript">javascript</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>12</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Go Ledger</td>
<td>2016</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/abourget/ledger">go</a></td>
<td>3</td>
<td>37</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>uledger</td>
<td>2015</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/danpat/uledger">python</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>17</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>pacioli</td>
<td>2013</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mdipierro/pacioli">python</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>31</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ledger.pl</td>
<td>2013</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dimonf/ledger.pl">perl</a></td>
<td>1</td>
<td>6</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Penny</td>
<td>2012</td>
<td>2014</td>
<td>haskell</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>UMM</td>
<td>2009</td>
<td>2010</td>
<td><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/UMM">haskell</a></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>sm-Ledger</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://gist.github.com/simonmichael/bb611dba654ccb1573e1">squeak</a></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>cl-ledger</td>
<td>2007</td>
<td></td>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ledger/cl-ledger">lisp</a></td>
<td>4</td>
<td>66</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>`` [Ledger (Go)]: <a href="https://howeyc.github.io/ledger/">https://howeyc.github.io/ledger/</a> [ledger-go-src]: <a href="https://github.com/howeyc/ledger">https://github.com/howeyc/ledger</a></p>
<!-- [compare at openhub](https://www.openhub.net/p/_compare?project_0=Ledger&project_1=hledger&project_2=beancount) -->
<h3 id="editor-plugins"><a href="#editor-plugins">Editor
plugins</a></h3>
<p><strong>Atom</strong> - <a href="https://atom.io/packages/language-ledger">language-ledger</a> - <a href="https://atom.io/packages/ledger">ledger</a><br>
<strong>Emacs</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/beancount/beancount-mode">beancount-mode</a> -
<a href="https://github.com/narendraj9/hledger-mode">hledger-mode</a> -
<a href="https://ledger-cli.org/doc/ledger-mode.html">ledger-mode</a>
(good for hledger also)<br>
<strong>IntelliJ</strong> - <a href="https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/15405-ledger-cli">Ledger
CLI</a><br>
<strong>Nano</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/scopatz/nanorc/blob/master/ledger.nanorc">scopatz/nanorc</a><br>
<strong>Sublime</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/moeffju/sublime-ledger-syntax">sublime-ledger-syntax</a><br>
<strong>TextMate</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/lifepillar/Ledger.tmbundle">Ledger.tmbundle</a><br>
<strong>VIM</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/ledger/vim-ledger">vim-ledger</a> - <a href="https://github.com/nathangrigg/vim-beancount">vim-beancount</a> -
<a href="https://github.com/anekos/hledger-vim">hledger-vim</a> - <a href="https://github.com/crispgm/cmp-beancount">cmp-beancount</a><br>
<strong>VS Code</strong> - <a href="https://github.com/mhansen/hledger-vscode">hledger-vscode</a> - <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=mariosangiorgio.ledger">ledger</a>
- <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=Lencerf.beancount">vscode-beancount</a></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/editors.html">hledger: Editor
configuration</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="data-importconversion"><a href="#data-importconversion">Data
import/conversion</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.ledger-cli.org/3.0/doc/ledger3.html#Comma-Separated-Values-files">Ledger</a>
and <a href="https://hledger.org/csv.html">hledger</a> have CSV
conversion built in. Also:</li>
<li>bean-identify, bean-extract, bean-file - Beancount built-in
tools</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tomszilagyi/banks2ledger">banks2ledger</a> -
CSV to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jbms/beancount-import">beancount-import</a> web
app/framework for converting various formats to beancount (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/redstreet/beancount_reds_importers">beancount-reds-importers</a>
Simple importers and tools for Beancount. A framework to allow you to
easily write your own importers.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hoostus/beancount-ynab">beancount-ynab</a>
Import YNAB4 (legacy desktop-based version) into beancount</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hoostus/beancount-ynab5">beancount-ynab5</a>
Import YNAB5 (cloud-based version) transactions into beancount</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-extract">beanhub-extract</a>
Simple Python library for extracting all kinds of bank export CSV files
into standardized transaction data objects</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-import">beanhub-import</a>
Declarative idempotent rule-based beancount transaction import engine in
Python consumes data extracted by <a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-extract">beanhub-extract</a></li>
<li><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/buchhaltung">buchhaltung</a>
CSV/FinTS/HBCI/OFX to *ledger conversion/deduplication (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.costflow.io/">Costflow</a> convert one line
message to beancount/*ledger format</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/PaNaVTEC/csv2beancount">csv2beancount</a> CSV
to beancount converter (clojure)</li>
<li><a href="https://launchpad.net/csv2ledger">CSV2Ledger</a> CSV to
*ledger converter (perl)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/deb-sig/double-entry-generator">double-entry-generator</a>
Rule-based double-entry bookkeeping importer (from Alipay/WeChat/Huobi
etc. to Beancount)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MoritzR/fints2ledger">fints2ledger</a>
FinTS/HBCI to csv to *ledger or beancount journals (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/nonducor/ddc97e787810d52d067206a592a35ea7/">gcash2ledger.py</a>
GNUCash XML to *ledger converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/henriquebastos/gnucash-to-beancount/">gnucash-to-beancount</a>
GNUCash sqlite to beancount converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MatzeB/pygnucash/blob/master/gnucash2ledger.py">gnucash2ledger.py</a>
GNUCash sqlite to *ledger converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Hawk777/grisbi2ledger">grisbi2Ledger</a>
Grisbi to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/simonmichael/hledger/blob/master/bin/gsheet-csv.hs">gsheet-csv.hs</a>
a script to download Google sheets (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/phobo3s/hledger-Excel">hledger-Excel</a>
Excel spreadsheet to *ledger journal converter (visual basic for
applications)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hpdeifel/hledger-import-dsl">hledger-import-dsl</a>
alternate, programmable CSV converter for hledger</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/barrucadu/hledger-scripts#hledger-to-influxdb">hledger-to-influxdb</a>
hledger to InfluxDB converter (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tjroth/hledger2beancount">hledger2beancount</a>
hledger to beancount converter (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/chazmcgarvey/homebank2ledger">homebank2ledger</a>
HomeBank to ledger and beancount converter (perl)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/quentinsf/icsv2ledger">icsvledger</a>
interactive CSV to *ledger converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/manishrjain/into-ledger">into-ledger</a>
CSV to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/invoice-x/invoice2data">invoice2data</a>
extract data from PDF invoices (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://git.darmstadt.ccc.de/jali/jali">jali</a>
downloader/importer to *ledger (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/maridonkers/kmymoney2hledger">kmymoney2hledger</a>
KMyMoney to *ledger converter (clojure)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isabekov/kmymoney2ledgers">kmymoney2ledgers</a>
KMyMoney to *ledger/beancount converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/isabekov/kmymoney2ledgers.awk">kmymoney2ledgers.awk</a>
KMyMoney to *ledger/beancount converter (Awk)</li>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.com/IanTwenty/ldgclip">ldgclip</a> import
bank transactions via the clipboard with one click (bash/awk)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/howeyc/ledger">Ledger in Go</a> has
limport, a CSV to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.com/egh/ledger-autosync">ledger-autosync</a>
OFX download, OFX to *ledger conversion, deduplication</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/j3k0/ledger-guesser">ledger-guesser</a>
neural network for generating entries like past ones, can be used with
ledger-autosync (javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ony/ledger-myexpenses">ledger-myexpenses</a>
MyExpenses android app sqlite db to *ledger conversion (python,
2017)</li>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.com/IanTwenty/ledgermyexpenses">ledgermyexpenses</a>
sync MyExpenses android app to/from Ledger (bash, 2023)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/glasserc/ledger-to-beancount/">ledger-to-beancount</a>
yet another simple ledger to beancount converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tlvince/ledger-tutorials">ledger-tutorials</a>
convert Pete Keen's tutorials to ebook format</li>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/travisdahlke/71152286b0a8826249fe">ledger2beancount.py</a>
*ledger to beancount converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/beancount/ledger2beancount">ledger2beancount</a>/<a href="https://github.com/beancount/beancount2ledger">beancount2ledger</a>
the best converter between h/ledger and beancount formats (perl).</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/lukasbestle/moneymoney-ledger">moneymoney-ledger</a>
MoneyMoney export extension for *ledger</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rcaputo/outofit">outofit</a> QuickBooks
to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sdementen/piecash">piecash</a> GNUCash
SQL to *ledger converter (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ebridges/plaid2qif">plaid2qif</a>
Download transactions from plaid as QIF or CSV files</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/madhat2r/plaid2text">plaid2text</a>
Plaid API to *ledger/beancount download/conversion</li>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/genegoykhman/3765100">qb2ledger</a>
QuickBooks General Journal CSV to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Kolomona/QIFtoLedger">QIFtoLedger</a>
(Bank of America's) QIF to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cantino/reckon">reckon</a> smart
interactive/non-interactive CSV to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/marvinpinto/slc">slc</a> generates
Ledger accounting entries, works with generic CSV files as well as the
Stripe API</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/johannesjh/smart_importer">smart_importer</a>
library for building smarter CSV to beancount/Fava converters</li>
<li><a href="https://www.tillerhq.com/">Tiller</a> service to download
from mostly-US banks to google or microsoft spreadsheets (commercial but
pretty good)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/eval/total_recall">total_recall</a> CSV
to *ledger converter</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vermiceli/ynab-to-ledger">ynab-to-ledger</a>
You Need A Budget (YNAB) to *ledger converter. Handles multiple
currencies, multiple number formats, reconciliation, memos, transfers,
and split transactions</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pgr0ss/ynab_to_ledger">ynab_to_ledger</a> You
Need A Budget to *ledger converter</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="price-fetching"><a href="#price-fetching">Price
fetching</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1thYRAMell_QT1Da1F_laprSs6BlROZjyK_h3V8qHW9c">bean-price</a>
Beancount's price fetching tool (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/prikhi/hledger-stockquotes">hledger-stockquotes</a>
download market prices for your hledger commodities (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/nathankot/ledger-get-prices">ledger-get-prices</a>
download market prices (ruby)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/adchari/LedgerStockUpdate">LedgerStockUpdate</a>
update a Ledger price database (go)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/barrucadu/hledger-scripts#market-prices">market-prices</a>
download market prices from several sources (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/maralorn/a288329af50955dff353e5529f377488">market-prices.hs</a>
small, easy to adapt script to scrape market data from the internet
(Haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.com/chrisberkhout/pricehist">pricehist</a>
fetch and format historical price data, with support for multiple
sources and output formats (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/the-solipsist/scripts/">the-solipsist/scripts</a>
download prices for your hledger commodities, including indian
commodities (bash)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="data-generation"><a href="#data-generation">Data
generation</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Mayeu/beancount-scripts">beancount-extract-price</a>
generate prices transactions based on your beancount ledger
(python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tazzben/DepreciateForLedger">DepreciateForLedger</a>
generate *ledger depreciation transactions (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/hledger-interest">hledger-interest</a>
generate *ledger interest entries (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hamsterbase/ledger-ts">ledger-ts</a>
typescript EDSL for generating beancount journals (typescript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/scarpent/ledgerbil">ledgerbil</a>
schedule recurring txns, interactive reconcile, date sorting</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tazzben/LedgerScheduler">LedgerScheduler</a>
move entries from one file to another when they come due (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://src.d10.dev/lotter">lotter</a> generate postings
for capital gain/loss (go)</li>
<li><a href="https://hub.darcs.net/simon/ledgertools/browse/recurring">recurring</a>
generate recurring *ledger entries (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/amitaibu/hledger-example/blob/master/reorder-journal.sh">reorder-journal.sh</a>
sort hledger entries, preserving directives/comments at top of file
(bash)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jvasile/sassetti">sassetti</a> adds lisp
macros to ledger files (common lisp)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="invoicing"><a href="#invoicing">Invoicing</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://kairosdotapp.github.io/">kairos</a> (<a href="https://github.com/kairosdotapp/kairos">repo</a>) generate
invoices from hledger timedot files (go)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="workflows"><a href="#workflows">Workflows</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://gitea.com/EvergreenCrypto/docker-finance">docker-finance</a>
hledger/hledger-flow/docker-based system for tracking and reporting on
traditional and cryptocurrency finances</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/adept/full-fledged-hledger">Full-fledged
hledger</a> scripts and detailed tutorial for generating hledger
journals from CSV files (haskell, shell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/apauley/hledger-flow">hledger-flow</a>
command-line tool to generate hledger (or Ledger) journals from CSV
files (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rotorkunstkultur/rtrledger">rtrledger</a>
another hledger journals from CSV files system, designed for chaotic
German freelancers (shell etc.)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Evernight/lazy-beancount">Lazy
Beancount</a> Beancount packaged in Docker with additional plugins and
tools</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="formatting"><a href="#formatting">Formatting</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beancount-black">beancount-black</a>
opinionated beancount file formatter</li>
<li><a href="https://app.beanhub.io/tools/beancount-formatter">beancount-black
web app</a> opinionated beancount file formatter as a web-based app</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="reporting"><a href="#reporting">Reporting</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sulemankm/budget_report">budget_report</a>
budget reporting with beancount (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/glorat/gainstrack">gainstrack</a>
personal wealth analysis app with beancount export
(scala/typescript)</li>
<li><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/hledger-diff">hledger-diff</a>
report differing transactions between two journals (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/hledger-irr">hledger-irr</a>
calculate an account's internal rate of return (superseded by <a href="https://hledger.org/hledger.html#roi">roi</a>) (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/adept/hledger-sankey">hledger-sankey</a>
Script + HTML files to plot income next to expense money flows from an
hledger ledger file (shell + javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rmuratov/hledger-tools">hledger-tools</a>
generating charts from hledger (typescript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/xitian9/hledger-vega">hledger-vega</a>
makes configurable <a href="https://vega.github.io/vega-lite/">vega-lite</a> charts from
hledger (shell)</li>
<li><a href="https://pypi.org/project/hreports">hreports</a> customise
hledger reports with templates and PDF output (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Tagirijus/ledger-plot">ledger-plot</a>
interactive tool for making GNUplot charts from Ledger (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/esovetkin/ledger-plots">ledger-plots</a>
R package &amp; script to make charts from Ledger (R)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/trevorld/r-ledger">r-ledger</a> an R
package for reading and reporting on ledger/hledger/beancount files
(R)</li>
<li><a href="https://framagit.org/jkepler/TaxingLots">TaxingLots</a>
calculates capital gains for a ledger journal (python)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="time-logging"><a href="#time-logging">Time logging</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jwiegley/org2tc">org2tc</a> org to
timeclock converter</li>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/wbsch/d977b0ac29aa1dfa4437">on-modify.timetrack.py</a>
taskwarrior hook for timeclock output</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/nuex/t">t</a> ledger timeclock
shellscript</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MatthiasKauer/tim">tim</a> time
logging/reporting tool using hledger</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/bbarker/timekeeping-template">timekeeping-template</a>
time logging/reporting examples/how-to using hledger</li>
<li><a href="https://mostlyabsurd.com/files/tito">tito</a> time logging
bash scripts that avoid double clock-in</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="ui-console"><a href="#ui-console">UI, console</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/simon-v/bean-add">bean-add</a>
interactive transaction entry tool (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/hledger.html#add">hledger add</a>
interactive transaction entry tool (builtin command)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ninewise/dotfiles/blob/master/local/bin/ladd">ladd</a>
create and edit a new *ledger transaction by fuzzy-matching past
descriptions</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/brandonpittman/ldgr">ldgr</a> command
line tool to add/sort/tag ledger files (ruby)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ledger-cli.org/3.0/doc/ledger3.html#xact">ledger
xact</a> history-aware transaction generator (builtin command)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="ui-curses"><a href="#ui-curses">UI, curses</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hpdeifel/hledger-iadd">hledger-iadd</a>
TUI for *ledger transaction entry (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/hledger-ui">hledger-ui</a> TUI
for *ledger browsing (haskell, <a href="https://asciinema.org/a/29665">video</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Tagirijus/ledger-add">ledger-add</a> TUI
for *ledger transaction entry (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/siddhantac/puffin">puffin</a> TUI for
hledger browsing (go)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/guillaumechereau/regdel">regdel</a> TUI
for browsing Ledger files (python)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="ui-gui"><a href="#ui-gui">UI, GUI</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sbridges/ledgerble">ledgerble</a>
reporting GUI with charts &amp; adjustable reports (Javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Rudd-O/ledgerhelpers">ledgerhelpers</a>
misc. GUI tools + helper library (Python, GTK)</li>
<li><a href="https://prudent.me/">Prudent</a> integrated journal
editing/importing/reporting GUI for Ledger (Javascript, mac only, closed
source)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="ui-web"><a href="#ui-web">UI, web</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/beancount/fava">fava</a> web UI for
beancount browsing (python, <a href="https://fava.pythonanywhere.com/">demo</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://hackage.haskell.org/package/hledger-web">hledger-web</a>
web UI for *ledger browsing, data entry (haskell, <a href="https://demo.hledger.org/">demo</a>, <a href="https://apps.sandstorm.io/app/8x12h6p0x0nrzk73hfq6zh2jxtgyzzcty7qsatkg7jfg2mzw5n90">Sandstorm
app</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://paisa.fyi/">Paisa</a> web UI or desktop app for
ledger, hledger and beancount (go, javascript, <a href="https://demo.paisa.fyi/">demo</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/howeyc/ledger">Ledger in Go</a> web UI
for browsing ledger transactions, reports, and porfolios</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/peterkeen/Ledger-Web">Ledger Web</a>
ledger HTML reporting system (ruby, postgres)</li>
<li><a href="https://vifon.github.io/ledger-web">Ledger Web</a> web
UI/API for ledger browsing, data entry (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/kendricktan/ledger-analytics">ledger-analytics</a>
web UI for ledger data analytics (javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Ikke/ledger-dashboard">ledger-dashboard</a> web
UI for ledger browsing, data entry (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://yingtongli.me/git/ledger-pyreport/about/">ledger-pyreport</a>
web UI for standard accounting statements and unrealised gains
(python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/thecount2a/ledgeraccounting">ledgeraccounting</a>
web UI for hledger: data entry, basic reports and budgets
(javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/lipidity/ledgible">ledgible</a> web UI
for ledger browsing, data entry (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/n4s-linux/n4s-gratis-regnskab/">n4s</a>
danish-language ERP system (php)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/slashdotdash/node-ledger-web">node-ledger-web</a>
web UI for ledger browsing (javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/readysetmark/WealthPulse">WealthPulse</a> web
UI for ledger browsing, price fetching (F#)</li>
<li><a href="https://beanhub.io/">BeanHub</a> web UI for beancount
browsing, data entry with a Git repository (proprietary SaaS; some
components open source)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="ui-mobile"><a href="#ui-mobile">UI, mobile</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://beancount.io/">Beancount</a> mobile app (Android,
IOS)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/xuhcc/beancount-mobile">beancount-mobile</a>
data entry app (Android)</li>
<li><a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/be.chvp.nanoledger">NanoLedger</a>
data entry app supporting the ledger and hledger syntax (Android)</li>
<li><a href="https://gitlab.com/alensiljak/cashier">cashier</a> mobile
or desktop client for ledger and hledger-web (Android/Desktop,
javascript, <a href="https://cashier.alensiljak.eu.org/">app</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://f-droid.org/en/packages/info.tangential.cone/">cone</a>
data entry app for the h/ledger format (Android, <a href="https://github.com/bradyt/cone">dart</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://fossdroid.com/a/mole.html">MoLe</a> mobile client
for hledger-web (Android, <a href="https://git.ktnx.net/?p=mobile-ledger.git">java</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://hledger.org/mobile.html">hledger.org: Mobile
apps</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="library"><a href="#library">Library</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beancount-parser">beancount-parser</a>
standalone <a href="https://github.com/lark-parser/lark">Lark-based</a>
beancount syntax parser (not relying on the beancount library)</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.rs/beancount-parser/latest/beancount_parser/">beancount-parser</a>
a Beancount parser in Rust using <a href="https://docs.rs/nom/latest/nom/">nom</a></li>
<li><a href="https://docs.rs/beancount-parser-lima/latest/beancount_parser_lima/">beancount-parser-lima</a>
another Beancount parser in Rust using <a href="https://docs.rs/logos/latest/logos/">Logos</a> and <a href="https://docs.rs/chumsky/latest/chumsky/">Chumsky</a></li>
<li><a href="https://sr.ht/~trs-80/beancount-txn-elisp">beancount-txn-elisp</a>
a library to read/parse and write/insert individual Beancount
transactions, implemented in Emacs Lisp</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-forms">beanhub-forms</a>
a library provides data types and processors of custom beancount forms
for inputting repeating similar entries easily</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-web-react">beanhub-web-react</a>
react components for beancount entry input forms and <a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-forms">beanhub-forms</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ericaltendorf/magicbeans/">magicbeans</a>
Beancount extensions for cryptocurrency tax tracking and reporting</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="utilities"><a href="#utilities">Utilities</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-cli">beanhub-cli</a>
beancount command line tools come with features like formatter, <a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beancount-import">beanhub-import</a>
and a <a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-forms">beanhub-forms</a>
web app</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="api"><a href="#api">API</a></h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/gledger/gledger">gledger</a> Go package
to interface with Ledger (go)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/simonmichael/hledger/tree/master/hledger-lib">hledger-lib</a>
library for parsing and generating reports from *ledger files
(haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/simonmichael/hledger/tree/master/hledger-web">hledger-web</a>
the web app includes a JSON API server for *ledger files (haskell)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Rudd-O/ledgerhelpers">ledgerhelpers</a>
extends Ledger's python library (python)</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rstacruz/node-hledger">node-hledger</a>
Node.js API for *ledger files (javascript)</li>
<li><a href="https://api.beanhub.io/redoc">BeanHub API</a> proprietary
SaaS API for operating on hosted beancount repositories and <a href="https://github.com/LaunchPlatform/beanhub-forms">beanhub-forms</a></li>
</ul>

<hr>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Paraguay Loves Mickey, the Cartoon Mouse. Disney Doesn't (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/14/world/americas/paraguay-mickey-mouse-disney.html</link>
            <guid>41550417</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 21:09:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/14/world/americas/paraguay-mickey-mouse-disney.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/14/world/americas/paraguay-mickey-mouse-disney.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550417">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/09/14/world/americas/paraguay-mickey-mouse-disney.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[g1: Using Llama-3.1 70B on Groq to create o1-like reasoning chains (293 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1</link>
            <guid>41550364</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 21:02:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1">https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550364">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">g1: Using Llama-3.1 70b on Groq to create o1-like reasoning chains</h2><a id="user-content-g1-using-llama-31-70b-on-groq-to-create-o1-like-reasoning-chains" aria-label="Permalink: g1: Using Llama-3.1 70b on Groq to create o1-like reasoning chains" href="#g1-using-llama-31-70b-on-groq-to-create-o1-like-reasoning-chains"></a></p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description g1_demo.1.mp4">g1_demo.1.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/175069511/367515444-db2a221f-f8eb-48c3-b5a7-8399c6300243.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjY0NTc3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyNjQ1NzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNzUwNjk1MTEvMzY3NTE1NDQ0LWRiMmEyMjFmLWY4ZWItNDhjMy1iNWE3LTgzOTljNjMwMDI0My5tcDQ_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwOTE2JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDkxNlQwMzMwMDJaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1kYjM3ZjNkYzI0OTU4Y2NiYzkxYjljYjNiN2JmYzkyYTFjNzA2MjUyMjU4YzIzOTA5ODAyZWU1YTA0ZGFkZGVlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.8QHjUArFx1iXwnDMtC6STsXvwQNgKo2k4ervEg4kdNo" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/175069511/367515444-db2a221f-f8eb-48c3-b5a7-8399c6300243.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjY0NTc3MDIsIm5iZiI6MTcyNjQ1NzQwMiwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNzUwNjk1MTEvMzY3NTE1NDQ0LWRiMmEyMjFmLWY4ZWItNDhjMy1iNWE3LTgzOTljNjMwMDI0My5tcDQ_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwOTE2JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDkxNlQwMzMwMDJaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1kYjM3ZjNkYzI0OTU4Y2NiYzkxYjljYjNiN2JmYzkyYTFjNzA2MjUyMjU4YzIzOTA5ODAyZWU1YTA0ZGFkZGVlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.8QHjUArFx1iXwnDMtC6STsXvwQNgKo2k4ervEg4kdNo" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto">This is an early prototype of using prompting strategies to improve the LLM's reasoning capabilities through o1-like reasoning chains. This allows the LLM to "think" and solve logical problems that usually otherwise stump leading models. Unlike o1, all the reasoning tokens are shown, and the app uses an open source model.</p>
<p dir="auto">g1 is experimental and being open sourced to help inspire the open source community to develop new strategies to produce o1-like reasoning. This experiment helps show the power of prompting reasoning in visualized steps, not a comparison to or full replication of o1, which uses different techniques. OpenAI's o1 is instead trained with large-scale reinforcement learning to reason using Chain of Thought, achieving state-of-the-art performance on complex PhD-level problems.</p>
<p dir="auto">g1 demonstrates the potential of prompting alone to overcome straightforward LLM logic issues like the Strawberry problem, allowing existing open source models to benefit from dynamic reasoning chains and an improved interface for exploring them.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How it works</h3><a id="user-content-how-it-works" aria-label="Permalink: How it works" href="#how-it-works"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">g1 powered by Llama3.1-70b creates reasoning chains, in principle a dynamic Chain of Thought, that allows the LLM to "think" and solve some logical problems that usually otherwise stump leading models.</p>
<p dir="auto">At each step, the LLM can choose to continue to another reasoning step, or provide a final answer. Each step is titled and visible to the user. The system prompt also includes tips for the LLM. There is a full explanation under Prompt Breakdown, but a few examples are asking the model to “include exploration of alternative answers” and “use at least 3 methods to derive the answer”.</p>
<p dir="auto">The reasoning ability of the LLM is therefore improved through combining Chain-of-Thought with the requirement to try multiple methods, explore alternative answers, question previous draft solutions, and consider the LLM’s limitations. This alone, without any training, is sufficient to achieve ~70% accuracy on the Strawberry problem (n=10, "How many Rs are in strawberry?"). Without prompting, Llama-3.1-70b had 0% accuracy and ChatGPT-4o had 30% accuracy.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h3><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Important</p><p dir="auto">g1 is not perfect, but it can perform significantly better than LLMs out-of-the-box. From initial testing, g1 accurately solves simple logic problems 60-80% of the time that usually stump LLMs. However, accuracy has yet to be formally evaluated. See examples below.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How many Rs are in strawberry?</h5><a id="user-content-how-many-rs-are-in-strawberry" aria-label="Permalink: How many Rs are in strawberry?" href="#how-many-rs-are-in-strawberry"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Prompt: How many Rs are in strawberry?</p>
<p dir="auto">Result:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1/blob/main/examples/strawberry.png"><img src="https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1/raw/main/examples/strawberry.png" alt="Strawberry example"></a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">Prompt: Which is larger, .9 or .11?</p>
<p dir="auto">Result:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1/blob/main/examples/math.png"><img src="https://github.com/bklieger-groq/g1/raw/main/examples/math.png" alt="0.9 or 0.11 example"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quickstart</h3><a id="user-content-quickstart" aria-label="Permalink: Quickstart" href="#quickstart"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To use the Streamlit UI, follow these instructions:</p>


<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip3 install -r requirements.txt"><pre><code>pip3 install -r requirements.txt
</code></pre></div>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export GROQ_API_KEY=gsk..."><pre><code>export GROQ_API_KEY=gsk...
</code></pre></div>

<hr>
<p dir="auto">Alternatively, follow these additional instructions to use the Gradio UI:</p>

<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip3 install -r requirements.txt"><pre><code>pip3 install -r requirements.txt
</code></pre></div>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Prompting Strategy</h3><a id="user-content-prompting-strategy" aria-label="Permalink: Prompting Strategy" href="#prompting-strategy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The prompt is as follows:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="You are an expert AI assistant that explains your reasoning step by step. For each step, provide a title that describes what you're doing in that step, along with the content. Decide if you need another step or if you're ready to give the final answer. Respond in JSON format with 'title', 'content', and 'next_action' (either 'continue' or 'final_answer') keys. USE AS MANY REASONING STEPS AS POSSIBLE. AT LEAST 3. BE AWARE OF YOUR LIMITATIONS AS AN LLM AND WHAT YOU CAN AND CANNOT DO. IN YOUR REASONING, INCLUDE EXPLORATION OF ALTERNATIVE ANSWERS. CONSIDER YOU MAY BE WRONG, AND IF YOU ARE WRONG IN YOUR REASONING, WHERE IT WOULD BE. FULLY TEST ALL OTHER POSSIBILITIES. YOU CAN BE WRONG. WHEN YOU SAY YOU ARE RE-EXAMINING, ACTUALLY RE-EXAMINE, AND USE ANOTHER APPROACH TO DO SO. DO NOT JUST SAY YOU ARE RE-EXAMINING. USE AT LEAST 3 METHODS TO DERIVE THE ANSWER. USE BEST PRACTICES.

Example of a valid JSON response:
json
{
    &quot;title&quot;: &quot;Identifying Key Information&quot;,
    &quot;content&quot;: &quot;To begin solving this problem, we need to carefully examine the given information and identify the crucial elements that will guide our solution process. This involves...&quot;,
    &quot;next_action&quot;: &quot;continue&quot;
}"><pre><code>You are an expert AI assistant that explains your reasoning step by step. For each step, provide a title that describes what you're doing in that step, along with the content. Decide if you need another step or if you're ready to give the final answer. Respond in JSON format with 'title', 'content', and 'next_action' (either 'continue' or 'final_answer') keys. USE AS MANY REASONING STEPS AS POSSIBLE. AT LEAST 3. BE AWARE OF YOUR LIMITATIONS AS AN LLM AND WHAT YOU CAN AND CANNOT DO. IN YOUR REASONING, INCLUDE EXPLORATION OF ALTERNATIVE ANSWERS. CONSIDER YOU MAY BE WRONG, AND IF YOU ARE WRONG IN YOUR REASONING, WHERE IT WOULD BE. FULLY TEST ALL OTHER POSSIBILITIES. YOU CAN BE WRONG. WHEN YOU SAY YOU ARE RE-EXAMINING, ACTUALLY RE-EXAMINE, AND USE ANOTHER APPROACH TO DO SO. DO NOT JUST SAY YOU ARE RE-EXAMINING. USE AT LEAST 3 METHODS TO DERIVE THE ANSWER. USE BEST PRACTICES.

Example of a valid JSON response:
json
{
    "title": "Identifying Key Information",
    "content": "To begin solving this problem, we need to carefully examine the given information and identify the crucial elements that will guide our solution process. This involves...",
    "next_action": "continue"
}
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Breakdown</h4><a id="user-content-breakdown" aria-label="Permalink: Breakdown" href="#breakdown"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">First, a persona is added:</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">You are an expert AI assistant that explains your reasoning step by step.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Then, instructions to describe the expected step-by-step reasoning process while titling each reasoning step. This includes the ability for the LLM to decide if another reasoning step is needed or if the final answer can be provided.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">For each step, provide a title that describes what you're doing in that step, along with the content. Decide if you need another step or if you're ready to give the final answer.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">JSON formatting is introduced with an example provided later.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Respond in JSON format with 'title', 'content', and 'next_action' (either 'continue' or 'final_answer') keys.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">In all-caps to improve prompt compliance by emphesizing the importance of the instruction, a set of tips and best practices are included.</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Use as many reasoning steps as possible. At least 3. -&gt; This ensures the LLM actually takes the time to think first, and results usually in about 5-10 steps.</li>
<li>Be aware of your limitations as an llm and what you can and cannot do. -&gt; This helps the LLM remember to use techniques which produce better results, like breaking "strawberry" down into individual letters before counting.</li>
<li>Include exploration of alternative answers. Consider you may be wrong, and if you are wrong in your reasoning, where it would be. -&gt; A large part of the gains seem to come from the LLM re-evaluating its initial response to ensure it logically aligns with the problem.</li>
<li>When you say you are re-examining, actually re-examine, and use another approach to do so. Do not just say you are re-examining. -&gt; This encourages the prevention of the LLM just saying it re-examined a problem without actually trying a new approach.</li>
<li>Use at least 3 methods to derive the answer. -&gt; This helps the LLM come to the right answer by trying multiple methods to derive it.</li>
<li>Use best practices. -&gt; This is as simple as the "Do better" prompts which improve LLM code output. By telling the LLM to use best practices, or do better, it generally performs better!</li>
</ol>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">USE AS MANY REASONING STEPS AS POSSIBLE. AT LEAST 3. BE AWARE OF YOUR LIMITATIONS AS AN LLM AND WHAT YOU CAN AND CANNOT DO. IN YOUR REASONING, INCLUDE EXPLORATION OF ALTERNATIVE ANSWERS. CONSIDER YOU MAY BE WRONG, AND IF YOU ARE WRONG IN YOUR REASONING, WHERE IT WOULD BE. FULLY TEST ALL OTHER POSSIBILITIES. YOU CAN BE WRONG. WHEN YOU SAY YOU ARE RE-EXAMINING, ACTUALLY RE-EXAMINE, AND USE ANOTHER APPROACH TO DO SO. DO NOT JUST SAY YOU ARE RE-EXAMINING. USE AT LEAST 3 METHODS TO DERIVE THE ANSWER. USE BEST PRACTICES.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Finally, after the problem is added as a user message, an assistant message is loaded to provide a standardized starting point for the LLM's generation.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Assistant: Thank you! I will now think step by step following my instructions, starting at the beginning after decomposing the problem</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Credits</h3><a id="user-content-credits" aria-label="Permalink: Credits" href="#credits"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This app was developed by <a href="https://x.com/benjaminklieger" rel="nofollow">Benjamin Klieger</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bluesky Reaches 10M Accounts (188 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bsky.app/profile/bsky.app/post/3l47prg3wgy23</link>
            <guid>41550053</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 20:20:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/bsky.app/post/3l47prg3wgy23">https://bsky.app/profile/bsky.app/post/3l47prg3wgy23</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550053">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux dev swatted and handcuffed live during a development video stream (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tomshardware.com/software/linux/linux-dev-swatted-live-during-a-development-video-stream</link>
            <guid>41550043</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 20:19:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/software/linux/linux-dev-swatted-live-during-a-development-video-stream">https://www.tomshardware.com/software/linux/linux-dev-swatted-live-during-a-development-video-stream</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550043">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article-body">
<p>Two days ago, tech streamer and host of Code Therapy René Rebe was streaming one of many T2 Linux (his own custom distribution) development sessions from his office in Germany when he abruptly had to remove his microphone and walk off camera due to the arrival of police officers. The officers subsequently cuffed him and took him to the station for an hour of questioning, a span of time during which the stream continued to run until he made it back.</p><p>René Rebe and fans of his work can only guess what motivated this incident. Unfortunately, the police seemingly have no idea who did it and acted based on a tip sent with an email. Finding the perpetrators could take a while, and options will be fairly limited if they don't also live in Germany.&nbsp;</p><div data-nosnippet="">
<div>
<p><span>I got SWAT'ed and handcuffed LIVE while Linux development streaming! - YouTube</span>
<img src="https://img.youtube.com/vi/FIEwcTKUFCA/maxresdefault.jpg" alt="I got SWAT'ed and handcuffed LIVE while Linux development streaming! - YouTube" data-aspect-ratio="16/9" loading="lazy">
</p>
</div>
<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 234.67 165.33"><path fill="red" d="M229.763 25.817c-2.699-10.162-10.65-18.165-20.748-20.881C190.716 0 117.333 0 117.333 0S43.951 0 25.651 4.936C15.553 7.652 7.6 15.655 4.903 25.817 0 44.236 0 82.667 0 82.667s0 38.429 4.903 56.85C7.6 149.68 15.553 157.681 25.65 160.4c18.3 4.934 91.682 4.934 91.682 4.934s73.383 0 91.682-4.934c10.098-2.718 18.049-10.72 20.748-20.882 4.904-18.421 4.904-56.85 4.904-56.85s0-38.431-4.904-56.85"></path><path fill="#fff" d="m93.333 117.559 61.333-34.89-61.333-34.894z"></path></svg>
<a href="https://youtu.be/FIEwcTKUFCA" target="_blank" data-url="https://youtu.be/FIEwcTKUFCA" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">Watch On <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 507.9 113.39"><g fill="#fff"><path d="M64.792 80.99V32.396l42.082 24.297zm93.803-63.285a20.285 20.285 0 0 0-14.32-14.32C131.642 0 80.99 0 80.99 0S30.337 0 17.705 3.385a20.286 20.286 0 0 0-14.32 14.32C0 30.338 0 56.693 0 56.693S0 83.049 3.385 95.68A20.285 20.285 0 0 0 17.705 110c12.632 3.386 63.285 3.386 63.285 3.386s50.652 0 63.285-3.386a20.284 20.284 0 0 0 14.32-14.32c3.385-12.632 3.385-38.988 3.385-38.988s0-26.355-3.385-38.988m94.473 74.326c.887-2.314 1.332-6.098 1.332-11.35V58.556c0-5.097-.445-8.822-1.332-11.178-.888-2.355-2.452-3.533-4.69-3.533-2.163 0-3.69 1.178-4.577 3.533-.888 2.356-1.332 6.081-1.332 11.178V80.68c0 5.25.424 9.035 1.275 11.35.848 2.318 2.392 3.475 4.633 3.475 2.239 0 3.803-1.157 4.691-3.475zm-17.953 11.122c-3.207-2.16-5.486-5.52-6.835-10.079-1.352-4.554-2.027-10.617-2.027-18.185v-10.31c0-7.644.771-13.784 2.316-18.417 1.544-4.633 3.956-8.011 7.24-10.135 3.282-2.123 7.587-3.186 12.916-3.186 5.251 0 9.459 1.082 12.626 3.243 3.165 2.162 5.482 5.542 6.95 10.136 1.466 4.595 2.2 10.715 2.2 18.36v10.31c0 7.567-.714 13.65-2.142 18.243-1.43 4.595-3.747 7.955-6.951 10.077-3.205 2.124-7.548 3.186-13.03 3.186-5.64 0-10.06-1.082-13.263-3.243m248.053-57.981c-.81 1.005-1.352 2.646-1.621 4.923-.272 2.278-.404 5.734-.404 10.367v5.097h11.697V60.46c0-4.555-.155-8.011-.463-10.367-.309-2.355-.868-4.014-1.678-4.98-.812-.966-2.067-1.449-3.766-1.449-1.7 0-2.954.503-3.765 1.506zm-2.025 29.886v3.591c0 4.557.132 7.974.404 10.251.269 2.279.828 3.94 1.68 4.982.849 1.041 2.16 1.564 3.938 1.564 2.392 0 4.035-.927 4.923-2.781.887-1.853 1.37-4.942 1.447-9.268l13.785.812c.077.62.116 1.469.116 2.548 0 6.565-1.795 11.47-5.387 14.712-3.589 3.242-8.669 4.865-15.232 4.865-7.876 0-13.398-2.47-16.564-7.414-3.168-4.94-4.75-12.586-4.75-22.935V63.589c0-10.657 1.641-18.436 4.924-23.342 3.281-4.903 8.9-7.355 16.854-7.355 5.482 0 9.691 1.004 12.626 3.012 2.933 2.01 5 5.137 6.197 9.383 1.197 4.247 1.796 10.117 1.796 17.607v12.163h-26.757m-284.953-1.33-18.187-65.68h15.869l6.37 29.77c1.623 7.339 2.82 13.594 3.591 18.766h.464c.54-3.706 1.738-9.922 3.591-18.65l6.603-29.886h15.869l-18.417 65.68v31.51h-15.754v-31.51M322.115 34.23v71.007h-12.511l-1.39-8.688h-.347c-3.399 6.564-8.496 9.845-15.291 9.845-4.71 0-8.185-1.543-10.425-4.633-2.24-3.087-3.359-7.915-3.359-14.48V34.23h15.985v52.126c0 3.168.348 5.426 1.043 6.776.695 1.353 1.853 2.027 3.475 2.027 1.39 0 2.722-.423 3.996-1.275 1.274-.849 2.22-1.928 2.838-3.241V34.229h15.986m81.995.001v71.007h-12.511l-1.391-8.688h-.345c-3.402 6.564-8.498 9.845-15.292 9.845-4.711 0-8.186-1.543-10.426-4.633-2.24-3.087-3.358-7.915-3.358-14.48V34.23h15.985v52.126c0 3.168.347 5.426 1.041 6.776.696 1.353 1.855 2.027 3.476 2.027 1.391 0 2.723-.423 3.996-1.275 1.275-.849 2.22-1.928 2.839-3.241V34.229h15.985"></path><path d="M365.552 20.908h-15.87v84.329h-15.637v-84.33h-15.869V8.05h47.376v12.858m76.811 53.636c0 5.174-.215 9.229-.639 12.162-.424 2.937-1.139 5.021-2.143 6.255-1.004 1.236-2.357 1.854-4.053 1.854a7.404 7.404 0 0 1-3.65-.927c-1.12-.618-2.026-1.544-2.722-2.78V50.796c.54-1.93 1.467-3.513 2.78-4.749 1.313-1.234 2.74-1.853 4.285-1.853 1.623 0 2.876.637 3.766 1.91.886 1.275 1.505 3.418 1.853 6.43.348 3.011.523 7.297.523 12.857zm14.652-28.964c-.967-4.478-2.531-7.721-4.692-9.73-2.163-2.007-5.136-3.011-8.919-3.011-2.935 0-5.676.83-8.224 2.49a16.926 16.926 0 0 0-5.908 6.545h-.117l.001-37.416h-15.405v100.777h13.204l1.622-6.717h.347c1.235 2.393 3.088 4.285 5.56 5.675 2.47 1.39 5.213 2.085 8.225 2.085 5.404 0 9.382-2.491 11.931-7.471 2.548-4.982 3.823-12.76 3.823-23.341V64.23c0-7.953-.484-14.17-1.448-18.65"></path></g></svg></a>
</div><p>For those unfamiliar with René's body of work, let's get you caught up. Per his official About page, he's been contributing to Linux since as early as 1998 and started his own T2 SD3 Embedded Linux distribution in 2004, as well. Since then,&nbsp;<a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://github.com/rxrbln?tab=repositories" target="_blank" data-url="https://github.com/rxrbln?tab=repositories" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">his GitHub page has ballooned to nineteen public repositories,</a>&nbsp;and he's known throughout the FOSS (Free and Open Source Software) community as a contributor to numerous major projects.&nbsp;</p><p>Linux, FOSS, and other such communities are compelled by little-to-no profit motive, so in essence, René has been providing unpaid software development for the greater good for the past two decades.</p><p>Speculation is still abound as to who did this. Thirty minutes before the stream was interrupted, René did have to ban an angry troll, whom he mentions in a YouTube comment as one possible perpetrator. Others think someone from the Rust (programming language, not video game) development community was responsible due to how critical René has been of that project, but those claims are entirely unsubstantiated.&nbsp;</p><p>Fortunately, René Rebe and his loved ones are safe in the aftermath of this incident, though they likely won't feel totally safe for quite some time.&nbsp;</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-2kDTr5jAfA3yAWwWNUwqUo"><section><p>Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.</p></section></div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Lead Your Team When the House Is on Fire (343 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://peterszasz.com/how-to-lead-your-team-when-the-house-is-on-fire/</link>
            <guid>41550017</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2024 20:16:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://peterszasz.com/how-to-lead-your-team-when-the-house-is-on-fire/">https://peterszasz.com/how-to-lead-your-team-when-the-house-is-on-fire/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41550017">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p>The tech industry is going through challenging times: from one side, funding dried up <a href="https://newsletter.pragmaticengineer.com/p/zirp?ref=peterszasz.com">due to the end of the Zero Interest-Rate Period</a>; on the other one, <a href="https://unchartedterritories.tomaspueyo.com/p/how-ai-disrupts-tech-investing?ref=peterszasz.com">the rapid rise of AI disrupts previously safe domains and business models</a>. These forces are <strong>pushing companies to "wartime" mode</strong>, a concept I first read about in the works of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/stores/David-B.-Black/author/B001KJ1JI2?ref=peterszasz.com">David B. Black</a>, some of which were published in "<a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/19497794-wartime-software?ref=peterszasz.com">Wartime Software: Building Software when Speed Matters</a>"; or the <a href="https://a16z.com/peacetime-ceo-wartime-ceo?ref=peterszasz.com">Peacetime CEO / Wartime CEO</a> article from Ben Horowitz, similarly from more than a decade ago. </p><p>These works describe "wartime" as an existential fight for survival that requires a different type of leadership compared to the relative prosperity of "peacetime". Many of the principles outlined by both Horowitz and Black are as relevant as ever for Engineering Managers leading in today's climate. For EMs, wartime means leading low-morale teams through <strong>ambiguity, hard constraints, frequently changing goals, and intense pressure to perform</strong>. It can feel like working in a house on fire. What can an EM do in this situation? </p><p>Let's get back to the basics, and look at the role of an Engineering Manager first.</p><h2 id="the-three-focus-areas-of-an-engineering-manager">The three focus areas of an Engineering Manager</h2><ol><li>Ensuring <strong>delivery</strong> that's aligned with company goals;</li><li>Building and sustaining a <strong>high-performing engineering team</strong>;</li><li>Supporting the success and <strong>personal growth</strong> of the individuals on the team.</li></ol><p>Wartime doesn't change these fundamentals, but it does require some shifts in approach and priorities. Let's go through them by focus areas.</p><h2 id="focus-area-1-ensuring-goal-aligned-delivery">Focus Area 1: Ensuring Goal-Aligned Delivery</h2><p>In wartime, you need your team <strong>laser-focused on shipping what matters most, now</strong>. Your organization might not have the luxury of years of runway, and the environment you're operating in is rapidly changing. A few key things to get right:</p><p><strong>Ruthless prioritization is essential.</strong> Narrow the team's attention to the top few goals that are critical for the company's survival and success. Communicate these repeatedly and reinforce them through your own behavior. Be ready to say no and drop anything that doesn't directly contribute. It's hard because you'll also need to say "no" to genuinely valuable, profitable things, projects you were planning to work on, just to be able to deliver the ones that are the most impactful now. Mentally you might find it easier to categorize these projects as "not now".</p><p>Next, you need to <strong>empower the team to move fast</strong>. Decentralize decision-making authority as much as possible. Remove barriers in their way, slash approval layers, attack dependencies. "Perfection is the enemy of done" and "Better to ask for forgiveness than permission" are good guidance. </p><p>To enable quick decisions, ensure you are frequently and clearly giving high-level context to the team, so they are aligned on company objectives. Set up a clear process for them to rapidly get input on critical choices and transparently communicate the decision to keep everyone aligned. <strong>Bias heavily toward action</strong> - it's better to decide and be wrong sometimes than to paralyze the team with analysis.</p><p><strong>Protect the team's focus time</strong>. The chaos and uncertainties of wartime can be incredibly distracting. Set up processes to shield the team from constant interruptions so they can have deep, creative work sessions. Remove them from low-value meetings and relieve them from monotonous administrative duties. One effective technique is to establish a rotating "firefighter" role to singlehandedly deal with any incoming requests, represent the team in meetings, and handle the necessary amount of bureaucracy, allowing the rest to stay heads-down on the critical priorities.</p><p>Another option is to <strong>get in the trenches with your team</strong>. If you're a hands-on manager, wartime is when you can put some effort into technical tasks. Stay closely involved to understand the technical context, and help out where it makes sense. This can mean doing some code reviews, participating in pair programming, handling an incident, and even pushing small commits if that's what's needed. Make sure you're not taking the spotlight from your team members, and know that your impact in management areas can be magnitudes bigger than a small code cleanup.</p><p>It's important to note that these wartime actions will probably increase<strong> tech debt</strong> in your code. With the emphasis on velocity over quality, architectural compromises and maintenance shortcuts are often taken. To mitigate this, consider techniques like:</p><ul><li>Keeping a visible, prioritized backlog of tech debt items to revisit later</li><li>Allocating a small percentage of each sprint to debt paydown</li><li>Pairing tech debt work with feature development</li><li>Conducting regular architecture reviews to spot and address emerging issues</li><li>Encouraging engineers to flag risky shortcuts during code reviews</li></ul><p>You have more chance to succeed if your tech debt strategy is backward-looking, refactoring parts of the code that are causing concrete pain for developers today – as opposed to forward-looking, dreaming up grandiose plans for new frameworks that will be ready for any unknown challenge of the future. (Recognise that these challenges are unknown by definition, so your solution for them will be a hit-and-miss.) The risk of overengineering is real and can cripple developer performance significantly in a wartime era. </p><h2 id="focus-area-2-building-and-leading-the-team">Focus Area 2: Building and Leading the Team</h2><h3 id="retaining">Retaining</h3><p>To keep your team engaged and performing at their peak, <strong>don't neglect morale and energy</strong>. Celebrate quick wins, show frequent appreciation, praise the behavior you want to see. Acknowledge that the situation is tough, but project confidence that you'll get through it together.</p><p>One major pitfall to avoid is letting an <strong>"us vs. them" mentality</strong> take hold on the team. Naturally, the stress of painful decisions can erode trust in leadership and other departments, but reinforcing a negative mindset will hurt you more than the temporary warm camaraderie you'll enjoy by joining the chorus of cynics. </p><p>Don't dismiss or avoid the negative reactions, in fact, you should actively solicit concerns and input rather than waiting for issues to erupt. You cannot choose if people will discuss stressful events, but you can <strong>choose to be a part of these discussions</strong> or not. So never skip your one-on-one meetings, hold ad-hoc Q&amp;As, and maintain these as a safe, open forum for any topics. Share the "why" behind difficult decisions, even if you can't always explain all the details – and acknowledge what you don't know transparently. Assume good intent and extend empathy, even when tension is running high. <em>(I write more about this and related topics in </em><a href="https://peterszasz.com/how-to-represent-decisions-you-disagree-with/"><em>How To Represent Decisions You Disagree With</em></a><em>.)</em></p><p><strong>Focus on the positive aspects of the job that can be taken for granted</strong>, like the opportunity to work on cutting-edge challenges, the company's still existing perks and benefits, the amazing team you have, the chance to work with a modern tech stack, or how your product is helping its users. Showing your team how you appreciate what's still good can help with morale.</p><p>At the same time, <strong>accept that you won't be able to retain everyone</strong> through a stressful wartime period. If someone does decide to leave, support their decision and work to make the transition as smooth as possible for them and the remainder of the team.</p><h3 id="hiring">Hiring</h3><p>Yes, there is still hiring in wartime, though more limited than during the growth-heavy periods of peace. If for no other reason, you might need to backfill folks due to the increased attrition. When you receive a new headcount, you need to<strong> prioritize hiring experienced, self-sufficient, autonomous engineers</strong> who can tolerate (even better, strive) in high-stress environments and are experienced enough to contribute immediately. Tighten onboarding to the bare essentials and focus on deploying code fast. You don't have months to train, the company might not exist long enough to get back the investment in juniors if you focus on the long term now. </p><p>Fortunately for you, the current job market is full of experienced developers due to mass layoffs. However, expectations are still high (especially around compensation and remote work), and AI companies are paying above market rate to the best talent. These, and the massive work necessary to go through sometimes hundreds of applications make your work harder, so you need to get creative and proactive to attract great candidates. Some ideas:</p><ul><li>Leverage your network for referrals and backdoor references;</li><li>Emphasize anything that makes your company unique: its mission, product, tech stack, learning opportunities, compensation policies, hybrid friendliness, etc. Maybe someone out there is looking for the same exact criteria. </li><li>Partner closely with recruiters or the talent acquisition team to increase the quality of the first-level filtering, and to refine and expedite the hiring process;</li><li>Move quickly and decisively when you find a strong fit, to minimize the distraction of hiring on you and the team – but due to the current job market you have more luxury now than a few years ago. Consider allowing 2-3 candidates to pass through all rounds, and choose the best fit from them. Still, don't let this grow into indecisiveness, and don't drag the team into a long period of interviewing.</li></ul><h3 id="performance-management">Performance Management</h3><p>Wartime pressure can breed <strong>negativity</strong> that you'll need to manage carefully. Understand the context that may be contributing, like uncertainty around job security or maybe some additional personal issues. However, infectious negativity and lack of engagement are performance issues, so handle them accordingly: <strong>give clear feedback on actions and their impact</strong>, separate from any judgment of the individual. Avoid public confrontation, but set firm expectations. Try to redirect negative energy productively by reframing complaints into problems to solve. <em>(I write more about this topic in </em><a href="https://peterszasz.com/how-to-deal-with-negative-behaviour/"><em>How to Deal with Negative Behavior</em></a><em>.)</em></p><p>Crucially, <strong>hold everyone to the same standards</strong>, regardless of circumstances. You can't afford to make exceptions for someone just because they have key knowledge or skills you don't want to lose. Consistent accountability is essential for team cohesion and morale – and if you forget this, you might end up with a disengaged, demoralized team, and the underperforming key developer that you wanted to save might already be interviewing anyway.</p><h2 id="focus-area-3-supporting-individuals-to-succeed">Focus Area 3: Supporting Individuals to Succeed</h2><p>When the house is on fire, it's tempting to put personal development on the back burner <em>(no pun intended)</em>. But now is the time when your team members need to feel more than ever that you're still invested in their success, to help them stay engaged and motivated. The trick is to <strong>reframe growth to fit the wartime context</strong>.</p><p>Instead of formal skills training or career pathing, focus on maximizing each person's impact by leaning into their strengths. Help them see how this challenging period is <strong>an opportunity to stretch and step up</strong> in ways that will serve them well in the future.</p><p><strong>Call out the valuable, transferrable experience they're gaining</strong> by operating in this high-stakes environment. Emphasize that they're building "career security" - capabilities and experiences that will be valued anywhere - even if short-term "job security" may feel shaky and uncertain.</p><p><strong>Identify on-the-job learning opportunities</strong>, like giving someone the chance to lead an incident response or a high-visibility project. Critical mistakes can still be catastrophic, but because of the fast-changing nature of wartime work, it's easier to process smaller errors with a healthy learning mindset. <em>(Read more about </em><a href="https://peterszasz.com/celebrating-failure/"><em>Celebrating Failure</em></a><em>.)</em></p><p>Finally, don't forget to look for <strong>opportunities to display small gestures to show you care</strong> about your team members' personal well-being despite everything that's going on. Make the few team-building occasions count, or simply send a note acknowledging a tough week. A little goes a long way.</p><h2 id="finally-take-care-of-yourself-first">Finally: Take Care of Yourself First</h2><p>Leading in wartime is incredibly demanding. You won't be able to show up for your team if you're running on empty. Remember to put on your own oxygen mask first, before you try to help others.</p><ul><li><strong>Prioritize the basics</strong> of healthy eating, sleeping, and exercising. Treat your body as a machine that needs regular maintenance.</li><li><strong>Find peers</strong> within or outside of your organization who get the challenges you're facing, to vent with and get support. </li><li><strong>Carve out little breaks of relief</strong>, whether it's a walk, a short meditation, or just a quick game of chess (or backgammon!) in the communal area. A small recharge can help a lot.</li><li><strong>Keep a healthy context</strong>: while it might seem overpowering during the day, after all, this is just a job, and you should find other sources of satisfaction in your life besides your work.</li></ul><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2><p>Wartime stretches and strains Engineering Managers especially hard because they receive pressure from above and below. By ruthlessly focusing on well-aligned delivery, building a resilient team, investing in individuals, and maintaining your own health, you can lead your team to not just survive but thrive under pressure. Keep calm, "lean into the suck", and trust that you've got what it takes. Your people count on you.</p><p>I write about Engineering Leadership topics similar to this one.&nbsp;<a href="https://peterszasz.com/how-to-lead-your-team-when-the-house-is-on-fire/#/portal/signup" rel="noreferrer">Sign up here to receive my future articles by email.</a></p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>