<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 15:00:11 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: What is your experience with Nano-Hydroxyapatite toothpaste? (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37888728</link>
            <guid>37888728</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 11:01:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37888728">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="37888891"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889386"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889386" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889386&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Maybe Tooth Mousse is great.<p>But I gotta call BS on the idea that dentists don’t promote it because it’s against their interests. By that logic, they wouldn’t promote brushing and flossing at all.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889785"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889785" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889785&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>If you look up academic studies on flossing they nearly all say the same thing, it doesn’t prevent cavities more than brushing and the studies normally end with “well flossing isn’t hurting anything so might as well keep doing it”.<p>Flossing only helps with gingivitis in which case mouth rinses perform better.</p><p>In the studies that do show flossing helps against cavities they are about professional flossing and not self flossing.</p><p>So dentists continue to push unfounded claims regarding flossing.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890017"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890017" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890017&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; If you look up academic studies on flossing they nearly all say the same thing, it doesn’t prevent cavities more than brushing and the studies normally end with “well flossing isn’t hurting anything so might as well keep doing it”.<p>That’s actually a misrepresentation of the studies. It gets pushed by journalists because contrarian “doctors are wrong” takes are very popular, especially when they tell people what they want to hear.</p><p>The issue with flossing is that it’s hard to rigorously study over the duration needed to provide significant results. You also can’t really construct a study where you ask one cohort to not study for a couple decades to see if they do worse, because that has ethical concerns. So we’re left with self-reported flossing activity retrospectives. The problem with those is that people who floss tend to have better hygiene and self-care overall, so now we can’t isolate flossing as the reason for better dental health over a lifetime.</p><p>&gt; In the studies that do show flossing helps against cavities they are about professional flossing and not self flossing.</p><p>This is an example of what I’m talking about: There are studies out there that show positive benefits of flossing, but if you find someone aggressively searching for reasons to discredit flossing then they’ll always find a reason to dismiss the evidence. When the goal becomes to be contrarian or to disprove something, you can always find a reason to dismiss the studies.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890007"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890007" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890007&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>If brush my teeth, then I floss, bits of food still come out from between my teeth (they're quite tightly spaced). I don't need an academic study to confirm whether or not the flossing is helpful (unless you're disputing the causal link between food residue and tooth decay)</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890198"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890198" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890198&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I don't get the criticisms about the effectiveness of flossing. I'm a regular flosser and get all sorts of stuff out from between my teeth that brushing doesn't. Without flossing, that stuff would surely just be stuck there for longer and causing bad breath and whatever else. Maybe other people's teeth aren't as tightly packed or something.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890022"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890158"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889462"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889462" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889462&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I don't think GP meant dentists don't promote it so you keep coming back. Sometimes doctors and pharmacists recommend drugs because they've been paid to promote it, and if nobody's paying to promote this one it's not going to get recommended as often, especially if there's a competing drug that does the same thing.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889042"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889042" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889042&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Thank you, this is the first time I’ve come across this company/product so I’ll give it a shot. One thing that always confuses me about these speciality toothpastes is do I have to keep using them for an indefinite period of time (like fluoride) or do I stop once I get what I want out of it? Right now I use Sensodyne with Stannous Fluoride.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37888927"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888927" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888927&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Now I’m suddenly curious: does enamel regrow the way a precipitate mineral will fill in gaps of a porous rock, or is it a more biological process?<p>Anyways, thanks for the link. I’m going to read then probably try this out.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37888997"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889012"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889012" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889012&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I think its the former because enamel is a mineral and not living tissue—This is just my uneducated opinion though.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889261"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889261" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889261&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Last few times I went for a teeth cleaning, I was told about how "tarter" (the supposed "bad stuff") develops mostly around where the saliva glands excrete into the mouth.<p>I added this to how I was able to have a full hole in my tooth fill back (when poor and in college) in by just keeping it clean, not eating junk food, and swishing spit in my mouth around that tooth religiously for a long time.</p><p>Dentist later said, "nope, didn't happen, teeth don't work that way"
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889589"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889589" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889589&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Happened to me too, I was surprised  when it just stopped hurting one day and healed<p>Aside: My wife recently had a kid and the experience taught me how much work gets done to you just because you're being monitored that you may not actually need. You definitely need to know your own body and trust yourself to some degree. At least pregnancy is having a resurgence in "natural" birth.</p><p>Is dentistry the same? I could see this as plausible. My assumption at times has been that people's teeth all just fell out immediately before the 1900s lol, which is probably further from the truth
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889311"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889311" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889311&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; keeping it clean, not eating junk food, and swishing spit in my mouth around that tooth religiously for a long time.<p>This is why I’ve decided to follow an OMAD (One Meal a Day) diet, if I have to dirty up my mouth to survive, I’ll at least do it one time a day.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889341"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889341" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889341&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I removed white sugar/corn syrup from my diet and my teeth have rarely had issues for many years. Even when I skipped regular teeth brushing in the past.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889779"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889779" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889779&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Note: It can take several decades for the damage to accumulate, even for completely absurd diets. It is very difficult to observe results from changes to lifestyle or routine and correctly attribute them.<p>Take these anecdotes with a grain of salt.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890068"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889627"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889627" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889627&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I want to do that too but it’s a hellish nightmare because sugar is in nearly everything sold at  grocery stores, and living in a big city there are also endless temptations. I did manage to kick the habit of putting sugar in tea and coffee though, which is good because I drink those nearly everyday.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890097"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="6"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="240"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890097" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890097&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Congrats!! Building/stopping habits step by step is easier. Your freewill is  stronger than the groceries, wish you success.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890276"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="7"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="280"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890276" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890276&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I love this comment because I am a strong advocate of free will, but sometimes I forget that I have it. Thank you.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="37889725"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889725" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889725&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>One meal a day honestly sounds like a good way to mess with your blood sugar - at the very least it won't do you any favors, and you'll still have calcium build-up and possible staining from what you drink, and little mechanical use also means whatever gets in gets to stick around longer.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890087"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890087" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890087&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I mean it may at first but the body is good at adapting to changes like this for long term (Keto diet is an excellent example of this). Besides I will still be eating carbohydrates (simple and complex) just one time a day but not in the same quantity as 3 meals a day. Reserves of sugar are also stored in the liver in case the body is really desperate for it.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889880"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889880" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889880&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>It doesn't mess with your blood sugar. Assuming you're eating a low sugar meal with high fat and complex starches, your blood sugar stays at a normal level. It does take time for your body to adjust, though.<p>I can wake up and go for a 15 mile hike with no breakfast and not feeling hungry.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890061"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890061" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890061&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>If you could do serious damage to yourself only eating once a day we would've died out hundreds of thousands of years ago.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890113"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37890058"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889829"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889829" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889829&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>There is an American meme that believes that not eating often and regularly is unhealthy.  It’s untrue.  Study after study shows that fasting is good for us.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889938"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="6"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="240"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889938" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889938&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Exactly. And no one wonders why the countries with the highest rates of obesity are those in which a high calorie breakfast is the norm and actively recommended.<p>Breakfast is the least natural meal, you should not even be hungry when you wake up, it's unhealthy and should be skipped.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                          <tr id="37888974"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888974" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888974&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Fwiw, our dentist in Australia recommended this for a brief period for one of our kids as he had concerns about their enamel.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889153"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889070"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889070" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889070&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I used GC Tooth-Mousse after teeth whitening, and the sensitivity noticeably decreased. It is simple to apply and has a nice taste. Recommend it!</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889095"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890270"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890043"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890043" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890043&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>In a dental office they would squeeze quite a lot into the tooth trays and have it sit on your teeth for 3 mins or so, much like a fluoride treatment.<p>At home, put some on your finger and rub it on the front and back of your teeth, let sit for 3 mins.</p><p>Rinse it off after that time, no eating or drinking for at least 30 mins after.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37889076"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37888928"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889174"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37890195"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890251"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889411"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889411" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889411&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I’m so glad I made this thread, a wealth of information and recommendations from many people. I no longer feel my situation is hopeless, thank you guys.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37888964"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889292"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889292" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889292&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>There's some association between grinding and sleep apnea, so keep an eye out for it.  I ground my teeth for years before apnea, and now that I use a CPAP I notice I grind less. I used to have to get the strongest mouthguard available because I'd chew through them. I got clear aligners a couple years ago and they're quite thin and haven't chewed through my retainer yet.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890143"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890143" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890143&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Caffeine as well. When I cut caffeine to 200mg a day, grinding drops by like 90%. Supplementing magnesium before bed helps significantly.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889052"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889052" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889052&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>&gt; Another thing which is extremely helpful and I wish I had begun much earlier in life is night mouthguards because grinding your teeth in your sleep even in a subtle way does add up over years and years.<p>I use one too and usually need replacement about every 18 months. I'm wondering how bad it is to swallow all the plastic. I guess most of it is too big and just moves through the digestive system as is, but I wonder if that grinding also creates particles that are small enough to stay around in the body.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889139"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889139" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889139&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>18 months?  Wow, mine has lasted 15 years so far. At this point the food chain is so contaminated with microplastics that the amount we are getting from our mouth guards is probably the least of our problems.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889147"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889147" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889147&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Add it to the massive pile of other sources of microplastics entering the body, including the air we breathe and food we eat. I’m inhaling microplastics as I write this comment because of my shirt, we’re all fucked!</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37888967"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37888984"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889014"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889014" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889014&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I sometimes have to come back to it, but rarely now, maybe once a year. But I changed many things about my oral and physical health so hard to say what is keeping them mineralized.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889609"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889609" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889609&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>What other things did you change about oral health? I’ve been using probiotics and biofilm dissolvers to great success, but am always looking for more ways.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889685"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889108"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889731"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889731" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889731&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>FWIW if you want a "quick and easy" (not necessarily great/long term) solution, toothpastes like sensodyne do work pretty decently. I had very painful teeth as a kid, reducing (gum/tooth) inflammation + a few weeks of those tooth-sensitivity toothpaste has reduced my sensitivity permanently by a good bit, maybe 60%.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889823"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889823" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889823&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I already use Sensodyne protect and repair (stannous fluoride and potassium something, not Novamin) and while it does certainly help I just want a permanent fix because the sensitivity has gotten really, really tiresome.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889146"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889633"><td></td></tr>
                                          <tr id="37890038"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890038" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890038&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>On the topic of toothpaste, I developed a reaction to SLS - Sodium Laurel Sulfate. That's when I switched to Sensodyne, because it doesn't contain SLS. For awhile, Sensodyne was a problem and I began using Baking Soda. Then returned to Sensodyne after a few weeks.<p>Before this sensitivity, someone asked if I whitened my teeth because they were whiter. Using an electric toothbrush changed the color of my teeth for the better.</p><p>A Water-Pik helps the gums rejuvenate as does flossing.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889182"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889182" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889182&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I have been using Dr. Jen's Super Paste: <a href="https://drjennatural.com/products/dr-jen-super-paste-with-nano-hydroxyapatite-fluoride" rel="nofollow noreferrer">https://drjennatural.com/products/dr-jen-super-paste-with-na...</a><p>I landed on this one out of all the N-Ha brands because it also has flouride.  Also, it doesn't have SLS, which I feel good about.</p><p>I used to need Sensodyne to manage tooth sensitivity.  I would go out of my way to buy Canadian or UK Sensodyne with Novamin, since the Novamin formulations aren't sold in the U.S.  However, Jen's has eliminated the tooth sensitivity without needing a numbing agent like Sensodyne, which was surprising to me.</p><p>I've stuck with Jen's even though it's more expensive.  I can't speak to whether it's strengthened my enamel appreciably, but my teeth feel much better.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890203"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889397"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889397" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889397&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Since we are talking dental health, any insights into gingival recession? I think my gums have receded due to brushing them too hard over the years. You can’t tell unless you flip my gums back.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890172"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889534"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889534" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889534&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Oh boy that’s another beast I am trying to slay. All I keep hearing is that once gums start receding there’s no regenerating it, only stopping it from getting worse and I just have a hard time buying such a simple explanation. It could be hubris talking, I can’t really tell you one way or the other.<p>Uneducated Speculation:
My theory is that the gums can regenerate and regain attachment loss but only in the right conditions -&gt; in practice that would mean that they are not inflamed, and clean underneath the gum line (you can do that by flossing and getting a deep cleaning at a dentist if you need one), as well as doing your best to eliminate harmful bacteria that turn into calculus, and having a healthy diet.</p><p>The trickiest part is probably selectively eliminating the bad bacteria while retaining the good ones The mouth is full of both  and mouthwashes like Listarine, or any Alcohol based ones are sledgehammers. Some washes are too harsh on the tissue itself too which I imagine impairs healing of any kind.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889636"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889636" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889636&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Xylitol does selectively inhibit some bad strains, and some oral probiotics (K2 BLIS, L. Sakei, B. Subtilis) are quite aggressive in killing off other species.<p>Might also be worth looking into all the substrates required for bone and connective tissue building, apart from the obvious (calcium, magnesium), e.g. silica, iron and copper.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889893"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37889579"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889579" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889579&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Have the same. I changed the way I brush. I used to push hard into the gum line.<p>Now what I do is more like sweeping; I use a regular toothbrush, and pull it over my teeth and gums at an angle to increase the sweeping area. This cleans much more of my month, so it’s less acidic, and this just feels better than what I was doing before. I also floss to break up biofilms in the gumline. Gums much happier.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889461"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37890045"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889017"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889017" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889017&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>In the US and Germany they say there is no solid evidence suggesting that they keep what they promise. I personally use what seems to be an Italian brand called Biorepair and they clearly help with my tooth sensitivities(I have a bad habit of chewing on my nails when stressed).<p>Biorepair seems to have split into an Italian version and a German version with less active ingredients called Bioniq. The Italian versions seems to add xylitol.</p><p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/s?k=biorepair&amp;i=hpc&amp;crid=3BEZX0VR8DUDG&amp;sprefix=biorepair%2Chpc%2C337&amp;ref=nb_sb_noss_1" rel="nofollow noreferrer">https://www.amazon.com/s?k=biorepair&amp;i=hpc&amp;crid=3BEZX0VR8DUD...</a>
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889495"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889495" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889495&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Relative bought this toothpaste recently and it looks sketchy AF. No ingredients listed anywhere (clearly violating EU regulations) plus snake oil name. I looked into company and they started making this toothpaste very recently so its not even like they have any experience.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37888854"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888854" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888854&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I'm curious too, so this is more a piggybacking question: Silver diamine is said to be the perfect cavity treatment, cheap, fast, and effective with the only downside being staining of the teeth. Does anyone on HN have silver diamine experiences to share?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37888996"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888996" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888996&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>When my oldest daughter began developing cavities in her baby molars, our dentist used silver diamine to stave off putting in a filling until she was older.<p>It was a stopgap measure; it only slowed the decay, not prevent or reverse it, and we had to switch to a three month checkup cycle to monitor the situation and reapply the silver diamine.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889697"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889697" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889697&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I use apagard premio, came across it while doing research a couple of years ago (4-5) on nano hydroxyapatite. I've never really had problems with my adult teeth and I continue to not have problems, so at the very least, in my case, is not any worse than fluoride toothpaste. My dentist loves my teeth :D she told me whatever I'm doing, don't change a single thing.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37888837"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888837" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888837&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I use MI Paste. I don't brush with it. Instead I place it in custom teeth whitening trays and let it sit for an hour or so. It's very helpful for reducing sensitivity!<p>I also have Curodont Protect, but haven't tried it yet.</p><p>Curious to hear others' experiences!
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889307"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889307" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889307&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>To be fair I don't really have any real problems with my teeth apart from having had an overeager/greedy childhood dentist who put in a ton of fillings, making for a lifetime of occasionally having to redo one and needing 2 crowns.<p>I switched to Apagard about 8 months ago. My hygienist seemed happy about it. I like the fact that it's not overwhelmingly minty like most American toothpastes and doesn't foam up too much. I think if I manage to avoid needing new fillings or a redo for 6-7 years (about the frequency at which I need one) I would consider it a good switch.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889364"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889364" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889364&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Damn greedy dentists are some of worst kinds of people imo. It’s like in their head they swore to do harm, not the opposite.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889439"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889543"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889543" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889543&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Knowing what I know now about dentistry, I would only ever let a dentist drill a tooth where I can actually see decay.  If I can't see it, and the X-ray looks dubious, I'd just outright refuse.  And then I'd see another dentist.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="37889161"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889161" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889161&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Lots of Vitamin D and Vitamin K2 removed most if not all of my tooth sensitivity over the course of a month.<p>About 5 normal Vitamin D pills every few days so.</p><p>I was trying to treat something else out of desperation and noticed my tooth sensitivity more or less vanished.</p><p>Which makes sense when considering their role.</p><p>But as always, n=1.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889240"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889240" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889240&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>This is really interesting to me because D helps in Calcium and Phosphate (building blocks of enamel) absorption, and K2 helps in using them to build bone. If they really were the only culprit in ridding you of your sensitivity than that means your body regenerated Enamel on its own. n=1 aside your comment gives me renewed faith in the human body.<p>What brand of K2 and Vitamin D did you use?
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37890030"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890030" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890030&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Be careful with very high doses of vitamin D supplements if you have a family history of heart disease - over the long term it can increase calcium buildup elsewhere as well, which can damage the heart (amongst other things).</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889303"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889730"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889730" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889730&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I've been using a tooth paste with hydroxypatite for a little more than one year. Mostly for the enamel in my front teeth. I can see it works to some extend. The corrosion from the upper side of the teeth have stopped and I can see improvement of the already eroded side but I am talking about less than a milimiter. It is not a quick solution, and it requires dental higyne routinely. As for the price, I found that of you get the tooth paste in bulk it is more affordable.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889474"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889474" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889474&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I use a sensodyne toothpaste that has biomin in it. I'm not good about brushing and every once in a while the right side of my face hurts around my upper or lower molars or something and I'll remember to brush again and take an Aleve and it goes away within a day or two.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889512"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889512" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889512&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Do you have an electric toothbrush? It helps with timing and is generally considered to brush better.<p>But really, get back into the habit of brushing your teeth twice daily. It's one investment that pays of hugely in avoided trouble and costs.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889772"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889100"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889013"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889013" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889013&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>You should also try Sensodyne repair and protect. I heard it's not available in the US,  but the EU ones contain Novamin which really helps sensitive tooth.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889047"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37888867"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888867" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888867&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Bought both apagard royal and apagard premio. I like the taste much more compared to classic ones, but I can't say I've seen some improvements in my teeth, looks the same as when I used Splat or Sesnsodyne protect&amp;repair.<p>Also, consider that apagard usually doesn't have compounds that make your teeth less sensible like other toothpaste</p><p>Also, fyi- you should not wash your mouth after brushing, just spit the extra paste and wash after ~10-20 mins, this is valid for fluoride variations too</p><p>Anyway, just buy a tube (start with premio) and see how it goes
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889106"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889106" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889106&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Apagard workded for me.  Dentist noticed a difference, too.<p>I later added a xylitol rinse after brushing, and that seems to be doing even better.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889780"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37890197"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37890197" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37890197&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>When my teeth get too sensitive I swish with clove oil and that works well. I put a couple drops of oil in the bottom of a glass and fill it with about a cup of water.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889554"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37889554" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37889554&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Since no one's mentioned it yet - I had really sensitive gums for a while, and it was because I was very anemic, after the anemia was dealt with the sensitivity was gone. So if you have other symptoms of anemia also (fatigue, random dizziness, wanting to chew ice, etc) &amp; haven't had it checked in a while maybe ask your doctor about it.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889574"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889944"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37888876"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37888876" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37888876&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37888728"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Have tried Boka, Apagard, David’s, and Elims. I have come to much prefer the lack of foaming (I think due to SLS) and they’ve helped my sensitivity slightly. I would recommend them to anyone over fluoride toothpastes due to the possible neurotoxicity of the latter, especially for children.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889791"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37889198"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37889300"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37888929"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37889887"><td></td></tr>
                  </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA["Hacker News" for retro computing and gaming (237 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.jgc.org/2023/10/hacker-news-for-retro-computing-and.html</link>
            <guid>37888144</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 08:57:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.jgc.org/2023/10/hacker-news-for-retro-computing-and.html">https://blog.jgc.org/2023/10/hacker-news-for-retro-computing-and.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37888144">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-2143438896200001510" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p>I noticed over time that I was drawn to the retro computing or gaming posts on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/news">Hacker News</a>. So, I've set up a dedicated web site in the same style called <a href="https://twostopbits.com/news">Two Stop Bits</a>. The site works pretty much exactly the same as Hacker News because it's running my modified version of the Hacker News source code as released with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arc_(programming_language)">Arc language</a>.</p><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhR_XxfD3pIr33XalzCPIe8PxBkgmoG4V8KTvM50k3oz0O6KleKPvy146xFDBjPrNnxePmI_6GpAFFTeZVi-VjKcV6Wh53gbYlzq2ICmNm-Cr2rTy29gbaxGEN66tQ1jnIl0c-ZTom9uFKCpPG_x4lZu9ePyB4LBXFxRk91mGuS8fYYy4_FAznVDQ/s1454/tsb-1.png" imageanchor="1"><img data-original-height="1454" data-original-width="1390" height="640" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhR_XxfD3pIr33XalzCPIe8PxBkgmoG4V8KTvM50k3oz0O6KleKPvy146xFDBjPrNnxePmI_6GpAFFTeZVi-VjKcV6Wh53gbYlzq2ICmNm-Cr2rTy29gbaxGEN66tQ1jnIl0c-ZTom9uFKCpPG_x4lZu9ePyB4LBXFxRk91mGuS8fYYy4_FAznVDQ/w612-h640/tsb-1.png" width="612"></a></p><p>If you're interested in reading about (and posting about) retro computing or gaming <a href="https://twostopbits.com/news">feel free to stop by.</a></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cloudflare Sippy: Incrementally Migrate Data from AWS S3 to Reduce Egress Fees (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.infoq.com/news/2023/10/cloudflare-sippy-migrate-s3/</link>
            <guid>37888135</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 08:55:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2023/10/cloudflare-sippy-migrate-s3/">https://www.infoq.com/news/2023/10/cloudflare-sippy-migrate-s3/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37888135">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
								<p>Cloudflare recently announced the<a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/sippy-incremental-migration-s3-r2/"> open beta of Sippy</a>, an incremental data migration service that copies data from Amazon S3 to Cloudflare R2 only the first time the data is requested. Sippy is designed to minimize migration-specific egress fees by leveraging requests within existing application flows while simultaneously copying objects to R2.</p>

<p>Earlier this year, Cloudflare announced <a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2022/11/cloudflare-r2-super-slurper/">Super Slurper</a>, a data migration tool to copy large amounts of data from other object storage providers to Cloudflare R2. The new option targets scenarios where developers want to move only accessed data. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/phillipdjones/">Phillip Jones</a>, senior product manager at Cloudflare, and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/vlad-krasnov-2a00a666/">Vlad Krasnov</a>, principal system engineer at Cloudflare, explain the benefits of Sippy over the existing Super Slurper:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>While Super Slurper is perfect for cases where you want to move all of your data to R2 at once, there are scenarios where you may want to migrate your data incrementally over time. Maybe you want to avoid the one-time upfront AWS data transfer bill? Or perhaps you have legacy data that may never be accessed, and you only want to migrate what’s required?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The new option acts as a middle layer between the client and the source object storage: when an object is requested from Workers, S3 API, or a public bucket, it is served from <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/r2">Cloudflare R2</a> if it is found. If not, the object will be returned from the source S3 bucket and copied simultaneously to R2. All other operations on R2, including put and delete, continue to work. Jones and Krasnov add:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>On top of addressing vendor lock-in, Sippy makes stressful, time-consuming migrations a thing of the past. All you need to do is replace the S3 endpoint in your application or attach your domain to your new R2 bucket and data will start getting copied over.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/r2/data-migration/sippy/">documentation</a> shows how to enable Sippy for an existing R2 bucket with <em>cURL</em>:</p>

<pre><code>curl -X PUT https://api.cloudflare.com/client/v4/accounts/{account_id}/r2/buckets/{bucket_name}/sippy \
--header "Authorization: Bearer &lt;API_TOKEN&gt;" \
--data '{"provider": "AWS", "bucket": "&lt;AWS_BUCKET_NAME&gt;", "zone": "&lt;AWS_REGION&gt;","key_id": "&lt;AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID&gt;", "access_key":"&lt;AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY&gt;", "r2_key_id": "&lt;R2_ACCESS_KEY_ID&gt;", "r2_access_key": "&lt;R2_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY&gt;"}'</code></pre>

<p>Cloudflare plans on making incremental migration configurable from the dashboard and providing analytics showing the progress of the migration and how much has been saved on egress fees for objects that have been copied over.</p>

<p>Sippy is currently in open beta and supports only Amazon S3 as a migration source. During the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/birthday-week-2023-wrap-up/">Birthday Week</a>, the connectivity company made other announcements that target migrations from what Cloudflare calls "legacy cloud providers": <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/amazon-2bn-ipv4-tax-how-avoid-paying/">how to avoid paying Amazon’s IPv4 tax</a>, the general availability of <a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2023/10/cloudflare-turnstile-ga-free/">Turnstile</a>, a reCAPTCHA alternative, and <a href="https://www.infoq.com/news/2023/10/cloudflare-hyperdrive-postgres/">Hyperdrive</a>, a service that accelerates SQL queries reducing the load and cost on cloud-managed databases.<br>
&nbsp;</p>

								









  
    <div> <!-- main wrapper for authors section -->
        <h2>About the Author</h2> <!-- section title -->

        
            
                
            
            <div data-id="author-Renato-Losio">
                    <h4><strong>Renato Losio</strong></h4>
                    
                </div>
        
    </div>

							</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google has sent internet into 'spiral of decline', claims DeepMind co-founder (310 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.telegraph.co.uk/business/2023/10/14/google-internet-spiral-of-decline-deepmind-mustafa-suleyman/</link>
            <guid>37887562</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 07:01:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/business/2023/10/14/google-internet-spiral-of-decline-deepmind-mustafa-suleyman/">https://www.telegraph.co.uk/business/2023/10/14/google-internet-spiral-of-decline-deepmind-mustafa-suleyman/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37887562">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-test="article-body-text">
  
  

	

	
	

	
	



  
  
    <p>Google has plunged the internet into a “spiral of decline”, the co-founder of the company’s artificial intelligence (AI) lab has claimed.</p><p><a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/technology/2019/12/06/deepminds-founder-leaves-britains-brightest-ai-lab-really-free/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mustafa Suleyman</a>, the British entrepreneur who co-founded DeepMind, said: “The business model that Google had broke the internet.”</p><p>He said search results had become plagued with “clickbait” to keep people “addicted and absorbed on the page as long as possible”.</p><p>Information online is “buried at the bottom of a lot of verbiage and guff”, Mr Suleyman argued, so websites can “sell more adverts”, fuelled by Google’s technology.</p><p>Mr Suleyman was one of three people who set up pioneering AI lab DeepMind in London 2010. The company was bought by Google for £400m and it has become the cornerstone of the search giant’s AI operations.</p><p>Mr Suleyman, 39, quit Google 18 months ago and has since set up a rival venture, Inflection AI. The company is developing a conversational chatbot, similar to ChatGPT, amid a race by AI companies to usurp Google’s dominance of the web.</p><p>The entrepreneur has developed a chatbot called Pi, which he says can act as a kind of AI confidante or coach. He has raised more than $1.5bn for the new technology.</p><p>The criticism of his former employer came as Mr Suleyman told the Telegraph about plans for a new international body to monitor AI threats.</p><p>Mr Suleyman, along with billionaire former Google chief executive Eric Schmidt, plan to present proposals for an International Panel on AI Safety at Prime Minister <a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/business/2023/09/23/artificial-intelligence-safety-summit-sunak-ai-experts/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rishi Sunak’s global summit</a> on the technology next month.&nbsp;</p><p>The DeepMind co-founder said the panel could be “modelled on the IPCC” – the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change – to “establish the scientific consensus around the current capabilities” of AI.</p><p>Mr Suleyman said the IPCC, which was first set up in 1988, was a “good inspiration” for establishing a “rigorous body” for making predictions about AI risks. Other backers of the plan include Reid Hoffman, the billionaire LinkedIn founder, and Florentino Cuéllar, president of the Carnegie think tank.</p><p>The AI panel would provide governments with regular assessments on the level of danger posed by the technology.</p><p>The UK’s AI Safety Summit is due to take place at Bletchley Park and is expected to gather world leaders and tech entrepreneurs to address the challenges of “frontier AI” that might cause “significant harm, including the loss of life”.</p><p>The two-day summit on Nov 1 and 2 is expected to be attended by top lobbyists from the likes of Meta and Google. Kamala Harris, the US vice president, is expected to attend, while a Chinese delegation has been invited.&nbsp;</p><p>The leaders will try to find common ground on tackling AI risks. Officials are also understood to be considering setting up an international institute for AI safety.</p>
  
</div><div data-test="article-body-text">
  
  

	

	
	

	
	



  
  
    <p>Michelle Donelan, the technology secretary, told the Telegraph the&nbsp;conference would “consider the biggest risks and biggest opportunities that come from frontier AI”, bringing together “companies, countries and also experts”.&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/business/2023/05/23/chatgpt-sam-altman-ai-regulation-risk-fears/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Concern about the technology</a> has been sparked by the overnight success of ChatGPT, which was seen as a wake-up call for world leaders about the speed at which the technology was being developed.&nbsp;</p><p>A new wave of chatbots, built on so-called “large language models”, can answer questions and have online conversations in an almost uncannily human way. They can write emails, essays, poetry or music, prompting concerns they could create upheaval in the jobs market.</p><p>Writing in his recent book, The Coming Wave, Mr Suleyman called for a “containment” of high-risk AI advances, so governments can get ahead of developments that may threaten jobs, elections and human life.&nbsp;</p><p>Mr Suleyman said chatbots could “take on Google” by providing more accurate information than internet search.</p><p>However, despite recent advances, many chatbots suffer from errors and in some cases may make up false information, creating a hurdle to taking on search engines.&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/business/2023/02/13/google-microsofts-ai-bots-will-pollute-internet-digital-effluence/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Google is also developing</a> a rival AI chatbot project, called Bard.&nbsp;</p><p>Google was approached for comment.&nbsp;</p><p>Meanwhile on Saturday, the Government confirmed 100 winners of £5m in grant funding for AI start-ups, including a business tackling clothing waste and a company finding a use for the technology in vineyards.&nbsp;</p><p>Ms Donelan also announced a further £32m in grant funding for high-growth businesses using AI, to be confirmed after the UK summit.</p>
  
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[BeagleV-Ahead open-source RISC-V single board computer (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.beagleboard.org/boards/beaglev-ahead</link>
            <guid>37887341</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 06:12:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.beagleboard.org/boards/beaglev-ahead">https://www.beagleboard.org/boards/beaglev-ahead</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37887341">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
  <div>
    <nav>
  <div>
      <nav aria-label="breadcrumb"><ol>&nbsp;»&nbsp;<li><a href="https://www.beagleboard.org/" rel="v:url" property="v:title">Home</a></li>&nbsp;»&nbsp;<span typeof="v:Breadcrumb"><a rel="v:url" property="v:title" href="https://www.beagleboard.org/board-selection">Board</a></span>&nbsp;»&nbsp;<span>BeagleV®-Ahead</span></ol><!-- .breadcrumbs --></nav><!-- .breadcrumbs -->
    </div>
</nav>
    <div>
        <div>
          <h2>BeagleV®-Ahead</h2>
<h2>Enabling the future of open source</h2>
<p>BeagleV<sup>®</sup>-Ahead is an open-source RISC-V single board computer (SBC) in the form factor of BeagleBone Black with compatible P8 &amp; P9 cape header pins allowing you to stack your favorite BeagleBone cape on top to expand it’s capability. Featuring a powerful quad-core RISC-V processor, BeagleV<sup>®</sup>-Ahead is designed as an affordable RISC-V enabled pocket-size computer for anybody who want’s to dive deep into the new RISC-V ISA.</p>
<p><iframe id="_ytid_42987" width="480" height="270" data-origwidth="480" data-origheight="270" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/SVC9peUUzE0?enablejsapi=1&amp;origin=https://www.beagleboard.org&amp;autoplay=0&amp;cc_load_policy=0&amp;cc_lang_pref=&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;loop=0&amp;modestbranding=1&amp;rel=0&amp;fs=1&amp;playsinline=1&amp;autohide=2&amp;theme=dark&amp;color=red&amp;controls=1&amp;" title="YouTube player" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" data-no-lazy="1" data-skipgform_ajax_framebjll=""></iframe></p>
        </div>

                    <div>
            <p><img width="500" height="281" src="https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-500x281.png" data-src="https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-500x281.png" alt="" decoding="async" data-srcset="https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-500x281.png 500w, https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-300x169.png 300w, https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-400x225.png 400w, https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4.png 512w" data-sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" srcset="https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-500x281.png 500w, https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-300x169.png 300w, https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4-400x225.png 400w, https://www.beagleboard.org/app/uploads/2023/07/beaglev-ahead-pr-fig4.png 512w">
            </p>
          </div>
              </div>
  </div>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The fascist state of Paw Patrol (2021) (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thecritic.co.uk/the-fascist-state-of-paw-patrol/</link>
            <guid>37887217</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 05:46:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thecritic.co.uk/the-fascist-state-of-paw-patrol/">https://thecritic.co.uk/the-fascist-state-of-paw-patrol/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37887217">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">

                                                                                                
                
<p><span><span>I</span> have a dirty secret. When some of our friends at church nod in approval upon hearing that we haven’t got a proper television, I am happy to let them think that this is largely because we want to protect our children from all the woke nonsense in cartoons. We go to one of those scary parishes where the old Latin Mass is said twice on Sundays, and I must say the sexual proclivities of </span><i><span>Dora the Explorer </span></i><span>are a major topic of concern.</span></p>
<p><span>Our friends have a point. There is a lot of this stuff going around, and you have to wonder whether even the most progressive parents really believe their kids need to learn whether in addition to being blue and wearing a diaper, Gonzo in </span><i><span>Muppet Babies</span></i><span> is gender-queer. (Do Muppets in fact have sex? Inquiring minds don’t in fact want to know.)&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>But in our case the objections are aesthetic as much as anything else. I have always admired the artistry of traditional hand-drawn animation, and the CGI you see on TV (usually farmed out to digital sweatshops in Asia) is even uglier than the top-shelf Disney/Pixar version. The color palette is unimaginably garish, a lot of neon fuschias, turquoises, and oranges, plus a distinct shade of cyan that looks like radioactive Mountain Dew. (Thank goodness the backgrounds are always empty.)</span></p>
<blockquote><p><span>In a typical episode the Paw Patrol send an entire fleet of vehicles to an attempted misdemeanor</span></p></blockquote>
<p><span>Then there is the sheer inanity of the dialogue, characters, and situations. When I was a child, Doug Funny was subjected to various ethical dilemmas, and even the Ninja Turtles of blessed memory had quarrels and existential crises — I recall Michaelangelo once seeking hypnotherapy for his pizza addiction — in between fighting some genuinely frightening baddies. These days we have </span><i><span>Super Truck</span></i><span>. Have you heard of </span><i><span>Super Truck</span></i><span>? It’s a quite popular show about a truck. Our three-year-old, quite perceptively, calls it “Stupid Truck.”</span></p>
<p><span>Despite my best efforts, the kids have managed to see a lot of these shows, mostly at grandparents’ houses. The worst one, worse than </span><i><span>Daniel Tiger</span></i><span> or </span><i><span>PJ Masks</span></i><span> or even </span><i><span>My Little Pony</span></i><span> (which is the subject of a pedophile cult in these United States) is </span><i><span>Paw Patrol</span></i><span>. This program centers around a group of talking dogs who work for various emergency services: Chase is the cop, Marshall the fireman (or rather firepup), Skye the helicopter pilot, and so on.</span></p>
<p><span>Unfortunately, emergency services seem to be the only thing going on in this horrifying world. Every episode revolves around some poor citizen finding himself on the wrong side of the law or the victim of an alleged natural disaster or public health crisis. In a typical episode, the Paw Patrol send an entire fleet of vehicles — cars, trucks, boats, aeroplanes, submarines, and even, insanely, a recycling van — to respond to an attempted misdemeanor or a minor traffic accident.</span></p>
<p><span>All of this activity is carried out under the aegis of one Mayor Goodway. She is very much a ruler in the Nero fiddling or Elagabalus line, a deranged eccentric who collects chickens (curiously enough, they cannot speak in this universe otherwise full of anthropomorphic animals) and seems totally uninterested in the actual well-being of her subjects, much less the material and other costs of maintaining a rather large police force. (I say “subjects” rather than “citizens” because as far as I can tell, there is no evidence of elections ever being carried out.)</span></p>
<p><i><span>Paw Patrol </span></i><span>is Giorgio Agamben’s nightmare, a country in which a permanent state of emergency exists, under which governments have limitless power to rule unilaterally. There is no society or even commerce in </span><i><span>Paw Patrol</span></i><span>, only the relentless unthinking force of the police state, ostensibly responding to a never-ending crisis. It is the most influential work of fascist art since Ezra Pound.</span></p>
<p><span>Worse still than the omnidirectional sense of faux-crisis is the depiction of the offenders on the receiving end of the Paw Patrol’s mob justice. The Ruff-Ruff Pack, collar-less and dirty, are clearly working class dogs; no attempt is ever made to reform or otherwise induce them to behave better. It’s as if they exist to be brutalised. (One thinks of those lines of Auden: “Somebody chose their pain, / What needn’t have happened did.”)</span></p>
<blockquote><p><span>I like to imagine that somewhere in Adventure Bay there is some sort of resistance movement</span></p></blockquote>
<p><span>But perhaps the oddest thing of all is the fact that apart from the pups, the dictator Goodway, and the handful of people whom they routinely assault, the island seems somewhat sparsely populated. I like to imagine that somewhere in Adventure Bay there is some sort of resistance movement, a faction of poets and religious types opposed to the mayor’s tyrannical regime. Which is when it occurs to me: </span><i><span>they’re all freaking dead, aren’t they? Or maybe we are talking about a gulag situation. Where else is all the production happening? There are no visible factories, but someone has to build all the machines and tools and perform the necessary agricultural work to keep the mayor’s chickens fed.</span></i></p>
<p><span>All of this no doubt is taking a bunch of magenta pixels too seriously. Maybe. I can’t help but think that in addition to their deleterious effect on children’s imaginations, shows like </span><i><span>Paw Patrol</span></i><span> are a serious political threat. I hate to go all Frankfurt School in a light column like this one, but it is always worrying when citizens of a democratic society are taught to worship the police, to accept so-called “states of exception” without question, and to delight in the machinery of punishment. This is the reason that, growing up in the 1990s, I always hated</span><i><span> Cops</span></i><span>, my love of moustaches and aviator sunglasses notwithstanding. Somehow I always wanted the guy in the wife beater shirt (invariably removed during the course of the episode for reasons that were always mysterious) with the 40 ounce bottle of malt liquor and the cigarette to get away. Like the supposed villains in </span><i><span>Paw Patrol</span></i><span>, he never did.</span></p>


                

            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Decline in independent activity as a cause of  decline in child mental health (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/2023-02/Children%27s%20Independence%20IN%20PRESS%20.pdf</link>
            <guid>37887071</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 05:15:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/2023-02/Children%27s%20Independence%20IN%20PRESS%20.pdf">https://cdn2.psychologytoday.com/assets/2023-02/Children%27s%20Independence%20IN%20PRESS%20.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37887071">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vercel employee used customer information to pursue a personal trademark matter (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/vercel_support/status/1713295474998772215</link>
            <guid>37887049</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 05:10:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/vercel_support/status/1713295474998772215">https://twitter.com/vercel_support/status/1713295474998772215</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37887049">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/vercel_support/status/1713295474998772215: Error [ERR_FR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS]: Maximum number of redirects exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[On the Experience of Being Poor-Ish, for People Who Aren't (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.residentcontrarian.com/p/on-the-experience-of-being-poor-ish</link>
            <guid>37886818</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 04:11:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.residentcontrarian.com/p/on-the-experience-of-being-poor-ish">https://www.residentcontrarian.com/p/on-the-experience-of-being-poor-ish</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37886818">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p><strong>Meta-Note: I’m sorry it’s been so long between articles; for better or worse writing here is something that I do for fun, and sometimes work and family get in the way. In this case, I was spending a lot of time trying to learn SQL; you will be pleased to note I am now able to pad my resume with “Intermediate Database Language Skills” with the best of them.</strong></p><p>A few years back, my wife was at a baby shower hosted by a friend by a mutual acquaintance. In a conversation with the hostess, my wife learned they were in a tough financial position - they were always broke, and no amount of budgeting seemed to help them get ahead; they had cut every cost they could and things were just getting worse and worse. She admitted to my wife that she just felt like she was sinking further and further underwater, and didn’t see any way out for her or her family.</p><p>Note: The hostess and her husband were both doctors. They had a combined income somewhere upwards of $200,000 a year, and as the conversation developed my wife learned that their problems started and stopped with the hostess not being able to save quite as much as she’d like once the payments on their very nice house and current-year cars were made. At the time she leaned on my wife for emotional support over finances, our family of four’s income was less than $30,000 a year.</p><p>You should know the hostess wasn’t mean-spirited in the least, and we liked her then and continue to do so. But she did have a kind of tunnel vision I’ve since noticed is increasingly common: If you came from a family that did pretty well financially, went to college and then immediately started to do pretty well yourself, it’s hard to get any kind of context for what life is like at lower income levels. This isn’t a matter of the relatively-wealthy being dumb or insensitive; it’s just legitimately difficult to get a handle on what it’s like in a life you’ve never lived, and often being legitimately confused as to why anyone would opt to make less money instead of improving their lot with training and education.</p><p>In that spirit, I’d like to offer my services as a sort of has-been-poor guide, to fill you in on what it’s like on the other side of the tracks. In this role, I’m qualified in two ways. The first is common - we’ve never done exceptionally well financially. Things have been better in recent years as I’ve finally clawed towards the upper-end of lower-class, but Covid has reminded us how short-lived that kind of qualified success can be. We’ve had to economize in dozens of interesting ways, make hard choices here and there and sometimes/often do entirely without. It hasn’t been easy.</p><p><span>At the same time, I’m mostly </span><em>happy.</em><span> I have a wonderful wife who is very satisfying to be near, two kids who are about as custom-fit to my personality as possible, and dozens of friends online and off who would take a bullet for me, and vice versa. This is important because I want you to know I’m not trying to make you feel bad - I know and understand that everyone has a different set of problems, and that I’m not unique in living in an imperfect world. I’m not trying to exaggerate problems for political points or to try to get legislation passed. Take no guilt from this article - It’s informational, not a call to arms.</span></p><p>One of the bigger disconnects I run into in talking to people at or above living wage levels of income is that it’s usually assumed that the quality of things has a pretty linear association to the price. This is true at most price points, from “doing OK” all the way up to “Jeff Bezos” - if you pay a little more, you get a little more. If you pay a little less, you get a little less.</p><p><span>Because this relationship is what you’d expect, you get a lot of reasonable-sounding advice that, while not exactly wrong, fails to capture the nuance of poor-people-price-mechanics very well. According to this randomly selected article, </span><a href="https://smartasset.com/mortgage/how-much-should-i-spend-on-rent#:~:text=While%20everyone's%20circumstances%20are%20unique,30%25%20of%20your%20household%20income." rel="">I should really make sure not to spend more than 30% of my income on rent</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p>While everyone’s circumstances are unique, many experts&nbsp;say it’s best to spend no more than 30% of your monthly gross income on housing-related expenses, including rent and utilities. Under that rule, it’s best to make sure that the amount you spend on rent is well below 30% of your household income. In other words, if you’re making $3,000 a month, it’s a good idea to pay no&nbsp;more than $900 for rent and other housing costs.  </p></blockquote><p>The general thinking here is that if I spend more than 30%, I’m making myself vulnerable in all other aspects of my budget; why burden yourself with more than you can handle, when I could take a slightly worse place and be that much closer to financial health? From the perspective of the 50k a year and up crowd, this makes sense - $1250, after all, will rent a reasonable house or apartment in a lot of markets. In metropolitan Phoenix, this might look something like this:</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png" width="893" height="544" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:544,&quot;width&quot;:893,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1170609,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F33df3846-bcbc-437b-b469-61cf37d20a24_893x544.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>And this is perfectly livable - it’s very small (think ~900 sqft), but otherwise it’s a well-kept place. It’s not exactly Versailles, but you wouldn’t necessarily feel like a monster telling someone to live within their means by renting an apartment here. But what happens when you are dealing with someone making $17.50 an hour?  What does 840 a month get you?</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png" width="793" height="528" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://bucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:528,&quot;width&quot;:793,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:983497,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fbucketeer-e05bbc84-baa3-437e-9518-adb32be77984.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fea0e103a-bfea-4614-8154-9226f5dcdba3_793x528.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>I’m not 100% sure this is a converted Motel 6, but I’m not 100% sure it’s not. And while the first apartment I showed you was in a relatively nice, livable part of town this one is in a more gun-fire prone area ominously referred to by locals as “the triangle”. Phoenix’s mostly gravel-and-concrete landscaping style cleans up nice (note the still-wet recently hosed concrete), but make no mistake: this isn’t the kind of apartment complex where hypodermic needles are exclusively owned by diabetics.</p><p>That’s the drop-off you experience at the lower price levels - there’s nothing between “This is a tiny but acceptable apartment” and “Slum apartments in stab-ville”. </p><p>None of this is to discount the budget advice above completely - this is absolutely the kind of apartment I should be living in right now, if I was making perfect budgetary decisions. But consider that this is a choice I have to make - do I spend 50% more on an apartment and stress my budget to death, or make my wife and kids in a place where I have 5 front doors within 15 feet of ours in the murder-iest part of town? Neither choice is great, but the lack of intermediate choices forces you to do one or the other. </p><p>Whichever you choose, a person of less-than-intermediate income has to be prepared to stick with the rental long-term, should things not go well. This is because apartments at both of these levels quite accurately assume that you can’t afford a lawyer - while it’s normal to put down a month or two worth of rent as a security deposit, it’s much less normal to get it back; the apartment complex has no reason to give back thousands of dollars they can simply keep. This means every time you move, you pay something like a third to a month’s wages for the privilege. Since breaking a lease often means you lose your privilege to live anywhere non-hellish, this means if you don’t have cash reserves (more on these later*) at the exact right time of year, you might end up in the same place for another full year whether you like it or not.</p><p><strong>Note: It’s been pointed out to me that I completely forgot to talk about cash reserves and how they effect this kind of thing. It’s also been pointed out that these numbers only “make sense” in particular markets - i.e. it’s cheaper or more expensive to live other places, so the exact figures here don’t translate well for everyone. I’ll write a follow up post incorporating some of this kind of feedback soon to make up for it.</strong></p><p><span>I am always consistently shocked by how little people living at a decent-to-great income level fear their cars; it seems like they hardly lie awake at night thinking about their iffy alternator much, if at all. Scott Alexander does a pretty good job of explaining the obverse experience </span><a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2018/05/16/basic-income-not-basic-jobs-against-hijacking-utopia/" rel="">here</a><span>:</span></p><blockquote><p>When I first started working with poor patients, I was shocked how many of the problems in their lives were car-related. For well-off people like me, having a car is background noise; you buy or lease it for a reasonable price, then never worry about it again. Poor people can’t afford to buy and don’t always have good enough credit to lease. They tend to get older, sketchier cars that constantly break down. A constant complaint I heard: “My car broke, I can’t afford repairs, and I’m going to get fired if I can’t make it to my job”. Some of them can’t afford insurance and take their chances without it. Others have had various incidents with the police that cost them their license, but they can’t just not show up to work, so they drive anyway and hope they don’t get arrested.  </p></blockquote><p>This is actually pretty close to the experience. It’s telling that Scott thinks the problem with a lease comes only from credit issues - a pretty bottom-barrel ford leases for 300-400 a month. For a person who makes 30,000-40000k a year, that’s something like 10-15% of their income, before we talk about insurance; couple that with the fact that you can’t squeak by on liability-only insurance in most leases, and we are already into a prohibitively expensive range.</p><p>But there’s other things - liability insurance, as mentioned above, is often your only option that makes sense - if your car costs $2000, paying an extra $50-100 per month for high-deductible doesn’t add up; you are still $1000 out of pocket to cover the deductible in the event you need to use it. But since you can’t afford it in the first place, you don’t think about that; you just start driving insanely carefully at all times and pray any accidents you get in aren’t your fault. One slip-up and you either can’t get to work at all, or you spend a lot more time doing it. Remember: Uber isn’t an option here; the ~$400 a month it would cost would bankrupt you.</p><p>You are also more or less forced to learn to do mechanic work. I’m an administrator by trade - I usually work in the kind of jobs that have “assistant” appended to them. One of my greatest prides is typing speed, and when people ask me my hobby I tell them “Excel”. If you were judging me by my interests and natural skillset, you wouldn’t expect me to be able to change my own tires. But over the years necessity has forced me to get pretty decent at car work - I’ve done clutch rebuilds and head gasket jobs and a bunch of other miserable (for me) work that I would have rather avoided. But this was often the only option I had - it was either figuring out how to replace an alternator or do a full brake job over the weekend or lose my ability to get to the grocery store in under an hour. Keep in mind the money saved here is just the labor - parts still have a cost that’s unavoidable. </p><p>The practical upshot of this is whenever I drive, it’s very slowly, very carefully, and listening in terror to any small noise the car makes. It’s a constant stress, and it’s limiting; we don’t go on long road trips often, and when we do my joke with my wife is usually something like “Well, if the car breaks down somewhere else, we’ll just start living there”.</p><p>It’s reasonable to ask “If cars are so terrible, why not use public transport?”. I live in a city, and this is in fact an option that would solve many of my problems: I wouldn’t have to worry about repairs, my gasoline and insurance bills would disappear and anything that happened to the bus is the city’s problem, not mine. Especially in an emergency public transit would be a godsend and might be the difference between keeping and losing my job.</p><p>But there’s other things to consider on this, as well. My commute isn’t short, and isn’t bus-friendly; it would go from about 30 minutes each way to just under 4 hours roundtrip. And when your commute starts and ends in a bad area, which is typical of a low-income family in a low-paying job, this means those four hours a day are spent surrounded by people who range from normal commuters at best to visibly mentally imbalanced and trying to speak to you the whole ride. I understand from talking to friends in “our mass transit is great!” towns that this isn’t the case everywhere but this is something that on average gets worse the poorer you get. I could make the commute shorter by taking a worse job (Maybe - the job market isn’t great right now), but that comes with career-limiting downsides of it’s own.</p><p>When I’m trying to explain to my sons how a company decides what to pay someone, it usually goes something like this: A company is looking to pay a person as little as they can and keep them, so a person’s pay is determined by how rare their skills are and how much demand there is for those skills. The value of their work doesn’t factor in as much - An administrative assistant might touch every department in the company every day and facilitate a massive amount of work, but they still don’t get paid much - it’s hard to justify when you could hire and train up someone to do the same thing nearly as well with very little difficulty.</p><p>I think this is a fairly accurate way to look at pay, but it applies to other aspects of the job. If you got sick more often than usual this year and used up your legally mandated sick days, would your company fire you for getting sick again, or demand you work sick? If the company decides it needs to cut wages, is your position the cheap-to-hire-for job the company didn’t spend a lot of money and time filling? If you don’t have rare skills, management is aware that they can ask for you to work extra hours, avoid letting you use paid time off and change your list of job duties on a whim - both they and you know that if you won’t do it, they can find somebody who will tomorrow. Not every company is bad in these ways - good people do exist - but every company is aware they could, and that tends to color every aspect of the job whether they intend it to or not. </p><p>The worst treatment you tend to get is, perhaps counterintuitively, in jobs that approach living wage despite your low value and replaceability as a worker. These jobs tend towards needing someone who can put in a lot of hours for customer interactions that require a single point of contact; they reward intense focus over long periods of time in unpleasant situations. Another way to say this is that these are high-stress jobs with a lot of mandatory overtime and very fast pacing - they pay a lot because they can’t get people to do them otherwise. Turnover in these jobs is absurd despite the pay - some people can keep up with them but it isn’t typical. In my first (and hopefully last) claims adjuster job, two people had heart attacks in my office in a six month period.</p><p>The obvious solution for the worker here would seem to be to train themselves in such a way as to be more valuable, but this is often a bit harder or less plausible than it sounds. Some of this can be personal reasons (if you are barely holding things together, it’s hard to find the time and energy to get a bachelors degree from scratch) or financial (It’s nice to think you could learn a new skill and start a new career, but if you are barely keeping your family fed as it is, you might not actually be able to take the pay cut dropping back to entry level would require. </p><p>To give you an example of how this looks, 2020 started with me in my second month at a sustainable job with a salary around 50k, the most I had ever made. When the job was disrupted by Covid, I was the first to go - I had little tenure and no rare specialty absolutely required by the company, so my responsibilities could at least theoretically be divided among the retained employees. I then took one of those high-stress high-intensity jobs in the mortgage industry, made kind of a lot of money (for me, on pace to do about 60k in a year) but eventually had a minor nervous breakdown; the company informed me I couldn’t use my paid time off without a month’s notice to handle it, and that they’d simply let my workload pile up while I was gone, leaving me in a worse place. I managed to switch to another company, but found out once I started that the job duties, pay, and hours were all misrepresented in the interview process - I’m free to leave if I don’t like it, since the job will be easy to fill. </p><p>In the meantime, I’ve added a few skills to my resume associated with better jobs and lifestyles, and I’m hopeful things get better. But “just the skill without an associated degree” means this is a slog - I’ve applied for about 100 jobs in the past month, but haven’t had a single response; there’s simply better qualified candidates at the kind of pay I can support my family with, and the kind of extremely junior positions I might have a better shot at would leave us unable to pay bills within a few months. </p><p>This isn’t evil on anyone’s part, and you shouldn’t feel bad about it - I’ve made a lot of choices in my life that led to this point and I have a lot of responsibility in terms of where I find myself. But understand that even if you are willing to sacrifice the labor and time it takes to work towards an uncertain goal, there’s still a fair amount of luck involved. And some people are at my level or below it because they simply lack the capability to do better - not everyone can or should learn to code, or would be able to successfully go back to school. </p><p>The summary here is that low-paying jobs are often uniquely bad for reasons beyond the pay itself. The people who work them aren’t unwilling to change this, but often they are unable to, either because the means to change their circumstance is outside of their control or because their attempts to do so fail. Some are lazy and unmotivated, but not all.</p><p><span>When someone is telling me they are or have been poor and I’m trying to determine </span><em>how poor exactly</em><span> they were, there’s one evergreen question I ask that has never failed to give me a good idea of what kind of situation I’m dealing with. That question is: “How many times have they turned off your water?”.</span></p><p>The reason this question works is because it lets me know whether the person I’m talking to has “felt” broke - I.E. been in a situation where they felt resource strapped for some reason or another - or has “been broke”, actually factually unable to pay for basic services they needed to survive at a minimally decent human level. </p><p>A person who feels broke might not have a lot of money, or might not have any liquid dollars in their wallet at all. But just being out of money doesn’t make you broke in the sense that they turn off your water - that takes time. Usually you can be over a month late before the water company actually goes to the trouble of sending someone out to turn off your water. Even if someone feels broke and can’t immediately pay their bills (this is rare for people who feel broke, by the way; they usually have a few hundred dollars they can get at somewhere, some space on a credit card, etc.) this only means they need to cut their spending somewhat the next month and catch up; they might not be King Midas after watching their budget for 30 days, but they won’t turn the tap some morning and finds nothing comes out.</p><p>Obviously being broke is the opposite; you are legitimately out of funds you need to cover a bill. It’s not a matter of watching your budget closer, either - you’ve cut the fat from every possible place and you still just don’t have enough to make everything work. Sometimes this is because you lost a job and your income dried up (more common these Covid days) and sometimes it’s because a surprise bill caused your budget to get behind in a way you couldn’t recover from. But as opposed to someone who simply overspent, being broke implies you have some structural problem with your income and finances that you can’t fix - all it took was a small bump of some kind to upset your apple cart, and now you’ve moved from “hanging on” to “asking your neighbor to use their hose to fill up a bucket so you can flush your toilet”.</p><p>It also implies there’s no place left to cut - you don’t have a car payment, and your insurance is minimal if it hasn’t lapsed already. You don’t have cable. You are eating a lot of rice. There’s simply nothing “extra” left to cut, and now you are choosing between things like power and internet (which you need to work and find work, these days) and water (which you need to survive).  Often you’ve already even prioritized those things, because as I’ve said they don’t turn off your water for a while; you’ve been juggling things like power and water, now with late fees, for a while. And one day your wife calls you and tells you the water is off, and there’s nothing you can do; maybe some family member can help you out, or maybe you live without utilities for a week or so until you get paid and start the next pay cycle that much more behind. </p><p>The best case scenario is you get helped, and you try to accept that graciously and thankfully, but consider the shame of this - you can’t support your family, and you’ve been forced to go to someone who can, implicitly admit you can’t fulfil your basic purpose as a human, and ask them to take away from their family to do what you can’t. And often they do - family and friends are a wonderful thing. I’m thankful more than I can say for mine; I’m blessed by them. But it’s exhausting; you understand going through it why so many people give up on trying to make things better, because you’ve already reached this point where you and everyone around you understands that you just can’t function to minimum levels as a father and husband; it’s hard to wake up the next day and go “well, I’m sure that’s all in the past - let’s learn Java!”.</p><p>If you are broke enough, you get what in some ways is very good health insurance: zero deductible, all prescriptions paid for, and no coverage limits. The reason you get this is because everyone else in the country pays for it for you - it’s government insurance, given to those at income levels so low it’s clear they have no chance at all of covering their own bills. It’s not without downsides (the doctors suck, for the most part, and referrals for anything beyond basic family care are time-consuming to get) but you  know that if your children or wife got seriously hurt or sick, there would be some level of care available that wouldn’t instantly bankrupt you.</p><p>There’s a point at which you are making too much money to get government insurance, though. As of today this number is &nbsp;$36,156, or ~138% of the federal poverty limit. This creates an interesting situation - if you were making 35k at a job and offered a job at 40k with healthcare benefits, taking the job would actually leave you in a worse place than before in most cases; insurance is expensive, and the government offers exactly zero help if you A. make more than a certain amount of money and B. work for a place with benefits. So where you had insurance and made 35k before, now you have insurance and make 32k; your step forward put you further in the hole.</p><p>This is what’s usually referred to as a perverse incentive - it’s a situation that “pays” you for doing the wrong thing. In this case, the wrong thing is rejecting jobs that pay more and offer more advancement out of fear that someone will get sick and you either won’t be able to get them care or will bankrupt yourself doing so. If you are smart, you probably take this risk - after all, you might eventually make 70k and be in a place where insurance is merely expensive rather than a complete budget disaster. But it’s a real risk you have to take as you climb towards financial security, and not everyone chooses to take it.</p><p>Dental insurance is worse. There’s an internet meme that says that teeth are “luxury bones” that insurance doesn’t cover, and this is more or less true - even with dental insurance, you are still out of pocket significant amounts of money for even basic dental care. I haven’t been to a dentist since I was 11 years old for reasons related to this. I often consider the fact that I’m in a bit of a race against time with my own teeth - at some point they will go from “merely crooked” to “visibly rotting”, and very few people will hire a person with visibly rotten teeth for work. </p><p>Note for other people of limited income: Take the time to check and see if there’s a dental school in your town. The care dental school clinics give isn’t free, but it’s significantly cheaper and in my experience pretty good. One of my children has significant dental care needs, and he regularly goes to the dentist at a clinic of this sort - they treat him well and do good work. I can’t compare it to a “real dentist”, but it’s infinitely better than nothing.</p><p>I mentioned this before, but I can work on cars, and I’m able to do anything less complex than a full engine or transmission rebuild. This is an example of what I refer to with friends as “poor people skills”, or capabilities you develop beyond the norm because it’s necessary to survive.</p><p>The most fun poor person skill by far is buying things off of Craigslist. It’s by no means rocket science, but having little money means you end up buying all but the very cheapest of durable goods used, and repeated practice at this makes you skilled at finding deals other people might miss.</p><p>It’s been decades since I bought new furniture besides IKEA; most of that comes from Craigslist. Cars come from Craigslist - you can buy used cars at dealerships and it’s less risky, but comes with a 25-50% markup for the safety that a lot of people can’t afford. Durable cookware, like pots and pans? Craigslist, if you want anything kind of nice; the stuff you can afford at target starts flaking teflon into your eggs a week in.</p><p>Rich person tip: Unless you really, really need everything in your house to clearly be part of a unified set, you are a sucker if you buy furniture new; this is especially true for non-upholstered wooden furniture. Antique furniture is prettier, studier, has more street cred and can be had for a song compared to retail store prices; let other people pay those and look average while you put in a minimum effort, save money, and get cooler older furniture that makes you look like a person of taste rather than an every day jive-turkey retail sucker.</p><p>Poor people tip: Stop buying spatulas on Craigslist. Just work some more overtime. Yes, I know it’s a lot of overtime already but spatulas cost $5 new - a $2 spatula is not a deal and the savings don’t pay for even minimum-wage time spent driving to talk to a guy named “Pastor Dave” about used discount cookware in a Circle K parking lot.</p><p>That last tip to poor people seems like a joke, but at some point it’s something you have to look out for - you get so used to thinking of money as an extremely finite resource that any amount of absolute savings in purchase price looks necessary to you. But once you conquer that, it’s like a superpower; you can save hundreds or thousands of dollars furnishing a room; you can buy a box of books with the one book you want in it for less than the price of that individual book from a bookstore. </p><p>The only downside to your new found x-man discount used goods status is the possibility of getting stabbed; it’s a good idea to look at the approximate area of the guy selling you a hamster cage before you find yourself in the more murder-prone parts of town at night, conspicuously button-down and muggable hoping nobody notices you. Get that one little bit down, though, and it’s like the skies open up and the heavens beam savings down; all the discount archery sets and knock-off kitchen knives of the world are suddenly at your fingertips.</p><p>That’s it! We made it through. As I said before, none of this was meant to make you feel guilty and I hope and pray I managed not to sound like I was whining - I really want to emphasize that outside of everything I’ve talked about here, I’m absurdly wealthy in terms of the people who choose to spend their lives in my vicinity. I’m mostly a happy guy, and anymore one who can often pay his bills on time. I can really honestly confirm that money isn’t the operative thing that makes you happy; it really is  more about having good people around to talk to, take care of and to be taken care of by.</p><p>And if you do better than I do - say, if you are a person who completed college on time and went on to your deserved place in the upper-middle class -  I hereby command you not to feel bad about it. It’s OK to do well, and I have an idea of the kind of work you’ve put in to get to where you are; there’s a great chance you deserve to have the things you have. I hope this was instructive for you, and I wish you continued success.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jupe: Off-grid shelters that pop up anywhere on Earth (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jupe.com/get-jupe</link>
            <guid>37886420</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 02:47:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jupe.com/get-jupe">https://www.jupe.com/get-jupe</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37886420">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-w-id="7302c42f-dc2d-d462-aac5-e8bb58ca8290"><div data-w-id="2aa56685-b26b-a89b-2a8a-7f6204430753"><h2>Just Add Land.</h2><h2>Off-grid shelters that pops up anywhere on Earth.</h2><div><div><p>Flat-packed &amp; delivered within 24 hours</p></div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6410d8510a67407688089ad1_finance-31.png" loading="lazy" width="24" alt=""></p></div></div><div data-w-id="e628f492-0533-3268-a0fb-c244bf0eec5c"><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6315bb7acf6f3b4ad54ebde8_joshua-tree-forground.png" loading="eager" srcset="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6315bb7acf6f3b4ad54ebde8_joshua-tree-forground-p-500.png 500w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6315bb7acf6f3b4ad54ebde8_joshua-tree-forground-p-800.png 800w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6315bb7acf6f3b4ad54ebde8_joshua-tree-forground-p-1080.png 1080w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6315bb7acf6f3b4ad54ebde8_joshua-tree-forground.png 1400w" sizes="100vw" alt=""></p></div><div data-w-id="aade9602-9a4e-a541-2371-df4030e04f1f"><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e21764ca29dd745f1059f2_joshua-tree-background.jpg" loading="lazy" sizes="100vw" srcset="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e21764ca29dd745f1059f2_joshua-tree-background-p-500.webp 500w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e21764ca29dd745f1059f2_joshua-tree-background-p-800.webp 800w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e21764ca29dd745f1059f2_joshua-tree-background-p-1080.webp 1080w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e21764ca29dd745f1059f2_joshua-tree-background.jpg 2000w" alt=""></p></div></div><div data-w-id="d6bf4046-c9db-f455-015f-c256fab172c1"><p><h2>Inspired by the stars, Jupes are designed by former SpaceX &amp; Tesla earthlings as a vessel for exploring new frontiers in space and time. Jupe isn’t just a place to stay for a night, it’s your escape pod into the surreal.</h2></p></div><div data-w-id="4444a32c-1f6f-0b0f-28eb-dcba7554298c"><div id="jupe-spec"><div><div><p>features</p><h3>Jupes are super-tents, powered by the Sun.</h3><h4>Each Jupe comes with device charging, dimmable premium lighting, a heated memory foam luxury mattress, real Doug Fir wood floors and furniture, optional on-grid A/C, and lockable storage for your goodies. All ‘in the box’.</h4></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6261ab3c0284291aae9a7743_896B2843-CBB5-433F-957B-EDB0211747BE.jpeg" loading="lazy" id="w-node-b0584822-e9df-d16e-caa8-9f6aae0aae78-d8f49284" sizes="(max-width: 479px) 100vw, (max-width: 767px) 90vw, (max-width: 991px) 43vw, (max-width: 1919px) 44vw, 624px" alt="" srcset="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6261ab3c0284291aae9a7743_896B2843-CBB5-433F-957B-EDB0211747BE-p-500.jpeg 500w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6261ab3c0284291aae9a7743_896B2843-CBB5-433F-957B-EDB0211747BE-p-800.jpeg 800w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/6261ab3c0284291aae9a7743_896B2843-CBB5-433F-957B-EDB0211747BE.jpeg 848w"></p></div></div><div id="w-node-_42177f28-8d8c-dd48-0c92-2efc7154abab-d8f49284"><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e2e76a1750f182f5b811be_home-34.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>12" Queen Memory Foam Mattress </p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e2e8000c1b9764190a5d8e_keyboard-11.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>Floor to Ceiling Dimmable Lighting</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e2e769d7b1c7d39713afce_home-33.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>Heat &amp; AC Temperature Controlled</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e2e84ad1757ffcb7ed33a3_ui-19.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>Two 120V AC Power Outlets</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62ebdd0f7ba9005bf9454fc4_others-32.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>11' Vaulted Ceiling &amp; Front Door</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e2e768588067290ff96ca4_home-15.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>Built-In Lockable Storage Compartments</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e2e768d7b1c7c83a13afc9_clothes-21.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>Closable &amp; Secure Entryways</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62c37d441c248d100bae0b26_tent.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><p>Weather Resistant Enclosure</p></div></div></div><div data-w-id="7b3455a6-bae6-253d-affa-4ce40e7ccf63"><div data-w-id="3df11f44-cf87-d114-2600-a92c149bd715"><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>You get the sensation of fresh air and daylight with the comfort of a high end hotel.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>Staying in the Jupe was like keeping all of the best parts about being out in nature, while maintaining the comfort of a bed and safe space to rest at night.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>Magical! I loved everything about it.</p></div></div><div data-w-id="3df11f44-cf87-d114-2600-a92c149bd7c0"><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>The comfort of a 5 star hotel bedding in the middle of nature</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>A much needed architectural overhaul on the classic yurt.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>Clean, simple, comfortable in the outdoors!</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>Pleasant, calming very comfortable</p></div></div><div data-w-id="3a3b5ba5-87e5-40c1-11a9-1cf80d802cde"><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>The best glamping tent I've ever stayed in. As comfortable as a cabin, but with the sense that you are still camping.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>The experience was like sleeping in a fancy bed that was surrounded by REAL nature. It’s like I was the princess in sleeping beauty.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>It was very enjoyable and a new experience - I really loved waking up in the jupe (the bed was also incredibly comfortable) and also having a cozy night inside.</p></div></div><div data-w-id="dc0b1de5-bb85-a88e-b04b-befa1b6b8e6a"><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>It was so comfortable and relaxing</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>Peaceful. Sacred. It’s the kinda place you go to disconnect.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>It was really nice. The recessed storage was great, and the Jupe was really comfortable.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>It was great to be in the quiet zone, and I need this very much.</p></div></div><div data-w-id="ff9d1af1-633d-8ec1-167c-0d3a38de2401"><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>I LOVE it. You get the full spaceship effect.</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>Relaxing and restorative. I loved the fresh breeze contrasted by the heated mattress</p></div><div data-tippy-content="Dropbox"><p>A zen/tech-y designed space</p></div></div></div><div><p><h2>PEOPLE HAVE&nbsp;TAKEN&nbsp;NOTICE</h2></p><div data-w-id="3d9128bd-3f5a-d8c6-7285-8dfc3e7f6a3c"><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e116b24aea86240f8fa634_press-dwell.png" loading="lazy" width="90" height="70" alt=""></p><h4>Dwell</h4><p>"panoramic views over the desert, mountains, ocean, or whatever natural marvel lies beyond the front door"</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e06da7bdef6f0d3f2c4655_gearjunkie.png" loading="lazy" height="70" alt=""></p><h4>GearJunkie</h4><p>"engineered by designers from SpaceX and Tesla; those design chops shine through in the aesthetics"</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e116b247918b7babe105aa_press-techcrunch.png" loading="lazy" height="70" alt=""></p><h4>TechCrunch</h4><p>"allow anyone to live anywhere on the planet, comfortably and with an internet connection via satellite"</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e116b216206d6124780b11_press-creative.png" loading="lazy" height="70" alt=""></p><h4>Fair Companies</h4><p>"luxury queen mattress and bed, furniture, LED lighting, solar panels, and backup batteries, and even the linens"</p></div><div><p><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/62e116b25da41e3bcb197419_press-innovation.png" loading="lazy" height="70" alt=""></p><h4>InnovationLab</h4><p>"111-square foot home that is reinventing off-grid housing from the foundation up"</p></div></div></div><div><div><h2>Designed to Roam.</h2><p>Jupes drag and drop into any situation, fully tricked out and ready to go in hours. In as little as 36 hours, Jupes go from our factory to your land, ready-to-stay. </p></div><a href="#"><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/63f79315c3bd0053cc5bea39_577A2434-504F-496A-960B-6CAFE197AC30_1_105_c%20(1).jpg" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 1919px) 90vw, 1280px" srcset="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/63f79315c3bd0053cc5bea39_577A2434-504F-496A-960B-6CAFE197AC30_1_105_c%20(1)-p-500.jpg 500w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/63f79315c3bd0053cc5bea39_577A2434-504F-496A-960B-6CAFE197AC30_1_105_c%20(1)-p-800.jpg 800w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/63f79315c3bd0053cc5bea39_577A2434-504F-496A-960B-6CAFE197AC30_1_105_c%20(1)-p-1080.jpg 1080w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/63f79315c3bd0053cc5bea39_577A2434-504F-496A-960B-6CAFE197AC30_1_105_c%20(1).jpg 1182w" alt=""></a></div></div><div id="subscribe"><div><p><h2>Stay in touch! Subscribe to our mailer.</h2></p><p>Drop your email below to receive regular product updates, launches, and more.</p></div><div><div><p>👍 Awesome, you're on the list!</p></div><div><p>Oops! Something went wrong while submitting the form.</p></div></div></div><a href="https://jupeinc.notion.site/Jupe-let-s-house-the-Earthlings-and-do-the-Earth-a-solid-while-we-re-at-it-bdd61c2d3e4f4e1e97c98c47b3719228" target="_blank"><img src="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/64db2680f270a03232429c22_jupe-housing.jpg" loading="lazy" sizes="(max-width: 991px) 100vw, 300px" srcset="https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/64db2680f270a03232429c22_jupe-housing-p-500.jpg 500w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/64db2680f270a03232429c22_jupe-housing-p-800.jpg 800w, https://uploads-ssl.webflow.com/61e4cdc7bf88d504807aef3e/64db2680f270a03232429c22_jupe-housing.jpg 900w" alt=""><p><h4>Help Us Shelter Maui<br>#MauiStrong</h4></p></a>






</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: 3D Binpacking Algorithm Visualized (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://skusavvy.com/bin-packing-preview</link>
            <guid>37885813</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 01:01:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://skusavvy.com/bin-packing-preview">https://skusavvy.com/bin-packing-preview</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37885813">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Recursive Recipes (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/</link>
            <guid>37885636</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2023 00:30:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/">https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37885636">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h2>
                <span>Recipes are</span>
                <span>ingredients.</span>
            </h2>
            <p>A recursive recipe is one where ingredients in the recipe can be replaced by another recipe. The more ingredients you replace, the more that the recipe is made truly <em>from scratch</em>.</p>
            <p><strong>Select a recipe below to get started.</strong> Don't see your favorite recipe? <a href="https://github.com/schollz/recursive-recipes/issues/new?template=recipe-missing.md">Request it</a> and it can be added!</p>
            <div>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/refried-beans';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/refried-beans"></a>
                            Refried Beans
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/chocolate-chip-cookies';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/chocolate-chip-cookies"></a>
                            Chocolate Chip Cookies
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/pancakes';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/pancakes"></a>
                            Pancakes
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/yogurt';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/yogurt"></a>
                            Yogurt
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/eggs-benedict';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/eggs-benedict"></a>
                            Eggs Benedict
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/english-muffin';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/english-muffin"></a>
                            English Muffin
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/tortilla';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/tortilla"></a>
                            Tortilla
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/noodles';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/noodles"></a>
                            Noodles
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/cheese';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/cheese"></a>
                            Cheese
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/vanilla-ice-cream';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/vanilla-ice-cream"></a>
                            Vanilla Ice Cream
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
                <p onclick="location.href='/recipe/apple-pie';">
                    <h3>
                        
                        <span>
                            <a href="https://recursiverecipes.schollz.com/recipe/apple-pie"></a>
                            Apple Pie
                        </span>
                    </h3>
                </p>
                
            </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The British Mosquito once carried Niels Bohr in its bomb bay (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/the-nuclear-scientist-and-the-warplane-that-became-britains-most-unlikely-airliner</link>
            <guid>37884749</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 22:16:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/the-nuclear-scientist-and-the-warplane-that-became-britains-most-unlikely-airliner">https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/the-nuclear-scientist-and-the-warplane-that-became-britains-most-unlikely-airliner</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37884749">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="page-content" data-og-area="article-blocks" id="incArticle"><p>Matt Damon announces to the crowd, “We have an early Christmas present for you.” Kenneth Branagh takes over, holding court with an adoring audience. Playing General Leslie Groves, director of the Manhattan Project, and nuclear physicist Niels Bohr respectively, the two A-listers herald the arrival of the Danish scientist at Los Alamos. This is the secret facility established in New Mexico in 1943 to build the first <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/why-vertical-smoke-trails-are-seen-during-nuclear-explosions">atom bomb</a> and recreated 80 years later by Christopher Nolan to film his epic hit movie, <em>Oppenheimer</em>.</p><p>“The British pilots put me in the bomb bay,” Branagh as Bohr laughingly recounts in his best Danish accent, they “showed me the oxygen — of course, I messed it up. When they opened me up in Scotland I was unconscious. I pretended I’d been napping.”</p><div data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="1" data-og-block-type="core/embed"><p itemprop="associatedMedia"><iframe frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/bK6ldnjE3Y0?feature=oembed&amp;rel=0&amp;enablejsapi=1" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></div><p>The scene barely hints at the knife-edge circumstances of the Dane’s dramatic escape from Nazi-occupied Europe, nor the remarkable story behind his flight to safety. While researching my new book, <em>Mosquito</em>, about the U.K. Royal Air Force <a target="_blank" href="https://www.peoplesmosquito.org.uk/2013/12/06/operation-carthage-the-shell-house-raid-21st-march-1945/">raid on the Gestapo headquarters</a> in Copenhagen, I discovered the fascinating truth about both.</p><p>At the time he joined the Manhattan Project, Niels Bohr was perhaps the most famous scientist in the world after Albert Einstein. His Danish homeland had been under German occupation since April 1940.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="1" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">Kenneth Branagh as nuclear physicist Niels Bohr, and the man himself, known to the British Special Operations Executive as the ‘Great Dane.’ <em>via the author</em> </span></figure><p>On the day of the invasion, the professor was in the lab in Copenhagen that he had set up, attempting to dissolve a pair of Nobel medals in a mixture of nitric and hydrochloric acid. Bohr was trying to stop the Nazis from getting their hands on two 23-karat-gold Nobels he’d been given for safekeeping by two Jewish German physicists fleeing the antisemitism of Hitler’s Germany. He’d auctioned off his <em>own</em> Nobel medal in 1940 to raise money for victims of Finland’s ‘Winter War’ with the Soviet Union. That he’d allowed the institute in Copenhagen that carried his name to provide sanctuary for those German exiles also spoke to his altruism. But it was also personal. By virtue of his Jewish mother, Niels Bohr was Jewish by heritage, if not through religious belief.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="2" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">German troops patrol the streets of Copenhagen, during the Nazi occupation of Denmark. <em>Getty Images</em> </span></figure><p>Britain’s Special Operations Executive (SOE), set up in 1940 with instructions from Winston Churchill to “set Europe ablaze” through sedition and sabotage, had first tried to prompt Bohr’s departure from Denmark in 1943 by sending a secret agent to the scientist’s home. Bohr’s polite rejection of London’s invitation was hidden beneath the stamps stuck to three separate postcards. Next time, SOE sent a written message, along with detailed instructions:</p><p><em>“A small hole to a depth of 4mm has been bored in the two keys. The holes were plugged up and concealed after the message was inserted. Professor Bohr should gently file the keys at the point indicated until the hole appears. The message can then be syringed or floated out onto a micro-slide.”</em></p><p>The message inside from Bohr’s friend Professor James Chadwick of Liverpool University was the size of a grain of sand and contained in a hole the width of a pinhead and had to be deciphered using a 600-power lens microscope. Chadwick urged him to leave Denmark for the United Kingdom, alluding to “a particular problem in which your assistance would be of the greatest help.”</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="3" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">James Chadwick, photographed circa 1945. <em>Los Alamos National Laboratory</em> </span></figure><p>Chadwick, his fellow Nobel Laureate for his discovery of the neutron, was leading Britain’s research into the atomic bomb.</p><p>Again, Bohr politely declined, feeling he could do more good in occupied Denmark, but he was in no doubt about the nature of the “particular problem” his friend alluded to. He just didn’t believe that given the current state of the art, an atomic bomb was feasible.</p><p>Two months later Bohr reported to Chadwick that new information had convinced him that Germany had established the means to develop a nuclear reactor using uranium and heavy water. But as the British scientist prepared to take on a new role as head of the British Mission to the Manhattan Project at Los Alamos Laboratory in New Mexico, it still wasn’t enough to persuade the ‘Great Dane,’ as he was known to SOE, to leave Copenhagen.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="4" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">Supervised by the U.S. Army, the German experimental nuclear reactor is dismantled at Haigerloch, southwest Germany, in April 1945. <em>U.S. Army</em><br><a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Irving"></a> </span></figure><p>It wasn’t until a Danish woman working for the Gestapo saw an order for Bohr’s arrest and tipped off Bohr’s brother, Harald, that the physicist finally accepted that he had to go. Evidence of imminent action by the Nazis against Denmark’s Jewish community and the threat to him specifically was now impossible to ignore. Senior SS personnel poured into Copenhagen. A large German ship, the <em>Wartheland</em>, was alongside harbor, ready to carry as many of the country’s 7,000 Jews as could be packed in.</p><p>Bohr and his wife, Margarethe, left their home at <a target="_blank" href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/alexknapp/2012/11/28/for-winning-the-nobel-prize-niels-bohr-got-a-house-with-free-beer/">the Carlsberg brewery estate</a> within hours of the tip-off from Harald. As they slipped out of the back of their house a Nazi snatch squad was already on its way. When the couple later crawled on all-fours from a beach hut to a waiting boat, the most famous man in Denmark had with him a single bag, a beer bottle full of heavy water retrieved from the lab, and a sketch purporting to be of the Nazi’s reactor design. There had been no time to gather any more possessions before being smuggled across the strait to Sweden.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="5" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">A German general decorating with the Iron Cross some soldiers of the Expeditionary Force and two soldiers of the SS, in Denmark, April 1940. <em>Photo by Mondadori via Getty Images</em> </span></figure><p>Niels and Margarethe Bohr may have thought that, with their arrival in Malmø, they were safe from the clutches of the Nazis, but that was neither how the Gestapo nor Danish Army intelligence saw the situation.</p><p>Like Madrid, Lisbon, or Casablanca, the capital of neutral Sweden was a hotbed of wartime intrigue, with spies from intelligence agencies from around the world operating side-by-side all competing for advantage. Secrets, lies, treachery, and deception were all common currency in Stockholm, and <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cutout_(espionage)">cutouts</a>, agents, safe houses, dead drops, surveillance, and ciphers were the means by which they were traded. And with the arrival of the world’s most celebrated nuclear physicist, they had a prize worth playing for. </p><p>At first, the Swedish authorities were reluctant to acknowledge that Bohr was at risk of abduction or assassination, telling the Danish Army captain charged with his protection, “This is Stockholm, not Chicago.”</p><p>When it came to ruthlessness and brutality, the officer replied, there was no gangster that could compare to the Gestapo, and that “if anything happens to the professor it will be a disgrace to your country.” The captain never left Bohr’s side while he was in Sweden. But from now on, he was also joined by three armed Swedish secret police. Arriving in Stockholm, Bohr was bundled from a taxi into a house owned by Swedish intelligence, led through the attics to the other side of the building, and met by a second taxi, which took him to a safe house.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="6" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">The Danish scientist Niels Bohr in his laboratory in the 1940s. <em>Photo by Keystone-France/Gamma-Keystone via Getty Images</em> </span></figure><p>Three days later, the Nazis moved against <a target="_blank" href="https://www.yadvashem.org/articles/academic/denmark-and-the-holocaust.html">Denmark’s Jews</a> as planned, but it was already too late. Alerted, like Bohr, to the imminent danger, they were taken in, hidden, and, over time, evacuated by their countrymen. Sweden, after lobbying from Bohr himself, agreed to take them all in. Of Denmark’s 7,000 or so Jews, just 284 of the weakest and most vulnerable had been arrested.</p><p>It wasn’t even enough, remarked a crestfallen Nazi official “to justify the dispatch of a train to the concentration camp.”</p><p>For Bohr himself to reach ultimate safety, he would now be relying on the ‘Stockholm Express.’ And, despite the name, it was not a train, but one of a small fleet of unarmed de Havilland Mosquito aircraft that, operated by British Airways’ precursor, BOAC — the British Overseas Airways Corporation — ran the gauntlet of Luftwaffe night-fighters to carry VIP passengers between RAF Leuchars in Scotland and Sweden’s Bromma Airport. Those passengers rode in the claustrophobic confines of the Masquitos' felt-lined bomb bays. The flight nearly killed Bohr. And for that, the Mosquito’s peerless performance was to blame. That bundling a VIP into the belly of a warplane was even an option was all down to ball bearings.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="7" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">BOAC Mosquitos carried a single passenger in the felt-lined bomb bay. They were given oxygen, a reading light, a blanket, and a flask of coffee for the two-and-a-half-hour flight. <em>Crown Copyright</em> </span></figure><p>For 35 years, the Swedish company SKF had led the world in the production of quality ball bearings, opening factories in the United Kingdom, Germany, France, and the United States. But with the advent of World War II, their plant in Luton, England, despite working day and night, couldn’t keep up with demand.</p><p>Each <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/35474/the-british-had-a-plan-to-drop-anthrax-laced-cattle-feed-over-germany-in-1942">Avro Lancaster bomber</a> for the RAF required over 175 pounds of quality ball bearings and these aircraft were rolling off the production line at a rate of around 25 a week. But there were also Spitfires, Hurricanes, and plenty more besides. Britain had a huge variety of aircraft types in production, powered by a wide variety of different engines, and <em>all</em> required ball bearings of their own. Nor was it just aircraft. Tanks, armored cars, warships, and anti-aircraft guns all needed ball bearings. In fact, there were very few pieces of complex military machinery that <em>didn’t</em>. And that, of course, included the <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/21198/listen-to-a-p-82-twin-mustang-pur-a-glorious-sound-not-heard-in-over-30-years">Merlin-engined</a> Mosquito itself.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="8" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">A scene from an SKF ball-bearing plant, photographed soon after World War II. <em>Photo by Walter Nurnberg/SSPL/Getty Images</em> </span></figure><p>SOE ships carrying Swedish ball bearings first successfully ran the German blockade of the Skagerrak — the strait providing access between the North Sea and Sweden — in 1941. Since June 1942, though, BOAC had been running semi-regular courier flights along the 500-mile route between RAF Leuchars and Stockholm. The airbridge, so critical to both British intelligence and war industry, crossed some of the most hostile and heavily defended skies in the world, yet BOAC had struggled to find an aircraft to serve its needs.</p><p>To begin with, the airline was given cast-off <a target="_blank" href="https://www.baesystems.com/en/heritage/armstrong-whitworth-aw38-whitley">Armstrong Whitworth Whitleys</a>. Slow and vulnerable, the obsolete RAF bombers were soon dispensed with in favor of new types acquired from the United States, small Lockheed Lodestars and Hudsons and a one-off, <em>St. Louis</em>, the first prototype of the new Curtiss C-46 Commando transport. The C-46 was capable of carrying heavy loads but remained vulnerable to the Luftwaffe. So too were the Douglas DC-3s that replaced it in the spring of 1943.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="9" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">The BOAC-operated Curtiss CW-20A (the prototype of the C-46), G-AGDI, named <em>St. Louis</em>, is refueled at Gibraltar, in 1941 or 1942. <em>Crown Copyright</em> </span></figure><p>At Leuchars, BOAC was very firmly of the view that “the Skagerrak is no place for a Dak” — a reference to the vulnerability of the Dakota, as the <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/39236/theres-one-place-in-the-world-where-ac-47-spooky-gunships-still-fly">DC-3/C-47</a> was known in British service. But in the spring of 1943, the pressure to keep up the flights only intensified with a telegram from the British Minister in Stockholm, Sir Victor Mallett:</p><p><em>“Since the need for at least 100 tons of bearings is desperate I recommend that risks should be taken as in any other wartime operation and that freight aircraft without passengers should fly regardless of bright nights throughout the summer months. If the Germans take to shooting them down the position can be reconsidered and at the worst, we will have lost one or two Dakotas and crews.”</em></p><p>BOAC disagreed and, after trialing an alternative route to Sweden, concluded in a report that what was required was “an aircraft with great performance — speed, higher ceiling, and more endurance.”</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="10" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">No. 105 Squadron Mosquito B.IVs. The B.IV was the first Mosquito to enter service with BOAC and remained popular with crews after the introduction of the&nbsp;subsequent FB.VI&nbsp;because it was a few miles per hour faster. <em>Crown Copyright</em> </span></figure><p>When, in 1938, as the prospect of war loomed over Europe, Geoffrey de Havilland first suggested the idea of a lightweight twin-engine bomber to the U.K. Air Ministry he was met with little enthusiasm. Undeterred, he decided that his company would build it anyway. And, if the new machine was built from wood, he knew he would not only be able to get it into production much more quickly than a metal design but would also avoid making any demand on vital supplies of the aluminum required to build every other military aircraft. In top secret, on the grounds of a moated stately home near St. Albans, north of London, his team got to work on a prototype.</p><p>They were fortunate that despite the Air Ministry’s skepticism their efforts enjoyed determined and far-sighted support from Air Marshal Wilfred Freeman, the man responsible for research, development, and production of new aircraft for the RAF. Impressed as a young pilot in the Royal Flying Corps (the RAF’s immediate successor) by the performance of an earlier de Havilland bomber design, Freeman circumvented the objections of Bomber Command to the notion of an unarmed bomber by ordering 50 of de Havilland’s sleek new Mosquitos to fulfill a separate RAF requirement for high-flying spyplanes.</p><p>Powered by two Rolls-Royce Merlin engines, the Mosquito was capable of flying to Berlin and back with the same 4,000-pound bombload as Boeing’s <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/41454/the-b-17-bombers-combat-debut-80-years-ago-today-was-a-fiasco">B-17 Flying Fortress</a> yet flown by a crew of two instead of 10.</p><div data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="3" data-og-block-type="core/embed"><p itemprop="associatedMedia"><iframe frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/JTsnMKzmdWs?feature=oembed&amp;rel=0&amp;enablejsapi=1" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></div><p>Following a remarkable flying display laid on for Gen. Hap Arnold, the head of the United States Army Air Corps, in April 1941, he rated it “outstanding” and insisted on taking a set of the blueprints home with him. Three months later, in the same week that it entered frontline service, a Mosquito recorded a top speed of 433 miles per hour at a time when the RAF’s top fighter, the <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/39633/yes-the-u-s-navy-also-took-the-spitfire-into-battle-during-world-war-ii">Spitfire Mk V</a>, topped out at 370 miles per hour. Suddenly everyone wanted the Mosquito and because of its unique wood and glue construction, furniture factories, cabinetmakers, and musical instrument manufacturers around Britain were able to put their carpentry-skilled workforces to work helping keep up with demand.</p><p>After first entering RAF service with a photo-reconnaissance unit in the summer of 1941, the first Mosquito bomber squadron formed a few months later. No. 105 Squadron’s operations remained classified for nearly a year until, in September 1942, after a low-level raid on a Gestapo HQ in Oslo, the Mosquito’s existence was revealed to the public in enthusiastic reports that noted its ability to “outpace the latest Focke-Wulf [Fw 190].”</p><p>And that was exactly what BOAC needed.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="11" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">A Luftwaffe Focke-Wulf Fw 190 at its airbase. As of mid-1942, this was the most potent German fighter in large-scale service and a major threat to the RAF. <em>Photo by Weltbild/ullstein bild via Getty Images</em> </span></figure><p>The first BOAC machine completed the ball-bearing run to Sweden in February 1943. Although not immune to the attentions of the German fighter squadrons that pincered the route, the Mosquitos, their camouflaged wings overpainted top and bottom with their civilian registration in huge letters and the airline’s iconic <a target="_blank" href="https://londonairtravel.com/2019/08/11/british-airways-100-years-theyre-lee-elliotts-speedbird/">‘speedbird’ logo</a> on the nose, at least loaded the odds in favor of the airline pilots.</p><p>A single Mosquito could carry a load of 1,400 pounds of Swedish ball bearings packed in cases and stowed in the bomb bay, but its speed meant it could complete two or even three runs between Leuchars and Stockholm in a single night. In June of 1943, the airline’s Mosquito fleet completed 30 round trips to help chip away at Britain’s ball-bearing deficit, but their greater contribution was made through a single, game-changing flight at the end of the month.</p><p>Henry Waring and Ville Siberg had been kicking their heels in St. Andrews, on Scotland’s east coast, for nearly a week. Waring, a representative of the British Iron and Steel Corps, and his colleague, who ran SKF’s Luton factory, knew valuable time was being wasted. Ball bearings from neutral Sweden were supplied on a first-come, first-served basis and it was understood in London that the Germans, after Allied bombing of their own ball-bearing factories, were on the verge of placing a large order. Twice Waring phoned London urging action but was told that long, hot summer days and a complete lack of cloud cover meant attempting the flight in the waiting Lockheed 14 would be suicide.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="12" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">A BOAC Mosquito FB.VI G-AGGD prepares to land. <em>Crown Copyright </em> </span></figure><p>Waring was sunbathing by the swimming pool when, on June 24, an RAF driver pulled up at the hotel. Still in his swimming trunks, Waring was taken to Leuchars and informed that he and Siberg would be traveling to Sweden that night in a pair of hastily adapted BOAC Mosquitos.</p><p>Each fortified by a stiff whisky before departure, the two businessmen reached Bromma just hours before the German negotiating team to secure SKF’s ball bearings for the Allies, and, as well as catering for British requirements, also deliberately placed&nbsp;orders for gauges they believed were in short supply in the Reich. Their safe delivery was recorded on the freight manifest as “one package Waring, one package Siberg.”</p><p>Geoffrey de Havilland once wrote that “if the size is right, the aeroplane becomes very versatile.” But the Mosquito had a sort of Goldilocks quality to it. It could do anything. Doctrine has it that there are four roles of air power: control of the air; intelligence, surveillance, and reconnaissance; attack; and mobility. Broadly speaking, an air force requires fighters, spyplanes, bombers, and transport aircraft to perform these tasks, each usually requiring very different characteristics in an airframe. Prior to 1943, though, the Mosquito had already made its mark as an exceptional example of the first three.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="13" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">A BOAC Mosquito pilot climbing aboard an FB.VI. Note the four sealed 20mm cannon gun ports in the nose. <em>Crown Copyright</em> </span></figure><p>In going on to drop a total of nearly 27,000 tons of bombs on the enemy, Mosquitos suffered fewer losses per thousand sorties than any other aircraft in Bomber Command. And so accurate were they that, after the campaign to destroy <a target="_blank" href="https://airandspace.si.edu/collection-objects/v-1-cruise-missile/nasm_A19600341000">V-1 flying-bomb</a> launch sites in the autumn of 1942, records showed that Mosquito crews required less than a quarter of the tonnage of bombs to destroy each target than the next most effective bomber. There were single nights on either side of D-Day when Mosquito fighter-bombers would destroy nearly a thousand separate pieces of German motor transport.</p><p>As heavily armed eight-gun fighters — especially as radar-equipped night-fighters — Mosquitos shot down over 800 enemy aircraft. Such was the fear that they induced within the Luftwaffe in the latter stages of the war as they loitered around German airfields after dark, ready to pounce on anything coming in or out, that the term <em>Moskitopanik</em> was coined.</p><p>Flying photo-reconnaissance missions, Mosquitos crisscrossed Europe with near impunity gathering critical photographic intelligence that, among other things, helped delay the threat from Hitler’s <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/the-v-2-rocket-changing-the-trajectory-of-warfare">V-2 ballistic missile</a>. In assuming the mantle of airliner/transport for BOAC between Leuchars and Stockholm, the Mosquito became perhaps the only machine in history to successfully combine all four of these essential roles.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="14" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">BOAC crew with an RAF Flying Control officer at RAF Leuchars before departing for Stockholm. <em>Crown Copyright</em> </span></figure><p>In the six months that followed Waring and Viberg’s flight, Mosquitos flew another 129 round trips to Sweden and hauled back over 100 tons of ball bearings. But it was the human cargoes they carried to and from Scandinavia that really distinguished the British and Norwegian civilian pilots and radio operators employed by BOAC. As well as maintaining the flow of intelligence and personnel to and from Sweden, and by extension, Denmark, they were also responsible for repatriating downed Allied aircrews, many of whom had been spirited out of Denmark to Sweden by local resistance groups.</p><p>A little before 6:30 a.m. at Bromma Airport on October 6, 1943, the crew of BOAC Mosquito FB.VI G-AGGG installed Niels Bohr in the bomb bay and briefed him on how to use the intercom and oxygen system. They said they would tell him when he was required to switch it on. He was given flares and a parachute in case they had to abandon the aircraft, then sealed into the claustrophobically compact space for the duration of the two-and-a-half-hour flight.</p><p>Climbing west through 15,000 feet towards the thin air of what mountaineers call the death zone near 25,000 feet, the BOAC crew was confident that, behind them, Bohr would follow his instructions. Unknown to them, the leather flying helmet that contained his intercom didn’t fit easily over the scientist’s large head, so he couldn’t hear them. Nor did Bohr, who could be remarkably unworldly, properly understand how to use the oxygen.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="15" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">A BOAC Mosquito lines up for takeoff from RAF Leuchars in Scotland. <em>Crown Copyright</em> </span></figure><p>When the radio operator asked how he was getting on there was no answer from the bomb bay. He feared that Bohr had passed out through oxygen starvation. But until G-AGGG had swept through the jaws of the German air defenses ranged to the north and south, they had to stay high.</p><p>Two and half hours after taking off from Bromma, after completing the final leg of the journey low over the North Sea, the Mosquito FB.VI landed at RAF Leuchars and taxied towards an anxious crowd waiting by the terminal. Where, to their great relief, the Great Dane, weak but alive, was liberated from the belly of the aircraft. </p><p>The following month Bohr sailed for America, arriving at Los Alamos to join the Manhattan Project in the new year. Here, as historian Alex Wellerstein&nbsp;<a target="_blank" href="https://blog.nuclearsecrecy.com/2015/05/11/bohr-at-los-alamos/">writes</a>, Bohr’s contribution to building the first functional nuclear devices was highly significant, although subsequently underplayed.</p><figure data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="16" data-og-block-type="core/image"><span data-rawhtml="1">Capt. Gilbert Rae, a BOAC Mosquito pilot, at the controls of his aircraft. Rae was killed when his Mosquito crashed into the North Sea in 1944. <em>Photo by The Print Collector/Getty Images</em> </span></figure><p>Meanwhile, as a fighter, bomber, and spyplane, de Havilland’s ‘Wooden Wonder’ enjoyed a near-legendary reputation and established itself as something of a bête noire to <a target="_blank" href="https://www.rafmuseum.org.uk/blog/the-wooden-wonder-of-the-raf/#:~:text=%E2%80%9CIt%20makes%20me%20furious%20when,unable%20to%20intercept%20the%20Mossie.">Hermann Göring</a>, commander-in-chief of the Luftwaffe.</p><p>The string of daring low-level Mosquito raids against pinpoint targets across occupied Europe that captured the imagination of the public inspired the 1964 film <em>633 Squadron</em>, which in turn provided inspiration for the <a target="_blank" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AA_D__HMuFw">X-Wing’s trench-run attack</a> against the Death Star in <em>Star Wars</em>.</p><div data-og-block-area="article-blocks" data-og-block-nth="4" data-og-block-type="core/embed"><p itemprop="associatedMedia"><iframe frameborder="0" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/y09ssRENr9I?feature=oembed&amp;rel=0&amp;enablejsapi=1" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p></div><p>But, now almost forgotten, BOAC’s small fleet of unarmed couriers, more <em><a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/38140/this-navigator-aboard-a-russian-il-76-looks-like-a-tie-fighter-pilot-from-star-wars">Millennium Falcon</a></em> than <a href="https://www.thedrive.com/the-war-zone/31249/disneys-plan-to-fly-x-wings-over-star-wars-park-speaks-to-perception-manipulation-tactics">X-Wing</a>, made a crucial contribution of their own, flying vital personnel, cargo, and intelligence to and from Sweden. Completing their own Kessel Run over 520 times before the war’s end — on one occasion in early 1944, three times in a single night — the unarmed speedsters suffered losses due to bad weather and bad luck, but not one, despite coming under attack, was ever believed to have been lost to the Luftwaffe.</p><p>Perhaps, though, that brief, seemingly insignificant scene in <em>Oppenheimer</em> will be as close as they ever get to movie stardom of their own.</p><p><strong><em>Mosquito: The RAF’s Legendary Wooden Wonder and its Most Extraordinary Mission</em> by Rowland White is <a target="_blank" href="https://www.amazon.com/Mosquito-Legendary-Wooden-Extraordinary-Mission-ebook/dp/B0BY1PR6GF/">published by Bantam Books</a></strong>.</p><p><em>Contact the editor: thomas@thedrive.com</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anti-Anti-Adblocker uBlock filter to get rid of the annoying YouTube message (330 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/endermanch/status/1713129854818742684</link>
            <guid>37884683</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 22:06:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/endermanch/status/1713129854818742684">https://twitter.com/endermanch/status/1713129854818742684</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37884683">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/endermanch/status/1713129854818742684: Error [ERR_FR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS]: Maximum number of redirects exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Widely accepted mathematical results that were later shown to be wrong? (2010) (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mathoverflow.net/questions/35468/widely-accepted-mathematical-results-that-were-later-shown-to-be-wrong</link>
            <guid>37884177</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 20:53:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/35468/widely-accepted-mathematical-results-that-were-later-shown-to-be-wrong">https://mathoverflow.net/questions/35468/widely-accepted-mathematical-results-that-were-later-shown-to-be-wrong</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37884177">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<p>The Busemann-Petty problem (posed in 1956) has an interesting history. It asks the following question: if $K$ and $L$ are two origin-symmetric convex bodies in $\mathbb{R}^n$ such that the volume of each central hyperplane section of $K$ is less than the volume of the corresponding section of $L$:
$$\operatorname{Vol}_{n-1}(K\cap \xi^\perp)\le \operatorname{Vol}_{n-1}(L\cap \xi^\perp)\qquad\text{for all } \xi\in S^{n-1},$$
does it follow that the volume of $K$ is less than the volume of $L$: $\operatorname{Vol}_n(K)\le \operatorname{Vol}_n(L)?$</p>

<p>Many mathematician's gut reaction to the question is that the answer must be yes and Minkowski's uniqueness theorem provides some mathematical justification for such a belief---Minkwoski's uniqueness theorem implies that an origin-symmetric star body in $\mathbb{R}^n$ is completely determined by the volumes of its central hyperplane sections, so these volumes of central hyperplane sections <em>do</em> contain a vast amount of information about the bodies. It was widely believed that the answer to the Busemann-Problem must be true, even though it was still a largely unopened conjecture.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, in 1975 everyone was caught off-guard when Larman and Rogers produced a counter-example showing that the assertion is false in $n \ge 12$ dimensions. Their counter-example was quite complicated, but in 1986, Keith Ball proved that the maximum hyperplane section of the unit cube is $\sqrt{2}$ regardless of the dimension, and a consequence of this is that the centered unit cube and a centered ball of suitable radius provide a counter-example when $n \ge 10$. Some time later Giannopoulos and Bourgain (independently) gave counter-examples for $n\ge 7$, and then Papadimitrakis and Gardner (independently) gave counter-examples for $n=5,6$.</p>

<p>By 1992 only the three and four dimensional cases of the Busemann-Petty problem remained unsolved, since the problem is trivially true in two dimensions and by that point counter-examples had been found for all $n\ge 5$. 
Around this time theory had been developed connecting the problem with the notion of an "intersection body". Lutwak proved that if the body with smaller sections is an intersection body then the conclusion of the Busemann-Petty problem follows. Later work by Grinberg, Rivin, Gardner, and Zhang strengthened the connection and established that the Busemann-Petty problem has an affirmative answer in $\mathbb{R}^n$ iff every origin-symmetric convex body in $\mathbb{R}^n$ is an intersection body. But the question of whether a body is an intersection body is closely related to the positivity of the inverse spherical Radon transform. In 1994, Richard Gardner used geometric methods to invert the spherical Radon transform in three dimensions in such a way to prove that the problem has an <em>affirmative</em> answer in three dimensions (which was surprising since all of the results up to that point had been <em>negative</em>). Then in 1994, Gaoyong Zhang published a paper (in the Annals of Mathematics) which claimed to prove that the unit cube in $\mathbb{R}^4$ is not an intersection body and as a consequence that the problem has a negative answer in $n=4$.</p>

<p>For three years everyone believed the problem had been solved, but in 1997 Alexander Koldobsky (who was working on completely different problems) provided a new Fourier analytic approach to convex bodies and in particular established a very convenient Fourier analytic characterization of intersection bodies. Using his new characterization he showed that the unit cube in $\mathbb{R}^4$ <em>is</em> an intersection body, contradicting Zhang's earlier claim. It turned out that Zhang's paper was incorrect and this re-opened the Busemann-Petty problem again.</p>

<p>After learning that Koldobsky's results contradicted his claims, Zhang quickly proved that in fact every origin-symmetric convex body in $\mathbb{R}^4$ <em>is</em> an intersection body and hence that the Busemann-Petty problem has an affirmative answer in $\mathbb{R}^4$---the opposite of what he had previously claimed. This later paper was also published in the Annals, and so Zhang may be perhaps the only person to have published in such a prestigious journal both that $P$ and that $\neg P$!</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Comcast squeezing 2Gbps internet speeds through decades-old coaxial cables (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.engadget.com/comcast-starts-squeezing-2-gbps-symmetrical-internet-speeds-through-decades-old-coaxial-cables-143657830.html</link>
            <guid>37882622</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 17:53:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.engadget.com/comcast-starts-squeezing-2-gbps-symmetrical-internet-speeds-through-decades-old-coaxial-cables-143657830.html">https://www.engadget.com/comcast-starts-squeezing-2-gbps-symmetrical-internet-speeds-through-decades-old-coaxial-cables-143657830.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37882622">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main role="main"><div id="module-moreStories" data-wf-sticky-offset="130px   10px" data-wf-sticky-position="" data-wf-sticky-target="#adsStream" data-wf-trigger-percentage=""><ul><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/JfO8nQJyRxjJXHHfIehd_A--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-10/c3321090-69fb-11ee-bffc-c0eb1ec5c327" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="e57a73d9-fba2-42bc-9eff-80681f65291d" href="https://www.engadget.com/proton-vpn-review-2023-why-its-our-top-choice-vpn-153046020.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:12;ct:story;g:e57a73d9-fba2-42bc-9eff-80681f65291d" data-hosted-type="HOSTED" data-wf-caas-prefetch="1" data-wf-caas-uuid="e57a73d9-fba2-42bc-9eff-80681f65291d">Proton VPN review 2023: Why it's our top-choice VPN</a></h4><p>Proton promises “privacy by default,” but that left me wondering if the company meant rigorous security testing — and if a focus on privacy would take away from ease of use. Because it balanced all of the above, Proton VPN landed at the top of our list.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li></li><li><div><p><img src="https://s.yimg.com/cv/apiv2/default/20190501/placeholder.gif" data-wf-src="https://s.yimg.com/uu/api/res/1.2/fJfPE6lqMhQCUBONyUUgTQ--~B/Zmk9c3RyaW07aD0yODg7dz01MTQ7YXBwaWQ9eXRhY2h5b24-/https://s.yimg.com/os/creatr-uploaded-images/2023-10/ea7c1b10-69f5-11ee-bbee-e7715f55958f" alt=""></p><div><p><span>Engadget</span></p><h4><a data-uuid="ec60c2eb-ba5e-4748-8019-1b4fd38b0f30" href="https://www.engadget.com/chevys-first-hybrid-corvette-isnt-what-you-think-it-is-171111642.html" data-ylk="elm:hdln;itc:0;pos:1;sec:strm;subsec:moreforyou;cpos:15;ct:story;g:ec60c2eb-ba5e-4748-8019-1b4fd38b0f30" data-hosted-type="HOSTED" data-wf-caas-prefetch="1" data-wf-caas-uuid="ec60c2eb-ba5e-4748-8019-1b4fd38b0f30">Chevy’s first hybrid Corvette isn’t what you think it is</a></h4><p>It’s hard to imagine that anyone in the world was demanding a hybrid Corvette, but those crazy engineers at Chevrolet went and did it anyway. Meet the 2024 Chevrolet Corvette E-Ray, but if you’re already angry at the concept, you shouldn't be.</p></div></div></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li><li></li></ul></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Firefox add-on to open YouTube videos in alternative front ends (277 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon</link>
            <guid>37881771</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 16:22:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon">https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37881771">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/blob/main/src/icons/logo.png"><img width="460" src="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/raw/main/src/icons/logo.png" alt="YT Siphon Logo"></a>
</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-yt-siphon" dir="auto"><a href="#yt-siphon">YT Siphon</a></h2>
<h3 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-redirect-youtube-urls-to-alternative-frontends-manually" dir="auto"><a href="#redirect-youtube-urls-to-alternative-frontends-manually">Redirect YouTube URLs to Alternative Frontends Manually</a></h3>
<p dir="auto"><strong>YT Siphon</strong> is a browser extension that lets you choose to open YouTube videos in alternative frontends. Instead of auto-redirecting, it gives you the power to decide with simple shortcuts.
<strong>Key Features</strong>:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong><code>Alt+J</code></strong>: Open the current YouTube video in your chosen frontend.
<ul dir="auto">
<li><em>Tip</em>: You can customize this shortcut in your browser settings.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong><code>Shift+Click</code></strong>: While on YouTube, use this to open a video (by clicking on thumbnails / links) in the configured frontend in a new tab.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Perfect for those who like to browse the YouTube homepage and selectively watch videos on alternative frontends. Also handy if someone shares a YouTube link with you and you prefer watching it on a different frontend.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-motivation" dir="auto"><a href="#motivation">Motivation</a></h2>
<p dir="auto">YouTube started cracking down on Ad Blocker usage, so this is my workaround.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/blob/main/screenshots/adblocker-notallowed.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/raw/main/screenshots/adblocker-notallowed.jpg" alt="Ad Blocker Not Allowed"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/blob/main/screenshots/adblocker-tos.png"><img src="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/raw/main/screenshots/adblocker-tos.png" alt="Ad Blocker TOS"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/blob/main/screenshots/adblocker-counter.png"><img src="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/raw/main/screenshots/adblocker-counter.png" alt="Ad Blocker Counter"></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-installation" dir="auto"><a href="#installation">Installation</a></h2>
<h3 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-mozilla-add-ons-site" dir="auto"><a href="#mozilla-add-ons-site">Mozilla Add-Ons site</a></h3>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/yt-siphon/" rel="nofollow">Get the add-on from addons.mozilla.org</a></p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-manual" dir="auto"><a href="#manual">Manual</a></h3>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Download the <code>.xpi</code> addon file from the <a href="https://github.com/d3vr/yt-siphon/releases/">Releases page</a></li>
<li>Go to <code>about:addons</code></li>
<li>Click the gear icon and select <code>Install Add-on From File</code></li>
</ol>
<h3 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-cloned-repo" dir="auto"><a href="#cloned-repo">Cloned repo</a></h3>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Clone the repository or download as zip</li>
<li>Go to <code>about:debugging</code></li>
<li>Click on <code>This Firefox</code></li>
<li>Then <code>Load Temporary Add-on</code></li>
<li>Select <code>manifest.json</code> in the <code>src/</code> directory from the cloned repo.</li>
</ol>
<h2 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-configuration" dir="auto"><a href="#configuration">Configuration</a></h2>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Visit YouTube then click the Add-Ons icon to open the panel and click the gear icon next to <code>YT Siphon</code></li>
<li>Select <code>Always Allow on www.youtube.com</code></li>
<li>...</li>
<li>Profit?</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">You can change the default configured alternative frontend (<code>piped.video</code>) from the options page. You can click the extension's icon to access the options page.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-credit" dir="auto"><a href="#credit">Credit</a></h2>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>GPT-4 and <a href="https://www.phind.com/" rel="nofollow">Phind</a> helped a lot while creating this add-on.</li>
<li>DALL-E 3 created the logo / icon.</li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" id="user-content-license" dir="auto"><a href="#license">License</a></h2>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.tldrlegal.com/license/mit-license" rel="nofollow">MIT</a></p>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Germany's terrible trains are no joke for a nation built on efficiency (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/oct/14/its-the-same-daily-misery-germanys-terrible-trains-are-no-joke-for-a-nation-built-on-efficiency</link>
            <guid>37881767</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 16:22:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/oct/14/its-the-same-daily-misery-germanys-terrible-trains-are-no-joke-for-a-nation-built-on-efficiency">https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/oct/14/its-the-same-daily-misery-germanys-terrible-trains-are-no-joke-for-a-nation-built-on-efficiency</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37881767">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p><span><span>T</span></span>he sleek high-speed train is 10 minutes behind schedule when it slides into Cologne’s main station before continuing its journey north to Dortmund. The delay is now such a common occurrence that the train manager does not even both to mention it to disembarking passengers.</p><p>In late afternoon on an unremarkable weekday in this western German city, holidaymakers are hauling suitcases through the station, workers are commuting home, and the late arrival of Deutsche Bahn’s IC 118 from Innsbruck is no surprise.</p><p>It does cause annoyance, though: a glance at the departures and arrivals board prompts one middle-aged man carrying a backpack to swear loudly as he enters the station.</p><p>It’s hard to blame him: on the afternoon the <em>Observer</em> visited, the arrivals board showed that eight out of the next nine trains due into Cologne were behind schedule. The degree of lateness ranged from minutes to several hours, and a lengthy queue had formed at the entrance hall’s information desk.</p><p>“The situation has severely deteriorated in recent years,” said Detlef Neuss, chair of the passenger lobby group Pro Bahn, standing outside Cologne’s main station, in the shadow of the city’s gothic cathedral with its distinctive twin spires.</p><figure id="93f3aa06-1494-43d5-bca9-9a12f75a6bd0" data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Detlef Neuss outside station" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/7bc57d826d50bf061f683a0bf3c96dd747fe87a7/0_490_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="266.9779265873016" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Detlef Neuss, chairman of passenger lobby group Pro Bahn.</span> Photograph: Joanna Partridge</figcaption></figure><p>“They tried to keep the trains running on time, so some building projects were postponed,” Neuss continues. “That was a big mistake, and the rail network has been run even further into the ground.”</p><p>For travellers in the UK, this may sound familiar. Earlier this month, after weeks of speculation over the future of Britain’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2023/oct/02/hs2-timeline-rail-high-speed-rail-project" data-link-name="in body link">planned HS2 high-speed rail link</a> from Birmingham to Manchester, the prime minister finally announced that <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/politics/2023/oct/04/rishi-sunak-conservative-conference-speech-hs2" data-link-name="in body link">the northern leg was to be scrapped</a>. But the UK’s train passengers are far from the only ones in Europe facing rail problems.</p><p>Germany’s railways, once a source of national pride, have become something of an embarrassment in a country with a reputation for efficiency and engineering prowess. And this comes amid a time of economic anxiety, with <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/sep/19/germany-world-economic-slowdown-oecd-interest-rates-china" data-link-name="in body link">Europe’s largest economy stagnating</a> amid weaker global growth.</p><p>Deutsche Bahn has been described as being in “permanent crisis” by Germany’s national audit office, the <em>Bundesrechnungshof</em>, which is usually known for its sober language.</p><p>In an <a href="https://www.bundesrechnungshof.de/SharedDocs/Kurzmeldungen/EN/kurzmeldungen-berichte/db-dauerkrise/db-dauerkrise.html" data-link-name="in body link">excoriating special report</a> published earlier this year, the public audit body did not mince its words as it sounded the alarm, warning that the company responsible for running the national rail network, its stations and signals, along with many long-distance and local trains, risked becoming a “bottomless pit” for taxpayer money.</p><p>It said debts at the company – which is wholly owned by Germany’s federal government – were growing at the rate of more than €5m (£4.3m) a day, and its total debt was now more than €30bn.</p><figure id="47474344-3980-4659-8c73-a4cdc19a1cb9" data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-3"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Passengers on the concourse at Cologne station " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/e52dc1af64bbc3d37557c9ef15b32d4f897d7b53/0_365_4032_2419/master/4032.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="266.9779265873016" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Passengers on the concourse at Cologne station check a departure board showing delays of several hours.</span> Photograph: Joanna Partridge</figcaption></figure><p>Worsening reliability, including delays, cancellations and lengthy closures of large sections of track during upgrade work, have become a popular topic of conversation across Germany. Meanwhile passengers in neighbouring Austria are complaining about the knock-on effect of hold-ups across the border, and Switzerland’s famously punctual railways have stopped waiting for the arrival of connections from Germany.</p><p>It was not always thus. Teacher Max Winter, 43, did not think twice about accepting a job at a school in the city of Wolfsburg, despite it being more than 140 miles from his home in Berlin, because Wolfsburg was on the line between the capital and Hanover, and there were regular rail services.</p><p>“I didn’t consider it a big distance,” he says. “At the start I never thought about it, or even considered moving to Wolfsburg.”</p><p>When he began his daily commute in January 2016, he had few problems with the hour-long journey on a high-speed intercity train, bookended by cycle rides. The trip would have taken three times as long by car.</p><p>“In the past few years it has really changed, and I can’t defend Deutsche Bahn any more,” he says.</p><p>Despite paying some €4,400 for an annual season ticket, in recent months Winter has had to put up with a weeks-long closure of the track between Wolfsburg and Berlin for upgrades, coupled with delays, cancelled trains and lack of staff. At one point, the father-of-one even had to temporarily rent a room in Wolfsburg to ensure he could make it to work.</p><p>Back in western Germany Birgit Schmitt-Janssen, 61, also feels let down. “You can 100% count on Deutsche Bahn to be late,” she laughs. “It’s the same daily misery.”</p><p>She does not have a driving licence, and describes herself as “dependent” on Deutsche Bahn for the daily 13-mile commute from her home in Mönchengladbach to her office in the town of Krefeld.</p><p>Schmitt-Janssen, who volunteers with passenger group Pro Bahn, says the journey, which she has made for the past nine years, has been unreliable ever since the staffing shortages that followed the pandemic. “I get really annoyed when I’m standing on the platform and it becomes clear there are lots of delays,” says, adding that rail replacement buses could double the length of her commute.</p><p>“You get the feeling they run through a catalogue of excuses. Today it was damaged signal boxes, tomorrow they’ll say it was defective train doors, and the following day it’ll be an earlier train running late. Everyone on the platform says, ‘oh, not again.’”</p><p>Frustrated passengers regularly take to social media to share complaints or <a href="https://twitter.com/AmreiBahr/status/1679529846395764736" data-link-name="in body link">joke about the most improbable reason</a> they’ve been given for a disrupted service.</p><p>The extent of Deutsche Bahn’s problems is not just anecdotal. Official figures showed record delays in 2022, when more than a third of long-distance trains ran late, and delays to regional and freight trains became more frequent.</p><figure id="6b6123aa-2fe0-4361-8e43-7d5dc5386d40" data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-4"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Engineering work on Germany’s tracks" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/ff4c8186173fa00bc65926ac5b02b6179649d93e/0_3_7478_4486/master/7478.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="266.9523936881519" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Engineering work on Germany’s tracks can mean lines close for weeks.</span> Photograph: Getty Images</figcaption></figure><p>But things <a href="https://www.deutschebahn.com/de/konzern/konzernprofil/zahlen_fakten/puenktlichkeitswerte-6878476" data-link-name="in body link">have got worse</a> in recent months: more than 36% of long-distance trains were delayed in August, along with almost 9% of regional trains. This was blamed on the high volume of building work across the rail network – despite the company giving itself the buffer of saying passenger trains are on time if they are less than six minutes late.</p><p>Germany may be the home of an ever-powerful carmaking lobby and an <em>autobahn </em>which includes some sections free of speed limits, but it is also heavily reliant on its extensive rail network.</p><p>It connects the country’s major cities – Hamburg to Munich, Frankfurt to Berlin – to each other and to the rest of the continent, although the track network has in fact been shrinking for years.</p><p>Many believe that decades of chronic underinvestment have now come home to roost, with the railways becoming a symbol of Germany’s creaking infrastructure – alongside motorways and bridges – at a time of economic malaise. The IMF and OECD have warned that the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/sep/19/germany-world-economic-slowdown-oecd-interest-rates-china" data-link-name="in body link">country will be a laggard among the world’s leading economies this year</a>.</p><p>It also comes as many are reassessing the priorities pursued during the Angela Merkel years, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/dec/09/neckarwestheim-delay-phasing-out-nuclear-power-dividing-german-village" data-link-name="in body link">including the country’s energy policy</a> and its dealings with Russia.</p><p>Deutsche Bahn is in its biggest crisis since its creation almost 30 years ago, in the 1994 “rail reform” that followed the fall of the Berlin Wall and German reunification.</p><p>The company, formed from the existing West and East German railways, was freed from previous debts with the idea that it would be able, in time, to become profitable, with the goal of boosting Germany’s GDP and floating on the stock market.</p><p>Except it did not quite work out that way. Unlike other similarly privatised companies such as <a href="https://www.telekom.com/en/media/media-information/archive/25-years-of-deutsche-telekom-ag-589922" data-link-name="in body link">Deutsche Telekom and the postal service Deutsche Post, which successfully went public</a>, Deutsche Bahn remains in government hands.</p><p>Its company structure is unusual in that it has one sole owner, shareholder and financial backer: the German state. Indeed, the German constitution requires the government to retain majority ownership of the national railway infrastructure.</p><p>Critics have blamed this arrangement for what they see as Deutsche Bahn’s major failings, such as its decision to expand its global operations while ignoring its main objective and responsibility to German taxpayers: the operation of Germany’s rail network.</p><p>“It is very clear that the company’s core business, rail in Germany, has to be its focus,” says Kay Scheller, the president of Germany’s federal audit office, from his office overlooking the Rhine in Bonn. “We have all the disadvantages of this company structure, without the benefits.”</p><p>Since 1994, Deutsche Bahn has ballooned into an international transport giant: passengers in 10 European countries ride on buses run by its Arriva subsidiary, which also operates London Overground trains for <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/transport" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Transport</a> for London, while its Schenker division handles international air, land and sea freight.</p><p>The German transport ministry, which has responsibility for Deutsche Bahn, stands accused of years of failure to get a grip on the company’s management and operations, all while stumping up funding.</p><p>Scheller says: “The German federal government needs to coordinate the company more, and steer it more. That means if things don’t work, it has to intervene.”</p><p>He adds: “All criticism rolls off the back of Deutsche Bahn’s management, because they don’t have to fear any sanctions or reforms which would fundamentally change the system. However, these are necessary and I’m not confident that the situation will improve otherwise.”</p><p>Indeed, the company’s most recent financial results, for the first six months of 2023, illustrate a worsening situation: Deutsche Bahn made a net loss of €71m in the first half, compared with a profit of €424m for the same period a year earlier.</p><p>As a result, Germany’s current three-way coalition government will not be able to achieve some of its loftier ambitions for rail during this decade, according to the federal audit office.</p><p>The <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2021/nov/24/german-parties-agree-coalition-deal-to-make-olaf-scholz-chancellor" data-link-name="in body link">governing agreement</a> struck by the Social Democrats, Greens and Liberals in late 2021 committed them to doubling the capacity of passenger services by 2030, while setting a target for 25% of freight to be carried by rail by that date, and electrifying more railway lines amid attempts to meet climate goals.</p><p>Contrary to the view of the country’s audit office, Neuss and passenger representatives believe more investment is the answer to many of Deutsche Bahn’s problems.</p><p>At a recent rail summit organised by the government and Deutsche Bahn, Germany’s transport minister, Volker Wissing, called it “unacceptable” that rail infrastructure had been “neglected for decades”.</p><p>Despite a “tight budgetary position”, he promised €40bn of additional investment in the railways to 2027, <a href="https://twitter.com/Wissing/status/1702688099904426373" data-link-name="in body link">as part of what he called</a> “the largest refurbishment and modernisation agenda in the history of this country’s railways”.</p><p>A Deutsche Bahn spokesperson told the <em>Observer</em> that the country’s rail infrastructure had not kept pace with increased passenger and freight traffic, and admitted that the network was “in parts too old, too overloaded and too prone to faults”.</p><p>The company has vowed to expand the most intensively used stretches of track, while replacing sleepers, track beds, rails, signal boxes and stations.</p><p>While this plan may be music to the ears of Neuss and passenger groups, who have been calling for significantly more investment, it received a mixed response from the country’s frustrated rail passengers, many of whom took to social media to decry the announcement as “too little too late”.</p><p>Scheller, the audit office president, also remains unconvinced. “So poor performance leads to even greater investment from the government,” he says. “This strengthens our argument: it won’t work without fundamental reform. Lots of money on its own isn’t a panacea.”</p><p>Germany’s transport ministry did not respond to the <em>Observer’s</em> repeated requests for comment.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Escape analysis hates copy elision (2021) (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2021/03/07/copy-elision-borks-escape-analysis/</link>
            <guid>37881699</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 16:16:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2021/03/07/copy-elision-borks-escape-analysis/">https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2021/03/07/copy-elision-borks-escape-analysis/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37881699">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <p>Yesterday Lauri Vasama showed me <a href="https://godbolt.org/z/jG7x5h">this awesome Godbolt</a>:</p>

<div><pre><code>struct S {
    static std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; make() noexcept;
    ~S();

    static std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; factory() {
        std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; s = S::make();
        return M(s);
    }
};

void take_ownership(S*) noexcept;

void test() {
    std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; p = S::factory();
    take_ownership(p.release());
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>When <code>M(s)</code> is defined as <code>std::move(s)</code>, Clang gives pretty much optimal codegen
for <code>test</code>:</p>

<div><pre><code>  pushq %rax
  movq %rsp, %rdi
  callq S::make()
  movq (%rsp), %rdi
  callq take_ownership(S*)
  popq %rax
  retq
</code></pre></div>

<p>But by defining <code>M(s)</code> as <code>std::move(s)</code>, we’re actually creating a return statement
of the form <code>return std::move(s)</code>, which is widely known as an antipattern in C++.
Returning “by <code>move</code>” disables <a href="https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2019/08/02/the-tough-guide-to-cpp-acronyms/#rvo-nrvo-urvo">RVO</a>,
and even when RVO doesn’t happen, <code>return std::move(x)</code> is (in 99% of cases)
no more efficient than <code>return x</code>, because <code>return x</code> triggers a special case in the
standard known as “implicit move,” which means that the copy into the return slot uses
the <em>move</em> constructor, not the <em>copy</em> constructor, even though the returned expression
<code>x</code> is totally an lvalue.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I have a proposal before EWG right now —
<a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2021/p2266r0.html">P2266</a> —
which in C++23 will make that <code>x</code> into an rvalue, literally. This radically simplifies
the wording and compiler implementation around “implicit move.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Okay, so, let’s get rid of that “return by <code>move</code>.” Let’s define <code>M(s)</code> to just <code>(s)</code>,
and see what happens. (Here’s the <a href="https://godbolt.org/z/jG7x5h">Godbolt</a> again.)</p>

<div><pre><code>  pushq %rbx
  subq $16, %rsp
  leaq 8(%rsp), %rdi
  callq S::make()
  movq 8(%rsp), %rdi
  movq $0, 8(%rsp)
  callq take_ownership(S*)
  movq 8(%rsp), %rbx
  testq %rbx, %rbx
  je .LBB0_2
  movq %rbx, %rdi
  callq S::~S() [complete object destructor]
  movq %rbx, %rdi
  callq operator delete(void*)
.LBB0_2:
  addq $16, %rsp
  popq %rbx
  retq
</code></pre></div>

<p>Whoa! The code got way longer! What happened?</p>

<hr>

<p>What happened was <em>copy elision.</em> When the body of <code>factory</code> was this:</p>

<div><pre><code>static std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; factory() {
    std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; s = S::make();
    return std::move(s);
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>the meaning was “Create an object named <code>s</code>, whose initial value comes from
being used as the return slot of <code>S::make()</code>. Then, construct the object
in my own return slot by calling <code>S</code>’s move constructor on xvalue <code>s</code>.”</p>

<p>When the body of <code>factory</code> changed to this:</p>

<div><pre><code>static std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; factory() {
    std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; s = S::make();
    return s;
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>the meaning changed as well, to “<em>Either</em> do the same thing as above; <em>or</em>,
let <code>s</code> be another name for my return slot, and give it its initial value by
using it as the return slot of <code>S::make()</code>.” In the latter case we’ve gone
from having “<code>s</code>” and “my return slot” be two separate objects, to having
them be one single object. This is normally a big performance win; we like it.</p>

<p>But in this case, this optimization interfered with Clang’s <em>escape analysis</em>.
Escape analysis is the thing that tells us, in</p>

<div><pre><code>void f(int);
int test() {
    int x = 42;
    f(x);
    return x + 1;  // i.e., return 43
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>that <code>x</code> must still be 42 after the call to <code>f</code>, because
(even though we don’t know what that function does in general) we know it
can’t modify <code>x</code>, because it doesn’t know <code>x</code>’s address on our stack.
Escape analysis tracks everything we do with <code>x</code>’s address, and can prove
in this case that that address has never <em>escaped</em> into the wider world.</p>

<p>However, if you change <code>f</code> to take its parameter as <code>const int&amp;</code>,
then <code>x</code>’s stack address <em>does</em> escape, and so the compiler can’t assume
the value of <code>x</code> remains unchanged after the call to <code>other_function</code>:
it must reload <code>x</code> from memory and actually compute that addition.
(<a href="https://godbolt.org/z/751Yc3">Godbolt.</a>) Because <code>f</code> might do</p>

<div><pre><code>void f(const int&amp; x) {
    *const_cast&lt;int*&gt;(&amp;x) = 918;
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>Even worse, consider this caller:</p>

<div><pre><code>void g(const int&amp;);
void h();
int test() {
    int x = 0;
    g(x);
    x = 42;
    h();
    return x + 1;
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>In this case, <code>h</code> doesn’t even receive <code>x</code>’s address… yet <code>h</code> can still
modify <code>x</code>, because by this point <code>x</code>’s address has already escaped! <code>g</code> and <code>h</code>
might collude together:</p>

<div><pre><code>int *global;
void g(const int&amp; x) {
    global = const_cast&lt;int*&gt;(&amp;x);
}
void h() {
    *global = 918;
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>The compiler’s escape analysis cannot rule out this possibility, and so,
<em>for all the compiler knows,</em> it might be the truth! After the call to <code>h</code>,
the compiler cannot assume that <code>x</code>’s value remains 42.</p>

<hr>

<p>Back to our <code>unique_ptr</code> example.</p>

<div><pre><code>struct S {
    static std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; make() noexcept;
    ~S();

    static std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; factory() {
        std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; s = S::make();
        return M(s);
    }
};

void take_ownership(S*) noexcept;

void test() {
    std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; p = S::factory();
    take_ownership(p.release());
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>Escape analysis reasons as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>The address of <code>factory</code>’s stack variable <code>s</code> escapes into <code>S::make</code>,
  as part of the calling convention for how <code>S::make</code> returns its prvalue
  result. We don’t know what <code>S::make</code> does with that address.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Later, we null out <code>test</code>’s stack variable <code>p</code>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Then, we call <code>take_ownership</code>. We don’t know what it does.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Finally, we destroy <code>p</code>, which is a no-op if and only if <code>p</code> is still null.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Could <code>take_ownership</code> affect <code>p</code>’s value, the way <code>h</code> affected <code>x</code>’s value in our
simpler example? Or can we assume that <code>p</code>’s value is definitely still null?
In short: does <code>p</code>’s address <em>escape?</em></p>

<p>Well, <code>p</code> is just another name for the return slot of <code>S::factory</code>.
When <code>S::factory</code> returns “by <code>move</code>,” it is constructing that object <em>right there</em>,
using the move-constructor of <code>unique_ptr</code>, which is fine for escape analysis
because that move-constructor is <code>inline</code> — we know what it does, and it <em>doesn’t</em>
stash any addresses in global variables. So <code>p</code>’s address doesn’t escape, which
means that <code>take_ownership</code> can’t possibly have access to <code>p</code>, which means that
<code>p</code> is still null when <code>take_ownership</code> returns, which means that we don’t need
to reload its value nor generate any code to call <code>delete</code> on it if it’s non-null.</p>

<p>But, when <code>S::factory</code> returns “by name,” copy elision kicks in. Now the returned
variable <code>s</code> becomes an alias for the object in <code>factory</code>’s return slot (which
you’ll recall is already an alias for <code>p</code>). And <code>s</code>’s address <em>does</em> escape —
it escapes into <code>S::make</code>!</p>

<p>Suppose <code>S::make</code> and <code>take_ownership</code> were secretly colluding, like this:</p>

<div><pre><code>std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; *global;

std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; S::make() {
    std::unique_ptr&lt;S&gt; origp = std::make_unique&lt;S&gt;();
    global = &amp;origp;
    return origp;
}

void take_ownership(S *rawp) {
    delete rawp;
    *global = std::make_unique&lt;S&gt;();
}
</code></pre></div>

<p>The compiler cannot rule out this possibility, and so it must assume that calling
<code>take_ownership</code> might repopulate the stack variable <code>p</code> with a new value.
So it generates all that extra code in <code>test</code> to reload, check, and possibly <code>delete</code>
the value of <code>p</code>.</p>

<hr>

<p>Clang and ICC behave pretty uniformly as described in this blog post.
GCC “succeeds” in generating good code for both variations of the Godbolt above (with
or without <code>std::move</code>), but this appears to be <a href="https://stackoverflow.com/questions/48749440/c-nrvo-copy-elision-with-return-statement-in-parentheses">due to a GCC bug</a> —
it thinks <code>return (s)</code> with parentheses is a request to disable copy elision!
A slight tweak to my <code>M</code> macro, to remove the redundant parentheses,
and GCC joins the pack: <a href="https://godbolt.org/z/361sfY">Godbolt</a>.</p>

<hr>

<p>It would be interesting to see a compiler patch that instrumented escape analysis somehow,
so that it could give an optimization-time note such as “Object <code>x</code>’s address escapes only
because copy elision in <code>f</code> gave <code>x</code> the same address as object <code>y</code>.” I think that would happen
a lot, and certainly isn’t something you’d want to see in your daily builds; but it might be
very interesting to trawl through the output.</p>

<hr>

<p>Anton Zhilin’s <a href="http://www.open-std.org/jtc1/sc22/wg21/docs/papers/2020/p2025r1.html">P2025R1 “Guaranteed copy elision for return variables”</a>
(June 2020) talks a bit about escape analysis in section 6.5, “What about the invalidation of optimizations?”
The more we expand the scope of copy-elision, the easier it will be for copy-elision to bump up against
escape analysis. The example dissected in today’s blog post is interesting precisely <em>because</em> it is
obscure and happens so rarely.</p>

<p>Please do not use this post as evidence that copy elision is bad! Copy elision is awesome!
Mainly this post is an interesting piece of trivia. But, secondarily, if any change to C++ <em>is</em> needed
in this area, it would be <em>tightening up the object model</em> so that escape analysis could
become more aggressive. I hope we all agree that the kind of “collusion” shown in this post is
terribly contrived, and nothing of value would be lost if C++ disallowed it. Escape analysis should
not allow for the possibility that a function has “remembered” the address of its own prvalue return
slot.</p>

<hr>

<p>Previously on this blog:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://quuxplusone.github.io/blog/2018/04/17/downsides-of-omitting-trivial-destructor-calls">“Downsides of omitting trivial destructor calls”</a> (2018-04-17)</li>
</ul>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Examining the silicon dies of the Intel 386 processor (260 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.righto.com/2023/10/intel-386-die-versions.html</link>
            <guid>37881656</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 16:12:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.righto.com/2023/10/intel-386-die-versions.html">http://www.righto.com/2023/10/intel-386-die-versions.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37881656">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-4071644285770837621" itemprop="description articleBody"><p>
You might think of the Intel 386 processor (1985) as just an early processor in the x86
line, but the 386 was a critical turning point for modern computing in several ways.<span id="fnref:second-source"><a href="#fn:second-source">1</a></span>
First, the 386 moved the x86 architecture to 32 bits, defining the dominant computing
architecture for the rest of the 20th century.
The 386 also established the overwhelming importance of x86, not just for Intel, but for the entire computer
industry.
Finally, the 386 ended IBM's control over the PC market, turning Compaq into the architectural
leader.</p>
<p>In this blog post, I look at die photos of the Intel 386 processor and explain what they reveal
about the history of the processor, such as the move from the 1.5 µm process to the
1 µm process.
You might expect that Intel simply made the same 386 chip at a smaller scale, but there were
substantial changes to the chip's layout, even some visible to the naked eye.<span id="fnref:keychains"><a href="#fn:keychains">2</a></span>
I also look at why the 386 SL had over three times the transistors as the other 386 versions.<span id="fnref:variants"><a href="#fn:variants">3</a></span></p>
<p>The 80386 was a major advancement over the 286: it implemented a 32-bit architecture,
added more instructions, and supported 4-gigabyte segments.
The 386 is a complicated processor (by 1980s standards), with 285,000 transistors, ten times the number of the original 8086.<span id="fnref:transistors"><a href="#fn:transistors">4</a></span>
The 386 has eight logical units
that are pipelined<span id="fnref:parallelism"><a href="#fn:parallelism">5</a></span> and operate mostly autonomously.<span id="fnref:block-diagram"><a href="#fn:block-diagram">6</a></span>
The diagram below shows the internal structure of the 386.<span id="fnref:die-diagram"><a href="#fn:die-diagram">7</a></span></p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/386-die-labeled.jpg"><img alt="The 386 with the main functional blocks labeled. Click this image (or any other) for a larger version. I created this image using a die photo from Antoine Bercovici." height="641" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/386-die-labeled-w600.jpg" title="The 386 with the main functional blocks labeled. Click this image (or any other) for a larger version. I created this image using a die photo from Antoine Bercovici." width="600"></a></p><p>The 386 with the main functional blocks labeled. Click this image (or any other) for a larger version. I created this image using a die photo from Antoine Bercovici.</p>
<p>The heart of a processor is the datapath, the components that hold and process data.
In the 386, these components are in the lower left: the ALU (Arithmetic/Logic Unit), a barrel shifter to shift data, and the registers.
These components form regular rectangular blocks, 32 bits wide.
The datapath, along with the circuitry to the left that manages it, forms the Data Unit.
In the lower right is the microcode ROM, which breaks down machine instructions into
micro-instructions, the low-level steps of the instruction.
The microcode ROM, along with the microcode engine circuitry, forms the Control Unit.</p>
<p>The 386 has a complicated instruction format.
The Instruction Decode Unit breaks apart an instruction into its component parts
and generates a pointer to the microcode that implements the instruction.
The instruction queue holds three decoded instructions.
To improve performance, the Prefetch Unit reads instructions from memory before they are
needed, and stores them in the 16-byte prefetch queue.<span id="fnref:queue"><a href="#fn:queue">8</a></span></p>
<!-- Introduction to the 80386 p52 -->

<p>The 386 implements segmented memory and virtual memory, with access protection.<span id="fnref:protection"><a href="#fn:protection">9</a></span>
The Memory Management Unit
consists of the Segment Unit and the Paging Unit:
the Segment Unit translates a logical address to a linear address, while the Paging Unit
translates the linear address to a physical address.
The segment descriptor cache and page cache (TLB) hold data about segments and pages;
the 386 has no on-chip instruction or data cache.<span id="fnref:cache"><a href="#fn:cache">10</a></span>
The Bus Interface Unit in the upper right handles communication between the 386 and the external
memory and devices.</p>
<!--
The 386 can support thousands of segments, with the most recent segment information stored
in the [segment descriptor cache](https://web.archive.org/web/20220405211445/http://www.rcollins.org/ddj/Aug98/Aug98.html).
The 32-entry translation lookaside buffer (TLB or page cache) caches the translation information for
the most recently used pages.
El-Ayat p14 discusses the protection test unit.
-->

<p>Silicon dies are often labeled with the initials of the designers. The 386 DX, however,
has an unusually large number of initials. In the image below, I have enlarged the tiny initials so they are visible.
I think the designers put their initials next to the unit they worked on, but 
I haven't been able to identify most of the names.<span id="fnref:et"><a href="#fn:et">11</a></span></p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/386-initials.jpg"><img alt="The 386 die with the initials magnified." height="641" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/386-initials-w600.jpg" title="The 386 die with the initials magnified." width="600"></a></p><p>The 386 die with the initials magnified.</p>
<h2>The shrink from 1.5 µm to 1 µm</h2>
<p>The original 386 was built on a process called CHMOS-III that had 1.5 µm features (specifically the gate channel length for a transistor).
Around 1987, Intel moved to an improved process called CHMOS-IV, with 1 µm features,
permitting a considerably smaller die for the 386.
However, shrinking the layout wasn't a simple mechanical process. Instead, many changes were
made to the chip, as shown in the comparison diagram below.
Most visibly, the Instruction Decode Unit and the Protection Unit in the center-right are
horizontal in the smaller die, rather than vertical.
The standard-cell logic (discussed later) is considerably more dense, probably due to
improved layout algorithms.
The data path (left) was highly optimized in the original so it remained essentially unchanged, but smaller.
One complication is that the bond pads around the border needed to remain the same size so bond wires could be attached.
To fit the pads around the smaller die, many of the pads are staggered.
Because different parts of the die shrank differently, the blocks no longer fit together as compactly, creating wasted space at the bottom of the die.
For some reason, the numerous initials on the original 386 die were removed.
Finally, the new die was labeled 80C386I with a copyright date of 1985, 1987; it is unclear what "C" and "I" indicate.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/shrink.jpg"><img alt="Comparison of the 1.5 µm die and the 1 µm die at the same scale. Photos courtesy of Antoine Bercovici." height="442" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/shrink-w700.jpg" title="Comparison of the 1.5 µm die and the 1 µm die at the same scale. Photos courtesy of Antoine Bercovici." width="700"></a></p><p>Comparison of the 1.5 µm die and the 1 µm die at the same scale. Photos courtesy of Antoine Bercovici.</p>
<p>The change from 1.5 µm to 1 µm may not sound significant, but it reduced the die size by
60%.
This allowed more dies on a wafer, substantially dropping the manufacturing cost.<span id="fnref:wafer"><a href="#fn:wafer">12</a></span>
The strategy of shrinking a processor to a new process before designing a new microarchitecture
for the process became Intel's <a href="https://retailedge.intel.com/content/pdf/asmo/201303art_computerpoweruser.pdf">tick-tock</a> strategy.</p>

<p>In 1988, Intel introduced the 386 SX processor, the low-cost version of the 386,
with a 16-bit bus instead of a 32-bit bus.
(This is reminiscent of the 8088 processor with an 8-bit bus versus the 8086 processor
with a 16-bit bus.)
According to the <a href="https://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/access/text/2015/06/102702019-05-01-acc.pdf#page=25">386 oral history</a>,
the cost of the original 386 die decreased to the point where the chip's package cost about as
much as the die.
By reducing the number of pins, the 386 SX could be put in a one-dollar plastic package
and sold for a considerably reduced price.
The SX allowed Intel to segment the market, moving low-end customers <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=fSMW_RgWwIgC&amp;lpg=PT95&amp;pg=PT94#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">from the 286</a> to the 386 SX, while preserving the
higher sales price of the original 386, now called the DX.<span id="fnref:286"><a href="#fn:286">13</a></span>
<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1988/06/21/science/personal-computers-new-chip-less-cost-for-power.html">In 1988</a>, Intel sold the 386 SX for $219, at least $100 less than the 386 DX.
A complete SX computer could be $1000 cheaper than a similar DX model.</p>
<!-- p25 Shrink of 386.-->
<!-- p25 claim that the 8-bit bus of the 8088 was what tipped the IBM PC processor choice to Intel -->

<p>For compatibility with older 16-bit peripherals, the original 386 was designed to support a mixture of 16-bit and 32-bit buses, dynamically
switching on a cycle-by-cycle basis if needed.
Because 16-bit support was built into the 386, the 386 SX didn't require much design work.
(Unlike the 8088, which required a redesign of the 8086's bus interface unit.)</p>
<p>The 386 SX was built at both 1.5 µm and 1 µm.
The diagram below compares the two sizes of the 386 SX die.
These photos may look identical to the 386 DX photos in the previous section,
but close examination shows a few differences.
Since the 386 SX uses fewer pins, it has fewer bond pads, eliminating the staggered pads of
the shrunk 386 DX.
There are a few differences at the bottom of the chip, with wiring in much of the 386 DX's
wasted space.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/dies-sx.jpg"><img alt="Comparison of two dies for the 386 SX. Photos courtesy of Antoine Bercovici." height="462" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/dies-sx-w700.jpg" title="Comparison of two dies for the 386 SX. Photos courtesy of Antoine Bercovici." width="700"></a></p><p>Comparison of two dies for the 386 SX. Photos courtesy of Antoine Bercovici.</p>
<p>Comparing the two SX revisions,
the larger die is labeled "80P9"; Intel's internal name for the chip was "P9", using their
confusing series of <a href="https://www.righto.com/search?q=i960#fn:processor-numbers">P numbers</a>.
The shrunk die is labeled "80386SX", which makes more sense.
The larger die is copyright 1985, 1987, while the shrunk die (which should be newer) is copyright 1985 for some reason.
The larger die has mostly the same initials as the DX, with a few changes.
The shrunk die has about 21 sets of initials.</p>
<h2>The 386 SL die</h2>
<p>The 386 SL (1990) was a major extension to the 386, combining a 386 core and other functions on one chip to save power and space.
Named "SuperSet", it was designed to corner the notebook PC market.<span id="fnref:superset"><a href="#fn:superset">14</a></span>
The 386 SL chip included an ISA bus controller, power management logic, a cache controller 
for an external cache, and the main memory controller.</p>
<p>Looking at the die photo below, the 386 core itself takes up about 1/4 of the SL's die.
The 386 core is very close to the standard 386 DX, but there are a few visible differences.
Most visibly, the bond pads and pin drivers have been removed from the core.
There are also some circuitry changes. For instance, the 386 SL core supports the <a href="https://websrv.cecs.uci.edu/~papers/mpr/MPR/ARTICLES/060805.PDF">System Management
Mode</a>, which suspends normal execution, allowing power management and other low-level hardware
tasks to be performed outside the regular operating system.
System Management Mode is now a standard part of the x86 line, but it was introduced in the 386 SL.</p>
<!-- 386 SL system management patent https://patents.google.com/patent/US5175853A/en?oq=+US5175853A -->

<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/386sl-die-labeled.jpg"><img alt="The 386 SL die with functional blocks labeled.  Die photo courtesy of Antoine Bercovici." height="606" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/386sl-die-labeled-w600.jpg" title="The 386 SL die with functional blocks labeled.  Die photo courtesy of Antoine Bercovici." width="600"></a></p><p>The 386 SL die with functional blocks labeled.  Die photo courtesy of Antoine Bercovici.</p>
<p>In total, the 386 SL contains 855,000 transistors,<span id="fnref:quickref"><a href="#fn:quickref">15</a></span> over 3 times as many as the regular 386 DX.
The cache tag RAM takes up a lot of space and transistors.
The cache data itself is external; this on-chip circuitry just manages the cache.
The other new components are largely implemented with standard-cell logic (discussed below); this is visible as uniform stripes
of circuitry, most clearly in the ISA bus controller.</p>
<h2>A brief history of the 386</h2>
<p>From the modern perspective, it seems obvious for Intel to extend the x86 line from the
286 to the 386, while keeping backward compatibility.
But at the time, this path was anything but clear.
This history starts in the late 1970s, when Intel decided to build a "micromainframe" processor, an advanced 32-bit
processor for object-oriented programming that had objects, interprocess communication,
and memory protection implemented in the CPU.
This overly ambitious project fell behind schedule, so Intel created a stopgap processor to
sell until the micromainframe processor was ready.
This stopgap processor was the 16-bit 8086 processor (1978).</p>
<p>In 1981, IBM decided to use the Intel 8088 (an 8086 variant) in the IBM Personal Computer (PC),
but Intel did not realize the importance of this at the time.
Instead, Intel was focused on their
micromainframe processor, also released in 1981 as the iAPX 432, but this became
"one of the great disaster stories of modern computing" as the <a href="https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/library/tech/98/04/biztech/articles/05merced.html">New York Times</a> called it.
Intel then reimplemented the ideas of the
ill-fated iAPX 432 on top of a RISC architecture, creating the more successful <a href="https://www.righto.com/2023/07/the-complex-history-of-intel-i960-risc.html">i960</a>. </p>
<p>Meanwhile, things weren't going well at first for the 286 processor, the follow-on to the 8086<span id="fnref:186"><a href="#fn:186">16</a></span>.
Bill Gates and others called its design "brain-damaged". 
IBM was unenthusiastic about the 286 for their own reasons.<span id="fnref:ibm-286"><a href="#fn:ibm-286">17</a></span>
As a result, the 386 project was a low priority for Intel and the 386 team felt that it was the
"stepchild"; internally, the 386 was pitched as another <a href="https://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/text/Oral_History/Intel_386_Business_Strategy/102701962.05.01.pdf#page=14">stopgap</a>, not Intel's "official" 32-bit processor.</p>
<p>Despite the lack of corporate enthusiasm, the 386 team came up with two proposals to
extend the 286 to a 32-bit architecture.
The first was a minimal approach to extend the existing registers and
address space to 32 bits.
The more ambitious proposal would add more registers and create a 32-bit instruction set that
was significantly different from the 8086's 16-bit instruction set.
At the time, the IBM PC was still relatively new, so the importance of the installed
base of software wasn't obvious; software compatibility was viewed as a "nice to have" feature rather than essential.
After much debate, the decision was made around the end of 1982 to go with the minimal proposal,
but supporting both segments and flat addressing, while keeping compatibility with the 286.</p>
<!--
A key design challenge was if it was possible to be compatible with the 8086's segment-based addressing, while
supporting the flat 32-bit address space that would support Unix well.
-->

<p>By 1984, though, the PC industry was booming and the 286 was proving to be a success.
This produced enormous political benefits for the 386 team, who saw the project change from
"stepchild" to "king". <!-- p17 -->
Intel introduced the 386 in 1985, which was otherwise
"a miserable year for Intel and the rest of the semiconductor industry,"
as Intel's <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/dam/doc/report/history-1985-annual-report.pdf">annual report</a> put it.
Due to an industry-wide business slowdown, Intel's net income "essentially disappeared."
Moreover, facing heavy competition from Japan, Intel dropped out of the DRAM business, a crushing blow
for a company that got its start in the memory industry.
Fortunately, the 386 would change everything.</p>
<p>Given IBM's success with the IBM PC, Intel was puzzled that IBM wasn't interested in the 386 processor, but IBM had a strategy of their own.<span id="fnref:ibm"><a href="#fn:ibm">18</a></span>
By this time, the IBM PC was being cloned by many competitors, but IBM had a plan to regain
control of the PC architecture and thus the market: in 1987, IBM introduced the PS/2 line.
These new computers ran the OS/2 operating system instead of Windows and used the proprietary Micro Channel architecture.<span id="fnref:ps2"><a href="#fn:ps2">19</a></span>
IBM used multiple engineering and legal strategies to make cloning the PS/2 slow, expensive, and risky,
so IBM expected they could take back the market from the clones.</p>
<!-- https://doi.org/10.1109/CMPCON.1988.4889 -->

<p>Compaq took the risky approach of ignoring IBM and following their own architectural direction.<span id="fnref:compaq"><a href="#fn:compaq">20</a></span>
Compaq introduced the high-end Deskpro 386 line in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1986/09/10/business/company-news-compaq-introduces-more-powerful-pc.html">September 1986</a>, becoming the first major company to build 386-based computers.
An "executive" system, the Deskpro 386 model 40 had a 40-megabyte hard drive and sold for $6449 (over $15,000 in current dollars).
Compaq's <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1987/09/20/business/the-executive-computer-compaq-s-gamble-on-an-advanced-chip-pays-off.html">gamble paid off</a>
and the Deskpro 386 was a rousing success.</p>
<!--
![The Compaq Deskpro 386. From a <a href="https://archive.org/details/personalcomputercompaq/page/n4/mode/1up">Compaq brochure</a>.](deskpro-386.jpg "w400")
-->

<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/compaq-386.jpg"><img alt="The Compaq Deskpro 386 in front of the 386 processor (not to scale). From PC Tech Journal, 1987. Curiously, the die image of the 386 has been mirrored, as can be seen both from the positions of the microcode ROM and instruction decoder at the top as well as from the position of the cut corner of the package." height="548" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/compaq-386-w400.jpg" title="The Compaq Deskpro 386 in front of the 386 processor (not to scale). From PC Tech Journal, 1987. Curiously, the die image of the 386 has been mirrored, as can be seen both from the positions of the microcode ROM and instruction decoder at the top as well as from the position of the cut corner of the package." width="400"></a></p><p>The Compaq Deskpro 386 in front of the 386 processor (not to scale). From <a href="https://archive.org/details/PC_Tech_Journal_vol05_n03/page/n51/mode/2up">PC Tech Journal</a>, 1987. Curiously, the die image of the 386 has been mirrored, as can be seen both from the positions of the microcode ROM and instruction decoder at the top as well as from the position of the cut corner of the package.</p>
<!-- BYTE Technical implications of PS/2 https://www.ardent-tool.com/docs/scans/BYTE_1987_10_Technical_Implications_of_PS2.pdf -->

<p>As for IBM, the PS/2 line was largely unsuccessful and failed to become the standard.
Rather than
regaining control over the PC,
"IBM lost control of the PC standard in 1987 when it introduced its PS/2 line of systems."<span id="fnref:logic"><a href="#fn:logic">21</a></span>
IBM exited the PC market in <a href="https://www.smh.com.au/business/ibms-exit-from-pc-business-seen-as-turning-point-20041209-gdka6w.html">2004</a>, selling the business to Lenovo.
One slightly hyperbolic <a href="https://amzn.to/3ZyK7nq">book title</a> summed it up: "Compaq Ended IBM's PC Domination and Helped Invent Modern Computing".
The 386 was a huge moneymaker for Intel, leading to Intel's first billion-dollar quarter in 1990.
It cemented the importance of the x86 architecture, not just for Intel but for the entire
computing industry, dominating the market up to the present day.<span id="fnref:marketshare"><a href="#fn:marketshare">22</a></span></p>
<h2>How the 386 was designed</h2>
<p>The design process of the 386 is interesting because it illustrates Intel's migration
to automated design systems and heavier use of simulation.<span id="fnref:design-and-test"><a href="#fn:design-and-test">23</a></span>
At the time, Intel was behind the industry in its use of tools so the leaders of the 386
realized that more automation would be necessary to build a complex chip like the 386 on schedule.
By making a large investment in automated tools, the 386 team completed the design ahead of schedule.
Along with proprietary CAD tools, the team made heavy use of standard Unix tools such as <code>sed</code>, <code>awk</code>, <code>grep</code>, and <code>make</code> to manage the various design databases.</p>
<p>The 386 posed new design challenges compared to the previous 286 processor.
The 386 was much more complex, with twice the transistors.
But the 386 also used fundamentally different circuitry.
While the 286 and earlier processors were built from NMOS transistors, the 386 moved to
CMOS (the technology still used today). Intel's CMOS process was called CHMOS-III
(complementary high-performance metal-oxide-silicon) and had a feature size of 1.5 µm.
CHMOS-III was based on Intel's HMOS-III process (used for the 286), but extended to
CMOS. Moreover, the CHMOS process provided two layers of metal instead of one, changing
how signals were routed on the chip and requiring new design techniques.</p>
<p>The diagram below shows a cross-section through a CHMOS-III circuit, with an NMOS
transistor on the left and a PMOS transistor on the right.
Note the jagged three-dimensional topography that is formed as layers cross each other
(unlike modern polished wafers).
This resulted in the
"<a href="https://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/access/text/2015/06/102702019-05-01-acc.pdf#page=21">forbidden gap</a>" problem that caused difficulty for the 386 team.
Specifically second-layer metal (M2) could be close to the first-layer metal (M1) or it could be far apart,
but an in-between distance would cause problems: the forbidden gap.
If the metal layer crossed in the "forbidden gap", the metal could crack and whiskers of metal
would touch, causing the chip to fail.
These problems reduced the yield of the 386.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/process-cross-section.jpg"><img alt="A cross-section of circuitry formed with the CHMOS-III process. From A double layer metal CHMOS III technology." height="203" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/process-cross-section-w500.jpg" title="A cross-section of circuitry formed with the CHMOS-III process. From A double layer metal CHMOS III technology." width="500"></a></p>
<!-- -->

<p>The design of the 386 proceeded both top-down, starting with the architecture definition,
and bottom-up, designing standard cells and other basic circuits at the transistor level.
The processor's microcode, the software that controlled the chip, was a fundamental component.
It was designed with two CAD tools: an assembler and microcode rule checker.
The high-level design of the chip (register-level RTL)
was created and refined until clock-by-clock and phase-by-phase timing were represented.
The RTL was programmed in <a href="http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/xidak/mainsail_v12/Mainsail_Tutorial_Volume_1_Mar89.pdf">MAINSAIL</a>, a portable Algol-like language based
on SAIL (Stanford Artificial Intelligence Language).
Intel used a proprietary simulator called Microsim to simulate the RTL, stating that
full-chip RTL simulation was "the single most important simulation model of the 80386".</p>
<p>The next step was to convert this high-level design into a detailed logic design, specifying
the gates and other circuitry
using Eden, a proprietary schematics-capture system.
Simulating the logic design required
a dedicated IBM 3083 mainframe that compared it against the
RTL simulations.
Next, the circuit design phase created the transistor-level design.
The chip layout was performed on <a href="https://www.shapr3d.com/history-of-cad/applicon">Applicon</a> and Eden graphics systems.
The layout started with critical blocks such as the ALU and barrel shifter. 
To meet the performance requirements, the TLB (translation lookaside
buffer) for the paging mechanism required a creative design, as did the binary adders.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/standard-cell-colored.jpg"><img alt="Examples of standard cells used in the 386. From &quot;Automatic Place and Route Used on the 80386&quot; by Joseph Krauskopf and Pat Gelsinger. I have added color." height="205" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/standard-cell-colored-w700.jpg" title="Examples of standard cells used in the 386. From &quot;Automatic Place and Route Used on the 80386&quot; by Joseph Krauskopf and Pat Gelsinger. I have added color." width="700"></a></p><p>Examples of standard cells used in the 386. From "Automatic Place and Route Used on the 80386" by Joseph Krauskopf and Pat Gelsinger, Intel Technology Journal spring 1986. I have added color.</p>
<p>The "random" (unstructured) logic was implemented with standard cells, rather than the
transistor-by-transistor design of earlier processors.
The idea of standard cells is to have fixed blocks of circuitry (above) for logic gates, flip-flops,
and other basic functions.<span id="fnref:standard-cell-library"><a href="#fn:standard-cell-library">24</a></span>
These cells are arranged in rows by software to implement the specified logic description.
The space between the rows is used as a wiring channel for connections between the cells.
The disadvantage of a standard cell layout is that it generally takes up more space than
an optimized hand-drawn layout, but it is much faster to create and easier to modify.</p>
<p>These standard cells are visible in the die as regular rows of circuitry.
Intel used the <a href="https://ee.sharif.edu/~asic/References/Physical%20Design%20Papers/timberwolf-P2.pdf">TimberWolf</a> automatic placement and routing package, which used simulated annealing to
optimize the placement of cells.
TimberWolf was built by a Berkeley <a href="http://www.aycinena.com/index2/index3/archive/uw%20-%20sechen.html">grad student</a>; one 386 engineer said,
"If management had known that we were using a tool by some grad
student as the key part of the methodology, they would never have let us use it. "
Automated layout was a new thing at Intel; using it improved the schedule, but 
the lower density raised the risk that the chip would be too large.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/standard-cells.jpg"><img alt="Standard cells in the 386. Each row consists of numerous standard cells packed together. Each cell is a simple circuit such as a logic gate or flip flop. The wide wiring channels between the rows hold the wiring that connects the cells. This block of circuitry is in the bottom center of the chip." height="308" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/standard-cells-w350.jpg" title="Standard cells in the 386. Each row consists of numerous standard cells packed together. Each cell is a simple circuit such as a logic gate or flip flop. The wide wiring channels between the rows hold the wiring that connects the cells. This block of circuitry is in the bottom center of the chip." width="350"></a></p><p>Standard cells in the 386. Each row consists of numerous standard cells packed together. Each cell is a simple circuit such as a logic gate or flip flop. The wide wiring channels between the rows hold the wiring that connects the cells. This block of circuitry is in the bottom center of the chip.</p>
<p>The data path consists of the registers, ALU (Arithmetic Logic Unit), barrel shifter,
and multiply/divide unit that process the 32-bit data.
Because the data path is critical to the performance of the system,
it was laid out by hand using a CALMA system.
The designers could optimize the layout, taking advantage of regularities in the circuitry,
optimizing the shape and size of each transistor and fitting them together like puzzle pieces.
The data path is visible on the left side of the die, forming orderly 32-bit-wide rectangles
in contrast to the tangles of logic next to it.</p>
<p>Once the transistor-level layout was complete,
Intel's Hierarchical Connectivity Verification System checked that the final layout matched
the schematics and adhered to the process design rules.
The 386 set an Intel speed record, taking just 11 days from completing the layout to "tapeout",
when the chip data is sent on magnetic tape to the mask fabrication company.
(The tapeout team was led by Pat Gelsinger, who later became CEO of Intel.)
After the glass masks were created using
an electron-beam process, Intel's "Fab 3" in Livermore (the first to wear the <a href="https://www.elivermore.com/photos/intel_fab3.htm">bunnysuits</a>) produced the 386 silicon wafers.</p>
<p>Chip designers like to claim that their chip worked the first time, but that was not
the case for the 386.  <!-- p19 -->
When the team received the first silicon for the 386, they ran a trivial do-nothing test
program, "NoOp, NoOp, Halt", and it failed.
Fortunately, they found a small fix to a PLA (Programmable Logic Array). Rather than create new masks, they were able to
patch the existing mask with ion milling and get new wafers quickly. <!-- p20 -->
These wafers worked well enough that they could start the long cycles of debugging and fixing.</p>
<p>Once the processor was released, the problems weren't over.<span id="fnref:bugs"><a href="#fn:bugs">25</a></span>
Some early 386 processors had a <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.arch/c/qm7FVR_YV4A/m/VKR47yLoUdEJ">32-bit multiply problem</a>, where some arguments would
unpredictably produce the wrong results under particular temperature/voltage/frequency conditions.
(This is unrelated to the famous <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pentium_FDIV_bug">Pentium FDIV bug</a> that cost Intel $475 million.)
The root cause was a layout problem, not a logic problem; they didn't allow enough margin to
handle the worst case data in combination with manufacturing process and environment factors.
This tricky problem didn't show up in simulation or chip verification, but was only found in
stress testing.
Intel sold the faulty processors, but marked them as only valid for 16-bit software, while marking the
good processors with a double sigma, as seen below.<span id="fnref:xbts"><a href="#fn:xbts">26</a></span>
This led to embarrassing headlines such as <a href="https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_mDsEAAAAMBAJ/page/n5/mode/1up?view=theater">Some 386 Systems Won't Run 32-Bit Software, Intel Says</a>.
The multiply bug also caused a shortage of 386 chips in
<a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=u5dYmhF7jc4C&amp;lpg=PA96&amp;pg=PA96#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">1987</a>
and <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=Av0xuNrEJakC&amp;lpg=RA6-PT4&amp;pg=RA6-PT4#v=onepage&amp;q&amp;f=false">1988</a> as Intel redesigned the chip to fix the bug.
Overall, the 386 issues probably weren't any worse than other processors and the problems were soon
forgotten.</p>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/steppings.jpg"><img alt="Bad and good versions of the 386. Note the labels on the bottom line. Photos (L), (R) by Thomas Nguyen, (CC BY-SA 4.0)." height="257" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/steppings-w500.jpg" title="Bad and good versions of the 386. Note the labels on the bottom line. Photos (L), (R) by Thomas Nguyen, (CC BY-SA 4.0)." width="500"></a></p><p>Bad and good versions of the 386. Note the labels on the bottom line. Photos (<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Intel_A80386-16_16_bit_SW_Only.jpg">L</a>), (<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Intel_A80386-16_%CE%A3%CE%A3.jpg">R</a>) by Thomas Nguyen, (<a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/deed.en">CC BY-SA 4.0</a>).</p>
<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p><a href="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/wall.jpg"><img alt="A 17-foot tall plot of the 386. The datapath is on the left and the microcode is in the lower right. It is unclear if this is engineering work or an exhibit at MOMA. Image spliced together from the 1985 annual report." height="621" src="https://static.righto.com/images/386-versions/wall-w600.jpg" title="A 17-foot tall plot of the 386. The datapath is on the left and the microcode is in the lower right. It is unclear if this is engineering work or an exhibit at MOMA. Image spliced together from the 1985 annual report." width="600"></a></p><p>A 17-foot tall plot of the 386. The datapath is on the left and the microcode is in the lower right. It is unclear if this is engineering work or an exhibit at MOMA. Image spliced together from the <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/dam/doc/report/history-1985-annual-report.pdf">1985 annual report</a>.</p>
<p>The 386 processor was a key turning point for Intel.
Intel's previous processors sold very well, but this was largely due to heavy marketing
("<a href="https://www.computerhistory.org/collections/catalog/102746836">Operation Crush</a>") and the
good fortune to be selected for the IBM PC.
Intel was technologically behind the competition, especially Motorola.
Motorola had introduced the 68000 processor in 1979, starting a powerful line of
(more-or-less) 32-bit processors.
Intel, on the other hand, lagged with the "brain-damaged" 16-bit 286 processor in 1982.
Intel was also slow with the transition to CMOS; Motorola had moved to CMOS in 1984 with the 68020.</p>
<p>The 386 provided the necessary technological boost for Intel, moving to a 32-bit architecture,
transitioning to CMOS, and fixing the 286's memory model and multitasking limitations, while
maintaining compatibility with the earlier x86 processors.
The overwhelming success of the 386 solidified the dominance of the x86 and Intel, and put
other processor manufacturers on the defensive.
Compaq used the 386 to take over PC architecture leadership from IBM, leading to the success of Compaq, Dell, and other
companies, while IBM eventually departed the PC market entirely.
Thus, the 386 had an oversized effect on the computer industry, shaping the winners and losers for decades.</p>
<!--
Moreover, as a result of the 386, IBM lost control of the IBM PC architecture to Compaq.
-->

<p>I plan to write more about the 386, so 
follow me on Twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/kenshirriff">@kenshirriff</a> or <a href="http://www.righto.com/feeds/posts/default">RSS</a> for updates.
I'm also on Mastodon occasionally as <a href="https://oldbytes.space/@kenshirriff">@<span data-cfemail="29424c475a41405b5b404f4f6946454d4b505d4c5a075a59484a4c">[email&nbsp;protected]</span></a>.
Acknowledgements: The die photos are courtesy of Antoine Bercovici; you should follow him on Twitter as <a href="https://twitter.com/Siliconinsid">@Siliconinsid</a>.<span id="fnref:s-specs"><a href="#fn:s-specs">27</a></span>
Thanks to Pat Gelsinger and Roxanne Koester for providing helpful papers.</p>
<h2>Notes and references</h2>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mindblowing dissertations (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ideophone.org/mindblowing-dissertations/</link>
            <guid>37881604</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 14 Oct 2023 16:07:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ideophone.org/mindblowing-dissertations/">https://ideophone.org/mindblowing-dissertations/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37881604">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>