<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 20:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Marble Fountain (219 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://willmorrison.net/posts/marble-fountain/</link>
            <guid>45866697</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 16:26:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://willmorrison.net/posts/marble-fountain/">https://willmorrison.net/posts/marble-fountain/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45866697">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentcolor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><circle cx="12" cy="12" r="10"></circle><polyline points="12 6 12 12 16 14"></polyline></svg>5 minutes</p><article><div><p>I really enjoy procedural generation, especially systems designed to work with hardware outputs. After starting work at Formlabs in September of 2023 and gaining access to much nicer printers than I was used to, I started wanting to tackle some large algorithmic structure projects. Complexity is free in 3d printing, the limit of design geometry is mostly how much time you’re willing to spend in CAD. I wanted to print the most complicated art piece I could think of. Marble Fountain is what I came up with.</p><p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ULpNiZU2tpg" allowfullscreen="" title="YouTube Video"></iframe></p><h2 id="tracks">Tracks</h2><p>My initial system came together quickly. Randomly placing spaced out points, drawing a spline through them, and setting a constant slope just works. My first draft was just subtracting a tube from the solid support structure which worked but was super limited. I wanted to add more parts and so I started working on a path solver. I wanted to fit as much motion into the volume of the printer as possible. This turned out to be extremely challenging.</p><p>The solver starts by making a random series of line segments connecting the top and bottom of the lift. There are several different algorithms to generate this guess, as the initial conditional has a noticeable impact on the shape of the structure for lower path counts. It’s interesting to play with different variants of the starting conditions and see how they change during generation.</p><p>A series of functions update the positions over time to “pull” the points into a followable path.
The points making up each path:</p><ul><li>Stay in the bounding box</li><li>Evenly space themselves out</li><li>Pull towards a fixed height to enforce a constant slope</li><li>Enforce min and max turning radius of the path</li><li>Repel away from other tracks</li><li>Repel away from distant sections of our own track</li><li>Smooth out changes in slope to prevent jumps</li><li>Prevent slope from ever increasing</li></ul><p>Velocity is a much harder problem than I anticipated. The tracks break a lot of the obvious assumptions if you act like the marble is a point mass, as changing the bank of the track moves the axis of rotation and can burn off rotational inertia to friction. Long straight sections would build up too much speed and bearings fly off on the turns, but balls taking sharp turns at slow speed will lose too much momentum and stop. I settled on setting a minimum turn radius for the track and banking much more aggressively than is technically necessary for any given speed, so it constantly snakes back and forth to burn off speed.</p><p>One of the most elegant designs of the whole structure is how the lift acts like a ball screw. The the screw is constrained by the balls on all sides which allows it to run with no bearing at the top. This also leads to a failure mode where if the screw ever only has balls on one side it will immediately start wobbling badly enough that all the balls currently rolling will fall off the tracks.</p><h2 id="supports">Supports</h2><p>The support generation was surprisingly simple. Iterating from the top down and treating the support pillars as a particle system is quite robust. I spent more time tweaking the geometry for aesthetics than I did for actual structure and collision issues, although I did heavily lean on the overhang tolerance of the printer.</p><p>Each support:</p><ul><li>Pulls towards other supports, weighted by distance and similarity in size</li><li>Repels away from other supports</li><li>Pulls to stay in the bounding box</li><li>Pulls towards a fixed radius from the center of the structure</li></ul><p>Supports also have inertia, which is where the arcs in the structure of the support columns come from.</p><h2 id="looking-forward">Looking forward</h2><p>The final models take around 5-20 minutes to export. There’s a ton I could do to optimize the models, but at this point the geometry is simply beyond the scope of OpenSCAD. If I was rewriting this I would probably use a different tool more optimized for this type of organic geometry, likely an SDF library. I have vague ambitions to do a big rewrite eventually but figured sharing <a href="https://github.com/Will-Morr/MarbleFountain" target="_blank">janky code</a>
is better than none. I started this just planning for the janky splines as a weekend project but it has gotten thoroughly out of hand.</p><p>I have a ton of other ideas to play with if I do that big rewrite. There is no realistic velocity estimation at any point in the whole system right now, just a pile of heuristics. I was originally trying to not overcomplicate but building a proper acceleration model by measuring velocity with a camera would have almost definitely saved time overall. Trying to maintain a fixed slope makes collision prevention much harder but is required to keep speed within bounds. At this point I’m also just curious about the response curve, there’s a knee somewhere where the surfaces start to slip that I want to track down.</p><h2 id="looking-back">Looking back</h2><p>This was the most work I have ever put into a hobby project. I started in February 2024 and worked on it on and off until September. I applied to show it in a gallery (shoutout to <a href="https://www.newalliancegallery.com/" target="_blank">New Alliance Gallery</a>
in Somerville) with two months of warning, which wound up leading to a large crunch trying to make the system reliable enough to show in person in the weeks before the show. I was able to get it working consistently, although it did lose 2-3 balls an hour and could only run for a few hours without the motor overheating. I got pretty burned out and dropped the project, which is why I shelved it for a full year before sharing anything.</p><p>Finally, a huge thanks to my friend Alex who listened to me ramble about marbles for several months every day while walking home from work, gave a ton of helpful input, and lived with the dozens of ball bearings scattered across our apartment.</p><figure><img src="https://willmorrison.net/img/MarbleFountain/gallery.jpg" alt="Marble Fountain installed in New Alliance Gallery"></figure><p><a href="https://github.com/Will-Morr/MarbleFountain" target="_blank">GitHub Repo</a></p></div></article><hr><div><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentcolor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M20.59 13.41l-7.17 7.17a2 2 0 01-2.83.0L2 12V2h10l8.59 8.59a2 2 0 010 2.82z"></path><line x1="7" y1="7" x2="7" y2="7"></line></svg><span><a href="https://willmorrison.net/tags/proceduralgeneration/">ProceduralGeneration</a></span>
<span><a href="https://willmorrison.net/tags/art/">Art</a></span>
<span><a href="https://willmorrison.net/tags/3d-printed/">3D Printed</a></span>
<span><a href="https://willmorrison.net/tags/python/">Python</a></span></p><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentcolor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M14 2H6A2 2 0 004 4v16a2 2 0 002 2h12a2 2 0 002-2V8z"></path><polyline points="14 2 14 8 20 8"></polyline><line x1="16" y1="13" x2="8" y2="13"></line><line x1="16" y1="17" x2="8" y2="17"></line><polyline points="10 9 9 9 8 9"></polyline></svg>983 Words</p><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentcolor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><rect x="3" y="4" width="18" height="18" rx="2" ry="2"></rect><line x1="16" y1="2" x2="16" y2="6"></line><line x1="8" y1="2" x2="8" y2="6"></line><line x1="3" y1="10" x2="21" y2="10"></line></svg>2025-11-01 00:00
(Last updated: 2025-11-03 01:40)</p><p><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentcolor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><circle cx="12" cy="12" r="4"></circle><line x1="1.05" y1="12" x2="7" y2="12"></line><line x1="17.01" y1="12" x2="22.96" y2="12"></line></svg><a href="https://willmorrison.net/posts/marble-fountain/789ee9a85a58b45e99dcf05c1993007ea0a6fda3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">789ee9a</a>
@ 2025-11-03</p></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI isn't replacing jobs. AI spending is (410 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fastcompany.com/91435192/chatgpt-llm-openai-jobs-amazon</link>
            <guid>45866243</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:30:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91435192/chatgpt-llm-openai-jobs-amazon">https://www.fastcompany.com/91435192/chatgpt-llm-openai-jobs-amazon</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45866243">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.fastcompany.com/91435192/chatgpt-llm-openai-jobs-amazon: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Manuscripts of Edsger W. Dijkstra (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/</link>
            <guid>45866224</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:27:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/">https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45866224">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div height="3739" colspan="2" xpos="123">
								<table>
									<tbody><tr>
										<td><img src="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/EWDwww.jpg" alt="Photo of Edsger W. Dijkstra" height="306" width="237"><span size="-3">(<i>photo</i> ©2002 <i>Hamilton Richards</i>)</span></td>
										<td></td>
										<td><br>
											Edsger Wybe Dijkstra was one of the most influential members of computing science’s founding generation. Among the domains in which his scientific contributions are fundamental are
											<ul>
												<li type="disc">algorithm design
												</li><li type="disc">programming languages
												</li><li type="disc">program design
												</li><li type="disc">operating systems
												</li><li type="disc">distributed processing
												</li><li type="disc">formal specification and verification
												</li><li type="disc">design of mathematical arguments
											</li></ul>
											<p>In addition, Dijkstra was intensely interested in teaching, and in the relationships between academic computing science and the software industry.</p>
											<p>During his forty-plus years as a computing scientist, which included positions in both academia and industry, Dijkstra’s contributions brought him many prizes and awards, including computing science’s highest honor, the ACM Turing Award.</p>
										</td>
									</tr>
								</tbody></table>
								<hr>
								<h2>The Manuscripts</h2>
								<p>Like most of us, Dijkstra always believed it a scientist’s duty to maintain a lively correspondence with his scientific colleagues. To a greater extent than most of us, he put that conviction into practice. For over four decades, he mailed copies of his consecutively numbered technical notes, trip reports, insightful observations, and pungent commentaries, known collectively as “EWDs”, to several dozen recipients in academia and industry. Thanks to the ubiquity of the photocopier and the wide interest in Dijkstra’s writings, the informal circulation of many of the EWDs eventually reached into the thousands.</p>
								<p>Although most of Dijkstra’s publications began life as EWD manuscripts, the great majority of his manuscripts remain unpublished. They have been inaccessible to many potential readers, and those who have received copies have been unable to cite them in their own work. To alleviate both of these problems, the department has collected over a thousand of the manuscripts in this permanent web site, in the form of PDF bitmap documents (to read them, you’ll need a copy of <a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/acrobat/readstep.html">Acrobat Reader</a>). We hope you will find it convenient, useful, inspiring, and enjoyable.</p>
								<p>The original manuscripts, along with diaries, correspondence, photographs, and other papers, are housed at <a href="http://www.lib.utexas.edu/taro/utcah/00378/cah-00378.html#a0">The Center for American History</a> of The University of Texas at Austin.</p>
								<h3>Indexes</h3>
								<p>Each manuscript file is accessible through either of two indexes:</p>
								<p><b><span size="+1">0. <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/indexBibTeX.html">BibTeX</a> index. </span></b>Each entry includes all the available bibliographic data.</p>
								<p><b><span size="+1">1. Ad-hoc indexes. </span></b>These contain titles only, but are faster if you know what you’re looking for.</p>
								<blockquote>
									<p><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/indexChron.html"><b>EWD-numbered documents</b></a><b> </b>(This index gives an approximate correspondence between manuscripts’ EWD numbers and the year in which they appeared.)</p>
									<p><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/indexMCreps.html"><b>Technical reports</b></a> from the Mathematical Centre (now CWI: Centrum voor Wiskunde en Informatica)</p>
									<p><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/PhDthesis/PhDthesis.PDF" target="_blank"><b>PhD thesis</b></a><b> (5.3 MB)</b></p>
									<p><a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/indexOtherDocs.html"><b>Other documents</b></a></p>
								</blockquote>
								<p>You can find a table relating EWD numbers to publication years <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/indexChron.html">here</a>.</p>
								<p>Many of the privately circulated manuscripts collected here were subsequently published; their <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/copyrights.html">copyrights</a> are held by their respective publishers.</p>
								<h3>Transcripts and translations</h3>
								<p>A growing number of the PDF bitmap documents have been <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/transcriptions/transcriptions.html">transcribed</a> to make them searchable and accessible to visitors who are visually impaired.</p>
								<p>A few of the manuscripts written in Dutch have been <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/translations/translations.html">translated</a> into English, and one —EWD1036— has been translated into <a title="Spanish translation of EWD 1036" href="http://www.smaldone.com.ar/documentos/ewd/sobre_la_crueldad.html">Spanish</a>. EWD28  has been translated from English into <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/translations/EWD28%20Russian.html">Russian</a>.</p>
								<p>For these transcriptions and translations we are grateful to over sixty <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/transcriptions/transcribers.html">contributors</a>. <span color="#ff0033"><b>Volunteers</b></span> willing to transcribe manuscripts are always <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/transcriptions/invitation.html">welcome</a> (<b>Note</b>: doing EWDs justice in translation has turned out to be too difficult, so we are no longer soliciting translations).</p>
								<p><b>Proofreading</b> Each transcription gets a cursory scan as it’s prepared for uploading, but since a web page can always be updated, I don’t strive for (unattainable) perfection before installing it. On the web, proofreading is a game that can be played by every reader; if you spot an error, please 
									
								</p>
								
								<h3>Links between EWDs</h3>
								<p>A compilation of <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/AnnotationsEtc/Michaelis.html" target="_blank">cross-references</a> has been contributed by Diethard Michaelis. As its author notes, the collection is incomplete, and all readers are invited to add to it.</p>
								<p>Dijkstra often returned to topics about which he had already written, when he had something new to say or even just a better way of saying it. When Dijkstra himself didn’t provide the backward references, we indicate the relationship by "see also" links in the index, leaving the judgment of the extent to which the earlier EWD is superseded by the later one to the reader. Any reader who notices such a relationship is invited to 
									
								</p>
								
								
								<h3>Summaries</h3>
								<p>We have begun adding <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/Summaries/Summaries.html">summaries</a> of the EWDs. This innovation was suggested by Günter Rote, who contributed the first dozen summaries. Additional contributions of summaries—especially summaries in English of EWDs in Dutch—are most welcome.</p>
								<hr>
								<h3>Copyrights</h3>
								<p>Copyrights in most EWDs  are  held by his children, one of whom —



                                
—  handles  requests for permission to publish reproductions. The exceptions are documents that were published, and whose copyrights are held by their publishers; those documents are listed <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/copyrightsDetail.html" title="Copyrights">here</a>, and each one is provided with a cover page identifying the copyright holder.</p>
								<p>Because the original manuscripts are in possession of the Briscoe Center for American History at The University of Texas, <a href="http://www.cah.utexas.edu/research/permission_publish.php" title="BCAH permission policies">the Center’s policies</a> are also applicable.</p>
								<hr>
								<h2>Video and audio</h2>
								<p>In addition to the manuscripts, you may enjoy some <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/video-audio/video-audio.html">recordings</a> of Dijkstra lectures and interviews.</p>
								<hr>
								<h2>About Dijkstra and his work</h2>
								<p>An <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/misc/vanVlissingenInterview.html">interview</a> with Dijkstra (Spanish translation <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/misc/vanVlissingenEntrevista.html">here</a>) was conducted in 1985 by Rogier F. van Vlissingen, who has also written a <a href="http://digitalundivide.blogspot.com/2005/12/ewd-personal-reflection.html">personal reflection</a> on “Dijkstra’s sense of what computer science and programming are and what they aren’t.”</p>
								<p>Another interview was conducted by Philip L. Frana in August 2001. A <a title="link to Dijkstra oral-history interview" href="https://hdl.handle.net/11299/107247">transcript</a> is available in the on-line collection of the Charles Babbage Institute.</p>
								<p>To mark the occasion of Dijkstra’s retirement in November 1999 from the Schlumberger Centennial Chair in Computer Sciences, which he had occupied since 1984, and to celebrate his forty-plus years of seminal contributions to computing science, the Department of Computer Sciences organized a symposium, <i>In Pursuit of Simplicity</i>, which took place on his birthday in May 2000. The symposium’s <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/symposiumProgram.pdf">program</a> (10 MB) contains an outline of Dijkstra’s career, as well as a collection of quotes culled from his writings, from his blackboard, and from what others have said about him. Banquet speeches by David Gries, Fred Schneider, Krzysztof Apt, W.M. Turski, and H. Richards were recorded on a <a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/videos/EWD6.mpg" target="_blank">video</a>.</p>
								<p>Dijkstra’s death in August 2002 was marked by many <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/obituaries/obits.html">obituaries</a> and memorials, including the Computer Sciences department’s <a href="http://www.cs.utexas.edu/users/EWD/memorial/" target="_blank">memorial celebration.</a></p>
								<p>A <a title="Maarten van Emden: I remember Edsger Dijkstra" href="http://vanemden.wordpress.com/2008/05/06/i-remember-edsger-dijkstra-1930-2002/">remembrance</a> of Dijkstra was posted in May 2008 by Maarten van Emden (thanks to Tristram Brelstaff for noting it).</p>
								<p>In 2021 Krzysztof R. Apt and Tony Hoare edited a 
									<a name="commemoration" href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/commemoration/EWD-commemoration-2021.pdf">commemoration of Edsger Dijkstra</a>
									written by more than twenty computer scientists who knew him as a colleague, teacher, and friend.</p>
								<p>A <a title="E.G.Daylight's Dijkstra blog" href="http://www.dijkstrascry.com/">blog</a> devoted to Dijkstra’s works and thoughts has been created, and is being maintained, by the historian of computing Edgar G. Daylight. An <a title="article: Dijkstra's Rallying Cry for Generalization: the Advent of the Recursive Procedure, late 1950s - early 1960s" href="http://www.dijkstrascry.com/node/4">article</a> by Daylight, “Dijkstra’s Rallying Cry for Generalization: the Advent of the Recursive Procedure, late 1950s - early 1960s,” appeared in <i>The Computer Journal</i>, March 2011.</p>
								<p>In his blog A Programmer’s Place, Maarten van Emden has an <a title="link to van Emden's blog entry" href="http://vanemden.wordpress.com/2011/01/15/another-scoop-by-dijkstra/#more-366">entry entitled “Another scoop by Dijkstra?”.</a> The entry describes Dijkstra’s “remarkable insight [in “<a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/ewd02xx/EWD249.PDF">Notes on Structured Programming” (EWD 249)</a>] that resolves the stand-off between the Sieve of Eratosthenes (efficient in terms of time, but not memory) and the method of Trial Division (efficient in terms of memory, but not time)” by applying the Assembly-line Principle.</p>
								<p>The <a href="http://www.podc.org/dijkstra/">Edsger W. Dijkstra Prize in Distributed Computing</a> honors Dijkstra’s “foundational work on concurrency primitives (such as the semaphore), concurrency problems (such as mutual exclusion and deadlock), reasoning about concurrent systems, and self-stabilization [, which] comprises one of the most important supports upon which the field of distributed computing is built.” </p>
								<hr>
								<h2><b>The Dijkstra Memorial Lectures</b></h2>
								<p>A <a title="link to the index page of the Dijkstra Memorial Lectures" href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/DijkstraMemorialLectures/lectureIndex.html">series of annual lectures</a> in memory of Dijkstra commenced at The University of Texas in October 2010.</p>
								<hr>
								<h2>About this site</h2>
								<p>Recent significant changes in the site are listed <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/recentChanges.html">here</a>; the most recent change was posted on 30 March 2021.</p>
								<p>The folks who contributed most significantly to the site’s creation are acknowledged <a href="https://www.cs.utexas.edu/~EWD/acknowledgments.html">here</a>.</p>
								<p>Comments and suggestions about the site are always welcome; please email them to the<br>
									
								</p>
								
								<hr>
								<h2>Related site</h2>
								<p>If you find this site interesting, you may also be interested in another site:</p>
								<blockquote>
									<p><a href="http://www.mathmeth.com/" target="_blank">Discipline in Thought</a> which is a website dedicated to disciplined thinking, calculational mathematics, and mathematical methodology. The members of this site are markedly influenced by the works of EWD, and the material shared through the website continues in the traditions set by EWD (among others).</p>
								</blockquote>
								<hr>
								
								<p><i><span size="-1">Revised <csobj format="MedDate" h="16" region="15" t="DateTime" w="95">
								  <!-- #BeginDate format:En2 -->2020-01-12<!-- #EndDate -->
								</csobj>
								</span></i></p>
							</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Samsung Family Hub fridges will start showing adds to "Elevate" Home Ecosystem (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.samsung.com/us/samsung-family-hub-2025-update-elevates-smart-home-ecosystem/</link>
            <guid>45866165</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 15:18:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.samsung.com/us/samsung-family-hub-2025-update-elevates-smart-home-ecosystem/">https://news.samsung.com/us/samsung-family-hub-2025-update-elevates-smart-home-ecosystem/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45866165">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://news.samsung.com/us/samsung-family-hub-2025-update-elevates-smart-home-ecosystem/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Montana Becomes First State to Enshrine 'Right to Compute' into Law (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://montananewsroom.com/montana-becomes-first-state-to-enshrine-right-to-compute-into-law/</link>
            <guid>45865289</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 13:03:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://montananewsroom.com/montana-becomes-first-state-to-enshrine-right-to-compute-into-law/">https://montananewsroom.com/montana-becomes-first-state-to-enshrine-right-to-compute-into-law/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45865289">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-td-block-uid="tdi_61">
<p>Montana has made history as the first state in the U.S. to legally protect its citizens’ right to access and use computational tools and artificial intelligence technologies. Governor Greg Gianforte signed Senate Bill 212, officially known as the Montana Right to Compute Act (MRTCA), into law.</p>
<p>The groundbreaking legislation affirms Montanans’ fundamental right to own and operate computational resources — including hardware, software, and AI tools — under the state’s constitutional protections for property and free expression. Supporters of the bill say it represents a major step in securing digital freedoms in an increasingly AI-driven world.</p>
<p>“Montana is once again leading the way in defending individual liberty,” said Senator Daniel Zolnikov, the bill’s sponsor and a longtime advocate for digital privacy. “With the Right to Compute Act, we are ensuring that every Montanan can access and control the tools of the future.”</p>
<p>While the law allows state regulation of computation in the interest of public health and safety, it sets a high bar: any restrictions must be <em>demonstrably necessary</em> and <em>narrowly tailored</em> to serve a compelling interest. Legal experts note that this is one of the most protective standards available under Montana law.</p>
<p>The act also includes provisions for AI-controlled critical infrastructure, requiring both a “shutdown mechanism” to allow human control and annual safety reviews — a move aimed at balancing innovation with public safety concerns.</p>
<p>The bill has drawn praise from privacy advocates and tech policy groups. Tanner Avery, Policy Director at the free-market think tank Frontier Institute, called the law a “flag in the ground” for digital rights, adding: “Montana has made clear it will treat any attempt to infringe on fundamental digital freedoms with the utmost scrutiny.”</p>
<p>The MRTCA stands in stark contrast to recent regulatory efforts in other states, such as California, Virginia, and New York, where proposals to rein in AI technologies have either failed or been heavily revised. Montana’s approach leans toward empowering individual users rather than restricting access.</p>
<p>The law has already inspired similar efforts in New Hampshire, where lawmakers are pushing a constitutional amendment guaranteeing access to computation. Rep. Keith Ammon, the state’s Majority Floor Leader, praised Montana’s leadership: “This is the kind of bold move that sets the tone for the rest of the country.”</p>
<p>Nationally, the Right to Compute movement is gaining traction. Spearheaded by the grassroots group RightToCompute.ai, the campaign argues that computation — like speech and property — is a fundamental human right. “A computer is an extension of the human capacity to think,” the organization states.</p>
<p>The movement is supported by Haltia.AI, a Dubai-based AI startup, and the ASIMOV Protocol, a blockchain consortium advocating for decentralized AI infrastructure. Talal Thabet, Co-Founder of both groups, praised Montana’s law as “a monumental step forward in ensuring individuals retain control of their own data and digital tools.”</p>
<p>As debates over AI governance and digital rights continue to evolve, Montana’s bold new law could serve as a blueprint for other states seeking to safeguard freedom in the digital era.</p>
<p><a href="https://digitalnewsupdates.com/montana-becomes-first-state-to-enshrine-right-to-compute-into-law/">By: DNU staff</a></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reviving Classic Unix Games: A 20-Year Journey Through Software Archaeology (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vejeta.com/reviving-classic-unix-games-a-20-year-journey-through-software-archaeology/</link>
            <guid>45865159</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 12:44:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vejeta.com/reviving-classic-unix-games-a-20-year-journey-through-software-archaeology/">https://vejeta.com/reviving-classic-unix-games-a-20-year-journey-through-software-archaeology/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45865159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><br>How I spent two decades tracking down the creators of a 1987 USENET game and learned modern packaging tools in the process.<br></p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-the-discovery-a-digital-time-capsule-from-1987"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-the-discovery-a-digital-time-capsule-from-1987"></a>The Discovery: A Digital Time Capsule from 1987</h2>



<p>Picture this: October 26, 1987. The Berlin Wall still stands, the World Wide Web is just text, and software is distributed through USENET newsgroups in text files split across multiple posts. On that day, Edward Barlow posted something special to <code>comp.sources.games</code>:</p>



<p><strong>“conquest – middle earth multi-player game, Part01/05”</strong></p>



<p>That’s how Ed Barlow <a href="http://https//groups.google.com/g/comp.sources.games/c/188dE9OtKhg/m/6vJvv6V4SzIJ">announced it</a> at the time, before quickly changed the name to Conquer.</p>



<p>This was <strong>Conquer</strong> – a sophisticated multi-player strategy game that would influence countless others. Players controlled nations in Middle Earth, managing resources, armies, magic systems, and diplomatic relations. What made it remarkable wasn’t just the gameplay, but how it was built and distributed in an era when “open source” wasn’t even a term yet.</p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-0-university-days-"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-chapter-0-university-days-"></a>Chapter 0: University Days.<p><img decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/edificiorojo.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/edificiorojo.jpg 700w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/edificiorojo-300x300.jpg 300w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/edificiorojo-150x150.jpg 150w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/edificiorojo-120x120.jpg 120w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"></p></h2>



<p>It was during these days, in the middle of the 90s, that my fellow students and I spent hours experimenting with terminals in the <a href="http://https//www.informatica.us.es/index.php/historia/la-facultad">Computer Unix Labs</a>, USENET, links, news, msgs, and of course: conquer. That game was a gem that required to be the leader of a country, and with a map representing as characters each player could control their elven kingdom, orcish empire, or human armies to fight each other while controlling all the details of the economy.</p>



<p>But by 2006, this piece of computing history was trapped in legal limbo.</p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-1-the-quest-begins-2006-"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-chapter-1-the-quest-begins-2006-"></a>Chapter 1: The Quest Begins (2006)</h2>



<p>As a university student in Spain in the early ’90s, I’d encountered Conquer in the Unix labs. Fast forward to 2006, and I realized this pioneering game was at risk of being lost forever. The source code existed, scattered across ancient USENET archives, but its licensing was unclear – typical of the “post it and see what happens” era of early internet software distribution.</p>



<p>I started what I thought would be a simple project: get permission from the original authors to <a href="http://https//lists.debian.org/debian-legal/2006/10/msg00063.html">relicense the code under GPL</a> so it could be properly preserved and packaged for modern Linux distributions.</p>



<p><strong>Simple, right?</strong></p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-2-digital-detective-work"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-chapter-2-digital-detective-work"></a>Chapter 2: Digital Detective Work</h2>



<p>Finding Edward Barlow and Adam Bryant in 2006 was like archaeological work. Email addresses from the 1980s were long dead. USENET posts provided few clues. I scoured old university directories, googled fragments of names, and followed digital breadcrumbs across decades-old forums.</p>



<p>The breakthrough came through pure persistence and a bit of luck. After months of searching, I managed to contact Ed Barlow. His response was refreshingly casual: <em>“Yes i delegated it all to adam aeons ago. Im easy on it all…. copyleft didnt exist when i wrote it and it was all for fun so…”</em></p>



<p>But there was a catch – I needed permission from Adam Bryant too, and he seemed to have vanished into the digital ether.</p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-3-the-long-wait-2006-2011-"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-chapter-3-the-long-wait-2006-2011-"></a>Chapter 3: The Long Wait (2006-2011)</h2>



<p>I documented everything on the Debian Legal mailing lists, created a GNU Savannah task (<a href="http://https//savannah.nongnu.org/task/?5945">#5945</a>), and even wrote blog posts hoping Adam would find them. The legal experts were clear: I needed explicit written permission from both copyright holders.</p>



<p>Years passed. The project stalled.</p>



<p>Then, on February 23, 2011, something magical happened. My phone buzzed with a contact form submission:</p>



<p><strong>“I heard news of the request to release the code. I grant permission to release the code under GPL.”</strong> – Adam Bryant</p>



<p><em>He had found one of my articles online and reached out on his own.</em></p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-4-the-plot-twist-version-5-emerges-2025-"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-chapter-4-the-plot-twist-version-5-emerges-2025-"></a>Chapter 4: The Plot Twist – Version 5 Emerges (2025)</h2>



<p>Fast forward to 2025, and Stephen Smoogen contacts me about my relicesing efforts in 2006 and how he was particularly interested in reviving: <strong>Conquer Version 5</strong> – a complete rewrite by Adam with advanced features like automatic data conversion, enhanced stability, and sophisticated administrative tools. This wasn’t just an update; it was a complete reimagining of the game.</p>



<p>But V5 had a different legal history. In the ’90s, there had been commercial arrangements. Would Adam agree to GPL this version too?</p>



<p>His response: <em>“I have no issues with applying a new GPL license to Version 5 as well.”</em></p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-5-the-missing-piece-postscript-magic"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-chapter-5-the-missing-piece-postscript-magic"></a>Chapter 5: The Missing Piece – PostScript Magic</h2>



<p>Just when I thought the story was complete, I discovered another contributor: MaF, who had created PostScript utilities for generating printable game maps – a crucial feature in the pre-GUI era when players needed physical printouts to strategize.</p>



<div><p>Tracking down MaF in 2025 led me to his company, where he’s now Director of Product Security. His response: <em>“Oh, that was a long time ago. But yes, that was me. And I have no problem with relicensing it to GPL.”</em></p><p><strong>Richard Caley: More Than Just a Legal Footnote</strong></p></div>



<p>But not all searches end with an answer. Some end with silence.</p>



<p>My investigation of Richard Caley followed the same digital breadcrumbs. I traced him to the University of Edinburgh, where he worked on speech synthesis. I found his technical contributions to FreeBSD. But the trail went cold around 2005.</p>



<p>Then I found him – not in a USENET archive, but on the front page of his own website, preserved exactly as he left it in web.archive.org.</p>



<p><em>“Richard Caley suffered a fatal heart attack on the 22nd of April, 2005. He was only 41, but had been an undiagnosed diabetic, probably for some considerable time. His web pages remain as he left them.”</em></p>



<p>Reading those words felt different from finding a historical record. This wasn’t archival research – this was walking into someone’s house years after they’d gone and finding a note on the table.</p>



<p>The page continued:</p>



<p><em>“Over and above his tremendous ability with computers and programming, Richard had a keen mind and knowledge of an extraordinary range of topics, both of which he used in frequent contributions to on-line discussions. Despite his unique approach to speling, his prolific contributions to various news group debates informed and amused many over the years.”</em></p>



<p><strong>The “Caleyisms” – The Man Behind the Code</strong></p>



<p>And then I discovered his “Caleyisms” – a curated collection of his most brilliant USENET responses that revealed not just a programmer, but a person:</p>



<p><em>What’s a shell suit?</em></p>



<blockquote>
<p>“Oil company executive.”</p>
</blockquote>



<p><em>How do you prepare for a pyroclastic flow hitting Edinburgh?</em></p>



<blockquote>
<p>“Hang 1000 battered Mars bars on strings and stand back?”</p>
</blockquote>



<p><em>On his book addiction:</em></p>



<blockquote>
<p>“I never got the hang of libraries, they keep wanting the things back and get upset when they need a crowbar to force it out of my hands.”</p>
</blockquote>



<p>His humor was dry, intelligent, and uniquely British. In technical discussions, he could be brutally precise:</p>



<p><em>“Lack of proper punctuation, spacing, line breaks, capitalisation etc. is like bad handwriting, it doesn’t make it impossible to read what was written, just harder. But you probably write in green crayon anyway.”</em></p>



<p><strong>A Digital Office Preserved</strong></p>



<p>Exploring his preserved website felt like walking through his digital office. The directory structure revealed his passions: FreeBSD how-tos, POVRAY experiments, wallpaper images, technical projects. His self-deprecating humor shone through in his “About” section:</p>



<p><em>“Thankfully I don’t have a photograph to inflict on you. Just use the picture of Iman Bowie to the left and then imagine someone who looks exactly the opposite in every possible way. This probably explains why she is married to David Bowie and I’m not.”</em></p>



<p>Here was a complete person – technical director at Interactive Information Ltd, speech synthesis researcher, FreeBSD enthusiast, Kate Bush fan, and a wit who brightened countless online discussions.</p>



<p>The legal reality was harsh: Richard’s contributions to Conquer couldn’t be relicensed. The university couldn’t help contact heirs due to privacy laws.</p>



<div><p>His friends had preserved his memory with a simple ASCII tribute at the end of his page:</p></div>



<pre>      ^_^<br>     (O O) <br>     \_/@@\<br>      \\~~/ <br>        ~~<br>               - RJC RIP<br></pre>



<p>In the Conquer project documentation, Richard Caley isn’t remembered as a “problem case” or “unlicensable code.” He’s honored as the vibrant person he was – the brilliant mind behind the “Caleyisms,” the researcher who contributed to speech synthesis, the FreeBSD advocate, and the witty participant in early online communities whose words continue to amuse and inform, decades after he wrote them.</p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-chapter-6-modern-renaissance-enter-melange">Chapter 6: Modern Renaissance – Enter GitHub, CICD and Modern Distributions</h2>



<p><img decoding="async" width="150" height="47" src="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer-pipeline.png" alt="" srcset="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer-pipeline.png 1228w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer-pipeline-300x95.png 300w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer-pipeline-1024x324.png 1024w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer-pipeline-768x243.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px"></p>



<p>Here’s where the story gets really interesting. While working on preserving these Unix classics, I decided to learn modern packaging techniques. I chose to implement both <strong>APK (Alpine Linux)</strong> and <strong>Debian</strong> packaging for the games.</p>



<p>For APK packages, I used <strong>Melange</strong> – a sophisticated build system that creates provenance-tracked, reproducible packages for the Wolfi “undistro”. The irony? I discovered this tool when some friend started to work for the company that created it.<img decoding="async" src="blob:https://sandbox.cryptpad.info/05b5f619-e6f1-4ad4-b677-8b91f59dd1ec" alt=""></p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-the-technical-journey-from-usenet-to-modern-ci-cd"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-the-technical-journey-from-usenet-to-modern-ci-cd"></a>Chapter 7: The Technical Journey: From USENET to Modern CI/CD</h2>



<p>The transformation has been remarkable:</p>



<p><strong>1987 Original:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Distributed as split USENET posts</li>



<li>Manual compilation with system-specific Makefiles</li>



<li>No version control or automated testing</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>2025 Revival:</strong></p>



<pre><code># Modern CI/CD with GitHub Actions
- name: Build APK package
  run: melange build conquer.yaml
- name: Build Debian package  
  run: dpkg-buildpackage -b
</code></pre>



<p><strong>Key Modern Additions:</strong></p>



<ul>
<li><strong>GPLv3 relicensing</strong></li>



<li><strong>Make building system modernization</strong></li>



<li><strong>C Codebase partially updated to support modern ANSI C99 specification</strong></li>



<li><strong>Debian packaging</strong></li>



<li><strong>APK packaging with Melange</strong></li>
</ul>



<p>You can see the complete transformation in the repositories:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vejeta/conquer">Conquer v4</a> – The original classic</li>



<li><a href="https://github.com/vejeta/conquerv5">Conquer v5</a> – The advanced rewrite</li>
</ul>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="614" src="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer_ttyd_web1-1024x614.png" alt="" srcset="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer_ttyd_web1-1024x614.png 1024w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer_ttyd_web1-300x180.png 300w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer_ttyd_web1-768x461.png 768w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer_ttyd_web1-1536x921.png 1536w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/conquer_ttyd_web1.png 1687w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p><img decoding="async" src="blob:https://sandbox.cryptpad.info/658f34fe-2ad8-43e2-b3bc-f9e3a28e8a88" alt=""></p>



<p>Original Conquer v4 code, by Ed Barlow and Adam Bryant</p>



<div><p>(Conquer running in docker container alongside Apache, Curses to WebSockets output thanks to <a href="http://https//github.com/tsl0922/ttyd">ttyd</a>. <strong>Now we can play through the web!</strong>)<img decoding="async" src="blob:https://sandbox.cryptpad.info/231bb900-b8f0-4c15-9baa-2b0fb40cd689" alt=""></p></div>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="573" src="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/ConquerV5b-1024x573.png" alt="" srcset="https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/ConquerV5b-1024x573.png 1024w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/ConquerV5b-300x168.png 300w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/ConquerV5b-768x429.png 768w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/ConquerV5b-1536x859.png 1536w, https://vejeta.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/ConquerV5b-2048x1145.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>Conquer Version 5 – The evolution of the classical Conquer, by Adam Bryant</p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-the-human-element-why-this-matters"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-the-human-element-why-this-matters"></a>Chapter 8: The Human Element: Why This Matters</h2>



<p>This isn’t just about preserving old games – it’s about preserving the <strong>story of computing itself</strong>. Ed Barlow and Adam Bryant were pioneers who built sophisticated multiplayer experiences when most people had never heard of the internet. They distributed software through USENET because that’s what you did – you shared cool things with the community.</p>



<p>Martin Forssen’s PostScript utilities represent the ingenuity of early developers who solved problems with whatever tools were available. Want to visualize your game state? Write a PostScript generator!</p>



<p><strong>The 20-year relicensing effort demonstrates something crucial about open source:</strong> it’s not just about code, it’s about <strong>community and continuity</strong>. Every time someone maintains a legacy project, documents its history, or tracks down long-lost contributors, they’re weaving the threads that connect computing’s past to its future.</p>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-lessons-for-modern-developers"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-lessons-for-modern-developers"></a>Lessons for Modern Developers</h2>



<ol>
<li><strong>Document everything</strong>: Those casual USENET posts became crucial legal evidence decades later</li>



<li><strong>License clearly</strong>: Ed’s comment that “copyleft didnt exist when i wrote it” highlights how licensing landscapes evolve</li>



<li><strong>Community matters</strong>: Adam found my articles because the community was talking about preservation</li>



<li><strong>Technical debt is temporal</strong>: What seems like legacy tech today might be tomorrow’s archaeological treasure</li>



<li><strong>Modern tools can revive ancient code</strong>: Melange and modern CI/CD gave 1987 software a 2025 renaissance</li>
</ol>



<h2 id="cp-md-0-the-continuing-story"><a href="https://cryptpad.fr/#cp-md-0-the-continuing-story"></a>The Continuing Story</h2>



<p>Both Conquer games are now fully GPL v3 licensed and available with modern packaging. They represent not just playable software, but a complete case study in software archaeology, legal frameworks for preservation, and the evolution of development practices across four decades.</p>



<p>The next chapter? Teaching these classic strategy games to a new generation of developers and gamers, while demonstrating that proper legal frameworks and modern tooling can give any historical software a second life.</p>



<p><em>Sometimes the best way to learn cutting-edge technology is by applying it to preserve computing history.</em></p>



<hr>



<p><strong>What historical software deserves preservation in your field? Have you ever traced the lineage of code back to its original creators?</strong></p>



<p>#FreeSoftware #OpenSource #SoftwarePreservation #Unix #GNU #Linux #Packaging #Melange #TechHistory #GameDevelopment #Unix #USENET #GPL #FST #Debian #ncurses #terminal #shell</p>



<p><strong>Read this article in Spanish</strong> / <strong>Lee este artículo en español</strong>: <br><a href="https://vejeta.com/conquer-una-odisea-de-20-anos-en-arqueologia-digital/">https://vejeta.com/conquer-una-odisea-de-20-anos-en-arqueologia-digital/</a></p>



<p><em>This article was originally written in both English and Spanish, with additional insights and cultural context in the Spanish version.</em></p>





</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Alive internet theory (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://alivetheory.net/</link>
            <guid>45865098</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 12:33:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://alivetheory.net/">https://alivetheory.net/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45865098">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: How would you set up a child’s first Linux computer? (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45864732</link>
            <guid>45864732</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 11:12:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45864732">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="bigbox"><td><table><tbody><tr id="45864732"><td><span></span></td><td><center><a id="up_45864732" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=45864732&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D45864732"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45864732">Ask HN: How would you set up a child’s first Linux computer?</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span><span id="score_45864732">102 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=evolve2k">evolve2k</a> <span title="2025-11-09T11:12:02 1762686722"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45864732">6 hours ago</a></span> <span id="unv_45864732"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=45864732&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D45864732">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Ask%20HN%3A%20How%20would%20you%20set%20up%20a%20child%E2%80%99s%20first%20Linux%20computer%3F&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=45864732&amp;auth=96db6e67d8cc947bbf31ac0e54b795835281c4a8">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45864732">141&nbsp;comments</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>As a tech parent I think one of the best things I did for both my son and daughter was for their first computer to help them to build and setup their own Linux computer (It was Ubuntu back then but they’ve both moved themselves to Arch these days).</p><p>We went together and bought a second hand desktop (exciting the people selling to us also) and when I got home I pulled out the Ram, HD and CD drive and set them aside; and then together with a screwdriver we “built the computer” over a few days.</p><p>In windows when a child goes searching the web for a “movie maker for windows” they are going to be in a world of hurt either finding expensive commercial options or super scammy sites promising the world.</p><p>By comparison on Linux if they search the local “app store” they’ll find stacks and stacks of free, useful, open licensed software.</p><p>My kids loved the power, freedom and later unexpected community this bought them.</p><p>Now my friend wants the same for their daughter who is 8 years old.</p><p>I’m planning to do the same and go with her parents and her and buy a second hand desktop together and then put Linux on it.</p><p>My question is where would you go from there? What suggestions do you have? What to install? Any mini “curriculums” or ideas?</p><p>Would love to hear your ideas and experiences. Linux with free and open software is the goal and focus.</p></div></td></tr><tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr></tbody></table><br>
</td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Am Mark Zuckerberg (1006 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/</link>
            <guid>45863360</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 06:13:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/">https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45863360">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wrapper"> 
  <h2>Welcome to iammarkzuckerg.com</h2>
 
  <p>No, not <b>THAT</b> Mark Zuckerberg-this one's busy helping Hoosiers, not launching social networks.
</p><p><img src="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/images/zuck-200.jpg" width="200" height="127" alt="Mark Zuckerberg Bankruptcy Lawyer"></p>

<p>Relax, you haven't accidentally logged into Facebook or the Metaverse. You're on the site of <b>Mark S. Zuckerberg</b>, Indiana's original bearer of the name, proud <a href="http://zucklaw.com/" target="_blank" title="Bankruptcy Law Office of Mark S. Zuckerberg">bankruptcy attorney</a>, and frequent recipient of confused emails from people seeking tech support or handouts of money.</p>

<p>
<b>What I Really Do</b>:
</p><ul>
	<li>Help people obtain a fresh financial start (no passwords required)<br>
	</li><li>Offer dependable, human-involved advice (my artificial intelligence is powered by coffee)<br>
	</li><li>Answer local legal questions, not privacy scandals<br>
</li></ul>


<p>
<b>Real Zuckerberg Facts</b>:
</p><ul>
	<li> Shares a name, not fortune, with the Facebook founder<br>
	</li><li> Gets mistaken daily for a tech billionaire <br>
	</li><li> Has written zero social media apps, but plenty of court briefs<br>
</li></ul>


<p>

<b>Fun Fact</b>:<br>
In Indiana, saying "I'm Mark Zuckerberg" gets more laughs than likes. But if you need trustworthy bankruptcy help, you're in exactly the right place!
Click around, get to know your (non-billionaire) local Mark, and remember: No login required.
  </p>
  
  <p>
 <img src="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/images/MediaIcon.png" width="70" height="67" alt="">
 </p><h3>
<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/media.html">
Click Here to See How Other <br>Websites Have Reacted to This
</a>
</h3>
<!--
<p>
<div id ="picright"><img src="images/zuck-200.jpg" width="200" height="127" alt="Mark Zuckerberg Bankruptcy Lawyer" /></div>
I started practicing law in central Indiana nearly 38 years ago. Most of my career has focused on consumer and commercial bankruptcy laws. I was one of the first  board certified Consumer Bankruptcy Specialists in Indiana.  In the nearly 34 years since I opened the Bankruptcy Law Office of <a href="https://zucklaw.com" target="_blank" ><strong>Mark S. Zuckerberg</strong></a>, I have helped literally tens of thousands of Hoosiers weather difficult times in their lives. Along the way, I've become a national lecturer on the topic of consumer bankruptcy law. In fact, I've spoken at both the American Bankruptcy Institute Conference and annual National Conference of Bankruptcy Judges. I have been recognized by Who's Who in American Law, the Best Lawyers in America Consumer Guide, and was the only consumer bankruptcy attorney to be named in the March 2005 Edition of the Indianapolis Monthly Magazine's list of Indiana Super Lawyers, a distinction I have repeated several times. I was awarded Master Distinguished Fellow by the Indianapolis Bar Association.</p>
<br /><br />

<p><div id ="picleft"><a href="media.html" target="_blank" name="Mark Zuckerberg in the News" title="Mark Zuckerberg in the News"><img src="images/media3.jpg" width="200" height="216" alt="Mark Zuckerberg media" /></a></div>I tell you all of this to make this point: I have put a lot of energy into becoming an exceptional bankruptcy attorney and establishing my good name nationally. If you had Googled <strong>Mark Zuckerberg</strong> in 2004, you would have found me. No one else. Mark S. Zuckerberg, bankruptcy attorney. If you had repeated the search two years later, you wouldn't have found me at all. Now my name isn't mine any more. The website HowManyofMe.com claims that only 1 <strong>Mark Zuckerberg</strong> exists in the entire United States. Which one do you think they're counting?</p>
<br /><br />

<p>Other than the name, the two of us have little else in common. He was born in Dobbs Ferry, NY at about the same time that I was graduating from Indiana University. To date, he hasn't finished his college education, but Harvard is known for granting honorary degrees to its successful technology dropouts. He has been immersed in technology almost since birth. I'm happy to be able to accomplish my electronic tasks without screaming. Columbia Pictures will release a movie about him this Fall. I have a series of bankruptcy related videos on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@markzuckerberg1486" target="_blank">YouTube</a>. One thing we do share is a laser sharp focus on what we do. Facebook's success owes to the determination and intensity of young Mr. Zuckerberg. My Indiana bankruptcy law practice gets the same laser focus from me and my competent staff. </p>
<br />

<div id="things">
-->
<br>
<h3>Interesting Things That Have Happened to Me Because My Name is Mark Zuckerberg</h3>
<br>
<li> <b>I was sued by the state of Washington due to mistaken Identity.</b> They thought I was the founder of FaceBook who was accused of endangering an adult in need of services. (<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/20250821111936235R.pdf" target="_blank">click to see full document</a>)</li><li> My personal Facebook account has been disabled five times and my business account four times because Facebook believes I am impersonating a celebrity or using a fake name (<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/20250821112119987R.pdf" target="_blank">click to see full document</a>)</li><li> My FaceBook account is constantly being hacked, and I am asked to constantly reset my password multiple times a day. (<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/20250821111852349R.pdf" target="_blank">click to see full document</a>)</li><li> I must turn off my phone at night to avoid the flood of notifications I receive.</li><li> I was forced to provide multiple forms of identification (birth certificate, drivers license, credit card) in order to open my orginal Facebook account and again each time my account is disabled.  Far beyond the norm.</li><li> When a Facebook scam promised money from "Mark Zuckerberg" I was inundated with calls and emails from strangers, receiving phone calls at all hours of the night.</li><li> I receive over 100+ friend requests daily from people confusing me with the "other" Mark Zuckerberg.</li><li> I continually receive packages and letters containing complaints, suggestions, or demands for how to "improve Facebook" </li><li> I receive phone calls at my office every day from angry people demanding tech support, or help with Facebook from resets to remove photos to locked accounts.</li><li> I was removed from Nextdoor app for using a fake name (<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/20250821111606286.pdf" target="_blank">click to see full document</a>)</li><li> I routinely receive death threats and harassment on the Messenger app directed to the "other" Mark Zuckerberg (<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/threats.pdf" target="_blank">click to see full document</a>)</li><li> I get Venmo payment requests and money solicitations from total strangers (<a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/venmo.pdf" target="_blank">click to see full document</a>)<p>



For a complete list of things that have happened to Mark Zuckerberg <a href="https://iammarkzuckerberg.com/docs/20250821111548341.pdf" target="_blank">click here</a></p>

<!--
<br>
<p>I suppose there are worse things. I could have had the fate of the poor guy in <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0151804/" target="_blank">Office Space</a> who was named Michael Bolton, or the real Westchester, NY funeral director named <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/23/nyregion/nyregionspecial2/23colwe.html?unlocked_article_code=1.jk4.llxX.Mhq31hu_gWFk&smid=url-share" target="_blank">Frank Sinatra</a>. Or I could share my name with some infamous criminal like David Berkowitz. I have to say that my take on name sharing is more in line with funeral director Sinatra than fictional office worker Bolton. I don't wish my namesake any ill will. I hope the best for him. I'm even one of the 350 million Facebook users, with an account and a <a href="https://www.facebook.com/profile.php?id=100064104602276" target="_blank">business page</a>. You can't imagine the number of friend requests I get every day! I wouldn't have  suggested that he turn down that billion dollar offer from Yahoo a couple of years ago, but time will tell.</p>
<br /><br />
-->

<p>Like I said, I don't wish Mark E. Zuckerberg any ill will at all. I hope the best for him, but let me tell you this: I will rule the search for "<a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;safe=off&amp;q=mark+zuckerberg+bankruptcy&amp;aq=f&amp;aqi=g1&amp;aql=&amp;oq=&amp;gs_rfai=" target="_blank">Mark Zuckerberg bankruptcy</a>". And if he does fall upon difficult financial times, and happens to be in Indiana, I will gladly handle his case in honor of our eponymy.</p>
 <!--
 <p>
 <img src="images/MediaIcon.png" width="70" height="67" alt="" hspace="20" align="left" />
 <h2>
<a href="media.html">
Visit Marks News Page to See Additional Videos, Listen to <br />Radio Programs, and See What Other Websites Say About This 
</a>
</h2></p>
-->
   </li></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Study finds memory decline surge in young people (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://onepercentrule.substack.com/p/under-40s-declining-memory</link>
            <guid>45863057</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 05:05:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://onepercentrule.substack.com/p/under-40s-declining-memory">https://onepercentrule.substack.com/p/under-40s-declining-memory</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45863057">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg" width="1456" height="971" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:971,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:314179,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://onepercentrule.substack.com/i/178335673?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!q36V!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff27993bc-ac91-4115-bff8-9c086ee5bfca_1920x1280.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>Has social media engineered the collapse of the human mind? The answer is yes, if we believe the results of a measurable scientific research of this catastrophe, which was recently published in the journal </span><em><a href="https://www.neurology.org/doi/pdf/10.1212/WNL.0000000000214226" rel="">Neurology</a></em><span>. The paper, by Ka-Ho Wong and colleagues, is a data-rich examination of 4.5 million survey responses. Its finding is that “serious difficulty concentrating, remembering, or making decisions” is no longer a fringe complaint, but a surging public health crisis.</span></p><p><span>Those 4.5 million survey responses were gathered over a decade through the </span><a href="https://www.cdc.gov/brfss/index.html" rel="">CDC’s</a><span> Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System. Its outcome is clear on the data, more and more younger people have: </span><em><strong>serious difficulty concentrating, remembering, or making decisions because of a physical, mental, or emotional condition.</strong></em></p><p><span>The numbers are unambiguous. From 2013 to 2023, the age-adjusted prevalence of such “cognitive disability” in U.S. adults rose from 5.3 to 7.4 percent. But the real shock lies in who changed. </span><strong>Among adults 18 to 39 years old, the supposed cognitive prime, the prevalence nearly doubled, from 5.1 to 9.7 percent</strong><span>. It climbed across every racial and economic line. It tripled even among the highest-income bracket, those meant to be buffered by privilege. </span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg" width="642" height="346" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:346,&quot;width&quot;:642,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Cognitive disability&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="Cognitive disability" title="Cognitive disability" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!_305!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7356a1e3-8d18-46bc-aeb5-27e89265835f_642x346.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>This being said the authors do acknowledge that “Younger adults, racial minorities, and socioeconomically disadvantaged groups are disproportionately affected, highlighting the urgent need for targeted interventions.” And, with scientific rigor, the researchers “excluded participants who self-reported depression … to better identify non-psychiatric cognitive impairment.”</p><p>Because what they have found is not a disorder hidden in a subpopulation. It is the first measurable biological signature of a civilization rewiring its own nervous system.</p><p><span>For fifteen years we have been building, at planetary scale, a machinery of disattention: social platforms that auction attention by the millisecond; search engines that outsource memory; feeds that weaponize emotion for engagement. The result is an economy that grows in inverse proportion to our capacity to think. Now the data have arrived like a coroner’s note. </span><strong>The youngest generation, those who have never known a world before the machine, are reporting that they can no longer concentrate, remember, or decide.</strong></p><p>The authors, although cautious, propose the polite hypotheses. Social isolation. Increased reliance on technology. Maybe “greater awareness” of cognitive problems. One almost applaud the decorum and understatements. A “greater awareness” of forgetting, what a phrase. As though we are choosing to notice that our minds are leaking. People are not more willing to report it; they are less able to conceal it.</p><p>The study itself betrays the timeline. The statistically significant rise began in 2016, four years before lockdowns, before “long COVID.” The pandemic did not cause the decline; it simply sealed us inside the apparatus that was already doing the work.</p><p>And what an apparatus. We have built a trillion-dollar system to externalize thought, then act astonished when the interior world collapses. To name “reliance on technology” as a risk factor is like diagnosing “submersion” in a drowning victim.</p><p>What the paper records is not a warning but a postscript, the data catching up to what daily life has been telling us for years.</p><p><span>A friend of mine, a novelist, disciplined, once able to lose herself for hours in text, told me recently that she can no longer read a book. Her eyes move, but the mind skitters. “It’s as though my attention has been trained to hover,” she said, “like a cursor that can’t click.” The Wong et al. study gives her condition a bureaucratic dignity: </span><em>cognitive disability</em><span>. Her failure is no longer moral; it is systemic. She is not weak. She is collateral damage from being constantly online.</span></p><p>Yet this is larger than individual suffering. A population unable to concentrate, remember, or choose is not merely an unproductive workforce. It is an ungovernable polity. Democracy presumes a citizen capable of following an argument across paragraphs, of remembering yesterday’s promise when voting tomorrow. If cognition fragments, so does self-government. A people who cannot remember are condemned not just to repeat the past, but to be told what the past was, and to believe it.</p><p><strong>The political question of our century is no longer </strong><em><strong>who controls the means of production?</strong></em><strong> but </strong><em><strong>who controls the means of perception?</strong></em></p><p><span>In that light, the paper’s most haunting choice, the exclusion of the depressed, acquires philosophical weight. The researchers sought a “clean” signal, free of affect. They wished to see the thing itself. And what they found was a doubling. Perhaps this </span><em>is</em><span> the affect. Perhaps the mind, faced with an environment of perpetual stimulation, begins to disable itself as a last act of defense, a biological attempt to lower the volume by breaking the dial.</span></p><p><strong>Meanwhile, at the far end of the data, a small mercy: among adults 70 and older, the prevalence of cognitive disability has declined. They are, in statistical terms, the last generation to have lived most of life before the feed. Their synapses were wired by books, conversations, and silence. They can still recall what it felt like to finish a thought.</strong></p><p>The young cannot. They are digital natives in the truest, bleakest sense, born in a country that remembers nothing of itself.</p><p>Wong’s paper will be filed, cited, and forgotten like the rest. But read plainly, it documents the first epidemiological evidence of a cognitive collapse engineered by design. The authors close with professional understatement: the findings “warrant further investigation.” One hopes we remain capable of conducting it.</p><p>Stay curious</p><p>Colin</p><p><span>Image </span><a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/group-of-people-standing-on-brown-floor-HN6uXG7GzTE" rel="">Creative Christians on Unsplash</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grok 4 Fast now has 2M context window (159 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://docs.x.ai/docs/models</link>
            <guid>45862833</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 04:10:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://docs.x.ai/docs/models">https://docs.x.ai/docs/models</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862833">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://docs.x.ai/docs/models: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Reverse engineering Codex CLI to get GPT-5-Codex-Mini to draw me a pelican (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/</link>
            <guid>45862802</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 04:02:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/">https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862802">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-permalink-context="/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/">

<p>9th November 2025</p>



<p>OpenAI partially released a new model yesterday called GPT-5-Codex-Mini, which they <a href="https://x.com/OpenAIDevs/status/1986861734619947305">describe</a> as "a more compact and cost-efficient version of GPT-5-Codex". It’s currently only available via their Codex CLI tool and VS Code extension, with proper API access "<a href="https://x.com/OpenAIDevs/status/1986861736041853368">coming soon</a>". I decided to use Codex to reverse engineer the Codex CLI tool and give me the ability to prompt the new model directly.</p>
<p>I made <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9o1_DL9uNlM">a video</a> talking through my progress and demonstrating the final results.</p>



<ul>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/#this-is-a-little-bit-cheeky">This is a little bit cheeky</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/#codex-cli-is-written-in-rust">Codex CLI is written in Rust</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/#iterating-on-the-code">Iterating on the code</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/#let-s-draw-some-pelicans">Let’s draw some pelicans</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Nov/9/gpt-5-codex-mini/#bonus-the-debug-option">Bonus: the --debug option</a></li>
</ul>

<h4 id="this-is-a-little-bit-cheeky">This is a little bit cheeky</h4>
<p>OpenAI clearly don’t intend for people to access this model directly just yet. It’s available exclusively through Codex CLI which is a privileged application—it gets to access a special backend API endpoint that’s not publicly documented, and it uses a special authentication mechanism that bills usage directly to the user’s existing ChatGPT account.</p>
<p>I figured reverse-engineering that API directly would be somewhat impolite. But... Codex CLI is an open source project released under an Apache 2.0 license. How about upgrading that to let me run my own prompts through its existing API mechanisms instead?</p>
<p>This felt like a somewhat absurd loophole, and I couldn’t resist trying it out and seeing what happened.</p>
<h4 id="codex-cli-is-written-in-rust">Codex CLI is written in Rust</h4>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/openai/codex">openai/codex</a> repository contains the source code for the Codex CLI tool, which OpenAI rewrote in Rust just a few months ago.</p>
<p>I don’t know much Rust at all.</p>
<p>I made my own clone on GitHub and checked it out locally:</p>
<div><pre>git clone git@github.com:simonw/codex
<span>cd</span> codex</pre></div>
<p>Then I fired up Codex itself (in dangerous mode, because I like living dangerously):</p>
<div><pre>codex --dangerously-bypass-approvals-and-sandbox</pre></div>
<p>And ran this prompt:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Figure out how to build the rust version of this tool and then build it</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This worked. It churned away for a bit and figured out how to build itself. This is a useful starting point for a project like this—in figuring out the compile step the coding agent gets seeded with a little bit of relevant information about the project, and if it can compile that means it can later partially test the code it is writing while it works.</p>
<p>Once the compile had succeeded I fed it the design for the new feature I wanted:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Add a new sub-command to the Rust tool called “codex prompt”</p>
<p>codex prompt “prompt goes here”—this runs the given prompt directly against the OpenAI API that Codex uses, with the same code path and authentication credentials as the rest of Codex.</p>
<p>codex prompt -m &lt;model_name&gt; “prompt goes here”—same again but lets you set the model</p>
<p>codex prompt “prompt goes here” -s/--system “system prompt goes here”—runs with a custom system/developer message</p>
<p>codex prompt --models—this lists all available models that can be used with the “codex prompt” command</p>
</blockquote>
<p>My design for this new sub-command is lifted directly from my own <a href="https://llm.datasette.io/en/stable/help.html#llm-prompt-help">llm command</a>.</p>
<h4 id="iterating-on-the-code">Iterating on the code</h4>
<p>Codex got to work. I’ve <a href="https://gistpreview.github.io/?ddabbff092bdd658e06d8a2e8f142098">shared the full transcript here</a> (using the tool <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Oct/23/claude-code-for-web-video/">I described here</a>), but this TODO list it made itself is a useful summary of what it decided to do:</p>
<pre><code>Updated Plan
└ ✔ Inspect CLI structure and relevant core utilities for sending prompts and listing models
  ✔ Implement new `codex prompt` subcommand (CLI plumbing + command handler)
  ✔ Format, lint, and test (`just fmt`, `just fix -p codex-cli`, `cargo test -p codex-cli`)
</code></pre>
<p>I like that it figured out <a href="https://github.com/openai/codex/blob/a47181e471b6efe55e95f9858c913fc89a3a44fa/codex-rs/justfile">the justfile</a> in the repo and decided to use it to run formatting and linting commands without me needing to tell it to.</p>
<p>I tried running the first version of the code it wrote like this:</p>
<div><pre>./target/debug/codex prompt <span><span>'</span>Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle<span>'</span></span> -m gpt-5-codex-mini</pre></div>
<p>... and it didn’t quite work. I got this:</p>
<pre><code>(reasoning summary) **Seeking
(reasoning summary)  instructions
(reasoning summary)  and
(reasoning summary)  sandbox
(reasoning summary)  info
(reasoning summary) **
(reasoning summary) **Dec
(reasoning summary) iding
(reasoning summary)  on
(reasoning summary)  SVG
(reasoning summary)  creation
(reasoning summary)  approach
(reasoning summary) **
(reasoning summary) **Checking
(reasoning summary)  current
(reasoning summary)  directory
(reasoning summary) **
(reasoning summary) **Preparing
(reasoning summary)  to
(reasoning summary)  check
(reasoning summary)  current
(reasoning summary)  directory
(reasoning summary) **
I�m ready to help�what would you like me to do next?I�m ready to help�what would you like me to do next?
Token usage: total=2459 input=2374 cached_input=0 output=85 reasoning_output=64
</code></pre>
<p>Note that it DID think about SVG creation, but then decided it should look at the current directory. This isn’t what I want—it appeared to be running in Codex’s normal mode with a system prompt telling it to edit files on disk. I wanted it to respond to the prompt without acting as if it had a full workspace available to it.</p>
<p>I prompted it again, pasting in the broken output:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>this did not seem to work—here is what happened—note that the reasoning summary comes out on a lot of lines when I would rather it streams out to stderr on the same line (flushing constantly)—and then despite the reasoning summary thinking about pelican on SVG it did not actually act on that and display the result, which is very surprising. [pasted content]</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It churned for a bit more, but from the output it looked like it was still trying to include Codex-specific tools and workspace information. So I said:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Note that this new ’codex prompt’ command should NOT be able to execute any tools at all, and should not have to think about the workspace or sandbox—it should send a single prompt with no tools and then stream and display a response and then stop.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This got me a new build, but when I ran it:</p>
<pre><code>Error: unexpected status 400 Bad Request: {"detail":"Instructions are not valid"}
</code></pre>
<p>My guess is that OpenAI’s custom backend API for Codex doesn’t like it if you attempt to call it <em>without</em> passing in the expected instructions. Fair enough!</p>
<p>Rather than paste that error in I got Codex to try the command itself, so it could see the error:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You try running this and see what happens: ./target/debug/codex prompt ’Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle’</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Codex switched back to the default instructions. From its reply:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><code>cli/src/prompt_cmd.rs#L1-L320</code> now forces a tool-free request: we keep the workspace defaults, inject a lightweight system/developer message (“don’t run tools”), disable apply_patch/web search via config overrides, and build the outbound prompt as just that system span plus the user text.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I guess that will have to do. I asked for one more feature:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Add a --debug option to the codex prompt command which causes the full JSON request and response to be printed to stderr, plus the URL that is being accessed and the HTTP verb</p>
</blockquote>
<p>... and we’re ready to try this thing out!</p>
<p>Notably I haven’t written a single line of Rust myself here and paid almost no attention to what it was actually doing. My main contribution was to run the binary every now and then to see if it was doing what I needed yet.</p>
<p>I’ve pushed the working code to <a href="https://github.com/simonw/codex/compare/a47181e471b6efe55e95f9858c913fc89a3a44fa...ae5f98a9248a8edb5d3c53261273a482fc0b5306">a prompt-subcommand branch in my repo</a> if you want to take a look and see how it all works.</p>

<h4 id="let-s-draw-some-pelicans">Let’s draw some pelicans</h4>
<p>With the final version of the code built, I drew some pelicans. Here’s the <a href="https://gistpreview.github.io/?a11f9ac456d2b2bc3715ba900ef1203d">full terminal transcript</a>, but here are some highlights.</p>
<p>This is with the default GPT-5-Codex model:</p>
<div><pre>./target/debug/codex prompt <span><span>"</span>Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p>I pasted it into my <a href="https://tools.simonwillison.net/svg-render">tools.simonwillison.net/svg-render</a> tool and got the following:</p>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/codex-hacking-default.png" alt="It's a dumpy little pelican with a weird face, not particularly great"></p>
<p>I ran it again for GPT-5:</p>
<div><pre>./target/debug/codex prompt <span><span>"</span>Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle<span>"</span></span> -m gpt-5</pre></div>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/codex-hacking-gpt-5.png" alt="Much better bicycle, pelican is a bit line-drawing-ish but does have the necessary parts in the right places"></p>
<p>And now the moment of truth... GPT-5 Codex Mini!</p>
<div><pre>./target/debug/codex prompt <span><span>"</span>Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle<span>"</span></span> -m gpt-5-codex-mini</pre></div>
<p><img src="https://static.simonwillison.net/static/2025/codex-hacking-mini.png" alt="This is terrible. The pelican is an abstract collection of shapes, the bicycle is likewise very messed up"></p>
<p>I don’t think I’ll be adding that one to my SVG drawing toolkit any time soon.</p>

<h4 id="bonus-the-debug-option">Bonus: the --debug option</h4>
<p>I had Codex add a <code>--debug</code> option to help me see exactly what was going on.</p>
<div><pre>./target/debug/codex prompt -m gpt-5-codex-mini <span><span>"</span>Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle<span>"</span></span> --debug</pre></div>
<p>The output starts like this:</p>
<pre><code>[codex prompt debug] POST https://chatgpt.com/backend-api/codex/responses
[codex prompt debug] Request JSON:
</code></pre>
<div><pre>{
  <span>"model"</span>: <span><span>"</span>gpt-5-codex-mini<span>"</span></span>,
  <span>"instructions"</span>: <span><span>"</span>You are Codex, based on GPT-5. You are running as a coding agent ...<span>"</span></span>,
  <span>"input"</span>: [
    {
      <span>"type"</span>: <span><span>"</span>message<span>"</span></span>,
      <span>"role"</span>: <span><span>"</span>developer<span>"</span></span>,
      <span>"content"</span>: [
        {
          <span>"type"</span>: <span><span>"</span>input_text<span>"</span></span>,
          <span>"text"</span>: <span><span>"</span>You are a helpful assistant. Respond directly to the user request without running tools or shell commands.<span>"</span></span>
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      <span>"type"</span>: <span><span>"</span>message<span>"</span></span>,
      <span>"role"</span>: <span><span>"</span>user<span>"</span></span>,
      <span>"content"</span>: [
        {
          <span>"type"</span>: <span><span>"</span>input_text<span>"</span></span>,
          <span>"text"</span>: <span><span>"</span>Generate an SVG of a pelican riding a bicycle<span>"</span></span>
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  <span>"tools"</span>: [],
  <span>"tool_choice"</span>: <span><span>"</span>auto<span>"</span></span>,
  <span>"parallel_tool_calls"</span>: <span>false</span>,
  <span>"reasoning"</span>: {
    <span>"summary"</span>: <span><span>"</span>auto<span>"</span></span>
  },
  <span>"store"</span>: <span>false</span>,
  <span>"stream"</span>: <span>true</span>,
  <span>"include"</span>: [
    <span><span>"</span>reasoning.encrypted_content<span>"</span></span>
  ],
  <span>"prompt_cache_key"</span>: <span><span>"</span>019a66bf-3e2c-7412-b05e-db9b90bbad6e<span>"</span></span>
}</pre></div>
<p>This reveals that OpenAI’s private API endpoint for Codex CLI is <code>https://chatgpt.com/backend-api/codex/responses</code>.</p>
<p>Also interesting is how the <code>"instructions"</code> key (truncated above, <a href="https://gist.github.com/simonw/996388ecf785ad54de479315bd4d33b7">full copy here</a>) contains the default instructions, without which the API appears not to work—but it also shows that you can send a message with <code>role="developer"</code> in advance of your user prompt.</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boring Company fined nearly $500K after it dumped drilling fluids into manholes (217 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.yahoo.com/news/articles/elon-musk-boring-company-fined-150000426.html</link>
            <guid>45862674</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 03:32:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.yahoo.com/news/articles/elon-musk-boring-company-fined-150000426.html">https://www.yahoo.com/news/articles/elon-musk-boring-company-fined-150000426.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862674">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-article-body="true"><p>A county environmental regulator has fined Boring Company, Elon Musk’s tunneling venture, nearly $500,000 after the company dumped “drilling fluids” into manholes around Las Vegas, which led to “substantial damage” to the broader county’s infrastructure, according to a notice of violation sent to the company last week.</p><p>Clark County Water Reclamation District (CCWRD) claims that, this summer, Boring Company employees refused to stop dumping drilling fluids when inspectors arrived at its project site near the center of town and directed them to stop, according to the violation. The next day, Boring apparently “feigned compliance” only to continue dumping the wastewater after a company manager “assumed district inspectors had departed the property,” according to a cease-and-desist letter. CCWRD says that its crews ultimately had to clean 12 cubic yards of “drilling mud, drilling spoils, and miscellaneous solid waste” from one of its sewage treatment facilities due to Boring’s discharges across two of its project sites, according to the notice of violation, which was obtained by <em>Fortune</em> via a records request.</p><p>The drilling fluids and spoils noted in the citation appear to refer to the toxic liquid that collects in the bottom of the tunnels as Boring’s machinery drills through earth and rock—liquid which can contain a variety of chemicals including MasterRoc AGA 41S. Many Boring workers have <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/02/27/flirted-death-elon-musk-boring-company-employees-injuries-osha-citations/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:gotten burned;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">gotten burned</a> by these chemicals when their skin was directly exposed to them.</p><p>The new fines and allegations are the latest controversy to flare up around Boring Company. The company has on several occasions been accused by employees and regulators of skirting safety protocols or regulations as it constructs a network of tunnels below Las Vegas that the company says will serve as an “underground highway” for Teslas to zip through.</p><p>The Clark County water agency said that Boring Company’s actions had violated federal laws and regulations, and told Boring it was issuing $493,297.08 in fines, including $131,297.08 for the district’s expenses to remedy the fluid dumping. CCWRD said the fine was due to “the egregious nature of the violations, the substantial damage to district infrastructure, the district emergency resources expended responding to the Violations, and [Boring Company’s] acknowledgement of responsibility for the Violations,” according to the notice of violation. CCWRD has only issued a fine greater than $100,000 to one other company for wastewater discharge in the last three years, according to other documents obtained by <em>Fortune</em> in a separate records request.</p><p>The violation records show that several Boring Company executives attended a hearing with CCWRD at the end of September and that Boring Company acknowledged responsibility and agreed not to expand Boring’s operations to new drilling locations “until certain conditions were met.”</p><p>Boring Company did not respond to multiple requests for comment. A spokeswoman for the Las Vegas Convention and Visitors Authority, which pays Boring to operate the tunnel system below the Convention Center, said the agency was still reviewing the documents and declined to comment further.</p><p>CCWRD says the agency began to look into the dumpings after an anonymous complaint that was sent to the state’s environmental regulator on Aug. 12. Inspectors at CCWRD went out to the project site and confirmed that drilling fluids and spoils were “actively” being discharged into two on-site cleanouts (capped pipe fittings that connect to sewer lines), as well as into two manholes, and that there was “extensive damage to the District’s infrastructure” as a result, according to the documents. CCWRD says that “TBC staff refused” to stop dumping the fluids when inspectors told them to stop.</p><p>The next day, on Aug. 14, inspectors returned and again instructed Boring Company employees to stop discharging. CCWRD says that Boring’s superintendent, Filippo Fazzino, “feigned compliance” and removed connections to on-site cleanouts, but the regulators says that he immediately replaced them “after he assumed District inspectors had departed the Property,” according to a cease-and-desist letter that was sent to Boring later that day.</p><p>“Notably, Mr. Fazzino attempted to minimize the extent of the discharge by falsely claiming that the discharge was initiated only the night before—contrary to the District’s inspection records from the day prior. TBC’s brazen refusal to stop its illicit discharges after being caught in the act, coupled with TBC’s representative’s false statements to District inspectors, proves TBC’s activities to be knowing and intentional,” the cease-and-desist letter wrote.</p><p>Fazzino did not respond to multiple requests for comment.</p><p>In a letter Boring sent to CCWRD Aug. 15, the day after the second inspection, Boring’s director of legal affairs acknowledged that “water was improperly discharged to the sewer system,” that it was investigating the matter, and that the company had taken certain actions as a result, including physically disconnecting certain sewage connections and sealing leaks in its tunnels.</p><div id="recirc-0cf5b9e6-0c04-3521-8370-e765bbb1d90e"><p><h2>More in U.S.</h2></p></div><p>One current Boring Company employee, who spoke with&nbsp;<em>Fortune&nbsp;</em>on the condition of anonymity for fear of reprisal, confirmed that, while the company is required under county rules to pretreat water and fluids before disposing of it, Boring Co. workers were pumping it directly into the sewage system without pretreating it.</p><p>Founded in 2017, the Boring Company is a lower-profile venture in Musk’s empire of moonshots, though no less ambitious than his rocket startup <a href="https://fortune.com/company/spacex/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:SpaceX;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">SpaceX</a> or brain chip operation Neuralink. The idea for Boring is to eliminate traffic by digging tunnels below cities that can shuttle passengers with autonomous Teslas. Boring has raised more than $900 million in funding from some of Silicon Valley’s top investment firms such as Sequoia Capital, according to PitchBook, though it has struggled with delays and <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/02/27/flirted-death-elon-musk-boring-company-employees-injuries-osha-citations/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:employee safety incidents;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">employee safety incidents</a>.</p><p>Boring has made the most progress in Nevada, where a 4-mile stretch underneath the Las Vegas Convention Center is currently the lone working example of Musk’s vision. But the company has had several brushes with regulators in the state. In September, Nevada’s Bureau of Water Pollution Control fined the company nearly $250,000 for violating environmental regulations nearly 800 times in the last two years, including for spilling untreated groundwater onto public roads and not reporting it to authorities, ProPublica first <a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/elon-musk-boring-company-violations-fines-vegas-loop" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:reported;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">reported</a>. Boring had previously entered into a settlement agreement in 2022 with the regulator for similar violations.</p><p>In June 2023, Boring Co. exposed the foundations of two pillars supporting Las Vegas’s elevated monorail while searching for an irrigation pipe, <em>Fortune</em> <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/04/12/elon-musk-boring-company-las-vegas-tunnel-regulators-shut-down-monorail/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:reported;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">reported</a> in April 2024. Regulators ordered the active monorail to temporarily halt&nbsp;operations for a day, with Boring workers exposing the base of another column a few months later. Clark County issued three violations related to the two incidents, accusing Boring Co. of doing work without a permit and creating a potential hazard.&nbsp; (Boring Company, at the time, didn’t respond to a request for comment. The LVCVA said that “TBC was fixing a broken irrigation line and inadvertently exposed a Monorail foundation, so we took the correct steps to repair that, including pausing operations for a day.”)</p><p>Boring has also dealt with investigations from Nevada’s Occupational Safety and Health Administration, including <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/02/27/flirted-death-elon-musk-boring-company-employees-injuries-osha-citations/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:eight citations;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">eight citations</a> in 2023 that Boring is still contesting. According to those citations, many employees have been burned by the chemicals in the liquid that pools up in Boring’s tunnels. (Boring is disputing these violations and will defend itself in an upcoming hearing)</p><p><em>Are you a current or former Boring Company employee with thoughts on this topic? Have a tip to share? Contact Jessica Mathews at <a href="mailto:jessica.mathews@fortune.com" data-ylk="slk:jessica.mathews@fortune.com;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">jessica.mathews@fortune.com</a> or <a href="mailto:jessica.m101@proton.me" data-ylk="slk:jessica.m101@proton.me;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">jessica.m101@proton.me</a></em>,<em> or through the secure messaging app Signal at jessica_mathews.36. You can also contact her <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jessicakmathews/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:on LinkedIn;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">on LinkedIn</a>.</em></p><p><strong>More coverage from Fortune on the Boring Co.</strong>:<br>—<a href="https://fortune.com/2025/09/11/boring-company-job-site-injury-reported-safety/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:Tunneling halted at Boring Company job site in Las Vegas after ‘crushing injury’ of worker reported;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">Tunneling halted at Boring Company job site in Las Vegas after ‘crushing injury’ of worker reported</a><br>—<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/03/12/ceo-las-vegas-agency-boring-company-safety-tunnels/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:The CEO of the Las Vegas agency behind Boring Company’s first tunnel system says his team will be ‘more involved’ after safety incidents;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">The CEO of the Las Vegas agency behind Boring Company’s first tunnel system says his team will be ‘more involved’ after safety incidents</a><br>—<a href="https://fortune.com/2024/02/27/flirted-death-elon-musk-boring-company-employees-injuries-osha-citations/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:‘We have consistently flirted with death’: Elon Musk wanted the Boring Co. to build a tunnel system below Las Vegas. Former employees say they feared for their lives while working there;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">‘We have consistently flirted with death’: Elon Musk wanted the Boring Co. to build a tunnel system below Las Vegas. Former employees say they feared for their lives while working there</a><a href="https://fortune.com/2025/09/11/boring-company-job-site-injury-reported-safety/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas"><br></a></p><p>This story was originally featured on <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/11/08/boring-company-drilling-fluid-fine-wastewater-elon-musk/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" data-ylk="slk:Fortune.com;elm:context_link;itc:0;sec:content-canvas">Fortune.com</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tabloid: The Clickbait Headline Programming Language (287 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tabloid.vercel.app/</link>
            <guid>45862470</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 02:53:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tabloid.vercel.app/">https://tabloid.vercel.app/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45862470">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Airbus took off (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://worksinprogress.co/issue/how-airbus-took-off/</link>
            <guid>45861984</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 01:19:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://worksinprogress.co/issue/how-airbus-took-off/">https://worksinprogress.co/issue/how-airbus-took-off/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861984">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div role="presentation"><p>Would you rather fly in an Airbus or a Boeing? It seems like an easy question.</p>



<p>As Alaska Airlines Flight 1282 flight climbed to 16,000 feet on a January evening in 2024, passengers <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-us-canada-68583149">were stunned</a> when a hole was blasted in the side of the plane. They were hit by howling winds as tray tables were ripped from the backs of seats. Were it not for their seatbelts, they would likely have been sucked out of the plane. It later transpired that the plug which sealed the exit door was missing four critical bolts that held it in place.</p><a href="https://worksinprogress.co/print"><img src="https://wip.gatspress.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/WIP-Cover-Layered-1.png"><div><p><span>Get the print magazine</span></p><hr><p>Subscribe for $100 to receive six beautiful issues per year.</p><p>Subscribe</p></div></a>



<p>The Alaska Airlines incident fortunately didn’t result in any fatalities. Not everyone who has flown on a Boeing 737 MAX in the last few years has been so lucky.</p>



<p>2018 and 2019 saw two 737 crashes that killed 346 people after the plane’s Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System, a feature that pushes the plane’s nose down to prevent stalling, triggered repeatedly due to a faulty sensor. It later transpired that Boeing <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.reuters.com/business/aerospace-defense/us-faa-tells-manufacturers-disclose-safety-critical-information-after-boeing-737-2023-07-26/#:~:text=Boeing%20did%20not%20disclose%20key,review%20allegations%20raised%20by%20whistleblowers.">had not adequately disclosed</a> how the system worked in training manuals.</p>



<p>While Boeing wrestles with <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/c4gxvkq109ko">lawsuits and regulatory investigations</a>, its rival Airbus has stayed out of the headlines – a happier place for the manufacturer of commercial airliners.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!c0B3!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7214d102-0b46-46cd-b346-aa354b9c4451_650x426.png" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!c0B3!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7214d102-0b46-46cd-b346-aa354b9c4451_650x426.png" alt=""></a>
          <figcaption>
            <div>
              <p>
                Boeing 737 and Airbus A320 family deliveries over time.
              </p>
              <div>
                <p>Image</p>
                <p>
                  Javier Irastorza via Wikimedia.
                </p>
              </div>
            </div>
          </figcaption>
        </figure></div>


<p>Europe is a graveyard of failed national champions. They span from the glamorous Concorde to obscure ventures like pan-European computer consortium <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://publishing.cdlib.org/ucpressebooks/view?docId=ft609nb394&amp;chunk.id=d0e7004&amp;toc.id=d0e7081&amp;brand=ucpress/">Unidata</a> or notorious Franco-German search engine <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2008/03/21/technology/21iht-quaero24.html">Quaero</a>.</p>



<p>Airbus is the rare success story. European governments pooled resources and subsidized their champion aggressively to face down a titan of American capitalism in a strategically vital sector. Why did Airbus succeed when so many similar initiatives crashed and burned?</p>



<p>Airbus prevailed because it was the least European version of a European industrial strategy project ever. It put its customer first, was uninterested in being seen as European, had leadership willing to risk political blowback in the pursuit of a good product, and operated in a unique industry.</p>



<h2 id="an-industry-on-the-brink">An industry on the brink</h2>



<p>In the early days of commercial aviation, US aerospace companies <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://interfas.univ-tlse2.fr/nacelles/index.php?id=1492">dominated the market</a> for passenger jets.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!sK97!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdf90b634-b4af-4c7b-8027-4dfcfa93ca8d_1292x768.png" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!sK97!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fdf90b634-b4af-4c7b-8027-4dfcfa93ca8d_1292x768.png" alt=""></a>
          <figcaption>
            <div>
              <p>
                The market share of aircraft manufacturers over time.
              </p>
              <div>
                <p>Image</p>
                <p>
                  INTERFAS.
                </p>
              </div>
            </div>
          </figcaption>
        </figure></div>


<p>The Buy America Act of 1933 forced the US government to buy from American producers where possible. Military orders supercharged the industry and brought significant knowledge spillovers.</p>



<p>The Boeing B-47 bomber, introduced in the late 1940s, pioneered the use of 35-degree swept wings, which  point backwards at an angle of 35 degrees and reduce drag at high speeds. This design went on to inspire nearly every commercial airliner around the world.</p>



<p>Meanwhile the Boeing 707, the company’s first ever airliner, shared a fuselage with the KC-135 Stratotanker, a military refueling aircraft.</p>



<p>In the face of the US, European aerospace companies cut a sorry figure. The British Aircraft Corporation, Sud Aviation in France, and Messerschmitt-Bölkow-Blohm (MBB) in West Germany were all left to compete for orders in a fragmented continental market, with little research or marketing heft. Meanwhile, European airliners who bought American planes could apply for discounted loans from EXIM, the America’s credit export agency.</p>



<p>Between 1960 and 1967, British and French manufacturers <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/20202765" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">saw a 50 percent </a>decline in aircraft deliveries. In 1966, the UK government had even contemplated forcibly merging and nationalizing much of the country’s industry.</p>



<p>European governments had poured money into their national champions in the belief that the maintenance of a civilian aerospace industry was critical for sovereignty, but it was unclear if these companies would survive the decade.</p>



<p>Amid this gloomy backdrop, European governments concluded that their industry’s future depended on cooperation.</p>



<p>The UK and France agreed to pool the resources behind Concorde in 1962 to fight what Charles De Gaulle <a href="https://researchbriefings.files.parliament.uk/documents/SN02764/SN02764.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">called</a> ‘the American colonization of the skies’, but the Germans declined to participate due to their (well-founded) skepticism about the project’s economics. This didn’t stop the Germans teaming up with the Dutch on the long-forgotten <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/VFW-Fokker_614" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">VFW-Fokker 614</a>. This short-haul jet struggled to find customers at a time when airlines preferred to use cheap prop aircraft for regional city-hopping, dooming the project to collapse once state aid was withdrawn in 1977.</p>



<p>In 1965, the French, British, and German governments launched a working group to evaluate the potential of a wide-body commercial aircraft, which would later become the A300. Two years later, the three governments agreed to bear the entire costs of the development of the ‘European Airbus’. In 1970, the coalition was formalized with the creation of Airbus Industrie. The consortium quickly expanded to include Spain and the Netherlands.</p>



<h2 id="the-making-of-a-world-leader">The making of a world leader</h2>



<p>So how did this unlikely band of brothers go on to build a global leader, rather than another Econ101 case study about the perils of industrial policy?</p>



<p>The single biggest factor was a focus on the customer.</p>



<p>Unlike many future industrial strategy projects, which would focus on creating European-owned capabilities for their own sake, the Airbus team were seized by the need to build a jet that airliners would want to buy. They didn’t have much choice: if they failed, there was a reasonable chance the consortium’s domestic aerospace suppliers would collapse.</p>



<p>They were helped enormously in this by their setup. While Airbus didn’t become a unified corporate entity until 2001, the partnership had a strong central leadership from the beginning. Unlike other industrial consortia, which tended to be leaderless venues for intra-European turf wars, Airbus united marketing, procurement, and design.</p>



<p>Roger Béteille, who led the A300 program, probably bears more responsibility for Airbus’s early success than anyone else. Béteille wasn’t interested in building an inferior European Boeing copy. Instead, he invested <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20241006171917/https://www.airbus.com/en/our-history/commercial-aircraft-history/first-order-first-flight-1970-1972" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">significant time in getting to know his potential customers</a> and what they needed. This led to Airbus quickly tossing the original design for a 300-seat A300, in favor of a 225-250 seater, when it became clear that Air France and Lufthansa wanted a smaller product.</p>



<p>The revised A300B would prove much cheaper to develop, in part because it allowed the consortium to dispense with the expensive Rolls Royce engine in favour of a cheaper American alternative. In response, the UK exited the project, only to later return with a lower ownership stake.</p>



<p>This willingness to risk political blowback and avoid petty chauvinism in equipment choice was rare in industrial strategy.</p>



<p>Béteille went one step further. He <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.key.aero/article/inside-story-airbus-first-commercial-aircraft">designated </a>English the official language of the project, instead of the usual mixture of languages that characterised European projects, and forbade the use of metric measurements to make it easier to sell into the US market.</p>



<p>Along with Felix Kracht, Airbus’s first production director, Béteille set a division of labour between the different countries that has persisted, with minor adjustments. French firms handled the cockpit, control systems, and lower-center fuselage; Hawker Siddeley (the inventor of the Harrier jump jet) in the UK designed and built the wings; German companies produced various fuselage sections; the Netherlands managed moving wing components; and Spain was responsible for the horizontal tailplane.</p>



<p>Based on Béteille’s market research, the A300B was <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20241006171917/https://www.airbus.com/en/our-history/commercial-aircraft-history/first-order-first-flight-1970-1972">optimised for fuel efficiency</a>. The team stripped out unnecessary weight by using composite materials and raised the cabin floor to add cargo space. Hawker Siddeley’s wings, which would go on to influence industry standards, were designed with a curved shape on top to reduce air resistance, allowing greater lift and fuel efficiency.</p>



<p>At a time when almost every commercial jet had three or four engines, Airbus opted for a twin-engine design. The plane could theoretically fly on one and the company concluded that only a single extra engine was needed to provide redundancy for safety. The much cheaper twin-engine design is now the industry standard, even for ultra long-haul flights.</p>



<p>Despite the technical ingenuity behind the A300B, early business was slow. By the time the aircraft entered service in 1974, it had struggled to attract commercial interest beyond state-owned flag carriers like Air France, which had placed the first A300B order in 1971 for six jets. Even these airlines continued to operate Boeing-dominated fleets.</p>



<p>One problem was unfortunate timing: the oil shock of 1973 had caused operating costs to spiral for airliners, so there was little appetite for experimentation in the air.</p>



<p>There was <a href="https://interfas.univ-tlse2.fr/nacelles/1576" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">also residual suspicion of European industry among US airliners</a>. Sud Aviation’s Caravelle had been used by some American airliners, but the company was notorious for its sloppy after sales maintenance and service. There had also been an ugly dispute over landing rights for Concorde, with the US heavily restricting the aircraft’s operation out of noise concerns. The French suspected more sinister commercial motivations were at work. Jacques Chirac, then French Prime Minister, raised the temperature, <a href="https://interfas.univ-tlse2.fr/nacelles/1576" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">declaring that</a>:<em> </em>‘The Airbus consortium will not be daunted by the Americans who killed off the Concorde. … We will fight any trade war blow-by-blow as the future of the aeronautical industry and their employees is at stake’.</p>



<p>Against this backdrop, Airbus did everything it could <a href="https://interfas.univ-tlse2.fr/nacelles/1576" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">to deemphasize its European heritage</a> as it toured the US. It refused to involve the French or German embassies in its sales efforts, much to their irritation. Airbus representatives drove home how a third of the plane’s value derived from US-made components, more than any single European partner nation’s contribution. They also mastered the world of DC lobbying, successfully outmaneuvering Boeing and Lockheed’s attempts to use anti-trust regulations to shut the European entrant out of the US market.</p>



<p>Sustained by early European market commitments and early sales in Asia, Airbus was eventually able to clinch its first US order in 1977. Eastern Airlines (EAL), which had been impressed by the A300B’s fuel economy and low noise levels, agreed to the trial lease of four aircraft and three spare engines for … one dollar. These terms would have been unconscionable for a normal private company, but they were transformative for state-backed Airbus’s fortunes. Frank Borman, conservative Republican, former NASA astronaut, and EAL’s CEO emerged as a public champion of the A300B as an ‘American aircraft’.</p>



<h2 id="the-a320">The A320</h2>



<p>Béteille and Kracht weren’t content with building one aircraft. From the beginning, Airbus had targeted a 30 percent global market share. This meant building more than wide-body aircraft like the A300B.</p>



<p>The A320, which entered operation in 1988 was a narrow-bodied aircraft that could carry 150-180 passengers. It was optimized to fly short- and medium-haul routes economically, and a masterclass in engineering and timing.</p>



<p>By the 1980s, airliners were looking to replace their aging narrow-bodied fleets, with the Boeing 272 and McDonnell Douglas DC-9 having been in operation for more than two decades.</p>



<p>The A320 was the first commercial aircraft to <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.airbus.com/en/newsroom/stories/2022-06-safety-innovation-1-fly-by-wire-fbw">implement full digital fly-by-wire controls</a>. Before the A320, the pilot’s controls pulled physical cables attached to the flaps, rudder, and other control surfaces on the plane. Fly-by-wire meant that controls sent electric signals to the plane’s computers, which then commanded motors to move the control surfaces. This made life easier for the pilots by reducing the need for constant manual adjustment and stripped out heavy components that needed maintenance.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EWRk!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7746944f-54e1-45df-b731-9ec6d7ce87a1_1440x961.png" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!EWRk!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7746944f-54e1-45df-b731-9ec6d7ce87a1_1440x961.png" alt=""></a>
          <figcaption>
            <div>
              <p>
                A digital fly-by-wire system.
              </p>
              <div>
                <p>Image</p>
                <p>
                  Airbus.
                </p>
              </div>
            </div>
          </figcaption>
        </figure></div>


<p>The A320 was also the first commercial aircraft to <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.airbus.com/en/newsroom/stories/2023-02-safety-innovation-7-flight-envelope-protection">introduce envelope protection</a>, a system that automatically prevents dangerous actions, such as tilting too steeply, flying too slowly, or making maneuvers that could overstress the aircraft structure.</p>



<p>Again, the A320 wasn’t an overnight success, with new technology and existing relations with Boeing slowing uptake. Airbus again relied on British and French orders to gain market credibility. But by the early 1990s, its superior technology combined with Airbus’s willingness to flex the design, with the A319 (smaller) and A321 (larger) allowing airliners to operate mixed fleets with common cockpits, began to win fans. The A320 is now the most popular airliner family in history and remains in widespread use today.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VThI!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4fd8278a-13e6-4111-99c8-391635680f30_1200x800.png" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!VThI!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4fd8278a-13e6-4111-99c8-391635680f30_1200x800.png" alt="" width="840" height="560"></a>
          <figcaption>
            <div>
              <p>
                The Airbus A320.
              </p>
              <div>
                <p>Image</p>
                <p>
                  Pedro Aragão via Wikimedia.
                </p>
              </div>
            </div>
          </figcaption>
        </figure></div>


<p>The success of the A320 led Airbus to profitability in the mid-1990s. By 2019, Airbus had displaced Boeing as the largest aerospace company by revenue.</p>



<h2 id="why-airbus-s-success-is-so-hard-to-repeat">Why Airbus’s success is so hard to repeat</h2>



<p>If Airbus proves industrial strategy can work, why haven’t other European ventures fared better?</p>



<p>Good industrial strategy requires favorable market conditions, consistent strategy in the face of political headwinds, and the courage to call it a day if failure seems likely. Getting one of these right is tough, and all three is exceptionally rare.</p>



<p>Concorde was a marvel of engineering, but even without US obstructionism, it had little prospect of commercial viability. In today’s money, it cost £16 billion to develop, roughly ten times the cost of the Boeing 727, making it the most expensive plane of its age by some margin. Its limited passenger capacity, fuel inefficiency, and expensive maintenance meant that a ticket for a round trip cost in excess of £10,000 adjusted for inflation. The ultra-premium air travel market wasn’t big enough in the 1980s or 1990s to bear the costs of 1960s technology, leading to Concorde’s retirement in 2003.</p>



<p>Other European projects have lacked the centralized control or clear rationale that characterized Airbus.</p>



<p>We see this in <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://ideas.repec.org/h/spr/sprchp/978-3-540-74038-4_10.html">Unidata</a>, a 1973 consortium that brought together CII (France), Philips (the Netherlands), and Siemens (Germany) to produce a European mainframe line to rival IBM. With no clear leadership, rival members of the consortium pushed their own hardware and software approaches. Engineering efforts were duplicated. The project collapsed within two years amid recriminations.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Lbo0!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F219bf25b-4b76-4c92-b77c-9cd26b7d6bf0_500x318.png" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Lbo0!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F219bf25b-4b76-4c92-b77c-9cd26b7d6bf0_500x318.png" alt=""></a>
          <figcaption>
            <div>
              <p>
                Signing of the Unidata agreement, 1973.
              </p>
              <div>
                <p>Image</p>
                <p>
                  FEB-Patrimoine.
                </p>
              </div>
            </div>
          </figcaption>
        </figure></div>


<p>Meanwhile, it was unclear why the 2005 Franco-German search engine project Quaero ever needed to exist. Widely seen as a vanity project at the time, the attempt to build a search engine by committee similarly<a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2007/01/02/business/worldbusiness/02iht-search.4081237.html"> splintered along national lines</a>. It was also a victim of mission creep, evolving from a direct Google competitor to a multimedia search platform that would be powered by image and voice analysis. The project limped on until its mercy killing in 2013.</p>



<p>It’s also easier to build a global leadership position when your main rival wages a prolonged campaign of self-sabotage. By the new millennium, the competition had been reduced to a simple showdown between Airbus and Boeing. Lockheed had decided to bail on commercial aviation in the 1970s after losing billions of dollars on the <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lockheed_L-1011_TriStar">L-1011</a>, while Boeing acquired McDonnell Douglas in a $13 billion deal in 1997.</p>



<p>While Airbus has retained a strong engineering culture at the helm, this disappeared from Boeing. Harry Stonecipher, Boeing’s CEO in the early 2000s, <a href="https://fortune.com/2024/04/22/how-to-fix-boeing-airbus-technology-chief-leadership-culture/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">notoriously claimed that:</a><em> </em>‘When people say I changed the culture of Boeing, that was the intent, so that it is run like a business rather than a great engineering firm’.</p>



<p>Stonecipher’s successor, James McNerney, took this even further: ‘Every 25 years a big moonshot… and then produce a 707 or a 787 – that’s the wrong way to pursue this business. The more-for-less world will not let you pursue moonshots’.</p>



<p>The McDonnell Douglas acquisition is often marked as a turning point for Boeing. Despite being the acquiring firm, Boeing absorbed much of their target’s management philosophy. This disconnect was embodied in the company’s <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://siteselection.com/ssinsider/incentive/ti0106.htm">decision to move its headquarters</a> from Seattle (where its main production facility was located) to Chicago, for the sake of just $63 million in tax credits. Fatal crashes in 2018 and 2019 have since caused regulatory investigations and multi-billion dollar compensation claims to pile up, as well as allegations that the company has put shareholders and dividends before safety.</p>



<h2 id="a-strange-industry">A strange industry</h2>



<p>Does the Airbus story make a good case for a disciplined, well-executed industrial strategy?</p>



<p>To answer this question, we need to take a step back from Airbus and Boeing and think about their customers.</p>



<p>Airlines have one of the worst business models of any industry. They have eye-watering capital expenditures (a large jet costs in excess of $200 million). The product offering (flights) is relatively undifferentiated, while many of their customers are price-conscious and disloyal. Safety regulations, along with route and landing slot regulations mean there’s little space to drive painless efficiencies. This leaves airlines with two main routes to success: worsening their service through cost-cutting and engaging in kamikaze price wars.</p>



<p>This is why airlines <a target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.airlines.org/dataset/u-s-bankruptcies-and-services-cessations/">frequently go bankrupt</a>, with US Airways, United Airlines, Northwest Airlines, Delta Air Lines and American Airlines among the dozens to almost collapse in the 2000s. Only three airlines without state ties (Southwest, Ryanair, and Copa) have consistently maintained profitability while avoiding bankruptcy or major restructuring.</p>



<p>In his 2007 letter to Berkshire Hathaway shareholders, Warren Buffett <a href="https://som.yale.edu/sites/default/files/2021-12/Module8-Readng.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">described the</a> airline industry as ‘the worst sort of business’, and noted that, ‘if a farsighted capitalist had been present at Kitty Hawk, he would have done his successors a huge favor by shooting Orville down’.</p>



<p>Airbus, as a supplier to these businesses, has not been immune to these pressures. In the early 2000s, airliners were enthused about the ‘hub and spoke’ model. Passengers would fly on large aircraft between major hubs, then transfer to smaller aircraft for their final destinations. With a maximum capacity of over 800, the double-decker Airbus A380 would help allow airliners to consolidate their flights between busy international hubs. By the time it entered commercial operation in 2007, fashions had reversed and consumers were willing to pay a premium to fly direct. Airbus never came close to recouping its $25 billion development costs.</p>



<p>Against this backdrop, companies like Airbus and Boeing face a constant downward price pressure, operating on single digit margins in good years. The merry-go-round of buyers as airliners fall in and out of bankruptcy makes them fickle customers. With this in mind, Boeing’s desire to slash costs seems like a much more rational response, even if its execution was flawed.</p>



<p>It may be nearly impossible to operate the multi-billion dollar, multi-decade product development cycle this industry requires without some form of government backstop, whether it is a direct subsidy (Airbus) or reliable military orders (Boeing).</p>



<p>It is a business that is well-suited to subsidy for other reasons too. Governments are generally better at supporting companies in established markets where innovation takes place slowly and incrementally. This is likely why state-backed efforts have found it easier to be competitive against aerospace companies than Silicon Valley giants working at breakneck pace to keep pace with changing consumer tastes.</p>



<p>We can learn from Airbus’s engineering ingenuity and relentless customer focus. But its success in such an idiosyncratic sector probably isn’t as template for successful industrial policy in many of the other sectors that some people would like it to be.</p>
</div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Judge says Education Dept partisan out-of-office emails violated First Amendment (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.npr.org/2025/11/08/nx-s1-5602859/education-department-out-of-office-emails-ruling</link>
            <guid>45861897</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 01:03:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/11/08/nx-s1-5602859/education-department-out-of-office-emails-ruling">https://www.npr.org/2025/11/08/nx-s1-5602859/education-department-out-of-office-emails-ruling</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861897">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="storytext">
      <div id="resg-s1-97077">
            <div data-crop-type="">
        <picture>
            <source srcset="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/400/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 400w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/600/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/800/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 800w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/900/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 900w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1200/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 1200w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1600/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 1600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1800/quality/85/format/webp/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 1800w" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1025px) 650px, calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/webp">
            <source srcset="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/400/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 400w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/600/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/800/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 800w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/900/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 900w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1200/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 1200w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1600/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 1600w,
https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1800/quality/85/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg 1800w" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg" sizes="(min-width: 1025px) 650px, calc(100vw - 30px)" type="image/jpeg">
            <img src="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/1100/quality/50/format/jpeg/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg" data-template="https://npr.brightspotcdn.com/dims3/default/strip/false/crop/7230x4822+0+0/resize/{width}/quality/{quality}/format/{format}/?url=http%3A%2F%2Fnpr-brightspot.s3.amazonaws.com%2F43%2F09%2Fc6fc89eb470c9591bb0688ea5f5f%2Fgettyimages-2204719133.jpg" alt="The Washington headquarters of the Department of Education on March 12. A federal judge ruled that the Trump administration violated the First Amendment rights of Education Department employees when it replaced their personalized out-of-office e-mail notifications with partisan language." fetchpriority="high">
        </picture>
</div>
<div>
    <div>
        <p>
                The Washington headquarters of the Department of Education on March 12. A federal judge ruled that the Trump administration violated the First Amendment rights of Education Department employees when it replaced their personalized out-of-office notifications with partisan language.
                <b aria-label="Image credit">
                    
                    Win McNamee/Getty Images
                    
                </b>
                <b><b>hide caption</b></b>
            </p>


            <p><b><b>toggle caption</b></b>
    </p></div>

    <p><span aria-label="Image credit">
        
        Win McNamee/Getty Images
        
    </span>
</p></div>
   </div>
   <p>A federal judge ruled that the Trump administration violated the First Amendment rights of Education Department employees when it replaced their personalized out-of-office e-mail notifications with partisan language blaming Democrats for the government shutdown.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5602859-100" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>"When government employees enter public service, they do not sign away their First Amendment rights," U.S. District Judge Christopher Cooper <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/opinion/10733279/american-federation-of-government-employees-v-us-department-of-education/?q=AMERICAN+FEDERATION+OF+GOVERNMENT+EMPLOYEES&amp;type=o&amp;order_by=score+desc&amp;judge=Cooper&amp;stat_Published=on&amp;court=dcd" target="_blank">wrote in his decision</a> on Friday, "and they certainly do not sign up to be a billboard for any given administration's partisan views."</p>   <p>The lawsuit was brought by the American Federation of Government Employees (AFGE).</p>   <p>"This ridiculous ploy by the Trump administration was a clear violation of the First Amendment rights of the workers at the Education Department," said Rachel Gittleman, the president of AFGE Local 252, which represents many Education Department workers, in a statement. She added it is "one of the many ways the Department's leadership has threatened, harassed and demoralized these hardworking public servants in the last 10 months."</p>   
   <p>Cooper ordered the department to restore union members' personalized out-of-office email notices immediately. If that could not be done, he warned, then the department would be required to remove the partisan language from all employees' accounts, union member or not.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5602859-101" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>According to court records, in the run-up to the government shutdown, Education Department employees were told to create an out-of-office message for their government email accounts to be used while workers were furloughed. The department even gave employees boilerplate language they could adapt that simply said:</p>   <p>"We are unable to respond to your request due to a lapse in appropriations for the Department of Education. We will respond to your request when appropriations are enacted. Thank you."</p>   <p>But, on the shutdown's first day, the department's deputy chief of staff for operations overrode staffers' personal messages and replaced them with this partisan autoreply:</p>   <p>"Thank you for contacting me. On September 19, 2025, the House of Representatives passed H.R. 5371, a clean continuing resolution. Unfortunately, Democrat Senators are blocking passage of H.R. 5371 in the Senate which has led to a lapse in appropriations. Due to the lapse in appropriations I am currently in furlough status. I will respond to emails once government functions resume."</p>   
   <p>While the message was written in the first person, multiple employees <a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/10/05/nx-s1-5563182/shutdown-lawsuit-education-department-partisan-messages" target="_blank">told NPR</a> they did not write it and were not told it would replace the out-of-office messages they had written.</p>   
   
<!-- END ID="RESNX-S1-5602859-102" CLASS="BUCKETWRAP INTERNALLINK INSETTWOCOLUMN INSET2COL " -->
   <p>At the time, Madi Biedermann, deputy assistant secretary for communications, said in a statement to NPR: "The email reminds those who reach out to Department of Education employees that we cannot respond because Senate Democrats are refusing to vote for a clean CR and fund the government. Where's the lie?"</p>   <p>In his decision, Cooper lambasted the department for "turning its own workforce into political spokespeople through their official email accounts. The Department may have added insult to injury, but it also overplayed its hand."</p>   <p>The department did not respond to an NPR request to comment on the ruling.</p>   <p>"Nonpartisanship is the foundation of the federal civil-service system," Cooper wrote, a principle that Congress enshrined in the Hatch Act.</p>   <p>That law, passed in 1939, was intended to protect public employees from political pressure and, according to the <a href="https://osc.gov/Services/pages/hatchact.aspx" target="_blank">U.S. Office of Special Counsel</a>, "to ensure that federal programs are administered in a nonpartisan fashion."<br></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Judge denies request to exempt Flock footage from Public Records Act (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.goskagit.com/news/local_news/court-denies-request-that-it-find-flock-safety-camera-data-is-exempt-from-public-records/article_f1edd028-d242-479c-ada8-f2dfca73a1b1.html</link>
            <guid>45861829</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 09 Nov 2025 00:53:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.goskagit.com/news/local_news/court-denies-request-that-it-find-flock-safety-camera-data-is-exempt-from-public-records/article_f1edd028-d242-479c-ada8-f2dfca73a1b1.html">https://www.goskagit.com/news/local_news/court-denies-request-that-it-find-flock-safety-camera-data-is-exempt-from-public-records/article_f1edd028-d242-479c-ada8-f2dfca73a1b1.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45861829">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.goskagit.com/news/local_news/court-denies-request-that-it-find-flock-safety-camera-data-is-exempt-from-public-records/article_f1edd028-d242-479c-ada8-f2dfca73a1b1.html: Error: Request failed with status code 451]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US Air Traffic Controllers Start Resigning as Shutdown Bites (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thedailybeast.com/air-traffic-controllers-start-resigning-as-shutdown-bites/</link>
            <guid>45860865</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 23:06:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/air-traffic-controllers-start-resigning-as-shutdown-bites/">https://www.thedailybeast.com/air-traffic-controllers-start-resigning-as-shutdown-bites/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45860865">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article id="main-article"><p>Overtaxed and unpaid air traffic controllers are resigning “every day” due to stress from the government shutdown.</p><p>“Controllers are resigning every day now because of the prolonged nature of the shutdown,” Nick Daniels, president of the National Air Traffic Controllers Association, told <a onclick="_sendArticleBodyInlineLinkClickAnalytics('https://edition.cnn.com/politics/live-news/trump-government-shutdown-faa-11-6-25')" href="https://edition.cnn.com/politics/live-news/trump-government-shutdown-faa-11-6-25" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer" title="https://edition.cnn.com/politics/live-news/trump-government-shutdown-faa-11-6-25">CNN</a>. </p><div><a href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/trump-orders-air-chaos-across-america-in-shutdown-tantrum/" aria-label="/trump-orders-air-chaos-across-america-in-shutdown-tantrum/"><picture><source alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" media="(max-width: 375px)" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=400" width="400"><source alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" media="(max-width: 500px)" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=600" width="600"><source alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" media="(max-width: 703px)" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=800" width="800"><source alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" media="(max-width: 900px)" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=1000" width="1000"><source alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" media="(max-width: 1031px)" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=1200" width="1200"><source alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" media="(min-width: 1032px)" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=1400" width="1400"><img aria-label="" data-chromatic="ignore" alt="WASHINGTON, DC - JANUARY 30:  U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy&nbsp;(L) takes the podium from U.S. President Donald Trump as they speak to reporters about the collision of an American Airlines flight with a military Black Hawk helicopter near Ronald Reagan National Airport, in the Brady Press Briefing Room at the White House on January 30, 2025 in Washington, DC. Officials believe that all 64 people on the commercial jet and the three service members on the U.S. Army helicopter died when they collided midair and crashed into the Potomac River airport outside Washington, D.C. on Wednesday. (Photo by Chip Somodevilla/Getty Images)" loading="lazy" src="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/ZGXFABPD3ZCYDFIM3TX7EKN75M.jpg?auth=770ff2bc863df63b956df3b3ce2726b29f9b77b32c31f444bbc7b56b84e17900&amp;smart=true&amp;width=300" width="300"></picture></a></div><p>“We hadn’t seen that before. And we’re also 400 controllers short—shorter than we were in the 2019 shutdown.”</p><p>Air traffic controllers are federal workers, which means they are part of the approximately 730,000 federal employees working without pay since the shutdown began on Oct. 1. </p><figure><img data-chromatic="ignore" alt="NEW YORK, NEW YORK - OCTOBER 28: Nick Daniels, President of the National Air Traffic Controllers Association, speaks during a press conference at LaGuardia Airport on October 28, 2025 in New York City. Transportation Secretary Sean Duffy spoke about how the government shutdown, now on its 28th day, is affecting travel at airports throughout the country. Duffy has stated that delays stemming from staffing issues has jumped from its usual mark of 5 % to 53% amid the shutdown.  (Photo by Michael M. Santiago/Getty Images)" loading="lazy" src="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/FKICYEOBZRGHHEXLJD2SMSW4ZI.jpg?auth=98c7410cdaf3a7718831a4800b1d322fa7d3595d89f94304edeeb37100c32c48&amp;width=800&amp;height=533" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/FKICYEOBZRGHHEXLJD2SMSW4ZI.jpg?auth=98c7410cdaf3a7718831a4800b1d322fa7d3595d89f94304edeeb37100c32c48&amp;width=274&amp;height=182 274w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/FKICYEOBZRGHHEXLJD2SMSW4ZI.jpg?auth=98c7410cdaf3a7718831a4800b1d322fa7d3595d89f94304edeeb37100c32c48&amp;width=400&amp;height=266 400w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/FKICYEOBZRGHHEXLJD2SMSW4ZI.jpg?auth=98c7410cdaf3a7718831a4800b1d322fa7d3595d89f94304edeeb37100c32c48&amp;width=768&amp;height=511 768w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/FKICYEOBZRGHHEXLJD2SMSW4ZI.jpg?auth=98c7410cdaf3a7718831a4800b1d322fa7d3595d89f94304edeeb37100c32c48&amp;width=1024&amp;height=682 1024w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/FKICYEOBZRGHHEXLJD2SMSW4ZI.jpg?auth=98c7410cdaf3a7718831a4800b1d322fa7d3595d89f94304edeeb37100c32c48&amp;width=1440&amp;height=959 1440w" width="800" height="533"><figcaption><span>Nick Daniels (center), President of the National Air Traffic Controllers Association, warned that air traffic controllers are resigning en masse over shutdown stress.  </span><span>Michael M. Santiago/Getty Images </span></figcaption></figure><p>Daniels warned that the controllers who remain are stretched dangerously thin. Many are calling in sick due to burnout as they struggle to pay bills. </p><p>“They’re calling their employer and saying, ‘I have no gas today. I cannot pay for my child care. Can I bring my children to work?’” he said.</p><figure><img data-chromatic="ignore" alt="A man stands outside Terminal C with the airport control tower in the background at Newark Liberty International Airport." loading="lazy" src="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/I6BPDGUPENCKFNJ2S55QMDDKO4.jpg?auth=957aa784b511bc5adbf6bfdd05bbe1b93e3877d6ba784b6c91c5a11ef31f3885&amp;width=800&amp;height=450" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/I6BPDGUPENCKFNJ2S55QMDDKO4.jpg?auth=957aa784b511bc5adbf6bfdd05bbe1b93e3877d6ba784b6c91c5a11ef31f3885&amp;width=274&amp;height=154 274w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/I6BPDGUPENCKFNJ2S55QMDDKO4.jpg?auth=957aa784b511bc5adbf6bfdd05bbe1b93e3877d6ba784b6c91c5a11ef31f3885&amp;width=400&amp;height=225 400w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/I6BPDGUPENCKFNJ2S55QMDDKO4.jpg?auth=957aa784b511bc5adbf6bfdd05bbe1b93e3877d6ba784b6c91c5a11ef31f3885&amp;width=768&amp;height=432 768w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/I6BPDGUPENCKFNJ2S55QMDDKO4.jpg?auth=957aa784b511bc5adbf6bfdd05bbe1b93e3877d6ba784b6c91c5a11ef31f3885&amp;width=1024&amp;height=576 1024w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/I6BPDGUPENCKFNJ2S55QMDDKO4.jpg?auth=957aa784b511bc5adbf6bfdd05bbe1b93e3877d6ba784b6c91c5a11ef31f3885&amp;width=1440&amp;height=810 1440w" width="800" height="450"><figcaption><span>The airport control tower at Newark Liberty International Airport. </span><span>Andres Kudacki/Getty Images </span></figcaption></figure><p>On Oct. 7, less than a week after the shutdown began, Transportation Secretary Sean Duffy noted that some air traffic controllers were already taking second jobs—a practice he discouraged. “I don’t want them delivering for DoorDash; I don’t want them driving Uber,” he said. “I want them coming to their facilities and controlling the airspace.”</p><p>The resignations are adding to the tremendous stress being placed on airports due to the government shutdown. Just this week, staffing shortages reached their highest levels since the shutdown began.</p><p>The Trump administration has responded to the crisis by <a onclick="_sendArticleBodyInlineLinkClickAnalytics('https://www.thedailybeast.com/trump-orders-air-chaos-across-america-in-shutdown-tantrum/')" href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/trump-orders-air-chaos-across-america-in-shutdown-tantrum/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer" title="https://www.thedailybeast.com/trump-orders-air-chaos-across-america-in-shutdown-tantrum/">curbing air traffic</a> by 10 percent in 40 “<a onclick="_sendArticleBodyInlineLinkClickAnalytics('https://apnews.com/article/faa-government-shutdown-flight-cuts-airports-list-a11237fe6d6e14bed0935930dffed72e')" href="https://apnews.com/article/faa-government-shutdown-flight-cuts-airports-list-a11237fe6d6e14bed0935930dffed72e" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer" title="https://apnews.com/article/faa-government-shutdown-flight-cuts-airports-list-a11237fe6d6e14bed0935930dffed72e">high-traffic</a>” markets, including New York City, Boston, Los Angeles, and other major American cities.</p><p>The resignations also mean Americans can’t expect things to instantly return to normal once the shutdown ends, which is bad news for the upcoming holiday season. </p><p>“It will take us months to come out of all the impacts that it’s causing,” said Daniels. </p><p>Speaking to reporters at Reagan National Airport in Northern Virginia on Friday, Duffy acknowledged that the shutdown was weighing heavily on air traffic controllers who have gone unpaid since it began on Oct. 1.</p><figure><img data-chromatic="ignore" alt="U.S. Secretary of Transportation Sean Duffy gestures during a press conference on air traffic controller pay and the government shutdown at the U.S. Capitol on October 23, 2025 in Washington, DC." loading="lazy" src="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/SNMOVA72K5EIPMAZ2TOXYATXQM.jpg?auth=110726bf870d99f0bbf45c9a1aa50b0cac50195eb8eb3507ebaf23cfee8eea3c&amp;width=800&amp;height=450" srcset="https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/SNMOVA72K5EIPMAZ2TOXYATXQM.jpg?auth=110726bf870d99f0bbf45c9a1aa50b0cac50195eb8eb3507ebaf23cfee8eea3c&amp;width=274&amp;height=154 274w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/SNMOVA72K5EIPMAZ2TOXYATXQM.jpg?auth=110726bf870d99f0bbf45c9a1aa50b0cac50195eb8eb3507ebaf23cfee8eea3c&amp;width=400&amp;height=225 400w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/SNMOVA72K5EIPMAZ2TOXYATXQM.jpg?auth=110726bf870d99f0bbf45c9a1aa50b0cac50195eb8eb3507ebaf23cfee8eea3c&amp;width=768&amp;height=432 768w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/SNMOVA72K5EIPMAZ2TOXYATXQM.jpg?auth=110726bf870d99f0bbf45c9a1aa50b0cac50195eb8eb3507ebaf23cfee8eea3c&amp;width=1024&amp;height=576 1024w, https://www.thedailybeast.com/resizer/v2/SNMOVA72K5EIPMAZ2TOXYATXQM.jpg?auth=110726bf870d99f0bbf45c9a1aa50b0cac50195eb8eb3507ebaf23cfee8eea3c&amp;width=1440&amp;height=810 1440w" width="800" height="450"><figcaption><span>Transportation Secretary Sean Duffy has curbed air traffic across America to try and ease the burden on air traffic controllers. </span><span>Eric Lee/Getty Images </span></figcaption></figure><p>“Let’s not lie about the pressure,” he said. “The ones who do come to work, they’re the ones that are working six days a week, 10 hours a day. You can do that for a couple weeks, but at one point, you’re going to get burned out, and that’s what we’re seeing. Now, there’s a higher level of fatigue with the controllers.”</p><p>The government shutdown, <a onclick="_sendArticleBodyInlineLinkClickAnalytics('https://www.thedailybeast.com/donald-trump-breaks-own-record-for-longest-shutdown-in-history/')" href="https://www.thedailybeast.com/donald-trump-breaks-own-record-for-longest-shutdown-in-history/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer" title="https://www.thedailybeast.com/donald-trump-breaks-own-record-for-longest-shutdown-in-history/">the longest in history</a>, has stretched into its second month as senators refuse to negotiate on a government spending bill. Democrats have requested that Republicans include an extension of Affordable Care Act subsidies in the budget, and Republicans have refused to budge. </p></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ironclad – formally verified, real-time capable, Unix-like OS kernel (334 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ironclad-os.org/</link>
            <guid>45860843</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 23:03:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ironclad-os.org/">https://ironclad-os.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45860843">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://ironclad-os.org/: Error: getaddrinfo ENOTFOUND ironclad-os.org]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[IP Blocking the UK Is Not Enough to Comply with the Online Safety Act (290 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/</link>
            <guid>45860654</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 22:33:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/">https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45860654">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-28808">
		<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		
<p><em>A follow up to The <a href="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/10/16/the-ofcom-files/">Ofcom Files</a>.</em></p>



<h2>Some notes on Ofcom’s strategy to date.</h2>



<p>As many of you know, I represent the U.S. website 4chan, pro bono, in&nbsp;<a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/71209929/4chan-community-support-llc-v-uk-office-of-communications/">its U.S. federal lawsuit</a>&nbsp;against the UK’s communications regulator, Ofcom, together with my co-counsel Ron Coleman. The suit seeks to defend 4chan from the UK’s attempts to censor that website using the UK’s new Internet censorship law, the Online Safety Act.</p>



<p>What some of you may <em>not</em> know is that I have personally committed to defend, pro bono, any U.S. website which operates lawfully in the United States – no matter how large or small – against the UK’s attempts to infringe on the First Amendment.</p>



<p>And indeed, I am currently representing every single U.S. social-media enforcement target of the UK Online Safety Act, again pro bono,<em> </em>without exception. I will continue to do so until the Online Safety Act’s capacity to harm American citizens is destroyed, by America <a href="https://x.com/prestonjbyrne/status/1979579530344813000">enacting a shield law</a>.</p>



<p>This means, necessarily, taking on some of the most controversial sites on the web as one’s clients. One such client, a social media forum called “Sanctioned Suicide” or “SaSu,” has long been a target for Ofcom’s ire because of the subject matter that the site hosts – principally, it is a mental health webforum where suicidal people are allowed to discuss the most taboo subject of all taboo subjects, suicide itself, and how they plan to go about it.</p>



<p>To say that this site’s subject matter is controversial is an understatement; as a Catholic I freely admit I struggled at first with representing the site. SaSu, 4chan, Gab, and Kiwi Farms – the complete list of Ofcom’s U.S. enforcement targets to date – are some of the most unsympathetic websites in the world, from a political point of view.</p>



<p>This was, in my view, a deliberate strategy by Ofcom: pick the most radioactive free speech targets in the world, isolate them in confidential proceedings, punish them, and publicly shame them when you claim the fine notices or blocking orders as a win. The only way to counter that strategy is to ensure that no target goes without competent counsel, every target knows what Ofcom is trying to do, and every case will be fought like hell, in as public a fashion as possible. As Justice Brandeis said, “sunlight is the best disinfectant.”</p>



<p>The victory condition of the U.S. pushback against Ofcom is the successful defense of the First Amendment – all of the First Amendment. If we concede even a scintilla of our constitutional rights, we fail. If we let any target fight alone, we fail. If any censorship demand gets through our border, we fail.</p>



<p>That means we defend every site, however small or controversial it may be, from foreign attempts to infringe on their constitutional rights. It means not giving up so much as an inch of ground without a major fight, if those are the instructions. It means we must not ever lose.</p>



<p>We do this because the defense of any American is the defense of us all. </p>



<h2>The story of Ofcom v SaSu</h2>



<p>SaSu is a tiny forum which didn’t have much of an appetite for a fight. Accordingly, when Ofcom came calling at the end of February, SaSu more or less immediately IP blocked the entire UK in hopes of avoiding enforcement action. (Ofcom claims this occurred in July; it in fact occurred in May.)</p>



<p>And, for a time, this worked. Today, however, I can reveal that Ofcom has reversed its decision and is going after the site anyway.</p>



<p>Ofcom alleges that SaSu’s geo-block went down. </p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="739" height="294" data-attachment-id="28869" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/g5gcvchxyaaqmc5-1/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?fit=902%2C359&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="902,359" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?fit=300%2C119&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?fit=739%2C294&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?resize=739%2C294&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?w=902&amp;ssl=1 902w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?resize=300%2C119&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?resize=768%2C306&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5GCVChXYAAQmc5-1.png?resize=900%2C359&amp;ssl=1 900w" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>



<p>This is demonstrably false. The block has been consistently functional for months, and when Ofcom’s e-mail landed in my inbox, I went to check it myself by using my own VPN to access the Internet through a London IP (unlike UK policymakers, I know how to use one). Sure enough, SaSu’s nationwide site block prevented me from viewing the site.</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="739" height="183" data-attachment-id="28968" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11-43-30-am/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?fit=1856%2C460&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1856,460" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Screenshot 2025-11-07 at 11.43.30 AM" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?fit=300%2C74&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?fit=739%2C183&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=739%2C183&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=1024%2C254&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=300%2C74&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=768%2C190&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=1536%2C381&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=1200%2C297&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?resize=1088%2C270&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?w=1856&amp;ssl=1 1856w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/Screenshot-2025-11-07-at-11.43.30-AM.png?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>



<p>What appears to have happened is that SaSu had a site mirror and that someone figured out a way to hit the mirror – which was also subject to the geoblock, something which took me under a minute to personally confirm – without using a VPN.</p>



<p>This is possible for a range of reasons. The primary one is that the notion of a “UK based IP” is nonsense. Geolocation databases work by figuring out where people log in from and only after doing a lot of pattern recognition do those addresses get associated with that location. So there will be UK-based IPs that geolocate to Poland, for example, even though the end-user is sitting in the UK, because the database thinks that that IP address belongs in Poland.</p>



<p>What might have happened is that a third party, understanding this, could have found SaSu’s mirror, hit SaSu’s mirror with one of these IPs, and then handed the file off to the regulator as some kind of “gotcha” demonstrating that the IP geoblock was ineffective, and using the fact of the access plus the fact that there was a mirror URL to claim that SaSu was somehow trying to dishonestly mislead the regulator about its compliance with the OSA through geoblocking. (The reasons why SaSu had a mirror are SaSu’s alone/none of Ofcom’s fucking business; what it suffices to note is that both SaSu’s main site and the mirror blocked the UK.) If this is in fact what happened, it would have been a profoundly dishonest tactic by UK activists to try to bring down regulatory hellfire on a disfavored American company, and it merits a full parliamentary investigation (though, I won’t hold my breath waiting for that).</p>



<p>Ofcom, in reopening the investigation on the basis that the geoblock was down when the geoblock was in fact up, (1) reveals that it has no idea how the Internet works and (2) has made a pretty titanic mistake. Now it’ll either need to assert that the geoblock isn’t effective (when, for the most part, it is) or it’ll need to climb down (causing fury among the political constituencies which have so much power in Westminster that they forced the file to reopen in the first place).</p>



<p>What seems clear to me is that Ofcom needs a scalp to present to Ofcom’s political masters. It’s been decided that SaSu is it. SaSu is, arguably, the most important scapegoat that was used to justify the Online Safety Act. Web censorship advocates like the Molly Rose Foundation – one of the major NGO sponsors of the Online Safety Act – seemingly exist for the sole purpose of advocating for increasingly insane levels of censorship of the Internet for everyone in the UK, always pointing to a single target as the justification, and never calling for any solution other than mass censorship of the entire country.</p>



<p>That target is, and for years has been, SaSu. The NGOs in question refuse to name the site, ostensibly for harm reduction purposes, but this also prevents people from openly engaging with the issue and having an honest conversation about what the site is, what (American) legal protections it benefits from, and, therefore, what practical limitations there are on the UK trying to close it down, both now and when the UK was drafting and enacting the UK Online Safety Act. </p>



<p>The UK’s inability to have those honest conversations at the proper time is what is causing the Online Safety Act to, slowly but surely, fail as an international regulatory scheme. This habit also led the UK to enact the Online Safety Act instead of adopting other, less censorial, approaches to make the Internet a safer place, which were ignored.</p>



<p>Even today, aforementioned “Safety” NGO and others are using the simple fact of the SaSu’s existence to try to convince legislators that a nationwide <a href="https://x.com/moo9000/status/1981702036493393991">VPN ban</a> that applies to every one of the 69 million men, women, and children in the United Kingdom is necessary to end SaSu specifically – tantamount to using a thermonuclear bomb to swat a fly. Only three weeks ago, these groups called for the Prime Minister to open a parliamentary inquiry and wrote a <a href="https://mollyrosefoundation.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/MissedChancesLostLives.pdf">51-page report</a> seeking to apply additional pressure for retaliatory action and additional global censorship powers. SaSu was even <a href="https://www.the-independent.com/news/uk/home-news/keir-starmer-donald-trump-prime-minister-xi-jinping-truth-social-b2797406.html">mentioned by Keir Starmer</a>, albeit not by name, when he tried justifying the Online Safety Act to President Trump.</p>



<p>There was even direct political pressure put on Ofcom <a href="https://committees.parliament.uk/publications/50025/documents/269445/default/">by Parliament itself</a> on October 31st to do something about SaSu. </p>



<p>One could be forgiven for thinking that SaSu is the UK censorship-industrial complex’s favorite company, given how much they talk about it to practically anyone who will listen. In a way, it is the Online Safety Act’s necessary target: these organizations have spent years saying that the Online Safety Act was the required solution to a company like SaSu. If the Act fails to end it, the Act itself also fails. The credibility of the entire regime rests on beating this one website. </p>



<p>For this reason, SaSu was the very first site Ofcom targeted for enforcement action in February 2025, months before Ofcom went after 4chan or anyone else. When that happened, the UK censorship NGO sector clearly expected SaSu to get wiped off the face of the Earth. </p>



<p>But SaSu, rudely, <em>didn’t die</em>, a fact which makes the UK censorship-industrial apparatus incandescent. </p>



<p>The UK has no power to shut the site down, because t<strong>he site and its operators are in the United States, they are not violating U.S. law, and they are conducting themselves in a manner that is protected by the First Amendment</strong>.</p>



<p>So, it appears, as with 4chan, Ofcom has elected to proceed with a mock execution. Based on the fact that the nationwide IP block is still live, the precedent they want to set – the message they want to send – seems pretty clear to me: <strong>Geo-IP blocking the entire UK is no longer enough to comply with the Online Safety Act</strong>.</p>



<p>Ofcom is trying to set the precedent that no matter where you are in the world, and no matter how much you try to keep UK users off your site, Ofcom believes you have to follow its rules – even if you’re American and you’re engaged in constitutionally protected speech and conduct. To that end, Ofcom has <strong>renewed its previous threats of fines, arrest, and imprisonment, against SaSu and its operators – all Americans</strong>.</p>



<p>This is not what I expected. I had expected the UK, after encountering serious resistance to its extraterritorial expansion plans in the United States with 4chan’s refusal to comply, to start considering the merits of backing down. Instead, the UK is choosing to escalate, going after a target who the Online Safety Act’s political masters desperately want to, even <em>need </em>to, eradicate, even though that target made good-faith efforts to block the UK from its services.</p>



<p>Hate to spoil the party, but Ofcom will need to go try some other country’s websites to set that precedent. The UK is not going to be allowed to lay a finger on an American.</p>



<p>I reproduce relevant correspondence below. We have also sent this correspondence to the White House, both Houses of Congress, individuals spearheading legislative initiatives to erect <a href="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/10/18/the-granite-act-how-congress-can-strike-back-against-foreign-censors/">censorship shield laws</a> in four different states, and the nation’s leading free speech advocacy organizations.</p>



<h2>My message to Washington and state legislators</h2>



<p>Free speech test cases are rarely made in relation to popular speech. But we call them “test cases” for a reason: because they are the test of the boundaries, and their outcome determines the future trajectory of the law and human behavior.</p>



<p>The lesson from this correspondence is unmistakable: the UK thinks that anyone who refuses to adhere to its content rules, wherever they are based, is fair game for threats of fines and imprisonment, even if they try to wall themselves off from the UK with comprehensive blocks of UK IP addresses.</p>



<p>This includes every single person in the United States. Companies like SaSu are the canaries in the coal mine. Companies most of us use every day like Meta or X are next.</p>



<p>This problem is not going to go away. As we have seen with the <a href="https://x.com/SkyNews/status/1986319410244518258">escalating war of words between the UK and X</a>, which culminated in a British King’s Counsel putting X’s Head of Global Government Affairs through a Maoist-style <a href="https://x.com/ShipleyWrites/status/1986479109489226085">pro-Online Safety Act struggle session</a> at an inquiry hearing only yesterday, it is clear the United Kingdom – or, at least, the bunch of yahoos who currently run it – will not be content to allow any American to enjoy the full measure of their constitutional rights online, no matter how obscure the U.S. site in question may be.</p>



<p>See, e.g.:</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" decoding="async" width="739" height="949" data-attachment-id="28825" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/g5d2z4fwiaapirs/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?fit=750%2C963&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="750,963" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?fit=234%2C300&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?fit=739%2C949&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?resize=739%2C949&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?w=750&amp;ssl=1 750w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5D2Z4fWIAAPirs.jpg?resize=234%2C300&amp;ssl=1 234w" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>







<p>They will attempt to crush anyone who resists, even if that resistance is in the form of Americans doing everything in our power to block the entire UK from our services to try to get British censors off our backs. The UK is willing to punish and threaten American companies – large and small – and American citizens in order to set the precedent that the UK is in charge of America’s Internet.</p>



<p>Our government should not allow this to be done to any American, on principle. No American client of mine will ever bend to that sort of pressure. We need to act now to prevent our most valuable companies, and their hundreds of millions of American users, from being subjected to it.</p>



<p>These attempts to disrespect and override American sovereignty must be answered before the same thing is done to websites used by millions of other American citizens, when the UK inevitably turns its attention to the larger and more well-moderated services we all know and love, including all of our <a href="https://x.com/fttechnews/status/1984123722412810485">world-beating AI companies</a>.</p>



<p>In the final analysis, American citizens shouldn’t have to put up with this bullshit from foreigners. We fought, and won, many wars to secure our freedoms.</p>



<p>As I have been doing for nearly an entire year, I strongly urge the White House and Congress, and legislators in each of the fifty States, to intervene to protect the free speech of all American citizens.</p>



<h2>UPDATE, 7 NOVEMBER 2025</h2>



<p>Ofcom replied to our initial e-mail responding to their reopening this investigation (see first PDF at the bottom of this post) and this blog post as follows:</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="739" height="433" data-attachment-id="28987" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/g5lpgy9wqaifsm_/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?fit=2442%2C1432&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="2442,1432" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?fit=300%2C176&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?fit=739%2C433&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=739%2C433&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=1024%2C600&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=300%2C176&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=768%2C450&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=1536%2C901&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=2048%2C1201&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=1200%2C704&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?resize=1088%2C638&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?w=1478&amp;ssl=1 1478w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPgY9WQAIfSm_.jpg?w=2217&amp;ssl=1 2217w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>



<p>This e-mail is extraordinary: Ofcom didn’t like that I referred to its enforcement effort against SaSu as a coordinated, politically motivated hit, so it felt the need – <em>in correspondence to a target’s lawyer</em> – to specifically respond to the allegation and complain about the public defense of my client that I made in a blog post. </p>



<p>As to the blog post, we’ll deal with that in a second.</p>



<p>It’s pretty obviously a true statement that this investigation has a political dimension to it. </p>



<p>Putting aside, for a moment, the fact that a certain UK NGO – the country’s leading pro-censorship organization…</p>



<ul>
<li>kvetched to Parliament about this matter in September, </li>



<li>called for the Prime Minister to open an investigation into my client in October, and then </li>



<li>triggered the House of Lords’ Digital Committee to give Ofcom a written dressing-down repeating that NGO’s point of view,<em> verbatim,</em> <a href="https://www.parliament.uk/business/lords/media-centre/house-of-lords-media-notices/2025/october2025/lords-communications-committee-write-to-ofcom-to-flag-concerns-with-implementation-of-the-online-safety-act/">only last week</a>,</li>
</ul>



<p>…it remains true that Ofcom reopened the investigation to minor but noticeable press fanfare and – miraculously! – also had that very NGO extensively quoted in a <a href="https://www.mirror.co.uk/news/politics/major-update-online-suicide-forum-36204155">press drop</a> that landed a mere <strong>57 minutes</strong> after I received Ofcom’s message, followed up by prime morning TV spots for that UK NGO 14 hours later (approximately 8AM local time in London) – during which time the UK NGO called for my client to be fined, arrested, and prosecuted!</p>



<p>All for conduct that is perfectly lawful in the United States. Exhibit A:</p>



<figure></figure>



<p>If my client’s site is truly that dangerous to UK internet users, <strong>why did Ofcom wait two days preparing a press campaign instead of, oh, I dunno, calling us up and reporting any suspected “bugs” in the geo-block so that they can be patched?</strong></p>



<p>Particularly when the target was voluntarily doing so <em>already</em>?</p>



<p>The answer, in all probability, is that highly political pressure groups are working hand-in-glove with the UK’s public bodies, Parliament and others, to try to show that the OSA can be successfully wielded against all those pesky Americans who won’t just be sensible and surrender our rights simply because a bunch of censors in the UK ordered us to.</p>



<p>Interesting how Ofcom treats investigations as confidential every time they get a FOIA request or a request for comment from a journalist, but not, apparently, when Parliament wants a prominent American scalp and they need to coordinate with friendly media and pro-censorship groups.</p>



<p>Approaching the matter from this perspective, I replied to Ofcom as follows:</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="739" height="331" data-attachment-id="28993" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/g5lphj0xsaaqcqh/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?fit=1066%2C478&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1066,478" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?fit=300%2C135&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?fit=739%2C331&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?resize=739%2C331&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?resize=1024%2C459&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?resize=300%2C135&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?resize=768%2C344&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LPhJ0XsAAqcQH.png?w=1066&amp;ssl=1 1066w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>



<p>As to the blog post, it occurred to me I forgot to clear up the record on that so I added the following:</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="739" height="284" data-attachment-id="28995" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/g5lfc7ewwae9yui/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?fit=1510%2C580&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1510,580" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?fit=300%2C115&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?fit=739%2C284&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?resize=739%2C284&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?resize=1024%2C393&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?resize=300%2C115&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?resize=768%2C295&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?resize=1200%2C461&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?resize=1088%2C418&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5LfC7EWwAE9YUi.png?w=1510&amp;ssl=1 1510w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>







<p>Ofcom then issued its own response, in public:</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?ssl=1"><img data-recalc-dims="1" loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="739" height="461" data-attachment-id="28996" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2025/11/06/the-ofcom-files-part-2-ip-blocking-the-uk-is-not-enough-to-comply-with-the-online-safety-act/g5mzmhbwuaasou2/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?fit=900%2C562&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="900,562" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="G5MzmhbWUAASoU2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?fit=300%2C187&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?fit=739%2C461&amp;ssl=1" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?resize=739%2C461&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?w=900&amp;ssl=1 900w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?resize=300%2C187&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/G5MzmhbWUAASoU2.png?resize=768%2C480&amp;ssl=1 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px"></a></figure>



<p>Utterly extraordinary. Let me explain what probably happened here.</p>



<p>The UK regulator has now publicly confirmed that the “mirror” site for my client’s site is not accessible in the UK. This, of course, has been the case all along, as I verified within ten minutes of receiving Ofcom’s email on Thursday afternoon. I’m not sure what, exactly, happened here, but I am advised that both mirror and the base site in this case were both covered by the IP block at all times. </p>



<p>If I had to guess, it’s that some NGO found some UK-based IP addresses which weren’t captured by the block because they weren’t properly geolocated. They probably then assembled a dossier and reported this to the UK regulator, and the UK regulator, under pressure from its political masters in Westminster, decided to do a rush job on enforcement and drive a truck through a hole that can be measured in micrometers, betting no one would be willing to publicly defend what is, arguably, the most controversial lawful website on the planet.</p>



<p>They bet wrong.</p>



<p>And the fact that Ofcom felt the need to put up a corrective press release 36 hours after the start of the reopened “investigation,” and a mere 72 hours (max) after getting a tip from the Samaritans? They’re not treating this like a law enforcement investigation, where they’d take their time and make sure they got it right.</p>



<p>They’re definitely not treating it like a public safety matter, where they know how to reach us and know that I generally respond within the hour.  </p>



<p>When you’re doing advance leaks to the press and rushing out statements to rebut your critics in real time, you’re not running a public safety operation. Ofcom is running a media campaign to defend the credibility of the Online Safety Act project.</p>



<p>At the end of the day, the IP block doesn’t really matter: my client has that block up to minimize hassle from aggressive foreign regulators and to keep their spam out of its inbox, not because it has any legal obligation to give a single solitary fuck about what an unelected British bureaucrat tells it to do.</p>



<p>Ofcom doesn’t have the legal power to order around my dog in the United States. It certainly doesn’t have the legal power to order around American citizens.</p>



<p><strong>I hope Washington, D.C. sees this and understands that this bullshit is what awaits every American Internet company, including Meta and X, if the United States doesn’t put a stop to this now.</strong> </p>



<p>Ultimately, what Ofcom is doing here is the perfect modern-day lesson lesson for why the First Amendment exists in the first place. A British regulator is threatening Americans in order to censor them, on pain of jail time, using only the flimsiest of excuses and immense, overbroad, and highly discretionary enforcement powers, to please politicians.</p>



<p>America and the UK fought a war over this. UK regulators doing this to Americans for doing nothing other than lawfully exercising their constitutional rights is not a situation the United States should ever accept.</p>



<div><p>I call upon the Trump Administration to use all available trade levers to put this misbehavior to an end, and upon the U.S. Congress to enact a foreign censorship shield law.</p><p>—</p></div>
























			</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->

			<!-- .entry-auhtor -->
		</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I want you to understand Chicago (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aphyr.com/posts</link>
            <guid>45859840</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 08 Nov 2025 20:49:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts">https://aphyr.com/posts</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45859840">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>I want you to understand what it is to live in Chicago.</p>


<p>Every day my phone buzzes. It is a neighborhood group: four people were
kidnapped at the corner drugstore. A friend a mile away sends a Slack message:
she was at the scene when masked men assaulted and abducted two people on the
street. A plumber working on my pipes is distraught, and I find out that two of his
employees were kidnapped that morning. A week later it happens again.</p>


<p>An email arrives. Agents with guns <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/immigration/2025/11/05/daycare-teacher-taken-by-ice-north-side-immigration">have chased a teacher</a> into the school where she
works. They did not have a warrant. They dragged her away, ignoring her and her colleagues’ pleas to show proof of her documentation. That evening I stand a few feet from the parents of Rayito de Sol and listen to them describe, with anguish, how good
Ms. Diana was to their children. What it is like to have <a href="https://ca.news.yahoo.com/video-shows-ice-agents-grabbing-202310296.html">strangers with guns
traumatize your
kids</a>.
For a teacher to hide a three-year-old child <a href="https://www.chalkbeat.org/chicago/2025/11/05/daycare-worker-pulled-out-of-school-by-armed-federal-agents-traumatizing-parents-say/">for fear they might be
killed</a>.
How their relatives will no longer leave the house. I hear the pain and fury in
their voices, and I wonder who will be next.</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/397-i-want-you-to-understand-chicago">Continue reading (1592 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p><em>If this were one person, I wouldn’t write this publicly. Since there are apparently multiple people on board, and they claim to be looking for investors, I think the balance falls in favor of disclosure.</em></p>
<p>Last week Prothean Systems <a href="https://www.facebook.com/reel/2528744020845660">announced they’d surpassed AGI</a> and <a href="https://www.beprothean.org/TECHNICAL_WHITE_PAPER#9-conclusion">called for the research community</a> to “verify, critique, extend, and improve upon” their work. Unfortunately, Prothean Systems has not published the repository they say researchers should use to verify their claims. However, based on their posts, web site, and public GitHub repositories, I can offer a few basic critiques.</p>

              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/396-notes-on-prothean-ai">Continue reading (1341 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>A few months back I wound up concluding, <a href="https://blog.woof.group/announcements/updates-on-the-osa">based on conversations with Ofcom</a>, that aphyr.com might be illegal in the UK due to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Online_Safety_Act_2023">UK Online Safety Act</a>. I wrote <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/379-geoblocking-the-uk-with-debian-nginx">a short tutorial</a> on geoblocking a single country using Nginx on Debian.</p>


<p>Now Mississippi’s 2024 HB 1126 has made it illegal for essentially any web site to know a user’s e-mail address, or other “personal identifying information”, unless that site also takes steps to "verify the age of the person creating an account”. Bluesky <a href="https://bsky.social/about/blog/08-22-2025-mississippi-hb1126">wound up geoblocking Mississippi</a>. Over on a small forum I help run, we paid our lawyers to look into HB 1126, and the conclusion was that we were <a href="https://blog.woof.group/announcements/woof-group-will-block-mississippi">likely in the same boat</a>. Collecting email addresses put us in scope of the bill, and it wasn’t clear whether the LLC would shield officers (hi) from personal liability.</p>


<p>This blog has the same problem: people use email addresses to post and confirm their comments. I think my personal blog is probably at low risk, but a.) I’d like to draw attention to this legislation, and b.) my risk is elevated by being gay online, and having written and called a whole bunch of Mississippi legislators about HB 1126. Long story short, I’d like to block both a country <em>and</em> an individual state. Here’s how:</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/395-geoblocking-multiple-localities-with-nginx">Continue reading (536 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>In the hopes that it saves someone else two hours later: the ISP <a href="https://www.astound.com/">Astound</a> only supports IPv6 in Washington State. You might find <a href="https://www.astound.com/support/internet/symmetrical/">this page</a> which says “Astound supports IPv6 in most locations”. Their tech support agents might tell you that they support v6 on your connection, even if you are not in Washington. “Yes, we do support both DHCPv6 and SLAAC”, they might say, and tell you to use a prefix delegation size of 60. If you are staring at <code>tcpdump</code> and wondering why you’re not seeing anything coming back from your router’s plaintive requests for address information, it is because they do not, in fact, support v6 anywhere but Washington.</p>


              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/390-astound-supports-ipv6-only-in-washington">Continue reading (112 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>In my free time, I help run a small Mastodon server for roughly six hundred queer leatherfolk. When a new member signs up, we require them to write a short application—just a sentence or two. There’s a small text box in the signup form which says:</p>


<blockquote>
<p>Please tell us a bit about yourself and your connection to queer leather/kink/BDSM. What kind of play or gear gets you going?</p>
</blockquote>


<p>This serves a few purposes. First, it maintains community focus. Before this question, we were flooded with signups from straight, vanilla people who wandered in to the bar (so to speak), and that made things a little awkward. Second, the application establishes a baseline for people willing and able to read text. This helps in getting people to follow server policy and talk to moderators when needed. Finally, it is <em>remarkably</em> effective at keeping out spammers. In almost six years of operation, we’ve had only a handful of spam accounts.</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/389-the-future-of-forums-is-lies-i-guess">Continue reading (1995 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>I’ve been involved in content moderation since roughly 2004. I’ve built spam prevention for corporate and personal e-mail, moderated open-source mailing lists and IRC channels, worked at a couple social media networks, and help moderate a Mastodon instance for a few hundred people. In the last few years I’ve wasted more time fighting blog comment spam, and I’m pretty sure Large Language Models (LLMs) are to blame.</p>


<p>I think of spam as a space with multiple equilibria. Producing spam takes work. Spammers are willing to invest that work because each message has a small chance to make money, or achieve political or emotional goals. Some spam, like the endless identical Viagra scams in my email spam folder, or the PHPBB comment spam I filter out here on aphyr.com, is cheap to generate and easy to catch. I assume the spammers make it up in volume. Other spam, like <a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/spear-phishing">spear phishing attacks</a>, is highly time-consuming: the spammer must identify a target, carefully craft a plausible message using, say, the identity of the target’s co-workers, or construct a facade of a bank’s log-in page, and so on. This kind of spam is more likely to make it through filters, but because it takes a lot of human work, is generally only worth it for high-value targets.</p>


<p>LLMs seem to be changing these equilibria. Over the last year I’ve seen a new class of comment spam, using what I’m fairly sure is LLM-generated text. These comments make specific, plausible remarks about the contents of posts and images, and work in a link to some web site or mention a product. Take this one I caught a few months back:</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/388-the-future-of-comments-is-lies-i-guess">Continue reading (1075 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p><em>Update, 2025-05-22: TrueNAS was kind enough to reach out and let me know that their support process does not normally incorporate LLMs. They’re talking about what happened internally, and intend to prevent it from happening again through improved documentation and reviewing the support process as a whole. I’m happy to hear it!</em></p>


<p><a href="https://www.truenas.com/">TrueNAS</a> makes file servers, also known as Network Attached Storage (NAS). I bought one of their smaller boxes to house backups, and it’s a great little NAS. For many years TrueNAS sold boxes with a BSD-based operating system, but in the last few years they’ve released a new, Linux-backed operating system called <a href="https://www.truenas.com/truenas-scale/">TrueNAS SCALE</a>, also called “Community Edition”. I was considering migrating to TrueNAS SCALE, but the docs <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20250408163343/https://www.truenas.com/docs/scale/gettingstarted/migrate/migrate-community/">started off with this warning</a>:</p>


<blockquote>
<p>TrueNAS Enterprise customers should consult with TrueNAS Enterprise Support before attempting migrate.</p>
<p>The process requires an extended maintenance window, requires executing steps in the correct order to prevent issues with system configuration and operation, and additional system review post-migration to catch and correct any configuration issues.</p>
</blockquote>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/387-the-future-of-customer-support-is-lies-i-guess">Continue reading (1153 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p><em>Update, 2023-05-23: Added a paragraph about Dr. Howard Whiteman’s non-existent quote.</em></p>


<p><em>I subscribe to the Chicago Sun-Times, a non-profit newspaper. This week they sent me a sixty-four page special insert, branded with the Chicago Sun-Times logo, full of LLM nonsense. Yesterday I wrote the following letter to the Chicago Sun-Times. That evening, they published <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/news/2025/05/20/syndicated-content-sunday-print-sun-times-ai-misinformation">this followup</a>.</em></p>


<p>Dear Mr. Buscaglia and the Chicago Sun-Times,</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/386-the-future-of-newspapers-is-lies-i-guess">Continue reading (582 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>Back in 2023 I went through an inter-state move with <a href="https://www.flatrate.com/moving/">Flat Rate Movers,
LTD.</a>, a.k.a. Flat Rate Moving, US DOT 488466, MC 254356. They bungled the job, damaged my stuff
and my house, and then refused to talk to me or their own insurance company. I
placed dozens of calls, wrote letters, emails, nothing worked. I finally got
some money for the damage by working with their insurer directly. I know a lot
of folks struggle with moving companies, and figured I’d write up a bit of this
story in case it helps. You can <a href="#finding-their-insurance">skip ahead</a> if you
just want to know about the FMCSA insurer database.</p>


<p>In November 2022 I scheduled the move with Flat Rate. We took a detailed video
inventory of everything to be moved. I paid over $14,000 for an “all inclusive
move”, which, per the move plan, included full packing services, blankets for furniture, boxes for electronics, lamps, and bicycles, a custom crate for a tabletop, and “extended valuation coverage”—their insurance policy.</p>


<p>A few days before the move in March 2023, Flat Rate called to tell me a
five-person team would arrive. When the crew arrived, it wasn’t Flat Rate. It
was a team of two from <a href="https://www.esquiremoving.com/">Esquire Moving Inc</a> (US DOT 2820253, MC 940499). They had
no idea they were supposed to provide packing services. The crate I paid for was nowhere to be found. They didn’t have enough boxes or blankets. I had to have everything out that day, so
there wasn’t any choice—I worked alongside the team for thirteen hours to
complete the packing and move-out.</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/381-when-flat-rate-movers-wont-answer-your-calls">Continue reading (1108 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p><em>Submitted to the Department of State, which is <a href="https://www.federalregister.gov/documents/2025/02/18/2025-02696/30-day-notice-of-proposed-information-collection-application-for-a-us-passport-for-eligible">requesting comments</a> on a proposed change which would align US passport gender markers with <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/01/defending-women-from-gender-ideology-extremism-and-restoring-biological-truth-to-the-federal-government/">executive order 14168</a>.</em></p>


<p>Executive order 14168 is biologically incoherent and socially cruel. All passport applicants should be allowed to select whatever gender markers they feel best fit, including M, F, or X.</p>


<p>In humans, neither sex nor gender is binary at any level. There are several possible arrangements of sex chromosomes: X, XX, XY, XXY, XYY, XXX, tetrasomies, pentasomies, etc. A single person can contain a mosaic of cells with different genetics: some XX, some XYY. Chromosomes may not align with genitalia: people with XY chromosomes may have a vulva and internal testes. People with XY chromosomes and a small penis may be surgically and socially reassigned female at birth—and never told what happened. None of these biological dimensions necessarily align with one’s internal concept of gender, or one’s social presentation.</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/380-comments-on-executive-order-14168">Continue reading (394 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>A few quick notes for other folks who are <a href="https://geoblockthe.uk/">geoblocking the UK</a>. I just set up a basic geoblock with Nginx on Debian. This is all stuff you can piece together, but the Maxmind and Nginx docs are a little vague about the details, so I figure it’s worth an actual writeup. My Nginx expertise is ~15 years out of date, so this might not be The Best Way to do things. YMMV.</p>


<p>First, register for a free <a href="https://www.maxmind.com/en/geolite2/signup">MaxMind account</a>; you’ll need this to subscribe to their GeoIP database. Then set up a daemon to maintain a copy of the lookup file locally, and Nginx’s GeoIP2 module:</p>


<pre><code><span></span>apt install geoipupdate libnginx-mod-http-geoip2
</code></pre>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/379-geoblocking-the-uk-with-debian-nginx">Continue reading (412 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  
    <article>
        

        <div>
          
            
              <p>This is not at all news, but it comes up often enough that I think there should be a concise explanation of the problem. People, myself included, like to say that POSIX time, also known as Unix time, is the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Global_Objects/Date">number</a> <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/manual/html_node/Seconds-since-the-Epoch.html">of</a> <a href="https://man7.org/linux/man-pages/man2/time.2.html">seconds</a> <a href="https://pkg.go.dev/time#Unix">since</a> <a href="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.4/en/datetime.html">the</a> <a href="https://ruby-doc.org/core-3.0.0/Time.html">Unix</a> <a href="https://docs.datastax.com/en/cql-oss/3.x/cql/cql_reference/timestamp_type_r.html">epoch</a>, which was 1970-01-01 at 00:00:00.</p>


<p>This is not true. Or rather, it isn’t true in the sense most people think. For example, it is presently 2024-12-25 at 18:51:26 UTC. The POSIX time is 1735152686. It has been 1735152713 seconds since the POSIX epoch. The POSIX time number is twenty-seven seconds lower.</p>


<p>This is because POSIX time is derived <a href="https://nvlpubs.nist.gov/nistpubs/Legacy/FIPS/fipspub151-1.pdf">in IEEE 1003.1</a> from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Coordinated_Universal_Time">Coordinated Universal Time</a>. The standard assumes that every day is exactly 86,400 seconds long. Specifically:</p>
              <p>
              <a href="https://aphyr.com/posts/378-seconds-since-the-epoch">Continue reading (899 words)</a></p>
            
          
        </div>
    </article>
  

  <p>
    <nav class="page"><a href="https://aphyr.com/posts?page=1">Next</a></nav>
  </p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>