<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 14:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Email They Shouldn't Have Read (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/10/08/the-email-they-shouldnt-have-read/</link>
            <guid>45515657</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 12:56:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/10/08/the-email-they-shouldnt-have-read/">https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/10/08/the-email-they-shouldnt-have-read/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45515657">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" itemprop="articleBody"><p><strong>Author's Note:</strong> Before we begin, an important clarification. What follows is a horror story based on real events from my career. However, to protect the privacy of the people and companies involved, I have deliberately mixed things up: technologies, contexts, and specific details have been modified or merged with other experiences. I therefore invite you to read this story not as a strict chronicle of a single event, but as an archetype of a widespread problem in the IT world: vendor lock-in and predatory business practices. Any attempt to identify the specific company or software described would lead to an incorrect conclusion.</p><hr><p>When the phone rang, I was in a meeting - so I didn’t answer. But I recognized the number and sent a quick message: </p><blockquote><p>"I’m with a client right now. If it’s not urgent, please send me an email - otherwise I’ll call you ASAP".</p></blockquote><p>The reply, via SMS, left me speechless: </p><blockquote><p>"That’s exactly the problem. I can’t send you an email. Call me as soon as you can".</p></blockquote><p>From that moment on, my perception of a certain kind of world changed forever.</p><hr><p>A few years earlier, a major public institution - let’s call it <em>Agency A</em> - was still running an ancient Exchange mail server. It hadn’t received security updates for ages, the anti-spam was completely ineffective, and the new regulations were clear: embrace Open Source solutions whenever possible.</p><p>They had already received a proposal - expensive but seemingly reasonable - for a managed service, hosted by an external provider, built on an open source mail stack. The company offered a managed version with its own proprietary additions and enterprise support. The catch? The price was absurd, and <em>Agency A</em> already had solid infrastructure - reputable IP classes, redundant datacenters, everything working fine. We had built and maintained that environment for years, and it was still running perfectly.</p><p>The request was simple: <em>“Evaluate this solution, and if it’s suitable, we’ll migrate.”</em>. About 500 active mailboxes, roughly the same number of aliases. Manageable, but far from trivial.</p><p>So I started experimenting. I had heard of that stack before but never used it directly. I deployed it in some non-critical environments - ours, and a few test clients who agreed to try it at a discounted rate. Everything worked flawlessly for almost a year. I began to appreciate its design and flexibility. Confident, I told <em>Agency A</em> we could proceed with a pilot migration.</p><p>We built a new server, deployed the stack, and assigned a few secondary domains for early adopters. The feedback was great - so good that users started pushing for a full migration.<br> The IT team planned carefully: created accounts and aliases, migrated selected mailboxes, and kept the old Exchange server online (hidden, for legacy access).</p><p>The morning after the MX switch I was tense, waiting for trouble - but it never came. A couple of small questions, nothing serious. The internal team handled everything perfectly. It was a success.</p><hr><p>Word spread quickly.</p><p><em>Agency B</em> - smaller, but in some ways more influential - contacted me. They were customers of the same managed-service company that had pitched to <em>Agency A</em>. Once they saw the potential savings (at less than a tenth of the annual cost), the stability, and the freedom of keeping their data on their own servers, they became very interested. Their contract, however, was a five-year deal with automatic renewal - two years left. The legal office said the notice period was six months, so there was time.</p><p>They wanted to prepare silently. Their supplier was known for <em>aggressive commercial behavior</em> and often retaliated when customers tried to leave. So we built everything quietly - users, aliases, test setups - and froze the system, waiting for the official termination notice.</p><p>That day finally came. The notice was sent, about eight months before expiration. Migration would begin upon confirmation of receipt - or the following month at the latest.</p><p>Meanwhile, I learned that <em>Agency C</em> - another institution - was also planning to leave the same provider. They wanted to keep the same software stack for consistency, so I told them about our experience. They asked for a quote, which I prepared (without mentioning <em>Agency B</em>, of course). My margin would have been small, but the project made sense: it was about <em>owning your data</em>, not making money.</p><p>Everything seemed to move smoothly - until that SMS.</p><hr><p>I called back immediately.</p><blockquote><p>"There’s been a problem with the termination" said the IT manager of <em>Agency B</em>.<br> "Somehow they found out what we were doing. There are hidden clauses we didn’t know about, and now we can’t leave - at least not for another five years. They know everything. Even your quote.".</p></blockquote><p>I was stunned. How could they possibly know?</p><p>Minutes later, my phone rang again - <em>Agency C</em> this time. </p><blockquote><p>"Forget the proposal", they said. "They called us. Threatened us, actually. They even mentioned your name and said they might take legal action against you for unfair competition - claiming they’re the only <em>‘authorized’</em> installers of that software. Which is absurd, of course. It’s open source. But our director doesn’t want trouble.".</p></blockquote><p>Sometimes, when public money is involved, people prefer avoiding troubles over doing what’s right.</p><hr><p>Something didn’t add up.<br> Then someone at <em>Agency C</em> noticed a clue: a former interim IT manager still had an email client connected via token authentication - with access to all messages. And that person had signed the original contract with the provider years before. Informally questioned, he admitted contacting them "to warn them" but claimed it was harmless. He never mentioned me - supposedly.</p><p>That still didn’t explain how they knew about <em>Agency B</em>’s internal steps. To test a theory, we set a trap: I asked a friend abroad to send <em>Agency B</em> a fake quote, from a company outside the EU.<br> The following Monday, the provider called <em>Agency B</em> and said, "We advise against working with non-EU companies - compliance can get tricky.".</p><p>That strongly suggested it: <strong>it looked as if they might have been reading the emails.</strong></p><p>The IT manager exploded and confronted them. The response was chilling: </p><blockquote><p>"I’m not saying we do - but we could. It’s in the contract. You should read the fine print, especially the unilateral amendment from two years ago.".</p></blockquote><p>That amendment, quietly accepted, included horrifying clauses:<br> - notice period extended from 6 to 12 months<br> - formerly free services could become paid at the provider’s discretion<br> - and, "for security reasons", they could disable any access other than the webmail - which they promptly did.</p><p>All of this happened before the GDPR era, when certain practices could still slip through.</p><hr><p>I tried to contact the company’s owner directly - no reply. Calls, emails, nothing. Their support lines were "not authorized to forward requests". I wanted to confront them about the <em>“not accredited”</em> nonsense and the so-called <em>unfair competition</em>. But bullies never like a fair conversation.</p><p>I urged <em>Agency B</em> and <em>C</em> to investigate - not only legally, but ethically.<br> They were horrified, yes - but in the end, nothing changed.<br> Worse: the provider, invoking that same contract amendment, made previously free features paid ones, increasing their costs by another 30%.<br> Management wasn’t outraged by the abuse - just by the extra expense, "hard to justify in the budget".</p><hr><p>Years later, those directors were gone. The technical staff remained - older, wiser, and determined not to repeat the mistake. They eventually switched providers, though to something "safer", not necessarily better.</p><p>I couldn’t solve that problem. The battle had to come from them, and I would have supported them all the way - not for profit, but for principle.<br> Because when a company that claims to <em>“support open source”</em> behaves like that, we all lose.<br> We all get labeled the same way.</p><p>And that’s the real horror of the story - not the software, but what people do with it.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2025 (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/</link>
            <guid>45514164</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 09:49:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/">https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45514164">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Synology Reverses Policy Banning Third-Party HDDs After NAS Sales Plummet (659 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.guru3d.com/story/synology-reverses-policy-banning-thirdparty-hdds-after-nas-sales-plummet/</link>
            <guid>45513485</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 08:19:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.guru3d.com/story/synology-reverses-policy-banning-thirdparty-hdds-after-nas-sales-plummet/">https://www.guru3d.com/story/synology-reverses-policy-banning-thirdparty-hdds-after-nas-sales-plummet/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45513485">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article itemprop="articleBody">
                                <div>
                                    
                        <!-- Contentteller Template: publish_teaser_image -->
                        <p><img src="https://www.guru3d.com/data/teaser/226/8042eeca5148cf31ca512f2f80ee2eb8dbb74a/2025-10-08_09_05_51-guru3d.webp" alt="teaser"></p><p>Synology has backtracked on one of its most unpopular decisions in years. After seeing NAS sales plummet in 2025, the company has decided to lift restrictions that forced users to buy its own Synology hard drives. The policy, introduced earlier this year, made third-party HDDs from brands like Seagate and WD practically unusable in newer models such as the DS925+, DS1825+, and DS425+.

That change didn’t go over well. Users immediately criticised Synology for trying to lock them into buying its much more expensive drives. Many simply refused to upgrade, and reviewers called out the move as greedy and shortsighted. According to some reports, sales of Synology’s 2025 NAS models dropped sharply in the months after the restriction was introduced.
                                    </p><p>Now, with the release of <strong>DSM 7.3</strong>, Synology has quietly walked the policy back. Third-party hard drives and <strong>2.5-inch SATA SSDs</strong> can once again be used without triggering warning messages or reduced functionality. Drives from Seagate, WD, and others will work exactly as they did before—complete with full monitoring, alerts, and storage features.</p>
<p>For users, this means more choice and lower costs when building or upgrading a NAS. For Synology, it’s a much-needed course correction after months of backlash. While the company hasn’t publicly admitted fault, it’s clear that sales pressure and community outrage played a major role in reversing the decision.</p>
<p>Critics say the entire episode has damaged Synology’s reputation. The company seemed to believe that after QNAP’s well-known ransomware troubles, it could tighten control of the market without losing customers. Instead, the plan backfired—hard. Many loyal users have since turned to alternative brands or expressed hesitation about buying another Synology product.</p>

<p>Still, the return of open drive support is good news for anyone running a Synology NAS. It restores the flexibility that made the brand so popular in the first place. Whether this move is enough to win back frustrated users remains to be seen, but for now, DSM 7.3 brings a welcome dose of freedom back to the platform.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.guru3d.com/data/publish/226/8042eeca5148cf31ca512f2f80ee2eb8dbb74a/7846uhj.webp" target="_top"><img src="https://www.guru3d.com/data/publish/226/8042eeca5148cf31ca512f2f80ee2eb8dbb74a/7846uhj.webp" alt="7846uhj"></a></p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.synology.com/en-global/releaseNote/DSM" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Synology </a>/ <a href="https://nascompares.com/2025/10/07/synology-support-seagate-wd-again-too-little-too-late" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">nascompares</a></p>
                                </div>
                            </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Without data centers, GDP growth was 0.1% in the first half of 2025 (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2025/10/07/data-centers-gdp-growth-zero-first-half-2025-jason-furman-harvard-economist/</link>
            <guid>45512317</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 05:13:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/10/07/data-centers-gdp-growth-zero-first-half-2025-jason-furman-harvard-economist/">https://fortune.com/2025/10/07/data-centers-gdp-growth-zero-first-half-2025-jason-furman-harvard-economist/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45512317">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>U.S. GDP growth in the first half of 2025 was almost entirely driven by investment in data centers and information processing technology, according to <a href="https://www.hks.harvard.edu/faculty/jason-furman" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.hks.harvard.edu/faculty/jason-furman">Harvard economist Jason Furman</a>. Excluding these technology-related categories, Furman <a href="https://x.com/jasonfurman/status/1971995367202775284" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://x.com/jasonfurman/status/1971995367202775284">calculated in a Sept. 27 post on X.com</a> GDP growth would have been just 0.1% on an annualized basis, a near standstill that underlines the increasingly pivotal role of high-tech infrastructure in shaping macroeconomic outcomes.<a href="https://www.cmacrodev.com/the-global-economy-is-on-a-two-way-track/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.cmacrodev.com/the-global-economy-is-on-a-two-way-track/"></a></p><div>



<div><p>Furman’s findings, shared online and echoed by financial analysts including Robert Armstrong of the <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802"><em>Financial Times</em>‘ Unhedged</a> (the same writer who coined the term “TACO trade’), echo <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/08/06/data-center-artificial-intelligence-bubble-consumer-spending-economy/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/08/06/data-center-artificial-intelligence-bubble-consumer-spending-economy/">several months of observations</a> on the remarkable surge in data-center infrastructure. In August, Renaissance Macro Research estimated, to date in 2025, the dollar value contributed to GDP growth by AI data-center buildout had surpassed U.S. consumer spending for the first time ever. That’s remarkable considering <a href="https://www.congress.gov/crs-product/IF11657" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.congress.gov/crs-product/IF11657">consumer spending is two-thirds of GDP</a>.<a href="https://x.com/AllVentured/status/1951770496711934459" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://x.com/AllVentured/status/1951770496711934459"></a></p><p>Technically, as Furman notes, investment in information-processing equipment and software was only 4% of U.S. GDP for the first half of 2025, yet it also accounted for fully 92% of GDP growth over that period. Furman added it’s probably not the case the U.S. economy would have recorded almost no expansion at all absent this buildout, reasoning that “absent the AI boom we would probably have lower interest rates [and] electricity prices, thus some additional growth in other sectors. In very rough terms that could maybe make up about half of what we got from the AI boom.” But still, it’s big.<a href="https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802"></a></p></div><p>Tech giants such as <a href="https://fortune.com/company/microsoft/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/microsoft/">Microsoft</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/alphabet/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/alphabet/">Google</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/">Amazon</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/facebook/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/facebook/">Meta</a>, and <a href="https://fortune.com/company/nvidia/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/nvidia/">Nvidia</a> have poured tens of billions of dollars into building and upgrading data centers, responding to explosive demand for artificial intelligence and large language models that require massive computing resources. 



</p><p>Lisa Shallet, chief investment officer for <a href="https://fortune.com/company/morgan-stanley/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/morgan-stanley/">Morgan Stanley</a> Wealth Management, flagged on Sept. 29 that spending was truly massive among the so-called “hyperscalers” who are striving for huge computing, storage and networking capacity. 



</p><p>“In recent years, hyperscaler capex on data center and related items has risen fourfold and is nearing $400 billion annually,” she wrote. “The speed of growth and size of the investment are skewing its aggregate economic impact, with the top 10 spenders accounting for nearly a third of all spending … For perspective, it’s estimated that data center-linked spending is adding roughly 100 basis points to U.S. real GDP growth.”</p><p><img alt="" loading="lazy" width="764" height="426" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 60vw, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1200px) 33vw" srcset="https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=128&amp;q=85 128w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=256&amp;q=85 256w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=320&amp;q=85 320w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=384&amp;q=85 384w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=480&amp;q=85 480w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=576&amp;q=85 576w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=768&amp;q=85 768w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1024&amp;q=85 1024w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1280&amp;q=85 1280w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1440&amp;q=85 1440w" src="https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1440&amp;q=85"></p>



<h2>The ‘mystery’ of the economy</h2>



<p>This surge in technology-led growth comes against a backdrop of wider economic sluggishness and paradoxically strong GDP growth. Job creation has slowed, raising concerns that, absent technology investment, the U.S. economy could have slipped into recession. <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/spending-ai-data-centers-massive-150110727.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://finance.yahoo.com/news/spending-ai-data-centers-massive-150110727.html"></a>Other sectors—from manufacturing and real estate to retail and services—contributed little or even detracted from overall output in the first half of 2025. 



</p><p>And yet, as <a href="https://fortune.com/company/apollo-global-management/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/apollo-global-management/">Apollo Global Management</a> Chief Economist Torsten Sløk has noted, the <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/10/01/us-economy-getting-stronger-not-weaker-apollo-torsten-slok-growth-gdp-spending-jobs/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/10/01/us-economy-getting-stronger-not-weaker-apollo-torsten-slok-growth-gdp-spending-jobs/">GDP figures speak of a (statistically) strong economy</a>. 



</p><p>“The consensus has been wrong since January,” Sløk said in a note circulated to clients in early October, adding the average of economists’ forecasts has said the U.S. economy would slow down for nine months consecutively. “But the reality is that it has simply not happened … We in the economics profession need to look ourselves in the mirror.”



</p><p>Furman’s analysis adds to the snarky and accurate observation by <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/17/style/today-in-tabs-rusty-foster-media-gossip-maine.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/17/style/today-in-tabs-rusty-foster-media-gossip-maine.html">Rusty Foster</a> of&nbsp;<em><a href="https://www.todayintabs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.todayintabs.com/">Today in Tabs</a></em>&nbsp;who quipped: “Our economy might just be three AI data centers in a trench coat”—an allusion to the data-center buildout boom and to the cartoon trope/sight gag of <a href="https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-origin-of-the-sight-gag-where-three-small-people-stack-up-in-a-trench-coat-and-pretend-to-be-one-ordinary-size-adult" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-origin-of-the-sight-gag-where-three-small-people-stack-up-in-a-trench-coat-and-pretend-to-be-one-ordinary-size-adult">several young boys</a> teaming up to disguise themselves as an adult.</p><p>Morgan Stanley Chief Economist Michael Gapen ventured a guess on Oct. 6 about “the mystery” of the 2025 economy, “between solid spending data and weak hiring.” He argued that it “can be explained by a corporate sector that absorbed the initial cost of tariffs and reduced unit labor costs and profitability rather than raising prices.” 



</p><p>In other words, something that has nothing to do with the data-center buildout that is widely fueling bubble fears, <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/10/04/jeff-bezos-amazon-openai-sam-altman-ai-bubble-tech-stocks-investing/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/10/04/jeff-bezos-amazon-openai-sam-altman-ai-bubble-tech-stocks-investing/">even among Amazon founder Jeff Bezos himself</a>, who insists these data centers are an “industrial bubble” rather than a financial one, and we will all be glad someday to have such incredible computing power at our fingertips with so many hundreds of billions spent. The question of sustainable GDP growth is a separate one.<br></p></div><p><strong>Fortune Global Forum</strong> returns Oct. 26–27, 2025 in Riyadh. CEOs and global leaders will gather for a dynamic, invitation-only event shaping the future of business. <a href="https://conferences.fortune.com/event/global-forum-2025/summary?utm_source=fortunecom&amp;utm_medium=plealink" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://conferences.fortune.com/event/global-forum-2025/summary?utm_source=fortunecom&amp;utm_medium=plealink">Apply for an invitation.</a></p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bob Ross paintings to be auctioned to fund US public broadcasting (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly10275v5zo</link>
            <guid>45511265</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 02:06:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly10275v5zo">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly10275v5zo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45511265">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>Paintings by celebrated art tutor Bob Ross will be auctioned to help support public television stations that have faced funding cuts under the Trump administration.</p><p>About 30 of his artworks, which he mostly created on-air during his TV show, the Joy of Painting, in the 80s and 90s, will be auctioned by Bonhams from November.</p><p>Bob Ross Inc said the auction "ensures Bob's legacy continues to support the very medium that brought his joy and creativity into American homes for decades". </p><p>It comes after Congress passed <a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly1jwe7582o">Trump's request to strip public broadcast funding</a>, leaving some 330 Public Broadcasting Service (PBS) and National Public Radio (NPR) stations scrambling for a new funding source. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Ross' show saw a resurgence during the Covid pandemic, as audiences enjoyed his soft-spoken, paint-along lessons. Misplaced brush strokes, the former Air Force drill sergeant would say, were just "happy accidents". He died at the age of 52 in 1995. </p><p>Bob Ross Inc said it donated the paintings to American Public Television, and that all of the net proceeds go to local public TV stations nationwide.</p><p>This includes programmes such as America's Test Kitchen, Julia Child's French Chef Classics and This Old House, the Associated Press news agency reported. </p><p>In August, the auction of two of Ross' works shattered records, having sold for double and triple what had been expected. </p><p>Lake Below Snow-Capped Peaks and Cloudy Sky sold for $114,800, while Lake Below Snow-Covered Mountains and Clear Sky sold for $95,750.</p><p>"I can tell you that Bob would have been quite shy to learn that his paintings are now selling at six figures," Joan Kowalski, the president of Bob Ross Inc, <a target="_blank" href="https://nypost.com/2025/08/15/us-news/bob-ross-paintings-easily-surpass-estimated-sale-prices-at-auction-marking-milestone-for-the-late-artist/">told the New York Post</a> after the lots sold.  </p><p>"He was never really that interested in his finished works, Bob was more fascinated with the process of painting and sharing that with other people."</p><p>"Truthfully, I can still hear him saying something like, 'You don't want my paintings, you want to create your own and hang them proudly on your wall.'"</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Study of 1M-year-old skull points to earlier origins of modern humans (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/sep/25/study-of-1m-year-old-skull-points-to-earlier-origins-of-modern-humans</link>
            <guid>45510582</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:17:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/sep/25/study-of-1m-year-old-skull-points-to-earlier-origins-of-modern-humans">https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/sep/25/study-of-1m-year-old-skull-points-to-earlier-origins-of-modern-humans</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45510582">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>A million-year-old human skull suggests that the origins of modern humans may reach back far deeper in time than previously thought and raises the possibility that <em>Homo sapiens</em> first emerged outside of Africa.</p><p>Leading scientists reached this conclusion after reanalysis of a skull known as Yunxian 2 discovered in China and previously classified as belonging to a member of the primitive human species <em>Homo erectus</em>.</p><p>After applying sophisticated reconstruction techniques to the skull, scientists believe that it may instead belong to a group called <em>Homo longi </em>(dragon man), closely linked to the elusive Denisovans who lived alongside our own ancestors.</p><p>This repositioning would make the fossil the closest on record to the split between modern humans and our closest relatives, the Neanderthals and Denisovans, and would radically revise understanding of the last 1m years of human evolution.</p><p>Prof Chris Stringer, an anthropologist and research leader in human evolution at the Natural History Museum in London, said: “This changes a lot of thinking because it suggests that by 1m years ago our ancestors had already split into distinct groups, pointing to a much earlier and more complex human evolutionary split than previously believed. It more or less doubles the time of origin of <em>Homo sapiens</em>.”</p><p>The skull was first unearthed in Hubei province in 1990, badly crushed and difficult to interpret. Based on its age and some broad-brush traits, it was assigned as <em>Homo erectus</em>, a group that is thought to have contained direct ancestors of modern humans.</p><p>The latest work used advanced CT imaging, high-resolution surface scanning and sophisticated digital techniques to produce a virtual reconstruction of the skull. The skull’s large, squat brain case and jutting lower jaw are reminiscent of <em>Homo erectus</em>. But the overall shape and size of the brain case and teeth appear to place it much closer to <em>Homo longi</em>, a species that scientists have <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/apr/10/jawbone-fossil-builds-richer-image-of-ancient-denisovans" data-link-name="in body link">recently argued</a> should incorporate the Denisovans.</p><p>This would push the split between our own ancestors, Neanderthals and <em>Homo longi</em> back by at least 400,000 years and, according to Springer, raises the possibility that our common ancestor – and potentially the first <em>Homo sapiens</em> – lived in western Asia rather than Africa.</p><p>“This fossil is the closest we’ve got to the ancestor of all those groups,” Stringer said.</p><p>A computational analysis of a wider selection of fossils suggests that in the last 800,000 years, large-brained humans evolved along just five major branches: Asian erectus, heidelbergensis, sapiens, Neanderthals and <em>Homo longi</em> (including the Denisovans).</p><p>“We feel that this study is a landmark step towards resolving the ‘muddle in the middle’ [the confusing array of human fossils from between 1m and 300,000 years ago] that has preoccupied palaeoanthropologists for decades,” Stringer said.</p><p>The findings run counter to some recent analyses based on genetic comparisons of living humans and ancient DNA, meaning the conclusions are likely to be contentious.</p><p>Dr Frido Welker, an associate professor in human evolution at the University of Copenhagen, who was not involved in the research, said: “It’s exciting to have a digital reconstruction of this important cranium available. If confirmed by additional fossils and genetic evidence, the divergence dating would be surprising indeed. Alternatively, molecular data from the specimen itself could provide insights confirming or disproving the authors’ morphological hypothesis.”</p><p>The findings are published in the journal <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9202" data-link-name="in body link">Science</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Six surgeons general: It's our duty to warn the nation about RFK Jr (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/</link>
            <guid>45510421</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 23:54:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45510421">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Become unbannable from your email (212 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://karboosx.net/post/PJOveGVa/become-unbannable-from-your-emailgmail</link>
            <guid>45509243</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 21:39:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://karboosx.net/post/PJOveGVa/become-unbannable-from-your-emailgmail">https://karboosx.net/post/PJOveGVa/become-unbannable-from-your-emailgmail</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45509243">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/BlogPosting">
            

            <div itemprop="articleBody">
                <p>Clickbait-y title, I know :D but I stand by it!</p>
<p>I noticed that many people still treat email like some sort of second-class citizen when it comes to personal information, and the urgency here is real.
I think, in today's world where everything is in apps and requires an account, email has become even more important than your <strong>home address</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Why Your Email Is Your Digital Home</h2>
<p>Think about it for a moment. What would happen to you if you lost access to your email and needed to change it? Now, compare that to changing your home address.</p>
<p>For the second one, maybe you'd need to change some delivery addresses, and update government documents and bills. But that's common practice, and most places probably have procedures to handle that, and it's still not that many places. It's a solvable chore.</p>
<p>Now think if you lost access to your email address. What would you have to do to fix it? Create a new one, fine. But how will you log into all of your apps where the identifier is the email address itself? You need to contact each of the companies through their customer service, which is often painful.</p>
<p>And think how many conversations you would have to have? Uber? Customer service. Netflix? Customer service. YouTube/Google? Customer service. It's just a <strong>nightmare</strong>.</p>
<p>Look at how many important things you are getting today in your emails. Invoices → email. Password resets → email. Security notices → email.</p>
<p>My point here is that email has become our second home address on the internet. And we use that one piece of personal information way more than our normal address these days.</p>
<hr>
<h2>The "How": Taking Control of Your Email</h2>
<p>Okay, so the boring "why" we covered. Now it's the part where I'm showing you how to deal with it.</p>
<p>I will show you how I have it set up.</p>
<h3>Step 1: Get Your Own Domain</h3>
<p>The biggest problem with free email addresses is that they are under someone else's domain, so they have <strong>full control</strong> over your email address.</p>
<p>To fix that, you first need to have your email address under your <strong>own domain</strong>.</p>
<p>For that, you need to find a provider that is well-respected in the "email community." Why? Because the email protocol is quite an interesting case of "we don't ditch old stuff." To properly use email without constant rejection from various email providers, your domain needs to be "known" by them. So, setting up your own email server is, in practice, out of the question.</p>
<p>But you can go, for example, with Google (G Suite/Google Workspace), or with Proton Email, or anything else that is somewhat well known.</p>
<p>I went with G Suite from Google because it comes with a slightly different privacy policy than normal Gmail, and only G Suite offers custom domains in the Google ecosystem. So, to ease myself from having a second, secondary Gmail, I went with this one. But others are also viable options.</p>
<p>Next, you need to follow the instructions of your chosen provider to set up your own email address on your domain. In practice, it will involve setting <strong>DNS MX records</strong> for your domain and some verification.</p>
<p>Oh, and I highly recommend providers that offer a <strong>"catch-all" feature</strong>. This way, you can have one main email address and unlimited <code>&lt;put something here&gt;@yourdomain.com</code> email addresses. It's useful to have it separated, like <code><a href="https://karboosx.net/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="b4dad1c0d2d8ddccf4cddbc1c6d0dbd9d5ddda9ad7dbd9">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></code>, but still receive the emails inside the same inbox.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Step 2: The Unbannable Backup</h3>
<p>Now, you have your domain, and your email is under that domain. We don't stop here. Your emails are still inside your email provider. If they block you, you will probably lose access to previous emails, but at least now you have the option to just switch MX records to a different provider to start receiving emails again.</p>
<p>But we don't want that! We want <strong>full control</strong> over our emails!!!</p>
<p>So how do we handle it? Simple: making a <strong>backup</strong>!</p>
<p>The easiest would be to set up your local email software like Outlook or Thunderbird to download all emails to your local computer. It's something, and it will work, but if you happen to have some local server, I have a better proposition.</p>
<p>Set up some simple email server on your local server. I'm using my <strong>NAS</strong>. Just pick a subdomain for your email so it will look like <code><a href="https://karboosx.net/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="492b282a223c39092b282a223c396730263c3b2d2624282027672a2624">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></code>.</p>
<p>With your simple local email server, you can set up your email provider to <strong>always forward</strong> any email to your local server.</p>
<p>With that, you will always have a copy of every email on your server. So even if you are on vacation and your service provider blocks you from accessing your inbox, you will still have your copy.</p>
<p>graph LR
    A[Author/Sender] --&gt; B(Your Email Provider);
    B --&gt; C(Online Inbox/Access);
    B -- Forward Email --&gt; D(Local Backup Server);
    D --&gt; E[Your Local Email Copy];
</p>
<p>And would you like to hear the bonus tip? With this solution, there's a high chance that if they ban you by mistake (AI bots are to blame), they will <strong>not disable the forwarding mechanism</strong>. They will just not allow you to authenticate to your account. That means you will still be able to read all your emails even when banned from your inbox!</p>
<hr>
<p>So there you have it. That's my method for making your most important internet asset, your email, truly <strong>unbannable</strong> and resilient. It takes a little setup, but the peace of mind knowing that I'm in control of my digital life—not some huge corporation—is totally worth it. Now go take back control!</p>

            </div>

            
        </article>

        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model (560 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-computer-use-model/</link>
            <guid>45507936</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 19:49:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-computer-use-model/">https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-computer-use-model/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507936">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="jump-content" tabindex="-1">
            

    
    

    <article>

    
    





    

    
      








<div data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Hero Menu&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
  }">
  
  <div>
      
      
        <p>
          Available in preview via the API, our Computer Use model is a specialized model built on Gemini 2.5 Pro’s capabilities to power agents that can interact with user interfaces.
        </p>
      
    </div>
  
  <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_1" data-component="uni-ai-generated-summary" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;event&quot;: &quot;module_impression&quot;,
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;ai_summary&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;CTA&quot;
  }">
          <h2>General summary</h2>
          <p>Google is releasing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model via the Gemini API, enabling developers to build agents that can interact with user interfaces. This model outperforms others in web and mobile control benchmarks with lower latency. You can access it now on Google AI Studio and Vertex AI to start building and share feedback in the Developer Forum.</p>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
</div>

    

    
      










<div>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Gemini Computer Use" data-component="uni-progressive-image" fetchpriority="high" height="150px" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-200.format-webp.webp" width="360px" data-sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw,(min-width: 1024px and max-width: 1259) 80vw, 1046px" data-srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-800.format-webp.webp 800w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-1200.format-webp.webp 1200w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-1600.format-webp.webp 1600w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-2200.format-webp.webp 2200w">
        </p>
      </div>
      
    </figure>
  </div>






    

    
    <div data-reading-time="true" data-component="uni-article-body">

            
              





<uni-article-speakable page-title="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" listen-to-article="Listen to article" data-date-modified="2025-10-07T20:39:24.825126+00:00" data-tracking-ids="G-HGNBTNCHCQ,G-6NKTLKV14N" data-voice-list="en.ioh-pngnat:Cyan,en.usb-pngnat:Lime" data-script-src="https://www.gstatic.com/readaloud/player/web/api/js/api.js" data-highlight-mode="word-over-paragraph"></uni-article-speakable>

            

            
            
<!--article text-->

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="pa3tk">Earlier this year, we <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/o8NiE3XMPrM?si=9uCZ5JXT0xtGyr1H&amp;t=874">mentioned</a> that we're bringing computer use capabilities to developers via the Gemini API. Today, we are releasing the <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model</a>, our new specialized model built on Gemini 2.5 Pro’s visual understanding and reasoning capabilities that powers agents capable of interacting with user interfaces (UIs). It outperforms leading alternatives on multiple web and mobile control benchmarks, all with lower latency. Developers can access these capabilities via the Gemini API in <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use">Google AI Studio</a> and <a href="https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/generative-ai/docs/computer-use">Vertex AI</a>.</p><p data-block-key="b74v6">While AI models can interface with software through structured APIs, many digital tasks still require direct interaction with graphical user interfaces, for example, filling and submitting forms. To complete these tasks, agents must navigate web pages and applications just as humans do: by clicking, typing and scrolling. The ability to natively fill out forms, manipulate interactive elements like dropdowns and filters, and operate behind logins is a crucial next step in building powerful, general-purpose agents.</p><h2 data-block-key="2t6df">How it works</h2><p data-block-key="7bmpr">The model’s core capabilities are exposed through the new `computer_use` tool in the Gemini API and should be operated within a loop. Inputs to the tool are the user request, screenshot of the environment, and a history of recent actions. The input can also specify whether to exclude functions from the <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use#supported-actions">full list of supported UI actions</a> or specify additional custom functions to include.</p></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Diagram of AI agent loop: Initial task leads to a screenshot/context, which is sent to the Model, which returns a response to the computer environment to execute an action." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="9i6az">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use Model flow</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Diagram of AI agent loop: Initial task leads to a screenshot/context, which is sent to the Model, which returns a response to the computer environment to execute an action." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Diagram-RD4-V01.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Diagram-RD4-V01.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Diagram-RD4-V01.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="pa3tk">The model then analyzes these inputs and generates a response, typically a function call representing one of the UI actions such as clicking or typing. This response may also contain a request for an end user confirmation, which is required for certain actions such as making a purchase. The client-side code then executes the received action.</p><p data-block-key="b440f">After the action is executed, a new screenshot of the GUI and the current URL are sent back to the Computer Use model as a function response restarting the loop. This iterative process continues until the task is complete, an error occurs or the interaction is terminated by a safety response or user decision.</p><p data-block-key="36n25">The Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model is primarily optimized for web browsers, but also demonstrates strong promise for mobile UI control tasks. It is not yet optimized for desktop OS-level control.</p><p data-block-key="79qun">Check out a few demos below to see the model in action (shown here at 3X speed).</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }">
        <p data-block-key="nly14"><b>Prompt:</b> “From <a href="https://tinyurl.com/pet-care-signup">https://tinyurl.com/pet-care-signup</a>, get all details for any pet with a California residency and add them as a guest in my spa CRM at <a href="https://pet-luxe-spa.web.app/">https://pet-luxe-spa.web.app/</a>. Then, set up a follow up visit appointment with the specialist Anima Lavar for October 10th anytime after 8am. The reason for the visit is the same as their requested treatment.”</p>
      </div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="5" thumbnail-alt="Gemini Computer Use demo at a pet spa" video-id="_lu-FcPUIfM" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }">
        <p data-block-key="nly14"><b>Prompt: “</b>My art club brainstormed tasks ahead of our fair. The board is chaotic and I need your help organizing the tasks into some categories I created. Go to <a href="http://sticky-note-jam.web.app/">sticky-note-jam.web.app</a> and ensure notes are clearly in the right sections. Drag them there if not.”</p>
      </div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="7" thumbnail-alt="Demo of computer use model using sticky notes" video-id="slOLc1nkKY0" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="pa3tk">How it performs</h2><p data-block-key="ac68d">The Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model demonstrates strong performance on multiple web and mobile control benchmarks. The table below includes results from self-reported numbers, evaluations run by Browserbase and evaluations we ran ourselves. Evaluation details are available in the <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemini/computer_use_eval_additional_info.pdf">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use evaluation info</a> and in <a href="https://www.browserbase.com/blog/evaluating-browser-agents">Browserbase’s blog post</a>. Unless otherwise indicated, scores shown are for computer use tools exposed via API.</p></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Benchmark performance table: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use leads in Online-Mind2Web, WebVoyager, and AndroidWorld benchmarks." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="9i6az">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use outperforms leading alternatives on multiple benchmarks</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Benchmark performance table: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use leads in Online-Mind2Web, WebVoyager, and AndroidWorld benchmarks." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Benchmark_Chart-RD5_V01.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Benchmark_Chart-RD5_V01.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Benchmark_Chart-RD5_V01.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }">
        <p data-block-key="pa3tk">The model offers leading quality for browser control at the lowest latency, as measured by performance on the Browserbase harness for Online-Mind2Web.</p>
      </div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Latency vs. Quality scatterplot: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use is lowest in latency and highest in accuracy (70%+ accuracy, ∼225 sec latency)." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="9i6az">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use delivers high accuracy while maintaining low latency</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Latency vs. Quality scatterplot: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use is lowest in latency and highest in accuracy (70%+ accuracy, ∼225 sec latency)." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Scatterplot-RD7.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Scatterplot-RD7.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Scatterplot-RD7.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="vcpc9">How we approached safety</h2><p data-block-key="26l5s">We believe that the only way to build agents that will benefit everyone is to be responsible from the start. AI agents that control computers introduce unique risks, including intentional misuse by users, unexpected model behavior, and prompt injections and scams in the web environment. Thus, it is critical to implement safety guardrails with care.</p><p data-block-key="ab068">We have trained safety features directly into the model to address these three key risks (described in the <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/Model-Cards/Gemini-2-5-Computer-Use-Model-Card.pdf">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use System Card</a>).</p><p data-block-key="7liej">Further, we also provide developers with safety controls, which empower developers to prevent the model from auto-completing potentially high-risk or harmful actions. Examples of these actions include harming a system's integrity, compromising security, bypassing CAPTCHAs, or controlling medical devices. The controls:</p><ul><li data-block-key="3f5gh"><b>Per-step safety service:</b> An out-of-model, inference-time safety service that assesses each action the model proposes before it’s executed.</li><li data-block-key="cu905"><b>System instructions:</b> Developers can further specify that the agent either refuses or asks for user confirmation before it takes specific kinds of high-stakes actions. (Example in <a href="https://googledevai.devsite.corp.google.com/gemini-api/docs/computer-use#supported-actions">documentation</a>).</li></ul><p data-block-key="65eg3">Additional recommendations for developers on safety measures and best practices can be found in our <a href="https://googledevai.devsite.corp.google.com/gemini-api/docs/computer-use#safety-best-practices">documentation</a>. While these safeguards are designed to reduce risk, we urge all developers to thoroughly test their systems before launch.</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="pa3tk">How early testers have used it</h2><p data-block-key="cnndn">Google teams have already deployed the model to production for use cases including UI testing, which can make software development signficantly faster. Versions of this model have also been powering <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/project-mariner/">Project Mariner</a>, the <a href="https://firebase.blog/posts/2025/04/app-testing-agent/">Firebase Testing Agent</a>, and some agentic capabilities in <a href="https://blog.google/products/search/ai-mode-agentic-personalized/">AI Mode in Search</a>.</p><p data-block-key="9h8sv">Users from our early access program have also been testing the model to power personal assistants, workflow automation, and UI testing, and have seen strong results. In their own words:</p></div>
  

  
    




<uni-pull-quote content-style="block" quote="“A lot of our workflows require interacting with interfaces meant for humans where speed is especially important. Gemini 2.5 Computer Use is far ahead of the competition, often being 50% faster and better than the next best solutions we’ve considered.” - Poke.com, a proactive AI assistant in iMessage, WhatsApp and SMS with multiple third-party and agentic workflows." section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model">
</uni-pull-quote>


  

  
    




<uni-pull-quote content-style="block" quote="“Our agents run fully autonomously, performing work where small mistakes in collecting and parsing data are unacceptable. Gemini 2.5 Computer Use outperformed other models at reliably parsing context in complex cases, increasing performance by up to 18% on our hardest evals.”  — Autotab, a drop-in AI agent." section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model">
</uni-pull-quote>


  

  
    




<uni-pull-quote content-style="block" quote="“When conventional scripts encounter failures, the model assesses the current screen state and autonomously ascertains the required actions to complete the workflow. This implementation now successfully rehabilitates over 60% of executions (which used to take multiple days to fix).” — Google’s payments platform team, which implemented the Computer Use model as a contingency mechanism to address fragile end-to-end UI tests that contributed to 25% of all test failures." section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model">
</uni-pull-quote>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="22clf">How to get started</h2><p data-block-key="envv8">Starting today, the model is available in public preview, accessible via the Gemini API on Google AI Studio and Vertex AI.</p><ul><li data-block-key="b1ua4"><b>Try it now:</b> In a demo environment hosted by <a href="http://gemini.browserbase.com/">Browserbase</a>.</li><li data-block-key="fdtcr"><b>Start building</b>: Dive into our <a href="https://github.com/google/computer-use-preview">reference</a> and <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use">documentation</a> (see <a href="https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/generative-ai/docs/computer-use">Vertex AI docs for enterprise use</a>) to learn how to build your own agent loop locally with Playwright or in a cloud VM with Browserbase.</li><li data-block-key="ds8mg"><b>Join the community:</b> We’re excited to see what you build. Share feedback and help guide our roadmap in our <a href="https://discuss.ai.google.dev/c/gemini-api/4">Developer Forum</a>.</li></ul></div>
  


            
            

            
              




            
          </div>
  </article>
  





  

  


<div data-component="uni-related-articles" aria-roledescription="carousel" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Article Footer Related Stories&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;
  }">
        <h3>
          <p>
            Related stories
          </p>
        </h3>
      </div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[User ban controversy reveals Bluesky’s decentralized aspiration isn’t reality (253 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://plus.flux.community/p/banning-controversy-reveals-blueskys</link>
            <guid>45507880</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 19:44:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://plus.flux.community/p/banning-controversy-reveals-blueskys">https://plus.flux.community/p/banning-controversy-reveals-blueskys</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507880">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg" width="1456" height="764" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:764,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>When it launched in 2023 in private beta, Bluesky was pitched as a different kind of social network, one that placed openness and user-friendliness at its core. It came along at just the right moment as Elon Musk’s purchase and takeover of Twitter led millions of users head toward any type of exit.</p><p>The initial destination for many was Mastodon, but its Linux geek ethos and system of numerous “federated” servers that communicate via the open-source ActivityPub protocol proved to be too complicated for people who just wanted to crack jokes. Acting on the opportunity, Bluesky opened up to the public in February 2024 and saw a rapid influx of users.</p><p><span>Besides being easier to sign up and use than Mastodon, Bluesky offered a different approach to content moderation that was more flexible and user-driven. In addition to making its software source code available under open licenses, Bluesky wanted to put moderation decisions in the hands of its users, encouraging them to make lists of accounts that could be automatically blocked or labeled—and thereby removing itself as much as possible from moderation decisions that have plagued discussion group administrators </span><a href="https://flux.community/matthew-sheffield/2021/11/problems-social-media-are-not-technology-challenges-they-are-social/" rel="">since the days of Usenet newsgroups</a><span>.</span></p><p>Millions of people flooded in after Bluesky opened its doors to the public. By November of 2024, there were nearly 1.5 million daily posters, most of them anti-Musk Twitter refugees who were eager to get away from Musk’s right-wing makeover of the site into X.</p><p><span>However, as time has gone by, </span><a href="https://bsky.jazco.dev/stats" rel="">Bluesky’s traffic has declined</a><span> (</span><a href="https://backlinko.com/twitter-users" rel="">X’s has as well</a><span>) and some of its users have become increasingly upset at its moderation decisions, including allowing U.S. Vice President J.D. Vance and </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/13/bluesky-is-at-a-crossroads-as-users-petition-to-ban-jesse-singal-over-anti-trans-views-harassment/" rel="">anti-trans writer Jesse Singal</a><span> to remain as users of the platform. Singal became a particular target, prompting a </span><a href="https://www.change.org/p/bluesky-must-enforce-its-community-guidelines-equally" rel="">petition</a><span> with more than 28,000 signatures urging Bluesky to “enforce its Community Guidelines” against him that has not been successful, although he has been </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/13/bluesky-is-at-a-crossroads-as-users-petition-to-ban-jesse-singal-over-anti-trans-views-harassment/" rel="">temporarily banned</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Accusations of indifference to anti-trans bigotry seem to have exacerbated some users’ frustrations with the platform for its alleged tolerance of racist content. In 2023, many launched a “</span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/07/27/bluesky-racism-slur-apology-feedback/" rel="">posting strike</a><span>” after they discovered that Bluesky allowed people to sign up for user names containing racial slurs, a policy the company quickly reversed and apologized for.</span></p><p><span>The labeling feature of Bluesky has been more positively regarded, with many people subscribing to lists to label or block Trump supporters, Singal, and other widely disliked journalists. But things have not been perfect. Several users have complained about being added to libelously named lists, while others have complained that stalkers have added them to numerous lists out of revenge. Trying to balance concerns between legitimate blocklist maintainers and victims of false accusations, Bluesky </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/18/bluesky-addresses-trust-and-safety-concerns-around-abuse-spam-and-more/?utm_source=chatgpt.com" rel="">unveiled a series of changes</a><span> to its </span><a href="https://bsky.social/about/support/tos" rel="">terms of service</a><span> which brought it more in line with other social platforms, but also sparked controversy because now users can get blocklists hidden by reporting on them.</span></p><p>The failure of the Singal ban effort has also continued to grate on Bluesky’s most persistent critics, and the site’s executives have been met with many critical and often off-topic replies and quote posts.</p><p>While Bluesky has been navigating user concerns, its engineering team has been moving ahead with its long-promised open source efforts, breaking up its software stack into several pieces to enable a federated Authenticated Transfer Protocol (ATProto) network where anyone with the know-how and funds could run their own copy of Bluesky.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png" width="708" height="575" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:575,&quot;width&quot;:708,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>There are several key pieces of code that combine to make the Bluesky network function: A personal data server (PDS) which hosts the official/canonical copies of its users’ posts and profile information. Whenever it’s updated, the data is combined and sent to a Relay server, which combines and indexes posts from many different PDSes to create what social networks call the “firehose,” the collection of all posts made on the network.</p><p><span>The firehose data is imported by a labeler program which categorizes it in various ways set up by users, the processed data is combined together by an application server (or AppViews as they’re called </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/pfrazee.com/post/3lyucxfxq622w" rel="">for now</a><span> in Bluesky). When a user logs into their PDS and pushes “refresh,” their local app connects to the PDS’s designated feed generator which serves up a cached version of the accounts they follow.</span></p><p><span>While the ATProto system has been criticized as overly complicated </span><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/4/20/23689570/activitypub-protocol-standard-social-network" rel="">compared to the ActivityPub system</a><span> that powers the Fediverse, it has one key feature that ActivityPub lacks: the ability to transfer servers while keeping all of your followers and posts.</span></p><p>Due to the complexity of the Bluesky software stack, whether its federation model actually works in practice has not really been put to the test. While ActivityPub has several instances with millions of users (like Facebook Threads, Flipboard, and even Donald Trump’s Truth Social), it also has many much smaller ones run by small organizations and individuals.</p><p><span>As of this writing, however, the only completely independent implementation of ATProto is Bluesky. But that isn’t for want of trying on the part of Rudy Fraser, the creator of </span><a href="https://blacksky.community/" rel="">Blacksky</a><span>, an alternative service that he unveiled in May of 2023 in response to Black American users’ complaints about Bluesky’s moderation policies.</span></p><p>Despite Fraser’s efforts to implement his own PDS, Relay, and App View, however, Blacksky still remains partially dependent upon Bluesky’s application server, largely because while the code to implement the dataplane of posts and users within an application server is released, the open-source version is slower. As a result, Blacksky is dependent on Bluesky’s application server to give users a fast experience, which also means that it is dependent on Bluesky’s labeling system and its moderation choices.</p><p>The labeling software, called Ozone, also has issues, according to Bluesky engineer Bryan Newbold.</p><p>“Making it easier to run moderation services is something we want to do. we invested a lot of time and effort in Ozone, but have not been able to focus on making it usable/accessible for independent folks,” he wrote in an Oct. 3 post, adding that “we are looking at funding folks to fork or re-implement it for community use-case.”</p><p>This limitation is likely to be another reason why Blacksky relies on Bluesky's AppView. Without it, Blacksky’s independent moderators couldn't actually perform their task. (Fraser did not respond to repeated attempts to contact him for comment.)</p><p>Blacksky’s continued dependency on Bluesky came into focus on Sunday after a Blacksky user going by the handle Link suddenly found himself unable to view his own posts on the alternative site.</p><p><span>“My account was taken down without any explanation for almost a full day,” Link told me in a Signal message, showing me a screenshot indicating that he had been banned even as his Blacksky account remained capable of viewing others’ posts and changing preferences. Unbeknownst to him, Link’s account had been banned by Bluesky’s moderators and this meant that even though he was in good standing at Blacksky, no one there, including himself, was able to read his posts. (They are visible </span><a href="https://pdsls.dev/at://did:plc:63hvnyjvqi2nzzcsjgnry5we/app.bsky.feed.post" rel="">within the ATProto firehose feed</a><span>, however, as several sharp-eyed users soon discovered.)</span></p><p><span>Link’s banning came at a very bad moment for Bluesky, just weeks after it had banned or suspended several users following the Sept. 10 murder of far-right activist Charlie Kirk, which many Republican officials have sought to use as a tool for </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/kirk-trump-cancel-culture-assassination-4d69649e382ea46d8dcf794150a1d3c9" rel="">government censorship</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Federal Communications Commission Brendan Carr’s threats against late night comedian Jimmy Kimmel led to his temporary suspension by ABC, and he was far from the only Republican to issue them. Louisiana Rep. Clay Higgins, chair of the House subcommittee on federal law enforcement, </span><a href="https://clayhiggins.house.gov/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/9.15.25_Rep.-Higgins-Letter-to-Big-Tech-re-Charlie-Kirk-1.pdf" rel="">sent a menacing letter</a><span> to Bluesky and other social media networks demanding that they identify and ban anyone deemed to be celebrating Kirk’s killing.</span></p><p>“The authors of these posts are to be identified and banned from your platform, as well as any new pages they may create,” he wrote. “The reasonable restriction of public statements that lie far beyond the standards of our own society is not an oppression of free speech, it is, rather, the protection of free speech.”</p><p><span>There’s no proof that Higgins’s threats against social media platforms led to Bluesky banning anyone, but in any case, more than a few users were permanently or temporarily banned for mocking Kirk’s death, including horror author </span><a href="https://www.tcj.com/horror-it-girl-gretchen-felker-martin-on-dc-pulling-red-hood-after-charlie-kirk-comments-i-had-no-regrets/" rel="">Gretchen Felker-Martin</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>The fallout from the Kirk controversies and the months of replies seems to have irked Bluesky CEO Jay Graber, and she began pushing back on the user complaints. On Oct. 1, she </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m25dl2ibnc2y" rel="">approvingly quoted</a><span> a user who had referenced the famous </span><a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/no-bitch-dats-a-whole-new-x-wtf-is-you-talkin-about" rel="">pancakes-waffle Twitter meme</a><span> about how liking pancakes doesn’t mean disliking waffles, adding: “Too real. We’re going to try to fix this. Social media doesn’t have to be this way.”</span></p><p><span>Graber’s post was soon met by </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/antioccident.bsky.social/post/3m25emit7w22r" rel="">a reply</a><span> asking if she’d banned Singal yet, prompting her to </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m25esnq4t22y" rel="">respond</a><span> in all-caps: “WAFFLES.”</span></p><p><span>The next day, Thursday, Graber returned to her theme, </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m2a73ot5uk2e" rel="">posting a photograph</a><span> of a berry-covered waffle, accompanied with the caption: “Amazing breakfast this morning. I love waffles.”</span></p><p><span>As might be expected, Graber’s trolling was not taken well by her critics. The waffles post received more than 1,700 replies, including many </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/billcorbett.bsky.social/post/3m2aajss5hs2q" rel="">mocking her</a><span> as a Musk-like figure.</span></p><p><span>On Friday, Graber turned more serious </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m2c7ge42us2t" rel="">in her pushback</a><span>: “Harassing the mods into banning someone has never worked. And harassing people in general has never changed their minds,” she wrote, </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m2c7hy7zus2t" rel="">adding later</a><span> that: “Yet it’s a behavior that persists across social media anyway, with negative consequences for civil discourse and society. Human nature is a contributing factor, but systems that reward outrage only make the problem worse.”</span></p><p><span>Among the more than 100 people who quoted Graber’s post that day was Link. He </span><a href="https://pdsls.dev/at://did:plc:63hvnyjvqi2nzzcsjgnry5we/app.bsky.feed.post/3m2cerd243k2a" rel="">posted a photo of Kirk</a><span> which he accompanied with descriptive text that read: “Charlie Kirk sitting in a white T-shirt that says freedom. A negative consequence follows.”</span></p><p><span>Link made a number of other posts after to that one, but on Sunday his Blacksky account stopped working. After receiving no contact from either Blacksky or Bluesky, Link messaged Bluesky’s moderation team and received </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/aliafonzy.blacksky.app/post/3m2jm7ugr6k2y" rel="">an email</a><span> about 3 hours later saying that he had violated the social network’s community guidelines in his quote of Graber days earlier, presumably its policies against “threats or encouragement of violence.”</span></p><p>That is not how Link sees his post.</p><p><span>“I want to be extremely clear I was not making a death threat or inciting violence,” he told me, saying that he had sent 12 separate examples of other people posting the same Kirk image as a </span><a href="https://x.com/liv_agar/status/1975210544018989119?s=42" rel="">reaction meme</a><span>. “I don’t wish death on Jay, I wish for her and her team to grow a conscience. I disagree with the decision and how it was handled. My account was taken down without any explanation for almost a full day in what can only be viewed as a retroactive ban.”</span></p><p>I’ve asked Bluesky whether the post had been reported as a violation by other users. I will update this story if I receive a response. Rudy Fraser, the Blacksky administrator has not responded to a request for comment.</p><p>Asked about why Link had to contact Bluesky to find out what had happened to his account rather than receiving a notice, Paul Frazee, the service’s CTO, said that it was “unfortunate,” and that Bluesky needed to finish adding a feature to let users of external PDSes know if they have been banned by Bluesky labelers.</p><p><span>Agree or disagree on whether Bluesky has treated Link fairly, the incident has exposed that the social network’s decentralization plans have yet to be fulfilled. Blacksky seems to be the furthest-along alternative ATProto implementation, but it’s still dependent on Bluesky. There’s another one called </span><a href="https://northskysocial.com/profile/posts" rel="">Northsky Social</a><span>, but it has not launched any services yet. And while there are several alternative AppViews such as </span><a href="https://deer.social/" rel="">Deer.social</a><span>, there does not seem to be any service (or combination of services) that can function as a full-stack implementation of ATProto.</span></p><p><span>This might explain why, despite having a network of </span><a href="https://bsky.jazco.dev/stats" rel="">nearly 40 million users</a><span>, no situation like Link’s banning seems to have happened during Bluesky’s very short lifespan.</span></p><p><span>The episode has sent more than a few Bluesky users to start wondering whether the snow-covered grass on Mastodon’s side of the road is </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/kozufox.bsky.social/post/3m2k5pf63ks2h" rel="">worth considering</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>But not everyone is looking forward to the idea: “I’d go back to Usenet before I went back to Mastodon,” wrote Bluesky user </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/horseknuckler.bsky.social/post/3m2abce3vss2w" rel="">Count Von Horse Knuckler</a><span>. “I do not need people yelling at me for not putting cat pictures behind trigger warnings or unwanted Linux advice.”</span></p><p><span>Help may be on the horizon, however. As developers are becoming more aware of the power of ATProto, they are building increasingly complex projects on it, including a promising service called </span><a href="https://slices.network/" rel="">Slices</a><span>, which aims to make it easy to build and deploy custom AppViews, a feature Blacksky and other Bluesky alternatives could certainly use. Bluesky execs have said they are working hard to make federation easier.</span></p><p>Meanwhile, Link is caught in limbo.</p><p>“Now my account is not viewable on either Blacksky or Bluesky,” he notes. “I’m fortunate that I moved over to Blacksky and I think that is the only reason I still have access to my account and data…Bluesky claims to want decentralization and composable moderation, but they still enjoy abusing the power of arbitrary banishment.”</p><p>This story has been updated to include a post from Bluesky developer Bryan Newbold.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eliminating contrails from flying could be cheap (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails</link>
            <guid>45507398</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 19:07:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails">https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507398">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p><span>Eliminating CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> emissions from flying is going to be expensive, regardless of the solution the world adopts.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-1-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-1-175436430" target="_self" rel="">1</a></span></p><p><span>But aviation also contributes to global warming through its non-CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> effects. Those are mostly “contrails”, which I’ll explain in more detail soon. Getting rid of those could be incredibly cheap. So cheap that it’s difficult to understand why we don’t just go ahead and fix it.</span></p><p><span>On a </span><a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/4aMv3y9bS6E93l9pmcN0F5" rel="">recent podcast</a><span>, I spoke to Ian McKay, CEO of Orca Sciences, about this. One of their portfolio projects is </span><a href="http://contrails.org/" rel="">Contrails.org</a><span>. Their solution to eliminating contrails is to accurately forecast and model the atmospheric conditions that generate them, and reroute planes so that they avoid these “contrail-forming” parts of the atmosphere.</span></p><p><span>This is a solution that </span><em>I</em><span> hadn’t really paid much attention to, and most people are unaware of. So I thought I’d do a deep dive on contrails; explore how this solution might work; and whether it’s really that cheap.</span></p><p><span>To pre-empt the critics: this solution does not mean the aviation industry can ignore the CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> impacts of flying. Tackling contrails would not absolve them of responsibility for finding low-carbon alternatives to jet fuel. It’s not a substitute, but an addition. Currently, their non-CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> impacts are not measured or reported, so bringing more attention to contrails means they’re taking </span><em>full</em><span> responsibility for their climate impact, which is not the case at the moment.</span></p><p>When you see a plane in the sky, you might see a small, white cloud-like trail behind it. Those are contrails (short for “condensation trails”).</p><p><span>Water vapour, soot and other particles (basically pollutants) are emitted from the back of jet engines. Water droplets can condense around these particles, and because it’s pretty cold up there, they can freeze to form ice crystals. Sometimes these white lines are very faint and hard to see. But in some cases, they can form “</span><a href="https://weather.metoffice.gov.uk/learn-about/weather/types-of-weather/clouds/high-clouds/cirrus" rel="">cirrus clouds</a><span>”: wispy ones that form at high altitudes.</span></p><p>These contrails can have both cooling and warming impacts. I’ve sketched this out in the schematic below.</p><p>Some sunlight can reflect off of them, rather than passing through to the surface, which has a cooling effect.</p><p>Most sunlight, though, does pass through, and outgoing irradiation then gets trapped by the cirrus clouds. This has a warming effect, which tends to be larger than the cooling one, so on net, contrails cause warming.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png" width="692" height="376.4175824175824" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/eeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:792,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:692,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!tHPb!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Feeafba6b-7f9e-4484-ad96-4de21143b989_2048x1114.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>Since someone asked about this over email: the fact that there is no sunlight at night, and less during winter, there is less to “reflect” off the top of cirrus clouds. That means the cooling effect is weaker at night, and in winter, and the net warming effect stronger. This means avoiding contrails in winter and at night has an even stronger impact on reducing warming.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-2-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-2-175436430" target="_self" rel="">2</a></span></p><p><span>It’s common to want to compare them to CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> emissions, but it’s first worth emphasising how different the contributions are in terms of intensity and persistence.</span></p><p>Contrails have a strong “effective radiative forcing” effect. This basically measures the net change in energy flow at the top of the atmosphere: and that change in energy flow dictates how much warming is needed at the surface to offset it. But, this warming effective is very short-lived. If we were to stop contrails today, the warming effect would disappear within a day or so.</p><p>Think of it like a very brief but strong pulse of energy.</p><p><span>CO</span><sub>2</sub><span>, on the other hand, has a smaller effect on radiative forcing, but once you emit it, it stays there for centuries or more.</span></p><p><span>I thought this diagram from </span><a href="http://contrails.org/" rel="">Contrails.org</a><span> makes this point clearly.</span><strong> </strong><span>This </span><a href="https://notebook.contrails.org/comparing-contrails-and-co2/" rel="">article by them</a><span> explains the comparison in much more detail.</span></p><p><span>When we think about the climate impacts of aviation, then, most of the warming from CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> emissions is not due to the emissions </span><em>this year</em><span>, but the cumulative effect (which persists) over the past 70 years. But for contrails, the warming impact is only really from those created very recently (hours to days); the small temperature response decays over months to a few years.</span></p><p><span>You might have heard people say that “more than half of the warming caused by aviation comes from non-CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> sources”. A big part of that is contrails. But this does not mean that for any given flight, half of the warming is coming from contrails and the other half from burning jet fuel.</span></p><p><span>This apparent ‘half-half’ balance is a coincidence of timing: the cumulative CO₂ effect built up over decades happens to be of similar order to the instantaneous contrail effect for that year. In the chart below you can see the effective radiative forcing caused by CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> and contrails in 2019. Again, the CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> emitted </span><em>in</em><span> 2019 is just a small part of the warming. Most of comes from emissions built over decades, that stay there. It just so happens that this cumulative amount of warming is not that different from the instantaneous, short-lived impact of contrails in 2019. Eventually more and more CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> emissions will accumulate, and the share coming from contrails will shrink in relative terms.</span></p><p>But as it stands today, we could get rid of around half of the warming impact — maybe slightly less — from aviation, if we were to tackle contrails. The impact would be almost immediate.</p><p><span>How, then, do contrails stack up in terms of total warming? They contribute roughly 2% to the world’s effective radiative forcing; tackling them would reduce that by a similar amount.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-3-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-3-175436430" target="_self" rel="">3</a></span></p><p><span>What this comparison should make extremely clear is that reducing contrails does not mean we don’t also need to tackle CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> emissions from aviation. Ultimately that is the persistent driver of long-term temperature change. What tackling contrails now would do is slightly reduce the </span><em>rate</em><span> of warming (and therefore do something reduce the risks of nearer-term feedbacks that could affect the release of CO</span><sub>2</sub><span> from natural systems, and also affect long-term temperature change). It is not an excuse or a substitute for finding a way to decarbonise jet fuel.</span></p><p>One crucial reason why eliminating contrails could be so cost-effective is that a very small percentage of flights create the majority of the impact. This means we don’t need to divert or shift the trajectory of all the world’s flights; only a few percent of them.</p><p><span>In the chart below, you can see the breakdown of the warming effect across the world’s flights.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-4-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-4-175436430" target="_self" rel="">4</a></span><span> On the left-hand side, we have the share of flights, and on the right, their collective contribution to the total warming impact of contrails.</span></p><p>Just 3% of flights generate 80% of the warming. A further 14% generate 29%.</p><p><span>You might notice that this sums to 109%. But this is because some flights generate a </span><em>cooling</em><span> effect of 9%. Put them together and we get 100%.</span></p><p>Most flights — three-quarters of them — barely generate contrails at all and cause no warming or cooling.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png" width="603" height="497.3921703296703" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1201,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:603,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!0Jwp!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fccf1a58f-a987-4b12-aded-fd39c23393a3_1542x1272.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>Some sources cite slightly different numbers for this “80% warming effect”. For example, </span><a href="http://contrails.org/" rel="">Contrails.org</a><span> cite 5% of flights. I’ve seen others quote 2%.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-5-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-5-175436430" target="_self" rel="">5</a></span><span> But the point remains the same: a few percent of the flights completely dominate the climate impact.</span></p><p>So, how can we get rid of these contrails?</p><p>Contrails with a strong warming impact mostly form in thin regions of the atmosphere, which are cold and humid. If planes fly through these zones of atmosphere, contrails are much more likely to form.</p><p>The solution, then, is for some planes to take a short detour to avoid them. You can see this in the schematic below.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png" width="1204" height="460" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/faed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:460,&quot;width&quot;:1204,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!5NvF!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffaed822d-d416-4fea-9790-9f95ff34b82a_1204x460.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Source: Contrails.org</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>How</span><strong> </strong><span>would we know which planes to re-route and by how much?</span></p><p><span>Using detailed weather forecasts, satellite images, and flight plans, scientists can identify where these zones will be far in advance and work with flight planners to find a way to reroute flights crossing these zones to avoid them. These forecasts and models are what </span><a href="http://contrails.org/" rel="">Contrails.org</a><span> do.</span></p><p><span>Google also launched “</span><a href="https://sites.research.google/gr/contrails/" rel="">Project Contrails</a><span>” which uses Artificial Intelligence (AI) to build models that can do this.</span></p><p>Of course, this wouldn’t work if these planes had to do a severe detour. People would not be happy about a longer flight time. And, the extra fuel that would need to be burned to go the extra distance would eventually cancel out the climate benefits from getting rid of the contrails.</p><p><span>The proposed detours typically result in a 1% shift (and again, this is only for a small percentage of flights). That means increasing fuel use and flight time </span><a href="https://www.aerosociety.com/media/26061/iata-d1-devaiah-and-simon-iata-raes-contrails-workshop-10-11-march-2025.pdf" rel="">by around 1%</a><span>. So if your flight is three hours long, it’s only adding an extra two minutes. For a 10-hour flight, six minutes. This seems socially acceptable to me; most people would barely notice.</span></p><p>The fact that the warming impact is skewed towards such a small share of flights dramatically reduces the costs.</p><p>What are the costs associated with implementing this?</p><p>There are operational costs associated with weather prediction, modelling, and integration into flight planning. Especially with the integration of AI, this is probably not that expensive. A bit more costly is the extra jet fuel that’s needed for rerouted planes.</p><p><span>When I spoke with Ian McKay, he suggested the additional cost would be around $5 per flight. I </span><em>think</em><span> he meant this as $5 spread across the entire flight (not per passenger). This is also the figure they give on </span><a href="http://contrails.org/" rel="">Contrails.org</a><span>.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-6-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-6-175436430" target="_self" rel="">6</a></span><span> I also think that in this assumption, the costs are spread evenly across the entire airline fleet (regardless of whether they’re rerouted or not). For the small share of rerouted flights alone, the “per flight” cost would be higher.</span></p><p>That’s incredibly low. Spreading that over 100 passengers, and each is paying just 5 cents extra.</p><p>Other studies have reported higher costs, although they’re still incredibly cheap.</p><p><a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/2634-4505/ad310c/meta" rel="">This paper</a><span> modelled over 84,000 flights and found that the additional cost of operations and fuel burn for rerouting increased costs by around $1.1 million.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-7-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-7-175436430" target="_self" rel="">7</a></span><span> By my calculations, that’s around $10 to $15 </span><em>per flight</em><span>.</span></p><p><span>We can do a very basic back-of-the-envelope calculation to sense-check this. The total fuel cost of flying from Barcelona to Berlin is probably around $2,000.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-8-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-8-175436430" target="_self" rel="">8</a></span><span> If the flight burned 1% extra fuel due to rerouting, the extra cost for the flight would be around $20. Add the operational costs of the forecasting, and this could be $30 to $40. Then spread across </span><em>all</em><span> flights, not just the rerouted ones, and this falls back down to the $5 to $10 range again.</span></p><p><span>Transport &amp; Environment (T&amp;E) </span><a href="https://www.transportenvironment.org/articles/contrail-avoidance" rel="">estimates that</a><span> the cost could range from $2 to $5 </span><em>per passenger</em><span> (or </span><em>hundreds</em><span> of dollars per flight).</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-9-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-9-175436430" target="_self" rel="">9</a></span><span> They do note that they make very conservative assumptions, and therefore find costs that are 3 to 10 times higher than those from other sources.</span></p><p>For a flight in Europe, such as from Barcelona to Berlin, the cost would be €1.20 ($1.88) per passenger. A Transatlantic ticket would be more expensive, around €3.90 for a trip from Paris to New York. Given that an economy ticket from Paris to New York probably costs around €350 to €400, this would increase the cost by around 1%.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png" width="557" height="411.6291208791209" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1076,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:557,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ohZc!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7f2fac40-89ba-4048-b199-740e683c77ab_1600x1182.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Source: Transport and Environment (2024). Contrail avoidance: aviation’s climate opportunity of the decade.</figcaption></figure></div><p>Perhaps, then, the best estimate is somewhere in the middle: around 50 cents per passenger.</p><p><span>Translating this into the cost per tonne of carbon dioxide equivalent — the “carbon abatement” cost — shows how cheap this is compared to many other climate solutions. It’s probably in the range of a few dollars per tonne CO</span><sub>2</sub><span>e. </span><a href="http://contrails.org/" rel="">Contrails.org</a><span> estimates that it’s slightly below $1 per tonne.</span></p><p><span>Switching to “sustainable aviation fuel” currently has an estimated cost in the range of </span><em>hundreds</em><span> of dollars per tonne of CO</span><sub>2</sub><span>e avoided.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-10-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-10-175436430" target="_self" rel="">10</a></span><span> Rather than a flight ticket being 1% more expensive, it would be more than double the price. Eliminating contrails is therefore hundreds of times cheaper and can be scaled much more quickly than replacing the entire aircraft fleet or its fuel source.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-11-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-11-175436430" target="_self" rel="">11</a></span></p><p>When I asked Ian McKay why airlines were not doing more, he gave two main reasons.</p><p><span>The first is that even if the cost </span><em>per flight</em><span> is low, the total cost across their entire fleet adds up. Let’s take a quick example for British Airways. They operate around 300,000 flights per year. If we reroute 2% of those to avoid contrails, and rerouting increases fuel burn by around 2% (I’m being deliberately harsh here), then I estimate that the additional fuel costs are in the range of $1.2 to $2 million per year.</span><span><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-12-175436430" href="https://www.sustainabilitybynumbers.com/p/eliminating-contrails#footnote-12-175436430" target="_self" rel="">12</a></span><span> Let’s say that the operational costs of forecasting and modelling adds another 50%. That takes us to around $2.5 to $3 million.</span></p><p><span>In 2024, British Airways </span><a href="https://www.iairgroup.com/media/u0wjmpj4/full-year-results-release-for-the-year-to-31-december-2024.pdf" rel="">had an</a><span> operating profit of around $2.7 billion. Contrail avoidance would therefore be just 0.1% of its operating profits.</span></p><p>But I’m not convinced that this cost factor is the main reason. They could pass this cost on to consumers; flight prices vary by a lot more than a few dollars for a variety of factors. They could either make a huge deal of the fact that they’re dramatically cutting their climate impact, and get “PR” buy-in from consumers for that. Or they could keep quiet, and most consumers would never notice the difference in cost.</p><p>The second — which seems more likely — is that, currently, most people are unaware of the climate impact of contrails. In that sense, airlines can basically ignore it and pretend they don’t exist. By trying to tackle them, they’d only draw more attention. People would then be aware that the climate impact of aviation is even higher than they thought.</p><p><span>I still think that the airline that steps up and commits to eliminating contrails — possibly even claiming to have </span><em>halved</em><span> its climate impact — would be well-received by many customers. I would see it as reputational gain, rather than a risk. </span></p><p>Nonetheless, there are no signs that the aviation industry itself is going to step up. This is where government policy could step in.</p><p><span>Rather than an airline leading by example, a country or region could. In a more pro-climate political environment, the United States could have led this effort domestically, mandating that internal flights eliminate their contrails. More likely is the European Union. It has already been making some progress in this direction — not by mandating that airlines pay for contrail avoidance — but by simply reporting these climate impacts in the first place. Earlier this year, its trading system regulations </span><a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/eli/reg_impl/2018/2066/2025-01-01/eng" rel="">were updated</a><span> to require airlines to monitor and report non-CO2 impacts.  That sounds basic, but it is not the standard across most of the world; these impacts are usually not included. Unsurprisingly, it has received pushback from the aviation industry, with </span><a href="https://www.iata.org/en/pressroom/opinions/why-the-eu-mrv-on-non-co2-emissions-should-be-voluntary" rel="">them asking</a><span> for these reports to be voluntary.</span></p><p>Progress will undoubtedly be met with initial resistance, but I still think that regulatory policy seems like the most likely path to widespread implementation.</p><p><span>What would help a lot is increasing </span><em>public</em><span> awareness of the existence of contrails, their climate impacts, and how inexpensive it could be to eliminate them. There is a general understanding that decarbonising aviation is expensive, and this often means the aviation industry gets more of a free ride. But this is based on replacing jet fuel. If people were aware that it could cut a huge chunk of its footprint at a fraction of the cost, they might be more demanding.</span></p><p>Eliminating a few percent of the world’s warming is a big deal when the costs are so small. It seems insane to me that such a cheap solution is sitting there, completely untapped.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The murky economics of the data-centre investment boom (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/30/the-murky-economics-of-the-data-centre-investment-boom</link>
            <guid>45507195</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 18:52:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/30/the-murky-economics-of-the-data-centre-investment-boom">https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/30/the-murky-economics-of-the-data-centre-investment-boom</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507195">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.economist.com/business/2025/09/30/the-murky-economics-of-the-data-centre-investment-boom: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google's Requirement for Developers to Be Verified Threatens App Store F-Droid (202 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.techdirt.com/2025/10/07/googles-requirement-for-all-android-developers-to-register-and-be-verified-threatens-to-close-down-open-source-app-store-f-droid/</link>
            <guid>45507173</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 18:51:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2025/10/07/googles-requirement-for-all-android-developers-to-register-and-be-verified-threatens-to-close-down-open-source-app-store-f-droid/">https://www.techdirt.com/2025/10/07/googles-requirement-for-all-android-developers-to-register-and-be-verified-threatens-to-close-down-open-source-app-store-f-droid/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507173">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="storywrap-518759">

				


				


				<h3>from the <i>formerly-open-ecosystem</i> dept</h3>
				


				<p>It would be something of an understatement to say that Alphabet, Google’s holding company, is <a href="https://www.google.com/finance/quote/GOOG:NASDAQ">big and successful</a>. Some Wall Street analysts are even predicting it could become the <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/wall-street-says-alphabet-googl-052439525.html">world’s most valuable corporation</a>. Of course, even for business giants, enough is never enough. They always want more: more money, more power. As part of that tendency, Google seems to have decided that <a href="https://f-droid.org/">F-Droid</a>, the free and open source app store for the Android platform, is a threat to the official Google Play Store that needs to be neutralized. At least that is likely to be the effect of Google’s announcement that it will <a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2025/08/elevating-android-security.html">require all Android developers to register and be verified</a> before their apps can be allowed to run on certified Android devices. A <a href="https://f-droid.org/2025/09/29/google-developer-registration-decree.html">post on the F-Droid blog</a> explains what the problem is:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>In addition to demanding payment of a registration fee and agreement to their (non-negotiable and ever-changing) terms and conditions, Google will also require the <a href="https://developer.android.com/developer-verification#verify-your-identity">uploading of personally identifying documents</a>, including government ID, by the authors of the software, as well as <a href="https://developer.android.com/developer-verification#register-your-apps">enumerating</a> all the unique “application identifiers” for every app that is to be distributed by the registered developer.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>According to the blog post, the impact on the F-Droid project would be severe:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>the developer registration decree will end the F-Droid project and other free/open-source app distribution sources as we know them today, and the world will be deprived of the safety and security of the catalog of thousands of apps that can be trusted and verified by any and all. F-Droid’s myriad users will be left adrift, with no means to install — or even update their existing installed — applications.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p><a href="https://android-developers.googleblog.com/2025/08/elevating-android-security.html">Google says</a> registration is needed to “better protect users from repeat bad actors spreading malware and scams”. Registration “creates crucial accountability, making it much harder for malicious actors to quickly distribute another harmful app after we take the first one down.” Slightly less convenient, perhaps, but not much harder. The F-Droid blog post points out that its open source app store already has a far better approach to security than Google’s proposed registration and verification:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>every [F-Droid] app is free and open source, the code can be audited by anyone, the build process and logs are public, and reproducible builds ensure that what is published matches the source code exactly. This transparency and accountability provides a stronger basis for trust than closed platforms, while still giving users freedom to choose. Restricting direct app installation not only undermines that choice, it also erodes the diversity and resilience of the open-source ecosystem by consolidating control in the hands of a few corporate players.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Google is at pains to emphasize “Verified developers will have the same freedom to distribute their apps directly to users through sideloading or through any app store they prefer.” But that’s not true: their “freedom” will be soon be conditional, subject to Google’s whim and veto (as the company’s recent <a href="https://www.404media.co/google-calls-ice-agents-a-vulnerable-group-removes-ice-spotting-app-red-dot/">removal of the ICE-spotting app ‘Red Dot’</a> demonstrates). As a special concession, the company says:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>we are also introducing a free developer account type that will allow teachers, students, and hobbyists to distribute apps to a limited number of devices without needing to provide a government ID.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>But again that is subject to Google’s approval, and only allows distribution to a “limited number of devices” – a circumscribed “freedom”, in other words. And for F-Droid it’s not even an option, because of the following:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>How many F-Droid users are there, exactly? We don’t know, because we don’t track users or have any registration: <a href="https://f-droid.org/en/2022/02/28/no-user-accounts-by-design.html">“No user accounts, by design”</a></em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>As the F-Droid post comments, Google’s move is not credibly about “security”, but actually about “consolidating power and tightening control over a formerly open ecosystem”:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>If you own a computer, you should have the right to run whatever programs you want on it. This is just as true with the apps on your Android/iPhone mobile device as it is with the applications on your Linux/Mac/Windows desktop or server. Forcing software creators into a centralized registration scheme in order to publish and distribute their works is as egregious as forcing writers and artists to register with a central authority in order to be able to distribute their creative works. It is an offense to the core principles of free speech and thought that are central to the workings of democratic societies around the world.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Google’s attack on F-Droid is ironic. At the heart of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a>, and the key element that allowed it to become so successful so quickly, is the GPL-licensed <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linux_kernel">Linux kernel</a>. Over the years, Google has increased its control over Android by adding more <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)#Licensing">non-free elements</a>. If, as seems likely, its latest move leads to the shutdown of the <a href="https://f-droid.org/en/2025/09/04/twif.html">15-year-old F-Droid platform</a>, it would represent a further betrayal of the open source world it once supported.</p>

				
<p>

	Filed Under: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/android/" rel="tag">android</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/f-droid/" rel="tag">f-droid</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/freedom/" rel="tag">freedom</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/id/" rel="tag">id</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/linux/" rel="tag">linux</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/macintosh/" rel="tag">macintosh</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/malware/" rel="tag">malware</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/open-source/" rel="tag">open source</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/registration/" rel="tag">registration</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/reproducibility/" rel="tag">reproducibility</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/scams/" rel="tag">scams</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/security/" rel="tag">security</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/verification/" rel="tag">verification</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/wall-street/" rel="tag">wall street</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/windows/" rel="tag">windows</a>
	<br>

	Companies: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/company/alphabet/" rel="category tag">alphabet</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/company/google/" rel="category tag">google</a>
</p>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Solar energy is now the cheapest source of power, study (257 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.surrey.ac.uk/news/solar-energy-now-worlds-cheapest-source-power-surrey-study-finds</link>
            <guid>45506365</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 17:50:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.surrey.ac.uk/news/solar-energy-now-worlds-cheapest-source-power-surrey-study-finds">https://www.surrey.ac.uk/news/solar-energy-now-worlds-cheapest-source-power-surrey-study-finds</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45506365">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Solar energy is now so cost-effective that, in the sunniest countries, it costs as little as £0.02 to produce one unit of power, making it cheaper than electricity generated from coal, gas or wind, according to a new study from the University of Surrey.&nbsp;</p></div><div><p>The research team also found that the price of lithium-ion batteries has fallen by 89% since 2010, making solar-plus-storage systems as cost-effective as gas power plants. These hybrid setups, which combine solar panels with batteries, are now standard in many regions and allow solar energy to be stored and released when needed, turning it into a more reliable, dispatchable source of power that helps balance grid demand.&nbsp;</p><p>Despite many reasons to be optimistic, the ATI research team points to several challenges – particularly connecting large amounts of solar power to existing electricity networks. In some regions, such as California and China, high solar generation has led to grid congestion and wasted energy when supply exceeds demand.&nbsp;</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Less Is More: Recursive Reasoning with Tiny Networks (262 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04871</link>
            <guid>45506268</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 17:42:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04871">https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04871</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45506268">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2510.04871">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2510.04871v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Hierarchical Reasoning Model (HRM) is a novel approach using two small neural networks recursing at different frequencies. This biologically inspired method beats Large Language models (LLMs) on hard puzzle tasks such as Sudoku, Maze, and ARC-AGI while trained with small models (27M parameters) on small data (around 1000 examples). HRM holds great promise for solving hard problems with small networks, but it is not yet well understood and may be suboptimal. We propose Tiny Recursive Model (TRM), a much simpler recursive reasoning approach that achieves significantly higher generalization than HRM, while using a single tiny network with only 2 layers. With only 7M parameters, TRM obtains 45% test-accuracy on ARC-AGI-1 and 8% on ARC-AGI-2, higher than most LLMs (e.g., Deepseek R1, o3-mini, Gemini 2.5 Pro) with less than 0.01% of the parameters.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Alexia Jolicoeur-Martineau [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/5a806206/2510.04871" rel="nofollow">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Mon, 6 Oct 2025 14:58:08 UTC (259 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[German government comes out against Chat Control (1039 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xcancel.com/paddi_hansen/status/1975595307800142205</link>
            <guid>45506143</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 17:31:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xcancel.com/paddi_hansen/status/1975595307800142205">https://xcancel.com/paddi_hansen/status/1975595307800142205</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45506143">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://xcancel.com/paddi_hansen/status/1975595307800142205: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ICE bought vehicles equipped with fake cell towers to spy on phones (305 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2025/10/07/ice-bought-vehicles-equipped-with-fake-cell-towers-to-spy-on-phones/</link>
            <guid>45505854</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 17:12:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/10/07/ice-bought-vehicles-equipped-with-fake-cell-towers-to-spy-on-phones/">https://techcrunch.com/2025/10/07/ice-bought-vehicles-equipped-with-fake-cell-towers-to-spy-on-phones/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45505854">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement (ICE) paid $825,000 earlier this year to a company that manufactures vehicles equipped with various technologies for law enforcement, including fake cellphone towers known as “cell-site simulators,” which&nbsp;can be used to spy on nearby phones. &nbsp;</p>

<p>According to <a href="https://www.fpds.gov/ezsearch/fpdsportal?q=TECHOPS+SPECIALTY+VEHICLES%2C+LLC++AGENCY_NAME%3A%22Immigration+and+Customs+Enforcement%22&amp;s=FPDS.GOV&amp;templateName=1.5.3&amp;indexName=awardfull&amp;sortBy=SIGNED_DATE&amp;desc=Y" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">public records</a>, the award dated May 8 “provides Cell Site Simulator (CSS) Vehicles to support the Homeland Security Technical Operations program” and is a modification for “additional CSS Vehicles.” &nbsp;</p>







<p>The contract was signed with TechOps Specialty Vehicles (TOSV), a Maryland-based company. TOSV also signed a similar contract with ICE in September 2024 for $818,000, showing that the relationship between the agency and the company predates the Trump administration. &nbsp;</p>

<p>TOSV president Jon Brianas told TechCrunch in an email that he could not provide details about the ICE contracts and the vehicles, citing “trade secrets.” But Brianas did confirm that the company does provide cell-site simulators, although it does not make them.&nbsp;</p>

<p>“We don’t manufacture electrical, comms, and technology components, we integrate that product into our overall design of the vehicle,” said Brianas, who declined to say from where TOSV sources its cell-site simulators. &nbsp;</p>

<p>This is the latest federal contract that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/09/18/heres-the-tech-powering-ices-deportation-crackdown/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">reveals some of the technologies</a> powering the Trump administration’s deportation crackdown.&nbsp;</p>

<p>In early September, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/the-wiretap/2025/09/09/how-ice-is-using-fake-cell-towers-to-spy-on-peoples-phones/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">Forbes found a recently unsealed search warrant</a> that showed that ICE used a cell-site simulator to track down a person who allegedly was part of a criminal gang in the United States, and who had been ordered to leave the country in 2023.&nbsp;In the article, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/the-wiretap/2025/09/09/how-ice-is-using-fake-cell-towers-to-spy-on-peoples-phones/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">Forbes reported</a> that it also found a contract for “cell site simulator vehicles,” but the article did not name the company that provides the vans to the agency.&nbsp;</p>
<div>
		
		<p>Techcrunch event</p>
		<div>
			
			<p><span>San Francisco</span>
													<span>|</span>
													<span>October 27-29, 2025</span>
							</p>
			
		</div>
	</div>

<p>Cell-site simulators also go by the name “stingrays” because some of the earlier types of these devices, made by defense contractor Harris (now L3Harris), were named that way. Since then, stingrays have become a catch-all name for this type of technology, also known as <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2017/06/02/who-catches-the-imsi-catchers-researchers-demonstrate-stingray-detection-kit/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IMSI catchers</a>. (IMSI stands for International Mobile Subscriber Identity, a unique number that identifies every cellphone user in the world.)&nbsp;</p>

<p>As the name suggests, cell-site simulator tools can mimic a cellphone tower, tricking every phone in its nearby range to connect to the device and thus giving law enforcement the ability to better identify the real-world location of those phones and their owners. &nbsp;</p>

<p>Some cell-site simulators can also intercept regular calls, text messages, and internet traffic.&nbsp;</p>







<p>Authorities can get data from traditional cellphone towers to find the current or past location of a suspect, but the location is usually not very precise. &nbsp;</p>

<p>Stingray-like devices have been in use by law enforcement for more than a decade and have long been controversial because authorities do not always get a warrant for their use, and <a href="https://sls.eff.org/technologies/cell-site-simulators-imsi-catchers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">critics say</a> these devices ensnare innocent people by default.&nbsp;These devices are also shrouded in secrecy, because the law enforcement agencies that use them are under strict non-disclosure agreements not to reveal how the devices work.&nbsp;</p>

<p>ICE has a long history of using cell-site simulators. In 2020, documents obtained by the American Civil Liberties Union showed that <a href="http://techcrunch.com/2020/05/27/aclu-ice-stingray-documents/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ICE deployed them at least 466 times between 2017 and 2019</a>. The agency used these tools more than 1,885 times between 2013 and 2017, <a href="http://buzzfeednews.com/article/adolfoflores/this-is-how-many-times-the-department-of-homeland-security" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">according to documents obtained by BuzzFeed News</a> at the time.&nbsp;</p>

<p>ICE acknowledged TechCrunch’s request for comment, but did not respond to a series of questions, which included: what ICE uses these vehicles for, whether and where they have recently been deployed, and whether the agency always gets a warrant when using cell-site simulators. &nbsp;</p>

<h2 id="h-from-surveillance-vans-to-bookmobiles-nbsp">From surveillance vans to bookmobiles&nbsp;</h2>

<p>Headquartered just outside of Washington, DC, TOSV sells a wide range of customizable vehicles to <a href="https://www.techopssv.com/law-enforcement" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">law enforcement</a>, such as vans for SWAT armed response teams, bomb squads, and so-called “mobile lab” and “cover surveillance” vehicles.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>

<p>Among these vehicles for police forces, TOSV lists several “projects,” including one described as <a href="https://www.techopssv.com/projects/dhs-mobile-forensic-labs" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">DHS Mobile Forensic Labs</a>, referring to the Department of Homeland Security.&nbsp;</p>

<p>According to the website, these mobile forensic vans are “equipped for on-site forensic analysis and documentation,” have “secure compartments for evidence preservation and investigative tools,” and enable “seamless case file updates and evidence logging.”&nbsp;</p>

<p>Another project is the <a href="https://www.techopssv.com/projects-1/dhs-mobile-command-van" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">DHS Mobile Command Van</a>,” which TOSV says is “configurable for advanced surveillance and mission coordination.” &nbsp;</p>







<p>It’s unclear if these vans are the same vehicles that include cell-site simulators, as there’s no mention of the phone surveillance tool anywhere on TOSV’s website. &nbsp;</p>

<p>ICE has other contracts with TOSV for mobile forensic labs, which don’t specify which technologies are located in the vans.&nbsp;</p>

<p>According to its website, TOSV also sells so-called “<a href="https://www.techopssv.com/community-outreach" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">bookmobiles</a>,” which appear to be libraries on wheels, as well as <a href="https://www.techopssv.com/medical-projects" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">medical</a> and <a href="http://techopssv.com/fire-and-ems" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">fire department</a> vehicles.</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You're Doing Rails Wrong (358 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bananacurvingmachine.com/articles/you-re-doing-rails-wrong</link>
            <guid>45505692</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 17:01:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bananacurvingmachine.com/articles/you-re-doing-rails-wrong">https://www.bananacurvingmachine.com/articles/you-re-doing-rails-wrong</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45505692">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <p><em>Kevin</em>: Hey, have you tried Vite for Rails 8? It’s insanely fast.</p><p><em>John</em>: I’ve heard of it. Isn’t that a build tool? Didn’t Rails already come with one?</p><p><em>K</em>: Well, it did, but Vite is like… modern. You’ll need to install Node, npm, and configure a few scripts, but it’s totally worth it.</p><p><em>J</em>: Wait, Rails needs Node now?</p><p><em>K</em>: Well, yeah — if you want to use React. Everyone’s using React.</p><p><em>J</em>: Didn’t Rails have something for that?</p><p><em>K</em>: It did, but now you’ll want to use Vite with React Refresh so you get instant component reloads. And if you want TypeScript support, you’ll have to configure that too.</p><p><em>J</em>: Sounds… like a lot.</p><p><em>K</em>: Oh, not really. Just install Babel, configure your .babelrc, add vite-plugin-ruby, then you’ll want PostCSS for your styles.</p><p><em>J</em>: PostCSS?</p><p><em>K</em>: Yeah, and then Tailwind, obviously — you don’t want to write CSS like a peasant.</p><p><em>J</em>: Of course not.</p><p><em>K</em>: Then you’ll probably want to add ESLint and Prettier to make sure your code looks clean, and maybe Husky for pre-commit hooks.</p><p><em>J</em>: So... Vite, React, Babel, PostCSS, Tailwind, ESLint, Prettier, Husky. That’s it?</p><p><em>K</em>: Pretty much. Oh, unless you want server-side rendering — then you’ll need Next.js or Remix.</p><p><em>J</em>: Wait, we’re still talking about a Rails app, right?</p><p><em>K</em>: Yeah, but hybrid stacks are the way to go! You could also use StimulusReflex or Hotwire if you want reactive components without JS frameworks.</p><p><em>J</em>: StimulusReflex sounds like a Marvel character.</p><p><em>K</em>: Ha! No, it’s for real-time updates. But you’ll need ActionCable configured, Redis running, and—</p><p><em>J</em>: Redis?</p><p><em>K</em>: Yeah, you need a pub/sub layer. Don’t worry, it’s just another Docker container.</p><p><em>J</em>: Docker too?</p><p><em>K</em>: Yeah, to isolate your dependencies. And if you want everything reproducible, you’ll need Docker Compose, maybe Fly.io for deployment, and a build pipeline with GitHub Actions.</p><p><em>J</em>: That’s... quite a setup.</p><p><em>K</em>: It’s just modern web development, man. Keeps things simple. What are you doing?</p><p><em>J</em>: Just tinkering.</p><p><em>(John runs a single command. The app boots instantly, working forms, instant loading times, blazing fast navigation.)</em></p><p><em>K</em>: Wow, that looks like a pretty complex setup. What stack’s that?</p><p><em>J</em>: Vanilla Rails.</p><p><em>Just F#$%^&amp; use Rails.</em></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Robin Williams' daughter pleads for people to stop sending AI videos of her dad (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/c0r0erqk18jo</link>
            <guid>45505626</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 16:56:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/c0r0erqk18jo">https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/c0r0erqk18jo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45505626">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main id="main-content" data-testid="main-content"><article id="urn-bbc-ares--article-c0r0erqk18jo"><header data-component="headline-block"></header><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><picture><source srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg.webp 800w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/976/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg.webp 976w" type="image/webp"><img alt="Robin and Zelda Williams pictured at a red carpet for Happy Feet 2 in 2011 in Los Angeles" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/1920/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg 800w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/976/cpsprodpb/6ba0/live/e26fba40-a38b-11f0-9d41-9dadd041fb76.jpg 976w" width="1920" height="1080.0617601646939"></picture></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Robin and Zelda Williams, pictured in 2011</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p><b>Zelda Williams, the daughter of Robin Williams, has asked people to stop sending her AI-generated videos of her father, the celebrated US actor and comic who died in 2014.</b></p><p>"Please, just stop sending me AI videos of Dad," Zelda Williams posted on her Instagram stories.</p><p>"Stop believing I wanna see it or that I'll understand, I don't and I won't. If you're just trying to troll me, I've seen way worse, I'll restrict and move on. </p><p>"But please, if you've got any decency, just stop doing this to him and to me, to everyone even, full stop. It's dumb, it's a waste of time and energy, and believe me, it's NOT what he'd want."</p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>This is not the first time Zelda Williams, a film director, has criticised AI versions of her father, who took his own life in 2014 at his Californian home at the age of 63.</p><p>Williams, who was famous for films such as Good Morning Vietnam, Dead Poets Society and Mrs Doubtfire, was understood to have been battling depression at the time of his death.</p><p>In 2023, in an Instagram post supporting a campaign against AI by US media union SAG-Aftra, she described attempts at recreating his voice as "personally disturbing", while also pointing to the wider implications.</p></div><div data-component="image-block"><figure><p><span><picture><source srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg.webp 624w" type="image/webp"><img alt="Zelda and Robin Williams smiling together in 2007 at the People's Choice Awards " loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/654/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/29f1/live/f1d83b60-a395-11f0-95e7-93813d968835.jpg 624w" width="654" height="655"></picture></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p><figcaption><span>Image caption, </span><p>Zelda and Robin Williams attended the 2007 People's Choice Awards in Los Angeles</p></figcaption></figure></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Her post on Tuesday reflects a trend on social media, where images of people who have died are animated, featuring  captions like "bring your loved ones back to life". </p><p>Williams continued: "To watch the legacies of real people be condensed down to 'this vaguely looks and sounds like them so that's enough', just so other people can churn out horrible TikTok slop puppeteering them is maddening," she continued. </p><p>"You're not making art, you're making disgusting, over-processed hotdogs out of the lives of human beings, out of the history of art and music, and then shoving them down someone else's throat hoping they'll give you a little thumbs up and like it. Gross."</p><p>She concluded: "And for the love of EVERY THING, stop calling it 'the future,' AI is just badly recycling and regurgitating the past to be re-consumed. You are taking in the Human Centipede of content, and from the very very end of the line, all while the folks at the front laugh and laugh, consume and consume."</p><p>The Human Centipede is a reference to the 2009 body horror film.</p></div><p data-component="subheadline-block"><h2 id="She-sparks-conversation" tabindex="-1"><span role="text">'She sparks conversation'</span></h2></p><div data-component="text-block"><p>Her latest comments come in the wake of unease following the unveiling of "AI actor", Tilly Norwood. </p><p>Norwood was created by Dutch actor and comedian Eline Van der Velden, who reportedly said she wanted Norwood to become the "next Scarlett Johansson".</p><p>In a statement, SAG-Aftra said Norwood "is not an actor, it's a character generated by a computer program that was trained on the work of countless professional performers.</p><p>"It has no life experience to draw from, no emotion and, from what we've seen, audiences aren't interested in watching computer-generated content untethered from the human experience," the union added.</p><p>Actress Emily Blunt also recently said she found the idea of Norwood terrifying.</p><p>"That is really, really scary, Come on, agencies, don't do that. Please stop. Please stop taking away our human connection," she said on a podcast with Variety.</p><p><a href="https://deadline.com/2025/09/creator-ai-actress-tilly-norwood-statement-backlash-1236564727/">Van der Velden later said in a statement<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a>: "To those who have expressed anger over the creation of my AI character, Tilly Norwood, she is not a replacement for a human being, but a creative work – a piece of art. </p><p>"Like many forms of art before her, she sparks conversation, and that in itself shows the power of creativity."</p></div></article></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Seeing like a software company (290 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.seangoedecke.com/seeing-like-a-software-company/</link>
            <guid>45505539</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 16:49:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/seeing-like-a-software-company/">https://www.seangoedecke.com/seeing-like-a-software-company/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45505539">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><header></header><section><p>The big idea of James C. Scott’s <a href="https://files.libcom.org/files/Seeing%20Like%20a%20State%20-%20James%20C.%20Scott.pdf"><em>Seeing Like A State</em></a> can be expressed in three points:</p>
<ol>
<li>Modern organizations exert control by maximising “legibility”: by altering the system so that all parts of it can be measured, reported on, and so on.</li>
<li>However, these organizations are dependent on a huge amount of “illegible” work: work that cannot be tracked or planned for, but is nonetheless essential.</li>
<li>Increasing legibility thus often actually <em>lowers</em> efficiency - but the other benefits are high enough that organizations are typically willing to do so regardless.</li>
</ol>
<p>By “legible”, I mean work that is predictable, well-estimated, has a paper trail, and doesn’t depend on any contingent factors (like the availability of specific people). Quarterly planning, OKRs, and Jira all exist to make work legible. Illegible work is everything else: asking for and giving favors, using tacit knowledge that isn’t or can’t be written down, fitting in unscheduled changes, and drawing on interpersonal relationships. As I’ll argue, tech companies need to support both of these kinds of work.</p>
<p>Thinking in terms of legibility and illegibility explains so many of the things that are confusing about large software companies. It explains why companies do many things that seem obviously counter-productive, why the <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/breaking-rules">rules in practice</a> are so often out of sync with the rules as written, and why companies are surprisingly willing to tolerate rule-breaking in some contexts.</p>
<h3>Seeing like a state</h3>
<p>James C. Scott was writing about the “high modernist” movement in governance that produced (among other things) the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/German_Forest">tidy German forests</a> of the 19th century<sup id="fnref-1"><a href="#fn-1">1</a></sup>. In order to produce wood at scale, the German state demanded <em>legibility</em>: forests that an inspector could visit to tally up the amount of healthy trees. That means that you must be able to walk through the forest - i.e. the underbrush must be controlled - and the trees ought to be ideally laid out in neat rows of a single type.</p>
<p>Proponents of legibility often describe their processes as “efficiency measures” or ways to “avoid waste”. But overall, the new “efficient” forests were in fact far less efficient than the old, illegible forests. They produced less wood per year and required more effort to fight disease, because the underbrush proved surprisingly load-bearing to the health of the soil, and the variety of species turned out to have been an asset. The new homogeneous forests could be wiped out by a single parasite or disease in a way that the older, more varied forests could not.</p>
<p>However, the advantages of legibility are enormous. Once you know exactly how many trees you have, you can plan ahead, make large trade deals, avoid graft, and so on. To me, this is the most interesting point Scott makes. Large organizations did genuinely think that more legibility would necessarily increase efficiency<sup id="fnref-2"><a href="#fn-2">2</a></sup>. But even when it became clear that that was false, <em>those organizations continued pushing for legibility anyway</em>, because the other advantages were too powerful.</p>
<h3>Seeing like a software company</h3>
<p>It’s the same way in software companies. It’s almost a truism among software engineers that a single engineer can be more efficient alone than they can by working as part of a team. That’s why there are so many anecdotes about engineers taking leave to finally get some work done, or about productive work being done on nights and weekends.</p>
<p>Likewise, it should be obvious to any practicing engineer that engineer-driven work goes far more swiftly than work that is mandated from above. Engineer-driven work doesn’t need to be translated into something that makes sense, doesn’t need to be actively communicated in all directions, and can in general just be done in the most straightforward and efficient way.</p>
<p>This is why tiny software companies are often much better than large software companies at delivering software: it doesn’t matter that the large company is throwing ten times the number of engineers at the problem if the small company is twenty times more efficient<sup id="fnref-3"><a href="#fn-3">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Why don’t large companies react to this by doing away with all of their processes? <a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/is-he-stupid-is-she-smart-are-they-stupid">Are they stupid?</a> No. The processes that slow engineers down are the same processes that make their work <em>legible</em> to the rest of the company. And that legibility (in dollar terms) is more valuable than being able to produce software more efficiently.</p>
<h3>Why legibility is valuable to tech companies</h3>
<p>What does legibility mean to a tech company, in practice? It means:</p>
<ul>
<li>The head of a department knows, to the engineer, all the projects the department is currently working on</li>
<li>That head also knows (or can request) a comprehensive list of all the projects the department has shipped in the last quarter</li>
<li>That head has the ability to <em>plan</em> work at least one quarter ahead (ideally longer)</li>
<li>That head can, in an emergency, direct the entire resources of the department at <em>immediate</em> work</li>
</ul>
<p>Note that “shipping high quality software” or “making customers happy” or even “making money” is not on this list. Those are all things tech companies want to do, but they’re not <em>legibility</em>.</p>
<p>Our small-but-efficient software company meets only one of these criteria: the ability to pivot to some immediate problem that needs solving. The other information is all locked up in various engineers’ heads, who may or may not remember what they did two months ago (and who certainly won’t be willing to commit to work two months from now). That’s not necessarily a problem, so long as everyone’s on the same page about what needs doing and the product is continuing to improve.</p>
<p>A typical large software company meets almost all of these criteria - I say almost, because in some companies or departments the ability to direct <em>immediate</em> work has atrophied (more on that later). But aside from that, large companies are usually very good at cataloguing what is being worked on, remembering what’s been shipped in the past, and planning work in the medium-to-long-term.</p>
<p>Why are these capabilities so valuable to a large software company, when small software companies can do without them? This is leaving my area of expertise somewhat, but I’m pretty sure the main answer is <strong>large enterprise deals</strong>. Making deals with large enterprise customers is fantastically profitable. Any sufficiently large SaaS will thus pivot from small customers to enterprise customers, if it can<sup id="fnref-4"><a href="#fn-4">4</a></sup>. But enterprise deals (a) can take many, many months to set up, and (b) require making long-term feature commitments. An illegible company is not configured to be able to stick with a boring enterprise deal for many months, constantly answering questions and delivering features. Large enterprise customers simply won’t trust a small software company to deliver the things they need over the next year or two.</p>
<p>Customers like this typically value legibility very highly, and so demand that their vendors also be legible. In fact, highly legible organizations struggle to communicate at all with organizations that are less legible (and vice versa). They don’t have access to the right bona fides, they don’t talk the same language, and so on. This puts real pressure on growing tech companies to become more legible, even if it hurts their ability to deliver software.</p>
<h3>Legible assumptions</h3>
<p>In the pursuit of legibility, large tech companies make simplifying assumptions about the nature of tech work. For instance, they assume:</p>
<ul>
<li>Any engineers with the same job title perform roughly the same.</li>
<li>Engineers can be shuffled and reorganized without substantial loss of productivity.</li>
<li>A team will maintain the same level of productivity over time, if it has the same number of engineers.</li>
<li>Projects can be estimated ahead of time, albeit with some margin for error. The more time spent estimating a project, the more accurate the estimate will become.</li>
</ul>
<p>Of course, all of these are false. <strong>Within the same job title, there is <em>significant</em> variance in engineering ability.</strong> Engineers have different skillsets and interests, and will work much more productively on projects that are a good fit for them. Because of this, the productivity of a team has a weak relationship to the number of engineers on the team.</p>
<p>Project estimates are largely fantasy. More accurately, they’re <em>performative</em>: <strong>the initial estimate determines the kind of engineering work that gets done to deliver by that estimate, not the other way around</strong>. For this reason, breaking down a project into parts and estimating each part often delivers a less accurate estimate, because it makes it harder for engineers to align with the overall ship date.</p>
<p>However, these assumptions are true enough for their purpose, which is to provide legibility to the executives in charge of the company. Whether the project estimate is accurate or not, it can be used to plan and to communicate with other large organizations (who are themselves typically aware that these estimates ought not to be taken completely seriously).</p>
<h3>Temporary sanctioned zones of illegibility</h3>
<p>I mentioned above that large companies sometimes lose the ability to prioritize immediate work. This is because the processes that make work legible also impose a serious delay. Consider the steps that a hypothetical large company might take before beginning to write code on a problem:</p>
<ol>
<li>Somebody has a product idea.</li>
<li>They take that idea to the Product org, where it goes into the “planning” stage. Meetings are had about the idea.</li>
<li>Once the Product org formally decide they want to do it, the idea then passes to the Engineering org: into the hands of some council of engineering architects, who are tasked with the initial technical review. They figure out how it fits into the general engineering priorities and give it a very rough time estimate.</li>
<li>The VPs and senior managers in the engineering org then negotiate which team will own the work. Often this is a semi-technical, semi-organizational decision (because which service the work should fall into is at least partly a technical question).</li>
<li>Finally the work lands on the team. It enters the team planning backlog, where the team technical lead breaks it out into smaller pieces of work.</li>
<li>Those smaller pieces of work enter the team ticket backlog, and are estimated in the team’s weekly planning meeting.</li>
<li>Finally some of those pieces of work make it into the next sprint, and are picked up by an engineer who can actually do it.</li>
</ol>
<p>I’m leaving out many crucial parts of this process: the updates on each ticket, which then roll up to higher levels of management, legal and design review, which can themselves take weeks, and then the final steps involved in shipping the change to customers. All of this makes the work very legible, but <strong>none of this is compatible with work that has to be done <em>right now</em></strong>. What do you do when there’s a sudden, urgent technical problem - maybe you’re about to overflow your <code>int</code> ID column on the users table, or some very large customer is experiencing a show-stopping bug?<sup id="fnref-5"><a href="#fn-5">5</a></sup></p>
<p>To solve this kind of problem, tech companies often reserve the right to create <em>temporary</em> zones where illegible work is allowed. Sometimes these are called “virtual teams”, or “strike teams” (or even the colourful name “tiger teams”). They are composed of hand-picked engineers who are trusted by the organization. Often there is no manager assigned at all, but instead some very senior engineer who’s tasked with running the project. These teams are given a loose mandate - like “stop the database from falling over every few days” - and allowed to do basically whatever it takes to get it done.</p>
<p>This is a smart compromise between complete illegibility, which as I discussed above would make the company unable to make deals with its richest customers, and complete legibility, which would force even urgent company-killing issues to go through the entire laborious process of scoping, planning and estimating. </p>
<p>Even when siloed to a temporary team, sanctioned illegibility still coexists awkwardly with the rest of the organization. Engineers outside the team don’t like seeing other engineers given the freedom to work without the burden of process: either because they’re jealous, or because they’re believers in process and think that such work is unacceptably dangerous. Managers also don’t like extending that level of trust. That’s why sanctioned efforts like this are almost always temporary. The majority of the illegible work that occurs in large organizations is still <em>unsanctioned</em>.</p>
<h3>Permanent zones of unsanctioned illegibility</h3>
<p>If you’re an engineer on team A, and you need team B to do some kind of work for you, the formal way to do this is to create an issue in their “planning” backlog and wait for it to go through the entire twelve-step process before it finally makes its way into one of their sprints, where hopefully somebody will pick it up and do it. This can take weeks to months. When what you want is a one-line change, it’s incredibly frustrating to watch your requested work item go through all these steps - each one of which takes many times longer than it would take to simply do the work.</p>
<p>The official way around this problem is that team A should anticipate in their planning process that team B will need to do this work, so that piece for team B can enter their backlog at the same time as it enters team A’s backlog. That way (in theory) they should be complete at around the same time<sup id="fnref-6"><a href="#fn-6">6</a></sup>. Any practicing software engineer knows how ridiculous this idea is. You can never anticipate every change that has to be made months before you start writing code.</p>
<p>The <em>actual</em> way around this problem is <strong>illegible backchannels</strong>. An engineer on team A reaches out to an engineer on team B asking “hey, can you make this one-line change for me”. That engineer on team B then does it immediately, maybe creating a ticket, maybe not. Then it’s done! This works great, but it’s illegible because the company can’t expect it or plan for it - it relies on the interpersonal relationships between engineers on different teams, which are very difficult to quantify. If you’re a well-liked engineer, your ability to pull on these backchannels is significantly greater than if you’re brand-new or have a bad reputation. But how well-liked you are is not something companies can officially use when they’re planning projects.</p>
<p>Backchannels are a constant presence at all levels of the company. As well as engineer-engineer cross-team backchannels, there are backchannels inside teams, between managers, product managers, and so on. Often when a question is asked formally in a public space, it’s already been rehearsed and workshopped privately with the person who’s answering the question. None of this is or can be documented as part of the formal processes of the company, but it’s load-bearing nonetheless. Many formal processes simply cannot function without the consensus mechanisms or safety valves offered by backchannels.</p>
<p>Sometimes backchannels can go badly. Earlier this year I wrote <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/predators"><em>Protecting your time from predators in large tech companies</em></a> about how some people use backchannels to benefit themselves at the expense of the naive engineers they’re requesting work from. And it never feels good when you get the sense that everyone in a meeting has privately discussed the topic ahead of time except for you. For these reasons, some people think that backchannels themselves are a bad thing, and that all communication should go via formal, legible channels.</p>
<h3>Sociopaths, clueless, and losers</h3>
<p>There’s another text which has been as influential to many as <em>Seeing Like A State</em>. This one isn’t a book, but a blog post: <a href="https://www.ribbonfarm.com/2009/10/07/the-gervais-principle-or-the-office-according-to-the-office/"><em>The Gervais Principle</em></a> by Venkatesh Rao. Rao divides organizations into three groups. At the top are the “sociopaths”, who cynically use organizational rules for their own benefit. In middle management are the “clueless”, who are bought into the formal rules of the organization and don’t realise that there’s a deeper game being played above their heads. Below them are the “losers”, who realise there’s a game being played but don’t want to play it. The name “losers” is not a value judgement - I think it’s meant to affectionately pick out people like the leads in <em>Clerks</em>, who are too authentic to get involved in the corporate game.</p>
<p>I don’t agree with everything in <em>The Gervais Principle</em>, though I think it’s worth a read (if you’re interested in this stuff, you should also read the excellent <a href="https://www.amazon.com.au/Moral-Mazes-World-Corporate-Managers/dp/0199729883"><em>Moral Mazes</em></a>). But the categories here can be very naturally read in terms of <em>legibility</em>. Both sociopaths and losers are engaged with the illegible world of the organization. Sociopaths use this world to climb the ladder, while losers use it to carve out a cosy low-effort niche for themselves.</p>
<p>The “clueless” are only engaged with legible processes. They’re the people who, when they want to get promoted, go and look up the formal job ladder and make a plan for how they can exemplify each of the values at the next level. They’re concerned with doing everything by the book. When they’re forced into an encounter with the illegible world, their reaction is to shake their heads and start drafting updates to the legible process that can accommodate some pale approximation of the more-efficient illegible process.</p>
<p>I think it’s far too cynical to call these people clueless. Legible process is still very important - after all, it’s the large part of what the organization does. Improving formal processes is still very high-leverage work, even if formal processes can’t ever describe the entirety of how an organization operates. People who are invested in legibility have real value to any tech company.</p>
<p>However, thinking about people in Rao’s categories - people who exploit illegibility, people who find it distasteful, and people who use it casually - can be illuminating. Many frequent areas of conflict in software companies stem from the friction between these groups of people.</p>
<h3>Final thoughts</h3>
<p>I write a lot about recognizing and using illegibility in tech companies:</p>
<ul>
<li>Breaking the (formal, legible) rules is <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/breaking-rules">sometimes the right thing to do</a></li>
<li>Beware of savvy product managers (and others) exploiting illegible channels to <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/predators">chisel work out of naive engineers</a></li>
<li>Competent engineers should work on <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/side-bets">“side bets”</a> that are outside the normal planning process</li>
<li>Getting promoted to Staff and above has <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/staff-engineer-promotions">very little to do</a> with the formal job ladder</li>
</ul>
<p>In general, advice about illegible processes is what I call <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/dangerous-advice">“dangerous advice”</a>. It’s dangerous because if you make it legible - for instance, if you announce publicly that you’re getting a piece of work done through backchannels instead of the formal process - you will be punished by the organization <em>even if your management chain wanted you to do it</em>. You can’t speak too loudly about it. It has to stay illegible.</p>
<p>I get a lot of negative feedback on these posts from people who say that you should never sidestep the formal process. According to them, if it needs changing, you should change the process instead of going around it. In other words, everything that goes on in a tech company should be <em>legible</em>, and <em>illegible</em> processes should be stamped out and converted to legible ones.</p>
<p>I think this view is naive. All organizations - tech companies, social clubs, governments - have both a legible and an illegible side. The legible side is important, past a certain size. It lets the organization do things that would otherwise be impossible: long-term planning, coordination with other very large organizations, and so on. But the illegible side is just as important. It allows for high-efficiency work, offers a release valve for processes that don’t fit the current circumstances, and fills the natural human desire for gossip and soft consensus. </p>
</section><p>If you liked this post, consider <a href="https://buttondown.com/seangoedecke" target="_blank">subscribing</a> to email updates about my new posts, or <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/submitlink?u=https://www.seangoedecke.com/seeing-like-a-software-company/&amp;t=Seeing%20like%20a%20software%20company" target="_blank">sharing it on Hacker News</a>.</p><p>September 3, 2025<!-- -->&nbsp;│ Tags: <a href="https://www.seangoedecke.com/tags/tech%20companies/">tech companies</a></p><hr></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Police Said They Surveilled Woman Who Had an Abortion for Her 'Safety.' (295 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.404media.co/police-said-they-surveilled-woman-who-had-an-abortion-for-her-safety-court-records-show-they-considered-charging-her-with-a-crime/</link>
            <guid>45505103</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 16:18:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.404media.co/police-said-they-surveilled-woman-who-had-an-abortion-for-her-safety-court-records-show-they-considered-charging-her-with-a-crime/">https://www.404media.co/police-said-they-surveilled-woman-who-had-an-abortion-for-her-safety-court-records-show-they-considered-charging-her-with-a-crime/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45505103">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <div>
      
  <div>
    
    <p>Court records show that the narrative Flock and a Texas Sheriff's Office has told the public isn't the whole story, and that police were conducting a 'death investigation' into the abortion.</p>
  </div>
    <figure>
      <img data-srcset="/content/images/size/w300/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 300w,
                /content/images/size/w600/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 600w,
                /content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 1000w,
                /content/images/size/w2000/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 2000w" data-sizes="(max-width: 800px) 50vw,
                (max-width: 1170px) 60vw,
                1400px" data-src="/content/images/size/w2000/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png" src="https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w2000/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png" alt="Police Said They Surveilled Woman Who Had an Abortion for Her 'Safety.' Court Records Show They Considered Charging Her With a Crime" srcset="https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w300/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 300w,
                https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 600w,
                https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 1000w,
                https://www.404media.co/content/images/size/w2000/2025/10/CleanShot-2025-10-07-at-05.46.26@2x.png 2000w">
        <figcaption><span>Image: Flock, Collage by Jason Koebler</span></figcaption>
    </figure>
</div>
      <div>
        <article>
          <div>
              <div>
  
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p>In May, <a href="https://www.404media.co/a-texas-cop-searched-license-plate-cameras-nationwide-for-a-woman-who-got-an-abortion/"><u>404 Media reported</u></a> that the Johnson County Sheriff’s Office in Texas searched a nationwide network of Flock cameras, a powerful AI-enabled license plate surveillance tool, to look for a woman who self-administered an abortion. At the time, the sheriff told us that the search had nothing to do with criminality and that they were concerned solely about the woman’s safety, specifically the idea that she could be bleeding to death from the abortion. Flock itself said “she was never under criminal investigation by Johnson County. She was being searched for as a missing person, not as a suspect of a crime.”</p>
</div>

<div>
  <div>
    <h2>This post is for paid members only</h2>
    <p>Become a paid member for unlimited ad-free access to articles, bonus podcast content, and more.</p>
    <p><a href="https://www.404media.co/membership/">Subscribe</a>
  </p></div>
  <div>
    <h2>Sign up for free access to this post</h2>
    <p>Free members get access to posts like this one along with an email round-up of our week's stories.</p>
    <p><a href="https://www.404media.co/signup/">Subscribe</a>
  </p></div>
  <p>Already have an account? <a href="https://www.404media.co/signin/" data-portal="signin">Sign in</a></p>
</div>          </div>
        </article>
      </div>
      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Timelinize – Privately organize your own data from everywhere, locally (491 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://timelinize.com</link>
            <guid>45504973</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 16:10:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://timelinize.com">https://timelinize.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45504973">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
		<header>
	
	
</header>

		<div>
			
			<div>
				<h2>Discover your timeline</h2>
				<p>
						Timelinize <span>("time-lynn-eyes")</span> is an open source personal archival suite, designed for modern family history. It organizes all your data onto a single, unified timeline on your own computer.
					</p>
			</div>
			
			<!-- doodle modified from https://yuanchuan.dev/time-based-css-animations -->
<css-doodle>
	
</css-doodle>
			
		</div>

		<div>
				<p>
					 <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/B7h_oYAZQbo?si=BYJr4PGa-5FLIRaV" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
				</p>

				

				<h2>A place for everything...</h2>
				<p>
					Photos, videos, text messages, locations, chats, social media, and more. Timelinize unifies it all.
				</p>
				<p>
					By adding all your data, Timelinize documents your family's life with more detail and privacy, and gives you a more complete view of your story, than standard photo library and journaling apps.
				</p>

				

				<h2>...and everything at home.</h2>
				<p>
					Most apps store your data "in the cloud" and <i>out of your control</i>. What if you lost access to your Google/Apple/Facebook accounts, or your phone? By bringing that data home to your own computer, Timelinize preserves a richer story than any one app or service can do alone.
				</p>
				<p>
					Timelinize isn't a replacement for the apps and services you already use, so you don't need to disrupt your way of life. Instead, it "sits behind" what you already use to become the permanent private archive of your working copy from:
				</p>


				
			</div>

			<div>
					<h2>Explore more</h2>

					<p>
						With several projections for your data, it's easy to keep moments alive that would otherwise be forgotten, rotting on a hard drive in your closet... or in a bigcorp's cloud.
					</p>

					<div>
						<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="1.5" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path stroke="none" d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="none"></path><path d="M12 17v4"></path><path d="M10 20l4 -2"></path><path d="M10 18l4 2"></path><path d="M5 17v4"></path><path d="M3 20l4 -2"></path><path d="M3 18l4 2"></path><path d="M19 17v4"></path><path d="M17 20l4 -2"></path><path d="M17 18l4 2"></path><path d="M9 6a3 3 0 1 0 6 0a3 3 0 0 0 -6 0"></path><path d="M7 14a2 2 0 0 1 2 -2h6a2 2 0 0 1 2 2"></path></svg>
						<p>
							The images below show a real timeline with personal data, so the application was configured to obfuscate images, names, some locations, and other personal information. Your own timeline will appear normally.
						</p>
					</div>

					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path stroke="none" d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="none"></path><path d="M4 16l6 -7l5 5l5 -6"></path><path d="M15 14m-1 0a1 1 0 1 0 2 0a1 1 0 1 0 -2 0"></path><path d="M10 9m-1 0a1 1 0 1 0 2 0a1 1 0 1 0 -2 0"></path><path d="M4 16m-1 0a1 1 0 1 0 2 0a1 1 0 1 0 -2 0"></path><path d="M20 8m-1 0a1 1 0 1 0 2 0a1 1 0 1 0 -2 0"></path></svg>
								Timeline
							</h3>
							<p>
								The timeline view semantically groups all your data into a single linear layout. Easily see what occurred on a specific day in the order it happened.
							</p>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/timeline.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/timeline.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>A timeline showing: a multimedia message sent, GPS tracks on a map, a text message received, Twitter messages exchanged, and photos/videos taken.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path stroke="none" d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="none"></path><path d="M12 18.5l-3 -1.5l-6 3v-13l6 -3l6 3l6 -3v7.5"></path><path d="M9 4v13"></path><path d="M15 7v5.5"></path><path d="M21.121 20.121a3 3 0 1 0 -4.242 0c.418 .419 1.125 1.045 2.121 1.879c1.051 -.89 1.759 -1.516 2.121 -1.879z"></path><path d="M19 18v.01"></path></svg>
								Map
							</h3>
							<p>
								Visualize your data on a huge, beautiful map of the world that plots points when and where they happened, even for data that doesn't have coordinates (like text messages and emails).
							</p>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>The world map renders your path with a colored line indicating the passage of time.</figcaption>
							</figure>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map-augment.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map-augment.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Because Timelinize is entity-aware, it can even map data points without coordinates, like this text message received while I was at the beach.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path stroke="none" d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="none"></path><path d="M21 14l-3 -3h-7a1 1 0 0 1 -1 -1v-6a1 1 0 0 1 1 -1h9a1 1 0 0 1 1 1v10"></path><path d="M14 15v2a1 1 0 0 1 -1 1h-7l-3 3v-10a1 1 0 0 1 1 -1h2"></path></svg>
								Conversations
							</h3>
							<p>
								Follow connections with people across all kinds of chats and messages. Combine conversations with people across platforms into one view.
							</p>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/conversation.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/conversation.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Example of a conversation that unites text messages and Facebook messages.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>
								<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path stroke="none" d="M0 0h24v24H0z" fill="none"></path><path d="M7 3m0 2.667a2.667 2.667 0 0 1 2.667 -2.667h8.666a2.667 2.667 0 0 1 2.667 2.667v8.666a2.667 2.667 0 0 1 -2.667 2.667h-8.666a2.667 2.667 0 0 1 -2.667 -2.667z"></path><path d="M4.012 7.26a2.005 2.005 0 0 0 -1.012 1.737v10c0 1.1 .9 2 2 2h10c.75 0 1.158 -.385 1.5 -1"></path><path d="M17 7h.01"></path><path d="M7 13l3.644 -3.644a1.21 1.21 0 0 1 1.712 0l3.644 3.644"></path><path d="M15 12l1.644 -1.644a1.21 1.21 0 0 1 1.712 0l2.644 2.644"></path></svg>
								Gallery
							</h3>
							<p>
								Browse through a rich display of photos and videos from photo libraries, messages sent and received, and other sources.
							</p>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/gallery.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/gallery.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>You can view images and videos from all data sources in the gallery.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
	
					<h2>The ultimate personal archival suite</h2>

					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Flexible, high-speed imports</h3>
							<p>
								Add millions of data points to your timeline in a matter of minutes. You get full control over background jobs like imports, thumbnails, and embeddings.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/import.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/import.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Watch the progress of imports with live charts and tables showing a sample of what is being imported.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Pictures come alive with motion</h3>
							<p>
								Timelinize supports playing "live photos" (or "motion photos") for photos taken on Apple, Google, and Samsung devices.
							</p>
						</div>
						<p>
							<figure>
								<video src="https://timelinize.com/resources/videos/motion-pictures.mp4" loop="" muted="" autoplay="" playsinline=""></video>
								<figcaption>Live photos can be easily toggled so you can either view the higher-quality still image, or the video snippet.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</p>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Entity-aware processing</h3>
							<p>
								Timelinize specializes in combining data from multiple sets and sources. It can identify people and other entities across data sources by their attributes. If a person or contact appears in multiple data sets, it will automatically merge them if possible. If not, you can easily merge entities with the click of a button.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/merge-entities.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/merge-entities.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Manually merge duplicate people/contacts in your timeline for optimal comprehension.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Magically geo-locate data without coordinates</h3>
							<p>
								Because Timelinize is entity-aware, it can project data points onto a map even without coordinate data. If a geolocated point is known for an entity around the same time of others of that entity's data points, it will appear on the map.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map-augment-2.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map-augment-2.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>This message from social media has no geocoordinates, but we can still see it on the map when and where it was received.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Make your map pop</h3>
							<p>
								Customize the map to change its theme, layers, and even make it 3D.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map-3d.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/map-3d.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>A 3D map with the satellite layer really brings this hike to life and makes it much easier to appreciate.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>See your hot spots at a glance</h3>
							<p>
								The heatmap shows where your data is concentrated. It smoothly blends as you zoom in and out.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/heatmap.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/heatmap.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Heatmaps are comprised of a sampling of your data points and ensure they all have some visibility.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Combine data sets</h3>
							<p>
								Customize what defines a duplicate item, and how to handle that, with a fine degree of control—perfect for merging separate, disparate data sets.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/import-settings.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/import-settings.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Advanced import settings give you a fine degree of control during imports: what makes an item unique, what should be updated, etc?</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>
					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Unified conversations</h3>
							<p>
								An implicit conversation is discovered when a data source links items and entities with a "sent to" relation. You can easily view conversations between entities across modalities in a single scroll: chats, emails, messages, texts, and more.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<figure>
								<a href="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/conversations.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://timelinize.com/resources/images/conversations.jpg"></a>
								<figcaption>Conversations are made of anything sent to anyone, grouped by participants.</figcaption>
							</figure>
						</div>
					</div>

				</div>

			<section>
				<div>
					<h2>Features for humans</h2>

					<p>Since I need this to function well for my own family, I have tried to give special attention to less-visible aspects of this application, such as:</p>

					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Advanced location processor</h3>
							<p>
								Timelinize deduplicates, denoises, clusters, and simplifies location data for optimal preservation, with an algorithm that subjectively performs better than Google Maps Timeline.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>CLI and HTTP API</h3>
							<p>
								For nerds like me: you can use Timelinize through its CLI, which mirrors all the functions of the HTTP API used by the frontend.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Semantic search</h3>
							<p>
								Search for pictures and messages by describing them, or find similar items to what you're viewing.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Thumbnails and transcoding</h3>
							<p>
								All items are stored verbatim, then thumbnails are generated for all images and video media, which are stored separately. Your original data is not modified.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Flexible schema</h3>
							<p>
								The database schema has been meticulously designed and refined to be as adaptable as possible.
							</p>
						</div>
					</div>

					<h2>A timeline to the future</h2>

					<p>Timelinize will continue to develop and evolve. In the future, I anticipate the following capabilities:</p>

					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Create using your timeline</h3>
							<p>
								Annotate your timeline, write rich stories with live embeddings from your timeline data, or make physical media like photo books (but with more than just photos!).
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Augment with public data</h3>
							<p>
								Add context to your timeline with additional public timelines which have weather, local/regional news, and global events.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Secure data sharing</h3>
							<p>
								Securely and privately share parts of your timeline with trusted friends and family members, directly from your computer to theirs.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Mobile apps and first-class sync</h3>
							<p>
								Right now, Timelinize sits "behind" the apps and platforms you already use. But in the future, you could sync data directly to your timeline as it is originated.
							</p>
						</div>
					</div>

					<h2>Meet your personal timeline</h2>

					<p>Collect your data from <a href="https://timelinize.com/docs/data-preparation#data-sources">various sources</a>. Import it with a few clicks. Within minutes, explore millions of your data points in several intuitive ways.</p>

					<div>
						<div>
							<h3>Self-contained, portable repositories</h3>
							<p>
								Imported data is copied into your timeline folder, ensuring long-term stability and integrity. Timelines are portable—you can copy them or move them to other devices and computers.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>No proprietary storage scheme</h3>
							<p>
								Your timeline is simply a folder on disk containing a SQLite database alongside your data files. You can freely explore it with other tooling, so you're not locked into Timelinize.
							</p>
						</div>
						<div>
							<h3>Works with data you're already generating</h3>
							<p>
								Unlike writing a journal, you don't have to take extra time to create content. You're already making the data your timeline can display! And it doesn't replace your current workflow or apps.
							</p>
						</div>
					</div>

				</div>

				<iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/VRhtEjz6hws?si=H5FqU6QHyDHC4RW-" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
			</section>

			<!--
				<p>
					Inquiries: <a href="mailto:%6d%61%74%74%40%64%79%61%6e%69%6d%2e%63%6f%6d" class="email">matt@dya<em>antispam</em>nim<em>.nospam</em>.com</a>
				</p>
			-->


			<!-- All keepsakes, no deepfakes. -->

		
		
	
</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[IKEA Catalogs 1951-2021 (420 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/</link>
            <guid>45504470</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 15:35:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/">https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45504470">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

    
    <div>
        <div>
                
                <h2>
                    IKEA catalogue                </h2>
                                    
	<div>
		<p>For over 70 years, the IKEA catalogue was produced in Älmhult, constantly growing in number, scope and distribution. From the 1950s when Ingvar Kamprad wrote most of the texts himself, via the poppy, somewhat radical 1970s and all the way into the scaled-down 2000s – the IKEA catalogue always captured the spirit of the time. The 2021 IKEA catalogue was the very last one printed on paper.</p>
		
	</div>
                  
            </div>                    
                        </div>
			<div>
					<div>
					<p>Good question! We know that a lot of people are curious about what the IKEA catalogue has looked like through the ages. The catalogue has always reflected the age and its views on interior design and everyday living, especially in Sweden, but in recent decades also internationally. The catalogue was in print for 70 years, and by digitising all the catalogues we could make them available to everybody. Making the story of IKEA available to as many people as possible is our main task at IKEA Museum. So we hope that the catalogues will bring some joy and nostalgia, and maybe even a few surprises.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Just like the perception of the home, the catalogue has changed dramatically since 1951, when it was first published. Look in the older catalogues and you’ll be amazed at what you find. In fact, you’ll probably even have a giggle or two. In the 1950s and 1960s, there are rarely any people in the pictures, and never any children. But in the 1970s there are children playing all over the home, you can see adults smoking and even the occasional political poster on the wall. Browse on to the 1980s IKEA catalogues and the trends have changed again, with shiny fabrics and other fancy materials. In the 1990s homes become more scaled-down and clearly inspired by a Scandinavian tradition. In this way, the IKEA catalogues are a kind of time capsule for you to travel in. And who knows? When we look back at the most recent catalogues in 10 or 20 years’ time, we’ll probably shake our heads and give a sigh.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>IKEA Museum decided to start with the Swedish catalogue as it has been around the longest. In the future, we hope to be able to digitise catalogues from more countries in more languages. </p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>No. The IKEA catalogue has always only shown a selection of what’s available in the stores. The catalogues from the 1970s and onwards show around 30–50 per cent of the entire range. The products that are not featured are generally smaller ones in textiles, decorations and lighting. Temporary collections are rarely included either. But the farther back you go, the higher a percentage of the range can be found in the catalogue.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Yes, but the older a product is, the harder it may be to find information about it. If you have a specific question about a product, we’re happy to help you out if we can. But 70 years is a long time, so we can’t promise anything. While you’re waiting for our response you can always browse through the catalogues – the product texts that are there are quite detailed. You can search in the catalogues by product name and product type. There are also various stories about different products on our site, and more are constantly being added.<br>
<a href="https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/product-stories/">Browse through stories about IKEA products from 7 decades</a>. </p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>IKEA was founded in the 1940s, so why are you showing no catalogues from before 1951?<br>
The first catalogue did not come out until 1951. Before that, IKEA was a mail order company that didn’t sell furniture, but pens, clocks, electric razors, wallets and bags. At that time, the range was only presented in a small mail order brochure called ikéa-nytt (literally ikéa news). Sometimes it was distributed as a supplement in farming paper <i>Jordbrukarnas Föreningsblad</i>, which reached hundreds of thousands of people in the Swedish countryside. From autumn 1948 Ingvar Kamprad started including furniture in the range, and things quickly grew from there. In the 1950 ikéa-nytt, as many as six of the 18 pages featured furniture. And when you look at the 1951 catalogue, you’ll see that there are no more pens and wallets. Ingvar Kamprad was now truly focusing on home furnishing, and shelving the rest.<br>
<a href="https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/the-story-of-ikea/ikea-news/">Browse through all issues of ikéa-nytt</a>.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Not really. We do have a few copies of each year’s IKEA catalogue in our archives, which we’re saving for posterity. They should be handled as little as possible to keep them in good condition, so we’ve made the catalogues available digitally, both online and on monitors at IKEA Museum. You can browse through those as much as you like!</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Yes you can. The easiest way to share the catalogues is to click on the arrow at the bottom left corner for each catalogue, or in the left-hand menu once you’ve started browsing through. This will copy a link which you can share on a website or social media. If you would like to download and publish on your own digital platform, you can share a maximum of three complete digital catalogues. Don’t forget to state the copyright details, “© Inter IKEA Systems B.V.”, the catalogue year, and the link <a href="https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/">/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/</a> so that anyone interested can find out more. You may not publish the digital catalogues for commercial purposes.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Absolutely! You can share up to 30 images from the catalogues on your own digital platform, such as a blog, on Instagram or similar (as long as it’s not for commercial purposes). Don’t forget to state the copyright details, “© Inter IKEA Systems B.V.”, the catalogue year, and the link <a href="https://ikeamuseum.com/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/">/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/</a> so that anyone interested can find out more.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Yes! You can find all press material, including images, information about current exhibitions and much more, in the <a href="https://ikeamuseum.com/en/about/press-room/">IKEA Museum press room</a>.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>At the moment we have a good amount of catalogues in all languages at the museum, and do not need any more. Having said that, please contact us anyway if you’ve been collecting catalogues for several decades, or if you have any other material you think might be of interest to IKEA Museum.</p>
				</div>
					<div>
					<p>Unfortunately not. We sometimes wish we did, as we handle quite a lot of old products that may need putting together and taking apart.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
	    
    <template id="compass-search-result-item">
	<div>
		<a href="/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/%URL%" class="card card--thumbnail-left card--thumbnail-small card--hover-effect ">
			<div>
				<div class="card__thumbnail">
					<img src="/en/explore/ikea-catalogue/%THUMBNAIL%" loading="lazy">
				</div>
			</div>
			<div class="card__text">
				<div class="card__eyebrow fs-15">%EYEBROW%</div>
				<div class="card__heading">
					<span class="strong fs-17">%HEADING%</span>
				</div>
			</div>
		</a>
	</div>
</template>


	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gold Prices Top $4k for First Time (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/finance/commodities-futures/gold-prices-top-4-000-for-first-time-d63ab2bd</link>
            <guid>45504381</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 15:30:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/finance/commodities-futures/gold-prices-top-4-000-for-first-time-d63ab2bd">https://www.wsj.com/finance/commodities-futures/gold-prices-top-4-000-for-first-time-d63ab2bd</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45504381">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/finance/commodities-futures/gold-prices-top-4-000-for-first-time-d63ab2bd: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Swiss glaciers have shrunk by a quarter since 2015, study says (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.france24.com/en/live-news/20251001-swiss-glaciers-shrank-by-a-quarter-in-past-decade-study</link>
            <guid>45503882</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 14:56:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/live-news/20251001-swiss-glaciers-shrank-by-a-quarter-in-past-decade-study">https://www.france24.com/en/live-news/20251001-swiss-glaciers-shrank-by-a-quarter-in-past-decade-study</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45503882">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                                                <p><a href="https://www.france24.com/en/tag/switzerland/" target="_self">Switzerland</a>'s glaciers, which are disproportionately impacted by <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/tag/climate-change/" target="_self">climate change</a>, have lost a quarter of their volume in the past decade alone, a study warned Wednesday, heightening concerns over accelerating melting.</p> <p>In 2025, glacial melting in the Alpine nation was once again "enormous", the Glacier Monitoring in Switzerland (GLAMOS) network said, adding that it was close to the record set in 2022.</p> <p>A winter with little snow combined with summer heatwaves in June and August saw Switzerland's glaciers lose three percent of their volume.</p> <p>That marks the fourth-largest level of shrinkage since measurements began, trailing only 2022, 2023 and 2003, according to GLAMOS's annual report.</p> <p>Glaciers across the <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/tag/alps/" target="_self">Alps</a> have been retreating for more than a century.</p> <p>But in recent decades, the process has sped up as the climate warms, driven by humanity's burning of fossil fuels.</p> <p>"Since about 20 years, all glaciers in Switzerland are losing ice, and the rate of this loss is accelerating," GLAMOS chief Matthias Huss told AFP.</p> <p>Between 2015 and 2025 alone, the glaciers shed 24 percent of their volume, Wednesday's report said, compared to 10 percent between 1990 and 2000.</p> <h2>Melting away</h2> <p>GLAMOS researchers did extensive measurements at around 20 reference glaciers in September, and extrapolated the findings to Switzerland's 1,400 glaciers.</p> <p>Europe's Alpine region has been hard-hit by climate change, with warming in Switzerland progressing at twice the pace of the global average, according to the Swiss Federal Office of Meteorology and Climatology.</p> 

    <div>
                                    


        


<figure>
                

<picture>
        <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:246/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.webp 246w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:388/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.webp 388w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:720/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.webp 720w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:980/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.webp 980w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) calc(100vw - 32px), (min-width: 1024px) 850px">
<img fetchpriority="low" src="https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:980/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.jpg" srcset="https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:246/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.jpg 246w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:388/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.jpg 388w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:720/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.jpg 720w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cf74be36-9e95-11f0-a476-005056bf30b7/w:980/c0448f67f865997b83a64cc76133066aa21c217c.jpg 980w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) calc(100vw - 32px), (min-width: 1024px) 850px" alt="Since the early 1970s, more than 1,100 Swiss glaciers have disappeared completely, according to GLAMOS." loading="lazy"></picture>
                        <figcaption>
                <span>Since the early 1970s, more than 1,100 Swiss glaciers have disappeared completely, according to GLAMOS.</span>                <span>© Fabrice Coffrini, AFP</span>            </figcaption>
                
    </figure>
        </div> <p>Other Alpine countries are also seeing glaciers retreat, and researchers highlight that those in Switzerland -- whose mountain peaks are higher than in neighbouring <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/tag/austria/" target="_self">Austria</a> -- may have a better chance of surviving the increasingly hot summers.</p> <p>Even so, scientists warn that Switzerland's glaciers could all but disappear by the end of this century without more action to rein in global warming.</p> <p>"We can't avoid the glacier melting overall," GLAMOS head Huss said, but "we can slow it down... with globally coordinated climate action".</p> <p>If carbon dioxide emissions "are brought to zero within 30 years... we could still save about one-third of the Swiss glaciers", Huss added.</p> <p>Since the early 1970s, more than 1,100 Swiss glaciers have disappeared completely, according to GLAMOS.</p> <h2>'Destabilising' mountains</h2> <p>Overlooking the Rhone Glacier, near Gletsch village, Huss said the giant ice mass had lost more than 100 metres (330 feet) in height in the last 20 years.</p> <p>"It's really a devastation of the ice," he said.</p> <p>Argentine tourist Wincho Ponte, 29, agreed.</p> <p>It was "really sad that it's melting so quickly", Pointe said.</p> <p>Water reserves have meanwhile been dwindling as the glaciers retreat, causing increasing problems in the summer months.</p> <p>Huss cautioned that this could hit "water availability not only up here in the mountains but also all the way down to the <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/tag/mediterranean-sea/" target="_self">Mediterranean Sea</a>".</p> 

    <div>
                                    


        


<figure>
                

<picture>
        <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:246/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.webp 246w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:388/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.webp 388w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:720/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.webp 720w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:980/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.webp 980w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) calc(100vw - 32px), (min-width: 1024px) 850px">
<img fetchpriority="low" src="https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:980/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.jpg" srcset="https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:246/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.jpg 246w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:388/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.jpg 388w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:720/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.jpg 720w,https://s.france24.com/media/display/cedc7bda-9e95-11f0-8eb8-005056bfb2b6/w:980/d1dc66fc3af7de5bc455cb53b9a598bc59e1a98b.jpg 980w" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) calc(100vw - 32px), (min-width: 1024px) 850px" alt="The Swiss village of Blatten was wiped out by a dramatic glacier collapse in May." loading="lazy"></picture>
                        <figcaption>
                <span>The Swiss village of Blatten was wiped out by a dramatic glacier collapse in May.</span>                <span>© Fabrice Coffrini, AFP</span>            </figcaption>
                
    </figure>
        </div> <p>"The continuous diminishing of glaciers also contributes to the destabilising of mountains", he warned, pointing to the Swiss village of Blatten, which was wiped out by a dramatic glacier collapse in May.</p> <p>GLAMOS determined that Swiss glacier volume will total 45.1 cubic kilometres (10.8 cubic miles) at the end of this year -- or 30 km3 less than in 2000.</p> <p>At present, the surface area of Swiss glaciers covers 755 square kilometres -- a decline of 30 percent over the past 25 years.</p> <p>This year, Switzerland's second-hottest June on record contributed to snow melting rapidly, even at the highest altitudes.</p> <p>August brought a fresh <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/tag/heatwave/" target="_self">heatwave</a>, pushing the freezing line as high as 5,000 metres above sea level -- well above the peak of western Europe's highest mountain, Mont Blanc.</p> <p>Only a rather cool and damp July "provided some relief and prevented an even worse outcome", GLAMOS said, with a few cold fronts resulting in individual days with fresh snow at higher altitudes.</p> <p>The overall summer melt this year was therefore only 15 percent above the 2010-2020 average -- its lowest level in the past four years.</p> <p><em>(FRANCE 24 with AFP)</em></p>
                                                                            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vibe engineering (249 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://simonwillison.net/2025/Oct/7/vibe-engineering/</link>
            <guid>45503867</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 14:55:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Oct/7/vibe-engineering/">https://simonwillison.net/2025/Oct/7/vibe-engineering/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45503867">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-permalink-context="/2025/Oct/7/vibe-engineering/">

<p>7th October 2025</p>



<p>I feel like <strong>vibe coding</strong> is <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Mar/19/vibe-coding/">pretty well established now</a> as covering the fast, loose and irresponsible way of building software with AI—entirely prompt-driven, and with no attention paid to how the code actually works. This leaves us with a terminology gap: what should we call the other end of the spectrum, where seasoned professionals accelerate their work with LLMs while staying proudly and confidently accountable for the software they produce?</p>
<p>I propose we call this <strong>vibe engineering</strong>, with my tongue only partially in my cheek.</p>
<p>One of the lesser spoken truths of working productively with LLMs as a software engineer on non-toy-projects is that it’s <em>difficult</em>. There’s a lot of depth to understanding how to use the tools, there are plenty of traps to avoid, and the pace at which they can churn out working code raises the bar for what the human participant can and should be contributing.</p>
<p>The rise of <strong>coding agents</strong>—tools like <a href="https://www.claude.com/product/claude-code">Claude Code</a> (released February 2025), OpenAI’s <a href="https://github.com/openai/codex">Codex CLI</a> (April) and <a href="https://github.com/google-gemini/gemini-cli">Gemini CLI</a> (June) that can iterate on code, actively testing and modifying it until it achieves a specified goal, has dramatically increased the usefulness of LLMs for real-world coding problems.</p>
<p>I’m increasingly hearing from experienced, credible software engineers who are running multiple copies of agents at once, tackling several problems in parallel and expanding the scope of what they can take on. I was skeptical of this at first but <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Oct/5/parallel-coding-agents/">I’ve started running multiple agents myself now</a> and it’s surprisingly effective, if mentally exhausting!</p>
<p>This feels very different from classic vibe coding, where I outsource a simple, low-stakes task to an LLM and accept the result if it appears to work. Most of my <a href="https://simonwillison.net/">tools.simonwillison.net</a> collection (<a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/4/highlighted-tools/">previously</a>) were built like that. Iterating with coding agents to produce production-quality code that I’m confident I can maintain in the future feels like a different process entirely.</p>
<p>It’s also become clear to me that LLMs actively reward existing top tier software engineering practices:</p>
<ul id="techniques">
<li>
<strong>Automated testing</strong>. If your project has a robust, comprehensive and stable test suite agentic coding tools can <em>fly</em> with it. Without tests? Your agent might claim something works without having actually tested it at all, plus any new change could break an unrelated feature without you realizing it. Test-first development is particularly effective with agents that can iterate in a loop.</li>
<li>
<strong>Planning in advance</strong>. Sitting down to hack something together goes much better if you start with a high level plan. Working with an agent makes this even more important—you can iterate on the plan first, then hand it off to the agent to write the code.</li>
<li>
<strong>Comprehensive documentation</strong>. Just like human programmers, an LLM can only keep a subset of the codebase in its context at once. Being able to feed in relevant documentation lets it use APIs from other areas without reading the code first. Write good documentation first and the model may be able to build the matching implementation from that input alone.</li>
<li>
<strong>Good version control habits</strong>. Being able to undo mistakes and understand when and how something was changed is even more important when a coding agent might have made the changes. LLMs are also fiercely competent at Git—they can navigate the history themselves to track down the origin of bugs, and they’re better than most developers at using <a href="https://til.simonwillison.net/git/git-bisect">git bisect</a>. Use that to your advantage.</li>
<li>Having <strong>effective automation</strong> in place. Continuous integration, automated formatting and linting, continuous deployment to a preview environment—all things that agentic coding tools can benefit from too. LLMs make writing quick automation scripts easier as well, which can help them then repeat tasks accurately and consistently next time.</li>
<li>A <strong>culture of code review</strong>. This one explains itself. If you’re fast and productive at code review you’re going to have a much better time working with LLMs than if you’d rather write code yourself than review the same thing written by someone (or something) else.</li>
<li>A <strong>very weird form of management</strong>. Getting good results out of a coding agent feels uncomfortably close to getting good results out of a human collaborator. You need to provide clear instructions, ensure they have the necessary context and provide actionable feedback on what they produce. It’s a <em>lot</em> easier than working with actual people because you don’t have to worry about offending or discouraging them—but any existing management experience you have will prove surprisingly useful.</li>
<li>Really good <strong>manual QA (quality assurance)</strong>. Beyond automated tests, you need to be really good at manually testing software, including predicting and digging into edge-cases.</li>
<li>Strong <strong>research skills</strong>. There are dozens of ways to solve any given coding problem. Figuring out the best options and proving an approach has always been important, and remains a blocker on unleashing an agent to write the actual code.</li>
<li>The ability to <strong>ship to a preview environment</strong>. If an agent builds a feature, having a way to safely preview that feature (without deploying it straight to production) makes reviews much more productive and greatly reduces the risk of shipping something broken.</li>
<li>An instinct for <strong>what can be outsourced</strong> to AI and what you need to manually handle yourself. This is constantly evolving as the models and tools become more effective. A big part of working effectively with LLMs is maintaining a strong intuition for when they can best be applied.</li>
<li>An updated <strong>sense of estimation</strong>. Estimating how long a project will take has always been one of the hardest but most important parts of being a senior engineer, especially in organizations where budget and strategy decisions are made based on those estimates. AI-assisted coding makes this <em>even harder</em>—things that used to take a long time are much faster, but estimations now depend on new factors which we’re all still trying to figure out.</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’re going to really exploit the capabilities of these new tools, you need to be operating <em>at the top of your game</em>. You’re not just responsible for writing the code—you’re researching approaches, deciding on high-level architecture, writing specifications, defining success criteria, <a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Sep/30/designing-agentic-loops/">designing agentic loops</a>, planning QA, managing a growing army of weird digital interns who will absolutely cheat if you give them a chance, and spending <em>so much time on code review</em>.</p>
<p>Almost all of these are characteristics of senior software engineers already!</p>
<p>AI tools <strong>amplify existing expertise</strong>. The more skills and experience you have as a software engineer the faster and better the results you can get from working with LLMs and coding agents.</p>
<h4 id="-vibe-engineering-really-">“Vibe engineering”, really?</h4>
<p>Is this a stupid name? Yeah, probably. “Vibes” as a concept in AI feels a little tired at this point. “Vibe coding” itself is used by a lot of developers in a dismissive way. I’m ready to reclaim vibes for something more constructive.</p>
<p>I’ve never really liked the artificial distinction between “coders” and “engineers”—that’s always smelled to me a bit like gatekeeping. But in this case a bit of gatekeeping is exactly what we need!</p>
<p><strong>Vibe engineering</strong> establishes a clear distinction from vibe coding. It signals that this is a different, harder and more sophisticated way of working with AI tools to build production software.</p>
<p>I like that this is cheeky and likely to be controversial. This whole space is still absurd in all sorts of different ways. We shouldn’t take ourselves too seriously while we figure out the most productive ways to apply these new tools.</p>
<p>I’ve tried in the past to get terms like <strong><a href="https://simonwillison.net/tags/ai-assisted-programming/">AI-assisted programming</a></strong> to stick, with approximately zero success. May as well try rubbing some vibes on it and see what happens.</p>
<p>I also really like the clear mismatch between “vibes” and “engineering”. It makes the combined term self-contradictory in a way that I find mischievous and (hopefully) sticky.</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No account? No Windows 11, Microsoft says as another loophole snaps shut (329 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/07/windows_11_local_account_loophole/</link>
            <guid>45503726</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 14:45:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/07/windows_11_local_account_loophole/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/07/windows_11_local_account_loophole/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45503726">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Microsoft is closing a popular loophole that allowed users to install Windows 11 without a Microsoft account.</p>
<p>The change has appeared in <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2025/10/06/announcing-windows-11-insider-preview-build-26220-6772-dev-channel/">recent Insider builds</a> of Windows 11, indicating it is likely to be included in the production version soon.</p>
<p>Microsoft refers to these loopholes as "known mechanisms" and is talking about local commands in this instance. You can learn all about these in our <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/08/05/set_up_windows11_local_account/">piece</a> for getting Windows 11 installed with a local account, but suffice to say <code>start ms-cxh:localonly</code> is no more.</p>

    

<p>"While these mechanisms were often used to bypass Microsoft account setup, they also inadvertently skip critical setup screens, potentially causing users to exit OOBE with a device that is not fully configured for use," Microsoft said.</p>

        


        

<p>"Users will need to complete OOBE with internet and a Microsoft account, to ensure [the] device is set up correctly."</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/02/windows_10_statcounter/">Windows 10 refuses to go gentle into that good night</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/01/hundreds_businesses_urge_microsoft_not_end_win10_support/">Hundreds of orgs urge Microsoft: don't kill off free Windows 10 updates</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/10/01/windows_11_25h2/">Windows 11 25H2 is mostly 24H2 with bits bolted on or ripped out</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/09/30/windows_11_healthcare/">Healthcare lags in Windows 11 upgrades – and lives may depend on it</a></li>
</ul>
<p>As far as Redmond is concerned, this is all for the user's own good. It is also important to note that managed devices are not directly affected, just hardware that users want to get running with Windows 11 without having to deal with a Microsoft Account during setup.</p>
<p>The change is part of Microsoft's ongoing game of Whac-A-Mole with users trying to find ways of avoiding its online services. In <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/03/31/windows_11_insiders/">March</a>, it removed the <code>bypassnro.cmd</code> script that allowed users to get through the Windows 11 setup without needing an internet connection. That time, Microsoft said the change was to "enhance security and user experience of Windows 11."</p>
<p>There remain a number of ways to avoid the Microsoft account requirement during setup, including setting up an unattended installation, but these are more complicated. It is also clear that Microsoft is determined to continue closing loopholes where it can.</p>

        

<p>It is getting increasingly difficult to use Windows 11 on an unmanaged device without a Microsoft account. Users who don't want to sign up should perhaps consider whether it's time to look at an alternative operating system instead. ®</p>                                


                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>