<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 04:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux Sandboxes and Fil-C (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fil-c.org/seccomp</link>
            <guid>46259064</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 22:58:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fil-c.org/seccomp">https://fil-c.org/seccomp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46259064">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        
        <main>


<p>Memory safety and sandboxing are two different things. It's reasonable to think of them as orthogonal: you could have memory safety but not be sandboxed, or you could be sandboxed but not memory safe.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Example of <strong>memory safe</strong> <em>but not</em> <strong>sandboxed</strong>: a pure Java program that opens files on the filesystem for reading and writing and accepts filenames from the user. The OS will allow this program to overwrite any file that the user has access to. This program can be quite dangerous even if it is memory safe. Worse, imagine that the program didn't have any code to open files for reading and writing, but also had no sandbox to prevent those syscalls from working. If there was a bug in the memory safety enforcement of this program (say, because of a bug in the Java implementation), then an attacker could cause this program to overwrite any file if they succeeded at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weird_machine">achieving code execution via weird state</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Example of <strong>sandboxed</strong> <em>but not</em> <strong>memory safe</strong>: a program written in assembly that starts by requesting that the OS revoke all of its capabilities beyond just pure compute. If the program did want to open a file or write to it, then the kernel will kill the process, based on the earlier request to have this capability revoked. This program could have lots of memory safety bugs (because it's written in assembly), but even if it did, then the attacker cannot make this program overwrite any file unless they find some way to bypass the sandbox.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>In practice, sandboxes have holes by design. A typical sandbox allows the program to send and receive messages to broker processes that have higher privileges. So, an attacker may first use a memory safety bug to make the sandboxed process send malicious messages, and then use those malicious messages to break into the brokers.</p>

<p><strong>The best kind of defense is to have both a sandbox and memory safety.</strong> This document describes how to combine sandboxing and Fil-C's memory safety by explaining what it takes to port OpenSSH's seccomp-based Linux sandbox code to Fil-C.</p>

<h2>Background</h2>

<p><a href="https://fil-c.org/how.html">Fil-C is a memory safe implementation of C and C++</a> and this site <a href="https://fil-c.org/documentation.html">has a lot of documentation about it</a>. Unlike most memory safe languages, Fil-C enforces safety down to where your code meets Linux syscalls and the <a href="https://fil-c.org/runtime.html">Fil-C runtime</a> is robust enough that it's possible to use it in <a href="https://fil-c.org/pizlix.html">low-level system components like <code>init</code> and <code>udevd</code></a>. <a href="https://fil-c.org/programs_that_work.html">Lots of programs work in Fil-C</a>, including OpenSSH, which makes use of seccomp-BPF sandboxing.</p>

<p>This document focuses on how OpenSSH uses seccomp and other technologies on Linux to build a sandbox around its <a href="http://www.citi.umich.edu/u/provos/ssh/privsep.html">unprivileged <code>sshd-session</code> process</a>. Let's review what tools Linux gives us that OpenSSH uses:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><code>chroot</code> to restrict the process's view of the filesystem.</p></li>
<li><p>Running the process with the <code>sshd</code> user and group, and giving that user/group no privileges.</p></li>
<li><p><code>setrlimit</code> to prevent opening files, starting processes, or writing to files.</p></li>
<li><p>seccomp-BPF syscall filter to reduce the attack surface by allowlisting only the set of syscalls that are legitimate for the unprivileged process. Syscalls not in the allowlist will crash the process with <code>SIGSYS</code>.</p></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://chromium.googlesource.com/chromium/src/+/0e94f26e8/docs/linux_sandboxing.md">The Chromium developers</a> and <a href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Security/Sandbox/Seccomp">the Mozilla developers</a> both have excellent notes about how to do sandboxing on Linux using seccomp. <a href="https://www.kernel.org/doc/html/v4.19/userspace-api/seccomp_filter.html">Seccomp-BPF is a well-documented kernel feature</a> that can be used as part of a larger sandboxing story.</p>

<p>Fil-C makes it easy to use <code>chroot</code> and different users and groups. The syscalls that are used for that part of the sandbox are trivially allowed by Fil-C and no special care is required to use them.</p>

<p>Both <code>setrlimit</code> and seccomp-BPF require special care because the Fil-C runtime starts threads, allocates memory, and performs synchronization. This document describes what you need to know to make effective use of those sandboxing technologies in Fil-C. First, I describe how to build a sandbox that prevents thread creation without breaking Fil-C's use of threads. Then, I describe what tweaks I had to make to OpenSSH's seccomp filter. Finally, I describe how the Fil-C runtime implements the syscalls used to install seccomp filters.</p>

<h2>Preventing Thread Creation Without Breaking The Fil-C Runtime</h2>

<p>The Fil-C runtime uses <a href="https://fil-c.org/fugc.html">multiple background threads for garbage collection</a> and has the ability to automatically shut those threads down when they are not in use. If the program wakes up and starts allocating memory again, then those threads are automatically restarted.</p>

<p>Starting threads violates the "no new processes" rule that OpenSSH's <code>setrlimit</code> sandbox tries to achieve (since threads are just lightweight processes on Linux). It also relies on syscalls like <code>clone3</code> that are not part of OpenSSH's seccomp filter allowlist.</p>

<p>It would be a regression to the sandbox to allow process creation just because the Fil-C runtime relies on it. Instead, I added a new API to <a href="https://fil-c.org/stdfil.html"><code>&lt;stdfil.h&gt;</code></a>:</p>

<pre><code>void zlock_runtime_threads(void);
</code></pre>

<p>This forces the runtime to immediately create whatever threads it needs, and to disable shutting them down on demand. Then, I added a call to <code>zlock_runtime_threads()</code> in OpenSSH's <code>ssh_sandbox_child</code> function before either the <code>setrlimit</code> or seccomp-BPF sandbox calls happen.</p>

<h2>Tweaks To The OpenSSH Sandbox</h2>

<p>Because the use of <code>zlock_runtime_threads()</code> prevents subsequent thread creation from happening, most of the OpenSSH sandbox just works. I did not have to change how OpenSSH uses <code>setrlimit</code>. I did change the following about the seccomp filter:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Failure results in <code>SECCOMP_RET_KILL_PROCESS</code> rather than <code>SECCOMP_RET_KILL</code>. This ensures that Fil-C's background threads are also killed if a sandbox violation occurs.</p></li>
<li><p><code>MAP_NORESERVE</code> is added to the <code>mmap</code> allowlist, since the Fil-C allocator uses it. This is not a meaningful regression to the filter, since <code>MAP_NORESERVE</code> is not a meaningful capability for an attacker to have.</p></li>
<li><p><code>sched_yield</code> is allowed. This is not a dangerous syscall (it's semantically a no-op). The Fil-C runtime uses it as part of its lock implementation.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Nothing else had to change, since the filter already allowed all of the <code>futex</code> syscalls that Fil-C uses for synchronization.</p>

<h2>How Fil-C Implements <code>prctl</code></h2>

<p>The OpenSSH seccomp filter is installed using two <code>prctl</code> calls. First, we <code>PR_SET_NO_NEW_PRIVS</code>:</p>

<pre><code>if (prctl(PR_SET_NO_NEW_PRIVS, 1, 0, 0, 0) == -1) {
        debug("%s: prctl(PR_SET_NO_NEW_PRIVS): %s",
            __func__, strerror(errno));
        nnp_failed = 1;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This prevents additional privileges from being acquired via <code>execve</code>. It's required that unprivileged processes that install seccomp filters first set the <code>no_new_privs</code> bit.</p>

<p>Next, we <code>PR_SET_SECCOMP, SECCOMP_MODE_FILTER</code>:</p>

<pre><code>if (prctl(PR_SET_SECCOMP, SECCOMP_MODE_FILTER, &amp;preauth_program) == -1)
        debug("%s: prctl(PR_SET_SECCOMP): %s",
            __func__, strerror(errno));
else if (nnp_failed)
        fatal("%s: SECCOMP_MODE_FILTER activated but "
            "PR_SET_NO_NEW_PRIVS failed", __func__);
</code></pre>

<p>This installs the seccomp filter in <code>preauth_program</code>. Note that this will fail in the kernel if the <code>no_new_privs</code> bit is not set, so the fact that OpenSSH reports a fatal error if the filter is installed without <code>no_new_privs</code> is just healthy paranoia on the part of the OpenSSH authors.</p>

<p>The trouble with both syscalls is that they affect the calling <em>thread</em>, not all threads in the process. Without special care, Fil-C runtime's background threads would not have the <code>no_new_privs</code> bit set and would not have the filter installed. This would mean that if an attacker busted through Fil-C's memory safety protections (in the unlikely event that they found a bug in Fil-C itself!), then they could use those other threads to execute syscalls that bypass the filter!</p>

<p>To prevent even this unlikely escape, the Fil-C runtime's wrapper for <code>prctl</code> implements <code>PR_SET_NO_NEW_PRIVS</code> and <code>PR_SET_SECCOMP</code> by <em>handshaking</em> all runtime threads using this internal API:</p>

<pre><code>/* Calls the callback from every runtime thread. */
PAS_API void filc_runtime_threads_handshake(void (*callback)(void* arg), void* arg);
</code></pre>

<p>The callback performs the requested <code>prctl</code> from each runtime thread. This ensures that the <code>no_new_privs</code> bit and the filter are installed on all threads in the Fil-C process.</p>

<p>Additionally, because of ambiguity about what to do if the process has multiple user threads, these two <code>prctl</code> commands will trigger a Fil-C safety error if the program has multiple user threads.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>The best kind of protection if you're serious about security is to combine memory safety with sandboxing. This document shows how to achieve this using Fil-C and the sandbox technologies available on Linux, all without regressing the level of protection that those sandboxes enforce or the memory safety guarantees of Fil-C.</p>
        </main>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Recovering Anthony Bourdain's (really) lost Li.st's (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sandyuraz.com/blogs/bourdain/</link>
            <guid>46258163</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 21:18:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sandyuraz.com/blogs/bourdain/">https://sandyuraz.com/blogs/bourdain/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46258163">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>
🥐 At least 2 days ago
</p>
<p>
Loved reading through <em>GReg TeChnoLogY</em> <a href="https://bourdain.greg.technology/" title="">Anthony Bourdain’s Lost Li.st’s</a> and seeing the list of lost Anthony Bourdain li.st’s made me think on whether at least <strong>some</strong> of them we can recover.
</p>
<p>
Having worked in security and crawling space for majority of my career—I don’t have the access nor permission to use the proprietary storages—I thought we might be able to find something from publicly available crawl archives.
</p>

<h2 id="common-crawl">Common Crawl</h2>
<p>
If <em>Internet Archive</em> had the partial list that Greg published, what about the <em>Common Crawl</em>? Reading through their <a href="https://commoncrawl.org/get-started" title="">documentation</a>, it seems straightforward enough to get prefix index for Tony’s lists and grep for any sub-paths.
</p>
<p>
Putting something up with help of Claude to prove my theory, we have <code>commoncrawl_search.py</code> that makes a single index request to a specific dataset and if any hits discovered, retrieve them from the public s3 bucket—since they are small straight-up HTML documents, seems even more feasible than I had initially thought.
</p>
<p>
Simply have a python version around 3.14.2 and install the dependencies from <code>requirements.txt</code>. Run the below and we are in business. Now, below, you’ll find the command I ran and then some manual archeological effort to prettify the findings.
</p></div><div>

<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>Images <strong>have been lost</strong>. Other avenues had struck no luck. I’ll try again later.</p>
</div>
<p>
Any and all emphasis, missing punctuation, cool grammar is all by Anthony Bourdain. The only modifications I have made is to the layout, to represent <code>li.st</code> as closely as possible with <strong>no changes to the content.</strong>
</p>
<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>If you see these blocks, that’s me commenting if pictures have been lost.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="recovering-what-we-lost">Recovering what we lost</h2>
<p>
From Greg’s page, let’s go and try each entry one by one, I’ll put the table of what I wasn’t able to find in <strong>Common Crawl</strong>, but I would assume exists elsewhere—I’d be happy to take another look. And no, none of this above has been written by AI, only the code since I don’t really care about <code>warcio</code> encoding or writing the same python requests method for the Nth time. Enjoy!
</p>
<h2 id="things-i-no-longer-have-time-or-patience-for">Things I No Longer Have Time or Patience For</h2>

<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Cocaine
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
True Detective
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Scripps Howard
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Dinners where it takes the waiter longer to describe my food than it takes me to eat it.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Beer nerds
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="nice-views">Nice Views</h2>

<p>
I admit it: my life doesn’t suck. Some recent views I’ve enjoyed
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Montana at sunset : There’s pheasant cooking behind the camera somewhere. To the best of my recollection some very nice bourbon. And it IS a big sky .
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Puerto Rico: Thank you Jose Andres for inviting me to this beautiful beach!
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Naxos: drinking ouzo and looking at this. Not a bad day at the office .
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
LA: My chosen final resting place . Exact coordinates .
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Istanbul: raki and grilled lamb and this ..
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Borneo: The air is thick with hints of durian, sambal, coconut..
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Chicago: up early to go train #Redzovic
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="if-i-were-trapped-on-a-desert-island-with-only-three-tv-series">If I Were Trapped on a Desert Island With Only Three Tv Series</h2>

<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
The Wire
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Tinker, Tailor, Soldier, Spy (and its sequel : Smiley’s People)
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Edge of Darkness (with Bob Peck and Joe Don Baker )
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="the-film-nobody-ever-made">The Film Nobody Ever Made</h2>

<p>
Dreamcasting across time with the living and the dead, this untitled, yet to be written masterwork of cinema, shot, no doubt, by Christopher Doyle, lives only in my imagination.
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
This guy
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
And this guy
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
All great films need:
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
The Oscar goes to..
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
And
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>Sorry, each item had a picture attached, they’re gone.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="i-want-them-back">I Want Them Back</h2>

<p>
If you bought these vinyls from an emaciated looking dude with an eager, somewhat distracted expression on his face somewhere on upper Broadway sometime in the mid 80’s, that was me . I’d like them back. In a sentimental mood.
</p>
<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>There were 11 images here.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="objects-of-desire">Objects of Desire</h2>

<p>
material things I feel a strange, possibly unnatural attraction to and will buy (if I can) if I stumble across them in my travels. I am not a paid spokesperson for any of this stuff .
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Vintage Persol sunglasses : This is pretty obvious. I wear them a lot. I collect them when I can. Even my production team have taken to wearing them.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
19th century trepanning instruments: I don’t know what explains my fascination with these devices, designed to drill drain-sized holes into the skull often for purposes of relieving "pressure" or "bad humours". But I can’t get enough of them. Tip: don’t get a prolonged headache around me and ask if I have anything for it. I do.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Montagnard bracelets: I only have one of these but the few that find their way onto the market have so much history. Often given to the indigenous mountain people ’s Special Forces advisors during the very early days of America’s involvement in Vietnam .
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Jiu Jitsi Gi’s: Yeah. When it comes to high end BJJ wear, I am a total whore. You know those people who collect limited edition Nikes ? I’m like that but with Shoyoroll . In my defense, I don’t keep them in plastic bags in a display case. I wear that shit.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Voiture: You know those old school, silver plated (or solid silver) blimp like carts they roll out into the dining room to carve and serve your roast? No. Probably not. So few places do that anymore. House of Prime Rib does it. Danny Bowein does it at Mission Chinese. I don’t have one of these. And I likely never will. But I can dream.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Kramer knives: I don’t own one. I can’t afford one . And I’d likely have to wait for years even if I could afford one. There’s a long waiting list for these individually hand crafted beauties. But I want one. Badly. http://www.kramerknives.com/gallery/
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
R. CRUMB : All of it. The collected works. These Taschen volumes to start. I wanted to draw brilliant, beautiful, filthy comix like Crumb until I was 13 or 14 and it became clear that I just didn’t have that kind of talent. As a responsible father of an 8 year old girl, I just can’t have this stuff in the house. Too dark, hateful, twisted. Sigh...
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE MAGNIFICENT AMBERSONS : THE UNCUT, ORIGINAL ORSON WELLES VERSION: It doesn’t exist. Which is why I want it. The Holy Grail for film nerds, Welles’ follow up to CITIZEN KANE shoulda, coulda been an even greater masterpiece . But the studio butchered it and re-shot a bullshit ending. I want the original. I also want a magical pony.
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>Each bulleted point had an image too.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="four-spy-novels-by-real-spies-and-one-not-by-a-spy">Four Spy Novels by Real Spies and One Not by a Spy</h2>

<p>
I like good spy novels. I prefer them to be realistic . I prefer them to be written by real spies. If the main character carries a gun, I’m already losing interest. Spy novels should be about betrayal.
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Ashenden–Somerset Maugham<br>Somerset wrote this bleak, darkly funny, deeply cynical novel in the early part of the 20th century. It was apparently close enough to the reality of his espionage career that MI6 insisted on major excisions. Remarkably ahead of its time in its atmosphere of futility and betrayal.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
The Man Who Lost the War–WT Tyler<br>WT Tyler is a pseudonym for a former "foreign service" officer who could really really write. This one takes place in post-war Berlin and elsewhere and was, in my opinion, wildly under appreciated. See also his Ants of God.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
The Human Factor–Graham Greene<br>Was Greene thinking of his old colleague Kim Philby when he wrote this? Maybe. Probably. See also Our Man In Havana.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
The Tears of Autumn -Charles McCarry<br>A clever take on the JFK assassination with a Vietnamese angle. See also The Miernik Dossier and The Last Supper
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Agents of Innocence–David Ignatius<br>Ignatius is a journalist not a spook, but this one, set in Beirut, hewed all too closely to still not officially acknowledged events. Great stuff.
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="hotel-slut--that-s-me">Hotel Slut (That’s Me)</h2>

<p>
I wake up in a lot of hotels, so I am fiercely loyal to the ones I love. A hotel where I know immediately wher I am when I open my eyes in the morning is a rare joy. Here are some of my favorites
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
CHATEAU MARMONT ( LA) : if I have to die in a hotel room, let it be here. I will work in LA just to stay at the Chateau.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
CHILTERN FIREHOUSE (London): Same owner as the Chateau. An amazing Victorian firehouse turned hotel. Pretty much perfection
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE RALEIGH (Miami): The pool. The pool!
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
LE CONTINENTAL (Saigon): For the history.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
HOTEL OLOFSSON (Port au Prince): Sagging, creaky and leaky but awesome .
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
PARK HYATT (Tokyo): Because I’m a film geek.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
EDGEWATER INN (Seattle): kind of a lumber theme going on...ships slide right by your window. And the Led Zep "Mudshark incident".
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE METROPOLE (Hanoi): there’s a theme developing: if Graham Greene stayed at a hotel, chances are I will too.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
GRAND HOTEL D'ANGKOR (Siem Reap): I’m a sucker for grand, colonial era hotels in Asia.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE MURRAY (Livingston,Montana): You want the Peckinpah suite
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="steaming-hot-porn">Steaming Hot Porn</h2>

<p>
from my phone
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Bun Bo Hue
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Kuching Laksa
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Pot au Feu
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Jamon
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Linguine
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Meat
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Dessert
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Light Lunch
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Meat on a Stick
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Oily Little Fish
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Snack
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Soup
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Homage
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>Pictures in each have not been recovered.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="5-photos-on-my-phone--chosen-at-random">5 Photos on My Phone, Chosen at Random</h2>

<p>
Not TOO random
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Madeline
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Beirut
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Musubi
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
BudaeJiggae
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Dinner
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<div>
<p>NOTE</p>
<p>Shame, indeed, no pictures, there was one for each.</p>
</div>
<h2 id="people-i-d-like-to-be-for-a-day">People I’d Like to Be for a Day</h2>

<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Bootsy Collins
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Bill Murray
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="i-m-hungry-and-would-be-very-happy-to-eat-any-of-this-right-now">I’m Hungry and Would Be Very Happy to Eat Any of This Right Now</h2>

<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Spaghetti a la bottarga . I would really, really like some of this. Al dente, lots of chili flakes
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
A big, greasy double cheeseburger. No lettuce. No tomato. Potato bun.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
A street fair sausage and pepper hero would be nice. Though shitting like a mink is an inevitable and near immediate outcome
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Some uni. Fuck it. I’ll smear it on an English muffin at this point.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
I wonder if that cheese is still good?
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="observations-from-a-beach">Observations From a Beach</h2>

<p>
In which my Greek idyll is Suddenly invaded by professional nudists
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Endemic FUPA. Apparently a prerequisite for joining this outfit.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Pistachio dick
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
70’s bush
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
T-shirt and no pants. Leading one to the obvious question : why bother?
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="guilty-pleasures">Guilty Pleasures</h2>

<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
Popeye’s Mac and Cheese
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
The cheesy crust on the side of the bowl of Onion Soup Gratinee
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Macaroons . Not macarons . Macaroons
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Captain Crunch
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Double Double Animal Style
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Spam Musubi
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
Aerosmith
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="some-new-york-sandwiches">Some New York Sandwiches</h2>

<p>
Before he died, Warren Zevon dropped this wisdom bomb: "Enjoy every sandwich". These are a few locals I’ve particularly enjoyed:
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
PASTRAMI QUEEN: (1125 Lexington Ave. ) Pastrami Sandwich. Also the turkey with Russian dressing is not bad. Also the brisket.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
EISENBERG'S SANDWICH SHOP: ( 174 5th Ave.) Tuna salad on white with lettuce. I’d suggest drinking a lime Rickey or an Arnold Palmer with that.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE JOHN DORY OYSTER BAR: (1196 Broadway) the Carta di Musica with Bottarga and Chili is amazing. Is it a sandwich? Yes. Yes it is.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
RANDOM STREET FAIRS: (Anywhere tube socks and stale spices are sold. ) New York street fairs suck. The same dreary vendors, same bad food. But those nasty sausage and pepper hero sandwiches are a siren song, luring me, always towards the rocks. Shitting like a mink almost immediately after is guaranteed but who cares?
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
BARNEY GREENGRASS : ( 541 Amsterdam Ave.) Chopped Liver on rye. The best chopped liver in NYC.
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>

<h2 id="great-dead-bars-of-new-york">Great Dead Bars of New York</h2>

<p>
A work in progress
</p>
<div>
<ol>

<li>
<p>
SIBERIA in any of its iterations. The one on the subway being the best
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
LADY ANNES FULL MOON SALOON a bar so nasty I’d bring out of town visitors there just to scare them
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE LION'S HEAD old school newspaper hang out
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
KELLY'S on 43rd and Lex. Notable for 25 cent drafts and regularly and reliably serving me when I was 15
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE TERMINAL BAR legendary dive across from port authority
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
BILLY'S TOPLESS (later, Billy’s Stopless) an atmospheric, working class place, perfect for late afternoon drinking where nobody hustled you for money and everybody knew everybody. Great all-hair metal jukebox . Naked breasts were not really the point.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE BAR AT HAWAII KAI. tucked away in a giant tiki themed nightclub in Times Square with a midget doorman and a floor show. Best place to drop acid EVER.
</p>
</li>

<li>
<p>
THE NURSERY after hours bar decorated like a pediatrician’s office. Only the nursery rhyme characters were punk rockers of the day.
</p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
</div><div>

<h2 id="lost-page">Lost page</h2>
<p>
It was surprising to see that only one page was not recoverable from the common crawl.
</p></div><div>

<h2 id="what-s-next">What’s next?</h2>
<p>
I’ve enjoyed this little project tremendously—a little archeology project. Can we declare victory for at least this endeavor? Hopefully, we would be able to find images, but that’s a little tougher, since that era’s cloudfront is fully gone.
</p>
<p>
What else can we work on restoring and setting up some sort of a public archive to store them? I made this a <a href="https://github.com/thecsw/bourdain" title="">git repository</a> for the sole purpose so that anyone interested can contribute their interest and passion for these kinds of projects.
</p>
<p>
Thank you and until next time! <b>◼︎</b>
</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Want to sway an election? Here’s how much fake online accounts cost (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/content/article/want-sway-election-here-s-how-much-fake-online-accounts-cost</link>
            <guid>46257871</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 20:48:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/content/article/want-sway-election-here-s-how-much-fake-online-accounts-cost">https://www.science.org/content/article/want-sway-election-here-s-how-much-fake-online-accounts-cost</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46257871">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/content/article/want-sway-election-here-s-how-much-fake-online-accounts-cost: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Twilio Segment moved from microservices back to a monolith (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.twilio.com/en-us/blog/developers/best-practices/goodbye-microservices</link>
            <guid>46257714</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 20:30:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.twilio.com/en-us/blog/developers/best-practices/goodbye-microservices">https://www.twilio.com/en-us/blog/developers/best-practices/goodbye-microservices</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46257714">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="">

    
    
    




    
        
        
            
            

        
        
    
        
        
            
            

        
        
    
        
        
            
            <div>




    
        
        
        
            
            

<div data-ext-icon="<svg viewBox=&quot;0 0 79 79&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; class=&quot;icon--decorative&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;>
    <title>An icon of a outbound link arrow</title>
    <path class=&quot;icon-stroke&quot; d=&quot;M75.3037 3.98207L3 75.5935M75.3037 3.98207L76.0435 43.3021M75.3037 3.98207L35.951 3.59351&quot; stroke=&quot;#F22F46&quot; stroke-width=&quot;5.5&quot; stroke-linecap=&quot;round&quot; stroke-linejoin=&quot;round&quot;/>
</svg>
">
        <h2 id="introduction"><a href="#introduction">Goodbye Microservices: From 100s of problem children to 1 superstar</a></h2>
<p>Microservices is a service-oriented software architecture in which server-side applications are constructed by combining many single-purpose, low-footprint network services. The touted benefits are improved modularity, reduced testing burden, better functional composition, environmental isolation, and development team autonomy. The opposite is a Monolithic architecture, where a large amount of functionality lives in a single service which is tested, deployed, and scaled as a single unit.</p>
<p>Twilio Segment&nbsp;adopted this as a best practice&nbsp;early-on, which served us well in some cases, and, as you’ll soon learn, not so well in others.</p>
<p>In the early days of Twilio Segment, we reached a tipping point with a core piece of <a href="https://segment.com/product?utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.twilio.com%2Fen-us%2Fblog%2Fdevelopers%2Fbest-practices%2Fgoodbye-microservices" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twilio&nbsp;Segment’s product</a>. It seemed as if we were falling from the microservices tree, hitting every branch on the way down. Instead of enabling us to move faster, the small team found themselves mired in exploding complexity. Essential benefits of this architecture became burdens. As our velocity plummeted, our defect rate exploded.</p>
<p>Eventually, the team found themselves unable to make headway, with 3 full-time engineers spending most of their time just keeping the system alive. Something had to change. This post is the story of how we took a step back and embraced an approach that aligned well with our product requirements and needs of the team.</p>
<h2 id="why-microservices-worked"><a href="#why-microservices-worked">Why Microservices worked</a></h2>
<p>Twilio Segment’s customer data infrastructure ingests hundreds of thousands of events per second and forwards them to partner APIs, what we refer to as <b>server-side destinations</b>. There are <a target="_blank" href="https://segment.com/docs/connections/destinations/catalog/?utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.twilio.com%2Fen-us%2Fblog%2Fdevelopers%2Fbest-practices%2Fgoodbye-microservices" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">over one hundred types of these destinations</a>, such as Google Analytics, Optimizely, or a custom webhook.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Years back, when the product initially launched, the architecture was simple. There was an API that ingested events and forwarded them to a distributed message queue. An event, in this case, is a JSON object generated by a web or mobile app containing information about users and their actions. A sample payload looks like the following:</p>
<p>As events were consumed from the queue, customer-managed settings were checked to decide which destinations should receive the event. The event was then sent to each destination’s API, one after another, which was useful because developers only need to send their event to a single endpoint, Twilio Segment’s API, instead of building potentially dozens of integrations. Twilio Segment handles making the request to every destination endpoint.</p>
<p>If one of the requests to a destination fails, sometimes we’ll try sending that event again at a later time. Some failures are safe to retry while others are not. Retry-able errors are those that could potentially be accepted by the destination with no changes. For example, HTTP 500s, rate limits, and timeouts. Non-retry-able errors are requests that we can be sure will never be accepted by the destination. For example, requests which have invalid credentials or are missing required fields.</p>

    </div>
        
    
        
        
        
            
            





	
	
	

	<figure>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_QhV9GV3m.png" alt="A flow diagram illustrating a request processing system with components including an API, a queue, a destination worker, and multiple output endpoints such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com." loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_QhV9GV3m.png" alt="A flow diagram illustrating a request processing system with components including an API, a queue, a destination worker, and multiple output endpoints such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com." loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		
	</figure>




        
    
        
        
        
            
            

<div data-ext-icon="<svg viewBox=&quot;0 0 79 79&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; class=&quot;icon--decorative&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;>
    <title>An icon of a outbound link arrow</title>
    <path class=&quot;icon-stroke&quot; d=&quot;M75.3037 3.98207L3 75.5935M75.3037 3.98207L76.0435 43.3021M75.3037 3.98207L35.951 3.59351&quot; stroke=&quot;#F22F46&quot; stroke-width=&quot;5.5&quot; stroke-linecap=&quot;round&quot; stroke-linejoin=&quot;round&quot;/>
</svg>
">
        <p>At this point, a single queue contained both the newest events as well as those which may have had several retry attempts, across all destinations, which resulted in <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Head-of-line_blocking" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">head-of-line blocking</a>. Meaning in this particular case, if one destination slowed or went down, retries would flood the queue, resulting in delays across <i>all</i> our destinations.</p>
<p>Imagine destination X is experiencing a temporary issue and every request errors with a timeout. Now, not only does this create a large backlog of requests which have yet to reach destination X, but also every failed event is put back to retry in the queue. While our systems would automatically scale in response to increased load, the sudden increase in queue depth would outpace our ability to scale up, resulting in delays for the newest events. Delivery times for all destinations would increase because destination X had a momentary outage. Customers rely on the timeliness of this delivery, so we can’t afford increases in wait times anywhere in our pipeline.</p>

    </div>
        
    
        
        
        
            
            





	
	
	

	<figure>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_joMYeSNt.png" alt="A flow diagram illustrating a data processing pipeline with components including an API, a queue, a destination worker, and multiple output endpoints such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com. It also includes annotations indicating &quot;backpressure&quot; and &quot;retry events.&quot;" loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_joMYeSNt.png" alt="A flow diagram illustrating a data processing pipeline with components including an API, a queue, a destination worker, and multiple output endpoints such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com. It also includes annotations indicating &quot;backpressure&quot; and &quot;retry events.&quot;" loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		
	</figure>




        
    
        
        
        
            
            

<div>
        
    
    <p>To solve the head-of-line blocking problem, the team created a separate service and queue for each destination. This new architecture consisted of an additional router process that receives the inbound events and distributes a copy of the event to each selected destination. Now if one destination experienced problems, only it’s queue would back up and no other destinations would be impacted. This microservice-style architecture isolated the destinations from one another, which was crucial when one destination experienced issues as they often do.</p>

        
    </div>
        
    
        
        
        
            
            





	
	
	

	<figure>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_ElKl4CZv.png" alt="A flow diagram illustrating a request processing system with components including an API, a router, queues, and multiple output endpoints such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com, with flow annotations." loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_ElKl4CZv.png" alt="A flow diagram illustrating a request processing system with components including an API, a router, queues, and multiple output endpoints such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com, with flow annotations." loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		
	</figure>




        
    
        
        
        
            
            

<div data-ext-icon="<svg viewBox=&quot;0 0 79 79&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; class=&quot;icon--decorative&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;>
    <title>An icon of a outbound link arrow</title>
    <path class=&quot;icon-stroke&quot; d=&quot;M75.3037 3.98207L3 75.5935M75.3037 3.98207L76.0435 43.3021M75.3037 3.98207L35.951 3.59351&quot; stroke=&quot;#F22F46&quot; stroke-width=&quot;5.5&quot; stroke-linecap=&quot;round&quot; stroke-linejoin=&quot;round&quot;/>
</svg>
">
        <h2 id="the-case-for-individual-repos"><a href="#the-case-for-individual-repos">The Case for Individual Repos</a></h2>
<p>Each destination API uses a different request format, requiring custom code to translate the event to match this format. A basic example is destination X requires sending birthday as&nbsp;traits.dob&nbsp;in the payload whereas our API accepts it as&nbsp;traits.birthday. The transformation code in destination X would look something like this:</p>
<p>Many modern destination endpoints have adopted Twilio Segment’s request format making some transforms relatively simple. However, these transforms can be very complex depending on the structure of the destination’s API. For example, for some of the older and most sprawling destinations, we find ourselves shoving values into hand-crafted XML payloads.</p>
<p>Initially, when the destinations were divided into separate services, all of the code lived in one repo. A huge point of frustration was that a single broken test caused tests to fail across all destinations. When we wanted to deploy a change, we had to spend time fixing the broken test even if the changes had nothing to do with the initial change. In response to this problem, it was decided to break out the code for each destination into their own repos. All the destinations were already broken out into their own service, so the transition was natural.</p>
<p>The split to separate repos allowed us to isolate the destination test suites easily. This isolation allowed the development team to move quickly when maintaining destinations.</p>
<h2 id="scaling-microservices-and-repos"><a href="#scaling-microservices-and-repos">Scaling Microservices and Repos</a></h2>
<p>As time went on, we added over 50 new destinations, and that meant 50 new repos. To ease the burden of developing and maintaining these codebases, we created shared libraries to make common transforms and functionality, such as HTTP request handling, across our destinations easier and more uniform.</p>
<p>For example, if we want the name of a user from an event,&nbsp;event.name()&nbsp;can be called in any destination’s code. The shared library checks the event for the property key&nbsp;name&nbsp;and&nbsp;Name. If those don’t exist, it checks for a first name, checking the properties&nbsp;firstName,&nbsp;first_name, and&nbsp;FirstName. It does the same for the last name, checking the cases and combining the two to form the full name.</p>
<p>The shared libraries made building new destinations quick. The familiarity brought by a uniform set of shared functionality made maintenance less of a headache.</p>
<p>However, a new problem began to arise. Testing and deploying changes to these shared libraries impacted all of our destinations. It began to require considerable time and effort to maintain. Making changes to improve our libraries, knowing we’d have to test and deploy dozens of services, was a risky proposition. When pressed for time, engineers would only include the updated versions of these libraries on a single destination’s codebase.</p>
<p>Over time, the versions of these shared libraries began to diverge across the different destination codebases. The great benefit we once had of reduced customization between each destination codebase started to reverse. Eventually, all of them were using different versions of these shared libraries. We could’ve built tools to automate rolling out changes, but at this point, not only was developer productivity suffering but we began to encounter other issues with the microservice architecture.</p>
<p>The additional problem is that each service had a distinct load pattern. Some services would handle a handful of events per day while others handled thousands of events per second. For destinations that handled a small number of events, an operator would have to manually scale the service up to meet demand whenever there was an unexpected spike in load.</p>
<p>While we did have auto-scaling implemented, each service had a distinct blend of required CPU and memory resources, which made tuning the auto-scaling configuration more art than science.</p>
<p>The number of destinations continued to grow rapidly, with the team adding three destinations per month on average, which meant more repos, more queues, and more services. With our microservice architecture, our operational overhead increased linearly with each added destination. Therefore, we decided to take a step back and rethink the entire pipeline.</p>
<h2 id="ditching-microservices-and-queues"><a href="#ditching-microservices-and-queues">Ditching Microservices and Queues</a></h2>
<p>The first item on the list was to consolidate the now over 140 services into a single service. The overhead from managing all of these services was a huge tax on our team. We were literally losing sleep over it since it was common for the on-call engineer to get paged to deal with load spikes.</p>
<p>However, the architecture at the time would have made moving to a single service challenging. With a separate queue per destination, each worker would have to check every queue for work, which would have added a layer of complexity to the destination service with which we weren’t comfortable. This was the main inspiration for&nbsp;Centrifuge. Centrifuge would replace all our individual queues and be responsible for sending events to the single monolithic service. (Note that Centrifuge became the back-end infrastructure for <a href="https://segment.com/product/connections/?utm_referrer=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.twilio.com%2Fen-us%2Fblog%2Fdevelopers%2Fbest-practices%2Fgoodbye-microservices" target="_self" rel="noopener noreferrer">Connections</a>.)</p>

    </div>
        
    
        
        
        
            
            





	
	
	

	<figure>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_a0ViVzT6.png" alt="A flow diagram showing an API request passing through a router, then a concentrator, and finally reaching multiple destination services such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com." loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/global/en/blog/legacy/2018/goodbye-microservices/asset_a0ViVzT6.png" alt="A flow diagram showing an API request passing through a router, then a concentrator, and finally reaching multiple destination services such as google-analytics.com, api.optimizely.com, and api.mixpanel.com." loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		
	</figure>




        
    
        
        
        
            
            

<div data-ext-icon="<svg viewBox=&quot;0 0 79 79&quot; fill=&quot;none&quot; xmlns=&quot;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&quot; class=&quot;icon--decorative&quot; role=&quot;presentation&quot;>
    <title>An icon of a outbound link arrow</title>
    <path class=&quot;icon-stroke&quot; d=&quot;M75.3037 3.98207L3 75.5935M75.3037 3.98207L76.0435 43.3021M75.3037 3.98207L35.951 3.59351&quot; stroke=&quot;#F22F46&quot; stroke-width=&quot;5.5&quot; stroke-linecap=&quot;round&quot; stroke-linejoin=&quot;round&quot;/>
</svg>
">
        <h2 id="moving-to-a-monorepo"><a href="#moving-to-a-monorepo">Moving to a Monorepo</a></h2>
<p>Given that there would only be one service, it made sense to move all the destination code into one repo, which meant merging all the different dependencies and tests into a single repo. We knew this was going to be messy.</p>
<p>For each of the 120 unique dependencies, we committed to having one version for all our destinations. As we moved destinations over, we’d check the dependencies it was using and update them to the latest versions. We fixed anything in the destinations that broke with the newer versions.</p>
<p>With this transition, we no longer needed to keep track of the differences between dependency versions. All our destinations were using the same version, which significantly reduced the complexity across the codebase. Maintaining destinations now became less time consuming and less risky.</p>
<p>We also wanted a test suite that allowed us to quickly and easily run all our destination tests. Running all the tests was one of the main blockers when making updates to the shared libraries we discussed earlier.</p>
<p>Fortunately, the destination tests all had a similar structure. They had basic unit tests to verify our custom transform logic was correct and would execute HTTP requests to the partner’s endpoint to verify that events showed up in the destination as expected.</p>
<p>Recall that the original motivation for separating each destination codebase into its own repo was to isolate test failures. However, it turned out this was a false advantage. Tests that made HTTP requests were still failing with some frequency. With destinations separated into their own repos, there was little motivation to clean up failing tests. This poor hygiene led to a constant source of frustrating technical debt. Often a small change that should have only taken an hour or two would end up requiring a couple of days to a week to complete.</p>
<h2 id="building-a-resilient-test-suite"><a href="#building-a-resilient-test-suite">Building a Resilient Test Suite</a></h2>
<p>The outbound HTTP requests to destination endpoints during the test run was the primary cause of failing tests. Unrelated issues like expired credentials shouldn’t fail tests. We also knew from experience that some destination endpoints were much slower than others. Some destinations took up to 5 minutes to run their tests. With over 140 destinations, our test suite could take up to an hour to run.</p>
<p>To solve for both of these, we created Traffic Recorder. Traffic Recorder is built on top of <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/flickr/yakbak" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">yakbak</a>, and is responsible for recording and saving destinations’ test traffic. Whenever a test runs for the first time, any requests and their corresponding responses are recorded to a file. On subsequent test runs, the request and response in the file is played back instead requesting the destination’s endpoint. These files are checked into the repo so that the tests are consistent across every change. Now that the test suite is no longer dependent on these HTTP requests over the internet, our tests became significantly more resilient, a must-have for the migration to a single repo.</p>
<p>It took milliseconds to complete running the tests for all 140+ of our destinations after we integrated Traffic Recorder. In the past, just one destination could have taken a couple of minutes to complete. <i>It felt like magic.</i></p>
<h2 id="why-a-monolith-works"><a href="#why-a-monolith-works">Why a Monolith works</a></h2>
<p>Once the code for all destinations lived in a single repo, they could be merged into a single service. With every destination living in one service, our developer productivity substantially improved. We no longer had to deploy 140+ services for a change to one of the shared libraries. One engineer can deploy the service in a matter of minutes.</p>
<p>The proof was in the improved velocity. When our microservice architecture was still in place, we made 32 improvements to our shared libraries. One year later,&nbsp; we’ve made 46 improvements.</p>
<p>The change also benefited our operational story. With every destination living in one service, we had a good mix of CPU and memory-intense destinations, which made scaling the service to meet demand significantly easier. The large worker pool can absorb spikes in load, so we no longer get paged for destinations that process small amounts of load.</p>
<h2 id="trade-offs"><a href="#trade-offs">Trade Offs</a></h2>
<p>Moving from our microservice architecture to a monolith overall was huge improvement, however, there are trade-offs:</p>
<ol><li><p><b>Fault isolation is difficult.</b> With everything running in a monolith, if a bug is introduced in one destination that causes the service to crash, the service will crash for all destinations. We have comprehensive automated testing in place, but tests can only get you so far. We are currently working on a much more robust way to prevent one destination from taking down the entire service while still keeping all the destinations in a monolith.</p>
</li><li><p><b>In-memory caching is less effective.</b> Previously, with one service per destination, our low traffic destinations only had a handful of processes, which meant their in-memory caches of control plane data would stay hot. Now that cache is spread thinly across 3000+ processes so it’s much less likely to be hit. We could use something like Redis to solve for this, but then that’s another point of scaling for which we’d have to account. In the end, we accepted this loss of efficiency given the substantial operational benefits.</p>
</li><li><p><b>Updating the version of a dependency may break multiple destinations.</b> While moving everything to one repo solved the previous dependency mess we were in, it means that if we want to use the newest version of a library, we’ll potentially have to update other destinations to work with the newer version. In our opinion though, the simplicity of this approach is worth the trade-off. And with our comprehensive automated test suite, we can quickly see what breaks with a newer dependency version.</p>
</li></ol>
<h2 id="conclusion"><a href="#conclusion">Conclusion</a></h2>
<p>Our initial microservice architecture worked for a time, solving the immediate performance issues in our pipeline by isolating the destinations from each other. However, we weren’t set up to scale. We lacked the proper tooling for testing and deploying the microservices when bulk updates were needed. As a result, our developer productivity quickly declined.</p>
<p>Moving to a monolith allowed us to rid our pipeline of operational issues while significantly increasing developer productivity. We didn’t make this transition lightly though and knew there were things we had to consider if it was going to work.</p>
<ol><li>We needed a rock solid testing suite to put everything into one repo. Without this, we would have been in the same situation as when we originally decided to break them apart. Constant failing tests hurt our productivity in the past, and we didn’t want that happening again.</li><li>We accepted the trade-offs inherent in a monolithic architecture and made sure we had a good story around each. We had to be comfortable with some of the sacrifices that came with this change.</li></ol>
<p>When deciding between microservices or a monolith, there are different factors to consider with each. In some parts of our infrastructure, microservices work well but our server-side destinations were a perfect example of how this popular trend can actually hurt productivity and performance. It turns out, the solution for us was a monolith.</p>
<h2 id="acknowledgements"><a href="#acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</a></h2>
<p>The transition to a monolith was made possible by <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/stephenmathieson" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">Stephen Mathieson</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/rbranson" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rick Branson</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/achille-roussel" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">Achille Roussel</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/tsholmes" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tom Holmes</a>, and many more.</p>
<p>Special thanks to <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/rbranson" data-dynamic-link="true" rel="noopener noreferrer">Rick Branson</a> for helping review and edit this post at every stage.</p>

    </div>
        
    
</div>

        
        
    
        
        
        
            
            
<div class="page" id="" background-image="" is-background-video="false" mobile-background-image="">
         
            
            








    <p>
        
        
  <h3>
    Ready to see what Twilio Segment can do for you?
  </h3>

        
    </p>


         
            
            







    
    
    
    



         
      </div>


    

        
    
        
        
        
            
            
<div id="" class="page" background-image="" is-background-video="false" mobile-background-image="">

   
   
      <div>
         
            
            





	
	
	

	<figure>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/cdp-report/CDP-cover-2025.png/_jcr_content/renditions/compressed-original.webp" loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		<p><img src="https://www.twilio.com/content/dam/segment/cdp-report/CDP-cover-2025.png/_jcr_content/renditions/compressed-original.webp" loading="lazy">
			
		</p>
		
	</figure>




         
      </div>
   
   

   
   
      <div>
         
            
            








    <p>
        
        
  <h2>
    The Customer Data Platform Report 2025
  </h2>

        
    </p>


         
            
            





    
    <p>Drawing on anonymized insights from thousands of Twilio customers, the Customer Data Platform report explores how companies are using CDPs to unlock the power of their data.</p>




         
            
            







    
    
    
    



         
      </div>
   
   

</div>


    

        
    

    
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I fed 24 years of my blog posts to a Markov model (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://susam.net/fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html</link>
            <guid>46257607</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 20:19:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://susam.net/fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html">https://susam.net/fed-24-years-of-posts-to-markov-model.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46257607">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>By <b>Susam Pal</b> on 13 Dec 2025</p>
<p>
  Yesterday I shared a little program called <em>Mark V. Shaney
  Junior</em> at
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs">github.com/susam/mvs</a>.  It
  is a minimal implementation of a Markov text generator inspired by
  the legendary Mark V. Shaney program from the 1980s.  If you don't
  know about Mark V. Shaney, read more about it on the Wikipedia
  article <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_V._Shaney">Mark
  V. Shaney</a>.
</p>
<p>
  It is a very small program with only about
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs/blob/main/mvs">30 lines of
  Python</a> that favours simplicity over efficiency.  As a hobby, I
  often engage in exploratory programming where I write computer
  programs not to solve a specific problem but simply to explore a
  particular idea or topic for the sole purpose of recreation.  I must
  have written small programs to explore Markov chains for various
  kinds of state spaces over a dozen times by now.  Every time, I just
  pick my last experimental code and edit it to encode the new state
  space I am exploring.  That's usually my general approach to such
  one-off programs.  I have hundreds of tiny little experimental
  programs lying on my disk at any given time.
</p>
<p>
  Once in a while, I get the itch to take one of those exploratory
  programs, give it some finishing touches, wrap it up in a nice Git
  repo along with a <code>README.md</code>, <code>CHANGES.md</code>
  and the whole shebang and share it on
  <a href="https://github.com/susam">github.com/susam</a> and
  <a href="https://codeberg.org/susam">codeberg.org/susam</a>.  The
  Mark V. Shaney Junior program that I shared yesterday happened to be
  one such exercise.
</p>
<p>
  If you scroll down the
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs#readme">README</a> of this
  project, you'll find some nice examples of the gibberish produced by
  this program.  The first few examples there are the result of
  training the model on <em>A Christmas Carol</em> by Charles Dickens,
  one of my favourite authors.  It is often said that Dickens never
  used fewer words when more would suffice.  So I thought there
  couldn't be a better piece of text when it comes to testing out my
  tiny Markov model.  I'll not reproduce the generated text examples
  here for the sake of brevity.  If you are interested to take a look,
  just head over to the
  <a href="https://github.com/susam/mvs#gibberish-examples">Gibberish</a>
  section of the README.
</p>
<p>
  Soon after sharing the project, I wondered what kind of gibberish it
  would produce if I fed all 24 years of my blog
  <a href="https://susam.net/pages.html">posts and pages</a> into the program.
  Well, here's one of the results:
</p>
<pre><samp>$ <kbd>./mvs &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
while a query replace operation is approved by the user. The above
variable defines the build job. It can be incredibly useful while
working on assembly language and machine code. In fact, all internal
resources like the result to refine the search prompt changes from
bck-i-search: to fwd-i-search:. Now type C-SPC (i.e. ctrl+space) to
set a mark causes Emacs to use 32-bit registers like EBP, ESP,
etc. Thus the behaviour is undefined. Such code may behave differently
when compiled with the readily available GNU tools like the shape
of 8. Flipping "P" horizontally makes it a proper quine: cat $0</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  This is the text that comes out after the program consumes over 200
  posts consisting of about 200,000 words.  My blog also has
  a <a href="https://susam.net/comments/">comments section</a> with over 500
  comments consisting of about 40,000 words.  All comments were
  excluded while training the model.  Here is another output example:
</p>
<pre><samp>$ <kbd>./mvs &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
enjoy asking "what happens if" and then type M-x zap-up-to-char RET
b. The buffer for this specific video, the actual fare for 8.3 km and
11 are all written from scratch. No prior knowledge is expected to
slow down in future. For now, I will add a statement like x =
0.999... , the inner corner square as discussed in the code segment
into the REPL window. Unlike Slimv, Vlime can work with and debug
executable files, it can be more convenient. M-x: Execute Extended
Command The key sequence M-q invokes the command cat and type TAB to
indent the</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Here is a particularly incoherent but amusing one:
</p>
<pre><samp>$ <kbd>./mvs &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
Then open a new Lisp source file and the exact answer could harm
students' self-esteem. Scientists have arbitrarily assumed that an
integral domain. However, the string and comment text. To demonstrate
how a build job can trigger itself, pass input to standard output or
standard error), Eshell automatically runs the following command in
Vim and Emacs will copy the message length limit of 512 characters,
etc. For example, while learning to play the game between normal mode
to move the point is on an old dictionary lying around our house and
that is moving to the small and supportive community</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  No, I have never said anywhere that opening a Lisp source file could
  harm anyone's self-esteem.  The text generator has picked up the
  'Lisp source file' phrase from my
  <a href="https://susam.net/lisp-in-vim.html">Lisp in Vim</a> post and the
  'self-esteem' bit from the <a href="https://susam.net/from-perl-to-pi.html">From Perl
  to Pi</a> post.
</p>
<p>
  By default, this program looks at trigrams (all sequences of three
  adjacent words) and creates a map where the first two words of the
  trigram are inserted as the key and the third word is appended to
  its list value.  This map is the model.  In this way, the model
  captures each pair of adjacent words along with the words that
  immediately follow each pair.  The text generator then chooses a key
  (a pair of words) at random and looks for a word which follows.  If
  there are multiple followers, it picks one at random.  That is
  pretty much the whole algorithm.  There isn't much more to it.  It
  is as simple as it gets.  For that reason, I often describe a simple
  Markov model like this as the 'hello, world' for language models.
</p>
<p>
  Of course, in 2025, given the overwhelming popularity of large
  language models (LLMs), Markov models like this look unimpressive.
  Unlike LLMs, a simple Markov model cannot capture global structure
  or long-range dependencies within the text.  It relies entirely on
  local word transition statistics.  Also, these days, one hardly
  needs a Markov model to generate gibberish; social media provides an
  ample supply.  Nevertheless, I think the simplicity of its design
  and implementation serves as a good entry point into language
  models.
</p>
<p>
  In my implementation, the number of words in the key of the map can
  be set via command line arguments.  By default, it is 2 as described
  above.  This value is also known as the order of the model.  So by
  default the order is 2.  If we increase it to, say, 3 or 4, the
  generated text becomes a little more coherent.  Here is one such
  example:
</p>
<pre><samp>$ <kbd>./mvs 4 &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
It is also possible to search for channels by channel names. For
example, on Libera Chat, to search for all channels with 'python' in
its name, enter the IRC command: /msg alis list python. Although I
have used Libera Chat in the examples above, there are plenty of
infinite fields, so they must all be integral domains too. Consider
the field of rational numbers Q. Another quick way to arrive at this
fact is to observe that when one knight is placed on a type D square,
only two positions for the second knight such that the two knights
attack</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Except for a couple of abrupt and meaningless transitions, the text
  is mostly coherent.  We need to be careful about not increasing the
  order too much.  In fact, if we increase the order of the model to
  5, the generated text becomes very dry and factual because it begins
  to quote large portions of the blog posts verbatim.  Not much fun
  can be had with that.
</p>
<p>
  Before I end this post, let me present one final example where I ask
  it to generate text from an initial prompt:
</p>
<pre><samp>$ <kbd>./mvs 2 100 'Finally we' &lt; susam.txt</kbd>
Finally we divide this number by a feed aggregrator for Emacs-related
blogs. The following complete key sequences describe the effects of
previous evaluations shall have taken a simple and small to contain
bad content. This provides an interactive byte-compiled Lisp function
in MATLAB and GNU bash 5.1.4 on Debian is easily reproducible in
Windows XP. Older versions might be able to run that server for me it
played a significant burden on me as soon as possible. C-u F: Visit
the marked files or directories in the sense that it was already
initiated and we were to complete the proof.</samp>
</pre>
<p>
  Apparently, this is how I would sound if I ever took up speaking
  gibberish!
</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[VPN location claims don't match real traffic exits (287 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ipinfo.io/blog/vpn-location-mismatch-report</link>
            <guid>46257339</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 19:46:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ipinfo.io/blog/vpn-location-mismatch-report">https://ipinfo.io/blog/vpn-location-mismatch-report</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46257339">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>In a large-scale analysis of 20 popular VPNs, IPinfo found that 17 of those VPNs exit traffic from <em>different countries than they claim</em>. Some claim 100+ countries, but many of them point to the same handful of physical data centers in the US or Europe.</p><p>That means the majority of VPN providers we analyzed don’t route your traffic via the countries they claim to, and they claim many more countries than they actually support.&nbsp;</p><p>Analyzing over <strong>150,000 exit IPs</strong> across <strong>137 possible exit countries,</strong> and comparing what providers claim to what IPinfo measures, shows that:</p><ul><li><strong>17 in 20 providers </strong>had traffic exiting in a different country.</li><li><strong>38 countries</strong> were “virtual-only” in our dataset (claimed by at least one provider, but never observed as the actual traffic exit country for any provider we tested).</li><li>We were only able to verify all provider announced locations for <strong>3 providers</strong> out of the 20.</li><li>Across ~150,000 VPN exit IPs tested, ProbeNet, our internet measurement platform, detected roughly <strong>8,000 cases</strong> where widely-used IP datasets placed the server in the wrong country — sometimes thousands of kilometers off.</li></ul><p>This report walks through what we saw across VPN and IP data providers, provides a closer look at two particularly interesting countries, explores why measurement-based IP data matters if you care where your traffic really goes, and shares how we ran the investigation.</p><h2 id="which-vpns-matched-reality-and-which-didn%E2%80%99t">Which VPNs Matched Reality (And Which Didn’t)</h2><p>Here is the overlap between the number of listed countries each VPN provider claims to offer versus the countries with real VPN traffic that we measured — lower percentages indicate providers whose claimed lists best match our data:</p>
</div><div>
<table><colgroup><col width="222"><col width="136"><col width="132"></colgroup><tbody><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Provider</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Claimed Countries</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>% Virtual or Unmeasurable</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>IPVanish</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>108</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>61</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>CyberGhost</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>100</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>57</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>ExpressVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>105</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>57</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>NordVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>126</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>53</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Private Internet Access</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>91</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>52</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>ProtonVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>110</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>51</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>FastVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>112</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>49</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>X-VPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>89</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>43</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Surfshark</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>100</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>41</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>BelkaVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>63</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>41</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>ZoogVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>76</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>34</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>VyprVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>63</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>27</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>FastestVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>47</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>26</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>TrustZone</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>39</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>18</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>PrivateVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>62</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>13</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>TunnelBear</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>47</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>9</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>VeePN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>84</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>6</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>IVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>41</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Mullvad</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>50</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Windscribe</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>70</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
</div><div>
<p><em>It's important to note that we used the most commonly and widely supported technologies in this research, to make comparison between providers as fair as possible while giving us significant data to analyze, so this will not be the full coverage for each provider.</em></p><p>These are some of the most visible names in the market. They also tend to have very long country lists on their websites. Notably, three well-known providers had zero mismatches across all the countries we tested: Mullvad, IVPN, and Windscribe<strong>.</strong></p><p>Country mismatches doesn’t automatically mean some providers offer “bad VPNs,” but it does mean that if you’re choosing a VPN because it claims “100+ countries,” you should know that a significant share of those flags may be labels, or virtual locations.</p><h2 id="what-%E2%80%9Cvirtual-locations%E2%80%9D-really-mean">What “Virtual Locations” Really Mean</h2><p>When a VPN lets you connect to, for example, “Bahamas” or “Somalia,” that doesn’t always mean traffic routes through there. In many cases, it’s somewhere entirely different, like Miami or London, but presented as if traffic is in the country you picked.</p><p>This setup is known as a virtual location:</p><ul><li>The VPN app shows “Country X” (e.g. Bahamas).</li><li>The IP registry data also says “Country X” — because the provider self-declared it that way.</li><li>But the network measurements (latency and routing) show the traffic actually exits in “Country Y” — often thousands of kilometers away.</li></ul><p>The problem? Without active network measurement, most IP datasets will rely on what the IP’s owner told the internet registry or published in WHOIS/geofeeds: a self-reported country tag. If that record is wrong or outdated, the mistake spreads everywhere. That’s where IPinfo’s ProbeNet comes in: by running live RTT tests from 1,200+ points of presence worldwide, we anchor each IP to its real-world location, not just its declared one.</p><p>Across the dataset, we found <strong>97 countries</strong> where at least one VPN brand only ever appeared as virtual or unmeasurable in our data. In other words, for a noticeable slice of the world map, some “locations” in VPNs never show up as true exits in our measurements.&nbsp;</p><p>We also found <strong>38 countries</strong> where every mention behaved this way: at least one VPN claimed them, but <strong>none</strong> ever produced a stable, measurable exit in that country in our sample.</p><p>You can think of these 38 as the “unmeasurable” countries in this study – places that exist in server lists, config files, and IP geofeeds, but never once appeared as the actual exit country in our measurements. They’re not randomly scattered – they cluster in specific parts of the map. By region, that includes:</p><figure><img src="https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/2025/12/VPN-research----unmeasurable--countries-map---Non-measurable.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="2000" height="1055" srcset="https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w600/2025/12/VPN-research----unmeasurable--countries-map---Non-measurable.png 600w, https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2025/12/VPN-research----unmeasurable--countries-map---Non-measurable.png 1000w, https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w1600/2025/12/VPN-research----unmeasurable--countries-map---Non-measurable.png 1600w, https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w2400/2025/12/VPN-research----unmeasurable--countries-map---Non-measurable.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>This doesn’t prove there is zero VPN infrastructure in those countries globally. It does show that, across the providers and locations we measured, the dominant pattern is to serve those locations from elsewhere. Here are three of the most interesting examples of how this looks at the IP level.</p><h2 id="case-studies-two-countries-that-only-exist-on-the-map">Case Studies: Two Countries That Only Exist on the Map</h2><p>To make this concrete, let’s look at three countries where every provider in our dataset turned out to be virtual: <strong>Bahamas</strong>, and <strong>Somalia</strong>.</p><h3 id="bahamas-all-inclusive-hosted-in-the-us">Bahamas: All-Inclusive, Hosted in the US</h3><p>In our measurements, five providers offered locations labeled as “Bahamas”: NordVPN, ExpressVPN, Private Internet Access, FastVPN, and IPVanish.</p><p>For all of them, measured traffic was in the United States, usually with sub-millisecond RTT to US probes.</p>
</div><div>
<table><colgroup><col width="133"><col width="97"><col width="104"><col width="205"><col width="159"></colgroup><tbody><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Provider</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Claimed as</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Measured exit country</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>RTT to nearest ProbeNet vantage point in (evidence)</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Example exit IP</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>NordVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇧🇸</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Bahamas</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇺🇸</span><span><br></span><span>United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.27 ms from Miami, United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>45.95.160.61</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>ExpressVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇧🇸</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Bahamas</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇺🇸</span><span><br></span><span>United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.15 ms from Miami, United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>64.64.117.18</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Private Internet Access</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇧🇸</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Bahamas</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇺🇸</span><span><br></span><span>United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.42 ms from New York, United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>95.181.238.101</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>FastVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇧🇸</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Bahamas</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇺🇸</span><span><br></span><span>United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.42 ms from Miami, United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>108.171.106.198</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>IPVanish</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇧🇸</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Bahamas</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇺🇸</span><span><br></span><span>United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.37 ms from Miami, United States</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>108.171.106.207</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
</div><div>
<h3 id="somalia-mogadishu-via-france-and-the-uk">Somalia: Mogadishu, via France and the UK</h3><p>Somalia appears in our sample for only two providers: NordVPN and ProtonVPN.&nbsp;</p><p>Both label Mogadishu explicitly in their naming, but these RTTs are exactly what you’d expect for traffic in Western Europe, and completely inconsistent with traffic in East Africa. Both providers go out of their way in the labels (e.g. “SO, Mogadishu”), but the actual traffic is in Nice and London, not Somalia.</p>
</div><div>
<table><colgroup><col width="98"><col width="97"><col width="119"><col width="231"><col width="147"></colgroup><tbody><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Provider</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Claimed as</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Measured exit country</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>RTT to nearest probe (evidence)</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Example exit IP</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>NordVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇸🇴</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Somalia</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇫🇷</span><span><br></span><span>France</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.33 ms from Nice, France</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>212.32.91.11</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>ProtonVPN</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇸🇴</span></p><p dir="ltr"><span>Somalia</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>🇬🇧</span><span><br></span><span>United Kingdom</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>0.37 ms from London, UK</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>74.118.126.204</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
</div><div>
<h2 id="when-legacy-ip-providers-agree-with-the-wrong-vpn-locations">When Legacy IP Providers Agree With the Wrong VPN Locations</h2><p>So far, we’ve talked about VPN claims versus our measurements. But other IP data providers don’t run active RTT tests. They rely on self-declared IP data sources, and often assume that if an IP is tagged as “Country X,” it must actually be there.</p><p>In these cases, the IP legacy datasets typically “follow” the VPN provider’s story: if the VPN markets the endpoint as Country X, the legacy IP dataset also places it in Country X.</p><p>To quantify that, we looked at 736 VPN exits where ProbeNet’s measured country disagreed with one or more widely used legacy IP datasets.</p><p>We then compared the country IPinfo's ProbeNet measured (backed by RTT and routing) with the country reported by these other IP datasets and computed the distance between them. The gaps are large:</p><h3 id="how-far-off-were-the-other-ip-datasets">How Far Off Were the Other IP Datasets?</h3>
</div><div>
<table><colgroup><col width="298"><col width="235"></colgroup><tbody><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Distance between legacy IP databases and IPinfo country</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>Share of disagreement cases</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>&gt; 1,000 km</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>83%</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>&gt; 2,000 km</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>63%</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>&gt; 5,000 km</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>28%</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p dir="ltr"><span>&gt; 8,000 km</span></p></td><td><p dir="ltr"><span>12%</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table>
</div><div>
<p>The median error between ProbeNet and the legacy datasets was roughly 3,100 km<strong>. </strong>On the ProbeNet side, we have strong latency evidence that our measured country is the right one:</p><ul><li><strong>The median minimum RTT</strong> to a probe in the measured country was <strong>0.27 ms</strong>.</li><li>About <strong>90%</strong> of these locations had a <strong>sub-millisecond</strong> RTT from at least one probe.</li></ul><p>That’s what you expect when traffic is genuinely in that country, not thousands of kilometers away.</p><h3 id="an-ip-example-you-can-test-yourself">An IP Example You Can Test Yourself</h3><p>This behavior is much more tangible if you can see it on a single IP.&nbsp;</p><p>Here's <a href="https://ipinfo.io/74.118.126.154?ref=ipinfo.io"><u>one VPN exit IP</u></a> where ProbeNet places the server in the United Kingdom, backed by sub-millisecond RTT from local probes, while other widely used legacy IP datasets place the same IP in Mauritius, 9,691 kilometers away.</p><p><strong>🇬🇧 United Kingdom vs 🇲🇺 Mauritius (ProtonVPN)</strong></p><figure><img src="https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/2025/12/location-alert.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="697" height="86" srcset="https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w600/2025/12/location-alert.png 600w, https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/2025/12/location-alert.png 697w"></figure><figure><img src="https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/2025/12/location-evidence.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1574" height="648" srcset="https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w600/2025/12/location-evidence.png 600w, https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2025/12/location-evidence.png 1000w, https://ipinfo.io/blog/content/images/2025/12/location-evidence.png 1574w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>If you want to check this yourself, you can plug it into a public measurement tool like <a href="https://ping.sx/?ref=ipinfo.io"><u>https://ping.sx/</u></a> and run pings or traceroutes from different regions. Tools like this one provide a clear visual for where latency is lowest.</p><p>ProbeNet uses the same basic idea, but at a different scale: we maintain a network of 1,200+ points of presence (PoPs) around the world, so we can usually get even closer to the real physical location than public tools with smaller networks.</p><p>If you’d like to play with more real IPs (not necessarily VPNs) where ProbeNet and IPinfo get the country right and other datasets don’t, you can find a fuller set of examples on our IP geolocation <a href="http://ipinfo.io/accuracy/?ref=ipinfo.io"><u>accuracy page</u></a>.</p><h2 id="why-this-happens-and-how-it-impacts-trust">Why This Happens and How It Impacts Trust</h2><p>It’s worth separating technical reasons from trust issues. There are technical reasons to use virtual or hubbed infrastructure:</p><ul><li><strong>Risk &amp; regulation.</strong> Hosting in certain countries can expose both the provider and users to local surveillance or seizure.</li><li><strong>Infrastructure quality.</strong> Some regions simply don’t have the same density of reliable data centers or high-capacity internet links, so running servers there is harder and riskier.</li><li><strong>Performance &amp; cost.</strong> Serving “Bahamas” from Miami or “Cambodia” from Singapore can be cheaper, faster, and easier to maintain.</li></ul><p>From this perspective, a virtual location can be a reasonable compromise: you get a regional IP and content unblocking without the downsides of hosting in a fragile environment.</p><h3 id="where-it-becomes-a-trust-problem">Where It Becomes a Trust Problem</h3><p>Three things change the picture:</p><ul><li><strong>Lack of disclosure. </strong>Marking something clearly as “Virtual Bahamas (US-based)” is transparent. Listing “Bahamas” alongside “Germany” without any hint that one is virtual and the other is physical blurs the line between marketing and reality.</li><li><strong>Scale of the mismatch. </strong>It’s one thing to have a few virtual locations in hard-to-host places. It’s another when dozens of countries exist only as labels across your entire footprint, or when more than half of your tested locations are actually somewhere else.</li><li><strong>Downstream reliance. </strong>Journalists, activists, and NGOs may pick locations based on safety assumptions. Fraud systems, compliance workflows, and geo-restricted services may treat “Somalia” vs “France” as a meaningful difference. If both the VPN UI and the IP data say “Somalia” while the traffic is physically in France, everyone is making decisions on a false premise.</li></ul><p>That last point leads directly into the IP data problem that we are focused on solving.</p><h2 id="so-how-much-should-you-trust-your-vpn">So How Much Should You Trust Your VPN?</h2><p>If you’re a VPN user, here are some practical takeaways from this work:</p><ul><li><strong>Treat “100+ countries” as a marketing number, not a guarantee. </strong>In our sample, 97 countries existed only as claims, not reality, across 17 providers.</li><li><strong>Check how your provider talks about locations. </strong>Do they clearly label “virtual” servers? Document where they’re actually hosted? Or do they quietly mix virtual and physical locations in one long list?</li><li><strong>If you rely on IP data professionally, ask where it comes from. </strong>A static “99.x% accurate worldwide” claim doesn’t tell you how an IP data provider handles fast-moving, high-stakes environments like VPN infrastructure.</li></ul><p>Ultimately, this isn’t an argument against VPNs, or even against virtual locations. It’s an argument for honesty and evidence. If a VPN provider wants you to trust that map of flags, they should be willing, and able, to show that it matches the real network underneath.</p><h2 id="how-ipinfo-approaches-ip-data-differently">How IPinfo Approaches IP Data Differently</h2><p>Most legacy IP data providers rely on regional internet registry (RIR) allocation data and heuristics around routing and address blocks. These providers will often accept self-declared data like customer feedback, corrections, and geofeeds, without a clear way to verify them.&nbsp;</p><p>IPinfo takes a measurement-first approach:</p><ol><li><strong>Proprietary ProbeNet with 1,200+ points of presence</strong><br>We maintain an internet measurement platform of PoPs in locations around the world.</li><li><strong>Active measurements</strong><br>For each visible IP on the internet, including both IPv4 and IPv6 addresses, we measure RTT from multiple probes.</li><li><strong>Evidence-based geolocation</strong><br>We combine these measurements with IPinfo’s other signals to assign a country (and more granular location) that’s grounded in how the internet actually behaves.</li></ol><p>This measurement-first approach is unique in the IP data space. Once we realized how much inaccuracy came from self-declared data, we started investing heavily in research and building ProbeNet to use active measurements at scale. Our goal is to make IP data as evidence-based as possible, verifying with observation on how the internet actually behaves.</p><h2 id="our-methodology-for-this-report">Our Methodology for This Report</h2><p>We approached this VPN investigation the way a skeptical but well-equipped user would: start from the VPNs’ own claims, then test them.</p><h3 id="step-1-collecting-what-providers-say">Step 1: Collecting What Providers Say</h3><p>For each of the <strong>20 VPN providers</strong>, we pulled together three kinds of data:</p><ul><li><strong>Marketing promises: </strong>The “servers in X countries” claims and country lists from their websites. When a country was clearly listed there, we treated it as the locations they actively promote.&nbsp;</li><li><strong>Configurations and locations lists: </strong>Configurations from different protocols like OpenVPN or WireGuard were collected along with location information available on provider command-line tools, mobile applications, or APIs.</li><li><strong>Unique provider–location entries: </strong>We ended up with over 6,000,000 data points and a list of provider + location combinations we could actually try to connect to with multiple IPs each.</li></ul><h3 id="step-2-observing-where-the-traffic-really-goes">Step 2: Observing Where the Traffic Really Goes</h3><p>Next, we used IPinfo infrastructure and ProbeNet to dial into those locations and watch what actually happens:</p><ul><li>We connected to each VPN “location” and captured the exit IP addresses.</li><li>For each exit IP address, we used IPinfo + ProbeNet’s active measurements to determine a measured country, plus:<ul><li>The nearest ProbeNet vantage point (e.g., US, Brazil, France)</li><li>The round-trip time (RTT) from that probe (often under 1 ms), which is a strong hint about physical proximity</li></ul></li></ul><p>Now we had two views for each location:</p><ul><li><strong>Expected/Claimed country</strong>: What the VPN claims in its UI/configs/website</li><li><strong>Measured country</strong>: Where IPinfo + ProbeNet actually see the exit IP</li></ul><h3 id="step-3-comparing-claims-vs-reality">Step 3: Comparing Claims vs Reality</h3><p>For each location where a country was clearly specified, we asked a very simple question: Does the expected country match the measured country?</p><p>If yes, we counted it as a match. If not, it became a mismatch: a location where the app says one country, but the traffic exits somewhere else.</p><h3 id="acknowledgements-limitations-and-constrains">Acknowledgements, Limitations, and Constrains</h3><p>We deliberately used a very narrow definition of “mismatch.” For a location to be counted, two things had to be true: the provider had to clearly claim a specific country (on their website, in their app, or in configs), and we had direct active measurements from ProbeNet for the exit IPs behind that location.</p><p>We ignored any locations where the marketing was ambiguous, where we hadn’t measured the exit directly, or where we only had weaker hints like hostname strings, registry data, or third-party IP databases. Those signals can be useful and true, but we wanted our numbers to be as hard-to-argue-with as possible.</p><p>The result is that the mismatch rates we show here are conservative. With a looser methodology that also leaned on those additional hints, the numbers would almost certainly be higher, not lower.&nbsp;</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dick Van Dyke turns 100 (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/film/2025/dec/13/dick-van-dyke-centenarian-100-mary-poppins-chitty-chitty-bang-bang</link>
            <guid>46256954</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 18:58:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2025/dec/13/dick-van-dyke-centenarian-100-mary-poppins-chitty-chitty-bang-bang">https://www.theguardian.com/film/2025/dec/13/dick-van-dyke-centenarian-100-mary-poppins-chitty-chitty-bang-bang</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46256954">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p><span>A</span>ll Hollywood stars grow old and die except perhaps one - Dick Van Dyke - who turns 100 today. The real world Peter Pan who used to trip over the ottoman on The Dick Van Dyke Show is still standing. The man who impersonated a wind-up toy in Chitty Chitty Bang Bang hasn’t wound down just yet. He has outlived mentors, co-stars, romantic partners and several studios. He’s even outlived the jokes about his performance in Mary Poppins. These days his <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/2025/nov/20/do-you-expect-me-to-talk-dick-van-dyke-says-he-turned-down-playing-james-bond" data-link-name="in body link">mangled cockney accent</a> is regarded with more fondness than contempt. It’s seen as one of the great charms of the 1964 classic, along with the carousel chase or the cartoon dancing penguins.</p><figure id="9cfd5a00-ebe1-4e6a-a661-a75e1c524273" data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Accent on the charm … Dick Van Dyke with Julie Andrews in Mary Poppins." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/8cbbf0f601da373c12c7d5e4502e749c643db8f8/0_0_4502_4200/master/4502.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="415.14882274544647" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Accent on the charm … Dick Van Dyke with Julie Andrews in Mary Poppins.</span> Photograph: Donaldson Collection/Getty Images</figcaption></figure><p>Charm is the magic ingredient of every popular entertainer and few have possessed it in such abundance as Van Dyke, the impoverished son of a travelling cookie salesman who dropped out of high school and educated himself at the movies. “His job in this life is to make a happier world,” his Broadway co-star Chita Rivera once said - and this may explain his stubborn refusal to quit, not while times are tough and he feels that audiences still need cheering up.</p><p>Naturally his workrate has now slowed, but in the past few years he has competed on the TV show <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vz8qbw8dTkg" data-link-name="in body link">The Masked Singer,</a> starred in a<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=pSeaHfkd3M8" data-link-name="in body link"> Coldplay video</a> and enthusiastically <a href="https://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-8063625/Bernie-Sanders-rallies-LA-Dick-Van-Dyke-Sarah-Silverman.html" data-link-name="in body link">stumped for Bernie Sanders</a>. Van Dyke simply couldn’t understand why America’s older citizens were resistant to Sanders’ democratic socialist domestic policies. He said, “I want to urge my generation to get out and vote for him, please.”</p><figure id="1ff74deb-d9af-412a-a6ca-835fa0f747ea" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-3"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Too much energy … Dick Van Dyke in Chitty Chitty Bang Bang." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/6b060c20f62c6c1ff808948d52ea992c00d2ee98/130_995_3528_3423/master/3528.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="431.75595238095235" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Too much energy … Dick Van Dyke in Chitty Chitty Bang Bang.</span> Photograph: Moviestore/REX/Shutterstock</figcaption></figure><p>As he nudges into triple figures, he has become a piece of living history: a walking, talking chronicle of US showbusiness itself. Van Dyke began his career performing for the troops in the second world war and proceeded to rub shoulders with the likes of Phil Silvers and Walt Disney. He had one foot in music-hall slapstick and the other in screwball comedy, and possibly splayed fingers in his midwestern hometown of Danville, Illinois.</p><p>In bridging these worlds, he perfected an outward-facing public image that was one part Stan Laurel to two parts Jimmy Stewart: a pratfalling clown who was decent and honest and smarter than he first appeared. And while he was already nearing 40 when The Dick Van Dyke Show and Mary Poppins made him an international star, the actor remained irrepressibly boyish. In 1968’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/chitty-chitty-bang-bang" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Chitty Chitty Bang Bang</a>, he played Caractacus Potts, the madcap inventor who dreams up a flying car, while Lionel Jeffries - six months younger - played Potts’s addled and eccentric dad.</p><p>Van Dyke, by and large, has steered clear of dark films. He famously turned down the lead role in The Omen and insists that he mostly played a version of himself. “Wholesome,” he says. “An all-round good boy.” That’s true so far as it goes, although it’s probably only half the story, because Van Dyke’s interpretation conveniently sidesteps a 25-year struggle with alcoholism that spanned his professional heyday. Possibly it also glosses over the air of dancing mischief – even wildness – that animates his most feted, family-friendly performances.</p><figure id="cc826a94-2386-46e8-89cf-4c94a7d23457" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-4"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Sparring mutual respect … Mary Tyler Moore and Dick Van Dyke in The Dick Van Dyke Show (1961)." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/38f194ab146eb921724a564f5323e2535b15ab57/0_445_2436_2700/master/2436.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="493.2266009852217" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Sparring mutual respect … Mary Tyler Moore and Dick Van Dyke in The Dick Van Dyke Show (1961). </span> Photograph: CBS Photo Archive/CBS/Getty Images</figcaption></figure><p>Or to put it more bluntly, Van Dyke may have been mainstream but he never once felt conservative, nor even cosy, exactly. He brought too much energy to the room. It was as though he’d just blown in from outside and wasn’t entirely housetrained. The <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/dick-van-dyke" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Dick Van Dyke</a> Show – an otherwise standard 60s family sitcom – is notable for the crackling sexual chemistry and sparring mutual respect which Van Dyke cooked up with his co-star, Mary Tyler Moore.</p><p>Caractacus Potts, for his part, is the ultimate rackety dad: loving and exciting and liable to forget every birthday and dentist appointment. And then there is Bert, the sweep from <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/film/mary-poppins" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Mary Poppins</a> who trips across London’s rooftops like an urbanised Puck of Pook’s Hill. The evidence suggests that Bert isn’t cockney at all. He’s a spooky nature spirit, antic and mercurial, who is gamely attempting to pass himself off as a local.</p><figure id="d044bd79-0ffb-4f26-96c9-0ce0eaf31e72" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-5"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Campaigning for Bernie Sanders, 2020." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/439b4bf60dc8bff6915613b026900f4f9f8cd8a0/0_0_5000_3333/master/5000.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.637" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Campaigning for Bernie Sanders, 2020.</span> Photograph: Étienne Laurent/EPA</figcaption></figure><p>Van Dyke is 100 and therefore no longer looks like Peter Pan. He looks, if anything, the platonic ideal of old age, with laughter lines and a thick white beard, the weathered embodiment of a life well lived. In his later years, he has grown used to people asking him for health advice, to the point where he even sat down and listed it all in a book (<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/28/well/dick-van-dyke-health-habits.html" data-link-name="in body link">100 Rules for Living to 100</a>).</p><figure id="f508b87a-40e0-4d8b-8418-a57b479d78cc" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:13,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Porpoises rescue Dick Van Dyke&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;f508b87a-40e0-4d8b-8418-a57b479d78cc&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/film/2010/nov/11/dick-van-dyke-porpoises-rescue&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;design&quot;:10,&quot;display&quot;:2,&quot;theme&quot;:3}}"></gu-island></figure><p>The man is too self-aware to present himself as a paragon of good living. Instead he credits his longevity to a sprinkle of everyday magic – a combination of good genes, solid friendships and a positive mental outlook. “My life has been a magnificent indulgence,” he says. “I’ve been able to do what I love and share it with the world.”</p><p>It’s an arrangement that has sustained him for a full century on the planet. It’s fuelled a career so rewarding and fun that it barely felt like work at all. Van Dyke started out as showbusiness’s gawky gatecrasher, a controlled explosion of elastic limbs and rubber-faced double-takes, before maturing by degrees into Hollywood’s twinkling Father Time. He is ancient but evergreen, feted and cherished. And he’s altogether as lucky as lucky can be.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are we stuck with the same Desktop UX forever? [video] (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fZTOjd_bOQ</link>
            <guid>46256834</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 18:39:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fZTOjd_bOQ">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1fZTOjd_bOQ</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46256834">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Analysis finds anytime electricity from solar available as battery costs plummet (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pv-magazine-usa.com/2025/12/12/analysis-finds-anytime-electricity-from-solar-available-as-battery-costs-plummet/</link>
            <guid>46256249</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 17:32:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/2025/12/12/analysis-finds-anytime-electricity-from-solar-available-as-battery-costs-plummet/">https://pv-magazine-usa.com/2025/12/12/analysis-finds-anytime-electricity-from-solar-available-as-battery-costs-plummet/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46256249">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                                                                    <p>Ember’s report outlines how falling battery capital expenditures and improved performance metrics have lowered the levelized cost of storage, making dispatchable solar a competitive, anytime electricity option globally.</p>
                                                                                <p><time datetime="2025-12-12T09:44:59-05:00" itemprop="datePublished" title="Friday, December 12, 2025, 9:44 am">December 12, 2025</time>
                                            

                                        
                                    </p></div><div>

                                        <p><span data-contrast="none">A report from energy think tank Ember details how cost reductions in battery storage technology are enabling dispatchable solar power to compete with conventional power sources.</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">Ember’s assessment draws on data from recent auctions across international markets, including Italy, Saudi Arabia, and India, supplemented by expert interviews conducted in October 2025. </span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">This research indicates the industry is moving into a new environment where scaling of manufacturing capacity and competition have pushed costs down. The cost of core BESS equipment fell by 40% in 2024 compared with 2023, according to BloombergNEF’s global benchmark, reaching a record low of $165 per kWh. </span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">Ember’s October 2025 data said a further large fall in 2025 is on track. Over the last 10 years, installed costs have fallen by 20% per year on average, while deployment has increased by around 80% per year.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">According to the findings, the all-in capital expenditure for building a large, long-duration utility-scale battery energy storage system&nbsp;project in global markets outside of the U.S. and China is now approximately $125 per kWh. This figure reflects project pricing, comprising $75 per kWh for core equipment sourced from China, including battery enclosures, the power conversion system (PCS), and energy management system (EMS) and $50 per kWh for local installation, engineering, and grid connection activities.</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">These capital costs translate into a levelized cost of storage (LCOS) of $65 per MWh. This LCOS reflects the cost of shifting electricity to a different time period.</span></p>
<figure id="attachment_126618"><img decoding="async" src="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Ember121.png" alt="" width="706" height="474" srcset="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Ember121.png 1132w, https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2025/12/Ember121-600x403.png 600w" sizes="(max-width: 706px) 100vw, 706px"><figcaption><i> Image: Ember </i> </figcaption></figure>
<p><span data-contrast="none">Ember said this reduction in LCOS is driven by equipment costs and improved performance metrics, such as a 20-year design life for LFP technology, 90% efficiency, and lower project financing costs due to de-risked revenue models. Longer lifetimes, higher efficiency, and lower project risks reduce the LCOS by 35% even before accounting for the falling equipment prices, said the report.</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">The core implication of this analysis is the economic viability of dispatchable solar. </span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">Storing 50% of a day’s solar output to meet night-time demand adds $33 per MWh to the generation cost. Using the 2024 global average solar price of $43 per MWh, the total cost for dispatchable solar is calculated at $76 per MWh. </span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">This positions dispatchable solar as a cost-effective alternative to new gas power plants, particularly in regions reliant on imported LNG.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">For the U.S., core equipment costs can reach $100 per kWh or higher in markets with higher tariffs or stricter standards. With the U.S. market facing various tariffs on Chinese imports and domestic content requirements via the Inflation Reduction Act (IRA), the $125 per kWh BESS project capex estimate is not directly applicable to the U.S. market. </span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">The total equipment costs are 10% to 15% cheaper for four-hour projects, a key project duration in the U.S., as some components are sized to power rather than energy. However, even with cost variations, the U.S. is the second biggest BESS market globally, behind China, and saw record growth in Q1 2025 across all segments. </span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">In 2024, Texas, California, Arizona, and Nevada all saw significant utility-scale battery growth, with the U.S. adding 10 GW of utility-scale batteries nationally, an 80% increase over the previous year. This growth is accelerating the integration of solar into the grid.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span data-contrast="none">Ember’s conclusion is that solar has evolved beyond daytime electricity; coupled with storage, it becomes dispatchable, anytime power, positioned to meet a substantial portion of the world’s future energy needs.</span><span data-ccp-props="{&quot;134233117&quot;:false,&quot;134233118&quot;:false,&quot;201341983&quot;:0,&quot;335551550&quot;:0,&quot;335551620&quot;:0,&quot;335557856&quot;:1577488,&quot;335559738&quot;:240,&quot;335559739&quot;:240,&quot;335559740&quot;:360}">&nbsp;</span></p>
<div>
<p>This content is protected by copyright and may not be reused. If you want to cooperate with us and would like to reuse some of our content, please contact: <a href="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#9bbdb8e3adaea0bdb8e3adafa0bdb8e3ada2a0bdb8e3acafa0bdb8e3adfda0bdb8e3aca9a0bdb8e3aca8a0bdb8e3afaba0bdb8e3acaba0bdb8e3acada0bdb8e3a9ffa0bdb8e3adffa0bdb8e3adaaa0bdb8e3adaca0bdb8e3adaaa0bdb8e3acfaa0bdb8e3ada2a0bdb8e3adfea0bdb8e3adaea0bdb8e3a9fea0bdb8e3ada8a0bdb8e3adfda0bdb8e3adffa0">editors@pv-magazine.com</a>.</p>

</div>
<div>
					<h3>Popular content</h3>
					<div>
						<p><a href="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/2025/12/10/pennsylvania-township-approves-permit-for-solar-project-on-2000-acres-of-toxic-coal-mine-land/" target="_blank"><img src="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/wordpress-popular-posts/126573-featured-1200x800.jpg" srcset="https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/wordpress-popular-posts/126573-featured-1200x800.jpg, https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/wordpress-popular-posts/126573-featured-1200x800@1.5x.jpg 1.5x, https://pv-magazine-usa.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/wordpress-popular-posts/126573-featured-1200x800@2x.jpg 2x" width="1200" height="800" alt="" decoding="async"></a></p>
						
					</div>
				</div>                                                                                
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I tried Gleam for Advent of Code (247 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.tymscar.com/posts/gleamaoc2025/</link>
            <guid>46255991</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 17:00:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.tymscar.com/posts/gleamaoc2025/">https://blog.tymscar.com/posts/gleamaoc2025/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255991">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I do Advent of Code every year.</p><p>For the last seven years, including this one, I have managed to get all the stars. I do not say that to brag. I say it because it explains why I keep coming back.</p><p><img src="https://blog.tymscar.com/gleamadventofcode2025/events.png" alt="My Advent of Code stars"></p><p>It is one of the few tech traditions I never get bored of, even after doing it for a long time. I like the time pressure. I like the community vibe. I like that every December I can pick one language and go all in.</p><p>This year, I picked Gleam.</p><h2 id="a-much-shorter-year">A much shorter year<a href="#a-much-shorter-year" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>Advent of Code is usually 25 days. This year Eric decided to do 12 days instead.</p><p>So instead of 50 parts, it was 24.</p><p>That sounds like a relaxed year. It was not, but not in a bad way.</p><p>The easier days were harder than the easy days in past years, but they were also really engaging and fun to work through. The hard days were hard, especially the last three, but they were still the good kind of hard. They were problems I actually wanted to wrestle with.</p><p>It also changes the pacing in a funny way. In a normal year, by day 10 you have a pretty comfy toolbox. This year it felt like the puzzles were already demanding that toolbox while I was still building it.</p><p>That turned out to be a perfect setup for learning a new language.</p><h2 id="why-gleam-felt-like-a-good-aoc-language">Why Gleam felt like a good AoC language<a href="#why-gleam-felt-like-a-good-aoc-language" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>Gleam is easy to like quickly.</p><p>The syntax is clean. The compiler is helpful, and the error messages are super duper good. Rust good.</p><p>Most importantly, the language strongly nudges you into a style that fits Advent of Code really well. Parse some text. Transform it a few times. Fold. Repeat.</p><p>Also, pipes. Pipes everywhere. I love pipes.</p><p>One thing I did not expect was how good the editor experience would be. The LSP worked much better than I expected. It basically worked perfectly the whole time. I used the Gleam extension for IntelliJ and it was great.</p><p><a href="https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/25254-gleam-language">https://plugins.jetbrains.com/plugin/25254-gleam-language</a></p><p>I also just like FP.</p><p>FP is not always easier, but it is often easier. When it clicks, you stop writing instructions and you start describing the solution.</p><h2 id="the-first-gleam-superpower-echo">The first Gleam superpower: <code>echo</code><a href="#the-first-gleam-superpower-echo" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>The first thing I fell in love with was <code>echo</code>.</p><p>It is basically a print statement that does not make you earn it. You can <code>echo</code> any value. You do not have to format anything. You do not have to build a string. You can just drop it into a pipeline and keep going.</p><p>This is the kind of thing I mean:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span>list<span>.</span><span>range</span>(<span>0</span>, <span>5</span>)
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> <span>echo</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span><span>map</span>(int<span>.</span>to_string)
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> <span>echo</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>You can quickly inspect values at multiple points without breaking the flow.</p><p>I did miss string interpolation, especially early on. <code>echo</code> made up for a lot of that.</p><p>It mostly hit when I needed to generate text, not when I needed to inspect values. The day where I generated an LP file for <code>glpsol</code> is the best example. It is not hard code, but it is a lot of string building. Without interpolation it turns into a bit of a mess of <code>&lt;&gt;</code>s.</p><p>This is a small excerpt from my LP generator:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span><span>"Minimize</span><span>\n</span><span>"</span>
</span></span><span><span>&lt;&gt; <span>"  total: "</span>
</span></span><span><span>&lt;&gt; buttons
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> string<span>.</span><span>join</span>(<span>" + "</span>)
</span></span><span><span>&lt;&gt; <span>"</span><span>\n\n</span><span>Subject To</span><span>\n</span><span>"</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>It works. It is just the kind of code where you really feel missing interpolation.</p><h2 id="options-everywhere-and-why-that-matters-for-grid-puzzles">Options everywhere, and why that matters for grid puzzles<a href="#options-everywhere-and-why-that-matters-for-grid-puzzles" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>A lot of AoC is grids.</p><p>Grids are where you normally either crash into out of bounds bugs, or you litter your code with bounds checks you do not care about.</p><p>In my day 4 solution I used a dict as a grid. The key ergonomic part is that <code>dict.get</code> gives you an option-like result, which makes neighbour checking safe by default.</p><p>This is the neighbour function from my solution:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span><span>fn</span> <span>get_neighbours</span>(grid<span>:</span> <span>Grid</span>(<span>Object</span>), pos<span>:</span> <span>Position</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>List</span>(<span>Object</span>) {
</span></span><span><span>  [
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>    #(pos<span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>, pos<span>.</span><span>1</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>),
</span></span><span><span>  ]
</span></span><span><span>  <span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span><span>filter_map</span>(<span>fn</span>(neighbour_pos) { grid <span>|&gt;</span> dict<span>.</span><span>get</span>(neighbour_pos) })
</span></span><span><span>}
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>That last line is the whole point.</p><p>No bounds checks. No sentinel values. Out of bounds just disappears.</p><p>I expected to write parsers and helpers, and I did. What I did not expect was how often Gleam already had the exact list function I needed.</p><h3 id="listtranspose-saved-a-whole-day"><code>list.transpose</code> saved a whole day<a href="#listtranspose-saved-a-whole-day" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><p>Day 6 part 1 was basically a transpose problem in disguise.</p><p>I read the input, chunked it into rows, transposed it, and suddenly the rest of the puzzle became obvious.</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span>input
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span>transpose
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span><span>map</span>(<span>fn</span>(line) { line <span>|&gt;</span> calculate_instruction })
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> bigi<span>.</span>sum
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>In a lot of languages you end up writing your own transpose yet again. In Gleam it is already there.</p><h3 id="listcombination_pairs-is-a-cheat-code"><code>list.combination_pairs</code> is a cheat code<a href="#listcombination_pairs-is-a-cheat-code" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><p>Another example is <code>list.combination_pairs</code>.</p><p>In day 8 I needed all pairs of 3D points. In an imperative language you would probably write nested loops and then question your off by one logic.</p><p>In Gleam it is a one liner:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span>boxes
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span>combination_pairs
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Sometimes FP is not about being clever. It is about having the right function name.</p><h2 id="fold_until-is-my-favorite-thing-i-found"><code>fold_until</code> is my favorite thing I found<a href="#fold_until-is-my-favorite-thing-i-found" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>If I had to pick one feature that made me want to keep writing Gleam after AoC, it is <code>fold_until</code>.</p><p>Early exit without hacks is fantastic in puzzles.</p><p>In day 8 part 2 I kept merging sets until the first set in the list contained all boxes. When that happens, I stop.</p><p>The core shape looks like this:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span><span>fold_until</span>(initial, <span>fn</span>(acc, pair) {
</span></span><span><span>  <span>case</span> done_yet {
</span></span><span><span>    <span>True</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Stop</span>(new_acc)
</span></span><span><span>    <span>False</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Continue</span>(new_acc)
</span></span><span><span>  }
</span></span><span><span>})
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>It is small, explicit, and it reads like intent.</p><p>I also used <code>fold_until</code> in day 10 part 1 to find the smallest combination size that works.</p><h2 id="where-gleam-fought-me-a-bit">Where Gleam fought me a bit<a href="#where-gleam-fought-me-a-bit" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>Even though I enjoyed Gleam a lot, I did hit a few recurring friction points.</p><p>None of these are deal breakers. They are just the kind of things you notice when you do 24 parts in a row.</p><h3 id="file-io-is-not-in-the-standard-library">File IO is not in the standard library<a href="#file-io-is-not-in-the-standard-library" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><p>This one surprised me on day 1.</p><p>For AoC you read a file every day. In this repo I used <code>simplifile</code> everywhere because you need something. It is fine, I just did not expect basic file IO to be outside the standard library.</p><h3 id="regex-is-a-dependency-too">Regex is a dependency too<a href="#regex-is-a-dependency-too" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><p>Day 2 part 2 pushed me into regex and I had to add <code>gleam_regexp</code>.</p><p>This is the style I used, building a regex from a substring:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span><span>let</span> <span>assert</span> <span>Ok</span>(re) <span>=</span> regexp<span>.</span><span>from_string</span>(<span>"^("</span> &lt;&gt; substring &lt;&gt; <span>")+$"</span>)
</span></span><span><span>regexp<span>.</span><span>check</span>(re, val)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Again, totally fine. It just surprised me.</p><h3 id="list-pattern-matching-limitations">List pattern matching limitations<a href="#list-pattern-matching-limitations" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><p>You can do <code>[first, ..rest]</code> and you can do <code>[first, second]</code>.</p><p>But you cannot do <code>[first, ..middle, last]</code>.</p><p>It is not the end of the world, but it would have made some parsing cleaner.</p><h3 id="comparisons-are-explicit">Comparisons are explicit<a href="#comparisons-are-explicit" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h3><p>In Gleam a lot of comparisons are not booleans. You get an <code>order</code> value.</p><p>This is great for sorting. It is also very explicit. It can be a bit verbose when you just want an <code>&lt;=</code> check.</p><p>In day 5 I ended up writing patterns like this:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span><span>case</span> cmp_start, cmp_end {
</span></span><span><span>  order<span>.</span><span>Lt</span>, _ <span>-&gt;</span> <span>False</span>
</span></span><span><span>  _, order<span>.</span><span>Gt</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>False</span>
</span></span><span><span>  _, _ <span>-&gt;</span> <span>True</span>
</span></span><span><span>}
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="big-integers-and-targeting-javascript">Big integers, and targeting JavaScript<a href="#big-integers-and-targeting-javascript" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>I used <code>bigi</code> a few times this year.</p><p>On the Erlang VM, integers are arbitrary precision, so you usually do not care about overflow. That is one of the nicest things about the BEAM.</p><p>If you want your Gleam code to also target JavaScript, you do care. JavaScript has limits, and suddenly using <code>bigi</code> becomes necessary for some puzzles.</p><p>I wish that was just part of <code>Int</code>, with a single consistent story across targets.</p><h2 id="the-most-satisfying-part-xor-as-bitmasks">The most satisfying part: XOR as bitmasks<a href="#the-most-satisfying-part-xor-as-bitmasks" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>Day 10 part 1 was my favorite part of the whole event.</p><p>The moment I saw the toggling behavior, it clicked as XOR. Represent the lights as a number. Represent each button as a bitmask. Find the smallest combination of bitmasks that XOR to the target.</p><p>This is the fold from my solution:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span>combination
</span></span><span><span><span>|&gt;</span> list<span>.</span><span>fold</span>(<span>0</span>, <span>fn</span>(acc, comb) {
</span></span><span><span>  int<span>.</span><span>bitwise_exclusive_or</span>(acc, comb)
</span></span><span><span>})
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>It felt clean, it felt fast, and it felt like the representation did most of the work.</p><h2 id="the-least-satisfying-part-shelling-out-to-glpsol">The least satisfying part: shelling out to <code>glpsol</code><a href="#the-least-satisfying-part-shelling-out-to-glpsol" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>Day 10 part 2 was the opposite feeling.</p><p>I knew brute force was out. It was clearly a system of linear equations.</p><p>In previous years I would reach for Z3, but there are no Z3 bindings for Gleam. I tried to stay in Gleam, and I ended up generating an LP file and shelling out to <code>glpsol</code> using <code>shellout</code>.</p><p>It worked, and honestly the LP format is beautiful.</p><p>Here is the call:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span><span>let</span> _ <span>=</span>
</span></span><span><span>  shellout<span>.</span><span>command</span>(
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"glpsol"</span>,
</span></span><span><span>    [<span>"--lp"</span>, <span>"temp.lp"</span>, <span>"-w"</span>, <span>"temp_sol.txt"</span>],
</span></span><span><span>    <span>"."</span>,
</span></span><span><span>    [],
</span></span><span><span>  )
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>It is a hack, but it is a pragmatic hack, and that is also part of Advent of Code.</p><h2 id="memoization-keys-that-actually-model-the-problem">Memoization keys that actually model the problem<a href="#memoization-keys-that-actually-model-the-problem" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>Day 11 part 2 is where I was happy I was writing Gleam.</p><p>The important detail was that the memo key is not just the node. It is the node plus your state.</p><p>In my case the key was:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span>#(neighbour, new_seen_dac, new_seen_fft)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Once I got the memo threading right, it ran instantly.</p><h2 id="the-finale-and-the-troll-heuristic">The finale, and the troll heuristic<a href="#the-finale-and-the-troll-heuristic" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>The last day was the only puzzle I did not fully enjoy.</p><p>Not because it was bad. It just felt like it relied on assumptions about the input, and I am one of those people that does not love doing that.</p><p>I overthought it for a bit, then I learned it was more of a troll problem. The “do the areas of the pieces, when fully interlocked, fit on the board” heuristic was enough.</p><p>In my solution it is literally this:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="gleam"><span><span>heuristic_area <span>&lt;=</span> max_area
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Sometimes you build a beautiful mental model and then the right answer is a single inequality.</p><h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing thoughts<a href="#closing-thoughts" arialabel="Anchor">#</a></h2><p>I am very happy I picked Gleam this year.</p><p>It has sharp edges, mostly around where the standard library draws the line and a few language constraints that show up in puzzle code. But it also has real strengths.</p><p>Pipelines feel good. Options and Results make unsafe problems feel safe. The list toolbox is better than I expected. <code>fold_until</code> is incredible. Once you stop trying to write loops and you let it be functional, the solutions start to feel clearer.</p><p>I cannot wait to try Gleam in a real project. I have been thinking about using it to write a webserver, and I am genuinely excited to give it a go.</p><p>And of course, I cannot wait for next year’s Advent of Code.</p><p>If you want to look at the source for all 12 days, it is here:</p><p><a href="https://github.com/tymscar/Advent-Of-Code/tree/master/2025/gleam/aoc/src">https://github.com/tymscar/Advent-Of-Code/tree/master/2025/gleam/aoc/src</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LG TV's new software update installed MS Copilot, which cannot be deleted (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1plldqo/my_lg_tvs_new_software_update_installed_microsoft/</link>
            <guid>46255335</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 15:41:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1plldqo/my_lg_tvs_new_software_update_installed_microsoft/">https://old.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1plldqo/my_lg_tvs_new_software_update_installed_microsoft/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255335">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><blockquote>
<p><a href="https://td.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/#image"></a>
<a href="https://td.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/#button">Enter mildyinfuriating &nbsp; &nbsp;( ͡° ͜ʖ ͡°)</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Is your day filled with midly infuriating problems? You came to the right place then.</p>

<p><strong>Rules</strong>:</p>

<p>A: No reddit meta posts.</p>

<p>1) <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/1exsuk/meta_modpost_new_rule_see_inside_for_details/">No Memes or "meme-like" image macros.</a> No Memes or "meme-like" image macros. These include overdone references in the title (e.g. “banana for scale”, “potato quality”, and so on).</p>

<p>8) Content requirements:</p>

<ul>
<li>a) Please try to post original content. Reposts or crossposts of someone else's content will be removed if it has been posted on Reddit within the past 6 months. At the moderator's discretion, content posted without the author's original consent or without linking to an original source will also be removed.</li>
<li>b) No GIFs that end slightly before something happens (<a href="http://i.imgur.com/Lq6m5QY.gifv">Example</a>)</li>
<li>c) Unn<sup>ecessarily</sup> overdone <sup>text,</sup> ar→rows, scribbles, or substantive edits over the original content are not allowed.</li>
<li>d) No posting surveys - posts about surveys are allowed, however bear in mind they are often overdone.</li>
<li>f) Blur out any personal information. (Full names, phone numbers, license plates etc.)</li>
<li>f) R3: Respect Reddiquette and Follow Reddit Rules</li>
<li>g) R4: No grandstanding, politics, or pushing agendas. No meta reddit posts.
This includes posts that could be, within reason, regarded as politically, sexually, racially, or socially inappropriate or unnecessary. (<a href="https://i.imgur.com/Um3eIs7.jpg">Example</a>). Posts that push an agenda of any sort is also prohibited, including inappropriate posts about this subreddit or other subs as described in "prevent brigading" rule. If you're unsure if your post or comment falls under this rule, message the mods to ask!</li>
</ul>

<p>6) Prevent brigading. We do not allow any kind of content about reddit, including links to other subreddits in comments - Use modmail for disputes, not posts. </p>

<p>These rules are <strong>subject to the moderator's discretion</strong>, and can change at any time. A full, in-dpeth explanation can be found in the wiki <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/about/rules">here</a>.</p>

<p><em>Repeated violation of rules may result in banning</em></p>

<p>3) Added emphasis on rule 8g: NO POLITICS</p>

<p>7) <a href="https://old.reddit.com/u/dnanf">/u/dnanf</a> may post whatever he wants, even if it's shit. It is your duty as a good redditor to upvote his posts.</p>

<p><strong>The Mild Network:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyAmusing">/r/MildlyAmusing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyAwesome">/r/MildlyAwesome</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyAww">r/MildlyAww</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyBestOf">/r/MildlyBestOf</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyConfusing">/r/MildlyConfusing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyCreepy">/r/MildlyCreepy</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyDangerous">r/MildlyDangerous</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyDepressing">/r/MildlyDepressing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyDisgusting">/r/MildlyDisgusting</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyDisturbing">/r/MildlyDisturbing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyEnteristing">/r/MildlyEnteristing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyImpressive">/r/MildlyImpressive</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyMotivated">/r/MildlyMotivated</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyInteresting">/r/MildlyInteresting</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyInterestingIAmA">r/MildlyInterestingIAmA</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyInterestingMC">/r/MildlyInterestingMC</a> (Minecraft)</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyMetal">/r/MildlyMetal</a> </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyOffensive">/r/MildlyOffensive</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyPleasing">/r/MildlyPleasing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlySatisfying">/r/MildlySatisfying</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyStartledCats">/r/MildlyStartledCats</a> </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyStupid">r/MildlyStupid</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyUninteresting">/r/MildlyUninteresting</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyWeird">/r/MildlyWeird</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/MildlyWTF">/r/MildlyWTF</a></p></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Our Friends:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/extremelyinfuriating">/r/extremelyinfuriating</a> </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/gifsthatendtoosoon">/r/gifsthatendtoosoon</a> <strong>NEW: Please post gifs that end too soon in that sub, instead of here.</strong></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/QuestionCollege">/r/QuestionCollege</a> <strong>NEW</strong></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/UnnecessaryQuotes">/r/UnnecessaryQuotes</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/PerfectFit">/r/PerfectFit</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/FakeRedditNews">/r/FakeRedditNews</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/OddlySatisfying">/r/OddlySatisfying</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/SlightlyUnsatisfying">/r/SlightlyUnsatisfying</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/FunnyAndSad">/r/FunnyAndSad</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Today_I_Realized">r/Today_I_Realized</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/WellThatSucks">/r/WellThatSucks</a> </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/BadParking">/r/BadParking</a> </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/BloodFueledRage">r/BloodFueledRage</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Rage">/r/Rage</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Infuriating">/r/Infuriating</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Amusing">/r/Amusing</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/BenignExistence">/r/BenignExistence</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/CasualIAmA">/r/CasualIAmA</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/InterestingAnecdote">/r/InterestingAnecdote</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/GrindsMyGears">/r/GrindsMyGears</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/HowToNotGiveaFuck">/r/HowToNotGiveaFuck</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/NotQuiteWTF">/r/NotQuiteWTF</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Onejob">/r/Onejob</a></p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/Vastlystupid">/r/Vastlystupid</a> </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/PleaseJustStop">/r/PleaseJustStop</a>  </p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/BadYTAds">/r/BadYTAds</a>  </p></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/mildlyinteresting/comments/zytpk/list_of_similar_subreddits_and_mild_network/">More mildly related subreddits</a></p>

<p><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/comments/17nzkh/meta_announcement_new_flair_options/">Click Here</a> for details about flair!</p>

<h2><a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/mildlyinfuriating/new">New Posts</a></h2>





<p>jukmifgguggh</p>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: How can I get better at using AI for programming? (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255285</link>
            <guid>46255285</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 15:37:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255285">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="bigbox"><td><table><tbody><tr id="46255285"><td><span></span></td><td><center><a id="up_46255285" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46255285&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46255285"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255285">Ask HN: How can I get better at using AI for programming?</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span><span id="score_46255285">111 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=lemonlime227">lemonlime227</a> <span title="2025-12-13T15:37:16 1765640236"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255285">5 hours ago</a></span> <span id="unv_46255285"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=46255285&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46255285">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Ask%20HN%3A%20How%20can%20I%20get%20better%20at%20using%20AI%20for%20programming%3F&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=46255285&amp;auth=27b216620c161daf3f870336ebc89a9223f27442">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46255285">141&nbsp;comments</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>I've been working on a personal project recently, rewriting an old jQuery + Django project into SvelteKit. The main work is translating the UI templates into idiomatic SvelteKit while maintaining the original styling. This includes things like using semantic HTML instead of div-spamming, not wrapping divs in divs in divs, and replacing bootstrap with minimal tailwind. It also includes some logic refactors, to maintain the original functionality but rewritten to avoid years of code debt. Things like replacing templates using boolean flags for multiple views with composable Svelte components.</p><p>I've had a fairly steady process for doing this: look at each route defined in Django, build out my `+page.server.ts`, and then split each major section of the page into a Svelte component with a matching Storybook story. It takes a lot of time to do this, since I have to ensure I'm not just copying the template but rather recreating it in a more idiomatic style.</p><p>This kind of work seems like a great use case for AI assisted programming, but I've failed to use it effectively. At most, I can only get Claude Code to recreate some slightly less spaghetti code in Svelte. Simple prompting just isn't able to get AI's code quality within 90% of what I'd write by hand. Ideally, AI could get it's code to something I could review manually in 15-20 minutes, which would massively speed up the time spent on this project (right now it takes me 1-2 hours to properly translate a route).</p><p>Do you guys have tips or suggestions on how to improve my efficiency and code quality with AI?</p></div></td></tr><tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr></tbody></table><br>
</td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We built another object storage (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fractalbits.com/blog/why-we-built-another-object-storage/</link>
            <guid>46254087</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 12:29:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fractalbits.com/blog/why-we-built-another-object-storage/">https://fractalbits.com/blog/why-we-built-another-object-storage/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46254087">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>  <h2 id="a-crowded-market-but-an-unsolved-problem">A Crowded Market, But An Unsolved Problem</h2>
<p>Object storage is the backbone of modern data infrastructure. AWS S3, Google Cloud Storage, MinIO, Ceph, newer players like Tigris Data—the market is saturated. So why build another one?</p>
<p>Because the fundamental assumptions behind these systems are shifting. High performance is no longer optional—but having high performance available isn’t the same as being able to afford using it.</p>
<h2 id="beyond-cold-storage-why-performance-matters-now">Beyond “Cold Storage”: Why Performance Matters Now</h2>
<p>Traditional object storage had a clear priority order: cost first, performance later. This worked fine for archiving backups and storing large, rarely accessed files.</p>
<p>But today, object storage is increasingly the primary data layer for AI, analytics, and cloud-native applications. Latency directly translates to compute costs—stalled GPUs waiting on I/O are expensive GPUs doing nothing.</p>
<p>High-performance object storage exists now. S3 Express One Zone, for example, delivers single-digit millisecond latency. But there’s a catch: the per-request pricing makes it prohibitively expensive to actually <em>use</em> at high IOPS. As one analysis put it, it’s “the right technology, at the right time with the wrong price” [1]. You have the performance on paper, but you can’t afford to run your workload at full speed. That’s the high-performance trap.</p>
<h2 id="the-new-challenge-ai-and-analytical-workloads">The New Challenge: AI and Analytical Workloads</h2>
<p>Modern workloads, especially in AI, impose demands that strain traditional designs:</p>
<p><strong>Small Objects at Scale</strong>: AI training datasets often consist of millions of small files (images, text snippets, feature vectors). A study of typical AI training workloads found over 60% of objects are 512KB or smaller [2]. This shifts the bottleneck from bandwidth to metadata performance.</p>
<p><strong>Latency Sensitivity</strong>: Training loops and inference pipelines are bottlenecked by I/O. When fetching thousands of small objects per batch, per-object latency compounds quickly, stalling expensive GPUs.</p>
<p><strong>The Need for Directories</strong>: S3’s flat namespace is a mismatch for many workflows. Data scientists expect atomic renames and efficient directory listings—operations that are either slow or missing in classic object stores.</p>
<h3 id="why-not-just-use-a-filesystem">”Why Not Just Use a Filesystem?”</h3>
<p>A reasonable question: if you want directories and atomic rename, why not just use a filesystem like AWS EFS? Object stores and filesystems are different concepts—why blur the line?</p>
<p>The answer is that the line is <em>already</em> blurring, driven by real workload demands. AWS themselves recognized this when they introduced S3 Express One Zone with explicit “directory bucket” semantics and atomic rename support (currently single-object) [3]. Google Cloud has made similar moves toward hierarchical namespace support [4]. The industry is converging on this because the clean separation between “object storage for scale” and “filesystem for semantics” doesn’t match how modern applications actually work.</p>
<p>We’re not trying to build a POSIX filesystem. But the subset of filesystem semantics that matter for data workflows—efficient directory listings, atomic rename for safe data handoffs—these belong in object storage. The alternative is forcing every application to build fragile workarounds on top of a flat namespace.</p>
<h2 id="where-current-solutions-hit-a-wall">Where Current Solutions Hit a Wall</h2>
<p>Existing systems struggle with these patterns in predictable ways:</p>
<p><strong>The High-Performance Trap</strong>: High-performance tiers like S3 Express One Zone solve the latency problem, but the per-request cost means you can’t actually use that performance at scale. At 10K PUT/s, you’re looking at ~$29K/month in request fees alone. The performance is there; the economics aren’t.</p>
<p><strong>The Small Object Tax</strong>: With cloud object storage, you pay per request. Storing billions of 4KB objects means your API request costs can exceed your storage costs. The more objects you have, the worse it gets.</p>
<p><strong>Missing Directory Semantics</strong>: The lack of atomic rename forces complex workarounds in applications, limiting what you can build directly on object storage. Most systems with rename support rely on inode-like structures that struggle with scalability and performance—adding to the per-IOPS cost burden.</p>
<h2 id="introducing-fractalbits">Introducing FractalBits</h2>
<p>We built FractalBits to break out of the high-performance trap: delivering performance you can actually afford to use at scale. In our benchmarks, we achieved nearly 1M GET/s on 4KB objects with a cluster totaling 64 cores across all data and metadata nodes.</p>
<p>Our focus:</p>
<ol>
<li>High IOPS at a cost that makes sense—so you can actually run your workload at full speed.</li>
<li>Native directory semantics, including atomic rename.</li>
<li>Strong consistency—no eventual consistency surprises.</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>The Cost Difference</strong></p>
<p>Here’s what the gap looks like for a small-object intensive workload (4KB objects, 10K IOPS):</p>





























<table><thead><tr><th>Metric</th><th>S3 Express One Zone</th><th>FractalBits</th><th>Reduction</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Monthly Cost for 10K PUT/s</td><td>~$29,290</td><td>~$166</td><td>~150×</td></tr><tr><td>Monthly Cost for 10K GET/s</td><td>~$778</td><td>~$42</td><td>~15×</td></tr><tr><td>Storage (1 TB Per Month)</td><td>~$110</td><td>$0 (included)</td><td>—</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p><em>S3 costs based on public pricing ($0.00113/1K PUTs, $0.00003/1K GETs, $0.11/GB/Month). FractalBits estimated using 1-year reserved instance pricing for required compute (e.g., i8g.2xlarge for data, m7g.4xlarge for metadata). Your savings will vary based on workload, but the magnitude is indicative.</em></p>

<p>At our core is a metadata engine built on an on-disk radix tree, optimized for path-like keys.</p>
<p>Most object stores use LSM-trees (good for writes, variable read latency) or B+ trees (predictable reads, write amplification). We chose a radix tree because it naturally mirrors a filesystem hierarchy:</p>
<p><strong>Prefix Sharing</strong>: Common path segments (e.g., <code>/datasets/cifar10/</code>) are stored once, saving memory and speeding up traversal.</p>
<p><strong>Efficient Directory Operations</strong>: Listing a directory becomes a subtree scan. Atomic rename is essentially updating a pointer at the branch point, not copying data.</p>
<p><strong>Crash Consistency</strong>: We use physiological logging to ensure metadata integrity and fast recovery.</p>
<p>Unlike most systems that use inode-based (or inode-like) structures to support directory features, we use a full-path approach for better scalability and performance.</p>
<p>By the way, we implemented the core engine in Zig for control and predictable performance.<br>
Why Zig?</p>
<ul>
<li><code>comptime</code> metaprogramming generates optimized code paths for different node types at compile time</li>
<li>Manual memory management means no GC pauses and predictable latency</li>
<li>Direct SIMD access for parallel key comparisons within tree nodes</li>
<li>io_uring in std library, so that we can easily try more recent io_uring kernel features (registered buffers, nvme IOPoll etc).</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="the-gateway-rust-based-s3-compatible-api-server">The Gateway: Rust-Based S3-Compatible API server</h2>
<p>Our S3-compatible API server, built in Rust, manages the data path:</p>
<p><strong>Safety &amp; Concurrency</strong>: Rust’s ownership model gives us thread safety without a garbage collector—important for high-concurrency request handling.</p>
<p><strong>Async I/O</strong>: Built on Tokio for handling thousands of concurrent connections.</p>
<p><strong>Production-Ready Frameworks</strong>: We support both axum and actix-web, defaulting to actix-web. Its thread-per-core architecture aligns with our design for maximum performance.</p>
<h2 id="the-model-bring-your-own-cloud-byoc">The Model: Bring Your Own Cloud (BYOC)</h2>
<p>FractalBits deploys as a managed software layer within your own cloud account (currently AWS only).</p>
<p><strong>For you:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Cost transparency—you pay the cloud provider’s raw costs for VMs and disks, no egress fees to us</li>
<li>Data sovereignty—your data never leaves your cloud tenant</li>
<li>Low latency—deploy in the same region/VPC as your compute</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>For us:</strong> We leverage the cloud’s proven infrastructure instead of building it from scratch, letting us focus on the storage engine itself.</p>
<h2 id="looking-ahead">Looking Ahead</h2>
<p>The object storage market has high-performance options, but the economics often make that performance unusable at scale. And systems that do offer directory semantics often struggle with performance or scalability. Getting both at a reasonable cost is still rare. We think there’s room for a different approach.</p>
<p>FractalBits is our answer. We’re early in this journey and learning from users who are pushing these limits.</p>
<hr>
<p>Hitting the performance or cost wall with your current object storage? We’d be interested to hear about your use case.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/fractalbits-labs/fractalbits-main">GitHub</a></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<p>[1]. S3 Express One Zone, Not Quite What I Hoped For, <a href="https://jack-vanlightly.com/blog/2023/11/29/s3-express-one-zone-not-quite-what-i-hoped-for">https://jack-vanlightly.com/blog/2023/11/29/s3-express-one-zone-not-quite-what-i-hoped-for</a></p>
<p>[2]. Mantle: Efficient Hierarchical Metadata Management for Cloud Object Storage Services. SOSP 2025.</p>
<p>[3]. Amazon S3 Express One Zone now supports renaming objects within a directory bucket, <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2025/06/amazon-s3-express-one-zone-renaming-objects-directory-bucket/">https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2025/06/amazon-s3-express-one-zone-renaming-objects-directory-bucket/</a></p>
<p>[4]. Google Cloud Storage hierarchical namespace, <a href="https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/storage-data-transfer/new-gcs-hierarchical-namespace-for-ai-and-data-lake-workloads">https://cloud.google.com/blog/products/storage-data-transfer/new-gcs-hierarchical-namespace-for-ai-and-data-lake-workloads</a></p>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[YouTube's CEO limits his kids' social media use – other tech bosses do the same (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/13/youtubes-ceo-is-latest-tech-boss-limiting-his-kids-social-media-use.html</link>
            <guid>46253985</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 12:03:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/13/youtubes-ceo-is-latest-tech-boss-limiting-his-kids-social-media-use.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/13/youtubes-ceo-is-latest-tech-boss-limiting-his-kids-social-media-use.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46253985">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="MakeItRegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-1" data-analytics="MakeItRegularArticle-articleBody-5-1"><div id="ArticleBody-InlineImage-108087244" data-test="InlineImage"><p>Neal Mohan, the CEO of YouTube speaks during a panel for the Summit for Democracy on March 30, 2023 in Washington, DC.</p><p>Anna Moneymaker | Getty Images</p></div><div><p>YouTube's CEO Neal Mohan is the latest in a line of tech bosses who have admitted to limiting their children's social media use, as the harms of being online for young people have become more evident. </p><p>Mohan, who took the helm of YouTube's leadership in 2023, was just named Time's 2025 CEO of the Year. He said in an <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@time/video/7582409839003946253?is_from_webapp=1&amp;amp;sender_device=pc&amp;amp;web_id=7571799858848482838" target="_blank">interview with the magazine</a> that his children's use of media platforms is controlled and restricted. </p><p>"We do limit their time on YouTube and other platforms and other forms of media. On weekdays we tend to be more strict, on weekends we tend to be less so. We're not perfect by any stretch," Mohan said in one <a href="https://www.tiktok.com/@time/video/7582409839003946253?is_from_webapp=1&amp;amp;sender_device=pc&amp;amp;web_id=7571799858848482838" target="_blank">TikTok video</a> posted by Time Magazine on Thursday. </p><p>He stressed "everything in moderation" is what works best for him and his wife, and that extends to other online services and platforms. Mohan has three children: two sons and one daughter. </p><p>Experts have continued to sound the alarm on how excessive smartphones and social media use has harmed children and teenagers. Jonathan Haidt, NYU professor and author of "The Anxious Generation,"&nbsp;has advocated for <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/02/19/jonathan-haidt-on-smartphone-free-childhood-key-is-enforcing-4-norms.html">children to not have smartphones</a> before the age of 14 and no access to social media before the age of 16.</p><p>"Let them have a flip phone, but remember, a smartphone isn't really a phone. They could make phone calls on it, but it's a multi-purpose device by which the world can get to your children,"&nbsp;Haidt said in an interview with CNBC's Tania Bryer earlier this year.</p><p>This week, Australia <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/10/australia-16-year-old-teens-ban-social-media-policy-law-ig-tiktok-fb-reddit-youtube-snapchat.html">became the first country to formally bar</a> users under the age of 16 from accessing major social media platforms. Ahead of the legislation's passage last year, a&nbsp;<a href="https://au.yougov.com/politics/articles/51000-support-for-under-16-social-media-ban-soars-to-77-among-australians" target="_blank">YouGov survey</a>&nbsp;found that 77% of Australians backed the under-16 social media ban. Still, the rollout has <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/12/12/reddit-challenges-australia-under-16-teen-social-media-ban-high-court.html">faced some resistance</a> since becoming law.</p><p>Mohan said in a more <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a3PenMxJpZ4" target="_blank">extensive interview with Time</a> on Wednesday that he feels a "paramount responsibility" to young people and giving parents greater control over how their kids use the platform. YouTube Kids was launched in 2015 as a child-friendly version of the Google-owned platform. </p><p>He said his goal is  "to make it easy for all parents" to manage their children's YouTube use "in a way that is suitable to their household," especially as every parent has a different approach. </p></div><h2><a id="headline0"></a>Bill Gates, Mark Cuban </h2><div><p><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/06/05/how-bill-gates-mark-cuban-and-others-limit-their-kids-tech-use.html">Several tech bosses</a> have taken a similar approach. <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2019/12/02/youtube-ceo-says-she-doesnt-let-her-young-children-watch-youtube.html">YouTube's former CEO Susan Wojcicki</a>, also barred her children from browsing videos on the app, unless they were using YouTube Kids. She also limited the amount of time they spent on the platform. </p><p>"I allow my younger kids to use YouTube Kids, but I limit the amount of time that they're on it," Wojcicki told CNBC in 2019. "I think too much of anything is not a good thing."</p><p>Bill Gates, Microsoft's co-founder, is amongst the tech titans who are against allowing young people too much screen time. With three children, now adults, Gates openly talked about not giving them cell phones until they were in their teens. </p><p>"We don't have cell phones at the table when we are having a meal, we didn't give our kids cell phones until they were 14 and they complained other kids got them earlier," Gates said years ago. </p><p>Meanwhile, billionaire Mark Cuban would even resort to installing Cisco routers and using management software to monitor which apps his children were on and shut off their phone activity.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Computer Animator and Amiga fanatic Dick Van Dyke turns 100 (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46252993</link>
            <guid>46252993</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 08:15:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46252993">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><tbody><tr id="46254490"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46254490" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46254490&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Here’s a great quote by him:</p><p>&gt; In my 30’s, I exercised to look good. In my 50’s, to stay fit. In my 70’s, to stay ambulatory. In my 80’s, to avoid assisted living. Now in my 90’s, I’m just doing it out of pure defiance</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46253979"><td></td></tr><tr id="46255070"><td></td></tr><tr id="46254187"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46254187" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46254187&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>THE Dick van Dyke, from Mary Poppins, Diagnosis: Murder, ans so many more?! I always thought it was just a coincidental same name as I never saw videos about this. Oh my! This guy is amazing</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46254503"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253445"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46253445" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46253445&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I had no idea he's an animator, that's so cool! In that video he says "Lightwave is so deep, I won't <i>live</i> long enough to see everything that's in it". I'm glad he's proven wrong there!</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46254357"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46254357" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46254357&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I know his son Barry. He said his first memory he has was his Dad doing real time drawings for people telling stories. He was behind the story teller on stage on giant pads of paper as a comedy bit at night clubs.</p><p>He also remembers having giant bags of toys dumped on the floor of the hotel rooms.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46254528"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46254528" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46254528&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Many A-listers are polymaths. For example, Phil Hartman, used to be Phil Hartmann (extra "n"), and designed some of the most iconic album covers of the 1970s, and Steve Martin is one of the best banjo players out there. It used to be part of his standup bit.</p><p>Dick Van Dyke came from the tail end of Vaudeville, where performers had to have a whole variety of skills.</p><p>Remember: Every one of these folks that hits the limelight, beat out <i>thousands</i> of others.</p><p>We think <i>our</i> vocation is competitive? Showbiz says "Hold my beer."</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46254938"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253386"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253718"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46253718" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46253718&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>&gt; The beloved actor credits his remarkable longevity to his positive outlook and never getting angry.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46254218"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46254218" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46254218&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Makes sense. My grandpa is one year his junior and you would never see him react too strongly to anything, even though grandma (also still alive) always had an, ahem, fiery personality.</p><p>Also he refuses to sit and moves around all the time, venturing outside every day from their apartment four floors above ground without a lift.</p><p>Interestingly his own father didn't make it to his 60s, so there's certainly a lifestyle component to this.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46253932"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253290"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46253290" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46253290&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Wow I had no idea, what a cool guy! Loved Mary Poppins as a kid, his British accent though… xD</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46254934"><td></td></tr><tr id="46254543"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46254543" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46254543&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>And then Commodore made the A3000 not high enough to take the Video Toaster. How to shoot yourself in the foot...</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46253698"><td></td></tr><tr id="46254573"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253041"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46253041" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46253041&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46252993"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Such a legend! I bet he still has his Amiga somewhere in his Hollywood hills mansion.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46253117"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253384"><td></td></tr><tr id="46254129"><td></td></tr><tr id="46254676"><td></td></tr><tr id="46253891"><td></td></tr></tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Doxers posing as cops are tricking big tech firms into sharing people's data (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/doxers-posing-as-cops-are-tricking-big-tech-firms-into-sharing-peoples-private-data/</link>
            <guid>46252171</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 05:06:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/doxers-posing-as-cops-are-tricking-big-tech-firms-into-sharing-peoples-private-data/">https://www.wired.com/story/doxers-posing-as-cops-are-tricking-big-tech-firms-into-sharing-peoples-private-data/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46252171">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content" tabindex="-1"><article lang="en-US"><div><header data-testid="SplitScreenContentHeaderWrapper"><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper"><div><p>A spoofed email address and an easily faked document is all it takes for major tech companies to hand over your most personal information.</p></div><div><p><span><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_120,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 120w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_240,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 240w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_320,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 320w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_640,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 640w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_960,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 960w" sizes="100vw"><source media="(min-width: 768px)" srcset="https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_120,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 120w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_240,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 240w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_320,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 320w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_640,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 640w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_960,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 960w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_1280,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 1280w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_1600,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 1600w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_1920,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 1920w, https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_2240,c_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg 2240w" sizes="100vw"><img alt="Folder eye and circuit board" loading="eager" src="https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_2560%2Cc_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg" data-src="https://media.wired.com/photos/693377a12cc5d911c8d9ae0f/master/w_2560%2Cc_limit/security_dataleak_GettyImages-471954773.jpg"></picture></span></p></div></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper"><p><span>Photograph: Maxkabakov/Getty Images</span></p></div></header></div><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks" data-attribute-verso-pattern="article-body"><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><figure data-testid="cne-audio-embed-figure"></figure><div><p><span>When a privacy</span> specialist at the legal response operations center of Charter Communications received an emergency data request via email on September 4 from Officer Jason Corse of the Jacksonville Sheriff’s Office, it took her just minutes to respond, with the name, home address, phone numbers, and email address of the “target.”</p><p>But the email had not in fact come from Corse or anyone else at the Jacksonville Sheriff’s Office. It was sent by a member of a hacking group that provides doxing-as-a-service to customers willing to pay for highly sensitive personal data held by tech companies in the United States.</p><p>“This took all of 20 minutes,” Exempt, a member of the group that carried out the ploy, told WIRED. He claims that his group has been successful in extracting similar information from virtually every major US tech company, including Apple and Amazon, as well as more fringe platforms like video-sharing site Rumble, which is popular with far-right influencers.</p><p>Exempt shared the information Charter Communications sent to the group with WIRED, and explained that the victim was a “gamer” from New York. When asked if he worried about how the information he obtained was used against the target, Exempt said: “I usually do not care.”</p><p>The victim did not respond to WIRED’s requests for comment.</p><p>“It is definitely concerning to hear criminals impersonating officers in such a manner, more so when they are claiming to be one of our employees,” says Christian Hancock, the media relations manager at the Jacksonville Sheriff’s Office. Officer Corse declined to comment.</p><p>Charter Communications declined to comment.</p><p>This method of tricking companies into handing over information that can be used to harass, threaten, and intimidate victims has been <a data-offer-url="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2022/03/hackers-gaining-power-of-subpoena-via-fake-emergency-data-requests/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://krebsonsecurity.com/2022/03/hackers-gaining-power-of-subpoena-via-fake-emergency-data-requests/&quot;}" href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2022/03/hackers-gaining-power-of-subpoena-via-fake-emergency-data-requests/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">known about for years</a>. But WIRED has gained unprecedented insight into how one of these doxing groups operates, and why, despite years of warnings, it is still happening so often.</p><p>The Charter Communications incident was one of up to 500 successful requests Exempt claims to have made in recent years. To back up his claims, the hacker shared multiple documents and recordings with WIRED, including what he claimed were screenshots of email requests, fake subpoenas, responses from tech companies, and even a video recording of a phone call with one company’s law enforcement response team, which was seeking to verify a request. Exempt also shared evidence suggesting that a current law enforcement officer (Exempt refused to provide the officer’s location or name) was in contact with the group about allegedly working with them to submit requests from his own account in return for a cut of the profits.</p></div></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>“All I need is an IP address, which I can gain pretty easily, [and] next thing you know I have names, addresses, emails, and cell numbers,” says Exempt, adding that he can then use that information to make emergency data requests. “And with a subpoena and search warrant, I can access DMs, texts, call logs. That’s someone’s full life in my hands in the space of hours, depending on the response times of the company or provider.”</p><p>This type of doxing appears to be a lucrative business. Exempt claims his group brought in over $18,000 in the month of August alone. In one case, Exempt says he was paid $1,200 for a single dox of a person who was supposedly “grooming minors on an online gaming platform he owns. The individual was then allegedly promptly swatted.”</p><p>WIRED reviewed the information posted online about a 23-year-old from the southwestern US, which includes their home address, phone number, email addresses, and social media accounts. The person did not respond to WIRED’s request for comment. WIRED was unable to independently confirm if the person was swatted.</p><p>In the US, federal, state, and local law enforcement agencies who need to identify the owner of a social media account, or details about a specific phone, send the relevant company a subpoena or warrant requesting the information.</p><p>All major companies operating in the US have departments and specific staff assigned to dealing with these requests, which are typically sent via email. The companies, once they review the subpoena and see it has come from what looks like a law enforcement agency, typically comply with the requests, sometimes taking additional verification steps such as phoning the officer involved to confirm that they did indeed send the request.</p><p>But officers can also make emergency data requests, or EDRs, in cases involving a threat of imminent harm or death. These requests <a data-offer-url="https://www.ic3.gov/CSA/2024/241104.pdf" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.ic3.gov/CSA/2024/241104.pdf&quot;}" href="https://www.ic3.gov/CSA/2024/241104.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">typically bypass</a> any additional verification steps by the companies who are under pressure to fulfill the request as quickly as possible.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>This is the loophole that hackers like Exempt, who says he is “a Gen Z male located within the Europe area,” can exploit.</p><p>The problem partly stems from the fact that there are around 18,000 individual law enforcement agencies in the US, all of which use their own email naming conventions and domain registrations, including .us, .net, .org, .gov, and .com.</p><p>The hackers typically use one of two ways to trick companies into making them believe the emails are coming from real law enforcement agencies. In some cases, they use authentic law enforcement email accounts that they have compromised via social engineering or using credentials stolen in previous hacks. Other times, they create convincing fake domains that closely mimic legitimate police departments.</p><p>“This was an email address that looked like the real thing,” says Exempt, explaining the mechanics of how he tricked Charter Communications. “The real domain of the Jacksonville Sheriff’s Office in Florida is jaxsheriff.org. We purchased jaxsheriff.us and then spoofed our number as the department’s, so that when we called them to verify receipt of the legal process, when they searched the number, it would come back to the sheriff’s office, giving them no reason to doubt it. We use real badge numbers and officer names as well.”</p><p>The hackers also craft highly convincing fake official documents by mimicking official records.</p><p>“We look at real subpoenas through public records where available and use the legally correct wording and sections of the law in the subpoena so that everything is legally correct and binding, so that we realistically have zero percent chance of them second-guessing it,” says Exempt. This has worked in multiple states and courts in the US, he claims.</p><p>“As an extra verification step, we sometimes check online to see if the named judge is actually in court that day, so that if a company was to phone up and verify, they would be in the building but most likely be too busy to be able to verify the singular document,” says Exempt.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>In many cases, Exempt says, the email and attached subpoena is enough to extract the information. In one example shared with WIRED, Exempt claims that his group, which he says is made up of around nine people located across Europe and the US, was able to obtain the information used to register the official Rumble account belonging to British far-right activist Tommy Robinson.</p><p>Robinson and Rumble did not respond to requests for comment.</p><p>Even in cases where companies do take additional steps to verify the subpoenas are coming from real officers, the hackers are able to circumvent this.</p><p>In a recording of a phone call shared with WIRED, a representative from Amazon’s law enforcement response team called the number included in the faked email Exempt sent, and spoke with Exempt to verify that they had received the documents she had sent him via an online portal.</p><p>“Amazon identified and blocked someone that was requesting data from us while impersonating law enforcement,” says Adam Montgomery, an Amazon spokesperson. “The impersonator received basic account data for fewer than 10 customers. We quickly took steps to protect these customer accounts, and have put additional safeguards in place to prevent this from happening again.”</p><p>When asked for details of what those safeguards were, Amazon declined to comment.</p><p>While the hackers are clearly exploiting massive loopholes in the system, in some cases, the tech companies themselves have laid out step-by-step guides on how to craft these requests.</p><p>“In order to request that Apple voluntarily disclose information on an emergency basis, the requesting government or law enforcement ofﬁcer should complete the Emergency Government &amp; Law Enforcement Information Request form and transmit it directly from their ofﬁcial government or law enforcement email address to [a specific @apple.com email address] with the words “Emergency Request” in the subject line,” Apple <a data-offer-url="https://www.apple.com/legal/privacy/law-enforcement-guidelines-us.pdf" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.apple.com/legal/privacy/law-enforcement-guidelines-us.pdf&quot;}" href="https://www.apple.com/legal/privacy/law-enforcement-guidelines-us.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">writes</a>.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Exempt shared with WIRED an example of a request he made to Apple using a fake subpoena as well as the information Apple sent back to him that included an iCloud account holder’s home address, cell phone number, and email addresses. Apple did not respond to a request for comment.</p><p>One <a data-offer-url="https://www.search.org/resources/isp-list/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.search.org/resources/isp-list/&quot;}" href="https://www.search.org/resources/isp-list/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">online database</a> maintained by SEARCH, a nonprofit criminal justice support organization, lists direct contact details for the law enforcement divisions of over 700 internet service providers and other online content providers.</p><p>“The core issue isn't companies being careless, it's that traditional communications channels, like email, weren't built for the level of identity verification, context evaluation, and real-time decisioning that modern investigations and legal compliance require,” says Matt Donahue, a former FBI agent who left the agency in 2020. Soon after, Donahue founded Kodex, a company that works with business clients to build secure online portals that law enforcement can use to make data requests.</p><p>While technologies like Kodex provide a much safer alternative to email, over 80 percent of the companies listed on the SEARCH database still accept emergency data requests via emails, according to one review <a data-offer-url="https://blog.kodexglobal.com/hubfs/2025Q2%20Quarterly%20Threat%20Intel%20Report.pdf" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://blog.kodexglobal.com/hubfs/2025Q2%20Quarterly%20Threat%20Intel%20Report.pdf&quot;}" href="https://blog.kodexglobal.com/hubfs/2025Q2%20Quarterly%20Threat%20Intel%20Report.pdf" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">conducted by Kodex</a>,</p><p>But even those who only use Kodex are not in the clear. Exempt claims that he was able to make requests through Kodex for a period of time, using compromised law enforcement email accounts. However, because of Kodex’s enhanced safety features, including whitelisting specific devices from which requests can be made, Exempt and his group have now lost access to the system.</p><p>The hacker claims, however, that they are now working to regain access via another avenue.</p><p>“We are in talks with a deputy from a large sheriff’s office … who we got paid to dox [and] who is now interested in either renting his Kodex account to us or he may submit the requests for us on his side,” says Exempt. “This is in [the] very early stages of talks. He would want a percentage of the money we make and his dox removed on a well-known doxing site.”</p></div><div data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>To back up his claim, Exempt shared a screenshot of an alleged text exchange with the officer, including a blurred image that he refers to as his ID card. “Y’all have the SSN and the rest of the info you need about me and my fam,” the alleged officer wrote in a message. “I’m on the fence about it right now, but we will all get what we want out of this if we do a d[eal].”</p><p>When asked if he thought it was possible the officer was trying to entrap them, Exempt said probably not, “just for the fact he has been doxed, and within that dox, some pretty damning stuff about said officer came out, which he clearly wants removed. So I’m pretty certain he is being honest about the fact he is considering it.”</p><p>Donahue says Kodex’s system could flag such behavior because it is able to “pattern-match” the behavior of law enforcement agents and how they interact with companies that use the Kodek platform. “We can and do detect behavioral changes that allow us to protect our customers on a continuous basis as opposed to a one-time verification,” says Donahue.</p><p>While the hackers are taking advantage of the weakness in email security, they are also taking advantage of companies’ desire to help law enforcement save lives.</p><p>“Public/private-sector coordination is an incredibly complex and nuanced space that could very well be the difference between a kid being found in a trunk, or not,” says Donahue. “Lawful government data requests sit at the very unique intersection of data privacy, public safety, security, legal compliance, and civil rights, so anyone suggesting these requests are carelessly responded to in minutes has little to no understanding of the subject matter.”</p></div></div></article><div><div data-testid="RowWrapper" data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper"><ul><li data-testid="LinkStackBullet"></li><li data-testid="LinkStackBullet"></li><li data-testid="LinkStackBullet"></li><li data-testid="LinkStackBullet"><p>Starlink devices are allegedly being used at <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/doj-issued-seizure-warrants-to-starlink-over-satellite-internet-systems-used-at-scam-compounds/">scam compounds</a></p></li><li data-testid="LinkStackBullet"></li></ul></div><div data-testid="RowWrapper" data-journey-hook="grid-wrapper"><p><a href="https://www.wired.com/author/david-gilbert/"><span><picture><source media="(max-width: 767px)" srcset="https://media.wired.com/photos/663a737bf79ecb6f05993e53/1:1/w_80,c_limit/David%20Gilbert-2.jpg 80w" sizes="100vw"><source media="(min-width: 768px)" srcset="https://media.wired.com/photos/663a737bf79ecb6f05993e53/1:1/w_90,c_limit/David%20Gilbert-2.jpg 90w" sizes="100vw"><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://media.wired.com/photos/663a737bf79ecb6f05993e53/1:1/w_90%2Cc_limit/David%2520Gilbert-2.jpg" data-src="https://media.wired.com/photos/663a737bf79ecb6f05993e53/1:1/w_90%2Cc_limit/David%2520Gilbert-2.jpg"></picture></span></a></p><div><p><a href="https://www.wired.com/author/david-gilbert/">David Gilbert</a> is a reporter at WIRED covering disinformation, online extremism, and how these two online trends impact people’s lives across the globe, with a special focus on the 2024 US presidential election. Prior to joining WIRED, he worked at VICE News. He lives in Ireland. ... <a href="https://www.wired.com/author/david-gilbert">Read More</a></p></div></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple has locked my Apple ID, and I have no recourse. A plea for help (1515 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://hey.paris/posts/appleid/</link>
            <guid>46252114</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 04:55:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://hey.paris/posts/appleid/">https://hey.paris/posts/appleid/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46252114">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>Summary:</strong> A major brick-and-mortar store sold an Apple Gift Card that Apple seemingly took offence to, and locked out my entire Apple ID, effectively bricking my devices and my iCloud Account, Apple Developer ID, and everything associated with it, and I have no recourse. Can you help? Email paris AT paris.id.au (and read on for the details). ❤️</p><p>Here’s how Apple “Permanently” locked my Apple ID.</p><p>I am writing this as a desperate measure. After nearly 30 years as a loyal customer, <a href="https://hey.paris/books-and-events/books/#books">authoring technical books on Apple’s own programming languages (Objective-C and Swift)</a>, and spending tens upon tens upon tens of thousands of dollars on devices, apps, conferences, and services, I have been locked out of my personal and professional digital life with no explanation and no recourse.</p><h2 id="the-situation">The Situation</h2><p>My Apple ID, which I have held for around 25 years (it was originally a username, before they had to be email addresses; it’s from the iTools era), has been permanently disabled. This isn’t just an email address; it is my core digital identity. It holds terabytes of family photos, my entire message history, and is the key to syncing my work across the ecosystem.</p><p><a href="https://hey.paris/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hey.paris/cardfail.png#center" alt=""></a></p><ul><li><strong>The Trigger:</strong> The only recent activity on my account was a recent attempt to redeem a $500 Apple Gift Card to pay for my 6TB iCloud+ storage plan. The code failed. The vendor suggested that the card number was likely compromised and agreed to reissue it. Shortly after, my account was locked.<ul><li>An Apple Support representative suggested that this was the cause of the issue: indicating that something was likely untoward about this card.</li><li>The card was purchased from a major brick-and-mortar retailer (Australians, think Woolworths scale; Americans, think Walmart scale), so if I cannot rely on the provenance of that, and have no recourse, what am I meant to do? We have even sent the receipt, indicating the card’s serial number and purchase location to Apple.</li></ul></li></ul><p><a href="https://hey.paris/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hey.paris/apple-account-locked.png#center" alt=""></a></p><ul><li><strong>The Consequence:</strong> My account is flagged as “closed in accordance with the Apple Media Services Terms and Conditions”.</li><li><strong>The Damage:</strong> I effectively have over $30,000 worth of previously-active “bricked" hardware. My iPhone, iPad, Watch, and Macs cannot sync, update, or function properly. I have lost access to thousands of dollars in purchased software and media.<ul><li>Apple representatives claim that only the “Media and Services” side of my account is blocked, but now my devices have signed me out of iMessage (and I can’t sign back in), and I can’t even sign out of the blocked iCloud account because… it’s barred from the sign-out API, as far as I can tell.</li><li>I can’t even login to the “Secure File Transfer” system Apple uses to exchange information, because it relies on an Apple ID. Most of the ways Apple has suggested seeking help from them involve signing in to an Apple service to upload something, or communicate with them. This doesn’t work as the account is locked.</li></ul></li></ul><p><a href="https://hey.paris/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hey.paris/accountfail.png#center" alt=""></a></p><ul><li>I can’t even download my iCloud Photos, as:<ol><li>There are repeated auth-errors on my account, so I can’t make Photos work;</li><li>I don’t have a 6TB device to sync them to, even if I could.</li></ol></li></ul><p><a href="https://hey.paris/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hey.paris/imessage.png#center" alt=""></a></p><h2 id="the-support-nightmare">The Support Nightmare</h2><p>I contacted Apple Support immediately (Case ID: 102774292094). The experience was terrifyingly dismissive:</p><ol><li><strong>No Information:</strong> Support staff refused to tell me <em>why</em> the account was banned or provide specific details on the decision.</li><li><strong>No Escalation:</strong> When I begged for an escalation to Executive Customer Relations (ECR), noting that I would lose the ability to do my job and that my devices were useless, I was told that “an additional escalation won’t lead to a different outcome”.<ul><li>Many of the reps I’ve spoken to have suggested strange things, one of the strangest was telling me that I could physically go to Apple’s Australian HQ at Level 3, 20 Martin Place, Sydney, and plead my case. They even put me on hold for 5 minutes while they looked up the address.</li></ul></li></ol><p><a href="https://hey.paris/"><img loading="lazy" src="https://hey.paris/chat.png#center" alt=""></a></p><h2 id="the-new-account-trap">The “New Account” Trap</h2><p>Most insultingly, the official advice from the Senior Advisor was to “create a new Apple account… and update the payment information”.</p><p>This advice is technically disastrous:</p><ul><li><strong>The Legal Catch:</strong> Apple’s Terms and Conditions rely on “Termination of Access.” By closing my account, they have revoked my license to use their services.</li><li><strong>The Technical Trap:</strong> If I follow their advice and create a new account on my current devices (which are likely hardware-flagged due to the gift card error), the new account will likely be linked to the banned one and disabled for circumventing security measures.</li><li><strong>The Developer Risk:</strong> As a professional Apple Developer, attempting to “dodge” a ban by creating a new ID could lead to my Developer Program membership being permanently blacklisted, amongst other things.</li></ul><h2 id="who-i-am">Who I Am</h2><p>I am not a casual user. I have <a href="https://hey.paris/books-and-events/books/#books">literally written the book on Apple development (taking over the <em>Learning Cocoa with Objective-C</em> series, which Apple themselves used to write, for O’Reilly Media, and then 20+ books following that)</a>. I help run the longest-running Apple developer event not run by Apple themselves, <a href="https://devworld.au/index.php">/dev/world</a>. I have effectively been an evangelist for this company’s technology for my entire professional life. We had an app on the App Store on Day 1 in every sense of the world.</p><h2 id="my-plea">My Plea</h2><p>I am asking for a human at Apple to review this case. I suspect an automated fraud flag regarding the bad gift card triggered a nuclear response that frontline support cannot override. I have escalated this through my many friends in WWDR and SRE at Apple, with no success.</p><p>I am desperate to resolve this and restore my digital life. If you can help, please email paris AT paris.id.au</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>