<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 21:30:11 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Global IT outage shows dangers of cashless society, campaigners say (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/jul/20/cash-global-it-outage-cashless-society-dangers-payment-choice-alliance</link>
            <guid>41018726</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 18:52:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/jul/20/cash-global-it-outage-cashless-society-dangers-payment-choice-alliance">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/article/2024/jul/20/cash-global-it-outage-cashless-society-dangers-payment-choice-alliance</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41018726">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>Campaigners say the chaos caused by the global IT outage last week underlines the risk of moving towards a cashless society.</p><p>Supermarkets, banks, pubs, cafes, train stations and airports were all hit by the failure of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/microsoft" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Microsoft</a> systems on Friday, leaving many unable to accept electronic payments. The impact was especially severe for businesses that no longer accept cash.</p><p>The Payment Choice Alliance (PCA), which campaigns against the move towards a cashless society, lists 23 firms and groups, at least some of whose outlets take only credit or debit cards.</p><p>“There will always be outages,” said Ron Delnevo, the PCA’s chair. “But if there is no alternative, then the whole thing can collapse around you.”</p><p>Cash payments increased for the first time in a decade last year, according to UK Finance, which represents banks. The number of people who never use cash, or use it less than once a month, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2023/sep/14/cash-payments-rise-in-uk-as-people-seek-ways-to-manage-budgets" data-link-name="in body link">reached 23.1m</a> in 2021, but declined to 21.6m last year.</p><p>UK Finance said there was “definitely still a place” for cash. “It’s up to individual businesses, but we think it’s good to give people a choice. Most businesses still do offer cash.”</p><p>The <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/gmb-union" data-link-name="in body link">GMB Union</a> said the outage reinforced what it had been saying for years: that “cash is a vital part of how our communities operate”. “When you take cash out of the system, people have nothing to fall back on, impacting on how they do the everyday basics.”</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-7">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-7" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><figure id="c4728897-74c3-4df7-aaec-41771abd2952" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="debit cards" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/edef2c1c699423db1f6df67391c56f780cd19478/4_0_1663_2078/master/1663.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none" width="445" height="556.0493084786531" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>In March big retailers suffered problems with their payment systems.</span> Photograph: Andrew Matthews/PA</figcaption></figure><p>Several smaller, unrelated outages had already affected retailers this year. In March, McDonald’s, Tesco, Sainsbury’s and Gregg’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/mar/16/sainsburys-grocery-deliveries-hit-by-technical-issue" data-link-name="in body link">suffered</a> problems with their payment systems. All of the outlets also accept cash.</p><p>Authorities in China and the US have fined businesses for not accepting cash. Delnevo said the UK should have a law requiring all businesses to take cash.</p><p>Martin Quinn, campaign director for the PCA, said using cash allowed for anonymity. “I don’t want my data sold on, and I don’t want banks, credit card companies and even online retailers to know every facet of my life,” he said. Budgeting by using cash is also easier for some, he added.</p><p>“If I go out for a night and decide to spend £50, then I might wake up with a bit of shrapnel in my pockets. But if I’m in the pub and I’m just going tap, tap, tap, then the next morning I’ll wake up and find I’ve gone into my overdraft.”</p><p>Link said that, overall, its cash machines were at normal levels, but busier around supermarkets.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Linux kernel syscall implementation tracker (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://syscalls.mebeim.net/?table=x86/64/x64/latest</link>
            <guid>41018135</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 17:34:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://syscalls.mebeim.net/?table=x86/64/x64/latest">https://syscalls.mebeim.net/?table=x86/64/x64/latest</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41018135">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="container">
			<h2>Architecture:  Kernel&nbsp;version: </h2>
			<h3>
				Powered by <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/mebeim/systrack" title="Systrack on GitHub">Systrack</a> v<span id="systrack-version"></span>
				<span>[<a id="json-link" target="_blank" href="" title="See this syscall table in JSON format">JSON&nbsp;table</a>]</span>
				<span>[<a id="config-link" target="_blank" href="" title="Configuration to build a kernel with the same syscalls in this table">kernel&nbsp;config</a>]</span>
				<span>[<a id="stderr-link" target="_blank" href="" title="Systrack analysis log">analysis&nbsp;log</a>]</span>
				<span>[<a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/mebeim/linux-syscalls" title="Source code for this website on GitHub">website&nbsp;source</a>]</span>
			</h3>
			<table>
				<tbody><tr>
					<th colspan="6"></th>
					<th data-column="signature"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Signature <span id="compact-sig-toggle" title="Click to toggle between compact C-style and extended multi-column arguments"></span></span></th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<th colspan="2" title="Click to sort by this column">Number</th>
					<th data-column="name" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Name</span></th>
					<th data-column="symbol" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Symbol</span></th>
					<th data-column="location" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Definition location</span></th>
					<th data-column="kconfig" title="Click to sort by this column"><span title="Click to expand/collapse"></span><span> Kconfig</span></th>
				</tr>
			</tbody></table>
			
		</section><p>Copyright © 2023-2024 Marco Bonelli — Licensed under the GNU General Public License v3.0</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CrowdStrike broke Debian and Rocky Linux months ago, but no one noticed (209 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.neowin.net/news/crowdstrike-broke-debian-and-rocky-linux-months-ago-but-no-one-noticed/</link>
            <guid>41018029</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 17:21:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/crowdstrike-broke-debian-and-rocky-linux-months-ago-but-no-one-noticed/">https://www.neowin.net/news/crowdstrike-broke-debian-and-rocky-linux-months-ago-but-no-one-noticed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41018029">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                                    <span>When you purchase through links on our site, we may earn an affiliate commission. <a href="https://www.neowin.net/terms">Here’s how it works</a>.</span>
                        
                        
                        <p>
    
    <time datetime="Jul 19, 2024 17:14 EDT" pubdate="pubdate">
    Jul 19, 2024 17:14 EDT
    </time>
         · <span>Hot!</span>    
    
    
    </p>

                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                                                        <figure><a href="https://cdn.neowin.com/news/images/uploaded/2024/07/1721412936_crowdstrike_linux.jpg"><img alt="crowdstrike" src="https://cdn.neowin.com/news/images/uploaded/2024/07/1721412936_crowdstrike_linux_story.jpg"></a></figure><p>A widespread <a href="https://www.neowin.net/news/the-crowdstrike-windows-outage-continues-to-affect-tons-of-critical-businesses-worldwide/">Blue Screen of Death (BSOD) issue on Windows PCs</a> disrupted operations across various sectors, notably impacting airlines, banks, and healthcare providers. The issue was caused by a problematic channel file delivered via an update from the popular cybersecurity service provider, CrowdStrike. CrowdStrike confirmed that this crash did not impact Mac or Linux PCs.</p>

<p>It turns out that similar problems have been occurring for months without much awareness, despite the fact that many may view this as an isolated incident. Users of Debian and Rocky Linux also experienced significant disruptions as a result of CrowdStrike updates, raising serious concerns about the company's software update and testing procedures. These occurrences highlight potential risks for customers who rely on their products daily.</p>

<p>In April, a CrowdStrike update caused all Debian Linux servers in a civic tech lab to crash simultaneously and refuse to boot. The update proved incompatible with the latest stable version of Debian, despite the specific Linux configuration being supposedly supported. The lab's IT team discovered that removing CrowdStrike allowed the machines to boot and reported the incident.</p>

                            <!-- PLACE THIS SECTION INSIDE OF YOUR BODY WHERE YOU WANT THE VIDEO PLAYER TO RENDER -->
            <p>A team member involved in the incident expressed dissatisfaction with CrowdStrike's delayed response. It took them weeks to provide a root cause analysis after acknowledging the issue a day later. The analysis revealed that the Debian Linux configuration was not included in their test matrix.</p>

<p>"Crowdstrike's model seems to be 'we push software to your machines any time we want, whether or not it's urgent, without testing it'," lamented the team member.</p>

<p>This was not an isolated incident. CrowdStrike users also reported similar issues after upgrading to RockyLinux 9.4, with their servers crashing due to a kernel bug. Crowdstrike support acknowledged the issue, highlighting a pattern of inadequate testing and insufficient attention to compatibility issues across different operating systems.</p>

<p>To avoid such issues in the future, CrowdStrike should prioritize rigorous testing across all supported configurations. Additionally, organizations should approach CrowdStrike updates with caution and have contingency plans in place to mitigate potential disruptions.</p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41005936">Ycombinator</a>, <a href="https://forums.rockylinux.org/t/crowdstrike-freezing-rockylinux-after-9-4-upgrade/14041">RockyLinux</a></p>
                        
                        
                                                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A brief interview with Tcl creator John Ousterhout (2023) (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pldb.io/blog/JohnOusterhout.html</link>
            <guid>41017367</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 15:56:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pldb.io/blog/JohnOusterhout.html">https://pldb.io/blog/JohnOusterhout.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41017367">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><span>February 8, 2023 — </span><a href="https://web.stanford.edu/~ouster/cgi-bin/home.php">Dr. John Ousterhout</a> is a computer science luminary who has made significant contributions to the field of computer science, particularly in the areas of operating systems and file systems. He is the creator of the <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/tcl.html">Tcl</a> scripting language, and has also worked on several major software projects, including the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Log-structured_file_system">Log-Structured file system</a> and the <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/sprite-os.html">Sprite operating system</a>. John Ousterhout's creation of Tcl has had a lasting impact on the technology industry, transforming the way developers think about scripting and automation.</p>
<p><span>*</span></p>
<div><h4>What is unique about Tcl?</h4>
<p><strong>Dr. Ousterhout:</strong> I would highlight 2 things:</p>
</div>
<p>The first thing is its embeddable nature: I designed Tcl so that the library could be embedded in applications, with Tcl providing generic scripting features and the application adding its own commands to the built-in command set. The boundary between Tcl and the application is extremely fluid, and applications can extend Tcl in very powerful ways, such as adding new control structures to the  language. I don't think any other scripting language has achieved embeddability to the degree that Tcl did.</p>
<p>The second thing is Tcl's "everything is a string" philosophy. This played a big role in Tcl's embeddability and made it easy to extend Tcl in a variety of ways. But, it also carried a performance penalty; even with a lot of work, Tcl has never become as efficient as other languages with more traditional types, such as <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/python.html">Python</a>. The string focus is also responsible for Tcl's unusual command syntax, which some people love and some people hate.</p>
<p><span>*</span></p>
<p><h4>How different would Tcl be had you stayed on with the development team? :)</h4>
</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Ousterhout:</strong> I don't think it would have been very different. Tcl was quite mature by the time I passed off development responsibility. Tcl had its heyday in the 1990's, due in large part to the power of the <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/tk.html">Tk toolkit</a> and the awfulness of the other X Window GUI toolkits; Tcl/Tk was the easiest and most powerful way to create GUI apps. Unfortunately, Tcl didn't make the jump to the Web, and most of the applications for which people would have used Tcl in the 1990s became Web applications.</p>
<p>Interesting footnote: the founding of Netscape occurred at the same time I was deciding where to go in industry when I left Berkeley in 1994. Jim Clarke and Marc Andreessen approached me about the possibility of my joining Netscape as a founder, but I eventually decided against it (they hadn't yet decided to do Web stuff when I talked with them). This is one of the biggest "what if" moments of my career. If I had gone to Netscape, I think there's a good chance that Tcl would have become the browser language instead of <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/javascript.html">JavaScript</a> and the world would be a different place! However, in retrospect I'm not sure that Tcl would actually be a better language for the Web than JavaScript, so maybe the right thing happened.</p>
<p><span>*</span></p>
<p><h4>As a long time educator, what do you predict the next paradigm shift in programming languages will be?</h4>
</p>
<p><strong>Dr. Ousterhout:</strong> I don't really know. It used to be that every 5-10 years a major new language came along, but it's been almost 20 or years since the last interesting new language I can think of (<a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/go.html">Go</a>). Maybe others would count <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/rust.html">Rust</a>, in which case maybe the 5-10 year interval is still holding.</p>
<p>One interesting note on this. Historically, I think the most widely used programming linkages have come not from the programming language research committee, but rather from people who build systems and wanted a language to help themselves. PL researchers tend to create languages that are useful for PL researchers: they have interesting theoretical and conceptual properties (e.g., <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/ml.html">ML</a>) but aren't usually useful for real systems. Systems people create languages that are useful for systems builders, so they get widely adopted. Examples are <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/c.html">C</a>, <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/cpp.html">C++</a> (I think?), <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/perl.html">Perl</a>, <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/java.html">Java</a>, and <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/go.html">Go</a>. I would put <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/tcl.html">Tcl</a> in this category as well, and perhaps <a href="https://pldb.io/concepts/python.html">Python</a> also?</p>
<p><span>⁂</span></p>
<figure><a href="https://pldb.io/blog/images/JohnO.jpg" target="_blank"><img src="https://pldb.io/blog/images/JohnO.jpg" width="1638" height="1068" loading="lazy"></a><figcaption><p><a href="https://www.facesofopensource.com/">Image source</a>. Thank you for your time Dr. Ousterhout!</p></figcaption></figure>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CrowdStrike debacle provides road map of American vulnerabilities to adversaries (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html</link>
            <guid>41017077</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 15:18:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41017077">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/07/19/us/politics/crowdstrike-outage.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to pwn a billion dollar VC firm using inspect element (490 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/</link>
            <guid>41016768</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 14:33:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/">https://www.kibty.town/blog/a16z/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016768">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><h2>background</h2>
<p>i like to do this thing where i search twitter, looking for companies, and then try giving them a quick pentest. i've done a lot of my hacks this way and its more effective than you think it is.</p>
<p>on this search, i use the "Relevant People" tab more often than you think, this is how i got to a16z</p>
<ul>
<li>crypto bullshit -&gt; venture capital firms for crypto -&gt; a16z crypto -&gt; a16z</li>
</ul>
<h2>the hack</h2>
<p>while looking into a16z, i did a usual subdomain scan and used tooling from <a href="https://lunchcat.dev/">lunchcat</a> which does common checks on domains, scanning for secrets in js files, etc.</p>
<p>in this search, i came across <code>portfolio.a16z.com</code>, a site that seems like a portfolio management tool for companies that are in a16z. while doing cursory checks like i usually do, lunchcat seemed to catch a AWS key referenced somewhere in the website.</p>
<p>i confirmed this and what i saw in the js, was this.</p>
<pre><code>{
    <span>MARKETPLACE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>DATABASE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_SECURITY_TOKEN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>npm_config_user_agent</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_USERNAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SESSION_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>API_USERNAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_ID_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>CLIENT_TOKEN_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_SECRET_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_BUCKET_NAME</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>npm_config_prefix</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>REACT_APP_SENTRY_DSN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_BUCKET_TEAM_PAGES</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_API_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_LOGO_BUCKET_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CLIENT_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>PAPERTRAIL_API_TOKEN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_CALLBACK_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_USER</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_ACCESS_KEY_ID</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>PNPM_CONFIG_CACHE</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>AWS_SECRET_ACCESS_KEY</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>MAILGUN_DOMAIN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CALLBACK_URL_DEVELOPMENT</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>API_PASSWORD</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SENTRY_DSN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>SALESFORCE_LOGIN_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>COOKIE_SECRET</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>OKTA_DOMAIN</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>NODE_MODULES_CACHE</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>GOOGLE_CALLBACK_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,,
    <span>NODE_ENV</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>HEROKU_POSTGRESQL_CRIMSON_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
    <span>TALENTPLACE_URL</span>: <span>"&lt;REDACTED&gt;"</span>,
}
</code></pre>
<p>this was. horrifying, it was the entire <code>process.env</code> of a heroku instance, in the JS. put in dynamically.</p>
<p>i did a quick valid look of the credentials and they didnt seem like fake credentials. they. were. real. and all someone had to do find them was go to the sources tab of inspect element.</p>
<h2>impact</h2>
<p>the compromised list of services:</p>
<ul>
<li>their database (containing PII)</li>
<li>their AWS</li>
<li>their salesforce (never checked, account may be limited)</li>
<li>mailgun (arbitrary emails from a16z domains, and also could read older emails)</li>
<li>... and probably more</li>
</ul>
<h2>reward</h2>
<p>a16z did not give me any bug bounty on this because of the fact i publicly reached out instead of trying to reach out privately. the only reason i did it this way was because:</p>
<ul>
<li>there was no available contact on their main site</li>
<li>the email i could find <code>engineering@a16z.com</code> bounced my emails</li>
</ul>
<p>so, i dunno. imo this is unfair.</p>
<h2>related</h2>
<p>techcrunch article (lorenzo reached out to me seeing my tweet trying to get in contact with them and wrote a piece!): https://techcrunch.com/2024/07/18/researcher-finds-flaw-in-a16z-website-that-exposed-some-company-data/</p>
</div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to choose a textbook that is optimal for oneself? (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://matheducators.stackexchange.com/questions/27964/how-to-choose-a-textbook-that-is-pedagogically-optimal-for-oneself</link>
            <guid>41016650</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 14:13:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://matheducators.stackexchange.com/questions/27964/how-to-choose-a-textbook-that-is-pedagogically-optimal-for-oneself">https://matheducators.stackexchange.com/questions/27964/how-to-choose-a-textbook-that-is-pedagogically-optimal-for-oneself</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016650">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<p><strong>Do you agree with my point that problems that are too hard is not the optimal way of learning and teaching?</strong></p>
<p>Yes.</p>
<p>A lot of people fall into the trap of thinking that to train up their math skills, they should be focusing on the hardest problem types where they think really hard, struggle for a while, and eventually solve it or look up the answer. These problems can be fun (for a certain type of person) but they're not an efficient way to learn.</p>
<p>Approaching challenging problems without having the foundational skills down pat is like jumping into a game of basketball without having developed dribbling and shooting skills. It might feel fun but you're just going to be whiffing every shot and getting the ball stolen from you. You might make one layup the entire game &amp; feel good about it, but that's barely any training volume.</p>
<p>It’s like going to the gym to lift weights but only eeking out a single rep over the entire course of your workout. You need to be banging out more reps if you want to get stronger, and the only way you can bang out those reps is by working with a level of weight that's appropriate for you.</p>
<p>Math is the same way. In an hour-long session, you're going to make a lot more progress by solving 30 problems that each take 2 minutes given your current level of knowledge, than by attempting a single competition problem that you struggle with for an hour. (This assumes those 30 problems are grouped into minimal effective doses, well-scaffolded &amp; increasing in difficulty, across a variety of topics at the edge of your knowledge.)</p>
<p>Now, I'm not saying that challenge problems are bad. I'm just saying that they're not a good use of time until you've developed the foundational skills that are necessary to grapple with these problems in a productive and timely fashion.</p>
<p><em>Some References</em></p>
<p>I should point out that while I've made heavy use of analogies here, this is all grounded in decades of research into the cognitive science of learning.</p>
<p>One key empirical result is the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expertise_reversal_effect" rel="nofollow noreferrer">expertise reversal effect</a>, a well-replicated phenomenon that instructional techniques that promote the most learning in experts, promote the least learning in beginners, and vice versa. It's true that many highly skilled professionals spend a lot of time solving open-ended problems, and in the process, discovering new knowledge as opposed to obtaining it through direct instruction. But that doesn't mean beginners should do the same. The expertise reversal effect suggests the opposite – that beginners (i.e., students) learn most effectively through direct instruction.</p>
<p>Additionally (and relatedly), there's a mountain of empirical evidence that you can increase the number of examples &amp; problem-solving experiences in a student's knowledge base – but a lack of evidence that you can increase the student’s ability to generalize from those examples (by doing things other than equipping them with progressively more advanced examples &amp; problem-solving experiences).</p>
<p>In other words, research indicates the best way to improve your problem-solving ability in any domain is simply by acquiring more foundational skills in that domain. The way you increase your ability to make mental leaps is not by learning to jump further, but by building bridges.</p>
<p>So, there does not seem to be any tangible, empirically-supported reason to struggle with a challenge problem for a long period of time, when you consider that you could be making more educational progress using that time to learn more content. For instance, in an hour-long session, you're going to make a lot more progress by solving 30 problems that each take 2 minutes given your current level of knowledge, than by attempting a single competition problem that you struggle with for an hour. (This assumes those 30 problems are grouped into minimal effective doses, well-scaffolded &amp; increasing in difficulty, across a variety of topics at the edge of your knowledge.)</p>
<p><em>(Note: When I say "2 minute problems" I don't mean that as a hard cap. I just mean that you come into the problem with enough background knowledge that you can work 100% productively to complete it in a minimal amount of time. For low-level high school math courses, the minimal amount of time might be lower for many problems, like 1 minute or less. For more theoretical courses in late undergrad, the minimal amount of time might rise to, say, 5-10 minutes for some problems. But I can't imagine a scenario in which a student spends a full hour on a non-research problem while working productively the whole time, unless the solution itself is commensurately long -- e.g., the solution requires writing a chunk of code to implement an algorithm, or there's a proof that requires many cases/sub-proofs, or there are otherwise many different parts to the problem that require solving.)</em></p>
<p>As Sweller, Clark, and Kirschner sum it up in their 2010 article <a href="https://ams.org/notices/201010/rtx101001303p.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Teaching General Problem-Solving Skills Is Not a Substitute for, or a Viable Addition to, Teaching Mathematics</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Although some mathematicians, in the absence of adequate instruction, may have learned to solve mathematics problems by discovering solutions without explicit guidance, this approach was never the most effective or efficient way to learn mathematics. ... In short, the research suggests that we can teach aspiring mathematicians to be effective problem solvers only by providing them with a large store of domain-specific schemas. Mathematical problem-solving skill is acquired through a large number of specific mathematical problem-solving strategies relevant to particular problems. There are no separate, general problem-solving strategies that can be learned."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another good reference is <a href="https://aft.org/sites/default/files/Clark.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Putting Students on the Path to Learning: The Case for Fully Guided Instruction</a> by the same authors in 2012. (It's like an expanded version of the 2010 article.)</p>
<p><strong>What is in your opinion the most pedagogically sound way of writing a textbook? And most importantly, how can you choose a textbook that is pedagogically optimal for oneself?</strong></p>
<p>I don't have a long checklist of highly-specific things to do or look for, but I can tell you the underlying principle that it all boils down to: <em>deliberate practice.</em></p>
<p>In the field of talent development, there is absolutely no debate about the most superior form of training. It's <em>deliberate practice</em>: mindful repetition on performance tasks just beyond the edge of one's capabilities.</p>
<p>Deliberate practice is about making performance-improving adjustments on every single repetition. Any individual adjustment is small and yields a small improvement in performance – but when you compound these small changes over a massive number of action-feedback-adjustment cycles, you end up with massive changes and massive gains in performance.</p>
<p>Deliberate practice is superior to all other forms of training. That is a "solved problem" in the academic field of talent development. It might as well be a law of physics. There is a mountain of research supporting the conclusion that the volume of accumulated deliberate practice is the single biggest factor responsible for individual differences in performance among elite performers across a wide variety of talent domains. (The next biggest factor is genetics, and the relative contributions of deliberate practice vs genetics can can vary significantly across talent domains.)</p>
<p><em>So, how can you write or find a textbook that implements deliberate practice?</em></p>
<p>What you need to do is avoid the two failure modes -- that is, cutting corners on either of the two key attributes of deliberate practice ("mindful" and "repetition").</p>
<p>Deliberate practice is not mindless repetition. If you're doing the same thing over and over again, then you're doing deliberate practice wrong. Deliberate practice is about making performance-improving adjustments on every single repetition. Any individual adjustment is small and yields a small improvement in performance, but when you compound these small changes over a massive number of cycles, you end up with massive changes and massive gains in performance. None of this happens if you're mindlessly doing the same thing over and over again without making adjustments.</p>
<p>Likewise, even if you're mindful during practice, you can't skimp on repetition and still call it "deliberate practice." Deliberate practice necessitates a high volume of action-feedback-adjustment cycles in every single training session. Otherwise, the compounding doesn't happen. Any activity that throttles the number of these cycles cannot be described as deliberate practice.</p>
<p>Many heated debates in math education stem from these misinterpretations of deliberate practice. Mindless repetition, doing the same thing over and over again without making performance-improving adjustments, is not deliberate practice. Likewise, any activity that throttles the volume of action-feedback-adjustment cycles (e.g., excessively challenging problems, or think-pair-share type of stuff) is not deliberate practice.</p>
<p><strong>Addendum 1: Worked examples are needed</strong></p>
<p>Math gets hard for different students at different levels – it can be as early as high school algebra or as late as graduate-level algebraic topology – but everyone eventually reaches a level where things no longer feel obvious and they can't figure things out as quickly on the fly. If you're not yet at the edge of human knowledge, that's where worked examples and instructional scaffolding come in to keep you making fast progress.</p>
<p>Without worked examples, learners eventually reach a point where unguided problem-solving overwhelms their working memory and puts them in a state of cognitive overload. They feel frustrated, confused, and are unable to solve problems. And even before that point, even if a student is able to solve problems successfully without worked examples, it typically takes a lot longer, which throttles the volume of practice.</p>
<p>If you don't have worked examples and instructional scaffolding to help carry you through once math becomes hard for you, then every problem basically blows up into a research project for you. That's okay if you're a research mathematician (or maybe late-stage graduate student) at the edge of your field, but if you're a student who still has a ways to go before reaching the edge of human mathematical knowledge, then it's just less efficient, even if you have fun with it.</p>
<p>If you want to maximize how far you get in a talent domain, then you need to grab all the examples &amp; problem-solving experiences in the direction that you're going, as quickly as possible, and then only once you reach the end of the road with known examples and problem-solving experiences, do you switch over to creative production. Creative production is a way less efficient way of moving forward so you want to save it for the end when it's the only way to continue moving forward.</p>
<p><em>(To be clear: this is not just my opinion, this is based on findings from Benjamin Bloom's research on talent development. This is the same Bloom who created Bloom's taxonomy, which many educators use as justification for having students spend a lot of time working on project – but that is actually misinterpreting Bloom's taxonomy in a way that is not aligned with Bloom's seminal work that came later in his career. I've written more about that <a href="https://justinmath.com/how-blooms-taxonomy-gets-misinterpreted" rel="nofollow noreferrer">here</a>.)</em></p>
<p><strong>Addendum 2: But how can you develop deep understanding if you use worked examples?</strong></p>
<p>First of all: I'm not advocating for mindless mimicry here. There should be plenty of practice on theoretical foundations, including derivations, reasoning about the conditions under which a theorem might apply, etc. This is not inherently at odds with the idea of deliberate practice using worked examples &amp; practice problems. It is trickier to construct worked examples &amp; practice problems that meaningfully test learners on theoretical foundations, but it can be done.)</p>
<p>Second of all, when you continually layer advanced skills on top of existing skills, it forces you to deepen your understanding, really internalizing those existing skills and the ideas behind them. This is basically the idea of "structural integrity" in the context of knowledge.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>When advanced features are built on top of a system, they sometimes fail in ways that reveal previously-unknown foundational weaknesses in the underlying structure. This forces engineers to fortify the underlying structure so that the system can accommodate new elements without compromising its integrity.</p>
</li>
<li><p>Fortifying the underlying structure often requires improving its organization and elegance, which, in the context of student knowledge, produces deep understanding and insight.</p>
</li>
<li><p>When the structural integrity of a system is increased, it also becomes easier to add more advanced features in general. In the same way, when the structural integrity of a student’s knowledge is increased, it becomes easier to assimilate new knowledge in general.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>When you layer on advanced skills, it forces understanding. If there’s some level of understanding you're lacking in some component knowledge, you eventually get to a point where the lack of understanding prevents you from successfully learning more advanced skills.</p>
<p>For instance, there's no way that you can get through a legitimate calculus course without having a real understanding of algebra. In fact, many math students will tell you that calculus is what really deepened their understanding of algebra.</p>
<p><strong>Addendum 3: For anyone who suggests that this answer does not apply to advanced mathematics (analysis, topology, abstract algebra, etc.)...</strong></p>
<p>... I recognize that there's barely any empirical research into education at this level of math. But are you aware of any research where deliberate practice was not found to be the most efficient practice technique, in any talent domain? As far as I'm aware, no counterexamples have been found (though I'd be really interested to read about any if there's something I've missed).</p>
<p>Basically, it seems like there's a mountain of circumstantial empirical evidence (in both talent development &amp; cognitive science research) suggesting that the superiority of deliberate practice would carry over to the setting of advanced mathematics. So in the absence of any contradictory research, why would we expect anything otherwise?</p>
<p>If you're a math professor, then I recognize that you have plenty of experience studying/teaching advanced mathematics, and if you claim that doesn't carry over into advanced math in your personal experience, then that's a claim worth considering. But at the same time, I do have some experience myself in studying/teaching advanced mathematics (not as much as you, but some), and in my experience, the superiority of deliberate practice is fully supported.</p>
<p>Just to name one example: last year, I tutored a student who was taking analysis at an elite university, and each problem set consisted of those "think really hard for a long period of time" problems. Things were going the way of a train wreck: despite her best efforts, she was spinning her wheels on these problems and making very little progress. Not only was she unable to solve the problems, but also, she was not noticeably improving any supporting knowledge by trying and failing to solve them.</p>
<p>What I ended up doing was engaging her in deliberate practice on all of the component knowledge that was being pulled together in each problem. Something like this (the following is non-exhaustive):</p>
<ul>
<li><p><em>Deliberate Practice on Definitions:</em> I give you a mathematical object and you tell me whether it meets the definition (and why or why not). Repeat over and over again increasing in difficulty. Okay, now suppose we remove some criterion from the definition. What's an object that didn't meet the original definition but does now after dropping that criterion? Repeat over and over dropping different criteria.</p>
</li>
<li><p><em>Deliberate Practice on Theorems:</em> I give you a scenario and you tell me whether it meets the assumptions of the theorem. If so, you tell me specifically what else you know is true about the scenario, according to the theorem. Repeat over and over again increasing in difficulty. Okay, if this is a one-way implication, tell me some scenarios where the converse does not hold.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>As soon as we took a step back from the homework problems and started doing that, she started making actual progress on her supporting knowledge. After enough cycles of deliberate practice, she'd re-attempt the homework problems, often solving them completely or at least getting a lot further before starting to spin her wheels again.</p>
<p><em>The result:</em> her exam performance skyrocketed and she ended up finishing the course with an A.</p>
<p><em>What could have happened:</em> without this deliberate practice intervention, she would have gotten a low grade in the course and possibly even dropped out of the major entirely.</p>
<p><em>(Note: Even after learning metacognitive techniques for thinking critically about definitions and theorems, she still required me to create deliberate practice problems for her by targeting weaknesses and selecting specific objects / scenarios to highlight key features &amp; scaffold from easy to hard difficulty.</em></p>
<p><em>In general, a learner typically cannot construct their own deliberate practice experience without expert guidance since they are typically unable to construct information-rich &amp; scaffolded practice problems, much less correctly identify their areas of weakness for targeted practice to begin with.</em></p>
<p><em>So, it would <strong>not</strong> be accurate to suggest that the student could carry out future deliberate practice on her own after learning metacognitive skills for parsing definitions/theorems, implying that the kinds of problems given to the student could be construed as effective for independent practice once those metacognitive skills were learned.)</em></p>
<p><strong>Addendum 4: "Could you suggest some talent development / expertise literature in psychology? I'd greatly appreciate it."</strong></p>
<p>I'd start with K. Anders Ericsson, the academic father of deliberate practice. His work is <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=Ym0clGUAAAAJ" rel="nofollow noreferrer">extensive</a>. Here are some of my selections:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Ericsson, K. A. (2008). <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1111/j.1553-2712.2008.00227.x" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Deliberate practice and acquisition of expert performance: a general overview.</a> <em>Academic emergency medicine, 15</em>(11), 988-994.</p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A. (2006). <a href="https://www.ida.liu.se/%7Enilda08/Anders_Ericsson/Ericsson_delib_pract.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The influence of experience and deliberate practice on the development of superior expert performance.</a> <em>The Cambridge handbook of expertise and expert performance, 38</em>(685-705), 2-2.</p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A. (2003). <a href="https://nibmehub.com/opac-service/pdf/read/The%20Psychology%20of%20Problem%20Solving.pdf#page=86" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The acquisition of expert performance as problem solving: Construction and modification of mediating mechanisms through deliberate practice.</a> <em>The psychology of problem solving</em>, 31-83.</p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A., Krampe, R. T., &amp; Tesch-Römer, C. (1993). <a href="https://graphics8.nytimes.com/images/blogs/freakonomics/pdf/DeliberatePractice(PsychologicalReview).pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The role of deliberate practice in the acquisition of expert performance.</a> <em>Psychological review, 100</em>(3), 363.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Some other references worth checking out, related to deliberate practice:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Anderson, J. R., Reder, L. M., Simon, H. A., Ericsson, K. A., &amp; Glaser, R. (1998). <a href="http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/reder/publications/98_jra_lmr_has.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Radical constructivism and cognitive psychology.</a> <em>Brookings papers on education policy</em>, (1), 227-278. <strong>(See, especially, the comment by Ericsson starting on page 255)</strong></p>
<p>Coughlan, E. K., Williams, A. M., McRobert, A. P., &amp; Ford, P. R. (2014). <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/24001022/" rel="nofollow noreferrer">How experts practice: A novel test of deliberate practice theory.</a> <em>Journal of Experimental Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition, 40</em>(2), 449.</p>
<p>Lehtinen, E., Hannula-Sormunen, M., McMullen, J., &amp; Gruber, H. (2017). <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jake-Mcmullen/publication/317035771_Cultivating_mathematical_skills_From_drill-and-practice_to_deliberate_practice/links/6192129bd7d1af224bef75bb/Cultivating-mathematical-skills-From-drill-and-practice-to-deliberate-practice.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Cultivating mathematical skills: From drill-and-practice to deliberate practice.</a> <em>ZDM, 49</em>, 625-636.</p>
<p>Plant, E. A., Ericsson, K. A., Hill, L., &amp; Asberg, K. (2005). <a href="https://www.academia.edu/download/54133889/Why_study_time_does_not_predict_grade_po20170813-2588-hxvq2s.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Why study time does not predict grade point average across college students: Implications of deliberate practice for academic performance.</a> <em>Contemporary educational psychology, 30</em>(1), 96-116.</p>
<p>Reeves, W. R. (2014). <a href="https://repositories.lib.utexas.edu/server/api/core/bitstreams/c8cc4a4f-e641-462b-9a72-654e60f71485/content" rel="nofollow noreferrer"><em>Creativity as a learned skill: The role of deliberate practice in the development of creativity</em></a> (Doctoral dissertation).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And some lighter reading:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Clear, J. <a href="https://jamesclear.com/beginners-guide-deliberate-practice" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The Beginner’s Guide to Deliberate Practice.</a> <em>JamesClear.com.</em></p>
<p>Ericsson, K. A., Prietula, M. J., &amp; Cokely, E. T. (2007). <a href="https://hbr.org/2007/07/the-making-of-an-expert" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The making of an expert.</a> <em>Harvard business review, 85</em>(7/8), 114.</p>
<p>Parrish, S. <a href="https://fs.blog/deliberate-practice-guide/" rel="nofollow noreferrer">The Ultimate Deliberate Practice Guide: How to Be the Best.</a> <em>FS.blog.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh, you probably also want to read about Bloom's 3-stage process of talent development that describes the striking commonalities Bloom discovered when studying the backgrounds of extremely successful individuals across a wide variety of fields.</p>
<p>The 3-stage process is the main thesis of Benjamin Bloom’s 1985 book <a href="https://archive.org/details/developingtalent0000unse" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Developing Talent in Young People</a>. The stages are summarized well in the 2002 paper <a href="https://www.mcgill.ca/sportpsych/files/sportpsych/2002_-_bloom_g.a._2002._role_of_the_elite_coach_in_the_development_of_talent._in_j.m._silva_d.e._stevens_eds._psychological_foundations_of_sport_pp._466-483._boston-_allyn_and_bacon.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Role of the Elite Coach in the Development of Talent</a> by Gordon Bloom.</p>
<p>Some other interesting reads from Benjamin Bloom on the topic of talent development:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Bloom, B. S., &amp; Sosniak, L. A. (1981). <a href="https://files.ascd.org/staticfiles/ascd/pdf/journals/ed_lead/el_198111_bloom.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Talent development vs. schooling.</a> <em>Educational Leadership, 39</em>(2), 86-94.</p>
<p>Brandt, R. S. (1985). <a href="https://files.ascd.org/staticfiles/ascd/pdf/journals/ed_lead/el_198509_brandt2.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">On Talent Development: A Conversation with Benjamin Bloom.</a> <em>Educational Leadership, 43</em>(1), 33-35.</p>
<p>Bloom, B. S. (1986). <a href="https://files.ascd.org/staticfiles/ascd/pdf/journals/ed_lead/el_198602_bloom.pdf" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Automaticity: "The Hands and Feet of Genius."</a> <em>Educational leadership, 43</em>(5), 70-77.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Another reference worth checking out:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Luo, L., &amp; Kiewra, K. A. (2021). <a href="https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/full/10.1177/0261429420934436" rel="nofollow noreferrer">Parents' roles in talent development.</a> <em>Gifted Education International, 37</em>(1), 30-40.</p>
</blockquote>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[10% of Cubans left Cuba between 2022 and 2023 (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html</link>
            <guid>41016441</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 13:43:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html">https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016441">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.miamiherald.com/news/nation-world/world/americas/cuba/article290249799.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Uptime Hosting – Guaranteed Server Downtime (231 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nouptime.com/</link>
            <guid>41016290</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 13:21:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nouptime.com/">https://nouptime.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41016290">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">


<p>

	- 200Kb of Storage<br>

	- 10Mb of Bandwidth<br>

	- PHP 4, 5 and 6<br>

	- MySQL, SQL and Oracle<br>

	- Dedicated Dedication<br>

	- Host Up To 6.8 Sites<br>

	- Free Identity Theft

</p>



<p>

	- Lots of Storage<br>

	- 10Kb of Bandwidth<br>

	- PHP 5, 6 and 7<br>

	- MySQL and ReiserFS<br>

	- 2 Glow Sticks<br>

	- Free Broken Toaster<br>

	- 24/8 Email Support

</p>



<p>

	- 200Gb of Storage<br>

	- 10 Bytes of Path Bandwidth<br>

	- Ruby on Railroads<br>

	- Dedicated Support Geek<br>

	- Dedicated Win 3.11<br>

	- Steve Ballmer<br>

	- Ruby on Boats

</p>



<p>

	Currently Hosting Over <b>5,568,120</b> Websites

</p><!--sites-hosted-->



<p>

	Hosting Websites Since <b>1969</b>!

</p>



<br clear="all">



<div>

	<p><img id="graph" src="https://nouptime.com/images/graph.gif" alt="Downtime Graph"></p>

	<p>We are constantly working to improve our server downtime.</p>

	<p>Keeping you awake at night is our #1 priority.</p><br>

	<h2>Clusters and Scalability</h2>

	<p>If your websites go down we'll make sure to confuse</p>

	<p>you with technical terms and instructions. It's our</p>

	<p>job to keep you aggravated, and we never disappoint.<br clear="all"></p>

</div>



<div>

	<p><img id="testimonials" src="https://nouptime.com/images/testimonials.gif" alt="Testimonials"></p><p>We have over <b>359</b> testimonials from happy customers around the world:</p>

	<!--testimonial-box-->

	

</div>



<!--? include("bottom.php");?--></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Public toilets are vanishing and that's a civic catastrophe (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe</link>
            <guid>41015731</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 11:37:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe">https://psyche.co/ideas/public-toilets-are-vanishing-and-thats-a-civic-catastrophe</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41015731">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="articleContent"><h2>New research shows it is a nightmare for all of us, but especially for people with health issues and marginalised groups</h2><p>The most terrifying moments often unfold in mundane situations. My own taste of horror emerges every time I enter a bar and I’m met with a prolonged silence after asking: ‘Can I use the toilet, please?’ In supposedly affluent Western nations, the dire state or absence of public toilets has become a universal nightmare, impacting the health and quality of life of all of us, but particularly for marginalised groups.</p>
<p>What I find most scary is that we seem to be accepting this cruel reality without confronting it. It is like there is a monster in the city that is affecting the life of everyone, but the people who can make a difference don’t even care.</p>
<p>I have been aware of the monster since 2013 when I was diagnosed with ulcerative colitis. This is a chronic inflammatory bowel disease that causes long-lasting inflammation and ulcers in the digestive tract and affects life in different ways, such as needing the toilet frequently, pain and fatigue. That’s when I realised the impact a simple toilet can have, not only on an individual’s health but also on public health. This is the story of the <em>shitty</em> life that the poor quality of public toilets confers <span>upon us</span>.</p>
<p>Making public bathrooms accessible and appropriate is a matter of human dignity</p>
<p><strong>Toilets were one of the biggest steps</strong> forward for humanity: they allowed us to <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2071-1050/8/8/779" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">create</a> cleaner spaces, reducing death and improving health. By the <span>19th century</span>, in Western countries, bathrooms with toilets were increasingly included in home design, catering to essential human needs, such as urination, defecation and personal cleaning. With the emergence of new hygiene standards through the <span>20th century</span>, the focus of bathrooms shifted further towards convenience and cleanliness. In contemporary times, the role of domestic bathrooms has <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.2752/174063109X12462745321345" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">expanded</a> beyond their practical utility to symbolise places of wellbeing, with more affluent homes including features such as hot tubs and toilets with hi-tech and luxury functions.</p>
<p>And yet, the vast majority of public restrooms have not yet embraced this aspect of wellbeing. On the contrary, the poor state of them often elicits disgust and repulsion. In severe situations, for some people, these adverse psychological responses can escalate to pathological levels, including incontinence, urinary problems, anxiety, and significant alterations to their normal social life.</p>
<p>For many people, most of the time, the state of restrooms is something they think about only when they fail, if they are unusable or unavailable, or there simply aren’t any. Yet toilets often fail when you need them the most. And it’s in such moments you realise that these invisible parts of our cities are fundamental. So, why are restrooms typically tucked away at the back of establishments, hidden both literally and metaphorically? We all must keep in mind that the use of public bathrooms is inevitable, and that making them accessible and appropriate is a matter of human dignity.</p>
<p><strong>The toilet problem has two differentiable</strong> branches. The first is the global sanitation crisis in developing countries and in extreme situations such as refugee camps, which provokes disease and death. The second branch pertains to the problems in developed countries, causing issues in daily life and negatively impacting quality of life.</p>
<p>Fear of public bathrooms will be greater in those most disadvantaged by society</p>
<p>Worldwide, the World Bank highlights three critical <a href="https://blogs.worldbank.org/en/water/3-hard-truths-about-global-sanitation-crisis" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">facts</a>: a quarter of the world’s population lacks access to decent toilets, only <span>39 per cent</span> of human waste is safely managed worldwide, and the global cost of inadequate sanitation reaches <span>$260 billion</span> annually. These facts emphasise the severe health, economic and environmental impacts of inadequate sanitation. Lack of access to toilets is a silent global burden: people die as disease spreads due to the lack of sanitation.</p>
<p>The problem is different when looking to Western, educated, industrialised, rich and democratic (WEIRD) countries. Here we often take adequate sewage disposal for granted. And yet free access to toilets is gradually <a href="https://www.thelancet.com/journals/langas/article/PIIS2468-1253(21)00438-6/fulltext" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">disappearing</a>. As the journalist Lezlie Lowe <a href="https://chbooks.com/Books/N/No-Place-To-Go" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">documents</a> in <em>No Place to Go</em> (2018), institutions are retiring from ensuring the availability of public toilets. This withdrawal of support for basic sanitary facilities has left many people, especially in urban areas, struggling to find accessible restrooms when needed. For instance, data collected in the United Kingdom in 2018 showed that the number of public toilets had dropped by <span>39 per cent</span> over the previous two decades. Quite simply, Lowe was right: there is often no place <span>to go</span>.</p>
<p>Yet, having access to toilets is essential for everyone’s dignity and to help support everyone’s mental, physical and social health. When women can’t easily use public toilets, it harms their <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/31510038/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">wellbeing</a> and denies their <a href="https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0282917" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">basic rights</a>. The list of problems associated with public restrooms doesn’t end there. For instance, transgender and gender-nonconforming individuals <a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6747507/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">face</a> <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10964-017-0652-1" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">difficulties</a> accessing restrooms due to transphobia. There is also a noticeable rise in urogenital issues due to holding in the urge to use the restroom at <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/28671729/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">work</a> or due to <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/15987005/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">schools</a> not adapting to the needs of children. Everyone can easily find a reason to fear public bathrooms, although these fears will be greater in those most disadvantaged by society.</p>
<p>For those of us with gastrointestinal problems, our minds always reserve a considerable space for public restrooms: we often worry about when we’ll have to use them, if we’ll find one, and if it will meet minimum standards. Dependency reshapes your reality: you are no longer concerned about whether you can park at the beach, but whether there will be a nearby restroom; you are not so worried about being late for the bus, but suddenly having an urgency in a <span>45-minute</span>-long journey. Life changes when you are dependent on toilets. Note that everyone can find themselves toilet dependent, even if only temporarily – like that week after you ate a meal that upset your stomach.</p>
<p>Women reported more negative incidents with public restrooms than men</p>
<p><strong>These thoughts drove me to conduct</strong> some scientific studies on what people face with public toilets and how it affects their daily lives. Our studies started with interviews with the true experts in public restrooms: patients with bowel diseases (such as Crohn’s disease, ulcerative colitis or irritable bowel syndrome). In our case, these were people from Spain, and with their help we <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/1660-4601/17/21/7817" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">developed</a> some assessment tools to use in surveys. We confirmed what we suspected: people struggle with public toilets because they are dirty, don’t offer any privacy, and lack the basic things needed to use them. The ideal public toilet – the one with the adequate levels of cleanliness, privacy and usability – is hard to find. Another <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/nau.25118" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">study</a> from our team showed that, for people who are toilet dependent, these negative situations can increase the shame they feel about their illness. This illness-related shame is associated with poorer health outcomes, such as reduced seeking of help or support from others.</p>
<p>When we asked people about the struggles they face with public toilets, such as ‘being unable to find an open unoccupied public toilet’ or ‘feeling unsafe or exposed in a public toilet’, we <a href="https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/sjop.12914" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">found</a> that the more often they experienced these negative events, the lower their quality of life (even after accounting for any differences in their health or socioeconomic status). What’s more, we found that people from poorer and less educated backgrounds had more of these negative toilet experiences – probably because they usually live further from work and in places with fewer available high-quality toilets. Consistent with previous research, we found that gender also influences (negative) experiences with public restrooms: women reported more negative incidents than men, perhaps due to distinct needs that are so often ignored.</p>
<p>Considering the data and experiences, it might seem we’re losing the battle for quality public toilets. There is just cause for anger, which should be channelled into action. Yet, there’s also reason to hope for a future with better toilets that restore our dignity. Some public administrations are taking the availability of quality public restrooms seriously in their facilities. Increasingly, patient and consumer associations are initiating campaigns for universal access to public toilets. For instance, in my country of Spain, there is the ‘I can’t wait!’ <a href="https://www.nopucesperar.org/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">campaign</a> in Catalonia, and the <a href="https://cecu.es/publicaciones/informe-sobre-la-presencia-de-banos-publicos-y-fuentes-de-agua/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a> about public bathrooms from the Spanish Federation of Consumers and Users, which called for their greater availability.</p>
<p>Recognising this issue and assessing the situation is the initial stride toward a future where everyone can access high-quality restrooms tailored to their individual needs. One thing is clear: we need to talk about public restrooms openly, not in secret. Loudly, not whispering. We need to assert our fundamental right to access a restroom without having to wait until we’re back home.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Typst: An easy to learn alternative for LaTex (368 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/typst/typst</link>
            <guid>41014941</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 08:14:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst">https://github.com/typst/typst</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41014941">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/226108480-722b770e-6313-40d7-84f2-26bebb55a281.png"><img alt="Typst" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/226108480-722b770e-6313-40d7-84f2-26bebb55a281.png"></a>
</h2><a id="user-content---" aria-label="Permalink: " href="#--"></a></div>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://typst.app/docs/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Documentation" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/d4ce973908547985ad235179c01636c81ff82a006036dea43e9f0732a7588b63/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f776562736974653f646f776e5f6d6573736167653d6f66666c696e65266c6162656c3d646f63732675705f636f6c6f723d3030376166662675705f6d6573736167653d6f6e6c696e652675726c3d687474707325334125324625324674797073742e617070253246646f6373" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/website?down_message=offline&amp;label=docs&amp;up_color=007aff&amp;up_message=online&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ftypst.app%2Fdocs"></a>
  <a href="https://typst.app/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Typst App" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8f217dbac20c3a22ec5d60735e5cf9c364e453dcb1cebd0612aa3d5efb1226eb/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f776562736974653f646f776e5f6d6573736167653d6f66666c696e65266c6162656c3d74797073742e6170702675705f636f6c6f723d3233396461642675705f6d6573736167653d6f6e6c696e652675726c3d687474707325334125324625324674797073742e617070" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/website?down_message=offline&amp;label=typst.app&amp;up_color=239dad&amp;up_message=online&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Ftypst.app"></a>
  <a href="https://discord.gg/2uDybryKPe" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Discord Server" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/301accc7fe35bd2e5c40fb032c781bf753eca60c1d6478cf445527c6ed3e9c92/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f646973636f72642f313035343434333732313937353932323734383f636f6c6f723d353836354632266c6162656c3d646973636f7264266c6162656c436f6c6f723d353535" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/discord/1054443721975922748?color=5865F2&amp;label=discord&amp;labelColor=555"></a>
  <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/blob/main/LICENSE">
    <img alt="Apache-2 License" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/5e717e166730c9f15db9cd416e0dbcf68c10baf29f6208b6ee1c8cbfdc108ead/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f6c6963656e73652d417061636865253230322d627269676874677265656e" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/license-Apache%202-brightgreen"></a>
  <a href="https://typst.app/jobs/" rel="nofollow">
    <img alt="Jobs at Typst" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f605de5d6651c518139aec45f5183c54376710fd1423b6499798ee774b096ea3/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f64796e616d69632f6a736f6e3f75726c3d687474707325334125324625324674797073742e61707025324661737365747325324664617461253246736869656c64732e6a736f6e2671756572793d2532342e6a6f62732e74657874266c6162656c3d6a6f627326636f6c6f723d2532334135363146462663616368655365636f6e64733d31383030" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/dynamic/json?url=https%3A%2F%2Ftypst.app%2Fassets%2Fdata%2Fshields.json&amp;query=%24.jobs.text&amp;label=jobs&amp;color=%23A561FF&amp;cacheSeconds=1800"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">Typst is a new markup-based typesetting system that is designed to be as powerful
as LaTeX while being much easier to learn and use. Typst has:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Built-in markup for the most common formatting tasks</li>
<li>Flexible functions for everything else</li>
<li>A tightly integrated scripting system</li>
<li>Math typesetting, bibliography management, and more</li>
<li>Fast compile times thanks to incremental compilation</li>
<li>Friendly error messages in case something goes wrong</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">This repository contains the Typst compiler and its CLI, which is everything you
need to compile Typst documents locally. For the best writing experience,
consider signing up to our <a href="https://typst.app/" rel="nofollow">collaborative online editor</a> for free. It is
currently in public beta.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example</h2><a id="user-content-example" aria-label="Permalink: Example" href="#example"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A <a href="https://typst.app/docs/tutorial/" rel="nofollow">gentle introduction</a> to Typst is available in our documentation.
However, if you want to see the power of Typst encapsulated in one image, here
it is:</p>
<p dir="auto">
 <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/228031796-ced0e452-fcee-4ae9-92da-b9287764ff25.png"><img alt="Example" width="900" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/17899797/228031796-ced0e452-fcee-4ae9-92da-b9287764ff25.png"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">Let's dissect what's going on:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">We use <em>set rules</em> to configure element properties like the size of pages or
the numbering of headings. By setting the page height to <code>auto</code>, it scales to
fit the content. Set rules accommodate the most common configurations. If you
need full control, you can also use <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/styling/#show-rules" rel="nofollow">show rules</a> to completely redefine
the appearance of an element.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">We insert a heading with the <code>= Heading</code> syntax. One equals sign creates a top
level heading, two create a subheading and so on. Typst has more lightweight
markup like this, see the <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/syntax/" rel="nofollow">syntax</a> reference for a full list.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/math/" rel="nofollow">Mathematical equations</a> are enclosed in dollar signs. By adding extra
spaces around the contents of an equation, we can put it into a separate block.
Multi-letter identifiers are interpreted as Typst definitions and functions
unless put into quotes. This way, we don't need backslashes for things like
<code>floor</code> and <code>sqrt</code>. And <code>phi.alt</code> applies the <code>alt</code> modifier to the <code>phi</code> to
select a particular symbol variant.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Now, we get to some <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/scripting/" rel="nofollow">scripting</a>. To input code into a Typst document, we can
write a hash followed by an expression. We define two variables and a
recursive function to compute the n-th fibonacci number. Then, we display the
results in a center-aligned table. The table function takes its cells
row-by-row. Therefore, we first pass the formulas <code>$F_1$</code> to <code>$F_8$</code> and then
the computed fibonacci numbers. We apply the spreading operator (<code>..</code>) to both
because they are arrays and we want to pass the arrays' items as individual
arguments.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<details>
  <summary>Text version of the code example.</summary>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="#set page(width: 10cm, height: auto)
#set heading(numbering: &quot;1.&quot;)

= Fibonacci sequence
The Fibonacci sequence is defined through the
recurrence relation $F_n = F_(n-1) + F_(n-2)$.
It can also be expressed in _closed form:_

$ F_n = round(1 / sqrt(5) phi.alt^n), quad
  phi.alt = (1 + sqrt(5)) / 2 $

#let count = 8
#let nums = range(1, count + 1)
#let fib(n) = (
  if n <= 2 { 1 }
  else { fib(n - 1) + fib(n - 2) }
)

The first #count numbers of the sequence are:

#align(center, table(
  columns: count,
  ..nums.map(n => $F_#n$),
  ..nums.map(n => str(fib(n))),
))"><pre><span>#set</span> <span>page</span>(<span>width</span>: <span>10cm</span>, <span>height</span>: <span>auto</span>)
<span>#set</span> <span>heading</span>(<span>numbering</span>: <span><span>"</span>1.<span>"</span></span>)

<span>= <span>Fibonacci sequence</span></span>
The Fibonacci sequence is defined through the
recurrence relation <span><span>$</span>F_n = F_(n-1) + F_(n-2)<span>$</span></span>.
It can also be expressed in <span>_closed form:_</span>

<span><span>$</span> F_n = round(1 / sqrt(5) phi.alt^n), quad</span>
<span>  phi.alt = (1 + sqrt(5)) / 2 <span>$</span></span>

<span>#let</span> <span>count</span> <span>=</span> <span>8</span>
<span>#let</span> <span>nums</span> <span>=</span> <span>range</span>(<span>1</span>, <span>count</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span>)
<span>#let</span> <span>fib</span>(<span>n</span>) <span>=</span> (
  <span>if</span> <span>n</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>2</span> { <span>1</span> }
  <span>else</span> { <span>fib</span>(<span>n</span> <span>-</span> <span>1</span>) <span>+</span> <span>fib</span>(<span>n</span> <span>-</span> <span>2</span>) }
)

The first <span>#count</span> numbers of the sequence are:

<span>#align</span>(center, table(
  columns: count,
  ..nums.map(n =&gt; <span><span>$</span>F_#n<span>$</span></span>),
  ..nums.map(n =&gt; str(fib(n))),
))</pre></div>
</details>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Typst's CLI is available from different sources:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">You can get sources and pre-built binaries for the latest release of Typst
from the <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/releases/">releases page</a>. Download the archive for your platform and
place it in a directory that is in your <code>PATH</code>. To stay up to date with future
releases, you can simply run <code>typst update</code>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">You can install Typst through different package managers. Note that the
versions in the package managers might lag behind the latest release.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Linux: View <a href="https://repology.org/project/typst/versions" rel="nofollow">Typst on Repology</a></li>
<li>macOS: <code>brew install typst</code></li>
<li>Windows: <code>winget install --id Typst.Typst</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">If you have a <a href="https://rustup.rs/" rel="nofollow">Rust</a> toolchain installed, you can install</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>the latest released Typst version with
<code>cargo install --locked typst-cli</code></li>
<li>a development version with
<code>cargo install --git https://github.com/typst/typst --locked typst-cli</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Nix users can</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>use the <code>typst</code> package with <code>nix-shell -p typst</code></li>
<li>build and run a development version with
<code>nix run github:typst/typst -- --version</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Docker users can run a prebuilt image with
<code>docker run -it ghcr.io/typst/typst:latest</code>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Once you have installed Typst, you can use it like this:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Creates `file.pdf` in working directory.
typst compile file.typ

# Creates PDF file at the desired path.
typst compile path/to/source.typ path/to/output.pdf"><pre><span><span>#</span> Creates `file.pdf` in working directory.</span>
typst compile file.typ

<span><span>#</span> Creates PDF file at the desired path.</span>
typst compile path/to/source.typ path/to/output.pdf</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can also watch source files and automatically recompile on changes. This is
faster than compiling from scratch each time because Typst has incremental
compilation.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Watches source files and recompiles on changes.
typst watch file.typ"><pre><span><span>#</span> Watches source files and recompiles on changes.</span>
typst watch file.typ</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Typst further allows you to add custom font paths for your project and list all
of the fonts it discovered:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Adds additional directories to search for fonts.
typst compile --font-path path/to/fonts file.typ

# Lists all of the discovered fonts in the system and the given directory.
typst fonts --font-path path/to/fonts

# Or via environment variable (Linux syntax).
TYPST_FONT_PATHS=path/to/fonts typst fonts"><pre><span><span>#</span> Adds additional directories to search for fonts.</span>
typst compile --font-path path/to/fonts file.typ

<span><span>#</span> Lists all of the discovered fonts in the system and the given directory.</span>
typst fonts --font-path path/to/fonts

<span><span>#</span> Or via environment variable (Linux syntax).</span>
TYPST_FONT_PATHS=path/to/fonts typst fonts</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For other CLI subcommands and options, see below:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Prints available subcommands and options.
typst help

# Prints detailed usage of a subcommand.
typst help watch"><pre><span><span>#</span> Prints available subcommands and options.</span>
typst <span>help</span>

<span><span>#</span> Prints detailed usage of a subcommand.</span>
typst <span>help</span> watch</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you prefer an integrated IDE-like experience with autocompletion and instant
preview, you can also check out the <a href="https://typst.app/" rel="nofollow">Typst web app</a>, which is currently in
public beta.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Community</h2><a id="user-content-community" aria-label="Permalink: Community" href="#community"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The main place where the community gathers is our <a href="https://discord.gg/2uDybryKPe" rel="nofollow">Discord server</a>.
Feel free to join there to ask questions, help out others, share cool things
you created with Typst, or just to chat.</p>
<p dir="auto">Aside from that there are a few places where you can find things built by
the community:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>The official <a href="https://typst.app/docs/packages" rel="nofollow">package list</a></li>
<li>The <a href="https://github.com/qjcg/awesome-typst">Awesome Typst</a> repository</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If you had a bad experience in our community, please <a href="https://typst.app/contact" rel="nofollow">reach out to us</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We would love to see contributions from the community. If you experience bugs,
feel free to open an issue. If you would like to implement a new feature or bug
fix, please follow the steps outlined in the <a href="https://github.com/typst/typst/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md">contribution guide</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">To build Typst yourself, first ensure that you have the
<a href="https://rustup.rs/" rel="nofollow">latest stable Rust</a> installed. Then, clone this repository and build the
CLI with the following commands:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/typst/typst
cd typst
cargo build --release"><pre>git clone https://github.com/typst/typst
<span>cd</span> typst
cargo build --release</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The optimized binary will be stored in <code>target/release/</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Another good way to contribute is by <a href="https://github.com/typst/packages/">sharing packages</a> with the
community.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Pronunciation and Spelling</h2><a id="user-content-pronunciation-and-spelling" aria-label="Permalink: Pronunciation and Spelling" href="#pronunciation-and-spelling"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">IPA: /taɪpst/. "Ty" like in <strong>Ty</strong>pesetting and "pst" like in Hi<strong>pst</strong>er. When
writing about Typst, capitalize its name as a proper noun, with a capital "T".</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Design Principles</h2><a id="user-content-design-principles" aria-label="Permalink: Design Principles" href="#design-principles"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">All of Typst has been designed with three key goals in mind: Power,
simplicity, and performance. We think it's time for a system that matches the
power of LaTeX, is easy to learn and use, all while being fast enough to realize
instant preview. To achieve these goals, we follow three core design principles:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Simplicity through Consistency:</strong>
If you know how to do one thing in Typst, you should be able to transfer that
knowledge to other things. If there are multiple ways to do the same thing,
one of them should be at a different level of abstraction than the other. E.g.
it's okay that <code>= Introduction</code> and <code>#heading[Introduction]</code> do the same thing
because the former is just syntax sugar for the latter.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Power through Composability:</strong>
There are two ways to make something flexible: Have a knob for everything or
have a few knobs that you can combine in many ways. Typst is designed with the
second way in mind. We provide systems that you can compose in ways we've
never even thought of. TeX is also in the second category, but it's a bit
low-level and therefore people use LaTeX instead. But there, we don't really
have that much composability. Instead, there's a package for everything
(<code>\usepackage{knob}</code>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Performance through Incrementality:</strong>
All Typst language features must accommodate for incremental compilation.
Luckily we have <a href="https://github.com/typst/comemo/"><code>comemo</code></a>, a system for incremental compilation which does
most of the hard work in the background.</p>
</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google's shortened links will stop working next year (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support</link>
            <guid>41014089</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 04:36:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support">https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/19/24201734/google-url-link-shortening-service-shut-down-support</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41014089">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>If you ever used Google’s URL shortening service goo.gl before it was shut down in 2019, be warned — those links will stop working on August 25th, 2025. Google <a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/google-url-shortener-links-will-no-longer-be-available/">announced in a blog post</a> that “the time has come to turn off the serving portion of Google URL Shortener” and that any links in the https://goo.gl/* format will respond with a 404 error next year.</p><p>Ahead of the shutdown, goo.gl links will start showing an interstitial page on August 23rd, 2024, notifying users that “this link will no longer work in the near future.” This message will initially appear for a “percentage of existing links,’’ which will increase as the deadline draws closer. Google is encouraging developers to update impacted links as soon as possible, however, as this interstitial page may cause disruptions to link redirections.</p><div><div role="button" aria-label="Zoom" tabindex="0"><figure><div><p><span><img alt="The interstitial page that will appear on goo.gl links after August 23rd." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="fill" sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw, 744px" srcset="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/376x167/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 376w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/384x170/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 384w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/415x184/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 415w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/480x213/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 480w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/540x240/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 540w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/640x284/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 640w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/750x333/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 750w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/828x368/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 828w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1080x479/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1080w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1200x533/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1200w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1440x639/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1440w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/1920x852/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 1920w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/2048x909/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 2048w, https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/2400x1065/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png 2400w" src="https://duet-cdn.vox-cdn.com/thumbor/0x0:820x364/2400x1065/filters:focal(410x182:411x183):format(webp)/cdn.vox-cdn.com/uploads/chorus_asset/file/25537594/Google_url_shortener_shutdown.png" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div></figure></div><div><figcaption><em>Here’s the interstitial page that will start popping up on goo.gl links after August 23rd.</em></figcaption> <p><cite>Image: Google</cite></p></div></div><p>When <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/3/31/17184164/google-alphabet-url-shortening-service-closed">Google announced in 2018</a> that it was shutting down goo.gl, the company encouraged developers to migrate to Firebase Dynamic Links (FDL) — which has also since been <a href="https://firebase.google.com/support/dynamic-links-faq">deprecated</a>. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Converting Codebases with LLMs (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/</link>
            <guid>41014052</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 04:27:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/">https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41014052">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>When it comes to software development at Mantle, we always strive to challenge the status quo. We were faced with a large but common challenge: turning a prototype project into a production project in the style and structure of our other existing production code.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Once we saw Gemini’s release of 1.0 Pro with a one million token window, we developed an approach that reduced the scope by two-thirds and saved months of developer time by using an LLM to assist this large engineering task.</p>







<h2>The Challenge</h2>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="301" data-attachment-id="1013" data-permalink="https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/blog_languageconversion/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?fit=1280%2C376&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1280,376" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="blog_languageConversion" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?fit=300%2C88&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?fit=1024%2C301&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?resize=1024%2C301&amp;ssl=1" alt="Converting a prototype written in R to Golang and ReactJS" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?resize=1024%2C301&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?resize=300%2C88&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?resize=768%2C226&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?resize=1200%2C353&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/blog_languageConversion.png?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>There is a recurring need in the software world for teams to convert a codebase from one language to another. These initiatives always seem like a daunting task, but there are several compelling reasons why organizations take the plunge:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Improved Maintainability:</strong> Legacy codebases can become cumbersome and difficult to maintain, especially if the original maintainers are no longer contributing. Switching to a language with a larger knowledge pool can make the code easier for developers to understand and modify.</li>



<li><strong>Performance Boost:</strong> Different languages excel in different areas. If a team finds their application is struggling to meet performance benchmarks, migrating to a language known for speed or efficiency can provide a significant boost.</li>



<li><strong>Talent Pool:</strong> Finding developers with expertise in a particular language can be challenging. If the current language has a limited talent pool, migrating to a more common one can make it easier to recruit and retain skilled developers.</li>



<li><strong>Productizing Prototypes:</strong> Concepts that might be written in languages/frameworks that are quick and easy to prototype a solution, but aren’t well suited for production use cases.</li>
</ul>



<p>When these types of pressure points arise, there’s a common understanding as to why the effort to convert is justified, yet a shared acknowledgement that the process will be painful. Instead of moving a customer-facing roadmap forward, you are now going to be spending a significant portion of valuable engineering time recreating existing functionality. Also, it’s no secret that these project timelines often go beyond estimates and are riddled with unforeseen issues and risks.&nbsp;</p>



<p>At Mantle, we came up with a different approach. </p>



<p>Our team had a prototype written in the language, R, and wanted to convert this to our standard production tech stack, Golang and ReactJS. The goal was to take the prototype’s logic and intent and use an LLM to translate the R code using our production code patterns, file structures, and libraries.</p>



<p>Our goal wasn’t to achieve 100% perfectly crafted code. The goal was to get 80% of the boilerplate and repeated patterns out of the way so that engineers could focus on the 20% – high value polish to ship the project to customers.</p>







<h2>Gathering context</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="634" data-attachment-id="1014" data-permalink="https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/blog_llm_context/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?fit=1280%2C792&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1280,792" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Blog_LLM_Context" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?fit=300%2C186&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?fit=1024%2C634&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?resize=1024%2C634&amp;ssl=1" alt="Steps of gathering context" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?resize=1024%2C634&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?resize=300%2C186&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?resize=768%2C475&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?resize=1200%2C743&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_Context.png?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>While generating working code from an idea or instruction has been possible for a while now, generating large scale codebases written in our style and structure, and connected to common utilities, is something that’s only recently been enabled thanks to the latest generations of Gemini LLMs and their &gt;1 million token context windows.&nbsp;</p>



<p>There are ways to cope with smaller context windows when reasoning about codebases, but larger context windows allow you to put full codebases into a prompt with additional instructions/context with ease. We took full advantage of this in many ways.</p>







<h2>Inputting prototype source code</h2>



<p>We inserted the existing prototype codebase as context into our prompt by giving a bit of text explaining what it is and then injecting the source in a human-readable way.</p>



<pre><code>Context: Here is a list of files from an application written in typescript.

file: ./app/R/components.R

&lt;source code for components.R&gt;

file: ./app/R/table.R

&lt;source code for table.R&gt;</code></pre>



<p>This format of source code and file path is an important nuance as we ask to output individual files later on in the process. Where they sit in relation to each other is important context as we generate files.</p>







<h2>Derive existing code patterns</h2>



<p>With this context, we could have started generating code, but the style and approach could vary wildly by file. The output code could also be written in a way that the LLM seems adequate based on its training data.</p>



<p>In our initial attempts, where we included existing production source code from the target language as a reference, showed that it would too heavily influence the output. The solution we used was to abstract the code patterns out of the production source code using a prompt.</p>



<pre><code>Creating a summary prompt can generate code that would use the patterns in the code below that includes its code structure and patterns.

&lt;target language source code&gt;</code></pre>



<p>The output from this prompt would then be added to our context using the file path format that can be used to associate the files we generate later on in the process.</p>



<pre><code>Context: Here is an overview of the target architecture:

file: ./src/utils/time.ts

&lt;summary prompt output&gt;</code></pre>



<p>This works well with individual files that you want to give context on or it also works well with giving context to wildcard file paths (e.g. file: ./src/utils/*.ts) which is very convenient.</p>







<h2>Existing libraries</h2>



<p>We have certain libraries that we prefer, so adding a section of context with the current libraries from existing codebases was very helpful to make sure the LLM outputs code that is compatible with them. In this case, we insert the go.mod and package.json file from one of our existing codebases directly into the context.</p>



<pre><code>Context: Here is a list of libraries that are available to use.

&lt; go.mod &gt;
&lt; package.json &gt;</code></pre>







<h2>Screenshots as visual reference points</h2>



<p>When dealing with frontend code, we use the screenshots to help reinforce what is needed from the output. This is especially helpful when dealing with frontend code where the UI is generated by third party libraries, so layout specifics may not be clearly defined in the code. Screenshots of the existing application give the LLM a visual layout of the application.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="339" data-attachment-id="1057" data-permalink="https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/blog_llm_screenshot-alt2/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?fit=1280%2C424&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1280,424" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?fit=300%2C99&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?fit=1024%2C339&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?resize=1024%2C339&amp;ssl=1" alt="AI visual prompting" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?resize=1024%2C339&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?resize=300%2C99&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?resize=768%2C254&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?resize=1200%2C398&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_screenshot-alt2.png?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>







<h2>Reinforce with already generated or ported code</h2>



<p>As we generated code file-by-file, we included it in the context so the LLM always has a view of the current state of the codebase we’re generating. This helps a LLM make decisions to connect and build off of the code that is already there.</p>



<p>While iterating on this process, we found that adding any portable internal libraries or utilities from other existing projects as early as possible was very helpful. Otherwise, you might find that it recreates abstracted and refactored code that already exists.</p>



<pre><code>Here is some code that's already been generated:

file: ./src/utils/time.ts
&lt; source code &gt;</code></pre>



<p>Compiling context is a complex but crucial task in order to recreate a holistic view for reasoning about code. This process mirrors how developers approach tasks, but the information needs to be formatted in a way that is compatible for an LLM.</p>



<p>In terms of overall input token usage, the prototype codebase we worked with was ~43,379 tokens (12,137 lines code). Taking into account everything else, this amounted to about ~80,000. As we started generating files and approached feature parity with original code, our usage was &gt;500,000 tokens. There’s definite room for optimization here, and the amount of context needed will vary depending on the programming languages and frameworks involved.</p>







<h2>Generating Files</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="717" data-attachment-id="1016" data-permalink="https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/blog_llm_gereratefiles/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?fit=1280%2C896&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1280,896" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Blog_LLM_gererateFiles" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?fit=300%2C210&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?fit=1024%2C717&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?resize=1024%2C717&amp;ssl=1" alt="Generating code from AI prompts" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?resize=1024%2C717&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?resize=300%2C210&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?resize=768%2C538&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?resize=1200%2C840&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_gererateFiles.png?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>







<p>At this point, we had taken full advantage of the large token input limits to set up all the necessary context to reason about the problem. However, due to the limitation on output (often around 8,192 tokens), we had to generate files one by one, or sometimes, section by section.&nbsp;</p>



<p>With all the context from the previous section, the general cycle of code generation looked like this.</p>



<ol>
<li>Add any additional context that might be helpful for the specific file you want to generate.</li>



<li>Generate some code.</li>



<li>Decide whether to re-generate with additional context or tidy up any imperfections in the source code and add it to the context.</li>



<li>Rinse and repeat.</li>
</ol>







<h2>The Approach</h2>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="656" data-attachment-id="1017" data-permalink="https://blog.withmantle.com/code-conversion-using-ai/blog_llm_approach/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?fit=1280%2C820&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1280,820" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Blog_LLM_approach" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?fit=300%2C192&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?fit=1024%2C656&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?resize=1024%2C656&amp;ssl=1" alt="Best approach to code generation" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?resize=1024%2C656&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?resize=300%2C192&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?resize=768%2C492&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?resize=1200%2C769&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/blog.withmantle.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Blog_LLM_approach.png?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>We found that the best way to approach the generation is from backend to frontend and starting at leaf node (bottom-up tree traversal) files (utilities, libraries, database layer, etc) then up to the more common and connected (API interface or routing) ones. This gives the LLM a way of triangulating which files relate to each other and decide when it’s appropriate to import and use them.</p>







<h2>Executing the Prompt</h2>



<p>In our case, the prototype app had a database schema we wanted to build up from. This helped us indicate if we were getting closer to feature parity since both apps could be run side-by-side and pointing at the same data source.</p>



<p>When beginning this process from scratch, the first files had little context to work off of. It helped to add some extra context to help educate the LLM towards a good outcome. We did this by adding the database schema to the context, then generating the database models for our application.</p>



<pre><code>Here is the database schema for the generated code:

&lt;database schema&gt;</code></pre>



<p>Now we add the code conversion instruction that will be used when generating files.</p>



<pre><code>Prompt: You are a software engineer and you can only answer with source code. Convert the provided &lt;prototype code language&gt; application code to a &lt;Production language&gt; application, maintaining a similar structure and functionality as the given example and using libraries provided. Output the full source code without explanations.

Output ./server/db/models/company.go</code></pre>



<p>Once the file was generated, our team either reviewed and adjusted the output manually or adjusted the prompt to recreate the output. It’s important to catch any patterns early on before they compound and multiply, so taking this step to review is critical. Once we were satisfied with the output, we added it into the overall context so that the newly generated file could reinforce the next file we created.</p>







<h2>Dealing with Large Files</h2>



<p>In our prototype app, the database querying layer was quite verbose and greatly exceeded an LLM’s output token limit. We slightly adjusted the approach in order to generate complete segments of files that we could concatenate together in our context.</p>



<p>To do this, we adjusted the output line of our prompt.</p>



<pre><code>Output the interface for ./server/db/manager.go</code></pre>



<p>An example of the output looked something like this.</p>



<pre><code>// Companies

CreateCompany(ctx context.Context, org dbmodels.Company) (dbmodels.Company, error)

GetCompany(ctx context.Context, id uuid.UUID) (*dbmodels.Company, error)

UpdateCompany(ctx context.Context, org dbmodels.Company) error

DeleteCompany(ctx context.Context, orgId string) error

ListCompany(ctx context.Context) ([]dbmodels.Company, error)</code></pre>



<p>After reviewing and adding this partially created file to the context, we did follow-up prompts to help generate the rest of the file and while keeping within the output token limit.</p>



<pre><code>Output the implementation of Companies for ./server/db/manager.go</code></pre>



<p>Repeating this process, we were able to generate the implementation of the entire interface and then move on to the next file. With token windows evolving quickly, hopefully this step won’t be necessary in the near future.</p>







<h2>Conclusion</h2>



<p>This article explored how Mantle leveraged LLMs streamline code conversion from prototype to production. By utilizing the model’s capabilities to generate code with context, we were able to save two-thirds of the time needed for our task of converting a codebase to another language.</p>



<p>Using these techniques, the approach taken will have to differ depending on the context you have around you. This article is a glimpse into how you can use things like folder structures, code patterns, and/or adjacent code/schemas as context to complete a number of coding tasks using LLMs.</p>



<p>As token windows continue to grow and models become more adept at understanding and generating code, there will be even greater efficiencies and improved code quality in the conversion process. This will undoubtedly lead to more rapid and cost-effective software development, which will benefit the whole ecosystem.</p>



<p><em>This was article is Part 2 of the Working with AI series. <a href="https://blog.withmantle.com/working-with-ai-understanding-the-art-of-the-prompt/">Read Part 1: Understanding the Art of the Prompt.</a> </em></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Technical Details on Today's Outage (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/technical-details-on-todays-outage/</link>
            <guid>41013198</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 01:19:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/technical-details-on-todays-outage/">https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/technical-details-on-todays-outage/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41013198">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<h2><span>What Happened?</span></h2>
<p><span>On July 19, 2024 at 04:09 UTC, as part of ongoing operations, CrowdStrike released a sensor configuration update to Windows systems. Sensor configuration updates are an ongoing part of the protection mechanisms of the Falcon platform. This configuration update triggered a logic error resulting in a system crash and blue screen (BSOD) on impacted systems.</span></p>
<p><span>The sensor configuration update that caused the system crash was remediated on Friday, July 19, 2024 05:27 UTC.</span></p>
<p><span>This issue is not the result of or related to a cyberattack.</span></p>
<h2><span>Impact</span></h2>
<p><span>Customers running Falcon sensor for Windows version 7.11 and above, that were online between Friday, July 19, 2024 04:09 UTC and Friday, July 19, 2024 05:27 UTC, may be impacted.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Systems running Falcon sensor for Windows 7.11 and above that downloaded the updated configuration from 04:09 UTC to 05:27 UTC – were susceptible to a system crash.</span></p>
<h2><span>Configuration File Primer</span></h2>
<p><span>The configuration files mentioned above are referred to as “</span><a href="https://supportportal.crowdstrike.com/s/article/ka16T000000wuddQAA"><span>Channel Files</span></a><span>” and are part of the behavioral protection mechanisms used by the Falcon sensor. Updates to Channel Files are a normal part of the sensor’s operation and occur several times a day in response to novel tactics, techniques, and procedures discovered by CrowdStrike. This is not a new process; the architecture has been in place since Falcon’s inception.</span></p>
<h2><span>Technical Details</span></h2>
<p><span>On Windows systems, Channel Files reside in the following directory:</span></p>
<p><code><span>C:\Windows\System32\drivers\CrowdStrike\</span></code></p>
<p><span>and have a file name that starts with “</span><code><span>C-</span></code><span>”. Each channel file is assigned a number as a unique identifier. The impacted Channel File in this event is 291 and will have a filename that starts with “</span><code><span>C-00000291-</span></code><span>” and ends with a </span><code><span>.sys</span></code><span> extension. Although Channel Files end with the SYS extension, </span><span><span>they are not kernel drivers</span></span><span>.</span></p>
<p><span>Channel File 291 controls how Falcon evaluates named pipe<sup>1</sup></span><span> execution on Windows systems. Named pipes are used for normal, interprocess or intersystem communication in Windows.</span></p>
<p><span>The update that occurred at 04:09 UTC was designed to target newly observed, malicious named pipes being used by common C2 frameworks in cyberattacks. The configuration update triggered a logic error that resulted in an operating system crash.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2><span>Channel File 291</span></h2>
<p><span>CrowdStrike has corrected the logic error by updating the content in Channel File 291. No additional changes to Channel File 291 beyond the updated logic will be deployed. Falcon is still evaluating and protecting against the abuse of named pipes.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>This is not related to null bytes contained within Channel File 291 or any other Channel File.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2><span>Remediation</span></h2>
<p><span>The most up-to-date remediation recommendations and information can be found on our </span><a href="https://www.crowdstrike.com/blog/statement-on-falcon-content-update-for-windows-hosts/"><span>blog</span></a><span> or in the </span><a href="https://supportportal.crowdstrike.com/s/article/Tech-Alert-Windows-crashes-related-to-Falcon-Sensor-2024-07-19"><span>Support Portal</span></a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>We understand that some customers may have specific support needs and we ask them to contact us directly.</span></p>
<p><span>Systems that are </span><span>not</span><span> currently impacted will continue to operate as expected, continue to provide protection, and have </span><span>no risk</span><span> of experiencing this event in the future.</span></p>
<p><span>Systems running Linux or macOS do not use Channel File 291 and were not impacted.&nbsp;</span></p>
<h2><span>Root Cause Analysis</span></h2>
<p><span>We understand how this issue occurred and we are doing a thorough root cause analysis to determine how this logic flaw occurred. This effort will be ongoing. We are committed to identifying any foundational or workflow improvements that we can make to strengthen our process. We will update our findings in the root cause analysis as the investigation progresses.</span></p>

<p><sup>1 </sup>https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/win32/ipc/named-pipes</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Doom on Playdate (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://devforum.play.date/t/doom-on-playdate/852</link>
            <guid>41013159</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 01:10:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://devforum.play.date/t/doom-on-playdate/852">https://devforum.play.date/t/doom-on-playdate/852</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41013159">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/DiscussionForumPosting">
      <meta itemprop="headline" content="Doom on Playdate">
      
      <meta itemprop="datePublished" content="2020-05-25T21:50:30Z">
        <meta itemprop="articleSection" content="Games">
      <meta itemprop="keywords" content="">
      


          <div itemprop="text" id="post_1">
              <p>Last week end I finally started to work on porting Doom on the Playdate.</p>
<p>This is a very early result, just to run the game, but that was the hardest part for me. Dealing with makefiles and compiler is really not my cup of tea so having the game running means that now I can focus on the game control, presentation and optimization.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/ad0bca29eb788fe9bfed240366cd41ee2a4639bf.gif" alt="04" data-base62-sha1="oGPRqp9vmPbukHgOoJDHnql4w8v" width="400" height="240"></p>
<p>This is a gif from the simulator but I got the game running on the hardware too.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/7c0f0a9386f96b3029520f6f76648db93a399eb6.gif" alt="05" data-base62-sha1="hHtqNnHnN2GfthLDtz2yS3xf5Rk" width="400" height="225"></p>
<p>The most difficult part was to deal with the linker that was complaining about some missing references in libc. After spending two evenings chasing every libc functions that might be problematic, I found out that there is some magical linker option.</p>
<p>I've added the following line in CMakeLists.txt<br>
<code>add_link_options(-specs=nano.specs -specs=nosys.specs)</code></p>
<p>Since the linker was complaining about the symbol end missing, I've added it to the link_map.ld in the playdate SDK</p>
<pre><code>	.bss :
	{
		. = ALIGN(4);
		__bss_start__ = .;
		*(.bss*)
		*(COMMON)
		. = ALIGN(4);
		__bss_end__ = .;
		end = __bss_end__;

	} &gt; EXTRAM
</code></pre>
            </div>
          <div id="post_2" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/matt"><span itemprop="name">matt</span></a>
                (gingerbeardman)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-25T22:33:56Z">
                    May 25, 2020, 10:33pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-25T22:33:56Z">
              <span itemprop="position">2</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Nic! You're crazy. In a good way.</p>
<p>Awesome</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_3" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/ast-rsk"><span itemprop="name">ast-rsk</span></a>
                
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-25T23:07:57Z">
                    May 25, 2020, 11:07pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-25T23:07:57Z">
              <span itemprop="position">3</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>This officially makes the playdate a viable product! If it can run doom, it's a solid device <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/3c05b67d820920114bafac96e31bfbefd6a4944d.png?v=12" title=":playdate:" alt=":playdate:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_4" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/squirrelboy"><span itemprop="name">squirrelboy</span></a>
                (Jake White)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-25T23:25:39Z">
                    May 25, 2020, 11:25pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-25T23:25:39Z">
              <span itemprop="position">4</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>Woah. I already wanted to make a Wolfenstein/Doom style game on this, but now even more.</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_5" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/dustin"><span itemprop="name">dustin</span></a>
                (Dustin Mierau)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T00:00:20Z">
                    May 26, 2020, 12:00am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T00:00:20Z">
              <span itemprop="position">5</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/d04cb21f40800c547fa08bc80d3c8dff0bc580c6.png?v=12" title=":playdate_shocked:" alt=":playdate_shocked:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/f444a5a65c415828c203bcb1b25076709723e907.png?v=12" title=":playdate_heart:" alt=":playdate_heart:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_6" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Dreezn"><span itemprop="name">Dreezn</span></a>
                (Dries Vienne)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T07:30:21Z">
                    May 26, 2020,  7:30am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T07:30:21Z">
              <span itemprop="position">6</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>I love you man.<br>
This is beautiful <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/smiling_face_with_three_hearts.png?v=12" title=":smiling_face_with_three_hearts:" alt=":smiling_face_with_three_hearts:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_7" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/SamanthaZero"><span itemprop="name">SamanthaZero</span></a>
                (Samantha Kalman)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T08:39:28Z">
                    May 26, 2020,  8:39am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T08:39:28Z">
              <span itemprop="position">7</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>very cool! <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/clap.png?v=12" title=":clap:" alt=":clap:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/clap.png?v=12" title=":clap:" alt=":clap:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/clap.png?v=12" title=":clap:" alt=":clap:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_8" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <div>
              <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span></p>

              <p><span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T10:01:16Z">
                    May 26, 2020, 10:01am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T10:01:16Z">
              <span itemprop="position">8</span>
              </span>
            </p></div>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Wow thank you all <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/f444a5a65c415828c203bcb1b25076709723e907.png?v=12" title=":playdate_heart:" alt=":playdate_heart:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
<p>But I have to say that this is possible mostly because the Doom engine is extremely well done and organized and can be easily ported. It is not a mystery why this is the game that is always ported everywhere.</p>
<p>Something I forgot to mention is that I used STM32Doom for the port which itself in based on chocolate doom. I will share the source when I am a bit further and after cleaning some code (If anyone want to source already, feel free to DM me).</p>

<p>For anyone interested, I also recommend the book from Fabien Sanglard which analyze the source code. That was the book that pick my interest in porting the game.<br>
<a href="https://fabiensanglard.net/gebbdoom/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://fabiensanglard.net/gebbdoom/index.html</a></p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_9" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Dreezn"><span itemprop="name">Dreezn</span></a>
                (Dries Vienne)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-26T12:02:57Z">
                    May 26, 2020, 12:02pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-26T12:02:57Z">
              <span itemprop="position">9</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Wow thanks for sharing!</p>
<p>I didn't know that book existed <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/3c05b67d820920114bafac96e31bfbefd6a4944d.png?v=12" title=":playdate:" alt=":playdate:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"> . Although I never attempted porting, I dove into the source a few times to get inspiration for various clones and such. This makes my week!</p>
<p>What next steps are you planning, now that you got it up and running?</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_10" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/DJLink"><span itemprop="name">DJLink</span></a>
                (David)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-29T20:39:52Z">
                    May 29, 2020,  8:39pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-29T20:39:52Z">
              <span itemprop="position">10</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>wow this is so cool, thanks for sharing</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_11" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <div>
              <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span></p>

              <p><span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-30T17:12:32Z">
                    May 30, 2020,  5:12pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-30T17:12:32Z">
              <span itemprop="position">11</span>
              </span>
            </p></div>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>I was not able to work on the port so much this week. This is still a gif of the rolling demo and this is not playable yet.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/45a72288f2aaca1680556bcc2edfabb22b71cd51.gif" alt="06" data-base62-sha1="9Wb1SCfukHAEAsvNGWkQLwoF6Gl" width="400" height="240"></p>
<p>This is still pretty rough. I tried to add controls but now the game crashes in the simulator when I try to launch the proper game. I also have a new crash on device, a totally different one. It will be (not) fun to track them down.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/831f4a1754fb7fb0e96227829fa4be398b4e78a9.jpeg" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="iHXAkc5VIVpibnRjHfObJxDlL29" width="300" height="225"></p>
<p>At least the rendering is a bit better. I use a dithering map texture which indicate which part of the screen is blue noise, ordered of just threshold. On the long term the key will be to add contrast to make some element like enemies pop more.</p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/bd8bb0089cf2a258971e14d7d7738d44d34cbc5e.png" alt="image" data-base62-sha1="r2NwjONof7FsOhFRe46a25dlW5U" width="320" height="200"></p>
<p>But now I went back to the blue noise rabbit hole and started to experiment generating my own blue noise textures. That will be interesting to improve the picture quality (and I have an idea that might force me to go back to my video experiments)</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_12" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/donald.hays"><span itemprop="name">donald.hays</span></a>
                (Donald Hays)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-30T23:50:22Z">
                    May 30, 2020, 11:50pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-30T23:50:22Z">
              <span itemprop="position">12</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>That is amazingly awesome.</p>
<p>I don't want to throw extra work on your plate, but this made me think about <a href="https://forums.tigsource.com/index.php?topic=40832.msg1363742#msg1363742" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">a post about dithering in Return of the Obra Dinn</a>, and how the dither pattern was rotated with the camera. Since you're working with Doom's source directly, I would imagine this means you have easy access to the camera rotation angle, yes? If so, I wonder how easy it would be to scroll the blue noise texture correspondingly, and if it would make the scene look any better or worse?</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_13" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-05-31T05:08:14Z">
                    May 31, 2020,  5:08am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-05-31T05:08:14Z">
              <span itemprop="position">13</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>That’s an excellent idea!<br>
I will look into it but it shouldn’t be too hard indeed.</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_14" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <div>
              <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span></p>

              <p><span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-01T21:27:41Z">
                    June 1, 2020,  9:27pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-01T21:27:41Z">
              <span itemprop="position">14</span>
              </span>
            </p></div>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>So if you don't go on the discord you might not have seen that Poom is kind of playable. I say kind of because I still have a lot of random crashes when navigating the menus. I am waiting to be able to debug on the simulator figure out what is the issue.</p>
<p>And because of popular demand I've added using the crank to use the Gatling. <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/d04cb21f40800c547fa08bc80d3c8dff0bc580c6.png?v=12" title=":playdate_shocked:" alt=":playdate_shocked:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
<p><img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/62f76ee198cb00799bf45990690c10531b8f6d7f.gif" alt="DoomGatlingMini.2020-06-01 23_25_12" data-base62-sha1="e7uUJNqPr1l5EejChDvwKfT8oub" width="330" height="220"></p>
<p>We also had a discussion about Chex Quest and I don't think my code can support it so I am considering switch fully to Doom Chocolate. That would be an opportunity to clean up the code I did.</p>
<p>The early results are encouraging but there is still so much to do. <img src="https://devforum-cdn.play.date/original/1X/d5fcf966698d4f0ed1188749a3aca4707508f293.png?v=12" title=":playdate_dizzy:" alt=":playdate_dizzy:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
            </div>

            

            

                
          </div>
          <div id="post_15" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/dustin"><span itemprop="name">dustin</span></a>
                (Dustin Mierau)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-01T22:25:24Z">
                    June 1, 2020, 10:25pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-01T22:25:24Z">
              <span itemprop="position">15</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>SO FREAKING GOOD <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/smiley.png?v=12" title=":smiley:" alt=":smiley:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_16" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/ast-rsk"><span itemprop="name">ast-rsk</span></a>
                
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-01T23:27:32Z">
                    June 1, 2020, 11:27pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-01T23:27:32Z">
              <span itemprop="position">16</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>Incredible progress!</p>
<p>A couple friends of mine who don't know anything about playdate or that I'm in the preview, individually shared your update tweet with me saying how cool it is and how the device is so unique and looks fun.</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_17" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Drarok"><span itemprop="name">Drarok</span></a>
                
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-02T20:04:47Z">
                    June 2, 2020,  8:04pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-02T20:04:47Z">
              <span itemprop="position">17</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>This is absolutely nuts in a brilliant way.</p>
<p>How's the music sound? <img src="https://devforum.play.date/images/emoji/apple/grimacing.png?v=12" title=":grimacing:" alt=":grimacing:" loading="lazy" width="20" height="20"></p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_18" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/Nic"><span itemprop="name">Nic</span></a>
                (Nic Magnier)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-06-02T21:11:39Z">
                    June 2, 2020,  9:11pm
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-06-02T21:11:39Z">
              <span itemprop="position">18</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <div itemprop="text">
              <p>No sound or music yet.</p>
<p>This is not my specialty so I didn't even look at it yet. Especially since this seem to have been the least portable part of the original doom. But I will come to that [art eventually.</p>
            </div>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_19" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/HaitoH3"><span itemprop="name">HaitoH3</span></a>
                (Jason A. Huff)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-07-01T05:08:37Z">
                    July 1, 2020,  5:08am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-07-01T05:08:37Z">
              <span itemprop="position">19</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>oh man so good... i'll just start over now</p>

            

            

          </div>
          <div id="post_20" itemprop="comment" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Comment">
            <p><span itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
                <a itemprop="url" href="https://devforum.play.date/u/spencer"><span itemprop="name">spencer</span></a>
                (spencer cap)
              </span>



              <span>
                  <time itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2020-07-21T07:33:23Z">
                    July 21, 2020,  7:33am
                  </time>
                  <meta itemprop="dateModified" content="2020-07-21T07:33:23Z">
              <span itemprop="position">20</span>
              </span>
            </p>
            <p>Great job with this! would love to try out how it feels to shoot using the crank. do you have a pdx avail to play test?</p>

            

            

          </div>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Garage: Open-Source Distributed Object Storage (412 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/</link>
            <guid>41013004</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:40:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/">https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41013004">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <div>
        <h2>Our Goals</h2>
        
        <p>We made it lightweight and kept the efficiency in mind:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <span>Self-contained</span>
            <p>We ship a single dependency-free binary that runs on all Linux distributions</p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <span>Fast to deploy, safe to operate</span>
            <p>We are sysadmins, we know the value of operator-friendly software</p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            <span>Deploy everywhere on every machine</span>
            <p>We do not have a dedicated backbone, and neither do you,<br>
              so we made software that run over the Internet across multiple datacenters</p>
          </li>
          
          <li>
            Highly resilient
            <p><span>to network failures</span>,
              <span>network latency</span>,
              <span>disk failures</span>,
              <span>sysadmin failures</span>
            </p>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Keeping requirements low</h2>
        
        <p>
          We worked hard to keep requirements as low as possible:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/cpu.svg" width="24">
              <span>CPU</span>
            </p>
            <span>Any x86_64 CPU from the last 10 years, ARMv7 or ARMv8</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/ram.svg" width="24">
              <span>RAM</span>
            </p>
            <span>1 GB</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/disk.svg" width="24">
              <span>Disk space</span>
            </p>
            <span>At least 16 GB</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/network.svg" width="24">
              <span>Network</span>
            </p>
            <span>200 ms or less, 50 Mbps or more</span>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/icons/hardware.svg" width="24">
              <span>Heterogeneous hardware</span>
            </p>
            <span>Build a cluster with whatever second-hand machines are available</span>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Data resiliency for everyone</h2>
        
        <p>
          We built Garage to suit your existing infrastructure:
        </p>
        <p>
          Garage implements the Amazon S3 API<br>and thus is already compatible with many applications.
        </p>
        
      </div>

      <div>
        <h2>Standing on the shoulders of giants</h2>
        
        <p>
          Garage leverages insights from recent research in distributed systems:
        </p>
        
      </div>
    </div><div>
        <h2>Sponsors and funding</h2>
        <p>Garage has received funding from <a href="https://pointer.ngi.eu/" target="_blank">NGI POINTER</a> (3 full-time employees for one year, in 2021-2022),
          and from <a href="https://nlnet.nl/entrust/" target="_blank">NLnet / NGI0 Entrust</a> (1 full-time employee for one year, in 2023-2024).
        </p>
        <p>If you want to participate in funding Garage development,
          either through donation or support contract,
          please <a href="mailto:garagehq@deuxfleurs.fr">get in touch with us</a>.
        </p>
        <p>
          <img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/images/ngi-pointer-eu.png" alt="NGI Pointers">
        </p>
        <p>
         <img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/images/nlnet.svg" alt="NLnet logo">
         <img src="https://garagehq.deuxfleurs.fr/images/NGI0Entrust_tag.svg" alt="NGI0 Entrust logo">
        </p>
        <p>This project has received funding from the European Union's Horizon 2021 research and innovation programme
          within the framework of the NGI-POINTER Project funded under grant agreement N° 871528.</p>
        <p>This project has received funding from the NGI0
          Entrust Fund, a fund established by NLnet with financial support from the
          European Commission's Next Generation Internet programme, under the aegis of DG
          Communications Networks, Content and Technology under grant agreement No
          101069594.
        </p>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I mapped almost every USA traffic death in the 21st century (685 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://roadway.report</link>
            <guid>41012443</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 23:16:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://roadway.report">https://roadway.report</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41012443">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://roadway.report: Error: connect ECONNREFUSED 2600:3c00::f03c:94ff:fe0d:a614:443]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Multisatellite data depicts a record-breaking methane leak from a well blowout (311 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399</link>
            <guid>41012193</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 22:42:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399">https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41012193">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://pubs.acs.org/doi/10.1021/acs.estlett.4c00399: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Academics shocked after T&F sells access to their research to Microsoft AI (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai</link>
            <guid>41011779</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 21:53:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai">https://www.thebookseller.com/news/academic-authors-shocked-after-taylor--francis-sells-access-to-their-research-to-microsoft-ai</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41011779">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <p>Authors have expressed their shock after the news that academic publisher Taylor &amp; Francis, which owns Routledge, had sold access to its authors’ research as part of an Artificial Intelligence (AI) partnership with Microsoft—a deal worth almost £8m ($10m) in its first year.</p>
<p>The agreement with Microsoft was included in a trading update by the publisher’s parent company in May this year.&nbsp;However, academics published by the group claim they have not been told about the AI deal, were not given the opportunity to opt out and are receiving no extra payment for the use of their research by the tech company.&nbsp;</p>
<p>The Society of Authors said it is "concerned to see publishers signing deals with tech companies without consulting authors and creators first".</p>
<p>Dr Ruth Alison Clemens, a lecturer in modern English literature whose work has been published by Taylor &amp; Francis and Routledge, claimed authors hadn’t been contacted about the AI deal.</p>
<p>Clemens told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller </em>: "I only found out about this via word of mouth in the past few days. I was shocked that they had not publicised this more widely to their authors, as the use of AI and LLMs is a prominent concern for academic researchers today."</p>
<p>A spokesman from the Taylor &amp; Francis group, which is owned by Informa—a FTSE 100 international B2B Events, B2B Digital Services and Academic Markets group—confirmed to <em>The Bookseller </em>that "it is providing Microsoft non-exclusive access to advanced learning content and data to help improve relevance and performance of AI systems".</p>
<p>The&nbsp;<a href="https://www.informa.com/globalassets/documents/investor-relations/2024/informa-plc---market-update.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">agreement</a>, details of which were published by Informa during a trading update in May, states that Informa will be paid $10m+ for "an initial data access" of the works it has the rights to, with a recurring payment of an undisclosed sum to be made over the subsequent three years. &nbsp;</p>
<p>When contacted by <em>The Bookseller, </em>Taylor &amp; Francis said it is "protecting the integrity of our authors’ work and limits on verbatim text reproduction, as well as authors’ rights to receive royalty payments in accordance with their author contracts".</p>
<p>Informa is expecting revenues to reach just shy of £3.5bn in the current financial year, up from £3.2bn in 2023.</p>
<p>Taylor &amp; Francis, with its portfolio of specialist publishing brands (Routledge, CRC Press, F1000),&nbsp;<a href="https://www.thebookseller.com/news/taylor--francis-revenues-up-43-in-strong-trading-performance%3Ca%20href=" https:="" www.thebookseller.com="" news="" taylor--francis-revenues-up-43-in-strong-trading-performance"="" target="_blank">www.thebookseller.com/news/taylor--francis-revenues-up-43-in-strong-trading-performance</a>" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;revealed in March that its revenues went up 4.3% for 2023 to £619m, with adjusted operating profit up 4.4% to £217.9m.</p>
<p>One of the biggest concerns raised by Clemens is over whether it is possible for Taylor &amp; Francis’ authors to opt out of the AI partnership with Microsoft. Clemens told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller</em>: "There is no clarity from Taylor &amp; Francis about whether an opt-out policy is in place or on the cards. But as they did not inform their authors about the deal in the first place, any opt-out policy is now not functional."</p> </div><div> <p><em>The Bookseller</em> asked Taylor &amp; Francis if it was possible to opt out and requested clarification over whether authors had been told about the AI deal. The publisher’s spokesman said he couldn’t comment further. <em>The Bookseller</em> has also contacted Microsoft for comment.</p>
<p>Clemens told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller </em>the response from the academic community following her post on X shows the issue has "struck a nerve, and authors around the world are rightfully concerned".</p>
<p>"We are at a crossroads in the production and dissemination of research knowledge, and in my view the biggest problem with this deal is the reduction of academic research into raw content from which data can be extracted and repackaged as knowledge," Clemens said.</p>
<p>Mia Gray, professor of economic geography at the University of Cambridge, wrote on X: "This is disturbing and an increasingly important issue for academics."</p>
<p>James McConnachie, author and journalist posted on X: "Authors: check your contracts! Ask your publisher about their AI policy."</p>
<p>Ambre Morvan, senior policy manager and contracts advisor at the Society of Authors, told&nbsp;<em>The Bookseller</em>: “The Society of Authors is concerned to see publishers signing deals with tech companies without consulting authors and creators first."</p>
<p>She added: "There are copyright, moral rights and data protection questions that need to be carefully considered, as well as questions about transparency and fairness of payment from (authorised) uses by tech companies. The impact of such uses on traditional sales of the author’s work and the author’s professional future more widely must also be considered. Creators are the backbone of our world-leading creative industries, and we cannot emphasise enough the vital need to protect them."</p>
<p>The Society of Authors (SoA) urged authors who "find their work has been used without their consent" to contact them for guidance and encouraged authors to complete <a href="https://www.alcs.co.uk/news/alcs-launches-survey-on-ai-licenses/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">a survey currently being conducted by the Authors’ Licensing and Collecting Society</a> (ALCS) around collective licensing options for authors.</p>
<p>ALCS’s c.e.o Barbara Hayes, told <em>The Bookseller:</em> "We know that developments in generative AI technologies are happening at speed with deals between publishers and technology companies the subject of regular media reports. We believe it’s imperative that the interests and rights of authors are fully represented within these discussions and negotiations which is unfortunately often the step missing at present."</p>
<p><span dir="ltr">Earlier this week the Copyright Clearance Centre announced the availability of AI re-use rights within its&nbsp;<a title="https://gbr01.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3a%2f%2fwww.copyright.com%2fsolutions-annual-copyright-license%2f&amp;data=05%7c02%7cmatilda.battersby%40thebookseller.com%7c8d60b159185e4d4723f208dca7d0a573%7c681bf9290a374aebb6da197c32182db1%7c0%7c0%7c638569761768939727%7cunknown%7ctwfpbgzsb3d8eyjwijoimc4wljawmdailcjqijoiv2lumziilcjbtii6ik1hawwilcjxvci6mn0%3d%7c0%7c%7c%7c&amp;sdata=yqt%2bv6lxusxjfigo%2bg53f%2b6iqugfi9xid8ggklpibho%3d&amp;reserved=0" href="https://gbr01.safelinks.protection.outlook.com/?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.copyright.com%2Fsolutions-annual-copyright-license%2F&amp;data=05%7C02%7CMatilda.Battersby%40thebookseller.com%7C8d60b159185e4d4723f208dca7d0a573%7C681bf9290a374aebb6da197c32182db1%7C0%7C0%7C638569761768939727%7CUnknown%7CTWFpbGZsb3d8eyJWIjoiMC4wLjAwMDAiLCJQIjoiV2luMzIiLCJBTiI6Ik1haWwiLCJXVCI6Mn0%3D%7C0%7C%7C%7C&amp;sdata=YQt%2BV6lXuSxJfigO%2Bg53F%2B6IQUGfi9xID8GgKlpiBho%3D&amp;reserved=0" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Link Annual Copyright License">Annual Copyright License</a> (ACL) — which it claims is "the first-ever collective licensing solution for the internal use of copyrighted materials in AI systems." The license will provides holders with rights and remuneration for new uses of their content.&nbsp;</span></p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>