<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 19 Apr 2025 01:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Full Text Search of US Court records (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.judyrecords.com/</link>
            <guid>43731552</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 20:24:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/">https://www.judyrecords.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43731552">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                        <p><a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/">judyrecords</a></p><form action="/" method="get">

<div>

        <p>
    

    <a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/info#searchTipsHeader">search tips</a>
</p></div>

</form>



            <p><span>740 million<span>+</span></span>
                <br><span>United States Court Cases</span>
            </p>

            <ul>

                <li><a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/">home</a></li>
                <li><a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/terms">terms</a></li>
                <li><a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/info">info</a></li>
                
                <li><a href="https://www.judyrecords.com/api">API</a></li>            </ul>

                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[15,000 lines of verified cryptography now in Python (244 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jonathan.protzenko.fr/2025/04/18/python.html</link>
            <guid>43731165</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 19:28:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jonathan.protzenko.fr/2025/04/18/python.html">https://jonathan.protzenko.fr/2025/04/18/python.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43731165">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>In November 2022, I opened <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/issues/99108">issue 99108</a> on
Python’s GitHub repository, arguing that after a recent CVE in its implementation of
SHA3, Python should embrace verified code for all of its hash-related infrastructure.</p>

<p>As of last week, this issue is now closed, and every single hash and HMAC algorithm exposed by
default in Python is now provided by <a href="https://github.com/project-everest/hacl-star/">HACL*</a>, the
verified cryptographic library. There was no loss of functionality, and the transition was entirely
transparent for Python users. Python now vendors (includes in its repository) 15,000 lines of
verified C code from HACL*. Pulling newer versions from the upstream HACL* repository
is entirely automated and is done by invoking a script. HACL* was able to successfully implement
new features to meet all of the requirements of Python, such as: additional modes for the Blake2
family of algorithms, a new API for SHA3 that covers all Keccak variants, strict abstraction
patterns to deal with build system difficulties, proper error management (notably, allocation
failures), and instantiating HACL’s generic “streaming” functionality with the HMAC algorithm,
including an optimization that requires keeping two hash states at once.</p>

<p>This is the culmination of 2.5 years of work, and could not have happened without the invaluable
help of <a href="https://aymericfromherz.github.io/">Aymeric Fromherz</a>, who shouldered a lot of the
implementation burden. <a href="https://www.sonho.fr/">Son Ho</a> had a key contribution early on, generalizing
HACL’s “streaming” functionality to be able to handle block algorithms that require a “pre-input”.
This slightly obscure generalization was actually essential to implement a suitable, optimized HMAC
that keeps two hash states under the hood. On the Python side, Gregory P. Smith, Bénédikt Tran, and
later Chris Eibl were big champions and provided a lot of help. Finally, the HACS series of
workshops created connections (hello, Paul Kehrer!) and provided sufficient momentum to make this
happen. A warm thank you to both the Python and verified cryptographic communities!</p>

<p>As I oftentimes like to do, I’ll provide a little bit of a look behind the scenes, and comment on
some of the more interesting technical aspects that are too low-level for a research paper.</p>

<h2 id="a-primer-on-streaming-apis">A Primer on Streaming APIs</h2>

<p>Many cryptographic algorithms are <em>block</em> algorithms, meaning that they assume their input is
provided block by block, with special treatment for the first and last blocks. Well-known block
algorithms include hash algorithms, MAC algorithms (e.g. Poly1305, HMAC), and more. In practice, the
block API is not user-friendly: rarely does one have the data already chunked in blocks;
furthermore, computing a result (e.g., a hash) invalidates the state of the block algorithm, which
makes e.g. computing the intermediary hashes of the TLS transcript difficult.</p>

<p>For these reasons, cryptographic libraries typically expose <em>streaming</em> APIs, meaning clients can
provide inputs of any length; the library then takes care of buffering the input, flushing the
buffer as soon as a full block is obtained. A streaming API typically also allows extracting
intermediary hashes without invalidating the state.</p>

<p>Streaming APIs are hard, because they manipulate long-lived state with complex invariants: the
(unverified) reference implementation of SHA3 was hit with a <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/cve-2022-37454">bad
CVE</a> in 2022, which Python “inherited”, because it
vendored that very same SHA3 implementation.</p>

<p>Streaming APIs are hard also because the
underlying block algorithms differ in a myriad of different ways: all hash algorithms accept an
empty final block, <em>except</em> for Blake2; some need to retain the key at run-time (Poly1305), some can discard it
after initialization (HMAC, optimized); some need some initial input before processing the key
(Blake2), some don’t; and so on.</p>

<p>Given this inherent complexity, streaming algorithms are a good candidate for verification: we wrote
a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.01644">research paper</a> in 2021 about this very problem.</p>

<h2 id="fully-generic-verification">Fully generic verification</h2>

<p>The main idea from the paper is that one can capture, using dependent types, what a block algorithm
<em>is</em>. Once that’s done, it suffices to author and verify a generic streaming construction once and
for all over an abstract definition of block algorithms. Then, just like you instantiate a template
in C++, you apply the generic streaming construction to a concrete block API and voilà – a
streaming API for that one block algorithm, “for free”.</p>

<p>The fist hitch is that there’s quite a big delta between what we presented in the paper (Listing
12), and <a href="https://github.com/hacl-star/hacl-star/blob/897e23d315c08f7a375408d60d1a4918477fcaa0/code/streaming/Hacl.Streaming.Interface.fsti#L254">what actually lives in the
repository</a>.
Specifically, capturing <em>any</em> block algorithm requires a lot of genericity.</p>
<ul>
  <li>The user may or may not specify the length of the final digest – for instance,
each SHA3 hash has a fixed output length, but the Shake variants produce a result whose length is
user-provided.</li>
  <li>The block algorithm may expect to receive a pre-input before the blocks of data. For e.g. SHA2,
the pre-input is empty, but for Blake2 in keyed hash mode, the pre-input is the key block.</li>
  <li>Blocks cannot be processed eagerly, because some algorithms (Blake2) do not allow for the final
block to be empty – this vastly complicates buffer management, and interacts with the pre-input.</li>
  <li>Some algorithms need to retain extra pieces of state: for instance, the key length for Blake2 can
be tweaked at initialization-time, but needs to be retained in the long-lived state.</li>
  <li>To avoid invalidating the block state upon intermediary digest extraction, our streaming API
copies the state under the hood – in some cases, it’s easier to stack-allocate this copy, but in
other cases, a heap-allocated copy makes more sense.</li>
  <li>In some cases, we wanted one API per algorithm (we have four APIs for
SHA2-{224,256,384,512}); in other cases, we wanted one API per algorithm family (we have one API
that covers all 6 Keccak algorithms: 4 variants of SHA3, and 2 variants of Shake).</li>
</ul>

<p>Getting to that level of genericity took multiple rounds, driven by the successive requirements of
Python. Ultimately, for HMAC, which was the final algorithm we landed in Python, we realized that
our proofs and definitions were generic enough that we did not need any further tweaks to
“instantiate” our generic streaming API with HMAC.</p>

<h2 id="a-bulletproof-build">A bulletproof build</h2>

<p>One highlight of submitting a PR to Python is that their infrastructure has more CI coverage than we
could possibly dream of: a complete build of Python runs over 50+ toolchains and architectures. The
flipside? We discovered some pretty annoying corner cases.</p>

<p>One particularly tricky build issue surfaced when dealing with HMAC. As a reminder,
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HMAC">HMAC</a> is a generic construction that, given a hash algorithm,
provides a keyed message authentication code – in short, there is a high-level HMAC piece of code
that defers most of the work to individual hash algorithms. Each hash algorithm may itself come in a
variety of <em>implementations</em>: for instance, HMAC-Blake2b is implemented both by HMAC-Blake2b-32
(regular implementation) and HMAC-Blake2b-256 (AVX2 wide-vector implementation).</p>

<p>This already causes problems: <code>HMAC.c</code> may call functions from <code>Blake2b_256.c</code>, if Python is running
on a machine with AVX2. However, only <code>Blake2b_256.c</code> may be compiled with <code>-mavx2</code>: code from
<code>HMAC.c</code> will execute on all machines, even those without AVX2, meaning it must <em>not</em> be compiled
with <code>-mavx2</code>. So far, so good, and this is something we had done before.</p>

<p>The problem came with <code>HMAC.c</code> creating the initial state for <code>Blake2b_256.c</code>:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>#include</span> <span>&lt;immintrin.h&gt;</span><span>
</span>
<span>// ...</span>
  <span>__m256i</span> <span>*</span><span>blake2b_256_state</span> <span>=</span> <span>aligned_malloc</span><span>(</span><span>sizeof</span><span>(</span><span>__m256i</span><span>)</span><span>*</span><span>4</span><span>);</span>
<span>// ...</span>

</code></pre></div>

<p>Most toolchains were happy with this code – <code>immintrin.h</code> defines the type <code>__m256i</code>, and even
though <code>HMAC.c</code> cannot assume AVX2 instructions are available, it’s not to hard for a
compiler to zero-initialize <code>blake2b_256_state</code> without resorting to AVX2 instructions… except,
some older compilers refused to process the <code>immintrin.h</code> header unless <code>-mavx2</code> was used, which
defeated the whole purpose.</p>

<p>This required a considerable amount of refactoring to use the well-known “C abstract struct”
pattern, which essentially defines an abstract type in C.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>// Blake2b_256.h</span>
<span>typedef</span> <span>struct</span> <span>blake2b_256_st_s</span> <span>blake2b_256_st</span><span>;</span>
<span>blake2b_256_st</span> <span>*</span><span>blake2b_256_malloc</span><span>();</span>

<span>// Blake2b_256.c</span>
<span>#include</span> <span>&lt;immintrin.h&gt;</span><span>
</span><span>typedef</span> <span>struct</span> <span>blake2b_256_st_s</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>__m256i</span> <span>contents</span><span>[</span><span>4</span><span>];</span>
<span>}</span> <span>blake2b_256_st</span><span>;</span>

<span>// HMAC.c</span>
<span>blake2b_256_st</span> <span>*</span><span>blake2b_256_state</span> <span>=</span> <span>blake2b_256_malloc</span><span>();</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>What made this extra difficult is that the C code is auto-generated from F*, which has a <em>very</em>
different notion of abstraction. The compiler that goes from F* to C,
<a href="https://github.com/FStarLang/karamel/">krml</a>, had to be overhauled to perform a much more
fine-grained analysis that handles various levels of visibility (public functions, library-internal
functions, translation-unit internal functions) even in the presence of such “abstract structs”.</p>

<h2 id="handling-memory-allocation-failures">Handling memory allocation failures</h2>

<p>While our original modeling of C in F* allowed reasoning about memory allocation failures, no one
had ever bothered to do so in practice. For Python, it was desirable to be able to propagate memory
allocation failures. This meant we had to refine our definition of a generic, mutable piece of state
(such as the block state); our definition of a block algorithm (such as SHA2-256); and our generic
streaming construction to all be able to propagate memory allocation failures all the way up to the
caller. Thankfully, this didn’t turn out to be a huge deal: we inserted <code>option</code> types all along the
way, and because we had one single generic streaming construction, the implementation and proofs had
to be updated only once for the 15+ concrete instances of the streaming API.</p>

<p>The presence of <code>option</code> types in the source compiles to tagged unions in the generated C; this is a
little verbose, and we may change our definition of a piece of state to feature a <code>has_failed</code>
run-time function that can assess whether a memory allocation failed, at the expense of more
complexity and verification effort.</p>

<h2 id="propagating-changes-from-upstream-hacl-to-python">Propagating changes from upstream HACL* to Python</h2>

<p>My initial Python PR contained a shell script that would fetch the required files from the upstream
HACL* repository; ditch a bunch of superfluous definitions in headers via well-crafted sed
invocations; and tweak a few include paths in-place, also using my favorite refactoring tool (yes,
sed). The benefit was the the initial PR was lean and clean.</p>

<p>Later on, once it became clear that the upstream code was maintainable and pretty stable, that pile
of seds was eliminated, on the basis that it’s not the end of the world if a header contains a few
extra definitions, and it all makes maintenance easier.</p>

<p>Now, anyone who wishes to refresh HACL* can run the shell script in their checkout of Python, and
provided they tweak the expected hash in Python’s SBOM (software bill of materials), they are good
to go and can integrate the latest improvements.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I’m delighted to see such a large-scale integration of verified cryptographic code in a flagship
project like Python. This demonstrates that verified cryptographic is not only ready from an
academic perspective, but also mature enough to be integrated in real-world software while meeting
all engineering expectations. Thanks to everyone who helped along this journey!</p>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Judge Rules Blanket Search of Cell Tower Data Unconstitutional (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.404media.co/judge-rules-blanket-search-of-cell-tower-data-unconstitutional/</link>
            <guid>43730545</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 18:16:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.404media.co/judge-rules-blanket-search-of-cell-tower-data-unconstitutional/">https://www.404media.co/judge-rules-blanket-search-of-cell-tower-data-unconstitutional/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43730545">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <article>
          <div>
              
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p><em>This article was produced in collaboration&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.courtwatch.news/?ref=404media.co" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>with Court Watch</em></a><em>, an independent outlet that unearths overlooked court records.&nbsp;</em><a href="https://www.courtwatch.news/?ref=404media.co" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Subscribe to them here</em></a><em>.</em></p><p>A judge in Nevada has ruled that “tower dumps”—the law enforcement practice of grabbing vast troves of private personal data from cell towers—is unconstitutional. The judge also ruled that the cops could, this one time, still use the evidence they obtained through this unconstitutional search.&nbsp;</p><p>Cell towers record the location of phones near them about every seven seconds. When the cops request a tower dump, they ask a telecom for the numbers and personal information of every single phone connected to a tower during a set time period. Depending on the area, these tower dumps can return tens of thousands of numbers.</p>
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p>Cops have been able to sift through this data to solve crimes. But tower dumps are also a massive privacy violation that flies in the face of the Fourth Amendment, which protects people from unlawful search and seizure. When the cops get a tower dump they’re not just searching and seizing the data of a suspected criminal, they’re sifting through the information of everyone who was in the location.</p><p>A Nevada man, Cory Spurlock, is facing charges related to dealing marijuana and a murder-for-hire scheme. Cops used a tower dump to connect his cellphone with the location of some of the crimes he is accused of. Spurlock’s lawyers argued that the tower dump was an unconstitutional search and that the evidence obtained during it should not be. The cops got a warrant to conduct the tower dump but argued it wasn’t technically a “search” and therefore wasn’t subject to the Fourth Amendment.</p><p>U.S. District Juste Miranda M. Du rejected this argument, but wouldn’t suppress the evidence. “The Court finds that a tower dump is a search and the warrant law enforcement used to get it is a general warrant forbidden under the Fourth Amendment,” she said in a ruling filed on April 11. “That said, because the Court appears to be the first court within the Ninth Circuit to reach this conclusion and the good faith exception otherwise applies, the Court will not order any evidence suppressed.”</p><p>Du argued that the officers acted in good faith when they filed the warrant and that they didn’t know the search was unconstitutional when they conducted it. According to Du, the warrant wasn’t unconstitutional when a judge issued it.</p><p>Du’s ruling is the first time the United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit has ruled on the constitutionality of tower dumps, but this isn’t the first time a federal judge has weighed in. One in Mississippi <a href="https://www.courtwatch.news/p/exclusive-judge-rules-tower-dumps-unconstitutional?ref=404media.co"><u>came to the same conclusion</u></a> in February. A few weeks later, the Department of Justice <a href="https://www.courtwatch.news/p/exclusive-doj-to-appeal-tower-dump-ruling?ref=404media.co"><u>appealed the ruling</u></a>.</p><p>There’s a decent chance that one of these cases will wind its way up to the Supreme Court and that SCOTUS will have to make a ruling about tower dumps. The last time the issue was in front of them, they kicked the can back to the lower courts.</p><p>In 2018, the Supreme Court considered <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/2017/16-402?ref=404media.co"><em><u>Carpenter v. United States</u></em></a>, a case where the FBI used cell phone location data to investigate a series of robberies. The Court decided that law enforcement agencies violate the Fourth Amendment when they ask for cell phone location data without a warrant. But the ruling was narrow and the Court declined to rule on the issue of tower dumps.</p><p>According to the court records for Spurlock’s case, the tower dump that caught him captured the private data of 1,686 users. An expert who testified before the court about the dump noted that “the wireless company users whose phones showed up in the tower dump data did not opt in to sharing their location with their wireless provider, and indeed, could not opt out from appearing in the type of records received in response to [the] warrant.”</p>
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->

                    <div>
    <div>
      <p>About the author</p>
      <p>Matthew Gault is a writer covering weird tech, nuclear war, and video games. He’s worked for Reuters, Motherboard, and the New York Times.</p>
      
    </div>
      <p><img data-src="https://www.gravatar.com/avatar/87e07bd5bb3d003b0b135303a3e7f8b9?s=250&amp;r=x&amp;d=mp" alt="Matthew Gault" src="https://www.gravatar.com/avatar/87e07bd5bb3d003b0b135303a3e7f8b9?s=250&amp;r=x&amp;d=mp">  
      </p>
  </div>
          </div>
        </article>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I made a Doom-like game fit inside a QR code (328 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/Kuberwastaken/backdooms</link>
            <guid>43729683</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 16:40:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/Kuberwastaken/backdooms">https://github.com/Kuberwastaken/backdooms</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43729683">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The Backdooms: Running DOOM on a QR Code</h2><a id="user-content-the-backdooms-running-doom-on-a-qr-code" aria-label="Permalink: The Backdooms: Running DOOM on a QR Code" href="#the-backdooms-running-doom-on-a-qr-code"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">
    <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/Kuberwastaken/backdooms/blob/main/qrcode.png"><img src="https://github.com/Kuberwastaken/backdooms/raw/main/qrcode.png" alt="QR Code for The Backdooms"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
    Yes, this is literally the entire game. You can <a href="https://scanqr.org/" rel="nofollow">scan it</a> to play.
</p>
<p dir="auto">
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1fa4cef0c40c141ac0ed954ecdb8d2119b7b110a222d5feef9b9ff01e3363977/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f7374617469632f76313f6c6162656c3d4b7562657277617374616b656e266d6573736167653d4261636b646f6f6d7326636f6c6f723d626c61636b266c6f676f3d676974687562"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1fa4cef0c40c141ac0ed954ecdb8d2119b7b110a222d5feef9b9ff01e3363977/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f7374617469632f76313f6c6162656c3d4b7562657277617374616b656e266d6573736167653d4261636b646f6f6d7326636f6c6f723d626c61636b266c6f676f3d676974687562" alt="Kuberwastaken - Backdooms" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/static/v1?label=Kuberwastaken&amp;message=Backdooms&amp;color=black&amp;logo=github"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/90d2eb9460dae650d20e525e61ffe4973f067ee0dde23e1e5b706b5630d039e9/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f76657273696f6e2d31332e302d626c61636b"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/90d2eb9460dae650d20e525e61ffe4973f067ee0dde23e1e5b706b5630d039e9/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f76657273696f6e2d31332e302d626c61636b" alt="Version 13.0" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/version-13.0-black"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/56265e049c38cb332bf7419805d7c1d985832a34e869aef4801771fe9b416133/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4c6963656e73652d4d49542d626c61636b"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/56265e049c38cb332bf7419805d7c1d985832a34e869aef4801771fe9b416133/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4c6963656e73652d4d49542d626c61636b" alt="License MIT" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/License-MIT-black"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 Project Overview</h2><a id="user-content--project-overview" aria-label="Permalink: 🚀 Project Overview" href="#-project-overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>The Backdooms</strong> is a compressed, self-extracting and infinitely generating HTML game inspired by DOOM 1993 and The Backrooms that can be launched and played in a web browser directly from a QR code.</p>
<p dir="auto">This project was a week-long study I performed (now slightly longer) designed to push the limits of QR code storage and compression, to demonstrate an innovative method of hosting lightweight web applications entirely within a QR code.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto">
    <a href="https://kuberwastaken.github.io/backdooms" rel="nofollow">Play a slightly less compressed version of this game here</a>
    <br>
    <span>Yes, it's 8bit Undertale Music There</span>
</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📜 Features</h2><a id="user-content--features" aria-label="Permalink: 📜 Features" href="#-features"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">✅ <strong>Fully Offline:</strong> No internet connection is required to play the game after scanning the QR code. The URL basically has the ENTIRE code to the game</p>
<p dir="auto">✅ <strong>Extreme Compression:</strong> Utilizes a combination of Zlib compression with Gzip Decompression stream along with base64 encoding to make the final result extremely compressed.</p>
<p dir="auto">✅ <strong>Self-Extracting Webpage:</strong> Uses the <code>DecompressionStream</code> API to dynamically decompress and execute the game within the browser.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📦 Installation &amp; Dependencies</h2><a id="user-content--installation--dependencies" aria-label="Permalink: 📦 Installation &amp; Dependencies" href="#-installation--dependencies"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Well, technically speaking, just a modern web browser.</p>
<p dir="auto">But if we do get into the nitty gritty of generating a QR code of a ≈ 2.5kb game:</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Prerequisites</h3><a id="user-content-prerequisites" aria-label="Permalink: Prerequisites" href="#prerequisites"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Python 3.7+</strong></li>
<li><code>qrcode</code> library (for generating QR codes)</li>
<li><code>pillow</code> (for QR code image handling)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install Dependencies</h3><a id="user-content-install-dependencies" aria-label="Permalink: Install Dependencies" href="#install-dependencies"></a></p>

<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🛠️ Usage</h2><a id="user-content-️-usage" aria-label="Permalink: 🛠️ Usage" href="#️-usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">1️⃣ Convert Your Game to a QR Code</h3><a id="user-content-1️⃣-convert-your-game-to-a-qr-code" aria-label="Permalink: 1️⃣ Convert Your Game to a QR Code" href="#1️⃣-convert-your-game-to-a-qr-code"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Run the script with the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python3 QRGEN.py <your-game.html> <output-qrcode.png>"><pre>python3 QRGEN.py <span>&lt;</span>your-game.html<span>&gt;</span> <span>&lt;</span>output-qrcode.png<span>&gt;</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Example:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python3 QRGEN.py EVEN-SMALLER-SLAMMER-BACKROOMS.html qrcode.png"><pre>python3 QRGEN.py EVEN-SMALLER-SLAMMER-BACKROOMS.html qrcode.png</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">2️⃣ Scan the QR Code</h3><a id="user-content-2️⃣-scan-the-qr-code" aria-label="Permalink: 2️⃣ Scan the QR Code" href="#2️⃣-scan-the-qr-code"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Use a smartphone or QR scanner to open the game directly in a web browser.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">3️⃣ Play Instantly 🎮</h3><a id="user-content-3️⃣-play-instantly-" aria-label="Permalink: 3️⃣ Play Instantly 🎮" href="#3️⃣-play-instantly-"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Enjoy <em>The Backdooms</em> without needing to download or install anything!</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🔍 Technical Breakdown</h2><a id="user-content--technical-breakdown" aria-label="Permalink: 🔍 Technical Breakdown" href="#-technical-breakdown"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Compression Workflow</h3><a id="user-content-compression-workflow" aria-label="Permalink: Compression Workflow" href="#compression-workflow"></a></p>
<section data-identity="4a077bf4-deaa-438f-a48b-a67a51b6075d" data-host="https://viewscreen.githubusercontent.com" data-src="https://viewscreen.githubusercontent.com/markdown/mermaid?docs_host=https%3A%2F%2Fdocs.github.com" data-type="mermaid" aria-label="mermaid rendered output container">
  <div dir="auto" data-json="{&quot;data&quot;:&quot;flowchart TD\n    A[Read Input HTML] --&amp;gt; B[Compress with Zlib]\n    B --&amp;gt;|wbits=15| C[Base64 Encode]\n    C --&amp;gt; D[Embed in HTML Wrapper]\n    \n    subgraph browser[Browser Processing]\n        D --&amp;gt; E[DecompressionStream 'gzip']\n        E --&amp;gt; F{Format Mismatch}\n    end\n    \n    F --&amp;gt; G[Convert to Data URI]\n    G --&amp;gt; H{Fits QR Code?}\n    H --&amp;gt;|Yes| I[Generate QR]\n    H --&amp;gt;|No| J[Reduce HTML Size]\n    J --&amp;gt; A\n&quot;}" data-plain="flowchart TD
    A[Read Input HTML] --> B[Compress with Zlib]
    B -->|wbits=15| C[Base64 Encode]
    C --> D[Embed in HTML Wrapper]
    
    subgraph browser[Browser Processing]
        D --> E[DecompressionStream 'gzip']
        E --> F{Format Mismatch}
    end
    
    F --> G[Convert to Data URI]
    G --> H{Fits QR Code?}
    H -->|Yes| I[Generate QR]
    H -->|No| J[Reduce HTML Size]
    J --> A
">
      <pre lang="mermaid" aria-label="Raw mermaid code">flowchart TD
    A[Read Input HTML] --&gt; B[Compress with Zlib]
    B --&gt;|wbits=15| C[Base64 Encode]
    C --&gt; D[Embed in HTML Wrapper]
    
    subgraph browser[Browser Processing]
        D --&gt; E[DecompressionStream 'gzip']
        E --&gt; F{Format Mismatch}
    end
    
    F --&gt; G[Convert to Data URI]
    G --&gt; H{Fits QR Code?}
    H --&gt;|Yes| I[Generate QR]
    H --&gt;|No| J[Reduce HTML Size]
    J --&gt; A
</pre>
    </div>
  <span role="presentation">
    <span data-view-component="true">
      <span>Loading</span>
</span>
  </span>
</section>

<p dir="auto"><strong>Read Input HTML:</strong> The process starts by reading the given HTML content from a file or input source.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Zlib Compression + GZip decompression:</strong> The HTML is compressed using Zlib and uses Decompressionstream from GZip for best compression</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Base64 Encoding:</strong> The compressed data is encoded in Base64, ensuring that it remains text-based and can be embedded in an HTML file safely.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Embedding in HTML Wrapper:</strong> A JavaScript-based self-extracting HTML wrapper is created. This wrapper includes a DecompressionStream API function that automatically decompresses the content when opened in a browser.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Data URI Conversion:</strong> The entire HTML is converted into a data:text/html;base64,... format, allowing it to be stored and shared easily without a physical file.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">QR Code Generation Logic</h3><a id="user-content-qr-code-generation-logic" aria-label="Permalink: QR Code Generation Logic" href="#qr-code-generation-logic"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The system first tries to generate the smallest possible QR version using qr.make(fit=True), which dynamically adjusts the QR size based on content length.</p>
<p dir="auto">If the required version exceeds 40 (the QR code standard limit), it forces version 40 with fit=False.</p>
<p dir="auto">The lowest error correction level L (which allows the maximum data capacity) is used to fit as much data as possible.</p>
<p dir="auto">If the data is still too large for QR v40 with level L, the process fails, and an error is returned.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Outcome</h3><a id="user-content-outcome" aria-label="Permalink: Outcome" href="#outcome"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If successful, a QR code is generated and displayed.</p>
<p dir="auto">If not, the process terminates with an error message indicating that the data is too large to be encoded in a QR code.</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Understand the Frustration and Trial and Error</h2><a id="user-content-understand-the-frustration-and-trial-and-error" aria-label="Permalink: Understand the Frustration and Trial and Error" href="#understand-the-frustration-and-trial-and-error"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Read about the development journey on my blog <a href="https://kuberwastaken.github.io/blog/Projects/How-I-Managed-To-Get-Doom-In-A-QR-Code" rel="nofollow">MindDump</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📜 License</h2><a id="user-content--license" aria-label="Permalink: 📜 License" href="#-license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is released under the <strong>MIT License</strong>—free to use, modify, and share.
It would make me EXTREMELY happy to see other QR games or even seeing better versions of DOOM in a QR code, given there's so little resources related to this</p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🙌 Credits</h2><a id="user-content--credits" aria-label="Permalink: 🙌 Credits" href="#-credits"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>id Software for Developing DOOM</li>
<li>matttkc for putting this idea in my head 5 years ago</li>
<li>Toby Fox for the amazing music in Undertale, this game's GitHub hosted version uses an 8 bit version of Bonetrousle</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Developed by <strong>Kuber Mehta</strong> :)</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A New ASN.1 API for Python (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.trailofbits.com/2025/04/18/sneak-peek-a-new-asn.1-api-for-python/</link>
            <guid>43728279</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 14:11:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.trailofbits.com/2025/04/18/sneak-peek-a-new-asn.1-api-for-python/">https://blog.trailofbits.com/2025/04/18/sneak-peek-a-new-asn.1-api-for-python/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43728279">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main role="main"><article><div><p>If you’ve ever worked with cryptography, PKI schemes, or low-level networking
in Python, you’ve likely encountered <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASN.1">ASN.1</a>.
ASN.1 undergirds every TLS handshake (via <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X.509">X.509</a> path validation),
provides the serialization layer for core internet protocols like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lightweight_Directory_Access_Protocol">LDAP</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simple_Network_Management_Protocol">SNMP</a>,
and <a href="https://www.3gpp.org/">3GPP</a>, and generally operates as the <em>lingua franca</em> of cryptographic
primitive and protocol representation.</p><p>ASN.1’s critical role is complemented by a colorful security history:
implementations of ASN.1’s encoding rules have historically been a
rich source of
<a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvekey.cgi?keyword=asn.1">memory corruption and denial-of-service vulnerabilities</a>. Similarly,
ASN.1’s presence at the lowest layers of the internet’s protocols
makes performance and a lack of <a href="https://langsec.org/">parser differentials</a> a critical requirement.</p><p>Python has multiple excellent ASN.1 implementations (like <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyasn1/">pyasn1</a>,
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/asn1/">asn1</a>, and
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/asn1tools/">asn1tools</a>), but these generally
fall into the latter category: being written purely in Python makes performance
a concern, and integration into a stack where other ASN.1 parsers are used
(e.g., at the X.509 layer) introduces a differential risk.</p><p>We’re changing that: with the help of funding from <a href="https://alpha-omega.dev/">Alpha-Omega</a>,
we’re building an ASN.1 API for <a href="https://cryptography.io/">PyCA Cryptography</a> that addresses
three key shortcomings in the Python ecosystem today:</p><ol><li><strong>Performance</strong>: This new API will use a <a href="https://github.com/alex/rust-asn1">pure Rust ASN.1 parser</a>,
giving us close-to-native parsing performance.</li><li><strong>Differential reduction</strong>: The parser mentioned above is already used
by <a href="https://cryptography.io/">PyCA Cryptography</a> for its X.509 APIs. This will reduce the need for
“mix and match” approaches to ASN.1 parsing, which in turn drive
differential vulnerabilities.</li><li><strong>Modernization</strong>: The new API will expose a declarative <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/dataclasses.html"><code>dataclasses</code></a>
style interface replete with type hints, making it familiar, idiomatic,
and compatible with type checkers.</li></ol><p>For example, an ASN.1 definition like this:</p><figure><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="asn.1"><span><span>Doohickies ::= SEQUENCE {
</span></span><span><span>    tschotchkes       OCTET STRING,
</span></span><span><span>    baubles           INTEGER,
</span></span><span><span>    knickknacks       UTF8String,
</span></span><span><span>    whatchamacallits  SEQUENCE OF OBJECT IDENTIFIER,
</span></span><span><span>    gizmos            SET OF GeneralizedTime OPTIONAL
</span></span><span><span>}</span></span></code></pre></figure><p>…will correspond to the following Python code:</p><figure><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="python"><span><span><span>from</span> <span>datetime</span> <span>import</span> <span>datetime</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>from</span> <span>cryptography.hazmat</span> <span>import</span> <span>asn1</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>@asn1.sequence</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>class</span> <span>Doohickies</span><span>:</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>tschotchkes</span><span>:</span> <span>bytes</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>baubles</span><span>:</span> <span>int</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>knickknacks</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>whatchamacallits</span><span>:</span> <span>list</span><span>[</span><span>asn1</span><span>.</span><span>ObjectIdentifier</span><span>]</span>
</span></span><span><span>    <span>gizmos</span><span>:</span> <span>set</span><span>[</span><span>datetime</span><span>]</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>doohickies</span> <span>=</span> <span>Doohickies</span><span>.</span><span>from_der</span><span>(</span><span>b</span><span>"..."</span><span>)</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>print</span><span>(</span><span>doohickies</span><span>.</span><span>tschotchkes</span><span>)</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>doohickies</span><span>.</span><span>to_der</span><span>()</span> <span># b"..."</span></span></span></code></pre></figure><p>This work is a logical continuation of our previous work on
<a href="https://blog.trailofbits.com/2024/01/25/we-build-x-509-chains-so-you-dont-have-to/">X.509 path validation</a>, as funded by the <a href="https://www.sovereign.tech/programs/fund">Sovereign Tech Fund</a>. It
reflects our ongoing commitment to improving the Python ecosystem, particularly
in the areas of cryptography and supply chain security.</p><p>Please <a href="mailto:ecosystem@trailofbits.com">get in touch</a> if you’re interested in learning more, or funding
similar work!</p><h2 id="some-quick-background-on-asn1">Some quick background on ASN.1</h2><p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/ASN.1">ASN.1</a>, or Abstract Syntax Notation One, is an <em>interface description language</em>
(IDL). That’s a fancy way of saying that it’s a syntax for describing
data structures in a language- and platform-agnostic manner.</p><p>Confusingly, ASN.1 is <strong>not itself</strong> a serialization format. Instead, it defines
<em>encoding rules</em>, which in turn define serialization and deserialization
of ASN.1 structures in different settings. In practice,
ASN.1 is synonymous<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> with the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X.690#DER_encoding">Distinguished Encoding Rules</a>, or DER.</p><figure><img src="https://blog.trailofbits.com/img/encoding-rules.png" alt="A helpful visual explanation of ASN.1’s different encoding rules"><figcaption>Figure 1: A helpful visual explanation of ASN.1's different encoding rules</figcaption></figure><p>We’ll treat “ASN.1” and “DER” as interchangeable for the purposes of this post.
Instead of delving too deeply into the intricacies of both
(<a href="https://letsencrypt.org/docs/a-warm-welcome-to-asn1-and-der/">Let’s Encrypt covers them excellently</a>), we’ll focus on the properties
of DER that have kept it relevant for decades:</p><ul><li><p><strong>DER is a <em>canonical</em> encoding:</strong> There’s only one way to encode a given ASN.1
structure in DER. In other words, the encoding of an ASN.1 structure in DER
is deterministic and can be round-tripped while preserving bit-for-bit
equality.</p></li><li><p><strong>DER is <em>relatively compact</em>:</strong> DER defines a binary format and, as a
consequence of being canonical, forbids non-minimal encodings of integers,
booleans, and times.</p></li><li><p><strong>DER is a <em>self-describing</em> and <em>self-delimiting</em> encoding:</strong> A given DER
message can be fully and soundly parsed without prior reference to a
schema or format description beyond the encoding rules of DER themselves.</p><p>These properties lend themselves naturally to what web developers would
call “progressive enhancement”: an application that consumes DER can
decode the specific structures it cares about while skipping the ones it
doesn’t, decoding only their length in order to jump ahead to the next one.</p></li><li><p><strong>DER supports <em>arbitrary-precision integers</em>:</strong> The <code>INTEGER</code> type in DER
is functionally unconstrained in size, which makes it suitable for
representing the kinds of large numbers that regularly appear in
cryptographic settings (e.g., primes).</p></li></ul><p>Put together, these properties make DER very popular in cryptographic,
networking, and telecommunications settings.</p><p>More precisely, it’s very popular in the guts of each of these settings:
ASN.1 is used to represent the X.509 certificates that secure the world’s TLS
traffic, is widely used with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Privacy-Enhanced_Mail#PEM_encoding">PEM-encoded</a> formats, and provides the
description and serialization for much of the internet’s lower protocol layers.</p><h2 id="motivating-an-asn1-library-for-python">Motivating an ASN.1 library for Python</h2><p>You might reasonably ask: why does Python need this?</p><p>After all, most Python developers aren’t touching ASN.1 on a daily basis, and
those that do are mostly doing so in predefined ways (such as X.509
certificates). Why does the ecosystem need <em>generic</em> support for ASN.1?</p><p>The answer to this is that, for better or worse, there are <em>many</em> situations
in which Python developers need to do ASN.1 encoding and decoding outside
of the “standard” shapes of X.509 and other well-known formats and protocols.</p><p>This can be seen in the <a href="https://sigstore.dev/">Sigstore</a> ecosystem: Sigstore is
<em>primarily</em> an ordinary <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc5280">RFC 5280</a>–style PKI, but it also includes some custom
<a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc5280#section-4.2">X.509 extensions</a> for its own purposes. For example, an excerpt
of a <a href="https://search.sigstore.dev/?logIndex=147137139">Sigstore log entry</a> shows the following extensions:</p><figure><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="plaintext"><span><span>OIDC Issuer: https://token.actions.githubusercontent.com
</span></span><span><span>Runner Environment: github-hosted
</span></span><span><span>Source Repository URI: https://github.com/pypa/sampleproject
</span></span><span><span>Source Repository Ref: refs/heads/main
</span></span><span><span>Source Repository Owner URI: https://github.com/pypa</span></span></code></pre></figure><p>If we want to consume these from Python (e.g., for the purposes of verifying
a Sigstore certificate against a policy), we need to extract them:</p><figure><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="python"><span><span><span>from</span> <span>cryptography</span> <span>import</span> <span>x509</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>raw_cert</span> <span>=</span> <span>b</span><span>"""
</span></span></span><span><span><span>-----BEGIN CERTIFICATE-----
</span></span></span><span><span><span>MIIGoTCCBiigAwIBAgITFai+PDKak1xA1HLq0mskqhDV5zAKBggqhkjOPQQDAzA3
</span></span></span><span><span><span>MRUwEwYDVQQKEwxzaWdzdG9yZS5kZXYxHjAcBgNVBAMTFXNpZ3N0b3JlLWludGVy
</span></span></span><span><span><span>bWVkaWF0ZTAeFw0yNDExMDYyMjM3MDdaFw0yNDExMDYyMjQ3MDdaMAAwWTATBgcq
</span></span></span><span><span><span>hkjOPQIBBggqhkjOPQMBBwNCAARbx1Fse2Ln00On5aFaL+lHNGFYLaqeKDduplZD
</span></span></span><span><span><span>PJS+w2PjYfNPL0g/n4sDWEQFZfyIExEWKulZ2GKNzAc0+SmUo4IFSDCCBUQwDgYD
</span></span></span><span><span><span>VR0PAQH/BAQDAgeAMBMGA1UdJQQMMAoGCCsGAQUFBwMDMB0GA1UdDgQWBBT/uSEI
</span></span></span><span><span><span>XmQzuRkppWXrTKVkfZFJbzAfBgNVHSMEGDAWgBTf0+nPViQRlvmo2OkoVaLGLhhk
</span></span></span><span><span><span>PzBhBgNVHREBAf8EVzBVhlNodHRwczovL2dpdGh1Yi5jb20vcHlwYS9zYW1wbGVw
</span></span></span><span><span><span>cm9qZWN0Ly5naXRodWIvd29ya2Zsb3dzL3JlbGVhc2UueW1sQHJlZnMvaGVhZHMv
</span></span></span><span><span><span>bWFpbjA5BgorBgEEAYO/MAEBBCtodHRwczovL3Rva2VuLmFjdGlvbnMuZ2l0aHVi
</span></span></span><span><span><span>dXNlcmNvbnRlbnQuY29tMBIGCisGAQQBg78wAQIEBHB1c2gwNgYKKwYBBAGDvzAB
</span></span></span><span><span><span>AwQoNjIxZTQ5NzRjYTI1Y2U1MzE3NzNkZWY1ODZiYTNlZDhlNzM2YjNmYzAVBgor
</span></span></span><span><span><span>BgEEAYO/MAEEBAdSZWxlYXNlMCAGCisGAQQBg78wAQUEEnB5cGEvc2FtcGxlcHJv
</span></span></span><span><span><span>amVjdDAdBgorBgEEAYO/MAEGBA9yZWZzL2hlYWRzL21haW4wOwYKKwYBBAGDvzAB
</span></span></span><span><span><span>CAQtDCtodHRwczovL3Rva2VuLmFjdGlvbnMuZ2l0aHVidXNlcmNvbnRlbnQuY29t
</span></span></span><span><span><span>MGMGCisGAQQBg78wAQkEVQxTaHR0cHM6Ly9naXRodWIuY29tL3B5cGEvc2FtcGxl
</span></span></span><span><span><span>cHJvamVjdC8uZ2l0aHViL3dvcmtmbG93cy9yZWxlYXNlLnltbEByZWZzL2hlYWRz
</span></span></span><span><span><span>L21haW4wOAYKKwYBBAGDvzABCgQqDCg2MjFlNDk3NGNhMjVjZTUzMTc3M2RlZjU4
</span></span></span><span><span><span>NmJhM2VkOGU3MzZiM2ZjMB0GCisGAQQBg78wAQsEDwwNZ2l0aHViLWhvc3RlZDA1
</span></span></span><span><span><span>BgorBgEEAYO/MAEMBCcMJWh0dHBzOi8vZ2l0aHViLmNvbS9weXBhL3NhbXBsZXBy
</span></span></span><span><span><span>b2plY3QwOAYKKwYBBAGDvzABDQQqDCg2MjFlNDk3NGNhMjVjZTUzMTc3M2RlZjU4
</span></span></span><span><span><span>NmJhM2VkOGU3MzZiM2ZjMB8GCisGAQQBg78wAQ4EEQwPcmVmcy9oZWFkcy9tYWlu
</span></span></span><span><span><span>MBgGCisGAQQBg78wAQ8ECgwIMTQ4OTk1OTYwJwYKKwYBBAGDvzABEAQZDBdodHRw
</span></span></span><span><span><span>czovL2dpdGh1Yi5jb20vcHlwYTAWBgorBgEEAYO/MAERBAgMBjY0NzAyNTBjBgor
</span></span></span><span><span><span>BgEEAYO/MAESBFUMU2h0dHBzOi8vZ2l0aHViLmNvbS9weXBhL3NhbXBsZXByb2pl
</span></span></span><span><span><span>Y3QvLmdpdGh1Yi93b3JrZmxvd3MvcmVsZWFzZS55bWxAcmVmcy9oZWFkcy9tYWlu
</span></span></span><span><span><span>MDgGCisGAQQBg78wARMEKgwoNjIxZTQ5NzRjYTI1Y2U1MzE3NzNkZWY1ODZiYTNl
</span></span></span><span><span><span>ZDhlNzM2YjNmYzAUBgorBgEEAYO/MAEUBAYMBHB1c2gwWQYKKwYBBAGDvzABFQRL
</span></span></span><span><span><span>DElodHRwczovL2dpdGh1Yi5jb20vcHlwYS9zYW1wbGVwcm9qZWN0L2FjdGlvbnMv
</span></span></span><span><span><span>cnVucy8xMTcxMzAzODk4MS9hdHRlbXB0cy8xMBYGCisGAQQBg78wARYECAwGcHVi
</span></span></span><span><span><span>bGljMIGKBgorBgEEAdZ5AgQCBHwEegB4AHYA3T0wasbHETJjGR4cmWc3AqJKXrje
</span></span></span><span><span><span>PK3/h4pygC8p7o4AAAGTA5/X5AAABAMARzBFAiA6nYK0GxqVzJutrjrYA1bAIKHU
</span></span></span><span><span><span>jGrsHMLrOJTTEUiERAIhAJZotATnSwlKt7C3Zwhx3fcSrhGfOakTlM2w+8qmltcj
</span></span></span><span><span><span>MAoGCCqGSM49BAMDA2cAMGQCMB+ilsPgy4ynUG9GtqDEBqW8+ZqjX6LpuxQqjCr7
</span></span></span><span><span><span>s4ytyt2ppFdgjrGrG1DY4nSZtQIwblrgq9t9izAMTkJeqhQBs2OUiyIJZipceD5v
</span></span></span><span><span><span>AAE/Nfgd/9uK0MZAHFsLgalqOBl8
</span></span></span><span><span><span>-----END CERTIFICATE-----
</span></span></span><span><span><span>"""</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>cert</span> <span>=</span> <span>x509</span><span>.</span><span>load_pem_x509_certificate</span><span>(</span><span>raw_cert</span><span>)</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span># 1.3.6.1.4.1.57264.1.16 corresponds to Source Repository Owner URI above</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>ext</span> <span>=</span> <span>cert</span><span>.</span><span>extensions</span><span>.</span><span>get_extension_for_oid</span><span>(</span><span>x509</span><span>.</span><span>ObjectIdentifier</span><span>(</span><span>"1.3.6.1.4.1.57264.1.16"</span><span>))</span><span>.</span><span>value</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>ext</span><span>.</span><span>value</span> <span># =&gt; b'\x0c\x17https://github.com/pypa'</span></span></span></code></pre></figure><p>As we can see, the X.509 extension’s value is <em>itself</em> DER encoded, and
PyCA Cryptography’s APIs (rightfully) leave it up to us to interpret
it<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p><p>So, we need <em>some</em> kind of DER parser. Luckily, Python is a mature ecosystem,
and we can avail ourselves of <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyasn1/"><code>pyasn1</code></a>:</p><figure><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="python"><span><span><span>from</span> <span>pyasn1.codec.der.decoder</span> <span>import</span> <span>decode</span>
</span></span><span><span><span>from</span> <span>pyasn1.type.char</span> <span>import</span> <span>UTF8String</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>ext_value</span> <span>=</span> <span>decode</span><span>(</span><span>ext</span><span>.</span><span>value</span><span>,</span> <span>UTF8String</span><span>)[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>decode</span><span>()</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>ext_value</span> <span># =&gt; 'https://github.com/pypa'</span></span></span></code></pre></figure><p>Now we have our inner extension value, and we can get on with our lives.</p><h2 id="but-why-a-_new_-library">But why a <em>new</em> library?</h2><p>But wait: if we have <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyasn1/"><code>pyasn1</code></a>, why do we need a <em>new</em> ASN.1 library?</p><p>The answer to this is threefold, and is <em>not</em> a knock against <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyasn1/"><code>pyasn1</code></a>
(which is an excellent library that performs its role admirably):</p><ol><li><p><strong>Performance</strong>: Python is not a fast language, and <a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyasn1/"><code>pyasn1</code></a> is written in
pure Python. The Python ecosystem has historically compensated for that by
putting performance-sensitive code in native extensions: at first C, but now
increasingly Rust. By leveraging <a href="https://github.com/alex/rust-asn1"><code>rust-asn1</code></a>, we can approach the
performance of native code without leaving the comforts of Python.</p></li><li><p><strong>Differential reduction</strong>: The ASN.1 ecosystem is notoriously
heterogenous, and implementations of ASN.1 vary widely in their conformance
to the strict requirements of DER.</p><p>In particular, many implementations have found it tempting to apply
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Robustness_principle">Postel’s Law</a> to the parsing of incoming “DER” data, allowing improperly
canonicalized or outright malformed data so long as the user’s intent
can be inferred. This has had a <a href="https://alexgaynor.net/2025/mar/25/postels-law-and-the-three-ring-circus/">deleterious effect</a> on both
protocol evolution and security: protocols struggle to evolve under the
pressure of unspecified behavior, and <a href="https://langsec.org/">parser differentials</a> are a
<a href="https://github.blog/security/sign-in-as-anyone-bypassing-saml-sso-authentication-with-parser-differentials/">consistent source</a> of major security incidents.</p><p>For this reason, reducing the number of independent parsers for a single
format in a given codebase is generally a sound engineering choice.
PyCA Cryptography is already built up around <a href="https://github.com/alex/rust-asn1"><code>rust-asn1</code></a>,
so it makes sense to use the exact same parsing routines in a new ASN.1
library.</p></li><li><p><strong>Modernization</strong>: <a href="https://docs.python.org/3/library/dataclasses.html"><code>dataclasses</code></a> and <code>dataclass</code>-style declarative APIs
have taken the Python ecosystem by storm, and for good reason: they’re
uniform, integrate cleanly with type checkers<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>, and define
types as <em>code</em> rather than as <em>data</em>.</p><p><a href="https://pypi.org/project/pyasn1/"><code>pyasn1</code></a> has a fantastic declarative API, but that API predates
the dataclass concept and therefore needs to mix code and data to define
its types. Modernizing this API would be at least as difficult
(in our estimation) as creating a new one from <a href="https://github.com/alex/rust-asn1"><code>rust-asn1</code></a> but without
the performance and differential reduction benefits.</p></li></ol><h2 id="stay-tuned-for-more">Stay tuned for more</h2><p>This is just a sneak peek; watch this space for updates!</p><p>We’re still early in the development process for this work; our plan is as
follows:</p><ul><li>Build an initial version with support for <code>@asn1.sequence</code> and <code>@asn1.enum</code>
as the main decorators, along with support for ASN.1’s basic types
and modifiers (e.g., <code>OPTIONAL</code>, <code>DEFAULT</code>, <code>IMPLICIT</code>, and <code>EXPLICIT</code>).</li><li>Integrate this version into PyCA Cryptography, tentatively as
<code>cryptography.asn1</code> or <code>cryptography.hazmat.asn1</code> or similar, then work
on deduplicating types where possible. For example, the
<code>cryptography.x509.ObjectIdentifier</code> type is already present and should
be shared or reused across both APIs.</li><li>Get it released with a major version of PyCA Cryptography!</li></ul><p>We’d like to thank <a href="https://alpha-omega.dev/">Alpha-Omega</a> for funding this work, as well as
the <a href="https://cryptography.io/">PyCA Cryptography</a> maintainers for their support and design review.</p></div></article></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Math Lesson From Hitler’s Germany (2017) (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://undark.org/2017/02/01/math-lesson-hitlers-germany/</link>
            <guid>43728130</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 13:55:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://undark.org/2017/02/01/math-lesson-hitlers-germany/">https://undark.org/2017/02/01/math-lesson-hitlers-germany/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43728130">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				
				<p><span>I</span><span>n 1934, David Hilbert</span>, by then a grand old man of German mathematics, was dining with Bernhard Rust, the Nazi minister of education. Rust asked, “How is mathematics at Göttingen, now that it is free from the Jewish influence?” Hilbert replied, “There is no mathematics in Göttingen anymore.”</p>
		<div>
																<p><img decoding="async" alt="" src="https://undark.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/hilbert.jpg"></p><div>
					<p>“There is no mathematics in Göttingen anymore”: the German math giant David Hilbert.</p><p><em>Visual: Shelby White and Leon Levy Archives Center, Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, NJ, USA.</em></p>				</div>
			</div>
		
<p>Or so the story goes. It is folklore at this point, a story mathematicians tell one another over coffee while exchanging knowing looks. The details vary in different retellings, but every version has Hilbert speaking this truth to power: Nazis destroyed mathematics at the University of Göttingen. “It’s one of the most well-known stories in the history of science,” says Reinhard Siegmund-Schultze, a math historian at the University of Agder in Norway. “Göttingen was so dominant in mathematics internationally.”</p>
<p>
<a href="http://www.ams.org/notices/199510/maclane.pdf">In 1933, that dominance came crashing down</a>. On April 7, two months after Hitler became chancellor, Germany <a href="https://www.ushmm.org/learn/timeline-of-events/1933-1938/law-for-the-restoration-of-the-professional-civil-service">passed a law</a> making it illegal for Jews — or rather those considered Jewish by the Nazis — and Communists to hold civil service jobs, with a few exceptions including for people who had served Germany in World War I. That immediately forced several Göttingen mathematicians from their jobs. The crisis snowballed, and over the course of the year, a total of 18 left or were driven out.</p>
<p>By the time of Hilbert’s legendary dinner with Rust, Germany had lost its status as the world’s foremost country for mathematical research. America took its place — and today, though globalization has spread the wealth, the U.S. has retained its eminence. From <a href="http://www-history.mcs.st-andrews.ac.uk/Biographies/Bochner.html">Princeton</a> and <a href="http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/history/Biographies/Bers.html">Columbia</a> to <a href="http://www-history.mcs.st-and.ac.uk/Biographies/Tarski.html">Berkeley</a> and <a href="http://www-history.mcs.st-and.ac.uk/Biographies/Szego.html">Stanford</a>, it’s hard to find a great math department in the United States that was not <a href="http://www.ams.org/samplings/math-history/hmath1-bers16.pdf">shaped in part by European mathematicians</a> who came to or stayed in the U.S. because of the Nazis.</p>
<p>As a new administration with a pronounced anti-science bent takes power in the United States, some scholars are recalling what happened at Göttingen as a cautionary tale. Donald Trump is not Hitler, of course, and “history doesn’t repeat,” as Siegmund-Schultze puts it. Still, he quickly adds, “One also knows from pain that mankind doesn’t really learn from history. Otherwise we wouldn’t do all the same foolish things all the time.”</p>
<p>American democracy is far stronger and longer-lived than was Germany’s between the wars. But we should take the similarities seriously. “I think what you see in both cases is this disaffection of the lower middle class,” says Julia Ault, an expert on German history at the University of Utah. “Part of their status rests on being better than someone else.” Lower-middle-class Germans in 1930 might have felt a loss of status if they perceived Jews to be advancing more quickly than they were. Ault sees a parallel to what some white people in rural America feel: They perceive immigrants as coming in and rising more quickly than they are.</p>
<p>Rather than a drastic Nazi-style crackdown on free speech, what is alarming many scholars today is the idea of a <a href="https://en.oxforddictionaries.com/word-of-the-year/word-of-the-year-2016">post-truth world</a>, in which <a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/meet-the-press/wh-spokesman-gave-alternative-facts-inauguration-crowd-n710466">evidence doesn’t matter</a> if a story reinforces your beliefs.</p>
<p>“In some sense every scholar is at risk,” says Robbert Dijkgraaf, the current director of the Institute for Advanced Study, which attracted many of the scientists and mathematicians who fled Göttingen and other German universities in the 1930s. “It’s not so much that people are persecuted because of their beliefs, but there is a certain trend where careful reasoning, the search for truth, all the delicacies of having a balanced point of view, acting on facts, being honest about what you do and don’t know, your uncertainty, all these values we have in science and scholarship are at risk.”</p>
<p>The dismissal of experts and the appeals to populism are dangerous, says Ault. “It’s going to be hugely devastating to the EPA, to climate science.” Trump, who <a href="http://www.vox.com/energy-and-environment/2017/1/18/14313126/trump-pruitt-climate-hoax-lukewarmism">has called climate change a Chinese hoax</a>, has asked for the names of scientists who study global warming. His transition team <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/news/energy-environment/wp/2016/12/14/trump-transition-says-request-for-names-of-climate-scientists-was-not-authorized/?utm_term=.73b3c602f5b6">backpedaled on the request</a>, but it was <a href="http://www.npr.org/sections/thetwo-way/2016/12/13/505440178/department-of-energy-defies-trump-wont-name-climate-change-workers">unsettling for employees</a> of the Department of Energy. More recently, it was reported that his administration <a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/news/politics/2017/01/24/trump-bans-epa-employees-from-updating-public-via-press-social-media/Anr90pkwhavC2kzK8pwsyK/story.html">issued</a> a temporary ban on external communication from the EPA and blocked the agency from awarding new grants or contracts. “It’s going to take most of our lifetimes to redo what’s going to get undone in the next four years,” Ault says. And for that reason, the political cataclysm that upended the mathematical world in the 1930s is no mere historical curiosity.</p>

		<div>
																									<div>
																																					<p><img decoding="auto" src="https://undark.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Weyl-portrait-reading.jpg"></p><p>
										Left, Hermann Weyl, Hilbert’s successor at Göttingen and one of the German émigrés who helped build the Institute for Advanced Study.
																					<em>Visual: Shelby White and Leon Levy Archives Center, Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, NJ, USA.</em>																			</p>
								
															</div>
																															<div>
																																					<p><img decoding="auto" src="https://undark.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/A-Flexner-B-color-300-dpi.jpg"></p><p>
										Right, Abraham Flexner, a founder and guiding spirit of the institute.
																					<em>Visual: Shelby White and Leon Levy Archives Center, Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, NJ, USA.</em>																			</p>
								
															</div>
															</div>

		
<p>Carl Friedrich Gauss, one of the greatest mathematicians of all time, helped establish Göttingen’s prominence in the early to mid-19th century. The tradition was continued by a legion of people whose names are sprinkled throughout calculus and physics textbooks today: Riemann, Dirichlet, Schwarz, Klein, Minkowski, Landau, Noether, and Hilbert, who had to a large extent set the mathematical research agenda of the 20th century with his <a href="http://aleph0.clarku.edu/~djoyce/hilbert/">1900 list of 23 unsolved problems</a> he thought mathematicians should devote themselves to in the new century. Richard Courant, who was part of the 1933 flood of mathematicians leaving Göttingen and for whom a <a href="http://cims.nyu.edu/about/history.html">New York University institute of mathematical sciences is now named</a>, helped secure funding from the Rockefeller Foundation for a new building to house the mathematics institute at Göttingen. It opened in 1929, and for the next few years, mathematics in Göttingen continued to thrive.</p>
<p>Providentially, the institution that would in many ways take Göttingen’s place — as a home not just for world-class mathematicians but for German Jewish ones — was being born at just that moment, in Princeton, New Jersey.</p>
<p>The Institute for Advanced Study, known to mathematicians and scientists simply as “the institute,” <a href="https://www.ias.edu/about/mission-history">was founded in 1930</a> by the Bamberger family, who had sold their department store to Macy’s shortly before the stock market crash in 1929 and had thus managed to prosper through the Great Depression. At the time, many American <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2005/10/10/getting-in">institutions of higher education were anti-Semitic</a>, and the Bambergers’ initial vision was to create a medical school that did not discriminate against Jews. Instead, Abraham Flexner, who had studied and written about medical and higher education, convinced them that an institute dedicated to basic research in mathematics and science was more important. He ended up joining them as a founder.</p>
<p>The institute opened in 1933 and was housed in Princeton University’s Fine Hall, home of its mathematics department, until the institute’s own facilities opened in 1939. (This has led to decades of <a href="https://www.ias.edu/about/faqs">confusion</a> about the institute’s relationship with Princeton. They are in the same town, but they have no formal affiliation.) The timing could not have been better for the German Jews whose jobs at home had been abolished. Flexner and the trustees decided, with the help of the Rockefeller Foundation, to create positions for exiled researchers at the institute.</p>
<p>It wasn’t an easy sell. American anti-Semitism was not the only issue; unemployment was high, and <a href="http://www.ams.org/samplings/math-history/hmath1-reingold13.pdf">some believed that</a> “every foreign scholar imported means an American out of a job,” as the MIT mathematics professor Norbert Wiener described it. He feared that “any appointment for more than a year would cause a feeling of resentment that would wreck our hopes of doing anything whatsoever.” Dijkgraaf, the IAS’s current director, says the institute had to walk a fine line. “All these efforts had to be done in a very subtle way,” he says. For one, each grant was fairly modest. But by getting a position at the institute, even a temporary one, a researcher “could at least get a visa and would have a foothold” as they worked to find jobs elsewhere in the U.S., says Dijkgraaf. “There was this joke that the institute was a little bit like an Ellis Island for these scholars at risk.”</p>
<p>In a 1939 report to the Institute for Advanced Study trustees, Flexner wrote, “Fifty years from now the historian looking backward will, if we act with courage and imagination, report that during our time the center of gravity in scholarship moved across the Atlantic to the United States.” And he was right. “In the end America profited hugely,” says Siegmund-Schultze, who adds that “many of these developments would have happened anyway even without the Nazis.” After all, America had more resources, the population was growing, and the nation was starting to replace private financing for the fundamental sciences with public financing — a large part of the reason the U.S. was able to retain its mathematical and scientific dominance after World War II. Nevertheless, America’s willingness to take in scholars fleeing the Nazis provided a boost to its rising scientific establishment and caused the balance of power to shift almost overnight.</p>
<p>“We now think of it as a given that the United States is a center of research and scholarship,” Dijkgraaf says. “It wasn’t at all in the 1930s. It was this brave act and this generosity that allowed this to happen.”</p>
<p>Albert Einstein is the most famous émigré scientist who ended up at the institute as a result of that generosity. Other luminaries included John von Neumann, a Hungarian mathematician, computer scientist, and physicist who worked on the Manhattan Project; Hermann Weyl, who had been Hilbert’s successor at Göttingen; and Kurt Gödel, who <a href="http://nautil.us/issue/2/uncertainty/the-deepest-uncertainty">changed the way mathematicians think about certainty</a>.</p>
<p>As that star-studded list suggests, taking in these refugees was not simply an act of generosity. Oswald Veblen, who had been influential in getting the institute to Princeton in the first place and had become one of the first scholars at the institute, “had a very clear vision that this was a win-win situation,” says Dijkgraaf. “He could help the refugees, but it was also a unique opportunity to strengthen mathematics in the United States.”</p>

		<div>
																																					<p><img decoding="auto" src="https://undark.org/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Neumann-MS-final-1.jpg"></p><p>
										John von Neumann, who worked at Göttingen in the 1920s, became a pillar of the Institute for Advanced Study. He annotated this manuscript for publication. (From the institute’s Box 35, File: von Neumann, John: Publication of Collected Works.)
																			</p>
								
															</div>

		
<p>Institutions are fragile. They are easier to destroy than build. A few months of Hitler’s policies unraveled two centuries of mathematical progress in Göttingen. That university, and Germany more broadly, never fully recovered. As von Neumann correctly <a href="https://global.britannica.com/biography/John-von-Neumann">predicted</a> in 1933, “If these boys continue for only two more years (which is unfortunately very probable) they will ruin German science for a generation — at least.”</p>
<p>America benefited hugely from the intellects of displaced mathematicians and scientists 80 years ago. And while America’s scientific institutions are not facing the same sudden existential threat Göttingen did in April 1933, their work and their scholars can still be seriously undercut by anti-science and anti-intellectual policies. It would be a tragic irony if American mathematics and science, which owe much of their status and success to the German prejudices of another era, were brought low by a kindred set of attitudes in this one.</p>
<p><em>Evelyn Lamb is a writer based in Salt Lake City. She taught mathematics and math history at the college level before leaving academia to pursue writing full time. She was AAAS mass media fellow at Scientific American in 2012 and has written for outlets including Scientific American, Nature News, the Smithsonian Magazine website, and Slate.</em></p>

							</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Less Slow C++ (179 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.cpp</link>
            <guid>43727743</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 13:09:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.cpp">https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.cpp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43727743">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Learning to Write <em>Less Slow</em> C, C++, and Assembly Code</h2><a id="user-content-learning-to-write-less-slow-c-c-and-assembly-code" aria-label="Permalink: Learning to Write Less Slow C, C++, and Assembly Code" href="#learning-to-write-less-slow-c-c-and-assembly-code"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">The benchmarks in this repository don't aim to cover every topic entirely, but they help form a mindset and intuition for performance-oriented software design.
It also provides an example of using some non-<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_Template_Library" rel="nofollow">STL</a> but de facto standard libraries in C++, importing them via CMake, and compiling from source.
For higher-level abstractions and languages, check out <a href="https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.rs"><code>less_slow.rs</code></a> and <a href="https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.py"><code>less_slow.py</code></a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Much modern code suffers from common pitfalls, such as bugs, security vulnerabilities, and <strong>performance bottlenecks</strong>.
University curricula often teach outdated concepts, while bootcamps oversimplify crucial software development principles.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/ashvardanian/ashvardanian/blob/master/repositories/less_slow.cpp.jpg?raw=true"><img src="https://github.com/ashvardanian/ashvardanian/raw/master/repositories/less_slow.cpp.jpg?raw=true" alt="Less Slow C++"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This repository offers practical examples of writing efficient C and C++ code.
It leverages C++20 features and is designed primarily for GCC and Clang compilers on Linux, though it may work on other platforms.
The topics range from basic micro-kernels executing in a few nanoseconds to more complex constructs involving parallel algorithms, coroutines, and polymorphism.
Some of the highlights include:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>100x cheaper random inputs?!</strong> Discover how input generation sometimes costs more than the algorithm.</li>
<li><strong>40x faster trigonometry:</strong> Speed-up standard library functions like <a href="https://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/numeric/math/sin" rel="nofollow"><code>std::sin</code></a> in just 3 lines of code.</li>
<li><strong>4x faster lazy-logic</strong> with custom <a href="https://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/ranges" rel="nofollow"><code>std::ranges</code></a> and iterators!</li>
<li><strong>Compiler optimizations beyond <code>-O3</code>:</strong> Learn about less obvious flags and techniques for another 2x speedup.</li>
<li><strong>Multiplying matrices?</strong> Check how a 3x3x3 GEMM can be 70% slower than 4x4x4, despite 60% fewer ops.</li>
<li><strong>Scaling AI?</strong> Measure the gap between theoretical <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arithmetic_logic_unit" rel="nofollow">ALU</a> throughput and your <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Basic_Linear_Algebra_Subprograms" rel="nofollow">BLAS</a>.</li>
<li><strong>How many if conditions are too many?</strong> Test your CPU's branch predictor with just 10 lines of code.</li>
<li><strong>Prefer recursion to iteration?</strong> Measure the depth at which your algorithm with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Segmentation_fault" rel="nofollow"><code>SEGFAULT</code></a>.</li>
<li><strong>Why avoid exceptions?</strong> Take <code>std::error_code</code> or <a href="https://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/utility/variant" rel="nofollow"><code>std::variant</code></a>-like wrappers?</li>
<li><strong>Scaling to many cores?</strong> Learn how to use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/OpenMP" rel="nofollow">OpenMP</a>, Intel's oneTBB, or your custom thread pool.</li>
<li><strong>How to handle <a href="https://www.json.org/json-en.html" rel="nofollow">JSON</a> avoiding memory allocations?</strong> Is it easier with C++ 20 or old-school C 99 tools?</li>
<li><strong>How to properly use STL's associative containers</strong> with custom keys and transparent comparators?</li>
<li><strong>How to beat a hand-written parser</strong> with <a href="https://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/language/consteval" rel="nofollow"><code>consteval</code></a> RegEx engines?</li>
<li><strong>Is the pointer size really 64 bits</strong> and how to exploit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tagged_pointer" rel="nofollow">pointer-tagging</a>?</li>
<li><strong>How many packets is <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ddos/glossary/user-datagram-protocol-udp/" rel="nofollow">UDP</a> dropping</strong> and how to serve web requests in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Io_uring" rel="nofollow"><code>io_uring</code></a> from user-space?</li>
<li><strong>Scatter and Gather</strong> for 50% faster vectorized disjoint memory operations.</li>
<li><strong>Intel's oneAPI vs Nvidia's CCCL?</strong> What's so special about <code>&lt;thrust&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;cub&gt;</code>?</li>
<li><strong>CUDA C++, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parallel_Thread_Execution" rel="nofollow">PTX</a> Intermediate Representations, and SASS</strong>, and how do they differ from CPU code?</li>
<li><strong>How to choose between intrinsics, inline <code>asm</code>, and separate <code>.S</code> files</strong> for your performance-critical code?</li>
<li><strong>Tensor Cores &amp; Memory</strong> differences on CPUs, and Volta, Ampere, Hopper, and Blackwell GPUs!</li>
<li><strong>How coding FPGA differs from GPU</strong> and what is High-Level Synthesis, Verilog, and VHDL? 🔜 #36</li>
<li><strong>What are Encrypted Enclaves</strong> and what's the latency of Intel SGX, AMD SEV, and ARM Realm? 🔜 #31</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To read, jump to the <a href="https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.cpp/blob/main/less_slow.cpp"><code>less_slow.cpp</code> source file</a> and read the code snippets and comments.
Follow the instructions below to run the code in your environment and compare it to the comments as you read through the source.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running the Benchmarks</h2><a id="user-content-running-the-benchmarks" aria-label="Permalink: Running the Benchmarks" href="#running-the-benchmarks"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The project aims to be compatible with GCC, Clang, and MSVC compilers on Linux, MacOS, and Windows.
That said, to cover the broadest functionality, using GCC on Linux is recommended:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>If you are on Windows, it's recommended that you set up a Linux environment using <a href="https://docs.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/wsl/install" rel="nofollow">WSL</a>.</li>
<li>If you are on MacOS, consider using the non-native distribution of Clang from <a href="https://brew.sh/" rel="nofollow">Homebrew</a> or <a href="https://www.macports.org/" rel="nofollow">MacPorts</a>.</li>
<li>If you are on Linux, make sure to install CMake and a recent version of GCC or Clang compilers to support C++20 features.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If you are familiar with C++ and want to review code and measurements as you read, you can clone the repository and execute the following commands.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.cpp.git # Clone the repository
cd less_slow.cpp                                            # Change the directory

pip install cmake --upgrade                                 # PyPI has a newer version of CMake
sudo apt-get install -y build-essential g++                 # Install default build tools
sudo apt-get install -y pkg-config liburing-dev             # Install liburing for kernel-bypass
sudo apt-get install -y libopenblas-base                    # Install numerics libraries

cmake -B build_release -D CMAKE_BUILD_TYPE=Release          # Generate the build files
cmake --build build_release --config Release                # Build the project
build_release/less_slow                                     # Run the benchmarks"><pre>git clone https://github.com/ashvardanian/less_slow.cpp.git <span><span>#</span> Clone the repository</span>
<span>cd</span> less_slow.cpp                                            <span><span>#</span> Change the directory</span>

pip install cmake --upgrade                                 <span><span>#</span> PyPI has a newer version of CMake</span>
sudo apt-get install -y build-essential g++                 <span><span>#</span> Install default build tools</span>
sudo apt-get install -y pkg-config liburing-dev             <span><span>#</span> Install liburing for kernel-bypass</span>
sudo apt-get install -y libopenblas-base                    <span><span>#</span> Install numerics libraries</span>

cmake -B build_release -D CMAKE_BUILD_TYPE=Release          <span><span>#</span> Generate the build files</span>
cmake --build build_release --config Release                <span><span>#</span> Build the project</span>
build_release/less_slow                                     <span><span>#</span> Run the benchmarks</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The build will pull and compile several third-party dependencies from the source:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Google's <a href="https://github.com/google/benchmark">Benchmark</a> is used for profiling.</li>
<li>Intel's <a href="https://github.com/uxlfoundation/oneTBB">oneTBB</a> is used as the Parallel STL backend.</li>
<li>Meta's <a href="https://github.com/facebookexperimental/libunifex">libunifex</a> is used for senders &amp; executors.</li>
<li>Eric Niebler's <a href="https://github.com/ericniebler/range-v3">range-v3</a> replaces <code>std::ranges</code>.</li>
<li>Victor Zverovich's <a href="https://github.com/fmtlib/fmt">fmt</a> replaces <code>std::format</code>.</li>
<li>Ash Vardanian's <a href="https://github.com/ashvardanian/stringzilla">StringZilla</a> replaces <code>std::string</code>.</li>
<li>Hana Dusíková's <a href="https://github.com/hanickadot/compile-time-regular-expressions">CTRE</a> replaces <code>std::regex</code>.</li>
<li>Niels Lohmann's <a href="https://github.com/nlohmann/json">json</a> is used for JSON deserialization.</li>
<li>Yaoyuan Guo's <a href="https://github.com/ibireme/yyjson">yyjson</a> for faster JSON processing.</li>
<li>Google's <a href="https://github.com/abseil/abseil-cpp">Abseil</a> replaces STL's associative containers.</li>
<li>Lewis Baker's <a href="https://github.com/lewissbaker/cppcoro">cppcoro</a> implements C++20 coroutines.</li>
<li>Jens Axboe's <a href="https://github.com/axboe/liburing">liburing</a> to simplify Linux kernel-bypass.</li>
<li>Chris Kohlhoff's <a href="https://github.com/chriskohlhoff/asio">ASIO</a> as a <a href="https://en.cppreference.com/w/cpp/experimental/networking" rel="nofollow">networking TS</a> extension.</li>
<li>Nvidia's <a href="https://github.com/nvidia/cccl">CCCL</a> for GPU-accelerated algorithms.</li>
<li>Nvidia's <a href="https://github.com/nvidia/cutlass">CUTLASS</a> for GPU-accelerated Linear Algebra.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To control the output or run specific benchmarks, use the following flags:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="build_release/less_slow --benchmark_format=json             # Output in JSON format
build_release/less_slow --benchmark_out=results.json        # Save the results to a file instead of `stdout`
build_release/less_slow --benchmark_filter=std_sort         # Run only benchmarks containing `std_sort` in their name"><pre>build_release/less_slow --benchmark_format=json             <span><span>#</span> Output in JSON format</span>
build_release/less_slow --benchmark_out=results.json        <span><span>#</span> Save the results to a file instead of `stdout`</span>
build_release/less_slow --benchmark_filter=std_sort         <span><span>#</span> Run only benchmarks containing `std_sort` in their name</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">To enhance stability and reproducibility, disable Simultaneous Multi-Threading <strong>(SMT)</strong> on your CPU and use the <code>--benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true</code> flag, which shuffles and interleaves benchmarks as described <a href="https://github.com/google/benchmark/blob/main/docs/random_interleaving.md">here</a>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="build_release/less_slow --benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true"><pre>build_release/less_slow --benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Google Benchmark supports <a href="https://github.com/google/benchmark/blob/main/docs/perf_counters.md">User-Requested Performance Counters</a> through <code>libpmf</code>.
Note that collecting these may require <code>sudo</code> privileges.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sudo build_release/less_slow --benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true --benchmark_format=json --benchmark_perf_counters=&quot;CYCLES,INSTRUCTIONS&quot;"><pre>sudo build_release/less_slow --benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true --benchmark_format=json --benchmark_perf_counters=<span><span>"</span>CYCLES,INSTRUCTIONS<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Alternatively, use the Linux <code>perf</code> tool for performance counter collection:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sudo perf stat taskset 0xEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFF build_release/less_slow --benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true --benchmark_filter=super_sort"><pre>sudo perf stat taskset 0xEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFFEFFF build_release/less_slow --benchmark_enable_random_interleaving=true --benchmark_filter=super_sort</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Project Structure</h2><a id="user-content-project-structure" aria-label="Permalink: Project Structure" href="#project-structure"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The primary file of this repository is clearly the <code>less_slow.cpp</code> C++ file with CPU-side code.
Several other files for different hardware-specific optimizations are created:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ tree .
.
├── CMakeLists.txt          # Build &amp; assembly instructions for all files
├── less_slow.cpp           # Primary CPU-side benchmarking code with the majority of examples
├── less_slow_amd64.S       # Hand-written Assembly kernels for 64-bit x86 CPUs
├── less_slow_aarch64.S     # Hand-written Assembly kernels for 64-bit Arm CPUs
├── less_slow.cu            # CUDA C++ examples for parallel algorithms for Nvidia GPUs
├── less_slow_sm70.ptx      # Hand-written PTX IR kernels for Nvidia Volta GPUs
└── less_slow_sm90a.ptx     # Hand-written PTX IR kernels for Nvidia Hopper GPUs"><pre>$ tree <span>.</span>
<span>.</span>
├── CMakeLists.txt          <span><span>#</span> Build &amp; assembly instructions for all files</span>
├── less_slow.cpp           <span><span>#</span> Primary CPU-side benchmarking code with the majority of examples</span>
├── less_slow_amd64.S       <span><span>#</span> Hand-written Assembly kernels for 64-bit x86 CPUs</span>
├── less_slow_aarch64.S     <span><span>#</span> Hand-written Assembly kernels for 64-bit Arm CPUs</span>
├── less_slow.cu            <span><span>#</span> CUDA C++ examples for parallel algorithms for Nvidia GPUs</span>
├── less_slow_sm70.ptx      <span><span>#</span> Hand-written PTX IR kernels for Nvidia Volta GPUs</span>
└── less_slow_sm90a.ptx     <span><span>#</span> Hand-written PTX IR kernels for Nvidia Hopper GPUs</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Memes and References</h2><a id="user-content-memes-and-references" aria-label="Permalink: Memes and References" href="#memes-and-references"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Educational content without memes?!
Come on!</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Google Benchmark Functionality</h2><a id="user-content-google-benchmark-functionality" aria-label="Permalink: Google Benchmark Functionality" href="#google-benchmark-functionality"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This benchmark suite uses most of the features provided by Google Benchmark.
If you write a lot of benchmarks and avoid going to the full <a href="https://github.com/google/benchmark/blob/main/docs/user_guide.md">User Guide</a>, here is a condensed list of the most useful features:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>-&gt;Args({x, y})</code> - Pass multiple arguments to parameterized benchmarks</li>
<li><code>BENCHMARK()</code> - Register a basic benchmark function</li>
<li><code>BENCHMARK_CAPTURE()</code> - Create variants of benchmarks with different captured values</li>
<li><code>Counter::kAvgThreads</code> - Specify thread-averaged counters</li>
<li><code>DoNotOptimize()</code> - Prevent compiler from optimizing away operations</li>
<li><code>ClobberMemory()</code> - Force memory synchronization</li>
<li><code>-&gt;Complexity(oNLogN)</code> - Specify and validate algorithmic complexity</li>
<li><code>-&gt;SetComplexityN(n)</code> - Set input size for complexity calculations</li>
<li><code>-&gt;ComputeStatistics("max", ...)</code> - Calculate custom statistics across runs</li>
<li><code>-&gt;Iterations(n)</code> - Control exact number of iterations</li>
<li><code>-&gt;MinTime(n)</code> - Set minimum benchmark duration</li>
<li><code>-&gt;MinWarmUpTime(n)</code> - To warm up the data caches</li>
<li><code>-&gt;Name("...")</code> - Assign custom benchmark names</li>
<li><code>-&gt;Range(start, end)</code> - Profile for a range of input sizes</li>
<li><code>-&gt;RangeMultiplier(n)</code> - Set multiplier between range values</li>
<li><code>-&gt;ReportAggregatesOnly()</code> - Show only aggregated statistics</li>
<li><code>state.counters["name"]</code> - Create custom performance counters</li>
<li><code>state.PauseTiming()</code>, <code>ResumeTiming()</code> - Control timing measurement</li>
<li><code>state.SetBytesProcessed(n)</code> - Record number of bytes processed</li>
<li><code>state.SkipWithError()</code> - Skip benchmark with error message</li>
<li><code>-&gt;Threads(n)</code> - Run benchmark with specified number of threads</li>
<li><code>-&gt;Unit(kMicrosecond)</code> - Set time unit for reporting</li>
<li><code>-&gt;UseRealTime()</code> - Measure real time instead of CPU time</li>
<li><code>-&gt;UseManualTime()</code> - To feed custom timings for GPU and IO benchmarks</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[IBM orders US sales to locate near customers, RTO for cloud staff, DEI purge (195 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/18/ibm_orders_us_sales_staff/</link>
            <guid>43727727</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 13:08:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/18/ibm_orders_us_sales_staff/">https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/18/ibm_orders_us_sales_staff/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43727727">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p><span>Exclusive</span> IBM, which employees wryly or ruefully say stands for I've Been Moved, is once again moving its employees.</p>
<p>On Tuesday, Big Blue shared new rules on where it expects its US sales staff to work: At least three days a week at a client, a flagship office, or a sales hub.</p>
<p>And the mainframe giant last week told all US Cloud employees, sales or otherwise, to return to the office at least three days per week at designated "strategic" locations.</p>

    

<p>Several current and former IBM employees who have spoken to <em>The Register</em> about IBM's work directives argue that these policies represent stealth layoffs because older (and presumably more highly compensated) employees tend to be less willing to uproot their lives, and families where applicable, than the "early professional hires" IBM has been courting <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2022/02/14/ibm_age_discrimination_court_documents/">at some legal risk</a>.</p>
<h3>US sales RTO – sorry, RTC</h3>
<p>In a staff memo seen by <em>The Register</em>, Adam Lawrence, general manager for IBM Americas, billed the return-to-office for most stateside sales personnel as a "return to client initiative."</p>
<p>Citing how "remarkable it is when our teams work side by side" at IBM's swanky Manhattan flagship office, <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://newsroom.ibm.com/2024-09-06-ibm-unveils-new-flagship-office-at-one-madison-avenue-in-new-york-city">unveiled</a> in September 2024, Lawrence added IBM is investing in an Austin, Texas, office to be occupied in 2026.</p>

        


        

<p>Whether US sales staff end up working in NYC, Austin, or some other authorized location, Lawrence told them to brace for – deep breath – IBM's "new model" of "effective talent acquisition, deployment, and career progression." We're told that model is "centered on client proximity for those dedicated to specific clients, and anchored on core IBM locations for those dedicated to territories or those in above-market leadership roles."</p>
<p>The program requires most IBM US sales staff "to work at least three days a week from the client location where their assigned territory decision-makers work, a flagship office, or a sales hub." Those residing more than 50 miles from their assigned location will be offered relocation benefits to move. Sales hubs are an option only for those with more than one dedicated account.</p>

        

<p>IBM presently has five flagship offices for this purpose, one of each in: New York, Austin, Raleigh, Washington DC, and the San Francisco Bay Area. It also has eight sales hubs: Atlanta, Georgia; Boston, Massachusetts; Charlotte, North Carolina; Chicago, Illinois; Columbus, Ohio; Dallas, Texas; Los Angeles, California; and Seattle, Washington. Additional sales hubs may be added later.</p>
<p>Lawrence said Dallas-based workers involved with the Digital Sales center at that location will be moved to Austin in 2026.</p>
<p>The "return to client initiative" applies to sales people associated with US Enterprise, Strategic, and Horizon clients' sites. Those serving US National market territories, Canada, Latin America, US Federal markets, Technology Expert Labs Delivery, Web Methods, and Software Migration Project Office sellers are exempt.</p>

        

<p>By early May, managers are expected to discuss arrangements with team members; team member colocation decisions are due by early June.</p>
<p>As we <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/02/20/ibm_colocation_program_described_as/">reported</a> in February, IBM in 2024 began rolling out a co-location/return to office plan that started with managers and has now reached the corporation's broader workforce. Co-location expands on return to office directives by insisting that teams operate out of the same location – it's not enough to work out of any IBM office – and by requiring some workers who have never worked from an office to begin doing so.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/11/ibm_shareholders_asked_to_back/">IBM shareholders asked to back greater lobbying transparency</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/04/04/appeals_court_revives_ibm_lawsuit/">Appeals court revives lawsuit alleging IBM bilked pensioners</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/03/27/ibm_cuts_jobs_in_us/">IBM US cuts may run deeper than feared ‒ and the jobs are heading to India</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/03/20/ibm_cuts_us_jobs/">It looks like IBM is cutting jobs again, with Classic Cloud hit hard</a></li>
</ul>
<h3>US Cloud RTO and India</h3>
<p>IBM's office policy change reached US Cloud employees in an April 10 memo from Alan Peacock, general manager of IBM Cloud. Peacock set a July 1, 2025, deadline for US Cloud employees to work from an office at least three days per week, with relocating workers given until October 1, 2025.</p>
<p>The employee shuffling has been accompanied by <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/03/27/ibm_cuts_jobs_in_us/">rolling layoffs</a> in the US, but hiring in India – there are at least 10x as many open IBM jobs in India as there are in any other IBM location, according to the corporation's <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.ibm.com/careers/search">career listings</a>. And earlier this week, IBM <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/ibm_lucknowopeningteaser1920x1080mp4-activity-7317418941553733632-FbUr">said</a> it "is setting up a new software lab in Lucknow," India.</p>
<h3>DEI'ing inside</h3>
<p>This push to hire ever more in India is perhaps what IBM chief human resources officer Nickle LaMoreaux meant in a de-DEI memo earlier this month that equated inclusion with talent acquisition while deemphasizing diversity and equity, the two other elements of DEI.</p>
<p>Citing differing opinions about DEI programs and the need to be compliant "with all applicable laws, executive orders and government policies – even as they shift," LaMoreaux insisted that IBM's broad commitment to inclusion – which dates back to 1954 when chairman Thomas Watson Jr penned IBM Policy Letter #4 – has not changed.</p>
<p>But, she added, "practices are ever evolving" – as if efforts to hire underrepresented groups wax and wane like phases of the moon, outside of corporate control, rather than being deliberate executive-driven directives.</p>
<p>The opinion shaping IBM's realignment appears to be that of President Trump, who on January 20, announced an <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/01/ending-radical-and-wasteful-government-dei-programs-and-preferencing/">executive order</a> titled: "Ending radical and wasteful government DEI programs and preferencing." The order seeks to remove DEI considerations from the federal government, though it's not a done deal. Earlier this week, a federal judge <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-dei-chicago-women-diversity-f3c9773c8f8cb39f70b1250e80704789">blocked</a> the US Department of Labor from requiring that government contractors – like IBM – certify that they don't operate any DEI programs.</p>
<p>Whatever the outcome of that legal battle, the evolution described by LaMoreaux has already brought change.</p>
<p>"As a result, we have adjusted some of our programs and our communications over the past few months," explained LaMoreaux.</p>
<p>"For example, aspirational diversity goals are no longer part of the executive incentive program, which is instead focused on talent and innovation measures. You may also notice changes to our website designed to attract the most qualified talent pool, and to eliminate outdated content and terminology."</p>
<p>These website changes can be seen, for example, in the disappearance of a <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://web.archive.org/web/20241104025317/https://www.ibm.com/blogs/nordic-msp/i-pledge-to-be-equal/">March 25, 2019 blog post</a> that at least until November 4, 2024 – one day before the US Presidential election – appeared at <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.ibm.com/blogs/nordic-msp/i-pledge-to-be-equal/">this URL</a>.</p>
<p>The post began, "IBM has a continued commitment to diversity and inclusion. A decade before the Civil Rights Act, IBM’s chairman wrote Policy Letter #4 – history’s first corporate mandate on equal employment, for everyone."</p>
<p>IBM did not respond to a request for comment. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Walled Gardens Can Kill (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aneesiqbal.ai/2025-04-18-walled-gardens-can-kill</link>
            <guid>43726672</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 10:27:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aneesiqbal.ai/2025-04-18-walled-gardens-can-kill">https://aneesiqbal.ai/2025-04-18-walled-gardens-can-kill</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43726672">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I'm an Apple ecosystem user, owning an iPhone ever since a past employer got it for me to test our company app some 8 years ago. Over time, as I've upgraded, I've also incrementally moved over my family to the ecosystem, replacing our hp/dell laptops with macbooks and Samsung Galaxy phones with Apple iPhones.</p>
<p>Apple's application ecosystem is pretty famously locked down. You cannot side load applications onto your iPhone, quite as easily as you can with an Android. There has been some legislative push to change this (with the EU enacting the Digital Markets Acts or DMA) but the sentiments among lawmakers and users are still divided.</p>
<p>I didn't feel strongly about this, one way or the other until the experiences of last week. My wife suddenly fell ill and we had to figure out which hospital to go to, we were ill-prepared for this situation as we hadn't installed the insurance providers' application to check the in-network hospitals.</p>
<p>Unfortunately for us, the insurance app is geo-restricted to United Arab Emirates (UAE) and Apple refused to install it on my phone. Normally this would be a simple problem to fix, just go to your Apple account settings and switch the region, but this too was denied, as I had the yearly Apple Music subscription. Changing the region in this case required calling Apple Support to cancel the yearly Apple Music subscription first, and we didn't have the time for this.</p>
<p>Luckily I was prototyping with the idea of an Android Application the past week so I had the Android Emulator in my laptop, which I used to install the application, add our insurance information and figure out where to go. Just to be safe, I also ordered an Android phone to be delivered to me while I went to the hospital, where I used my iPhone's hotspot to set it up and show all the insurance information to the hospital staff.</p>
<p>Had I not prototyped the Android Application the week prior, or had Android similarly locked down their ecosystem, we would've been in a much worse situation. This experience has significantly changed my opinions on the matter, I now carry a spare Android phone at home with all the insurance information loaded <em>just in case</em>.</p>
<p>Walled Gardens can kill. I hope Apple, the lawmakers and users will reconsider their stance and consider a worldwide DMA-like law to prevent others from falling down the same path.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[arXiv moving from Cornell servers to Google Cloud (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://info.arxiv.org/hiring/index.html</link>
            <guid>43726640</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 10:21:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://info.arxiv.org/hiring/index.html">https://info.arxiv.org/hiring/index.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43726640">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-md-component="container">
      
      
        
          
        
      
      <main data-md-component="main">
        <div data-md-component="content">
              <article>
                
                  

  <a href="https://github.com/arXiv/arxiv-docs/blob/develop/source/hiring/index.md" title="Edit this page">
    
    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path d="M20.71 7.04c.39-.39.39-1.04 0-1.41l-2.34-2.34c-.37-.39-1.02-.39-1.41 0l-1.84 1.83 3.75 3.75M3 17.25V21h3.75L17.81 9.93l-3.75-3.75L3 17.25Z"></path></svg>
  </a>



<p>arXiv is part of Cornell Tech, the graduate campus and research center of Cornell University. All arXiv employees are Cornell University employees.</p>
<ul>
<li>Positions at arXiv are <a href="https://hr.cornell.edu/understand-your-benefits">staff positions with benefits (endowed)</a>.</li>
<li>Visa sponsorship is not available. You must already possess the legal right to work in the US.</li>
<li>arXiv is headquartered at the <a href="https://tech.cornell.edu/">Cornell Tech campus on Roosevelt Island in New York City</a>. When hiring, there is a strong preference for candidates who can report to work at that location, but hybrid and/or remote work may be an option.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="software-development">Software development</h2>
<p>We are already underway on the arXiv CE ("Cloud Edition") project. This is a project to re-home all arXiv services from VMs at Cornell to a cloud provider (<a href="https://cloud.google.com/">Google Cloud</a>). There are a number of reasons for this transition, including improving arXiv's scalability while modernizing our infrastructure. This will not be a simple port of the existing arXiv code base because this project will:</p>
<ul>
<li>replace the portion of our backends still written in perl and PHP</li>
<li>re-architect our article processing to be fully asynchronous, and provide better insight into the processing workflows</li>
<li>containerize all, or nearly all arXiv services so we can deploy via Kubernetes or services like <a href="https://cloud.google.com/run/">Google Cloud Run</a></li>
<li>improve our monitoring and logging facilities so we can more quickly identify and manage production issues with arxiv.org</li>
<li>create a robust CI/CD pipeline to give us more confidence that changes we deploy will not cause services to regress</li>
</ul>
<p>The cloud transition is a pre-requisite to modernizing arXiv as a service. The modernization will enable:
 - arXiv to expand the subject areas that we cover
 - improve the metadata we collect and make available for articles, adding fields that the research community has requested such as funder identification
 - deal with the problem of ambiguous author identities
 - improve accessibility to support users with impairments, particularly visual impairments
 - improve usability for the entire arXiv community</p>
<p>We have three SWE openings, one general and two specialized</p>
<h3 id="software-engineer">Software Engineer</h3>
<p>This person should be a software generalist, who can work in a variety of environments, programming languages, frontend and backend. Should have web development and SQL experience.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cornell.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/CornellCareerPage/?q=arxiv">Software Engineer IV</a> (Software Engineer)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="devops-specialist">DevOps Specialist</h3>
<p>We are looking for a developer with Cloud DevOps experience to lead the effort of modernizing our devops system so we can efficiently, reliably, and securely deploy new code, using Infrastructure as code principles. This task will likely involve a fair amount of automation via <a href="https://github.com/readme/featured/defining-gitops">gitops</a>, as well as Google Cloud Platform tools. The devops lead will also put in place a robust CI/CD pipeline, and may also be asked to help fill in test cases.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cornell.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/CornellCareerPage/?q=arxiv">DevOps Software Engineer</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="scientistsoftware-developer">Scientist/Software Developer</h3>
<p>We're looking for someone with serious software development skills who has also used arXiv for scientific research, and preferably someone who has authored arXiv submissions. We expect this person to represent and be an advocate for the interests of all scientists, within the arXiv software development team (no pressure!). We believe there are lots of you scientists-turned-software-developers out there. Please apply!</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cornell.wd1.myworkdayjobs.com/en-US/CornellCareerPage/?q=arxiv">Software Engineer Scientist</a></li>
</ul>





                
              </article>
            </div>
        
      </main>
      






    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Deafening Silence from the Cybersecurity Industry (307 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.forbes.com/sites/tonybradley/2025/04/16/deafening-silence-from-the-cybersecurity-industry/</link>
            <guid>43726548</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 10:01:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/tonybradley/2025/04/16/deafening-silence-from-the-cybersecurity-industry/">https://www.forbes.com/sites/tonybradley/2025/04/16/deafening-silence-from-the-cybersecurity-industry/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43726548">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><figure role="presentation"><figcaption><fbs-accordion classname="expandable" current="-1"><p role="button">Chris Krebs, former CISA Director, became a symbol of truth in cybersecurity after affirming the <span data-ga-track="caption expand">... More</span><span> integrity of the 2020 election—and paying the price for it.</span></p></fbs-accordion><small>Getty Images</small></figcaption></figure>
<p>In the world of cybersecurity, where truth is paramount and trust is everything, silence can be louder than an alarm.</p>

<p>When President Trump issed an <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/fact-sheets/2025/04/fact-sheet-president-donald-j-trump-addresses-risks-from-chris-krebs-and-government-censorship/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.whitehouse.gov/fact-sheets/2025/04/fact-sheet-president-donald-j-trump-addresses-risks-from-chris-krebs-and-government-censorship/" aria-label="Executive Order targeting Chris Krebs">Executive Order targeting Chris Krebs</a>—a respected cybersecurity leader and the first director of the Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency—the cybersecurity industry should have responded with a unified voice of outrage and support. But instead, it largely whispered… or worse, said nothing at all.</p>


<p>This moment is not just about Krebs. It’s a constitutional stress test. A moral gut check. And the cybersecurity industry is failing it.</p>

<h2>What Happened in 2020?</h2>
<p>Chris Krebs isn’t a political agitator. His role and actions in 2020 were not partisan. He was Trump’s own appointee to lead CISA, the agency charged with protecting the nation’s critical infrastructure, including elections. In the run-up to the 2020 presidential election, Krebs and his team worked tirelessly with state and local election officials to safeguard systems against foreign interference and domestic cyber threats.</p>

<p>When the votes were counted and no credible evidence of widespread fraud emerged—despite a tidal wave of disinformation—CISA issued a joint statement declaring the 2020 election “the most secure in American history.” Over 60 lawsuits attempting to challenge the results were dismissed across the country—primarily due to a complete lack of evidence to support the claims. Many of those decisions came from Republican-appointed judges. The facts were clear.</p>

<p>But truth has become a political liability.</p>
<p>For doing his job—and doing it well—<a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/alisondurkee/2020/12/16/ex-election-security-chief-chris-krebs-says-gop-refusal-to-concede-election-corrosive-to-democracy/" data-ga-track="InternalLink:https://www.forbes.com/sites/alisondurkee/2020/12/16/ex-election-security-chief-chris-krebs-says-gop-refusal-to-concede-election-corrosive-to-democracy/" target="_self" aria-label="Krebs was fired via tweet">Krebs was fired via tweet</a>. And now, years later, he has been further targeted by an Executive Order that effectively seeks to blacklist him, his employer, and his professional associates. The message is unmistakable: disloyalty to the narrative will be punished.</p>
<h2>Is the Executive Order Even Legal?</h2>
<p>The Executive Order targeting Chris Krebs is not just a political stunt—it raises serious constitutional red flags.</p>
<p>At its core, it punishes a private citizen for protected speech, which violates the First Amendment. Krebs was fired from his role at CISA for publicly affirming that the 2020 election was secure—an assessment backed by dozens of court rulings and independent audits. Now, years later, he’s the subject of an order that calls for a federal investigation and labels him a “bad-faith actor” for doing his job.</p>


<p>According to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/petra-molnar/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.linkedin.com/in/petra-molnar/" aria-label="Petra Molnar">Petra Molnar</a>, a professor and author of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Walls-Have-Eyes-Artificial-Intelligence/dp/1620978369" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.amazon.com/Walls-Have-Eyes-Artificial-Intelligence/dp/1620978369" aria-label="The Walls Have Eyes: Surviving Migration in the Age of Artificial Intelligence"><em data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.amazon.com/Walls-Have-Eyes-Artificial-Intelligence/dp/1620978369">The Walls Have Eyes: Surviving Migration in the Age of Artificial Intelligence</em></a>, “targeting former officials perceived to be in opposition to the current administration is not constitutional.” She adds that the Executive Order “undermines the crucial separation of powers between the President’s Executive Office, the Legislative Branch, and the Justice Department.”</p>
<p>This is more than overreach—it’s retaliatory use of executive authority without legal basis. And while politically motivated targeting isn’t new, Molnar notes that what’s unprecedented is “the escalation of retribution campaigns against individuals perceived to be against the goals of the Trump Administration.”</p>

<p>The Constitution explicitly forbids Congress from issuing bills of attainder—laws that single out individuals for punishment without trial. While that restriction technically applies to the Legislative branch, the spirit of it clearly applies here. A president cannot simply declare someone an enemy of the state for contradicting a political narrative. That’s not national security—it’s authoritarianism, dressed up in executive language.</p>


<h2>The Cybersecurity Community’s Deafening Silence</h2>
<p>You’d think an industry built around defending truth, integrity, and the sanctity of systems would rally around one of its own. There are admittedly a few brave voices—like <a href="https://www.lutasecurity.com/post/in-support-of-chris-krebs-and-sentinelone" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.lutasecurity.com/post/in-support-of-chris-krebs-and-sentinelone" aria-label="Katie Moussouris of Luta Security">Katie Moussouris of Luta Security</a>, cybersecurity <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/04/trump-revenge-tour-targets-cyber-leaders-elections/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://krebsonsecurity.com/2025/04/trump-revenge-tour-targets-cyber-leaders-elections/" aria-label="journalist Brian Krebs">journalist Brian Krebs</a> (no relation to Chris Krebs), and a smattering of others. <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/stiennon/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.linkedin.com/in/stiennon/" aria-label="Richard Stiennon">Richard Stiennon</a>, chief research analyst with IT-Harvest and author of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Security-Yearbook-2025-Directory-Industry/dp/1394334869/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2YLKQQYOAUHCS&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.Ko80BjneOX-ZZje5tYrhsm8iCepxsA1O-dWS_7maDcLHuVMNUZqMN-0ojE_4iZGLhG5WJoUZICgdZs195U1Sv8pYxIN7cd0Mrb8Z6FzlKtw.Y5KSekwfxnoCynGjW8QKb4OLgHP-GD7Mw1lp35K0T_M&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=security+yearbook+2025&amp;qid=1744817521&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=security+yearbook+2025%2Cstripbooks%2C138&amp;sr=1-1" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.amazon.com/Security-Yearbook-2025-Directory-Industry/dp/1394334869/ref=sr_1_1?crid=2YLKQQYOAUHCS&amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.Ko80BjneOX-ZZje5tYrhsm8iCepxsA1O-dWS_7maDcLHuVMNUZqMN-0ojE_4iZGLhG5WJoUZICgdZs195U1Sv8pYxIN7cd0Mrb8Z6FzlKtw.Y5KSekwfxnoCynGjW8QKb4OLgHP-GD7Mw1lp35K0T_M&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;keywords=security+yearbook+2025&amp;qid=1744817521&amp;s=books&amp;sprefix=security+yearbook+2025%2Cstripbooks%2C138&amp;sr=1-1" aria-label="Security Yearbook 2025">Security Yearbook 2025</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/stiennon_donald-trump-signs-executive-orders-activity-7315892854743044098-IwVi/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.linkedin.com/posts/stiennon_donald-trump-signs-executive-orders-activity-7315892854743044098-IwVi/" aria-label="shared a video">shared a video</a> of Trump signing the Executive Order on LinkedIn with the statement, “This abhorrent president lashing out at those that served the country is sickening.”</p>
<p>In general, however, the cybersecurity industry has largely stayed quiet. In fact, many sources I reached out to refused to comment on the record for this story.</p>
<p>No public statements from RSAC conference organizers. No press releases from leading vendors. No formal pushback from industry alliances. It's not just disappointing—it’s damning.</p>
<p>This is not how you defend your values.</p>
<p>Many organizations seem to believe they can sidestep this conflict by remaining neutral. But neutrality in the face of injustice is a choice—it’s a choice to appease. And appeasement doesn’t work. Just ask Neville Chamberlain.</p>
<h2>The Illusion of Safety Through Silence</h2>
<p>We’ve seen this play out in other sectors. Columbia University has faced intense scrutiny and backlash not for what it said, but for what it failed to say—and <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoniopequenoiv/2025/03/21/columbia-agrees-to-trump-administrations-demands-after-losing-400-million-in-federal-funds/" data-ga-track="InternalLink:https://www.forbes.com/sites/antoniopequenoiv/2025/03/21/columbia-agrees-to-trump-administrations-demands-after-losing-400-million-in-federal-funds/" target="_self" aria-label="the compromises it made">the compromises it made</a> to stay in the good graces of political power. Paul Weiss, once a symbol of legal prestige, has <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/mariagraciasantillanalinares/2025/03/26/why-lawyers-are-standing-up-to-big-law/" data-ga-track="InternalLink:https://www.forbes.com/sites/mariagraciasantillanalinares/2025/03/26/why-lawyers-are-standing-up-to-big-law/" target="_self" aria-label="come under fire for pulling away">come under fire for pulling away</a> from defending academic clients under political pressure.</p>
<p>Contrast that with Harvard University, which has rejected demands from the Trump administration and <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/04/harvard-chooses-defiance/682457/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer" data-ga-track="ExternalLink:https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2025/04/harvard-chooses-defiance/682457/" aria-label="publicly defended democratic norms">publicly defended democratic norms</a>. Or Perkins Coie, the law firm that continues to represent election officials and fight disinformation, even under threat.</p>
<p>Where are the Harvard Universities and Perkins Coie law firms of the cybersecurity world?</p>
<p>The Krebs case is a crucible. It reveals who is willing to stand for principle—and who is hoping the storm passes them by. But that’s not how this works. You don’t avoid authoritarianism by looking the other way. You feed it. You enable it.</p>
<h2>“First They Came…”</h2>
<p>We all know Niemöller’s haunting poem:</p>
<p><em>“First they came for the socialists, and I did not speak out—because I was not a socialist...”</em></p>
<p>It has become the go-to cautionary tale for the dangers of silence in the face of rising authoritarianism. And yet, here we are—living it in real time—and most of the cybersecurity industry is failing the test.</p>
<p>They came for Krebs. And most watched. Quietly. Uncomfortably. Passively.</p>
<p>Everyone—or at least almost everyone over the age of 40—has probably wondered how Germany allowed Hitler to rise to power. We have gone through the thought exercise at some point of considering what we would have done if we lived in Germany during Hitler’s rise. People don’t ponder that question and think, “I would have remained silent.” They ponder that question and imagine themselves as a noble hero—standing up for liberty and freedom.</p>
<p>And yet, here we are.</p>
<p>Freedom isn’t free and actions have consequences. Will there be repercussions for organizations that defy Trump’s whims? Maybe. Current events suggest the odds are good. But, millions of Americans have given their lives to support and defend the Constitution and stand up for democracy and freedom. The least cybersecurity vendors, law firms, universities, and other targeted organizations can do is risk sacrificing government contracts and revenue to stand up for their principles and the rule of law.</p>
<p>If a former CISA director, a nationally respected cybersecurity expert, can be targeted for doing his job and speaking the truth, what makes you think you’ll be safe when your turn comes?</p>
<h2>The Stakes Are Bigger Than One Person</h2>
<p>This is not about left or right. It’s not about politics. It’s about whether we allow power to dictate truth, or whether we stand up to defend it—even when it’s hard. Especially when it’s hard.</p>
<p>The cybersecurity industry has always portrayed itself as the vanguard—defenders of infrastructure, truth, and resilience. But right now, it’s at risk of becoming just another silent institution, hoping the monster it won’t name doesn’t notice it.</p>
<p>That’s not defense. That’s surrender.</p>
<h2>A Call to Speak</h2>
<p>To every cybersecurity leader, CISO, vendor, and industry body: this is your moment. Not just to protect one man’s reputation, but to show what kind of industry we want to be.</p>
<p>Because if we can’t defend the truth—if we won’t even defend one of our own when truth itself is under attack—then what exactly are we protecting?</p>
<p>Silence isn’t safe.</p>
<p>Silence is surrender.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Defold: cross-platform game engine (326 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://defold.com</link>
            <guid>43726051</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 08:15:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://defold.com">https://defold.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43726051">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="pagecontent">
	<div>
				<p><a href="https://defold.com/"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/defold/logo/logo-ver-outline-white-64.png" height="32px" alt="Defold logo"></a>
				</p>
				
				
			</div>


	
	<div>
				<p>
				
				<img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/defold/logo_with_text/logo-ver-classic-white-160.png" alt="Defold Logo"></p><h2><b>The game engine for high-performance cross-platform games</b></h2>
				</div><!--
<div class="section">
	<div class="container">
		<div class="row">
			<div class="columns twelve dark-text">
				<div class="grid-250">
					<div class="card center light clickable"
	style="min-height: 225px;"><a href="/open" target="_self"><p class="ribbon">SOURCE&nbsp;AVAILABLE!</p><div class="row"><div class="column full"><span style="zoom: 0.5;"><img src="/images/icons/ic-64-box.svg" width="20%" alt="An open box"/></span><h5 class="left">Free to use - always!</h5>
				<p class="left">Defold is, and will always remain, completely free to use with a developer-friendly license for both personal and commercial use.<br/><p style='text-decoration:underline;'>Learn more</p></p>
			</div></div></a></div>


					<div class="card center light clickable"
	style="min-height: 225px;"><a href="/showcase" target="_self"><div class="row"><div class="column full"><span style="zoom: 0.5;"><img src="/images/icons/ic-64-rocket.svg" width="20%" alt="A rocket"/></span><h5 class="left">Games</h5>
				<p class="left">Defold is used by professional game developers and hobbyists all over the world. It’s a proven tool for games of all genres.<br/><p style='text-decoration:underline;'>Learn more</p></p>
			</div></div></a></div>


					<div class="card center light clickable"
	style="min-height: 225px;"><a href="/product" target="_self"><div class="row"><div class="column full"><span style="zoom: 0.5;"><img src="/images/icons/ic-64-performance.svg" width="20%" alt="A gauge at full throttle"/></span><h5 class="left">Performance first</h5>
				<p class="left">Built from the ground up with a clear focus on performance. Spend time making games, not waiting for builds.<br/><p style='text-decoration:underline;'>Learn more</p></p>
			</div></div></a></div>

				</div>
			</div>
		</div>
	</div>
</div>
-->

<div>
		<div>
			<div>
				<h4 id="no-setup">No setup</h4>
				<p>Defold comes fully featured out of the box. There's nothing to set up or configure, not even when building. Simply download the editor and get creative!</p>
				<div>
					<ul>
						<li>Visual Editor</li>
						<li>Code Editor</li>
						<li>Lua Scripting</li>
						<li>Lua Debugger</li>
						<li>Scene Editor</li>
						<li>Particle Editor</li>
						<li>Tilemap Editor</li>
						<li>2D &amp; 3D</li>
					</ul>
				</div>
			</div>
			<p><img src="https://defold.com/images/editor/nosetup-editor.png" alt="Bring me Cakes by PotatoJam" loading="lazy">
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
				<h4 id="cross-platform">Truly cross-platform</h4>
				<p>Using just one code base, and without the need for external tools, Defold lets you publish your game to all of the major platforms:</p>
				<div>
					<ul>
						<li>PlayStation®5</li>
						<li>PlayStation®4</li>
						<li>Nintendo Switch</li>
						<li>Android</li>
						<li>iOS</li>
						<li>macOS</li>
						<li>Linux</li>
						<li>Windows</li>
						<li>Steam</li>
						<li>HTML5</li>
						<li>Facebook</li>
						<li>Q3 2024 XBox</li>
					</ul>
				</div>
			</div>
		
		<div>
			<div>
				<h4 id="turn-key-solution">Turn-key solution</h4>
				<ul>
					<li>Use basic building blocks to create complex behaviour.</li>
					<li>Everything you need to make a game in one tool</li>
					<li>Write game logic using Lua.</li>
					<li>Zero-config cloud build for native code</li>
				</ul>
			</div>
			<p><img src="https://defold.com/images/editor/editor-screenshot-hero-right-dragosha.png" alt="Isometric turn-based roguelike by Dragosha" loading="lazy">
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://defold.com/images/editor/editor-screenshot-hero-left-dragosha-3d.png" alt="Star Jammer by Ben James" loading="lazy">
			</p>
			<div>
				<h4 id="custom-configuration">Custom configuration</h4>
				<ul>
					<li>Add new functionality from the <a href="https://defold.com/assets">Asset Portal</a>.</li>
					<li>Setup your own local build environment.</li>
					<li>Write your own native code to extend the engine.</li>
					<li>Integrated with tools such as Atom, VS Code, Rive, Spine, TexturePacker and Tiled.</li>
				</ul>
			</div>
		</div>
		
		<div>
			
			<p><img src="https://defold.com/images/editor/editor-screenshot-hero-right.png" alt="Particle effects editor with live preview" loading="lazy">
			</p>
		</div>
		<div>
			<p><img src="https://defold.com/images/editor/editor-screenshot-duovikings.png" alt="Duo Vikings by Flazm" loading="lazy">
			</p>
			<div>
				<h4 id="production-ready">Production ready</h4>
				<ul>
					<li>Proven track record of <a href="https://defold.com/showcase">game releases</a> on mobile, web, desktop and consoles.</li>
					<li>Integrations with analytics, app economy and game services available out of the box.</li>
					<li>Actively developed, with a new release every month.</li>
					<li>Technical <a href="https://defold.com/support">support contracts available</a> if needed.</li>
				</ul>
			</div>
		</div>
		
		
	</div>
<p><a href="https://defold.com/showcase" target="_blank">
		<img src="https://defold.com/images/games/familyisland-full.png" width="100%" loading="lazy">
	</a>
</p>

<div>
			<div>
				<h5>Family Island</h5>
				<p>What would your life be without modern technology on the deserted island? Dive into simplicity of the primal world with the modern Stone Age family in this thrilling offline adventure game. Stranded on the remote island, a family of four - Bruce, Eva and their kids - needs your guidance and help starting a new family home from scratch and navigating through various family life situations with humour.</p>
			</div>
			<div>
				<table>
					<tbody><tr>
						<td>Developer</td>
						<td>Melsoft</td>
					</tr><tr>
						<td>Release date</td>
						<td>2019</td>
					</tr><tr>
						<td>Platforms</td>
						<td>iOS, Android</td>
					</tr><tr>
						<td>Downloads</td>
						<td>50M+ on Google Play (Sep 2023)</td>
					</tr></tbody></table>
			</div>
		</div>



<div>
			<div>
				<h3>Blog updates</h3>
<p><b>Defold release 1.9.8</b><br>
<small>Published on Mar 10, 2025</small><br>
Defold 1.9.8 has been released. - <a href="https://defold.com/2025/03/10/Defold-1-9-8/">READ</a></p>

<p><b>Defold release 1.9.7</b><br>
<small>Published on Feb 03, 2025</small><br>
Defold 1.9.7 has been released. - <a href="https://defold.com/2025/02/03/Defold-1-9-7/">READ</a></p>

<p><b>Defold release 1.9.6</b><br>
<small>Published on Dec 18, 2024</small><br>
Defold 1.9.6 has been released. - <a href="https://defold.com/2024/12/18/Defold-1-9-6/">READ</a></p>
</div>
			<div>
				<h3>Latest News</h3>
<p><b>Defold 2024 Showreel</b><br>
<small>Published on Mar 05, 2025</small><br>
The Defold 2024 showreel has been published on YouTube. The showreel contains some of the amazing games which have been released in 2024. - <a href="https://defold.com/2025/03/05/Defold-2024-showreel/">READ</a></p>

<p><b>Announcing editor scripts for UI creation</b><br>
<small>Published on Sep 26, 2024</small><br>
We are excited to announce our first technical preview of editor scripting API for creating interactive UI elements in the editor! - <a href="https://defold.com/2024/09/26/Announcing-editor-scripts-for-ui/">READ</a></p>

<p><b>Defold cloud builder improvements</b><br>
<small>Published on Sep 23, 2024</small><br>
We are happy to announce that we've finished a large overhaul of the build servers to simplify development, maintenance and the setup of local build servers. - <a href="https://defold.com/2024/09/23/Defold-cloud-builder-improvements/">READ</a></p>
</div>
		</div>


<div>
<p>
<h2>Learn Defold</h2>
<br>
</p>


</div>




<div><div>
				<h5>Corporate Platinum Partners</h5>
				<p><a href="https://www.rive.app/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/rive.png" alt="Rive logo"></a><a href="https://melsoft-games.com/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/melsoft.png" alt="Melsoft Games logo"></a></p></div><div>
				<h5>Corporate Gold Partners</h5>
				<p><a href="https://www.heroiclabs.com/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/heroiclabs.png" alt="Heroic Labs logo"></a><a href="https://www.poki.com/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/poki.png" alt="Poki logo"></a></p></div><div>
				<h5>Corporate Bronze Partners</h5>
				<p><a href="https://denda-corporate.com/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/denda-corporate.png" alt="Denda Games logo"></a></p></div><div>
				<h5>Special Partners</h5>
				<p><a href="https://www.grantfortheweb.org/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/gftw.png" alt="Grant for the Web logo"></a><a href="https://opgames.org/" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/op-games.png" alt="OP Games logo"></a></p></div><div>
				<h5>Top Community Donors</h5>
				
			</div><div>
				<h5>Memberships</h5>
				<p><a href="https://dataspelsbranschen.se/english" target="_blank"><img src="https://defold.com/images/logo/others/dataspelsbranschen.png" alt="Swedish Game Developers Association logo"></a></p>
			</div></div>




	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AMP and why emails are not (and should never be) interactive (179 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://buttondown.com/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email</link>
            <guid>43725865</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 07:31:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://buttondown.com/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email">https://buttondown.com/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43725865">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-sentry-component="Prose" data-sentry-source-file="Prose.tsx"><p>“Email has largely stayed the same,” <a href="https://blog.google/products/gmail/take-action-and-stay-up-to-date-with-dynamic-email-in-gmail/">wrote Gmail product manager Aakash Shaney</a> in 2019, while the web rapidly evolved around it.</p><p>No more. Google’s AMP for email meant “your emails can stay up to date” and “you can easily take action directly from the message itself.”</p><p>Four years earlier, the search giant had come for the mobile web with AMP—accreted mobile pages. Devs would code mobile versions of their site using AMP libraries, host them in Google’s CDN, and reap the benefits of near-instant load times and preferential placement in Google search results.</p><p>And now they were coming for your emails, dangling the benefits of a modernized messaging experience where you could book flights and hotels, respond to meeting invites and Google Docs comments, all from the comfort of your inbox.</p><p>“Who would ever want this?” <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=32408370">asked @waste_monk on Hacker News</a>. “We are living in hell.”</p><h2>Dante's inbox</h2><p>Yet the road to hell is paved with good intentions, as they say. That, and more than a little hubris.</p><p>On the web, AMP had gained grudging adoption through carrots and sticks. Build an AMP site, and you’d get <a href="https://venturebeat.com/business/google-creates-dedicated-placement-in-search-results-for-amp-stories-starting-with-travel-category/">preferential placement in search results</a>, a grey lightning bolt near your site’s name in search results, and a near-zero latency page load from Google’s CDN—all carrots. “We are here to make the web great again,” <a href="https://www.theverge.com/23711172/google-amp-accelerated-mobile-pages-search-publishers-lawsuit">said Google’s vice president of news, Richard Gingras</a> in 2015, only months after Donald Trump brought that phrase into the vernacular. Google assumed publishers the world over would happily rewrite their mobile sites to the search giant’s whims.</p><p>The implicit stick, though, was that without an AMP page, your site wouldn’t rank as highly as it may have previously. And with <a href="https://gs.statcounter.com/search-engine-market-share">over 89% of global search volume</a>, when Google asks web publishers to jump, they say how high.</p><p>There were always issues with AMP. It brought back the dynamics of the mobile versus the desktop web, for one. Instead of the same web for everyone, you now had one page on mobile, another page on desktop—exactly what responsive web design had been fighting against ever since the iPhone brought a desktop-class browser to mobile. And, more critically, it lessened your control over your site.&nbsp;</p><p>AMP required allowing any AMP CDN to cache your pages. Visitors might be served your page from a Google domain instead of your own, or the ad tech and other scripts on your site might be incapable of running on your AMP site (handily, it seemed, for Google, who might prefer you to use their ad tech instead).</p><p>It was all enough that, over the coming years, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/23711172/google-amp-accelerated-mobile-pages-search-publishers-lawsuit">Google would come under two antitrust lawsuits</a> that referenced AMP as part of what the US Justice Department saw as Google’s attempt to monopolize online advertising and the web in general.</p><p><a href="https://amp.dev/documentation/">AMP libraries</a> themselves were open-source. And you could offer a competing AMP CDN; <a href="https://www.bing.com/webmaster/help/bing-amp-cache-bc1c884c">Microsoft’s Bing did</a>, for one. But web developers viewed AMP with suspicion from the onset, as much due to the coercion as anything. “It’s a threat to the open web,” as <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/explainlikeimfive/comments/ecrzvp/comment/fbdfq7x/">@ImprobableValue summed up</a> the prevailing opinion on Reddit.</p><p>And then Google brought AMP to email.</p><h2>What if email was interactive?</h2><p><img src="https://buttondown.com/next-assets/img/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email/Pinterest-AMP.gif" alt="Pinterest AMP email in Gmail" title=""></p><p>Emails has always moved at its own, slower pace. The first email was sent twenty years before the first web page was published, and to this day, plain text emails without HTML are still considered compliant <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/html/rfc2822">internet messages</a>.</p><p>As Ray Tomlinson, who implemented and sent the first email from ARPANET in 1971 <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2012/5/2/2991486/ray-tomlinson-email-inventor-interview-i-see-email-being-used">said about adding formatting to email</a>: “That’s too complicated: we just want to send messages to people.”</p><p>That, for better or worse, has been the ethos of email. It’s why every email message, today, should include both an HTML and plain text version, why you can email anyone and trust that they can read your message. It’s one of the remaining decentralized parts of modern communications, one where <a href="https://www.caniemail.com/clients/gmail/#desktop-webmail">Gmail supports only 152 of the 301 email HTML and CSS features</a> yet your messages still typically look fine.</p><p>Email’s great because “No company owns it. It works reliably and as intended on every platform, every operating system, every device. That’s a rarity today and a hell of a valuable one, ” <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2018/02/13/amp-for-email-is-a-terrible-idea/">said TechCrunch’s Devin Coldewey</a>.&nbsp;</p><p>And here came Google, recommending everyone change how they write emails.</p><p>AMP email used the same frameworks as AMP on the web, with a <a href="https://amp.dev/documentation/components/email/">scaled-down set of components</a>. Some new stuff: AMP-form to gather info, AMP-autocomplete to suggest search and filter results, AMP-carousel to showcase said results. Some older stuff, rewritten: AMP-image to “replace the HTML5 img tag” and lazy-load images, AMP-anim to “manage an animated image, typically a gif,” and AMP-timeago for fuzzy timestamps.</p><p><img src="https://buttondown.com/next-assets/img/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email/Yahoo-shopping-AMP.gif" alt="AMP eCommerce email in Yahoo! Mail" title=""></p><p>It all worked, in Gmail, Yahoo! Mail, and (inexplicably) Mail.ru. Launch partner OYO Rooms let you browse hotel listings and reviews from emails. <a href="https://booking.com/">Booking.com</a> let you flip through room photos—and change your email preferences from daily to weekly from an interactive form in emails. Pinterest emails let you flip through recipes and save them to your boards. And Google Docs, most notably, let you reply to and close comments from your inbox.</p><p>“It’s the biggest thing happening to email since the creation of email,” <a href="https://amp.dev/about/email">Booking.com’s Antony Malone said</a> to the AMP team.</p><h2>AMPing up your emails</h2><p><img src="https://buttondown.com/next-assets/img/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email/Screenshot.png" alt="AMP Playground from Google to code AMP emails" title=""></p><p>You, too, could code an AMP email, as long as you were willing to now write AMP, HTML, and plain text versions of every email. The AMP version was familiar enough, HTML if you squint. You’d open with an &lt;html ⚡4email lang="en" data-css-strict&gt; or &lt;html amp4email&gt; tag, then add standard HTML components alongside &lt;amp-img&gt; or &lt;amp-carousel&gt; or other elements as needed. You could build an interactive tick-tack-toe game, if you were so inclined.</p><p>Then, just as today you write HTML and plain text versions of your emails, you’d need to code AMP and HTML versions of each message. You’d need alternatives for core features. Google Docs, for instance, let you reply to a Google Doc comment directly from an email in Gmail. On other email apps without AMP support, the reply button would instead open a New Email window complete with a custom @docs.google.com address where you could email in a reply. That requires a magnitude more effort to build and support, for a simulacrum of interactivity.</p><p>And, even after all of that work, you couldn’t just send your email. You’d need to authenticate your domain with <a href="https://buttondown.com/blog/migration-explained">DKIM, DMARC, and SPF</a>—good ideas, regardless. You’d also need to send a sample email to both <a href="https://developers.google.com/gmail/ampemail/register">Google</a> and <a href="https://senders.yahooinc.com/amp/">Yahoo!</a>, and register your domain with each of them. Then, if you were lucky, within 5 days you’d be approved to start sending AMP emails.</p><p>All of that, for emails that would only work in a handful of email apps.</p><p>AMP emails, today, still aren’t supported by Gmail or any other service in Microsoft Edge (or Internet Explorer, but that’s more understandable). Yahoo! only added AMP support to mobile in 2022, two years after the initial launch. Microsoft <a href="https://techcommunity.microsoft.com/blog/outlook/developer-preview-of-amp-for-email-in-outlook-com---no-longer-supported/821020">added “preview” support for AMP</a> to <a href="https://outlook.com/">Outlook.com</a> in 2019, only to turn it off a year later in favor of their Exchange-only, JSON-powered “<a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/outlook/actionable-messages/">Actionable Messages</a>.”</p><p>The writing seemed on the wall from the beginning. It was all too much effort, for too little, in a developer environment primed to distrust anything new from Google.</p><p>“It’s okay,” declared <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20255877">@_ofdw</a> on Hacker News, 3 months after AMP for Email’s initial release. “Google will kill AMP in a year or two, just like they kill everything else.”</p><h2><strong>AMP, expunged</strong></h2><p>666 days later (seriously!), Google blinked. “We will no longer show the AMP badge icon to indicate AMP content,” <a href="https://developers.google.com/search/blog/2021/04/more-details-page-experience">announced the Google Search Central Blog</a> in April 2021, and “using the AMP format is no longer required” to be featured in Google News’ Top Stories carousel.</p><p>AMP for Email went more quietly into that dark night. No announcements that AMP for Email was over, no disabling of AMP features in Gmail. It didn’t join the 296 other projects that have been <a href="https://killedbygoogle.com/">killed by Google</a>, from AngularJS to Zeitgeist (and Google Reader, Google Wave, and so many more).</p><p>Google itself still uses AMP for email, branded as <a href="https://support.google.com/mail/answer/9266768?sjid=10526709383943153796-AP">Dynamic Email</a>. You can still reply to Google Docs comments and accept Google Calendar events without leaving Gmail thanks to AMP for email.</p><p><img src="https://buttondown.com/next-assets/img/blog/whatever-happened-to-amp-email/Gmail-comment-AMP.gif" alt="AMP powered Gmail comments" title=""></p><p>But AMP the project has been left to die. The AMP by Example site, linked to in all of the announcements, is dead. AMP’s <a href="https://github.com/ampproject/amphtml/tree/main/docs/spec/email">Email spec</a> hasn’t been updated since a few typos were fixed in 2023, while the <a href="https://github.com/ampproject/wg-amp4email">wg-amp4email working group</a> hasn’t seen an update since 2021. Google’s own <a href="https://playground.amp.dev/?runtime=amp4email">AMP Playground</a> site is stuck in the past, featuring the iPhone XS and Pixel 2 phones.</p><p>AMP “got as far as Google could prop it up and as soon as Google gave up on that everyone promptly ditched it,” <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/webdev/comments/1g2u0p3/comment/lrqvrpv/">remarked Rarst</a> on a Reddit r/webdev thread about AMP.</p><p>Interactivity in email didn’t die with AMP. You don’t need anything beyond good ol’ HTML. HTML buttons and forms are supported by Gmail and almost every app other than Outlook for Windows or Yahoo! Mail for iOS. The HTML5 &lt;video&gt; element works in Apple Mail, Thunderbird, and Outlook on Mac (as well as, strangely, Outlook 2003 for Windows but no other versions)—just not in Gmail. You can make polls and surveys in email with HTML links and buttons, as <a href="https://docs.buttondown.com/surveys">we do at Buttondown</a>—enough to RSVP to events, even if not enough to dynamically view hotel prices, say.</p><p>AMP, though, wasn’t just interactive. It made emails impermanent. The email you receive today with a comment may not look the same tomorrow after someone edits their comment or adds a new reply. The price on a home listing or plane ticket might dynamically update, gaslighting you about what you know you saw in your inbox yesterday. Email’s the last bastion of permanency on the internet, one place where at least you have a record of what went down. That’s worth preserving. Fuzzy timestamps are the last thing email needed.</p><p>Email’s lasted for 54 years. Over <a href="https://buttondown.com/blog/emails-lindy-lifetime">the next 54 years</a>, expect email to change, slowly. Expect plain text email to stick around forever. Expect people to continue to predict the death of email. And, expect the death of everything that says it’ll usurp email.</p><p>You can’t kill—or change, really—something that’s lasted that long.</p><p><em>Image Credits: Animated demos of AMP emails from Google’s launch posts.</em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I gave up on self-hosted Sentry (2024) (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bugsink.com/blog/why-i-gave-up-on-self-hosted-sentry/</link>
            <guid>43725815</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 07:24:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bugsink.com/blog/why-i-gave-up-on-self-hosted-sentry/">https://www.bugsink.com/blog/why-i-gave-up-on-self-hosted-sentry/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43725815">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                




          <div>
                <p><img src="https://www.bugsink.com/static/images/klaas.beec86a2df8b.webp" alt="Klaas van Schelven">
                </p>
                <p><span>
                    Klaas van Schelven;
                  </span>
                  <span>
                    September 6, 2024 - 6 min read
                  </span>
                </p>
              </div>


          <figure>
            <p><img src="https://www.bugsink.com/static/images/self-hosting-sentry.56ae43bfd99e.webp" alt="Self-hosting Sentry">
            </p>
          </figure>

<p>In the early 2010s, I was a big fan of <a href="https://sentry.io/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" target="_blank">Sentry</a>. It was a great tool for tracking errors in web
applications. At the time, I was making software for law firms, so sending error reports to a third-party service was
out of the question, I needed to host it myself. So I did.</p>
<p>After leaving the law firm world, I worked as a contractor for a few years. So when I overheard one of my colleagues
asking whether it would be possible to host Sentry on-premise, I figured I could help. I had already done it, after
all. <em>Big mistake</em>.</p>
<h3 id="scare-mongering">Scare-mongering</h3>
<p>The first thing I noticed was that the Sentry documentation was full of warnings about how self-hosting was a bad idea.
Here’s the <a href="https://sentry.io/resources/self-hosted-vs-cloud/" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" target="_blank">kind of quote</a> that you couldn’t make up if you were
<a href="https://www.bugsink.com/">their direct competitor</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>we don’t necessarily recommend self-hosting to everyone. In addition to existing hidden costs, as Sentry evolves,
our self-hosted version will become more complex, demanding additional types of infrastructure. Our internal system
that powers our newest features will also advance and require more containers, including one for a new database.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And they even have pretty pictures and a whole <a href="https://www.bugsink.com/static/build-vs-buy.4bd46d420f4e.pdf">pdf</a> to go with it:</p>

          <figure>
            <img src="https://www.bugsink.com/static/images/build-vs-buy.c31834c5d5e3.webp" alt="The cost of self-hosting Sentry">
            <figcaption>
                Credit: sentry.io
            </figcaption>
          </figure>


<h3 id="hardware-requirements">Hardware requirements</h3>
<p>Despite the warnings, I hadn’t given up yet. I had already done it once, after all. So I opened the
<a href="https://develop.sentry.dev/self-hosted/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">documentation</a> and started reading. More warnings, in this case about the lack
of support for the self-hosted version. Given that they have to make money too, I could understand those (more than the
scary pictures).</p>
<p>But then come the hardware requirements: they recommend at least <strong>16GB of RAM</strong> and 4 cores. Coming from the time when
I ran Sentry on a 512MB VPS, this was a bit of a shock. So is that a real problem, or should I just get with the times,
and accept that 16GB is the new normal? I’d argue that it <em>is</em> a problem, for a few reasons.</p>
<p>First, there’s a <strong>signal being given</strong> about the <strong>complexity and fragility</strong> of the software. A 16GB RAM requirement
just screams “this is a big, complex piece of software that will break in mysterious ways”. Not very scientific, I know,
but based on experience.</p>
<p>Second, there’s the <strong>simple matter of cost</strong>. The cheapest VM at the super-cheap hosting company Hetzner costs €3.29
per month, but if you need 16GB, you’ll pay 15.90 per month – almost a factor 5 more. And that’s assuming you can run
things at el-cheapo hosting. If you pay-per-compute, or if you work at some big corp, the cost of machines may be much
higher.</p>
<p>Also relevant in corporate environments: there may very well be some threshold where it is easy to spin up “small”
machines (for some value of small), but above which you’ll need to <strong>beg for permission</strong> with a bean counter, sysadmin or manager.</p>
<p>Finally, as <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=idLyobOhtO4&amp;t=3030s" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Linus
Torvalds</a> said</p>
<blockquote>
<p>if you can do something really fast, really well, people start using it differently.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The same applies for “if it’s small”. One such different use-case is to just <strong>run it
locally</strong>, as an aid in local development. If you need 16GB of RAM to run Sentry, you’ll run the risk of slowing down
your laptop to a crawl, or at least having to think about it. If it’s in the 100MB range, you can just run it and forget
about it.</p>
<p>Oh and if you were thinking of running it on a Raspberry Pi, forget about it, but not (just) because of the RAM. The Pi
has an ARM processor, and <a href="https://github.com/getsentry/self-hosted/issues/1585" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Sentry only supports amd64</a>.</p>
<h3 id="so-many-scripts">So many scripts…</h3>
<p>The next chapter in the documentation is about the <a href="https://develop.sentry.dev/self-hosted/#getting-started" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">actual
installation</a>.</p>
<p>The first thing you’ll notice is that the installation is done with a shell script. That is not a problem in itself, but
I’m also not the type of person who would just run a shell script from the internet without reading it first, so I did.</p>
<p>The actual script is some 30 lines, but each of those is an include of another script. Counting those, you get:</p>
<pre><code><div><pre><span></span>me@mymachine~/../self-hosted/install$ wc -l *.sh
  [...]
  837 total
</pre></div></code></pre>
<p>That’s not a time-investment I’m willing to make. Especially since this is, as per the documentation, only a first step
towards a reliable installation:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>packaged up for low-volume deployments and proofs-of-concept</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And remember that the whole reason for setting up Sentry was to help a colleague. I’m not going to leave them with a
proof-of-concept, and I also don’t want to become the guy who maintains the Sentry installation. And I’m not going to
tell them to read 837 lines of shell script either.</p>
<h3 id="further-searching">Further searching</h3>
<p>Finally, I did some random internet searching, to see what the actual experience was of people who had self-hosted
Sentry. Here are <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/sre/comments/17xosxi/selfhosting_sentry_your_experience/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">some quotes</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s a ton of docker containers. Things will fail randomly or maybe with a lot of traffic, don’t remember well. Hard
to upgrade or it would upgrade automatically and break?.</p>
</blockquote><blockquote>
<p>if you can dedicate like 1/4 to 1/2 an engineer on it then i think its worth it. keeping in mind that it is an
absolutely bear with an ungodly amount of stateful dependencies nowadays.</p>
</blockquote><blockquote>
<p>I can’t say it’s been pleasant, probably my least favorite service to do maintenance on or interact with</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Now let’s just assume these aren’t astro-turfed by Sentry’s own marketing department, i.e that these are real.
None of this looks very promising. And since I don’t have a 1/4 to 1/2 an engineer to dedicate to this, I would be
looking at a significant share of my own time.</p>
<h3 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>I gave up on self-hosted Sentry before even getting started.</p>
<p>I’m not going to run a piece of software that requires 16GB of RAM, has a complex
installation script, and is known to be a pain to maintain. I’m not going to recommend it to anyone else either.</p>
<p>So did some good come out of this? I’d like to think so… this small journey got me mad enough to just write a <a href="https://www.bugsink.com/">drop-in
replacement for Sentry</a> that can <a href="https://www.bugsink.com/scalable-and-reliable/">run on any cheap hardware you can find</a>. I hope that it is
a useful alternative for people with the same taste in software as me.</p>


                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Viral ChatGPT trend is doing 'reverse location search' from photos (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/17/the-latest-viral-chatgpt-trend-is-doing-reverse-location-search-from-photos/</link>
            <guid>43725648</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 06:49:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/17/the-latest-viral-chatgpt-trend-is-doing-reverse-location-search-from-photos/">https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/17/the-latest-viral-chatgpt-trend-is-doing-reverse-location-search-from-photos/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43725648">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">There’s a somewhat concerning new trend going viral: People are using ChatGPT to figure out the location shown in pictures.</p>

<p>This week, OpenAI released its newest AI models, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/16/openai-launches-a-pair-of-ai-reasoning-models-o3-and-o4-mini/">o3 and o4-mini</a>, both of which can uniquely “reason” through uploaded images. In practice, the models can crop, rotate, and zoom in on photos — even blurry and distorted ones — to thoroughly analyze them.</p>







<p>These image-analyzing capabilities, paired with the models’ ability to search the web, make for a potent location-finding tool. Users on X quickly discovered that o3, in particular, is quite good at deducing <a href="https://x.com/k_kohlbrenner/status/1912728015760486626" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">cities</a>, <a href="https://x.com/emollick/status/1912726124913623143" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">landmarks</a>, and even restaurants and bars from subtle visual clues.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Wow, nailed it and not even a tree in sight. <a href="https://t.co/bVcoe1fQ0Z" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">pic.twitter.com/bVcoe1fQ0Z</a></p>



<p>— swax (@swax) <a href="https://twitter.com/swax/status/1912728143682760934?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">April 17, 2025</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>In many cases, the models don’t appear to be drawing on “memories” of past ChatGPT conversations, or <a href="https://x.com/datapoint2200/status/1912729205554524495" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">EXIF data</a>, which is the metadata attached to photos that reveal details such as where the photo was taken.</p>

<p>X is filled with examples of users giving ChatGPT <a href="https://x.com/deedydas/status/1912607561947230575" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">restaurant menus</a>, <a href="https://x.com/swax/status/1912728143682760934" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">neighborhood snaps</a>, <a href="https://x.com/izyuuumi/status/1912726186679226451" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">facades</a>, and <a rel="nofollow" href="https://x.com/vyrotek/status/1912702767531192392">self-portraits</a>, and instructing o3 to imagine it’s playing “GeoGuessr,” an online game that challenges players to guess locations from Google Street View images.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>this is a fun ChatGPT o3 feature. geoguessr! <a href="https://t.co/HrcMIxS8yD" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">pic.twitter.com/HrcMIxS8yD</a></p>



<p>— Jason Barnes (@vyrotek) <a href="https://twitter.com/vyrotek/status/1912702767531192392?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">April 17, 2025</a></p>
</blockquote>




<p>It’s an obvious potential privacy issue. There’s nothing preventing a bad actor from screenshotting, say, a person’s Instagram Story and using ChatGPT to try to doxx them. </p>

<blockquote>
<p>o3 is insane<br>I asked a friend of mine to give me a random photo<br>They gave me a random photo they took in a library<br>o3 knows it in 20 seconds and it’s right <a href="https://t.co/0K8dXiFKOY" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">pic.twitter.com/0K8dXiFKOY</a></p>



<p>— Yumi (@izyuuumi) <a href="https://twitter.com/izyuuumi/status/1912726186679226451?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">April 17, 2025</a></p>
</blockquote>



<p>Of course, this could be done even before the launch of o3 and o4-mini. TechCrunch ran a number of photos through o3 and an older model without image-reasoning capabilities, GPT-4o, to compare the models’ location-guessing skills. Surprisingly, GPT-4o arrived at the same, correct answer as o3 more often than not — and took less time.</p>







<p>There was at least one instance during our brief testing when o3 found a place GPT-4o couldn’t. Given a picture of a purple, mounted rhino head in a dimly-lit bar, o3 correctly answered that it was from a Williamsburg speakeasy — not, as GPT-4o guessed, a U.K. pub.</p>

<p>That’s not to suggest o3 is flawless in this regard. Several of our tests failed — o3 got stuck in a loop, unable to arrive at an answer it was reasonably confident about, or volunteered a wrong location. Users on X noted, too, that o3 can be <a href="https://x.com/GrantSlatton/status/1912676624556023985" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">pretty</a> <a href="https://x.com/neilsuperduper/status/1912706630459806162" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">far off</a> in its location deductions.</p>

<p>But the trend illustrates some of the emerging risks presented by more capable, so-called reasoning AI models. There appear to be few safeguards in place to prevent this sort of “reverse location lookup” in ChatGPT, and OpenAI, the company behind ChatGPT, doesn’t address the issue in its <a href="https://openai.com/index/o3-o4-mini-system-card/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">safety report</a> for o3 and o4-mini.</p>

<p>We’ve reached out to OpenAI for comment. We’ll update our piece if they respond. </p>

<p><em>Updated 10:19 p.m. Pacific: Hours after this story was published, an OpenAI spokesperson sent TechCrunch the following statement: </em></p>

<p><em>“OpenAI o3 and o4-mini bring visual reasoning to ChatGPT, making it more helpful in areas like accessibility, research, or identifying locations in emergency response. We’ve worked to train our models to refuse requests for private or sensitive information, added safeguards intended to prohibit the model from identifying private individuals in images, and actively monitor for and take action against abuse of our usage policies on privacy.”</em></p>
</div><div>
	
	
	
	

	
<div>
	<p>
		Kyle Wiggers is TechCrunch’s AI Editor. His writing has appeared in VentureBeat and Digital Trends, as well as a range of gadget blogs including Android Police, Android Authority, Droid-Life, and XDA-Developers. He lives in Manhattan with his partner, a music therapist.	</p>
</div>


	
	<p>
		<a data-ctatext="View Bio" data-destinationlink="https://techcrunch.com/author/kyle-wiggers/" data-event="button" href="https://techcrunch.com/author/kyle-wiggers/">View Bio <svg style="width: 1em;" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" fill="none" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><path fill="var(--c-svg, currentColor)" d="M16.5 12 9 19.5l-1.05-1.05L14.4 12 7.95 5.55 9 4.5z"></path></svg></a>
	</p>
	
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kagi Assistant is now available to all users (462 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.kagi.com/assistant-for-all</link>
            <guid>43724941</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 04:12:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.kagi.com/assistant-for-all">https://blog.kagi.com/assistant-for-all</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43724941">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            
            <p><img src="https://kagifeedback.org/assets/files/2025-04-17/1744906692-864216-image.png" alt="Kagi Assistant: No training on user data. Combines top LLMs with optional results from Kagi Search. Privacy by default."></p>

<p>At Kagi, our mission is simple: to humanise the web. We want to deliver a search experience that prioritises human needs, allowing you to explore the web effectively, privately, and without manipulation. We evaluate new technologies not for their acclaim but for their true potential to support our mission.</p>

<p>Since its launch, Kagi Assistant has been a favorite for many users as it allows access to world top large language models, grounded in Kagi Search, all in one place in one beautiful user interface - and all that for +$15/mo upgrade from our Professional plan that provides unlimited Kagi Search.</p>

<p>Today, we’re excited to announce that <a href="https://kagi.com/assistant">Kagi Assistant</a> is now available to all users across all plans, expanding from its previous exclusivity to <a href="https://kagi.com/signup?plan_id=ultimate">Ultimate</a> subscribers, as an added value to all Kagi customers, without increasing the price.</p>

<p><strong>An important note:</strong> We are enabling the Assistant for all users in phases, based on regions, starting with USA today. The full rollout for ‘Assistant for All’ is scheduled to be completed by Sunday, 23:59 UTC.</p>

<p><img src="https://kagifeedback.org/assets/files/2025-04-17/1744906741-483590-image.png" alt="kagi assistant screenshot"></p>

<p>Our <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/why-kagi/ai-philosophy.html">approach to integrating AI</a> is shaped by these realities and guided by three principles:</p>

<ol>
<li>AI serves a defined, search-relevant context: Kagi Assistant is a research aid.</li>
<li>AI enhances, it doesn’t replace: Kagi Search remains our core offering, functioning independently. Kagi Assistant is an optional tool you can use as needed.</li>
<li>AI should enhance humanity, not diminish it: Our goal is to improve your research process by helping you synthesise information or explore topics grounded in Kagi Search results, not to replace your critical thinking.</li>
</ol>

<p>Kagi Assistant embodies these principles, working within the context of Kagi’s search results to provide a new way to interact with information. It’s built to make research easier while respecting your privacy and AI’s limits.</p>

<p>By making Kagi Assistant available to everyone, we’re giving all users the choice to explore this capability as part of their Kagi toolkit - at no additional cost to their subscription. Use it when and how it suits your workflow, knowing it’s built with privacy, responsibility, and human-centric values at its core.</p>

<h2>Let’s talk about the specifics!</h2>

<p><img src="https://kagifeedback.org/assets/files/2025-04-17/1744906767-320589-image.png" alt="lets talk about sepcifics doggo"></p>

<h3>AI grounded in Kagi search, guided by you</h3>

<p>When you enable web access, the Assistant has access to Kagi Search results. It will also respect your <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/features/website-info-personalized-results.html">personalised domain rankings</a> and allows the use of <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/features/lenses.html">Lenses</a> to narrow search scope.</p>

<p>Or, if you’d prefer to discuss directly with the model, you can also turn off web access. It also supports file uploads, allowing you to provide additional context or information for your queries.</p>

<h3>Custom assistants tailored to your needs</h3>

<p>Create <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/ai/custom-assistants.html">specialized assistants</a> with unique instructions, defining their purpose, context, and web access preferences. Need help with coding, grammar reviews, or diagnosing an issue with your classic VW Bus? Build an assistant for it.</p>

<p>Pro-tip: assign a custom bang (!name) for instant access via your browser’s search bar.</p>

<h3>Refine and redirect with editing</h3>

<p>Conversations don’t always go as planned. If a response misses the mark, Kagi Assistant lets you edit prompts, switch models, or adjust settings mid-thread. This ensures you stay in control and can redirect the conversation without starting over.</p>

<h3>Privacy as a foundation</h3>

<p>Your privacy is our priority. Assistant threads are private by default, automatically expire based on your settings, and your interaction data is not used to train AI models.  This applies to both Kagi and third-party providers, under strict contractual terms.</p>

<p>Please see <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/ai/llms-privacy.html#llms-privacy">Kagi LLMs privacy</a> for additional information.</p>

<h3>A note on our fair-use policy</h3>

<p>Providing powerful AI tools requires significant resources. To ensure sustainability, we’re starting to enforce our <a href="https://kagi.com/privacy#Terms-of-use">fair-use policy</a>.</p>

<p>Basically our policy states that you can use AI models based on your plan’s value. For example, a $25 monthly plan allows up to $25 worth of raw token cost across all models (there is a 20% built-in margin that we reserve for providing searches, development and infrastructure for the service). From our token usage statistics, 95% of users should never hit this limit.</p>

<p>While most users won’t be affected, those exceeding the generous threshold will have the possibility to renew their subscription cycle instantly. Soon, we’ll introduce credit top-ups for added flexibility. This approach ensures a fair, user-funded model while maintaining quality service and is a simple way to control usage, compared to arbitrary usage limits found in other services.</p>

<h2>Your favourite models are waiting for you</h2>

<p>Choose from a range of leading LLMs from OpenAI, Anthropic, Google, Mistral, and more. You can switch models mid-thread and explore their performance through our regularly updated <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/ai/llm-benchmark.html">open-source LLM benchmark</a>.  Choice of models in non-Ultimate plans will be limited compared to our full offering in the Ultimate plan, please see below.</p>

<p>Access to your favourite LLMs makes Kagi Assistant mould to your requirements and query customisations, so we feature an array of models for you to choose from.</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Model Name</th>
<th>Plan</th>
</tr>
</thead>

<tbody>
<tr>
<td>GPT 4o mini</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>GPT 4.1 mini</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>GPT 4.1 nano</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Gemini 2.5 Flash</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Mistral Pixtral</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Llama 3.3 70B</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Llama 4 Scout</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Llama 4 Maverick</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Nova Lite</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>DeepSeek Chat V3</td>
<td>All</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>GPT 4o</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>o3 mini</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>o4 mini</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>GPT 4.1</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>ChatGPT 4o</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Grok 3</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Grok 3 Mini</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Claude 3.5 Haiku</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Claude 3.7 Sonnet</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Claude 3.7 Sonnet with extended thinking</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Claude 3 Opus</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Gemini 1.5 Pro</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Gemini 2.5 Pro Preview</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Mistral Large</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Llama 3.1 405B</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Qwen QwQ 32B</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>Nova Pro</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>DeepSeek R1</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>

<tr>
<td>DeepSeek R1 Distill Llama 70B</td>
<td>Ultimate</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<h2>Explore further</h2>

<p>This is just the beginning for Kagi Assistant. Explore more in our <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/ai/assistant.html">documentation</a>.</p>

<p>Happy fetching,<br>
Team Kagi.</p>

<h2>F.A.Q.</h2>

<p><strong>Q: Does using a less costly model (like DeepSeek) compared to larger ones use fewer credits?</strong><br>
<strong>A:</strong> Yes. The fair use policy calculates usage based on the actual cost charged by the model provider. Therefore, using smaller, less expensive models will allow for significantly more token usage compared to larger models.</p>

<p><strong>Q: Does Kagi receive discounted rates from AI model providers?</strong><br>
<strong>A:</strong> No, Kagi does not receive discounts. However, we utilize smart caching techniques for the models to reduce operational costs, and these savings are passed on to the user.</p>

<p><strong>Q: Why did Kagi start enforcing the fair use policy?</strong><br>
<strong>A:</strong> The policy was enforced due to excessive use. For instance, the top 10 users accounted for approximately 14% of the total costs, with some individuals consistently using up to 50 million tokens per week on the most advanced models. Our profit margins are already quite narrow. 95% of users should never hit any usage limits.</p>

<p><strong>Q: What is the specific usage limit?</strong><br>
<strong>A:</strong> The limit corresponds directly to the monetary value of your Kagi plan, converted into an equivalent token amount. For example, a $25 plan provides $25 worth of token usage. This calculation includes a 20% margin for Kagi to cover search provision, development, and infrastructure costs. Savings achieved through prompt caching and other optimizations are passed on to you.</p>

<p><strong>Q: Where can I view my token usage?</strong><br>
<strong>A:</strong> Currently, you can monitor your token usage on the Consumption page: <a href="https://kagi.com/settings?p=consumption">https://kagi.com/settings?p=consumption</a>. We plan to display cost and interaction details more prominently soon, potentially on the billing page or directly within the Assistant interface.</p>

<p><strong>Q: I can not access Assistant!</strong><br>
A: We are doing staged rollout beginning with USA, full rollout scheduled by Sunday, 23:59 UTC. This will include other regions and even the trial plan.</p>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why is Good Friday called Good Friday? (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.historyextra.com/period/general-history/good-friday-facts-why-called/</link>
            <guid>43724870</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 03:59:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.historyextra.com/period/general-history/good-friday-facts-why-called/">https://www.historyextra.com/period/general-history/good-friday-facts-why-called/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43724870">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-placement="Body"><p>Good Friday is an annual commemoration on the Friday before Easter Sunday to mark the day when Jesus Christ was crucified.</p><p>Having been arrested and sentenced to death by Pontius Pilate, the governor of the Roman province of Judaea, Christ was flogged, had a crown of thorns placed on his head – to ridicule his title as ‘king of the Jews’ – and made to carry the cross to the place of crucifixion outside the walls of Jerusalem.</p><p>Here he was nailed to the cross and crucified. Before his death after hours of torment, he cried out, “Eli, Eli, lama sabachthani?” (“My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?”) Afterwards, he was removed from the cross, wrapped in linen and placed in a tomb, with a large stone rolled across to block the entrance.</p><p>This series of events is often depicted in churches with images or statues. These 14 events, from Christ’s sentence to death to being laid in the tomb, are called the Stations of the Cross.</p><h2 id="why-is-good-friday-called-good-friday-0ea06373">Why is Good Friday called Good Friday?</h2><p>Although it might seem incongruous to refer to the day of Christ’s crucifixion as ‘good’, the meaning of the name Good Friday can be understood as historically meaning ‘holy’. The use of ‘good’ denotes that this is a day of religious observance, and since this Friday is one of the most important in Christianity it is also one of the holiest.</p><p>The earliest-known use of “goude friday” comes from c1300, according to the Oxford English Dictionary.</p><p>It is not a day of celebration, like Easter Sunday, but a solemn time of reflection. In Germany, the day is known as <em>Karfreitag</em> (Sorrowful Friday).</p><ul><li><strong>Read more | <a href="https://www.historyextra.com/membership/true-story-nativity-how-much-known-about-birth-jesus-christmas/">The history of the nativity: how much is known about the birth of Jesus?</a></strong></li></ul><p>In Christianity, however, the meaning of ‘good’ has been reinterpreted so that Good Friday can indeed be held as a good day. It was when Christ made his ultimate sacrifice for all people, dying for their sins so that they can achieve forgiveness and find eternal peace in Heaven.</p><p>The sorrow of Good Friday is also short-lived, with Christ’s victory over death on Easter Sunday. The day of the crucifixion can therefore signal the deliverance of good over evil.</p><h2 id="how-is-good-friday-marked-around-the-world-eaf8ddf2">How is Good Friday marked around the world?</h2><p>Good Friday is marked in a multitude of ways, depending on the denomination of Christianity. The focus of all commemoration, however, is the veneration of the cross – from the ones seen in churches to even those on top of hot cross buns.</p><p>Services are held, with readings and hymns that relate to the Passion of Christ (the events leading up to Christ’s crucifixion). As a sombre occasion, more focus is given to prayer and reflection. The Three Hours’ Devotion is a service lasting between noon and 3pm, the hours that Christ spent on the cross.</p><p>For Roman Catholics, Good Friday is traditionally also a time of fasting, and no mass is held (though other religious services are). In Rome, the pope leads a procession, called the Way of the Cross, from the Colosseum to the Palatine Hill.</p><ul><li><strong>Read more | <a href="https://www.historyextra.com/period/ancient-history/history-bible-origins-who-wrote-when-how-reliable-historical-record/">A history of the Bible: who wrote it and when?</a></strong></li></ul><p>In the Eastern Orthodox Church, during the Vespers evening prayer, the epitaphios, a richly decorated cloth depicting the body of Christ, is processed to the centre of the church and placed on an intricately carved table covered in flowers, which represents the tomb of Christ.</p><p>Another common sight around the world are reenactments of the Passion of Christ. In Jerusalem, pilgrims retrace the footsteps of Christ, some carrying their own crosses, to the hill where he was crucified, Golgotha.</p><p>In parts of Central and South America, people observe Lent (the 40 days from Ash Wednesday through to Holy Thursday, the day before Good Friday) by making Alfombras, beautiful carpets made out of flowers, grasses, fruits, vegetables and coloured sawdust on the streets. Then during the Good Friday processions, they are trampled on to honour Christ’s sacrifice.</p><h2 id="are-there-any-strange-good-friday-customs-and-traditions-8752915e">Are there any strange Good Friday customs and traditions?</h2><p>The painted eggs, chocolate and bunnies are not common parts of the religious observance of Holy Week. Although, there is a tradition in Jamaica of placing an egg white in a glass of water on Maundy Thursday and the pattern it has made by Good Friday, when dried by the Sun, is believed to predict a person’s future.</p><p>According to tradition, Good Friday is the right time for a woman in Ireland to get a haircut, as it will grow back thicker and longer. Even just getting it washed that day will protect from headaches.</p><p>Similarly, anything planted in the garden on Good Friday is certain to grow. But blacksmiths and carpenters would not use hammers on the day that nails were hammered into Christ’s hands and feet.</p><p>In relation to the crucifixion, a severe custom is held in the Philippines every year. In the Cutud Lenten Rites Festival, volunteers flagellate themselves before actually being crucified, albeit temporarily.</p><p>One man, Ruben Enaje, has done it every year since 1986, except during the pandemic, meaning that – as of 2024 – he has been crucified 35 times.</p><h2 id="when-is-good-friday-in-2025-7da53069">When is Good Friday in 2025?</h2><p>Good Friday takes place on Friday, 18 April 2025.</p><ul><li><strong>Read more | <a href="https://www.historyextra.com/period/20th-century/northern-ireland-good-friday-agreement-protestants-catholics-brexit-border-ira/">What is the Good Friday Agreement?</a> </strong></li></ul><h2 id="what-else-happens-in-holy-week-09bc84e5">What else happens in Holy Week?</h2><p>Good Friday is one of several holy days that take place in the week leading to Easter Sunday. Holy Week begins with Palm Sunday, when Christ made his triumphal entry into Jerusalem as the crowds waved palm branches.</p><p>Monday, Tuesday, and Wednesday all mark events in the last days of Christ, including his cleansing of the temple and Judas Iscariot’s betrayal.</p><p>Maundy Thursday, the day before Good Friday, was when Christ and his Apostles sat together for the Last Supper before his arrest. The day after the crucifixion, Holy Saturday, commemorates Christ’s burial.</p><p>Holy Week ends with Easter Sunday, celebrating the resurrection of Christ.</p><h2 id="why-does-the-date-of-easter-change-every-year-7a45e6f0">Why does the date of Easter change every year?</h2><p>The exact dates of Christ’s death and resurrection have long been debated in the history of Christianity. As such, Easter is not celebrated on a fixed date, unlike the birth of Christ which is always celebrated on 25 December.</p><p>Instead, the date depends on the Moon: Easter Sunday takes place on the first Sunday that comes after the first full Moon following the spring equinox. For the purposes of calculating Easter, the spring equinox is set in the Christian calendar to 21 March (known as the ecclesiastical equinox), which means Easter can be any time between 22 March and 25 April.</p><ul><li><strong>Read more | <a href="https://www.historyextra.com/period/medieval/easter-treats-what-are-biddenden-cakes/">What are the Easter treats known as Biddenden cakes?</a></strong></li></ul><p>Easter is linked to the Jewish holiday of Passover, the date of which similarly changes every year. This marks the exodus of the Israelites from slavery in <a href="https://www.historyextra.com/period/ancient-egypt/facts-ancient-egypt-mummification-cleopatra-pharaohs-tutankhamun-life-death/">ancient Egypt</a>: the last of the 10 plagues of Egypt sent by God was the killing of every firstborn child, but the Israelites painted their doorposts with the blood of a lamb so that the angel of death would pass over them.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intuit, Owner of TurboTax, Wins Battle Against America's Taxpayers (428 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://prospect.org/power/2025-04-17-intuit-turbotax-wins-battle-against-taxpayers-irs-direct-file/</link>
            <guid>43724267</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 02:13:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://prospect.org/power/2025-04-17-intuit-turbotax-wins-battle-against-taxpayers-irs-direct-file/">https://prospect.org/power/2025-04-17-intuit-turbotax-wins-battle-against-taxpayers-irs-direct-file/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43724267">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content" data-transition="content" data-loop="false" itemprop="articleBody">

    <p>For nearly three decades, a cold war has raged through the halls of Congress and in high-end shellfish restaurants perched precariously on Washington, D.C.’s southern coast. The battle lines have shifted between successive administrations, sometimes tilting toward proletariat victory, and sometimes cutting fast toward total surrender to corporate America.</p>

<p>This month, thanks to the whims of the president and hefty sums of cash, Donald Trump has amended an old axiom to guarantee that nothing in life is certain but death, and paying money to file your taxes.</p>

<p>According to a <u><a href="https://apnews.com/article/irs-direct-file-tax-returns-free-trump-4bb0bca02fab9b3d06ae6f45ac67b7ab" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (report)">report</a></u> by the Associated Press this week, the IRS is moving to shut down its free tax filing program known as <u><a href="https://directfile.irs.gov/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Direct File)">Direct File</a></u>, with employees working on the program told to stall work on future iterations. The news comes after Intuit, the maker of TurboTax and the biggest player in tax preparation software, spent years tirelessly fighting any attempt by the government to bring the nightmarish American system of tax collection into line with European nations that have streamlined most citizens’ filing process down to the click of a button.</p>

<p><a href="https://prospect.org/topics/daniel-boguslaw/"><em><strong>More from Daniel Boguslaw</strong></em></a></p>

<p>Even when the Biden administration broke through in the Inflation Reduction Act to fund a pilot program for Direct File, which expanded to 25 states this tax season, Intuit didn’t stop fighting. Instead, it continued cajoling lawmakers and the White House into forcing millions of Americans to shell out hundreds, sometimes thousands, of dollars to file with expensive and confusing tax prep software.</p>

<p>A glance at Intuit’s 2025 first-quarter lobbying disclosures gets at this continued, quarter-century saga. The company <u><a href="https://disclosurespreview.house.gov/?index=%22lobbying-disclosures%22&amp;size=10&amp;keyword=%22intuit%22&amp;filters=%7B%22reportYear%22:%5B%222025%22%5D%7D&amp;sort=%5B%7B%22_score%22:true%7D,%7B%22field%22:%22registrant.name%22,%22order%22:%22asc%22%7D%5D" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (shelled out $240,000)">shelled out $240,000</a></u> to lobby members of Congress on tax-related issues. Forty thousand dollars was doled out to <u><a href="https://disclosurespreview.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2025/Q1/301711402.xml" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Raffaniello &amp; Associates)">Raffaniello &amp; Associates</a></u> to curry favor on issues like “Tax Administration &amp; tax system integrity” and “Regulation of tax return preparers.” It also lobbied on implementation of Public Law 117-169, which is the <u><a href="https://www.congress.gov/117/plaws/publ169/PLAW-117publ169.pdf" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (statute that created IRS Direct File)">statute that created IRS Direct File</a></u>.</p>

<p><u><a href="https://disclosurespreview.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2025/Q1/301696911.xml" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Jake Perry + Partners)">Jake Perry + Partners</a></u> received $30,000 to lobby on the same issues, including personal outreach to Elon Musk’s lackeys in Congress. According to the firm’s filing, at least part of that money was spent on “Communications with DOGE Caucus members regarding tax simplification, waste, fraud and abuse.”</p>

<p><u><a href="https://disclosurespreview.house.gov/ld/ldxmlrelease/2025/Q1/301696545.xml" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Wilmer Cutler Pickering Hale and Dorr LLP)">Wilmer Cutler Pickering Hale and Dorr LLP</a></u>, a law firm targeted with legal sanction by the Trump administration for employing special counsel Robert Mueller, received $60,000 for its work on behalf of Intuit. Its services included advocacy to “Enhance tax administration and tax system integrity” and “support tax simplification and voluntary compliance.” WilmerHale is <u><a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/03/28/politics/law-firms-challenge-trump-executive-order/index.html" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (suing the Trump administration)">suing the Trump administration</a></u> over attacks on their firm, while also cozying up to Republicans to make tax filing more expensive. Money talks.</p>

<blockquote><p>Intuit shelled out $240,000 to lobby members of Congress on tax-related issues in the first quarter of 2025.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This work has paid off. In December, 29 House Republicans <u><a href="https://adriansmith.house.gov/sites/evo-subsites/adriansmith.house.gov/files/evo-media-document/Letter%20to%20President-Elect%20Trump%20re%20IRS%20Direct%20File%20-%20Version%20%232%20-%2012-10-2024%20%40%2005-22%20PM.pdf" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (wrote)">wrote</a></u> to then-President-elect Trump at Mar-a-Lago, asking him to end Direct File on day one. A <u><a href="https://www.citizen.org/article/house-republicans-do-the-bidding-of-big-tax-prep/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (report from Public Citizen)">report from Public Citizen</a></u> showed that these lawmakers have received $1.8 million in campaign contributions from opponents of Direct File over their political careers.</p>

<p>The relatively paltry first-quarter lobbying sum pales in comparison to the big kahuna spend that Intuit made last year: a direct payment to Trump’s inaugural committee. As Politico <u><a href="https://www.politico.com/newsletters/playbook/2024/12/21/shutdown-averted-crisis-delayed-00195800" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (reported in December)">reported in December</a></u>, Intuit handed Trump $1 million for inaugural festivities that were eventually sent indoors due to bad weather. This was a common bribe-like substance from corporate America intended to show fealty to Washington’s new overlords.</p>

<p>A company spokesperson told Politico that the donation was “part of our decades-long commitment to bipartisan advocacy … Intuit is committed to ensuring our customers’ voices are heard on important issues, and our expanded participation in the democratic process reflects our growth as a company and the variety of policy issues that impact the approximately 100 million diverse consumers and businesses we serve.”</p>

<p>“Congratulations to President <a href="https://x.com/realDonaldTrump" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (@realDonaldTrump)">@realDonaldTrump</a> and Vice President <a href="https://x.com/JDVance" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (@JDVance)">@JDVance</a> on your inauguration,” Intuit CEO Sasan Goodarzi, who <u><a href="https://aflcio.org/paywatch/highest-paid-ceos?industry=All&amp;state=All&amp;sp500=1&amp;combine=&amp;page=2" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (made $27 million)">made $27 million</a></u> last year, <u><a href="https://x.com/sasan_goodarzi/status/1881796616010731688" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (tweeted)">tweeted</a></u> on January 21st. “We encourage Washington to promote innovation to strengthen small businesses that are the backbone of the economy and to simplify the tax code to help Americans prosper.”</p>

<p>Intuit certainly knew the importance of persuading Trump to ditch the IRS free filing program. In its <u><a href="https://www.sec.gov/ix?doc=/Archives/edgar/data/0000896878/000089687825000015/intu-20250131.htm#i3a88bc58bc1b4166afb68013b05313fe_139" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (quarterly financial statement to investors)">quarterly financial statement to investors</a></u>, Intuit listed among its risk factors “increasing competition from the public sector,” specifically IRS Direct File, which “could expand with increased awareness of and government support for the program … federal and state governments are or could become publicly funded direct competitors of the U.S. tax services industry and of Intuit. Government funded services that curtail or eliminate the role of taxpayers in preparing their own taxes could potentially have material and adverse revenue implications on us.”</p>

<p>They should have been scared. Customer satisfaction with Direct File was high, with <u><a href="https://thehill.com/opinion/finance/5248523-irs-direct-file-is-a-government-success-story/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (over 90 percent of users)">over 90 percent of users</a></u> ranking it as excellent or above average in surveys.</p>

<p>In 2019, ProPublica published an extensive <u><a href="https://www.propublica.org/article/inside-turbotax-20-year-fight-to-stop-americans-from-filing-their-taxes-for-free" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (investigation)">investigation</a></u> into Intuit’s efforts to safeguard a business model it long marketed as consumer-friendly, despite the millions of dollars lifted off of everyday Americans attempting to file their taxes on time. Intuit focused on carrying out two simultaneous objectives to ensure a maximum windfall: “stoking innovation in Silicon Valley while stifling it in Washington.” In a confidential <u><a href="https://embed.documentcloud.org/documents/6483065-Intuit-board-of-directors-presentation-2007/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (document)">document</a></u> obtained by ProPublica, Intuit outlines the maneuvers it undertook from 1997 to 2006 to block any attempt at making tax filing cheaper and easier for consumers. “For a decade proposals have sought to create IRS tax software or a ReturnFree Tax System; All were stopped,” the title slide reads.</p>

<p>Since 2002, Intuit and other tax preparation services have been legally required to offer a free private-sector version of what the government should have built and provided all along. But Intuit’s playbook has been to create a booby-trapped version of its expensive software, with embedded code that once hid the free offering from search engines like Google, making it exceedingly difficult for those seeking free filing to discover.</p>

<p>In 2023, Intuit was forced <u><a href="https://www.attorneygeneral.gov/taking-action/attorney-general-henry-announces-141-million-settlement-for-millions-of-americans-decieved-by-turbotax-owner-intuit/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (to pay out)">to pay out</a></u> over $100 million in a multistate class action lawsuit that accused the firm of tricking customers into overpaying for services that the firm is legally required to offer for free. 4.4 million consumers nationwide received checks as the result of the multistate settlement. “By requiring consumers to pay for tax-return services that should have been available for free, Intuit cheated taxpayers out of their hard earned money,” then-Pennsylvania Attorney General Michelle Henry said at the time. “Intuit’s deceptive practices and aggressive advertising campaign were unnecessary and illegal; especially when the IRS offers free tax-return services for eligible consumers.”</p>

<p>On April 15, tax filing day, Sen. Elizabeth Warren (D-MA), long a sworn foe of for-profit tax filing companies, slammed the Trump administration for its failures to simplify the filing process.</p>

<p>“Despite Treasury Secretary Bessent’s promise to keep Direct File going through the 2025 tax filing season, the long-term future of the program continues to be threatened, in no small part due to Intuit’s lobbying,” Warren wrote. “Intuit has spent nearly $4 million in 2023 and again in 2024 attempting to kill the program. During the 2024 election cycle, Intuit joined other commercial tax preparation companies to make large donations to Republican congressmembers who later worked to eliminate Direct File.”</p>

<p>Yet after tens of millions in lobbying, hundreds of millions in lawsuits, and a cool million for Trump’s inauguration, it seems that Intuit’s ceaseless spending has paid off.</p>


    
    

    </div><p><span><span><strong>I’m writing to you today</strong> with a sense of urgency that I haven’t felt since I began my journalism career. As executive editor of <i><span>The American Prospect</span></i><span>, I’ve witnessed firsthand how independent journalism serves as a crucial bulwark against the erosion of our democratic institutions. Today, that role is more vital than ever. </span><u><a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/tap-spring-2025?refcode=articlebottom_041625"><span><span><span><span>Can you step up today and show your support?</span></span></span></span></a></u><p>

The winds of authoritarianism are blowing stronger. We’re seeing alarming signs of a coordinated effort to silence critical voices and undermine the very foundations that support progressive causes. As Bob Kuttner presciently wrote in our August 2024 issue, </p><u><a href="https://prospect.org/power/2024-07-30-lefts-fragile-foundations/"><span>a weaponized IRS could attack the very foundations of the progressive movement</span></a></u>.&nbsp;We need readers to step up and help us dig in for the long haul.<p>

We’re falling behind in our spring fundraising campaign, and with so much at stake we can’t afford to come up short. If you value fearless, independent journalism that holds the powerful accountable and defends democracy, now is the time to step up. <i><span>The American Prospect </span></i><span>depends on reader support to stay in the fight. Pitch in today and help us close the gap. </span></p><u><a href="https://secure.actblue.com/donate/tap-spring-2025?refcode=articlebottom_041625"><span>Please consider making a donation today.</span></a></u><p>

<em>–David Dayen, Executive Editor</em></p></span></span></p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DHL suspends B2C shipments over 800 USD until further notice (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.dhl.com/au-en/home/important-information/2025/shipments-to-the-united-states-with-a-customs-value-exceeding-usd-800.html</link>
            <guid>43724123</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 01:45:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.dhl.com/au-en/home/important-information/2025/shipments-to-the-united-states-with-a-customs-value-exceeding-usd-800.html">https://www.dhl.com/au-en/home/important-information/2025/shipments-to-the-united-states-with-a-customs-value-exceeding-usd-800.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43724123">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="text-ba122cfe75">
     
<ul>
 <li><span><strong>As a result of recent U.S. Customs regulatory updates, we are experiencing multi-day transit delays to the U.S from any origin for shipments with a declared customs value exceeding USD 800.<br></strong></span></li>
 <li><span><strong>Effective Monday, April 21st, 2025, and until further notice, we will temporarily suspend the collection and shipping of business-to-consumer (B2C) shipments to private individuals in the United States where the declared customs value exceeds USD 800.<br>
     Shipments – both B2B &amp; B2C - with a declarable customs value below USD 800 are not affected by the suspension. </strong></span></li>
 <li><span><strong>Business-to-business (B2B) shipments to U.S. companies with a declarable value above USD 800 are not affected by the suspension, though they may also face delays.</strong></span></li>
</ul>
<p><span>Effective April 5, 2025, all shipments to the U.S. with a declared customs value over USD 800 require formal entry processing - down from the previous USD 2,500 threshold due to new U.S. Customs regulations.</span></p>
<p><span>This change has caused a surge in formal customs clearances, which we are handling around the clock.</span></p>
<p><span>While we are working diligently to scale up and manage this increase, shipments over USD 800—regardless of origin—may experience multi-day delays.</span></p>
<p><span>To manage this, starting Monday, April 21, 2025, and until further notice, we will temporarily suspend B2C shipments to private individuals in the U.S. where the declared value exceeds USD 800.</span></p>
<p><span>Business-to-business (B2B) shipments to U.S. companies with a declarable value above USD 800 are not affected by the temporary suspension, though they may also face delays.</span></p>
<p><span>This is a temporary measure, and we will share updates as the situation evolves.</span></p>     
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>