<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 16:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[“A calculator app? Anyone could make that” (447 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chadnauseam.com/coding/random/calculator-app</link>
            <guid>43066953</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 10:16:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chadnauseam.com/coding/random/calculator-app">https://chadnauseam.com/coding/random/calculator-app</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43066953">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[50 Years of Travel Tips (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kk.org/thetechnium/50-years-of-travel-tips/</link>
            <guid>43066720</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 09:31:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kk.org/thetechnium/50-years-of-travel-tips/">https://kk.org/thetechnium/50-years-of-travel-tips/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43066720">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>





<p>I’ve been seriously traveling for more than 50 years, and I’ve learned a lot.</p>



<p>I’ve traveled solo, and I’ve led a tour group of 40 friends. I’ve slept in dormitories and I’ve stayed in presidential suites with a butler. I’ve hitchhiked penniless for months, and I’ve flown by private jet. I’ve traveled months with siblings, and with total strangers. I’ve gone by slow boat and I’ve ridden my bicycle across America, twice. I’ve been to the largest gathering of humans on the planet, and trekked into remotest areas on the planet on my own. I’ve paid for luxury tours, and I’ve done my own self-guided tours. I regularly travel for business, and once I went to Hawaii on a door-prize award. I’ve circumnavigated the globe in only 48 hours, and I traveled uninterrupted for 9 months. I’ve gone first class and third class, sometimes on the same trip. So far I’ve visited half the world’s countries, and usually manage to get far from the capital city when I do. Here is what I know about how to travel.</p>



<p>There are two modes of travel; retreat or engage. People often travel to escape the routines of work, to recharge, relax, reinvigorate, and replenish themselves— R&amp;R. In this mode you travel to remove yourself from your routines, or to get the pampering and attention you don’t ordinarily get, and ideally to do fun things instead of work things. So you travel to where it is easy. This is called a vacation, or R&amp;R.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The other mode is engagement and experience, or E&amp;E. In this mode you travel to discover new things, to have new experiences, to lean into an adventure whose outcome is not certain, to meet otherness. You move to find yourself by encountering pleasures and challenges you don’t encounter at home. This kind of travel is a type of learning, and of the two modes, it is the one I favor in these tips.</p>



<p>***********</p>



<p>Organize your travel around passions instead of destinations. An itinerary based on obscure cheeses, or naval history, or dinosaur digs, or jazz joints will lead to far more adventures, and memorable times than a grand tour of famous places. It doesn’t even have to be your passions; it could be a friend’s, family member’s, or even one you’ve read about. The point is to get away from the expected into the unexpected.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>If you hire a driver, or use a taxi, offer to pay the driver to take you to visit their mother. They will ordinarily jump at the chance. They fulfill their filial duty and you will get easy entry into a local’s home, and a very high chance to taste some home cooking. Mother, driver, and you leave happy. This trick rarely fails.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Make no assumptions about whether something will be open. There are other norms at work. If possible check at the last minute, if not, have a plan B.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Crash a wedding. You are not a nuisance; you are the celebrity guest! The easiest way to do this is to find the local wedding hall where weddings happen on schedule and approach a wedding party with a request to attend. They will usually feel honored. You can offer the newlyweds a small token gift of cash if you want. You will be obliged to dance. Take photos of them; they will take photos of you. It will make your day and theirs. (I’ve crashed a wedding in most of the countries I have visited.)</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Don’t balk at the spendy price of admission for a museum or performance. It will be a tiny fraction of your trip’s total cost and you invested too much and have come too far to let those relative minor fees stop you from seeing what you came to see.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Google maps will give you very detailed and reliable directions for taking public transit, including where to make transfers in most cities.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>When visiting a foreign city for the first time, take a street food tour. Depending on the region, the tour will include food carts, food trucks, food courts, or smaller eateries. It will last a few hours, and the cost will include the food. You’ll get some of the best food available, and usually the host will also deliver a great introduction to the culture. Google “street food tour for city X.”</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>The most significant criteria to use when selecting travel companions is: do they complain or not, even when complaints are justified? No complaining! Complaints are for the debriefing afterwards when travel is over.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>As in any art, constraints breed creativity. Give your travel creative constraints: Try traveling by bicycle, or with only a day bag for luggage, or below the minimum budget, or sleep only on overnight trains. Mix it up. Even vagabonding can become a rut.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Renting a car is easier than ever today, even in developing countries, and oftentimes the best bet for getting around if you are headed for many places outside of cities. It is an option worth considering, especially if you are 2 to 3 people traveling. On the other hand, there are still plenty of places where you don’t want to drive because of chaotic roads, lawless attitudes, and unfavorable liabilities. In those places hiring a driver plus car for a multi-day trip is often a surprisingly appealing bargain—especially if you have 2 to 3 people to split the costs. The total could be less than taking trains and taxis, and you get door to door service, and often a built-in guide who knows the local roads and also local festivities and best places to eat. They will be at least 2x the cost of renting a car, but for some kinds of travel 2x as good. If you are a spontaneous traveler, a hired driver is by far the best option allowing you to change your itinerary immediately as mood, weather, or lucky timing dictate. I usually find drivers by searching travel forums for recommendations. I score candidates primarily by their communication skills.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>If you are fortunate, a fantastic way to share your fortune is to gift a friend the cost of travel with you. You both will have a great time.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Go to a cemetery. Look for sacred places. People live authentically there. Don’t just visit the markets, but also go to small workshops, hardware stores and pharmacies –&nbsp; places with easy access to local practices. See how it’s different and the same all at once.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p><a href="https://www.flightaware.com/">FlightAware</a> is the best free phone app for the status of your flight. It will often tell you about delays hours before the airline will. Tip: use FlightAware to check whether your plane has even arrived at your departure airport.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Sketchy travel plans and travel to sketchy places are ok. Take a chance. If things fall apart, your vacation has just turned into an adventure. Perfection is for watches. Trips should be imperfect. There are no stories if nothing goes amiss.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Your enjoyment of a trip will be inversely related to the weight of your luggage. Counterintuitively, the longer your trip, the less stuff you should haul. Travelers still happy on a 6-week trip will only have carry-on luggage. That maximizes your flexibility, enabling you to lug luggage up stairs when there is no elevator, or to share a tuk-tuk, to pack and unpack efficiently, and to not lose stuff. Furthermore, when you go light you intentionally reduce what you take in order to increase your experience of living. And the reality of today is that you can almost certainly buy whatever you are missing on the road.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Getting an inside tour is the ultimate travel treat. How about a factory tour, a visit to an Amish home, or backstage at an opera? When I travel for business I will sometimes ask for inside access to an uncommon place in lieu of a speaking fee. You are aiming for experiences that simple money can’t buy. Good ones will take planning ahead.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>It is always colder at night than you think it should be, especially in the tropics. Pack a layer no matter what.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Planning your itinerary: You want to see it all and you are likely to never return, so the temptation is to pile it on, maximize your visit. Since we are in X, and Y and Z&nbsp; are so close, we might as well see Y and Z….. Paradoxically when you are traveling you should minimize the amount of time you spend in transit—once you arrive. The hard-to-accept truth is that it is far better to spend more time in a few places than a little time in a bunch of places.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>To book a train anywhere in the world outside your home country, your first stop should be <a href="https://www.seat61.com/">The Man in Seat 61</a>, a sprawling website which will conveniently help you book the train you want.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>In 53 years of travelling with all kinds of people, I’ve seen absolutely no correlation between where you eat and whether you have intestinal problems, so to maximize the enjoyment of local foods, my rule of thumb is to eat wherever healthy-looking locals eat.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>The list of most coveted cities to visit have one striking thing in common—they are pedestrian centric. They reward walking.<strong> </strong>Better online hotel sites like<a href="http://booking.com/"> Booking.com</a> have map interfaces which allow you to select hotels by their location. Whenever possible I book my hotel near to where it is best to walk, so I can stroll out the door and begin to wander.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>For a truly memorable trip, go without reservations, just winging it along the way. If you like somewhere, stay a day longer, or if you don’t, split a day earlier. If the train is full, take a bus. That freedom can be liberating.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>The <a href="https://apps.apple.com/tr/app/google-translate/id414706506">Google Translate app</a> for your phone is seriously good, and free. It will translate voice, text, or script to and from 250 languages. Use for deciphering menus, signs, talking with clerks, etc. It is often a lifesaver.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Large-scale luxury cruises have no appeal to me, yet a small boat cruise is an entirely different species and a valid option worth considering. The advantage of a cruise is that your hotel travels with you, so you unpack only once. It is especially useful for small groups because it eliminates the eternal negotiation of deciding where to eat. (You always eat on the boat.) The advantages of a small boat cruise over a huge boat are several: you disembark very quickly, very often, at smaller more intimate places than large boats can do. And the options for activities are more active than just shopping: such as snorkeling, kayaking, bicycling, hiking, visiting local families and communities. Overall you spend far more time doing things off the boat than on. I define a small boat as 40 passengers or fewer. The per day cost is high, but almost every minute of it is quality time, unlike a series of bus rides. Examples of places I’ve loved a small boat cruise; The Galapagos, Alaska inland passageway, Mekong River, Coast of Turkey, and Kerala, India.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>The rate you go is not determined by how fast you walk, bike or drive, but by how long your breaks are. Slow down. Take lots of breaks. The most memorable moments—conversations with amazing strangers, an invite inside, a hidden artwork—will usually happen when you are not moving.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>I generally find “professional” tour guides uninteresting, and too scripted. They are mostly repeating what can be found in guide books. So I rarely hire them. I much prefer to have a friend or local acquaintance show me what interests them in an ad hoc way, with no script. Let friends know you are coming to their area.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>A few <a href="https://amzn.to/4gKbKAV">laundry detergent sheets</a> in a tiny ziplock bag weigh nothing and won’t spill and are perfect for emergency laundry washing in the sink or shower.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>These days it is mandatory that you are connected. You need cell coverage as well as wifi. You’ll want robust mobile coverage for navigation, translation apps, ride shares and a digital wallet for payments. Best option is to use a carrier with “free” international plans (such as T-Mobile or <a href="https://fi.google.com/about/">Google Fi</a>) so you need to do nothing. Second best is to get either a sim card or e-sim for your phone for your visiting country. E-sim apps (such <a href="https://www.airalo.com/">Airalo</a>) can be loaded by yourself virtually. Sims and e-sims are also sold at most international airports when you exit. Most are reputable. One tip, turn off your photo and video cloud backup while on the sim to reduce data usage.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>People in other places are not saints. You might get cheated, swindled, or taken advantage of. Paradoxically, the best way to avoid that is to give strangers your trust and treat them well. Being good to them brings out their good. If you are on your best behavior, they will be on their best behavior. And vice versa. To stay safe, smile. Be humble and minimize your ego. I don’t know why that works everywhere in the world—even places with “bad” reputations—but it does.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>You can get an inexpensive and authentic meal near a famous tourist spot simply by walking at least five blocks away from the epicenter.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Digital wallets on your phone are displacing local currencies in many places. For instance I did not use any cash on my last trips to the UK and China. And in places where it has not completely eliminated cash you can reduce your cash needs by half with mobile payments. Set up your Apple pay, Google Pay or Alipay before you leave. There is no need to exchange money anywhere, especially at airports. Get any cash you need at local ATMs, which are now everywhere. Use a card that does not charge, or reimburses, a foreign fee.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>If you detect slightly more people moving in one direction over another, follow them. If you keep following this “gradient” of human movement, you will eventually land on something interesting—a market, a parade, a birthday party, an outdoor dance, a festival.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Splurge in getting the most recent version of a guidebook to your destination. It is worth the price of a lunch to get the latest, most helpful, reliable information. I supplement the latest guidebook research with recommendations suggested in travel forums online. Guidebooks have depth and breadth, while forums offer speed—results from a week ago.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>If you are starting out and have seen little of the world, you can double the time you spend traveling by heading to the places it is cheapest to travel. If you stay at the budget end, you can travel twice as long for half price. Check out <a href="https://www.cheapestdestinationsblog.com/">The Cheapest Destination Blog</a>. In my experience, these off-beat destinations are usually worth visiting.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>In many parts of the world today motorcycles play the role of cars. That means you can hire a moto-taxi to take you on the back seat, or to summon a moto-taxi with an uber-like app, or to take a motorcycle tour with a guide doing the driving. In areas where motorcycles dominate they will be ten times more efficient than slowly going by car.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Put inexpensive <a href="https://amzn.to/4hxt9y4">Apple AirTags</a> into your bags, so you can track them when they are out of your sight. More and more airlines are integrating AirTags into their system to help find wayward bags. The tags work for luggage left in hotel storage, or stashed beneath the bus, or pieces you need to forward.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>For the best travel experiences you need either a lot of money, or a lot of time. Of the two modes, it is far better to have more time than money. Although it tries, money cannot buy what time delivers. You have enough time to attend the rare festival, to learn some new words, to understand what the real prices are, to wait out the weather, or to get to that place that takes a week in a jeep. Time is the one resource you can give yourself, so take advantage of this if you are young without money.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Being beautiful, or well crafted, or cheap is not enough for a souvenir. It should have some meaning from the trip. A good question you may want to ask yourself when buying a souvenir is where will this live when I get home?</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>The best souvenirs from a trip are your memories of the trip so find a way to memorialize them; keep a journal, send updates to a friend, take a sketchbook, post some observations, make a photo book.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>When asking someone for a restaurant recommendation, don’t ask them where is a good place you should eat; ask them where they eat. Where did they eat the last time they ate out?</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>Here in brief is the method I’ve honed to optimize a two-week vacation: When you arrive in a new country, immediately proceed to the farthest, most remote, most distant place you intend to reach during the trip. If there is a small village, remote spa, a friend’s farm, or a wild place you plan on seeing on the trip, go there immediately. Do not stop near the airport. Do not rest overnight in the arrival city. Do not pause to acclimate. If at all possible proceed by plane, bus, jeep, car directly to the furthest point without interruption. Make it an overnight journey if you have to. Then once you reach your furthest point, unpack, explore, and work your way slowly back to the big city, wherever your international departure airport is.</p>



<p>In other words you make a laser-straight rush for the end, and then meander back. Laser out, meander back. This method is somewhat contrary to many people’s first instincts, which are to immediately get acclimated to the culture in the landing city before proceeding to the hinterlands. The thinking is: get a sense of what’s going on, stock up, size up the joint. Then slowly work up to the more challenging, more remote areas. That’s reasonable, but not optimal because most big cities around the world are more similar than different. All big cities these days feel same-same on first arrival. In Laser-Back travel what happens is that you are immediately thrown into Very Different Otherness, the maximum difference that you will get on this trip. You go from your home to extreme differences so fast it is almost like the dissolve effect in a slide show. Bam! Your eyes are wide open. You are on your toes. All ears. And there at the end of the road (but your beginning), your inevitable mistakes are usually cheaper, easier to recover from, and more fun. You take it slower, no matter what country you are in. Then you use the allotted time to head back to the airport city, at whatever pace is your pace. But, when you arrive in the city after a week or so traveling in this strangeness, and maybe without many of the luxuries you are used to, you suddenly see the city the same way the other folks around you do. After eight days in less fancy digs, the bright lights, and smooth shopping streets, and late-night eateries dazzle you, and you embrace the city with warmth and eagerness. It all seems so … civilized and ingenious. It’s brilliant! The hustle and bustle are less annoying and almost welcomed. And the attractions you notice are the small details that natives appreciate. You see the city more like a native and less like a jaded tourist in a look-alike urban mall. You leave having enjoyed both the remote and the adjacent, the old and new, the slow and the fast, the small and the big. </p>



<p>We’ve also learned that this intensity works best if we aim for 12 days away from home. That means 10 days for in-country experience, plus a travel day (or two) on each end. We’ve found from doing this many times, with many travelers of all ages and interests, 14 days on the ground is two days too many. There seems to be a natural lull at about 10 days of intense kinetic travel. People start to tune out a bit. So we cut it there and use the other days to come and go and soften the transitions. On the other hand 8 days feels like the momentum is cut short. So 10 days of intensity, and 12 days in a country is what we aim for. Laser-back travel is not foolproof, nor always possible, but on average it tends to work better than the other ways I’ve tried.</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>If you work while you travel, or work remotely, you may enjoy our newsletter <a href="https://nomadico.substack.com/">Nomadico</a>, which is a weekly one-pager with four brief travel tips. It’s free.&nbsp;</p>



<p>• </p>



<p>(Thanks to early readers, Craig Mod, Derek Sivers, Chris Michel and Will Milne.)</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US goverment seeks to rehire recently fired nuclear workers (310 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g3nrx1dq5o</link>
            <guid>43066182</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 07:45:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g3nrx1dq5o">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g3nrx1dq5o</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43066182">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>The US government is trying to bring back nuclear safety employees it fired on Thursday, but is struggling to let them know they should return to work, NBC News has reported.<!-- --></p><p>The National Nuclear Security Administration workers were among hundreds of employees in the energy department who received termination letters.<!-- --></p><p>An email obtained by NBC said the letters for some NNSA employees "are being rescinded, but we do not have a good way to get in touch with those personnel". <!-- --></p><p>The terminations are part of massive effort by President Donald Trump to slash the ranks of the federal workforce, a project he began on his first day in office, less than a month ago.<!-- --></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Last week, nearly 10,000 federal workers were let go, according to multiple US outlets. <!-- --></p><p>That figure was in addition to the estimated 75,000 workers who have accepted an offer from the White House to leave voluntarily in the autumn. <!-- --></p><p>The nuclear security officials who were laid off on Thursday helped oversee the nation's stockpile of nuclear weapons. That included staff who are stationed at facilities where the weapons are built, according to CNN. <!-- --></p><p>Attempting to reach the workers, the email, which was sent to current employees, said: "Please work with your supervisors to send this information (once you get it) to people's personal contact emails."<!-- --></p><p>Trump is working to slash spending across the board, abroad and at home, and going so far as to call for eliminating the education department. He is getting help from the world's richest man, Elon Musk, who, through an effort called Department of Government Efficiency (Doge), has sent workers to comb through data at federal agencies and helped implement the "buyout" offer.<!-- --></p><p>Last week, the Trump administration ordered agencies to fire nearly all probationary employees, those who had generally been in their positions for less than a year and not yet earned job protection. That included the NNSA staff members.<!-- --></p><p>Altogether, the move could potentially affect hundreds of thousands of people. <!-- --></p><p>Several of the Trump administration's efforts to shrink the government's size and spending have been met with legal challenges. <!-- --></p><p>More than 60 lawsuits have been filed against the Trump administration since the president was inaugurated on 20 January.<!-- --></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gixy: Nginx Configuration Static Analyzer (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy</link>
            <guid>43065217</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 04:06:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy">https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43065217">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">GIXY</h2><a id="user-content-gixy" aria-label="Permalink: GIXY" href="#gixy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/LICENSE"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/d8a56712f4d915bb52addd8864305c7e7ebc8f3e9d9cd667fe98b7182b476e2d/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f647665727368696e696e2f676978792e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" alt="Mozilla Public License 2.0" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/license/dvershinin/gixy.svg?style=flat-square"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/actions/workflows/pythonpackage.yml"><img src="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/actions/workflows/pythonpackage.yml/badge.svg" alt="Python tests"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/issues/new"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/2c2224cce5695c8074d9847852e5584ff66c57a66f469345ee728f23c8a77940/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6d61696e74656e616e63652f7965732f323032332e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" alt="Your feedback is greatly appreciated" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/maintenance/yes/2023.svg?style=flat-square"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/issues"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/fab36ce3abc759f60fe3da59253803e3e7459ffb4e036358c0c32dbbca56cc85/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6973737565732f647665727368696e696e2f676978792e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" alt="GitHub issues" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/issues/dvershinin/gixy.svg?style=flat-square"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/pulls"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/26494b557e581639e05981320aa382c95a36a9f784cb8a6a093063e8d611c5fa/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6973737565732d70722f647665727368696e696e2f676978792e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" alt="GitHub pull requests" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/issues-pr/dvershinin/gixy.svg?style=flat-square"></a></p>
<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Tip</p><p dir="auto">This is an <strong>actively maintained fork</strong> of the original <a href="https://github.com/yandex/gixy">Gixy</a> project by <strong>Yandex LLC</strong>.</p>
</div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Overview</h2><a id="user-content-overview" aria-label="Permalink: Overview" href="#overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/gixy.png"><img width="192" height="192" src="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/raw/master/docs/gixy.png"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Gixy is a tool to analyze Nginx configuration.
The main goal of Gixy is to prevent security misconfiguration and automate flaw detection.</p>
<p dir="auto">Currently supported Python versions are 3.6 through 3.13.</p>
<p dir="auto">Disclaimer: Gixy is well tested only on GNU/Linux, other OSs may have some issues.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What it can do</h2><a id="user-content-what-it-can-do" aria-label="Permalink: What it can do" href="#what-it-can-do"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Right now Gixy can find:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/ssrf.md">[ssrf] Server Side Request Forgery</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/httpsplitting.md">[http_splitting] HTTP Splitting</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/origins.md">[origins] Problems with referrer/origin validation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/addheaderredefinition.md">[add_header_redefinition] Redefining of response headers by  "add_header" directive</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/hostspoofing.md">[host_spoofing] Request's Host header forgery</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/validreferers.md">[valid_referers] none in valid_referers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/addheadermultiline.md">[add_header_multiline] Multiline response headers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/aliastraversal.md">[alias_traversal] Path traversal via misconfigured alias</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/if_is_evil.md">[if_is_evil] If is evil when used in location context</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/allow_without_deny.md">[allow_without_deny] Allow specified without deny</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/add_header_content_type.md">[add_header_content_type] Setting Content-Type via add_header</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.zorinaq.com/nginx-resolver-vulns/" rel="nofollow">[resolver_external] Using external DNS nameservers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/en/plugins/version_disclosure.md">[version_disclosure] Using insecure values for server_tokens</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.getpagespeed.com/server-setup/nginx-try_files-is-evil-too" rel="nofollow">[try_files_is_evil_too] The try_files directive is evil without open_file_cache</a></li>
<li><a href="https://joshua.hu/proxy-pass-nginx-decoding-normalizing-url-path-dangerous#nginx-proxy_pass" rel="nofollow">[proxy_pass_normalized] proxy_pass will decode and normalize paths when specified with a path</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">You can find things that Gixy is learning to detect at <a href="https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aopen+label%3A%22new+plugin%22">Issues labeled with "new plugin"</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">CentOS/RHEL and other RPM-based systems</h2><a id="user-content-centosrhel-and-other-rpm-based-systems" aria-label="Permalink: CentOS/RHEL and other RPM-based systems" href="#centosrhel-and-other-rpm-based-systems"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="yum -y install https://extras.getpagespeed.com/release-latest.rpm
yum -y install gixy"><pre>yum -y install https://extras.getpagespeed.com/release-latest.rpm
yum -y install gixy</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Other systems</h3><a id="user-content-other-systems" aria-label="Permalink: Other systems" href="#other-systems"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Gixy is distributed on <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/gixy-ng" rel="nofollow">PyPI</a>. The best way to install it is with pip:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install gixy-ng"><pre>pip install gixy-ng</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Run Gixy and check results:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="gixy"><pre>gixy</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">By default, Gixy will try to analyze NGINX configuration placed in <code>/etc/nginx/nginx.conf</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">But you can always specify the needed path:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ gixy /etc/nginx/nginx.conf

==================== Results ===================

Problem: [http_splitting] Possible HTTP-Splitting vulnerability.
Description: Using variables that can contain &quot;\n&quot; may lead to http injection.
Additional info: https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/ru/plugins/httpsplitting.md
Reason: At least variable &quot;$action&quot; can contain &quot;\n&quot;
Pseudo config:
include /etc/nginx/sites/default.conf;

	server {

		location ~ /v1/((?<action>[^.]*)\.json)?$ {
			add_header X-Action $action;
		}
	}


==================== Summary ===================
Total issues:
    Unspecified: 0
    Low: 0
    Medium: 0
    High: 1"><pre><code>$ gixy /etc/nginx/nginx.conf

==================== Results ===================

Problem: [http_splitting] Possible HTTP-Splitting vulnerability.
Description: Using variables that can contain "\n" may lead to http injection.
Additional info: https://github.com/dvershinin/gixy/blob/master/docs/ru/plugins/httpsplitting.md
Reason: At least variable "$action" can contain "\n"
Pseudo config:
include /etc/nginx/sites/default.conf;

	server {

		location ~ /v1/((?&lt;action&gt;[^.]*)\.json)?$ {
			add_header X-Action $action;
		}
	}


==================== Summary ===================
Total issues:
    Unspecified: 0
    Low: 0
    Medium: 0
    High: 1
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or skip some tests:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ gixy --skips http_splitting /etc/nginx/nginx.conf

==================== Results ===================
No issues found.

==================== Summary ===================
Total issues:
    Unspecified: 0
    Low: 0
    Medium: 0
    High: 0"><pre><code>$ gixy --skips http_splitting /etc/nginx/nginx.conf

==================== Results ===================
No issues found.

==================== Summary ===================
Total issues:
    Unspecified: 0
    Low: 0
    Medium: 0
    High: 0
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Or something else, you can find all other <code>gixy</code> arguments with the help command: <code>gixy --help</code></p>
<p dir="auto">You can also make <code>gixy</code> use pipes (stdin), like so:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo &quot;resolver 1.1.1.1;&quot; | gixy -"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>"</span>resolver 1.1.1.1;<span>"</span></span> <span>|</span> gixy -</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Docker usage</h2><a id="user-content-docker-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Docker usage" href="#docker-usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Gixy is available as a Docker image <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/getpagespeed/gixy/" rel="nofollow">from the Docker hub</a>. To
use it, mount the configuration that you want to analyse as a volume and provide the path to the
configuration file when running the Gixy image.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ docker run --rm -v `pwd`/nginx.conf:/etc/nginx/conf/nginx.conf getpagespeed/gixy /etc/nginx/conf/nginx.conf"><pre><code>$ docker run --rm -v `pwd`/nginx.conf:/etc/nginx/conf/nginx.conf getpagespeed/gixy /etc/nginx/conf/nginx.conf
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If you have an image that already contains your nginx configuration, you can share the configuration
with the Gixy container as a volume.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$  docker run --rm --name nginx -d -v /etc/nginx
nginx:alpinef68f2833e986ae69c0a5375f9980dc7a70684a6c233a9535c2a837189f14e905

$  docker run --rm --volumes-from nginx dvershinin/gixy /etc/nginx/nginx.conf

==================== Results ===================
No issues found.

==================== Summary ===================
Total issues:
    Unspecified: 0
    Low: 0
    Medium: 0
    High: 0
"><pre><code>$  docker run --rm --name nginx -d -v /etc/nginx
nginx:alpinef68f2833e986ae69c0a5375f9980dc7a70684a6c233a9535c2a837189f14e905

$  docker run --rm --volumes-from nginx dvershinin/gixy /etc/nginx/nginx.conf

==================== Results ===================
No issues found.

==================== Summary ===================
Total issues:
    Unspecified: 0
    Low: 0
    Medium: 0
    High: 0

</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Contributions to Gixy are always welcome! You can help us in different ways:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Open an issue with suggestions for improvements and errors you're facing;</li>
<li>Fork this repository and submit a pull request;</li>
<li>Improve the documentation.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Code guidelines:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Python code style should follow <a href="https://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0008/" rel="nofollow">pep8</a> standards whenever possible;</li>
<li>Pull requests with new plugins must have unit tests for it.</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How Medical Research Cuts Would Hit Colleges and Hospitals in Every State (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/02/13/upshot/nih-trump-funding-cuts.html</link>
            <guid>43064637</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 02:07:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/02/13/upshot/nih-trump-funding-cuts.html">https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2025/02/13/upshot/nih-trump-funding-cuts.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43064637">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="g-2025-02-11-nih-funding-loss" data-preview-slug="2025-02-11-nih-funding-loss" data-birdkit-hydrate="e47fdbe69256eefc">	
			
	  <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A proposal by the Trump administration to <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/07/us/politics/medical-research-funding-cuts-university-budgets.html">reduce the size of grants</a> for institutions conducting medical research would have far-reaching effects, and not just for elite universities and the coastal states where many are located.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Also at risk could be grants from the National Institutes of Health to numerous hospitals that conduct clinical research on major diseases, and to state universities across the country. North Carolina, Missouri and Pennsylvania could face disproportionate losses, because of the concentration of medical research in those states.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><figure>  <div><div><p>N.I.H. funding in 2024</p> <p><span>Per capita</span>
			|
			<span>Total</span></p></div>   </div> <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Based on spending in the 2024 fiscal year.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p></div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In the 2024 fiscal year, the N.I.H. spent at least $32 billion on nearly 60,000 grants, including medical research in areas like cancer, genetics and infectious disease. Of that, $23 billion went to “direct” research costs, such as microscopes and researchers’ salaries, according to an Upshot analysis of <a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024">N.I.H. grant data</a>.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The other $9 billion went to the institutions’ overhead, or “indirect costs,” which can include laboratory upkeep, utility bills, administrative staff and access to hazardous materials disposal, all of which research institutions say is essential to making research possible.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The <a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/NOT-OD-25-068.html">N.I.H. proposal</a>, which has been <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/02/11/health/nih-research-funding-lawsuit-injunction.html">put on hold by a federal court</a>, aims to reduce funding for those indirect costs to a set 15 percent rate that the administration says would save <a href="https://x.com/NIH/status/1888004759396958263">about $4 billion a year</a>. The Upshot analysis estimates that a 15 percent rate would have reduced funding for the grants that received N.I.H. support in 2024 by at least $5 billion. The White House said the savings would be reinvested in more research, but the rate cuts would open up sizable budget holes in most projects at research institutions.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->It is not clear whether those organizations can fill the gaps with other funding sources or by shifting how they apply for grants. Instead, many officials at universities and hospitals have said that they may have to pull back on medical or scientific research.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“It’s not an overstatement to say that a slash this drastic in total research funding slows research,” said Heather Pierce, senior director for science policy at the Association of American Medical Colleges, which has <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.mad.280609/gov.uscourts.mad.280609.1.0.pdf">sued along with other education and hospital associations</a> to block the policy. And slower scientific progress, she said, would affect anyone who depends on the development of new treatments, medical interventions and diagnostic tools.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->We estimate that virtually all universities and hospitals would see fewer funds on similar projects in the future. The 10 institutions that receive the most money from N.I.H. stand to lose more than $100 million per year on average.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->To understand how the change would work, let’s look at <a href="https://reporter.nih.gov/search/JbRgAtchAUKHOoW2X1vObQ/projects/map/project-details/10821480">one grant for about $600,000</a> sent last year to the University of Alabama at Birmingham to study whether exercise can improve memory for people with epilepsy.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><figure>  <div>  <svelte-scrollstory id="g-scrollstory_1">    <svelte-scroller-outer><svelte-scroller-background-container><svelte-scroller-background><svelte-scrollstory-background slot="background"> </svelte-scrollstory-background></svelte-scroller-background></svelte-scroller-background-container> <svelte-scroller-foreground><svelte-scrollstory-foreground slot="foreground"><div>  <div id="g-scrollstory_1-item-0"><p><span><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The N.I.H. sent the university this funding in the 2024 fiscal year, as part of a multiyear grant.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </span></p>  </div><div id="g-scrollstory_1-item-1"><p><span><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->A majority of the money went to <strong>direct costs</strong> associated with the study.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </span></p>  </div><div id="g-scrollstory_1-item-2"><p><span><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->And an additional 45 percent went to <strong>indirect costs </strong>supporting the research, like building maintenance and administrative staff.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </span></p>  </div><div id="g-scrollstory_1-item-3"><p><span><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Under the new rules, the university would receive <strong>a 15 percent rate</strong> on such grants, bringing the total down.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </span></p>  </div><div id="g-scrollstory_1-item-4"><p><span><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->That would have been a funding loss of nearly $130,000 on this project alone.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </span></p>  </div> </div></svelte-scrollstory-foreground></svelte-scroller-foreground> </svelte-scroller-outer></svelte-scrollstory> </div> <div><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Figures are rounded.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p></div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The calculation above, which we have repeated for every grant paid last year, is a bit simplified. In reality, the researchers would lose even more money than we’ve shown, because of the way indirect funding is calculated (see our methodology at the bottom of this article).<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Our analysis also makes some other conservative assumptions given the policy’s uncertainty. We assume, for instance, that the new 15 percent rate is a flat rate that all grantees would receive, and not a maximum rate (a distinction left unclear in the N.I.H. guidance). We also assume that the change applies not just to institutions of higher education, but also to all kinds of grantees, including hospitals.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->In a statement, the White House indicated it would reserve any savings for additional research grants. “Contrary to the hysteria, redirecting billions of allocated N.I.H. spending away from administrative bloat means there will be more money and resources available for legitimate scientific research, not less,” said Kush Desai, a White House spokesman.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The N.I.H. announcement, however, coincides with the Trump administration’s moves to cut spending across the government, and with the N.I.H.’s withholding of funding for grants — their direct and indirect costs alike — in <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/01/31/us/trump-freeze-blocked.html">apparent conflict</a> <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/01/28/us/politics/states-lawsuit-trump-federal-grants-pause.html">with separate court orders</a>.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The N.I.H. <a href="https://grants.nih.gov/grants/guide/notice-files/NOT-OD-25-068.html">guidance document</a> includes a number of conflicting statements and statistics the Upshot could not reconcile. The N.I.H. also declined to answer questions about the policy and about its public-facing data tracking grant spending.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The N.I.H. since 1950 has provided these overhead funds in a formulaic way, and since 1965, the government has used a rate individually calculated for each institution. Federal officials review cost summaries, floor plans and other information to determine that rate. That number can be higher for institutions in more expensive parts of the country, or for those that use more energy-intensive equipment. The proposal from the Trump administration would set aside those differences in standardizing the rate at 15 percent for every grantee.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->The lists below estimate what would have happened to the 10 universities and hospitals that received the most N.I.H. grant money in the 2024 fiscal year, if the formula change had been in effect then.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><figure><div><p><h3><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Largest N.I.H. grant recipients among colleges, universities and medical schools<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h3>  </p></div>  <div><table><colgroup data-svelte-h="svelte-1dstzqh"><col> <col> <col></colgroup> <thead data-svelte-h="svelte-1s18ww"><tr><th>Name</th> <th>Total ’24 Funding</th> <th>Estimated reduction</th></tr></thead> <tbody><tr><td><p>University of California, San Francisco</p> <p>San Francisco</p>  </td> <td>$793 mil.</td> <td>$121 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Johns Hopkins University</p> <p>Baltimore</p>  </td> <td>$788 mil.</td> <td>$136 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Washington University</p> <p>St. Louis</p>  </td> <td>$717 mil.</td> <td>$108 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>University of Michigan</p> <p>Ann Arbor, Mich.</p>  </td> <td>$708 mil.</td> <td>$119 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>University of Pennsylvania</p> <p>Philadelphia</p>  </td> <td>$652 mil.</td> <td>$129 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>University of Pittsburgh</p> <p>Pittsburgh, Pa.</p>  </td> <td>$632 mil.</td> <td>$115 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Columbia University Health Sciences</p> <p>New York</p>  </td> <td>$611 mil.</td> <td>$111 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Yale University</p> <p>New Haven, Conn.</p>  </td> <td>$602 mil.</td> <td>$131 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Stanford University</p> <p>Stanford, Calif.</p>  </td> <td>$584 mil.</td> <td>$107 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>University of Washington</p> <p>Seattle</p>  </td> <td>$542 mil.</td> <td>$86 mil.</td> </tr></tbody></table> </div> <div> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Source: National Institutes of Health<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Based on spending in the 2024 fiscal year.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>  </div> </figure><figure><div><p><h3><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Largest N.I.H. grant recipients among hospitals<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h3>  </p></div>  <div><table><colgroup data-svelte-h="svelte-1dstzqh"><col> <col> <col></colgroup> <thead data-svelte-h="svelte-1s18ww"><tr><th>Name</th> <th>Total ’24 Funding</th> <th>Estimated reduction</th></tr></thead> <tbody><tr><td><p>Massachusetts General Hospital</p> <p>Boston</p>  </td> <td>$641 mil.</td> <td>$98 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Vanderbilt University Medical Center</p> <p>Nashville</p>  </td> <td>$468 mil.</td> <td>$71 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Brigham and Women’s Hospital</p> <p>Boston</p>  </td> <td>$364 mil.</td> <td>$77 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Boston Children’s Hospital</p> <p>Boston</p>  </td> <td>$218 mil.</td> <td>$54 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center</p> <p>Houston</p>  </td> <td>$180 mil.</td> <td>$39 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Children’s Hospital of Philadelphia</p> <p>Philadelphia</p>  </td> <td>$162 mil.</td> <td>$32 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</p> <p>Boston</p>  </td> <td>$161 mil.</td> <td>$35 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Cincinnati Childrens Hospital Medical Center</p> <p>Cincinnati</p>  </td> <td>$153 mil.</td> <td>$28 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Beth Israel Deaconess Medical Center</p> <p>Boston</p>  </td> <td>$117 mil.</td> <td>$23 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Cedars-Sinai Medical Center</p> <p>Los Angeles</p>  </td> <td>$100 mil.</td> <td>$23 mil.</td> </tr></tbody></table> </div> <div> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Source: National Institutes of Health<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Based on spending in the 2024 fiscal year, which extends from Oct. 1 to Sept. 30.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>  </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->If courts allow the change to move forward, some of its consequences are hard to predict.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Advocates for the policy change note that these organizations receive numerous other federal subsidies. Most universities and research hospitals are nonprofits that pay no federal taxes, for example. The N.I.H. announcement also noted that these same institutions often accept grants from charitable foundations that offer much lower overhead rates than the federal government, a signal that universities and hospitals willingly pursue research opportunities with less supplemental funding.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Because the indirect payments are based on broad formulas and not specific line items, critics say institutions may be diverting these federal dollars into unaccountable funds to pay for programs that taxpayers can’t see, such as the kinds of diversity, equity and inclusion programs targeted by the Trump administration.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“That’s how you get things like the ability of administrators to use larger overhead pools of money to build out D.E.I. bureaucracies, or to fund Ph.D. programs in the humanities,” said Jay Greene, a senior research fellow in the Center for Education Policy at the Heritage Foundation, a conservative research group. Mr. Greene was the coauthor of <a href="https://www.heritage.org/education/report/indirect-costs-how-taxpayers-subsidize-university-nonsense">a 2022 article</a> urging the N.I.H. to cut or eliminate indirect grant funding. But he did not have specific examples to cite of research funds being spent in this way.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Researchers say the indirect funds have a branding problem, but are a necessary component of research.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->“The term ‘indirect costs’ or the alternative term ‘overhead’ sounds dangerously close to ‘slush fund’ to some people,” said Jeremy Berg, who was the director of the National Institute of General Medical Sciences at the N.I.H. from 2003 to 2011. “There are real costs somebody has to pay for, and heating and cooling university laboratory buildings is a real cost.”<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Some grant recipients already receive low overhead payments, but a large majority of them currently receive more than 15 percent, meaning they will need to make budgetary changes to absorb the loss. Among the 2024 grants that we analyzed, institutions that received more than $1 million in N.I.H. support got an average of 40 cents of indirect funding for every dollar of direct funding.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><figure aria-label="graphic"><div><h3><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Distribution of overhead funding at N.I.H.-funded institutions in 2024<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></h3> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->As a share of direct funding<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> </div>   <div> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Source: National Institutes of Health<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Calculated for 613 institutions that received at least $1 million in funding in fiscal year 2024. Federally negotiated rates are higher than these.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></p>  </div> </figure><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Universities and hospitals may adjust their overall budgets to keep supporting medical research by cutting back on other things they do. Some might be able to raise money from donors to fill the shortfalls, though most universities are already raising as much philanthropic money as they can.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->But many research institutions have said they would adjust by simply doing less medical research, because they would not be able to afford to do as much with less government help.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Universities and hospitals might also shift the kinds of research they do, avoiding areas that require more lab space, regulatory compliance or high-tech equipment, and focusing on types of research that will require them to provide less overhead funding themselves. That may mean disproportionate reductions in complex areas of research like genetics.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Those effects may be spread unevenly across the research landscape, as some organizations find a way to adjust, while others abandon medical research altogether.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->We’ve compiled a list of institutions that received at least $1 million in N.I.H. funding in the 2024 fiscal year, along with our estimates of how much less they would have gotten under the new policy. Most of these institutions are universities or hospitals, but there are also some private companies and nonprofit research groups. Our numbers tend to be underestimates of the cuts.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><figure>  <div>  <table><colgroup data-svelte-h="svelte-1yz33f5"><col> <col> <col> <col></colgroup> <colgroup data-svelte-h="svelte-bht1ri"><col> <col> <col> <col></colgroup> <thead><tr><th>Institution </th> <th>No. of grants </th> <th>Total ’24 Funding ▼</th> <th>Estimated change </th></tr></thead> <tbody><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1833205&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Columbia University Health Sciences </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>1,024</td> <td>$611 mil.</td> <td>-$111 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5998304&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York University School of Medicine </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>596</td> <td>$480 mil.</td> <td>-$63 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=3839801&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>714</td> <td>$453 mil.</td> <td>-$93 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1514803&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Weill Medical College of Cornell University </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>540</td> <td>$293 mil.</td> <td>-$55 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5079202&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Sloan-Kettering Institute Cancer Research </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>331</td> <td>$197 mil.</td> <td>-$54 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10053556&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Albert Einstein College of Medicine </a></p></div> <p>Bronx, N.Y. </p></td> <td>311</td> <td>$184 mil.</td> <td>-$35 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=7047101&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">University of Rochester </a></p></div> <p>Rochester, N.Y. </p></td> <td>384</td> <td>$180 mil.</td> <td>-$32 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1514802&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Cornell University </a></p></div> <p>Ithaca, N.Y. </p></td> <td>221</td> <td>$102 mil.</td> <td>-$21 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992614&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">State University of New York at Buffalo </a></p></div> <p>Amherst, N.Y. </p></td> <td>204</td> <td>$83 mil.</td> <td>-$13 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5998301&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York University </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>195</td> <td>$76 mil.</td> <td>-$13 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=7056601&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Rockefeller University </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>129</td> <td>$69 mil.</td> <td>-$17 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992612&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Stony Brook University </a></p></div> <p>Stony Brook, N.Y. </p></td> <td>176</td> <td>$64 mil.</td> <td>-$13 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1833202&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Columbia University Morningside </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>124</td> <td>$50 mil.</td> <td>-$9 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=3934901&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Roswell Park Cancer Institute Corp. </a></p></div> <p>Buffalo, N.Y. </p></td> <td>77</td> <td>$48 mil.</td> <td>-$9 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=4155008&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Feinstein Institute for Medical Research </a></p></div> <p>Manhasset, N.Y. </p></td> <td>61</td> <td>$39 mil.</td> <td>-$9 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=4577101&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory </a></p></div> <p>Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y. </p></td> <td>78</td> <td>$34 mil.</td> <td>-$12 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992619&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Upstate Medical University </a></p></div> <p>Syracuse, N.Y. </p></td> <td>72</td> <td>$25 mil.</td> <td>-$5 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1590919&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York State Psychiatric Institute DBA Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>49</td> <td>$24 mil.</td> <td>-$3 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992616&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">SUNY Downstate Medical Center </a></p></div> <p>Brooklyn, N.Y. </p></td> <td>29</td> <td>$23 mil.</td> <td>-$2 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1590925&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Nathan S. Kline Institute for Psychiatric Research </a></p></div> <p>Orangeburg, N.Y. </p></td> <td>17</td> <td>$17 mil.</td> <td>-$3 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10032222&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York Genome Center </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>20</td> <td>$14 mil.</td> <td>-$3 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=8455007&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Albany Medical College </a></p></div> <p>Albany, N.Y. </p></td> <td>30</td> <td>$13 mil.</td> <td>-$3 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992621&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Binghamton University </a></p></div> <p>Binghamton, N.Y. </p></td> <td>38</td> <td>$13 mil.</td> <td>-$2 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1605017&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">City College of New York </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>28</td> <td>$12 mil.</td> <td>-$2 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=4121701&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York Structural Biology Center </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>7</td> <td>$11 mil.</td> <td>-$3 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992604&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">State University of New York at Albany </a></p></div> <p>Albany, N.Y. </p></td> <td>38</td> <td>$11 mil.</td> <td>-$2 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10041176&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Graduate School of Public Health and Health Policy </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>13</td> <td>$11 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1605019&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Hunter College </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>20</td> <td>$10 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1520301&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Syracuse University </a></p></div> <p>Syracuse, N.Y. </p></td> <td>33</td> <td>$10 mil.</td> <td>-$2 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=4081105&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Hospital for Special Surgery </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>25</td> <td>$10 mil.</td> <td>-$3 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=6910301&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute </a></p></div> <p>Troy, N.Y. </p></td> <td>25</td> <td>$9 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10051177&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Sparian Biosciences, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>New York City, N.Y. </p></td> <td>2</td> <td>$8 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10045586&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Nirsum Laboratories, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>2</td> <td>$8 mil.</td> <td>+$371k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1782801&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York Blood Center </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>9</td> <td>$7 mil.</td> <td>-$2 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10011562&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Regenerative Research Foundation </a></p></div> <p>Albany, N.Y. </p></td> <td>7</td> <td>$6 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5948901&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York Medical College </a></p></div> <p>Valhalla, N.Y. </p></td> <td>17</td> <td>$6 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10059523&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">NYU Long Island School of Medicine </a></p></div> <p>Mineola, N.Y. </p></td> <td>9</td> <td>$6 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=7035701&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Rochester Institute of Technology </a></p></div> <p>Rochester, N.Y. </p></td> <td>20</td> <td>$6 mil.</td> <td>-$759k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=2943902&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Winifred Masterson Burke Medical Research Institute </a></p></div> <p>White Plains, N.Y. </p></td> <td>10</td> <td>$5 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5966012&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Wadsworth Center </a></p></div> <p>Menands, N.Y. </p></td> <td>10</td> <td>$5 mil.</td> <td>-$961k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1605021&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Queens College </a></p></div> <p>Flushing, N.Y. </p></td> <td>14</td> <td>$5 mil.</td> <td>-$540k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10023818&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Advanced Science Research Center </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>9</td> <td>$5 mil.</td> <td>-$535k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=3801901&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Brookhaven Science Associates-Brookhaven Lab </a></p></div> <p>Upton, N.Y. </p></td> <td>1</td> <td>$5 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=6594901&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Population Council </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>3</td> <td>$4 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=2698001&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Fordham University </a></p></div> <p>Bronx, N.Y. </p></td> <td>10</td> <td>$3 mil.</td> <td>-$158k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10006802&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Foundation for AIDS Research </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>1</td> <td>$3 mil.</td> <td>+$213k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10061175&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Gilgamesh Pharmaceuticals Inc. </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>1</td> <td>$3 mil.</td> <td>+$144k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5992605&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">State College of Optometry </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>9</td> <td>$3 mil.</td> <td>-$607k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=7839401&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">St. John’s University </a></p></div> <p>Queens, N.Y. </p></td> <td>15</td> <td>$3 mil.</td> <td>-$647k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1618801&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Clarkson University </a></p></div> <p>Potsdam, N.Y. </p></td> <td>9</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$270k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1605022&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Herbert H. Lehman College </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>13</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$313k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=5017901&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Hauptman-Woodward Medical Research Institute </a></p></div> <p>Buffalo, N.Y. </p></td> <td>5</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$745k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=4888701&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Masonic Medical Research Laboratory, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>Utica, N.Y. </p></td> <td>4</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$738k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10056635&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">NDRI-USA, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>4</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$259k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10073271&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">GE Medical Systems Information Technologies, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>Niskayuna, N.Y. </p></td> <td>3</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$459k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1833204&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Columbia University Teachers College </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>8</td> <td>$2 mil.</td> <td>-$142k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1605016&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Brooklyn College </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>6</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$333k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1605023&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">York College </a></p></div> <p>Jamaica, N.Y. </p></td> <td>5</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$415k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10004387&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Rogosin Institute </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>1</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>+$113k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10013528&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">American Federation for Aging Research </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>3</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$35k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=10006678&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Partnership to End Addiction </a></p></div> <p>New York </p></td> <td>4</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$336k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=1519002&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">New York Institute of Technology </a></p></div> <p>Old Westbury, N.Y. </p></td> <td>3</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$199k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=4014501&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Kitware, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>Clifton Park, N.Y. </p></td> <td>3</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$315k</td> </tr><tr><td><div><p><a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024&amp;state=USS,AL,AK,AZ,AR,CA,CO,CT,DE,DC,FL,GA,HI,ID,IL,IN,IA,KS,KY,LA,ME,MD,MA,MI,MN,MS,MO,MT,NE,NV,NH,NJ,NM,NY,NC,ND,OH,OK,OR,PA,RI,SC,SD,TN,TX,UT,VT,VA,WA,WV,WI,WY,PR&amp;ic=&amp;fm=&amp;orgid=593801&amp;distr=&amp;rfa=&amp;om=n&amp;pid=&amp;view=state#tab5" target="_blank">Hastings Center, Inc. </a></p></div> <p>Garrison, N.Y. </p></td> <td>2</td> <td>$1 mil.</td> <td>-$27k</td> </tr><tr><td><p>Other</p> </td> <td>56</td> <td>$16 mil.</td> <td>-$1 mil.</td> </tr></tbody> <tfoot><tr><td data-svelte-h="svelte-1u00c7s">Total</td> <td>5,887</td> <td>$3.3 bil.</td> <td>-$618 mil.</td></tr></tfoot></table> </div>  </figure><figure>  <div><p>About our analysis</p> <p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->To estimate changes in funding, we relied on data from RePORT, the N.I.H.’s online <a href="https://report.nih.gov/award/index.cfm?ot=&amp;fy=2024">registry</a> of grants and projects. We limited our analysis to grants listed within the 50 U.S. states, the District of Columbia or Puerto Rico. We also limited it to grants where the amount of indirect funding was known and where the combined indirect and direct funding was within five percent of the listed total funding. These filters resulted in removing many grants to private organizations such as domestic for-profits.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->We calculated how much indirect funding each grant would have received under the new guidance by multiplying the listed direct funding amount by 15 percent. We then compared that number to the listed indirect funding amount for each great to estimate the impact of the policy.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->There are two reasons our calculations are most likely conservative estimates of true reductions in funding. First, only a portion of the direct funding for each grant is considered to be “eligible” for the purposes of calculating indirect funding. For example, laboratory equipment and graduate student tuition reimbursements are deducted from the direct costs before applying the negotiated overhead rate, whereas our calculations assumed 100 percent of the listed direct costs would be eligible. We performed a more accurate version of our calculations for the 10 universities and 10 hospitals receiving the most N.I.H. funds by inferring their eligible direct costs from their reported negotiated rates. When we did this, we saw an additional increase in losses of about 20 percent.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p><p><!-- HTML_TAG_START -->Second, we applied a 15 percent rate to all grants in the database, including those with an initial indirect rate <em>below</em> 15 percent. An <a href="https://jamessmurphy.com/2025/02/09/the-impact-of-an-nih-15-indirect-cost-rate/">analysis by James Murphy</a> helped inform this approach. According to our analysis, then, some grants would actually receive more money under the new guidance. If the new rate operated more like a cap — and grants with rates currently below 15 percent did not change — the overall reductions in funding would be larger, as the reductions would no longer be offset by some small number of funding increases.<!-- HTML_TAG_END --> </p></div>  </figure> 
			
			
		

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US Forest Service and National Park Service to fire thousands of workers (118 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/feb/15/us-forest-service-national-park-service-layoffs</link>
            <guid>43064466</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 01:37:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/feb/15/us-forest-service-national-park-service-layoffs">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/feb/15/us-forest-service-national-park-service-layoffs</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43064466">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>The US Forest Service is firing about 3,400 recent hires while the National Park Service is terminating about 1,000 workers under Donald Trump’s push to cut federal spending and bureaucracy, according to a report on Friday.</p><p>The terminations target employees who are in their probationary employment periods, which includes anyone hired less than a year ago, according to Reuters, and will affect sites such as the Appalachian trail, Yellowstone, the birthplace of Martin Luther King Jr and the Sequoia national forest.</p><p>The cuts represent about 10% of the Forest Service workforce and about 5% of National Park Service employees, but excludes firefighters, law enforcement and certain meteorologists, as well as 5,000 seasonal workers, from the cutbacks.</p><p>“Allowing parks to hire seasonal staff is essential, but staffing cuts of this magnitude will have devastating consequences for parks and communities,” the National Parks Conservation Association (NPCA) president, Theresa Pierno, said in a statement.</p><p>The association warned <a href="https://www.npca.org/articles/6680-how-the-new-administration-s-actions-will-affect-national-parks" data-link-name="in body link">in a statement this month</a> that staffing levels were not keeping pace with increasing demands on the national park system, which saw 325m visits in 2023 alone – an increase of 13m from 2022.</p><p><em><strong>Send us a tip</strong><br>
  If you have information you’d like to share securely with the Guardian about the impact of cuts to federal programs, please use a non-work device to contact us via the Signal messaging app at (646) 886-8761. </em></p><p>Kristen Brengel, the NPCA’s senior vice-president of government affairs, warned that visitors from around the world expecting a once-in-a-lifetime experience could now be faced with “overflowing trash, uncleaned bathrooms and fewer rangers to provide guidance”.</p><p>Like other government agencies, the National Park Service was taken by surprise by a late January order from the White House office of management and budget <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/25506191-omb-memo-1-27/" data-link-name="in body link">pausing</a> federal grants. The administration rescinded the order two days later and is re-evaluating it.</p><p>Across the federal government, about 280,000 employees out of the 2.3 million-member civilian federal workforce were hired in the last two years, with most still on probation and easier to fire, according to government data.</p><p>In addition to the visits to national parks, about 159 million people visit national forests annually. The Department of Agriculture, which oversees the Forest Service, said it could not comment on personnel matters.</p><p>The agriculture department said in a statement that protecting people and communities, as well as infrastructure, businesses and resources, remains “a top priority”.</p><p>“Our wildland firefighter and other public safety positions are of the utmost priority,” it added.</p><p>However, the federal funding freeze is affecting programs meant to mitigate wildfire risk in western states as well as freezing the hiring of seasonal firefighters.</p><p>The reduction in resources for wildfire prevention comes a month after devastating blazes in Los Angeles that are expected to be the costliest in US history.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-14">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-14" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>The Oregon-based Lomakatsi Restoration Project non-profit said its contracts with federal agencies, including the US Forest Service and Bureau of Land Management, to reduce hazardous fuels in Oregon, California and Idaho have been frozen.</p><p>“The funding freeze has impacted more than 30 separate grants and agreements that Lomakatsi has with federal agencies, including pending awards as well as active agreements that are already putting work on the ground,” the project’s executive director, Marko Bey, said in a letter to the senator Jeff Merkley of Oregon.</p><p>A spokesperson for the interior department, the parent agency of the Bureau of Land Management and the National Park Service, said it was reviewing funding decisions.</p><p>Senate Democrats have called on the administration to unlock fire-mitigation funding, and separately have asked interior and agriculture department leadership to exempt seasonal firefighters from a broad federal hiring freeze.</p><p>Grassroots Wildland Firefighters, an advocacy group for federal firefighters, said its members have been unable to hire the hundreds of firefighters that are typically brought on at this time of year to gear up for the summer fire season.</p><p>“The agencies already have had a recruitment and retention problem,” Riva Duncan, vice-president of the Grassroots Wildland Firefighters, said in an interview. “This just exacerbates that problem.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Sims Game Design Documents (1997) (333 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/</link>
            <guid>43064273</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2025 01:06:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/">https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43064273">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">

  <table>
   <tbody><tr><th><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/blank.gif" alt="[ICO]"></th><th><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/?C=N;O=D">Name</a></th><th><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/?C=M;O=A">Last modified</a></th><th><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/?C=S;O=A">Size</a></th><th><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/?C=D;O=A">Description</a></th></tr>
   <tr><th colspan="5"><hr></th></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/back.gif" alt="[PARENTDIR]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/">Parent Directory</a>       </td><td>&nbsp;</td><td>  - </td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/3DPeopleQuestion.pdf">3DPeopleQuestion.pdf</a>   </td><td>2012-12-20 10:41  </td><td>215K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/AnimationClassBreakdown.pdf">AnimationClassBreakd..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 12:07  </td><td> 48K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/AnimationDocumentation.pdf">AnimationDocumentati..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:27  </td><td>156K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ArtDepartmentPostMortum.pdf">ArtDepartmentPostMor..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:21  </td><td>106K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/BrainstormProblemListForArtTeam.pdf">BrainstormProblemLis..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:23  </td><td> 57K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch00-TableOfContents.pdf">Ch00-TableOfContents..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td> 64K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch01-Goals.pdf">Ch01-Goals.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:54  </td><td> 67K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch02-World.pdf">Ch02-World.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:52  </td><td>416K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch03-Objects.pdf">Ch03-Objects.pdf</a>       </td><td>2012-12-20 10:53  </td><td>1.5M</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch04-People.pdf">Ch04-People.pdf</a>        </td><td>2012-12-20 10:53  </td><td>460K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch05-PetsAndPests.pdf">Ch05-PetsAndPests.pdf</a>  </td><td>2012-12-20 10:54  </td><td> 57K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch06-Simulator.pdf">Ch06-Simulator.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td> 70K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch08-Framework.pdf">Ch08-Framework.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-20 10:54  </td><td> 81K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch09-Architecture.pdf">Ch09-Architecture.pdf</a>  </td><td>2012-12-20 10:57  </td><td>836K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch10-Graphics.pdf">Ch10-Graphics.pdf</a>      </td><td>2012-12-20 10:56  </td><td>832K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch11-Movement.pdf">Ch11-Movement.pdf</a>      </td><td>2012-12-20 10:53  </td><td>759K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch12-CharacterAnim.pdf">Ch12-CharacterAnim.pdf</a> </td><td>2012-12-20 10:54  </td><td>105K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch13-Sound.pdf">Ch13-Sound.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td> 76K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch14-Resources.pdf">Ch14-Resources.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td>132K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch16-Tools.pdf">Ch16-Tools.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td> 81K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch17-TDSB.pdf">Ch17-TDSB.pdf</a>          </td><td>2012-12-20 10:53  </td><td>273K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch18-ContentDevelopment.pdf">Ch18-ContentDevelopm..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td> 68K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch19-SoftwareDevelopment.pdf">Ch19-SoftwareDevelop..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:55  </td><td> 75K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch20-Documentation.pdf">Ch20-Documentation.pdf</a> </td><td>2012-12-20 10:56  </td><td> 74K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch21-Happy.pdf">Ch21-Happy.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:52  </td><td>226K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Ch22-ContainedInteractions.pdf">Ch22-ContainedIntera..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:56  </td><td>249K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/CharacterRenderingDevelopmentPlan.pdf">CharacterRenderingDe..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:40  </td><td>539K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ComprehensiveArtAssessment.pdf">ComprehensiveArtAsse..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:23  </td><td> 68K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ContentCreationRules.pdf">ContentCreationRules..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:24  </td><td> 86K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/CuckooClock.pdf">CuckooClock.pdf</a>        </td><td>2012-12-20 10:27  </td><td> 65K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/EdithDocumentationOverview.pdf">EdithDocumentationOv..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:34  </td><td> 99K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/EdithPrimitives.pdf">EdithPrimitives.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 10:34  </td><td>148K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/FailureTrees.pdf">FailureTrees.pdf</a>       </td><td>2012-12-20 12:07  </td><td> 49K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/FigureNG.pdf">FigureNG.pdf</a>           </td><td>2012-12-20 12:08  </td><td>218K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/FloatCompression.pdf">FloatCompression.pdf</a>   </td><td>2012-12-20 12:08  </td><td> 45K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/GuineaPigCage.pdf">GuineaPigCage.pdf</a>      </td><td>2012-12-20 10:25  </td><td> 80K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/HappyFriendsHome-2-10-96.pdf">HappyFriendsHome-2-1..&gt;</a></td><td>2011-02-11 03:51  </td><td>501K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/HitSoundRevivew.pdf">HitSoundRevivew.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 10:28  </td><td>137K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/HitSystemDesign.pdf">HitSystemDesign.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 10:27  </td><td>139K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/HowToPursueHappiness.pdf">HowToPursueHappiness..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:37  </td><td>144K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/JeffersonCharacterMotives.pdf">JeffersonCharacterMo..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:39  </td><td> 78K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/JeffersonDemoTutorial.pdf">JeffersonDemoTutoria..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 11:07  </td><td>170K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/JeffersonDevelopmentMilestones.pdf">JeffersonDevelopment..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:38  </td><td>114K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/JeffersonGameDescription.pdf">JeffersonGameDescrip..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:36  </td><td> 75K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/JeffersonSpectrumOfChallenge.pdf">JeffersonSpectrumOfC..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:45  </td><td>118K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/JeffersonTools.pdf">JeffersonTools.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-20 12:09  </td><td> 61K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/MasterIDAndSubIndexOverview.pdf">MasterIDAndSubIndexO..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:38  </td><td>137K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/MaxisSimRules.pdf">MaxisSimRules.pdf</a>      </td><td>2012-12-20 10:26  </td><td> 60K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/MooseHead.pdf">MooseHead.pdf</a>          </td><td>2012-12-20 10:26  </td><td> 65K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/NotesFromMaxisNewPencilPostmortem.pdf">NotesFromMaxisNewPen..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:28  </td><td> 92K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ObjectFileFormat.pdf">ObjectFileFormat.pdf</a>   </td><td>2012-12-20 10:29  </td><td>132K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ObjectIFFFileFormat.pdf">ObjectIFFFileFormat.pdf</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:30  </td><td>130K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ObjectList.pdf">ObjectList.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:30  </td><td>105K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ObjectMakingProcedure.pdf">ObjectMakingProcedur..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:30  </td><td> 69K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ProgrammingObjectsInTheSimsV3.pdf">ProgrammingObjectsIn..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:31  </td><td>2.4M</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ProgrammingSimsDialogs.pdf">ProgrammingSimsDialo..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:33  </td><td> 96K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ProposalForExtendingTheSimsFranchise.pdf">ProposalForExtending..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:41  </td><td> 85K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/QuickReferenceGuideForTheBewSimsSpriteExporter.pdf">QuickReferenceGuideF..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:42  </td><td> 89K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ResourceEXE.pdf">ResourceEXE.pdf</a>        </td><td>2012-12-20 10:42  </td><td> 84K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/ResourceFileOverview.pdf">ResourceFileOverview..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:42  </td><td> 63K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SimTransmogrifierDesign.pdf">SimTransmogrifierDes..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:44  </td><td> 49K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SimTransmogrifierTODO.pdf">SimTransmogrifierTOD..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 12:11  </td><td> 50K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SimsBoxXSpecAndDesign.pdf">SimsBoxXSpecAndDesig..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:42  </td><td>172K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SimsContentLibraryNotes.pdf">SimsContentLibraryNo..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 12:11  </td><td> 70K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SimsFileFormat.pdf">SimsFileFormat.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-20 10:43  </td><td> 52K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SimsScripts.pdf">SimsScripts.pdf</a>        </td><td>2012-12-20 12:11  </td><td>140K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SlotMachine.pdf">SlotMachine.pdf</a>        </td><td>2012-12-20 10:44  </td><td> 68K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SpriteGeneration.pdf">SpriteGeneration.pdf</a>   </td><td>2012-12-20 10:45  </td><td> 78K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SpriteRotations.pdf">SpriteRotations.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 12:12  </td><td> 39K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Storytelling.pdf">Storytelling.pdf</a>       </td><td>2012-12-20 12:05  </td><td>380K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Strategy.pdf">Strategy.pdf</a>           </td><td>2012-12-20 10:46  </td><td>685K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/SuitConventions.pdf">SuitConventions.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 10:46  </td><td> 90K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TDRObjects.pdf">TDRObjects.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 10:46  </td><td>144K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TDSB.pdf">TDSB.pdf</a>               </td><td>2012-12-20 10:48  </td><td>198K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TDSBInfo.pdf">TDSBInfo.pdf</a>           </td><td>2012-12-20 10:47  </td><td>112K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TDSEditToDo.pdf">TDSEditToDo.pdf</a>        </td><td>2012-12-20 10:48  </td><td>145K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TechnicalEmail.pdf">TechnicalEmail.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-21 16:11  </td><td>3.2M</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsDesignDocumentDraft3-DonsReview.pdf">TheSimsDesignDocumen..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:18  </td><td>342K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsDesignDocumentDraft5-8-31-98-DonsReview.pdf">TheSimsDesignDocumen..&gt;</a></td><td>2011-02-11 02:40  </td><td>2.4M</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsDesignDocumentDraft5-DonsReview.pdf">TheSimsDesignDocumen..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:19  </td><td>384K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsDesignDocumentDraft7-DonsReview.pdf">TheSimsDesignDocumen..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:19  </td><td>508K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsPieMenus.pdf">TheSimsPieMenus.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 11:06  </td><td> 20M</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsProjectCompletion-18-12-98.pdf">TheSimsProjectComple..&gt;</a></td><td>2011-02-11 03:30  </td><td>267K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSimsQuickStartGuide.pdf">TheSimsQuickStartGui..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 11:05  </td><td>108K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheSoulOfTheSims.pdf">TheSoulOfTheSims.pdf</a>   </td><td>2012-12-20 14:28  </td><td>2.9M</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TheStateOfTheArtAndGoingForwardToE3.pdf">TheStateOfTheArtAndG..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 10:21  </td><td> 91K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/Tools%20Proposal%20Updated.pdf">Tools Proposal Updat..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 11:06  </td><td> 89K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/TransmogriferRenovationPlan.pdf">TransmogriferRenovat..&gt;</a></td><td>2012-12-20 11:06  </td><td> 71K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/VM.pdf">VM.pdf</a>                 </td><td>2012-12-20 11:08  </td><td> 78K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/VMDesign.pdf">VMDesign.pdf</a>           </td><td>2012-12-20 11:08  </td><td>115K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/VirtualMachine.pdf">VirtualMachine.pdf</a>     </td><td>2012-12-20 11:07  </td><td>129K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/VitaboyOverview.pdf">VitaboyOverview.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 11:07  </td><td>140K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/WallLights.pdf">WallLights.pdf</a>         </td><td>2012-12-20 11:08  </td><td> 68K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
<tr><td><img src="https://donhopkins.com/icons/layout.gif" alt="[   ]"></td><td><a href="https://donhopkins.com/home/TheSimsDesignDocuments/XAnimatorDesign.pdf">XAnimatorDesign.pdf</a>    </td><td>2012-12-20 11:09  </td><td> 44K</td><td>&nbsp;</td></tr>
   <tr><th colspan="5"><hr></th></tr>
</tbody></table>

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jellyfin: The Free Software Media System (415 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jellyfin.org/</link>
            <guid>43063167</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 22:39:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jellyfin.org/">https://jellyfin.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43063167">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__docusaurus_skipToContent_fallback"><header><div><p>Jellyfin is the volunteer-built media solution that puts <em>you</em> in control of your media. Stream to any device from your own server, with no strings attached. Your media, your server, your way.</p><p><a href="https://jellyfin.org/docs/general/community-standards/servers">Note: We do not run servers for users.</a></p></div></header><main><div><h2>What is Jellyfin?</h2><p>Jellyfin enables you to collect, manage, and stream your media. Run the Jellyfin server on your system and gain access to the leading free-software entertainment system, bells <em>and</em> whistles included.</p></div><div><h2>Your media, wherever you&nbsp;are</h2><p>With a large array of official and third-party clients, Jellyfin is available on most popular platforms. Your media is ready to follow you, wherever you go.</p></div><div><p><h2>See Jellyfin in Action</h2></p></div><div><div><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="48" height="48" fill="currentColor" viewBox="0 0 24 24"><title>Open Source Initiative</title><path d="M11.959.447A11.938 11.938 0 000 12.407c0 5.576 3.874 10.097 7.783 11.114.193.05.392-.05.467-.234l2.771-6.822a.396.396 0 00-.246-.528C9.365 15.47 8.53 14.32 8.48 12.4c-.024-1.828 1.5-3.45 3.561-3.447 1.931.003 3.479 1.632 3.479 3.453 0 .966-.203 1.687-.575 2.238-.371.552-.922.951-1.695 1.239a.396.396 0 00-.23.515l2.685 6.903a.396.396 0 00.465.24C20.163 22.534 24 18.062 24 12.406 24 5.804 18.603.447 11.959.447zm0 .791c6.22 0 11.25 4.997 11.25 11.168 0 5.138-3.423 9.208-6.895 10.272L13.9 16.47c.703-.308 1.302-.79 1.702-1.384.477-.708.709-1.602.709-2.68 0-2.266-1.898-4.24-4.27-4.244-2.48-.004-4.382 1.976-4.352 4.25.023 1.995.934 3.492 2.451 4.13L7.648 22.66C4.251 21.592.791 17.458.791 12.406A11.13 11.13 0 0111.959 1.238zm10.617 20.149a1.03 1.03 0 000 2.058 1.03 1.03 0 000-2.058zm0 .162c.48 0 .865.388.865.867a.856.856 0 01-.271.623l-.172-.342a.847.847 0 00-.111-.178.263.263 0 00-.114-.084.301.301 0 00.17-.117.356.356 0 00.061-.21c0-.13-.038-.227-.113-.292-.076-.064-.192-.095-.346-.095h-.41v1.343h.181v-.568h.2c.072 0 .128.015.17.045a.48.48 0 01.129.18l.171.343.157.001a.878.878 0 01-.567.216.865.865 0 010-1.732zm-.26.322h.229c.088 0 .155.018.2.059.044.04.066.099.066.177 0 .079-.022.14-.067.18-.044.04-.111.06-.2.06h-.228z"></path></svg><h3>Free Software</h3><p>Jellyfin is Free Software, licensed under the GNU GPL. You can use it, study it, modify it, build it, and distribute it for free, as long as your changes are licensed the same way.</p></div><div><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" style="width:48px;height:48px" role="presentation"><path d="M12,5.5A3.5,3.5 0 0,1 15.5,9A3.5,3.5 0 0,1 12,12.5A3.5,3.5 0 0,1 8.5,9A3.5,3.5 0 0,1 12,5.5M5,8C5.56,8 6.08,8.15 6.53,8.42C6.38,9.85 6.8,11.27 7.66,12.38C7.16,13.34 6.16,14 5,14A3,3 0 0,1 2,11A3,3 0 0,1 5,8M19,8A3,3 0 0,1 22,11A3,3 0 0,1 19,14C17.84,14 16.84,13.34 16.34,12.38C17.2,11.27 17.62,9.85 17.47,8.42C17.92,8.15 18.44,8 19,8M5.5,18.25C5.5,16.18 8.41,14.5 12,14.5C15.59,14.5 18.5,16.18 18.5,18.25V20H5.5V18.25M0,20V18.5C0,17.11 1.89,15.94 4.45,15.6C3.86,16.28 3.5,17.22 3.5,18.25V20H0M24,20H20.5V18.25C20.5,17.22 20.14,16.28 19.55,15.6C22.11,15.94 24,17.11 24,18.5V20Z" style="fill:currentColor"></path></svg><h3>Community Built</h3><p>The project relies entirely on contributions from volunteers. Want to help out? There’s lots of ways to do so, and you don’t even have to code! See our <a href="https://jellyfin.org/contribute">contribution guide</a> for more details.</p></div><div><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" style="width:48px;height:48px" role="presentation"><path d="M3,4.27L4.28,3L21,19.72L19.73,21L16.06,17.33C15.44,18 14.54,18.55 13.5,18.82V21H10.5V18.82C8.47,18.31 7,16.79 7,15H9C9,16.08 10.37,17 12,17C13.13,17 14.14,16.56 14.65,15.92L11.68,12.95C9.58,12.42 7,11.75 7,9C7,8.77 7,8.55 7.07,8.34L3,4.27M10.5,5.18V3H13.5V5.18C15.53,5.69 17,7.21 17,9H15C15,7.92 13.63,7 12,7C11.63,7 11.28,7.05 10.95,7.13L9.4,5.58L10.5,5.18Z" style="fill:currentColor"></path></svg><h3>No Fees</h3><p>The Jellyfin server and official clients are free to download, now and always. There are no costs, hidden or otherwise, to use Jellyfin, either for yourself, for your friends, or for your company. All our incidental costs are paid through donations from users like you.</p></div><div><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" style="width:48px;height:48px" role="presentation"><path d="M12,17A2,2 0 0,0 14,15C14,13.89 13.1,13 12,13A2,2 0 0,0 10,15A2,2 0 0,0 12,17M18,8A2,2 0 0,1 20,10V20A2,2 0 0,1 18,22H6A2,2 0 0,1 4,20V10C4,8.89 4.9,8 6,8H7V6A5,5 0 0,1 12,1A5,5 0 0,1 17,6V8H18M12,3A3,3 0 0,0 9,6V8H15V6A3,3 0 0,0 12,3Z" style="fill:currentColor"></path></svg><h3>Privacy Focused</h3><p>Jellyfin has no tracking, phone-home, or central servers collecting your data. We believe in keeping our software open and transparent. We’re also not in the media business, so the only media you see is your own.</p></div></div><div><h2>Get Started Now</h2><p>Check out our Getting Started guide to download and set up your server today.</p><p><a href="https://jellyfin.org/downloads/server">Download Jellyfin</a></p></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Watt The Fox? (273 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://h.43z.one/blog/2025-02-12/</link>
            <guid>43062546</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 21:32:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://h.43z.one/blog/2025-02-12/">https://h.43z.one/blog/2025-02-12/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43062546">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
  
  <h3>how websites waste CPU cycles &amp; battery and Firefox lets them</h3>
<h4>by <a href="https://x.com/h43z">h43z</a> (<a href="https://h.43z.one/">hompage</a>)</h4>
  <p>I recently got a new notebook and noticed that the speakers would occasionally emit a faint but annoying white noise. This issue was only noticeable in a quiet room when no music or other audio was playing through the speakers.</p>
  <p>After some digging, I came across the following command</p>
  <pre><code>pactl list sinks short</code></pre>
  <p>(check powercfg /requests on windows?!)</p>
  <p>This command lists all available audio sinks for PulseAudio on Linux along with their current state. The states can be one of the following: IDLE, SUSPENDED, or RUNNING.</p>
  <p>I observed that the speakers remained silent whenever the audio sink was in the SUSPENDED state. However, the white noise would sometimes occur when the sink was in IDLE or RUNNING, even when no music or sounds were being played.</p>
  <p>Even though I had the setting to automatically suspend the audio sinks after 10 seconds of inactivity:</p>
  <pre><code>% grep -R module-suspend-on-idle /etc/pulse/
/etc/pulse/default.pa:load-module module-suspend-on-idle
/etc/pulse/system.pa:load-module module-suspend-on-idle</code></pre>
  <p>But sometimes, the sink never went IDLE and therefore never got SUSPENDED.</p>
  <p>The manual for module-suspend-on-idle says:</p>
  <pre><code>Since 0.9.11. Disconnects sinks and sources from their backend after a
predetermined amount of idle time. Idle time is accumulated when the sink/source
in question is not connected to any streams.

Advantages: Saves power. ALSA uses considerably more CPU cycles when pulseaudio
has to send empty data to the soundcard during idle. If you don't plan to have
an active stream all the time, set the timer to a low value for best power savings.</code></pre>
  <p>I began using the command:</p>
  <pre><code>pactl list sink-inputs</code></pre>
  <p>whenever I noticed the white noise, trying to identify which program was using the audio sink.</p>
  <p>It turned out to always be Firefox. However, none of the open tabs were supposed to play any sound—not even muted videos.</p>
  <p>To get behind what was going on, I created a small script for my i3 status bar. The script displays a red indicator whenever the audio sink switched to the RUNNING state.</p>
  <p>The culprit seemed to be the notification sound from my pinned tab of <a href="https://outlook.office.com/">outlook.office.com</a>. Whenever I received an email, the white noise would start and wouldn't stop until I reloaded the tab or restarted Firefox.</p>
  <p>This issue was not just about the annoying white noise—it was also draining my notebook’s battery faster.</p>
  <p>Here’s the CPU/power consumption without the white noise:</p>
  <pre><code>$ htop -F pulseaudio
    PID USER      PRI  NI  VIRT   RES   SHR S CPU% MEM%   TIME+ ▽Command
   3770 h43z        9 -11 1094M 30924 21580 S  0.0  0.1 10:57.51 /usr/bin/pulseaudio --daemonize=no --log-target=journal

$ powerstat -d0 3
  Time    User  Nice   Sys  Idle    IO  Run Ctxt/s  IRQ/s  Watts
20:54:31   0.8   0.1   0.5  98.6   0.0    1    957    900   4.42
20:54:34   0.0   0.1   0.2  99.7   0.0    1    728    591   4.34
20:54:37   0.3   0.1   1.3  98.2   0.1    1   1444   1241   4.32
20:54:40   0.0   0.1   0.1  99.8   0.0    1    695    556   4.46
20:54:43   0.4   0.1   0.4  99.1   0.0    1   1322    935   5.08
20:54:46   0.1   0.1   0.4  99.4   0.0    1   1216    944   4.50
20:54:49   0.0   0.1   0.1  99.8   0.0    1   1032    742   4.45
20:54:52   0.0   0.1   0.2  99.7   0.1    1    952    667   4.44
20:54:55   0.0   0.0   0.3  99.7   0.0    1    873    676   4.31
20:54:58   0.2   0.1   1.1  98.4   0.1    1   1508   1244   4.26
20:55:01   0.1   0.1   0.3  99.5   0.0    1   1191    877   4.42
20:55:04   0.1   0.1   0.3  99.6   0.0    1    994    757   4.44
20:55:07   0.6   0.1   0.3  99.0   0.0    1   1304    947   4.20
20:55:10   0.1   0.1   0.2  99.6   0.0    1    953    696   4.30
20:55:13   0.0   0.2   0.3  99.5   0.0    1    903    701   4.17
<code></code></code></pre><code><code>
  <p>And here with the noise:</p>
  <pre><code>$ htop -F pulseaudio
    PID USER      PRI  NI  VIRT   RES   SHR S CPU% MEM%   TIME+ ▽Command
   3770 h43z        9 -11 1094M 30924 21580 S  4.7  0.1 10:56.31 /usr/bin/pulseaudio --daemonize=no --log-target=journal

$ powerstat -d0 3
  Time    User  Nice   Sys  Idle    IO  Run Ctxt/s  IRQ/s  Watts
20:52:42   0.7   0.1   1.3  98.0   0.0    1   3460   1542   5.98
20:52:45   0.7   0.1   1.4  97.8   0.0    2   3723   1788   6.00
20:52:48   0.7   0.1   1.4  97.8   0.0    3   3487   1719   5.99
20:52:51   1.1   0.1   1.4  97.5   0.0    1   3916   1861   6.34
20:52:54   0.6   0.1   1.3  98.0   0.0    1   3514   1692   5.89
20:52:57   0.7   0.1   1.8  97.3   0.1    1   3956   2067   6.57
20:53:00   0.8   0.1   1.1  98.0   0.0    1   3534   1522   5.88
20:53:03   0.6   0.1   1.2  98.0   0.0    1   3437   1626   5.87
20:53:06   0.7   0.0   1.2  98.0   0.0    1   3400   1700   5.94
20:53:09   0.8   0.1   1.3  97.9   0.0    2   3474   1421   5.88
20:53:12   0.7   0.1   1.2  98.0   0.0    1   3317   1441   5.84
20:53:15   1.3   0.1   1.6  97.0   0.0    4   3841   1777   5.83
20:53:18   1.1   0.1   1.6  97.1   0.1    1   4161   1906   5.87
20:53:21   0.7   0.1   1.3  97.9   0.0    1   3422   1505   5.90
20:53:24   1.5   0.1   1.7  96.8   0.0    3   3430   1707   5.91
20:53:27   0.7   0.1   1.3  97.9   0.0    1   3375   1511   6.73
20:53:30   0.7   0.0   1.2  98.0   0.0    1   3572   1563   6.13
<code></code></code></pre><code><code>
  <p>It's not nothing—about 1.5 Watt more.</p>
  <p>So, with a heavy heart, I decided to disable email notifications—even though I really wanted to keep them—but eliminating the white noise was my priority.</p>
    <p>I thought I had “fixed” the problem. Of course, I blamed Microsoft, right?</p>
    
    <div><p>But the red sound indicator on my i3 status bar kept lighting up occasionally.</p><p>

    And it turned out other websites were also triggering the white noise.</p></div>
    
    <p>For instance, as soon as I clicked anywhere on <a href="https://x.com/" target="_blank">x.com</a>, the noise started. Similarly, whenever I listened to a translation on <a href="https://translate.google.com/" target="_blank">translate.google.com</a>, there was the noise.</p>
    
    <p>And just having the <a href="https://discord.com/app" target="_blank">Discord (web app)</a> website open, same ugly effect.</p>
    
    <p>So now I was really curious. What is going on here.</p>
    
    <p>I started to look up how you can play audio with HTML/JavaScript.<br>
    There seem to be two ways: Either with the <code>&lt;audio&gt;</code> tag or the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Web_Audio_API" target="_blank">WebAudio API</a>.</p>
    
    <p>As Outlook plays sound dynamically, I knew it must use the WebAudio API.<br>
    And to do anything with audio, you first have to create an <code>AudioContext</code>.</p>

  <pre><code>const audioCtx = new AudioContext();</code></pre>
  <p>And already here I realized the problem. Just creating this AudioContext makes my speakers play white noise.</p>
  <p>You can test it here: <a href="https://editor.43z.one/sqare/i">https://editor.43z.one/sqare</a></p>
  <p>The MDN article is pretty clear about it.</p>
  <pre><code>AudioContext.suspend()
Suspends the progression of time in the audio context, temporarily halting<br> audio hardware access and reducing CPU/battery usage in the process.

AudioContext.resume()
Resumes the progression of time in an audio context that has previously<br> been suspended.</code></pre>
<p>(easy peasy <a href="https://editor.43z.one/13zzt">https://editor.43z.one/13zzt)</a>
  </p><p>Yet, most websites never bother suspending the AudioContext and create one without the immediate need for playing sound.</p>

<p>Chrome stops the battery/CPU waste automatically afte some time. Firefox not. It just keeps playing the whitenoise.</p>

<p>I understand that the websites are to blame here.</p>
<p>But still, Cmon Firefox, protect me from this resource theft?!</p>
<p>Oh and btw I suspect this also wastes my bluetooth headphones battery if they are connected?! Once I do a click on x.com the sending of white noise starts.</p>
<video width="320" height="240" controls="" preload="none">
  <source src="https://h.43z.one/blog/2025-02-12/bluetooth.mp4" type="video/mp4">
</video>

  <p>To address this total mess, I created an extension that automatically suspends the AudioContext while also
tries to resume it if the websites wants to play sound.</p><p>It's not perfect as resuming takes a little bit of time and it
  may not always resume, as there are multiple paths to starting audio. But it's good enough for me.</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/audiocontext-suspender/">Firefox Addon: AudioContext Suspender</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://github.com/h43z/audiocontextsuspender">GitHub Repository</a></li>
  </ul>
  <p>Some Relevant Bugzilla reports</p>
  <ul>
    <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1165677">Bug 1165677</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1706993">Bug 1706993</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1638685">Bug 1638685</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1427937">Bug 1427937</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1863193">Bug 1863193</a></li>
<li><a href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1771179">Bug 1771179</a></li>
  </ul>

More fun stuff at <a href="https://h.43z.one/">h.43z.one</a>.<br>
Unshadow ban me at <a href="https://x.com/h43z">𝕏</a>



</code></code></code></code></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The European Vat Is Not a Discriminatory Tax Against US Exports (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://taxfoundation.org/blog/trump-reciprocal-tariffs-eu-vat-discriminatory/</link>
            <guid>43062457</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 21:20:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/blog/trump-reciprocal-tariffs-eu-vat-discriminatory/">https://taxfoundation.org/blog/trump-reciprocal-tariffs-eu-vat-discriminatory/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43062457">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    
<article id="post-183416">
    
  
  <div>
    
<p>The <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/research/federal-tax/trump-administration-tax-proposals/">Trump</a> administration has once again floated the idea of “reciprocal” <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/research/all/federal/trump-tariffs-trade-war/">tariffs</a> on foreign countries. While it is unclear what formula the administration will use to determine what is “reciprocal,” the intention of responding to foreign charges—real and perceived—is clear enough.</p>
<p>In the past, the administration has made general assertions about different <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tariffs/">tariff</a><cite>Tariffs are taxes imposed by one country on goods imported from another country. Tariffs are <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/topics/tariffs-and-trade/">trade barriers</a> that raise prices, reduce available quantities of goods and services for <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/research/all/federal/trump-tariffs-biden-tariffs/">US businesses and consumers</a>, and create an economic burden on foreign exporters.
</cite></span> and nontariff barriers that American exporters face that should be rectified by “reciprocal” US tariffs. Trump commonly <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/european-carmakers-crossfire-united-states-europe-trade-war/">mentions</a> that the EU charges a 10 percent import <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax/">tax</a><cite>A tax is a mandatory payment or charge collected by local, state, and national governments from individuals or businesses to cover the costs of general government services, goods, and activities.
</cite></span> on US vehicles while the US only levies a 2.5 percent tariff on European cars coming into the US. Though one can certainly find examples of higher trade barriers abroad, the <a href="https://www.cato.org/commentary/tariff-myths-debunked?gad_source=1&amp;gclid=CjwKCAiAqrG9BhAVEiwAaPu5zgSuxH-XwbT7Kgb7FE6uvM7OAkMDDekbiXjFKgJwJ802UUqtLUJabhoC4ukQAvD_BwE">overall tariff gap</a> between the US and its trading partners is <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/fernando-mart%C3%ADn-711a5790_us-export-coverages-activity-7295353938608820224-aT4M?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAA_TE_ABEkKJ4JUzvJbx21NNIBaNIUkAoX8">relatively minor</a>—and any increase in US tariffs will ultimately be paid by US businesses and consumers.  </p>
<p>However, when discussing trade with the EU specifically, White House deputy chief of staff, Stephen Miller, <a href="https://www.realclearpolitics.com/video/2025/02/09/miller_trump_trade_action_against_europe_will_offset_eu_regulations_and_vat_taxes_on_american_products.html" rel="nofollow">added</a> a new policy grievance to the mix: <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/value-added-tax-vat/">value-added taxes (VAT)</a>.  </p>
<p>“Did you know when you ship a car from the US to Europe, if they let it in at all because they have many nontariff barriers, between the VAT and duties, that car is taxed at 30%? The German car—or a European car sent the America is taxed at 2.5%—or basically 0.”</p>
<p>His statement assumes that a VAT discriminates against American car exports like a tariff, and conversely, that the VAT rebate provided to European car producers exporting to the US constitutes a subsidy and the car then simply faces a tariff and no VAT. (It is worth noting that both a domestic automobile and a European car sold in the US would face US state <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/sales-tax/">sales tax</a><cite>A sales tax is levied on retail sales of goods and services and, ideally, should apply to all final <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/consumption-tax/">consumption</a> with few <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax-exemption/">exemptions</a>. Many governments exempt goods like groceries; <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/base-broadening/">base broadening</a>, such as including groceries, could keep rates lower. A sales tax should exempt business-to-business transactions which, when taxed, cause <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax-pyramiding/">tax pyramiding</a>.
</cite></span>.) </p>
<p><span>While it</span> may seem like a compelling political argument to justify across-the-board tariffs on the EU, it instead reflects a complete misunderstanding of what a VAT is and how it works. Worse, it misplaces the blame for a lack of US competitiveness on the European VAT instead of reevaluating the flaws of both the US federal and state tax systems.  </p>
<h2><strong>What is VAT and how does it work for exported goods?</strong></h2>
<p><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/value-added-tax-vat/">VATs</a> are border-adjusted, meaning they rebate tax on exports and impose tax on imports. Despite the appearance of subsidizing exports and punishing imports, however, a border-adjusted VAT is trade neutral. A border adjusted tax leads to currency appreciation for the imposing country, which would make it cheaper to import goods, more expensive to export goods, and thus would cancel out the apparent benefits of the tax on imports and the rebate on exports.</p>
<p>If there is a complaint to be made about tax policy and implications for US competitiveness in Europe, it is about uncompetitive state sales tax structures in the US system that yield what is known as “<span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax-pyramiding/">tax pyramiding</a><cite><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax/">Tax</a> pyramiding occurs when the same final good or service is taxed multiple times along the production process. This yields vastly different effective tax rates depending on the length of the supply chain and disproportionately harms low-margin firms. <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/gross-receipts-tax/">Gross receipts taxes</a> are a prime example of tax pyramiding in action.
</cite></span>.”</p>
<h2><strong>What is US sales tax and how does it work for exported goods? </strong></h2>
<p>Unlike most countries, the <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/location/united-states/">United States</a> does not impose a broad-based <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/consumption-tax/">consumption tax</a><cite>A consumption tax is typically levied on the purchase of goods or services and is paid <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/direct-tax/">directly</a> or <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/indirect-tax/">indirectly</a> by the consumer in the form of retail <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/sales-tax/">sales taxes</a>, <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/excise-tax/">excise taxes</a>, <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tariffs/">tariffs</a>, <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/value-added-tax-vat/">value-added taxes (VAT)</a>, or an <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/individual-income-tax/">income tax</a> where all savings is tax-<a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax-deduction/">deductible</a>.
</cite></span> at the national (federal) level, and state-level consumption taxes are designed as general sales taxes rather than value-added taxes. Whereas a VAT is imposed on the incremental increase in value of a good or service at each stage of production, a <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/sales-tax/">sales tax</a> is imposed on the total transaction price of any taxed good or service.</p>
<p>If a sales tax is imposed exclusively on final consumption, then VATs and sales taxes are economically identical. However, when the sales tax is applied to some intermediate transactions (“business inputs”), it results in tax pyramiding, where the tax is embedded in the price multiple times over.</p>
<p>Consider the following example of a 5 percent VAT and two versions of a 5 percent sales tax—one which only applies to final consumption, and one which applies to certain intermediate transactions as well.</p>
<h4>VATs and Ideal Sales Taxes are Economically Identical</h4><h5><em>A 5% VAT compared to a 5% ideal sales tax and a 5% sales tax with business input taxation</em></h5>


<!-- #tablepress-803 from cache -->
<p>Note that, while a VAT is imposed at every stage of the process, the net effect is to apply the rate one time to the final sales price. The tax is collected in increments (on the “value added” at each stage), but unlike with a pyramiding sales tax, it does not double tax inputs. The VAT and ideal sales tax share an identical <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/tax-base/">tax base</a><cite>The tax base is the total amount of income, property, assets, consumption, transactions, or other economic activity subject to taxation by a tax authority. A narrow tax base is non-neutral and inefficient. A <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/base-broadening/">broad</a> tax base reduces tax administration costs and allows more revenue to be raised at lower rates.
</cite></span> and, if imposed at the same rates, yield identical collections.</p>
<p>US sales taxes are typically destination-based, meaning that the tax is owed where the product is received or consumed. If a European resident orders from a US retailer, they do not pay US sales tax, just like a US consumer can obtain a VAT rebate on purchases of European products. Neither is a subsidy. These are simply consumption taxes falling on the consumer.</p>
<p>In practice, however, US sales taxes diverge sharply from the ideal. More than 40 percent of US sales tax revenue comes from intermediate transactions, which impose costs on US producers. This design flaw is not present in VATs, which do not double-tax intermediate transactions. Consequently, the sales tax imposes a penalty on domestic production that a VAT (or a better designed sales tax) would not. European VATs aren’t subsidizing anything—US states are just shooting themselves in the foot.</p>
<p>Crucially, this is true in domestic as well as international sales. If a state’s sales tax only applied to final consumption, it would never put in-state businesses at a disadvantage against rivals in other states, because consumers elsewhere are subject to their own state’s sales tax. A <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/location/maryland/">Maryland</a> resident pays 6 percent sales tax on whatever she orders (that’s subject to Maryland’s sales tax), regardless of whether she buys from a retailer in Maryland, or <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/location/delaware/">Delaware</a> (with no sales tax), or <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/location/louisiana/">Louisiana</a> (with an average rate north of 10 percent). But when Maryland taxes business inputs, that imposes a cost on Maryland businesses that could be mitigated if businesses operated in lower-tax states or in states which include fewer inputs in their tax base.</p>
<p>The disadvantages created by the sales tax, therefore, aren’t unique to goods exported abroad. They aren’t the consequence of trade policy, but of poor tax policy. Europe’s VATs are not tariffs and are not subsidizing European exports. Instead, US states’ poorly-designed sales taxes are harming their own businesses’ competitiveness—whether they’re selling down the street, across state lines, or around the world.</p>
<h2><strong>What competitiveness issues remain with the US federal tax system?</strong></h2>
<p>Just like state sales tax systems can create a competitive disadvantage for producers, certain elements of the federal income tax system harm incentives to invest domestically. Despite progress made by the 2017 Tax Cuts and Jobs Act, the US maintains long <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/depreciation/">depreciation</a><cite>Depreciation is a measurement of the “useful life” of a business asset, such as machinery or a factory, to determine the multiyear period over which the cost of that asset can be deducted from <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/taxable-income/">taxable income</a>. Instead of allowing businesses to deduct the cost of investments immediately (i.e., <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/full-expensing/">full expensing</a>), depreciation requires deductions to be taken over time, reducing their value and discouraging investment.
</cite></span> schedules for structures investment, now requires amortization for research and development expenses, and is phasing out <span><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/taxedu/glossary/bonus-depreciation/">bonus depreciation</a><cite>Bonus depreciation allows firms to deduct a larger portion of certain “short-lived” investments in new or improved technology, equipment, or buildings in the first year. Allowing businesses to write off more investments partially alleviates a bias in the tax code and incentivizes companies to invest more, which, in the long run, raises worker productivity, boosts wages, and creates more jobs.
</cite></span> for machinery and equipment investment. The absence of full, immediate deductions for investment increases the cost of capital, and thus discourages investment and wage growth.</p>
<p>Rather than focus on raising tariffs, which i<a href="https://taxfoundation.org/testimony/tariffs-alternatives-boost-us-competitiveness/">ncrease the cost</a> of operating in the United States and <a href="https://taxfoundation.org/testimony/tariffs-alternatives-boost-us-competitiveness/">reduce total output and productivity</a>, fiscal policy reforms to improve the structure of the federal income tax system can better boost competitiveness of the US manufacturing sector.</p>
<h2><strong>Conclusion </strong></h2>
<p>Countries have many reasons why they apply different tariff rates to different products. In the case of the United States, some tariffs date back to the 1930s Smoot-Hawley tariff schedule, while other US trade barriers take on non-tariff forms. The Trump administration appears to be moving in a “reciprocal” policy direction despite the significant negative economic consequences for American consumers of across-the-board tariffs on goods coming into the US. However, the EU’s VAT system should not be used as a justification for retaliatory tariffs. </p>
<p><iframe title="YouTube video player" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/n_DRLnWgs6M?si=v9QmaIwzO7oQ5EsU" width="560" height="450" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"><span data-mce-type="bookmark" style="display: inline-block; width: 0px; overflow: hidden; line-height: 0;" class="mce_SELRES_start">&#65279;</span></iframe></p>
<div data-id="1"><h2>Stay informed on the tax policies impacting you.</h2><p>Subscribe to get insights from our trusted experts delivered straight to your inbox.</p>
<p><a href="https://taxfoundation.org/tax-newsletter">Subscribe</a></p></div>


  </div>

  

</article>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Is the ArXiv safe from the current US Government attacks? (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mathstodon.xyz/@MartinEscardo/114009071233958003</link>
            <guid>43062098</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 20:38:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mathstodon.xyz/@MartinEscardo/114009071233958003">https://mathstodon.xyz/@MartinEscardo/114009071233958003</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43062098">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[NASA has a list of 10 rules for software development (316 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cs.otago.ac.nz/cosc345/resources/nasa-10-rules.htm</link>
            <guid>43061977</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 20:24:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cs.otago.ac.nz/cosc345/resources/nasa-10-rules.htm">https://www.cs.otago.ac.nz/cosc345/resources/nasa-10-rules.htm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061977">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
<h2>NASA has a list of 10 rules for software development</h2>

<p>Read the <a href="https://www.cs.otago.ac.nz/cosc345/resources/nasa-10-rules.pdf">full document (local copy)</a>
or the <a href="http://spinroot.com/gerard/pdf/P10.pdf">original</a>.
Read it first, before reading these comments.

</p><p>Those rules were written from the point of view of people writing
embedded software for extremely expensive spacecraft, where tolerating
a lot of programming pain is a good tradeoff for not losing a mission.
I do not know why someone in that situation does not use the SPARK
subset of Ada, which subset was explicitly designed for verification,
and is simply a better starting point for embedded programming than C.
</p><p>I am criticising them from the point of view of people writing
programming language processors (compilers, interpreters, editors)
and application software.
</p><p>We are supposed to teach critical thinking.  This is an example.
</p><ul>
<li>How have Gerard J. Holzmann's and my different contexts affected
our judgement?
</li><li>Can you blindly follow his advice without considering <em>your</em>
context?
</li><li>Can you blindly follow <em>my</em> advice without considering
your context?
</li><li>Would these rules necessarily apply to a different/better
programming language?  What if <a href="#ppar">function pointers
were tamed</a>?  What if the language provided opaque abstract
data types as Ada does?
</li></ul>

<h3>1. Restrict all code to very simple control flow constructs —
do not use <code>goto</code> statements,
<code>setjmp()</code> or <code>longjmp()</code> constructs,
and direct or indirect <em>recursion</em>.</h3>

<p>Note that <code>setjmp()</code> and <code>longjmp()</code>
are how C does exception handling, so this rule bans any use
of exception handling.

</p><p>It is true that banning recursion and jumps and loops without
explicit bounds means that you <em>know</em> your program is
going to terminate.  It is also true that recursive functions
can be proven to terminate about as often as loops can, with
reasonably well-understood methods.  What's more important here is
that “sure to terminate” does not imply
“sure to terminate in my lifetime”:
</p><pre>    int const N = 1000000000;
    for (x0 = 0; x0 != N; x0++)
    for (x1 = 0; x1 != N; x1++)
    for (x2 = 0; x2 != N; x2++)
    for (x3 = 0; x3 != N; x3++)
    for (x4 = 0; x4 != N; x4++)
    for (x5 = 0; x5 != N; x5++)
    for (x6 = 0; x6 != N; x6++)
    for (x7 = 0; x7 != N; x7++)
    for (x8 = 0; x8 != N; x8++)
    for (x9 = 0; x9 != N; x9++)
        -- do something --;
</pre>
<p>This does a bounded number of iterations.  The bound is N<sup>10</sup>.
In this case, that's 10<sup>90</sup>.  If each iteration of the loop body
takes 1 nsec, that's 10<sup>81</sup> seconds, or about 7.9×10<sup>72</sup>
years.  What is the <em>practical</em> difference between “will stop
in 7,900,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000
years” and “will never stop”?

</p><p>Worse still, taking a problem that is <em>naturally</em> expressed
using recursion and contorting it into something that manipulates an
explicit stack, while possible, turns clear maintainable code into
buggy spaghetti.  (I've done it, several times.  There's an example
on this web site.  It is <em>not</em> a good idea.)

</p><h3>2. All loops must have a fixed upper-bound.  It must be trivially
possible for a checking tool to prove statically that a preset
upper-bound on the number of iterations of a loop cannot be exceeded.
If the loop-bound cannot be proven statically, the rule is considered
violated.</h3>

<p>This is an old idea.  As the example above shows, it is not enough
by itself to be of any practical use.  You have to try to make the
bounds reasonably <em>tight</em>, and you have to regard hitting an
artificial bound as a run-time error.

</p><p>By the way, note that putting depth bounds on recursive procedures
makes them every bit as safe as loops with fixed bounds.

</p><h3>3. Do not use dynamic memory allocation after initialization.</h3>

<p>This is also a very old idea.  Some languages designed for embedded
work don't even <em>have</em> dynamic memory allocation.  The big
thing, of course, is that embedded applications have a fixed amount of
memory to work with, are never going to get any more, and should not
crash because they couldn't handle another record.

</p><p>Note that the rationale actually supports a much stronger rule:
don't even <em>simulate</em> dynamic memory allocation.  You can of
course manage your own storage pool:
</p><pre>    typedef struct Foo_Record *foo;
    struct Foo_Record {
	foo next;
	...
    };
    #define MAX_FOOS ...
    static struct Foo_Record foo_zone[MAX_FOOS];
    foo foo_free_list = 0;

    void init_foo_free_list() {
	for (int i = MAX_FOOS - 1; i &gt;= 0; i--) {
	    foo_zone[i].next = foo_free_list;
	    foo_free_list = &amp;foo_zone[i];
	}
    }

    foo malloc_foo() {
	foo r = foo_free_list;
	if (r == 0) report_error();
	foo_free_list = r-&gt;next;
	return r;
    }

    void free_foo(foo x) {
	x-&gt;next = foo_free_list;
	foo_free_list = x;
    }
</pre>
<p>This <em>technically</em> satisfies the rule, but it
violates the <em>spirit</em> of the rule.  Simulating malloc()
and free() this way is <em>worse</em> than using the real
thing, because the memory in foo_zone is permanently tied up
for Foo_Records, even if we don't need any of those at the
moment but do desperately need the memory for something else.

</p><p>What you really need to do is to use a memory allocator
with known behaviour, and to prove that the amount of memory
in use at any given time (data bytes + headers) is bounded
by a known value.

</p><p>Note also that SPlint can verify at compile time that
the errors NASA speak of do not occur.

</p><p>One of the reasons given for the ban is that the performance
of malloc() and free() is unpredictable.  Are these the only
functions we use with unpredictable performance?  Is there
anything about malloc() and free() which makes them
<em>necessarily</em> unpredictable?  The existence of
hard-real-time garbage collectors suggests not.

</p><p>The rationale for this rule says that
</p><blockquote>
Note that the only way
to dynamically claim memory in the absence of memory allocation from the
heap is to use stack memory.  In the absence of recursion (Rule 1), an
upper bound on the use of stack memory can derived statically, thus
making it possible to prove that an application will always live within
its pre-allocated memory means.
</blockquote>
<p>Unfortunately, the sunny optimism shown here is unjustified.  Given
the ISO C standard (any version, C89, C99, or C11) it is <em>impossible</em>
to determine an upper bound on the use of stack memory.  There is not even
any standard way to determine how much memory a compiler will use for the
stack frame of a given function.  (There could have been.  There just isn't.)
There isn't even any requirement that two invocations of the same function
with the same arguments will use the same amount of memory.
Such a bound can only be calculated for a <em>specific</em> version of a
specific compiler with specific options.  Here's a trivial example:
</p><pre>void f() {
    char a[100000];
}
</pre>
<p>How much memory will that take on the stack?  Compiled for debugging,
it might take a full stack frame (however big that is) plus traceback
information plus a million bytes for a[].  Compiled with optimisation,
the compiler might notice that a[] isn't used, and might even compile
calls to f() inline so that they generate no code and take no space.
That's an extreme example, but not really unfair.  If you want bounds
you can rely on, you had better <em>check</em> what your compiler does,
and recheck every time anything about the compiler changes.

</p><h3>4.  No function should be longer than what can be printed on
a single sheet of paper in a standard reference format with one line per
statement and one line per declaration.  Typically, this means no more
than about 60 lines of code per function.</h3>

<p>Since programmers these days typically read their code on-screen,
not on paper, it's not clear why the size of a sheet of paper is
relevant any longer.

</p><p>The rule is arguably stated about the wrong thing.  The thing that
needs to be bounded is not the size of a function, but the size of a
chunk that a programmer needs to read and comprehend.

</p><p>There are also question marks about how to interpret this if you
are using a sensible language (like Algol 60, Simula 67, Algol 68,
Pascal, Modula2, Ada, Lisp, functional languages like ML, O'CAML,
F#, Clean, Haskell, or Fortran) that allows nested procedures.
Suppose you have a folding editor that presents a procedure to
you like this:
</p><pre>function Text_To_Floating(S: string, E: integer): Double;
   � variables �
   � procedure Mul(Carry: integer) �
   � function Evaluate: Double �

   Base, Sign, Max, Min, Point, Power := 10, 0, 0, 1, 0, 0;
   for N := 1 to S.length do begin
       C := S[N];
       if C = '.' then begin
          Point := -1
       end else
       if C = '_' then begin
          Base := Round(Evaluate);
          Max, Min, Power := 0, 1, 0
       end else
       if Char ≠ ' ' then begin
          Q := ord(C) - ord('0');
          if Q &gt; 9 then Q := ord(C) - ord('A') + 10
          Power := Point + Point
          Mul(Q)
       end
    end;
    Power := Power + Exp;
    Value := Evaluate;
    if Sign &lt; 0 then Value := -Value;
end;
</pre>
<p>which would be much bigger if the declarations
were expanded out instead of being hidden behind �folds�.
Which size do we count?  The folded size or the unfolded size?
</p><p>I was using a folding editor called Apprentice on the Classic Mac
back in the 1980s.  It was written by Peter McInerny and was lightning
fast.

</p><h3>5.  The <i>assertion density</i> of the code should average to a minimum of
two assertions per function.</h3>

<p>Assertions are wonderful documentation and the very best debugging tool
I know of.  I have never seen any real code that had too many assertions.

</p><p>The example here is one of the ugliest pieces of code I've seen in a while.
</p><pre>if (!c_assert(p &gt;= 0) == true) {
    return ERROR;
}
</pre>
<p>It should, of course, just be
</p><pre>if (!c_assert(p &gt;= 0)) {
    return ERROR;
}
</pre>
<p>Better still, it should be something like
</p><pre>check(ERROR, p &gt;= 0);
</pre>
<p><a name="check" id="check">with</a>
</p><pre>#ifdef NDEBUG
#define check(e, c) (void)0
#else
#define check(e, c) if (!(c)) return bugout(c), (e)
#ifdef NDEBUG_LOG
#define bugout(c) (void)0
#else
#define bugout(c) \
    fprintf(stderr, "%s:%d: assertion '%s' failed.\n", \
    __FILE__, __LINE__, #s)
#endif
#endif
</pre>
<p>Ahem.  The more interesting part is the required density.
I just checked an open source project from a large telecoms
company, and 23 out of 704 files (not functions) contained
at least one assertion.  I just checked my own Smalltalk
system and one SLOC out of every 43 was an assertion, but
the average Smalltalk “function” is only a few
lines.  If the biggest function allowed is 60 lines, then
let's suppose the average function is about 36 lines, so
this rule requires 1 assertion per 18 lines.
</p><p>Assertions are good, but what they are especially good
for is expressing the requirements on data that come
from outside the function.  I suggest then that
</p><ul>
<li>Every argument whose validity is not guaranteed by
its typed should have an assertion to check it.
</li><li>Every datum that is obtained from an external
source (file, data base, message) whose validity is
not guaranteed by its type should have an assertion
to check it.
</li></ul>
<p>The NASA 10 rules are written for embedded systems, where
reading stuff from sensors is fairly common.

</p><h3>6.  Data objects must be declared at the smallest possible level of
scope.</h3>

<p>This is excellent advice, but why limit it to data objects?
Oh yeah, the rules were written for crippled languages where you
<em>couldn't</em> declare functions in the right place.

</p><p>People using Ada, Pascal (Delphi), JavaScript, or functional
languages should also declare types and functions as locally as
possible.

</p><h3>7.  The return value of non-void functions must be checked by each
calling function, and the validity of parameters must be checked inside
each function.</h3>

<p>This again is mainly about C, or any other language that indicates
failure by returning special values.  “Standard libraries
famously violate this rule”?  No, the <em>C</em> library does.

</p><p>You have to be reasonable about this: it simply isn't practical
to check <em>every</em> aspect of validity for <em>every</em>
argument.  Take the C function
</p><pre>void *bsearch(
    void const *key  /* what we are looking for */,
    void const *base /* points to an array of things like that */,
    size_t      n    /* how many elements base has */,
    size_t      size /* the common size of key and base's elements */
    int (*      cmp)(void const *, void const *)
);
</pre>
<p>This does a binary search in an array.  We must have key≠0,
base≠0, size≠0, cmp≠0, cmp(key,key)=0, and for all
1&lt;i&lt;n,
</p><pre>cmp((char*)base+size*(i-1), (char*)base+size*i) &lt;= 0
</pre>
<p>Checking the validity in full would mean checking
that [key..key+size) is a range of readable addresses,
[base..base+size*n) is a range of readable addresses,
and doing n calls to cmp.  But the whole point of binary
search is to do O(log(n)) calls to cmp.

</p><p>The fundamental rules here are
</p><ul>
<li>Don't let run-time errors go un-noticed, and
</li><li>any check is safer than no check.
</li></ul>

<h3>8. The use of the preprocessor must be limited to the inclusion of
header files and simple macro definitions.  Token pasting, variable
argument lists (ellipses), and recursive macro calls are not allowed.</h3>

<p>Recursive macro calls don't really work in C, so no quarrel there.
Variable argument lists were introduced into macros in
C99 so that you could write code like
</p><pre>#define err_printf(level, ...) \
    if (debug_level &gt;= level) fprintf(stderr, __VA_ARGS__)
...
    err_printf(HIGH, "About to frob %d\n", control_index);
</pre>
<p>This is a <em>good</em> thing; conditional tracing like this is a
powerful debugging aid.  It should be <em>encouraged</em>, not banned.

</p><p>The rule goes on to ban macros that expand into things that are
not complete syntactic units.  This would, for example, prohibit
simulating try-catch blocks with macros.  (Fair enough, an earlier rule
banned exception handling anyway.)  Consider this code fragment, from
an actual program.
</p><pre>    row_flag = border;     
    if (row_flag) printf("\\hline");
    for_each_element_child(e0, i, j, e1)
        printf(row_flag ? "\\\\\n" : "\n");
        row_flag = true;  
        col_flag = false;
        for_each_element_child(e1, k, l, e2)
            if (col_flag) printf(" &amp; ");
            col_flag = true;
            walk_paragraph("", e2, "");
        end_each_element_child
    end_each_element_child
    if (border) printf("\\\\\\hline");
    printf("\n\\end{tabular}\n");
</pre>
<p>It's part of a program converting slides written in something like HTML
into another notation for formatting.  The <code>for_each_element_child</code>
… <code>end_each_element_child</code> loops walk over a tree.  Using
these macros means that the programmer has no need to know and no reason to
care how the tree is represented and how the loop actually works.
You can easily see that <code>for_each_element_child</code> must have at
least one unmatched { and <code>end_each_element_child</code> must have at least one
unmatched }.  That's the kind of macro that's banned by requiring
complete syntactic units.  Yet the readability and maintainability of
the code is <em>dramatically</em> improved by these macros.

</p><p>One thing the rule covers, but does not at the beginning stress, is
“no <em>conditional</em> macro processing”.  That is,
no #if.  The argument against it is, I'm afraid, questionable.  If there
are 10 conditions, there are 2<sup>10</sup> combinations to test,
whether they are expressed as compile-time conditionals or run-time
conditionals.

</p><p>In particular, the rule against conditional macro processing
would prevent you defining your own <a href="#check">assertion macros</a>.
It is not obvious that that's a good idea.

</p><h3>9.  The use of pointers should be restricted.  Specifically, no more
than one level of dereferencing is allowed.  Pointer dereference
operations may not be hidden in macro definitions or inside typedef
declarations.  Function pointers are not permitted.</h3>

<p>Let's look at the last point first.

</p><pre>double integral(double (*f)(double), double lower, double upper, int n) {
    // Compute the integral of f from lower to upper 
    // using Simpson's rule with n+1 points.
    double const h = (upper - lower) / n;
    double       s;
    double       t;
    int          i;
    
    s = 0.0;
    for (i = 0; i &lt; n; i++) s += f((lower + h/2.0) + h*i);
    t = 0.0;
    for (i = 1; i &lt; n; i++) t += f(lower + h*i);
    return (f(lower) + f(upper) + s*4.0 + t*2.0) * (h/6.0);
}
</pre>

<p>This kind of code has been important in numerical calculations since
the very earliest days.  Pascal could do it.  Algol 60 could do it.
In the 1950s, Fortran could do it.  And NASA would ban it, because in
C, <code>f</code> is a function pointer.

</p><p>Now it's important to write functions like this once and only once.
For example, the code has at least one error.  The comment says n+1
points, but the function is actually evaluated at 2n+1 points.  If we
need to bound the number of calls to f in order to meet a deadline,
having that number off by a factor of two will not help.
</p><p>It's nice to have just one place to fix.
Perhaps I should not have copied that code from a well-known source (:-).
Certainly I should not have more than one copy!

</p><p>What can we do if we're not allowed to use function pointers?
Suppose there are four functions foo, bar, ugh, and zoo that we need
to integrate.  Now we can write
</p><pre>enum Fun {FOO, BAR, UGH, ZOO};

double call(enum Fun which, double what) {
    switch (which) {
        case FOO: return foo(what);
        case BAR: return bar(what);
        case UGH: return ugh(what);
        case ZOO: return zoo(what);
    }
}

double integral(enum Fun which, double lower, double upper, int n) {
    // Compute the integral of a function from lower to upper 
    // using Simpson's rule with n+1 points.
    double const h = (upper - lower) / n;
    double       s;
    double       t;
    int          i;
    
    s = 0.0;
    for (i = 0; i &lt; n; i++) s += call(which, (lower + h/2.0) + h*i);
    t = 0.0;
    for (i = 1; i &lt; n; i++) t += call(which, lower + h*i);
    return (call(which, lower) + call(which, upper) + s*4.0 + t*2.0) * (h/6.0);
}
</pre>

<p>Has obeying NASA's rule made the code more reliable?  No, it has made
the code <em>harder</em> to understand, <em>less</em> maintainable, and
<em>prone to a mistake</em> that it wasn't before.  Here's a call
illustrating the mistake:
</p><pre>x = integral(4, 0.0, 1.0, 10);</pre>
<p>I have checked this with two C compilers and a static checker at their
highest settings, and they are completely silent about this.

</p><p>So there are legitimate uses for function pointers, and simulating
them makes programs <em>worse</em>, not better.

</p><p>Now <a name="ppar" id="ppar">this wasn't an issue</a> in Fortran,
Algol 60, or Pascal.  Those languages had procedure <em>parameters</em>
but not procedure <em>pointers</em>. You could pass a subprogram name as
a parameter, and such a parameter could be passed on, but you could not
store them in variables.  You could have a <em>subset</em> of C which
allowed function pointer parameters, but made all function pointer
variables read-only.  That would give you a statically checkable subset
of C that allowed integral().

</p><p>The other use of function pointers is simulating object-orientation.
Imagine for example
</p><pre>struct Channel {
    void (*send)(struct Channel *, Message const *);
    bool (*recv)(struct Channel *, Message *);
    ...
};
inline void send(struct Channel *c, Message const *m) {
    c-&gt;send(c, m);
}
inline bool recv(struct Channel *c, Message *m) {
    return c-&gt;recv(c, m);
}
</pre>
<p>This lets us use a common interface for sending and receiving
messages on different kinds of channels.  This approach has been
used extensively in operating systems (at least as far back as
the Burroughs MCP in the 1960s) to decouple the code that uses
a device from the actual device driver.     I would expect any
program that controls more than one hardware device to do something
like this.  It's one of our key tools for controlling complexity.
</p><p>Again, we can simulate this, but it makes adding a new kind of
channel harder than it should be, and the code is <em>worse</em>
when we do it, not better.

</p><p>The rule against more than one level of dereferencing is also
an assault on good programming.  One of the key ideas that was
developed in the 1960s is the idea of <em>abstract data types</em>;
the idea that it should be possible for one module to define a
data type and operations on it and another module to use instances
of that data type and its operations <em>without having to know
anything about what the data type is</em>.
</p><p>One of the things I detest about Java is that it spits in the
face of the people who worked out that idea.  Yes, Java (now) has
generic type parameters, and that's good, but you cannot use a
<em>specific</em> type without knowing what that type is.

</p><p>Suppose I have a module that offers operations
</p><ul>
<li>stash(item) → token
</li><li>recall(token) → item
</li><li>delete(token) → void
</li></ul>
<p>And suppose that I have two interfaces in mind.  One of them
uses integers as tokens.
</p><pre>// stasher.h, version 1.
typedef int token;
extern token stash(item);
extern item  recall(token);
extern void  delete(token);
</pre>
<p>Another uses pointers as tokens.
</p><pre>// stasher.h, version 2.
typedef struct Hidden *token;
extern  token stash(item);
extern  item  recall(token);
extern  void  delete(token);
</pre>
<p>Now let's have a client.
</p><pre>void snoo(token *ans, item x, item y) {
    if (better(x, y)) {
	*ans = stash(x);
    } else {
	*ans = stash(y);
    }
}
</pre>
<p>By the NASA rule, the function snoo() would not be accepted or rejected on
its own merits.  With stasher.h, version 1, it would be accepted.
With stasher.h, version 2, it would be rejected.

</p><p>One reason to prefer version 2 to version 1 is that version 2 gets
more use out of type checking.  There are ever so many ways to get an
int in C.  Ask yourself if it ever makes sense to do
</p><pre>token t1 = stash(x);
token t2 = stash(y);
delete(t1*t2);
</pre>

<p>I really do not like the idea of banning abstract data types.

</p><h3>10.  All code must be compiled, from the first day of development,
with all compiler warnings enabled at the compiler’s
most pedantic setting.  All code must compile with these setting without
any warnings.  All code must be checked daily with at least one, but
preferably more than one, state-of-the-art static source code analyzer
and should pass the analyses with zero warnings.</h3>

<p>This one is good advice.  Rule 9 is really about making your code
worse in order to get more benefit from limited static checkers.  (Since
C has no standard way to construct new functions at run time, the set of
functions that a particular function pointer <em>could</em> point to can
be determined by a fixed-point data flow analysis, at least for most
programs.)  So is rule 1.  



</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Perplexity Deep Research (272 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-perplexity-deep-research</link>
            <guid>43061827</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 20:07:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-perplexity-deep-research">https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-perplexity-deep-research</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061827">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.perplexity.ai/hub/blog/introducing-perplexity-deep-research: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My Life in Weeks (849 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://weeks.ginatrapani.org/</link>
            <guid>43061498</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 19:34:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://weeks.ginatrapani.org/">https://weeks.ginatrapani.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061498">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="fullscreen"><div><nav id="lifeinweeks-navbar"><div><ul><li><a href="#decade-0">Birth</a></li><li><a href="#decade-10">Teens</a></li><li><a href="#decade-20">20s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-30">30s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-40">40s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-50">50s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-60">60s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-70">70s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-80">80s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-90">90s</a></li><li><a href="#decade-100">100</a></li></ul></div></nav></div><div><p>👋 Hi, I’m <a href="https://ginatrapani.org/">Gina</a>. This is a map of my life, where each week I’ve been alive is a little box. Tap a box to see what I was doing where that week.</p><p>📍 Read more about <a href="https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/05/life-weeks.html">Life in Weeks at Wait But Why</a>. I adapted <a href="https://github.com/ginatrapani/life-in-weeks">the code that generated this page</a> from <a href="https://busterbenson.com/life-in-weeks">Buster Benson</a>.</p><p>🌱 This life and this map are a work in progress. I’ll update it as I go.</p><p>🍯 “I always get to where I am going by walking away from where I have been.” – Winnie the Pooh</p></div></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New SF public health chief was part of McKinsey opioid-marketing operation (243 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sfstandard.com/2025/02/14/san-francisco-department-public-health-daniel-tsai-opioids-mckinsey/</link>
            <guid>43061482</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 19:32:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2025/02/14/san-francisco-department-public-health-daniel-tsai-opioids-mckinsey/">https://sfstandard.com/2025/02/14/san-francisco-department-public-health-daniel-tsai-opioids-mckinsey/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061482">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>Daniel Tsai, Mayor Daniel Lurie’s choice to lead the Department of Public Health, has a blue-chip résumé: After studying at Harvard University, he landed a prestigious consulting gig before jumping into government, leading Medicaid programs in Massachusetts, then federally under former President Joe Biden.&nbsp;</p><p>Along the way, Tsai, in his capacity as an employee with McKinsey &amp; Company, helped to market a powerful painkiller called tramadol during the company’s years-long streak of pushing opioid sales. The company’s actions ultimately led to a criminal probe, more than $1 billion in settlements, and a public mea culpa over its role in fueling an overdose epidemic that has killed more than 500,000 Americans over 25 years.</p><p>Tsai’s actions at McKinsey are detailed in a tranche of documents that were released as part of a settlement with the consulting firm in which it was accused of accelerating opioid sales despite growing awareness of the risks.&nbsp;</p><p>The records show that Tsai —&nbsp;who worked for McKinsey from 2007 to 2015, according to his LinkedIn page — helped develop a marketing strategy for tramadol sold under the brand name Ultram ER, an effort that involved cultivating relationships with doctors who became prolific prescribers. The records are housed at the <a href="https://www.industrydocuments.ucsf.edu/opioids">UCSF-JHU Opioid Industry Documents Archive</a>.</p><p>In a March 2008 PowerPoint presentation, Tsai outlined a marketing strategy for the drug that included guidance on targeting “specific physician segments to grow high-prescriber group (i.e., physicians more sensitive to patient needs)” and an idea to introduce “coupons” for the drug as part of a pilot program.</p></div><figure id=""><div><p><span><span></span><img alt="A booth with &amp;quot;McKinsey &amp;amp; Company&amp;quot; in bright letters on a wooden panel. Two men stand nearby, one looking at a touchscreen display." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="responsive" sizes="(min-width: 1001px) 600px, (min-width: 768px) 700px, 100vw" srcset="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=768&amp;q=75 768w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=1024&amp;q=75 1024w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/gettyimages-1247557771.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div><figcaption>McKinsey &amp; Company has paid more than $1 billion in settlements related to its role in the opioid crisis.<span> | </span><span><span>Source: </span>Thomas Coex/AFP/Getty Images</span></figcaption></figure><div><p>“We hope to be interviewing some high-prescriber physicians next week,” Tsai wrote in an email the same month, attaching a list of questions that could be used to screen doctors. </p><p>Lurie’s office defended Tsai’s appointment as Public Health chief. In a statement, the mayor’s office wrote, “Nearly 20 years ago, Dan Tsai was a 23-year-old entry-level staffer assigned to conduct research for a project at work. He has spent nearly his entire two-decade career supporting those struggling with homelessness and addiction and helping tens of millions of our most vulnerable neighbors access critical medical care, and he will continue that work in San Francisco.”</p><p>Several drug and homelessness service providers in the city said they were disappointed by a lack of transparency surrounding Tsai’s appointment process. The revelation of his past role at McKinsey intensified those concerns, they said.&nbsp;</p><p>“You’d want a public health official of that caliber to articulate what his participation was in that role,” said Laura Guzman, director of the National Harm Reduction Coalition. “This is an important moment to bring in people with federal bureaucracy expertise. But if [Lurie] wants to address the lack of treatment, we need leadership with expertise in evidence-based interventions.”</p><p>Others were less diplomatic in their reaction to the news.</p><p>“Holy fucking shit,” said Liza Murawski, co-chair of the city’s Behavioral Health Commission, when told of Tsai’s role at McKinsey. “Why would he be the director? Why don’t you have someone in there who’s a mental health expert?”</p><p>It wasn’t immediately clear who Tsai’s client was when he was marketing Ultram ER. The brand, which has been discontinued, was developed by a Canadian company and licensed to a subsidiary of Johnson &amp; Johnson in 2005, <a href="https://pharmatimes.com/news/orthos_ultram_er_reaches_us_market_996469/">according to PharmaTimes</a>.&nbsp;</p><p>Experts say tramadol was initially thought to be less harmful than OxyContin, another product McKinsey marketed for Purdue Pharma. But that view has changed.&nbsp;</p><p>Tramadol is a Schedule IV drug — in the same category as Xanax, Valium, and Ambien — and has <a href="https://www.voanews.com/a/report-highly-potent-opioids-now-showing-up-in-drug-users-in-africa/7653980.html">more</a> <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-44306086">recently</a> <a href="https://www.occrp.org/en/news/un-report-tramadol-use-in-africa-is-increasing">been</a> linked to addiction in Africa. “It was seen as this alternative,” said Dr. Rachel Sussman, a South Bay-based addiction medicine specialist. “It is just as risky and just as dependency-creating as any other opioid medication.” In fact, the drug carries more complications than some other opioids, including a risk of seizure and negative interactions with antidepressants, said Sussman.</p></div><figure id=""><div><p><span><span></span><img alt="Two men in suits stand near a podium. One is holding papers, and the other rests a hand on his shoulder. A calendar and TV are visible in the background." loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-nimg="responsive" sizes="(min-width: 1001px) 600px, (min-width: 768px) 700px, 100vw" srcset="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=640&amp;q=75 640w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=750&amp;q=75 750w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=768&amp;q=75 768w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=828&amp;q=75 828w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=1024&amp;q=75 1024w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=1080&amp;q=75 1080w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=1200&amp;q=75 1200w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=1920&amp;q=75 1920w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=2048&amp;q=75 2048w, https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75 3840w" src="https://content.sfstandard.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/w2a5893.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"></span></p></div><figcaption>Mayor Daniel Lurie tapped Tsai to lead the city's Public Health Department. The sprawling agency has a roughly $3 billion budget.<span> | </span><span><span>Source: </span>Amanda Andrade-Rhoades/The Standard</span></figcaption></figure><div><p>Dr. David Juurlink, an expert on tramadol, called the drug a “minor player in the opioid crisis, but a player nevertheless.”</p><p>He added, “To the extent that McKinsey helped advertise it as a notionally safer opioid, I think they did a disservice in doing so. The main reason I say tramadol is a minor player is because it wasn’t prescribed like candy, like OxyContin was.”</p><p>McKinsey’s method of targeting high-volume prescribers was part of its playbook to juice opioid sales, despite mounting evidence that the drugs could be highly addictive. In other emails uncovered in the McKinsey documents, employees wrote excitedly about finding doctors who were willing to write opioid prescriptions. <a href="https://www.industrydocuments.ucsf.edu/opioids/docs/#id=hlmn0255">In one instance</a> in 2015, a McKinsey partner wrote, “The challenge which we need to start working on is to identify the sweet spot of docs so we can do targeting. … Fun be[g]ins on Monday!”</p><p>San Francisco’s fentanyl crisis is part of a broader trend of opioid overdoses <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/overdose-prevention/about/understanding-the-opioid-overdose-epidemic.html">that traces back to the 1990s,</a> when prescription opioids became popular among doctors for chronic pain management. Companies such as Purdue Pharma, which manufactured OxyContin, brought in consulting firms like McKinsey to help with sales strategies. After a Department of Justice probe and settlement, McKinsey <a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-ma/media/1380236/dl">acknowledged that it knew</a> the dangers of OxyContin but continued working with Purdue Pharma — even after several of the drugmaker’s executives pled guilty in 2007 to misrepresenting addiction risks.&nbsp;</p><p>McKinsey, along with a slew of drug companies and pharmacies, agreed to pay billions in settlement funds over their roles in fueling opioid addiction. California received <a href="https://oag.ca.gov/news/press-releases/attorney-general-becerra-announces-573-million-nationwide-settlement-mckinsey">roughly $60 million</a> from the 2021 McKinsey settlement. San Francisco, <a href="https://www.sfcityattorney.org/2023/05/17/san-francisco-city-attorney-announces-230-million-settlement-with-walgreens-after-victory-in-opioid-litigation/">under the 2023 settlement</a> of an opioid-related lawsuit, was expected to receive about $230 million from Walgreens.</p><p>In both instances, the funds were slated to be used for opioid recovery efforts.</p><p>In 2019, McKinsey said it would no longer work on opioid-related businesses.&nbsp;Last year, McKinsey formally apologized for its Purdue Pharma work, <a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/about-us/opioidfacts">saying it was “deeply sorry”</a> for its role in selling OxyContin. “This terrible public health crisis and our past work for opioid manufacturers will always be a source of profound regret for our firm,” the company said in a statement.</p><p>At the San Francisco Department of Public Health, Tsai replaced Dr. Grant Colfax, who took the reins in 2019 and led the city through the pandemic <a href="https://sfstandard.com/2025/01/16/grant-colfax-resign-san-francisco-public-health/">before stepping down in January</a>. The role paid $546,133 in 2024, one of the highest city salaries.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>On Monday, the San Francisco Health Commission unanimously nominated Tsai as director of Public Heath. Dr. Laurie Green, president of the commission, said the governing body conducted a “multi-hour” interview.</p></div><div><p>“In the interview with Mr. Tsai, the Health Commissioners focused on his preparedness to address the current public health challenges facing San Franciscans and his ability to sustain the Department through a potential tumultuous time ahead,” Green wrote in a statement. “This includes his unique expertise in Medicaid funding and programs, in addition to healthcare innovations and transformation.”</p><p>Tsai is expected to work with <a href="https://sfstandard.com/opinion/2025/01/07/the-fresh-faces-in-luries-cabinet-will-have-vast-power-but-will-they-know-how-to-wield-it/">Kunal Modi</a>, another McKinsey alum, whom Lurie has tapped to lead the city’s response to health and homelessness. In a statement this week, Tsai highlighted&nbsp;the city’s opioid and homelessness crises and said he was looking forward “to partnering with stakeholders and individuals with lived experience to find new, data-driven approaches to tackling this important challenge.”</p><p>Representatives of McKinsey did not respond to a request for comment.</p><div id=""><p>Richard Beal, director of recovery services at the Tenderloin Housing Clinic, said he appreciates Lurie’s early focus on the fentanyl crisis and remains optimistic about Tsai’s appointment.</p><p>“Just like [Tsai] distributed the drugs, maybe he can distribute the solution to the drugs,” Beal said. “Hopefully, he can use the knowledge he has from helping to create the monster to figure out how to solve it.”</p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US wants to un-fire nuclear safety workers can't figure out how to reach them (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/national-security/trump-administration-wants-un-fire-nuclear-safety-workers-cant-figure-rcna192345</link>
            <guid>43061481</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 19:32:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/national-security/trump-administration-wants-un-fire-nuclear-safety-workers-cant-figure-rcna192345">https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/national-security/trump-administration-wants-un-fire-nuclear-safety-workers-cant-figure-rcna192345</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061481">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>WASHINGTON — National Nuclear Security Administration officials on Friday attempted to notify some employees who had been let go the day before that they are now due to be reinstated — but they struggled to find them because they didn’t have their new contact information.</p><p>In an email sent to employees at NNSA and obtained by NBC News, officials wrote, “The termination letters for some NNSA probationary employees are being rescinded, but we do not have a good way to get in touch with those personnel.”</p><p>The individuals the letter refers to had been fired on Thursday and lost access to their federal government email accounts. NNSA, which is within the Department of Energy and oversees the nation’s nuclear stockpile, cannot reach these employees directly and is now asking recipients of the email, “Please work with your supervisors to send this information (once you get it) to people’s personal contact emails.”</p><p>The Department of Energy did not immediately respond to an NBC News request for comment.</p><p>President Donald Trump’s administration has acted with unprecedented speed — and in some cases, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/donald-trump/week-legal-setbacks-one-big-win-trumps-agenda-rcna192032" target="_blank">questionable legality</a> — in seeking to cut large portions of the federal government, laying off staff and ending contracts. But that speed has resulted in complications, including firing people agencies actually want to keep.</p><p>The emails come after multiple staff — all civil servants — at the NNSA <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/politics-news/live-blog/live-updates-trump-tariffs-ukraine-russia-rcna191174/rcrd73096?canonicalCard=true" target="_blank">received termination notices</a> late Thursday, according to a source with direct knowledge of the notifications. NBC News reviewed the termination notification, which included the subject line: “Notification of Termination During Probationary/Trial Period.”</p><p>The NNSA is tasked with designing, building and overseeing the U.S. nuclear weapons stockpile.</p><p>The termination notices, which read “effective today,” came within hours of a Russian drone striking the Chernobyl power plant in Ukraine. NNSA tracks nuclear risks in Ukraine, including through sensor systems.</p><p>The NNSA saga comes as the Trump administration <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/politics/doge/government-layoffs-trump-firings-department-probationary-employees-rcna192307" target="_blank">executed mass firings</a> throughout the federal government this week, primarily slashing the jobs of employees categorized as “probationary.”</p><p>Some departments saw massive numbers of layoffs, like the Department of Homeland Security, where over 400 people were told that their jobs were cut.</p><p>An NNSA nuclear safety specialist fired Thursday because she was a two-year probationary employee told NBC News she was still locked out of her email, but her manager had called to inform her that her “termination was rescinded” and to report to work on Tuesday.</p><p>“I will be honest, I intend to keep looking for work,” the employee said. “I will go back, but as soon as I find another role, I’ll be leaving.”</p><p>Asked why she will still look for employment elsewhere, she said that she has “no faith I will keep my job.”</p><p>The move comes as Trump and one of his top advisers, tech mogul Elon Musk, seek to slash the size of the federal government.</p><p>The federal cuts have been met with pushback from Democrats, labor unions and progressive organizations. <a href="https://www.justsecurity.org/107087/tracker-litigation-legal-challenges-trump-administration/" target="_blank">More than 60 lawsuits</a>&nbsp;against the Trump administration alleging executive overreach and other violations are pending.</p></div><div><div data-activity-map="expanded-byline-article-bottom"><div data-testid="byline-thumbnail"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/peter-alexander-ncpn945076" tabindex="-1"><picture data-testid="picture"><source media="(min-width: 320px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/newscms/2024_36/3661284/240904-peter-alexander.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_36/3661284/240904-peter-alexander.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_36/3661284/240904-peter-alexander.jpg" alt="" height="48" width="48"></picture></a></div><p><span data-testid="byline-name"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/peter-alexander-ncpn945076">Peter Alexander</a></span><span><a href="mailto:peter.alexander@nbcuni.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span></span></a></span></p><p>Peter Alexander is chief White House correspondent for NBC News.</p></div><div data-activity-map="expanded-byline-article-bottom"><div data-testid="byline-thumbnail"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/alexandra-marquez-ncpn1256666" tabindex="-1"><picture data-testid="picture"><source media="(min-width: 320px)" srcset="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_avif,q_auto:eco,dpr_2/newscms/2024_38/3662645/240613-alexandra-sasha-marquez.jpg 2x, https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_38/3662645/240613-alexandra-sasha-marquez.jpg 1x"><img loading="lazy" src="https://media-cldnry.s-nbcnews.com/image/upload/t_focal-60x60,f_auto,q_auto:best/newscms/2024_38/3662645/240613-alexandra-sasha-marquez.jpg" alt="" height="48" width="48"></picture></a></div><p><span data-testid="byline-name"><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/author/alexandra-marquez-ncpn1256666">Alexandra Marquez</a></span><span><a href="https://x.com/alexandramrqz" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span></span></a><a href="mailto:alexandra.marquez@nbcuni.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><span></span></a></span></p><p>Alexandra Marquez is a politics reporter for NBC News.</p></div><div><p>Kevin Collier</p><!-- --><p> and </p><!-- --><p>Daniel Arkin</p><!-- --> <!-- --><p>contributed</p><!-- --><p>.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Schemesh: Fusion between Unix shell and Lisp REPL (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh</link>
            <guid>43061183</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 19:00:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh">https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061183">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">schemesh</h2><a id="user-content-schemesh" aria-label="Permalink: schemesh" href="#schemesh"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Fusion between a Unix shell and a Lisp REPL</h2><a id="user-content-fusion-between-a-unix-shell-and-a-lisp-repl" aria-label="Permalink: Fusion between a Unix shell and a Lisp REPL" href="#fusion-between-a-unix-shell-and-a-lisp-repl"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Schemesh is an interactive shell scriptable in Lisp.</p>
<p dir="auto">It is primarily intended as a user-friendly Unix login shell, replacing bash, zsh, pdksh etc.</p>
<p dir="auto">As such, it supports interactive line editing, autocompletion, history and the familiar Unix shell syntax:
it can start commands, including redirections, pipelines, job concatenation with <code>;</code> <code>&amp;&amp;</code> <code>||</code>,
groups surrounded by <code>{ }</code>, subshells surrounded by <code>[ ]</code>, and manage foreground/background jobs.</p>
<p dir="auto">For more complex tasks, it seamlessly integrates a full Lisp REPL backed by Chez Scheme.</p>
<p dir="auto">Schemesh can be used as:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">a replacement for traditional interactive Unix shell, as for example bash/zsh/pdksh etc.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">a Unix shell scriptable in Chez Scheme.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">a Scheme REPL with additional syntax and functions to start, redirect and manage Unix processes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">a Scheme library for starting, redirecting and managing Unix processes.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For scripting and serious programming, schemesh completely replaces the slow, clumsy and error-prone
scripting language of a traditional shell (yes, the author has opinions) with a full-featured Lisp REPL,
backed by the fast and open-source Chez Scheme compiler that generates highly optimized native code.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to use</h3><a id="user-content-how-to-use" aria-label="Permalink: How to use" href="#how-to-use"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">As a traditional Unix shell: type a command and press Enter.<br>
As a Lisp REPL: type an expression starting with <code>(</code> and press Enter.<br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh/blob/main/doc/screenshot-1.png"><img src="https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh/raw/main/doc/screenshot-1.png" alt=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If the parentheses/braces/brackets/quotes are balanced,<br>
schemesh will execute the command and show any failure, or evaluate the expression and pretty-print its value.</p>
<p dir="auto">If the parentheses/braces/brackets/quotes are <em>not</em> balanced,<br>
schemesh will create a second line where you can continue typing.<br>
You can move between lines with the cursor keys, and use all the classical line-editing features including cut-and-paste.<br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh/blob/main/doc/screenshot-2.png"><img src="https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh/raw/main/doc/screenshot-2.png" alt=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Switching between shell syntax and Lisp syntax is extremely simple, and can be done basically everywhere:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">open parenthesis <code>(</code> temporarily switches to Lisp syntax until the corresponding <code>)</code>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">open brace i.e. <code>{</code> temporarily switches to shell syntax until the corresponding <code>}</code>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">open bracket i.e. <code>[</code> starts a new sub-form in current syntax until the corresponding <code>]</code>.<br>
If found in Lisp syntax, it is equivalent to <code>(</code>.<br>
If found in shell syntax, it is similar to <code>{</code> with the difference that commands will be executed in a subshell.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">the directives <code>#!scheme</code> <code>#!chezscheme</code> and <code>#!r6rs</code> temporarily switch to Scheme syntax
(with the appropriate flavor) until the end of current <code>( )</code>, <code>[ ]</code> or <code>{ }</code>.<br>
If entered at top level, they change the default syntax until another directive is entered at top level.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">the directive <code>#!shell</code> temporarily switches to shell syntax until the end of current <code>( )</code>, <code>[ ]</code> or <code>{ }</code>.<br>
If entered at top level, it changes the default syntax until another directive is entered at top level.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">shell syntax creates first-class Lisp <code>sh-job</code> objects, which can be started/stopped/managed from both syntaxes.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><code>sh-job</code> objects are discoverable and pretty-printable:<br>
<code>(values '{SOME-SHELL-SYNTAX})</code> shows how shell syntax is converted to <code>shell...</code> macros,<br>
<code>(expand '{SOME-SHELL-SYNTAX})</code> shows how <code>shell...</code> macros are expanded to <code>sh...</code> functions for creating jobs,<br>
<code>(values  {SOME-SHELL-SYNTAX})</code> - <em>without</em> quotes - pretty-prints the created <code>sh-job</code> objects.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The most common mechanisms to start/stop/manage jobs from shell syntax are:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>CTRL+C      interrupt the current foreground job</li>
<li>CTRL+Z      suspend the current foreground job</li>
<li><code>bg job-id</code> resume a job in background</li>
<li><code>fg job-id</code> resume a job in foreground</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The analogous job control mechanisms from Scheme syntax are:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>CTRL+C      as above</li>
<li>CTRL+Z      as above</li>
<li><code>(sh-start job-object)</code> start a job in background, return immediately</li>
<li><code>(sh-run/i job-object)</code> start a job in foreground, wait until job finishes or is suspended</li>
<li><code>(sh-run   job-object)</code> start a job in foreground, wait until job finishes</li>
<li><code>(sh-bg    job-or-id)</code> resume a job in background, return immediately</li>
<li><code>(sh-fg    job-or-id)</code> resume a job in foreground, wait until job finishes or is suspended</li>
<li><code>(sh-wait  job-or-id)</code> resume a job in foreground, wait until job finishes</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Some more advanced Scheme functions:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>(sh-run/string job-object)</code> start a job in foreground, wait until job finishes, return its output as a Scheme string</li>
<li><code>(sh-start/fd-stdout job-object)</code> start a job in background, return a file descriptor fixnum for reading its standard output - for example with <code>(open-fd-input-port fd)</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h3><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can mix shell command execution with Lisp control structures, loops and functions as for example:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(if (some_expression arg1 (sub_expression2))
  (sh-run/i {then_run_this_command foo bar $VAR})
  (sh-run/i {else_run_this_command foo bar $VAR}))"><pre>(<span>if</span> (some_expression arg1 (sub_expression2))
  (sh-run/i {then_run_this_command foo bar $VAR})
  (sh-run/i {else_run_this_command foo bar $VAR}))</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">instead of typical shell syntax, which is error prone as it's based on string expansion and splitting,
and geared toward command execution, as for example:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Note: this is POSIX shell syntax for `if-then-else`. It will NOT work in schemesh.
if some_command &quot;$arg1&quot; &quot;$(sub_command)&quot;
then
  then_run_this_command foo bar $VAR
else
  else_run_this_command foo bar $VAR
fi"><pre><span><span>#</span> Note: this is POSIX shell syntax for `if-then-else`. It will NOT work in schemesh.</span>
<span>if</span> some_command <span><span>"</span><span>$arg1</span><span>"</span></span> <span><span>"</span><span><span>$(</span>sub_command<span>)</span></span><span>"</span></span>
<span>then</span>
  then_run_this_command foo bar <span>$VAR</span>
<span>else</span>
  else_run_this_command foo bar <span>$VAR</span>
<span>fi</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">more examples mixing shell and Lisp syntax:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="find (lisp-function-returning-some-string) -type f | grep ^lib | wc -l &amp;
fg 1"><pre>find (lisp-function-returning-some-string) -type f <span>|</span> grep ^lib <span>|</span> wc -l <span>&amp;</span>
<span>fg</span> 1</pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(define job {ls -l > ls.out || echo &quot;ls failed&quot;})
(sh-start job)
(sh-fg job)"><pre>(define job {ls -l <span>&gt;</span> ls.out || echo <span><span>"</span>ls failed<span>"</span></span>})
(sh-start job)
(sh-fg job)</pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(define txt (sh-run/string {git log}))
(display txt)"><pre>(define txt (sh-run/string {git log}))
(display txt)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">a slighty more complex example - uses several additional functions and macros provided by schemesh</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="(import (schemesh all))

(for ((f (in-list (sh-run/string-split-after-nuls {find -type f -print0}))))
  (file-rename f (string-replace f &quot;.old&quot; &quot;.bak&quot;)))"><pre>(<span>import</span> (schemesh all))

(for ((f (in-list (sh-run/string-split-after-nuls {find -type f -print0}))))
  (file-rename f (string-replace f <span><span>"</span>.old<span>"</span></span> <span><span>"</span>.bak<span>"</span></span>)))</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h3><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> REPL with multi-line editing and parentheses highlighting</li>
<li> dual syntax parsing, allows mixing Scheme and shell expressions</li>
<li> shortcuts to execute commands by pressing a single key: KP- KP+</li>
<li> history searchable with PageUp and PageDown keys</li>
<li> cut-and-paste</li>
<li> context-sensitive autocompletion - some improvements pending</li>
<li> UTF-8b for losslessly converting byte sequences that are not valid UTF-8</li>
<li> shell commands, including <code>;</code> <code>&amp;</code> <code>!</code> <code>&amp;&amp;</code> <code>||</code> <code>{</code> <code>}</code> <code>[</code> <code>]</code></li>
<li> shell job control</li>
<li> shell aliases</li>
<li> shell builtins</li>
<li> shell environment variables</li>
<li> shell pipelines <code>|</code> <code>|&amp;</code></li>
<li> shell redirections <code>&lt;</code> <code>&gt;</code> <code>&lt;&gt;</code> <code>&gt;&gt;</code> <code>&lt;&amp;</code> <code>&gt;&amp;</code> <code>$()</code> <code>``</code></li>
<li> shell wildcard expansion</li>
<li> each job has its own current directory and environment variables,
initially inherited from parent job</li>
<li> customizable prompt, set by environment variable <code>$SCHEMESH_PS1</code></li>
<li> if the directory <code>$HOME/.cache/schemesh/</code> exists,<br>
history is automatically saved to and loaded from a file <code>history.txt</code> inside such directory</li>
<li> if the file <code>$HOME/.config/schemesh/repl_init.ss</code> exists,<br>
it is automatically executed when starting the REPL</li>
<li> if the file <code>$HOME/.config/schemesh/repl_quit.ss</code> exists,<br>
it is automatically executed when exiting the REPL</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Build instructions</h2><a id="user-content-build-instructions" aria-label="Permalink: Build instructions" href="#build-instructions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">On Debian Linux, execute the following commands:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sudo apt update
sudo apt install build-essential chezscheme-dev liblz4-dev libncurses-dev git uuid-dev zlib1g-dev
git clone https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh
cd schemesh
make -j
sudo make install"><pre>sudo apt update
sudo apt install build-essential chezscheme-dev liblz4-dev libncurses-dev git uuid-dev zlib1g-dev
git clone https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh
<span>cd</span> schemesh
make -j
sudo make install</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">On Fedora Linux:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="sudo dnf install gcc gcc-c++ make chez-scheme-devel lz4-devel ncurses-devel git libuuid-devel zlib-devel
git clone https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh
cd schemesh
make -j
sudo make install"><pre>sudo dnf install gcc gcc-c++ make chez-scheme-devel lz4-devel ncurses-devel git libuuid-devel zlib-devel
git clone https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh
<span>cd</span> schemesh
make -j
sudo make install</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For other systems, the instructions above can (hopefully) be adapted as needed.</p>
<p dir="auto">If all went well, you can execute <code>schemesh</code></p>
<p dir="auto">In case your environment variable <code>$PATH</code> does not contain <code>/usr/local/bin</code>,
the command <code>schemesh</code> will not suffice - you will need to run <code>/usr/local/bin/schemesh</code></p>
<p dir="auto">Troubleshooting:</p>
<p dir="auto">if <code>make -j</code> fails, a possible error is that it fails to autodetect Chez Scheme installation directory.
In such case you can manually specify it, as for example <code>make -j CHEZ_SCHEME_DIR="/usr/local/lib/csv10.0.0/ta6le"</code></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">RECENT CHANGES</h2><a id="user-content-recent-changes" aria-label="Permalink: RECENT CHANGES" href="#recent-changes"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/cosmos72/schemesh/blob/main/doc/recent_changes.md">doc/recent_changes.md</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">TO DO</h2><a id="user-content-to-do" aria-label="Permalink: TO DO" href="#to-do"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>autocomplete shell paths and scheme strings: unescape stems before searching for completions, escape completions</li>
<li>autocomplete shell paths and scheme strings: when autocompleting inside single or double quotes, the stem starts at the quotes.</li>
<li>autocomplete shell paths starting with ~</li>
<li>maybe add missing shell builtins "kill"</li>
<li>implement function <code>(string-&gt;sh-patterns)</code></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Multiple Russian Threat Actors Targeting Microsoft Device Code Authentication (171 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.volexity.com/blog/2025/02/13/multiple-russian-threat-actors-targeting-microsoft-device-code-authentication/</link>
            <guid>43061173</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 18:59:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.volexity.com/blog/2025/02/13/multiple-russian-threat-actors-targeting-microsoft-device-code-authentication/">https://www.volexity.com/blog/2025/02/13/multiple-russian-threat-actors-targeting-microsoft-device-code-authentication/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43061173">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
		<article>
			<div>
				
				<p>February 13, 2025</p>
									
					
				
				<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication.png" alt="Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication" width="2061" height="1078" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication.png 2061w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication-300x157.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication-1024x536.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication-768x402.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication-1536x803.png 1536w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Multiple-Russian-Threat-Actors-Targeting-Microsoft-Device-Code-Authentication-2048x1071.png 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2061px) 100vw, 2061px"></p>
<h5><span>KEY TAKEAWAYS</span></h5>
<ul>
<li><em>Volexity has observed multiple Russian threat actors conducting social-engineering and spear-phishing campaigns targeting organizations with the ultimate goal of compromising Microsoft 365 accounts via Device Code Authentication phishing.</em></li>
<li><em>Device Code Authentication phishing follows an atypical workflow to that expected by users, meaning users may not recognize it as phishing.</em></li>
<li><em>Recent campaigns observed have been politically themed, particularly around the new administration in the United States and the changes this might mean for nations around the world.</em></li>
</ul>
<p>Starting in mid-January 2025, Volexity identified several social-engineering and spear-phishing campaigns by Russian threat actors aimed at compromising Microsoft 365 (M365) accounts. These attack campaigns were highly targeted and carried out in a variety of ways. The majority of these attacks originated via spear-phishing emails with different themes. In one case, the eventual breach began with highly tailored outreach via Signal.</p>
<p>Through its investigations, Volexity discovered that Russian threat actors were impersonating a variety of individuals in order to socially engineer targets, including impersonating individuals from the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>United States Department of State</li>
<li>Ukrainian Ministry of Defence</li>
<li>European Union Parliament</li>
<li>Prominent research institutions</li>
</ul>
<p>Communications carried a variety of different themes and messages, but they all ultimately resulted in the attacker inviting the targeted user to one of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Microsoft Teams Meeting / Video Conference</li>
<li>Access to applications and data as an external M365 user</li>
<li>Join a chatroom on a secure chat application</li>
</ul>
<p>When these attacks were successful and the attackers gained access to accounts, the post-exploitation phase often had unique characteristics in each case:</p>
<ul>
<li>The way the attackers accessed material from compromised organizations (scripts versus native applications)</li>
<li>The infrastructure used to access stolen accounts</li>
</ul>
<p>Despite the differences, Volexity found the attacks had one thing in common: they were all <strong>Device Code Authentication</strong> attacks. While this attack method is not new, it is one that is definitely lesser known and not commonly leveraged by nation-state actors. Details on the social-engineering and spear-phishing campaigns, along with how Device Code Authentication attacks work, will be covered further in this blog post. What Volexity has observed is that this method has been more effective at successfully compromising accounts than most other targeted spear-phishing campaigns.</p>
<p>Volexity assesses with high confidence that the series of attacks described in this blog post are from Russia-based threat actors. At this time, Volexity is tracking this activity under three different threat actors and assesses with medium confidence that at least one of them is <strong>CozyLarch</strong> (overlapping with DarkHalo, APT29, Midnight Blizzard, CozyDuke). Volexity is tracking the remaining activity under <strong>UTA0304</strong> and <strong>UTA0307</strong>. It is possible that all the activity described in this blog post is a single threat actor, but despite the similar targeting, timing, and attack method, other observed components of the operations are different enough to be tracked separately, for now.</p>
<h3>From Secure Chat to Insecure Authentication</h3>
<p>The discovery of this threat activity started toward the end of January 2025, when Volexity uncovered a highly targeted attack that had successfully compromised the M365 account of one of its customers. This breach was discovered after Volexity identified suspicious sign-in activity to the account, which was followed by a rapid download of files from the user's OneDrive. All authentication and download events came from virtual private server (VPS) and Tor IP addresses, which is not the most subtle way to access an account. Volexity noted this activity was likely scripted, as the User-Agent string for later access and file downloads was the Python User-Agent string <code><em><strong>python-requests/2.25.1</strong></em></code>.</p>
<p>Volexity then performed a detailed investigation into this incident, in an effort to identify how the account was compromised. A review of login activity showed the legitimate user had logged in and approved a multi-factor authentication (MFA) request. However, subsequent access was not from the legitimate user's IP address. This caused Volexity to initially suspect a phishing attack involving an adversary-in-the-middle (AiTM) framework. As a result, Volexity reviewed emails to the user leading up the time of the authentication event. This review identified a suspicious email just moments before the login activity from an email address purporting to be from someone with the name of a high-ranking official from the Ukrainian Ministry of Defence. The email was structured to look like a meeting invite for a chatroom on the messaging application, <a href="https://element.io/">Element</a>. Element is another encrypted messaging application that offers the ability for users to self-host a server with functionality that includes group video chats. The “invitation” email sent is shown below .</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/element-ss-1024x381.png" alt="" width="690" height="256" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/element-ss-1024x381.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/element-ss-300x112.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/element-ss-768x285.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/element-ss.png 1286w" sizes="(max-width: 690px) 100vw, 690px"></p>
<p>In fact, all hyperlinks in the email were linked to <code><a href="https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/deviceauth"><strong>https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/deviceauth</strong></a></code>, the page used for the Microsoft Device Code authentication workflow. Clicking the link leads to the dialogue shown below.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/microsoft-deviceauth.png" alt="" width="419" height="372" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/microsoft-deviceauth.png 910w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/microsoft-deviceauth-300x266.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/microsoft-deviceauth-768x682.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 419px) 100vw, 419px"></p>
<p>Microsoft <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/identity-platform/v2-oauth2-device-code">describes</a> the purpose of this workflow as allowing <em>'"users to sign in to input-constrained devices such as a smart TV, IoT device, or a printer.</em>” However, in this case, it means if an attacker can convince a user to enter a specific code into this dialogue (and log in), they are granted long-term access to the user’s account.</p>
<h4>From Signal to Element</h4>
<p>After working with its customer more closely, Volexity learned that the victim had been contacted on Signal by an individual purporting to be from the Ukrainian Ministry of Defence. This individual then requested the victim move off Signal to another secure chat application called Element. The attacker then had the victim join an Element server they controlled under the domain <code><strong>sen-comms[.]com</strong></code>. This allowed the attacker to further communicate with the victim in real time and inform them they needed to click a link from an email to join a secure chat room. This is where the email Volexity had discovered came into play. The message was a ploy to fool the user into thinking they were being invited into a secure chat, when in reality they were giving the attacker access to their account. The generated Device Codes are only valid for 15 minutes once they are created. As a result, the real-time communication with the victim, and having them expect the "invitation", served to ensure the phish would succeed through timely coordination.</p>
<p>The diagram below s<span><span>hows a high-level depiction of how the attack worked.</span></span></p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Device-Code-Diagram-1024x908.png" alt="" width="690" height="612" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Device-Code-Diagram-1024x908.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Device-Code-Diagram-300x266.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Device-Code-Diagram-768x681.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Device-Code-Diagram-1536x1362.png 1536w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Volexity-Blog-Device-Code-Diagram-2048x1817.png 2048w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 690px) 100vw, 690px"></p>
<h4>UTA0304 Infrastructure</h4>
<p>Volexity tracks the threat actor behind this campaign as <strong>UTA0304</strong>. Through research conducted on the custom domain used by UTA0304 to operate its own Element server, Volexity was able to pivot and discover additional infrastructure it believes is likely operated by the group. The table below represents the list of infrastructure that Volexity has tied to this threat actor.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<td><strong>Domain</strong></td>
<td><strong>IP Address</strong></td>
<td><strong>Confidence</strong></td>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>sen-comms[.]com</code></td>
<td><code>107.189.27.41</code></td>
<td>High</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>afpi-sec[.]com</code></td>
<td><code>144.172.113.77</code></td>
<td>Medium</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>chromeelevationservice[.]com</code></td>
<td><code>167.88.162.72</code></td>
<td>Medium</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>comms-net[.]com</code></td>
<td><code>107.189.26.199</code></td>
<td>High</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<h3>Spoofing the United States Department of State</h3>
<p>In early February 2025, Volexity observed multiple spear-phishing campaigns targeting users with fake Microsoft invitations purporting to be from the United States (US) Department of State. These emails were themed as invitations to join the US Department of State’s Microsoft tenant as an external user, or as invitations to a Microsoft Teams chat named “<em><strong>Measuring Influence Operations</strong>".</em></p>
<p>Similar to the campaign conducted by UTA0304, these fake US Department of State emails were targeting users with a <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/identity-platform/v2-oauth2-device-code">Device Code OAuth</a> phishing workflow. Each email was aimed at convincing the user to accept the invitation and enter a unique code provided in the phishing email. The link in the invitations would direct users to the Microsoft Device Code <a href="https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/deviceauth">authentication page</a>. If the user entered the code provided in the phishing email, the authentication page would subsequently authorize the threat actor to access to the user’s account. However, it is worth noting that this campaign was sent out of the blue, with no precursor or build up to the emails, so users would not be expecting these messages. Even if they were to fall for the campaign, they would have to have done it within 15 minutes of receiving the email. This dramatically decreased the likelihood that this attack would be successful.</p>
<p>After reviewing various parts of the attack, Volexity assesses with medium confidence that the Russian threat actor CozyLarch (aka APT29 or Midnight Blizzard) was behind these US Department of State themed spear-phishing campaigns. Additional details on each campaign are described in the sections that follow.</p>
<h4>Campaign 1: M365 Tenant External User Invitation</h4>
<p>CozyLarch sent invitations to several users, inviting them to access applications within the M365 tenant for the US Department of State. The invitation email was designed to look like a real invitation that would be sent from Microsoft, as shown below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-teams-invite-1024x988.png" alt="" width="750" height="723" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-teams-invite-1024x988.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-teams-invite-300x289.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-teams-invite-768x741.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-teams-invite-1536x1481.png 1536w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-teams-invite.png 1746w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px"></p>
<p>In this instance, the “Accept invitation” hyperlink goes to <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/devicelogin">https://www.microsoft.com/devicelogin</a>, which is a simple redirect that sends the user to <a href="https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/deviceauth">https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/deviceauth</a>.</p>
<p>The redirect link takes the user to the Microsoft Device Code OAuth workflow, and it is the same URL that UTA0304 directly embedded in their phishing campaign. However, unlike UTA0304, CozyLarch opted to use the redirect URL rather than the final login URL, perhaps because it may look even more recognizable to a discerning user, given that it is hosted on the main Microsoft domain. If the user entered the code provided from the email and continued through the authentication process, the attacker was granted access to the user’s M365 account.</p>
<h4>Campaign 2: M365 Teams Chat Invitation</h4>
<p>CozyLarch launched a second campaign, in which they targeted users with a fake invitation to join a Microsoft Teams chat named “<strong><em>Measuring Influence Operations</em></strong>”. The email made it appear as though there were already 37 other members in the chat. &nbsp;A screenshot of one of the observed spear-phishing messages is shown below.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-external-invite-1024x989.png" alt="" width="685" height="661" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-external-invite-1024x989.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-external-invite-300x290.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-external-invite-768x742.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-external-invite-1536x1483.png 1536w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/cozylarch-state-department-external-invite.png 1860w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 685px) 100vw, 685px"></p>
<p>The “Sign in to Microsoft Teams” button in the email body is a hyperlink that leads to the same <a href="https://www.microsoft.com/devicelogin">https://www.microsoft.com/devicelogin</a> URL observed in the other campaign. The attack flow and end goal are the same, with only a small difference in the theme of the emails.</p>
<h4>Email Source Analysis</h4>
<p>The emails are designed to appear as though they come from Microsoft. The messages used mixed encoding in the “friendly” name that make the address difficult to discern. An example of the full “from” header used in one phishing email is given below:</p>
<blockquote><p><code>\"Mic\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\u200br\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30o\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30soft Invitations on behal f of US Dep\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30artme\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30nt of St\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30 ate \uff1cinvites\uff20mic\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30\u200br\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30o\udb40\udc30\udb40\udc30soft.co m\uff1e\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e \u180e\u3000\u180e \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e \u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e&nbsp; \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000 \u180e\u3000\u180e\u3000\u180e \u061c Cc:\" &lt;<a href="https://www.volexity.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="bfccd7dad6d3d2ded8d1dacbcbffd8d2ded6d391dcd0d2">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>&gt;</code></p></blockquote>
<p>The attacker attempted to make it appear as if the emails were from <code>invites@microsoft[.]com</code>, and also set the <code>Reply-To</code> header as <code>invites@microsoft[.]com</code>. However, the true address could be seen at the end of the <code>From:</code> field; all messages were sent via Google Gmail accounts. Volexity observed the following Gmail accounts as the actual senders of the messages observed:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>brensonkarl@gmail[.]com</code></li>
<li><code>kaylassammers@gmail[.]com</code></li>
<li><code>kendisggibson@gmail[.]com</code></li>
<li><code>leslytthomson@gmail[.]com</code></li>
<li><code>mikedanvil@gmail[.]com</code></li>
<li><code>sheilmagnett@gmail[.]com</code></li>
<li><code>susannmarton@gmail[.]com</code></li>
</ul>
<p>These addresses are believed to be controlled by CozyLarch and can be used to reliably detect phishing emails that may have been sent.</p>
<h4>Using Wireless Proxy Networks for Email Distribution</h4>
<p>Volexity also noted that the sending IP address associated with each spear-phishing email was recorded in the headers. Looking at the <code>Received</code> header in the messages, it became apparent that the attacker was using Proxy IP addresses based in the US to send messages. Volexity observed nearly a dozen IP addresses belonging to mobile networks in the US (AT&amp;T and Verizon Wireless).</p>
<h3>European Parliament and Donald Trump</h3>
<p>Starting in late January through to the publication of this blog (February 13, 2025), Volexity has observed another campaign by a Russian threat actor it tracks as <strong>UTA0307</strong> targeting numerous organizations. UTA0307 created a fake email under the identity of a member of the European Parliament who is on the Committee on Foreign Affairs. The threat actor reached out to numerous individuals with personalized emails requesting a Microsoft Teams meeting to discuss Donald Trump and his impact on relations between the US and the European Union. Volexity also observed a smaller set of campaigns centered on discussing China's foreign policy and China-European Union relations.</p>
<p>The email subject lines used in these various campaigns are listed below:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Trump and EU</em></li>
<li><em>Discussion on Eastern Europe and the Caucasus</em></li>
<li><em>Discussion about Donald Trump's new term</em></li>
<li><em>Discussion about Trump &amp; US relations with Europe</em></li>
<li><em>Collaboration on China and East Asia Research</em></li>
</ul>
<p>The image below shows an example spear phish that was sent by UTA0307.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-email-trump-us-relations-1024x760.png" alt="" width="690" height="512" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-email-trump-us-relations-1024x760.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-email-trump-us-relations-300x223.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-email-trump-us-relations-768x570.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-email-trump-us-relations-1536x1140.png 1536w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-email-trump-us-relations.png 1856w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 690px) 100vw, 690px"></p>
<p>None of the initial emails contained any malicious content or links at the onset. The threat actor was leveraging a tactic that has become commonplace for numerous nation-state actors, where they wait until a conversation has started prior to sending anything malicious. This serves the purpose of knowing they have an engaged target, and that the target's guard is potentially down. In the specific cases of Device Code Authentication phishing, it is especially important to have a responsive target, as the threat actor has only 15 minutes to convince the target to enter the code that has been generated.</p>
<h4>A Different Device Code OAuth Phishing Technique</h4>
<p>Volexity actually discovered the operations of UTA0307 following a successful compromise. Similar to the initial discovery of UTA0304, Volexity worked backwards from detecting a breach to identifying the above spear-phishing emails. In this case, the victim had engaged from the initial email and had several messages back and forth with UTA0307 regarding a meeting being set up. They agreed to join a Microsoft Teams meeting, and a fake invitation email was sent. However, this time the link in the email did not go to Microsoft. The target received an email with the subject "<em>Join Teams meeting</em>", and the body of the email, shown below, was designed to look like a real invitation.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-teams-invite.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-teams-invite-1024x415.png" alt="" width="590" height="239" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-teams-invite-1024x415.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-teams-invite-300x122.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-teams-invite-768x311.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-teams-invite.png 1046w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 590px) 100vw, 590px"></a></p>
<p>The “Join the meeting now” hyperlink, however, linked to a website controlled by UTA0307 (<code><strong>connect-71q.pages[.]dev</strong></code>). This page in turn was set up to automatically generate a new Microsoft Device Code each time it was visited. The website was designed to appear as an official Microsoft interstitial page before the user can join a Microsoft Teams meeting. The message that appears on the landing page (shown below) claims that the victim needs to pass a security check by copying a code and entering it on a subsequent page</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-security-check-1024x762.png" alt="" width="690" height="514" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-security-check-1024x762.png 1024w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-security-check-300x223.png 300w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-security-check-768x572.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-security-check-1536x1143.png 1536w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/uta0307-security-check.png 1822w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 690px) 100vw, 690px"></p>
<p>When the user clicks the “Next” button, a new tab is opened with the real Microsoft Device Code Authentication interface that requests an authentication code. If the victim enters the code supplied by the phishing page, they grant UTA0307 access to their M365 account. Interestingly, in the background of the initial phishing page, Volexity noted that the website would continuously poll the domain <code><strong>rosejob[.]com</strong></code>. It appears this domain was set up to monitor successful Device Code Authentication and, if detected, would redirect the user to a real Microsoft Teams meeting URL in an effort to make the activity appear legitimate.</p>
<p>The threat actor never joined this Microsoft Teams meeting. However, UTA0307 did add authorization for an authentication application under their control to enable multi-factor authentication when logging into the compromised account. Volexity assesses with medium confidence that this was a requirement of logging into the account, even with the stolen authentication token.</p>
<p>One benefit of this attack workflow versus other previously observed DeviceID phishing workflows is that, when a DeviceID code is generated, it is only valid for 15 minutes. Having an interstitial page that automatically generates new codes means UTA0307 does not have to worry about their phishing content expiring.</p>
<h4>UTA0307 Post-compromise Activities, Targeting and Attribution</h4>
<p>Volexity observed UTA0307 exfiltrating documents from a compromised M365 account that would be of interest to a Russian threat actor. This was determined based on identification of <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/purview/audit-log-activities">FileDownloaded operations</a> observed in M365 audit log data. Given this information about the threat actor’s objectives, their targeting, and their use of a highly similar technique to that used in recent days and weeks by CozyLarch and UTA0304, Volexity assesses with medium confidence that UTA0307 is also a Russian threat actor.</p>
<p>However, the exact implementation of the DeviceID OAuth phishing technique used in this activity differs slightly from those previously documented by Volexity, which provides some evidence that this activity may have been conducted by a separate threat actor. For example, while the previously observed phishing campaigns saw the attacker use the client ID for Microsoft Office when handling Device Code Authentication, this activity instead used the client ID for Microsoft Teams, as shown below (note that Microsoft uses <code>appId</code> and <code>client_id</code> interchangeably in their logs when referring to the ID for an application):</p>
<blockquote><p><code>"appDisplayName": "Microsoft Teams",</code></p>
<p><code>"appId": "1fec8e78-bce4-4aaf-ab1b-5451cc387264",</code></p></blockquote>
<p>Another difference between this and the UTA0304 campaign is that in this case, all subsequent access to the compromised account occurred via Mullad VPN exit nodes (versus the other observed VPS and Tor IP addresses). Based on these two factors, Volexity has chosen to track this activity under the UTA0307 alias, rather than CozyLarch or UTA0304.</p>
<h3>Detecting Device Code Authentication</h3>
<p>Volexity identified a way to reliably detect this attack through monitoring and analysis of Microsoft Entra ID sign-in logs. When a user enters a device code and subsequently authenticates, it results in a login to the application associated with the generated code. This can be a common application like Microsoft Office that is frequently accessed by users and would not be a reliable indicator. However, the good news is that Device Code Authentications result in the <code>authenticationProtocol</code> field being set with the value <code><strong>deviceCode</strong></code>.</p>
<p>The line below is what will appear in the JSON data in the Entra ID sign-in logs when a Device Code Authentication occurs:</p>
<blockquote><p><code>“authenticationProtocol": "deviceCode",</code></p></blockquote>
<p>Volexity further noted that as authenticated sessions refresh and are kept alive, subsequent sign-ins that initially occurred via a <code>deviceCode</code> often do not have anything set for <code>authenticationProtocol,</code> but they contain the following entry:</p>
<blockquote><p>&nbsp;<code> “originalTransferMethod": "deviceCodeFlow",</code></p></blockquote>
<p>These values can be searched and filtered on in the Entra Admin center by adding filters for "Authentications Protocol" and "Original Transfer Method". The latter can be filtered in both <em>interactive</em> and <em>non-interactive</em> sign-ins. The frequency and legitimacy of these values occurring in the sign-in logs for a particular organization may vary, as this is a legitimate Microsoft feature. An organization can evaluate their risk and usage of these workflows, and potentially use this information as a proactive detection mechanism.</p>
<p>If an organization has the ability to monitor URLs that are being accessed by users or sent in email, there are additional detection opportunities to discover Device Code Authentication attacks. The following official URLs can be monitored for as related to Microsoft Device Code Authentication:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>https://login.microsoftonline.com/common/oauth2/deviceauth</code></li>
<li><code>https://www.microsoft.com/devicelogin</code></li>
<li><code>https://aka.ms/devicelogin</code></li>
</ul>
<p>Organizations can monitor for access to these URLs or for their presence in various communication methods, such as email. Attackers can find other means to redirect users to these URLs, but one of the main advantages of using the list above in phishing attacks is that the URL displayed is hosted on a legitimate Microsoft domain.</p>
<h3>Preventing Device Code Authentication</h3>
<p>Volexity believes the most effective way to prevent this potential attack vector is through conditional access policies on an organization's M365 tenant. It is possible for organizations to create a conditional access policy that disallows device code authentication altogether. It is fairly trivial to set up, and Microsoft provides <a href="https://learn.microsoft.com/en-us/entra/identity/conditional-access/policy-block-authentication-flows">online guidance on exactly how to do this</a>. Based on Volexity's own testing, blocking the "Device code flow" from "Authentications flows" prevents this attack from working.&nbsp; The image below shows what a conditional access policy would look like once it's set up and in place to block this authentication flow.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/ConditionalAccess-Block_Device_Code-1-777x1024.png" alt="" width="569" height="750" srcset="https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/ConditionalAccess-Block_Device_Code-1-777x1024.png 777w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/ConditionalAccess-Block_Device_Code-1-228x300.png 228w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/ConditionalAccess-Block_Device_Code-1-768x1012.png 768w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/ConditionalAccess-Block_Device_Code-1-1165x1536.png 1165w, https://www.volexity.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/ConditionalAccess-Block_Device_Code-1.png 1264w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 569px) 100vw, 569px"></p>
<p>Prior to implementing such a policy, organizations should evaluate the use of Device Code Authentication in their environment. This feature is used legitimately, and blocking it could have a negative impact. Volexity's review of its own customers identified several instances of legitimate access to resources via these means. However, at the majority of Volexity's customers, there was either no recent Device Code Authentication activity or there was only activity tied to the attacks described in this blog post.</p>
<h3>Conclusion</h3>
<p>Volexity continues to track multiple spear-phishing campaigns targeting Device Code Authentication. This blog post serves to cover a few of the larger and unique campaigns observed. Volexity has observed other similar spear-phishing campaigns in recent weeks targeting Device Code Authentication that it believes are the work of Russian threat actors. Further, it should be noted that it is possible this is the work of a single threat actor running multiple, different campaigns. However, at this time, Volexity believes this activity is sufficiently different enough to warrant tracking this activity under two different unknown threat actors and one it believes is likely CozyLarch.</p>
<p>While Device Code Authentication attacks are not new, they appear to have been rarely leveraged by nation-state threat actors . Volexity's visibility into targeted attacks indicates this particular method has been far more effective than the combined effort of years of other social-engineering and spear-phishing attacks conducted by the same (or similar) threat actors. It appears that these Russian threat actors have made a concerted effort to launch several campaigns against organizations with a goal of simultaneously abusing this method before the targets catch on and implement countermeasures.</p>
<p>The detection mechanisms and countermeasures to these attacks have been available for years. However, Volexity believes they are seldom implemented and that most organizations are not even aware of this authentication flow, let alone the means to detect its misuse. These attacks serve as a reminder that threat actors will constantly look for ways to abuse legitimate features, and organizations must continually evaluate and implement methods to detect and prevent such attacks.</p>
<p>These attacks also serve as a good opportunity to engage with users and remind them to be on the lookout for anything out of the ordinary when it comes to accessing resources when they are asked for login credentials or authorization grants. This phishing workflow has proven useful for an attacker, as many traditional sources of evidence and detection, both for a user and network defenders, are not present. For example:</p>
<ol>
<li>There is no “malicious” link or attachment. The only link is to the provider’s infrastructure (in this case, Microsoft). This means users cannot easily identify the link as being suspicious, and automated solutions detecting malicious emails will likely fail to do so for the same reason.</li>
<li>Users are generally less aware of attacks that leverage legitimate services, and may be even less aware when it comes to those that involve entering a device code rather than their username or password.</li>
<li>After successful authentication, the logs will show the authenticating application as a legitimate or benign application, reducing signal that can be keyed off of in sign-in logs by detection teams.</li>
</ol>
<p>These are items that organizations should look to further train users on and implement technical countermeasures against where possible.</p>
<p><span data-teams="true">Indicators associated with these campaigns are available on the</span> <a href="https://github.com/volexity/threat-intel/blob/main/2025/2025-02-13%20Device%20Code%20Phishing/iocs.csv">Volexity GitHub</a>.</p>
<p><em>If you believe you have been targeted by a similar attack and want to share details with Volexity for informational purposes, additional investigation, or incident response, please <a href="https://www.volexity.com/company/contact/">contact us</a>.</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Volexity's Threat Intelligence research, such as the content from this blog, is published to customers via its </em><a href="https://www.volexity.com/services-overview/threat-intelligence/"><em>Threat Intelligence Service</em></a><em>. The activity described in this blog post was shared with Volexity Threat Intelligence customers in TIB-20250206, TIB-20250211, and TIB-20250213.</em></p>

<p><em>If you are interested in learning more about Volexity’s services, including <a href="https://www.volexity.com/services-overview/network-security-monitoring/">Network Security Monitoring</a> and <a href="https://www.volexity.com/services-overview/proactive-threat-assessments/">Incident Response</a>, or our leading memory forensics solutions, </em><a href="https://www.volexity.com/products-overview/surge/"><em>Volexity Surge Collect Pro</em></a><em> for memory acquisition and </em><a href="https://www.volexity.com/products-overview/volcano/"><em>Volexity Volcano</em></a><em> for memory analysis, please do not hesitate to </em><a href="https://www.volexity.com/company/contact/"><em>contact us</em></a><em>.</em></p></blockquote>
				
			</div>

		</article>

			</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PAROL6: 3D-printed desktop robotic arm (145 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://source-robotics.github.io/PAROL-docs/</link>
            <guid>43060818</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 18:26:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://source-robotics.github.io/PAROL-docs/">https://source-robotics.github.io/PAROL-docs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43060818">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-md-component="container">
      
      
        
          
        
      
      <main data-md-component="main">
        <div data-md-component="content">
              <article>
                
                  



<h2 id="home">Home</h2>
<p><img src="https://source-robotics.github.io/PAROL-docs/assets/img3.png" alt="drawing" width="5000"></p>
<p><strong>PAROL6</strong> is a high-performance 3D-printed desktop robotic arm. The design approach of PAROL6 was to be similar to industrial robots in terms of mechanical design, control software, and usability. Control software, GUI, and robots STL files are open-source. You can build your own PAROL6 robot by following the instructions located in <a href="https://github.com/PCrnjak/PAROL6-Desktop-robot-arm">Github</a> respository.</p>
<div>
<p>Note</p>
<p><strong>PAROL6 is in its version 1 release 1</strong><br></p>
</div>
<p>Visit our <a href="https://source-robotics.com/">Official website</a> </p>
<h2 id="project-links">Project links</h2>
<p>Source robotics website: <a href="https://source-robotics.com/">Link</a><br>
For building instructions visit: <a href="https://github.com/PCrnjak/PAROL6-Desktop-robot-arm/tree/main/Building%20instructions">Link</a><br>
All project files are on Github: <a href="https://github.com/PCrnjak/PAROL6-Desktop-robot-arm">Link</a><br>
PAROL commander software on Github: <a href="https://github.com/PCrnjak/PAROL-commander-software">Link</a><br>
For Discord community visit: <a href="https://discord.gg/prjUvjmGpZ">Link</a><br>
For official forum visit: <a href="https://discourse.source-robotics.com/">Link</a><br>
See more of our robots on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCp3sDRwVkbm7b2M-2qwf5aQ">Youtube</a>, <a href="https://www.instagram.com/5arcrnjak/">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/SourceRobotics">Twitter(X)</a></p>
<h2 id="documentation-layout">Documentation layout</h2>
<pre><code>docs/
    Home                    # Homepage of the project.
    About PAROL6            # Robot specifications, limits and.features
    General concepts        # General robotics concepts and theory.
    PAROL6 control board    # All about control board and how to use it.
    Getting started         # How to start using PAROL6 robot.
    Software                # All about PAROL6 software and API.
    PAROL6 commander GUI    # All about commander GUI interface
    Peripherals             # All about grippers, pneumatics, PLCs...
    Safety and handling     # How to not break your robot.
</code></pre>
<h2 id="preface">Preface</h2>
<p>This manual offers guidance on operating the 6-axis robot "Parol6" and its accompanying "Parol6" software. The Parol6 is a versatile robot designed for a wide audience, including educational institutions, robotics enthusiasts, and small-scale automation applications. It serves as a practical tool for learning, exploration, and implementing robotics in various fields.</p>
<h2 id="liability">Liability</h2>
<ol>
<li>
<p>Source Robotics shall not assume liability for any accidents, damages, and/or issues resulting from the improper use of the Parol6 robot</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Source Robotics retains the right to modify, revise, or update this manual without prior notice.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="licence">Licence</h2>
<p>All code, building instructions/BOM and STL files are under GPLv3 Licence.</p>







  
  






                
              </article>
            </div>
        
          
        
      </main>
      
        
      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Basketball has evolved into a game of calculated decision-making (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nabraj.com/blog/basketball-solved-sport/</link>
            <guid>43060769</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 18:21:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nabraj.com/blog/basketball-solved-sport/">https://nabraj.com/blog/basketball-solved-sport/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43060769">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Basketball has evolved from a game of unpredictability into a game of calculated decision-making with the use of data and analytics. From a game of points, assists, and rebounds, it has progressed into using thousands of data points to optimize every element of the game.</p><p>All decisions are made based on numbers not intuition. Long-range shooting and layups are preferred over mid-range shooting. Players are no longer do-it-alls; they are now given specialized roles.</p><h3>Three-point rain</h3><p>In the last decade, long-range shooting has gone from a secondary option to a primary choice for building offense. Recently, teams have realized three-pointers have higher point value despite their lower scoring percentage. This has led to a revolution in structuring an offense around taking long-range shots. The Golden State Warriors, led by Stephen Curry, probably jump-started this trend with 34 three-pointer attempts per game in the 2018-19 season, twice as much from five years ago. Celtics, this season, have averaged almost 50 three-pointers attempt this season (2024-25 season).</p><div data-gatsby-image-wrapper=""><picture><source type="image/webp" data-srcset="/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/83e39/basketball2.webp 100w,/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/53a86/basketball2.webp 200w,/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/4a8c8/basketball2.webp 400w" sizes="(min-width: 400px) 400px, 100vw"><img data-gatsby-image-ssr="" data-main-image="" sizes="(min-width: 400px) 400px, 100vw" decoding="async" loading="lazy" data-src="/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/14d1d/basketball2.png" data-srcset="/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/93a8b/basketball2.png 100w,/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/5fd93/basketball2.png 200w,/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/14d1d/basketball2.png 400w" alt="NBA 3-pt average per game" src="https://nabraj.com/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/14d1d/basketball2.png" srcset="https://nabraj.com/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/93a8b/basketball2.png 100w,https://nabraj.com/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/5fd93/basketball2.png 200w,https://nabraj.com/static/0725130a5ccae46a5f922c287a8a87b7/14d1d/basketball2.png 400w"></picture></div><p>In the past, the team built its roster around a big name like Shaq. Most of the offense were from the center. This has now changed, with the primary strategy being to stretch the opposition and take long-range shots.</p><h3>Rise of 3-and-D model</h3><p>The 3-and-D model refers to a player, usually a wing player, who is just above average at three-pointers and plays competent defense.  Forget about positions; just get a guy who can do some 3s and Ds.</p><p>Danny Green is probably the father of this model, with his 40% career three-point field goal percentage and he also made into all-defensive team.</p><p>In  recent years, every team has had at least one 3-and-D model player on the roster.</p><h3>Specialization</h3><p>Gone are the days of an all-around player. There is no longer a need for a player who does everything. Look at players like Kobe Bryant and Lebron James (early career); they not only scored but guarded defense, caught rebounds and played the role of playmakers.</p><p>Now, it’s all about creating lineups with specialized players. A team typically consists of a three-point shooter, a defensive specialist, a playmaker, and rebounders. They all have specific roles assigned to them.</p><div data-gatsby-image-wrapper=""><picture><source type="image/webp" data-srcset="/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/4999a/basketball1.webp 113w,/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/b2693/basketball1.webp 225w,/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/5b837/basketball1.webp 450w" sizes="(min-width: 450px) 450px, 100vw"><img data-gatsby-image-ssr="" data-main-image="" sizes="(min-width: 450px) 450px, 100vw" decoding="async" loading="lazy" data-src="/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/3c337/basketball1.png" data-srcset="/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/c8387/basketball1.png 113w,/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/26052/basketball1.png 225w,/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/3c337/basketball1.png 450w" alt="Average distance for goal attempt" src="https://nabraj.com/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/3c337/basketball1.png" srcset="https://nabraj.com/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/c8387/basketball1.png 113w,https://nabraj.com/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/26052/basketball1.png 225w,https://nabraj.com/static/a797bc0eac630491d1dea907b921fed5/3c337/basketball1.png 450w"></picture></div><h3>Technology</h3><p>A catch-all word for statistics, technology has played a pivotal role in shaping this game. </p><p>In addition to data collection, biomechanics and motion cameras track every player’s movement. NBA even brought SportVU from football; it follows the ball and supposedly captures images 25 times per second. Coaches can now use this to analyze the speed, position, form, and motion of each player on the court. </p><p>In the end, it’s all about optimizing every ball possession. </p><h3>What now?</h3><p>Basketball might have lost its flair; every move is now predictable and measured. What is the future of basketball, is anyone’s guess? Maybe a rule change is around the corner?</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Alzheimer's biomarkers now visible up to a decade ahead of symptoms (213 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://newatlas.com/brain/alzheimers-dementia/alzheimers-biomarkers-visible-decade-before-symptoms/</link>
            <guid>43060587</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 18:02:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://newatlas.com/brain/alzheimers-dementia/alzheimers-biomarkers-visible-decade-before-symptoms/">https://newatlas.com/brain/alzheimers-dementia/alzheimers-biomarkers-visible-decade-before-symptoms/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43060587">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Researchers at the University of Pittsburgh have devised a biomarker test that can spot small amounts of clumping tau protein in the brain and cerebrospinal fluid, which lead to Alzheimer's disease.</p><p>Catching these clumps early while still in minute quantities can enable effective intervention. This test can help detect the tangled proteins years in advance of them appearing prominently in brain scans – as much as up to a decade.</p><p>That's heartening because Alzheimer's disease not only has devastating impact on patients' lives long term, but is also currently incurable. It begins to show up as forgetfulness, and progresses to confusion and disorientation, delusions, hallucinations, and trouble sleeping. As the condition worsens, patients may experience difficulty eating, moving around, incontinence, loss of speech, and significant memory loss.</p><p>“Early detection is key to more successful therapies for Alzheimer’s disease since trials show that patients with little-to-no quantifiable insoluble tau tangles are more likely to benefit from new treatments than those with a significant degree of tau brain deposits," explained Thomas Karikari, senior author of the <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-024-03400-0" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">paper published in <i>Nature</i></a> this week.</p><p>Here's a quick bit of context on what's happening in and around the brain. <a href="https://www.nih.gov/news-events/nih-research-matters/scientists-build-largest-maps-date-cells-human-brain" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">Humans have some 86 billion nerve cells</a>, and they're connected by what are called synapses. These synapses are supported by 'rail tracks' that enable the flow of essential nutrients and information, and they're called microtubules.</p><p>Tau proteins (abbreviated from tubulin associated unit) stabilize these microtubules, and help keep the brain healthy. These proteins can malfunction, clump together and create tangles – preventing the microtubules from functioning properly.</p><p>As more tangles form, they spread through the brain in a predictable pattern, starting in regions involved in memory and gradually affecting areas responsible for other cognitive functions. That's one of <a href="https://www.nia.nih.gov/health/alzheimers-and-dementia/what-alzheimers-disease" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">several changes in the brain that causes Alzheimer's disease</a>.</p><p>Here's where this new biomarker test comes in. The researchers have found an important section of the tau protein that causes it to form harmful tangles in the brain. This section is made up of 111 building blocks (amino acids). Within this section, they discovered two specific spots that, when modified, can tell doctors if tau proteins are starting to clump together. This is important because if doctors can detect these changes early enough, they might be able to treat the problem before it gets worse.</p><p>The two specific spots they found (called p-tau-262 and p-tau-356) work like early warning signals, letting doctors know that tau proteins are beginning to malfunction. This could help identify Alzheimer's disease sooner, when treatments might be more effective.</p><p>This test joins a bunch of notable Alzheimer's-related breakthroughs we've learned about over the last year or so. For starters, <a href="https://newatlas.com/medical/five-subtypes-alzheimers-identified/" data-cms-ai="0">five subtypes of the disease were identified</a>, opening the doors to more targeted treatment. We also saw, for the first time, a high-resolution <a href="https://newatlas.com/brain/alzheimers-dementia/cell-atlas-alzheimers-treatment-targets/" data-cms-ai="0">timeline of images of the condition's progress</a> at the cellular level that helped better understand this condition.</p><p>Plus, researchers found that <a href="https://newatlas.com/medical/pde4b-alzheimers-treatment-pathway/" data-cms-ai="0">limiting a particular enzyme can protect against the effects</a> of the disease. Another team invented a molecule that can <a href="https://newatlas.com/health-wellbeing/memory-molecule-alzheimers/" data-cms-ai="0">boost electrical oscillations in the brain, improving memory and cognition</a> in mice that were modified to have Alzheimer's. </p><p>The next few years should reveal several new avenues to treat the disease more effectively – and that could go a long way towards improving the lives of <a href="https://www.alzint.org/about/dementia-facts-figures/dementia-statistics/" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">78 million people estimated to develop various dementias</a>, including Alzheimer's, worldwide by 2030.</p><p>Source: <a href="https://www.medschool.pitt.edu/news/biomarker-test-can-detect-alzheimers-pathology-earlier-pitt-study-shows" target="_blank" data-cms-ai="0">University of Pittsburgh</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[More Solar and Battery Storage Added to TX Grid Than Other Power Src Last Year (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://insideclimatenews.org/news/10022025/solar-battery-storage-texas-grid/</link>
            <guid>43059826</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Feb 2025 16:37:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://insideclimatenews.org/news/10022025/solar-battery-storage-texas-grid/">https://insideclimatenews.org/news/10022025/solar-battery-storage-texas-grid/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43059826">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
		<main id="main" role="main">

			
				<article id="post-91279">

					
						
<!-- .entry-header -->

					
					<div>

						
<p>As the market for renewables in Texas continues to strengthen and innovate, the power makeup of the state’s electric grid is slated to keep shifting toward adding more renewables. Last year, solar and battery storage installation led capacity growth within Texas’ electric grid, according to <a href="https://www.dallasfed.org/research/economics/2025/0114">research from the Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas</a> published in January.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Texas added nearly 1,500 megawatts of battery storage to the grid’s summer rated capacities in 2023. That figure almost tripled to 4,374 megawatts added in 2024, according to the report.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Capacity from solar power added to the grid enjoyed a similar trajectory. In 2023, 4,570 megawatts were added to the grid, while in 2024, nearly 9,700 megawatts were added.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Given that Texas has its own isolated energy grid, the Electricity Reliability Council of Texas (ERCOT) is responsible for managing the majority of energy for its residents.&nbsp;</p>


<div><h3>We’re hiring!</h3><p>Please take a look at the new openings in our newsroom.</p><p><a href="https://insideclimatenews.org/about/jobs/" target="_blank">See jobs</a></p></div> <!-- /.icn-call-out-block -->


<p>Historically, ERCOT, which manages 90 percent of the state’s power load, has primarily relied on natural gas. But other energy sources, like wind and solar, have played a critical role in offsetting high demand.&nbsp;</p>



<p>ERCOT added 3,400 megawatts from natural gas power plants in 2024. That’s after more than 1,000 megawatts of natural gas power were inactive within the grid from 2021 to 2023, according to Dallas Fed data.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The capacity growth from solar and battery storage allowed the grid to manage another hot Texas summer in 2024, reported Garret Golding, an assistant vice president for energy program at the Dallas Fed.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Battery storage is relatively new to ERCOT. One of the first battery power storage plants to be connected to ERCOT was in 2021, southeast of Dallas in Kaufman County.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The 50-megawatt plant run by Enel, one of the largest renewable energy owners and operators in the country, was the first of Enel’s 14 battery projects it has since developed across the state.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The forecasted power demand in Texas from population growth and heavy load users like data centers, cryptocurrency mining and artificial intelligence, alongside the competitive market for batteries, is dictating the rising use of storage within ERCOT, said Randald Bartlett, a senior director of operations and management for battery energy storage systems at Enel North America.</p>



<p>Texas’ permitting processes and ability to develop has made it easier to add and build new capacity in comparison to other states with more laborious entryways, Bartlett said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Before, there wasn’t really adequate criteria and evidence to forecast what batteries would contribute to the grid, ERCOT CEO Pablo Vegas said during a board of directors meeting on Tuesday.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Now, the grid operator added battery contribution to its report forecasting future capacity, demand and reserves.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Battery storage in the ERCOT grid has nearly doubled every year since 2021, Vegas said. At the end of 2024, there were nearly 10,000 megawatts from batteries within ERCOT.</p>



<p>Vegas said the capacity from batteries made a significant difference in ERCOT during bridge hours, or the winter morning hours when the sun has yet to rise and in the evenings after the sun sets.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“Batteries made a meaningful contribution to what those shoulder periods look like and how much scarcity we get into during these peak events,” Vegas said when analyzing the grid’s performance during recent winter storms.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In the spring of 2024, Texas’ installation of utility scale solar outpaced California’s, and jumped from 1,900 megawatts in 2019 to over 20,000 megawatts in 2024. As a result, solar met nearly 50 percent of the state’s peak power demand on some days.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The state’s quick deployment of utility scale solar didn’t happen overnight. It started in 2005, when the legislature instructed the Public Utility Commission of Texas to create competitive renewable energy zones, where the state planned transmission lines to connect cities to renewable energy sources in west Texas.</p>



<p>Initially, it was intended to capture wind power but was able to quickly include solar because of the existing infrastructure, said Dustin Mulvaney, an environmental studies professor at San Jose State University and an author of Planning to Build Faster: A Solar Energy Case Study, published in October by the Roosevelt Institute.&nbsp;</p>



<p>That forward-looking plan is often held up as a model renewable energy advocates and developers say the Federal Energy Regulatory Commission could implement across other regional transmission organizations, by requiring proactive planning and by creating rules of how to pay for transmission systems.&nbsp;</p>



<p>As the state’s grid continues to experience a rapid shift in the type of generation available to serve demand, the state’s grid operator is looking to build a higher voltage transmission system, upgrading from 345-kilovolt lines to 765-kilovolt lines.&nbsp;</p>



<p>In 2024, nearly 78 gigawatts of transmission-connected wind, solar and battery energy storage capacity was installed to the grid. And more than 102 gigawatts of transmission-connected renewable capacity is expected to be installed by the end of 2025, according to a December ERCOT report.</p>



<p>It’s that growth of both demand and renewables connected to the grid that’s led ERCOT to ask the Public Utility Commission to consider upgrading the state’s transmission system rather than expanding its existing one.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The 765-kV lines would provide significant economic and reliability benefits to the ERCOT system, wrote Kristi Hobbs, ERCOT’s vice president of system planning and weatherization, in the grid operator’s submission of its regional transmission plans to the commission in late January.</p>



<p>Regardless of which transmission plan is chosen, Hobbs wrote, the explosive growth projected throughout the next six years and beyond will require major public investment.&nbsp;</p>

						
<div>

		<h2>About This Story</h2>

		<p>Perhaps you noticed: This story, like all the news we publish, is free to read. That’s because Inside Climate News is a 501c3 nonprofit organization. We do not charge a subscription fee, lock our news behind a paywall, or clutter our website with ads. We make our news on climate and the environment freely available to you and anyone who wants it.</p>
		<p>That’s not all. We also share our news for free with scores of other media organizations around the country. Many of them can’t afford to do environmental journalism of their own. We’ve built bureaus from coast to coast to report local stories, collaborate with local newsrooms and co-publish articles so that this vital work is shared as widely as possible.</p>
		<p>Two of us launched ICN in 2007. Six years later we earned a Pulitzer Prize for National Reporting, and now we run the oldest and largest dedicated climate newsroom in the nation. We tell the story in all its complexity. We hold polluters accountable. We expose environmental injustice. We debunk misinformation. We scrutinize solutions and inspire action.</p>
		<p>Donations from readers like you fund every aspect of what we do. If you don’t already, will you support our ongoing work, our reporting on the biggest crisis facing our planet, and help us reach even more readers in more places? </p>
		<p>Please take a moment to make a tax-deductible donation. Every one of them makes a difference.</p>
		<p>Thank you,</p>

		 <!-- /.footer -->

	</div> <!-- /.icn-epic -->

						
 <!-- /.icn-share-holder -->

						
		<div>

			
				<p><img width="300" height="300" src="https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-300x300.jpg" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-300x300.jpg 300w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-150x150.jpg 150w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-768x768.jpg 768w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-64x64.jpg 64w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-600x600.jpg 600w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-400x400.jpg 400w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin.jpg 1365w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20300%20300'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-300x300.jpg 300w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-1024x1024.jpg 1024w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-150x150.jpg 150w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-768x768.jpg 768w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-64x64.jpg 64w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-600x600.jpg 600w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-400x400.jpg 400w, https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin.jpg 1365w" data-lazy-src="https://insideclimatenews.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/Arcelia-Martin-300x300.jpg">
				</p> <!-- /.image-holder -->

			
			<div>

				

				
				
					<h4>Reporter, Texas Renewables</h4>

				
				
				
					<p>Arcelia Martin is an award-winning journalist at Inside Climate News. She covers renewable energy in Texas from her base in Dallas. Before joining ICN in 2025, Arcelia was a staff writer at The Dallas Morning News and at The Tennessean. Originally from San Diego, California, she’s a graduate of Gonzaga University and Columbia University Graduate School of Journalism.</p>

				
				
	

	
			</div> <!-- /.bio -->

		</div> <!-- /.post-author-bio -->

		
					</div><!-- .entry-content -->

				</article><!-- #post-## -->

				 <!-- /.post-footer -->

			
		</main><!-- #main -->
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>