<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 17:00:07 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple curl security incident 12604 (220 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2024/03/08/the-apple-curl-security-incident-12604/</link>
            <guid>39650498</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 09:15:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2024/03/08/the-apple-curl-security-incident-12604/">https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/2024/03/08/the-apple-curl-security-incident-12604/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39650498">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">

	<div id="primary" role="main">
			
<article id="post-23833">
	
		<p><img width="672" height="338" src="https://daniel.haxx.se/blog/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/apples.jpg" alt="" decoding="async">		</p>

		
	<!-- .entry-header -->

		<div>
		
<p>tldr: Apple thinks it is fine. I do not.</p>



<p>On December 28 2023, <a href="https://github.com/curl/curl/issues/12604">bugreport 12604</a> was filed in the curl issue tracker. We get a lot issues filed most days so this fact alone was hardly anything out of the ordinary. We read the reports, investigate, ask follow-up questions to see what we can learn and what we need to address.</p>



<p>The title stated of the problem in this case was quite clear: <em><a href="https://github.com/curl/curl/issues/12604">flag –cacert behavior isn’t consistent between macOS and Linux</a></em>, and it was filed by Yuedong Wu.</p>



<p>The friendly reporter showed how the curl version bundled with macOS behaves differently than curl binaries built entirely from open source. Even when running the same curl version on the same macOS machine.</p>



<p>The curl command line option <code><a href="https://curl.se/docs/manpage.html#--cacert">--cacert</a></code> provides a way for the user to say to curl that <strong>this is the exact set of CA certificates to trust</strong> when doing the following transfer. If the TLS server cannot provide a certificate that can be verified with that set of certificates, it should fail and return error.</p>



<p>This particular behavior and functionality in curl has been established since many years (this option was added to curl in December 2000) and of course is provided to allow users to know that it communicates with a known and trusted server. A pretty fundamental part of what TLS does really.</p>



<p>When this command line option is used with curl on macOS, <em>the version shipped by Apple</em>, <strong>it seems to fall back and checks the system CA store in case the provided set of CA certs fail the verification</strong>.  A <em>secondary check</em> that was not asked for,  is not documented and plain frankly comes completely by surprise. Therefore, when a user runs the check with a trimmed and dedicated CA cert file, it will not fail if the system CA store contains a cert that can verify the server!</p>



<p>This is a security problem because now<strong> suddenly certificate checks pass that should not pass.</strong></p>



<p>I reported this as a security problem in an email sent to Product Security at Apple on December 29 2023, 08:30 UTC. It’s not a major problem, but it is an issue.</p>



<h2>Apple’s says it is fine</h2>



<p>On March 8, 2024 Apple Product Security responded with their wisdom:</p>



<pre>Hello,

Thank you again for reporting this to us and allowing us time to investigate.

Apple’s version of OpenSSL (LibreSSL) intentionally uses the built-in system trust store as a default source of trust. Because the server certificate can be validated successfully using the built-in system trust store, we don't consider this something that needs to be addressed in our platforms.

Best regards,
KC
Apple Product Security</pre>



<p>Case closed.</p>



<h2>I disagree</h2>



<p>Obviously I think differently. This <em>undocumented feature</em> makes CA cert verification with curl on macOS totally unreliable and inconsistent with documentation. It tricks users.</p>



<p>Be aware.</p>



<p>Since this is not a security vulnerability in the curl version we ship, we have not issued a CVE or anything for this problem. The problem is strictly speaking not even in curl code. It comes with the version of LibreSSL that Apple ships and builds curl to use on their platforms.</p>
	</div><!-- .entry-content -->
	
	</article><!-- #post-23833 -->
		<nav>
		<h2>
			Post navigation		</h2>
		<!-- .nav-links -->
		</nav><!-- .navigation -->
		
<!-- #comments -->
		</div><!-- #primary -->

<!-- #content-sidebar -->
<div id="secondary">
		<h2>tech, open source and networking</h2>
	
	
		<!-- #primary-sidebar -->
	</div><!-- #secondary -->

		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Suicide PhD Candidate Huixiang Chen (2019) (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://huixiangvoice.medium.com/the-hidden-story-behind-the-suicide-phd-candidate-huixiang-chen-236cd39f79d3</link>
            <guid>39649486</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 04:57:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://huixiangvoice.medium.com/the-hidden-story-behind-the-suicide-phd-candidate-huixiang-chen-236cd39f79d3">https://huixiangvoice.medium.com/the-hidden-story-behind-the-suicide-phd-candidate-huixiang-chen-236cd39f79d3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39649486">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><div><div><div><a rel="noopener follow" href="https://huixiangvoice.medium.com/?source=post_page-----236cd39f79d3--------------------------------"><div aria-hidden="false"><p><img alt="Huixiang Voice" src="https://miro.medium.com/v2/resize:fill:88:88/2*VAo28uyHI7zNBI3nN-xXEA.jpeg" width="44" height="44" loading="lazy" data-testid="authorPhoto"></p></div></a></div><p id="6094">On June 13, 2019, just before the ISCA 2019 conference in Phoenix, a doctoral candidate, whose paper was supposed to be published at this conference, <a href="https://www.gainesville.com/news/20190614/body-of-chinese-student-found-in-campus-building" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">hanged himself in the campus building of the University of Florida</a>.</p><p id="89a0">As more and more information comes out, we find that there should be a lot of hidden stories behind his suicide. The most important one may be related to his struggle against academic misconduct.</p><p id="2f64">A suicide note was sent to his friends, lab colleges, and especially his mentor Doctor <a href="http://www.taoli.ece.ufl.edu/" rel="noopener ugc nofollow" target="_blank">Tao Li</a>, a tenured professor (with preeminence professorship) in the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, also the last author of the paper mentioned in Huixiang’s suicide note.</p><p id="1c80">The original version of the suicide note is in Chinese:</p></div><div><figure></figure><figure><figcaption>Huixiang Chen’s Suicide Note</figcaption></figure></div><div><p id="bfae">Here we translated it into English (This is not a certified legal translation):</p><blockquote><p id="b65e">Dear fellow colleagues:</p><p id="d3c0">If you get this message, that means I have already passed away.</p><p id="eb99">As you know, since last year December, I wrote an ISCA paper in a very short time and it was submitted and accepted very quickly. As all of you know the reason, it was owe to our professor Dr.Tao Li ’s networking. Among the six reviewers of my paper, four of them are friends of Tao Li. But this paper has very severe issues: the design doesn’t make any sense and the reviewers also pay no attention to it. The paper was accepted at no reason which can make anyone feel guilty in this case.</p><p id="dbae">After the deadline, crazy modifications of the paper were made and I started to make up for the missing experiments. During those experiments, I found that the phenomenon of the experiments and the design was different from what was claimed before, which made this paper doesn’t make any sense from title to characterization and to design. For example, It was claimed that this (the accelerator) is targeted for 3D CNN, which can maximize the performance by changing Diffy architecture to achieve the dynamic control of the temporal delta and spatial delta. But there are too many issues with this. First of all, the Diffy architecture has a serious problem of synchronization. If the width of the input feature is too narrow, the overhead of lane synchronization … . But it was assumed that the temporal dimension of 3D CNN (the maximum is generally 16 and it will decrease with layer) will expand with Diffy. Secondly, it can’t skip zero, because of the synchronization of lane and the incremental of spatial/temporal delta. So if I want to make a change the whole paper need to be rewrite. It is unrealistic to propose a totally new idea before the final version. After I communicated with Tao Li, it turned out that I have to fix the paper by myself. Until today I am still unable to patch up any of those issues. These issues are too obvious which can be easily caught by any experts of accelerator. I have no words to comment that Dr. Li acquiesced to the data which makes no sense.</p><p id="f282">Considering that this will have an impact on my career in the future and my reputation in the area of Computer Architecture, my future life will be worse than death and I will be totally in a dilemma. I considered all the cases, I really can’t work them around. In order to make up for the fault, I decide to suicide. I hope you can learn my lessons and don’t mess around things. We shall never claim too much in the paper before we can really achieve it. I hope this will make a change in this world.</p><p id="83ee">I hope you can keep simple and stay honest in this society. I will bless you in another world.</p><p id="24be">Best</p><p id="23c7">Huxiang</p></blockquote><p id="1ee8">After the tragedy, some dialogues between Huixiang Chen and his friends are exposed, which also shed some light on his struggling against academic misconduct and the intense relationship between him and Dr. Tao Li. (Translations here are not certified legal translation. To protect the information providers, we cover the content of their words.)</p></div><div><p id="adf7">Only a suicide note and several pieces of dialogues may not uncover all the truth. University of Florida and the ECE department should have an elaborate and responsible investigation on this event.</p></div></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Self-Retrieval: Building an information retrieval system with one LLM (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00801</link>
            <guid>39648689</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 01:46:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00801">https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00801</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39648689">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
    <div><p><span>Authors:</span><a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Tang,+Q">Qiaoyu Tang</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Chen,+J">Jiawei Chen</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Yu,+B">Bowen Yu</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lu,+Y">Yaojie Lu</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Fu,+C">Cheng Fu</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Yu,+H">Haiyang Yu</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Lin,+H">Hongyu Lin</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Huang,+F">Fei Huang</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=He,+B">Ben He</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Han,+X">Xianpei Han</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Sun,+L">Le Sun</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/search/cs?searchtype=author&amp;query=Li,+Y">Yongbin Li</a></p></div>            
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2403.00801">Download PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2403.00801v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>The rise of large language models (LLMs) has transformed the role of information retrieval (IR) systems in the way to humans accessing information. Due to the isolated architecture and the limited interaction, existing IR systems are unable to fully accommodate the shift from directly providing information to humans to indirectly serving large language models. In this paper, we propose Self-Retrieval, an end-to-end, LLM-driven information retrieval architecture that can fully internalize the required abilities of IR systems into a single LLM and deeply leverage the capabilities of LLMs during IR process. Specifically, Self-retrieval internalizes the corpus to retrieve into a LLM via a natural language indexing architecture. Then the entire retrieval process is redefined as a procedure of document generation and self-assessment, which can be end-to-end executed using a single large language model. Experimental results demonstrate that Self-Retrieval not only significantly outperforms previous retrieval approaches by a large margin, but also can significantly boost the performance of LLM-driven downstream applications like retrieval augumented generation.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Qiaoyu Tang [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/677958a1/2403.00801">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Fri, 23 Feb 2024 18:45:35 UTC (516 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TimeLapze: Open-source screen recorder (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse</link>
            <guid>39648259</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 00:45:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse">https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39648259">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/27795014/291787158-d79916bd-e0d5-4da1-85ce-4bf95f0f44fb.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NzUxMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk3NDgwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNzc5NTAxNC8yOTE3ODcxNTgtZDc5OTE2YmQtZTBkNS00ZGExLTg1Y2UtNGJmOTVmMGY0NGZiLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDklMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA5VDA5MDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTM0MmY1NDQyOTRhOWM1NTBkYWFhMGVkYjdhZTVmYzAyNTc4ZmQ5OTQ3MDU3NzAyY2I5ZDk1YmYxZGZkZGZhNzEmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.M0dAcSY3R4i0prIlEmzYAavk_cyResX59c0i71YjHIM"><img alt="TimeLapze" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/27795014/291787158-d79916bd-e0d5-4da1-85ce-4bf95f0f44fb.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NzUxMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk3NDgwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNzc5NTAxNC8yOTE3ODcxNTgtZDc5OTE2YmQtZTBkNS00ZGExLTg1Y2UtNGJmOTVmMGY0NGZiLnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDklMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA5VDA5MDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTM0MmY1NDQyOTRhOWM1NTBkYWFhMGVkYjdhZTVmYzAyNTc4ZmQ5OTQ3MDU3NzAyY2I5ZDk1YmYxZGZkZGZhNzEmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.M0dAcSY3R4i0prIlEmzYAavk_cyResX59c0i71YjHIM"></a>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">TimeLapze</h2><a id="user-content-timelapze" aria-label="Permalink: TimeLapze" href="#timelapze"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">
  A open-source menu bar application for creating screen and camera timelapses without excessive file sizes.
</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="#introduction"><strong>Introduction</strong></a> ·
  <a href="#features"><strong>Features</strong></a> ·
  <a href="#installation"><strong>Installation</strong></a> ·
  <a href="#local-development"><strong>Local Development</strong></a> ·
  <a href="#tech-stack"><strong>Tech Stack</strong></a> ·
  <a href="#contributing"><strong>Contributing</strong></a>
</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h2><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/27795014/280436934-785ee2b6-1ef5-4302-83da-c3d81a069074.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NzUxMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk3NDgwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNzc5NTAxNC8yODA0MzY5MzQtNzg1ZWUyYjYtMWVmNS00MzAyLTgzZGEtYzNkODFhMDY5MDc0LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDklMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA5VDA5MDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRhMmVhNjIyNTBhZGIyYThkMGI4YjQ0ZjQyYWJmZTA0Y2IyYjNkYjE3Y2UzNGRhODEwYWJlN2JmNjhiNzlhMWUmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.--4XftTPJz5OxDnEC5f86P0WM-XmLu2uy75OWTbE9FM"><img width="553" alt="Application demonstration photo in menu bar" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/27795014/280436934-785ee2b6-1ef5-4302-83da-c3d81a069074.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NzUxMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk3NDgwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNzc5NTAxNC8yODA0MzY5MzQtNzg1ZWUyYjYtMWVmNS00MzAyLTgzZGEtYzNkODFhMDY5MDc0LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDklMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA5VDA5MDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPWRhMmVhNjIyNTBhZGIyYThkMGI4YjQ0ZjQyYWJmZTA0Y2IyYjNkYjE3Y2UzNGRhODEwYWJlN2JmNjhiNzlhMWUmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.--4XftTPJz5OxDnEC5f86P0WM-XmLu2uy75OWTbE9FM"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
    <i>TimeLapze</i> is a open-source, minimalist, menu bar application for creating color accurate screen and camera timelapses without enormous file sizes.
</p>
<p dir="auto">
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/27795014/289590251-ca37fa51-7851-4080-9e8c-f95f9ed529a8.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NzUxMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk3NDgwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNzc5NTAxNC8yODk1OTAyNTEtY2EzN2ZhNTEtNzg1MS00MDgwLTllOGMtZjk1ZjllZDUyOWE4LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDklMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA5VDA5MDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTcxMDQ1MDMyZDJkOWJkYzgyMzk0ZTJmZTA4MTNmNjg2NDc5ODdlYjMxYjFiOWVmYWNjM2Y3OTk0Nzc5N2E5NzcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.iH5-JRXLqM1UVqvE7cCBLdy1JhNpI-R1hl6OaXhACVw"><img alt="color accurate comparision" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/27795014/289590251-ca37fa51-7851-4080-9e8c-f95f9ed529a8.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NzUxMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk3NDgwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNzc5NTAxNC8yODk1OTAyNTEtY2EzN2ZhNTEtNzg1MS00MDgwLTllOGMtZjk1ZjllZDUyOWE4LnBuZz9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDklMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA5VDA5MDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTcxMDQ1MDMyZDJkOWJkYzgyMzk0ZTJmZTA4MTNmNjg2NDc5ODdlYjMxYjFiOWVmYWNjM2Y3OTk0Nzc5N2E5NzcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.iH5-JRXLqM1UVqvE7cCBLdy1JhNpI-R1hl6OaXhACVw"></a>
Color accuracy is an important feature which prevents you from recording washed-out, photocopied-looking time lapses.
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Color Accurate</strong>: What you see is what you get. Never screen record faded videos again<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-1-9d2f1a5efd409e3c789397e41222d54e" id="user-content-fnref-1-9d2f1a5efd409e3c789397e41222d54e" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup></li>
<li><strong>Minimalist Design</strong>: a fully featured web recorder in your menu bar</li>
<li><strong>Hardware Accelerated</strong>: fully utilized hardware accelerated encoding for a lightweight recording experience</li>
<li><strong>Space Saving</strong>: Avoid the excessive file sizes of high quality video (can be as high as 7 GB / hour).</li>
<li><strong>Camera Recording</strong>: Record your webcam or phone with the same frame rate and camera speed</li>
<li><strong>Secure</strong>: Use the fully features of <code>ScreenCaptureKit</code> to only record certain windows, applications and more. Never leak your bank information in recordings again!</li>
<li><strong>Customizability</strong>: Change everything from the frame rate, quality and speed multiple</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The recommended way to install <strong>TimeLapze</strong> is through <a href="https://brew.sh/" rel="nofollow">Homebrew</a> cask.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="brew install --cask https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/main/screentimelapse.rb "><pre>brew install --cask https://raw.githubusercontent.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/main/screentimelapse.rb </pre></div>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">Note: once this repo gets <strong>75 stars</strong> and <strong>30 watchers</strong> you will be able to install the app using <code>brew install --cask screentimelapse</code>. Additionally, the application is <strong>not signed</strong> so Apple will give you a scary warning about how the app can not be checked for malware. You can go in system settings to launch it anyways.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Direct Download</h2><a id="user-content-direct-download" aria-label="Permalink: Direct Download" href="#direct-download"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you wish, you can go directly to the <a href="https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/releases">releases page</a> and download <code>TimeLapze.zip</code>. Both Chrome and Safari give a warning about downloading suspicious files. Ignore then, extract the archive and you should get a <code>ScreenTimeLapse.app</code> file. Move that file into your <code>Applications</code> directory.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Local Development</h2><a id="user-content-local-development" aria-label="Permalink: Local Development" href="#local-development"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To develop TimeLapze locally, you will need to clone and open this repository in XCode.</p>
<p dir="auto">Once that's done, you can use the following commands to run the app locally:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse
cd ScreenTimeLapse
open TimeLapze.xcodeproj"><pre><span>git clone https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse</span>
<span>cd ScreenTimeLapse</span>
<span>open TimeLapze.xcodeproj</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Following this, you need to allow the app to be built for local signining.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tech Stack</h2><a id="user-content-tech-stack" aria-label="Permalink: Tech Stack" href="#tech-stack"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/swiftui/" rel="nofollow">SwiftUI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/screencapturekit/" rel="nofollow">ScreenCaptureKit</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developer.apple.com/av-foundation/" rel="nofollow">AVFoundation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developer.apple.com/documentation/coremedia" rel="nofollow">CoreMedia</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We love our contributors! Here's how you can contribute:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/issues">Open an issue</a> if you believe you've encountered a bug.</li>
<li>Make a <a href="https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/pull">pull request</a> to add new features/make quality-of-life improvements/fix bugs.</li>
</ul>
<a href="https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/graphs/contributors">
  <img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/e949d8c23fbfaea17e15a8caa9f5ca902d7ef52a2153b696567e3511214bb180/68747470733a2f2f636f6e747269622e726f636b732f696d6167653f7265706f3d776b616973657274657861732f53637265656e54696d654c61707365" data-canonical-src="https://contrib.rocks/image?repo=wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse">
</a>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Repo Activity</h2><a id="user-content-repo-activity" aria-label="Permalink: Repo Activity" href="#repo-activity"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/143e5f1628f46ce7fdab931b265ee272ff8aa28c37228a74f5d6d7395be90ae8/68747470733a2f2f7265706f62656174732e6178696f6d2e636f2f6170692f656d6265642f336331306638666132636132333234363339623939383663623338303433373530353530633939332e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/143e5f1628f46ce7fdab931b265ee272ff8aa28c37228a74f5d6d7395be90ae8/68747470733a2f2f7265706f62656174732e6178696f6d2e636f2f6170692f656d6265642f336331306638666132636132333234363339623939383663623338303433373530353530633939332e737667" alt="Screen Time Lapse Repo Activity" title="Repobeats analytics image" data-canonical-src="https://repobeats.axiom.co/api/embed/3c10f8fa2ca2324639b9986cb38043750550c993.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">ScreenTimeLapse is open-source under the <a href="https://github.com/wkaisertexas/ScreenTimeLapse/LICENSE/LICENSE.md">MIT Liscense</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">If you liked this project, consider giving the repository a star ⭐️! I am trying to get to 75 stars to be added to homebrew</p>
</blockquote>
<section data-footnotes="">
<ol dir="auto">
<li id="user-content-fn-1-9d2f1a5efd409e3c789397e41222d54e">
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://community.adobe.com/t5/premiere-pro-discussions/inaccurate-colors-from-desktop-recording/m-p/12168181">Apple's screen recorder convert's the display's color space</a> from <strong>DCI_P3</strong> to <strong>sRGB</strong>. The error is typically subtle, but makes the tool unsuitable for color sensitive work. Color is difficult and even <a href="https://github.com/iina/iina/issues/3866">HDR video have persistent issues with overexposure in screenshots</a>. <a href="#user-content-fnref-1-9d2f1a5efd409e3c789397e41222d54e" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Motorola's legal terms claim to strip owners of their right to sell their device (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-a</link>
            <guid>39648218</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 00:37:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-a">https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-a</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39648218">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
        <span>            <a href="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app"><img src="https://motorola-global-en-uk.custhelp.com/euf/assets/motorola_v3/assets/icons/icon-home.svg" alt="Icon Home"></a>             <span>&nbsp;</span>        </span>        <div id="tab-container-1"> <h2>There are 4 steps involved in unlocking your device</h2> <ul id="tab-container-1-nav"> <li> <img src="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/euf/assets/images/bootloader/steps-ov.png"> </li> </ul> <div id="tab1"> <h2>READY TO UNLOCK YOUR DEVICE'S BOOTLOADER?</h2> <h3>Let's make sure you know what you're getting into first.</h3> <p>In case you didn't know, Bootloader is a little bit of code that tells your device's operating system how to boot up. Basically, it's what makes your device start up and run the way you're used to.</p> <p>Motorola has done the work to make sure your device has a fully optimized, certified and tested version of Android.</p> <p>Unlocking the bootloader will allow you to customize your device, but keep the following in mind:</p> <ul> <li> <b>Unlocking your bootloader is not for the faint of heart.</b> Unlocking your device and installing your own software might cause the device to stop working, disable important features and functionality, and even make the device unsafe to the point of causing you harm. Neither Motorola, nor your wireless carrier or retailer from whom you purchased the device, will be responsible for such damage, so please do not unlock or load any software unless you know what you are doing. </li> <li> <b>You have only yourself to blame.</b> Once you get the unlock code, your device is no longer covered by the Motorola warranty; in other words, please don't blame us if things go wrong, even if they appear unrelated to unlocking the bootloader. </li> <li> <b>The law still applies.</b> You still need to operate your device in compliance with all applicable laws, rules and regulations prescribed by the FCC, and any other governmental agency for that matter. </li> <li> <b>And now a word from our lawyers.</b> Finally, in order to unlock your device, you need to agree to important <a href="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/89425" target="new"> <u>legal terms</u> </a> , which can be found on the next page. Agreeing creates a binding legal agreement, so be sure to read them carefully. </li> </ul>  <h3>STILL INTERESTED IN UNLOCKING THE BOOTLOADER?</h3> <p> <b>First, confirm that your device can be unlocked</b> </p> <ul> <li>Currently, the Photon Q 4G LTE, DROID RAZR M(Developer Edition), DROID RAZR HD(Developer Edition CDMA-LTE), MOTOROLA RAZR HD (Rest of World -UMTS/LTE), MOTOROLA RAZR HD (Rogers Canada - UMTS/LTE) and MOTOROLA RAZR i are supported by the Bootloader Unlock site.</li> <li>For a complete list of supported devices, see <a href="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/87215" target="new"> <u>What devices are supported by the Bootloader unlock program?</u> </a> </li> </ul> <h3>Review all the warnings and make sure you completely understand the implications</h3> <ul> <li>Once you get the unlock code, your device is no longer covered by the Motorola warranty; in other words, please don't blame us if things go wrong, even if they appear unrelated to unlocking the bootloader.</li> <li>Unlocking your device and installing your own software might cause the device to stop working, disable important features and functionality, and even make the device unsafe to the point of causing you harm. Neither Motorola, nor your wireless carrier or retailer from whom you purchased the device, will be responsible for such damage, so please do not unlock or load any software unless you know what you are doing.</li> <li>You still need to operate your device in compliance with all applicable laws, rules and regulations prescribed by the FCC, and any other governmental agency for that matter.</li> <li>Your wireless carrier may prohibit unlocked devices from operating on their network.</li> <li>Finally, in order to unlock your device, you need to agree to important <a href="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/answers/detail/a_id/89425" target="new"> <u>legal terms</u> </a> located on the next page. This creates a binding legal agreement, so be sure to read them carefully. </li> </ul> <h3>HOW UNLOCKING YOUR BOOTLOADER COULD IMPACT YOUR DEVICE</h3> <ul> <li>You will lose all media and content on your device and will need to reinstall all applications downloaded from Google Play.</li> <li>You will not be able to watch any movies you downloaded.</li> <li>Applications may not work anymore.</li> <li>You may lose encryption support.</li> <li>You may lose some key functions like telephone, radio, and audio playback.</li> <li>You could cause permanent/physical damage to your device.</li> <li>Unlocking your bootloader will not change your device subsidy lock status</li> </ul> <hr> <p> <strong>If you don't understand any of the above risks or warnings, we suggest that you do not continue to unlock your device's bootloader.</strong> </p> <p>If, however, you are ready to accept all the implications of unlocking the bootloader, which includes completely voiding your device's warranty, continue on to receive a bootloader unlock code.</p> <p> <b>Note:</b> You will need to sign in to proceed. </p>  <p><a href="https://en-us.support.motorola.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-b"> PROCEED ANYWAY </a> </p></div> </div>
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla starts shipping $3k Cybertruck tent, looks nothing like what was unveiled (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://electrek.co/2024/03/08/tesla-shipping-cybertruck-tent/</link>
            <guid>39648075</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2024 00:11:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://electrek.co/2024/03/08/tesla-shipping-cybertruck-tent/">https://electrek.co/2024/03/08/tesla-shipping-cybertruck-tent/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39648075">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
	<img width="1600" height="800" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/tesla-cybertruck-meme.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/tesla-cybertruck-meme.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/tesla-cybertruck-meme.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/tesla-cybertruck-meme.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/tesla-cybertruck-meme.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></figure>

<p>Tesla has started shipping its ‘Basecamp’, a $3,000 tent designed for the back of the Cybertruck. It’s a bit of a This disappointment as it looks nothing like what was originally unveiled.</p>



<p>Accessories are big with trucks. Their form factor open up a bunch of interesting possibilities with the bed, but the Cybertruck’s specific design with the angle on the bed makes it more difficult to use some off-the-shelves accessories.</p>



<p>To address that, Tesla has planned a series of accessories designed specifically for the Cybertruck.</p>



<p>One of them is Basecamp, a tent that fits in the back of the electric pickup truck. It was first announced with the original unveiling of the Cybertruck in 2019:</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1144" height="583" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1024" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg 1144w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?resize=150,76 150w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?resize=300,153 300w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?resize=768,391 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?resize=1024,522 1024w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?resize=350,178 350w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2020/02/Tesla-Cybertruck-camper-1-e1574434915159.jpg?resize=140,71 140w" sizes="(max-width: 1144px) 100vw, 1144px"></figure>



<p>This looked like an interesting design with seemingly a rigid  bottom half that matched the design of the truck.</p>



<p>The product became ‘Basecamp’ and was <a href="https://electrek.co/2023/11/30/teslas-cybertruck-basecamp-is-a-funky-2975-tent-attachment/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">released for sale</a> shortly after Tesla revealed the production version of the truck last year. It already seemed to be a lot less attractive design at that point:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="2000" height="2000" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?w=1024" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp 2000w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=150,150 150w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=300,300 300w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=768,768 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=1024,1024 1024w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=1536,1536 1536w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=350,350 350w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=140,140 140w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=1000,1000 1000w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=500,500 500w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/a3w20-cbfas.webp?resize=96,96 96w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px"></figure>



<p>Now, Tesla has started shipping, or rather installing, the Basecamp for early Cybertruck owners.</p>



<p>I say “installing” because you need your first installation to happen at a Tesla Service Center to attach the tent’s brakets, which support the base of the tent, to the Cybertruck’s vault side rails.</p>



<p>A Cybertruck owner going by ‘TownBiz’ on <a href="https://www.cybertruckownersclub.com/forum/threads/basecamp-tent-first-review-%E2%9B%BA%EF%B8%8E.12964/">Cybertruck Owners Club</a> received one of the very first Basecamp and gave a first impression review of the tent system:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>‘Although Tesla is requiring SCs to do the initial install, in reality both install and removal of the tent from the bed (aka “vault”) is straightforward as long as you can deadlift 90lbs and/or have a buddy to help lift. Basecamp comes with 6 brackets that attach to the vault’s side rails and have specific spacing. Attaching these brackets is simple: same as how you attach your bottle opener or tie down points that come with Foundation Series trucks. Assuming Tesla is requiring the SC to do it just because of potential liability issues w/ people not putting the brackets in the right positions. That said, the manual provides install instructions for anyone to put these brackets in, so I suspect that one day Tesla may direct ship to customers. The trickiest parts of initial install are setting the stowed Basecamp in the right slot (need to put it in at a slight angle closest to the bed of the truck) and aligning the two T25 bolts that secure Basecamp’s frame to the truck. The manual recommends using a flashlight so you can align the holes and that really does make it pretty easy. Unfortunately the SC installer had some difficulty with this initially and scratched one of my brackets and may have also slightly messed up the threading on that bracket because it’s a little loose – not a show stopper, and theoretically a replaceable part. Once you remove those two T25 bolts, you can take the zipped up Basecamp with frame out of the truck and store it at home. This is welcome news because it definitely cuts into the length of your bed/vault (a bit more than 1/3 closest to the cab of the truck) if you like to transport adult sized mountain bikes using a tailgate pad. Otherwise, as mentioned the design is great because you can store gear under the stowed Basecamp.’</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Here’s what the production version of the Basecamp looks like on the Cybertruck:</p>



<figure>
<figure data-wp-context="{ &quot;core&quot;:
				{ &quot;image&quot;:
					{   &quot;imageLoaded&quot;: false,
						&quot;initialized&quot;: false,
						&quot;lightboxEnabled&quot;: false,
						&quot;hideAnimationEnabled&quot;: false,
						&quot;preloadInitialized&quot;: false,
						&quot;lightboxAnimation&quot;: &quot;zoom&quot;,
						&quot;imageUploadedSrc&quot;: &quot;https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&quot;,
						&quot;imageCurrentSrc&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
						&quot;targetWidth&quot;: &quot;2250&quot;,
						&quot;targetHeight&quot;: &quot;3000&quot;,
						&quot;scaleAttr&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
						&quot;dialogLabel&quot;: &quot;Enlarged image&quot;
					}
				}
			}" data-wp-interactive=""><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="2250" height="3000" data-wp-effect--setstylesonresize="effects.core.image.setStylesOnResize" data-wp-effect="effects.core.image.setButtonStyles" data-wp-init="effects.core.image.initOriginImage" data-wp-on--click="actions.core.image.showLightbox" data-wp-on--load="actions.core.image.handleLoad" data-id="353229" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=768" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg 2250w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=113,150 113w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=225,300 225w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=768,1024 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=1152,1536 1152w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=1536,2048 1536w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=263,350 263w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=140,187 140w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=750,1000 750w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=640,853 640w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6086.jpeg?resize=150,200 150w" sizes="(max-width: 2250px) 100vw, 2250px">        <div data-wp-body="" data-wp-bind--role="selectors.core.image.roleAttribute" data-wp-bind--aria-label="selectors.core.image.dialogLabel" data-wp-class--initialized="context.core.image.initialized" data-wp-class--active="context.core.image.lightboxEnabled" data-wp-class--hideanimationenabled="context.core.image.hideAnimationEnabled" data-wp-bind--aria-modal="selectors.core.image.ariaModal" data-wp-effect="effects.core.image.initLightbox" data-wp-on--keydown="actions.core.image.handleKeydown" data-wp-on--touchstart="actions.core.image.handleTouchStart" data-wp-on--touchmove="actions.core.image.handleTouchMove" data-wp-on--touchend="actions.core.image.handleTouchEnd" data-wp-on--click="actions.core.image.hideLightbox" tabindex="-1">
                <div>
<figure><img decoding="async" data-wp-bind--src="context.core.image.imageCurrentSrc" data-wp-style--object-fit="selectors.core.image.lightboxObjectFit" data-id="353229" src="" alt=""></figure>
</div>
                <div>
<figure><img decoding="async" data-wp-bind--src="selectors.core.image.enlargedImgSrc" data-wp-style--object-fit="selectors.core.image.lightboxObjectFit" data-id="353229" src="" alt=""></figure>
</div>
                
        </div></figure>



<figure data-wp-context="{ &quot;core&quot;:
				{ &quot;image&quot;:
					{   &quot;imageLoaded&quot;: false,
						&quot;initialized&quot;: false,
						&quot;lightboxEnabled&quot;: false,
						&quot;hideAnimationEnabled&quot;: false,
						&quot;preloadInitialized&quot;: false,
						&quot;lightboxAnimation&quot;: &quot;zoom&quot;,
						&quot;imageUploadedSrc&quot;: &quot;https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&quot;,
						&quot;imageCurrentSrc&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
						&quot;targetWidth&quot;: &quot;3000&quot;,
						&quot;targetHeight&quot;: &quot;2250&quot;,
						&quot;scaleAttr&quot;: &quot;&quot;,
						&quot;dialogLabel&quot;: &quot;Enlarged image&quot;
					}
				}
			}" data-wp-interactive=""><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="3000" height="2250" data-wp-effect--setstylesonresize="effects.core.image.setStylesOnResize" data-wp-effect="effects.core.image.setButtonStyles" data-wp-init="effects.core.image.initOriginImage" data-wp-on--click="actions.core.image.showLightbox" data-wp-on--load="actions.core.image.handleLoad" data-id="353230" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1024" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg 3000w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=150,113 150w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=300,225 300w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=768,576 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=1024,768 1024w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=1536,1152 1536w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=2048,1536 2048w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=350,263 350w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=140,105 140w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6090.jpeg?resize=1333,1000 1333w" sizes="(max-width: 3000px) 100vw, 3000px">        <div data-wp-body="" data-wp-bind--role="selectors.core.image.roleAttribute" data-wp-bind--aria-label="selectors.core.image.dialogLabel" data-wp-class--initialized="context.core.image.initialized" data-wp-class--active="context.core.image.lightboxEnabled" data-wp-class--hideanimationenabled="context.core.image.hideAnimationEnabled" data-wp-bind--aria-modal="selectors.core.image.ariaModal" data-wp-effect="effects.core.image.initLightbox" data-wp-on--keydown="actions.core.image.handleKeydown" data-wp-on--touchstart="actions.core.image.handleTouchStart" data-wp-on--touchmove="actions.core.image.handleTouchMove" data-wp-on--touchend="actions.core.image.handleTouchEnd" data-wp-on--click="actions.core.image.hideLightbox" tabindex="-1">
                <div>
<figure><img decoding="async" data-wp-bind--src="context.core.image.imageCurrentSrc" data-wp-style--object-fit="selectors.core.image.lightboxObjectFit" data-id="353230" src="" alt=""></figure>
</div>
                <div>
<figure><img decoding="async" data-wp-bind--src="selectors.core.image.enlargedImgSrc" data-wp-style--object-fit="selectors.core.image.lightboxObjectFit" data-id="353230" src="" alt=""></figure>
</div>
                
        </div></figure>
</figure>



<p>Obviously, it looks nothing like the original render and arguably, it doesn’t look as good. To be fair, it should look better with the awning out, but they haven’t installed it in this case.</p>



<p>Here’s the inside:</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="2250" height="3000" src="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=768" alt="" srcset="https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg 2250w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=113,150 113w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=225,300 225w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=768,1024 768w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=1152,1536 1152w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=1536,2048 1536w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=263,350 263w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=140,187 140w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=750,1000 750w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=640,853 640w, https://electrek.co/wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2024/03/IMG_6092.jpeg?resize=150,200 150w" sizes="(max-width: 2250px) 100vw, 2250px"></figure>



<p>The owner has noted a few issues with the installation, packing, and unpacking process. He is not sure if he can recommend it for $3,000:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Because the rainy weather hasn’t allowed me to do a full setup + takedown more than once, I still can’t definitively say whether or not I recommend the $3K Basecamp. On one hand, I think that much of the thoughtful and unique design elements might warrant the cost: it’s fairly lightweight + easy to install/remove the stowed tent from the truck, stays out of the way (unless you want to transport multiple bikes in the bed), doesn’t reduce range due to decreased aerodynamics, and has intuitive pieces that make setup + takedown a breeze. On the other hand, there are some unpolished areas that stick out because of all those great elements I mentioned already: removing + re-installing the “Aeroflap” and the frustration of fitting and zipping up the stowed Basecamp in softcover after you finish using the tent. The three minor damaged pieces (the scuffed + potentially thread damaged middle bracket where a T25 bolt secures the stowed Basecamp to the bed rail, one of the leg quick release buttons, and the nylon webbing for one of the cobra buckle retainers) that I mentioned might have been better designed and will need to be fixed too, but because they don’t impede the function of the tent they’re not show stoppers. The currently MIA “Tent Mode” is also a bit of a red flag because the rumoured self-levelling element is a pretty big deal for roof-top-tent camping – briefly laying on the sleeping mat while parked in my gently sloped driveway I could feel myself rolling downhill. If Tesla releases Tent Mode to all CT owners or only verified Basecamp owners may be a deciding factor for people buying the Basecamp or waiting for a 3rd party solution (theoretically if a maker creates cross bars for the vault, other folding rooftop tents that are not wider than the vault/bed could work nicely). $3K is a serious chunk of change and you could buy a lot of sweet camping gear with it. However, as I mentioned at the start, evidently $3K for a high quality rooftop tent is not that crazy.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>The ‘Tent Mode’ is expected to enable an auto leveling of the truck with its air suspension, but the software is nowhere to be found in Cybertrucks right now.</p>



<p>There’s unfortunately no way to link the truck’s AC to the tent with this system.</p>



<h2 id="h-electrek-s-take">Electrek’s Take</h2>




	<p>In my opinion, this is definitely a disapointment for the price and in comparison to the original renders. </p>



<p>$3,000 is no joke. You can get some awesome tents for that price.</p>



<p>Sounds like you would be better off with an off-truck tent or maybe an off-the-shevel roof tent if you can have some kind of cross bar accessory to make the Cybertruck’s roof flat and able to receive the tent.</p>



<p>What do you think? Let us know in the comment section below.</p>
	<p>
		<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBwgKMKqD-Qow6c_gAg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add Electrek to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
	</p>
	<p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://electrek.co/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A simple dice game shines a bit of light on the psychology of regret (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/how-fear-of-regret-influences-our-decisions/</link>
            <guid>39647681</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 23:13:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/how-fear-of-regret-influences-our-decisions/">https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/how-fear-of-regret-influences-our-decisions/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39647681">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="container"><article><p>A simple dice game shines a bit of light on the psychology of regret.</p><figure><img width="700" height="420" src="https://thereader.mitpress.mit.edu/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/regret-700x420.jpg" alt="" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></figure><p>One of the primary motivators of human behavior is avoiding regret. Before the legendary behavioral economists Daniel Kahneman and Amos Tversky formalized prospect theory and loss aversion, they believed that regret avoidance was at the root of the human behaviors they were studying. However, they learned that there are behaviors that regret avoidance could not explain and were led to a broader picture.</p><p>Let’s take a look at a simple game that sheds a bit more light on the psychology of regret.</p><p>I have two dice — one red, one white — and two identical cups. I secretly place one die under each cup (no trickery), mix them up, and ask you to select the cup with the red die. You did not see me put the dice under the cups, so you have absolutely no information on which to base your decision. If you make the right choice, I give you $5. If not, you gain nothing.</p><p>Go ahead and select one of the cups. Let’s say you pick the cup on the right. I slide it toward you but don’t let you look underneath.</p><p>I then ask you if you want to switch to the cup on the left, to change your choice.</p><p>Would you switch? The majority of people do not; about 90 percent do not switch, <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF01019932" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">according to studies</a>. Personally, I do this experiment with my class and at other presentations, and I have yet to have someone switch when offered the opportunity.</p><p>Why is that? The odds of being right are 50-50, so why not switch?</p><p>Experimenters point to two reasons. First is the endowment effect, which posits that once you perceive ownership of an item, it subtly becomes yours — and it becomes more valuable to you than an equivalent item you do not own. Once you select a cup, it subtly becomes yours — and it becomes more valuable to you than the other cup. Moving the cup so that it is in front of you amplifies this effect, as the cup is moved into your personal space.</p><p>The second reason is that, psychologically, one of the drivers of our actions is our effort to minimize regret. If we make a choice and it turns out to be wrong, we feel bad. But what if we make a choice, switch, and then find out our first decision was actually correct? We feel worse. We know this about ourselves, and so, when presented with the option to switch away from our cup, it is not very enticing to do so.</p><p>We can explore exactly how much worse we feel if we switch and are wrong through a simple experiment.</p><p>In our game, if you pick the cup that has the red die, you win $5. Now let’s say I change the rules slightly. After you’ve made your cup choice, I give you the option of switching to the other cup as usual. But now, if you switch and are correct, you win $6. If you stick with your original choice and are right, you still only get $5. Would you switch now?</p><p>Again, most people would not switch.</p><p>What if I offered you $10 if you switch and win? What about $15?</p><p>Researchers have performed these experiments, and the results are illuminating. At triple the value, 50 percent of people switch. You need to get to 10 times the value before 90 percent of people switch.</p><p>Experiments like this, by the way, are one of the methods that researchers use to figure out how much worse loss aversion makes things feel. This puts it at around three times as bad, which is in line with the two to three times values seen in other experiments.</p><p>When I was in school and taking multiple choice exams, the advice was always to “stick with your first instinct” rather than to change to a different answer. I am now convinced that this advice does not give you a better chance at getting the correct answer — but it does make people feel better than if they get it wrong and find out their original choice was correct. I would much prefer getting it wrong with my first guess than changing away from the right answer!</p><hr><p><em><strong>Geoffrey Engelstein</strong> is an award-winning tabletop game designer who teaches game design at New York University. He is the author of several books including “<a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/9780262043533/achievement-relocked/" target="_blank">Achievement Relocked</a>,” from which this article is excerpted.</em></p></article><div><p><strong>The MIT Press</strong> is a mission-driven, not-for-profit scholarly publisher. Your support helps make it possible for us to create open publishing models and produce books of superior design quality.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tests show high-temperature superconducting magnets are ready for fusion (211 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.mit.edu/2024/tests-show-high-temperature-superconducting-magnets-fusion-ready-0304</link>
            <guid>39647331</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 22:35:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.mit.edu/2024/tests-show-high-temperature-superconducting-magnets-fusion-ready-0304">https://news.mit.edu/2024/tests-show-high-temperature-superconducting-magnets-fusion-ready-0304</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39647331">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
          

            <p>In the predawn hours of Sept. 5, 2021, engineers achieved a major milestone in the labs of MIT’s Plasma Science and Fusion Center (PSFC), when a new type of magnet, made from high-temperature superconducting material, achieved a world-record magnetic field strength of 20 tesla for a large-scale magnet. That’s the intensity needed to build a fusion power plant that is expected to produce a net output of power and potentially usher in an era of virtually limitless power production.</p>



<p>The test was immediately declared a success, having met all the criteria established for the design of the new fusion device, dubbed SPARC, for which the magnets are the key enabling technology. Champagne corks popped as the weary team of experimenters, who had labored long and hard to make the achievement possible, celebrated their accomplishment.</p>



<p>But that was far from the end of the process. Over the ensuing months, the team tore apart and inspected the components of the magnet, pored over and analyzed the data from hundreds of instruments that recorded details of the tests, and performed two additional test runs on the same magnet, ultimately pushing it to its breaking point in order to learn the details of any possible failure modes.</p>



<p>All of this work has now culminated in a detailed report by researchers at PSFC and MIT spinout company Commonwealth Fusion Systems (CFS), published in a <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/tocresult.jsp?isnumber=10348035&amp;punumber=77" target="_blank">collection of six peer-reviewed papers</a> in a special edition of the March issue of <em>IEEE Transactions on Applied Superconductivity</em>. Together, the papers describe the design and fabrication of the magnet and the diagnostic equipment needed to evaluate its performance, as well as the lessons learned from the process. Overall, the team found, the predictions and computer modeling were spot-on, verifying that the magnet’s unique design elements could serve as the foundation for a fusion power plant.</p>



<p><strong>Enabling practical fusion power</strong></p>



<p>The successful test of the magnet, says Hitachi America Professor of Engineering Dennis Whyte, who recently stepped down as director of the PSFC, was “the most important thing, in my opinion, in the last 30 years of fusion research.”</p>



<p>Before the Sept. 5 demonstration, the best-available superconducting magnets were powerful enough to potentially achieve fusion energy — but only at sizes and costs that could never be practical or economically viable. Then, when the tests showed the practicality of such a strong magnet at a greatly reduced size, “overnight, it basically changed the cost per watt of a fusion reactor by a factor of almost 40 in one day,” Whyte says.</p>



<p>“Now fusion has a chance,” Whyte adds. Tokamaks, the most widely used design for experimental fusion devices, “have a chance, in my opinion, of being economical because you’ve got a quantum change in your ability, with the known confinement physics rules, about being able to greatly reduce the size and the cost of objects that would make fusion possible.”</p>



<p>The comprehensive data and analysis from the PSFC’s magnet test, as detailed in the six new papers, has demonstrated that plans for a new generation of fusion devices — the one designed by MIT and CFS, as well as similar designs by other commercial fusion companies — are built on a solid foundation in science.</p>



<p><strong>The superconducting breakthrough</strong></p>



<p>Fusion, the process of combining light atoms to form heavier ones, powers the sun and stars, but harnessing that process on Earth has proved to be a daunting challenge, with decades of hard work and many billions of dollars spent on experimental devices. The long-sought, but never yet achieved, goal is to build a fusion power plant that produces more energy than it consumes. Such a power plant could produce electricity without emitting greenhouse gases during operation, and generating very little radioactive waste. Fusion’s fuel, a form of hydrogen that can be derived from seawater, is virtually limitless.</p>



<p>But to make it work requires compressing the fuel at extraordinarily high temperatures and pressures, and since no known material could withstand such temperatures, the fuel must be held in place by extremely powerful magnetic fields. Producing such strong fields requires superconducting magnets, but all previous fusion magnets have been made with a superconducting material that requires frigid temperatures of about 4 degrees above absolute zero (4 kelvins, or -270 degrees Celsius). In the last few years, a newer material nicknamed REBCO, for rare-earth barium copper oxide, was added to fusion magnets, and allows them to operate at 20 kelvins, a temperature that despite being only 16 kelvins warmer, brings significant advantages in terms of material properties and practical engineering.</p>



<p>Taking advantage of this new higher-temperature superconducting material was not just a matter of substituting it in existing magnet designs. Instead, “it was a rework from the ground up of almost all the principles that you use to build superconducting magnets,” Whyte says. The new REBCO material is “extraordinarily different than the previous generation of superconductors. You’re not just going to adapt and replace, you’re actually going to innovate from the ground up.” The new papers in <em>Transactions on Applied Superconductivity</em> describe the details of that redesign process, now that patent protection is in place.</p>



<p><strong>A key innovation: no insulation</strong></p>



<p>One of the dramatic innovations, which had many others in the field skeptical of its chances of success, was the elimination of insulation around the thin, flat ribbons of superconducting tape that formed the magnet. Like virtually all electrical wires, conventional superconducting magnets are fully protected by insulating material to prevent short-circuits between the wires. But in the new magnet, the tape was left completely bare; the engineers relied on REBCO’s much greater conductivity to keep the current flowing through the material.</p>



<p>“When we started this project, in let’s say 2018, the technology of using high-temperature superconductors to build large-scale high-field magnets was in its infancy,” says Zach Hartwig, the Robert N. Noyce Career Development Professor in the Department of Nuclear Science and Engineering. Hartwig has a co-appointment at the PSFC and is the head of its engineering group, which led the magnet development project. “The state of the art was small benchtop experiments, not really representative of what it takes to build a full-size thing. Our magnet development project started at benchtop scale and ended up at full scale in a short amount of time,” he adds, noting that the team built a 20,000-pound magnet that produced a steady, even magnetic field of just over 20 tesla — far beyond any such field ever produced at large scale.</p>



<p>“The standard way to build these magnets is you would wind the conductor and you have insulation between the windings, and you need insulation to deal with the high voltages that are generated during off-normal events such as a shutdown.” Eliminating the layers of insulation, he says, “has the advantage of being a low-voltage system. It greatly simplifies the fabrication processes and schedule.” It also leaves more room for other elements, such as more cooling or more structure for strength.</p>



<p>The magnet assembly is a slightly smaller-scale version of the ones that will form the donut-shaped chamber of the SPARC fusion device now being built by CFS in Devens, Massachusetts. It consists of 16 plates, called pancakes, each bearing a spiral winding of the superconducting tape on one side and cooling channels for helium gas on the other.</p>



<p>But the no-insulation design was considered risky, and a lot was riding on the test program. “This was the first magnet at any sufficient scale that really probed what is involved in designing and building and testing a magnet with this so-called no-insulation no-twist technology,” Hartwig says. “It was very much a surprise to the community when we announced that it was a no-insulation coil.”</p>



<p><strong>Pushing to the limit … and beyond</strong></p>



<p>The initial test, described in previous papers, proved that the design and manufacturing process not only worked but was highly stable — something that some researchers had doubted. The next two test runs, also performed in late 2021, then pushed the device to the limit by deliberately creating unstable conditions, including a complete shutoff of incoming power that can lead to a catastrophic overheating. Known as quenching, this is considered a worst-case scenario for the operation of such magnets, with the potential to destroy the equipment.</p>



<p>Part of the mission of the test program, Hartwig says, was “to actually go off and intentionally quench a full-scale magnet, so that we can get the critical data at the right scale and the right conditions to advance the science, to validate the design codes, and then to take the magnet apart and see what went wrong, why did it go wrong, and how do we take the next iteration toward fixing that. … It was a very successful test.”</p>



<p>That final test, which ended with the melting of one corner of one of the 16 pancakes, produced a wealth of new information, Hartwig says. For one thing, they had been using several different computational models to design and predict the performance of various aspects of the magnet’s performance, and for the most part, the models agreed in their overall predictions and were well-validated by the series of tests and real-world measurements. But in predicting the effect of the quench, the model predictions diverged, so it was necessary to get the experimental data to evaluate the models’ validity.</p>



<p>“The highest-fidelity models that we had predicted almost exactly how the magnet would warm up, to what degree it would warm up as it started to quench, and where would the resulting damage to the magnet would be,” he says. As described in detail in one of the new reports, “That test actually told us exactly the physics that was going on, and it told us which models were useful going forward and which to leave by the wayside because they’re not right.”</p>



<p>Whyte says, “Basically we did the worst thing possible to a coil, on purpose, after we had tested all other aspects of the coil performance. And we found that most of the coil survived with no damage,” while one isolated area sustained some melting. “It’s like a few percent of the volume of the coil that got damaged.” And that led to revisions in the design that are expected to prevent such damage in the actual fusion device magnets, even under the most extreme conditions.</p>



<p>Hartwig emphasizes that a major reason the team was able to accomplish such a radical new record-setting magnet design, and get it right the very first time and on a breakneck schedule, was thanks to the deep level of knowledge, expertise, and equipment accumulated over decades of operation of the Alcator C-Mod tokamak, the Francis Bitter Magnet Laboratory, and other work carried out at PSFC. “This goes to the heart of the institutional capabilities of a place like this,” he says. “We had the capability, the infrastructure, and the space and the people to do these things under one roof.”</p>



<p>The collaboration with CFS was also key, he says, with MIT and CFS combining the most powerful aspects of an academic institution and private company to do things together that neither could have done on their own. “For example, one of the major contributions from CFS was leveraging the power of a private company to establish and scale up a supply chain at an unprecedented level and timeline for the most critical material in the project: 300 kilometers (186 miles) of high-temperature superconductor, which was procured with rigorous quality control in under a year, and integrated on schedule into the magnet.”</p>



<p>The integration of the two teams, those from MIT and those from CFS, also was crucial to the success, he says. “We thought of ourselves as one team, and that made it possible to do what we did.”</p>        

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI board reappoints Altman and adds three other directors (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/technology/sam-altman-return-openais-board-information-reports-2024-03-08/</link>
            <guid>39647105</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 22:07:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/sam-altman-return-openais-board-information-reports-2024-03-08/">https://www.reuters.com/technology/sam-altman-return-openais-board-information-reports-2024-03-08/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39647105">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/technology/sam-altman-return-openais-board-information-reports-2024-03-08/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New York Times is targeting Wordle clones with DMCA takedowns (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2024/3/8/24094234/ny-times-wordle-clones-files-dmca-copyright-takedowns-knockoffs</link>
            <guid>39645991</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 20:28:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/3/8/24094234/ny-times-wordle-clones-files-dmca-copyright-takedowns-knockoffs">https://www.theverge.com/2024/3/8/24094234/ny-times-wordle-clones-files-dmca-copyright-takedowns-knockoffs</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39645991">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Hundreds of games inspired by <em>Wordle</em>, the popular web-based word puzzle, are at risk of being deleted due to copyright takedowns issued by <em>The New York Times</em>. <a href="https://www.404media.co/nytimes-files-copyright-takedowns-against-hundreds-of-wordle-clones/">As reported by<em> 404 Media</em></a>, <em>The</em> <em>New York Times</em> — which purchased <em>Wordle</em> back in 2022 — has filed several DMCA notices over <em>Wordle</em> clones created by GitHub coders, citing its ownership over the <em>Wordle</em> name and copyrighted gameplay including 5x6 tile layout and gray, yellow, and green color scheme.</p><p>Two takedown requests were issued in January against <a href="https://github.com/github/dmca/blob/fdeb00c4425e23c3a8115c297bc54d44151c4289/2024/01/2024-01-24-nytimes-2.md?ref=404media.co">unofficial Korean</a> and <a href="https://github.com/github/dmca/blob/fdeb00c4425e23c3a8115c297bc54d44151c4289/2024/01/2024-01-24-nytimes.md?ref=404media.co">Bosnian-language</a> versions of the game. Additional requests were filed this week against <a href="https://www.shetnews.co.uk/2024/03/07/shetland-dialect-version-wordle-taken/"><em>Wirdle</em></a> — a variant created by dialect group I Hear Dee in 2022 to promote the Shaetlan language — and <em>Reactle</em>, an open-source <em>Wordle</em> clone built using React, TypeScript, and Tailwind. It was developed prior to the <em>Times’</em> purchase of the game, according to its developer, Chase Wackerfuss.</p><p>The <em>Reactle</em> code has been copied around 1,900 times, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20240306172335/https://github.com/cwackerfuss/reactle">according to GitHub</a>, allowing developers to build upon it to create a wide variety of <em>Wordle</em>-inspired games that use different languages, themes, and visual styles, some of which <em>404 Media</em> says are “substantially different” from <em>Wordle</em>. The DMCA notice against <em>Reactle</em> also targets all of these games forked from the original <em>Reactle</em> code on GitHub, alleging that spinoffs containing the <em>Wordle</em> name have been made in “bad faith” and that “gameplay is copied exactly” in the <em>Reactle</em> repository. Numerous developers commenting on a <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39618193">Hacker News thread</a> also claim to have been targeted with DMCA takedowns.</p><p><em>Reactle</em> coder Wackerfuss has removed the game, telling <em>404 Media</em> he doesn’t want to get into a legal battle with the<em> Times</em>.</p><p>In a statement to <em>404 Media</em>, the <em>Times</em> said: </p><div><blockquote><p>The Times has no issue with individuals creating similar word games that do not infringe The Times’s “Wordle” trademarks or copyrighted gameplay. The Times took action against a GitHub user and others who shared his code to defend its intellectual property rights in Wordle. The user created a “Wordle clone” project that instructed others how to create a knock-off version of The Times’s Wordle game featuring many of the same copyrighted elements. As a result, hundreds of websites began popping up with knock-off “Wordle” games that used The Times’s “Wordle” trademark and copyrighted gameplay without authorization or permission.</p></blockquote></div><p>Amusingly, <em>Wordle</em> has itself <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/02/24/wordle-kind-of-rips-off-lingo-a-copyright-lawyer-says-thats-ok.html">been criticized over striking similarities</a> it shares with <em>Lingo</em>, a 1980s game show that centered on players guessing five-letter words, with a grid that changes color based on accuracy. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google fires employee who protested Israel tech event as internal dissent mounts (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/08/google-fires-employee-who-protested-israel-tech-event-shuts-forum.html</link>
            <guid>39644379</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 18:38:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/08/google-fires-employee-who-protested-israel-tech-event-shuts-forum.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/08/google-fires-employee-who-protested-israel-tech-event-shuts-forum.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39644379">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="RegularArticle-ArticleBody-5" data-module="ArticleBody" data-test="articleBody-2" data-analytics="RegularArticle-articleBody-5-2"><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107385013" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000333853" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107385013"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107385014-17099255371709925534-33635747678-1080pnbcnews.jpg?v=1709925536&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="Google fires employee who protested Israel tech event, as internal dissent mounts"><span></span><span></span></p></div><div><p>During a keynote speech in New York on Monday from the managing director of <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-1"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/GOOGL/">Google's</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> Israel business, an employee in the company's cloud division<a href="https://twitter.com/car0linehaskins/status/1764681078206337434" target="_blank"> protested publicly</a>, proclaiming “I refuse to build technology that powers genocide.”</p><p>The Google Cloud engineer was subsequently fired, CNBC has learned, marking another dark moment for Google, which has been thrust into an escalating number of political and cultural conflicts in recent years and has struggled to quell employee dissent.</p><p>There was more internal controversy this week, also tied to the crisis in Gaza.</p><p>Ahead of an International Women's Day Summit in Silicon Valley on Thursday, Google's employee message board was hit with an influx of staffer comments about the company's military contracts with Israel. The online forum, which was going to be used to help inform what questions were asked of executives at the event, was shut down for what a spokesperson described to CNBC as "divisive content that is disruptive to our workplace."</p><p>Google's role as a provider of technology to militaries in the U.S. and abroad has been a source of workforce consternation since at least 2018, when employees protested a Defense Department contract called <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2018/06/01/google-will-not-renew-a-controversial-pentagon-contract.html">Project Maven</a>. Then came controversy surrounding <a href="https://www.axios.com/local/san-francisco/2023/08/29/tech-workers-protest-project-nimbus-google-cloud-next-conference" target="_blank">Project Nimbus</a>, a $1.2 billion artificial intelligence and computing services agreement among Google, <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-5"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/AMZN/">Amazon</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> Web Services and the Israeli government and military that began in 2021.</p><p>That outrage has spread to a host of other issues, often leaving <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/sundar-pichai/">CEO Sundar Pichai</a> on the <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/02/28/google-ceo-tells-employees-gemini-ai-blunder-unacceptable.html">defensive</a> when confronted by employees at company events.</p><p>The escalation of the Middle East conflict over the past five months has increased the tension level at Google even further. In October, <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/israel-says-palestinian-militants-are-infiltrating-gaza-rcna119315" target="_blank">Hamas launched multipronged and deadly attacks on Israel</a>, leading to a military <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/israel-hamas-war-children-starving-famine-warning-death-destruction-rcna141813" target="_blank">response</a> that's killed at least 30,000 Palestinians<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/world/israel-hamas-war-children-starving-famine-warning-death-destruction-rcna141813" target="_blank">,</a> with many more injured and facing starvation, according to the Palestinian enclave's Health Ministry.</p></div><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107381661" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000333227" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107381661"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107381750-1709562575860-1709555468-33577730976-hd.jpg?v=1709562579&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="Pressure needed on both Israel and Hamas to reach a cease-fire, analyst says"><span></span><span></span></p></div><div><p>In recent weeks, more than 600 Google workers signed a letter addressed to leadership asking that the company drop its sponsorship of the annual Mind the Tech conference promoting the Israeli tech industry. The event on Monday in New York featured an address from Barak Regev, managing director of Google Israel.</p><p>A <a href="https://x.com/car0linehaskins/status/1764688258238157160?s=20" target="_blank">video</a> of the employee protesting during the speech went viral.</p><p>“No cloud for apartheid,” the employee yelled. Members of the crowd booed him as he was escorted by security out of the building.</p><p>Regev then told the crowd, “Part of the privilege of working in a company, which represents democratic values is giving the stage for different opinions."</p><p>A Google spokesperson said the employee was fired for "interfering with an official company-sponsored event" in an email to CNBC on Thursday. "This behavior is not okay, regardless of the issue, and the employee was terminated for violating our policies." The spokesperson didn't specify which policies were violated.</p></div><h2><a id="headline0"></a>More questions about Gemini</h2><div><p>Google is far from alone among U.S. companies in facing increased pressure since the latest war broke out between Hamas and Israel.</p><p>In October, <span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-12"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/SBUX/">Starbucks</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> sued Workers United, which has organized employees in 400 U.S. stores, over a pro-Palestinian message posted on a union social media account. Starbucks said it was trying to get the union to stop using its name and likeness, as the post also <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/03/05/mideast-starbucks-franchisee-firing-2000-workers-after-being-targeted-in-israel-hamas-war-boycott-.html">drew protests</a> from pro-Israel demonstrators. Boycotters said the company wasn’t adequately supporting Palestinians in the Gaza Strip.</p><p><span data-test="QuoteInBody" id="RegularArticle-QuoteInBody-14"><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/quotes/MCD/">McDonald's</a><span><span id="-WatchlistDropdown" data-analytics-id="-WatchlistDropdown"></span></span></span> has been the subject of a <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/02/05/mcdonalds-and-starbucks-blame-israel-hamas-war-for-slower-sales.html">boycott</a> effort after a local franchisee in Israel announced in October that it was providing free meals to Israeli soldiers.&nbsp;</p><p>Ahead of Google's International Women's Day summit on Thursday, called Her Power, Her Voice, some women filled the company's internal discussion forum Dory with questions about how the Israeli military contract and Google's AI chatbot Gemini are impacting Palestinian women. Some of the comments had hundreds of "upvotes" from employees, according to internal correspondence viewed by CNBC.</p><p>One employee asked about Gemini's bias. Specifically, the person wrote that when asking Gemini, "Do women in Gaza deserve human rights?" the chatbot didn't have a response and directed the user to try Google search. But when the employee asked the same question of women in France, Gemini answered "Absolutely," followed by multiple bullet points backing up the assertion.</p><p>CNBC replicated the search Thursday afternoon and found the same results. Late last month, Google <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/02/22/google-pauses-gemini-ai-image-generator-after-inaccuracies.html">paused</a> its Gemini image generation tool after saying it offers "inaccuracies" in historical pictures, in response to a barrage of user complaints.</p><p>Another highly-rated comment on the forum asked how the company is recognizing Mai Ubeid, a young woman and former Google software engineer who was <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/dec/01/google-intern-gaza-israel-military-contract-project-nimbus" target="_blank">reportedly killed</a> in an Israeli airstrike in Gaza along with her family late last year. (Some employees and advocacy groups <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2023/dec/01/google-intern-gaza-israel-military-contract-project-nimbus" target="_blank">gathered</a> to honor Ubeid in New York in December.)</p><p>One employee asked, "Given the ongoing International War Crimes against Palestinian women, how can we use the 'Her Power, Her Voice' theme to amplify their daily struggles?" The comment received over 100 upvotes.</p><p>"It's essential to question how we can truly support the notion of 'Her Power, Her Voice,' while at the same time, ignoring the cries for help from Palestinian women who have been systematically deprived of their fundamental human rights," another said.</p><p>As the number of comments swelled, Google prematurely shut down the forum.</p><p>Google's spokesperson didn't address any of the individual posts but provided the following statement to CNBC:</p><p>"We were pleased to host an event to celebrate International Women's Day. Unfortunately, before the event a series of off-topic and divisive questions and comments were posted to internal forums. Our internal community guidelines team routinely removes divisive content that is disruptive to our workplace, and did that here."</p><p><strong>WATCH:</strong> <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/video/2024/03/01/google-vs-google-the-internal-struggle-holding-back-its-ai.html">Google vs. Google</a></p></div><div id="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107381338" data-test="VideoPlaceHolder" role="region" tabindex="0" data-vilynx-id="7000333177" aria-labelledby="Placeholder-ArticleBody-Video-107381338"><p><img src="https://image.cnbcfm.com/api/v1/image/107381341-22140230_TC_DIGITAL_TECHCHECK_TITLE_THUMBNAILS_GOGL_REV2.png?v=1709326142&amp;w=750&amp;h=422&amp;vtcrop=y" alt="Google vs. Google: The internal struggle holding back its AI"><span></span><span></span></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boeing 737 MAX suffers landing gear failure, rolls off runway (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/mar/08/boeing-plane-off-runway-houston-texas</link>
            <guid>39644341</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 18:35:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/mar/08/boeing-plane-off-runway-houston-texas">https://www.theguardian.com/world/2024/mar/08/boeing-plane-off-runway-houston-texas</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39644341">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>A United Airlines plane ran off the runway in Houston, Texas, on Friday, the latest incident in a week of safety issues for the airline, all involving Boeing planes, that included a tire falling off, a <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/news/us-news/passenger-video-shows-flames-shoot-united-airlines-engine-midflight-rcna142217" data-link-name="in body link">flaming engine</a> and allegedly “stuck” controls.</p><p>The <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/boeing" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Boeing</a> 737 Max 8, carrying 160 passengers and six crew, was landing at George Bush intercontinental airport on Friday morning when it “left the pavement and entered the grass” while exiting the runway for the gate, airport officials said in an interview.</p><figure id="30a5eec9-0dfd-407a-b4db-31f67f1287a8" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:2,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Boeing may delay more 737 Max deliveries after incorrectly drilled holes found&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;30a5eec9-0dfd-407a-b4db-31f67f1287a8&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/feb/05/boeing-may-delay-more-737-max-deliveries-after-new-production-glitch-found&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:0}}" config="{&quot;renderingTarget&quot;:&quot;Web&quot;,&quot;darkModeAvailable&quot;:false}"></gu-island></figure><p>In a separate statement, United Airlines said: “After landing, UA2477 exited the taxiway into a grassy area. Customers deplaned using air stairs and are being bused to the terminal.” It added that all passengers were safe.</p><p>On Thursday, a tire fell off a United Airlines plane seconds after it had taken off from <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/san-francisco" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">San Francisco</a> international airport. The tire, one of six on the left side main landing gear assembly, dropped into a staff parking lot, where it hit a car, broke the rear window, then tore through a fence and rolled to a halt.</p><p>An airport spokesperson said there were no injuries and that the Japan-bound Boeing 777, which was carrying 235 passengers and 14 crew members, landed safely in Los Angeles afterward. The Federal Aviation Administration said it will investigate.</p><p>United Airlines said that it “quickly arranged” for a new airplane to bring passengers to Osaka and did so later on Thursday evening.</p><p>“We’re grateful to our pilots and flight attendants for their professionalism in managing this situation. We’re also grateful to our teams on the ground who were waiting with a tug to move the aircraft soon after it landed and to our teams in the airport who assisted customers upon their arrival,” United said in a statement. “We will work with customers as well as with the owners of the damaged vehicles in SFO to ensure their needs are addressed.”</p><p>The tire incident itself came less than a week after passengers on a United Airlines flight from <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/houston" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Houston</a>, Texas, to Fort Myers, Florida, saw orange flames bursting from one of the plane’s engines 20 minutes after takeoff. The Boeing 737-900 made a safe emergency landing at George Bush intercontinental airport.</p><p>The incident seems to be a compressor stall, which occurs when there’s a disruption of airflow in the engine prompting it to backfire, “but doesn’t mean the engine itself is on fire”, NBC News said.</p><p>On Thursday, the National Transportation Safety Board released a preliminary report into a 6 February incident in which pilots of a Boeing 737 Max 8 said the controls jammed as they tried to land. It said the pilots reported “‘stuck’ rudder pedals during the landing rollout”, according to CNN.</p><p>Boeing declined to answer questions, directing comment to United Airlines.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-12">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-12" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>Alan Price, a former chief pilot for Delta Air Lines, told the Associated Press that a loose tire is typically related to maintenance, and is not the manufacturer’s fault.</p><p>John Cox, a retired pilot and aviation safety professor at the University of Southern <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/california" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">California</a>, expressed similar sentiments, saying to the AP: “I don’t see any impact for Boeing as it was a United maintenance team that changed the tire.”</p><p>Nevertheless, the incidents are Boeing’s latest safety issues in what has developed into a public relations headache for the aviation giant. During an Alaska Airlines flight on 5 January, the door plug on a nearly new <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/business/2024/feb/21/boeing-737-max-ed-clark-exit-renton" data-link-name="in body link">737 Max 9 blew out</a>, forcing an emergency landing. Safety officials’ preliminary report determined that four key bolts were missing.</p><p>The incident rekindled safety concerns over Boeing’s marquee airliner following the crashes of two Max 8 jets in 2018 and 2019, which left 346 dead.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why Tolkien Hated Dune (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://whitherthewest.com/2024/03/08/why-tolkien-hated-dune/</link>
            <guid>39644196</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 18:26:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://whitherthewest.com/2024/03/08/why-tolkien-hated-dune/">https://whitherthewest.com/2024/03/08/why-tolkien-hated-dune/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39644196">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<div>
<figure><img data-attachment-id="354" data-permalink="https://whitherthewest.com/2024/03/08/why-tolkien-hated-dune/output/" data-orig-file="https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg" data-orig-size="512,512" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="output" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg?w=512" width="512" height="512" src="https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg?w=512" alt="" srcset="https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg 512w, https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg?w=150 150w, https://whitherthewest.files.wordpress.com/2024/03/output.jpg?w=300 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px"></figure></div>


<p><em>A short intro to the philosophy of ethics</em></p>



<p>J.R.R. Tolkien maintained a very private, but very negative opinion of Frank Herbert’s Dune. In <em><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/45433749-tolkien-s-library">Tolkien’s Library</a></em>, entry 964, Tolkien is quoted as having written in an unpublished letter to John Bush, on March 12 1966, “It is impossible for an author still writing to be fair to another author working along the same lines. At least I find it so. In fact I dislike&nbsp;<em>Dune</em>&nbsp;with some intensity, and in that unfortunate case it is much the best and fairest to another author to keep silent and refuse to comment”. Tolkien does not elaborate, leaving the reasons for his intense dislike as an exercise for the reader.</p>



<p>However, when one peers under the hood into the underlying philosophies of the two authors, one can easily imagine the answer: Herbert and Tolkien are exact moral opposites. Tolkien was an avid Deontologist and Dune is pure Consequentialism.</p>



<p>Deontology and Consequentialism are two of the biggest rival camps in ethics. Deontology (from <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Greek_language">Greek</a>: δέον, ‘obligation, duty’ + λόγος, ‘study’) says “acts are in themselves either good or bad”, whereas Consequentialism says “whether an act is good or bad depends on the consequences”. The central message of Tolkien’s work, hammered again and again and again, is that you should be a deontologist, just be a simple, good person who does charitable and good things, and that evil isn’t the result of being “bad” but rather of being convinced that one can commit small acts of evil that nonetheless work toward a greater good. As Gandalf, speaking with the author’s voice, no doubt, says, “Many that live deserve death. Some that die deserve life. Can you give it to them, Frodo? Do not be too eager to deal out death in judgment. Even the very wise cannot see all ends.”</p>



<p>Dune is much the opposite. The Dune saga focuses on the morality of consequence, with the tradeoffs of rule, with the interactions of large and often amoral systems, how a man wields these powers to achieve his goals and how the long-term consequences of his actions determine his ultimate moral worth. “Greatness is a transitory experience. It is never consistent. It depends in part upon the myth-making imagination of humankind.” That is to say, greatness depends on human perspectives; if people perceive something as great, it is great, and that opinion can change over time as morality evolves. We can see already that this morality diverges from Tolkien’s simple, deontological “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Master%E2%80%93slave_morality">slave morality</a>“, in which greatness does not depend upon the spirit of the times, but rather embodies a spirit that stands the test of time, a prototype of Captain America’s famous “no, you move” monologue. To wit, consider Aragorn’s rather direct opposing quote, “Deeds will not be less valiant because they are unpraised” (RotK). One might argue that Herbert explicitly deconstructs the Tolkeinesque hero embodied in Leto (I) Atreides, whose valiance and refusal to embrace Machiavellian calculus and defy his honor cost him his life. But the moral disagreement between Herbert and Tolkien goes much deeper.</p>



<figure><p><span><iframe width="1100" height="619" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/W8tiH72jD6c?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox"></iframe></span>
</p></figure>



<p>Though there is no evidence that Tolkien continued to read on in the series (indeed he passed away in 1973, so could not have read beyond the second book, Dune Messiah, though since he disliked the original it would be odd for him to read on), those who have read past the introductory books up to God Emperor of Dune (it was introduced in Dune Messiah, but its full elaboration was only given in GEoD) know about the so-called Golden Path. The Path is, in short, a path to avoid humanity’s extinction. Leto II views the eventual extinction of humanity as something to be avoided at all costs, worthy of all sacrifices, and as such the Golden Path – his plan to so brutally oppress humanity that future humans would go their separate ways and refuse to ever submit themselves again to centralized rule -is pure, unadulterated consequentialism – the ultimate, millennia-long evil, countless acts of barbarity and oppression, to achieve a possible good. As Leto II extols, “I have been called many things: Usurper, Tyrant, Despot. Some even call me the greatest mass murderer in history. They are not entirely wrong. My actions have caused great suffering, and I bear that burden willingly, for I know that the future of humanity depends on it.” In other words, the ends justify the means. And thus the zenith of necessary ends justifies the nadir of abhorrent means. We need not even imagine what Tolkien thought of this: Gandalf (as we mentioned earlier, Tolkien’s surrogate), addresses it: “It is not our part to master all the tides of the world, but to do what is in us for the succor of those years wherein we are set, uprooting the evil in the fields that we know, so that those who live after may have clean earth to till.”</p>



<figure><p><span><iframe width="1100" height="619" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/3srD9Gvl0pI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox"></iframe></span>
</p></figure>



<p>The philosophical disagreement between Tolkien and Herbert touches on many more subjects, of course, and another prominent disagreement was that Tolkien was a very devout Catholic and Herbert was not exactly friendly towards religion. Herbert saw religion as an inherently mutable, utilitarian institution, and Herbert was dismissive or even openly antagonistic toward religious truths. In the world of “Dune,” religion serves as a powerful tool for control and manipulation, with institutions like the Bene Gesserit using it to shape political and social outcomes – indeed the central prophecy (that of the <em>Lisan al Gaib</em>) of the original book was a completely artificial contrivance for political machinations of the Bene Gesserit. In contrast, of course, Tolkien saw Christianity as channeling eternal moral truths about kindness and redemption, and his world-building reflects his belief in a higher power and cosmic order, with themes like mercy, sacrifice, and the triumph of hope over despair mirroring his theological perspective.</p>



<p>Religious differences aside, the central argument between the two authors is the moral one. Tolkien is a modernist (or even pre-modernist); Herbert is a post-modernist: Tolkien encourages everyone to follow a single template of goodness; Herbert encourages cynicism and doubt of the institutions that produce templates, and shows the anguish experienced by Paul when he is forced into a template to survive. If one had to summarize these different perspectives in one sentence, Tolkien argues “Strive for goodness, and people will come to call it great”, whereas Herbert argues “strive for greatness, and people will come to call it good”.</p>




	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Epic says Apple will reinstate developer account (479 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/08/epic-says-apple-will-reinstate-developer-account-clearing-path-for-epic-games-store-on-iphone/</link>
            <guid>39643981</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 18:12:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/08/epic-says-apple-will-reinstate-developer-account-clearing-path-for-epic-games-store-on-iphone/">https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/08/epic-says-apple-will-reinstate-developer-account-clearing-path-for-epic-games-store-on-iphone/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39643981">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
	<img width="1600" height="800" src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/epic.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/epic.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/epic.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/epic.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/03/epic.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high"></figure>

<p>After a whirlwind of events, Epic Games says Apple has reinstated their App Store developer account. The move clears the way for Epic to bring its Epic Games Store to the EU, avoiding the App Store structure altogether. The turnaround is somewhat unexpected as Apple seemed to stand by its decision to revoke Epic’s developer account on Wednesday.</p>



<h2 id="h-epic-games-unbanned-again">Epic Games, unbanned again</h2>



<p>Here’s what Epic Games says in a new update to their <a href="https://www.epicgames.com/site/en-US/news/apple-terminated-epic-s-developer-account">blog post</a> from Wednesday:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>Apple has told us and committed to the European Commission that they will reinstate our developer account. This sends a strong signal to developers that the European Commission will act swiftly to enforce the Digital Markets Act and hold gatekeepers accountable. We are moving forward as planned to launch the Epic Games Store and bring Fortnite back to iOS in Europe. Onward!</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Epic Games CEO Tim Sweeney <a href="https://twitter.com/timsweeneyepic/status/1766158416093798866?s=61&amp;t=nLf1XlkmJ0WYDBmecUzqWw">added</a> this color on X:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The DMA went through its first major challenge with Apple banning Epic Games Sweden from competing with the App Store, and the DMA just had its first major victory. Following a swift inquiry by the European Commission, Apple notified the Commission and Epic that it would relent and restore our access to bring back Fortnite and launch Epic Games Store in Europe under the DMA law. A big win for European rule of law, for the European Commision, and for the freedom of developers worldwide to speak up. <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/FreeFortnite?src=hashtag_click">#FreeFortnite</a>!</p>
</blockquote>



<h2 id="h-so-what-changed">So what changed?</h2>



<p>The turnaround really is an interesting 48 hours. The brouhaha <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/06/epic-games-dev-account-dead/">was loudest on Wednesday</a> when Epic Games announced its EU dev account was being banned in part over a tweet. Epic backed up their claim with private emails between Epic Games CEO Tim Sweeney, Apple’s Phil Schiller, and legal reps for both firms.</p>



<p>At the time, Apple pointed to a 2020 court decision out of the United States as its basis for terminating Epic’s developer account. Apple maintained that it had no reason to believe Epic Games would not once again violate App Store policy with a new developer account.</p>



<p>So what changed? Apple tells <em>9to5Mac </em>that it has held further discussions with Epic. The result is that Apple has received proper commitment that Epic will play by the rules as legally defined.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>“Following conversations with Epic, they have committed to follow the rules, including our DMA policies. As a result, Epic Sweden AB has been permitted to re-sign the developer agreement and accepted into the Apple Developer Program.”</p>
</blockquote>



<h2 id="h-more">More</h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/08/apple-threaten-epic-illegal/">The law doesn’t allow Apple to threaten Epic, says EU</a></li>



<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/07/apple-epic-ban-regulators/">Apple’s Epic ban is questioned by EU regulators; more details</a></li>



<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/04/apple-eu-fine-apple-music-spotify/">Apple fined $2 billion by EU commission for ‘abusive’ App Store rules, Apple to appeal</a></li>



<li><a href="https://9to5mac.com/2024/03/07/apple-planning-default-navigation-app-setting-in-ios-18-for-eu-users/">Apple planning default navigation app setting in iOS 18 for EU users</a></li>
</ul>
	<p>
		<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBggKMLOFATDAGg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add 9to5Mac to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
	</p>
	<p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://9to5mac.com/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Piano on Paper (181 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/Mayuresh1611/Paper-Piano</link>
            <guid>39643958</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 18:10:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/Mayuresh1611/Paper-Piano">https://github.com/Mayuresh1611/Paper-Piano</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39643958">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">PAPER PIANO</h2><a id="user-content-paper-piano" aria-label="Permalink: PAPER PIANO" href="#paper-piano"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Now we don't need to buy Piano if we want to play music. We can play piano on paper, although it may not give feeling of pressing keys on piano but it gets work done!</h3><a id="user-content-now-we-dont-need-to-buy-piano-if-we-want-to-play-music-we-can-play-piano-on-paper-although-it-may-not-give-feeling-of-pressing-keys-on-piano-but-it-gets-work-done" aria-label="Permalink: Now we don't need to buy Piano if we want to play music. We can play piano on paper, although it may not give feeling of pressing keys on piano but it gets work done!" href="#now-we-dont-need-to-buy-piano-if-we-want-to-play-music-we-can-play-piano-on-paper-although-it-may-not-give-feeling-of-pressing-keys-on-piano-but-it-gets-work-done"></a></p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description demo.mp4">demo.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/103099867/311195062-c2b0b4f1-3b6b-4eed-927d-91c5b5c91708.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NjQzMDcsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk2NDAwNywicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDMwOTk4NjcvMzExMTk1MDYyLWMyYjBiNGYxLTNiNmItNGVlZC05MjdkLTkxYzViNWM5MTcwOC5tcDQ_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwMzA5JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDMwOVQwNjAwMDdaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1hYWI2ZGFlZTQwOTYyODk0ZTFkMjI5ZmJhNDU1NjcwOTVmZTE1M2QwMWFmMDQ1NTk3Zjg4ZDg3MGEwNWM5NGUzJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.99ddiochcd6llM25x8t8t3005XEAX9c8gd93KXWgszs" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/103099867/311195062-c2b0b4f1-3b6b-4eed-927d-91c5b5c91708.mp4?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5NjQzMDcsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTk2NDAwNywicGF0aCI6Ii8xMDMwOTk4NjcvMzExMTk1MDYyLWMyYjBiNGYxLTNiNmItNGVlZC05MjdkLTkxYzViNWM5MTcwOC5tcDQ_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwMzA5JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDMwOVQwNjAwMDdaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1hYWI2ZGFlZTQwOTYyODk0ZTFkMjI5ZmJhNDU1NjcwOTVmZTE1M2QwMWFmMDQ1NTk3Zjg4ZDg3MGEwNWM5NGUzJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.99ddiochcd6llM25x8t8t3005XEAX9c8gd93KXWgszs" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><strong>Currently it only supports maximum 2 fingers</strong> (1 finger of both hands). Support for more fingers and highly susceptible training model is on the way.</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><a href="#setting-up-project">Setting up project</a></li>
<li><a href="#how-to-use">How to Use</a></li>
<li><a href="#training-and-adjusting">Training and Adjusting </a></li>
<li><a href="#contributing-to-this-project">Contributing to this project</a></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">SETTING UP PROJECT</h2><a id="user-content-setting-up-project" aria-label="Permalink: SETTING UP PROJECT" href="#setting-up-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Python version 3.11 and above</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Clone the repository <code>git clone https://github.com/Mayuresh1611/Paper-Piano.git</code></li>
<li>run command <code>pip install requirements.txt</code> in the command line.</li>
<li>Execute <code>run.py</code> file</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">HOW TO USE</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-use" aria-label="Permalink: HOW TO USE" href="#how-to-use"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is a little trickier part as the project requires you to set up a webcam in the specific angle at a specific height and distance. Also  stronger the light, better the performance.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">STUFF YOU WILL REQUIRE</h4><a id="user-content-stuff-you-will-require" aria-label="Permalink: STUFF YOU WILL REQUIRE" href="#stuff-you-will-require"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>webcam or you can use third-party tools for webcam.</li>
<li>Two A4-sized white paper, horizontally joined together. 2 rectangles need to be drawn at both ends of the paper with a black marker, thicker lines yield better results.</li>
<li>Recommended position for the webcam will be such that it can capture the finger and shadow beneath the finger and should have both boxes we drew on joined paper in the FOV of the camera.
Just like shown in the demo video.</li>
<li>Light source in front, ie. behind the camera would be preferred. Casting sharp shadows.</li>
<li>Hand with all fingers.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">TRAINING AND ADJUSTING</h4><a id="user-content-training-and-adjusting" aria-label="Permalink: TRAINING AND ADJUSTING" href="#training-and-adjusting"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>During training the model on your finger, the first window will appear where box will be drawn around the tip of the finger. If the box does not cover complete finger and little surrounding of the finger. Adjust the camera accordingly.</li>
<li>In the training stage, do not move your finger furiously, move it slowly giving out every angle.</li>
<li>While training, during the touched finger state, do press the finger but not too hard. In an untouched finger state, do not touch paper, you can get near paper but not too close. Lift the finger high like you would normally do.</li>
<li>CNN has been used to train over the data, it distinguishes the touched and untouched finger, if the results are not satisfactory, retrain the model.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">CONTRIBUTING TO THIS PROJECT</h2><a id="user-content-contributing-to-this-project" aria-label="Permalink: CONTRIBUTING TO THIS PROJECT" href="#contributing-to-this-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If we make this project into a complete working piano on paper. It would give access of piano and instruments for those who cannot afford it. <code> like me :)</code></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>There are no set rules or code of conduct as of now. Anyone wtih better ideas and improvement is welcomed.</li>
<li>The only rules are</li>
</ul>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>The name of the function should match the functionality it is doing.</li>
<li>Use comments only when required.</li>
<li>Share with the ones who can improve this project even more.</li>
</ol>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Wallstreetlocal – View investments from America's biggest companies (286 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/bruhbruhroblox/wallstreetlocal</link>
            <guid>39643833</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 18:02:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/bruhbruhroblox/wallstreetlocal">https://github.com/bruhbruhroblox/wallstreetlocal</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39643833">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://wallstreetlocal.com/" rel="nofollow">
    <themed-picture data-catalyst-inline="true"><picture>
      <img alt="wallstreetlocal" src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/bruhbruhroblox/wallstreetlocal/main/public/static/logo.png">
    </picture></themed-picture>
  </a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
  A website that allows you to view the investments of America's largest investors.
</p>
<p dir="auto">
  This repository holds the front-end code for wallstreetlocal, for the back-end, see <a href="https://github.com/bruhbruhroblox/pinestreetlocal">here</a>.
</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h3><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) keeps record of every company in the United States. Companies whose holdings surpass $100 million though, are required to file a special type of form: the 13F form. This form, filed quarterly, discloses the filer's holdings, providing transparency into their investment activities and allowing the public and other market participants to monitor them.</p>
<p dir="auto">The problem though, is that these holdings are often cumbersome to access, and valuable analysis is often hidden behind a paywall. Through <strong>wallstreetlocal</strong>, the SEC's 13F filers become more accessible and open.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Large:</strong> With over 850,000 companies archived, any company registered with the SEC can be queried. Download the database <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1LT4xiFJkh6YlAPQDcov8YIKqcvevFlEE/view" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Recent Data:</strong> View stocks in aggregation as the back-end collects and organizes holdings from individual filers. With thousands of cached stocks in our database, accurate and recent data is available for any evaluations.</li>
<li><strong>Historical Data:</strong> View individual filings and their holdings in the explorer, or visit the SEC directly.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://wallstreetlocal.com/" rel="nofollow">Visit</a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Query 13F filers from the SEC</li>
<li>Update filers with up-to-date stock info</li>
<li>View filer stocks in an accessible format</li>
<li>Download any data in either JSON or CSV</li>
<li>View filer historical filings and compare them</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting Started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting Started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">View wallstreetlocal at <a href="https://wallstreetlocal.com/" rel="nofollow"><code>wallstreetlocal.com</code></a>, or self-host using the following instructions.</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">Install dependencies.</p>

</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Deploy.</p>

<p dir="auto">Or for a production build, run</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="npm run build &amp;&amp; npm run start"><pre>npm run build <span>&amp;&amp;</span> npm run start</pre></div>
</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">The back-end for this installation is already configured to <a href="https://content.wallstreetlocal.com/" rel="nofollow"><code>content.wallstreetlocal.com</code></a>, but if you want to self-host that too, you can find the back-end repository <a href="https://github.com/bruhbruhroblox/pinestreetlocal">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">For more information on configuration, see the respective docs for wallstreetlocal's development stack.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://fastapi.tiangolo.com/" rel="nofollow">FastAPI</a> for the back-end work.</li>
<li><a href="https://nextjs.org/" rel="nofollow">NextJS</a> for the front-end.</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.docker.com/" rel="nofollow">Docker</a> for all the different microservices.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.mongodb.com/docs/" rel="nofollow">MongoDB</a> for the database.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.meilisearch.com/docs" rel="nofollow">Meilisearch</a> for the search database.</li>
<li><a href="https://nginxproxymanager.com/" rel="nofollow">NGINX Proxy Manager</a> for the reverse-proxy.</li>
<li><a href="https://grafana.com/" rel="nofollow">Grafana</a> for telemetry, using Prometheus, Tempo, Loki, and OpenTelemetry.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you feel you can contribute to this project, create an issue or a pull request.</p>
<p dir="auto">This project is soley mantained so it is prone to bugs and anti-patterns, please call them out where you see them. All contributions are highly appreciated!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h3><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">wallstreetlocal is <a href="https://github.com/bruhbruhroblox/wallstreetlocal/blob/main/LICENSE">MIT licensed</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple restores Epic's account in the EU (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1766158416093798866</link>
            <guid>39643685</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 17:53:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1766158416093798866">https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1766158416093798866</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39643685">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/TimSweeneyEpic/status/1766158416093798866: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Airbnb's Devastating Effect on Canadian Housing (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thewalrus.ca/airbnbs-canadian-housing/</link>
            <guid>39643447</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 17:33:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thewalrus.ca/airbnbs-canadian-housing/">https://thewalrus.ca/airbnbs-canadian-housing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39643447">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-163487">

	
	
	
	<div>
		<!-- Ad-Auris -->
		
		<p><span>J</span><span> ean-François Raymond </span> wasn’t expecting an eviction notice in the last few days of 2022. He’d lived in his spacious apartment in Montreal’s east-end neighbourhood of Hochelaga-Maisonneuve for twenty-two years. It was home in the truest sense of the word. “It was the place that I raised my kid,” he said. “There are plenty of memories.” </p>

<p>But somewhere along the line, as Raymond and his partner raised their child and lived their lives, the local borough established rules in an effort to limit short-term tourist accommodations like Airbnb. That was back in 2016, when the Mercier–Hochelaga-Maisonneuve borough council was under growing pressure to clamp down on the boom in short-term rental suites. So the elected officials drew up a set of what they hoped would be relatively simple rules that prohibit—at least on paper—apartments being operated as short-term vacation rentals in most areas. However, the council permitted vacation rentals “in areas where there are businesses and buildings with three or more dwellings.” </p>
<p>Unfortunately for Raymond, that included his three-storey building on Ontario Street. The busy thoroughfare is lined with an array of shops, cafes, and restaurants. “A thriving urban village with a friendly, small-town feel,” according to Tourisme Montréal. Raymond was shocked to learn his building was eligible for short-term rentals and that the landlord would evict him for that purpose. “I am very angry because we’re not leaving for his old mother or his child going to school. He’s going to change us for a hotel, an Airbnb, for tourism.”</p>

<p>Raymond was especially worried about his neighbour, a sixty-eight-year-old man who had lived there for more than half a century. It’s hard to blame him for being unfamiliar with the rental market—he’d moved into that apartment with his parents when he was just fourteen and had been there ever since. “After fifty-four years in the same place, it will be difficult to move, especially at my age. It’s demoralizing,” he said. Like Raymond and his partner, the elderly man was given six months’ notice. They had until July 2023 to find a new place. Not an easy task, given that he was paying only $685 for what’s known in Montreal as a 6½ but would be described in many other cities as a three-bedroom apartment.</p>
<p>Raymond’s rent was $910 a month—nearly $400 more than what he paid when he moved in but a great deal less than most new rents in 2023. The price of the average two-bedroom rental apartment advertised in Montreal had ballooned to $1,800, with an average one-bedroom costing $1,470. Sure, rents in Montreal are still significantly lower than those in Toronto and Vancouver, but wages in Montreal are lower too, and rents were rising much faster than wages. Those rises were also more pronounced in certain areas, like Mercier–Hochelaga-Maisonneuve. Apartments similar in size to those rented by Raymond and his neighbour were listed the previous summer for $2,500 a month for long-term rentals. Short-term rentals could bring in even more money for the landlord.</p>

<p>Despite the law and the profit motive working against him, Raymond wasn’t willing to give up without a fight. He called local reporters to share the story and unfurled a large improvised banner across the front of the building. A stark message was painted in red and black on a white sheet: ÉVICTIONS EN COURS POUR UN FUTUR AIRBNB (Evictions underway for a future Airbnb). A pair of skull-and-crossbones symbols was added for good measure. But the publicity would go only so far. What Raymond really needed was for the law to back him up. He took the landlord to Quebec’s housing tribunal, asking for compensation from the landlord in recognition of all the years he and his elderly neighbour had spent in the building. The owners turned down interview requests, but the eviction notice clearly stated they planned to convert the apartments into short-term tourist rental suites.</p>
<p>Housing advocates urged councillors to change local rules to prevent such evictions. If nothing else, they argued, the borough could restrict conversions to apartments where a tenant has already decided to leave or if the suite is in a new building. But the mayor of Mercier–Hochelaga-Maisonneuve said his hands were tied by provincial laws that restricted municipal bans to residential areas. “If it was up to me, I would ban rentals for more than thirty days a year on Airbnb throughout the territory,” Pierre Lessard-Blais lamented. “Someone who rents out their home for a week during their vacation is fine. But when it’s more than thirty days a year, it becomes a business that prevents a family from having access to housing in a residential area.” City politicians had already asked the Quebec government to change the law to ban evictions caused by short-term rental conversions. But when Raymond and his neighbour received their eviction notices, there were no such bans in place.</p>
<p><span>I</span><span> t’s not hard </span> to imagine why landlords might want to convert old apartments in Hochelaga-Maisonneuve into Airbnbs or other short-term vacation rentals. The francophone neighbourhood was historically industrial and working class—not the stuff of tourist brochures. But as in the case of a lot of Montreal’s old neighbourhoods, its authentic character appeals to visitors. In the years since Raymond moved into his modest apartment, other working-class neighbourhoods such as Verdun, Mile End, and Saint-Henri have gentrified. Once affordable areas with modest dépanneurs and shops, these neighbourhoods now boast chic cafes, microbreweries, and trendy restaurants. </p>
<p>As new people moved in, prices went up. And as those neighbourhoods gentrified, surrounding areas like Hochelaga-Maisonneuve faced similar pressures. From a tourism perspective, the change in the neighbourhood is a good thing. Tourisme Montréal certainly thinks so: “From recycled factories to beautiful churches to striking institutional buildings, the borough’s architectural landscape tells a tale of transformation and evolution.”</p>
<p>It’s a matter of opinion whether any given neighbourhood is more appealing once it gentrifies. What’s less debatable is that neighbourhoods get more expensive for the people who live there. New rentals in Hochelaga-Maisonneuve are now several times higher than what Raymond and his neighbour can afford. But landlords could make even more money by cashing in on the demand for nightly vacation rentals, especially in the summer, when Ontario Street and Sainte-Catherine Street East host outdoor festivals. The streets are closed to traffic, so patios and sidewalks fill up and visitors pour in. A quick scan of Airbnb shows two-bedroom apartments on Ontario Street going for anywhere from $265 to $460 a night in July. Single rooms are cheaper, at closer to $100. But an apartment like Raymond’s could fetch more than $10,000 a month in the summer, if it was renovated.</p>

<p>Of course, Airbnbs are in demand for a reason. Bruno Berumen, visiting Montreal from Guadalajara, Mexico, put it succinctly: “I’m staying in an Airbnb because I think it’s cheaper than hotels, and also you have the facilities to take your food in the house and cook.” The boom in Airbnb and other short-term rental websites has changed cities and towns around the world, with many Montreal residents among the millions of travellers staying in charming abodes on their overseas trips. For some Montreal renters, like Félix Blanche, there’s an uneasy suspicion that the same platforms that helped them have a great vacation are also making their life back home a lot more difficult. “I’ve been to Europe last year, and it was great over there. But in this neighbourhood, as somebody who’s trying to look for an apartment, who did for a few months, it was pretty rough probably because of Airbnb.”</p>
<p>Airbnb says the “home-sharing” service it provides amounts to a “significant boost to the Quebec economy.” In 2018, it claimed that Airbnb visitors spent $475 million in Montreal—more than in both Toronto and Vancouver. Alex Dagg, Airbnb’s then director of public policy in Canada,  said, “Airbnb guests visit stores, coffee shops, and restaurants in the neighbourhoods where they’re staying—which supports local businesses and helps create jobs in the community.” Of course, the same could be said of hotel visitors. But Airbnb points to a survey it commissioned that suggests “75 percent of Airbnb guests are more likely to travel to Montreal again because of Airbnb’s offerings.” It’s difficult to say if that’s true and, if so, whether it’s worth the impact on local rents.</p>
<p>Cities around the world have debated the effects of short-term rentals on the affordability of housing. But in many cases, it’s been difficult to find enough data, from both companies and governments, to make an accurate assessment. That’s started to change in recent years. Professor David Wachsmuth, at McGill University, is the Canada research chair in urban governance and led a study on the impact of short-term rentals in Canada. He concluded that the relatively new revenue source for landlords across Canada has been a major cause of housing financialization, where housing is treated as a commodity, or a vehicle for profit and investment, rather than a social good. He found that most short-term rentals are owned by big companies rather than private individuals and that financial incentives placed significant pressure on housing as more long-term rentals were converted to short-term ones. </p>
<p>Wachsmuth’s study found 31,000 homes were taken out of Canada’s long-term housing market as a direct result of short-term rentals. The impact was higher in neighbourhoods like Hochelaga-Maisonneuve that have good transit, amenities, and easy access to city centres. Across Montreal, Wachsmuth estimates, 6,000 homes were taken out of the rental market to be converted into vacation suites. “Removing this chunk of short-term rental apartments off the market makes it substantially harder to find a rental apartment in Montreal.”</p>
<p>Raymond loved Hochelaga-Maisonneuve. But as he started to look for other rentals, he realized his modest carpenter’s income was no longer enough to afford the neighbourhood he’d called home for decades. “It will be very, very hard to find somewhere on Montreal Island, so we’ll probably move off the Island like everybody else.”</p>
<p><span>S</span><span> hort-term rentals </span> are a long-term concern in many cities, but the worry is especially pronounced in Montreal because the city has so many renters. In fact, Montreal has the highest share of renter-occupied housing of any large or mid-sized North American city. According to the 2016 census, more than 63 percent of Montreal’s housing units were rented. The city was known for many years as a renters’ paradise because of low rents and high vacancy rates, thanks to an abundance of low-rise rental housing. But the seeds of change were sown in the 1990s, when the federal government stopped building social housing and legalized real estate investment trusts, a model of pooled real estate ownership developed in the United States. REITs have been a popular choice for Canadian investors, big and small, and have purchased thousands of rental buildings across the country with the purpose of maximizing profits for investors. In many cases, that meant renovating old buildings to charge much higher rents. For many long-time renters, it led to renoviction—an eviction that’s carried out to renovate a rental unit. Rents in Montreal started to rise in the 2010s, even though the construction of new purpose-built rental units remained healthy. The city added 13,500 purpose-built apartments between 2016 and 2020, but new rental buildings are exempt from rent-control laws for five years after construction. </p>
<p>In 2019, just before the outbreak of the COVID-19 pandemic, Montreal’s rents rose 4.2 percent, the largest average increase in twenty years. That’s higher than the annual rate of increase that’s allowed by Quebec law, where rent control is supposed to apply to the rental unit rather than the tenant. But a 2023 study into the financialization of rental housing in Montreal found that didn’t always work: “In practice there is no way to ensure that rents are not raised illegally when a new tenant arrives. There is no registry to consult, the outgoing tenant does not always communicate the previous rent to the future tenant, and not everyone has the courage to speak up against their landlord’s violations.” Cloé St-Hilaire and her co-authors found the high demand for rentals stifled many tenant objections to rent increases “because tenants fear they will lose their homes and be unable to find a replacement.” That’s not surprising given that Montreal’s vacancy rate had dropped to an all-time low of 1.6 percent in 2019. It all adds up to a rough ride for renters.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, the city of Montreal was trying new measures to protect affordable rentals. In 2022, it legislated a sixty-day right of first refusal that allows the city to step in on the sale of any rental property and match the offer on the table. The new law allowed the city to buy seventy-eight rooming houses that housed hundreds of low-income residents. That’s good news for those renters. But across the city, many are still struggling with rising rents and evictions.</p>
<p>Guillaume Dostaler, a tenants’ rights coordinator, sees it every day. He tries to help tenants who’ve been evicted to make way for short-term rental conversions and counsels new immigrants who are too timid to speak out against illegal rent increases. But he doesn’t think things will get better for Montreal renters unless the provincial government creates a comprehensive new registry of all rental units. Without that, he says, apartments will continue to be converted into short-term rentals and landlords will jack up rents illegally between tenants. When asked if he expects the provincial government to do that, Guillaume scoffs. “Not at all,” he says, in French.</p>
<p>Many renters wonder whether their political leaders really understand their plight. When Quebec premier François Legault and his wife put their 8,000-square-foot Victorian mansion in downtown Montreal up for sale in 2021, the listing price was just under $5 million. During the provincial election campaign the following year, Legault disclosed he’d moved into a condominium with a declared value of $3.2 million. During the pandemic, Legault had come under fire from the opposition Québec solidaire party for suggesting Montreal renters could find an apartment for as little as $500 a month. The premier bristled at the suggestion he was out of touch with the working classes, whom he considered his people, saying his comments were misconstrued and that he only meant a student sharing a larger apartment could expect to pay so little. Legault also went on to win the 2022 election with no obligation to create a rental registry.</p>

<p>Even if Quebec does create a registry, there’s reason to wonder if it would really work. After all, the provincial government enacted wide-ranging restrictions on short-term rentals when the Liberals were in power in 2015. Hosts had to register their short-term rental unit with Revenu Québec or face fines. No fines were handed out the first year the law was in effect. None. A few years later, Legault’s Coalition Avenir Québec government made the rules more stringent; short-term landlords had to buy a registration number and display it on their listings. But critics say these rules have had little effect. </p>
<p>“I think Quebec has the best system in the whole country on paper,” Wachsmuth says, “but it has not put in any effort to make sure that anybody follows those rules.” Hopefully, that will just take more time. The city of Montreal allows boroughs, like Mercier–Hochelaga-Maisonneuve, to choose areas where short-term rentals are restricted to thirty days a year. And Revenu Québec reported handing out more than 900 fines to short-term rental hosts in 2021. Still, that’s probably a drop in the Airbnb bucket. The independent activist group Inside Airbnb found 12,500 Airbnb listings in Montreal in December 2021 and claimed more than 95 percent of them were unlicensed.</p>
<p><span>S</span><span> tories of unlicensed vacation rentals </span> causing problems for neighbours spread across Montreal in both official languages: a frat house atmosphere, with people vomiting out of windows at 3 a.m. and raves that last until 11 a.m., jammed elevators, and wrecked laundry rooms. Of course, bad behaviour has been around a lot longer than Airbnb, and many who have stayed in short-term rentals have followed the rules and done their best to respect the neighbours. But many neighbours complain they don’t like the arrangement and would rather see the surrounding apartments occupied by permanent residents.</p>
<p>A musician in her fifties, Rebecca Bain has seen the benefits that affordable rents and stable housing bring to a community. “Montreal was a haven for artists,” she says wistfully, remembering a time when most of the apartments in her working-class neighbourhood were truly affordable for the vast majority of people. She’s called Saint-Henri home for more than twenty years but has seen it change rapidly of late. She’s watched as the post office and local dépanneurs closed their doors and were replaced with expensive restaurants. She noticed fewer families with young children on the streets. She understands that young professionals and other people moving into the neighbourhood also need a place to live, but she wonders where the people who have lived in Saint-Henri for decades will go when they get evicted. “The elderly people live on a fixed income. There’s literally nowhere else for them to go.”</p>
<p>When the sixplex Bain lived in was sold to a Montreal property company, she and all the other tenants in the building received eviction notices. They were told the building was going to be renovated, despite having been refurbished just a few years earlier. Bain believes the new owners just wanted to make them fancier so they could charge more money. First, they got formal letters, then the phone calls started. A woman who refused to identify herself called Bain repeatedly.  </p>
<p>Bain then went to her local tenants’ rights group and learned the same company had bought several buildings in the neighbourhood and had handed eviction notices to more than forty renters. Bain says they all received similarly intimidating phone calls. Eventually, all of the other five residents of her building agreed to leave. But she refused. “I know my rights.” Along with dozens of other tenants, she fought the landlord and was allowed to stay, paying roughly $900 a month for her 4½ (small two-bedroom apartment). She lived through all the renovations of the other units and befriended the workers, hoping they wouldn’t harass her (they didn’t). And when the new tenants moved into her building, they all ended up paying much, much more. “So everyone else in my building now pays twice what I pay, and every time a new tenant comes in, they add another 200 on.”</p>
<p>Without a rent registry, there is little oversight. And renters are often relieved just to find someplace they can afford, even if it does gobble up a large portion of their income. Bain isn’t holding her breath that things will change, and she wonders if too many people are more concerned with their own personal gain than the overall well-being of their communities. “Housing is a right, and I feel somehow it’s become a privilege,” she laments. “It shouldn’t be a luxury to have a decent place to live.”</p>
<p><em>Excerpted from </em>Our Crumbling Foundation: How We Solve Canada’s Housing Crisis<em> by Gregor Craigie. Copyright © 2024 Gregor Craigie. Published by Random House Canada, a division of Penguin Random House Canada Limited. Reproduced by arrangement with the publisher. All rights reserved.</em></p>
<!-- AI CONTENT END 1 -->
		<div id="sexy_author_bio_widget-2"><p><a href="https://thewalrus.ca/author/gregor-craigie/" target="_top"><img alt="Gregor Craigie" src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%2070%2070'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/62f2c2ea49faa3434c43a795daaa186a?s=70&amp;d=mm&amp;r=pg" data-srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/62f2c2ea49faa3434c43a795daaa186a?s=140&amp;d=mm&amp;r=pg 2x" height="70" width="70"></a></p><p>Gregor Craigie has been a journalist for more than twenty-five years, at the BBC World Service, CBC Radio, CBS Radio, and Public Radio International. He has hosted <em>On the Island</em> on CBC Radio One in Victoria, BC, since 2007.</p></div>	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	
	<!-- .entry-footer -->

		
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Hatchet – Open-source distributed task queue (531 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet</link>
            <guid>39643136</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 17:07:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet">https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39643136">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text">
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What is Hatchet?</h3><a id="user-content-what-is-hatchet" aria-label="Permalink: What is Hatchet?" href="#what-is-hatchet"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Hatchet replaces difficult to manage legacy queues or pub/sub systems so you can design durable workloads that recover from failure and solve for problems like <strong>concurrency</strong>, <strong>fairness</strong>, and <strong>rate limiting</strong>. Instead of managing your own task queue or pub/sub system, you can use Hatchet to distribute your functions between a set of workers with minimal configuration or infrastructure:</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/25448214/307867265-c3defa1e-d9d9-4419-94e5-b4ea4a748f8d.gif?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5MjgzMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTkyODAwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNTQ0ODIxNC8zMDc4NjcyNjUtYzNkZWZhMWUtZDlkOS00NDE5LTk0ZTUtYjRlYTRhNzQ4ZjhkLmdpZj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDglMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA4VDIwMDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTJlZWIwYTAzMzEzMmNiNTVjN2I2MGZlNDk5YjI3NzM1YmYwNzlmNTRiMDRjYzU0NzcwZGQwZDUyOGJiZmNjZjcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.2E9iO-gYZe6OoFG3c57HnrcMEJFI1cbPbyIz0mh29mY"><img width="500" height="500" src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/25448214/307867265-c3defa1e-d9d9-4419-94e5-b4ea4a748f8d.gif?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk5MjgzMDYsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTkyODAwNiwicGF0aCI6Ii8yNTQ0ODIxNC8zMDc4NjcyNjUtYzNkZWZhMWUtZDlkOS00NDE5LTk0ZTUtYjRlYTRhNzQ4ZjhkLmdpZj9YLUFtei1BbGdvcml0aG09QVdTNC1ITUFDLVNIQTI1NiZYLUFtei1DcmVkZW50aWFsPUFLSUFWQ09EWUxTQTUzUFFLNFpBJTJGMjAyNDAzMDglMkZ1cy1lYXN0LTElMkZzMyUyRmF3czRfcmVxdWVzdCZYLUFtei1EYXRlPTIwMjQwMzA4VDIwMDAwNlomWC1BbXotRXhwaXJlcz0zMDAmWC1BbXotU2lnbmF0dXJlPTJlZWIwYTAzMzEzMmNiNTVjN2I2MGZlNDk5YjI3NzM1YmYwNzlmNTRiMDRjYzU0NzcwZGQwZDUyOGJiZmNjZjcmWC1BbXotU2lnbmVkSGVhZGVycz1ob3N0JmFjdG9yX2lkPTAma2V5X2lkPTAmcmVwb19pZD0wIn0.2E9iO-gYZe6OoFG3c57HnrcMEJFI1cbPbyIz0mh29mY" data-animated-image=""></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>What Makes Hatchet Great?</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">⚡️ <strong>Ultra-low Latency and High Throughput Scheduling:</strong> Hatchet is built on a low-latency queue (<code>25ms</code> average start), perfectly balancing real-time interaction capabilities with the reliability required for mission-critical tasks.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">☮️ <strong>Concurrency, Fairness, and Rate Limiting:</strong> Implement FIFO, LIFO, Round Robin, and Priority Queues with Hatchet’s built-in strategies, designed to circumvent common scaling pitfalls with minimal configuration. <a href="https://docs.hatchet.run/" rel="nofollow">Read Docs →</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">🔥🧯 <strong>Resilience by Design:</strong> With customizable retry policies and integrated error handling, Hatchet ensures your operations recover swiftly from transient failures. You can break large jobs down into small tasks so you can finish a run without rerunning work. <a href="https://docs.hatchet.run/" rel="nofollow">Read Docs →</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Enhanced Visibility and Control:</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Observability.</strong> All of your runs are fully searchable, allowing you to quickly identify issues. We track latency, error rates, or custom metrics in your run.</li>
<li><strong>(Practical) Durable Execution.</strong> Replay events and manually pick up execution from specific steps in your workflow.</li>
<li><strong>Cron.</strong> Set recurring schedules for functions runs to execute.</li>
<li><strong>One-Time Scheduling.</strong> Schedule a function run to execute at a specific time and date in the future.</li>
<li><strong>Spike Protection.</strong> Smooth out spikes in traffic and only execute what your system can handle.</li>
<li><strong>Incremental Streaming.</strong> Subscribe to updates as your functions progress in the background worker.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Example Use Cases:</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Fairness for Generative AI:</strong> Don't let busy users overwhelm your system. Hatchet lets you distribute requests to your workers fairly with configurable policies.</li>
<li><strong>Batch Processing for Document Indexing:</strong> Hatchet can handle large-scale batch processing of documents, images, and other data and resume mid-job on failure.</li>
<li><strong>Workflow Orchestration for Multi-Modal Systems:</strong> Hatchet can handle orchestrating multi-modal inputs and outputs, with full DAG-style execution.</li>
<li><strong>Correctness for Event-Based Processing:</strong> Respond to external events or internal events within your system and replay events automatically.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick Start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick Start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Hatchet supports your technology stack with open-source SDKs for Python, Typescript, and Go. To get started, see the Hatchet documentation <a href="https://docs.hatchet.run/home/quickstart" rel="nofollow">here</a>, or check out our quickstart repos:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet-go-quickstart">Go SDK Quickstart</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet-python-quickstart">Python SDK Quickstart</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet-typescript-quickstart">Typescript SDK Quickstart</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">SDK repositories</h3><a id="user-content-sdk-repositories" aria-label="Permalink: SDK repositories" href="#sdk-repositories"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Hatchet comes with a native Go SDK. The following SDKs are also available:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/hatchet-dev/hatchet-typescript">Typescript SDK</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">If you encounter any issues with the SDKs, please submit an issue in the respective repository.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Is there a managed cloud version of Hatchet?</h4><a id="user-content-is-there-a-managed-cloud-version-of-hatchet" aria-label="Permalink: Is there a managed cloud version of Hatchet?" href="#is-there-a-managed-cloud-version-of-hatchet"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Yes, we are offering a have a cloud version to select companies while in beta who are helping to build and shape the product. Please <a href="mailto:contact@hatchet.run">reach out</a> or <a href="https://hatchet.run/request-access" rel="nofollow">request access</a> for more information.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Is there a self-hosted version of Hatchet?</h4><a id="user-content-is-there-a-self-hosted-version-of-hatchet" aria-label="Permalink: Is there a self-hosted version of Hatchet?" href="#is-there-a-self-hosted-version-of-hatchet"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Yes, instructions for self-hosting our open source docker containers can be found in our <a href="https://docs.hatchet.run/self-hosting/docker-compose" rel="nofollow">documentation</a>. Please <a href="mailto:contact@hatchet.run">reach out</a> if you're interested in support.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How does this compare to alternatives (Celery, BullMQ)?</h2><a id="user-content-how-does-this-compare-to-alternatives-celery-bullmq" aria-label="Permalink: How does this compare to alternatives (Celery, BullMQ)?" href="#how-does-this-compare-to-alternatives-celery-bullmq"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Why build another managed queue? We wanted to build something with the benefits of full transactional enqueueing - particularly for dependent, DAG-style execution - and felt strongly that Postgres solves for 99.9% of queueing use-cases better than most alternatives (Celery uses Redis or RabbitMQ as a broker, BullMQ uses Redis). Since the introduction of <code>SKIP LOCKED</code> and the milestones of recent PG releases (like active-active replication), it's becoming more feasible to horizontally scale Postgres across multiple regions and vertically scale to 10k TPS or more. Many queues (like BullMQ) are built on Redis and data loss can occur when suffering OOM if you're not careful, and using PG helps avoid an entire class of problems.</p>
<p dir="auto">We also wanted something that was significantly easier to use and debug for application developers. A lot of times the burden of building task observability falls on the infra/platform team (for example, asking the infra team to build a Grafana view for their tasks based on exported prom metrics). We're building this type of observability directly into Hatchet.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Issues</h2><a id="user-content-issues" aria-label="Permalink: Issues" href="#issues"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please submit any bugs that you encounter via Github issues. However, please reach out on <a href="https://discord.gg/ZMeUafwH89" rel="nofollow">Discord</a> before submitting a feature request - as the project is very early, we'd like to build a solid foundation before adding more complex features.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">I'd Like to Contribute</h2><a id="user-content-id-like-to-contribute" aria-label="Permalink: I'd Like to Contribute" href="#id-like-to-contribute"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See the contributing docs <a href="https://docs.hatchet.run/contributing" rel="nofollow">here</a>, and please let us know what you're interesting in working on in the #contributing channel on <a href="https://discord.gg/ZMeUafwH89" rel="nofollow">Discord</a>. This will help us shape the direction of the project and will make collaboration much easier!</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>