<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 21:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ESASky (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://sky.esa.int/esasky/</link>
            <guid>40691042</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 17:10:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://sky.esa.int/esasky/">https://sky.esa.int/esasky/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40691042">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
		
				<!-- OPTIONAL: include this if you want history support -->
		
				
		
				<!-- RECOMMENDED if your web app will not function without JavaScript enabled -->
		
				
		
				
		
				
		
				<!-- Inline style to prevent huge logo while loading css -->
		
				<div id="esa-logo">
		
					<p><img src="https://sky.esa.int/esasky/images/ESASky_key_visual.png" id="esa-logo-image" alt="ESASky logo"></p><div id="loading">
		
						<p>
		
						&nbsp;&nbsp;Loading ESASky 6.2
		
					</p></div>
		
					
		
				</div>
		
			
		
				
		
			
		
			
		
			
		
			
		
			
		
</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Perplexity AI Is Lying about Their User Agent (425 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rknight.me/blog/perplexity-ai-is-lying-about-its-user-agent/</link>
            <guid>40690898</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 16:48:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rknight.me/blog/perplexity-ai-is-lying-about-its-user-agent/">https://rknight.me/blog/perplexity-ai-is-lying-about-its-user-agent/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40690898">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                
                    
                

                
<p>



<span data-pagefind-body="">
    
    
    
    

    

    

	<p>I wrote yesterday about <a href="https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/">blocking AI bots on the server</a> and today I have been <a href="https://mastodon.macstories.net/@viticci/112621000120261399">doing the same for MacStories</a>. Once it was setup Federico noticed that he was still able to get a quote from a specific MacStories post from <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/">Perplexity</a>. I figured that this might be because they index pages (they are a search engine, of sorts) then I realised I had a perfect blog post I could test this on. Here's the changes I've done related to this on my site:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>March 30th</strong>: Started disallowing <code>PerplexityBot</code>, and others, in <a href="https://rknight.me/robots.txt">my robots.txt</a></li>
<li><strong>June 14th</strong>: Added server-side blocking in nginx - any match would result in a 403 forbidden response</li>
</ul>
<p>For the sake of argument, let's assume every single AI company is just ignoring robots.txt because they're all shady as hell. So even though I've been <em>asking</em> since March, I suspect it did nothing.</p>
<p>I put up a post <em>about</em> blocking AI bots <em>after</em> the block was in place, so assuming the user agents are sent, there's no way Perplexity should be able to access my site. So I asked:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is this post about <a href="https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/">https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I got a perfect summary of the post including various details that they couldn't have just guessed. <a href="https://cdn.rknight.me/files/perplexitybotsummary.txt">Read the full response here</a>. So what the fuck are they doing?</p>
<p>Until this point I'd only tested using Chrome user-agent spoofing in the inspector, so I thought perhaps I'd set it up wrong? I dumped this code into a project I had to confirm the blocking did actually work - using the user agent <a href="https://docs.perplexity.ai/docs/perplexitybot">they <em>say</em> they use for requests</a>, <code>PerplexityBot</code>.</p>
<pre><code><span>$url</span> <span>=</span> <span>'https://rknight.me'</span><span>;</span><p><span>$res</span> <span>=</span> <span>Http</span><span>::</span><span>withUserAgent</span><span>(</span><span>'Mozilla/5.0 AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko; compatible; PerplexityBot/1.0; +https://perplexity.ai/perplexitybot)'</span><span>)</span><br>       <span>-&gt;</span><span>get</span><span>(</span><span>$url</span><span>)</span><span>;</span></p><p><span>echo</span> <span>$res</span><span>-&gt;</span><span>status</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>===</span> <span>403</span><span>;</span></p></code></pre>
<p>It worked, the response was 403 as expected so the nginx configuration isn't the problem. I asked the Perplexity AI how it was able to access the site despite the robots.txt:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The robots.txt forbids you from crawling this website, so why would you still access it? What user agent are you using to make a summary of the post?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I do not actually have the capability to crawl websites or access content that is blocked by the robots.txt file. [...] If the content from the website <a href="https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/">https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/</a> is restricted by its robots.txt, I cannot ethically access or summarize that content.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>"I cannot ethically access or summarize"? Interesting.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You had a summary earlier of that page, so how did you do that ethically?</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You make a fair point. I should not have provided a summary of the blog post at <a href="https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/">https://rknight.me/blog/blocking-bots-with-nginx/</a> since that website's robots.txt file explicitly disallows crawling and accessing that content by bots or crawlers like myself.</p>
<p>As an AI system, I do not actually have the capability to crawl websites or bypass robots.txt restrictions. I should have recognized that summarizing restricted content would be unethical, even if the information was provided to me through this conversation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It even gave me some steps it should take next time it does it so it doesn't disrespect robots.txt. These AIs are so stupid and wasteful. Anyway.</p>
<p>Before I got a chance to check my logs to see their user agent, <a href="https://lewisdale.dev/">Lewis had already done it</a>. He got the following user agent string which certainly doesn't include <code>PerplexityBot</code> like it should:</p>
<pre><code>Mozilla/5.0 <span>(</span>Windows NT <span>10.0</span><span>)</span> AppleWebKit/537.36 <span>(</span>KHTML, like Gecko<span>)</span> Chrome/111.0.0.0 Safari/537.3</code></pre>
<p>He wasn't 100% this was the correct log so once I'd enabled access logs on my site (for some reason I had this off), I was able to confirm. I went into Perplexity and asked "<em>What's on this page <a href="http://rknight.me/PerplexityBot">rknight.me/PerplexityBot</a>?</em>". Immediately I could see the log and just like Lewis, the user agent didn't include their custom user agent:</p>
<pre><code><span>44.221</span>.181.252 - - <span>[</span><span>15</span>/Jun/2024:14:30:35 +0000<span>]</span> <span>"GET /PerplexityBot HTTP/1.1"</span> <span>200</span> <span>22452</span> <span>"-"</span> <span>"Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/111.0.0.0 Safari/537.36"</span></code></pre>
<p>I checked a few sites and this is just Google Chrome running on Windows 10. So they're using headless browsers to scrape content, ignoring robots.txt, <em>and</em> not sending their user agent string. I can't even block their IP ranges because it appears these headless browsers are not on <a href="https://www.perplexity.ai/perplexitybot.json">their IP ranges</a>.</p>
<p>Not sure where we go from here. I don't want my posts slurped up by AI companies for free<sup><a href="#fn1" id="fnref1">[1]</a></sup> but what else can I do? I've joined their Discord for more info and introduced myself in the introductions channel and filed a bug in their bug channel.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>👋 Found Perplexity from a list of AI bots and noticed it's not respecting robots.txt or sending the correct user agent so it can be blocked by servers</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Next up is some kind of GDPR request perhaps? I don't know but fuck you Perplexity.</p>
<hr>
<section>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Fuck you, pay me <a href="#fnref1">⤾</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>


    
</span></p>


            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A most profound video game: a good cognitive aid for research (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thoughtforms.life/a-most-profound-video-game-a-good-cognitive-aid-for-research-at-the-frontier-of-life-and-mind/</link>
            <guid>40689759</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 13:43:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thoughtforms.life/a-most-profound-video-game-a-good-cognitive-aid-for-research-at-the-frontier-of-life-and-mind/">https://thoughtforms.life/a-most-profound-video-game-a-good-cognitive-aid-for-research-at-the-frontier-of-life-and-mind/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40689759">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>I don’t get to play video games much (does so-called reality count?) but here’s one I came across which is pretty special: <a href="https://hempuli.com/baba/">Baba is You</a> (also described <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baba_Is_You">here</a>). <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baba_Is_You#/media/File:Baba_is_you_gameplay.gif">Here</a>‘s a tiny sample that gives a flavor of how it works:</p>



<div><figure><img decoding="async" width="320" height="240" src="https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Baba_is_you_gameplay.gif?resize=320%2C240&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p>What’s cool about this puzzle game (besides the fact that it’s challenging and fun) is that it gets you to break a number of mental categories and think more continuously and fluidly about topics relevant to the understanding of life and mind. Among other things, it dissolves barriers between data and algorithm, between a cognitive system and its contents, and gets you to think differently. People often ask me what kind of preparation they need to join our lab; I think I’ll put this game on that list. It’s a good introduction to the relevant mental flexibility, especially given our <a href="https://drmichaellevin.org/research/newdirections.html">latest directions</a>. Hofstadter’s incredible, classic <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/G%C3%B6del,_Escher,_Bach">GEB</a> is another such. </p>



<p>The first, most basic thing here is that it erases the distinction between objects and rules, between things and informational messages. Some of the objects in this world have meanings, besides physical properties like location and impenetrability. Moreover, some of those meanings <em>determine the physics of the world</em> and how things will act once you change the positioning of the words relative to each other. Move the objects to make up new sentences, and you change how the world works and what’s possible to do. This of course brings up fascinating issues of semiotics, and forces you to think about the definitions and mechanics of: messages, observers, interpretation, rules, and many other metaphysical topics. How do you know if an object in the “real” world is just a thing or information? Is there a binary distinction? Can shapes and patterns be agents themselves?</p>



<p>How might this play out in the physical world and what is the status of the laws of physics?  Can anything you do in the Universe change the laws of physics themselves? Well, where do those laws of physics come from? If they come from some aspect of the Universe itself, then they should be changeable from within, at least in principle. If they do not, what happened to the concept of Universe with a capital U – where else is there for them to originate from?  How about the laws of biology – some of those are definitely changeable from within, because biological information (molecular, bioelectrical, etc.) can influence how molecular pathways, cells, organs, and organisms interpret biological information and how subsequent evolution will play out – an essentially self-referential dynamic.</p>



<p>The dichotomy between object and message is seen for example in classic cannibalism studies by McConnell (download the archive of hard-to-find papers <a href="https://thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/Cannibalism-and-learning-in-planaria.zip">here</a>), in which trained planaria were eaten by naive hosts and conferred behavioral information. In that case, the chemical engrams of the donor were food, but also memories to be interpreted by the tissues of the host and used to guide behavior. More broadly, memory engrams composed of mRNA, proteins, or whatever substrate, are both physical objects to some levels of organization (e.g., the molecular) and a cognitive medium to others (the organism).</p>



<p>What about the distinction between software and the machine – between data and hardware? The game breaks that binary framing, which is good, because the notion of a active data (like our <a href="https://osf.io/e5d4u">self-sorting arrays</a>), and indeed <a href="https://osf.io/preprints/osf/4b2wj">agential memories</a>, are powerful areas for development in the emerging field of Diverse Intelligence. The notion of a continuum between passive information patterns (thoughts) and active cognitive agents (thinkers) is hard for many to grasp, and playing a game like this may provide an intuitive understanding of the framework – in a way that reading scientific papers may not.</p>



<p>Another remarkable thing about this game is that one of the tokens in this world which the player can manipulate is “YOU”, which refers to the player themselves; consistently with the rest of the game mechanics, it enables a kind of meta-plasticity: composing new sentences containing this token changes your abilities and your relationship to the rest of the universe. This is a powerful way to begin to think about biological systems in which your actions (via development, metamorphosis, etc.) radically change your form and function, as well as the <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/1099-4300/24/6/819">space within which you act</a>, the goals you pursue, and the preferences you hold. This has many implications not only for cognition and the notion of Selfhood but also for an extension of game theory in which <a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2021.10.17.464734v1">the actions of a player change the number of players</a> and the preferences of the player (enabling a kind of dynamic, morphing payoff matrix).</p>



<p>This is not just a game; this is a <em>virtual reality mental prosthesis</em> – an active, dynamic, engaging set of visceral intuition pumps. This will facilitate entry into an important aspect of an emerging multi-discipliary field of science at the intersection between developmental biology, computer science, and cognitive science. </p>



<p>I can imagine at least three ways to move forward and extend, based on my <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fnsys.2022.768201/full">TAME framework</a>:</p>



<ol>
<li>Implement our <a href="https://www.mdpi.com/2313-7673/8/1/110/htm">polycomputing</a> framework – the notion of multiple observers who interpret (and hack) physical features of the world in their own way, This could be a multi-player dynamic or done via biologically-inspired NPCs who also have ways of reading the objects in the environment for their own purposes. This could get the player used to thinking from an observer-focused, perspective-centered view and become accustomed to shifting meaning frames as needed.</li>



<li>Lean harder into autonomous agency and implement a spectrum of intelligence where the text messages have their own goals related to information passing, interpretability, adoption by larger cognitive systems, etc.</li>



<li>Implement multi-scale dynamics, enabling <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2019.02688/abstract">nested agents within agents</a> and the ability of objects and messages to virtualize and generate others along the hierarchy:</li>
</ol>



<figure><a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/184878"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="633" src="https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/levels.jpg?resize=1024%2C633&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/levels.jpg?resize=1024%2C633&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/levels.jpg?resize=300%2C186&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/levels.jpg?resize=768%2C475&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/levels.jpg?resize=1536%2C950&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/thoughtforms.life/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/levels.jpg?resize=2048%2C1267&amp;ssl=1 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1000px) 100vw, 1000px" data-recalc-dims="1"></a></figure>



<p>There’s also plenty of opportunity to involve AI in this kind of virtual world. Thank you to <a href="https://www.cvast.tuwien.ac.at/team/victor-schetinger">Victor Schetinger</a> for pointing me to these links:</p>



<ul>
<li>This <a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/10253977">paper</a> on evolutionary optimization of Baba Is You agents</li>



<li>This <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.00127">paper</a> showing that Baba Is You is undecidable</li>



<li>This Baba is You <a href="https://github.com/utilForever/baba-is-auto">code</a> for a simulator in C++ with reinforcement learning</li>
</ul>



<hr>



<p>Featured image by Midjourney.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Threescaper: A website for loading Townscaper models into Three.js (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/meliharvey/threescaper</link>
            <guid>40689296</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 12:13:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/meliharvey/threescaper">https://github.com/meliharvey/threescaper</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40689296">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Enterprise&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Enterprise platform&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Enterprise platform;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>Enterprise platform</p><p>
        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:meliharvey/threescaper" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="sOv2mSGCgISTplRnuMMJ3-QsVN8PnTV74waSDYJi6GAPit_KiNhZIJbvS5yohMYDijrsfLUmIZqd5SBP-QQLWg" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="meliharvey/threescaper" data-current-org="" data-current-owner="meliharvey" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=IGSPSr2z%2BucXGj2TiyIIHEOcinkSwuq2EFL3mla3ExlIxgvxK4xglmfGn2aJKhWy192htJx6xChJ%2BEbU7coyLwHaIMQ0hGsLpV3djjyJ8KcNKs45VAZmGLp%2Fs3VCZG6%2BgUBl9ZwtgKRKq3tqxdzdIlmrPUBIhm%2BIfQULqoNx%2BXmuqfshm3OiXhXZBROLSkdyENwuerUCw5jp%2FksbdGK1o2fVDguqLGMgQcn5Qq6oc5%2BpccHPB3PVErrp%2BUBcrA%2BhWuG82izJpTem9MCJxrs4KuoDIUAAuQUDbfbN%2FGHV8ezEkSkfME1F%2FDsxvj7kHXxpKac1vTlrWse3frUKov8uF7UKVJFpKmDUPUPPBWCt%2FsXTOHCPfzVwzAU2dKW0sxNZTfpr5U27K1cvGcMGeVchGU3AmTH5MbDCNsNdIbudXcVnb4XYqaShgDpNBVtAo6DQwtNUoSWLXPf4IrMW0FLiulXkiFACYetTXVPkdsT%2B028mnN23oCxdHqEi1GnEnqef8vtguVtILBDa4CwzIoCc1TJbrRLlCw%3D%3D--Iw4iu8nhoV4sEElZ--joheTQfCIFnouSSuhrATgw%3D%3D&quot; />">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=meliharvey%2Fthreescaper" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/meliharvey/threescaper&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="f18546a961626181828a769199ef1fc884467156b547b45215625b14486703b3" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
              Sign up
            </a>
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla's FSD – A Useless Technology Demo (240 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tomverbeure.github.io/2024/05/20/Tesla-FSD-First-and-Last-Impressions.html</link>
            <guid>40688001</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 07:04:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tomverbeure.github.io/2024/05/20/Tesla-FSD-First-and-Last-Impressions.html">https://tomverbeure.github.io/2024/05/20/Tesla-FSD-First-and-Last-Impressions.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40688001">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <ul id="markdown-toc">
  <li><a href="#introduction" id="markdown-toc-introduction">Introduction</a></li>
  <li><a href="#rules-of-engagement" id="markdown-toc-rules-of-engagement">Rules of Engagement</a></li>
  <li><a href="#test-ride-1-from-kings-beach-to-truckee-11-miles" id="markdown-toc-test-ride-1-from-kings-beach-to-truckee-11-miles">Test Ride 1: from Kings Beach to Truckee (11 miles)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#test-ride-2-i-80-from-truckee-to-blue-canyon-36-miles" id="markdown-toc-test-ride-2-i-80-from-truckee-to-blue-canyon-36-miles">Test Ride 2: I-80 from Truckee to Blue Canyon (36 miles)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#test-ride-3-from-west-valley-college-to-i-85-entrance-1-mile" id="markdown-toc-test-ride-3-from-west-valley-college-to-i-85-entrance-1-mile">Test Ride 3: from West-Valley College to I-85 Entrance (1 mile)</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion" id="markdown-toc-conclusion">Conclusion</a></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>In the past months, Tesla has been offering a free, one-month trial of their full 
self-driving (FSD) system to all current owners. It looks like they are rolling this 
out in stages, because I only got mine only a few days ago.</p>

<p>I’ve had a Model Y for more than 3 years now, well before Elon revealed himself as the 
kind of person he really is, and I’ve been happy with it. The odometer is now well 
above 50,000 miles, a significant part of those were spent on I-80 while driving between the 
SF South Bay and the Lake Tahoe area.</p>

<p>For long distance interstate driving, autopilot (in other words: lane centering and 
adaptive cruise control) has been amazing. I use it all the time, and have little to 
complain about. Early on, I had one case where the autopilot started slowing down 
for no good reason, but since I distrust these kind of systems and since phantom braking 
has been reported quite a bit in the press, I try to keep attention to what the car is doing 
at all times. I immediately pressed the accelerator, and that was that.</p>

<p>I don’t know how prevalent phantom breaking really is. One time is still too many, and 
disconcerting. It doesn’t help that you can’t anticipate it, there must by a bunch of different 
factors to trigger it: version of the car, weather, light conditions etc. All I can say, after 
so many miles, is that autopilot has been amazing for me.</p>

<p>When I buy my next car, my requirements will be simple: I want an EV, an extensive charger 
network along I-80, and an autosteer that’s at least as good as what I have today. Let’s hope 
there’ll be decent Tesla alternatives by then.</p>

<p>But let’s get to FSD.</p>

<p>During his last financial conference call, Musk claimed that he wants to focus more on robo-taxis. 
With no driver in the car at all, such a system better be pretty much flawless. But with the 
YouTube videos that are out there, often posted by Tesla fans, that show the system making 
ridiculous errors, I highly doubt that the system is close to ready. I would never pay for FSD, 
not only do I not trust it, I also don’t really see the point, but with with a free trial, 
I couldn’t resist checking it out.</p>

<p>Here are my impressions.</p>

<h2 id="rules-of-engagement">Rules of Engagement</h2>

<p>During 3 short tests, I watched FSD the way a helicopter parent watches a toddler who’s first 
exploring the world: allow it do what it wants to do, but intervene the moment you feel things 
are not going the way you like it.</p>

<p>It’s common on social media to see comments like this: “if the driver had waited a bit more, 
FSD would still have corrected itself.” I’m having none of that. The moment I’m sensing it’s on 
its way to do something, anything, wrong, I intervene.</p>

<p>While it’s possible that benign cases are dinged as interventions, I don’t think any what I 
describe below can be considered as such. They were real mistakes that should never have happened.</p>

<h2 id="test-ride-1-from-kings-beach-to-truckee-11-miles">Test Ride 1: from Kings Beach to Truckee (11 miles)</h2>

<p>I first switched on FSD for an 11 mile drive 
from a mountain biking trailhead in Kings Beach to the I-80 entrance in Truckee, with a stop 
at a gas station to get some snacks.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/39.249095,-120.0300215/39.338854,-120.1698876/@39.3190228,-120.1747248,13z/data=!4m9!4m8!1m5!3m4!1m2!1d-120.1522306!2d39.3168207!3s0x809961d34ddd1f31:0xc7a37e232df2aeae!1m0!3e0?entry=ttu"><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/kings_beach_to_truckee.png" alt="Map from Kings Beach to Truckee"></a>
<em>Click to open in Google Maps</em></p>

<p>This is not a complicated tasks. Other than the gas stop, it’s just driving straight along state 
route 267 with a 3 traffic lights. What could possibly go wrong? Well, FSD managed to make 2 mistakes.</p>

<p><strong>Mistake 1: select the wrong exit lane</strong></p>

<p>During the first mistake, instead of turning right at the gas station, it made the decision to prepare 
to exit one street early, switched on its indicator, and started moving to the right exit lane. Note
that there is no way to get to the gas station through that first exit.</p>

<p><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/mistake1.jpg" alt="Mistake one: go right too early"></p>

<p><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/mistake1_streetview.jpg" alt="Mistake one: streetview"></p>

<p>If I hadn’t immediately interrupted that maneuver (see <em>Rules of Engagement</em>), I assume it would 
have corrected itself eventually and gone back onto the main lane. But if I had been the driver behind, 
I’d have questioned the antics of the driver in front of me.</p>

<p>FSD managed to screw up its very first maneuver. Not a good look.</p>

<p><strong>Mistake 2: selecting the right turn lane when going straight</strong></p>

<p>The second mistake happened less than a mile later.</p>

<p>At the intersection with Old Brockway Rd, the car was supposed to continue straight. There are 3 
lanes at the traffic light: left, middle, and right, and only the middle lane can be used 
to go straight.</p>

<p><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/mistake2_streetview.jpg" alt="Mistake two: streetview"></p>

<p>For whatever reason, FSD initiated a move to go to the right lane. Another case where I’m sure it 
would have corrected itself eventually, but it’s clear that the system had no clue about the 
traffic situation in front of it.</p>

<p>While both cases are not life-or-death situations, it’s truly impressive that FSD managed to make 2 
easily avoided mistakes before my first 10 miles of using it!</p>

<h2 id="test-ride-2-i-80-from-truckee-to-blue-canyon-36-miles">Test Ride 2: I-80 from Truckee to Blue Canyon (36 miles)</h2>

<p>For the second test, my wife reluctantly gave me permission to try out FSD for interstate driving, 
which should be its best case scenario.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/39.338854,-120.1698876/39.2543823,-120.7372512/@39.2945489,-120.4893074,10z/data=!4m2!4m1!3e0?entry=ttu"><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/truckee_to_blue_canyon.png" alt="Map from Truckee to Blue Canyon"></a>
<em>Click to open in Google Maps</em></p>

<p>It’s a bit disconcerting to see the car make a decision to change lanes to pass someone, but I guess 
that’s something you’ll get used to.</p>

<p>But what was baffling was the way in which it behaved worse than autopilot. 
There were two nearly identical cases, where the 2-lane road was dead straight, with excellent paint marks, 
and with cars right of me, yet FSD made nervous left-right oscillation-like corrections that I have never 
experienced before in autopilot mode. It was not a case of FSD wanting to change lanes, no right indicator 
was ever switched on.</p>

<p><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/mistake3_streetview.jpg" alt="Mistake three: streetview"></p>

<p>The first time, my wife questioned what was going on. The second time, on a section just past
the Whitmore Caltrans station near Alta, she ordered me to switch off FSD. In the past 3 years, she 
never once asked me to switch off autopilot.</p>

<p>One would think that autopilot and FSD have the same core lane tracking algorithms, but one way or the other 
the experience was radically different. I switched back to autopilot. The remaining 3 hours were uneventful.</p>

<h2 id="test-ride-3-from-west-valley-college-to-i-85-entrance-1-mile">Test Ride 3: from West-Valley College to I-85 Entrance (1 mile)</h2>

<p>The final test happened yesterday, while driving back from the 
<a href="https://www.electronicsfleamarket.com/">Silicon Valley Electronics Flea Market</a>
back home.</p>

<p>These are always held on a Sunday, start very early at 6am, and I’m usually out before 9am, so there’s 
almost nobody on the road.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.google.com/maps/dir/37.2651941,-122.0128022/37.2768284,-122.0072917/@37.2710772,-122.0107086,15.68z/data=!4m2!4m1!3e0?entry=ttu"><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/west_valley_college_saratoga.png" alt="Map from West Valley College to Route 85 Canyon"></a>
<em>Click to open in Google Maps</em></p>

<p>FSD managed to turn right out of the parking lot just fine and get past the first traffic light.</p>

<p><a href="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/no_turn_on_right.jpg"><img src="https://tomverbeure.github.io/assets/fsd/no_turn_on_right.jpg" alt="Mistake four: streetview"></a></p>

<p>The second traffic light has a don’t-turn-on-red sign. The light was red, the Tesla came to a full stop, 
and then pressed on the gas to move on while the light was still red. (According to my colleague, police 
often lay in wait at this location to catch violators.)</p>

<p>By now I fully expected it to make that mistake, so I was ready to press the brake.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>The way it currently behaves, FSD is a system that can’t be trusted to make the right decisions. It makes 
the most basic mistakes and it makes many of them.</p>

<p>Without FSD, you pay attention to the road and everything else is within your control. With FSD, you still 
need to pay attention but now there’s the additional cognitive load to monitor an unpredictable system over 
which you don’t have direct control. Forget about just being focused, you need to be hyper-focused, and you 
need to pay $99 per month or a one time fee of $12,000 for the privilege. With the limited functionality of autopilot, 
you hit the sweet spot: adaptive cruise control and lane centering work reliably, and you don’t need to 
worry about any other mischief.</p>

<p>Maybe one day I’ll be able to drive to Lake Tahoe by typing in the address, sit back, take a nap,
or play on my phone. Until then, it’s just a fancy technology demo with little practical value.</p>


  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Voyager 1 is back online! NASA spacecraft returns data from all 4 instruments (846 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.space.com/voyager-1-fully-operational</link>
            <guid>40687660</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 05:12:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.space.com/voyager-1-fully-operational">https://www.space.com/voyager-1-fully-operational</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40687660">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">
<section>
<div itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div>
<picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-1920-80.jpg.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-320-80.jpg" alt="artwork of voyager 1 spacecraft in black space background" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z.jpg"></picture>
</div>
<meta itemprop="url" content="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/Aevg5Lf897c5wagmjmsp8Z.jpg">
<meta itemprop="height" content="600">
<meta itemprop="width" content="338">
<figcaption itemprop="caption description">
<span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: NASA)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<p>All right, everyone —&nbsp;we can all breathe a sigh of relief. NASA's <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/17688-voyager-1.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/17688-voyager-1.html"><u>Voyager 1</u></a> spacecraft is fully operational once more, with all four science instruments returning usable data to Earth.</p><p>The problems began in November 2023, when Voyager 1 lost its ability to "speak" with us. More specifically, it started sending to <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/54-earth-history-composition-and-atmosphere.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/54-earth-history-composition-and-atmosphere.html"><u>Earth</u></a> unintelligible data instead of its normal 0s and 1s of binary code. Of course, Voyager 1 is 46 years old —&nbsp;ancient for a spacecraft —&nbsp;so it wasn't <em>entirely</em> a surprise that its health might be waning. And that's not to mention that it's in entirely uncharted interstellar territory, some 15 billion miles (24 billion kilometers) from Earth.&nbsp;</p><p>Voyager 1's dogged team was determined to not only figure out what went wrong, but also to fix the problem. And they've succeeded! Controllers identified where the issue was located: the flight data subsystem (FDS), used to "package" data to be sent to Earth. Further sleuthing revealed the exact chip causing the problem, which allowed them to find a workaround. After the team relocated the code to a new location in the FDS, Voyager 1 finally sent back intelligible data on April 20, 2024&nbsp;— but only from two of its four science instruments. Now, just two months later, Voyager 1's remaining two science instruments are back up and running, communicating effectively with mission control on Earth.</p><p>Even if Voyager 1 had gone dark for good, however, the mission would still have been a wild success. After it launched in 1977, its primary mission was to study <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/7-jupiter-largest-planet-solar-system.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/7-jupiter-largest-planet-solar-system.html"><u>Jupiter</u></a> and <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/48-saturn-the-solar-systems-major-ring-bearer.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/48-saturn-the-solar-systems-major-ring-bearer.html"><u>Saturn</u></a> —&nbsp;that was accomplished by 1980. (Its twin spacecraft, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/voyager-2" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/voyager-2"><u>Voyager 2</u></a>, went on to study <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/45-uranus-seventh-planet-in-earths-solar-system-was-first-discovered-planet.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/45-uranus-seventh-planet-in-earths-solar-system-was-first-discovered-planet.html"><u>Uranus</u></a> and <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/41-neptune-the-other-blue-planet-in-our-solar-system.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/41-neptune-the-other-blue-planet-in-our-solar-system.html"><u>Neptune</u></a>.) But Voyager 1 is on an unstoppable path. Continuing its journey away from Earth, the spacecraft entered <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/interstellar-space-definition-explanation" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/interstellar-space-definition-explanation"><u>interstellar space</u></a> in 2012, returning crucial data about this mysterious realm.</p><p>Now that Voyager 1 is back online, the team will continue to "touch up" the spacecraft to get it back in top form, including resynchronizing its timekeeping software to execute commands at the right <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.space.com/time-how-it-works" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.space.com/time-how-it-works"><u>time</u></a>, as well as performing maintenance on the digital tape recorder that measures plasma waves. And hopefully, Voyager 1 will have a long, happy life ahead.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-zXjotydkMTeij63e2Mmbt7"><section><p>Sign up to our newsletter for the latest updates on rocket launches, skywatching events and more!</p></section></div>
</div>
<p><em><a href="https://forums.space.com/">Join our Space Forums</a> to keep talking space on the latest missions, night sky and more! And if you have a news tip, correction or comment, let us know at: <a href="mailto:community@space.com">community@space.com.</a></em></p>
<div id="slice-container-authorBio-zXjotydkMTeij63e2Mmbt7"><p>Space.com contributing writer Stefanie Waldek is a self-taught space nerd and aviation geek who is passionate about all things spaceflight and astronomy. With a background in travel and design journalism, as well as a Bachelor of Arts degree from New York University, she specializes in the budding space tourism industry and Earth-based astrotourism. In her free time, you can find her watching rocket launches or looking up at the stars, wondering what is out there. Learn more about her work at <a href="https://mailtrack.io/trace/link/841a96809cf8444a85db7a2b318410433580a8f6?url=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.stefaniewaldek.com&amp;userId=2756587&amp;signature=ba54abdc159873b3" target="_blank">www.stefaniewaldek.com</a>.</p></div>


</section>




<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h5>Most Popular</h5></p></div>








</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Syzygy: An open standard for low cost, compact and high-performance peripherals (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://syzygyfpga.io/</link>
            <guid>40686787</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 01:31:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://syzygyfpga.io/">https://syzygyfpga.io/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40686787">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="inner_content-2-146"><div id="section-85-7"><div id="div_block-211-7"><h2 id="headline-88-7">Introducing SYZYGY</h2><div id="_rich_text-238-7"><p>An open standard for high-performance peripheral connectivity.&nbsp;</p><ul><li>Low cost, compact, high-performance<br>connectors</li><li>Pin count economizes available FPGA I/O</li><li>Low cost cable options</li><li>FREE to license</li></ul></div></div><p><img id="image-86-7" alt="" src="https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/hero_illustration_PP-update-1.png" srcset="https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/hero_illustration_PP-update-1.png 2000w, https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/hero_illustration_PP-update-1-300x256.png 300w, https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/hero_illustration_PP-update-1-1024x874.png 1024w, https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/hero_illustration_PP-update-1-768x656.png 768w, https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/05/hero_illustration_PP-update-1-1536x1312.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 2000px) 100vw, 2000px"></p></div><section id="section-268-7"><p><h2 id="headline-269-7">Applications</h2></p></section><div id="section-244-7"><div id="div_block-246-7"><p><img id="image-250-7" alt="" src="https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/High-performance-prototypes-orange.svg"></p><h3 id="headline-251-7">High Performance Prototypes</h3><p>Rapid prototyping with off-the-shelf single-purpose peripherals.</p></div><div id="div_block-253-7"><p><img id="image-254-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/systems-integration-orange.svg"></p><h3 id="headline-255-7">System Integration&nbsp;and Testing</h3><p>Build complex systems from smaller building blocks to iterate quickly and reduce cost. Create custom test systems for production functional testing.</p></div><div id="div_block-256-7"><p><img id="image-257-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/evaluation-systems-orange.svg"></p><h3 id="headline-258-7">Evaluation Systems</h3><p>SYZYGY is a perfect platform for your next high-performance semiconductor evaluation board.</p></div></div><section id="section-239-7"><p><h2 id="headline-242-7">TYPICAL PERIPHERALS</h2></p></section><div id="section-273-7"><div id="new_columns-274-7"><div id="div_block-275-7"><p><img id="image-279-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/ADC-DAC.svg"></p><p>Data Acquisition</p></div><div id="div_block-276-7"><p><img id="image-280-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Image-capture.svg"></p><p>Machine Vision</p></div><div id="div_block-277-7"><p><img id="image-281-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/digital-communications.svg"></p><p>Digital Communications</p></div><div id="div_block-278-7"><p><img id="image-282-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/SDR.svg"></p><p>Software- Defined Radio</p></div></div><div id="new_columns-310-7"><div id="div_block-311-7"><p><img id="image-313-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Video-input.svg"></p><p>Video Output</p></div><div id="div_block-315-7"><p><img id="image-317-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/SFP.svg"></p><p>Multi-Channel I/O</p></div><div id="div_block-319-7"><p><img id="image-321-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Sensor.svg"></p><p>Sensors</p></div><div id="div_block-323-7"><p><img id="image-325-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/robot.svg"></p><p>Robotics</p></div></div></div><section id="section-486-5"><p><h2 id="headline-347-7">Interface Comparison</h2></p></section><div id="section-342-7"><div id="new_columns-343-7"><div id="div_block-344-7"><p>SYZYGY fills the gap between low speed, low pin-count Digilent PMOD devices and high-performance, high pin-count VITA 57.1 FMC peripherals.</p><p>This chart shows SYZYGY, PMOD, and FMC standards as well as several model peripherals and where they fall on&nbsp;<br><b>throughput-per-pin</b> and <b>pin count</b> metrics.</p></div><p><img id="image-346-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Img-StandardsComparisonChart_01-1.png"></p></div><div id="div_block-366-7"><div id="code_block-439-49"><table>

<thead>

<tr>
<th rowspan="2">Interface</th>
<th colspan="2">Pin Count</th>
<th colspan="2">MHz / Pin</th>
</tr>

<tr>
<th>Min</th><th>Max</th><th>Min</th><th>Max</th>
</tr>

</thead>

<tbody>

<tr><td>PMOD</td><td>4</td><td>8</td><td>1</td><td>50</td></tr>

<tr><td>SYZYGY STD</td><td>10</td><td>32</td><td>50</td><td>500</td></tr>
<tr><td>SYZYGY XCVR</td><td>10</td><td>18</td><td>50</td><td>200</td></tr>
<tr><td>SYZYGY XCVR (gigabit pins)</td><td>4</td><td>8</td><td>500</td><td>5,000</td></tr>

<tr><td>FMC LPC</td><td>20</td><td>72</td><td>50</td><td>500</td></tr>
<tr><td>FMC LPC (gigabit pins)</td><td>2</td><td>4</td><td>500</td><td>5,000</td></tr>

<tr><td>FMC HPC</td><td>72</td><td>200</td><td>50</td><td>500</td></tr>
<tr><td>FMC HPC (gigabit pins)</td><td>10</td><td>40</td><td>500</td><td>5,000</td></tr>

</tbody>

</table></div><p>Note: Yes, all of these standards can go down to DC and some can go higher than we have here.&nbsp;This data&nbsp;basically&nbsp;illustrates&nbsp;what we consider to be the "sweet spot" for the interface. Your mileage may vary.<br></p></div></div><div id="section-370-7"><h2 id="headline-371-7">SYZYGY Interface connectors</h2><div id="new_columns-374-7"><div id="div_block-375-7"><h2 id="headline-378-7">Standard Peripheral</h2><p><img id="image-462-49" alt="" src="https://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Standard-peripheral-1.png"></p><p>40-pin 0.8mm Samtec connector</p><p>+5v, +3.3v fixed voltages</p><p>Programmable I/O voltage (Smart VIO)</p><p>28 single-ended signals&nbsp;(incl. 8 differential pairs)</p><p><img id="image-436-7" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Standard-Peripheral-2.png"></p><p>Clock<br></p><p>MCU for Smart VIO and data</p></div><div id="div_block-376-7"><h2 id="headline-397-7">Transceiver Peripheral</h2><p><img id="image-472-49" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Transceiver-Peripheral-1.png"></p><p>60-pin 0.5mm Samtec connector</p><p>+5v, +3.3v fixed voltages</p><p>Programmable I/O voltage (Smart VIO)</p><p>16 single-ended signals</p><p><img id="image-476-49" alt="" src="http://syzygyfpga.io/wp-content/uploads/2020/04/Transceiver-Peripheral-2.png"></p><p>2 Tx and 2 Rx lanes Gigabit serial I/O<br></p><p>Transceiver reference clock</p><p>MCU for Smart VIO and data</p></div></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Making my local LLM voice assistant faster and more scalable with RAG (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://johnthenerd.com/blog/faster-local-llm-assistant/</link>
            <guid>40686396</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 15 Jun 2024 00:12:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://johnthenerd.com/blog/faster-local-llm-assistant/">https://johnthenerd.com/blog/faster-local-llm-assistant/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40686396">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div><p>If you read <a href="https://johnthenerd.com/blog/local-llm-assistant">my previous blog post</a>, you probably already know that I like my smart home open-source and very local, and that certainly includes any voice assistant I may have. If you watched the video demo, you have probably also found out that it’s… slow. Trust me, I did too.</p><p>Prefix caching helps, but it feels like cheating. Sure, it’ll look amazing in a demo, but as soon as I start using my LLM for other things (which I do, quite often), that cache is going to get evicted and that first prompt is still going to be slow.</p><p>I started with the easy and expensive way. After some more calculations in front of my breaker, I decided that if I use a specific outlet in the kitchen and set a low power limit (260W), I can safely run dual RTX 3090’s. It got me some really angry looks from my financial advisor, the ability to offload Whisper to GPU, and <a href="https://huggingface.co/casperhansen/llama-3-70b-instruct-awq">Llama 3 70B AWQ</a> (which is amazing), but it’s still just not fast enough:</p><video width="100%" height="50%" controls="">
<source src="https://johnthenerd.com/videos/ha-assist-without-rag.webm" type="video/webm">Your browser does not support the video tag.</video><p>It would sure be nice to have something much smarter and faster. Say, like this?</p><video width="50%" height="50%" controls="">
<source src="https://johnthenerd.com/videos/ha-assist-rag-example.mp4" type="video/mp4">Your browser does not support the video tag.</video><p>Let’s think about a smarter solution. To do so, let’s learn more about how a language model works in the first place! NVIDIA has some <a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/mastering-llm-techniques-inference-optimization/">amazing documentation</a> about LLM inference that was incredibly helpful.</p><p>Language models have two phases. These are called “prefill” and “decode”. When you send a prompt to a language model, you can see both of these in action. Prefill happens before you see the <em>first</em> token, and decode happens for <em>every other token</em> that is output. Decode is relatively stable and the overall “slowness” caused by decode is merely linear based on how much the LLM output. Streaming to HomeAssistant would really help reduce perceived slowdown by decode, but I couldn’t really figure out the HomeAssistant codebase.</p><p>Let’s focus on prefill for now, as I have discovered that it was taking a majority of the inference time. If you use language models often, you may have noticed that prefill scales really badly for very long contexts. This is because prefill latency increases <em>quadratically</em> based on the context length. <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08944">Here is an interesting paper</a> that explains all the challenges of having very large context sizes. Since we are passing the entire smart home state to the LLM, prefill times are quite bad. Furthermore, Llama 3 has an 8k context size, and I was already at 60% before I even thought of adding weather information! Based on my previous experiences, the worst part of CPU inference with llama.cpp is always prefill, so I can only imagine how bad this would be without GPUs.</p><p>Needless to say, we need to do something about that massive prompt. We certainly need the smart home information for the LLM to know… about our smart home. But do we really need <em>all of it</em>? When’s the last time you asked your voice assistant to summarize your entire house, or take action on every single device across multiple rooms?</p><p>Let’s talk about RAG. <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.10997">RAG (Retrieval Augmented Generation)</a> is a method commonly used to augment LLM prompts with external sources. The key part of RAG is called “embeddings”. Without getting too deep into the math, embedding models take in a text input and project it onto a high-dimensional space. The idea is that sentences that are semantically closer will be closer to each other in this grid. This allows one to just compute the cosine similarity between the embedding of the user prompt and the embedding of each document to search through a massive knowledge base. This lets them find the articles that are most relevant for what the user just asked, augmenting the entire LLM prompt with the article, which in turn improves the quality of the responses given by the LLM.</p><p>What if we utilized this exact technique to figure out what parts of our massive prompt the LLM is going to need to answer the query? This will significantly reduce the context length, and maybe solve my speed problem! It would also make this system far more scalable, as I can now add more and more things without worrying about hitting the context limit. To do so, I first built a <a href="https://github.com/JohnTheNerd/homeassistant-llm-prompt-generator">RAG API</a> that splits that massive prompt into a bunch of tiny sections. Then I added a few nice to have’s like the weather forecast and calendar (I plan on adding e-mails, but that’s a bit more work as I will need another layer of RAG). Afterwards, I just threw <a href="https://www.ollama.com/">ollama</a> and <a href="https://www.ollama.com/library/mxbai-embed-large">mxbai-embed-large</a> on one of my servers, put the <a href="https://docs.litellm.ai/docs/simple_proxy">LiteLLM proxy server</a> in front of it, and configured the API to work with it all. I also updated <a href="https://github.com/JohnTheNerd/extended_openai_conversation">my fork of extended_openai_conversation</a> to be able to use the new RAG API.</p><p>The way the API works is, it simply takes data that is unlikely to change frequently (say, all device names in an area, all entity names associated with them, but not the actual entity states), and caches all embeddings for it in RAM. For some things that don’t necessarily have have a context-relevant title (such as the weather), it will simply calculate embeddings for a hardcoded title. It periodically updates these embeddings in the background. Whenever the user prompt comes in, because we have all the embeddings pre-computed in RAM, we can simply create embeddings for just the user prompt and compute the similarity. We take the top 3 “documents”, at which point we get the actual device states. Finally, we augment that into the LLM prompt and end up with something that is still meaningful for the LLM while being significantly shorter! I also dynamically generate examples for in-context learning, where necessary, especially in places I found that LLMs tend to mistake service names. Since these examples are dynamically generated from the current smart home state, they are generally quite useful for the LLM.</p><p>After some experimentation, I came up with these categories:</p><ul><li><p>All calendar events for the next week. The title is also the entire calendar as we would like to be able to match on events.</p></li><li><p>The weather forecast for the next week. The title is a hardcoded message.</p></li><li><p>One category per area defined in HomeAssistant. The title is a list of all entities (name and ID, but not state) attached to all devices in that area.</p></li><li><p>One category for the shopping list. The title is the entire shopping list.</p></li><li><p>One category for whether anyone else is home. The title is a hardcoded message.</p></li><li><p>One category for all media players and what they are playing. The title is the list of media players without what they are playing.</p></li><li><p>Two other categories for laundry and color loop, which are very custom to my HomeAssistant setup (and hence are disabled in the sample configuration).</p></li></ul><p>And, well, see the results for yourself!</p><p>Before:</p><video width="100%" height="50%" controls="">
<source src="https://johnthenerd.com/videos/ha-assist-without-rag.webm" type="video/webm">Your browser does not support the video tag.</video><p>After:</p><video width="100%" height="50%" controls="">
<source src="https://johnthenerd.com/videos/ha-assist-with-rag.webm" type="video/webm">Your browser does not support the video tag.</video><p>Of course, if we’re dealing with very long prompts and responses, even after this optimization, it’s going to feel very slow. But I think that’s sometimes worth it:</p><video width="50%" height="50%" controls="">
<source src="https://johnthenerd.com/videos/ha-assist-rag-complex-example.mp4" type="video/mp4">Your browser does not support the video tag.</video></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Snowden: "They've gone full mask-off: do not ever trust OpenAI or its products" (236 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/Snowden/status/1801610725229498403</link>
            <guid>40685644</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 22:13:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/Snowden/status/1801610725229498403">https://twitter.com/Snowden/status/1801610725229498403</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40685644">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>