<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 04:30:06 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hedge Funds Are Pocketing Much of Their Clients' Gains with 'No Limit' Fees (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2025-hedge-fund-investment-fees/</link>
            <guid>43006390</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 22:57:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2025-hedge-fund-investment-fees/">https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2025-hedge-fund-investment-fees/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43006390">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.bloomberg.com/graphics/2025-hedge-fund-investment-fees/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Elon Musk-Led Group Makes $97.4B Bid for Control of OpenAI (563 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/tech/elon-musk-openai-bid-4af12827</link>
            <guid>43004889</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 20:42:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/elon-musk-openai-bid-4af12827">https://www.wsj.com/tech/elon-musk-openai-bid-4af12827</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43004889">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/tech/elon-musk-openai-bid-4af12827: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kaspersky finds hardware backdoor in 5 generations of Apple Silicon (2024) (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.xstore.co.za/stuff/2024/01/kaspersky-finds-hardware-backdoor-in-5-generations-of-apple-silicon/</link>
            <guid>43003230</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 18:07:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.xstore.co.za/stuff/2024/01/kaspersky-finds-hardware-backdoor-in-5-generations-of-apple-silicon/">https://www.xstore.co.za/stuff/2024/01/kaspersky-finds-hardware-backdoor-in-5-generations-of-apple-silicon/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43003230">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>Audio transcript</p>



<figure><audio controls="" src="https://www.xstore.co.za/stuff/wp-content/uploads/2024/01/triangulation1.mp3"></audio></figure>



<p>There are some readers here who will understand the import of the statement above and not believe it, and there are others who are not in a position to understand it all. For both camps, I’ll attempt to explain the details around what is (confirmed and corroborated by others) arguably one of the most critical security events to happen in the last decade of IT security.</p>



<p>What’s completely astonishing is the almost complete lack of media coverage (ARS Technica alone did a great piece) of this issue since its announcement by Kaspersky on the 27th of Dec 2023. Is this due to the holiday period (news of the original Meltdown and Spectre vulnerabilities was also released during the Dec/Jan holidays and seemed to have had a much greater reception in the media) or the fact that it’s Kaspersky (supposedly Russian-backed) that found and announced the issue?</p>



<p>No matter your thoughts on Kaspersky and its alleged ties to the Russian government, their research has been confirmed by others.</p>



<p>I reference information in this blog post from @sggrc’s <a href="https://www.grc.com/sn/SN-955-Notes.pdf">Security Now 955 show</a> as well as publicly available information from <a href="https://www.kaspersky.com/about/press-releases/2023_kaspersky-discloses-iphone-hardware-feature-vital-in-operation-triangulation-case">Kaspersky themselves</a> and other 3rd parties/media.</p>



<p><strong>Problem Statement</strong></p>



<p>Kaspersky has found a hardware/silicon-based backdoor in 5 generations of Apple mobile silicon, starting with the A12 CPU (iPhone X) and continuing to the A16 CPU (iPhone 14/15). These CPUs have been used in other Apple products like the iPad, Watch and TV, so the iPhone is not the only affected product.</p>



<p><em>This backdoor allows complete remote access to, and control of, the affected devices</em> … let that statement stew for a few minutes. And then understand that this allows a 3rd party to see and control anything on your Apple-based phone.</p>



<p><strong>History</strong></p>



<p>The issue now commonly referred to as CVE-2023-38606, was announced by Kasperky on Dec 27 2023. It refers to a hardware backdoor that was found in Apple CPUs designed and manufactured over a 5 year period. They state the following in their announcement:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The discovered vulnerability is a hardware feature, possibly based on the principle of <em>“</em>security through obscurity,” and may have been intended for testing or debugging. Following the initial 0-click iMessage attack and subsequent privilege escalation, the attackers leveraged this hardware feature to bypass hardware-based security protections and manipulate the contents of protected memory regions. This step was crucial for obtaining full control over the device. Apple addressed the issue, identified as <a href="https://nvd.nist.gov/vuln/detail/CVE-2023-38606">CVE-2023-38606</a>.</p>
<cite>ARS Technica</cite></blockquote>



<p>Like Steve Gibson on the SN podcast, I take issue with Kaspersky’s characterisation of this being a vulnerability, which infers a bug as a result of a mistake in coding or design. To be very clear here, this backdoor was NO mistake – it was intentionally designed into the CPU.</p>



<p>Nonetheless, it does not diminish the severity of the issue.</p>



<p>So how did Kaspersky find this issue?</p>



<p>They had been following the propagation of Operation Triangulation, an APT (<span>a</span>dvanced <span>p</span>ersistent <span>t</span>hreat or complex malware that involves multiple stages of infection and attack using a variety of methods) which targets iOS devices through zero-click exploits distributed through iMessage. In other words, no action needs to be taken by the victim – they simply need to receive the attack message to be compromised. And this attack effects any Bionic CPU-based product from iPhones all the way to Apple Watches.</p>



<p>In the process of tracking the Triangulation malware (<a href="https://securelist.com/operation-triangulation/109842/">more details here</a>), Kaspersky found that the method for the initial attack vector sourced from an <em>undocumented</em> hardware feature that few, if anyone, outside of Apple and chip suppliers such as ARM Holdings knew of.</p>



<p>There are 2 aspects of Triangulation to consider:</p>



<ul>
<li>how did the hardware backdoor come about?</li>



<li>how did the attackers know about the backdoor and come to use it in their malware?</li>
</ul>



<p><em>On the first question</em>, It’s quite impossible for Apple to not have known about the backdoor in a CPU that their own engineers designed. Or might one suggest the even more ludicrous possibility that there are chip designers within Apple that have ulterior motives and that have slipped a backdoor past development, design, QA and all the other steps required to bring a CPU to market?</p>



<p><em>On the 2nd point</em>, the task of finding the backdoor at all is made almost impossible by the complexity of the design of the backdoor (Apple are generally regarded as good and efficient at designing secure systems) – Steve Gibson goes through some aspects of the backdoor in SN 955, and specifically why it’s close to impossible to discover it without prior knowledge. So we can quite validly assume that the attackers did not discover or identify the backdoor themselves. We may never know then how they come to access the backdoor ….</p>



<p>Kaspersky says:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>The exploit’s sophistication and the feature’s obscurity suggest the attackers had advanced technical capabilities,” Kaspersky researcher Boris Larin wrote in an email. “Our analysis hasn’t revealed how they became aware of this feature, but we’re exploring all possibilities, including accidental disclosure in past firmware or source code releases. They may also have stumbled upon it through hardware reverse engineering.</p>
<cite>Kasperskey</cite></blockquote>



<p>But at minimum, it could be posited that Apple was required by some agency to create the backdoor for “purposes”. Lateral thinking commence …</p>



<p><strong>Overview of the attack</strong></p>



<p>Details disclosed by Kaspersky on Wednesday Dec 27th, said that “Triangulation”—the name Kaspersky gave to both the malware and the campaign that installed it—exploited four critical zero-day vulnerabilities, meaning serious programming flaws that were known to the attackers before they were known to Apple. These include:</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/103837">CVE-2023-32434</a></li>



<li><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT213676">CVE-2023-32435</a></li>



<li><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT213841">CVE-2023-38606</a></li>



<li><a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/HT213842">CVE-2023-41990</a></li>
</ul>



<p>Besides affecting iPhones, these critical zero-days and the secret hardware function resided in Macs, iPods, iPads, Apple TVs, and Apple Watches. What’s more, the exploits Kaspersky recovered were intentionally developed to work on those devices as well. Apple has patched those platforms as well. Apple declined to comment for this article.</p>



<ul>
<li>Kaspersky initially became aware of issue due to finding Triangulation malware on their own staff devices</li>



<li>Kaspersky’s researchers affirmatively and without question found a deliberately concealed, never documented, deliberately locked but unlockable with a secret hash, hardware backdoor which was designed into all Apple devices starting with the A12, A13, A14, A15 and A16</li>



<li>Triangulation attackers used the aforementioned 4 CVEs in an attack chain, along with the hardware backdoor capability under discussion here, to implement their zero-day 0-click malware</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>The technical details</strong> (gloss over or skip this if you’re not a programmer)</p>



<p>IANAP (I am not a programmer), but I’ll relay some of the technical details as described by @sggrc in SN 955.</p>



<ul>
<li>Attackers send a malicious iMessage attachment, which the application processes without showing any signs to the user</li>



<li>This attachment exploits the remote code execution vulnerability CVE-2023-41990 in the undocumented, Apple-only ADJUST TrueType font instruction. This instruction had existed since the early 90’s until a patch removed it.</li>



<li>It uses return/jump oriented programming and multiple stages written in the NSExpression/NSPredicate query language, patching the JavaScriptCore library environment to execute a privilege escalation exploit written in JavaScript</li>



<li>This JavaScript exploit is obfuscated to make it completely unreadable and to minimize its size. Still, it has around 11,000 lines of code, which are mainly dedicated to JavaScriptCore and kernel memory parsing and manipulation.</li>



<li>It exploits the JavaScriptCore debugging feature DollarVM ($vm) to gain the ability to manipulate JavaScriptCore’s memory from the script and execute native API functions</li>



<li>It was designed to support both old and new iPhones and included a Pointer Authentication Code (PAC) bypass for exploitation of recent models</li>



<li>It uses the integer overflow vulnerability CVE-2023-32434 in XNU’s memory mapping syscalls to obtain read/write access to the entire physical memory of the device</li>



<li>It uses hardware memory-mapped I/O (MMIO) registers to bypass the Page Protection Layer (PPL). This was mitigated as CVE-2023-38606</li>



<li>After exploiting all the vulnerabilities, the JavaScript exploit can do whatever it wants to the device including running spyware. But the attackers chose to:</li>



<li>(a) launch the IMAgent process and inject a payload that clears the exploitation artifacts from the device;</li>



<li>(b) run a Safari process in invisible mode and forward it to a web page with the next stage.</li>



<li>The web page has a script that verifies the victim and, if the checks pass, receives the next stage: the Safari exploit.</li>



<li>The Safari exploit uses CVE-2023-32435 to execute a shellcode.</li>



<li>The shellcode executes another kernel exploit in the form of a Mach object file. The shellcode reuses the previously used vulnerabilities: CVE-2023-32434, CVE-2023-38606. It is also massive in terms of size and functionality, but completely different from the kernel exploit written in JavaScript. Certain parts related to exploitation of the above- mentioned vulnerabilities are all that the two share. Still, most of its code is also dedicated to parsing and manipulation of the kernel memory. It contains various post-exploitation utilities, which are mostly unused</li>



<li>The exploit obtains root privileges and proceeds to execute other stages, which load spyware</li>
</ul>



<blockquote>
<p>So the view we have from 10,000 feet is of an extremely potent and powerful attack chain which, unbeknownst to any targeted iPhone user, arranges to load, in sequence, a pair of extremely powerful and flexible attack kits. The first of the kits works to immediately remove all artifacts of its presence to erase any trace of what it is and how it got there. It also triggers the execution of the second extensive attack kit which obtains root privileges on the device and then loads whatever subsequent spyware the attackers have selected</p>
<cite>@sggrc</cite></blockquote>



<p>What the above demonstrates is an attack group that has stunning programming and technical code capabilities. And to be clear, Kaspersky did not discover the Apple CPU backdoor themselves, they only found out about it due its use by the Triangulation malware.</p>



<p>Kaspersky further says:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>What we want to discuss is related to the vulnerability that has been mitigated as CVE-2023-38606. Recent iPhone models have additional hardware-based security protection for sensitive regions of the kernel memory. This protection prevents attackers from obtaining full control over the device if they can read and write kernel memory, as achieved in this attack by exploiting CVE-2023-32434. We discovered that to bypass this hardware-based security protection, the attackers used another hardware feature of Apple-designed SoCs (systems on chip).</p>



<p>If we try to describe this feature and how the attackers took advantage of it, it all comes down to this: they are able to write data to a certain physical address while bypassing the hardware-based memory protection by writing the data, destination address, and data hash to unknown hardware registers of the chip unused by the firmware.</p>



<p>Our guess is that this unknown hardware feature was most likely intended to be used for debugging or testing purposes by Apple engineers or the factory, or that it was included by mistake. Because this feature is not used by the firmware, we have no idea how attackers would know how to use it.</p>
<cite>Kaspersky</cite></blockquote>



<p>Steve Gibson puts things plainly here:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>So let’s get this very clear because it’s an important point: There is nothing whatsoever obscure about this. The use of this backdoor required a priori knowledge — explicit knowledge in advance of its use. And that knowledge had to come from whatever entity implemented this. Period.</p>
<cite>@sggrc</cite></blockquote>



<p>Steve is saying that the knowledge of the backdoor had to have come from Apple (assuming they implemented the backdoor, which again is the only logical conclusion). Whether knowledge of the backdoor was a leak, or intentional, is unknown. </p>



<p>Kaspersky has done a brilliant job of disassembling the Triangulation malware, however the source of, and reason for, the backdoor used for the initial attack vector in the malware, remains a mystery.</p>



<p>It’s unlikely (as Kaspersky opines) that this backdoor was left in by mistake. There are too many checks and balances, in the design and manufacturing process of silicon, for deliberate functions like this to go unnoticed.</p>



<p>Bugs can happen yes, but not a deliberate design, which this clearly and unequivocally is.</p>



<p><strong>Conclusion</strong></p>



<p>Some points to wrap up</p>



<ul>
<li>unless Apple fesses, we may never know the source of, and reason for, this backdoor in their CPUs</li>



<li>we don’t know how the Triangulation malware attackers came to be in possession of the details of the backdoor, we do know however with reasonable surety that they would not have been able to find it themselves</li>



<li>the backdoor was not accessible from firmware and was undocumented but people within Apple knew of this backdoor. They knew that this backdoor was present and they knew how to access it. And somehow that secret escaped from Apple’s control</li>



<li>Apple have since patched all relevant CVEs so affected devices <em>should</em> now be secure from this issue</li>



<li>there is nothing to stop Apple from implementing similar backdoors in future silicon as long as they can keep it a secret</li>



<li>are ARM (who design/make some of the related silicon) involved?</li>



<li>do other silicon manufacturers have anything similar in play?</li>
</ul>



<p>The impact of the backdoor on Triangulation’s ability to propagate their malware can not be overstated. The backdoor was pivotal in allowing Triangulation’s malware to spawn without requiring action on an iOS user’s part. And the malware’s capabilities were impressive to put it bluntly, allowing complete compromise of iOS devices.</p>



<p>Kaspersky, no matter their reputation or allegiances, have done some stellar work in uncovering this issue, no matter its source or reasoning. But them finding out about the hardware backdoor may not be the obviously good thing it appears to be – involved parties now know that they need to take additional care when designing potential new backdoors; and these may never be found.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[1% Equity for Founding Engineers Is BS (171 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fetchfox.ai/a/founding-engineer-compensation</link>
            <guid>43002999</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 17:47:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fetchfox.ai/a/founding-engineer-compensation">https://fetchfox.ai/a/founding-engineer-compensation</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43002999">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="__next"><main><div><p>Feb 2025</p><p>The status quo for Founding Engineer compensation is broken. It’s unfair, outdated, and doesn’t work for founders or engineers.</p><p>A startup starts with the founders doing all the work. The founders write all the code and they talk to all the customers. If the startup is doing well, there is more coding and talking to do than the hours in the day, and you need to hire some help. This help will almost always be a technical hire.</p><p>The job title “Founding Engineer” was<!-- --> <a href="https://trends.google.com/trends/explore?date=all&amp;q=founding%20engineer&amp;hl=en">invented</a> to describe this role. It is kinda-sorta like a founder, but not a founder. You do similar work to a founder, but a little bit less. You take on similar risk to the founder, but a little bit less.</p><p>This is all fine, except for one part. These roles offer similar compensation to the founders, except it’s a<!-- --> <i>whole lot less</i>.</p><h2>Similar risk for 50x less reward?</h2><p>The exact numbers vary, but the typical equity grants for founding engineers are in the range of 0.5% to 2%. You can get a sense for it if you scan<!-- --> <a href="https://www.workatastartup.com/jobs/l/software-engineer">YC’s job board</a>. Getting 1% is typical, and it comes with a one year cliff and a four year vest. These grants are given to the first one or two engineering hires, and many of these companies have YC as their first and only investor.</p><p>Assuming two founders and a 7% stake by YC, the founders retain 48.5% equity. That means their stake is anywhere from 25x to 80x larger than the Founding Engineer’s stake.</p><p>To illustrate this in dollar terms, consider an acquihire exit. At 1% of $10 million, the acquihire nets the Founding Engineer around $100,000, enough to buy a nice Tesla. Meanwhile, the founders net $4.8 million, enough to buy a<!-- --> <a href="https://www.zillow.com/homedetails/3247-Murray-Way-Palo-Alto-CA-94303/19499495_zpid/">house in Palo Alto</a>, a <a href="https://www.yachtworld.com/boats-for-sale/make-princess/model-v40/">small yacht</a>, and two nice Teslas.</p><p>The founders certainly took on more risk, but not 80 times more. The risk reward ratio is completely out of proportion, and it's profoundly unfair to the Founding Engineer.</p><p><img src="https://fetchfox.ai/equity.png"></p><h2>When liquidity?</h2><p>Even if you ignore the reward proportions, there’s another problem with startup equity: liquidity.</p><p>Most startups put a one year cliff on your vesting, which means if you work there for 11 months and 29 days, you don’t get any equity at all.</p><p>But even once you start vesting, there’s another problem: you can’t sell your equity. There are no market makers for a typical startup's equity, which means there are no buyers and no sellers. You could try a second market deal, but even for Series A startups those markets are slow. Good luck trying to sell pre-seed shares.</p><p>Even mature startups have thin liquidity. When I worked at 23andMe, we had a once a year liquidity event, and you had to sell a large number of shares with high fees. If you missed the event, you had to wait a whole year before you could sell again.</p><p>Many VCs will tell you this is for “long term alignment” and to “maintain incentives.” It’s all shenanigans. These are the <a href="https://a16zcrypto.com/">exact</a> <a href="https://www.sequoiacap.com/">same</a> <a href="https://visionfund.com/">VCs</a> that happily<!-- --> <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/11/10/sequoia-capital-marks-down-its-ftx-investment-to-0.html">jumped</a> <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2022/11/14/softbank-ftx-crypto/">into</a> failed crypto projects for short term gains (or cashed out successful crypto pumps by<!-- --> <a href="https://www.benzinga.com/markets/cryptocurrency/21/07/22126163/polychain-a16z-face-unregistered-security-lawsuit-over-internet-computer-token-sale">dumping on retail</a>). Don’t believe their lies. With VCs, it’s “long term alignment” for you, and “cash now” for them.</p><h2>Who this works for</h2><p>This equity model works in some situations. It works in when the founders are bringing 50x more value than the Founding Engineer, for example:</p><ul><li><b>Famous founder.</b> If your startup has a famous founder like Sam Altman or Elon Musk, the equity is instantly valuable. A Sam Altman type brings so much weight to a startup that the absolute worst failure case is a $100 million exit. The best case for normal founders is the worst case for a famous founder.</li><li><b>Brand name investors.</b> If your startup has brand name investors like YC or a16z, it puts a floor on the exit value of your startup. If you fail, you are very likely to get acquired for a decent amount by virtue of your connections. Additionally, these brand names bring a little bit of guaranteed success, especially for B2B startups.</li><li><b>Proven hypergrowth.</b> If your startup is experiencing hypergrowth, like growing revenue by 2x monthly, then it has been de-risked substantially. At this point, you’re no longer an early stage startup, you are hiring regular engineers, not “Founding Engineers.”</li></ul><p>If one of these applies to your startup, then you are justified in offering 50x lower equity to founding engineers. But if you are in the vast majority of startups that do not fall in these buckets, your equity offering is out of line with the risk-reward for a Founding Engineer.</p><h2>Who this doesn’t work for</h2><p>This equity model does not work for tiny, no-name startups, like FetchFox.</p><p>Here at FetchFox, we very much want to hire<!-- --> <a href="https://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/06/done-and-gets-things-smart.html">great</a> <a href="https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2005/07/25/hitting-the-high-notes/">engineers</a>. Our goal is to build a super reliable, easy to use system on top of two super unreliable, flakey systems: LLMs and proxies. This is hard. We run into subtle errors and difficult to reproduce bugs. We are competing against larger teams with more funding and huge incumbents. We need engineers who can frame problems well, figure out leveraged solutions, make good tradeoffs, apply both intuition and empiricism, and quickly write high quality code.</p><p>The great engineers we want to hire are always in demand, and they are super rare. They have the option to work at FetchFox, or they have the option to work at OpenAI for the same salary. When they see a 1% equity offer,<!-- --> <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Anews.ycombinator.com+startup+equity+lottery">conventional wisdom</a> <!-- -->tells them to discount it down to zero after accounting for risk and time horizon. Meanwhile, the 0.005% equity offer from OpenAI will buy them a nice house in Palo Alto.</p><p>There are intangible benefits to working at an early stage startup like FetchFox: perhaps you want to own an entire component of the project, perhaps you enjoy the early stage startup experience, or perhaps you just like the vibe of the team. But these intangible benefits are stacked against the very tangible realities of cash compensation and exit liquidity.</p><h2>A 10x better model for Founding Engineer compensation</h2><p>FetchFox is inventing a new model for Founding Engineer compensation. Our goal is to solve the problems with the current model from above: disproportionate stake, and improbable liquidity.</p><p>First, we are dramatically increasing the stake that Founding Engineers receive. Generally we offer between 5% stake on the low end to 25% or more on the high end to the first few engineering hires. There is some tradeoff here with cash compensation. We believe this is a much more fair range that accounts for the risk and expected contribution for Founding Engineers.</p><p>Second, we are changing the vesting structure. We do have a vesting system, but you begin vesting your stake almost immediately upon joining the company. We do not have a one year cliff, and your stake does not expire if you leave the company.</p><p>Third, and most significant, we do not offer equity stakes using conventional instruments. We do not offer stock or options or equity in the<!-- --> <a href="https://github.com/jlevy/og-equity-compensation">traditional sense</a>. Instead, we offer a crypto token. This is a utility token that will be deployed under the ERC-20 standard, and live on the Ethereum blockchain. It will be set up so that if the product does well, the price of the token goes up, and if the product does badly, the price of the token goes down. You can read more about the<!-- --> <a href="https://docs.google.com/document/u/0/d/1VvxEQBRexuFJT5qCr9MCeZRVkzJUVSAFJ_hxa5yEDAg/edit">details of the token in a sister article</a>.</p><p>Finally, the founders and employees get exactly the same crypto token. Only difference is that the founders get a larger allocation of that token. In my case, I am taking $0 salary at FetchFox and my entire upside and compensation is through the token that me and Founding Engineers are getting.</p><p>As far as I know, very very few, if any, startups outside the crypto space use tokens for employee compensation. I believe this is out of habit, not rational analysis, and I predict that in the future, many many startups outside the crypto space will use tokens for employee compensation.</p><p>Using a crypto token gives our employees a very important,<!-- --> <a href="https://ortutay.substack.com/p/10x-better-10x-worse">10x improvement</a> over traditional stock grants. A crypto token enables continuous, 24/7 liquidity within the first months of the startup's life. No more waiting for a liquidity event that is contingent on the founders needs: you can sell anytime from day one.</p><p>Due to the unique structure of crypto AMM’s, any crypto token has infinite depth. Yes, infinite depth. A crypto AMM can absorb a token sale of any size, any time, zero sweat. It might not be at a price you like, but the option is there. If you haven’t read about them, I highly recommend learning about the<!-- --> <a href="http://ortutay.cc/articles/amm.html">math and intuition behind crypto AMM curves</a>.</p><p>What crypto AMM’s offer is better than the liquidity you get at a brand name startup (it comes a few times a year at best), better than you get on second markets (which have high fees and takes weeks to close), and even better than the gold standard of an IPO (these are closed on weekends, and have nasty employee lockout periods).</p><h2>Tradeoffs mean it's also 10x worse</h2><p>While I strongly believe that a crypto token is a 10x better model for early stage startups, there are downsides. Any innovation that is 10x better in some dimension is<!-- --> <a href="https://ortutay.substack.com/p/10x-better-10x-worse">10x worse</a> in another. Let's consider some of the downsides of the crypto token model.</p><p>First, granting a large amount of equity creates a signalling problem. If all the other startups are giving 1%, and FetchFox is giving up to 25%, does that mean FetchFox is a worthless company? It doesn’t, but many people will conclude it is.</p><p>Second, early stage startups are very volatile, and small cap crypto tokens are also volatile. Combine these two and you get volatility squared. This may create upset employees who could see their token grant values go up or down an order of magnitude overnight.</p><p>Finally, there is still a reputation risk associated with crypto. Mentioning crypto will set off alarm bells for some people, and it will often derail conversations because of its association with all manner of scammers.</p><p>Fortunately, these downsides are a necessary and worthwhile tradeoff. They are mostly related to perceptions (or misperceptions), and much of the impact can be mitigated by managing expectations. And remember that a startup should make<!-- --> <a href="https://kk.org/thetechnium/1000-true-fans/">a small group of people very happy</a>. It should not make everyone mildly ok.</p><h2>It’s not for everyone, but maybe it's for you</h2><p>I recently told the CEO of a recruiting agency about this compensation model. She told me that if you even mention crypto, more than half your engineering candidates will immediately say “no” to your company. The word triggers people, and many will wonder if you’re trying to pull some kind of get rich quick scheme. Even rational people will decide the risk model is not for them, or they don’t want to be guinea pigs on a new compensation model.</p><p>However, we don’t need to hire lots of people here at FetchFox. We just need a handful of<!-- --> <a href="https://steve-yegge.blogspot.com/2008/06/done-and-gets-things-smart.html">really great engineers</a>. I am betting there is a niche group of great engineers who will view this compensation as a huge big positive, and be excited to join us.</p><p>If that describes you, please email <a href="mailto:marcell@fetchfoxai.com">marcell@fetchfoxai.com</a> to chat about joining the team.</p><p>— Marcell Ortutay, Founder/CEO, FetchFox</p></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Undergraduate Upends a 40-Year-Old Data Science Conjecture (607 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture-20250210/</link>
            <guid>43002511</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 17:05:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture-20250210/">https://www.quantamagazine.org/undergraduate-upends-a-40-year-old-data-science-conjecture-20250210/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43002511">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p>
            A young computer scientist and two colleagues show that searches within data structures called hash tables can be much faster than previously deemed possible.        </p>
        
    </div><div>
            <h2>Introduction</h2>
            <div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Sometime in the fall of 2021, Andrew Krapivin, an undergraduate at Rutgers University, encountered a paper that would change his life. At the time, Krapivin didn’t give it much thought. But two years later, when he finally set aside time to go through the paper (“just for fun,” as he put it), his efforts would lead to a rethinking of a widely used tool in computer science.</p>
<p>The paper’s title, “<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2111.12800">Tiny Pointers</a>,” referred to arrowlike entities that can direct you to a piece of information, or element, in a computer’s memory. Krapivin soon came up with a potential way to further miniaturize the pointers so they consumed less memory. However, to achieve that, he needed a better way of organizing the data that the pointers would point to.</p>
<p>He turned to a common approach for storing data known as a hash table. But in the midst of his tinkering, Krapivin realized that he had invented a new kind of hash table, one that worked faster than expected — taking less time and fewer steps to find specific elements.</p>
<p><a href="https://engineering.nyu.edu/faculty/martin-farach-colton">Martín Farach-Colton</a>, a co-author of the “Tiny Pointers” paper and Krapivin’s former professor at Rutgers, was initially skeptical of Krapivin’s new design. Hash tables are among the most thoroughly studied data structures in all of computer science; the advance sounded too good to be true. &nbsp;But just to be sure, he asked a frequent collaborator (and a “Tiny Pointers” co-author), <a href="https://csd.cmu.edu/people/faculty/william-kuszmaul">William Kuszmaul</a> of Carnegie Mellon University, to check out his student’s invention. Kuszmaul had a different reaction. “You didn’t just come up with a cool hash table,” he remembers telling Krapivin. “You’ve actually completely wiped out a 40-year-old conjecture!”</p>
</div>
    </div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Together, Krapivin (now a graduate student at the University of Cambridge), Farach-Colton (now at New York University) and Kuszmaul demonstrated in a <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02305">January 2025 paper</a> that this new hash table can indeed find elements faster than was considered possible. ln so doing, they had disproved a conjecture long held to be true.</p>
<p>“It’s an important paper,” said <a href="https://ajhconway.com/">Alex Conway</a> of Cornell Tech in New York City. “Hash tables are among the oldest data structures we have. And they’re still one of the most efficient ways to store data.” Yet open questions remain about how they work, he said. “This paper answers a couple of them in surprising ways.”</p>
<p>Hash tables have become ubiquitous in computing, partly because of their simplicity and ease of use. They’re designed to allow users to do exactly three things: “query” (search for) an element, delete an element, or insert one into an empty slot. The first hash tables date back to the early 1950s, and computer scientists have studied and used them ever since. Among other things, researchers wanted to figure out the speed limits for some of these operations. How fast, for example, could a new search or insertion possibly be?</p>

<p>The answer generally depends on the amount of time it takes to find an empty spot in a hash table. This, in turn, typically depends on how full the hash table is. Fullness can be described in terms of an overall percentage — this table is 50% full, that one’s 90% — but researchers often deal with much fuller tables. So instead, they may use a whole number, denoted by <em>x</em>, to specify how close the hash table is to 100% full. If <em>x</em> is 100, then the table is 99% full. If <em>x</em> is 1,000, the table is 99.9% full. This measure of fullness offers a convenient way to evaluate how long it should take to perform actions like queries or insertions.<strong>&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p>Researchers have long known that for certain common hash tables, the expected time required to make the worst possible insertion — putting an item into, say, the last remaining open spot — is proportional to <em>x</em>. “If your hash table is 99% full,” Kuszmaul said, “it makes sense that you would have to look at around 100 different positions to find a free slot.”</p>
<p>In a <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3828.3836">1985 paper</a>, the computer scientist <a href="https://amturing.acm.org/award_winners/yao_1611524.cfm">Andrew Yao</a>, who would go on to win the A.M. Turing Award, asserted that among hash tables with a specific set of properties, the best way to find an individual element or an empty spot is to just go through potential spots randomly — an approach known as uniform probing. He also stated that, in the worst-case scenario, where you’re searching for the last remaining open spot, you can never do better than <em>x</em>. for 40 years, most computer scientists assumed that Yao’s conjecture was true.</p>
<p>Krapivin was not held back by the conventional wisdom for the simple reason that he was unaware of it. “I did this without knowing about Yao’s conjecture,” &nbsp;he said. His explorations with tiny pointers led to a new kind of hash table — one that did not rely on uniform probing. And for this new hash table, the time required for worst-case queries and insertions is proportional to (log <em>x</em>)<sup>2</sup> — far faster than <em>x</em>. This result directly contradicted Yao’s conjecture. Farach-Colton and Kuszmaul helped Krapivin show that (log <em>x</em>)<sup>2</sup> is the optimal, unbeatable bound for the popular class of hash tables Yao had written about.</p>
<p>“This result is beautiful in that it addresses and solves such a classic problem,” said <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~guyb/">Guy Blelloch</a> of Carnegie Mellon.</p>
<p>“It’s not just that they disproved [Yao’s conjecture], they also found the best possible answer to his question,” said <a href="https://cs.uwaterloo.ca/about/people/sassadi">Sepehr Assadi</a> of the University of Waterloo. &nbsp;“We could have gone another 40 years before we knew the right answer.”</p>
</div><div data-role="selectable">
    <p>In addition to refuting Yao’s conjecture, the new paper also contains what many consider an even more astonishing result. It pertains to a related, though slightly different, situation: In 1985, Yao looked not only at the worst-case times for queries, but also at the average time taken across all possible queries. He proved that hash tables with certain properties — including those that are labeled “greedy,” which means that new elements must be placed in the first available spot — could never achieve an average time better than log <em>x</em>.</p>
        
        
<p>Farach-Colton, Krapivin and Kuszmaul wanted to see if that same limit also applied to non-greedy hash tables. They showed that it did not by providing a counterexample, a non-greedy hash table with an average query time that’s much, much better than log <em>x</em>. In fact, it doesn’t depend on <em>x</em> at all. “You get a number,” Farach-Colton said, “something that is just a constant and doesn’t depend on how full the hash table is.” The fact that you can achieve a constant average query time, regardless of the hash table’s fullness, was wholly unexpected — even to the authors themselves.</p>
<p>The team’s results may not lead to any immediate applications, but that’s not all that matters, Conway said. “It’s important to understand these kinds of data structures better. You don’t know when a result like this will unlock something that lets you do better in practice.”</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CAPTCHAs: 'a tracking cookie farm for profit masquerading as a security service' (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/a-2023-study-concluded-captchas-are-a-tracking-cookie-farm-for-profit-masquerading-as-a-security-service-that-made-us-spend-819-billion-hours-clicking-on-traffic-lights-to-generate-nearly-usd1-trillion-for-google/</link>
            <guid>43002440</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 16:59:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/a-2023-study-concluded-captchas-are-a-tracking-cookie-farm-for-profit-masquerading-as-a-security-service-that-made-us-spend-819-billion-hours-clicking-on-traffic-lights-to-generate-nearly-usd1-trillion-for-google/">https://www.pcgamer.com/gaming-industry/a-2023-study-concluded-captchas-are-a-tracking-cookie-farm-for-profit-masquerading-as-a-security-service-that-made-us-spend-819-billion-hours-clicking-on-traffic-lights-to-generate-nearly-usd1-trillion-for-google/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43002440">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">

<section>
<div>
<div>
<picture data-new-v2-image="true">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1920-80.jpg.webp 1920w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-320-80.jpg.webp 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)">
<img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1200-80.jpg" alt="Mature professional business man suffering from a headache while working online on computer checking emails alone at work. One male manager feeling overworked, stressed and tired due to a deadline - stock photo" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1920-80.jpg 1920w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf-320-80.jpg 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/hpd4LbGpm6MBXYawDj9vwf.jpg" data-pin-nopin="true" fetchpriority="high">
</picture>
</div>
<figcaption>
<span>(Image credit: DMP via Getty Images)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<p>As reported by <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://boingboing.net/2025/02/07/recaptcha-819-million-hours-of-wasted-human-time-and-billions-of-dollars-google-profit.html" target="_blank" data-url="https://boingboing.net/2025/02/07/recaptcha-819-million-hours-of-wasted-human-time-and-billions-of-dollars-google-profit.html" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">Boing Boing</a>, a 2023 study out of UC Irvine, "<a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.10911" target="_blank" data-url="https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.10911" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">Dazed and Confused: A Large-Scale Real-World User Study of reCAPTCHAv2</a>" concluded that not only are CAPTCHAs ineffective at actually preventing bot traffic, they introduce privacy concerns through tracking cookies, have wasted millions of hours of our collective time, and generated nearly a trillion dollars worth of data for Google, which acquired the ubiquitous reCAPTCHA utility back in 2009.</p><p>The study focuses on the two most common forms of CAPTCHAs you'll find out in the wild through Google's reCAPTCHAv2: "Invisible" or behavior-based CAPTCHAs which analyze your inputs as you check that "not a robot" box or even surreptitiously as you browse a website, and image-based CAPTCHAs, where you select all the motorcycles, traffic lights, or what have you in images sourced from Google Street View. Both are valuable to Google, with the tracking cookies generated by the former potentially contributing to ad targeting, and data from the latter being applied toward AI model training, either internally at Google or sold to another company.</p><figure data-bordeaux-image-check=""><div><p><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-320-80.jpeg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-480-80.jpeg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-650-80.jpeg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-970-80.jpeg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-1024-80.jpeg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-1200-80.jpeg.webp 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-320-80.jpeg" alt="CAPTCHA bikes" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-320-80.jpeg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-480-80.jpeg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-650-80.jpeg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-970-80.jpeg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-1024-80.jpeg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW-1200-80.jpeg 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 970px, calc(100vw - 40px)" loading="lazy" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW.jpeg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/C6AqADWX2K4VKqGiYmbhvW.jpeg"></picture></p></div><figcaption itemprop="caption description"><span>1200 human lifetimes of these moments lost to time like tears in rain. </span><span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Google)</span></figcaption></figure><p>This experiment did not inform its subjects, and instead added Google's reCAPTCHAv2 to the account creation and password recovery functions of an internal student account system at the university, with the researchers both measuring time to complete the CAPTCHAs and surveying a subset of the 13-month study's 3,600 users about their experience. Predictably, they took more time and surveyed negatively when it came to the more involved image detection CAPTCHAs. The study also noted variations in completion time across education disciplines, experience level, and for whether they were creating or recovering an account.</p><p>The researchers took the average completion time of 3.53 seconds across both image and behavior CAPTCHAs and multiplied that against a low-end estimate of 512 billion v1 and v2 reCAPTCHAs completed across the internet between 2010 and 2023, resulting in the following estimations of their impact on our lives:</p><ul><li><strong>819 million hours</strong> spent solving CAPTCHAs.</li><li><strong>$6.1 billion </strong>worth of our time at the US federal minimum wage.</li><li><strong>134 Petabytes</strong> of internet bandwidth.</li><li>consuming <strong>7.5 million kWhs</strong> of energy.</li><li>which produced <strong>7.5 million pounds</strong> of CO2 pollution.</li><li>This one's from me: putting the 819 million hours against the average human lifespan of 79 years, that's <strong>1,182.7 lifetimes</strong> spent solving CAPTCHAs.</li></ul><p>Comparing the new study's time and accuracy rates to bots, while also looking at <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.pcgamer.com/new-research-shows-bots-beat-people-at-convincing-computers-theyre-not-bots/" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.pcgamer.com/new-research-shows-bots-beat-people-at-convincing-computers-theyre-not-bots/">previous studies</a> on the increasing capability of automated processes to solve CAPTCHAs, the researchers concluded that bots are now faster than humans at completing reCAPTCHAv2's checkboxes, while they take more time, but are more accurate when it comes to image detection. The researchers also argued that the tracking cookies in fact introduce a new security and privacy risk. Looking at Google's stated value for collections of labeled image detection data and the lifetime value of an individual tracking cookie multiplied by the estimated lifetime amount of reCAPTCHAv2s completed, the researchers came up with the following values for Google:</p><ul><li><strong>$8.75-$32.3 billion</strong> for its full reCAPTCHAv2 dataset, which could theoretically be sold multiple times to different vendors.</li><li>A lifetime value of <strong>$888 billion </strong>for all of reCAPTCHAv2's tracking cookies produced between 2010 and 2023.</li></ul><p>"It can be concluded that the true purpose of reCAPTCHAv2 is as a tracking cookie farm for profit masquerading as a security service," the researchers stated in the final portion of the study, arguing that reCAPTCHA should be deprecated for its lack of genuine contribution to the internet's safety or functionality. Two years on from this study, there's no sign of that happening any time soon.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-ZozyXgBL8hiqEj59pzDaW"><section><p>Keep up to date with the most important stories and the best deals, as picked by the PC Gamer team.</p></section></div>
</div>

<div id="slice-container-authorBio-ZozyXgBL8hiqEj59pzDaW"><p>Ted has been thinking about PC games and bothering anyone who would listen with his thoughts on them ever since he booted up his sister's copy of Neverwinter Nights on the family computer. He is obsessed with all things CRPG and CRPG-adjacent, but has also covered esports, modding, and rare game collecting. When he's not playing or writing about games, you can find Ted lifting weights on his back porch.</p></div>
</section>


<div data-test-id="more-about">
<p>More about gaming industry</p>


</div>

<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h3>Most Popular</h3></p></div>







</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Open Source Security & Compliance: Introducing Opencomply (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://opencomply.io</link>
            <guid>43001826</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 16:07:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://opencomply.io">https://opencomply.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43001826">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://opencomply.io: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bank CEO: Retract your debanking piece? Me: No (247 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kalzumeus.com/2025/02/10/retraction-request-denied/</link>
            <guid>43001441</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 15:32:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kalzumeus.com/2025/02/10/retraction-request-denied/">https://www.kalzumeus.com/2025/02/10/retraction-request-denied/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43001441">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <p>In December 2024, in response to the press/advocacy campaign by Marc Andreessen and other crypto advocates regarding a phenomenon they call <a href="https://a16zcrypto.com/posts/article/debanking-explained/">debanking</a>, I wrote <a href="https://www.bitsaboutmoney.com/archive/debanking-and-debunking/">Debanking (and Debunking?)</a> in Bits about Money.</p>

<p>That piece is the definitive explanation of the issue. It examines many angles including:</p>

<ul>
  <li>the constraints on banks and their incentive structures</li>
  <li>how AML regulation sometimes hurts innocent entrepreneurs</li>
  <li>a detailed history of Operation Choke Point</li>
  <li>a detailed analysis of why two crypto-affiliated banks closed</li>
  <li>what the crypto industry hopes to win through the press/advocacy campaign.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Debanking (and Debunking?)</em> won wide acclaim for being accurate, incisive, and balanced. Experts who publicly praised it include the crypto VC who coined the phrase “Choke Point 2.0” (<a href="https://x.com/nic__carter/status/1866308123742683279">“… the best and fairest treatment of the issue [I] could expect from a skeptic…”</a>) and a former federal banking regulator (<a href="https://x.com/bpetershome/status/1866973869979922650">“This is a tour-de-force. This is absolutely excellent. Anyone interested in this issue should read this piece.”</a>).</p>

<p>I am notoriously a crypto skeptic, but I do believe advocates have some points which are <em>just true</em> about debanking, a phenomenon which is much larger than crypto. They also have some arguments which deserve a fair hearing. They also say some things which are untrue and will not get more true simply by being strategically convenient.</p>

<h2 id="you-cant-please-everyone">You can’t please everyone</h2>

<p>In many years of writing for the Internet, I’ve gotten my fair share of negative comments. It happens; oh well. Sometimes randos use cliches like “Delete this post.” These are easy to ignore.</p>

<p>I recently received a <a href="https://x.com/nathanmccauley/status/1887635974064382198">request for retraction from a bank CEO</a>. (<a href="https://media.kalzumeus.com/bam-retraction-request/mccauley-thread-1-of-4.png">Tweets</a> <a href="https://media.kalzumeus.com/bam-retraction-request/mccauley-thread-2-of-4.png">sometimes</a> <a href="https://media.kalzumeus.com/bam-retraction-request/mccauley-thread-3-of-4.png">become</a> <a href="https://media.kalzumeus.com/bam-retraction-request/mccauley-thread-4-of-4.png">unavailable</a>.) <em>That</em> is a first, and it deserves careful attention.</p>

<p>Bits about Money is a <a href="https://www.bitsaboutmoney.com/memberships/">reader-supported</a> professional journal about the intersection of finance and technology. It has been my primary professional output and source of income for the last two years. It generally takes pains to avoid antagonizing specific banks, in part because banks can be <em>prickly</em> about their reputations. But there was always a risk, in writing candidly about banking, that a bank or banker could react with severe displeasure.</p>

<p>Bits about Money is, like most of my professional writing, published by Kalzumeus Software, LLC. The following is in the voice of the company.</p>

<blockquote>
Nathan McCauley, the CEO of <a href="https://anchorage.com/">Anchorage Labs, Inc.</a> d/b/a Anchorage Digital, and a board member (and, on faith and belief, CEO) of a federally chartered bank, has requested a retraction of the piece <em>Debanking (and Debunking?)</em>. He alleges inaccuracies, misleading statements, omission of key facts, and other improprieties.

<p>

This is a serious allegation, and we treated it seriously. We have undertaken a review of McCauley's points. This review included requesting input from Anchorage Digital's PR team, reviewing the text of the published essay, and consulting with our external advisors.

</p><p>

<strong>We find McCauley's allegations to lack merit.</strong> We therefore decline to retract the essay.
</p></blockquote>

<h3 id="the-bar-for-a-retraction-is-high">The bar for a retraction is high</h3>

<p>Retractions are, in the standard practice of journalism, research and other professional writing, extremely rare. They are reserved for the worst offenses: plagiarizing, fabricating quotations or data, committing libel, and the like.</p>

<p>I publish analytical essays about complex systems, and mostly do not break news. One is welcome to one’s opinion as to whether that counts as journalism.</p>

<p>I have a high regard for the truth. If I ever wander into error about the thing readers pay me to be an expert about, I try to correct the record. My preference is strongly towards corrections rather than retractions, as I have never unpublished a piece, but I <em>would do it</em> if warranted.</p>

<p>I have considered, and asked external advisors, whether it is possible that the CEO of a tech startup valued at <a href="https://www.anchorage.com/insights/anchorage-digital-raises-350-million-series-d-funding-led-by-kkr">over $3 billion</a> might be unaware of what the word “retraction” means or that asking for one is a serious act. We unanimously concluded that I am entitled to assume the professionalism and competence of a founder of a tech unicorn or a bank CEO. McCauley is both.</p>

<p>Because the specific allegations made do not show the professionalism and competence of the speaker in a positive light, I reached out to Anchorage Digital in advance of publication, via their <a href="https://www.anchorage.com/in-the-news">PR department’s published email address</a>. I asked, among other things, if they had reason to believe their CEO’s Twitter account was compromised. There is always a risk that someone <a href="https://www.loweringthebar.net/wp-content/uploads/2011/03/browns_letter_1974.pdf">is signing one’s name to stupid letters</a> without authorization.</p>

<p>Anchorage Digital’s PR team did not reply to my request for comment, despite receiving three emails and a clearly communicated timeline which was longer than one business day. As Anchorage Digital itself <a href="https://x.com/Anchorage/status/1887162623516725627">tagged</a> McCauley’s account the day prior on the occasion of <a href="https://www.banking.senate.gov/hearings/investigating-the-real-impacts-of-debanking-in-america">his testimony in front of the U.S. Senate Banking Committee</a>, and did not identify his account as compromised, I treat the authenticity of his messages as a settled question.</p>

<p>I will take the <em>charitable</em> perspective that a tech founder and bank CEO does not necessarily speak for the startup and/or bank themselves. Anchorage Digital knows my email address if they would like to clarify this or any other point.</p>

<h2 id="our-review-of-the-retraction-request">Our review of the retraction request</h2>

<p>On receiving the request for retraction we <a href="https://x.com/patio11/status/1887694095239217388">reached out</a> to McCauley to ask what specifically he believed was inaccurate in the piece. This was also an opportunity for McCauley to recharacterize his request as, for example, an indelicately phrased expression of personal opinion.</p>

<p>McCauley did not respond by walking back the request for retraction. Instead, he replied with what he seems to believe constitutes a litany of improprieties. As he has numbered his subpoints, we will address them in turn.</p>

<p>McCauley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A few areas were incorrect and misleading, lots of omission of key facts, and missing the point about what we mean by debanking.</p>

  <p>In order:</p>
</blockquote>

<h3 id="1-a-few-areas-were-incorrect-and-misleading">1. “A few areas were incorrect and misleading”</h3>

<p>McCauley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Silvergate was trivially solvent based on their call reports. Anyone assessing their liquidity position saw this (we were doing so).  Your implication that they were doomed due to BSA findings doesn’t comport with any regulatory practice—banks don’t get closed for this.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Our response regarding solvency:</strong> Had we stated or implied that Silvergate was insolvent, that would have been very improper. Insolvency of a financial institution is a serious charge. We assume McCauley believes we must have made it, because no bank CEO could possibly believe that solvency is <em>the only</em> obligation of a financial institution.</p>

<p>We did not make this accusation.</p>

<p>We reviewed the 4,300 words written about Silvergate specifically, and cannot identify any statement which can be reasonably read as alleging insolvency. A reader who wanted to quickly verify this might use Ctrl-F “solv” (three hits in the piece, none about Silvergate, and one expanding to “solving”). One could also run the piece by an expert in banking practice, who might point out the following is persuasive evidence of solvency.</p>

<p><em>Debanking (and Debunking?):</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Silvergate voluntarily liquidated in the wake of the FTX implosion. Limited props for them here: they managed to do this in a mostly orderly fashion, as opposed to Signature, which had substantially less crypto exposure but blew up.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If one’s bank does not employ an individual who understands the above paragraph to mean that Silvergate was solvent, <a href="https://anthropic.com/">Anthropic</a> will sell you artificial cognition for $20 a month. Claude 3.5 Sonnet demonstrates sufficient reading comprehension to analyze complex technical documents to the standards of an early-career employee in financial services. We would recommend supervising Claude with management at least as competent as it.</p>

<p><strong>Our response regarding Bank Secrecy Act (BSA) findings:</strong></p>

<p>We have reviewed our writings with respect to Silvergate’s broadly deficient BSA compliance regime, including the anti-moneylaundering (AML) errors it made. We stand by the entire analysis, most particularly the conclusion, which we did not articulate lightly.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Silvergate was not a competently run institution.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We charitably assume that Anchorage Digital has mandatory training regarding BSA/AML compliance. This is required of all banks. McCauley has even more reason to be familiar with this requirement than the typical bank CEO.</p>

<p>McCauley and Anchorage Digital Bank, National Association are signatories to <a href="https://www.occ.gov/static/enforcement-actions/ea2022-010.pdf">a 2022 consent order with the Office of the Comptroller of the Currency (OCC)</a>.</p>

<p>That consent order stems from the OCC’s finding that, quoting the order:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As of 2021, the Bank failed to adopt and implement a compliance program that
adequately covers the required BSA/AML program elements, including, in particular, internal controls for customer due diligence and procedures for monitoring suspicious activity, BSA officer and staff, and training.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We have no particularized knowledge as to what Anchorage Digital’s internal training instructs employees regarding the range of sanctions available for non-compliant behavior. If that training does not rhyme with every other training in the financial industry, we suggest Anchorage Digital might consider updating it.</p>

<p>(We gave McCauley and Anchorage Digital’s press team days of advance notice of our intention to mention the consent order. We gave them the opportunity to provide a comment regarding it. Neither offered a comment.)</p>

<p><em>Debanking</em> characterizes the standard training thusly:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If you’ve worked in the financial industry in any capacity, you went to mandatory Compliance training. Attendance is taken and you likely had a refresher annually. And there were smirks, and jokes. And your trainer said, very seriously, “Pay attention. This is important. If we eff this up, they can do anything to us, most likely large fines but up to and including closing this firm. You, personally, could go to jail.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Banks are, of course, welcome to their own risk analyses, and may consider the risk of being closed for AML/BSA compliance violations to be very low. This point of view appears common among crypto bankers. Silvergate executives have professed to share it.</p>

<p>As mentioned in <em>Debanking</em>, closing a bank is an extraordinary remedy, but it is on the table.</p>

<p>Case studies which might enliven one’s next training include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Farmington State Bank d/b/a Moonstone Bank (2023): closed by the <a href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/files/enf20230817a1.pdf">Federal Reserve</a> because it was puppeted by a coalition of Tether’s bankers, who are as-yet unindicted professional money launderers, and Sam Bankman-Fried et al, who are now-<a href="https://www.justice.gov/archives/opa/pr/samuel-bankman-fried-sentenced-25-years-his-orchestration-multiple-fraudulent-schemes">convicted</a> professional money launderers.</li>
  <li>ABLV Bank (2018): designated <a href="https://www.fincen.gov/news/news-releases/fincen-names-ablv-bank-latvia-institution-primary-money-laundering-concern-and">an Institution of Primary Money Laundering Concern</a> and forbidden from using dollar clearing, resulting in the European Central Bank <a href="https://www.bankingsupervision.europa.eu/press/pr/date/2018/html/ssm.pr180219.en.html">effectively directing</a> Latvia to close it, which <a href="https://www.bank.lv/en/operational-areas/supervision/monitoring-of-ablv-bank-voluntary-liquidation-process">Latvia did</a>.</li>
  <li>Washington Federal Bank for Savings (2017): closed <a href="https://www.occ.gov/news-issuances/news-releases/2017/nr-occ-2017-150.html">by the OCC</a> for a control fraud, BSA violations, and other malfeasance. The senior executives and directors were <a href="https://www.occ.gov/news-issuances/news-releases/2022/nr-occ-2022-140.html">sanctioned individually</a> and several <a href="https://chicago.suntimes.com/the-watchdogs/2024/08/13/bridgeport-bank-scandal-washington-federal-bank-for-savings-robert-kowalski-sentencing-john-gembara">went to prison</a>.</li>
  <li>FBME Bank (2017): designated <a href="https://www.fincen.gov/resources/statutes-regulations/federal-register-notices/imposition-special-measure-against-fbme">a Financial Institution of Primary Money Laundering Concern</a> by FinCEN. It was liquidated as a direct and intended consequence.</li>
  <li>Banca Privada d’Andorra (2015): designated <a href="https://www.fincen.gov/news/news-releases/fincen-names-banca-privada-dandorra-foreign-financial-institution-primary-money">a Foreign Financial Institution of Primary Money Laundering Concern</a> by FinCEN. It collapsed as a direct and intended consequence.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Summary:</strong> McCauley fails to identify an incorrect allegation of fact made by <em>Debanking</em>. Viewing his statements in a light most favorable to him, he disagrees with <em>our analysis</em>. He is welcome to articulate his point of view in his own spaces, the bank’s spaces, or the halls of the Senate. He is not entitled to a retraction.</p>

<p>To the extent McCauley believes that <em>any respectable publication</em> would retract over this, he is greatly miscalibrated. We could end the inquiry here, because his next two bullet points do not even purport to allege inaccuracies, but we will continue.</p>

<h3 id="2-lots-of-omission-of-key-facts">2. “lots of omission of key facts”</h3>

<p>McCauley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You completely fail to mention the exhaustive set of communications publicly coming from the regulators indicating clear guidance that crypto businesses are to be viewed as, quoting, “highly unlikely to be compatible with safe and sound banking practices”. Particularly joint letter of Jan 2023, OCC IL 1179, and the rescinding of the Fair Access to Financial Services rule. Credit for the fdic letter mention but the sum total of these moves had a clear chilling effect, that caused most large banks the country to 180 about face in crypto. You also dismiss sab121 as boring accounting (it is) without acknowledging the meta message of it to banks.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We concur that the Joint Statement on Crypto-Asset Risks to Banking Organizations (of the Federal Reserve, FDIC, and OCC, in January 2023) was an important milestone. Which is why <strong>we cited it as such</strong>. It was linked in the following discussion.</p>

<p><em>Debanking</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Banking regulators get to weigh in on proposed banking products. That is the absolute core of the job. That will extremely routinely result in saying something which rounds, like many of the letters do, to “We are going to have a considered think about this and get back to you, but in the meanwhile, please don’t roll this out widely.” (The think was had; the results <a href="https://www.fdic.gov/news/financial-institution-letters/2023/fil23001.html">were published</a>. Many crypto advocates do not like those results, and are asserting procedural irregularities because of that.)</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The piece extensively argues that, contra the claims of crypto advocates generally (and McCauley in <a href="https://www.banking.senate.gov/imo/media/doc/nathan_mccauley__anchorage_digital_testimony_2-5-25.pdf">his testimony before the Senate</a> after the piece was published), the publication of extensive written guidance (<em>which we linked to</em>) militates against concerns that these actions are, quoting McCauley’s testimony, “opaque [and] unfair.”</p>

<p><em>Debanking</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Conversely, when the government is capable of publishing extensively researched position papers and extensively footnoted indictments, that should give you more confidence that it is less likely to be engaged in lawless, arbitrary behavior. Not <em>limitless</em> confidence, certainly, but it is evidence in a direction.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Our response regarding <a href="https://www.sec.gov/rules-regulations/staff-guidance/staff-accounting-bulletins/staff-accounting-bulletin-121">SAB121</a>:</strong> McCauley is the CEO of a technology company with a custody business and a foothold within the regulated financial perimeter. We are extremely aware of why he has a particular interest in SAB121.</p>

<p>While this accounting arcana is material to his firms’ business interests, we judged it of only tangential interest to most readers. We only gestured at it to (<em><strong>accurately and fairly</strong></em>) identify changing SAB121 as a policy goal of the crypto industry. It has since <a href="https://www.duanemorris.com/alerts/sab_121_undone_will_bank_regulations_crypto_follow_0125.html">been rescinded</a>.</p>

<p>McCauley’s apparent dissatisfaction with the discussion of SAB121 asserts no inaccuracy and is accordingly not a reasonable grounds for retraction.</p>

<h3 id="3-missing-the-point-about-what-we-mean-by-debanking">3. “missing the point about what we mean by debanking”</h3>

<p>McCauley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Debanking wasn’t just about losing access to settlement services like SEN/signet. It was about comprehensively being unable to get bank accounts after those banks were closed. It was about banks we’d been working with for years kicking us out of the blue - and this happening across the whole industry.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Far from “missing the point” of what crypto advocates mean by “debanking”, <em>Debanking</em> points out that crypto advocates are engaged in strategic conflation of different issues. We could not have, at the time of publishing the following, known that McCauley would request a retraction using this <a href="https://slatestarcodex.com/2014/11/03/all-in-all-another-brick-in-the-motte/">strategic conflation</a>, <em>pretending</em> (a word we do not choose lightly) that advocates do not really care about bank supervision, and only want business checking accounts.</p>

<p><em>Debanking</em>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Advocates often invoke a user-centric perspective of debanking, focusing on the impact on individuals/firms. Then, they conflate it with regulators’ decisions regarding bank supervision, in ways which are facially not about direct user impact.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Crypto advocates routinely exaggerate the universality of banks’ treatment of crypto. As <em>Debanking</em> discusses extensively, we absolutely agree with advocates that crypto companies <em>have, at times, routinely</em> experienced banking friction. If one is demanding a retraction, though, it <em>pays to be precise</em> and not use words like “comprehensively” to mean “not comprehensively.”</p>

<p>For example, as McCauley admitted in his testimony to the Senate Banking Committee, Anchorage Digital <em>did find a banking partner</em>.</p>

<p><em>Debanking</em>, (following a discussion of our own two debanking incidents):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>That is the typical end to a debanking story. “And then, I opened a new account.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>McCauley asserts, in his testimony, his belief that “over forty banks” would not have rejected Anchorage Digital but for regulators pressuring banks to cut off services to the crypto industry.</p>

<p>We have no specific knowledge about Anchorage Digital’s relationship with its former bank or more than forty prospective banks, and will let the common factor in those discussions describe them.</p>

<p>Quoting McCauley’s testimony to the Senate:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One day in June 2023, we received an urgent email from the bank informing us
that they needed to speak with us that day. On the call, we were told that our account
would be closed in thirty days because they were not comfortable with our crypto
clients’ transactions. We attempted to explain the source of all payments from our
crypto clients were fully documented as a part of our robust KYC, AML, sanctions
compliance, and other internal transaction monitoring and attribution processes, and
that we would be willing to provide more information to their risk management team.
They were uninterested. They refused to engage in further discussions, provide any
additional explanation, or offer any chance to appeal the decision.</p>

  <p>Alongside this experience, we found ourselves shut out of the banking system at
other touchpoints. After the closure of some of the few banks that were willing to serve crypto clients in March of 2023, we were forced to find a new banks [sic] to hold clients’ cash funds in custody for trading purposes, as well as an account to hold segregated regulatory capital, both required to be held at an FDIC-insured bank under the terms of our bank charter. Again, we should have been a desirable, low-risk client for a bank. Yet over the course of a seven month period we spoke to over forty banks and were rejected by all of them. Many did not even cite a reason; others just vaguely told us it was not within their risk appetite to work with crypto clients.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><strong>Our response:</strong></p>

<p>We trust McCauley’s representation that this happened.</p>

<p>We also believe <em>Debanking</em> adequately explains to a non-involved individual <em>why</em> it happened. See the section <a href="https://www.bitsaboutmoney.com/archive/debanking-and-debunking/#debanking-specifically-for-aml-risk">Debanking specifically for AML risk</a>. Indeed, a reader of <em>Debanking</em> would have, months before McCauley’s testimony, been able to predict elements like the 30 day notice period, the disinterest in further negotiations, and the lack of appeals process.</p>

<p>McCauley, like many crypto advocates, professes to believe that a legitimate crypto company is a low-risk bank client. His testimony discusses the desire of Anchorage Digital to have demand deposit accounts, on its own behalf and on behalf of customers.</p>

<p>We empathized in <em>Debanking</em> with crypto entrepreneurs who are not banking experts. Some might not understand how a legitimate, legal business could be anything other than a low-risk bank client. We explained how. At substantial length.</p>

<p>Crypto advocates love a bit of risk, and love even more when somebody else has to buy them out of the downside, while they keep the upside. The demand that banks <em>just give them deposit accounts</em> is a demand that bank shareholders backstop their credit (and other) risk. Crypto advocates mostly do not intend to give their banks equity for this risk.</p>

<p>One can understand how a crypto founder who is raising their seed round might not yet be a banking expert.</p>

<p>Members of a bank board of directors, on the other hand, are charged with managing a variety of risks to their bank. They <em>must be able to articulate</em> how a legitimate business could pose credit (and other) risk to a bank with only demand deposit accounts.</p>

<p>This topic is discussed extensively in <em>Debanking</em>, including a worked example from the experience of Metropolitan Commercial Bank. Metropolitan primarily provided “low-risk” cash management services to Voyager Digital, a cryptocurrency platform/exchange. Voyager was a legitimate business, publicly traded, and believed to be well-capitalized. It represented to its bank, investors, and regulators that it had best-in-class risk and compliance programs in place.</p>

<p>Voyager blew up, due to its best-in-class risk program seeing <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/crypto-broker-voyager-digital-says-three-arrows-capital-hasnt-repaid-666-million-in-loans-11655915660">single-name exposure to $666 million</a> representing <a href="https://www.coppolacomment.com/2022/07/the-sinking-of-voyager.html">60% of loan book / 30% of all assets</a> and leaping at the opportunity. When it collapsed, customers who had sent Voyager money, but not received crypto in return, began to initiate reversals of those transfers. Metropolitan was faced with a credit loss large enough to imperil their entire crypto banking practice, which was approximately a quarter of deposits prior to the collapse. Metropolitan was dragged into Voyager’s contentious bankruptcy. It was sued over its conduct and alleged lapses.</p>

<p>One wonders whether Metropolitan, in clarity of hindsight, considers providing cash management services to an upstanding cryptocurrency platform to be “low-risk.”</p>

<p>Metropolitan attributes “the strategic assessment of the business case”, along with the regulatory environment, for deciding to fully exit crypto banking, which they claim they had pivoted from beginning in 2017.</p>

<p>McCauley’s assertion that <em>Debanking</em> ignores a constellation of regulatory activity which caused the banking industry to update negatively on its view of crypto is unsupported and unsupportable. We analyzed it extensively, along with <em>the other</em> reasons the banking industry negatively updated on crypto.</p>



<p>McCauley:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Broadly, the meta thesis of your piece is “nothing to see here regulators gonna regulate and banks gonna bank” which is just not what happened. Sprinkle in some non sequiturs about FTX and your humorous crypto skepticism and you have an entertainingly written piece that sadly misses the point. The biggest problem with it is how well it’s written! A passive observer unfamiliar with the details probably reads it and agrees with you and feels they are smarter.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>McCauley misinterprets the thesis of the piece, which is hinted at in the usual place and in the usual manner: stating it explicitly, very near the top.</p>

<p><em>Debanking:</em></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“It’s not a conspiracy theory if people really are out to get you.” sums up part of my reaction to [the claims of crypto advocates], but only part. There exists some amount of conflation between what private actors are doing, what state actors have de facto or de jure commanded that they do, and which particular state and political actors have their fingers on the keyboard. These create a complex system; the threads are not entirely divorced from each other.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We concur with McCauley that many readers might, after reading <em>Debanking</em>, feel that they are better informed about debanking than if they simply trust the representations of crypto advocates. Kalzumeus Software does not consider this a bug and WONTFIX.</p>

<p>We disagree with McCauley’s characterization of readers moved by the piece as “passive observer[s] unfamiliar with the details.” Many of our readers are extremely professionally invested in these topics, perhaps by dint of working in finance, financial technology, bank supervision, policy roles in the U.S. federal government, or the cryptocurrency industry.</p>

<p>McCauley has failed to identify a single fact alleged in <em>Debanking</em> which is incorrect, or any other malfeasance. Differences of opinion or different preferences in emphasis are, of course, not a reasonable basis for retraction. We accordingly reject his request for a retraction.</p>

<h2 id="bank-ceos-do-not-often-ask-writers-for-retractions">Bank CEOs do not often ask writers for retractions</h2>

<p>I need to promote an important subtext to text.</p>

<p>It is <em>exceedingly rare</em> for bank CEOs, who are chosen for probity, sound judgement, and professionalism, to demand retractions. It is rare enough for <em>banks</em> to do it, and when they do, it usually follows quiet outreach by e.g. PR or Legal teams.</p>

<p>Some might mismodel writers as being thrilled by unprofessional behavior.</p>

<p>The incorrect model is that the writer immediately enjoys the opportunity to embarrass someone, and probably gets paid to do it. There is an old saw about “Never pick a fight with someone who buys ink by the barrel”; a more modern articulation might mention the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Streisand_effect">Streisand Effect</a>. (Wow, more than 20 years old now?! There are <em>bank employees</em> too young for that reference. Yeet it into an LLM if you need to.)</p>

<p>These bits of folk wisdom do not match how serious professionals perceive the incentives and power dynamics at play here. Banks are, as a class, much better resourced than writers (and almost all publications).</p>

<p>I am a very atypical writer vis the financial industry.</p>

<ul>
  <li>I have substantial experience and expertise in the topics I write about.</li>
  <li>I have substantial resources and independent decisionmaking authority.</li>
  <li>I would take perverse joy in being sued by a crypto company.</li>
</ul>

<p>Most writers work for an institution, and that is a Faustian bargain. On the one hand, working for an institution means that <em>when a bank sues for libel</em>, they will sue your employer, and not you. On the other hand, one’s Legal department, being <em>very sensitive to the expense and annoyance of being sued for libel</em>, will tread very lightly around prickly institutions and individuals. This includes exercising prior restraint of reasonable reporting and commentary.</p>

<p>A demand for a retraction by the CEO of a well-resourced financial institution is reasonably read by most outlets as being backstopped by potential legal consequences if they do not comply. Well-calibrated professionals understand retractions will only happen in the event of serious malfeasance. Accordingly, a request for a retraction is a statement that one believes one has suffered serious malfeasance.</p>

<p>Not all CEOs are well-calibrated. But publishers have to take certain genres of statements from certain genres of business owners much more seriously than other people might take them.</p>

<p>This includes when those statements are communicated via the Internet. <strong>The Internet is real life.</strong> A statement made by a bank using the Internet is <em>a statement by a bank</em>. Of course it wasn’t transmitted by telegraph, stagecoach, or carrier pigeon! A statement made by a bank CEO, etc etc.</p>

<p>And thus the recital above that e.g. Kalzumeus Software, LLC was and is the publisher of <em>Debanking</em> (and this piece), and thus the serious discussions with professional advisors. While I sometimes feel like I am LARPing at running a business, the great state of Nevada, the bank holding my mortgage, the IRS, and my insurance company are unanimous that <em>I do in fact run a business</em>. I am obliged to operate it in a competent fashion, including taking my legal responsibilities seriously, and managing risk to the business and other stakeholders.</p>

<p>Perhaps some bank CEOs feel like they’re just LARPing sometimes. I can empathize. But, to quote U.S. District Court Judge Ana Reyes (in <a href="https://assets.ctfassets.net/sygt3q11s4a9/22j1EXHivrIHXgCM9EmyAZ/d9b5fb93c5f862052f7b16f3aecbe716/HA_v._FDIC_1.22.25_Hearing_Transcript.pdf">a hearing on FDIC’s recent tussle with Coinbase</a>), “welcome to the NFL.”</p>

<p>I speak only for myself and, as I’ve said for years, I work for the Internet. The Internet is humanity’s crowning achievement. It is also <em>a community</em> and <em>that community has norms.</em> One of those norms is that it fights attempts at censorship. As a Internet-native independent writer who is better resourced than almost all writers who will ever get a saber rattled at them by a bank or banker, I will say what they cannot.</p>

<p>This conduct is unwarranted, unprofessional, and dishonorable. It should cease.</p>

<p>The <em>opinions</em>, on the other hand, are merely wrong. One is welcome to publish one’s opinions to the Internet in a manner of one’s choosing. (One may have stricter obligations with respect to representations made to one’s regulators or e.g. Congress. Ask one’s lawyers.)</p>

<h2 id="some-context-regarding-custodial-banks">Some context regarding custodial banks</h2>

<p>Many readers might wonder why a bank needs a bank. Indeed, McCauley’s verbal statement to Congress has a <a href="https://x.com/Anchorage/status/1887162623516725627">mic drop moment</a> where he expresses incredulity that a federally chartered bank could be debanked. It’s great theatre.</p>

<p>A fun bit of banking Compliance trivia: there exist <em>banks</em> which one cannot <em>bank</em> at.</p>

<p>Anchorage Digital Bank, National Association is one such bank.</p>

<p>Quoting Anchorage Digital’s home page’s fine print:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Anchorage Digital” refers to services that are offered through the wholly-owned subsidiaries of Anchor Labs, Inc., a Delaware corporation.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Anchorage Labs, Inc. is a tech company, and not a bank. That tech company has a <em>relationship with</em> Anchorage Digital Bank, National Association. That relationship involves receiving fees from the bank for services. As to whether it is an <em>ownership</em> relationship, well, I’d bet their lawyers can tell you a <em>scintillating</em> and true story about bank holding companies.</p>

<p>Anchorage Digital Bank, National Association makes much of the fact that they are a federally chartered bank, operating under the auspices of an agreement with the OCC.</p>

<p>Quoting Article V of their <a href="https://www.occ.gov/news-issuances/news-releases/2021/nr-occ-2021-6b.pdf">operating agreement with the OCC</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Bank shall limit its business to the operations of a trust company and
activities related or incidental thereto. The Bank shall not engage in activities that would cause it to be a “bank” as defined in section 2(c) of the Bank Holding Company Act.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Those activities? Taking deposits and making loans, the traditional business of banking.</p>

<p>Anchorage Digital was previously a trust company in South Dakota prior to getting the OCC charter.</p>

<p>Trust companies, a type of regulated financial institution, can run custody businesses. A custodian maintains legal and operational control of an asset, but does not <em>own</em> it. The owner pays them because keeping that asset safe and useful increases the value of the asset by more than the cost of custody. You are yourself, reader, very likely a beneficial owner of assets held at a custodian. This is especially likely if you hold financial assets which are not cryptocurrency tokens. You have probably not paid an invoice for these professional services directly. Another entity, such as e.g. your brokerage or a fund you are invested in, paid for them as a prerequisite to offering you a bundle of services, of which custody is one necessary component.</p>

<p>A custody business might have other modern products such as e.g. a real-time settlement API. That is one of Anchorage Digital’s marquis <a href="https://www.anchorage.com/platform/settlement">products</a>. For a fuller discussion of real-time settlement APIs and why the crypto industry considers them structurally important, see <em>Debanking</em>’s discussion of the Silvergate Exchange Network.</p>

<p>Speaking of crypto trust companies, remember Prime Trust? It was a Nevada chartered trust company, which also had a custody business. Prime Trust <a href="https://www.prnewswire.com/news-releases/financial-infrastructure-innovator-prime-trust-raises-64m-in-new-funding-as-annual-revenue-run-rate-crossed-100m-mark-301343163.html">purported</a> to be the adults-in-the-room bilingual-in-TradFi eagerly-complying-with-regulations crypto custody company. They were going to clean up the cowboy behavior in the industry. This is a familiar sales pitch, also made by FTX, Voyager, BlockFi, Genesis, and probably some firms which are still with us, too.</p>

<p>Prime Trust lost a portion of the assets they were custodying due to technical incompetence (they wrote seed phrases allowing recovery of private keys on a piece of metal… then lost the metal). They then misappropriated other customer assets to buy substitute assets to fund withdrawals. This, per <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.deb.190581/gov.uscourts.deb.190581.14.0.pdf">their bankruptcy filing</a>, resulted in insolvency which they concealed from their regulators and customers through intentional fraud.</p>

<p>When this came to light, they were closed by their regulators. This was in June of 2023. By coincidence, that is the same month that Anchorage Digital lost their banking partner.</p>

<p>This loud and notorious collapse of a major competitor to Anchorage Digital, happening as a result of incompetence and malfeasance, despite that competitor having said all the right things, as <em>part of a pattern</em>, seems relevant to the interests of banks in the summer of 2023. One might choose to recount it in describing those banks’ reticence to do business with one’s industry. Perhaps one might acknowledge that one’s prospective banks might have had legitimate concerns. (Washington professionally appreciates a well-executed limited hangout.) Having done so, one might tease out the nuance that those concerns <em>might have been surmountable</em> but for excessive regulatory pressure.</p>

<p>Time is precious in front of elected officials, though, and Anchorage eschewed that and stuck to simpler messaging.</p>

<p>Anchorage Digital mentioned its strong commitment to seeking (direct quote) “the highest level of regulatory scrutiny and certainty”, and its determination to meet the obligations it has signed up for. This was repeated multiple times for emphasis.</p>

<p>At approximately <a href="https://www.banking.senate.gov/hearings/investigating-the-real-impacts-of-debanking-in-america">1:08:30 in the recording of the Senate hearing</a>, CEO McCauley stated “That’s right. I’m a bit of a square, and like following rules, and so we always followed all the rules and regulations.”</p>

<p>I am also a bit of a square. I have never signed a consent order with the OCC regarding deficiencies in my bank’s BSA/AML program, however.</p>

<h3 id="my-business-cards-do-say-wire-transfer-compliance-influencer">My business cards do say “wire transfer compliance influencer”</h3>

<p>McCauley’s testimony that Anchorage lacks the ability to facilitate customer wires to third parties, “a basic banking service that we previously had access to”, may have surprised some listeners.</p>

<p>Readers of <em>Debanking</em> might be able to predict what point of view a <a href="https://www.anchorage.com/insights/anchorage-digital-initial-partner-in-global-dollar-network">sub-custodian bank</a> might have regarding AML risk of third-party wires for crypto clientele. The sub-custodian might not be moved by a valued customer’s complaints their customers are simply crypto-native and traditional institutions requesting wires to crypto-native counterparties.</p>

<p>Why not?</p>

<p>For example, readers might remember the statement (quoted in <em>Debanking</em>, on the basis of <a href="https://www.piratewires.com/p/inside-biden-admin-plot-to-destroy-silvergate-and-debank-crypto-for-good-nic-carter?f=author">reporting by Nic Carter</a>): <em>Where we were not as buttoned up as we should have been was in regards to the FTX/Alameda clients. That was a function of the bank growing incredibly quickly[.] … Probably we could have figured out FTX was brokering deposits via Alameda. In retrospect I think we could have pieced this together and figured it out.</em></p>

<p>Readers are welcome to their estimate of whether the quoted Silvergate executive, who Carter granted anonymity to, will work in banking again. Executives at many other banks do not relish the possibility of waking up to news that a crypto company was, once again, <em>not as buttoned up as it should have been.</em></p>

<h2 id="returning-to-our-regularly-scheduled-programming">Returning to our regularly scheduled programming</h2>

<p>As I point out in <em>Debanking</em> and elsewhere, crypto advocates would prefer to be judged on their potential rather than their track record. As a sometimes resident of Washington put it memorably: “What can be, unburdened by what has been.”</p>

<p>Optimism about future potential is highly prized in the startup community. It does not require unpublishing true claims about track records.</p>

<p>I continue to agree with crypto advocates on many of their claims. I will continue writing about the reality, warts and all, of the financial system. I will explain how history, humans, policy decisions, and technology have come together to deliver it. I will cover upgrades we’re collectively trying to build for it.</p>

<p>When those systems confound our expectations, or when their regulators <a href="https://x.com/patio11/status/1887567967392538641">are disregulated</a>, interested readers will find facts and fearlessness in <a href="https://www.bitsaboutmoney.com/">Bits about Money</a>.</p>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Anthropic Economic Index (445 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.anthropic.com/news/the-anthropic-economic-index</link>
            <guid>43000529</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 14:14:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/the-anthropic-economic-index">https://www.anthropic.com/news/the-anthropic-economic-index</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43000529">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.anthropic.com/news/the-anthropic-economic-index: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Surnames from nicknames nobody has any more (750 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.plover.com/lang/etym/nickname-names.html</link>
            <guid>43000316</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 13:54:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.plover.com/lang/etym/nickname-names.html">https://blog.plover.com/lang/etym/nickname-names.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43000316">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.plover.com/lang/etym/nickname-names.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: HTML visualization of a PDF file's internal structure (342 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/desgeeko/pdfsyntax/blob/main/docs/browse.md</link>
            <guid>43000303</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 13:52:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/desgeeko/pdfsyntax/blob/main/docs/browse.md">https://github.com/desgeeko/pdfsyntax/blob/main/docs/browse.md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43000303">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true" aria-labelledby="file-name-id-wide file-name-id-mobile"><article itemprop="text">
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h3><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Inspecting the internal structure of a PDF file involves a lot of things (decompression, parsing, xref indexing, etc...) in order to make sense of the raw bytes.</p>
<p dir="auto">PDFSyntax takes care of the processing and proposes a visualization approach that consists in adding information and hyperlinks on top of a text that is a mostly a pretty-print of the PDF data once uncompressed. It respects the physical flow of the file while offering a logical navigation between revisions (incremental updates) and between objects.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Architecture</h3><a id="user-content-architecture" aria-label="Permalink: Architecture" href="#architecture"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">PDFSyntax is a self-contained Python package - without any dependency - and is principally a low-level PDF library.
The <code>browse</code> command is its highest and most visible part. It produces static HTML content that offers sufficient interactivity: JavaScript may be disabled.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Demo</h3><a id="user-content-demo" aria-label="Permalink: Demo" href="#demo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Please try the <a href="https://pdfsyntax.dev/simple_text_string.html" rel="nofollow"><strong>LIVE DEMO</strong></a> of a full static HTML output that you can browse, at <a href="https://pdfsyntax.dev/simple_text_string.html" rel="nofollow">https://pdfsyntax.dev/simple_text_string.html</a> (hosted on GitHub Pages).</p>
<p dir="auto">Here is the same example, as a partial screenshot:
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/desgeeko/pdfsyntax/main/docs/screenshot.png"><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/desgeeko/pdfsyntax/main/docs/screenshot.png" alt="PDFSyntax screenshot"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">NB: this is the output produced for the <a href="https://github.com/desgeeko/pdfsyntax/raw/main/samples/simple_text_string.pdf"><em>Simple Text String</em></a> example file from the PDF Specification.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h3><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">PDFSyntax can be installed from the GitHub repo (no dependency) or from PyPI:</p>

<p dir="auto">Redirect the standard output to a file that you can open in your browser:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python3 -m pdfsyntax browse file.pdf > inspection_file.html"><pre><code>python3 -m pdfsyntax browse file.pdf &gt; inspection_file.html
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h3><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The generated HTML "looks" like an augmented raw PDF file with the following additional work:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Add a reverse index: links to where an object is used</li>
<li>Add a page index in a navigation menu</li>
<li>Add a physical minimap in a navigation menu</li>
<li>Indent to pretty-print dictionary objects</li>
<li>Extract objects contained in object streams and insert them in the flow like regular objects</li>
<li>Decompress streams and display a small part of it</li>
<li>Turn indirect object references into hyperlinks</li>
<li>Turn offset references (for example a /Prev entry) into hyperlinks</li>
<li>Display file offsets of objects in a left margin</li>
<li>Put some color on important names (for example /Type)</li>
<li>Put some color on warnings (for example the presence of /JS)</li>
<li>Light &amp; dark modes</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">WARNING: Encrypted files are not supported yet</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">WORK IN PROGRESS: New features are on the roadmap</p>
</blockquote>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What about K? (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xpqz.github.io/kbook/Introduction.html</link>
            <guid>42999650</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 12:51:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xpqz.github.io/kbook/Introduction.html">https://xpqz.github.io/kbook/Introduction.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42999650">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://xpqz.github.io/kbook/Introduction.html: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I built an open source AI tool to find my autoimmune disease (369 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/1ij7s4m/how_i_built_an_open_source_ai_tool_to_find_my/</link>
            <guid>42999632</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 12:48:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/1ij7s4m/how_i_built_an_open_source_ai_tool_to_find_my/">https://old.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/1ij7s4m/how_i_built_an_open_source_ai_tool_to_find_my/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42999632">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://old.reddit.com/r/selfhosted/comments/1ij7s4m/how_i_built_an_open_source_ai_tool_to_find_my/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Advertising Is a Cancer on Society (268 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jacek.zlydach.pl/blog/2019-07-31-ads-as-cancer.html</link>
            <guid>42999561</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 12:38:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jacek.zlydach.pl/blog/2019-07-31-ads-as-cancer.html">https://jacek.zlydach.pl/blog/2019-07-31-ads-as-cancer.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42999561">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div id="content">

<p>
<i>(last update: 2019-10-02)</i>
</p>

<p>
I frequently say that advertising is a cancer on modern society. This view is met
with various reactions, including requests for a more detailed explanation. In this post,
I first explain why I believe the cancer analogy is apt, then continue with a nonexhaustive
list of observable symptoms of this disease, and end with some final thoughts. This post
is a living document, updated over time, and intended to be linked to.
</p>

<p>
(When I say "advertising", I use this term somewhat loosely; this text applies not
just to the advertising material presented to customers, but to the broader process surrounding
its creation as well, which is more correctly referred to via a bunch of buzzwords
grouped under the term "marketing".)
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org33f1891">
<h2 id="org33f1891">Advertising as cancer</h2>
<div id="text-org33f1891">
<p>
Cancer is a family of diseases sharing some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Hallmarks_of_Cancer">common characteristics</a>. Cancer cells abandon their
normal cooperative role in a body, and instead start to replicate uncontrollably, engaging
in complex behaviors not just to avoid getting killed off by immune system, but to actually
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Angiogenesis"><b>convince</b> the body</a> to give them access to more and more resources.
</p>

<p>
Advertising as currently practiced shares these characteristics. It's a malignant mutation of an idea
that efficient markets need a way to connect goods and services with people wanting to buy them.
Limited to honestly informing people about what's available on the market, it can serve
a crucial function in enabling trade. In the real world however, it's moved way past that role.
</p>

<p>
Real world advertising is not about informing, it's about convincing. Over time, it became
increasingly manipulative and dishonest. It also became more effective. In the process, it grew
to consume a significant amount of resources of every company on the planet. It infected every
communication medium in existence, both digital and analog. It shapes every product and service
you touch, and it affects your interactions with everyone who isn't your close friend
or family member. Through all that, it actively destroys trust in people and institutions alike,
and corrupts the decision-making process in any market transaction. It became a legitimized form
of industrial-scale psychological abuse, <a href="https://hackernoon.com/nobody-is-immune-to-ads-7142a4245c2c">and there's no way you can resist its impact</a>.
</p>

<p>
The growth of advertising is fueled by the enormous waste it creates. In any somewhat
saturated market - which, today, is most of them - any effort you spent on advertising serves
primarily to counteract the combined advertising efforts of your competitors. The same results
could be achieved if every market player limited themselves to just informing customers about
their goods and services. This, unfortunately, is impossible for humanity, and so we end up
with a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zero-sum_game">zero-sum game</a> instead (or really negative-sum, if you count the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Externality">externalities</a>). If you have
competitors, <a href="https://birdsite.link/@matthew_d_green/102731799491877657">you can't not participate</a>.
</p>

<p>
Tallying up: uncontrolled growth? Check. Destructive consequences? Check. Hard to kill?
Check. Co-opts resources? Check. Advertising has the characteristics of cancer.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org210d57d">
<h2 id="org210d57d">Symptoms of the disease</h2>
<p>
This list is nonexhaustive and will be updated over time, as I encounter more interesting
examples of advertising inconveniencing or hurting people.
</p>

<div id="outline-container-org2b33dd9">
<h3 id="org2b33dd9">Privacy violations</h3>
<div id="text-org2b33dd9">
<p>
The obvious one and a hot topic now. Adtech industry is solely responsible for creating and
deploying the most advanced surveillance system ever seen in history. Something far beyond
even the wildest dreams of the Stasi, NSA, or Orwell himself. The infrastructure is ready
and works today. You interact with it every time you go on-line, and increasingly off-line
as well. From <a href="https://twitter.com/GambleLee/status/862307447276544000/photo/1">being subject to face recognition when going for a pizza</a>, through
<a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-bose-lawsuit-idUSKBN17L2BT">your headphones recording and sending out what you listen to</a>, <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20183968">your phone telling on you as you walk through the mall</a>,
<a href="https://www.seattletimes.com/business/technology/how-your-smart-tv-is-keeping-track-of-more-than-what-youre-watching/">your TV knowing about what's going on in your house</a>, to <a href="https://www.consumerreports.org/automotive-technology/who-owns-the-data-your-car-collects/">your car spying on you as you drive</a>,
it's almost impossible to escape being surveilled now.  There's really <b>nothing</b> stopping
any government from tapping into this total surveillance infrastructure other than lack of will.
All they need to do is ask, and while your country may not care today, it might start after the
next terror attack (or news-about-terror induced panic).
</p>

<p>
(Ironically, what governments currently do is sell private data <b>to</b> advertisers. For instance, if
you live in the US and drive a car, there's a good chance your data was <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20438289">sold by your state's DMV</a>.)
</p>

<p>
Adtech industry is getting ever more creative. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evercookie">Evercookies</a> are now considered ancient technology;
apparently even fingerprinting factory sensor calibration <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20064961">is old-school</a>.
</p>

<p>
See also <a href="https://lockwood.dev/advertising/2019/06/14/adtech-sucks-this-time-its-personal-ids.html#fnref">this</a>, if you are wondering exactly what does the adtech industry do with all the data
it collects, how does it do it and why. Spoiler alert: all the data is being continuously
traded in order to cross-correlate it, ensuring no matter what steps you make to protect
your privacy, advertisers can recover the data they need. It also allows the advertisers
to scam each other on attribution, which isn't surprising if you consider that lying is <i>literally</i>
their job. Cancer cells don't play well with each other unless they have to.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org8c95da7">
<h3 id="org8c95da7">Health-related privacy violations</h3>
<div id="text-org8c95da7">
<p>
I'm making this into a separate headline because this is some of the most sensitive
and damaging if abused information, which nonetheless is being abused.
</p>

<p>
Did you know that popular apps used by women to track their periods
<a href="https://www.privacyinternational.org/long-read/3196/no-bodys-business-mine-how-menstruation-apps-are-sharing-your-data">spy on them and send the data off to advertisers</a>, who then use it to target both app users and
their partners? This data is <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20923895">surprisingly valuable</a>, at least for those with no dignity.
</p>

<p>
Mental health issues still have social stigma attached in the western world. For a person
seeking help in such a case, privacy is extremely important. Unfortunately, that privacy
is sometimes discarded in exchange for advertising revenue. A <a href="https://privacyinternational.org/long-read/3194/privacy-international-study-shows-your-mental-health-sale">recent investigation</a> into
popular mental health websites in France, Germany and the UK revealed that most of them
track visitors for advertising purposes, some even sharing mental health test answers
with third parties.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org69eccd4">
<h3 id="org69eccd4">Robocalls, telemarketing</h3>
<div id="text-org69eccd4">
<p>
Slight annoyance in the EU (slightly bigger if you run a business), makes phones near-useless
for receiving calls in the US. Some of the calls are pure fraud, others - those made
by otherwise reputable companies - are just attempts at selling you something you don't
need for the price that usually isn't fair. If you ever had your parents or grandparents
spend a big chunk of their income or pension on some low-quality trinket, you know who to thank.
</p>

<p>
Here's <a href="https://mastodon.cloud/@dredmorbius/102404468325136055">a decent argument</a> that advertising may ultimately kill phones as a service.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orge9efce4">
<h3 id="orge9efce4">Spam</h3>
<p>
Mostly handled today through filters built into every mail service, but a pure example
of what happens when advertising is near-free. Similarly to robocalls, it severely diminished
the utility of e-mail as a service, driving people towards walled-in social networks, where
spam is easier to control (mostly through directing advertisers to different channels).
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org6e4007f">
<h3 id="org6e4007f">Leaflets, snail mail spam</h3>
<p>
It's an off-line equivalent to spam, except you have to move them to the
garbage bin yourself - and a lot of people can't even be bothered to do that,
so <a href="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/3/36/Flyers_sobe_2.jpg">they litter cities everywhere</a>. It's a pure and unadulterated waste of
paper, paint and fuel, made in the hope that one in a thousand will convince
someone to maybe think about buying something.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org8af0ecc">
<h3 id="org8af0ecc">Search Engine Optimization</h3>
<div id="text-org8af0ecc">
<p>
SEO, AKA. gaming the search engines. Hugely popular. Often involves creating nonsense sites,
and spamming websites and web forums with comments. It pollutes search results for more
obscure queries, generally wasting people's time.
</p>

<p>
I used to run comments on this blog, and had my fair share of run-ins with SEO spammers.
I sometimes traced back the companies that were promoted in such way and contacted them with
requests to please stop spamming the Internet. It turned out that some of them didn't know
that the SEO agencies they hired engaged in comment spam (in one of those cases, upon me
contacting them the business apologized and immediately dropped their contact with their SEO agency;
<a href="https://jacek.zlydach.pl/blog/2011-09-19-spam-seo-i-fotografia-slubna.html">I keep a post praising them up to this day</a>.)
</p>
</div>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-org0d4d9cf">
<h3 id="org0d4d9cf">Exploiting children</h3>
<div id="text-org0d4d9cf">
<p>
Children usually don't have money, but they are easy to manipulate and do have the undivided attention of
their parents. A classical tactic is to <a href="https://mastodon.technology/@temporal/102258241583566636">drop a child-targeted ad in between episodes of a children's show</a>,
and watch the money flow in. But that's old-school now. Nowadays, both TV and streaming services
are full of content that mix branding and entertainment, and <a href="https://www.tubefilter.com/2019/03/22/youtube-toy-unboxing-advertising-children-lawsuit/">unboxing videos</a> are the new way
of working around the laws protecting children from advertising around the world. Ads don't stop there
either, they're <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/10/30/style/kids-study-apps-advertising.html">in almost every popular mobile app for kids</a>.
</p>

<p>
Also, the sophisticated adtech personalization algorithms, like always, <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-44448936">screw things up</a>.
</p>

<p>
This is why my kid isn't going to watch YouTube. If and when we decide to show her any children's show,
it'll be from a manually curated set of videos <a href="https://github.com/ytdl-org/youtube-dl">downloaded</a> and streamed from a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network-attached_storage">NAS</a>. In my opinion,
it's irresponsible to expose children to modern advertising.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orge0c52af">
<h3 id="orge0c52af">Lack of taste</h3>
<p>
This is a pet peeve. As (of 2019) a fresh father, I've recently been exposed to a lot of advertising
for infant care products. I can survive free samples of gunk of dubious utility given to us at every
possible occasion. But when I received the "child health book" - <b>an official medical document</b> in which
health information is recorded over the years - I was floored when I noticed it had multiple full-page
ads in it. This is a document that is provided by publicly-funded hospitals. A document that
will likely outlive all the companies advertising in it. This is what the ad industry jumping the shark
looks like.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org1b62037">
<h3 id="org1b62037">Brand-awareness</h3>
<div id="text-org1b62037">
<p>
Almost everybody on the planet knows about Coca Cola and McDonald's. A good chunk of the population
has tasted both. So why do both companies still spend <a href="https://www.statista.com/statistics/286541/mcdonald-s-advertising-spending-worldwide/">hundreds of millions</a> to <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/articles/markets/081315/look-cocacolas-advertising-expenses.asp">billions of dollars</a> on
ads that they know aren't going to convince you to drop everything you do and buy their products?
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brand_awareness">Brand awareness</a>. The goal here is to force an association between a product category and a brand,
so that when you are considering buying a product from that category, their brand will be the
one on your mind, and the one you feel safest buying.
</p>

<p>
Brand awareness competes for very limited real estate in your brain, so when you have
multiple brands competing, the end result is saturation bombing. That's why you can't walk
500 meters straight in a typical western city without seeing a Coca Cola logo somewhere.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org56705ea">
<h3 id="org56705ea">Dark UX patterns</h3>
<p>
<a href="https://www.darkpatterns.org/">Defined as</a> "tricks used in websites and apps that make you do things that you didn't mean to". Here's <a href="https://www.darkpatterns.org/types-of-dark-pattern">a non-exhaustive list</a>,
which unfortunately some morally bankrupt companies seem to use as a cookbook. It's an unfortunate feature
of a reality in which advertising has perverted the marketplace to the point it's very difficult to
compete by just offering a good product at a fair price.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org1f3b80a">
<h3 id="org1f3b80a">Advertising-induced design problems</h3>
<div id="text-org1f3b80a">
<p>
The consequence of long-term exposure to dark patterns is that people develop immunity, which sometimes
claims benign or beneficial use cases as collateral damage. See for example this article about
<a href="https://digital.nhs.uk/blog/transformation-blog/2019/icons-avoid-temptation-and-start-with-user-needs">redesign of UK's National Health Service website</a>, where boxes containing important health-related
information were found to be ignored by users:
</p>

<blockquote>
<p>
To our astonishment, a number of users said that they wouldn’t read the
information in the boxes. They likened them to advertising on news sites and
overlooked them because of the ambiguity of the icon and the ‘READ ME!!!’
look.
</p>
</blockquote>

<p>
Measures to combat web spam (i.e. advertisers doing their daily job) also at times
<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20058697">conflict with accessibility</a>, causing websites to be unusable for people utilizing screen readers.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org581716e">
<h3 id="org581716e">Malware and computing resource exhaustion</h3>
<div id="text-org581716e">
<p>
There are three main reasons people install ad blockers. Dislike of ads, preventing privacy
incursions, and protecting your own computer from malware and unwanted software that eats
up its resources.
</p>

<p>
If you haven't read the excellent essay by Maciej Ceglowski, <a href="https://idlewords.com/talks/website_obesity.htm">The Website Obesity Crisis</a>, take a break
now and hop over. Maciej is a much better writer than me, and gives an excellent explanation of why
all the websites you visit load so slowly and eat so much of your mobile data allowance. Spoiler alert:
ads are a big part of the problem.
</p>

<p>
As for malware, the technical term is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Malvertising">malvertising</a>. Given how ad delivery works today - auctions
triggered by your browsing, determining what ad you'll be shown next, almost entirely outside
of control of the site that you're visiting, the old wisdom of "don't visit porn sites or you'll get malware"
doesn't hold anymore. You can catch malware on almost any site that shows you ads now.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgf1538a6">
<h3 id="orgf1538a6">Flooding the Internet with garbage content</h3>
<p>
This includes things affectionately known as "blog spam" or "content marketing". Quite likely
the majority of articles regular people read on-line and share on social media. In its least
harmful form, it just wastes your time, providing you with very little actionable information
padded with some prose. I've seen first-hand how much work goes into making such material:
very little, mostly copy-pasting and rewording someone else's blog spam. The more dangerous incarnations
are purposeful misinformation. Bottom line, this content doesn't exist to help you - it exists
as a vector for delivering more advertising to you, either inline or through the site it's hosted on.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgc1c8fc8">
<h3 id="orgc1c8fc8">Native advertising</h3>
<p>
Though <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Native_advertising">defined</a> as advertising "that matches the form and function of the platform upon which it appears",
it's marketing code for "disguising an ad as legitimate content". While unmarked ads are technically illegal
in many places, ask yourself, <i>how can you tell</i> that the article you recently read mentioning a company
was honest, and not sponsored content? It ain't trivial.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org0ec9fc2">
<h3 id="org0ec9fc2">Influencers</h3>
<div id="text-org0ec9fc2">
<p>
AKA. people selling themselves out on the Internet. The whole idea is to subvert <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_proof">social proof</a> by finding
people others can relate to and getting them to indirectly push products. Hugely popular on YouTube
and Instagram, and is again preying on people having trouble distinguishing fake from genuine.
At this level of sophistication, aren't we all such people, at some point? When you look at that
newest Facebook photo of a family member, are they really that bad at cleaning kitchen they
leave bags of expensive coffee out in the open, or are they a <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2018/11/11/business/media/nanoinfluencers-instagram-influencers.html">nanoinfluencer</a>?
</p>

<p>
I can't stress enough how bad this is. In a world drowned in manipulative advertising, your circle
of friends and colleagues you know personally is your last source of trustworthy recommendations.
Sure, there were bad apples before - like people who join <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Multi-level_marketing">MLM cults</a> - but they were obnoxious
enough to easily be spotted. But in general, you could trust the direct and indirect advice
of people in your social circle. "Influencing" is an ongoing attempt to poison that.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org3996d45">
<h3 id="org3996d45">Billboards</h3>
<p>
They pollute our landscape and distract drivers. To my surprise, the studies I've seen so far (<a href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4411179/">1</a>, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0001457515301664">2</a>)
conclude that billboards aren't usually a safety issue, even though they measurably capture
the attention of drivers. Still, I think everyone who like me regularly travels outside the city
can attest that the experience would be better without them.
</p>
</div>





<div id="outline-container-org431d1d9">
<h3 id="org431d1d9">Decaying and ephemeral Internet services</h3>
<div id="text-org431d1d9">
<p>
Have you noticed how many free services get significantly worse over time? <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20525136">Have you noticed</a>
that just a couple of years ago, your Facebook and Instagram feeds contained almost exclusively
posts from your social network, whereas today they mostly show sponsored content and posts
from businesses?
</p>

<p>
Ad-driven business models win users over by offering a service for free, but in order to grow,
that service needs to continuously increase the amount of advertising and tracking it does.
Few of such services stay alive for long (usually thanks to the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_effect">network effect</a>), but all
of them prevent companies with more ethical and stable business models from entering the market by
sucking up all the available oxygen. You can't compete on price with free, doubly so in an era
where ad-driven businesses are what the investors prefer.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org4175850">
<h3 id="org4175850">Less innovation, worse products</h3>
<div id="text-org4175850">
<p>
Marketing these days seems to have so good ROI that, given a fixed sum of money,
you're better off spending it on shouting louder than on actually improving the product.
This reduces research, development and production spending, which indirectly reduces the actual value provided
to all of us by the economy.
</p>

<p>
(h/t <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/sorceryofthespectacle/comments/ckm9jk/advertising_is_a_cancer_on_society/evqcu2d/">u/slippage for reminding me of that</a>. I think everyone working in the software industry can relate.)
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org432f4cc">
<h3 id="org432f4cc">"It's just another revenue stream!"</h3>
<div id="text-org432f4cc">
<p>
With all the cries that free content must be paid for somehow, you'd expect that you can avoid
"being the product" if you pay the full price for a product or service. Nothing could be farther
from the truth. Movie theaters will still spam you with ads even though you paid for the ticket
and bought the popcorn. Newspapers will show you ads, whether or not you're a paying subscriber
(and they won't filter out native advertising content either). SaaS companies charge your credit
card with one hand, and sell your data with the other. Even your <a href="https://www.privacycompany.eu/en/new-dpia-on-microsoft-office-and-windows-software-still-privacy-risks-remaining-short-blog/">Office suite spies on you</a> (at least
the web and mobile versions do), and gives your data to a predictive profiling marketing firm.
</p>

<p>
This is a cultural problem. We've become so accustomed to advertising that not having it shoved
in our face is a premium service that needs to be explicitly requested, and is rarely available.
</p>

<p>
(h/t Stavros for pointing this out to me. I'm so used to it that I haven't even thought of it.)
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org69b7ee6">
<h3 id="org69b7ee6">Annoying cookie popups</h3>
<p>
People tend to blame this on the European Union, but the truth is that under cookie laws,
sites are only required to show you a consent popup if they're using cookies for things
other than primary functionality of the site. If you're annoyed by them, be annoyed at the site,
as it only shows the warning because it tracks you.
</p>
</div>



<div id="outline-container-org3dc1197">
<h3 id="org3dc1197">Subversion of science</h3>
<p>
I remember reading about cases of scientific papers that were advertisements pretending to be
research work. I'll update this point when I find some actual examples.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org741a51d">
<h2 id="org741a51d">Final thoughts</h2>
<div id="text-org741a51d">
<p>
Cancers ultimately damage critical functions of the body and lead to untimely death. Advertising,
similarly, poses a risk to our civilization through resource exhaustion, <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0195925517303505">climate impact</a>, and by eroding the
basic building block of societies - trust in one another, and trust in institutions we deal with.
What can be done about it?
</p>

<p>
I honestly have no good ideas. Advertising is so thoroughly embedded in our economies that trying
to "just" get rid of it would probably collapse our civilization (<a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=20447671">which is NOT a good thing</a>; I'll
expand on this in the future). I feel this problem will need to be solved the hard way, piece by
piece, slowly reclaiming our institutions, our trust, our dignity.
Here's a non-exhaustive list of suggestions I'll be updating over time:
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orged5685f">
<h3 id="orged5685f">Ad blockers and tracking blockers</h3>
<div id="text-orged5685f">
<p>
Obvious first step. Install <a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock">uBlock Origin</a> on all your browsers (on Android, switch to Firefox,
which supports extensions). Add <a href="https://www.eff.org/privacybadger">Privacy Badger</a> for good measure. Consider <a href="https://noscript.net/">NoScript</a> if you're
particularly annoyed by the website obesity crisis. If you have non-tech-savvy friends and family,
install uBlock Origin on their machines too - that'll let them extend the usable lifetime of their
computers by a couple of years.
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://adnauseam.io/">AdNauseam</a> is an interesting extension to consider too. It's based off uBlock Origin, except it
clicks on the ads in the background, in an attempt to make advertising more expensive and poison
the data they collect. Given the level of sophistication of fake click detection, it's unlikely to
make much difference, but "every small step counts", plus it also feels satisfying.
</p>

<p>
If you're willing to put up with some extra inconvenience on-line in order to both protect
yourself from advertisers and safeguard your privacy, consider using <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/gnuzilla/">GNU IceCat</a> as your main
browser. It's a Firefox variant with extra features aiming to defeat tracking and reduce
exposure to <a href="https://www.fsf.org/about/what-is-free-software">ethically questionable software</a>.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org92e5faf">
<h3 id="org92e5faf">GDPR</h3>
<div id="text-org92e5faf">
<p>
GDPR is doing an excellent job destroying some of the most privacy-invasive practices of the
adtech industry. It offers a great opportunity for individual meaningful action. If you're
an European and see a site trying to abuse you in a way that's illegal, <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/law-topic/data-protection/reform/rights-citizens/redress/what-should-i-do-if-i-think-my-personal-data-protection-rights-havent-been-respected_en">file a complaint</a>.
If you're not an EU citizen, lobby your government to enact similar legislation. The movements
around this are gaining steam worldwide.
</p>

<p>
Some people point out that <a href="https://cliqz.com/en/magazine/study-google-is-the-biggest-beneficiary-of-the-gdpr">Google benefited the most</a> from GDPR, and more legislation like it would
only make life even more difficult for innovative adtech upstarts, benefiting the large incumbents
instead. But this might actually be a <b>good thing</b> - we don't need more innovation in that market,
we need that market to wither and die. It's also easier for regulators to keep few larger companies
in line than it is to deal with a convoluted network of fly-by-night adtech startups.
</p>

<p>
(See also an <a href="https://www.gnu.org/philosophy/surveillance-vs-democracy.html">argument by Richard Stallman</a> that GDPR and similar legislation aren't nearly enough,
and one should aim to prevent data collection from happening in the first place. This is related
to the concept of <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/Datensparsamkeit.html">Datensparsamkeit</a>, or "data frugality".)
</p>

<p>
GDPR is primarily about control over data, not about advertising. But it's also important to push
for legislation targeting advertisers directly. São Paulo is among many cities that have managed
to <a href="https://99percentinvisible.org/article/clean-city-law-secrets-sao-paulo-uncovered-outdoor-advertising-ban/">ban outdoor advertising</a>, demonstrating it's both possible and worthwhile.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgb43df94">
<h3 id="orgb43df94">Fair business practices</h3>
<p>
Businesses are made of people, and people have ethics. If you're running one, consider the way you advertise.
Are you aiming at making mutually beneficial transactions, or are you just trying to milk
you users out of their hard-earned cash? Not all advertising is inherently harmful to individuals
or society. Choose the ethical option. It may cost your company some lost profits, but then again,
you may gain loyal customers who'll want to reward a honest business.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org22323f9">
<h3 id="org22323f9">Refuse to do business with companies behaving abusively</h3>
<div id="text-org22323f9">
<p>
Also known as "voting with your wallet". Out of set of options, pick the more honest one.
If you have a moment, tell the others why you didn't choose them.
</p>

<p>
Once again, businesses are made of people. Out of those that engage in abusive or harmful marketing,
not all have ill intent. These days, "dark patterns" are essentially forced upon
companies by competitive markets, and it's hard to resist. But maybe, just maybe, enough complaints
from real would-be customers will cause some of them to change their ways.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orgd20cff5">
<h3 id="orgd20cff5">Refuse to work on adtech</h3>
<p>
This applies to technologists out here - we're in a privileged position, where it's much easier
for us to be picky about the jobs we do than for most other people. Many of us already make
principled stances like refusing to work on defense projects; why not also avoid helping the
industry that harms people during peace time much more than defense companies?
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org7f50f2d">
<h3 id="org7f50f2d">Don't lose hope</h3>
<p>
There's light at the end of this tunnel (and it's not the incoming train).
A <a href="https://www.eff.org/deeplinks/2019/07/adblocking-how-about-nah">recent article by the EFF</a> reminds us of pop-up ads which, once the menace of the Internet, have
all but disappeared. The advertising industry is laser-focused on methods that manipulate people best.
If a technique stops working, e.g. because of legal, social or technical interference, it's
immediately abandoned. This means that advertising can be fought off piece by piece. It's hard,
but possible.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org1c8ea39">
<h3 id="org1c8ea39">Raise awareness</h3>
<p>
All of the suggestions above scale with the number of people who follow them. The more of us
rise against advertising, the stronger the market, social and political signals become.
So, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/V_for_Vendetta_(film)">if you see what I see, if you feel as I feel, and if you would seek as I seek</a>, then I ask you
to spread the message. Speak up about the cancerous nature of advertising, and how better off we all
would be if that disease was cured.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-org26c1c1d">
<h2 id="org26c1c1d">Credits</h2>
<p>
Thanks to Stavros Korokithakis and Michael McCune for reviewing drafts of this post and providing helpful suggestions.
</p>
</div>

<div id="outline-container-orga5cd233">
<h2 id="orga5cd233">Update history</h2>
<div id="text-orga5cd233">
<ul>
<li>2019-10-02 - Added: Spying in Office Mobile, menstruation apps, mental health websites; global warming angle;
marketing vs. development expenses; RMS thoughts on GDPR; outdoor advertising ban.</li>
<li>2019-07-31 - Initial publication</li>
</ul>
</div>
</div>
</div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The state of Rust trying to catch up with Ada [video] (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fosdem.org/2025/schedule/event/fosdem-2025-5356-the-state-of-rust-trying-to-catch-up-with-ada/</link>
            <guid>42998061</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 08:30:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fosdem.org/2025/schedule/event/fosdem-2025-5356-the-state-of-rust-trying-to-catch-up-with-ada/">https://fosdem.org/2025/schedule/event/fosdem-2025-5356-the-state-of-rust-trying-to-catch-up-with-ada/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42998061">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://fosdem.org/2025/schedule/event/fosdem-2025-5356-the-state-of-rust-trying-to-catch-up-with-ada/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[To buy a Tesla Model 3, only to end up in hell (423 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.myteslaexperience.com/2025-02-01/to-buy-a-tesla-mode-3-only-to-end-up-in-hell</link>
            <guid>42998024</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 08:25:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.myteslaexperience.com/2025-02-01/to-buy-a-tesla-mode-3-only-to-end-up-in-hell">https://www.myteslaexperience.com/2025-02-01/to-buy-a-tesla-mode-3-only-to-end-up-in-hell</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42998024">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <p><span>Written by</span>
    
        My Tesla Experience
    

    
      <br>
      <span>on&nbsp;</span><time datetime="2025-02-01 23:00:00 +0000">February 01, 2025</time>
    
  </p>

  
  

  <p>In October 2024 I decided to buy a <a href="https://www.tesla.com/model3">Tesla Model 3</a>. When I picked up the car, many of its features did not work (cameras, GPS navigation system, autopilot, software updates, etc.). It turned out to be <a href="https://electrek.co/2024/12/16/tesla-major-issue-self-driving-computer-inside-new-cars/">a major issue with Tesla’s brand-new on-board computer</a>. This is a common failure in Tesla Model 3 cars manufactured in the last quarter of 2024. The issue has affected thousands of Tesla customers. Two weeks later, the car began to <strong>lose 8% battery daily</strong>. Several drivers experiencing the same failure have also reported <strong>problems with the braking (ABS) and suspension (EPS) systems</strong>.</p>

<p>Tesla acknowledges all faults in the vehicle (except for battery losses, a fact on which it has not yet formally commented). The company refuses to accept a return of the vehicle without penalty, even though the problems were reported immediately. The only solution they offer is to make me wait 3 months for a miraculous replacement part. Ignored and without any type of compensation, I live attached to a car that needs a <strong>full recharge every 12 days to not die</strong>. For my own safety, and that of other drivers, I have stopped driving the vehicle.</p>

<p>In this blog I tell you how it happened. If you are the owner of a Tesla car, or you are thinking about buying one, I encourage you to read my blog and see up close how <strong>Elon Musk’s company</strong> treats their own customers. It is possible that if you have problems with your car, you will end up living in hell.</p>

<h2 id="the-road-to-a-tesla">The road to a Tesla</h2>

<p>It’s been over 4 years since I stopped driving regularly.</p>

<p>At the end of 2020, my partner and I moved to <strong>Shenzhen</strong> (China). My old car, a <strong>Renault Clio DCI 1.5</strong>, stayed in Spain. I had bought it second-hand in 2007, and it served me well for more than 10 years. I never had big problems. Upon returning from China, at the end of 2023, my wife and I went to live in <strong>Slovakia</strong>, where she is from. That’s when I made the decision that in 2024 I would buy a new car.</p>

<p>I’m not a motor enthusiast. I like to drive, and I have had the opportunity to take long car trips through Spain and other countries, but I know little about cars. Therefore, when purchasing a new vehicle, I decided to follow the advice of what experts call <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wisdom_of_the_crowd">“the wisdom of the crowd”</a>. Of the list of the <a href="https://www.xataka.com/movilidad/coches-vendidos-2023-2024-espana">10 best-selling cars in Spain</a>, the one that caught my attention the most was the <strong>Toyota Corolla</strong>. It is a car that I had already driven as a rental vehicle on several occasions. The decision was almost made, my next car would be a Toyota Corolla.</p>

<p>It was during a family gathering in August when I decided to ask my cousins, much more educated than me in the world of motors, for advice. One of them had a <a href="https://www.autocar.co.uk/car-review/kia/ev6">Kia EV6</a>. He was very satisfied with it, so the idea of buying an electric car began to float around in my head.</p>

<p>I started reading blogs and online magazines about electric cars. I soon came to the conclusion that the <strong>Tesla Model 3</strong> is, today, the best EV in terms of quality and price. It is the electric car with the lowest consumption (12.5 kW / 100 km), and it is also the best-selling EV in the world (again <em>the wisdom of the crowd</em>). In addition, there is the incentive of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tesla_Supercharger">Tesla Charger Network</a>. After reading an article on my friend Alberto Ruibal’s blog in which he argues <a href="https://www.alonsoruibal.com/el-tesla-model-3-sale-mas-barato-que-un-dacia-sandero/">why the Tesla Model 3 is cheaper than a Dacia Sandero</a> (in Spanish), I ended up being completely convinced. My next car would be a Tesla Model 3.</p>

<h2 id="buying-a-tesla-where-there-is-no-tesla">Buying a Tesla where there is no Tesla</h2>

<p>A Tesla car is always purchased through <a href="https://www.tesla.com/">Tesla’s website</a>. If you live in a country where Tesla is officially present, you would simply go to the website and buy your car from your country (for example, <em>Tesla Spain</em>). Unfortunately, Tesla is still not present in some countries in Europe. That is the case of countries such as Slovenia, Latvia, Lithuania or <strong>Slovakia</strong>, where I live. If Tesla is not present in your country of residence, you would go to Tesla’s website and buy your car at <strong>Tesla Europe</strong>, which is physically located in <strong>Tilburg</strong> (Holland). In short, when you live in a European country where there is no Tesla you have to import your car from Holland (See <strong>NOTE</strong>).</p>

<p>Importing the car from Holland implies an additional investment of time and money. More time, because you will have to complete <strong>more bureaucratic procedures to register the car</strong> in your country of residence. More money, because you will need to hire a transport company to <strong>bring your car from Holland</strong>. It is not possible to travel to Holland, get to Tilburg, and drive the car from there.</p>

<p>Another problem with importing the car is that, in case there is some type of subsidy for the acquisition of EVs in your country of residence, it is likely you will not be able to use it if the vehicle is imported.</p>

<p>I estimate that the total import costs were slightly over 2000 EUR.</p>

<p><strong>NOTE</strong>: In some Internet online boards I read that it is possible to buy the car in any other country in Europe, but normally users who choose this option usually have problems with VAT refunds.</p>

<h2 id="transporting-a-car-from-holland">Transporting a car from Holland</h2>

<p>I made my reservation on <strong>October 5, 2024</strong>. Three weeks later, specifically on <strong>October 31</strong>, the car was already available for pickup. I then contacted a vehicle transport company, <a href="https://www.tradisa.com/">Tradisa</a>, to organize the delivery.</p>

<p>Incidentally, just when the car was arriving, I was in Spain. Therefore, Tradisa suggested me to contact <a href="https://www.drivetesla.sk/">DriveTesla.sk</a>. This is a company in Slovakia that is dedicated to importing Tesla cars. They offer services such as vehicle purchase, registration, insurance, etc. I contracted several services with them: insurance, car registration and deposit service (in addition to winter tires). On <strong>November 4</strong>, Tradisa dropped the car off at DriveTesla facilities and three weeks later, once I was back in Slovakia, I went to Bratislava to pick up the car. It was <strong>Friday, November 29</strong>. After almost 2 months since the reservation, the car was finally in my hands!</p>

<p>But not everything was going to be good news. One of DriveTesla’s staff members warned me: <em>“By the way, the cameras are not working. Probably it can be fixed by updating the Operating System.”</em> I didn’t know it at the time, but my nightmare was about to begin…</p>

<h2 id="hands-on-the-wheel">Hands on the wheel</h2>

<p>Making the jump from a <strong>20-year-old Renault Clio</strong> to a <strong>Tesla Model 3</strong> is not trivial. I’d driven automatic cars before, but at least they had a physical gear-shifter! :) For 45 minutes, one of the DriveTesla staff members taught me the gist of how the car worked. We also took the opportunity to try to update the Operating System and solve the <strong>cameras problem</strong>, but <strong>the download got stuck halfway through</strong>. It seems like I wasn’t going to be able to fix the cameras, but did I really need them? <em>“My old Clio didn’t have cameras, I’m not going to miss them”</em>, I thought.</p>

<p>I was expecting a long trip, so before hitting the road I decided to take a few laps to practice. I practiced until I felt comfortable. Before leaving, I looked up my destination on the car’s <strong>GPS navigator</strong>. Bad luck, the GPS didn’t work either. <em>“What difference does it make? My old Clio didn’t have a GPS navigator either. I’m not going to miss it”</em>, I thought again. I pulled my phone out of my pocket, looked for my destination on Google Maps (a small town in the middle of Slovakia where I would meet my wife), and this time, I hit the road.</p>

<p>On the way it started to rain. I remembered what I was told me during the instruction: <em>“the Tesla Model 3 has a <strong>windshield wiper that comes into operation automatically</strong> when it starts raining”</em>. It was raining and raining, but the automatic windshield wipers didn’t kick in. On the steering wheel hub, there is also a physical button to activate the wipers manually. I had no choice but to start pressing that button, and continue doing it often because unfortunately it wasn’t raining, it was pouring. From the Tesla’s main screen, it’s possible to set the windshield wiper speed. However, I prefer to <strong>not take my eyes off the road</strong> when I drive. After a long time of almost continuously pressing the button, I discovered that the speed can also be set by pressing the button twice in a row very quickly.</p>

<p>After an hour and a half of driving, I stopped the car to rest and stretch my legs. That’s when I understood what was happening. Since the cameras were not working, the automatic windshield wipers did not work either. Paying more attention to the information screen, I realized of several notifications warning that other functionalities in the car were not available. For example, <strong>lane departure detection</strong>, <strong>sleep detection</strong> or <strong>emergency brake</strong>. That is to say, <strong>everything that depended on the car’s cameras didn’t work</strong>, including <strong>Autopilot</strong> obviously (but luckily it didn’t occur to me to try it lol). Another thing that didn’t work was <strong>syncing with Spotify</strong>. I mean, I managed to pair Spotify from my phone to the Tesla, but when I started playing music, the song stopped after 10 seconds. This always happened, regardless of which song.</p>

<p>Even so, I still had hope inside of me all this could be solved by updating the Operating System. Because we already know that hope is the last thing ever lost and we human beings are forever optimists.</p>

<h2 id="a-broken-car">A broken car</h2>

<p>On Sunday <strong>December 1</strong>, when I got home, I tried to update the Operating System again. No luck. Same problem again, the download hung halfway.</p>

<p>The next day, I gave it another try with the same result. So on Tuesday, <strong>December 3</strong>, I gave up completely and opened a ticket, through the Tesla app, at the <strong>Budapest Service Center</strong> (my closest Tesla Service Center). I described all the technical problems I had observed in the car so far:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The <strong>cameras</strong> are not working.</li>
  <li>The <strong>GPS navigator</strong> is not working.</li>
  <li>Nothing that depends on the cameras works: <strong>Autopilot</strong>, <strong>automatic windshield wipers</strong>, <strong>automatic lights</strong>, <strong>lane departure detection</strong>, <strong>drowsiness detection</strong>, etc.</li>
  <li><strong>OS updates</strong> are not working</li>
  <li><strong>Spotify</strong> is not working.</li>
</ul>

<p>After four days without receiving a response from the <strong>Budapest Service Center</strong>, I texted them again. On the sixth day, terribly worried, I called <strong>Tesla Customer Service</strong>. After a long wait, I managed to speak to an agent. As I was describing the problem, he already knew what the issue was about. This article, authored by <strong>Fred Lambert</strong> for <strong>Electrek</strong>, explains the problem in the car: <a href="https://electrek.co/2024/12/16/tesla-major-issue-self-driving-computer-inside-new-cars">Tesla is having major issue with its self-driving computer inside new cars</a>. The article describes a fault present in many of the Tesla Model 3 manufactured in the last quarter of 2024. A short circuit when calibrating the cameras leaves the new on-board computer, known as HW4, unusable.</p>

<p><em>“The problem is linked to a new version of Tesla’s HW4 (sometimes called AI4) onboard self-driving computer. Internally, some refer to the new version as AI4.1. The computers are short-circuiting.”</em></p>

<p>And then it continues:</p>

<p><em>“Tesla drivers are reporting computer failures after driving off with their brand-new cars over just the first few tens to hundreds of miles. Wide-ranging features powered by the computer, like active safety features, cameras, and even GPS, navigation, and range estimations, fail to work.”</em></p>

<p>These are exactly the problems that I had observed in the vehicle, along with other additional dysfunctions such as the inability to update the Operating System and the data transfer problems in Spotify.</p>

<p>The article also explains that Tesla <strong>does not have replacement stock</strong> for the new on-board computer, and is making its customers believe that the car is drivable in this state and poses no risk:</p>

<p><em>“One source said that Tesla service is being told to play down any safety concerns related to this problem to avoid people believing their brand-new cars are not drivable. It’s unclear if Tesla reported the issue to NHTSA despite the fact that the broken rear-view camera goes against federal safety regulations, which should force a recall.”</em></p>

<p><em>“Tesla service is currently being overwhelmed by the issue, and Tesla is pushing service appointments to next year.”</em></p>

<p>On <strong>December 10, 2024</strong>, I received a response from the Budapest Service Center <strong>confirming the problems in the vehicle</strong> and that <strong>the on-board computer had to be replaced</strong>. As the article points out, they informed me that at the moment they did not have the part in stock and they did not know when it would be available.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.myteslaexperience.com/files/2025/02/confirmation-budapest.png" alt="Confirmación Budapest"></p>

<p>Exactly one week later, I received a message in Hungarian from the Budapest Service Center letting me choose a date for my appointment. The earliest date, <strong>February 28, 2025</strong>.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.myteslaexperience.com/files/2025/02/appointment-date-budapest.png" alt="Fecha cita en Centro de Servicio de Budapest"></p>

<p>Almost 3 months of waiting to, hypothetically, repair the vehicle. Apparently, Tesla considers OK their customers to drive vehicles with the following features not working:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Cameras</strong>: essential for parking, surveillance, etc.</li>
  <li><strong>GPS navigation system</strong>: a crucial feature in the Tesla Model 3, as when planning a route, the car indicates where to stop for charging. Additionally, when approaching a charging point, the vehicle automatically preheats the battery for a faster recharge.</li>
  <li><strong>Braking (ABS) and suspension (EPS) systems</strong>: I have no way of knowing whether these systems are working correctly in my vehicle or not, as I never had the chance to drive the car in perfect condition. Regardless, I don’t believe I have to risk my own safety, or that of others, to find out whether these systems are working reliably.</li>
  <li><strong>Software updates</strong> and <strong>data downloads</strong> (e.g., from Spotify).</li>
  <li><strong>Other systems that rely on cameras</strong>: Autopilot, automatic windshield wipers, automatic lights, lane departure detection, drowsiness detection, etc.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="renault-clio-vs-tesla-model-3">Renault Clio vs Tesla Model 3</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://electrek.co/2024/12/16/tesla-major-issue-self-driving-computer-inside-new-cars">Electrotek article</a> cited above was published on <strong>December 15, 2024</strong>. Until I read it, I wasn’t fully aware of the impact of the breakdown. Especially, the part that affects the <strong>braking</strong> (ABS) and <strong>suspension</strong> (EPS) systems. In fact, I kept driving the car and joked with my friends that I had an <strong>Analog Tesla</strong>. That is, on the outside the car looked like a Tesla Model 3, but on the inside it worked like my old <strong>Renault Clio DCi 1.5</strong>. Let’s compare:</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>&nbsp;</td>
      <td><strong>Renault Clio DCI 1.5</strong></td>
      <td><strong>Tesla Model 3</strong> (Analógico)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Cameras</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Software updates</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Autopilot</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Automatic windshield wiper</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>automatic lights</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Lane departure detection</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Sleep detection</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Emergency brake</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Surveillance (Sentry mode)</td>
      <td>No</td>
      <td>No</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Spotify</td>
      <td><strong>Yes</strong> (external)</td>
      <td><strong>Yes</strong> (10 seconds)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Price</td>
      <td>6,600 EUR</td>
      <td>35,970 EUR</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>In fact, a 20-year-old Clio DCI is slightly superior to this <em>Analog Tesla Model 3</em>. It is true that the Clio does not have heated seats and steering wheel, but that does not justify the price difference I think.</p>

<p>The comparison may seem humorous, but it reveals something obvious: <strong>a Tesla Model 3 is superior to other cars for these and other features</strong>. These functionalities are not extras in the vehicle, they are an integral part of it, and have a cost for which customers pay. Some of these features are essential in a Tesla Model 3, such as <strong>GPS navigation</strong> or the <strong>camera system</strong>. Why should I take risks, whether or not I’m going to hit the car, when parking it? Planning a long-distance trip is much more difficult without GPS navigation since I have to schedule the stops myself to recharge the car and I cannot preheat the battery. When I charge on a Tesla charger, I do not know the cost since this information is only available in the GPS navigator, etc. I have left out of the picture the problems, reported by other users, in the braking (ABS) and suspension (EPS) systems, but without a doubt, they pose a risk to the safety of drivers.</p>

<p>But this story doesn’t end here. The worst was yet to come…</p>

<h2 id="doctor-my-car-is-losing-battery-is-it-serious">Doctor, my car is losing battery. Is it serious?</h2>

<p>It is expected for an EV to lose battery while it remains parked. There’s even a technical term for this. It is called <a href="https://www.ev.guide/lesson-articles/what-is-vampire-drain"><em>vampire drain</em></a> or <em>phantom drain</em>.</p>

<p>The <em><strong>vampire drain</strong></em> is the <strong>discharge that occurs in an electric car while we are not using it</strong>. It is something similar to what happens with mobile phones. Even if we are not using a cell phone, it loses battery unless it remains plugged in. The same thing happens in an EV. I don’t know what the average expected battery loss value is for a Tesla Model 3. During the 3 weeks the car was parked in Bratislava, the battery went from 83% to 79%. That is, 4% loss in 3 weeks. I think it’s a pretty reasonable number.</p>

<p>In addition to <em>vampire discharge</em>, EV owners need to be more aware about the care and maintenance of their vehicle’s battery. For example, the usual thing is to <strong>charge the car up to 80-85%</strong>, and <strong>never leave it below 20%</strong>. If the car falls below 20%, it is recommended to recharge it immediately. Electric car batteries, unlike laptop batteries, <strong>do not have a memory effect</strong>. Therefore, the battery is not damaged if the car is charged from 20% to 50%, for example. On the other hand, Tesla recommends <strong>charging the battery up to 100% at least once a week</strong>.</p>

<p>I don’t know whether it was a coincidence or not, but just when I charged the car for the first time to 100%, the battery started to drain. I charged the battery to 100% and just <strong>4 days later</strong>, without having used the car, <strong>the battery was at 83%</strong>. That means, the car had lost 4% battery daily. Just that day, my wife and I had planned a long trip to the <strong>High Tatras</strong>.</p>

<p>While driving, my wife was searching the Internet for information about what could have caused this sudden battery loss. <em>«Could it have been the cold?»</em> The car sleeps in a garage, and although it was winter the temperature never dropped below 0 degrees. It is true that extreme temperatures (very high or very low) can affect the battery, but <a href="https://www.visitnorway.com/plan-your-trip/getting-around/by-car/electric-cars">Norway has the highest number of EVs in the world per person</a>. Common sense tells me that it must be colder in Norway than in Slovakia. Therefore, it couldn’t be the cold. Another possibility could be some feature that had been left activated. It is known that the <strong>Sentry mode</strong> of the Tesla Model 3 consumes 1% every 2.5 hours. That means, if you inadvertently leave <em>Sentry mode</em> activated, the car <strong>can lose almost 10% of battery in a day</strong>. But <em>Sentry mode</em> was not activated.</p>

<p>Either way, this unexpected setback was a huge inconvenience to our trip. Arriving at our first stop, we had to spend all of our time finding a Tesla charger before resuming our journey. Fortunately, one recharge was enough to get me back home without having to stop again.</p>

<p>As soon as I returned, I went to charge the car. This time I decided to charge it up to 82-83%. This happened on Saturday <strong>December 21, 2024</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="christmas-in-hell">Christmas in hell</h2>

<p>The next day, I was flying from Budapest (Hungary) to Porto (Portugal). It was a bumpy flight, and I ended up arriving in Porto on Monday morning. Upon arrival, I opened the Tesla app to see if the car was still losing battery at 4%. My surprise was huge when I checked the <strong>battery was at 69%</strong>. That is to say, the car was losing battery at a greater pace than expected, around <strong>8% daily</strong>!! A chill ran through my entire body.</p>

<p>I was going to spend approximately a week in Spain. On <strong>December 29</strong> I would take a plane from Vigo to London to spend New Year’s Eve there with my wife and some friends. Until <strong>January 2</strong> I would not be back in Slovakia. I did a quick calculation. With a battery loss of 8% per day <strong>the battery would end up being consumed</strong> between <strong>December 31</strong> and <strong>January 1</strong>. Once I had made this calculation, the first thing that crossed my mind was to <strong>cancel my trip to London</strong> and <strong>make a 3000 km trip</strong> to Slovakia <strong>to charge the car</strong>. It was an absolutely irrational thought. I was putting my life, well-being and relationships with family and friends before the needs of a car. I had bought a car so I could move around more freely. But now the car was conditioning me. My life and my plans revolved around an object. I didn’t have a car, I had a <strong>tamagotchi with wheels</strong>. I had to take care of it, I had to see if it had slept well, and above all, I had to check if it still had battery left.</p>

<p>Going back to my senses, I looked for a <strong>plan B</strong>. I called my wife, who was still in Slovakia, and told her the bad news. The idea was to somehow charge the car enough so that it wouldn’t die before returning. I knew it wasn’t going to be easy for her because she hadn’t driven in years. In addition, she didn’t have much time since she was taking a flight to London that same day. Even so, with the help of a friend, she managed to charge the car up to 98% before leaving.</p>

<p>I spent Christmas <strong>calling Tesla</strong> and trying to figure out <strong>why the car had started losing 8% battery daily</strong>. I remember that on Christmas Eve I managed to speak with Tesla Spain. When I asked whether it was normal for the car to lose 8% of battery daily, the agent on the other end of the line answered: <em>“I don’t know”</em>. I was stunned. Now I really didn’t understand anything. <em>“Was it within expectations that the car would lose 8% battery per day? But, who could live with a car like that?”</em>, I thought. In my phone call with Tesla Spain, I insisted that they speak to the <strong>Budapest Service Center</strong> so that they could get back me. I had notified them immediately when I saw the car was losing battery, but I still had not received a response. I also sent an email to <strong>DeliveryEMEA</strong> (my only contact when purchasing the vehicle), demanding either a replacement of the vehicle or a full refund of the amount, since the car was defective from the very first day I laid my hands on it and now there was this huge battery problem. I also tried to contact the <strong>Tesla Sales Department</strong>, without success.</p>

<p>The days I went through were not pleasant at all. My head was constantly spinning around the car. Every day since <strong>December 23</strong>, I started sending a screenshot to the <strong>Budapest Service Center</strong> showing how the car was losing 8% battery per day. I asked them directly, repeatedly, what was causing this problem. But I never received a response. They had deliberately decided to ignore me. To this day, and as I write these lines, I am still waiting for the Budapest Service Center to explain to me what the battery losses are due to. I continue sending screenshots daily.</p>

<p><img src="https://www.myteslaexperience.com/files/2025/02/daily-report-battery-drainage.jpg" alt="Informe diario pérdida de batería"></p>

<h2 id="epilogue">Epilogue</h2>

<p>When I returned to Slovakia, the first thing I did was to charge the car. Then, I called Tesla again. On the other end of the line, an agent told me the battery losses were due to previous problems already existing in the car. I insisted that the <strong>Budapest Service Center</strong> confirmed this diagnosis, but as I have explained previously <strong>they have never done so</strong>. I asked for solutions or mitigations to this situation. The only solution they gave me was to keep waiting for that miraculous replacement part. There are no contingency plans, no replacement vehicles, no compensation for these problems.</p>

<p>The lack of management and planning at Tesla left me greatly disappointed and in disbelief. A car that is known to be defective should be evaluated at a mechanic immediately. Making a customer to wait 3 months for a proper diagnosis or replacement part is unacceptable. Forcing thousands of customers to drive a dysfunctional car, which depends so much on technology, is not only unacceptable but also <strong>irresponsible</strong>. It poses a serious risk to your safety, that of your companions, passers-by and other drivers. Forcing someone to live with a car that loses 8% battery a day is like forcing someone to live tied to a chain. Even charging the car to 100%, the battery does not last more than 12 days. <strong>I can’t go on vacation for 2 weeks because otherwise this car would die</strong>.</p>

<p>During my conversation with the Tesla agent, I asked whether the <strong>Vienna Service Center</strong> could handle my case more quickly. The agent told me that he could not check the waiting times of the centers, and suggested me not to switch Service Centers as I would lose my turn. All Tesla’s customers have their hands tied, even though they do not know it yet. I have absolutely lost my trust in this company, and the worst of all is that I feel like a prisoner of it.</p>

<p>I came to the conclusion that, even if Tesla were able to fix the problems in my car, I would not like to live within their <strong>walled garden</strong>. I don’t want to plan my life around the ineptitude and inefficiency of a company, which also <strong>ignores me</strong> and in a banal way <strong>puts my life at risk</strong>. On <strong>January 5, 2025</strong> I called <strong>Tesla Netherlands Sales Department</strong> to request the return of the vehicle and a refund of my money. Nobody picked up the phone on the other end of the line. Finally, after several calls, I managed to talk to an agent from another department. I requested a refund of my money since the vehicle was delivered broken and now the battery problems were added. The agent was not sure whether I was entitled to a full refund since the car had more than 100 km. He was also not sure whether I could leave the car in Budapest or should I transport it back to Tilburg. He promised me that on Monday, <strong>January 6, 2025</strong>, someone from the Sales Department would contact me. We agreed on a time, between 4 and 6 PM. After almost a month, I’m still waiting for that call.</p>

<p>All of this can be summarized in a single sentence: <strong>The Head of the Department of Government Efficiency is the CEO of an disfunctional company</strong>.</p>

<p>Since the battery problems occurred I have stopped driving the vehicle. Even more so, after reading the <a href="https://www.motorpasion.com/tesla/abs-esp-limpiaparabrisas-tesla-nuevos-se-estan-quedando-ayudas-marca-dice-que-sus-coches-electricos-siguen-siendo-seguros">article by Daniel Murias for Motorpasión</a> (in Spanish). I consider it a risk to drive the car in this state. And I don’t think I should risk my life, or the lives of other people, to find out whether the car’s braking or suspension systems are working properly. This should be done by a mechanic, either at a garage or a Tesla Service Center. But this is Tesla, and it seems like <strong>no one is behind the wheel</strong>.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple's Best Option: Decentralize iCloud (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.mnot.net/blog/2025/02/09/decentralize-icloud</link>
            <guid>42997647</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 07:03:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.mnot.net/blog/2025/02/09/decentralize-icloud">https://www.mnot.net/blog/2025/02/09/decentralize-icloud</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42997647">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.mnot.net/blog/2025/02/09/decentralize-icloud: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TL;DR of Deep Dive into LLMs Like ChatGPT by Andrej Karpathy (356 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://anfalmushtaq.com/articles/deep-dive-into-llms-like-chatgpt-tldr</link>
            <guid>42997340</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 05:56:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://anfalmushtaq.com/articles/deep-dive-into-llms-like-chatgpt-tldr">https://anfalmushtaq.com/articles/deep-dive-into-llms-like-chatgpt-tldr</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42997340">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://anfalmushtaq.com/articles/deep-dive-into-llms-like-chatgpt-tldr: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>