<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 19:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Doctorow: American tech cartels use apps to break the law (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lithub.com/how-american-tech-cartels-use-apps-to-break-the-law/</link>
            <guid>45518136</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 16:47:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lithub.com/how-american-tech-cartels-use-apps-to-break-the-law/">https://lithub.com/how-american-tech-cartels-use-apps-to-break-the-law/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45518136">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
								<p>The death of competition spells doom for regulation. Competition is an essential component of effective regulation, for two reasons: First, competition keeps the companies within a sector from all telling the same lie to its regulators. Second, competition erodes companies’ profits and thus starves them of the capital they need to overpower or outmaneuver their regulators.</p><p><span>Article continues after advertisement</span></p>
<p>While not all regulation is wise or helpful, a world without regulation is a catastrophe. That’s because, in a highly technological world, your ability to do well (or even to live out the day) requires that you correctly navigate innumerable highly technical questions that you can’t possibly answer.</p>
<p>You need to know whether you can trust the software in your car’s antilock braking system, whether you should heed your doctor’s advice to get vaccinated, whether the joists over your head at home are sufficient to keep the ceiling from falling in and killing you, and whether your kids’ schooling is adequate or likely to turn them into ignoramuses.</p>
<p>Tech-like apps can obfuscate what’s really going on, sloshing a coat of complexity over a business that allows its owners to claim that they’re not breaking the law.</p>
<p>It’s not that you lack the intellect and discernment to answer each of these questions. You’re a smart cookie. Given enough time, you could get a PhD’s worth of education in software engineering, cell biology, material science, structural engineering, and pedagogy; investigate each of the offerings before you in each of these categories; and make an intelligent choice that reflects your priorities and the trade-offs you’re willing to make.</p>
<p>The problem is that it would take you several lifetimes to acquire all that knowledge, and long before you could do so, you’d be killed by food poisoning because you guessed wrong about whether you could trust the hygiene policies at your local diner.</p><div><p><span>Article continues after advertisement</span></p><!-- GAM 22020028882/LTHB_lithubcom/Article_Incontent_1 -->
</div>
<p>It would be nice if you could let markets take care of these questions for you, but many of the consequences of wrong answers don’t manifest fast enough to steer your decision-making. Sure, if a private school turns one of your kids into an ignoramus, you can demand your money back and refuse to send your other kids to that school—but your kid is <em>still</em> an ignoramus. Likewise, you can punish a restaurant that gives you food poisoning by withholding your future custom, but if that’s a <em>lethal</em> poisoning, the fact that you don’t eat at that restaurant anymore isn’t quite the moral victory you might be hoping for.</p>
<p>To navigate all of these technical minefields, you need the help of a third party. In a modern society, that third party is an expert regulator who investigates or anticipates problems in their area of expertise and then makes rules designed to solve these problems.</p>
<p>To make these rules, the regulator convenes a truth-seeking exercise, in which all affected parties submit evidence about what the best rule should be and then get a chance to read what everyone else wrote and rebut their claims. Sometimes, there are in-person hearings, or successive rounds of comment and counter-comment, but that’s the basic shape of things.</p>
<p>Once all the evidence is in, the regulator—who is a neutral expert, required to recuse themselves if they have conflicts—makes a rule, citing the evidence on which the rule is based. This whole system is backstopped by courts, which can order the process to begin anew if the new rule isn’t supported by the evidence created while the regulator was developing the record.</p>
<p>This kind of adversarial process—something between a court case and scientific peer review—has a good track record of producing high-quality regulations. You can thank a process like this for the fact that you weren’t killed today by critters in your tap water or a high-voltage shock from one of your home’s electrical outlets.</p><div><p><span>Article continues after advertisement</span></p><!-- GAM 22020028882/LTHB_lithubcom/Article_Incontent_2 -->
</div>
<p>One key advantage of the process is that it relies on competitors to counter one another’s claims. The reinforced steel joist manufacturer that claims that only its products are suitable for use in high-rise apartment buildings will have to defend those claims against competitors who submit their own structural engineering and material science evidence. Regulators don’t need to look for holes in the arguments advanced by interested parties; they only need to assess the quality of the criticisms raised by other commenters who submit to the docket.</p>
<p>This process isn’t just a way to prevent corporate executives from cheating the public by knowingly overpromising about their own products or denigrating their rivals’; it’s also a way to stop firms that have tricked <em>themselves</em> from fooling the rest of us, too. As with the scientific method, the safeguards of peer review help us catch grubby attempts at both deception and <em>self</em>-deception, because it’s <em>very</em> easy to talk yourself into a sincere belief that you are right and everyone else is wrong.</p>
<p>This process works well on “disorganized” sectors composed of many firms that compete hard with one another. When hundreds of companies are all at one another’s throats, they suffer from a collective action problem—the same force that keeps users from leaving services like Facebook.</p>
<p>Hundreds of companies find it impossible to agree on almost <em>anything</em>, including where to have a meeting in which they could discuss what line they are going to feed their regulator. They probably can’t even agree on how to cater that meeting.</p>
<p>Hundreds of companies are a disorganized rabble. They can’t come to accord, and even if they could, a truly competitive sector produces smaller profits for each company (since one of the best ways to compete is by lowering prices to attract new customers and raising wages to attract the best workers). That leaves very little surplus capital with which to pursue regulatory adventures.</p><div><p><span>Article continues after advertisement</span></p><!-- GAM 22020028882/LTHB_lithubcom/Article_Incontent_3 -->
</div>
<p>But when a sector dwindles to five companies—or four, or three, or two, or just one—the collective action problem is annihilated by the inevitable coziness among the executives of the incestuous industries.</p>
<p>After all, the executives in an industry dominated by a handful of firms are apt to have worked at most or all of the companies in the sector. They know one another, came up together, and are part of one another’s social milieu.</p>
<p>Not only do concentrated industries find it easier to converge on a set of policy priorities and maintain message discipline while bargaining with their regulators, they also have a lot to bargain <em>with</em>. Concentrated sectors tend to have Mafia-style demarcations of turf. (Think of Pope Alexander VI dividing up the “New World” in 1494, of cable companies carving up the map of the United States into exclusive fiefdoms, or of Apple taking an annual $20 billion-plus payment from Google in exchange for not making its own search engine.)</p>
<p>This prevents “wasteful competition” and allows these companies to amass gigantic war chests that they can mobilize to win their policy priorities.</p>
<p>A hundred companies are a mob, a rabble. Five companies are a cartel.</p><div><p><span>Article continues after advertisement</span></p><!-- GAM 22020028882/LTHB_lithubcom/Article_Incontent_4 -->
</div>
<p>“Regulatory capture”—when a company suborns its regulator and teams up with it to screw over customers, rivals, and suppliers—starts with a regulator that is weaker than the company it is supposed to be watchdogging. The pro-monopoly policies of the past forty years have produced <em>gigantic</em> companies that find it easy to unite against their regulators, even as the deregulatory policies over the same period have starved regulators of the resources they need to fight back. The inevitable result is regulatory capture.</p>
<p>*</p>
<p>Regulatory capture has two faces: On the one hand, a captured industry is able to flout regulations that are meant to prevent it from harming the public, its employees and other stakeholders, and the environment. On the other hand, regulatory capture creates a <em>coalition</em> between the regulated industry and its regulators. They form a team and work together to enforce rules against other industries, startups, foreign adversaries, and so on. Regulatory capture isn’t the same as <em>underregulation</em>; rather, it is the combination of <em>underregulation</em> (for the industry that has effected the capture) and <em>overregulation</em> (against that industry’s enemies).</p>
<p>Tech companies don’t stop with “It’s not a crime if we do it with an app.” They also say, “It’s a crime if you fix our app to defend yourself from our crimes.”</p>
<p>The most common tactic used to flout regulation is to break the law with an app and then insist that the law hasn’t been broken at all, because the crime was committed with an app.</p>
<p>Sometimes literally (as Uber does when it argues that it’s not an employer because it directs its workers with an app) and sometimes figuratively. Tech-like apps can obfuscate what’s really going on, sloshing a coat of complexity over a business that allows its owners to claim that they’re not breaking the law. (“It’s not an illegal unregulated hotel, it’s an Airbnb!”)</p>
<p>Riley Quinn, showrunner for the excellent <em>Trashfuture</em> podcast, says that whenever you hear the word <em>fintech</em> (financial technology), you should mentally substitute <em>unregulated bank</em>.</p>
<p>App-based lending platforms ignore usury law and say it doesn’t count because they do it with an app. Cryptocurrency hustlers illegally trade in unregistered securities and say it doesn’t count because they do it with an app.</p>
<p>When Uber entered the taxi market without securing taxi licenses or extending the workforce protections required under law, it said the move didn’t count because it did it with an app.</p>
<p>The McDonald’s-backed company Plexure sells surveillance data on you to vendors, who use it to raise the price of items when they think you’ll pay more. In its promotional materials, Plexure uses the example of charging extra for your breakfast sandwich on payday. It says that such practices are not a rip-off because they’re done with an app.</p>
<p>RealPage gives “recommendations” to landlords about the minimum rents they should charge for all the apartments in your neighborhood, raising rents and worsening the housing crisis. The company says it’s not price-fixing because it’s done with an app.</p>
<p>On the subject of the housing crisis, Airbnb is racing to convert all the rental stock in your city into an unlicensed hotel room, but it says the conversion doesn’t count because it’s done with an app.</p>
<p>The legal regime for apps really <em>is</em> different from the rules governing web pages. Thanks to intellectual property laws that ban “circumvention,” companies that embed undesirable anti-features in apps can use the law to destroy rivals that disenshittify their offerings.</p>
<p>In other words, tech companies don’t stop with “It’s not a crime if we do it with an app.” They also say, “It’s a crime if you fix our app to defend yourself from our crimes.”</p>
<p>__________________________________</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="260427" data-permalink="https://lithub.com/how-american-tech-cartels-use-apps-to-break-the-law/enshittification-cover/" data-orig-file="https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-scaled.jpg" data-orig-size="1707,2560" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Enshittification Cover" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-200x300.jpg" data-large-file="https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-683x1024.jpg" src="https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-200x300.jpg" alt="" width="200" height="300" srcset="https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-200x300.jpg 200w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-40x60.jpg 40w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-33x50.jpg 33w, https://s26162.pcdn.co/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/Enshittification-Cover-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 200px) 100vw, 200px"></p>
<p><em>Excerpted from&nbsp;</em><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/132/9780374619329" target="_blank"><span>Enshittification: </span><span>Why</span>&nbsp;<span>Everything</span>&nbsp;<span>Suddenly</span>&nbsp;<span>Got</span>&nbsp;<span>Worse</span>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<span>What</span>&nbsp;to&nbsp;<span>Do</span>&nbsp;<span>About</span> It</a> <em>by Cory Doctorow</em><em>. Copyright © 2025 by Cory Doctorow. Published by Farrar, Straus and Giroux, October 2025. All rights reserved.&nbsp;</em></p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Suspicionless ChatControl must be taboo in a state governed by the rule of law (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://digitalcourage.social/@echo_pbreyer/115337976340299372</link>
            <guid>45517642</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 16:03:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://digitalcourage.social/@echo_pbreyer/115337976340299372">https://digitalcourage.social/@echo_pbreyer/115337976340299372</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45517642">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[After 2 decades of tinkering, MAME cracks the Hyper Neo Geo 64 (215 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.readonlymemo.com/mame-hyper-neo-geo-support-sound-emulation/</link>
            <guid>45516968</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 15:01:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/mame-hyper-neo-geo-support-sound-emulation/">https://www.readonlymemo.com/mame-hyper-neo-geo-support-sound-emulation/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45516968">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

    <article>

        <header>

                <a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/tag/newsletter-6593af58c07629001bce693b/">Newsletter</a>
            
                <p>How MAME devs finally got sound working for the 3D arcade system. Plus: PC Engine LaserActive support gets fast-tracked.</p>

            <div>
                <p><a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/author/wes/">
                                <img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w160/2024/01/noirlac-icon.png" alt="Wes Fenlon">
                            </a>
                </p>
                <div>
                    
                    <p><time datetime="2025-10-05">05 Oct 2025</time>
                            <span><span>—</span> 16 min read</span>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>

                <figure>
        <img srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w320/2025/10/terry-header.jpg 320w,
                    https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/terry-header.jpg 600w,
                    https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w960/2025/10/terry-header.jpg 960w,
                    https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1200/2025/10/terry-header.jpg 1200w,
                    https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2000/2025/10/terry-header.jpg 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1120px" src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1200/2025/10/terry-header.jpg" alt="After 2 decades of tinkering, MAME finally cracks the Hyper Neo Geo 64">
    </figure>

        </header>

        <section>
            <p>Let me test out a theory here: If you're into emulation, you're into older video games, ergo you're into <em>old stuff</em> of all kinds. That means you, savvy, good-taste-having reader, will love this spread of photos I took in Tokyo last week at the National Film Archive of Japan, which has a small but lovely set of exhibits from the history of Japanese film. Since you like playing Super Nintendo games this is absolutely your shit, right? Right??</p><p>Okay, I'll throw in a pic of some games to sweeten the deal.</p><figure><div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_140424.jpg" width="2000" height="1126" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_140424.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_140424.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_140424.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/20250928_140424.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_160730.jpg" width="2000" height="3552" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_160730.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_160730.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_160730.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_160730.jpg 2252w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_160512.jpg" width="2000" height="1126" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_160512.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_160512.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_160512.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/20250928_160512.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_161144.jpg" width="2000" height="1126" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_161144.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_161144.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_161144.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/20250928_161144.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_161328.jpg" width="2000" height="3552" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_161328.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_161328.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_161328.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_161328.jpg 2252w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_161721.jpg" width="2000" height="1126" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_161721.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_161721.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_161721.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/20250928_161721.jpg 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_162028.jpg" width="2000" height="3552" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/20250928_162028.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/20250928_162028.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/20250928_162028.jpg 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/20250928_162028.jpg 2252w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div></div></figure><p>This issue is coming a week late as I was off to Japan last week for my first-ever visit to the Tokyo Game Show, and too busy working (and working at eating sushi) to squeeze in a newsletter. And it's coming late in the day Sunday — apologies! But patience pays off!!</p><p>This issue's main story has been cookin' for a minute: last month the news landed that MAME had finally properly cracked Hyper Neo Geo 64 support, but the celebration was a little bit premature. The arcade system was playable in MAME, yes, but sound was in really shoddy shape — it wasn't yet a particularly good experience. </p><p>Over the last month or so that's been changing, and changing fast, with frequent improvements checked in by a pair of regular MAME contributors. So <em>now</em> is the time to talk about it, and <em><strong>soon</strong> </em>(with the very next MAME release!) it will be time to actually play it. Considering there are only seven Hyper Neo Geo 64 games, well, that's a week's worth of evenings sorted.</p><p>As with every trip to Tokyo I took a few hours to stop by Akihabara this time, but its pull has certainly lessened over the years as retro prices have skyrocketed from where they were a decade ago and the selection has gotten thinner and thinner. Still, browsing the stores is a fun time and there are great finds to be found as long as you're not looking for anything too in-demand. I picked up one game: Kamiwaza, a PS2 "stealth" game where you play as a thief in feudal Japan stealing hella stuff.</p><p>As you might guess, it's more silly than stealthy.</p><figure><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/GFLNxNU-54E?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="Kamiwaza PS2 Gameplay HD (PCSX2 v1.7.0)"></iframe></figure><p>Shout out to my shopping partner in crime, Paradise Killer's Oli Clarke Smith, for the recommendation. I've got a feature on the way in the coming weeks over at PC Gamer based on some of the games we picked up and how they speak to the "identity" of particular retro consoles. I'm hoping it'll be a fun read! </p><p>For now, let's hop into MAME; then stick around for an update on Pioneer LaserActive emulation!</p><div><p>💸</p><p><i><em>If you enjoy </em></i><i><b><strong>ROM</strong></b></i><i><em>, I'd love it if you'd consider </em></i><a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/#/portal/support"><i><b><strong>a small tip</strong></b></i></a><i><em> to help me cover my monthly costs. (Follow the link and click 'change amount' to whatever you want).</em></i></p></div><hr><h2 id="the-big-two">The Big Two</h2><h3 id="1-the-hyper-neo-geo-comes-to-mame-now-with-working-sound">1. The Hyper Neo Geo comes to MAME: Now with working sound!</h3><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/roadsedge-header.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="850" height="170" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/roadsedge-header.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/roadsedge-header.jpg 850w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>21 years ago, David "MameHaze" Haywood started looking into what it would take to add support for the Hyper Neo Geo 64 arcade system — then just five years past the end of its short lifespan — to MAME. "When I started looking at the system back in 2004 MAME didn't really do much 3D stuff at all, even things like the MIPS (main CPU) core were in a much rougher shape, there were no dumps of the I/O MCU at all (happened only a few years ago) and the PC I had at the time barely had enough memory to load and decode even the 2D graphics," he says. </p><p>"It was also pre-YouTube, and even in the early days of YouTube you didn't really get much in the way of good reference material. Kinda crazy to think that a lot of people who are probably interested in the emulation of the platform now as younger adults weren't even born when emulation work first started on it!"</p><p>A few weeks ago, two decades after he started looking into the system, Haywood finally promoted it to "working" status in MAME. But that move was a bit of a formality, or a bit sneaky, depending on how you look at it. Though the promotion got some buzz, it wasn't truly finished: proper sound emulation was still missing. Haywood actually hadn't worked on the core since 2023, and decided, well, people had been playing the games for long enough without sound, he might as well slap the "working" label on. It turned out to be the final push other MAME contributors needed to take a crack at tuning up the sound.</p><p>What's the Hyper Neo Geo's whole deal, anyway? Well, it makes some sense that the system would be more a curiosity for younger folks to discover than an object of intense nostalgia like some of MAME's more high-profile cores or the original Neo Geo; it was only active in arcades for two years from 1997 to 1999 during the awkward transitional period to 3D, with just seven games released for it:</p><ul><li>Road's Edge</li><li>Samurai Shodown 64</li><li>Xtreme Rally</li><li>Beat Busters: Second Nightmare</li><li>Samurai Shodown 64: Warriors Rage</li><li>Fatal Fury: Wild Ambition</li><li>Buriki One</li></ul><p>Here's a nice write-up of the system from Nicole Express that delves into the hardware: </p><figure><a href="https://nicole.express/2021/ultra-mega-hyper-neo-geo-64.html?ref=readonlymemo.com"><div><p>The failed heir: The Hyper Neo Geo 64!</p><p>In 1982, Commodore International introduced the technology world to the concept of 64. But it was a very intimidating; following Commodore’s 1994 collapse, 6…</p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/icon/favicon-9.ico" alt=""></p></div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/thumbnail/nicole_logo.png" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure><p>None of these games have the Bloodborne-style pull to individually inspire interest in emulation, but the MAME team's all-consuming drive to reverse-engineer and archive every arcade system in existence kept it on the radar. Haywood's initial investigation into it predated even MAME's high profile support of Capcom's CPS3 boards, for instance, but once that platform was decrypted support was added quite quickly because hell yeah people wanted to play Street Fighter III. By comparison, "Hyper64 has been a 21 year on-and-off slog," he says.</p><p>It's a perfect representation one of the eternal frustrations of emulation development: People often ask why no one's working on something when they actually are. Just invisibly.</p><blockquote>"The sheer number of times I picked up the Hyper64 driver and pumped weeks of work in it only to not be able to make any progress at all was frustrating at the best of times. Just trying to gain an understanding of it all, but ending up not making any headway at all.  That's something I don't think people really appreciate when it comes to emulation, the amount of time that you have to put in which often yields no positive results at all, where all you can really conclude is it doesn't work the way you were hoping it would work." </blockquote><p>A few years ago, Haywood finally made substantial progress: Someone dumped the I/O microcontroller, and he was able to write a CPU core to emulate it. "The inputs finally started working in a bunch of the games, which allowed me to explore them further and make video improvements," he said. </p><p>"Other components improving in MAME over the years has really helped too.  When I started MAME didn't have a CPU core for the V53 either (which is a V33 CPU with variolus peripherals) and is the CPU driving the sound DSP.  At some point in MAME's history the V53 support got fleshed out (for other systems) which has really come in handy now, as proper sound emulation requires that to be running properly."</p><p>When Haywood marked the platform as working, it caught the attention of another longtime MAME contributor: R. Belmont. For the last month or so, Belmont, as well as two other devs, Happy and O. Galibert, have been chipping away at making the games sound like they're supposed to. </p><p>"Haze marking them working did provide a push, and Happy had done a detailed disassembly of the sound CPU program which was quite useful," Belmont recently posted on Reddit. Belmont and Galibert have both been working on synthesizer support in MAME, and the Hyper Neo Geo 64's sound chip happens to be used it one, providing them with some convenient overlap in interest/speciality. </p><figure><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/YVrXnV33cjc?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="Hyper NeoGeo 64 Sound Improvements for MAME 0.282 (from O.Galibert &amp; R.Belmont)"></iframe></figure><p>The current MAME release, 0.281, includes a series of rapid-fire improvements as documented by Belmont in a few videos <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YKrXtzndXmw&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">on YouTube</a>:</p><ul><li>"Very early work in progress on better audio for the Hyper Neo Geo 64 system.  There is a loooong way to go, this is just some very basic fixes so far."</li><li>"Since the first video we've got the basic sample starts and stops working the actual correct way they're supposed to and added a preliminary support for volume envelopes, which also helps the audio balance.  Still a lot of work to go though."</li><li>"More progress today!  I figured out how the volume envelopes really work, and that made Buriki One's intro mostly awesome."</li><li>"Barring any last minute adjustments, this is what HNG64 audio will sound like in MAME 0.281. Since the last video, the per-voice low pass filter was added, which cleans up some of the high frequency 'hash' audible previously and makes the sound a bit cleaner."</li></ul><p>It was a ton of progress for a month, taking Hyper Neo Geo 64 sound support from messy and inaccurate to, at least, broadly playable without assaulting your ears. But the real refinements have been coming in just the last few days since 0.281's release in late September.</p><p>But the next build is gonna be the big one. October's upcoming MAME 0.282 release will notably fix up the audio issues in one of the the trickiest games, Xtreme Rally, while really polishing up the rest. Here's what Belmont's noted in update notes for 0.282 so far: </p><ul><li>"Olivier Galibert figured out how they squeezed 12 bits of dynamic range into 8 bits (presumably this is the format from Roger Linn's original MPC60 design) and replaced the biquad low-pass filter with a more likely Chamberlin one that fits the parameters better. Also there were some improvements to the filter envelope. All this results in much clearer and higher-fidelity sound."</li><li>"This time we've figured out how looping samples actually work, fixed the final mixdown to not introduce any distortion, and fixed the filter envelope. The result? A dramatic improvement to Beast Busters Second Nightmare's intro."</li><li>"So the previous fixes seem to have solved Samurai Shodown 64 and SS64 2, but Xtreme Rally (aka Off Beat Racer) was still extremely broken. The engine sound barely worked, sounds were missing, and some sounds would stick looping forever. This time the problem wasn't actually in the sound emulation itself; Xtreme Rally has unique code among the 7 HNG64 games that tries to push sound commands to the sound CPU as quickly as possible. This resulted in as many as 2/3rds of the commands getting dropped on the floor. I have fixed that issue so that all of the commands make it, and Xtreme Rally now sounds great."</li></ul><p>Since Belmont made that post he dialed in a few more improvements where the wrong sounds were playing in certain instances in the game. Here's a video from Haywood showing off the vastly improved audio (though he notes "some graphical issues, such as the fog in the tunnel still need addressing eventually.")</p><figure><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/H9P8_u6lRIA?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="Hyper NeoGeo 64 &quot;Xtreme Rally&quot; Sound Improvements for MAME 0.282 (from R.Belmont)"></iframe></figure><p>Once MAME 0.282 releases, the Hyper Neo Geo 64 will well and truly be worthy of the "working" label. Turns out it just needed that last little push.</p><p>In a perfect encapsulation of how these sorts of collaborative projects come together, Galibert noted on Reddit that despite their contributions to the core stemming from an interest in emulating synthesizers, "amusingly, the synth itself (MPC3000) is not working at all yet." Some parts of the synthesizer remain undumped and undocumented, just as parts of the Hyper Neo Geo once were; sometimes while you're waiting for all the pieces to fall into place, it turns out one of the pieces you do have happens to fit into another puzzle entirely.</p><p>"It's just been a long slow process," Haywood said. "Things have inched forward a little bit over the years, and the surrounding code in MAME has become better / more capable, allowing for more progress to be made, step by step."</p><hr><h3 id="2-cant-stop-pioneering-nec-support-and-big-laseractive-performance-improvements-arrive-in-the-latest-ares-nightlies">2. Can't stop Pioneering: NEC support and big LaserActive performance improvements arrive in the latest Ares nightlies</h3><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/demonsjudgmentheader.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1048" height="210" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/demonsjudgmentheader.jpg 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/demonsjudgmentheader.jpg 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/demonsjudgmentheader.jpg 1048w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>Often I end a big story, like the August issue's deep dive into the 16 years it took to emulate the Pioneer LaserActive, with the door open to a follow-up many months or years down the road. In this story, our hero — emudev Nemesis — finished work on one of two modules for the Laserdisc-based gaming console, making it possible to play Sega's Mega LD games via emulation for the first time.</p><figure><a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/this-is-the-first-the-16-year-odyssey-of-time-money-wrong-turns-and-frustration-it-took-to-finally-emulate-the-pioneer-laseractive/"><div><p>“This is the first:” The 16 year odyssey of “time, money, wrong turns and frustration” it took to finally emulate the Pioneer LaserActive</p><p>In April 2009, a Sega fan decided to look into emulating the Mega LD, a quirky and little-known hybrid of Genesis and LaserDisc. This week he finished the job.</p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/icon/rom-icon-2.jpg" alt=""><span>Read Only Memo</span><span>Wes Fenlon</span></p></div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/thumbnail/nemesis-laseractive-5.jpg" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure><p>As of publication time, Nemesis was juuuust starting to take a look at the work required to do the same for the other "pak" players could slot into the LaserActive to play NEC PC Engine games, but who knew how long that would take?</p><p>Maybe we'd come back to it before the end of 2026, or maybe next year, or maybe in half a deca-</p><p>Oh. He already did it.</p><p>"NEC LDROM2 support is functioning on nightly builds of the v147 prerelease, and will be included in the next official Ares release," Nemesis recently wrote <a href="https://techdocs.exodusemulator.com/Console/PioneerLaserActive/Software.html?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">on his website</a>. It took less than three weeks. While you can grab the <a href="https://github.com/ares-emulator/ares/releases/download/nightly/ares-windows-x64.zip?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">nightly build</a> anytime, when the next stable build of Ares releases, it'll be all official-like.</p><p>Considering the bulky size of the LaserActive game rips — they can take up dozens of gigabytes — some performance optimizations Nemesis has implemented <a href="https://github.com/ares-emulator/ares/pull/2241?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">in the last few days</a> are almost as exciting as the second console support. Because now you should be able to run the images off a decent HDD without performance issues. Here's the breakdown on Github:</p><blockquote>"This change brings speed enhancements to LaserActive games. The linear resampling coefficient precalculation reduces overall CPU overhead by approximately 30%, making slower CPUs much more likely to achieve full framerate. Additionally, frame prefetch using a background thread makes games much more tolerant of IO latency, making it possible to play games back from platter drives over SATA3.<p>This should be sufficient to make emulation performance acceptable on 95%+ of systems, and I don't have any further optimizations planned at this stage."</p></blockquote><p>So then — LaserActive support is more or less feature complete. What can you play? What <em>should</em> you play? Seeing as the system's deader than dead and nobody's likely to be playing copyright cop, the Laserdisc rips are being freely uploaded and shared <a href="http://techdocs.exodusemulator.com/Console/PioneerLaserActive/Software.html?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">here</a>. Not every game is available yet, but here's where you should probably start: </p><ul><li><a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=1KwgJCGCO8mJqdRgcMxn4UCyR6v5U8RdI&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">Vajra</a> and <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=1TVCnyWEq_lXUN6lCtxbrU68q5yofAOoa&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">Vajra 2</a> - A pair of LaserActive-exclusive rail shooters by Data West</li><li><a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=1X509a2AitDtpFw_cBUdu_bO01ZkXJbKL&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">Triad Stone</a> - An FMV game in the Dragon's Lair game</li><li><a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=17FYDwfqb9uQf1eVHt2F33sUNEAW6EIHT&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">J.B. Harold - Blue Chicago Blues</a> - As described by Nemesis, an "FMV murder mystery detective game, with a surprising amount of freedom. You have control over where to go, what actions to take, and what questions to ask. This title came on a double-sided CLV disc, giving it four times the video content of a typical single-sided CAV LaserActive title. The game also used separate video streams per field, to squeeze a whopping 4 hours of footage into one disc."</li></ul><p>There are a couple other cool games and curiosities on the system, including more rail shooters, some prototypes of Myst, and a German TV movie that lets you swap between different perspectives — but the above should give you a taste for that sweet sweet (or fuzzy, fuzzy) '90s laser gaming.</p><hr><h2 id="patching-in">Patching In</h2><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fac94fc02-b2d1-4e35-b730-79de780d09d7_1200x200.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="200" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fac94fc02-b2d1-4e35-b730-79de780d09d7_1200x200.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fac94fc02-b2d1-4e35-b730-79de780d09d7_1200x200.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fac94fc02-b2d1-4e35-b730-79de780d09d7_1200x200.png 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><a href="https://misterfpga.org/viewtopic.php?p=101244&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com#p101244" rel="noreferrer"><strong>MiSTer's Taito F2 core pulls off a Hat Tric</strong>k</a> – Taito's 1990 game Football Champ, aka Hat Trick Hero, is now playable on the MiSTer's arcade core, as is the baseball game Ah Eikou no Koshien. The latter's surprisingly expressive for its era and looks like a lot more fun than I expect from '90s baseball games.</p><p><strong>MiSTer's CDi core once again threatens you by functioning</strong> – In the latest unstable nightly build of the CDi core, developer Andre Zeps has committed several crimes of CDi improvement, including: "Fix dual SDRAM mode," "Add support for chroma subcarrier for clean composite video from external RGB converters," and "- Add bob deinterlacing to ascal." Go on then, but don't blame me if you start bleeding from every orifice while playing Wind of Gamelon.</p><p><a href="https://segaretro.org/Waku_Waku_Pajero?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer"><strong>MAME has emulated a car</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/WakuWakuPajero.jpg" alt="" loading="lazy" width="434" height="403"><figcaption><span>Waku Waku Pajero image via Black Squirrel on SegaRetro</span></figcaption></figure><hr><h2 id="core-report">Core Report</h2><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2f7fab92dc-51c6-485e-98db-6ca1333cd22e_1200x200.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="200" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2f7fab92dc-51c6-485e-98db-6ca1333cd22e_1200x200.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2f7fab92dc-51c6-485e-98db-6ca1333cd22e_1200x200.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2f7fab92dc-51c6-485e-98db-6ca1333cd22e_1200x200.png 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><strong>Windows builds of RPCS3 are back in business</strong> – Due to a compiler issue, RPCS3's latest builds haven't been available on Windows since back in June, but they're back and working again now. Meanwhile, contributor Whatcookie has created a surprisingly detailed breakdown of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3dkN-6TJNHs&amp;ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">how hard it is to do nothing, efficiently</a>.</p><p><strong>Eden is off the Play Store, for now</strong> – Well, so much for that. After launching on Android a few weeks ago, the Switch emulator has been taken down, though you can still find builds, including for Android, <a href="https://github.com/eden-emulator/Releases/releases/tag/v0.0.3?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">on the Github</a>. Aren't DMCA takedowns lovely?</p><p><a href="https://github.com/TASEmulators/BizHawk/releases/tag/2.11?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">Speedrunning-focused emulator BizHawk gets hexed</a> – But in a good way! The source port DSDA-Doom has been integrated into BizHawk, supporting Doom, Heretic and Hexen. It also now has an integrated DOSBox-X core, as well as <a href="https://docs.libretro.com/library/opera/?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">Opera</a>, for the 3DO.</p><p><a href="https://github.com/shadps4-emu/shadPS4/releases/tag/v.0.11.0?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer"><strong>ShadPS4 gets more Unreal</strong></a> – The latest build of ShadPS4 marks a significant milestone: some Unreal Engine games for the console are now playable, and even more are bootable. Look at all these games that work! </p><figure><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ybhSW0cn1es?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="10 working games on shadPS4 v0.11.0 released version"></iframe></figure><hr><h2 id="translation-station">Translation Station</h2><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fe1a50e1a-ba5a-49f6-a598-8b8bf56fe71e_1200x200.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="200" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fe1a50e1a-ba5a-49f6-a598-8b8bf56fe71e_1200x200.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fe1a50e1a-ba5a-49f6-a598-8b8bf56fe71e_1200x200.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fe1a50e1a-ba5a-49f6-a598-8b8bf56fe71e_1200x200.png 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p><a href="https://jackdbs.neocities.org/tl_dotb2?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer"><strong>Tis the season for brains... Dead of the Brain (2)</strong></a> – It's spooky season, which means the crew behind the translation of PC-98 adventure game Dead of the Brain is back with the sequel <a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/a-summer-vacation-in-november/" rel="noreferrer">two years after the first</a>! "Like the original game, this is also a point-and-click adventure involving zombies, but this time the gameplay is much simpler, but there's still a degree of brute force required," translation crew WINE says. Playing this one might be a bit tedious, but the art is :chefskiss:</p><figure><iframe width="200" height="113" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CL_gBo7b34U?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen="" title="Dead of the Brain 2 (PC-98, 1993) English Translation Trailer"></iframe></figure><p><a href="https://github.com/FeiYenKn/Virtual-On-PS3-English-Translation?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer"><strong>Virtual-On, on PS3</strong></a> – The PS3 re-release of this mecha game had English dialogue etc., but its UI was in Japanese. This translation patch changes that.</p><p><a href="https://segaxtreme.net/resources/wizardry-vi-vii-complete-english-translation-patch.457/?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer"><strong>Wizardy VI, on Saturn</strong></a> – There are <em>at least</em> nine platforms you can play Wizardry: Bane of the Cosmic Forge on, from the 1990 DOS original to the Amiga and FM Towns and modern ports, but the Japanese-only Saturn port is unique, incorporating features from Wizardry 7, and now playable with the original English script. This version has "more spells, more traps, and more skills (though most of the extra skills do nothing in 6, unfortunately), and the art style too is very reminiscent of 7 ... it’s also got a much easier early game, which a lot of new players have notoriously struggled with when playing the other versions," hacker and fan Remisse <a href="https://www.segasaturnshiro.com/2025/09/26/fan-patches-english-into-wizardry-vi-for-saturn/?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer">told Sega Saturn Shiro</a>.</p><p><a href="https://romhack.ing/database/content/entry/hPLkjUIbR7iNz5vFJ2vNTw?ref=readonlymemo.com" rel="noreferrer"><strong>Undercover Cops play board games on the GB</strong></a> – Prolific translation group Stardust Crusaders is back with a Game Boy board/card game based on the arcade game. I'm not gonna say it's one of Irem's all-timers (find me playing Ninja Baseball Bat Man instead), but it's cute!</p><hr><h2 id="good-pixels">Good pixels</h2><figure><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fceb81099-2d2d-4c69-99ce-a1727dd51c92_1200x200-1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1200" height="200" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fceb81099-2d2d-4c69-99ce-a1727dd51c92_1200x200-1.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fceb81099-2d2d-4c69-99ce-a1727dd51c92_1200x200-1.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/https-3a-2f-2fsubstack-post-media-s3-amazonaws-com-2fpublic-2fimages-2fceb81099-2d2d-4c69-99ce-a1727dd51c92_1200x200-1.png 1200w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>It's early October which means it's basically Halloween, right? Here's a load of screenshots from the first couple hours of Dead of the Brain 2. 👻</p><figure><div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134203.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134203.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134203.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134203.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134203.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134818.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134818.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134818.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134818.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-134818.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135838.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135838.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135838.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135838.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135838.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140802.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140802.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140802.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140802.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140802.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140858.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140858.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140858.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140858.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-140858.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135229.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135229.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135229.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135229.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-135229.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141723.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141723.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141723.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141723.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141723.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div></div></figure><figure><div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141828.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141828.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141828.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141828.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141828.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143040.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143040.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143040.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143040.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143040.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142354.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142354.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142354.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142354.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142354.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141930.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141930.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141930.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141930.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-141930.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142440.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142440.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142440.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142440.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142440.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142906.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142906.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142906.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142906.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-142906.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p><p><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143120.png" width="2000" height="1250" loading="lazy" alt="" srcset="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143120.png 600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1000/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143120.png 1000w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w1600/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143120.png 1600w, https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/size/w2400/2025/10/Dead-of-the-Brain-2---English-Translation--Patched--251004-143120.png 2400w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></p></div></div></figure><div><p>💸</p><p><i><em>If you dug this issue, I'd appreciate </em></i><a href="https://www.readonlymemo.com/#/portal/support"><i><b><strong>a small tip</strong></b></i></a><i><em>! </em></i>I write <i><b><strong>ROM</strong></b></i><i><em> entirely in my own free time and pay to host it out of pocket. If you didn't like this issue then uhh I dunno pay me to do a better job next time?? </em></i></p></div><div data-lexical-signup-form="">
            
        <picture><img src="https://www.readonlymemo.com/content/images/2024/01/policenauts-edit.gif" alt=""></picture>
    
            <div>
                    <h2><span>Sign up for Read Only Memo</span></h2>
                    <p><span>Videogame emulation news and exclusive interviews, from the aesthetics of razor sharp scanlines to the wild technical challenges of making yesterday's games run on tomorrow's hardware.</span></p>
                    
        
        
                    <p><span>No spam. Unsubscribe anytime.</span></p>
                </div>
        </div>
        </section>

    </article>

        

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bank of England flags risk of 'sudden correction' in tech stocks inflated by AI (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ft.com/content/fe474cff-564c-41d2-aaf7-313636a83e5b</link>
            <guid>45516265</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 13:55:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/fe474cff-564c-41d2-aaf7-313636a83e5b">https://www.ft.com/content/fe474cff-564c-41d2-aaf7-313636a83e5b</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45516265">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><main id="site-content"><div id="barrier-page"><div id="heroOffer-Hero offers-3d7b7f9f-830b-4cd1-b66c-7d64732bd9de" data-component="heroOffer" data-component-unique-name="Hero offers" data-o3-theme="inverse"><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><p><span></span><span></span><span></span><span>Subscribe to unlock this article</span><span></span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12 L6"><div><h2><span><span>Save 40% on Standard Digital</span></span></h2><p><span><span><span>was </span><span>Dkr4188</span><span> </span><span>now </span><span>Dkr2499</span><span> for your first year</span></span></span></p></div><p><span><span>Save now on essential digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Saving based on monthly annualised price.</span></span></p></div></div><div id="recommendedOffers-Recommended Offers" data-component="recommendedOffers" data-component-unique-name="Recommended Offers"><p><h2 data-o-grid-colspan="12">Explore more offers.</h2></p><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div><p><img src="https://images.ft.com/v3/image/raw/https%3A%2F%2Fbarrier-page-components.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com%2Fassets%2Ficons%2Fprimary_product_icon_trial.svg?format=svg&amp;source=next-barrier-page" alt=""></p><p><h3>Trial</h3></p></div><p><span><span>Dkr10</span><span> for 4 weeks</span></span></p><p><span><span>Then </span><span>Dkr535</span><span> per month. Complete digital access to quality FT journalism on any device. Cancel or change your plan anytime during your trial.</span></span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div><p><img src="https://images.ft.com/v3/image/raw/https%3A%2F%2Fbarrier-page-components.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com%2Fassets%2Ficons%2Fprimary_product_icon_premium.svg?format=svg&amp;source=next-barrier-page" alt=""></p><p><h3>Premium Digital</h3></p></div><p><span><span>Dkr535</span><span> per month</span></span></p><p><span><span>Complete digital access to quality FT journalism with expert analysis from industry leaders. Pay a year upfront and save 20%.</span></span></p></div><div data-o-grid-colspan="12"><div><p><img src="https://images.ft.com/v3/image/raw/https%3A%2F%2Fbarrier-page-components.s3.eu-west-1.amazonaws.com%2Fassets%2Ficons%2Fprimary_product_icon_bundle.svg?format=svg&amp;source=next-barrier-page" alt=""></p><p><h3>Print + Premium Digital</h3></p></div><p><span><span>was </span><span>Dkr5999</span><span> </span><span>now </span><span>Dkr5135</span><span> for your first year</span></span></p><p><span><span>Get Premium &amp; FT Weekend Print edition for the price of Premium. Complete digital access to quality analysis and expert insights, complemented with our award-winning Weekend Print edition.</span></span></p></div></div></div><div data-component="subscriptionOptions" data-component-unique-name="Subscription Options Offers API" data-o3-theme="inverse"><h2>Explore our full range of subscriptions.</h2><div><div><div><h3>For individuals</h3></div><p>Discover all the plans currently available in your country</p></div><div><div><h3> For multiple readers</h3></div><p>Digital access for organisations. Includes exclusive features and content.</p></div></div></div><div data-component="whyFT" data-component-unique-name="Why FT" data-o3-theme="inverse"><div><h2>Why the FT?</h2><p>See why over a million readers pay to read the Financial Times.</p></div><p><a href="https://subs.ft.com/whytheft?ft-content-uuid=fe474cff-564c-41d2-aaf7-313636a83e5b" aria-label="Find out why the FT">Find out why</a></p></div></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We found a bug in Go's ARM64 compiler (300 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/how-we-found-a-bug-in-gos-arm64-compiler/</link>
            <guid>45516000</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 13:33:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/how-we-found-a-bug-in-gos-arm64-compiler/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/how-we-found-a-bug-in-gos-arm64-compiler/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45516000">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><p>2025-10-08</p><section><p>10 min read</p><img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/1zaMttyutjMsqHUuEpCss3/8b7eb27d92e5fc53f6541d04fe0b778f/Bug_Bounty.png" alt=""><div><p>Every second, 84 million HTTP requests are hitting Cloudflare across our fleet of data centers in 330 cities. It means that even the rarest of bugs can show up frequently. In fact, it was our scale that recently led us to discover a bug in Go's arm64 compiler which causes a race condition in the generated code.</p><p>This post breaks down how we first encountered the bug, investigated it, and ultimately drove to the root cause.</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="investigating-a-strange-panic">Investigating a strange panic</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>We run a service in our network which configures the kernel to handle traffic for some products like <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/products/magic-transit/"><u>Magic Transit</u></a> and <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/products/magic-wan/"><u>Magic WAN</u></a>. Our monitoring watches this closely, and it started to observe very sporadic panics on arm64 machines.</p><p>We first saw one with a fatal error stating that <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/c0ee2fd4e309ef0b8f4ab6f4860e2626c8e00802/src/runtime/traceback.go#L566"><u>traceback did not unwind completely</u></a>. That error suggests that invariants were violated when traversing the stack, likely because of stack corruption. After a brief investigation we decided that it was probably rare stack memory corruption. This was a largely idle control plane service where unplanned restarts have negligible impact, and so we felt that following up was not a priority unless it kept happening.</p><p>And then it kept happening.&nbsp;</p>
    <p>
      <h4 id="coredumps-per-hour">Coredumps per hour</h4>
      
    </p>
    
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/7ohMD2ph3I9l7lbZQWZ4xl/243e679d8293565fc6a55a670c9f3583/BLOG-2906_2.png" alt="BLOG-2906 2" width="1999" height="526" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p>When we first saw this bug we saw that the fatal errors correlated with recovered panics. These were caused by some old code which used panic/recover as error handling.&nbsp;</p><p>At this point, our theory was:&nbsp;</p><ol><li><p>All of the fatal panics happen within stack unwinding.</p></li><li><p>We correlated an increased volume of recovered panics with these fatal panics.</p></li><li><p>Recovering a panic unwinds goroutine stacks to call deferred functions.</p></li><li><p>A related <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/issues/73259"><u>Go issue (#73259)</u></a> reported an arm64 stack unwinding crash.</p></li><li><p>Let’s stop using panic/recover for error handling and wait out the upstream fix?</p></li></ol><p>So we did that and watched as fatal panics stopped occurring as the release rolled out. Fatal panics gone, our theoretical mitigation seemed to work, and this was no longer our problem. We subscribed to the upstream issue so we could update when it was resolved and put it out of our minds.</p><p>But, this turned out to be a much stranger bug than expected. Putting it out of our minds was premature as the same class of fatal panics came back at a much higher rate. A month later, we were seeing up to 30 daily fatal panics with no real discernible cause; while that might account for only one machine a day in less than 10% of our data centers, we found it concerning that we didn’t understand the cause. The first thing we checked was the number of recovered panics, to match our previous pattern, but there were none. More interestingly, we could not correlate this increased rate of fatal panics with anything. A release? Infrastructure changes? The position of Mars? </p><p>At this point we felt like we needed to dive deeper to better understand the root cause. Pattern matching and hoping was clearly insufficient.&nbsp;</p><p>We saw two classes of this bug -- a crash while accessing invalid memory and an explicitly checked fatal error.&nbsp;</p>
    <p>
      <h4 id="fatal-error">Fatal Error</h4>
      
    </p>
    
            <pre><code>goroutine 153 gp=0x4000105340 m=324 mp=0x400639ea08 [GC worker (active)]:
/usr/local/go/src/runtime/asm_arm64.s:244 +0x6c fp=0x7ff97fffe870 sp=0x7ff97fffe860 pc=0x55558d4098fc
runtime.systemstack(0x0)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgc.go:1508 +0x68 fp=0x7ff97fffe860 sp=0x7ff97fffe810 pc=0x55558d3a9408
runtime.gcBgMarkWorker.func2()
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:1102
runtime.gcDrainMarkWorkerIdle(...)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:1188 +0x434 fp=0x7ff97fffe810 sp=0x7ff97fffe7a0 pc=0x55558d3ad514
runtime.gcDrain(0x400005bc50, 0x7)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:212 +0x1c8 fp=0x7ff97fffe7a0 sp=0x7ff97fffe6f0 pc=0x55558d3ab248
runtime.markroot(0x400005bc50, 0x17e6, 0x1)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:238 +0xa8 fp=0x7ff97fffe6f0 sp=0x7ff97fffe6a0 pc=0x55558d3ab578
runtime.markroot.func1()
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:887 +0x290 fp=0x7ff97fffe6a0 sp=0x7ff97fffe560 pc=0x55558d3acaa0
runtime.scanstack(0x4014494380, 0x400005bc50)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/traceback.go:447 +0x2ac fp=0x7ff97fffe560 sp=0x7ff97fffe4d0 pc=0x55558d3eeb7c
runtime.(*unwinder).next(0x7ff97fffe5b0?)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/traceback.go:566 +0x110 fp=0x7ff97fffe4d0 sp=0x7ff97fffe490 pc=0x55558d3eed40
runtime.(*unwinder).finishInternal(0x7ff97fffe4f8?)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/panic.go:1073 +0x38 fp=0x7ff97fffe490 sp=0x7ff97fffe460 pc=0x55558d403388
runtime.throw({0x55558de6aa27?, 0x7ff97fffe638?})
runtime stack:
fatal error: traceback did not unwind completely
       stack=[0x4015d6a000-0x4015d8a000
runtime: g8221077: frame.sp=0x4015d784c0 top=0x4015d89fd0</code></pre>
            
    <p>
      <h4 id="segmentation-fault">Segmentation fault</h4>
      
    </p>
    
            <pre><code>goroutine 187 gp=0x40003aea80 m=13 mp=0x40003ca008 [GC worker (active)]:
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/asm_arm64.s:244 +0x6c fp=0x7fff2afde870 sp=0x7fff2afde860 pc=0x55557e2d98fc
runtime.systemstack(0x0)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgc.go:1489 +0x94 fp=0x7fff2afde860 sp=0x7fff2afde810 pc=0x55557e279434
runtime.gcBgMarkWorker.func2()
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:1112
runtime.gcDrainMarkWorkerDedicated(...)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:1188 +0x434 fp=0x7fff2afde810 sp=0x7fff2afde7a0 pc=0x55557e27d514
runtime.gcDrain(0x4000059750, 0x3)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:212 +0x1c8 fp=0x7fff2afde7a0 sp=0x7fff2afde6f0 pc=0x55557e27b248
runtime.markroot(0x4000059750, 0xb8, 0x1)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:238 +0xa8 fp=0x7fff2afde6f0 sp=0x7fff2afde6a0 pc=0x55557e27b578
runtime.markroot.func1()
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:887 +0x290 fp=0x7fff2afde6a0 sp=0x7fff2afde560 pc=0x55557e27caa0
runtime.scanstack(0x40042cc000, 0x4000059750)
       /usr/local/go/src/runtime/traceback.go:458 +0x188 fp=0x7fff2afde560 sp=0x7fff2afde4d0 pc=0x55557e2bea58
runtime.(*unwinder).next(0x7fff2afde5b0)
goroutine 0 gp=0x40003af880 m=13 mp=0x40003ca008 [idle]:
PC=0x55557e2bea58 m=13 sigcode=1 addr=0x118
SIGSEGV: segmentation violation</code></pre>
            <p>Now we could observe some clear patterns. Both errors occur when unwinding the stack in <code>(*unwinder).next</code>. In one case we saw an intentional<a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/b3251514531123d7fd007682389bce7428d159a0/src/runtime/traceback.go#L566"> <u>fatal error</u></a> as the runtime identified that unwinding could not complete and the stack was in a bad state. In the other case there was a direct memory access error that happened while trying to unwind the stack. The segfault was discussed in the <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/issues/73259#issuecomment-2786818812"><u>GitHub issue</u></a> and a Go engineer identified it as dereference of a go scheduler struct, <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/924fe98902cdebf20825ab5d1e4edfc0fed2966f/src/runtime/runtime2.go#L536"><u>m</u></a>, when<a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/b3251514531123d7fd007682389bce7428d159a0/src/runtime/traceback.go#L458"> <u>unwinding</u></a>.&nbsp;  </p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="a-review-of-go-scheduler-structs">A review of Go scheduler structs</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>Go uses a lightweight userspace scheduler to manage concurrency. Many goroutines are scheduled on a smaller number of kernel threads – this is often referred to as M:N scheduling. Any individual goroutine can be scheduled on any kernel thread. The scheduler has three core types – <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/924fe98902cdebf20825ab5d1e4edfc0fed2966f/src/runtime/runtime2.go#L394"><code><u>g</u></code></a>&nbsp; (the goroutine), <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/924fe98902cdebf20825ab5d1e4edfc0fed2966f/src/runtime/runtime2.go#L536"><code><u>m</u></code></a> (the kernel thread, or “machine”), and <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/924fe98902cdebf20825ab5d1e4edfc0fed2966f/src/runtime/runtime2.go#L644"><code><u>p</u></code></a> (the physical execution context, or&nbsp; “processor”). For a goroutine to be scheduled a free <code>m</code> must acquire a free <code>p</code>, which will execute a g. Each <code>g</code> contains a field for its m if it is currently running, otherwise it will be <b>nil</b>. This is all the context needed for this post but the <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/master/src/runtime/HACKING.md#gs-ms-ps"><u>go runtime docs</u></a> explore this more comprehensively.&nbsp;</p><p>At this point we can start to make inferences on what’s happening: the program crashes because we try to unwind a goroutine stack which is invalid. In the first backtrace, if a <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/b3251514531123d7fd007682389bce7428d159a0/src/runtime/traceback.go#L446"><u>return address is null, we call </u><code><u>finishInternal</u></code><u> and abort because the stack was not fully unwound</u></a>. The segmentation fault case in the second backtrace is a bit more interesting: if instead the return address is non-zero but not a function then the unwinder code assumes that the goroutine is currently running. It'll then dereference m and fault by accessing <code>m.incgo</code> (the offset of <code>incgo</code> into <code>struct m</code> is 0x118, the faulting memory access). </p><p>What, then, is causing this corruption? The traces were difficult to get anything useful from – our service has hundreds if not thousands of active goroutines. It was fairly clear from the beginning that the panic was remote from the actual bug. The crashes were all observed while unwinding the stack and if this were an issue any time the stack was unwound on arm64 we would be seeing it in many more services. We felt pretty confident that the stack unwinding was happening correctly but on an invalid stack.&nbsp;</p><p>Our investigation stalled for a while at this point – making guesses, testing guesses, trying to infer if the panic rate went up or down, or if nothing changed. There was <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/issues/73259"><u>a known issue</u></a> on Go’s GitHub issue tracker which matched our symptoms almost exactly, but what they discussed was mostly what we already knew. At some point when looking through the linked stack traces we realized that their crash referenced an old version of a library that we were also using – Go Netlink.</p>
            <pre><code>goroutine 1267 gp=0x4002a8ea80 m=nil [runnable (scan)]:
runtime.asyncPreempt2()
        /usr/local/go/src/runtime/preempt.go:308 +0x3c fp=0x4004cec4c0 sp=0x4004cec4a0 pc=0x46353c
runtime.asyncPreempt()
        /usr/local/go/src/runtime/preempt_arm64.s:47 +0x9c fp=0x4004cec6b0 sp=0x4004cec4c0 pc=0x4a6a8c
github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl.(*NetlinkSocket).Receive(0x14360300000000?)
        /go/pkg/mod/github.com/!data!dog/<a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="90fef5e4fcf9fefbd0e6a1bea0bea1bda0bea2a0a2a4a0a2a2a3a1a9a5a3a2a0bdf3a7f1a4f6a8a3a2f1a3f4a1">[email&nbsp;protected]</a>/nl/nl_linux.go:803 +0x130 fp=0x4004cfc710 sp=0x4004cec6c0 pc=0xf95de0
</code></pre>
            <p>We spot-checked a few stack traces and confirmed the presence of this Netlink library. Querying our logs showed that not only did we share a library – every single segmentation fault we observed had happened while preempting<a href="https://github.com/vishvananda/netlink/blob/e1e260214862392fb28ff72c9b11adc84df73e2c/nl/nl_linux.go#L880"> <code><u>NetlinkSocket.Receive</u></code></a>.</p>
    <p>
      <h3 id="whats-async-preemption">What’s (async) preemption?</h3>
      
    </p>
    <p>In the prehistoric era of Go (&lt;=1.13) the runtime was cooperatively scheduled. A goroutine would run until it decided it was ready to yield to the scheduler – usually due to explicit calls to <code>runtime.Gosched()</code> or injected yield points at function calls/IO operations. Since<a href="https://go.dev/doc/go1.14#runtime"> <u>Go 1.14</u></a> the runtime instead does async preemption. The Go runtime has a thread <code>sysmon</code> which tracks the runtime of goroutines and will preempt any that run for longer than 10ms (at time of writing). It does this by sending <code>SIGURG</code> to the OS thread and in the signal handler will modify the program counter and stack to mimic a call to <code>asyncPreempt</code>.</p><p>At this point we had two broad theories:</p><ul><li><p>This is a Go Netlink bug – likely due to <code>unsafe.Pointer</code> usage which invoked undefined behavior but is only actually broken on arm64</p></li><li><p>This is a Go runtime bug and we're only triggering it in <code>NetlinkSocket.Receive</code> for some reason</p></li></ul><p>After finding the same bug publicly reported upstream, we were feeling confident this was caused by a Go runtime bug. However, upon seeing that both issues implicated the same function, we felt more skeptical – notably the Go Netlink library uses unsafe.Pointer so memory corruption was a plausible explanation even if we didn't understand why.</p><p>After an unsuccessful code audit we had hit a wall. The crashes were rare and remote from the root cause. Maybe these crashes were caused by a runtime bug, maybe they were caused by a Go Netlink bug. It seemed clear that there was something wrong with this area of the code, but code auditing wasn’t going anywhere. </p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="breakthrough">Breakthrough</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>At this point we had a fairly good understanding of what was crashing but very little understanding of <b>why</b> it was happening. It was clear that the root cause of the stack unwinder crashing was remote from the actual crash, and that it had to do with <code>(*NetlinkSocket).Receive</code>, but why? We were able to capture a <b>coredump</b> of a production crash and view it in a debugger. The backtrace confirmed what we already knew – that there was a segmentation fault when unwinding a stack. The crux of the issue revealed itself when we looked at the goroutine which had been preempted while calling <code>(*NetlinkSocket).Receive</code>.&nbsp;    </p>
            <pre><code>(dlv) bt
0  0x0000555577579dec in runtime.asyncPreempt2
   at /usr/local/go/src/runtime/preempt.go:306
1  0x00005555775bc94c in runtime.asyncPreempt
   at /usr/local/go/src/runtime/preempt_arm64.s:47
2  0x0000555577cb2880 in github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl.(*NetlinkSocket).Receive
   at
/vendor/github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl/nl_linux.go:779
3  0x0000555577cb19a8 in github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl.(*NetlinkRequest).Execute
   at 
/vendor/github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl/nl_linux.go:532
4  0x0000555577551124 in runtime.heapSetType
   at /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mbitmap.go:714
5  0x0000555577551124 in runtime.heapSetType
   at /usr/local/go/src/runtime/mbitmap.go:714
...
(dlv) disass -a 0x555577cb2878 0x555577cb2888
TEXT github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl.(*NetlinkSocket).Receive(SB) /vendor/github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl/nl_linux.go
        nl_linux.go:779 0x555577cb2878  fdfb7fa9        LDP -8(RSP), (R29, R30)
        nl_linux.go:779 0x555577cb287c  ff430191        ADD $80, RSP, RSP
        nl_linux.go:779 0x555577cb2880  ff434091        ADD $(16&lt;&lt;12), RSP, RSP
        nl_linux.go:779 0x555577cb2884  c0035fd6        RET
</code></pre>
            <p>The goroutine was paused between two opcodes in the function epilogue. Since the process of unwinding a stack relies on the stack frame being in a consistent state, it felt immediately suspicious that we preempted in the middle of adjusting the stack pointer. The goroutine had been paused at 0x555577cb2880, between<code> ADD $80, RSP, RSP and ADD $(16&lt;&lt;12), RSP, RSP</code>.&nbsp;</p><p>We queried the service logs to confirm our theory. This wasn’t isolated – the majority of stack traces showed that this same opcode was preempted. This was no longer a weird production crash we couldn’t reproduce. A crash happened when the Go runtime preempted between these two stack pointer adjustments. We had our smoking gun.&nbsp;</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="building-a-minimal-reproducer">Building a minimal reproducer</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>At this point we felt pretty confident that this was actually just a runtime bug and it should be reproducible in an isolated environment without any dependencies. The theory at this point was:</p><ol><li><p>Stack unwinding is triggered by garbage collection</p></li><li><p>Async preemption between a split stack pointer adjustment causes a crash</p></li><li><p>What if we make a function which splits the adjustment and then call it in a loop?</p></li></ol>
            <pre><code>package main

import (
	"runtime"
)

//go:noinline
func big_stack(val int) int {
	var big_buffer = make([]byte, 1 &lt;&lt; 16)

	sum := 0
	// prevent the compiler from optimizing out the stack
	for i := 0; i &lt; (1&lt;&lt;16); i++ {
		big_buffer[i] = byte(val)
	}
	for i := 0; i &lt; (1&lt;&lt;16); i++ {
		sum ^= int(big_buffer[i])
	}
	return sum
}

func main() {
	go func() {
		for {
			runtime.GC()
		}
	}()
	for {
		_ = big_stack(1000)
	}
}
</code></pre>
            <p>This function ends up with a stack frame slightly larger than can be represented in 16 bits, and so on arm64 the Go compiler will split the stack pointer adjustment into two opcodes. If the runtime preempts between these opcodes then the stack unwinder will read an invalid stack pointer and crash.&nbsp;</p>
            <pre><code>; epilogue for main.big_stack
ADD $8, RSP, R29
ADD $(16&lt;&lt;12), R29, R29
ADD $16, RSP, RSP
; preemption is problematic between these opcodes
ADD $(16&lt;&lt;12), RSP, RSP
RET
</code></pre>
            <p>After running this for a few minutes the program panicked as expected!</p>
            <pre><code>SIGSEGV: segmentation violation
PC=0x60598 m=8 sigcode=1 addr=0x118

goroutine 0 gp=0x400019c540 m=8 mp=0x4000198708 [idle]:
runtime.(*unwinder).next(0x400030fd10)
        /home/thea/sdk/go1.23.4/src/runtime/traceback.go:458 +0x188 fp=0x400030fcc0 sp=0x400030fc30 pc=0x60598
runtime.scanstack(0x40000021c0, 0x400002f750)
        /home/thea/sdk/go1.23.4/src/runtime/mgcmark.go:887 +0x290 

[...]

goroutine 1 gp=0x40000021c0 m=nil [runnable (scan)]:
runtime.asyncPreempt2()
        /home/thea/sdk/go1.23.4/src/runtime/preempt.go:308 +0x3c fp=0x40003bfcf0 sp=0x40003bfcd0 pc=0x400cc
runtime.asyncPreempt()
        /home/thea/sdk/go1.23.4/src/runtime/preempt_arm64.s:47 +0x9c fp=0x40003bfee0 sp=0x40003bfcf0 pc=0x75aec
main.big_stack(0x40003cff38?)
        /home/thea/dev/stack_corruption_reproducer/main.go:29 +0x94 fp=0x40003cff00 sp=0x40003bfef0 pc=0x77c04
Segmentation fault (core dumped)

real    1m29.165s
user    4m4.987s
sys     0m43.212s</code></pre>
            <p>A reproducible crash with standard library only? This felt like conclusive evidence that our problem was a runtime bug.</p><p>This was an extremely particular reproducer! Even now with a good understanding of the bug and its fix, some of the behavior is still puzzling. It's a one-instruction race condition, so it’s unsurprising that small changes could have large impact. For example, this reproducer was originally written and tested on Go 1.23.4, but did not crash when compiled with 1.23.9 (the version in production), even though we could objdump the binary and see the split ADD still present! We don’t have a definite explanation for this behavior – even with the bug present there remain a few unknown variables which affect the likelihood of hitting the race condition.&nbsp;</p>
    <p>
      <h2 id="a-single-instruction-race-condition-window">A single-instruction race condition window</h2>
      
    </p>
    <p>arm64 is a fixed-length 4-byte instruction set architecture. This has a lot of implications on codegen but most relevant to this bug is the fact that immediate length is limited.<a href="https://developer.arm.com/documentation/ddi0596/2020-12/Base-Instructions/ADD--immediate---Add--immediate--"> <code><u>add</u></code></a> gets a 12-bit immediate,<a href="https://developer.arm.com/documentation/dui0802/a/A64-General-Instructions/MOV--wide-immediate-"> <code><u>mov</u></code></a> gets a 16-bit immediate, etc. How does the architecture handle this when the operands don't fit? It depends – <code>ADD</code> in particular reserves a bit for "shift left by 12" so any 24 bit addition can be decomposed into two opcodes. Other instructions are decomposed similarly, or just require loading an immediate into a register first.&nbsp;</p><p>The very last step of the Go compiler before emitting machine code involves transforming the program into <code>obj.Prog</code> structs. It's a very low level intermediate representation (IR) that mostly serves to be translated into machine code.&nbsp;</p>
            <pre><code>//https://github.com/golang/go/blob/fa2bb342d7b0024440d996c2d6d6778b7a5e0247/src/cmd/internal/obj/arm64/obj7.go#L856

// Pop stack frame.
// ADD $framesize, RSP, RSP
p = obj.Appendp(p, c.newprog)
p.As = AADD
p.From.Type = obj.TYPE_CONST
p.From.Offset = int64(c.autosize)
p.To.Type = obj.TYPE_REG
p.To.Reg = REGSP
p.Spadj = -c.autosize
</code></pre>
            <p>Notably, this IR is not aware of immediate length limitations. Instead, this happens in<a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/2f653a5a9e9112ff64f1392ff6e1d404aaf23e8c/src/cmd/internal/obj/arm64/asm7.go"> <u>asm7.go</u></a> when Go's internal intermediate representation is translated into arm64 machine code. The assembler will classify an immediate in <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/2f653a5a9e9112ff64f1392ff6e1d404aaf23e8c/src/cmd/internal/obj/arm64/asm7.go#L1905"><u>conclass</u></a> based on bit size and then use that when emitting instructions – extra if needed.</p><p>The Go assembler uses a combination of (<code>mov, add</code>) opcodes for some adds that fit in 16-bit immediates, and prefers (<code>add, add + lsl 12</code>) opcodes for 16-bit+ immediates.&nbsp;  </p><p>Compare a stack of (slightly larger than) <code>1&lt;&lt;15</code>:</p>
            <pre><code>; //go:noinline
; func big_stack() byte {
; 	var big_stack = make([]byte, 1&lt;&lt;15)
; 	return big_stack[0]
; }
MOVD $32776, R27
ADD R27, RSP, R29
MOVD $32784, R27
ADD R27, RSP, RSP
RET
</code></pre>
            <p>With a stack of <code>1&lt;&lt;16</code>:</p>
            <pre><code>; //go:noinline
; func big_stack() byte {
; 	var big_stack = make([]byte, 1&lt;&lt;16)
; 	return big_stack[0]
; } 
ADD $8, RSP, R29
ADD $(16&lt;&lt;12), R29, R29
ADD $16, RSP, RSP
ADD $(16&lt;&lt;12), RSP, RSP
RET
</code></pre>
            <p>In the larger stack case, there is a point between <code>ADD x, RSP, RSP</code> opcodes where the stack pointer is not pointing to the tip of a stack frame. We thought at first that this was a matter of memory corruption – that in handling async preemption the runtime would push a function call on the stack and corrupt the middle of the stack. However, this goroutine is already in the function epilogue – any data we corrupt is actively in the process of being thrown away. What's the issue then?  </p><p>The Go runtime often needs to <b>unwind</b> the stack, which means walking backwards through the chain of function calls. For example: garbage collection uses it to find live references on the stack, panicking relies on it to evaluate <code>defer</code> functions, and generating stack traces needs to print the call stack. For this to work the stack pointer <b>must be accurate during unwinding</b> because of how golang dereferences sp to determine the calling function. If the stack pointer is partially modified, the unwinder will look for the calling function in the middle of the stack. The underlying data is meaningless when interpreted as directions to a parent stack frame and then the runtime will likely crash.&nbsp;</p>
            <pre><code>//https://github.com/golang/go/blob/66536242fce34787230c42078a7bbd373ef8dcb0/src/runtime/traceback.go#L373

if innermost &amp;&amp; frame.sp &lt; frame.fp || frame.lr == 0 {
    lrPtr = frame.sp
    frame.lr = *(*uintptr)(unsafe.Pointer(lrPtr))
}
</code></pre>
            <p>When async preemption happens it will push a function call onto the stack but the parent stack frame is no longer correct because sp was only partially adjusted when the preemption happened. The crash flow looks something like this:  </p><ol><li><p>Async preemption happens between the two opcodes that <code>add x, rsp</code> expands to</p></li><li><p>Garbage collection triggers stack unwinding (to check for heap object liveness)</p></li><li><p>The unwinder starts traversing the stack of the problematic goroutine and correctly unwinds up to the problematic function</p></li><li><p>The unwinder dereferences <code>sp</code> to determine the parent function</p></li><li><p>Almost certainly the data behind <code>sp</code> is not a function</p></li><li><p>Crash</p></li></ol>
          <figure>
          <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/5LKOBC6lQzuKvwy0vyEfk2/054c9aaedc14d155294a682f7de3a610/BLOG-2906_3.png" alt="BLOG-2906 3" width="784" height="491" loading="lazy">
          </figure><p>We saw earlier a faulting stack trace which ended in <code>(*NetlinkSocket).Receive</code> – in this case stack unwinding faulted while it was trying to determine the parent frame.&nbsp;   </p>
            <pre><code>goroutine 90 gp=0x40042cc000 m=nil [preempted (scan)]:
runtime.asyncPreempt2()
/usr/local/go/src/runtime/preempt.go:306 +0x2c fp=0x40060a25d0 sp=0x40060a25b0 pc=0x55557e299dec
runtime.asyncPreempt()
/usr/local/go/src/runtime/preempt_arm64.s:47 +0x9c fp=0x40060a27c0 sp=0x40060a25d0 pc=0x55557e2dc94c
github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl.(*NetlinkSocket).Receive(0xff48ce6e060b2848?)
/vendor/github.com/vishvananda/netlink/nl/nl_linux.go:779 +0x130 fp=0x40060b2820 sp=0x40060a27d0 pc=0x55557e9d2880
</code></pre>
            <p>Once we discovered the root cause we reported it with a reproducer and the bug was quickly fixed. This bug is fixed in <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/commit/e8794e650e05fad07a33fb6e3266a9e677d13fa8"><u>go1.23.12</u></a>, <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/commit/6e1c4529e4e00ab58572deceab74cc4057e6f0b6"><u>go1.24.6</u></a>, and <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/commit/f7cc61e7d7f77521e073137c6045ba73f66ef902"><u>go1.25.0</u></a>. Previously, the go compiler emitted a single <code>add x, rsp</code> instruction and relied on the assembler to split immediates into multiple opcodes as necessary. After this change, stacks larger than 1&lt;&lt;12 will build the offset in a temporary register and then add that to <code>rsp</code> in a single, indivisible opcode. A goroutine can be preempted before or after the stack pointer modification, but never during. This means that the stack pointer is always valid and there is no race condition.</p>
            <pre><code>LDP -8(RSP), (R29, R30)
MOVD $32, R27
MOVK $(1&lt;&lt;16), R27
ADD R27, RSP, RSP
RET</code></pre>
            <p>This was a very fun problem to debug. We don’t often see bugs where you can accurately blame the compiler. Debugging it took weeks and we had to learn about areas of the Go runtime that people don’t usually need to think about. It’s a nice example of a rare race condition, the sort of bug that can only really be quantified at a large scale.</p><p>We’re always looking for people who enjoy this kind of detective work. <a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers/jobs/?department=Engineering"><u>Our engineering teams are hiring</u></a>.   </p></div></section><div><p>Cloudflare's connectivity cloud protects <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, helps customers build <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerates any <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">wards off DDoS attacks</a>, keeps <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><astro-slot> <!--[if astro]>server-island-start<![endif]--> </astro-slot><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/deep-dive/">Deep Dive</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/go/">Go</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/programming/">Programming</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The weaponization of travel blacklists (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://papersplease.org/wp/2025/10/06/the-weaponization-of-travel-blacklists/</link>
            <guid>45515783</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 13:10:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2025/10/06/the-weaponization-of-travel-blacklists/">https://papersplease.org/wp/2025/10/06/the-weaponization-of-travel-blacklists/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45515783">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<div id="attachment_20428"><p><a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/2025.09.30_Final-Hearing-Documents.pdf"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-20428" loading="lazy" src="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/license-plate.png" alt="Excerpt from &quot;After Action Report&quot; by a Federal Air Marshal." width="1054" height="517" srcset="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/license-plate.png 1054w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/license-plate-300x147.png 300w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/license-plate-1024x502.png 1024w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/license-plate-768x377.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1054px) 100vw, 1054px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-20428"><em>[A Federal Air Marshal (FAM) tasked with surveillance of an airline passenger targeted by Quiet Skies lists and/or rules followed the traveler out to the curb and recorded the license plate number of the vehicle in which she left the airport, so that her airline reservations could be integrated with license plate reader data into an uninterrupted multi-modal travel history.]</em></p></div><p>On September 30, 2025, the <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/">Senate Committee on Homeland Security and Government Affairs</a> held a hearing on <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/hearings/examining-the-weaponization-of-the-quiet-skies-program/">Examining the Weaponization of the Quiet Skies Program</a>.</p>
<p>Coming just hours before the partial shutdown of Federal government operations, this hearing was sparsely attended, even by members of the committee, and got little press attention. The hearing opened with the Chair and Ranking Minority Member of the committee talking over each other at length.</p>
<p>Much of the argument between Senators and the questioning of witnesses focused not on the general problems of the <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2018/07/29/federal-air-marshals-blow-the-whistle-on-tsa-quiet-skies-traveler-surveillance-program/">Quiet Skies</a> traveler surveillance program program or government travel <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2021/01/19/put-them-on-the-no-fly-list/">blacklists</a> (referred to euphemistically as “watchlists” throughout the hearing) but on whether these programs have been weaponized to a greater extent under Democratic or Republican administrations.</p>
<p>But if we — and, we hope, members of Congress — can look past the partisan polemics, the <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/hearings/examining-the-weaponization-of-the-quiet-skies-program/">testimony</a> and <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/2025.09.30_Final-Hearing-Documents.pdf">documents introduced into the record</a> of this hearing provide important guidance on what can and should be done to protect <strong>all</strong> travelers —&nbsp; regardless of our party affiliation (if any), ethnicity, religious beliefs, or political opinions — against the weaponization of travel blacklists by <em>whatever</em> government is in power.<span id="more-20425"></span></p>
<p>The <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2018/07/29/federal-air-marshals-blow-the-whistle-on-tsa-quiet-skies-traveler-surveillance-program/">Quiet Skies</a> [sic] program assigned officers from the <a href="https://www.tsa.gov/videos/inside-look-federal-air-marshal-service">Federal Air Marshals Service</a> (one of the police agencies within the Transportation Security Administration) to accompany and surveil pre-selected airline passengers on flights and in airports.</p>
<p>Quiet Skies is just one of many travel surveillance and blacklisting programs. According to another report by the same Senate committee last yea (under a chair from the opposite side of the aisle), “There are at least 22 different mechanisms that might lead Americans to receive additional screening at airports and other ports of entry or be denied the ability to travel.”</p>
<p>According to <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2018/07/29/federal-air-marshals-blow-the-whistle-on-tsa-quiet-skies-traveler-surveillance-program/">precious whistleblower reports</a> and <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/2025.09.30_Final-Hearing-Documents.pdf">documents obtained by the Senate HSGAC Committee</a> and entered into the record of the hearing last week, Quite Skies targets were selected by a ruleset that incorporated other US government <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2021/01/19/put-them-on-the-no-fly-list/">blacklists</a> and <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2018/08/31/a-broader-legal-challenge-to-federal-blacklists/">watchlists </a>as well as profile-based rules that factored in ethnicity and countries previously visited.</p>
<div id="attachment_20445"><p><a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/2025.09.30_Final-Hearing-Documents.pdf"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-20445" loading="lazy" src="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/FAM-report.png" alt="Excerpt from trip report by a Federal Air Marshal." width="579" height="325" srcset="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/FAM-report.png 579w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/FAM-report-300x168.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 579px) 100vw, 579px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-20445"><em>[Redacted excerpt from a trip report by a Federal Air Marshal regarding a subject targeted through the Quiet Skies program.]</em></p></div><p>Targets of blacklisting and watchlisting have ranged from people selected based on having <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/12/09/public-private-partnerships-for-financial-surveillance/">used a credit card at a Washington-area airport on or around January 6, 2021</a>, to <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/08/15/travel-blacklists-target-political-critics/">critics of Israel’s military actions in Gaza</a>, among other activities protected by the First Amendment.</p>
<p>The Quiet Skies program was <a href="https://www.dhs.gov/news/2025/06/05/secretary-noem-ends-politicized-tsa-watchlist-program-has-failed-prevent-single">ended in June 2025</a> by the Secretary of Homeland Security, Kristi Noehm.&nbsp; The same day as the Senate hearing on Quiet Skies last week, the TSA&nbsp; <a href="https://www.tsa.gov/news/press/releases/2025/09/30/dhs-and-tsa-expose-targeting-political-opponents-former-biden">announced</a> that Secretary Noehm was firing five senior TSA officials associated with the Quite Skies program, including the TSA’s executive assistant administrator for operations support and the deputy assistant administrator for intelligence and analysis.</p>
<p>News reports, presumably based on DHS statements, described Quiet Skies as a “<a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/us-removes-senior-leaders-over-airline-passenger-watch-list-screening-program-2025-09-30/">Biden-era</a>” program even though <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2018/07/29/federal-air-marshals-blow-the-whistle-on-tsa-quiet-skies-traveler-surveillance-program/">its largest expansion came in 2018</a>&nbsp; during the first Trump administration. And according to the TSA’s <a href="https://www.tsa.gov/news/press/releases/2025/09/30/dhs-and-tsa-expose-targeting-political-opponents-former-biden">press release</a> last week:</p>
<blockquote><p>The TSA administrator has legal authority to prevent an individual from boarding an aircraft, task Federal Air Marshals with surveilling an individual, or place them on a watchlist, but it is only intended to be used to track and prevent dangerous criminals and terrorists from carrying out attacks on Americans.</p></blockquote>
<p>We question whether the TSA Administrator has the authority to prevent someone from traveling by common carrier without getting an order from a judge.&nbsp; And the TSA and DHS have consistently asserted authority and exercised power — legally or not — to blacklist and surveil travelers without needing any suspicion of criminality.</p>
<p>The bipartisanship of violations of the right to travel through blacklisting and watchlisting was brought out in the response of <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/Testimony-Ayoub-2025-09-30.pdf">Mr. Abed Ayoub</a>, Executive Director of the American-Arab Anti-Discrimination Committee (ADC) to one of the Senators’ questions about the weaponization of watchlists and blacklists against disfavored groups and individuals:</p>
<blockquote><p>That’s not a partisan problem. That’s a due process problem. When the government can quietly tag one group, it can quietly tag any group, left, right, neither, just depending on who holds power. The answer is the same for all of us: end the watchlists….</p>
<p>Quiet Skies captures only part of the story. It’s a window into a faulty surveillance architecture. The watchlist isn’t about who you vote for. It’s about whether the government has to prove its case when it takes away your rights….</p>
<p>Our community, for the past quarter of a century, we’re… targeted by all the administrations, so we can tell you the experience under Republican and Democratic administrations.</p></blockquote>
<p>Further guidance about what Congress can and should do was provided by another of the witnesses, <a href="https://www.hsgac.senate.gov/wp-content/uploads/Testimony-Harper-2025-09-30-Final.pdf">Mr. Jim Harper</a>, a Senior Nonresident Fellow of&nbsp; the American Enterprise Institute:</p>
<blockquote><p>We intuitively feel we have the right to travel, and there are cases from the Supreme Court that say you have a right to travel: You can move from one state to another and they can’t deny you Welfare benefits when you get there.</p>
<p>There are other cases: <a href="https://papersplease.org/gilmore/">A man in San Francisco wanted to fly to Washington, DC, to meet with his Representative</a>,&nbsp; and the 9th Circuit Court of Appeals <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2023/06/12/tsa-misstates-the-case-law-on-id-to-fly/">said</a> that you don’t have a right to travel on your preferred mode of transportation. They said, no, you can take the train, you can drive, if you want to go to Washington, DC.</p>
<p>A <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2021/11/22/freedom-to-travel-act-of-2021-introduced-in-congress/">clear right to travel</a> — Americans believe they have it, but the courts haven’t accorded it to them — would give them a position when they went to court.</p></blockquote>
<p>Court cases challenging the <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/4365955/fikre-v-federal-bureau-of-investigation">no-fly list</a> (ongoing since 2013, and now on remand following a <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/03/19/unanimous-supreme-court-rules-that-no-fly-case-can-go-forward/">unanimous favorable Supreme Court decision</a> in 2024) and <a href="https://www.courtlistener.com/docket/7653937/parties/jardaneh-v-barr/">other travel blacklists and watchlists</a> (ongoing <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2018/08/31/a-broader-legal-challenge-to-federal-blacklists/">since 2018</a>) have been dragged out for years by the government. The government continues to claim that “merely” being delayed for a few hours or days isn’t sufficiently harmful to a traveler’s rights to provide a basis for a lawsuit.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2021/11/22/freedom-to-travel-act-of-2021-introduced-in-congress/">Freedom to Travel Act</a> that was introduced in 2021 in the House of Representatives would provide both an explicit statutory right to travel by common carrier and a cause of action for violations of that right by government agencies, carriers, or other entities.</p>
<p>We hope Senators and Representatives moved to act on the issues raised in last week’s hearing on the TSA will re-introduce and co-sponsor the <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2021/11/22/freedom-to-travel-act-of-2021-introduced-in-congress/">Freedom to Travel Act</a> in this session of Congress, hold committee hearings on it, and incorporate it into appropriate omnibus legislation that has a better chance of passage than a standalone bill.</p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Email They Shouldn't Have Read (293 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/10/08/the-email-they-shouldnt-have-read/</link>
            <guid>45515657</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 12:56:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/10/08/the-email-they-shouldnt-have-read/">https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/10/08/the-email-they-shouldnt-have-read/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45515657">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" itemprop="articleBody"><p><strong>Author's Note:</strong> Before we begin, an important clarification. What follows is a horror story based on real events from my career. However, to protect the privacy of the people and companies involved, I have deliberately mixed things up: technologies, contexts, and specific details have been modified or merged with other experiences. I therefore invite you to read this story not as a strict chronicle of a single event, but as an archetype of a widespread problem in the IT world: vendor lock-in and predatory business practices. Any attempt to identify the specific company or software described would lead to an incorrect conclusion.</p><hr><p>When the phone rang, I was in a meeting - so I didn’t answer. But I recognized the number and sent a quick message: </p><blockquote><p>"I’m with a client right now. If it’s not urgent, please send me an email - otherwise I’ll call you ASAP".</p></blockquote><p>The reply, via SMS, left me speechless: </p><blockquote><p>"That’s exactly the problem. I can’t send you an email. Call me as soon as you can".</p></blockquote><p>From that moment on, my perception of a certain kind of world changed forever.</p><hr><p>A few years earlier, a major public institution - let’s call it <em>Agency A</em> - was still running an ancient Exchange mail server. It hadn’t received security updates for ages, the anti-spam was completely ineffective, and the new regulations were clear: embrace Open Source solutions whenever possible.</p><p>They had already received a proposal - expensive but seemingly reasonable - for a managed service, hosted by an external provider, built on an open source mail stack. The company offered a managed version with its own proprietary additions and enterprise support. The catch? The price was absurd, and <em>Agency A</em> already had solid infrastructure - reputable IP classes, redundant datacenters, everything working fine. We had built and maintained that environment for years, and it was still running perfectly.</p><p>The request was simple: <em>“Evaluate this solution, and if it’s suitable, we’ll migrate.”</em>. About 500 active mailboxes, roughly the same number of aliases. Manageable, but far from trivial.</p><p>So I started experimenting. I had heard of that stack before but never used it directly. I deployed it in some non-critical environments - ours, and a few test clients who agreed to try it at a discounted rate. Everything worked flawlessly for almost a year. I began to appreciate its design and flexibility. Confident, I told <em>Agency A</em> we could proceed with a pilot migration.</p><p>We built a new server, deployed the stack, and assigned a few secondary domains for early adopters. The feedback was great - so good that users started pushing for a full migration.<br> The IT team planned carefully: created accounts and aliases, migrated selected mailboxes, and kept the old Exchange server online (hidden, for legacy access).</p><p>The morning after the MX switch I was tense, waiting for trouble - but it never came. A couple of small questions, nothing serious. The internal team handled everything perfectly. It was a success.</p><hr><p>Word spread quickly.</p><p><em>Agency B</em> - smaller, but in some ways more influential - contacted me. They were customers of the same managed-service company that had pitched to <em>Agency A</em>. Once they saw the potential savings (at less than a tenth of the annual cost), the stability, and the freedom of keeping their data on their own servers, they became very interested. Their contract, however, was a five-year deal with automatic renewal - two years left. The legal office said the notice period was six months, so there was time.</p><p>They wanted to prepare silently. Their supplier was known for <em>aggressive commercial behavior</em> and often retaliated when customers tried to leave. So we built everything quietly - users, aliases, test setups - and froze the system, waiting for the official termination notice.</p><p>That day finally came. The notice was sent, about eight months before expiration. Migration would begin upon confirmation of receipt - or the following month at the latest.</p><p>Meanwhile, I learned that <em>Agency C</em> - another institution - was also planning to leave the same provider. They wanted to keep the same software stack for consistency, so I told them about our experience. They asked for a quote, which I prepared (without mentioning <em>Agency B</em>, of course). My margin would have been small, but the project made sense: it was about <em>owning your data</em>, not making money.</p><p>Everything seemed to move smoothly - until that SMS.</p><hr><p>I called back immediately.</p><blockquote><p>"There’s been a problem with the termination" said the IT manager of <em>Agency B</em>.<br> "Somehow they found out what we were doing. There are hidden clauses we didn’t know about, and now we can’t leave - at least not for another five years. They know everything. Even your quote.".</p></blockquote><p>I was stunned. How could they possibly know?</p><p>Minutes later, my phone rang again - <em>Agency C</em> this time. </p><blockquote><p>"Forget the proposal", they said. "They called us. Threatened us, actually. They even mentioned your name and said they might take legal action against you for unfair competition - claiming they’re the only <em>‘authorized’</em> installers of that software. Which is absurd, of course. It’s open source. But our director doesn’t want trouble.".</p></blockquote><p>Sometimes, when public money is involved, people prefer avoiding troubles over doing what’s right.</p><hr><p>Something didn’t add up.<br> Then someone at <em>Agency C</em> noticed a clue: a former interim IT manager still had an email client connected via token authentication - with access to all messages. And that person had signed the original contract with the provider years before. Informally questioned, he admitted contacting them "to warn them" but claimed it was harmless. He never mentioned me - supposedly.</p><p>That still didn’t explain how they knew about <em>Agency B</em>’s internal steps. To test a theory, we set a trap: I asked a friend abroad to send <em>Agency B</em> a fake quote, from a company outside the EU.<br> The following Monday, the provider called <em>Agency B</em> and said, "We advise against working with non-EU companies - compliance can get tricky.".</p><p>That strongly suggested it: <strong>it looked as if they might have been reading the emails.</strong></p><p>The IT manager exploded and confronted them. The response was chilling: </p><blockquote><p>"I’m not saying we do - but we could. It’s in the contract. You should read the fine print, especially the unilateral amendment from two years ago.".</p></blockquote><p>That amendment, quietly accepted, included horrifying clauses:<br> - notice period extended from 6 to 12 months<br> - formerly free services could become paid at the provider’s discretion<br> - and, "for security reasons", they could disable any access other than the webmail - which they promptly did.</p><p>All of this happened before the GDPR era, when certain practices could still slip through.</p><hr><p>I tried to contact the company’s owner directly - no reply. Calls, emails, nothing. Their support lines were "not authorized to forward requests". I wanted to confront them about the <em>“not accredited”</em> nonsense and the so-called <em>unfair competition</em>. But bullies never like a fair conversation.</p><p>I urged <em>Agency B</em> and <em>C</em> to investigate - not only legally, but ethically.<br> They were horrified, yes - but in the end, nothing changed.<br> Worse: the provider, invoking that same contract amendment, made previously free features paid ones, increasing their costs by another 30%.<br> Management wasn’t outraged by the abuse - just by the extra expense, "hard to justify in the budget".</p><hr><p>Years later, those directors were gone. The technical staff remained - older, wiser, and determined not to repeat the mistake. They eventually switched providers, though to something "safer", not necessarily better.</p><p>I couldn’t solve that problem. The battle had to come from them, and I would have supported them all the way - not for profit, but for principle.<br> Because when a company that claims to <em>“support open source”</em> behaves like that, we all lose.<br> We all get labeled the same way.</p><p>And that’s the real horror of the story - not the software, but what people do with it.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[One-man campaign ravages EU 'Chat Control' bill (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.politico.eu/article/one-man-spam-campaign-ravages-eu-chat-control-bill-fight-chat-control/</link>
            <guid>45514433</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 10:26:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/one-man-spam-campaign-ravages-eu-chat-control-bill-fight-chat-control/">https://www.politico.eu/article/one-man-spam-campaign-ravages-eu-chat-control-bill-fight-chat-control/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45514433">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-count="4" data-remainder="0" data-block-attributes="[]" data-page="0">
					
<div>
			<p><img src="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=380,height=253,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg" srcset="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=480,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 480w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=768,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 768w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1024,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 1024w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1280,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 1280w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1440,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 1440w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1920,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 1920w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=2640,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/01/12578581-scaled.jpg 2640w" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" alt="Cyber spying on the rise, EU agency warns" width="380" height="253" role="" loading="lazy" decoding="async">

					</p>
	
	
		
		<div>

			
			
			
			
			
							<h2>
										<a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/eu-institutions-target-more-hacking-espionage-campaigns-cyber-agency-warns/">
						Cyber spying on the rise, EU agency warns					</a>
				</h2>
			
			
							<p>State-backed hacking groups have “steadily intensified” their attacks on the EU, new report shows. </p>
			
			<p><span>
			Oct 1		</span>
	
	
	
<span>
	<span>2 mins read</span>
</span>
</p>

			
			
			
			
					</div>

			</div>

<div>
			<p><img src="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=380,height=253,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg" srcset="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=480,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 480w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=768,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 768w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1024,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 1024w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1280,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 1280w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1440,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 1440w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1920,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 1920w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=2640,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/25/GettyImages-2181968880.jpg 2640w" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" alt="Moldova’s electoral commission suffered cyberattack days ahead of vote" width="380" height="253" role="" loading="lazy" decoding="async">

					</p>
	
	
		
		<div>

			
			
			
			
			
							<h2>
										<a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/moldova-electoral-commission-cyberattack-days-ahead-vote-russia-democracy-doina-nistor/">
						Moldova’s electoral commission suffered cyberattack days ahead of vote					</a>
				</h2>
			
			
							<p>Sunday’s vote is mired in “most advanced hybrid threats of our times,” deputy prime minister tells POLITICO.</p>
			
			<p><span>
			Sep 26		</span>
	
	
	
<span>
	<span>3 mins read</span>
</span>
</p>

			
			
			
			
					</div>

			</div>

<div>
			<p><img src="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=380,height=253,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg" srcset="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=480,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 480w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=768,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 768w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1024,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 1024w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1280,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 1280w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1440,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 1440w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1920,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 1920w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=2640,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/17/GettyImages-2235698195-scaled.jpg 2640w" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" alt="EU tech chief sounds alarm over Spain’s Huawei contract" width="380" height="253" role="" loading="lazy" decoding="async">

					</p>
	
	
		
		<div>

			
			
			
			
			
							<h2>
										<a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/eu-tech-chief-henna-virkkunen-alarm-over-spain-huawei-contract/">
						EU tech chief sounds alarm over Spain’s Huawei contract					</a>
				</h2>
			
			
							<p>Contract with Chinese tech firm to store judicial wiretaps could lead to foreign interference, says EU commissioner.</p>
			
			<p><span>
			Sep 17		</span>
	
	
	
<span>
	<span>2 mins read</span>
</span>
</p>

			
			
			
			
					</div>

			</div>

<div>
			<p><img src="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=380,height=264,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg" srcset="https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=480,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 480w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=768,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 768w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1024,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 1024w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1280,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 1280w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1440,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 1440w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=1920,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 1920w, https://www.politico.eu/cdn-cgi/image/width=2640,quality=80,onerror=redirect,format=auto/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/12/NASK-scaled.jpg 2640w" sizes="(max-width: 380px) 100vw, 380px" alt="After testing Poland’s drone defenses, Russia tested its disinformation response too" width="380" height="264" role="" loading="lazy" decoding="async">

					</p>
	
	
		
		<div>

			
			
			
			
			
							<h2>
										<a href="https://www.politico.eu/article/after-testing-drone-defenses-russia-tested-nato-disinformation-response/">
						After testing Poland’s drone defenses, Russia tested its disinformation response too					</a>
				</h2>
			
			
							<p>Disinformation tried to blame the drone incursion on Ukraine and make out Poland to be weak and confused.</p>
			
			<p><span>
			Sep 12		</span>
	
	
	
<span>
	<span>2 mins read</span>
</span>
</p>

			
			
			
			
					</div>

			</div>
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nobel Prize in Chemistry 2025 (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/</link>
            <guid>45514164</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 09:49:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/">https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45514164">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2025/popular-information/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Synology Reverses Policy Banning Third-Party HDDs After NAS Sales Plummet (916 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.guru3d.com/story/synology-reverses-policy-banning-thirdparty-hdds-after-nas-sales-plummet/</link>
            <guid>45513485</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 08:19:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.guru3d.com/story/synology-reverses-policy-banning-thirdparty-hdds-after-nas-sales-plummet/">https://www.guru3d.com/story/synology-reverses-policy-banning-thirdparty-hdds-after-nas-sales-plummet/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45513485">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article itemprop="articleBody">
                                <div>
                                    
                        <!-- Contentteller Template: publish_teaser_image -->
                        <p><img src="https://www.guru3d.com/data/teaser/226/8042eeca5148cf31ca512f2f80ee2eb8dbb74a/2025-10-08_09_05_51-guru3d.webp" alt="teaser"></p><p>Synology has backtracked on one of its most unpopular decisions in years. After seeing NAS sales plummet in 2025, the company has decided to lift restrictions that forced users to buy its own Synology hard drives. The policy, introduced earlier this year, made third-party HDDs from brands like Seagate and WD practically unusable in newer models such as the DS925+, DS1825+, and DS425+.

That change didn’t go over well. Users immediately criticised Synology for trying to lock them into buying its much more expensive drives. Many simply refused to upgrade, and reviewers called out the move as greedy and shortsighted. According to some reports, sales of Synology’s 2025 NAS models dropped sharply in the months after the restriction was introduced.
                                    </p><p>Now, with the release of <strong>DSM 7.3</strong>, Synology has quietly walked the policy back. Third-party hard drives and <strong>2.5-inch SATA SSDs</strong> can once again be used without triggering warning messages or reduced functionality. Drives from Seagate, WD, and others will work exactly as they did before—complete with full monitoring, alerts, and storage features.</p>
<p>For users, this means more choice and lower costs when building or upgrading a NAS. For Synology, it’s a much-needed course correction after months of backlash. While the company hasn’t publicly admitted fault, it’s clear that sales pressure and community outrage played a major role in reversing the decision.</p>
<p>Critics say the entire episode has damaged Synology’s reputation. The company seemed to believe that after QNAP’s well-known ransomware troubles, it could tighten control of the market without losing customers. Instead, the plan backfired—hard. Many loyal users have since turned to alternative brands or expressed hesitation about buying another Synology product.</p>

<p>Still, the return of open drive support is good news for anyone running a Synology NAS. It restores the flexibility that made the brand so popular in the first place. Whether this move is enough to win back frustrated users remains to be seen, but for now, DSM 7.3 brings a welcome dose of freedom back to the platform.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.guru3d.com/data/publish/226/8042eeca5148cf31ca512f2f80ee2eb8dbb74a/7846uhj.webp" target="_top"><img src="https://www.guru3d.com/data/publish/226/8042eeca5148cf31ca512f2f80ee2eb8dbb74a/7846uhj.webp" alt="7846uhj"></a></p>
<p>Source: <a href="https://www.synology.com/en-global/releaseNote/DSM" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">Synology </a>/ <a href="https://nascompares.com/2025/10/07/synology-support-seagate-wd-again-too-little-too-late" target="_blank" rel="nofollow">nascompares</a></p>
                                </div>
                            </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Without data centers, GDP growth was 0.1% in the first half of 2025 (219 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2025/10/07/data-centers-gdp-growth-zero-first-half-2025-jason-furman-harvard-economist/</link>
            <guid>45512317</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 05:13:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/10/07/data-centers-gdp-growth-zero-first-half-2025-jason-furman-harvard-economist/">https://fortune.com/2025/10/07/data-centers-gdp-growth-zero-first-half-2025-jason-furman-harvard-economist/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45512317">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>U.S. GDP growth in the first half of 2025 was almost entirely driven by investment in data centers and information processing technology, according to <a href="https://www.hks.harvard.edu/faculty/jason-furman" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.hks.harvard.edu/faculty/jason-furman">Harvard economist Jason Furman</a>. Excluding these technology-related categories, Furman <a href="https://x.com/jasonfurman/status/1971995367202775284" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://x.com/jasonfurman/status/1971995367202775284">calculated in a Sept. 27 post on X.com</a> GDP growth would have been just 0.1% on an annualized basis, a near standstill that underlines the increasingly pivotal role of high-tech infrastructure in shaping macroeconomic outcomes.<a href="https://www.cmacrodev.com/the-global-economy-is-on-a-two-way-track/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.cmacrodev.com/the-global-economy-is-on-a-two-way-track/"></a></p><div>



<div><p>Furman’s findings, shared online and echoed by financial analysts including Robert Armstrong of the <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802"><em>Financial Times</em>‘ Unhedged</a> (the same writer who coined the term “TACO trade’), echo <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/08/06/data-center-artificial-intelligence-bubble-consumer-spending-economy/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/08/06/data-center-artificial-intelligence-bubble-consumer-spending-economy/">several months of observations</a> on the remarkable surge in data-center infrastructure. In August, Renaissance Macro Research estimated, to date in 2025, the dollar value contributed to GDP growth by AI data-center buildout had surpassed U.S. consumer spending for the first time ever. That’s remarkable considering <a href="https://www.congress.gov/crs-product/IF11657" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.congress.gov/crs-product/IF11657">consumer spending is two-thirds of GDP</a>.<a href="https://x.com/AllVentured/status/1951770496711934459" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://x.com/AllVentured/status/1951770496711934459"></a></p><p>Technically, as Furman notes, investment in information-processing equipment and software was only 4% of U.S. GDP for the first half of 2025, yet it also accounted for fully 92% of GDP growth over that period. Furman added it’s probably not the case the U.S. economy would have recorded almost no expansion at all absent this buildout, reasoning that “absent the AI boom we would probably have lower interest rates [and] electricity prices, thus some additional growth in other sectors. In very rough terms that could maybe make up about half of what we got from the AI boom.” But still, it’s big.<a href="https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.ft.com/content/603be7d5-13ac-4047-9854-24db5f0f0802"></a></p></div><p>Tech giants such as <a href="https://fortune.com/company/microsoft/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/microsoft/">Microsoft</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/alphabet/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/alphabet/">Google</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/amazon-com/">Amazon</a>, <a href="https://fortune.com/company/facebook/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/facebook/">Meta</a>, and <a href="https://fortune.com/company/nvidia/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/nvidia/">Nvidia</a> have poured tens of billions of dollars into building and upgrading data centers, responding to explosive demand for artificial intelligence and large language models that require massive computing resources. 



</p><p>Lisa Shallet, chief investment officer for <a href="https://fortune.com/company/morgan-stanley/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/morgan-stanley/">Morgan Stanley</a> Wealth Management, flagged on Sept. 29 that spending was truly massive among the so-called “hyperscalers” who are striving for huge computing, storage and networking capacity. 



</p><p>“In recent years, hyperscaler capex on data center and related items has risen fourfold and is nearing $400 billion annually,” she wrote. “The speed of growth and size of the investment are skewing its aggregate economic impact, with the top 10 spenders accounting for nearly a third of all spending … For perspective, it’s estimated that data center-linked spending is adding roughly 100 basis points to U.S. real GDP growth.”</p><p><img alt="" loading="lazy" width="764" height="426" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 60vw, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1200px) 33vw" srcset="https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=128&amp;q=85 128w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=256&amp;q=85 256w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=320&amp;q=85 320w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=384&amp;q=85 384w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=480&amp;q=85 480w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=576&amp;q=85 576w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=768&amp;q=85 768w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1024&amp;q=85 1024w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1280&amp;q=85 1280w, https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1440&amp;q=85 1440w" src="https://fortune.com/img-assets/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/lisa-shalett.png?w=1440&amp;q=85"></p>



<h2>The ‘mystery’ of the economy</h2>



<p>This surge in technology-led growth comes against a backdrop of wider economic sluggishness and paradoxically strong GDP growth. Job creation has slowed, raising concerns that, absent technology investment, the U.S. economy could have slipped into recession. <a href="https://finance.yahoo.com/news/spending-ai-data-centers-massive-150110727.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Go to https://finance.yahoo.com/news/spending-ai-data-centers-massive-150110727.html"></a>Other sectors—from manufacturing and real estate to retail and services—contributed little or even detracted from overall output in the first half of 2025. 



</p><p>And yet, as <a href="https://fortune.com/company/apollo-global-management/" target="_blank" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/apollo-global-management/">Apollo Global Management</a> Chief Economist Torsten Sløk has noted, the <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/10/01/us-economy-getting-stronger-not-weaker-apollo-torsten-slok-growth-gdp-spending-jobs/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/10/01/us-economy-getting-stronger-not-weaker-apollo-torsten-slok-growth-gdp-spending-jobs/">GDP figures speak of a (statistically) strong economy</a>. 



</p><p>“The consensus has been wrong since January,” Sløk said in a note circulated to clients in early October, adding the average of economists’ forecasts has said the U.S. economy would slow down for nine months consecutively. “But the reality is that it has simply not happened … We in the economics profession need to look ourselves in the mirror.”



</p><p>Furman’s analysis adds to the snarky and accurate observation by <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/17/style/today-in-tabs-rusty-foster-media-gossip-maine.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.nytimes.com/2024/04/17/style/today-in-tabs-rusty-foster-media-gossip-maine.html">Rusty Foster</a> of&nbsp;<em><a href="https://www.todayintabs.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.todayintabs.com/">Today in Tabs</a></em>&nbsp;who quipped: “Our economy might just be three AI data centers in a trench coat”—an allusion to the data-center buildout boom and to the cartoon trope/sight gag of <a href="https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-origin-of-the-sight-gag-where-three-small-people-stack-up-in-a-trench-coat-and-pretend-to-be-one-ordinary-size-adult" target="_blank" rel="noopener" aria-label="Go to https://www.quora.com/What-is-the-origin-of-the-sight-gag-where-three-small-people-stack-up-in-a-trench-coat-and-pretend-to-be-one-ordinary-size-adult">several young boys</a> teaming up to disguise themselves as an adult.</p><p>Morgan Stanley Chief Economist Michael Gapen ventured a guess on Oct. 6 about “the mystery” of the 2025 economy, “between solid spending data and weak hiring.” He argued that it “can be explained by a corporate sector that absorbed the initial cost of tariffs and reduced unit labor costs and profitability rather than raising prices.” 



</p><p>In other words, something that has nothing to do with the data-center buildout that is widely fueling bubble fears, <a href="https://fortune.com/2025/10/04/jeff-bezos-amazon-openai-sam-altman-ai-bubble-tech-stocks-investing/" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2025/10/04/jeff-bezos-amazon-openai-sam-altman-ai-bubble-tech-stocks-investing/">even among Amazon founder Jeff Bezos himself</a>, who insists these data centers are an “industrial bubble” rather than a financial one, and we will all be glad someday to have such incredible computing power at our fingertips with so many hundreds of billions spent. The question of sustainable GDP growth is a separate one.<br></p></div><p><strong>Fortune Global Forum</strong> returns Oct. 26–27, 2025 in Riyadh. CEOs and global leaders will gather for a dynamic, invitation-only event shaping the future of business. <a href="https://conferences.fortune.com/event/global-forum-2025/summary?utm_source=fortunecom&amp;utm_medium=plealink" target="_self" aria-label="Go to https://conferences.fortune.com/event/global-forum-2025/summary?utm_source=fortunecom&amp;utm_medium=plealink">Apply for an invitation.</a></p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bob Ross paintings to be auctioned to fund US public broadcasting (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly10275v5zo</link>
            <guid>45511265</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 02:06:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly10275v5zo">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly10275v5zo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45511265">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>Paintings by celebrated art tutor Bob Ross will be auctioned to help support public television stations that have faced funding cuts under the Trump administration.</p><p>About 30 of his artworks, which he mostly created on-air during his TV show, the Joy of Painting, in the 80s and 90s, will be auctioned by Bonhams from November.</p><p>Bob Ross Inc said the auction "ensures Bob's legacy continues to support the very medium that brought his joy and creativity into American homes for decades". </p><p>It comes after Congress passed <a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cly1jwe7582o">Trump's request to strip public broadcast funding</a>, leaving some 330 Public Broadcasting Service (PBS) and National Public Radio (NPR) stations scrambling for a new funding source. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>Ross' show saw a resurgence during the Covid pandemic, as audiences enjoyed his soft-spoken, paint-along lessons. Misplaced brush strokes, the former Air Force drill sergeant would say, were just "happy accidents". He died at the age of 52 in 1995. </p><p>Bob Ross Inc said it donated the paintings to American Public Television, and that all of the net proceeds go to local public TV stations nationwide.</p><p>This includes programmes such as America's Test Kitchen, Julia Child's French Chef Classics and This Old House, the Associated Press news agency reported. </p><p>In August, the auction of two of Ross' works shattered records, having sold for double and triple what had been expected. </p><p>Lake Below Snow-Capped Peaks and Cloudy Sky sold for $114,800, while Lake Below Snow-Covered Mountains and Clear Sky sold for $95,750.</p><p>"I can tell you that Bob would have been quite shy to learn that his paintings are now selling at six figures," Joan Kowalski, the president of Bob Ross Inc, <a target="_blank" href="https://nypost.com/2025/08/15/us-news/bob-ross-paintings-easily-surpass-estimated-sale-prices-at-auction-marking-milestone-for-the-late-artist/">told the New York Post</a> after the lots sold.  </p><p>"He was never really that interested in his finished works, Bob was more fascinated with the process of painting and sharing that with other people."</p><p>"Truthfully, I can still hear him saying something like, 'You don't want my paintings, you want to create your own and hang them proudly on your wall.'"</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Study of 1M-year-old skull points to earlier origins of modern humans (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/sep/25/study-of-1m-year-old-skull-points-to-earlier-origins-of-modern-humans</link>
            <guid>45510582</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 00:17:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/sep/25/study-of-1m-year-old-skull-points-to-earlier-origins-of-modern-humans">https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/sep/25/study-of-1m-year-old-skull-points-to-earlier-origins-of-modern-humans</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45510582">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>A million-year-old human skull suggests that the origins of modern humans may reach back far deeper in time than previously thought and raises the possibility that <em>Homo sapiens</em> first emerged outside of Africa.</p><p>Leading scientists reached this conclusion after reanalysis of a skull known as Yunxian 2 discovered in China and previously classified as belonging to a member of the primitive human species <em>Homo erectus</em>.</p><p>After applying sophisticated reconstruction techniques to the skull, scientists believe that it may instead belong to a group called <em>Homo longi </em>(dragon man), closely linked to the elusive Denisovans who lived alongside our own ancestors.</p><p>This repositioning would make the fossil the closest on record to the split between modern humans and our closest relatives, the Neanderthals and Denisovans, and would radically revise understanding of the last 1m years of human evolution.</p><p>Prof Chris Stringer, an anthropologist and research leader in human evolution at the Natural History Museum in London, said: “This changes a lot of thinking because it suggests that by 1m years ago our ancestors had already split into distinct groups, pointing to a much earlier and more complex human evolutionary split than previously believed. It more or less doubles the time of origin of <em>Homo sapiens</em>.”</p><p>The skull was first unearthed in Hubei province in 1990, badly crushed and difficult to interpret. Based on its age and some broad-brush traits, it was assigned as <em>Homo erectus</em>, a group that is thought to have contained direct ancestors of modern humans.</p><p>The latest work used advanced CT imaging, high-resolution surface scanning and sophisticated digital techniques to produce a virtual reconstruction of the skull. The skull’s large, squat brain case and jutting lower jaw are reminiscent of <em>Homo erectus</em>. But the overall shape and size of the brain case and teeth appear to place it much closer to <em>Homo longi</em>, a species that scientists have <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/science/2025/apr/10/jawbone-fossil-builds-richer-image-of-ancient-denisovans" data-link-name="in body link">recently argued</a> should incorporate the Denisovans.</p><p>This would push the split between our own ancestors, Neanderthals and <em>Homo longi</em> back by at least 400,000 years and, according to Springer, raises the possibility that our common ancestor – and potentially the first <em>Homo sapiens</em> – lived in western Asia rather than Africa.</p><p>“This fossil is the closest we’ve got to the ancestor of all those groups,” Stringer said.</p><p>A computational analysis of a wider selection of fossils suggests that in the last 800,000 years, large-brained humans evolved along just five major branches: Asian erectus, heidelbergensis, sapiens, Neanderthals and <em>Homo longi</em> (including the Denisovans).</p><p>“We feel that this study is a landmark step towards resolving the ‘muddle in the middle’ [the confusing array of human fossils from between 1m and 300,000 years ago] that has preoccupied palaeoanthropologists for decades,” Stringer said.</p><p>The findings run counter to some recent analyses based on genetic comparisons of living humans and ancient DNA, meaning the conclusions are likely to be contentious.</p><p>Dr Frido Welker, an associate professor in human evolution at the University of Copenhagen, who was not involved in the research, said: “It’s exciting to have a digital reconstruction of this important cranium available. If confirmed by additional fossils and genetic evidence, the divergence dating would be surprising indeed. Alternatively, molecular data from the specimen itself could provide insights confirming or disproving the authors’ morphological hypothesis.”</p><p>The findings are published in the journal <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/science.ado9202" data-link-name="in body link">Science</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Six surgeons general: It's our duty to warn the nation about RFK Jr (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/</link>
            <guid>45510421</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 23:54:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45510421">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/2025/10/07/surgeons-general-rfk-jr-robert-kennedy/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Become unbannable from your email (227 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://karboosx.net/post/PJOveGVa/become-unbannable-from-your-emailgmail</link>
            <guid>45509243</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 21:39:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://karboosx.net/post/PJOveGVa/become-unbannable-from-your-emailgmail">https://karboosx.net/post/PJOveGVa/become-unbannable-from-your-emailgmail</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45509243">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/BlogPosting">
            

            <div itemprop="articleBody">
                <p>Clickbait-y title, I know :D but I stand by it!</p>
<p>I noticed that many people still treat email like some sort of second-class citizen when it comes to personal information, and the urgency here is real.
I think, in today's world where everything is in apps and requires an account, email has become even more important than your <strong>home address</strong>.</p>
<hr>
<h2>Why Your Email Is Your Digital Home</h2>
<p>Think about it for a moment. What would happen to you if you lost access to your email and needed to change it? Now, compare that to changing your home address.</p>
<p>For the second one, maybe you'd need to change some delivery addresses, and update government documents and bills. But that's common practice, and most places probably have procedures to handle that, and it's still not that many places. It's a solvable chore.</p>
<p>Now think if you lost access to your email address. What would you have to do to fix it? Create a new one, fine. But how will you log into all of your apps where the identifier is the email address itself? You need to contact each of the companies through their customer service, which is often painful.</p>
<p>And think how many conversations you would have to have? Uber? Customer service. Netflix? Customer service. YouTube/Google? Customer service. It's just a <strong>nightmare</strong>.</p>
<p>Look at how many important things you are getting today in your emails. Invoices → email. Password resets → email. Security notices → email.</p>
<p>My point here is that email has become our second home address on the internet. And we use that one piece of personal information way more than our normal address these days.</p>
<hr>
<h2>The "How": Taking Control of Your Email</h2>
<p>Okay, so the boring "why" we covered. Now it's the part where I'm showing you how to deal with it.</p>
<p>I will show you how I have it set up.</p>
<h3>Step 1: Get Your Own Domain</h3>
<p>The biggest problem with free email addresses is that they are under someone else's domain, so they have <strong>full control</strong> over your email address.</p>
<p>To fix that, you first need to have your email address under your <strong>own domain</strong>.</p>
<p>For that, you need to find a provider that is well-respected in the "email community." Why? Because the email protocol is quite an interesting case of "we don't ditch old stuff." To properly use email without constant rejection from various email providers, your domain needs to be "known" by them. So, setting up your own email server is, in practice, out of the question.</p>
<p>But you can go, for example, with Google (G Suite/Google Workspace), or with Proton Email, or anything else that is somewhat well known.</p>
<p>I went with G Suite from Google because it comes with a slightly different privacy policy than normal Gmail, and only G Suite offers custom domains in the Google ecosystem. So, to ease myself from having a second, secondary Gmail, I went with this one. But others are also viable options.</p>
<p>Next, you need to follow the instructions of your chosen provider to set up your own email address on your domain. In practice, it will involve setting <strong>DNS MX records</strong> for your domain and some verification.</p>
<p>Oh, and I highly recommend providers that offer a <strong>"catch-all" feature</strong>. This way, you can have one main email address and unlimited <code>&lt;put something here&gt;@yourdomain.com</code> email addresses. It's useful to have it separated, like <code><a href="https://karboosx.net/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="b4dad1c0d2d8ddccf4cddbc1c6d0dbd9d5ddda9ad7dbd9">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></code>, but still receive the emails inside the same inbox.</p>
<hr>
<h3>Step 2: The Unbannable Backup</h3>
<p>Now, you have your domain, and your email is under that domain. We don't stop here. Your emails are still inside your email provider. If they block you, you will probably lose access to previous emails, but at least now you have the option to just switch MX records to a different provider to start receiving emails again.</p>
<p>But we don't want that! We want <strong>full control</strong> over our emails!!!</p>
<p>So how do we handle it? Simple: making a <strong>backup</strong>!</p>
<p>The easiest would be to set up your local email software like Outlook or Thunderbird to download all emails to your local computer. It's something, and it will work, but if you happen to have some local server, I have a better proposition.</p>
<p>Set up some simple email server on your local server. I'm using my <strong>NAS</strong>. Just pick a subdomain for your email so it will look like <code><a href="https://karboosx.net/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="492b282a223c39092b282a223c396730263c3b2d2624282027672a2624">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></code>.</p>
<p>With your simple local email server, you can set up your email provider to <strong>always forward</strong> any email to your local server.</p>
<p>With that, you will always have a copy of every email on your server. So even if you are on vacation and your service provider blocks you from accessing your inbox, you will still have your copy.</p>
<p>graph LR
    A[Author/Sender] --&gt; B(Your Email Provider);
    B --&gt; C(Online Inbox/Access);
    B -- Forward Email --&gt; D(Local Backup Server);
    D --&gt; E[Your Local Email Copy];
</p>
<p>And would you like to hear the bonus tip? With this solution, there's a high chance that if they ban you by mistake (AI bots are to blame), they will <strong>not disable the forwarding mechanism</strong>. They will just not allow you to authenticate to your account. That means you will still be able to read all your emails even when banned from your inbox!</p>
<hr>
<p>So there you have it. That's my method for making your most important internet asset, your email, truly <strong>unbannable</strong> and resilient. It takes a little setup, but the peace of mind knowing that I'm in control of my digital life—not some huge corporation—is totally worth it. Now go take back control!</p>

            </div>

            
        </article>

        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model (600 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-computer-use-model/</link>
            <guid>45507936</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 19:49:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-computer-use-model/">https://blog.google/technology/google-deepmind/gemini-computer-use-model/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507936">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="jump-content" tabindex="-1">
            

    
    

    <article>

    
    





    

    
      








<div data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Hero Menu&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
  }">
  
  <div>
      
      
        <p>
          Available in preview via the API, our Computer Use model is a specialized model built on Gemini 2.5 Pro’s capabilities to power agents that can interact with user interfaces.
        </p>
      
    </div>
  
  <div data-summary-id="ai_summary_1" data-component="uni-ai-generated-summary" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;event&quot;: &quot;module_impression&quot;,
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;ai_summary&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;CTA&quot;
  }">
          <h2>General summary</h2>
          <p>Google is releasing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model via the Gemini API, enabling developers to build agents that can interact with user interfaces. This model outperforms others in web and mobile control benchmarks with lower latency. You can access it now on Google AI Studio and Vertex AI to start building and share feedback in the Developer Forum.</p>
          
          <p><small>
            Summaries were generated by Google AI. Generative AI is experimental.
          </small>
        </p></div>
</div>

    

    
      










<div>
    <figure>
      <div>
        <p><img alt="Gemini Computer Use" data-component="uni-progressive-image" fetchpriority="high" height="150px" src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-200.format-webp.webp" width="360px" data-sizes="(max-width: 1023px) 100vw,(min-width: 1024px and max-width: 1259) 80vw, 1046px" data-srcset="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-800.format-webp.webp 800w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-1200.format-webp.webp 1200w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-1600.format-webp.webp 1600w, https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU_2096x1182_RD6-V01.width-2200.format-webp.webp 2200w">
        </p>
      </div>
      
    </figure>
  </div>






    

    
    <div data-reading-time="true" data-component="uni-article-body">

            
              





<uni-article-speakable page-title="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" listen-to-article="Listen to article" data-date-modified="2025-10-07T20:39:24.825126+00:00" data-tracking-ids="G-HGNBTNCHCQ,G-6NKTLKV14N" data-voice-list="en.ioh-pngnat:Cyan,en.usb-pngnat:Lime" data-script-src="https://www.gstatic.com/readaloud/player/web/api/js/api.js" data-highlight-mode="word-over-paragraph"></uni-article-speakable>

            

            
            
<!--article text-->

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="pa3tk">Earlier this year, we <a href="https://www.youtube.com/live/o8NiE3XMPrM?si=9uCZ5JXT0xtGyr1H&amp;t=874">mentioned</a> that we're bringing computer use capabilities to developers via the Gemini API. Today, we are releasing the <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model</a>, our new specialized model built on Gemini 2.5 Pro’s visual understanding and reasoning capabilities that powers agents capable of interacting with user interfaces (UIs). It outperforms leading alternatives on multiple web and mobile control benchmarks, all with lower latency. Developers can access these capabilities via the Gemini API in <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use">Google AI Studio</a> and <a href="https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/generative-ai/docs/computer-use">Vertex AI</a>.</p><p data-block-key="b74v6">While AI models can interface with software through structured APIs, many digital tasks still require direct interaction with graphical user interfaces, for example, filling and submitting forms. To complete these tasks, agents must navigate web pages and applications just as humans do: by clicking, typing and scrolling. The ability to natively fill out forms, manipulate interactive elements like dropdowns and filters, and operate behind logins is a crucial next step in building powerful, general-purpose agents.</p><h2 data-block-key="2t6df">How it works</h2><p data-block-key="7bmpr">The model’s core capabilities are exposed through the new `computer_use` tool in the Gemini API and should be operated within a loop. Inputs to the tool are the user request, screenshot of the environment, and a history of recent actions. The input can also specify whether to exclude functions from the <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use#supported-actions">full list of supported UI actions</a> or specify additional custom functions to include.</p></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Diagram of AI agent loop: Initial task leads to a screenshot/context, which is sent to the Model, which returns a response to the computer environment to execute an action." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="9i6az">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use Model flow</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Diagram of AI agent loop: Initial task leads to a screenshot/context, which is sent to the Model, which returns a response to the computer environment to execute an action." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Diagram-RD4-V01.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Diagram-RD4-V01.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Diagram-RD4-V01.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><p data-block-key="pa3tk">The model then analyzes these inputs and generates a response, typically a function call representing one of the UI actions such as clicking or typing. This response may also contain a request for an end user confirmation, which is required for certain actions such as making a purchase. The client-side code then executes the received action.</p><p data-block-key="b440f">After the action is executed, a new screenshot of the GUI and the current URL are sent back to the Computer Use model as a function response restarting the loop. This iterative process continues until the task is complete, an error occurs or the interaction is terminated by a safety response or user decision.</p><p data-block-key="36n25">The Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model is primarily optimized for web browsers, but also demonstrates strong promise for mobile UI control tasks. It is not yet optimized for desktop OS-level control.</p><p data-block-key="79qun">Check out a few demos below to see the model in action (shown here at 3X speed).</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }">
        <p data-block-key="nly14"><b>Prompt:</b> “From <a href="https://tinyurl.com/pet-care-signup">https://tinyurl.com/pet-care-signup</a>, get all details for any pet with a California residency and add them as a guest in my spa CRM at <a href="https://pet-luxe-spa.web.app/">https://pet-luxe-spa.web.app/</a>. Then, set up a follow up visit appointment with the specialist Anima Lavar for October 10th anytime after 8am. The reason for the visit is the same as their requested treatment.”</p>
      </div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="5" thumbnail-alt="Gemini Computer Use demo at a pet spa" video-id="_lu-FcPUIfM" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }">
        <p data-block-key="nly14"><b>Prompt: “</b>My art club brainstormed tasks ahead of our fair. The board is chaotic and I need your help organizing the tasks into some categories I created. Go to <a href="http://sticky-note-jam.web.app/">sticky-note-jam.web.app</a> and ensure notes are clearly in the right sections. Drag them there if not.”</p>
      </div>
  

  
    
  
    




  <uni-youtube-player-article index="7" thumbnail-alt="Demo of computer use model using sticky notes" video-id="slOLc1nkKY0" video-type="video">
  </uni-youtube-player-article>











  


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="pa3tk">How it performs</h2><p data-block-key="ac68d">The Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model demonstrates strong performance on multiple web and mobile control benchmarks. The table below includes results from self-reported numbers, evaluations run by Browserbase and evaluations we ran ourselves. Evaluation details are available in the <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/gemini/computer_use_eval_additional_info.pdf">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use evaluation info</a> and in <a href="https://www.browserbase.com/blog/evaluating-browser-agents">Browserbase’s blog post</a>. Unless otherwise indicated, scores shown are for computer use tools exposed via API.</p></div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Benchmark performance table: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use leads in Online-Mind2Web, WebVoyager, and AndroidWorld benchmarks." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="9i6az">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use outperforms leading alternatives on multiple benchmarks</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Benchmark performance table: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use leads in Online-Mind2Web, WebVoyager, and AndroidWorld benchmarks." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Benchmark_Chart-RD5_V01.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Benchmark_Chart-RD5_V01.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Benchmark_Chart-RD5_V01.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }">
        <p data-block-key="pa3tk">The model offers leading quality for browser control at the lowest latency, as measured by performance on the Browserbase harness for Online-Mind2Web.</p>
      </div>
  

  
    














<uni-image-full-width alignment="full" alt-text="Latency vs. Quality scatterplot: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use is lowest in latency and highest in accuracy (70%+ accuracy, ∼225 sec latency)." external-image="" or-mp4-video-title="" or-mp4-video-url="" section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model" custom-class="image-full-width--constrained-width uni-component-spacing">
  
    <div slot="caption-slot">
      <p data-block-key="9i6az">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use delivers high accuracy while maintaining low latency</p>
    </div>
  
  
    <p><img alt="Latency vs. Quality scatterplot: Gemini 2.5 Computer Use is lowest in latency and highest in accuracy (70%+ accuracy, ∼225 sec latency)." src="https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Scatterplot-RD7.width-100.format-webp.webp" loading="lazy" data-loading="{
            &quot;mobile&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Scatterplot-RD7.width-500.format-webp.webp&quot;,
            &quot;desktop&quot;: &quot;https://storage.googleapis.com/gweb-uniblog-publish-prod/images/CTU-Scatterplot-RD7.width-1000.format-webp.webp&quot;
          }">
    </p>
  
</uni-image-full-width>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="vcpc9">How we approached safety</h2><p data-block-key="26l5s">We believe that the only way to build agents that will benefit everyone is to be responsible from the start. AI agents that control computers introduce unique risks, including intentional misuse by users, unexpected model behavior, and prompt injections and scams in the web environment. Thus, it is critical to implement safety guardrails with care.</p><p data-block-key="ab068">We have trained safety features directly into the model to address these three key risks (described in the <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/Model-Cards/Gemini-2-5-Computer-Use-Model-Card.pdf">Gemini 2.5 Computer Use System Card</a>).</p><p data-block-key="7liej">Further, we also provide developers with safety controls, which empower developers to prevent the model from auto-completing potentially high-risk or harmful actions. Examples of these actions include harming a system's integrity, compromising security, bypassing CAPTCHAs, or controlling medical devices. The controls:</p><ul><li data-block-key="3f5gh"><b>Per-step safety service:</b> An out-of-model, inference-time safety service that assesses each action the model proposes before it’s executed.</li><li data-block-key="cu905"><b>System instructions:</b> Developers can further specify that the agent either refuses or asks for user confirmation before it takes specific kinds of high-stakes actions. (Example in <a href="https://googledevai.devsite.corp.google.com/gemini-api/docs/computer-use#supported-actions">documentation</a>).</li></ul><p data-block-key="65eg3">Additional recommendations for developers on safety measures and best practices can be found in our <a href="https://googledevai.devsite.corp.google.com/gemini-api/docs/computer-use#safety-best-practices">documentation</a>. While these safeguards are designed to reduce risk, we urge all developers to thoroughly test their systems before launch.</p></div>
  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="pa3tk">How early testers have used it</h2><p data-block-key="cnndn">Google teams have already deployed the model to production for use cases including UI testing, which can make software development signficantly faster. Versions of this model have also been powering <a href="https://deepmind.google/models/project-mariner/">Project Mariner</a>, the <a href="https://firebase.blog/posts/2025/04/app-testing-agent/">Firebase Testing Agent</a>, and some agentic capabilities in <a href="https://blog.google/products/search/ai-mode-agentic-personalized/">AI Mode in Search</a>.</p><p data-block-key="9h8sv">Users from our early access program have also been testing the model to power personal assistants, workflow automation, and UI testing, and have seen strong results. In their own words:</p></div>
  

  
    




<uni-pull-quote content-style="block" quote="“A lot of our workflows require interacting with interfaces meant for humans where speed is especially important. Gemini 2.5 Computer Use is far ahead of the competition, often being 50% faster and better than the next best solutions we’ve considered.” - Poke.com, a proactive AI assistant in iMessage, WhatsApp and SMS with multiple third-party and agentic workflows." section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model">
</uni-pull-quote>


  

  
    




<uni-pull-quote content-style="block" quote="“Our agents run fully autonomously, performing work where small mistakes in collecting and parsing data are unacceptable. Gemini 2.5 Computer Use outperformed other models at reliably parsing context in complex cases, increasing performance by up to 18% on our hardest evals.”  — Autotab, a drop-in AI agent." section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model">
</uni-pull-quote>


  

  
    




<uni-pull-quote content-style="block" quote="“When conventional scripts encounter failures, the model assesses the current screen state and autonomously ascertains the required actions to complete the workflow. This implementation now successfully rehabilitates over 60% of executions (which used to take multiple days to fix).” — Google’s payments platform team, which implemented the Computer Use model as a contingency mechanism to address fragile end-to-end UI tests that contributed to 25% of all test failures." section-header="Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model">
</uni-pull-quote>


  

  
    <div data-component="uni-article-paragraph" role="presentation" data-analytics-module="{
           &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Paragraph&quot;,
           &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Introducing the Gemini 2.5 Computer Use model&quot;
         }"><h2 data-block-key="22clf">How to get started</h2><p data-block-key="envv8">Starting today, the model is available in public preview, accessible via the Gemini API on Google AI Studio and Vertex AI.</p><ul><li data-block-key="b1ua4"><b>Try it now:</b> In a demo environment hosted by <a href="http://gemini.browserbase.com/">Browserbase</a>.</li><li data-block-key="fdtcr"><b>Start building</b>: Dive into our <a href="https://github.com/google/computer-use-preview">reference</a> and <a href="http://ai.google.dev/gemini-api/docs/computer-use">documentation</a> (see <a href="https://cloud.google.com/vertex-ai/generative-ai/docs/computer-use">Vertex AI docs for enterprise use</a>) to learn how to build your own agent loop locally with Playwright or in a cloud VM with Browserbase.</li><li data-block-key="ds8mg"><b>Join the community:</b> We’re excited to see what you build. Share feedback and help guide our roadmap in our <a href="https://discuss.ai.google.dev/c/gemini-api/4">Developer Forum</a>.</li></ul></div>
  


            
            

            
              




            
          </div>
  </article>
  





  

  


<div data-component="uni-related-articles" aria-roledescription="carousel" data-analytics-module="{
    &quot;module_name&quot;: &quot;Article Footer Related Stories&quot;,
    &quot;section_header&quot;: &quot;Related stories&quot;
  }">
        <h3>
          <p>
            Related stories
          </p>
        </h3>
      </div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[User ban controversy reveals Bluesky’s decentralized aspiration isn’t reality (265 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://plus.flux.community/p/banning-controversy-reveals-blueskys</link>
            <guid>45507880</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 19:44:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://plus.flux.community/p/banning-controversy-reveals-blueskys">https://plus.flux.community/p/banning-controversy-reveals-blueskys</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45507880">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg" width="1456" height="764" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:764,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!NbHl!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F7185be1f-b52a-44e7-a72b-2eba2a190fc1_2000x1050.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>When it launched in 2023 in private beta, Bluesky was pitched as a different kind of social network, one that placed openness and user-friendliness at its core. It came along at just the right moment as Elon Musk’s purchase and takeover of Twitter led millions of users head toward any type of exit.</p><p>The initial destination for many was Mastodon, but its Linux geek ethos and system of numerous “federated” servers that communicate via the open-source ActivityPub protocol proved to be too complicated for people who just wanted to crack jokes. Acting on the opportunity, Bluesky opened up to the public in February 2024 and saw a rapid influx of users.</p><p><span>Besides being easier to sign up and use than Mastodon, Bluesky offered a different approach to content moderation that was more flexible and user-driven. In addition to making its software source code available under open licenses, Bluesky wanted to put moderation decisions in the hands of its users, encouraging them to make lists of accounts that could be automatically blocked or labeled—and thereby removing itself as much as possible from moderation decisions that have plagued discussion group administrators </span><a href="https://flux.community/matthew-sheffield/2021/11/problems-social-media-are-not-technology-challenges-they-are-social/" rel="">since the days of Usenet newsgroups</a><span>.</span></p><p>Millions of people flooded in after Bluesky opened its doors to the public. By November of 2024, there were nearly 1.5 million daily posters, most of them anti-Musk Twitter refugees who were eager to get away from Musk’s right-wing makeover of the site into X.</p><p><span>However, as time has gone by, </span><a href="https://bsky.jazco.dev/stats" rel="">Bluesky’s traffic has declined</a><span> (</span><a href="https://backlinko.com/twitter-users" rel="">X’s has as well</a><span>) and some of its users have become increasingly upset at its moderation decisions, including allowing U.S. Vice President J.D. Vance and </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/13/bluesky-is-at-a-crossroads-as-users-petition-to-ban-jesse-singal-over-anti-trans-views-harassment/" rel="">anti-trans writer Jesse Singal</a><span> to remain as users of the platform. Singal became a particular target, prompting a </span><a href="https://www.change.org/p/bluesky-must-enforce-its-community-guidelines-equally" rel="">petition</a><span> with more than 28,000 signatures urging Bluesky to “enforce its Community Guidelines” against him that has not been successful, although he has been </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/12/13/bluesky-is-at-a-crossroads-as-users-petition-to-ban-jesse-singal-over-anti-trans-views-harassment/" rel="">temporarily banned</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Accusations of indifference to anti-trans bigotry seem to have exacerbated some users’ frustrations with the platform for its alleged tolerance of racist content. In 2023, many launched a “</span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/07/27/bluesky-racism-slur-apology-feedback/" rel="">posting strike</a><span>” after they discovered that Bluesky allowed people to sign up for user names containing racial slurs, a policy the company quickly reversed and apologized for.</span></p><p><span>The labeling feature of Bluesky has been more positively regarded, with many people subscribing to lists to label or block Trump supporters, Singal, and other widely disliked journalists. But things have not been perfect. Several users have complained about being added to libelously named lists, while others have complained that stalkers have added them to numerous lists out of revenge. Trying to balance concerns between legitimate blocklist maintainers and victims of false accusations, Bluesky </span><a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/18/bluesky-addresses-trust-and-safety-concerns-around-abuse-spam-and-more/?utm_source=chatgpt.com" rel="">unveiled a series of changes</a><span> to its </span><a href="https://bsky.social/about/support/tos" rel="">terms of service</a><span> which brought it more in line with other social platforms, but also sparked controversy because now users can get blocklists hidden by reporting on them.</span></p><p>The failure of the Singal ban effort has also continued to grate on Bluesky’s most persistent critics, and the site’s executives have been met with many critical and often off-topic replies and quote posts.</p><p>While Bluesky has been navigating user concerns, its engineering team has been moving ahead with its long-promised open source efforts, breaking up its software stack into several pieces to enable a federated Authenticated Transfer Protocol (ATProto) network where anyone with the know-how and funds could run their own copy of Bluesky.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png" width="708" height="575" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:575,&quot;width&quot;:708,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ggf1!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0e61cf95-68af-46bf-8f3c-c1213745ebdd_708x575.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>There are several key pieces of code that combine to make the Bluesky network function: A personal data server (PDS) which hosts the official/canonical copies of its users’ posts and profile information. Whenever it’s updated, the data is combined and sent to a Relay server, which combines and indexes posts from many different PDSes to create what social networks call the “firehose,” the collection of all posts made on the network.</p><p><span>The firehose data is imported by a labeler program which categorizes it in various ways set up by users, the processed data is combined together by an application server (or AppViews as they’re called </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/pfrazee.com/post/3lyucxfxq622w" rel="">for now</a><span> in Bluesky). When a user logs into their PDS and pushes “refresh,” their local app connects to the PDS’s designated feed generator which serves up a cached version of the accounts they follow.</span></p><p><span>While the ATProto system has been criticized as overly complicated </span><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/4/20/23689570/activitypub-protocol-standard-social-network" rel="">compared to the ActivityPub system</a><span> that powers the Fediverse, it has one key feature that ActivityPub lacks: the ability to transfer servers while keeping all of your followers and posts.</span></p><p>Due to the complexity of the Bluesky software stack, whether its federation model actually works in practice has not really been put to the test. While ActivityPub has several instances with millions of users (like Facebook Threads, Flipboard, and even Donald Trump’s Truth Social), it also has many much smaller ones run by small organizations and individuals.</p><p><span>As of this writing, however, the only completely independent implementation of ATProto is Bluesky. But that isn’t for want of trying on the part of Rudy Fraser, the creator of </span><a href="https://blacksky.community/" rel="">Blacksky</a><span>, an alternative service that he unveiled in May of 2023 in response to Black American users’ complaints about Bluesky’s moderation policies.</span></p><p>Despite Fraser’s efforts to implement his own PDS, Relay, and App View, however, Blacksky still remains partially dependent upon Bluesky’s application server, largely because while the code to implement the dataplane of posts and users within an application server is released, the open-source version is slower. As a result, Blacksky is dependent on Bluesky’s application server to give users a fast experience, which also means that it is dependent on Bluesky’s labeling system and its moderation choices.</p><p>The labeling software, called Ozone, also has issues, according to Bluesky engineer Bryan Newbold.</p><p>“Making it easier to run moderation services is something we want to do. we invested a lot of time and effort in Ozone, but have not been able to focus on making it usable/accessible for independent folks,” he wrote in an Oct. 3 post, adding that “we are looking at funding folks to fork or re-implement it for community use-case.”</p><p>This limitation is likely to be another reason why Blacksky relies on Bluesky's AppView. Without it, Blacksky’s independent moderators couldn't actually perform their task. (Fraser did not respond to repeated attempts to contact him for comment.)</p><p>Blacksky’s continued dependency on Bluesky came into focus on Sunday after a Blacksky user going by the handle Link suddenly found himself unable to view his own posts on the alternative site.</p><p><span>“My account was taken down without any explanation for almost a full day,” Link told me in a Signal message, showing me a screenshot indicating that he had been banned even as his Blacksky account remained capable of viewing others’ posts and changing preferences. Unbeknownst to him, Link’s account had been banned by Bluesky’s moderators and this meant that even though he was in good standing at Blacksky, no one there, including himself, was able to read his posts. (They are visible </span><a href="https://pdsls.dev/at://did:plc:63hvnyjvqi2nzzcsjgnry5we/app.bsky.feed.post" rel="">within the ATProto firehose feed</a><span>, however, as several sharp-eyed users soon discovered.)</span></p><p><span>Link’s banning came at a very bad moment for Bluesky, just weeks after it had banned or suspended several users following the Sept. 10 murder of far-right activist Charlie Kirk, which many Republican officials have sought to use as a tool for </span><a href="https://apnews.com/article/kirk-trump-cancel-culture-assassination-4d69649e382ea46d8dcf794150a1d3c9" rel="">government censorship</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Federal Communications Commission Brendan Carr’s threats against late night comedian Jimmy Kimmel led to his temporary suspension by ABC, and he was far from the only Republican to issue them. Louisiana Rep. Clay Higgins, chair of the House subcommittee on federal law enforcement, </span><a href="https://clayhiggins.house.gov/wp-content/uploads/2025/09/9.15.25_Rep.-Higgins-Letter-to-Big-Tech-re-Charlie-Kirk-1.pdf" rel="">sent a menacing letter</a><span> to Bluesky and other social media networks demanding that they identify and ban anyone deemed to be celebrating Kirk’s killing.</span></p><p>“The authors of these posts are to be identified and banned from your platform, as well as any new pages they may create,” he wrote. “The reasonable restriction of public statements that lie far beyond the standards of our own society is not an oppression of free speech, it is, rather, the protection of free speech.”</p><p><span>There’s no proof that Higgins’s threats against social media platforms led to Bluesky banning anyone, but in any case, more than a few users were permanently or temporarily banned for mocking Kirk’s death, including horror author </span><a href="https://www.tcj.com/horror-it-girl-gretchen-felker-martin-on-dc-pulling-red-hood-after-charlie-kirk-comments-i-had-no-regrets/" rel="">Gretchen Felker-Martin</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>The fallout from the Kirk controversies and the months of replies seems to have irked Bluesky CEO Jay Graber, and she began pushing back on the user complaints. On Oct. 1, she </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m25dl2ibnc2y" rel="">approvingly quoted</a><span> a user who had referenced the famous </span><a href="https://knowyourmeme.com/memes/no-bitch-dats-a-whole-new-x-wtf-is-you-talkin-about" rel="">pancakes-waffle Twitter meme</a><span> about how liking pancakes doesn’t mean disliking waffles, adding: “Too real. We’re going to try to fix this. Social media doesn’t have to be this way.”</span></p><p><span>Graber’s post was soon met by </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/antioccident.bsky.social/post/3m25emit7w22r" rel="">a reply</a><span> asking if she’d banned Singal yet, prompting her to </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m25esnq4t22y" rel="">respond</a><span> in all-caps: “WAFFLES.”</span></p><p><span>The next day, Thursday, Graber returned to her theme, </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m2a73ot5uk2e" rel="">posting a photograph</a><span> of a berry-covered waffle, accompanied with the caption: “Amazing breakfast this morning. I love waffles.”</span></p><p><span>As might be expected, Graber’s trolling was not taken well by her critics. The waffles post received more than 1,700 replies, including many </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/billcorbett.bsky.social/post/3m2aajss5hs2q" rel="">mocking her</a><span> as a Musk-like figure.</span></p><p><span>On Friday, Graber turned more serious </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m2c7ge42us2t" rel="">in her pushback</a><span>: “Harassing the mods into banning someone has never worked. And harassing people in general has never changed their minds,” she wrote, </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/jay.bsky.team/post/3m2c7hy7zus2t" rel="">adding later</a><span> that: “Yet it’s a behavior that persists across social media anyway, with negative consequences for civil discourse and society. Human nature is a contributing factor, but systems that reward outrage only make the problem worse.”</span></p><p><span>Among the more than 100 people who quoted Graber’s post that day was Link. He </span><a href="https://pdsls.dev/at://did:plc:63hvnyjvqi2nzzcsjgnry5we/app.bsky.feed.post/3m2cerd243k2a" rel="">posted a photo of Kirk</a><span> which he accompanied with descriptive text that read: “Charlie Kirk sitting in a white T-shirt that says freedom. A negative consequence follows.”</span></p><p><span>Link made a number of other posts after to that one, but on Sunday his Blacksky account stopped working. After receiving no contact from either Blacksky or Bluesky, Link messaged Bluesky’s moderation team and received </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/aliafonzy.blacksky.app/post/3m2jm7ugr6k2y" rel="">an email</a><span> about 3 hours later saying that he had violated the social network’s community guidelines in his quote of Graber days earlier, presumably its policies against “threats or encouragement of violence.”</span></p><p>That is not how Link sees his post.</p><p><span>“I want to be extremely clear I was not making a death threat or inciting violence,” he told me, saying that he had sent 12 separate examples of other people posting the same Kirk image as a </span><a href="https://x.com/liv_agar/status/1975210544018989119?s=42" rel="">reaction meme</a><span>. “I don’t wish death on Jay, I wish for her and her team to grow a conscience. I disagree with the decision and how it was handled. My account was taken down without any explanation for almost a full day in what can only be viewed as a retroactive ban.”</span></p><p>I’ve asked Bluesky whether the post had been reported as a violation by other users. I will update this story if I receive a response. Rudy Fraser, the Blacksky administrator has not responded to a request for comment.</p><p>Asked about why Link had to contact Bluesky to find out what had happened to his account rather than receiving a notice, Paul Frazee, the service’s CTO, said that it was “unfortunate,” and that Bluesky needed to finish adding a feature to let users of external PDSes know if they have been banned by Bluesky labelers.</p><p><span>Agree or disagree on whether Bluesky has treated Link fairly, the incident has exposed that the social network’s decentralization plans have yet to be fulfilled. Blacksky seems to be the furthest-along alternative ATProto implementation, but it’s still dependent on Bluesky. There’s another one called </span><a href="https://northskysocial.com/profile/posts" rel="">Northsky Social</a><span>, but it has not launched any services yet. And while there are several alternative AppViews such as </span><a href="https://deer.social/" rel="">Deer.social</a><span>, there does not seem to be any service (or combination of services) that can function as a full-stack implementation of ATProto.</span></p><p><span>This might explain why, despite having a network of </span><a href="https://bsky.jazco.dev/stats" rel="">nearly 40 million users</a><span>, no situation like Link’s banning seems to have happened during Bluesky’s very short lifespan.</span></p><p><span>The episode has sent more than a few Bluesky users to start wondering whether the snow-covered grass on Mastodon’s side of the road is </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/kozufox.bsky.social/post/3m2k5pf63ks2h" rel="">worth considering</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>But not everyone is looking forward to the idea: “I’d go back to Usenet before I went back to Mastodon,” wrote Bluesky user </span><a href="https://bsky.app/profile/horseknuckler.bsky.social/post/3m2abce3vss2w" rel="">Count Von Horse Knuckler</a><span>. “I do not need people yelling at me for not putting cat pictures behind trigger warnings or unwanted Linux advice.”</span></p><p><span>Help may be on the horizon, however. As developers are becoming more aware of the power of ATProto, they are building increasingly complex projects on it, including a promising service called </span><a href="https://slices.network/" rel="">Slices</a><span>, which aims to make it easy to build and deploy custom AppViews, a feature Blacksky and other Bluesky alternatives could certainly use. Bluesky execs have said they are working hard to make federation easier.</span></p><p>Meanwhile, Link is caught in limbo.</p><p>“Now my account is not viewable on either Blacksky or Bluesky,” he notes. “I’m fortunate that I moved over to Blacksky and I think that is the only reason I still have access to my account and data…Bluesky claims to want decentralization and composable moderation, but they still enjoy abusing the power of arbitrary banishment.”</p><p>This story has been updated to include a post from Bluesky developer Bryan Newbold.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>