<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 11:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Meet the real screen addicts: the elderly (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.economist.com/international/2025/10/23/meet-the-real-screen-addicts-the-elderly</link>
            <guid>45701305</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 04:09:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.economist.com/international/2025/10/23/meet-the-real-screen-addicts-the-elderly">https://www.economist.com/international/2025/10/23/meet-the-real-screen-addicts-the-elderly</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45701305">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.economist.com/international/2025/10/23/meet-the-real-screen-addicts-the-elderly: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New OSM file format: 30% smaller than PBF, 5x faster to import (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://community.openstreetmap.org/t/new-osm-file-format-30-smaller-than-pbf-5x-faster-to-import/137151</link>
            <guid>45699725</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 22:23:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://community.openstreetmap.org/t/new-osm-file-format-30-smaller-than-pbf-5x-faster-to-import/137151">https://community.openstreetmap.org/t/new-osm-file-format-30-smaller-than-pbf-5x-faster-to-import/137151</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45699725">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
              <p>The OSM dataset is huge, and keeps growing every day. Great news, of course, but sometimes the sheer volume can be overwhelming – there are just gobs and <em>gobs</em> of data!</p>
<p>Hence, we created GOB (“Geo-Object Bundle”), a new file format that makes tackling OSM data faster and easier. It’s a companion format to our now-familiar <a href="https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Geographic_Object_Library">Geo-Object Library</a> (essentially, a tightly-compressed GOL with its indexes stripped).</p>
<p>To support this new format, GOL Tool 2.1 has two new commands: <code>save</code> GOLs as GOBs and <code>load</code> GOBs into a GOL (Of course, like all of the GeoDesk Toolkit, the GOL Tool is free &amp; open-source).</p>
<div><a href="https://community-cdn.openstreetmap.org/uploads/default/original/3X/6/3/63cb08ad6b5f33578da3f529982ccd975caba949.jpeg" data-download-href="https://community-cdn.openstreetmap.org/uploads/default/63cb08ad6b5f33578da3f529982ccd975caba949" title="GOB Tiling &amp; Size Statistics"><img src="https://community-cdn.openstreetmap.org/uploads/default/optimized/3X/6/3/63cb08ad6b5f33578da3f529982ccd975caba949_2_690x358.jpeg" alt="GOB Tiling &amp; Size Statistics" data-base62-sha1="eeOgB0dnd7f5NRTE9l9cGzuDQvL" width="690" height="358" srcset="https://community-cdn.openstreetmap.org/uploads/default/optimized/3X/6/3/63cb08ad6b5f33578da3f529982ccd975caba949_2_690x358.jpeg, https://community-cdn.openstreetmap.org/uploads/default/optimized/3X/6/3/63cb08ad6b5f33578da3f529982ccd975caba949_2_1035x537.jpeg 1.5x, https://community-cdn.openstreetmap.org/uploads/default/optimized/3X/6/3/63cb08ad6b5f33578da3f529982ccd975caba949_2_1380x716.jpeg 2x" data-dominant-color="AFA6A4"></a></div>
<h2><a name="p-1172010-advantages-of-gob-1" href="#p-1172010-advantages-of-gob-1"></a>Advantages of GOB</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>GOB files are on average half the size of a GOL, and <strong>30% smaller</strong> than <a href="https://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/PBF_Format">PBFs</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Importing a GOB is <strong>5 times faster</strong> than building a GOL from a PBF. A modern system loads a planet-size GOB into a GOL in 3 minutes. The speed advantage grows more pronounced on memory-constrained machines: <code>gol build</code> starts paging heavily with less than 32 GB of RAM, whereas <code>gol load</code> requires minimal resources (even a decade-old laptop loads the whole planet in under an hour).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>GOBs are organized into tiles, so it’s easy to extract regional subsets (basically at file-copy speed) and stitch them back together; that makes GOB a convenient format for archiving and distributing geodata.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><em>The image above shows some of the tiling structure, which mimics that of tile renderers. On the left, the smallest squares are zoom 6, the right shows the most granular level (zoom 12). A typical planet GOB has about 60,000 tiles.</em></p>
<p>Below are some size statistics for the planet file and popular regional extracts (without metadata):</p>
<pre><code>                PBF      GOL               GOB
Planet      65.4 GB  93.6 GB  +43.1%   46.0 GB  -29.7%
California  1.18 GB  1.59 GB  +35.0%    770 MB  -36.5%
France      4.54 GB  5.89 GB  +29.7%   2.84 GB  -36.3%
Germany     4.29 GB  5.92 GB  +38.0%   2.67 GB  -37.5%
Italy       1.96 GB  2.63 GB  +34.0%   1.34 GB  -31.6%
Japan       2.13 GB  2.91 GB  +36.1%   1.34 GB  -37.0%
Poland      1.84 GB  2.72 GB  +47.6%   1.29 GB  -29.7%
Switzerland  487 MB   634 MB  +30.1%    311 MB  -36.2%
</code></pre>
<p>Dense, well-mapped areas tend to compress best as GOB. Less complete regions are below average in terms of GOB’s size advantage (GOBs for Brazil and China are only 23% smaller).</p>
<h2><a name="p-1172010-limitations-2" href="#p-1172010-limitations-2"></a>Limitations</h2>
<p>Just like GOLs, GOBs don’t store:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>metadata (timestamp of last edit, changeset, username, etc.)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>history (each GOB is a snapshot of the OSM dataset)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Therefore, it is not intended for editing, but for archival and distribution.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1172010-how-to-work-with-gobs-3" href="#p-1172010-how-to-work-with-gobs-3"></a>How to work with GOBs</h2>
<p>You will need GOL Tool 2.1 or above (<a href="https://www.geodesk.com/download" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">download</a>).</p>
<p>To export a GOL as a GOB:</p>
<pre data-code-wrap="bash"><code>gol save &lt;gol-file&gt; [&lt;gob-file&gt;]
</code></pre>
<p>If <code>&lt;gob-file&gt;</code> is omitted, it uses the same base name as the GOL. The <code>.gol</code> and <code>.gob</code> extensions are optional.</p>
<p>To limit the export to a specific area, use the <code>--area</code> (<code>-a</code>) option. You can specify a (multi)polygon as WKT, GeoJSON or simple coordinates (<code>lon,lat</code> pairs, rings are closed automatically), either directly or as a file. If no file extension is given, <code>.wkt</code> is assumed.</p>
<p>For example:</p>
<pre data-code-wrap="bash"><code>gol save world bodensee -a 9.55,47.4,8.78,47.66,9.01,47.88,9.85,47.58,9.82,47.46 
</code></pre>
<p>exports the tiles covering the region around the <a href="https://www.openstreetmap.org/relation/1156846">Bodensee</a> (Lake Constance).</p>
<p>To import tiles into a GOL:</p>
<pre data-code-wrap="bash"><code>gol load &lt;gol-file&gt; [&lt;gob-file&gt;]
</code></pre>
<p>As with <code>save</code>, if <code>&lt;gob-file&gt;</code> is omitted, the base name of the GOL is used. If the GOL does not exist, it is created. To load just a specific region, restrict it with the <code>-a</code> option.</p>
<pre data-code-wrap="bash"><code>gol load japan -a shikoku
</code></pre>
<p>loads tiles from <code>japan.gob</code> into <code>japan.gol</code> (creating it if it doesn’t yet exist), but only those intersecting the area defined in <code>shikoku.wkt</code>.</p>
<h2><a name="p-1172010-available-datasets-4" href="#p-1172010-available-datasets-4"></a>Available datasets</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://openplanetdata.com/" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">Open Planet Data</a> publishes the full planet as a GOB (&lt; 50 GB, updated daily).</li>
</ul>
<h2><a name="p-1172010-whats-next-5" href="#p-1172010-whats-next-5"></a>What’s next</h2>
<p>This is still a work in progress, so the format may change. I’m experimenting with different compression algos beyond zlib to make it even tighter and faster (zstd didn’t yield any significant gains). I’m also in the process of enabling <code>gol load</code> to download a GOB directly from a URL and build the GOL in the background, which would bring the wall-clock import time to zero.</p>
<p>As always, questions/feedback are welcome! Please stop on by <a href="https://github.com/clarisma">on Github</a> and <a href="https://en.osm.town/@geodesk" rel="noopener nofollow ugc">@geodesk@en.osm.town</a>.</p>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Study: MRI contrast agent causes harmful metal buildup in some patients (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ormanager.com/briefs/study-mri-contrast-agent-causes-harmful-metal-buildup-in-some-patients/</link>
            <guid>45698909</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 20:48:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ormanager.com/briefs/study-mri-contrast-agent-causes-harmful-metal-buildup-in-some-patients/">https://www.ormanager.com/briefs/study-mri-contrast-agent-causes-harmful-metal-buildup-in-some-patients/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45698909">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                                <p><strong>Editor's Note</strong></p>
<p><em>New research offers a potential explanation for why some patients retain toxic metals long after undergoing an MRI.</em></p>
<p><em>Published in the journal Magnetic Resonance Imaging, the findings show that gadolinium contrast agents used in MRI scans may react with common dietary compounds to form harmful metal nanoparticles in the body. As detailed in an April 7 Newsweek report on the study, gadolinium-based contrast agents are injected to sharpen MRI images and are typically excreted without causing harm. However, gadolinium particles have been found lingering in the brain, kidneys, blood, and urine years after exposure, and the US Food and Drug Administration links retained gadolinium to nephrogenic systemic fibrosis (NSF).</em></p><!-- [Ad Widget Id: ai_ad_widget-9 | Sidebar: ad-orm-native] --><!-- end [Ad Widget Id: ai_ad_widget-9 | Sidebar: ad-orm-native] -->
<p><em>The study specifically identifies a chemical reaction between gadolinium and oxalic acid—a compound found naturally in foods and produced in the body after ingesting vitamin C—as a likely contributor, Newsweek reports. Lab tests showed oxalic acid caused gadolinium to separate from its chelating agent and form nanoparticles capable of infiltrating cells in various organs.</em></p>
<p><em>Lead author Dr Brent Wagner told Newsweek he personally avoids vitamin C when undergoing MRI with contrast, citing its potential to increase gadolinium reactivity. “Metabolic milieu,” including high oxalic acid levels, could explain why some individuals experience severe symptoms while others do not, he said.</em></p>
<p><em>According to the article, nearly half of the patients found to have gadolinium traces in the body had received the contrast agent only once, suggesting that individual biology—not dosage—may influence risk. Dr Wagner theorized that nanoparticle formation could trigger a disproportionate immune response, with affected cells sending distress signals that intensify the body’s reaction.</em></p>
<p><em>The research team is now building an international patient registry to further study gadolinium accumulation. According to the article, the registry will collect blood, urine, hair, and fingernail samples to help identify individuals at greatest risk and understand long-term retention patterns.</em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.ormanager.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Newsweek.png"><img src="https://www.ormanager.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/Newsweek.png" alt="" width="277" height="182"></a></p>
                                                                                                    <p><a href="https://www.newsweek.com/scientists-mri-scans-toxic-metal-behind-body-2056295" target="_blank">Read More &gt;&gt;</a>
                                            </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Swift SDK for Android (553 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.swift.org/blog/nightly-swift-sdk-for-android/</link>
            <guid>45698570</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 20:06:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.swift.org/blog/nightly-swift-sdk-for-android/">https://www.swift.org/blog/nightly-swift-sdk-for-android/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45698570">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <header>
    
  
    <!-- mobile-navigation -->
    
  </header>
   <div id="post">
    

    
    
    

    <p><time pubdate="" datetime="2025-10-24T06:00:00-04:00">October 24, 2025</time>
      
    <img src="https://www.swift.org/assets/images/swift-sdk-for-android-blog/blog-hero@2x.png" alt="Featured blog image with the screenshot of Android Studio with Swift code">
     
    <img src="https://www.swift.org/assets/images/swift-sdk-for-android-blog/blog-hero-dark@2x.png" alt="Featured blog image with the screenshot of Android Studio with Swift code"></p><div>
      <p>Swift has matured significantly over the past decade — extending from cloud services to Windows applications, browser apps, and microcontrollers. Swift powers apps and services of all kinds, and thanks to its great interoperability, you can share code across platforms.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.swift.org/android-workgroup/">Android workgroup</a> is an open group, free for anyone to join, that aims to expand Swift to Android. Today, we are pleased to announce nightly preview releases of the <a href="https://www.swift.org/install/macos/#swift-sdk-buindles-dev">Swift SDK for Android</a>.</p>

<p>This milestone reflects months of effort by the Android workgroup, building on many years of grassroots community effort. With the SDK, developers can begin developing Android applications in Swift, opening new avenues for cross-platform development and accelerating innovation across the mobile ecosystem.</p>

<p>The Swift SDK for Android is available today, bundled with the <a href="https://www.swift.org/install/windows/">Windows installer</a> or downloadable separately for use on Linux or macOS.</p>



<p>We’ve published a <a href="https://www.swift.org/documentation/articles/swift-sdk-for-android-getting-started.html">Getting Started guide</a> to help you set up your first native Swift code on an Android device. The <a href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-android-examples">Swift for Android Examples</a> help demonstrate end‑to‑end application workflows on Android.</p>

<p>With the Swift SDK for Android, you can now start porting your Swift packages to Android. <a href="https://swiftpackageindex.com/blog/adding-wasm-and-android-compatibility-testing">Over 25% of packages in the Swift Package Index</a> already build for Android, and <a href="https://www.swift.org/packages/showcase.html">the Community Showcase</a> now indicates Android compatibility.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-java">swift-java project</a> enables you to interoperate between Java and Swift. It is both a library and a code generator, enabling you to integrate Swift and Java in both directions by automatically generating safe and performant bindings. To learn about generating bindings to bring your business logic to Android, check out the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=96IQAA7Nl8E&amp;t=982s">recent Swift Server Side meetup talk</a> by Mads Odgaard.</p>



<p>This preview release opens many new opportunities to continue improving these tools. We encourage you to share your experiences, ideas, tools and apps on the <a href="https://forums.swift.org/">Swift forums</a>. This post has been published on an <a href="https://forums.swift.org/t/announcing-the-swift-sdk-for-android/82845">associated thread</a> for discussion, and new posts can be shared in the <a href="https://forums.swift.org/c/platform/android/115">Android category</a>.</p>

<p>The Android workgroup is drafting <a href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/pull/2946">a vision document</a>, currently under review, for directing future work regarding Swift on Android. This vision will outline priority areas and guide community efforts to maximize impact across the ecosystem. In addition, we maintain a <a href="https://github.com/orgs/swiftlang/projects/17">project board</a> that tracks the status of major efforts, as well as <a href="https://ci.swift.org/job/oss-swift-package-swift-sdk-for-android/">official CI for the Swift SDK for Android</a>.</p>

<p>If you’re as excited as we are, join us and help make this ecosystem even better!</p>
 
      
      

      
        <hr>
        <h2>Authors</h2>
        <div>
        
        
          
          
            <p>Joannis is the chair of the Android Workgroup, member of the Server Workgroup and maintainer of Hummingbird.</p>
          
        
      </div>
      

      

      <hr>

      <h2>Continue Reading</h2>

      
      <nav>
        <div>
          <ul>
            
            <li>
              <div>
                <h3>Introducing Swift Profile Recorder: Identifying Performance Bottlenecks in Production</h3>
                <p><time pubdate="" datetime="2025-10-24T06:00:00-04:00">October 6, 2025</time></p><p>
                  Swift Profile Recorder, an in-process sampling profiler for Swift services, is..
                </p>
                <p><a href="https://www.swift.org/blog/swift-profile-recorder/" rel="prev"> More </a>
              </p></div>
            </li>
             
          </ul>
        </div>
      </nav>
      
    </div>
  </div>
 

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Harnessing America's Heat Pump Moment (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heatpumped.org/p/harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment</link>
            <guid>45698554</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 20:05:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heatpumped.org/p/harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment">https://www.heatpumped.org/p/harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45698554">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-blocks"><p><i>Editor’s note: This is a guest post by </i><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-denatale/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank"><i>Joseph DeNatale</i></a><i>, an entrepreneur and project coordinator at Jetson Home. It originally appeared in </i><a href="https://climatedrift.substack.com/p/whats-stopping-america-from-going?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank"><i>Climate Drift</i></a><i> earlier this year, and is republished on Heat Pumped with permission. </i></p><p><i>Joseph interviewed me when he was researching the piece, and I was excited to see that the final product touched many topics that I've been wanting to write about. </i></p><p><i>A big thank you to Joseph and Climate Drift for sharing with the Heat Pumped community - it's incredibly in-depth. Since there’s so much to digest, we’re splitting it up into 5 parts that we'll be sharing over the next few weeks. </i></p><p id="why-execution-is-everything-a-perso"><h2><span><b>Why Execution Is Everything: A Personal Perspective</b></span></h2></p><p><span>As a small business owner, I’ve built a career not around inventing new things, but around making things happen: making sure systems run smoothly, projects get completed on time, and clients feel taken care of.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>My work has been rooted in the real-world, hands-on, often chaotic rhythm of operations, logistics, and direct client service. Whether it’s organizing teams to execute live events, refining workflows to scale a growing business, or managing the delicate art of closing a sale, I’ve learned one simple truth: the hardest part is never the idea. It’s the execution.</span></p><p><span>So when I began diving into the world of home electrification—particularly heat pumps—that same truth surfaced again, just with higher stakes.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span><b>The technology isn’t the issue</b></span><span>. In fact, the technology is there. It’s been there for decades, and it is continuing to improve. We’re not waiting on some magical breakthrough or futuristic device.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span><b>We’re waiting on people</b></span><span>—mostly homeowners and home contractors, but also manufacturers and policy makers—to embrace, understand, and implement what already works.</span></p><p><span>This piece isn’t about reinventing the wheel. It’s about understanding why we’re not using the wheel we already have—and what it’s going to take, from the human side of the equation, to </span><span><b>make heat pumps the obvious, accessible, and default choice for millions of American homes</b></span><span>.</span></p><p id="heat-pumps-arent-new-but-this-momen"><h3><span><b>Heat Pumps Aren’t New—But This Moment Is</b></span></h3></p><p><span>In the world of climate solutions, it’s easy to get distracted by what’s shiny and new—sleek devices, breakthrough technologies, futuristic models of sustainability.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>But not every climate solution is some new-fangled wonder gadget. Some of them already exist. Some of them are sitting in basements and behind houses, quietly doing the work.</span></p><p><span><b>The heat pump is one of them.</b></span></p><p><span>Heat pumps are not new. In fact, </span><a href="https://yaleclimateconnections.org/2023/02/how-heat-pumps-of-the-1800s-are-becoming-the-technology-of-the-future?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">the idea has been around for well over a century</a><span>, and the technology has been used widely for decades—mostly in Europe and Asia, but also in pockets of the U.S.—for everything from water heating to whole-home climate control.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Modern heat pumps are </span><a href="https://www.energy-transitions.org/bitesize/its-in-the-charts-heat-pump-lifetime-cost-electricity-to-gas?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">highly efficient</a><span>—anywhere from 2-4x more efficient than a furnace—and capable of replacing both a furnace and an air conditioner with a single system in virtually every climate. For millions of homes across the country, they offer a cleaner, quieter, and more precise way to stay comfortable year-round.</span></p><p><span>Importantly, heat pumps have also been shown to </span><span><b>match or beat the operating costs</b></span><span> of even the cheapest heating option—natural gas—in many cases. This has been demonstrated through both </span><a href="https://www.energy.gov/energysaver/articles/most-americans-heat-pump-can-lower-bills-right-now?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">local</a><span> and </span><a href="https://www.energy.gov/energysaver/articles/most-americans-heat-pump-can-lower-bills-right-now?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">national </a><span>studies. One study showed that over </span><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2542435124000497?via%3Dihub=&amp;utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">90% of American households</a><span> would save on energy bills by replacing worn-out heating equipment with the right-sized heat pump.&nbsp;</span></p><p><a href="https://www.energysage.com/heat-pumps/heat-pumps-vs-furnaces/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Installation costs vary wildly</a><span> depending on many factors in a home, but with the introduction of </span><a href="https://homes.rewiringamerica.org/federal-incentives/home-electrification-appliance-rebates?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">generous incentives</a><span> via the Inflation Reduction Act (IRA) and additional state programs, even these costs can be on-par with fossil fuel alternatives.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span><b>So why aren’t they everywhere?</b></span></p><p><span>The answer isn’t technical. It’s cultural, economic, and human.&nbsp;</span></p><p id="tldr"><h3><span><b>TL;DR</b></span></h3></p><p><span>Heat pumps are </span><span><b>proven, efficient, and climate-friendly</b></span><span>—but adoption is still slow.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>The barrier isn’t the tech. </span><span><b>It’s people</b></span><span>:&nbsp;</span></p><div><ul><li><p><span>Contractors who default to what they know</span></p></li><li><p><span>Homeowners who need education and guidance</span></p></li><li><p><span>A fragmented market full of noise and misinformation</span></p></li></ul></div><p><span>This piece discusses these challenges, and then explores five keys to accelerating adoption:</span></p><div><ol start="1"><li><p><span><b>Educate homeowners</b></span><span> so heat pumps feel familiar and trustworthy.</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>Train the next-gen workforce</b></span><span> and upskill legacy HVAC pros.</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>Leverage better tools and data</b></span><span> to size and install systems right.</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>Prioritize quality and trust</b></span><span> to build social proof and demand.</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>Align policy</b></span><span> to phase out one-way ACs and normalize heat pumps.</span></p></li></ol></div><p><span>Execution—not invention—is what will move the needle.</span></p><p id="hold-on-whats-a-heat-pump-again"><h2><span><b>Hold On.. What’s A Heat Pump Again?</b></span></h2></p><p><span>If you’re reading this piece, you probably know what a heat pump is (and you can feel free to skip this section).</span></p><p><span>But if you’re among the uninitiated – </span><span><b>like, believe it or not, most people</b></span><span> – here’s a (very) quick primer. </span><span><i>(Editor’s note: check out </i></span><a href="https://www.heatpumped.org/p/heat-pumps-101">Heat Pumps 101</a>&nbsp;<i>if you want to dive deeper)</i></p><div><p><img alt="" src="https://media.beehiiv.com/cdn-cgi/image/fit=scale-down,format=auto,onerror=redirect,quality=80/uploads/asset/file/a971b762-8820-4d24-9d4b-ee070d7a7d5c/image.png?t=1758289180"></p><p><small><p>A heat pump works by drawing thermal energy (heat) out of the atmosphere and “pumping” it into the home. This process works in reverse for cooling. (<a href="https://www.theheatpumpwarehouse.co.uk/how-heat-pumps-work/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Source</a>)</p></small></p></div><p id="the-2-way-ac"><h3><span><b>The 2-Way AC</b></span></h3></p><p><span>The term “heat pump”, it turns out, is a fairly unhelpful name for most people. In fact, there are some leaders in the home electrification industry who believe the name itself is one of the barriers to adoption. It’s one of many ways that </span><span><b>the heat pump is misunderstood</b></span><span>.</span></p><p><span>Think of a heat pump as a “</span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_cpNebGqGBk&amp;t=3474s&amp;utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">2-way AC</a><span>.” An air conditioner cools your home by pulling heat from inside an enclosed space and transferring it outside. Your refrigerator works the same way.</span></p><p><span>A heat pump does the same thing, but can also </span><span><b>reverse the process to bring heat </b></span><span><i><b>into</b></i></span><span><b> the home</b></span><span>. It uses a few key components to make this happen:</span></p><div><ul><li><p><span><b>The fan</b></span><span> pulls air across the system’s coils to help move heat in or out of the space.</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>The evaporator coil</b></span><span> absorbs heat from the air inside your home (in cooling mode) or from the outside air (in heating mode).</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>The compressor</b></span><span> pressurizes and moves a fluid called refrigerant through the system, enabling the heat transfer process.</span></p></li><li><p><span><b>The refrigerant</b></span><span> is the working fluid that captures and carries heat from one place to another—either out of your home or into it.</span></p></li></ul></div><p><span>What’s important to understand is that </span><span><b>a heat pump does not </b></span><span><i><b>create</b></i></span><span><b> heat</b></span><span>. It also doesn’t create cold (cold is the absence of heat, just like darkness is the absence of light). A heat pump simply </span><span><i>transfers </i></span><span>– pumps! – heat from one place to another.</span></p><div><p>“The difference between a heat pump and a one-way AC is just one valve. It still works perfectly fine as an air conditioner—there’s no difference. That’s why we’ve started calling them “two-way ACs” as an education tool. It helps people compare a two-way AC, which has a reverse gear, with a one-way AC—which, in my mind, is basically broken.”</p></div><p><span><b>But what about in the winter when it’s below freezing?</b></span><span> In any environment where the temperature is above absolute zero (remember </span><a href="https://nationalmaglab.org/about-the-maglab/around-the-lab/maglab-dictionary/kelvin-temperature-scale/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">the Kelvin scale</a><span>?) there is still a significant amount of heat in the air in the form of thermal energy.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>That’s why a heat pump can still heat your home even on the coldest day of the year.</span></p><div id="da7ed52e-37ae-4fe9-80e4-ef859564db27"><p><iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" height="100%" src="https://youtube.com/embed/iQaycSD5GWE" width="100%"></iframe></p></div><p id="why-heat-pumps-matter"><h2><span><b>Why Heat Pumps Matter&nbsp;</b></span></h2></p><p><span>The fact that heat pumps simply transfer heat—and do not create it—gives them the potential to heat homes without doing the thing that humans have done since time immemorial to keep warm: </span><span><b>burn stuff</b></span><span>.</span></p><p><span>In the U.S., </span><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/climate-environment/interactive/2023/home-electrification-heat-pumps-gas-furnace/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">over half of all homes still rely on burning fossil fuels for heat</a><span>. Replacing those systems with electric, air source heat pumps (ASHPs) can </span><span><b>significantly reduce household emissions</b></span><span>, especially as the grid gets cleaner and moves towards a higher percentage of renewable energy (i.e. not burning stuff).&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>And, because they’re so efficient, heat pumps can </span><a href="https://www.energy.gov/energysaver/articles/most-americans-heat-pump-can-lower-bills-right-now?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">lower operating costs over time</a><span>—although this is highly dependent on where you live, as the cost of fuel and electricity varies widely. They’re also </span><span><b>safer</b></span><span> (no burning stuff), can </span><span><b>improve indoor air quality</b></span><span> (again, no burning), and create </span><span><b>healthier, more comfortable homes</b></span><span>.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Finally, heat pumps are a crucial component of an </span><span><b>energy-independent home</b></span><span>. Paired with solar panels and battery storage, a homeowner can heat and cool their home entirely with energy they generate on their own. Try that with a furnace!</span></p><div><table><tbody><tr><td><p><span><b>Metric</b></span></p></td><td><p><span><b>Gas Furnace</b></span></p></td><td><p><span><b>Air-Source Heat Pump (ASHP)</b></span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Fuel Source</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Natural gas, propane, or oil</span></p></td><td><p><span>Electricity</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Heating/Cooling</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Heating only</span></p></td><td><p><span>Heats and cools (dual function)</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Air Quality</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Can introduce combustion byproducts; potential for CO</span></p></td><td><p><span>No combustion; generally better indoor air quality</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Health/Safety</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Risk of gas leaks, carbon monoxide</span></p></td><td><p><span>No combustion risk; safer for indoor environments</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Comfort</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Delivers blasts of hot air; on/off “short cycles”</span></p></td><td><p><span>More consistent, even heating/cooling with variable-speed options</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Initial Cost</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Typically lower (although the cost of a furnace + AC if replaced at the same time is often higher)</span></p></td><td><p><span>Often higher upfront, especially for cold-climate models. Costs can be lowered via incentive programs.</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Operating Cost</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Depends on gas prices; cheaper where gas is low</span></p></td><td><p><span>Can be lower, especially with efficient models + incentives and/or when paired with solar + battery storage</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Emissions</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Emits CO₂ and other GHGs</span></p></td><td><p><span>Zero onsite emissions; cleaner with a green grid</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Climate Suitability</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Performs well in all climates</span></p></td><td><p><span>Cold-climate models now perform down to -15 to -20°F</span></p></td></tr><tr><td><p><span><b>Incentives/Rebates</b></span></p></td><td><p><span>Limited (varies by region)</span></p></td><td><p><span>Significant federal/state incentives available</span></p></td></tr></tbody></table></div><p id="the-heat-pump-moment-has-arrived"><h2><span><b>The Heat Pump Moment Has Arrived</b></span></h2></p><p><span>For years, heat pumps were a niche topic, something discussed by green building enthusiasts, early adopters, or homeowners with unusually high energy awareness.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>But that’s no longer the case. Here are four reasons why:</span></p><p id="cultural-momentum-is-building"><h3><span><b>Cultural Momentum Is Building</b></span></h3></p><p><span>The </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2023/04/14/climate/electric-car-heater-everything.html?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">electrification movement</a><span> is no longer a fringe concept. The push to </span><span><b>“electrify everything” </b></span><span>has gained traction among policymakers, climate advocates, startups, utilities, and even popular media.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>From Substack newsletters to YouTube explainers, there’s growing awareness that </span><span><b>building decarbonization</b></span><span>—and especially heating and cooling—is one of the most practical, scalable ways for regular people to cut their emissions. Campaigns like Rewiring America’s “</span><a href="https://www.rewiringamerica.org/go-electric?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Go Electric</a><span>” initiative frame heat pumps not just as energy-efficient appliances, but as a gateway to modern, climate-aligned homes.&nbsp;</span></p><p id="federal-and-state-policy-is-aligned"><h3><span><b>Federal and State Policy Is Aligned (For Now)</b></span></h3></p><p><span>The </span><span><b>Inflation Reduction Act (IRA)</b></span><span> has introduced a suite of rebates, tax credits, and grant programs designed to make heat pumps more affordable and accessible. Single-family households can receive up to </span><a href="https://www.energy.gov/save/home-upgrades?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">$8,000 in upfront rebates for heat pump installations and up to $2,000 in federal tax credits</a><span>, not to mention additional support for electrical panel upgrades and home energy audits.&nbsp;</span><span><i>Editor’s note: the IRA rebates are federally funded, but </i></span><span><a href="https://atlasbuildingshub.com/home-energy-rebates-tracker/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank"><i>implemented at the state level</i></a></span><span><i>. Not all states are participating, and some that are haven’t rolled out their programs yet. In other states like California, the </i></span><span><a href="https://www.heatpumped.org/p/it-s-not-that-hard" target="_blank"><i>funds are already exhausted</i></a></span><span><i>. </i></span></p><p><span>State and local governments are also leading the way in the transition away from fossil fuels on both the demand and supply sides. Programs like </span><a href="https://www.efficiencymaine.com/at-home/residential-heat-pump-incentives/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Efficiency Maine</a><span>, </span><a href="https://techcleanca.com/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">TECH Clean California</a><span>, and </span><a href="https://www.masssave.com/residential/rebates-and-incentives/heating-and-cooling/heat-pumps/air-source-heat-pumps?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Mass Save</a><span> offer </span><a href="https://homes.rewiringamerica.org/federal-incentives/home-electrification-appliance-rebates?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">generous incentives</a><span> and no-interest financing to homeowners that drive the cost of electrification upgrades down even further. Meanwhile, New York City has </span><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/us-cities-seeking-to-ban-natural-gas-in-new-buildings-just-got-a-big-win-in-court/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">banned gas in new construction</a><span>, and Massachusetts has ordered public utilities to begin </span><a href="https://www.volts.wtf/p/the-massachusetts-utility-regulator?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">phasing out natural gas</a><span>, a move which is being studied in at least </span><a href="https://insideclimatenews.org/news/07122023/massachusetts-natural-gas-ruling/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">11 other states</a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p><p id="private-capital-is-following"><h3><span><b>Private Capital Is Following</b></span></h3></p><p><span>The heat pump space is no longer just a niche for contractors and utilities—it’s attracting serious private investment. VC-backed companies like</span><a href="https://www.quilt.com/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank"> Quilt</a><span> are reimagining the user experience with sleek, design-forward equipment and app-based controls. Others, like </span><a href="https://elephantenergy.com/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Elephant Energy</a><span> and </span><a href="https://www.forgeco.com/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">Forge</a><span>, are building “heat pump concierge” platforms that manage the customer journey end-to-end—from sales to install to rebate navigation.</span></p><p id="the-cold-climate-performance-myth-h"><h3><span><b>The Cold-Climate Performance Myth Has Been Fully Debunked</b></span></h3></p><p><span>These systems are already in use in northern New England, the upper Midwest, and Canada. In Nordic countries—some of the coldest climates in the word—the technology has been </span><a href="https://www.carbonbrief.org/guest-post-how-heat-pumps-became-a-nordic-success-story/?utm_source=www.heatpumped.org&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=harnessing-america-s-heat-pump-moment" target="_blank">viable for decades</a><span>.</span></p><p><span><span><b>And yet, despite all this momentum, heat pump adoption is still slow</b></span></span><span><span>.</span></span><span>&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Why? Because the hardest part isn’t scaling the technology. It’s aligning the people—</span><span><b>contractors, homeowners, policymakers, and market actors</b></span><span>—who need to make it happen.</span></p><div><p>“We’ve had the technology dialed for 20, 30, 40 years, depending on how you’re arguing it—but it’s not being applied. It’s a human problem. It’s not a technical one. The technical one has been solved.”</p></div><p><span>That’s where we go next.</span></p><p><span><i>This is part 1 in a 5 part series about challenges and solutions in accelerating heat pump adoption across the US. Stay tuned for the next issue!</i></span></p><p id="want-a-heat-pump-in-your-own-home"><h2>Want a heat pump in your own home? </h2></p><p> The first <a href="https://www.heatpumped.org/c/groupbuy" target="_blank">Heat Pumped group buy</a> generated lots of enthusiasm! There are still a handful of slots left, but you’ll have to act fast if you’re interested. Sign-ups close later this month (or when all the slots fill, whichever comes first). </p><p id="ps-want-to-break-into-a-heat-pump-c"><h3>PS: Want to break into a heat pump career? <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/shreyassudhakar_i-need-your-help-sending-another-gas-furnace-activity-7382077500673396737-MBHQ?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop&amp;rcm=ACoAAAwpShABM3Tqla6ag8HlCLfauKD1KiX4nko" target="_blank">Vayu is looking for a part time project manager</a> - no prior HVAC experience required!</h3></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FBI Agents Visit Anti-ICE Protester: "Your name was brought up." (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester</link>
            <guid>45697395</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 18:07:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester">https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45697395">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>While the media continues to ignore and even mock Trump’s war on “Antifa” terrorism as legally impossible, the FBI is quietly interrogating protesters.</p><p><span>The Bureau is targeting anti-ICE protesters not charged with any crime, like Chicago-based English professor Elias Cepeda, as I </span><a href="https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/no-kings-protest-and-arrests-begin" rel="">recently reported</a><span>. Often people targeted have refused to go public with their experience, fearing retribution. But one protester, fed up with the culture of self-censorship, decided to share his story. His account sheds light on the FBI’s attempts to map out some organized Antifa superstructure — and in doing so, undermining Americans’ freedom of speech and political expression.</span></p><p>Special-needs teacher Miles Serafini, 26, was watching a movie with his roommate when the FBI knocked on his door in suburban Tucson, Arizona last Friday. Two special agents greeted him, introducing themselves only as “James” and “Keith.” They didn’t offer their own last names, but they knew Miles’ — as well as his home address, his social media handles, what car he owns, and, unbeknownst to him, his political activities.</p><p>“We came out here to ask you questions regarding a protest that happened on the the 11th of June,” one of the agents said in an exchange captured on a Ring camera and provided to me by Serafini. “We’ve been just basically going around asking questions for a few people … and your name was brought up.”</p><p>The suggestion that his name “was brought up,” puzzled Serafini, who told me he didn’t know anyone at the protest, which he’d learned about from a post on social media. When he asked the agents how they knew who he was, they wouldn’t say — though one agent, Serafini said, later told him that they knew “way more about me than I’d think.”</p><p>The exact scale of these FBI questionings is unclear, but I’ve heard similar accounts involving protesters in Portland and Chicago. (The FBI declined to comment on Serafini’s account, citing the government shutdown.)</p><p>Serafini attended an anti-ICE protest around an ICE facility in June so he could express his opposition to the deportations, he told me. </p><p>“ICE is impacting our community and people aren’t happy,” Serafini said. “People see people around them being kidnapped and shipped away in cages and they show up to protest — It’s as easy as that.”</p><p><span>The protest involved an estimated 300 people gathering near the ICE field office at East Valencia Road and South Country Club Road in Tucson on June 11. The demonstration started off peacefully but later became rowdy. As the crowd gathered at the ICE office, a smaller group of protesters began </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=skcpyzdeoxQ" rel="">throwing objects</a><span> — rocks, paint-balls, fireworks and smoke devices — at what appeared to be  security guards stationed outside the building. The guards responded with crowd-control munitions.</span></p><p>Windows of the ICE facility and adjacent buildings were broken and spray-painted with graffiti. A number of businesses nearby boarded up or posted signs distancing themselves from ICE operations. Tucson Police later announced that three people were taken into custody for charges including unlawful assembly, resisting arrest, obstructing a public thoroughfare and disorderly conduct — and said that their investigation could lead to more arrests.</p><p><span>Serafini said he didn’t engage in any violence and hasn’t been detained or charged with any crime. But last month’s </span><a href="https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/trumps-nspm-7-labels-common-beliefs" rel="">presidential directive NSPM-7</a><span> authorizes federal law enforcement to treat “extremism on migration” as an indicator of terrorism. </span></p><p><span>Under the domestic counter-terrorism cases of the Trump administration, no crime needs to be actually committed for authorities to open an investigation. In fact, NSPM-7 explicitly calls for a preemptive approach where law enforcement intervene in things “before they result in violent political acts.” Attorney General Pam Bondi cited NSPM-7 in her own </span><a href="https://www.justice.gov/ag/media/1415691/dl" rel="">directive</a><span>, ordering the FBI and other federal law enforcement agencies to crack down on anti-ICE “terrorism,” citing protests in front of ICE facilities specifically.</span></p><p>After 9/11, as the FBI reoriented itself to fighting terror groups like al Qaeda, they focused on identifying and locating individuals and then mapping out their networks of family, friends and associates. That’s the Trump administration approach to Antifa, imagining an organization network that encompasses everything from membership cards to elaborate funding.</p><p>This approach was evident to Serafini, who told me: “I could tell by their questioning that they were trying to figure out the shadowy entity behind the protest.”</p><p>He added: “What a waste of their time to go after shit that doesn’t exist.”</p><p>The FBI seemed more interested in who was behind the protest than the protest itself, with the agents repeatedly asking about who had produced the protest signs, he explained.</p><p>“They wanted to know where they were from and who supplied them,” Serafini said. “Nothing about what was actually on them.”</p><p>The signage has become a point of interest to the Trump administration. At a roundtable event on Antifa earlier this month, President Trump pointed to the quality of the signs as evidence that the protests must be funded by unseen benefactors. </p><p>Per Trump: </p><blockquote><p><span> </span><em>“When you see the signs, and they’re all made out of a beautiful, beautiful paper. Beautiful, nice, stiff, very expensive paper with beautiful wood handles all the same. All the same color. They come from very expensive printing machines. These are are people that write out their signs in a basement, that believe in something. These are paid anarchists.”</em><span> </span></p></blockquote><p>Attorney General Pam Bondi echoed the same sentiment recently. </p><p>“That’s one of the things about Antifa," Bondi said on Fox News earlier this month. “You’re seeing people out there with thousands of signs that all match — pre-bought, pre-put together — they’re organized and someone is funding it.”</p><p>The administration is convinced that these protests aren’t spontaneous, and because of NSPM-7, the FBI has to prioritize collecting intelligence to show that. Serafini said that a particular focus of the FBI agents was whether the violence at the protest had been premeditated; and he when he told them it all seemed spontaneous, they implied he was lying.</p><p>Per Serafini:</p><blockquote><p><em>“They asked me if the violence (rocks, paint balloons) seemed spontaneous or premeditated. I told them it seemed spontaneous once the ICE agents escalated. They brought up that some protestors showed up with riot shields, so they questioned why they would bring shields if violence wasn’t premeditated. And they kept drilling me on the fact that I showed up alone, [that I didn’t] remember where I saw the flyer, and didn’t know anybody there. They told me that’s unusual and pretty suspicious — as if I was holding back information about whoever organized the protest. They kept insinuating that I was lying to them.”</em></p><p><em>“They showed me photos of several protestors … and tried to get information on them. They said ICE officers were badly injured and that these were the real suspects they needed info on. I told them I had no idea who they were. They seemed frustrated by that, but it’s the truth.”</em></p></blockquote><p>According to Serafini, the two FBI agents showed him photos of himself at the protest as well as several other protesters — people he knew nothing about. The agents asked him for his cell phone, but he refused. The questioning lasted about an hour. Serafini said they left him with a chilling message: that they couldn’t guarantee this would be the last time they saw him.</p><p>The agents may not have learned anything from Serafini, but the visit — which took place one day before the No Kings protest — did accomplish one thing: Serafini decided against going to No Kings. He was spooked.</p><p>That is exactly the chilling effect on speech that the FBI investigating political matters risks creating. </p><p>“Worked on me,” he said.</p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester/comments&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Leave a comment&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester/comments" rel=""><span>Leave a comment</span></a></p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.kenklippenstein.com/p/video-fbi-agents-visit-anti-ice-protester?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share" rel=""><span>Share</span></a></p><p><span>— </span><em>Edited by William M. Arkin</em></p></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to make a Smith chart (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/10/23/smith-chart/</link>
            <guid>45696838</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 17:18:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/10/23/smith-chart/">https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/10/23/smith-chart/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45696838">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<p>The Smith chart from electrical engineering is the image of a Cartesian grid under the function</p>
<p><em>f</em>(<em>z</em>) = (<em>z</em> − 1)/(<em>z</em> + 1).</p>
<p>More specifically, it’s the image of a grid in the right half-plane.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smith_chart.png" alt="Smith chart"></p>
<p>This post will derive the basic mathematical properties of this graph but will not go into the applications. Said another way, I’ll explain how to&nbsp;<em>make</em> a Smith chart, not how to&nbsp;<em>use</em> one.</p>
<p>We will use&nbsp;<em>z</em> to denote points in the right half-plane and&nbsp;<em>w</em> to denote the image of these points under&nbsp;<em>f</em>. We will speak of lines in the&nbsp;<em>z</em> plane and the circles they correspond to in the&nbsp;<em>w</em> plane.</p>
<h2>Möbius transformations</h2>
<p>Our function&nbsp;<em>f</em> is a special case of a Möbius transformation. There is a theorem that says Möbius transformation map generalized circles to generalized circles. Here a generalized circle means a circle or a line; you can think of a line as a circle with infinite radius. We’re going to get a lot of mileage out of that theorem.</p>
<h2>Image of the imaginary axis</h2>
<p>The function <em>f</em>&nbsp;maps the imaginary axis in the <em>z</em> plane to the unit circle in the <em>w</em> plane. We can prove this using the theorem above. The imaginary axis is a line, so it’s image is either a line or a circle. We can take three points on the imaginary axis in the <em>z</em> plane and see where they go.</p>
<p>When we pick <em>z</em> equal to 0,&nbsp;<em>i</em>, and&nbsp;−<em>i</em> from the imaginary axis we get <em>w</em> values of −1, <em>i</em>, and −<em>i</em>. These three&nbsp;<em>w</em> values do not&nbsp;line on a line, so the image of the imaginary axis must be a circle. Furthermore, <a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2023/06/18/circle-through-three-points/">three points uniquely determine a circle</a>, so the image of the imaginary axis is the circle containing −1, <em>i</em>, and −<em>i</em>, i.e. the unit circle.</p>
<h2>Image of the right half-plane</h2>
<p>The imaginary axis is the boundary of the right half-plane. Since it is mapped to the unit circle, the right half-plane is either mapped to the interior of the unit circle or the exterior of the unit circle. The point&nbsp;<em>z</em> = 1 goes to&nbsp;<em>w</em> = 0, and so&nbsp;the right half-plane is mapped inside the unit circle.</p>
<h2>Images of vertical lines</h2>
<p>Let’s think about what happens to vertical lines in the <em>z</em> plane, lines with constant positive real part. The images of these lines in the <em>w</em> plane must be either lines or circles. And since the right-half plane gets mapped inside the unit circle, these lines must get mapped to circles.</p>
<p>We can say a little more. All lines contain the point ∞, and <em>f</em>(∞) = 1, so the image of every vertical line in the&nbsp;<em>z</em> plane is a circle in the&nbsp;<em>w</em> plane, inside the unit circle and tangent to the unit circle at <em>w</em> = 1. (Tossing around ∞ is a bit informal, but it’s easy to make rigorous.)</p>
<p>The vertical lines in the&nbsp;<em>z</em> plane</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smithchart0.png" width="480" height="360"></p>
<p>map to tangent circles in the&nbsp;<em>w</em> plane.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smithchart1.png" width="480" height="360"></p>
<h2>Images of horizontal lines</h2>
<p>Next, let’s think about horizontal lines in the <em>z</em> plane, lines with constant imaginary part. The image of these lines is either a line or a circle. Which is it? The image of a line is a line if it contains ∞, otherwise it’s a circle. Now <em>f</em>(<em>z</em>) = ∞ if and only if&nbsp;<em>z</em> = −1, and so the image of the real axis is a line, but the image of every other horizontal line is a circle.</p>
<p>Since <em>f</em>(∞) = 1, the image of every horizontal line passes through 1, just as the images of all the vertical lines passes through 1.</p>
<p>Since horizontal lines extend past the right half-plane, the image circles extend past the unit circle. The part of the line with positive real part gets mapped inside the unit circle, and the part of the line with negative real part gets mapped outside the unit circle. In particular, the image of the positive real axis is the interval [−1, 1].</p>
<p>Möbius transformations are conformal maps, and so they preserve angles of intersection. Since horizontal lines are perpendicular to vertical lines, the circles that are the images of the horizontal lines meet the circles that are the images of vertical lines at right angles.</p>
<p>The horizontal rays in the <em>z</em> plane</p>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smithchart2.png" width="480" height="360"></p>
<p>become partial circles in the <em>w</em> plane.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smithchart3.png" width="480" height="360"></p>
<p>If we were to look at horizontal <em>lines</em> rather than rays, i.e. if we extended the lines into the left half-plane, the images in the <em>w</em> plane would be full circles.</p>
<p>Now let’s put our images together. The grid</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smithchart4.png" width="480" height="360"></p>
<p>in the <em>z</em> plane becomes the following in the <em>w</em> plane.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/smithchart5.png" width="480" height="360"></p>
<p>An evenly spaced grid in the <em>z</em> plane becomes a very unevenly spaced graph in the&nbsp;<em>w</em> plane. Things are crowded on the right hand side and sparse on the left. A useable Smith chart needs to be roughly evenly filled in, which means it has to be the image of an unevenly filled in grid in the <em>z</em> plane. For example, you’d need more vertical lines in the <em>z</em> plane with small real values than with large real values.</p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Disable AI in Firefox (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://flamedfury.com/posts/disable-ai-in-firefox/</link>
            <guid>45696752</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 17:11:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://flamedfury.com/posts/disable-ai-in-firefox/">https://flamedfury.com/posts/disable-ai-in-firefox/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45696752">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main">
    <article>
      <div>
        


        <p>
          <time datetime="2025-10-24T00:00:00.000Z"> October 24, 2025 </time>

          <a href="https://flamedfury.com/tags/software" data-button-variant="primary" data-small-button="">
            software
          </a>

          <a href="https://flamedfury.com/tags/firefox" data-button-variant="primary" data-small-button="">
            firefox
          </a>


        </p>

        <p>What’s going on, Internet? To the outrage of the Firefox community across the web, Mozilla has started rolling out AI across our beloved browser and has enabled the features by default.</p>
        <p>I’ve found the new Firefox “AI” features, like the pop-ups that appear when highlighting text, to be more distracting than useful. The sidebar chat isn’t something I need either; if I want that experience, I’ll just open ChatGPT in a containerised tab.</p>
        <p>If you’d like to turn these features off, open <code>about:config</code> in the Firefox address bar, search for <code>browser.ml.enable</code>, set it to false, and that should disable everything.</p>
        <p>If you’d rather try some features while disabling others, keep <code>browser.ml.enable</code> set to true and toggle each feature individually.</p>
        <p>I’m giving Smart Tab Groups a try for now, as I’m curious to see how the “AI” handles organising my dozens of open tabs. I’ll let you know how that goes.</p>
        <p>Below is a list of the “AI” features you can disable in <code>about:config</code>, along with a short explanation of what I understand each one does. Enjoy.</p>
        <table>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th>Setting</th>
              <th>What it controls</th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.enable</code></td>
              <td>Master switch for Firefox’s built-in machine-learning platform. Turning this off disables all AI features.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.enabled</code></td>
              <td>Enables the AI chatbot integration.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.sidebar</code></td>
              <td>Shows the AI chat panel in the sidebar.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.shortcuts</code></td>
              <td>Lets you trigger chat from selected text or shortcuts.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.page</code></td>
              <td>Powers the on-page chat menu when you highlight text.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.page.footerBadge</code></td>
              <td>Displays the floating badge at the bottom of the page.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.page.menuBadge</code></td>
              <td>Shows the “Ask AI” badge in the page menu.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.chat.menu</code></td>
              <td>Adds “Chat about this” to right-click menus.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.linkPreview.enabled</code></td>
              <td>Generates AI-based link previews and suggestions.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>extensions.ml.enabled</code></td>
              <td>Allows browser extensions to use Firefox’s ML API.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.ml.pageAssist.enabled</code></td>
              <td>Runs the AI “page assist” summariser/assistant.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.tabs.groups.smart.enabled</code></td>
              <td>Uses AI to automatically group and label your tabs.</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td><code>browser.tabs.groups.smart.userEnable</code></td>
              <td>Lets users manually toggle the smart tab groups feature.</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <p>Later 👋</p>


        <hr>
        <p>
          Reply by <a href="mailto:hello@flamedfury.com?subject=RE:%20Disable%20AI%20In%20Firefox">email</a>, <a href="xmpp:flamed@omg.lol">XMPP</a>, or send a <a href="#webmention">webmention</a>.
        </p>
        <section>


          <p>No mentions yet.</p>


          <form id="webmention" action="https://webmention.io/flamedfury.com/webmention" method="post">
            <label for="form-webmention-source">Have you published a response on your own website?
              Let me know where:</label>
            
          </form>

        </section>

      </div>

      <!-- Author information -->
      
    </article>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Code Like a Surgeon (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2025/10/24/code-like-a-surgeon</link>
            <guid>45695621</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 15:25:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2025/10/24/code-like-a-surgeon">https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2025/10/24/code-like-a-surgeon</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45695621">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A lot of people say AI will make us all “managers” or “editors”…but I think this is a dangerously incomplete view!</p>

<p>Personally, I’m trying to <strong>code like a surgeon.</strong></p>

<p>A surgeon isn’t a manager, they do the actual work! But their skills and time are highly leveraged with a support team that handles prep, secondary tasks, admin. The surgeon focuses on the important stuff they are uniquely good at.</p>

<p>My current goal with AI coding tools is to spend 100% of my time doing stuff that matters. (As a UI prototyper, that mostly means tinkering with design concepts.)</p>

<p>It turns out there are a LOT of secondary tasks which AI agents are now good enough to help out with. Some things I’m finding useful to hand off these days:</p>

<ul>
<li>Before attempting a big task, write a guide to relevant areas of the codebase</li>
<li>Spike out an attempt at a big change. Often I won’t use the result but I’ll review it as a sketch of where to go</li>
<li>Fix typescript errors or bugs which have a clear specification</li>
<li>Write documentation about what I’m building</li>
</ul>

<p>I often find it useful to run these secondary tasks async in the background – while I’m eating lunch, or even literally overnight!</p>

<p>When I sit down for a work session, I want to feel like a surgeon walking into a prepped operating room. Everything is ready for me to do what I’m good at.</p>

<h2 id="mind-the-autonomy-slider">Mind the autonomy slider</h2>

<p>Notably, there is a <em>huge</em> difference between how I use AI for primary vs secondary tasks.</p>

<p>For the core design prototyping work, I still do a lot of coding by hand, and when I do use AI, I’m more careful and in the details. I need fast feedback loops and good visibility. (eg, I like Cursor tab-complete here)</p>

<p>Whereas for secondary tasks, I’m much much looser with it, happy to let an agent churn for hours in the background. The ability to get the job done eventually is the most important thing; speed and visibility matter less. Claude Code has been my go-to for long unsupervised sessions but Codex CLI is becoming a strong contender there too, possibly my new favorite.</p>

<p>These are <em>very</em> different work patterns! Reminds me of Andrej Karpathy’s <a href="https://www.latent.space/p/s3">“autonomy slider”</a> concept. <strong>It’s dangerous to conflate different parts of the autonomy spectrum</strong> – the tools and mindset that are needed vary quite a lot.</p>

<h2 id="your-agent-doesnt-need-a-career-trajectory">Your agent doesn’t need a career trajectory</h2>

<p>The “software surgeon” concept is a very old idea – Fred Brooks attributes it to Harlan Mills in his 1975 classic “The Mythical Man-Month”. He <a href="https://www.embeddedrelated.com/showarticle/1484.php#:~:text=Mills%20proposes%20that%20each%20segment%20of%20a%20large%20job%20be%20tackled%20by%20a%20team%2C%20but%20that%20the%20team%20be%20organized%20like%20a%20surgical%20team%20rather%20than%20a%20hog%2Dbutchering%20team.">talks about</a> a “chief programmer” who is supported by various staff including a “copilot” and various administrators. Of course, at the time, the idea was to have humans be in these support roles.</p>

<p>OK, so there is a super obvious angle here, that “AI has now made this approach economically viable where it wasn’t before”, yes yes… but <strong>I am also noticing a more subtle thing at play, something to do with status hierarchies.</strong></p>

<p>A lot of the “secondary” tasks are “grunt work”, not the most intellectually fulfilling or creative part of the work. I have a strong preference for teams where everyone shares the grunt work; I hate the idea of giving all the grunt work to some lower-status members of the team. Yes, junior members will often have more grunt work, but they should also be given many interesting tasks to help them grow.</p>

<p>With AI this concern completely disappears! <strong>Now I can happily delegate pure grunt work.</strong> And the 24/7 availability is a big deal. I would never call a human intern at 11pm and tell them to have a research report on some code ready by 7am… but here I am, commanding my agent to do just that!</p>

<h2 id="notion-is-for-surgeons">Notion is for surgeons?</h2>

<p>Finally I’ll mention a couple thoughts on how this approach to work intersects with my employer, <a href="https://notion.com/">Notion</a>.</p>

<p>First, as an employee, I find it incredibly valuable right now to work at a place that is bullish on AI coding tools. Having support for heavy use of AI coding tools, and a codebase that’s well setup for it, is enabling serious productivity gains for me – <em>especially</em> as a newcomer to a big codebase.</p>

<p>Secondly, as a product – in a sense I would say we are trying to bring this way of working to a broader group of knowledge workers beyond programmers. When I think about how that will play out, I like the mental model of enabling everyone to “work like a surgeon”.</p>

<p>The goal isn’t to delegate your core work, it’s to <strong>identify and delegate the secondary grunt work tasks, so you can focus on the main thing that matters.</strong></p>

<hr>



<p>If you liked this perspective, you might enjoy reading these other posts I’ve written about the nature of human-AI collaboration:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2025/07/27/enough-ai-copilots-we-need-ai-huds">Enough AI copilots! We need AI HUDs</a>: “anyone serious about designing for AI should consider non-copilot form factors that more directly extend the human mind…”</li>
<li><a href="https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2024/12/22/making-programming-more-fun-with-an-ai-generated-debugger">AI-generated tools can make programming more fun</a>: “Instead, I used AI to build a custom debugger UI… which made it more fun for me to do the coding myself…”</li>
<li><a href="https://www.geoffreylitt.com/2023/02/26/llm-as-muse-not-oracle">ChatGPT as muse, not oracle</a>: “What if we were to think of LLMs not as tools for answering questions, but as tools for asking us questions and inspiring our creativity?</li>
</ul>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Unlocking Free WiFi on British Airways (321 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.saxrag.com/tech/reversing/2025/06/01/BAWiFi.html</link>
            <guid>45695134</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 14:40:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.saxrag.com/tech/reversing/2025/06/01/BAWiFi.html">https://www.saxrag.com/tech/reversing/2025/06/01/BAWiFi.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45695134">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
  <p>
    <time datetime="2025-06-01 00:00:00 +0200">2025-06-01</time>
  </p>

  

  <p>I was recently flying between HKG &amp; LHR via British Airways. I’d done the same flight back in 2023, and remember relying on the in-flight entertainment for the 14 hour journey. However, this time on my way to London, they had an interesting offer: Free WiFi for “Messaging”, for members of “The British Airways Club”.</p>

<p>I was pretty sure I wasn’t a member of any sort of club (I’m only flying economy anyway); but turns out this is just the name of their frequent flyer program. Conveniently enough, you’re able to sign up for this via the captive portal while in the sky; and although it asks for your E-Mail you don’t need to verify it (thereby allowing you to complete the signup without access to the internet).</p>

<p>Once signed in, the captive portal invited me to “Start session”, which true to it’s word, let me start texting people. I tried Whatsapp, Signal, Wechat and Discord. The first three worked (though not for images), Discord expectedly did not. Not bad for free wifi!</p>

<h2 id="how-does-it-know">How does it know?</h2>

<p>This was the first question I had as soon as I confirmed messaging did work. It’s 2025; everything should be encrypted in transit. So how does it know if I’m using Whatsapp vs. Discord? One idea I had is it just somehow capped the bandwidth / data transfer of individual TCP connections; so when you’re sending a single message or two it gets through, but something larger would fail.</p>

<p>To test this, I used my phone to open up the classic: <a href="https://example.com/">example.com</a>. Unfortunately this didn’t load - so there must’ve been a bit more going on…</p>

<p>Thankfully I had my laptop on me, so the next step was to connect to WiFi with the devtools open to the network tab, and wireshark on the side for good measure. After registering for the WiFi again, it was time to play around a bit. Opening up something like <a href="https://example.com/">example.com</a> revealed a TCP reset in the wireshark, right after the Client Hello, and my brain immediately jumped to SNI. It’s something that’s really annoyed me about the TLS spec since it’s widely used by ISPs in India to block websites (although there is work being done to fix this; <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-tls-esni/">ECH</a> (which was itself previously ESNI)).</p>

<p>tl;dr SNI reveals the domain name of EVERY website you connect to in the TLS handshake, before the tunnel is established! Although the actual contents of what you’re doing, on say, totallynondodgywebsite.com are encrypted, anyone on the wire can see that you connected to it (including ISPs). My guess was that they had a set of whitelisted domains used by messaging apps, and if they see anything else, they just reset the connection.</p>

<p>Sidebar: people’s reactions when I try to tell this are always extremely varied. Many of my non-technical friends think anything you do without a VPN is visible to everyone, while some slightly technical ones still think that the URL (including query params) is visible, but the responses are not. Finally there is some subset of people who believe TLS means all data is encrypted in transit between client &amp; server, though they had no idea SNI leaks all the domains they visit!</p>

<h2 id="testing-out-the-theory">Testing out the theory</h2>

<p>Although BA blocks DNS queries to all (well all I could remember) public resolvers, they do resolve any domain you throw at them, including MX, TXT, HTTPS records. (This itself could be an interesting area of exploration; especially since the DNS resolution can be triggered before signing up for free WiFi. Something along the lines of arbitrary subdomains which represent the request payload, and a custom nameserver that returns responses via the TXT record or something. Anyway…).</p>

<p>Getting the A record of my personal server, I made a TLS handshake to the IP address directly, without any SNI. This was then reset by BA; so the lack of SNI is also blocked!</p>

<div><pre><code>$ openssl s_client -connect 95.217.167.10:443
Connecting to 95.217.167.10
CONNECTED(00000003)
write:errno=104
---
no peer certificate available
---
No client certificate CA names sent
---
SSL handshake has read 0 bytes and written 302 bytes
Verification: OK
---
New, (NONE), Cipher is (NONE)
Protocol: TLSv1.3
This TLS version forbids renegotiation.
Compression: NONE
Expansion: NONE
No ALPN negotiated
Early data was not sent
Verify return code: 0 (ok)
---
</code></pre></div>

<p>The next step was to try and test some SNI that might go through. Off the top of my head, I knew <code>wa.me</code> was used by Whatsapp for some stuff, so I decided to use it. The way SNI works is it tells the server which host you want to connect to, so it can present the right TLS certificate. In my case, my server did not have any cert for <code>wa.me</code> , but NGINX seemingly just ignores the SNI if it doesn’t exist and returns the first cert (I think; could also be related to my config but I didn’t look to much into this).</p>

<p>But basically, as long as I (the client) don’t care, I can complete the TLS connection for any random cert the server offers me, even if in the SNI I provide a domain I don’t control (e.g. <code>wa.me</code> in this case).</p>

<div><pre><code>$ openssl s_client -connect 95.217.167.10:443 -servername wa.me
Connecting to 95.217.167.10
CONNECTED(00000003)
depth=2 C=US, O=Internet Security Research Group, CN=ISRG Root X1
verify return:1
depth=1 C=US, O=Let's Encrypt, CN=R3
verify return:1
depth=0 CN=mijia.mywaifu.best
verify error:num=10:certificate has expired
notAfter=Jul 22 13:03:02 2023 GMT
verify return:1
depth=0 CN=mijia.mywaifu.best
notAfter=Jul 22 13:03:02 2023 GMT
verify return:1
---
Certificate chain
&lt;snip&gt;
</code></pre></div>

<p>Success! Using a Whatsapp SNI tricked BA into thinking I’m “messaging”, which allowed the TLS tunnel to be established. Since I am connected to the server, to make sure it works I wrote an HTTP/1.1 request within the socket; using the host header of a real website on my NGINX instance</p>

<div><pre><code>GET / HTTP/1.1
Host: saxrag.com

HTTP/1.1 200 OK
Server: nginx/1.18.0 (Ubuntu)
Date: Fri, 09 May 2025 19:14:46 GMT
Content-Type: text/html
Content-Length: 4968
Last-Modified: Wed, 09 Apr 2025 07:52:54 GMT
Connection: keep-alive
ETag: "67f62756-1368"
Cache-Control: no-cache
Accept-Ranges: bytes
&lt;snip&gt;
</code></pre></div>

<p>I successfully managed to request and receive my homepage! All ~5KiB of it, not bad. Now the challenge was to extend this to browse any website…</p>

<h2 id="enemies-to-lovers">Enemies to Lovers</h2>

<p>Ok, my relationship with SNI isn’t as cliche as that, and I think we’re still enemies. But this opens up some exciting opportunities to say the least. If I can convince BA that I’m connecting to <code>wa.me</code>, I can potentially do whatever I want over that connection (under the guise of “messaging”). So the requirments were:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Establish a TLS connection using the SNI <code>wa.me</code></li>
  <li>Tunnel arbitrary traffic through that connection</li>
  <li>Do all this without actually owning / controlling the <code>wa.me</code> domain</li>
</ul>

<p>From my past experiences w/ reverse-engineering etc., the most obvious way to do this seemed to be an HTTPS proxy. It had to be HTTPS specifically, since the connection to proxy was going to be what I’d “fake” as Whatsapp. If the TLS handshake to the HTTPS proxy had the SNI <code>wa.me</code> , BA <em>should</em> let it through, and then I can make the real requests I want via the proxy.</p>

<p>Unfortunately I was in the air, and without easy access to the internet to manage my servers and the like, I couldn’t quite set all of this up; I’d have to do that while on holiday and test it on the flight back. I could <em>try</em> and emulate the BA restrictions etc. while on thr ground, but I decided to YOLO it.</p>

<h2 id="the-setup">The Setup</h2>

<p>I managed to find one of my VPSs that wasn’t already using port 443. Let’s assume the public IP was <code>333.333.333.333</code> (yes I know octets don’t go beyond <code>0xFF</code>, if you really want my IP check the screenshots below). I then setup an HTTP proxy on it using <a href="https://github.com/tinyproxy/tinyproxy">tinyproxy</a>. However this just sets up a basic HTTP proxy, which was listening on <code>127.0.0.1:8080</code>.</p>

<p>To add the TLS layer, I used <a href="https://www.stunnel.org/">stunnel</a>. For the TLS setup of stunnel, I just generated some self-signed certs via openSSL using all defaults, except the common name (CN), for which I used <code>wa.me</code>, since I wanted to try and ensure max compatibility (e.g. the client doesn’t reject due to unexpected SNI vs. CN, or the server not knowing which cert to provide).</p>
<div><pre><code>openssl req -nodes -newkey ed25519 -keyout ssl.key -x509 -days 365 -out ssl.crt
</code></pre></div>

<p><strong>UPDATE:</strong> actually, on the client I decided to ignore TLS errors (self-signed cert), and stunnel didn’t care about SNI, so this (<code>CN</code>) didn’t matter too much. But for more legit use cases it definitely does!</p>

<h2 id="testing-it-out">Testing it out</h2>

<p>To just make sure the proxy worked as expected, I tried it via curl directly on the IP:</p>

<div><pre><code>$ curl -x https://user:pass@333.333.333.333:443 ifconfig.co -v
*   Trying 333.333.333.333:443...
* TLSv1.3 (OUT), TLS handshake, Client hello (1):
*  CAfile: /etc/ssl/certs/ca-certificates.crt
*  CApath: none
* TLSv1.3 (IN), TLS handshake, Server hello (2):
* TLSv1.3 (IN), TLS change cipher, Change cipher spec (1):
* TLSv1.3 (IN), TLS handshake, Encrypted Extensions (8):
* TLSv1.3 (IN), TLS handshake, Certificate (11):
* TLSv1.3 (OUT), TLS alert, unknown CA (560):
* SSL certificate problem: self-signed certificate
* closing connection #0
curl: (60) SSL certificate problem: self-signed certificate
More details here: https://curl.se/docs/sslcerts.html

curl failed to verify the legitimacy of the server and therefore could not
establish a secure connection to it. To learn more about this situation and
how to fix it, please visit the webpage mentioned above.
</code></pre></div>

<p>Of course! I just randomly generated the certs on my VPS, not signed by a “trusted” CA or anything. Well, we can tell cURL to ignore TLS errors for the proxy with the <code>--proxy-insecure</code> flag, and now it works; the response is the IP of my VPS.</p>

<p>However there’s a problem - if I connect to the proxy directly via the IP, there is no SNI extension set, so this would get blocked. The SNI extension is set when connection to a domain, so I need to configure <code>wa.me</code> to point to <code>333.333.333.333</code>. This can be done via the hosts file of course, but cURL also provides <a href="https://curl.se/mail/archive-2015-01/0042.html">a quick CLI hack via <code>--resolve</code></a>:</p>

<div><pre><code>curl --resolve wa.me:443:333.333.333.333 -x https://username:password@wa.me ifconfig.co --proxy-insecure -v
</code></pre></div>

<p>This tells cURL how to resolve the IP. With this, I could now see the SNI being set to <code>wa.me</code> via wireshark, and the connection to the proxy succeeding (TLS errors about the self-signed cert ignored of course). Not bad, now time to wait for my flight back to Hong Kong…</p>

<h2 id="testing-it-in-flight">Testing it in-flight</h2>

<p>If I’d messed something up, I was cooked, since without internet access I wouldn’t be able to fix it! My flight back was at 1935hrs local time, but I’d been up since 0400 thanks to an early morning flight in from Edinburgh, and then spent the day browsing the markets, having pints and watching the Emilia Romagna Grand Prix. The place I went to even had screens above the urinals!</p>

<p>Anyway, despite being up for ~16 hours already, I was ready to see if my work would, well, work. Once we were sky-high, I connected to the WiFi (from my laptop), signed up for the BA loyalty program, and activated the “Messaging” plan. Trying the curl command from above, I got back an HTTP 200 from <code>ifconfig.co</code> with my VPS IP; it worked! For good measure I tried cURLing some more websites like example.com, google.com etc. to make sure stuff seemed fine.</p>

<p>The next challenge was to extend this to web browsing. Thankfully most modern browsers support sending traffic through an HTTPS proxy, and chromium even has a flag to disable TLS cert warnings (so it won’t complain about my self-signed cert, which obviously doesn’t belong to the real <code>wa.me</code>).</p>

<p>I also had to set a DNS record for <code>wa.me</code> to <code>333.333.333.333</code> in my hosts file, so chromium would set the SNI to <code>wa.me</code> in the TLS handshake, but the connection would be made to my VPS. Since the bandwidth would probably be quite limited (owing to not just the internet on an airplane, but proxying it via a VPS in Netherlands), I decided to load a very simple, text-heavy website: <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/">Hacker News</a>.</p>

<picture>
  <source srcset="https://saxrag.com/bucket/ba/hn_wireshark.avif" type="image/avif">
  <img src="https://saxrag.com/bucket/ba/hn_wireshark.png">
</picture>

<p>Bada bing bada boom! Looks like we cooked. I can actually browse HN using BA’s free “messaging” WiFi! (Note: the reason you can see the HTTP requests in plaintext in wireshark is because I used <a href="https://everything.curl.dev/usingcurl/tls/sslkeylogfile.html">SSLKEYLOGFILE</a> and configured wireshark to decrypt TLS).</p>

<p>Unfortunately, trying to load websites with heavier assets would fail, with images on simple text blogs loading line-by-line. Well, at least its some dial-up nostalgia!</p>

<picture>
  <source srcset="https://saxrag.com/bucket/ba/image_loading.avif" type="image/avif">
  <img src="https://saxrag.com/bucket/ba/image_loading.png">
</picture>

<p>My guess is that on the free WiFi, apart from the SNI checks, they also throttle the bandwidth. Maybe they anticipated this kind of circumvention. On the other hand, if this is really the internet speed that the full plan unlocks…</p>

<h2 id="bonus-ech">Bonus: ECH</h2>

<p>Earlier above I talked about <a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-tls-esni/">work being done to fix the SNI leakage: ECH</a>. The scope of explaining how it works is out of scope here, but I do encourage you to read up on it. Pretty good stuff! It’ll help this section make more sense.</p>

<p><a href="https://rfc5746.mywaifu.best:4443/">I operate an ECH test website</a>, so I decided to do some more setup before my flight. I basically created <em>another</em> ECHConfig, with the public_name set to <code>wa.me</code>. <a href="https://ckcr4lyf.github.io/tech-notes/services/nginx/nginx-ech.html#generating-a-new-echconfig">I’ve a bit of a guide on how to do this btw</a>, though it could do with some improvements.</p>

<p>Anyway, since ECH world, the public SNI is purely for the server to complete the outer ClientHello, and since ECH clients set the public SNI based on the ECHConfig, I can <a href="https://rfc5746.mywaifu.best:7443/">type in my real domain</a> in firefox, which will still use the <code>wa.me</code> domain as the public SNI. The inner Client Hello will then occur securely, containing the real SNI of <code>rfc5746.mywaifu.best</code>, and the handshake will complete with the “legit” CA-signed certificate for that domain.</p>

<picture>
  <source srcset="https://saxrag.com/bucket/ba/ech.avif" type="image/avif">
  <img src="https://saxrag.com/bucket/ba/ech.png">
</picture>

<p>This worked as well, and without any TLS ignore flags, since the actual cert for <code>rfc5746.mywaifu.best</code> was signed by a “trusted CA” (Let’s Encrypt). What’s more interesting is that this worked even on a non-standart TLS port: <code>7443</code>! Not sure exactly why, but I’m not complaining.</p>

<h3 id="a-note-on-echconfig-resolution">A note on ECHConfig resolution</h3>

<p>Typically, ECHConfigs should be resolved via encrypted DNS, such as DNS-over-HTTPS. I believe this is what firefox does by default. I am not 100% sure if this is what happened while I was in flight, since I’d think the DoH would be blocked on messaging WiFi? Or maybe they allow the DoH SNI as well, since newer phones default to that. If any of you are flying BA anytime soon, try it out and let me know!</p>

<h2 id="sni-dont-blindly-trust-it">SNI: Don’t blindly trust it</h2>

<p>SNI, as the name indicates (sorry) is just a “hint” of sorts, from the client to the server. If someone controls both sides (client &amp; server), they can put whatever fake value they want in here, for middleboxes to sniff out and try to analyze. While this unfortunately does work for applications like censorship (<a href="https://cis-india.org/internet-governance/blog/reliance-jio-is-using-sni-inspection-to-block-websites">where an ISP</a> or country is trying to block a particular website), for use cases such as threat detection it should not be relied on; malwre authors can “spoof” the SNI when connecting to their C&amp;C, since they don’t actually need it, but it may look more innocent to middleboxes.</p>

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[First shape found that can't pass through itself (404 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/first-shape-found-that-cant-pass-through-itself-20251024/</link>
            <guid>45694856</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 14:12:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/first-shape-found-that-cant-pass-through-itself-20251024/">https://www.quantamagazine.org/first-shape-found-that-cant-pass-through-itself-20251024/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45694856">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="postBody">
                <div>
        <p>
            After more than three centuries, a geometry problem that originated with a royal bet has been solved.        </p>
        
    </div>
<figure>
    
</figure>
<div>
            <h2>Introduction</h2>
            <div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Imagine you’re holding two equal-size dice. Is it possible to bore a tunnel through one die that’s big enough for the other to slide through?</p>
<p>Perhaps your instinct is to say “Surely not!” If so, you’re not alone. In the late 1600s, an unidentified person placed a bet to that effect with Prince Rupert of the Rhine. Rupert — a nephew of Charles I of England who commanded the Royalist forces in the English Civil War — spent his sunset years studying metallurgy and glassmaking in his laboratory at Windsor Castle.</p>
<p>Rupert won the bet. The mathematician John Wallis, recounting the story in 1693, didn’t say whether Rupert wrote a proof or bored a hole through an actual cube. But Wallis himself proved mathematically that, if you drill a straight tunnel in the direction of one of the cube’s inner diagonals, it can be made wide enough to allow another cube through. It’s a tight squeeze: If you make the second cube just 4% larger, it will no longer fit.</p>
<p>It’s natural to wonder which other shapes have this property. “I think of this problem as being quite canonical,” said <a href="http://tom7.org/">Tom Murphy</a>, a software engineer at Google who has explored the question extensively in his free time. It “would have gotten rediscovered and rediscovered — aliens would have come to this one.”</p>
</div>
    </div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Self_Containing_Shapes-Fig1-crMarkBelan-Mobilev1.svg" alt="Panels showing a blue cube passing through an equal-size yellow cube." decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Self_Containing_Shapes-Fig1-crMarkBelan-Desktopv1.svg" alt="Panels showing a blue cube passing through an equal-size yellow cube." decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>Tip a cube on its corner, and another can pass through.</p>
            <p>Mark Belan/<em>Quanta Magazine</em></p>
        </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>The full menagerie of shapes is too diverse to get a handle on, so mathematicians tend to focus on convex polyhedra: shapes, like the cube, that have flat sides and no protrusions or indentations. When such a shape is much wider in some directions than others, it’s usually easy to find a straight tunnel that will allow another copy of the shape to pass through. But many famous convex polyhedra — for instance the dodecahedron, or the truncated icosahedron, the shape that forms a soccer ball — are highly symmetric and difficult to analyze. Among these, “for hundreds of years we only knew of the cube,” said Jakob Steininger, a mathematician at Statistics Austria, Austria’s federal statistics organization.</p>
<p>Then, in 1968, Christoph Scriba proved that the <a href="https://mathscinet.ams.org/mathscinet/relay-station?mr=0497615">tetrahedron and octahedron</a> also have the “Rupert property,” as mathematicians now call it. And in a burst of activity over the past decade, professional mathematicians and hobbyists have found Rupert tunnels through many of the most widely studied convex polyhedra, including the <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.4169/math.mag.90.2.87">dodecahedron, icosahedron</a> and <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00029890.2018.1449505">soccer ball</a>.</p>
<p>The Rupert property appeared to be so widespread that mathematicians conjectured a general rule: Every convex polyhedron <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00029890.2018.1449505">will have the Rupert property</a>. No one could find one that didn’t — until now.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Self_Containing_Shapes-Fig2-crMarkBelan-Mobilev1.svg" alt="A polyhedron with 152 faces." decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Self_Containing_Shapes-Fig2-crMarkBelan-Desktopv1.svg" alt="A polyhedron with 152 faces." decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>The Noperthedron. To date, it’s the only shape proved to not have Rupert’s property.</p>
                    </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>In a paper posted online in August, Steininger and <a href="https://yurkevi.ch/">Sergey Yurkevich</a> — a researcher at A&amp;R Tech, an Austrian transportation systems company — describe a shape with 90 vertices and 152 faces that they’ve named the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18475">Noperthedron</a> (after “Nopert,” a coinage by Murphy that combines “Rupert” and “nope”). Steininger and Yurkevich proved that no matter how you bore a straight tunnel through a Noperthedron, a second Noperthedron cannot fit through.</p>
<p>The proof required a mix of theoretical advances and massive computer calculations, and relies on a delicate property of the Noperthedron’s vertices. “It’s a miracle that it works,” Steininger said.</p>
<h2><strong>Passing Through the Shadows</strong></h2>
<p>To see how one cube can pass through another, imagine holding a cube over a table and examining its shadow (assuming it’s illuminated from above). If you hold the cube in the standard position, the shadow is a square. But if you point one of the corners directly upward, the shadow is a regular hexagon.</p>
<p>In 1693, Wallis showed that the square shadow fits inside the hexagon, leaving a thin margin. That means that if you point a cube’s corner upward, you can bore a vertical tunnel that’s big enough for a second cube to pass through. About a century later, Pieter Nieuwland showed that a different orientation casts an even better shadow — one that can accommodate a cube more than 6% larger than the cube with the tunnel.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/How_Can_A_Shape_Pass_Through_Itself-crMarkBelan-Mobilev1.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/How_Can_A_Shape_Pass_Through_Itself-crMarkBelan-Desktopv1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
            <p>Mark Belan/<em>Quanta Magazine</em></p>
        </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Every subsequent analysis of more complicated shapes has relied on this process of turning the shape in different directions and looking for one shadow that fits inside another. With the aid of computers, mathematicians have found Rupert passages through a wide variety of shapes. Some are incredibly tight fits — for instance, the passage in a “triakis tetrahedron” has a margin that’s only about 0.000002 times the length of the shape’s radius. “The world of mixing computation and discrete geometry has flowered to make these kinds of calculations possible,” said <a href="https://www.smith.edu/people/joseph-orourke">Joseph O’Rourke</a>, an emeritus professor at Smith College.</p>
<p>Researchers who have written algorithms to find Rupert passages have noticed a curious dichotomy: For any given convex polyhedron, the algorithm seems to either find a passage almost immediately, or not find one at all. In the past five years, mathematicians have accumulated a small collection of holdout shapes for which no passage has been found.</p>
<p>“I’ve had my desktop churn for two weeks on trying the rhombicosidodecahedron,” said <a href="https://www.ams.jhu.edu/~grimmer/">Benjamin Grimmer</a>, an applied mathematician at Johns Hopkins University, referring to a solid made of 62 regular triangles, squares and pentagons. “That one just seems to resist any attempt.”</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Self_Containing_Shapes-Fig3-crMarkBelan-Mobilev1.svg" alt="Polyhedron with 62 faces." decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Self_Containing_Shapes-Fig3-crMarkBelan-Desktopv1.svg" alt="Polyhedron with 62 faces." decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>The rhombicosidodecahedron is a leading Nopert candidate.</p>
                    </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>But such resistance doesn’t prove that a shape is a Nopert. There are infinitely many ways to orient a shape, and a computer can only check finitely many. Researchers don’t know whether the holdouts are true Noperts or just shapes whose Rupert passages are hard to find.</p>
<p>What they do know is that candidate Noperts are incredibly rare. Starting last year, Murphy began to <a href="http://tom7.org/ruperts/ruperts.pdf">construct hundreds of millions of shapes</a>. These include random polyhedra, polyhedra whose vertices lie on a sphere, polyhedra with special symmetries, and polyhedra in which he moved one vertex to intentionally mess up a previous Rupert passage. His algorithm easily found Rupert tunnels for nearly every one.</p>
<p>The contrast between these quick results and the stubbornness of the Nopert holdouts made some mathematicians suspect that true Noperts do exist. But until August, all they had were suspicions.</p>
<h2><strong>No Passage</strong></h2>
<p>Steininger, now 30, and Yurkevich, 29, have been friends since they participated together as teenagers in mathematics Olympiad competitions. Even though both eventually left academia (after a doctorate for Yurkevich and a master’s for Steininger), they have continued to explore unsolved problems together.</p>
<p>“We just had pizza three hours ago, and we talked about math almost the whole time,” Steininger told <em>Quanta</em>. “That’s what we do.”</p>
<p>Five years ago, the pair happened upon a YouTube video of one cube passing through another, and they were instantly smitten. They developed an algorithm to search for Rupert tunnels and soon became convinced that some shapes were Noperts. In a 2021 paper, they conjectured that <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.13754">the rhombicosidodecahedron is not Rupert</a>. Their work, which preceded Murphy’s and Grimmer’s recent explorations, was, “I think, the first to conjecture that there might be solids that don’t have this property,” Steininger said.</p>
<p>If you want to prove that a shape is a Nopert, you must rule out Rupert tunnels for every possible orientation of the two shapes. Each orientation can be written down as a collection of rotation angles. This collection of angles can then be represented as a point in a higher-dimensional “parameter space.”</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img width="1600" height="1165" src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/SergeyYurkevich-cr.Florentina-Stadlbauer.webp" alt="A smiling man sitting at a desk" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/SergeyYurkevich-cr.Florentina-Stadlbauer.webp 1600w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/SergeyYurkevich-cr.Florentina-Stadlbauer-520x379.webp 520w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/SergeyYurkevich-cr.Florentina-Stadlbauer-768x559.webp 768w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/SergeyYurkevich-cr.Florentina-Stadlbauer-1536x1118.webp 1536w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/SergeyYurkevich-cr.Florentina-Stadlbauer-98x71.webp 98w" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px">                </p>
                                <p><img width="1600" height="1504" src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JakobSteininger-cr.Courtesy-of-Jakob-Steininger-2-1.webp" alt="A smiling man with glasses sitting on a couch" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JakobSteininger-cr.Courtesy-of-Jakob-Steininger-2-1.webp 1600w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JakobSteininger-cr.Courtesy-of-Jakob-Steininger-2-1-520x489.webp 520w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JakobSteininger-cr.Courtesy-of-Jakob-Steininger-2-1-768x722.webp 768w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JakobSteininger-cr.Courtesy-of-Jakob-Steininger-2-1-1536x1444.webp 1536w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/JakobSteininger-cr.Courtesy-of-Jakob-Steininger-2-1-98x92.webp 98w" sizes="(max-width: 1600px) 100vw, 1600px">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>Sergey Yurkevich (left) and Jakob Steininger, friends since their teenage years, enjoy working on math problems together, even though neither has remained in academia.</p>
            <p>Florentina Stadlbauer; Courtesy of Jakob Steininger</p>
        </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Suppose you choose an orientation for your two shapes, and the computer tells you that the second shadow sticks out past the border of the first shadow. This rules out one point in the parameter space.</p>
<p>But you may be able to rule out much more than a single point. If the second shadow sticks out significantly, it would require a big change to move it inside the first shadow. In other words, you can rule out not just your initial orientation but also “nearby” orientations — an entire block of points in the parameter space. Steininger and Yurkevich came up with a result they called their global theorem, which quantifies precisely how large a block you can rule out in these cases. By testing many different points, you can potentially rule out block after block in the parameter space.</p>
<p>If these blocks cover the entire parameter space, you’ll have proved that your shape is a Nopert. But the size of each block depends on how far the second shadow sticks out beyond the first, and sometimes it doesn’t stick out very far. For instance, suppose you start with the two shapes in exactly the same position, and then you slightly rotate the second shape. Its shadow will at most stick out just a tiny bit past the first shadow, so the global theorem will only rule out a tiny box. These boxes are too small to cover the whole parameter space, leaving the possibility that some point you’ve missed might correspond to a Rupert tunnel.</p>

<p>To deal with these small reorientations, the pair came up with a complement to their global theorem that they called the local theorem. This result deals with cases where you can find three vertices (or corner points) on the boundary of the original shadow that satisfy some special requirements. For instance, if you connect those three vertices to form a triangle, it must contain the shadow’s center point. The researchers showed that if these requirements are met, then any small reorientation of the shape will create a shadow that pushes at least one of the three vertices further outward. So the new shadow can’t lie inside the original shadow, meaning it doesn’t create a Rupert tunnel.</p>
<p>If your shape casts a shadow that lacks three appropriate vertices, the local theorem won’t apply. And all the previously identified Nopert candidates have at least one shadow with this problem. Steininger and Yurkevich sifted through a database of hundreds of the most symmetric and beautiful convex polyhedra, but they couldn’t find any shape whose shadows all worked. So they decided to generate a suitable shape themselves.</p>
<p>They developed an algorithm to construct shapes and test them for the three-vertices property. Eventually, the algorithm produced the Noperthedron, which is made of 150 triangles and two regular 15-sided polygons. It looks like a rotund crystal vase with a wide base and top; one fan of the work has already 3D-printed a copy to use as a <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/fractalkitty.com/post/3lxkvjiqa2c2p">pencil holder</a>.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img width="2202" height="2560" src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-scaled.webp" alt="Painting of a man in a wig." decoding="async" srcset="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-scaled.webp 2202w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-1480x1720.webp 1480w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-447x520.webp 447w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-768x893.webp 768w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-1321x1536.webp 1321w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-1762x2048.webp 1762w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/PrinceRupertoftheRhine-cr.By-Peter-Lely-PublicDomain-1-98x114.webp 98w" sizes="(max-width: 2202px) 100vw, 2202px">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>Prince Rupert of the Rhine, a 17th-century army officer, naval commander, colonial governor and gentleman scientist, won a bet about whether it’s possible to pass a cube through another.</p>
            <p>Peter Lely</p>
        </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Steininger and Yurkevich then divided the parameter space of orientations into approximately 18 million tiny blocks, and tested the center point of each block to see if its corresponding orientation produced a Rupert passage. None of them did. Next, the researchers showed that each block satisfied either the local or global theorem, allowing them to rule out the entire block. Since these blocks fill out the entire parameter space, this meant that there is no Rupert passage through the Noperthedron.</p>
        
        
<p>The “natural conjecture has been proved false,” O’Rourke said.</p>
<p>It remains to be seen whether mathematicians can use the new method to generate other Noperts, or if they can find a different local theorem that can handle candidates like the rhombicosidodecahedron. But now that mathematicians know that Noperts do exist, “we’re on sound footing to study other shapes,” Murphy said.</p>
<p>Murphy, who like Steininger and Yurkevich has been exploring the question for its own sake, independent of his day job, feels a kinship across the centuries with Prince Rupert. “I like that he chose to use his retirement to do math and science in his castle,” he said.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, Steininger and Yurkevich are on the lookout for new questions to tackle. “We’re just humble mathematicians — we love working on such problems,” Steininger said. “We’ll keep doing that.”</p>
</div>
                
                
            </div><div>
        <div data-name="next-post__image-wrapper">
    <p><img width="1720" height="728" src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-1720x728.webp" alt="A tangle of stock tickers" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-1720x728.webp 1720w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-520x220.webp 520w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-768x325.webp 768w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-1536x650.webp 1536w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-2048x867.webp 2048w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/10/Algorithmic-Collusion-cr-Nash-Weerasekera-HP-98x41.webp 98w" sizes="(max-width: 1720px) 100vw, 1720px">    </p>
</div>
        
        <div>
                <h2>Next article</h2>
                <p>The Game Theory of How Algorithms Can Drive Up Prices</p>
            </div>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Asahi Linux Still Working on Apple M3 Support, M1n1 Bootloader Going Rust (293 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.phoronix.com/news/Asahi-Linux-M3-m1n1-Update</link>
            <guid>45694767</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 14:03:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Asahi-Linux-M3-m1n1-Update">https://www.phoronix.com/news/Asahi-Linux-M3-m1n1-Update</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45694767">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><img alt="APPLE" src="https://www.phoronix.com/assets/categories/apple.webp" width="100" height="100"></p><p>
The Asahi Linux developers involved with working on Linux support for Apple Silicon M-Series devices have put out a new progress report on their development efforts.
</p><p>
Asahi Linux developers have kept working on new kernel patches and some being upstreamed for Linux 6.17 and 6.18 cycles, as previously covered on Phoronix. Notably with Linux 6.18 is <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-6.18-SoC-DT-Changes">the Device Trees for the Apple M2 Pro / Max / Ultra devices</a> albeit more driver code is still working its way upstream.
</p><p>
Asahi Linux developers are also working on moving toward the Rust programming language with their important m1n1 bootloader for Apple Silicon. They feel going to Rust is important for such a critical piece of software for better maintainability, safety, and ensuring the correct logic.
</p><p>
Asahi Linux developers have also made progress on getting more games working on Apple Silicon devices. Wine is also now working outside of muvm and their graphics driver support continues maturing:
</p><p><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=2025&amp;image=asahi_october" alt="Asahi Linux running a game"></p>
<p>With the upstream Linux kernel work around Apple Silicon so far being focused on Apple M1 and M2, you may be wondering about M3 and M4 or the recently announced M5... They still are battling Apple M3 bring-up. Today's progress report comments:
</p><blockquote>"It may be surprising to learn that very basic, low-level support for M3 has existed for quite some time now. m1n1 is capable of initialising the CPU cores, turning on some critical peripheral devices, and booting the Asahi kernel. However, the level of support right now begins and ends with being able to boot to a blinking cursor. Naturally, this level of support is not at all useful for anything but low-level reverse engineering, but we of course plan on rectifying this in due time..."</blockquote>
<p>See the progress report in full over on <a href="https://asahilinux.org/2025/10/progress-report-6-17/">AsahiLinux.org</a>.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A sharded DuckDB on 63 nodes runs 1T row aggregation challenge in 5 sec (213 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gizmodata.com/blog/gizmoedge-one-trillion-row-challenge</link>
            <guid>45694122</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 12:54:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gizmodata.com/blog/gizmoedge-one-trillion-row-challenge">https://gizmodata.com/blog/gizmoedge-one-trillion-row-challenge</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45694122">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Typst 0.14 (593 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://typst.app/blog/2025/typst-0.14/</link>
            <guid>45693978</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 12:33:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://typst.app/blog/2025/typst-0.14/">https://typst.app/blog/2025/typst-0.14/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45693978">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-astro-cid-4eu74nwj=""> <div data-astro-cid-4eu74nwj="">  <p><strong data-astro-cid-4eu74nwj=""> <p data-astro-cid-4eu74nwj="">Typst 0.14 is out now. With accessibility by default, PDFs as images, character-level justification, and more, it has everything you need to move from draft to production.
</p> </strong></p> </div> <p>Typst's origins lie in academia, but over the past year, we've seen it expand to so much more. It's increasingly being used in the industry: For manually written documents, partially automated reports, and in fully automated batch PDF generation pipelines. Across these use cases, it's being used in production for critical documents.</p>
<p>In August, we <a href="https://typst.app/blog/2025/future">launched a new website</a> to reflect Typst's expanding scope, and now, with Typst 0.14, we're shipping crucial features that make Typst even more widely applicable.</p>
<p>If you need to comply with accessibility-related regulations, Typst 0.14 has your back. Typst now generates accessible documents <em>by default,</em> with opt-in support for stricter checks. For those working with complex illustrations, PDFs are now supported as a native image format. In case you're typesetting a book, the new character-level justification will give your layout the final touch. And if you're building a website or blog, many improvements to Typst's HTML export are waiting for you.</p>
<h2 id="contents">Contents</h2>
<p>In this blog post, we'll take a closer look at the highlights of this release:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="#accessibility">Accessibility</a></li>
<li><a href="#pdf-standards">PDF standards</a></li>
<li><a href="#pdfs-as-images">PDFs as images</a></li>
<li><a href="#character-level-justification">Character-level justification</a></li>
<li><a href="#richer-html-export">Richer HTML export</a></li>
<li><a href="#migrating">Migrating to Typst 0.14</a></li>
<li><a href="#community-call">Community Call</a></li>
</ul>
<p>To get started with Typst 0.14…</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>…in the web app:</strong> Just open any of your projects! You'll get a prompt offering you to upgrade to the latest version.</li>
<li><strong>…in the command line:</strong> Run <code>typst update</code> in your terminal or, if you haven't installed Typst previously, download the <a href="https://typst.app/open-source/#download">latest version of the CLI</a>.</li>
</ul>
<p>For a comprehensive overview of all changes in the release, visit the <a href="https://typst.app/docs/changelog/0.14.0/">changelog</a>. If you're looking to upgrade your document to Typst 0.14, you can also skip ahead to the <a href="#migrating">Migration section</a>.</p>
<h2 id="accessibility">Accessibility</h2>
<p>Not everyone reads PDF documents the same. Some people read on large screens or print; others use small phones or screen readers to have documents read aloud. To cater to all these uses, a file must contain <em>tags</em> that allow Assistive Technology (AT) like screen readers to learn about the reading order and semantic meaning of each piece of text. Tags allow AT users to learn which text is <code><span>*strongly emphasized*</span></code>, enable navigation of the document by skipping between headings, and more.</p>
<p>Tagging requires no additional work from you: If you are using the built-in markup and elements, Typst will automatically select the right tags! Unlike many other tools, PDF files created with Typst 0.14 are tagged by default, raising the bar for accessibility.</p>
<p>But tags are not enough to make a file accessible: To reach everyone, you need to design for universal accessibility from the start. The new features in Typst 0.14 can help you with that. Consider diagrams created with shapes or packages like cetz—their visual meaning is invisible to assistive technology. The new <code>alt</code> parameter on figures solves this:</p>
<div><pre><code><span>#</span><span>figure</span><span>(</span>
  <span>stack</span><span>(</span>
    dir<span>:</span> ltr<span>,</span>
    spacing<span>:</span> <span>0.5em</span><span>,</span>
    <span>rect</span><span>[</span>Tagged PDF<span>]</span><span>,</span>
    <span>text</span><span>(</span><span>2em</span><span>,</span> sym<span>.</span>arrow<span>.</span>long<span>)</span><span>,</span>
    <span>rect</span><span>[</span>Accessibility<span>]</span><span>,</span>
  <span>)</span><span>,</span>
  alt<span>:</span> <span>"Diagram with two rectangles. The first is labelled 'Tagged PDF'. An arrow points to the second, labelled 'Accessibility'"</span><span>,</span>
  caption<span>:</span> <span>[</span>
    Tags enable PDF accessibility
  <span>]</span><span>,</span>
<span>)</span>
</code></pre><p><img src="https://typst.app/assets/docs/pl7jZuMd4U0DyWwVHtHHPwAAAAAAAAAA.png" alt="Preview" width="600" height="123"></p></div>
<p>With this change, AT users hear the alternative description and can grasp the figure's purpose just like sighted users—no information is lost. We have put together a new <a href="https://typst.app/docs/guides/accessibility/">Accessibility Guide</a> that contains more tips on how to create accessible documents, including how to write good alternative descriptions, when to use the figure's vs. the image's <code>alt</code> parameter, and more.</p>
<p>To make sure you got everything right, you can enable the new PDF/UA-1 export. PDF/UA is an international standard that helps to create universally accessible PDF files. When it is enabled, Typst will run additional checks against your document to find accessibility issues and optimize for accessibility rather than compatibility. It will find issues such as missing document titles, wrong heading hierarchies, and missing alternative descriptions.</p>
<p>PDF/UA-1 helps you comply with existing and upcoming international accessibility regulation like the European Accessibility Act (EAA) in the EU and the new Americans with Disabilities Act's (ADA) Title II guidance by the DOJ. The former applies to many businesses active in the European Union since 28 June 2025 while the deadline for the latter is set for April 24, 2026. If you are using Typst in your business for customer- or government-facing documents, you should adopt Typst 0.14 as soon as possible.</p>
<h2 id="pdf-standards">PDF standards</h2>
<p>Alongside PDF/UA-1 support, we've also generally expanded Typst's support for PDF standards. Instead of just PDF 1.7, you can now choose between the PDF versions 1.4, 1.5, 1.6, 1.7, and 2.0. And for PDF/A, we've expanded support from just two specific substandards to all four parts with all their conformance levels. While Typst's defaults are perfectly fine for most use cases, choosing a standard can optimize your document specifically for your use case. Consult the expanded <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/pdf/#pdf-standards">PDF documentation in the reference</a> for guidance on which standards you should pick under which circumstances.</p>
<p><img src="https://typst.app/assets/images/blog/pdf-modal-014.webp" alt="A modal with the title 'PDF export'. It allows changing page range, PDF version, PDF standard, and whether the file is tagged. In the standards category, PDF/UA-1 is enabled, two checkmarks report that the standard is accessible and allows file attachments. Due to the selection, the Tagged PDF checkbox is selected and cannot be unchecked." width="310" height="271"></p><h2 id="pd-fs-as-images">PDFs as images</h2>
<p>Staying with the PDF theme, there are exciting news for authors that have a lot of complex illustrations. Typst now supports PDF as a native image format. What I personally find most exciting about it, is that PDF images are supported <em>across all export targets,</em> and for each export target in the most suitable format. In PDF export, PDFs are naturally directly embedded. Meanwhile, in HTML and SVG export, PDFs are converted to an embedded SVG on-the-fly. And, finally, in PNG export and the web app preview, PDFs are rasterized. All of this PDF processing functionality lives right in the Typst compiler, with no system dependencies. This is only possible thanks to the amazing work of community member <a href="https://github.com/LaurenzV">@LaurenzV</a>, who created a new PDF processing library called <a href="https://github.com/LaurenzV/hayro"><code>hayro</code></a> from scratch. The library is 100% written in the programming language Rust (which is also the language we use for the Typst compiler) and is thus highly portable.</p>
<div><pre><code><span>#</span><span>figure</span><span>(</span>
  <span>image</span><span>(</span>
    <span>"throwing-success.pdf"</span><span>,</span>
    alt<span>:</span> <span>"A diagram titled 'Throwing Success' that .."</span>
  <span>)</span><span>,</span>
  caption<span>:</span> <span>[</span>
    Effect of normalized thrust
    on X and Y position of
    thrown emojis
  <span>]</span><span>,</span>
<span>)</span>
</code></pre><p><img src="https://typst.app/assets/docs/eiWi60penyPIoLH9eF80JwAAAAAAAAAA.png" alt="Preview" width="480" height="433"></p></div>
<h2 id="character-level-justification">Character-level justification</h2>
<p>Producing a visually balanced paragraph was once a fine art, when professional typesetters still carefully set paragraphs with movable type. Nowadays, you could hope that optimal paragraph typesetting is a solved problem across all our software. But, alas, it is not!</p>
<p>There are different strategies we can employ to produce a well-justified paragraph. Of course, to justify the paragraph, we need to stretch each line to the width of the measure. There are different ways to do this: Most obviously, we can adjust the spacing between words. This is what most software does. But we can also adjust the spacing between characters. This is now implemented in Typst.</p>
<p>Other methods to do this (which we want to explore in the future) include stretching the width of characters (this is best done with <em>variable fonts</em>) or, for some scripts, inserting special textual elements. For example, in Arabic, there are <em>Kashida,</em> which allow spacing out glyphs in words by extending the connectors between individual glyphs.</p>
<p>But that's just part of the recipe. Arguably, the even more crucial part is how this interplays with <em>which linebreaks</em> we chose to insert. Naively, we can choose our break points based on how much text fits and then perform the stretching. But we can do much better by taking into account each line's potential for stretching with the various mechanisms discussed above! We can then choose the break points that minimize the amount of bad-looking stretching.</p>
<p>I was initially skeptical about supporting character-level justification because I've seen it done poorly in some books. But that's actually not the fault of character-level justification per se; it's just excessive use of it. Tastefully chosen maxima—together with an algorithm that minimizes displeasing typography—make it bring out the best in justification.</p>
<p>We hear a lot about microtypography when people compare Typst with LaTeX. And even though Typst uses the same fundamental algorithm as LaTeX does to optimize paragraphs, it's true that LaTeX has some extra tricks up its sleeve. Now we do too though, as character-level justification is a feature that LaTeX does <em>not</em> support.</p>
<p><img src="https://typst.app/assets/images/blog/character-level-justification.webp" alt="Two renderings of a justified paragraph about the 29 BC Yellow River flood from Wikipedia. The first has the caption 'Without character-level justification'. It has issues with grayness: For example, the 5th line is set very wide. The second has the caption 'With character-level justification'. Compared to the previous example, no line is overly wide or narrow." width="1473" height="800"></p><h2 id="richer-html-export">Richer HTML Export</h2>
<p>In Typst 0.13, we shipped a first, highly experimental version of HTML export. This very minimal version already introduced the primitives for flexible HTML generation. With these primitives, the mapping of Typst elements to HTML can be expressed through show rules, just like the mapping to visual elements is performed in paged export.</p>
<p>What was lacking though were show rules for many built-in elements, including elements like footnotes, outlines, and citations. Typst 0.14 makes good progress in this regard. Most semantic elements (those from the <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/model/"><em>Model</em> category</a>) are now properly mapped to semantic HTML. We've also improved handling of textual content in HTML export. The more visualization- and styling-focused parts of Typst's standard library remain largely unsupported, but we plan to add support for those (to the extent possible) in the future.</p>
<p>Below, you can see an example of a small, but non-trivial Typst document exported to HTML with Typst 0.14.</p>
<pre><code><span>#</span><span>set</span> <span>heading</span><span>(</span>numbering<span>:</span> <span>"1."</span><span>)</span>

<span>= Introduction</span> <span>&lt;intro&gt;</span>
In <span>@intro</span>, let's cite <span>@netwok</span>.

<span>#</span><span>bibliography</span><span>(</span><span>"works.bib"</span><span>)</span>
</code></pre><pre><span>&lt;!-- html, head, and body omitted for brevity --&gt;
</span><span>&lt;</span><span>h2 </span><span>id</span><span>=</span><span>"intro"</span><span>&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/</span><span>h2</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>&lt;</span><span>p</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>  In &lt;</span><span>a </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>"#intro"</span><span>&gt;Section&nbsp;1&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;, let’s cite
</span><span>  &lt;</span><span>a </span><span>id</span><span>=</span><span>"loc-1" </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>"#loc-2" </span><span>role</span><span>=</span><span>"doc-biblioref"</span><span>&gt;[1]&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;.
</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>p</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>&lt;</span><span>section </span><span>role</span><span>=</span><span>"doc-bibliography"</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>  &lt;</span><span>h2</span><span>&gt;Bibliography&lt;/</span><span>h2</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>  &lt;</span><span>ul </span><span>style</span><span>=</span><span>"</span><span>list-style-type</span><span>: </span><span>none</span><span>"</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>    &lt;</span><span>li </span><span>id</span><span>=</span><span>"loc-2"</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>      &lt;</span><span>span </span><span>class</span><span>=</span><span>"prefix"</span><span>&gt;&lt;</span><span>a </span><span>href</span><span>=</span><span>"#loc-1" </span><span>role</span><span>=</span><span>"doc-backlink"</span><span>&gt;[1]&lt;/</span><span>a</span><span>&gt;&lt;/</span><span>span</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>      R. Astley and L. Morris, “At-scale impact of the Net Wok: A culinarically
</span><span>      holistic investigation of distributed dumplings,”
</span><span>      &lt;</span><span>em</span><span>&gt;Armenian Journal of Proceedings&lt;/</span><span>em</span><span>&gt;, vol. 61, pp. 192–219, 2020.
</span><span>    &lt;/</span><span>li</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>  &lt;/</span><span>ul</span><span>&gt;
</span><span>&lt;/</span><span>section</span><span>&gt;
</span></pre>
<p>Another exciting addition to HTML export is the new <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/html/typed/">typed HTML</a> interface. Typst's <code>html</code> module now includes functions for constructing HTML elements with strongly-typed attributes. This means you can now write</p>
<pre><code><span>#</span><span>html</span><span>.</span><span>video</span><span>(</span>
  autoplay<span>:</span> <span>true</span><span>,</span>
  width<span>:</span> <span>1280</span><span>,</span>
  height<span>:</span> <span>720</span><span>,</span>
  src<span>:</span> <span>"sunrise.mp4"</span><span>,</span>
<span>)</span>
</code></pre>
<p>instead of</p>
<pre><code><span>#</span><span>html</span><span>.</span><span>elem</span><span>(</span><span>"video"</span><span>,</span> attrs<span>:</span> <span>(</span>
  autoplay<span>:</span> <span>""</span><span>,</span>
  width<span>:</span> <span>"1280"</span><span>,</span>
  height<span>:</span> <span>"720"</span><span>,</span>
  src<span>:</span> <span>"sunrise.mp4"</span><span>,</span>
<span>)</span><span>)</span>
</code></pre>
<p>As you can see, attributes are mapped to idiomatic Typst-native types.</p>
<p>Last but not least, we're happy to announce that HTML export will soon come to the Typst web app. We're still polishing up the implementation, but plan to ship it in the coming weeks.</p>
<p>Please note that HTML export remains experimental. To enable it in the CLI, pass <code>--features html</code> or set <code>TYPST_FEATURES=html</code>. In the web app, support for HTML export will also need to be enabled on a per-project basis.</p>
<h2 id="migrating">Migrating to Typst 0.14</h2>
<p>As far as breaking changes and deprecations go, this is a pretty calm release. Most documents should continue to work as before. There are a few minor breaking changes that make certain validations more strict. For instance, labels, link URLs, and font lists may not be empty anymore. To learn about all breaking changes, consult the <a href="https://typst.app/docs/changelog/" title="changelog">changelog</a> and search for "breaking change".</p>
<p>The release also contains a few <a href="https://typst.app/docs/changelog/0.14.0/#deprecations">deprecations</a>. In particular, you'll need to replace any use of <code>pdf.embed</code> with <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/pdf/attach/" title="`pdf.attach`"><code>pdf.attach</code></a>. Moreover, two bibliography styles were renamed and the <code>--make-deps</code> CLI flag was deprecated in favor of the new, more flexible <code>--deps</code> flag with <code>--deps-format make</code>. There are also a few deprecated <a href="https://typst.app/docs/reference/symbols/">symbols</a>. The compiler will warn you about all use of deprecated functionality.</p>
<h3 id="in-the-web-app">In the web app</h3>
<p>With this release, we're also bringing a better version upgrade experience to the web app. Previously, projects would always use the latest compiler version unless explicitly pinned to a specific version in the settings side panel.</p>
<p>We are now phasing out the "Latest" option. Instead, the web app detects when a new version is available since you've last edited a project, and offers you to upgrade. The upgrade assistant includes an automatic compatibility check that compiles your document with both versions, makes a verdict, and lists new errors and warnings.</p>
<p><img src="https://typst.app/assets/images/blog/migration-modal.webp" alt="Modal with the title 'Upgrade your project'. It contains this text: 'We updated the Typst compiler since you last edited this project. Upgrade this project to benefit from the new features and bug fixes in Typst 0.14.0. You can change the compiler version in the project settings panel at any time.' In a box with a green outline, it says 'Your project is ready to upgrade. Your project compiled without errors on Typst 0.14.0. Note that its appearance may have changed.'" width="491" height="320"></p>
<p>Typst 0.14 is the result of 8 months of hard work by us and the community. We hope you are as excited about it as we are!</p>
<p>Speaking of the community—We're hosting a <a href="https://discord.gg/KCMe6g7gPa?event=1430904365748846632">community call on Discord on Friday, November 7th</a>. Join us to share your experiences with the new version and to chat with the community!</p> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Poker fraud used X-ray tables, high-tech glasses and NBA players (261 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cz6nd9wnzn6o</link>
            <guid>45693599</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 11:42:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cz6nd9wnzn6o">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cz6nd9wnzn6o</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=45693599">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/aaad/live/9999e380-b0d4-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp" loading="eager" alt="NBAE via Getty Images / Reuters A composite image of Damon Jones on the left and Chauncey Billups on the right, both are headshots with them looking away from camera."><span>NBAE via Getty Images / Reuters</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Former NBA player Damon Jones (left) and basketball coach Chauncey Billups were arrested in connection with the scheme</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Celebrities, professional sports stars and wealthy gamblers sat at a table hoping to win big in a game of Texas Hold 'Em.</p><p>But they didn't know it was nearly impossible. They were "fishes" allegedly being targeted by the mafia in an elaborate poker gambling scheme that included X-ray card tables, secret cameras, analysers in chip trays and sunglasses and contact lenses that could read their hand. </p><p>In what sounds like an Ocean's Eleven film plot, prosecutors say these "unwitting" victims were cheated out of at least $7m (£5.25m) in poker games - with one person losing at least $1.8m.</p><p>The scheme, which US prosecutors described as "reminiscent of a Hollywood movie", was dismantled in a sprawling federal investigation that led to more than 30 arrests, including members of La Cosa Nostra crime families, Portland Trail Blazers basketball coach Chauncey Billups and former National Basketball Association (NBA) player Damon Jones. </p><p>FBI director Kash Patel called it a "mind-boggling" fraud scheme that cheated victims in New York, Miami, Las Vegas and other US cities. </p><p>Arrests in the scheme were announced on Thursday along with those in an alleged basketball betting plot, in which professional NBA players are accused of faking injuries to influence betting odds. </p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>The underground poker scheme started as early as 2019, prosecutors say, and was allegedly operated by the mafia - specifically by members of notorious crime families, including Bonnano, Gambino, Lucchese and Genovese. A cut of the profits, prosecutors say, helped fund their criminal enterprise. </p><p>Former professional athletes, described by prosecutors as "face cards", were enlisted to help in the scheme and entice victims into playing. </p><p>Lured in by the opportunity to play with a high-profile celebrity - such as Billups or Jones - a wealthy, "unwitting victim" would be recruited for illegal, underground poker games where tens of thousands of dollars were on the line, prosecutors allege. </p><p>Unbeknownst to the lured-in players - referred to in the scheme as a "fish" - everyone surrounding them was in on the elaborate scam - from the players to the dealers, even the technology used to shuffle the deck and count the chips, according to a lengthy federal indictment. </p><p>Sophisticated wireless technology was also used to deceive the players during the games, most commonly in Texas Hold 'Em.</p><ul><li><a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cpv1rkxjyyno">What we know about gambling arrests</a></li></ul></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/4b80/live/0016db40-b0c1-11f0-b2a1-6f537f66f9aa.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="A composite image showing the X-ray poker table, the cheater's view, and the card-shuffling machine"></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>An X-ray poker machine was employed to read facedown cards and a rigged card-shuffling machine was also used in the plot, prosecutors say</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>The technology was everywhere - an X-ray table that read any face-down card, analysers inside chip trays, a rigged shuffling machine that read cards and predicted who would have the best hand, and pre-marked cards that allowed those wearing special sunglasses and contact lenses to read what was in everyone's hands. </p><p>Secretive cameras - built into tables and light fixtures - also helped convey information to those helping in the plot, authorities say. </p><p>Then there was also a sophisticated method of communicating and rigging the game, prosecutors allege. </p><p>Information from the game would be sent to an off-site conspirator - called an "operator" by prosecutors - who then would send information to another player sitting at the table who was in on the scheme - who prosecutors call a "quarterback" or "driver". </p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/1842/live/5bd10500-b0cb-11f0-ba75-093eca1ac29b.png.webp" loading="lazy" alt="A graphic titled: How the poker fraud works. Step 1: X-ray table, chip tray and shuffle machine reads cards. Step 2: Information sent to off-site co-conspirator. Step 3: Details sent to 'quarterback' player by phone. Step 4: He secretly signals to colleagues. "></p></div></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>That person would then secretly signal to others, prosecutors allege, effectively stealing money and making it impossible for victims to win. </p><p>Texts from the US justice department's evidence suggest the "quarterback" would either touch the $1,000 poker chip, tap his chin, wrist or arm to signal which conspirator had the best hand. </p><p>If the victim had the best hand, the "quarterback" would touch his black chips.</p><p>The texts also appear to show that at times conspirators agreed to lose some hands in order to keep victims at the gambling table for longer.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251021-134202-667692b2c6-web-2.32.2-1/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/63a9/live/e3fde360-b0c8-11f0-aa13-0b0479f6f42a.png.webp" loading="lazy" alt="US Department of Justice Texts in the US justice department's evidence appears to show co-conspirators messaging. A text from 'Big Mikey' says: Guys please let him win a hand he's in for 40k in 40 minutes he will leave if he gets no traction. A reply from Gstacks Gee Stacks says: Agreed."><span>US Department of Justice</span></p></div></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Another series of texts suggests participants in the scheme avoided suspicion of cheating by swapping in players and losing money to co-conspirators.</p><p>Authorities estimate that each game would leave a victim out of tens or hundreds of thousands of dollars.</p><p>Prosecutors say the defendants allegedly laundered the funds from the scheme through cryptocurrency, cash exchanges and shell companies. </p><p>A cut of the profits went to those who helped in the plot, prosecutors say, and some allegedly went to fund the mafia's criminal enterprise. </p><p>"This alleged scheme wreaked havoc across the nation, exploiting the notoriety of some and the wallets of others to finance the Italian crime families," said FBI Assistant Director in Charge Christopher Raia.</p><p>Billups, who was accused of being a face card in the fixed card games, was arrested in Portland and was placed on leave by the NBA. The Portland Trail Blazers said in a statement that they were aware of the allegations involving their head coach and were "fully co-operating with the investigation".</p><p>Jones was arrested in relation to both the poker and NBA injuries scheme. He is charged with two counts each of wire fraud conspiracy and money laundering conspiracy.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>