<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 16:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Setelinleikkaus: When Finns snipped their cash in half to curb inflation (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://jpkoning.blogspot.com/2024/11/setelinleikkaus-when-finns-snipped.html</link>
            <guid>42243755</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 08:52:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://jpkoning.blogspot.com/2024/11/setelinleikkaus-when-finns-snipped.html">http://jpkoning.blogspot.com/2024/11/setelinleikkaus-when-finns-snipped.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42243755">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-7830074591186405092" itemprop="description articleBody">
<p>On the last day of 1945, with World War II finally behind it, Finland's government announced a new and very strange policy.</p><p>All Finns were required to take out a pair of scissors and snip their banknotes in half. This was known in Finland as <i>setelinleikkaus</i>, or banknote cutting. Anyone who owned any of the three largest denomination Finnish banknotes&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> the 5000 markka note, the 1000, or the 500&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> was required to perform this operation immediately. The left side of the note could still be used to buy things, but at only half its value. So if a Finn had a 1000 markka note in their wallet, henceforth he or she could now only buy 500 markka worth of items at stores. As for the right side, it could no longer be spent and effectively became a bond (more on this later).</p><p><br><i>Setelinleikkaus </i>was Finland's particular response to the post-War European problem of "monetary overhang," described <a href="https://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=987262">in a 1990 paper</a> by economists Rudi Dornbusch and Holger Wolf. After many years of war production, price controls, and rationing, European citizens had built-up a substantial chest of <i>forced savings</i>, or involuntary postponed consumption, as Dornbusch &amp; Wolf refer to it. With WWII now over, Europeans would soon want to begin living as they had before, spending the balances they had accumulated on goods and services. Alas, with most factories having been configured to military purposes or having been bombed into dust, there wasn't nearly enough consumption items to make everyone happy.</p><p>It was plain to governments all across Europe what this sudden making-up of postponed consumption in a war-focused economy would lead to: a big one time jump in prices.</p><p>This may sound familiar to the modern day reader, since we just went through our own wartime economy of sorts: the 2020-21 battle against COVID and subsequent return to a peacetime economy. The supply chain problem caused by the COVID shutdowns combined with the big jump in spending as lockdowns expired, spurred on by a big overhang of unspent COVID support cheques, led to the steepest inflation in decades.&nbsp;</p><p>According to Dornbusch and Wolf, European authorities fretted that the post-WWII jump in prices could very well spiral into something worse: all-out hyperinflation, as had happened after the first World War. Currencies were no longer linked to gold, after all, having lost that tether when the war started<span lang="en"><span>, </span></span>or earlier, in response to the Great Depression.&nbsp;</p><p>To prevent what they saw as imminent hyperinflation, almost all European countries began to enact monetary reforms. Finland's own unique reform&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> obliging their citizens to cut their stash of banknotes in two&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> would reduce the economy's stock of banknotes to just "lefts," thereby halving spending power and muting the wave of post-wartime spending. After February 16, 1946 the halves would be demonetized, but until then the Finns could continue to make purchases with them or bring them to the nearest bank to be converted into a new edition of the currency.</p><p>As for the right halves, they were to be transformed into a long-term investment. Finns were obligated to bring each right half in to be registered, upon which it would be converted into a Finnish government bond that paid 2% interest per year, to be repaid four years later, in 1949. It was illegal to try and spend right halves or transfer their ownership to anyone else (although it's not apparent how this was enforced).</p><p>In theory, turning right halves into bonds would shift a large part of the Finnish public's post-war consumption intentions forward to 1949, when the bonds could finally be cashed. By then, the economy would have fully transitioned back to a civilian one and would be capable of accepting everyone's desired consumption spending without hyperinflation occurring.</p><div><p>To our modern sensibilities, this is a wildly invasive policy. Had <i>setelinleikkaus</i> been proposed in 2022-23 as a way to dampen the inflationary effects of the reopening of COVID-wracked economies, and we all had to cut our dollar bills or yen or euros in half, there probably would have been a revolt. </p><p>With the benefit of hindsight, we know that <i>setelinleikkaus </i>didn't work very well. Finland continued to suffer from high inflation in the years after the war, much more so than most European countries did.</p></div><p>Why the failure? As Finish economist Matti Viren has <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20111018081609/http://www.rahamuseo.fi/monetaria/studia_monetaria_viren_kev%C3%A4t_2007.pdf">pointed out</a>, the reform only affected banknotes, not bank deposits. This stock of notes only comprised 8% of the total Finnish money supply, (Finns being&nbsp; uncommonly comfortable with banks) so a major chunk of the monetary overhang was left in place.</p><p>Another glitch appears to have been the public's anticipation of <i>setelinleikkaus</i>. According to <br>former central banker Antti Heinonen, who wrote <a href="https://www.suomenpankki.fi/fi/julkaisut/muut-julkaisut/hallitus-kansan-kukkarolla/">an entire book</a> on the subject, banks began to advertise their services as a way to avoid the dangers of the upcoming monetary reform (see images below). So Finns deposited their cash prior to the final date, the monetary overhang to some degree evading the blockade.</p><table><tbody><tr><td><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgl0LBywd5JlwBT3JynEswJWvqMV_Kb2-rUoIT3dqbParkpHHEo64VI2hc6n3KWktGjJfpYt1hIsR6GJI14HRAuOBSYSfA-7a1_GEed001newOG9bZu9RjTTsap8FUzaMs_XjFAeoKulmCg6V6yyR1x2N1ak9JUkP8wwBSR4tnQygH2wz9_QR7X_QQhqF4/s487/heinonen.PNG"><img data-original-height="364" data-original-width="487" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgl0LBywd5JlwBT3JynEswJWvqMV_Kb2-rUoIT3dqbParkpHHEo64VI2hc6n3KWktGjJfpYt1hIsR6GJI14HRAuOBSYSfA-7a1_GEed001newOG9bZu9RjTTsap8FUzaMs_XjFAeoKulmCg6V6yyR1x2N1ak9JUkP8wwBSR4tnQygH2wz9_QR7X_QQhqF4/s16000/heinonen.PNG"></a></td></tr><tr><td><span>Finnish bank advertisements warning of the upcoming note cutting<br>Left: <i>"Bank accounts are fully secured in the banknote exchange</i>." <br>Right: <i>"Depositors are protected</i>."<br> <b>Source</b>: <a href="https://www.suomenpankki.fi/fi/julkaisut/muut-julkaisut/hallitus-kansan-kukkarolla/">Hallitus kansan kukkarolla</a>, by Antti Heinonen (Translations via Google Translate)</span><br></td></tr></tbody></table><p><br>If the Finnish experiment was a dud, other European responses to the post WWII overhang&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> either&nbsp; redenominations, temporarily blocking of funds, or all-out write offs of bank accounts&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> were more successful. Germany's <a href="https://www.bundesbank.de/en/press/contributions/the-economic-and-currency-reform-of-1948-the-basis-for-stable-money-915302">monetary reform of 1948</a>, which introduced the Deutschmark and was later dubbed the <a href="https://www.econlib.org/library/Enc/GermanEconomicMiracle.html">"German economic miracle"</a>, is the one that captures the most attention, but here I want to focus on a lesser known reform.</p><div><p>Belgium's <i>Operation Gutt</i>, named after Belgium's Minister of Finance, Camille Gutt, was the earliest and perhaps the most dramatic of the post-war monetary operations. Taking place over four days in October 1944, Belgium contracted its entire money supply, both banknotes and deposits, from 165 billion to 57.5 billion francs. That's a two-thirds decline! You can see it illustrated in the chart below, along with the monetary reform enacted <a href="https://sci-hub.se/https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/financial-history-review/article/abs/netherlands-postwar-monetary-reform-1945521/36CF6F0267461A0A8E9BE14C807BC593">by the Dutch</a> the following year, inspired by the Belgians.</p></div><p>It's not just the size of Operation Gutt that is striking to the modern eye. It's also the oddity of the tool being used. Today, we control inflation with changes in interest rates, not changes in the quantity of money. To soften the effect of the global COVID monetary overhang, for instance, central banks in the U.S., Canada, and Europe began to raise rates in 2022 from around 0% to 4-5% in 2024.&nbsp;</p><div><p>By making it more lucrative for everyone to save and less attractive to borrow, central bankers were trying to reduce our propensity to spend our COVID support payments, and with less spending, prices wouldn't get pushed up as fast.&nbsp;This reliance on interest rates as our main tool of monetary policy is a relatively new phenomenon. In times past, central banks tended to lean heavily on changes in the supply of money, which may explain why in 1945, their main response&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> in Europe at least&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span>&nbsp; was to obliterate the public's money balances rather than to jack up interest rates to 25% or 50%.&nbsp; &nbsp;</p><p>It's worth exploring in some more detail how Operation Gutt was designed. On October 9, 1944, Belgian bank depositors had 90% of the money held in their accounts frozen, leaving just 10% in spendable form.</p></div><p>As for holders of banknotes, there was no Finnish-style cutting. Rather,
 Belgians had four days, beginning October 9, to bring all their 
banknotes to the nearest bank, only the first 2,000 francs qualifying 
for conversion to newly printed versions. All notes above that ceiling 
got blocked in a separate account (along with excess deposits), some of 
which would be released slowly over the next few years<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span>while
 the rest would remain frozen forever, subject to whether the owner was 
deemed to have been a collaborator who got rich during the occupation. 
(Finland's <i>setelinleikkaus </i>also had this same "cleansing" motivation.) <br></p><br><div><p>In this sense, the post-WWII European monetary reforms were not only designed to reduce inflation, but also had a moral basis. Think of them as progenitors to India's 2016 demonetization, which was designed to catch so-called "black money," although <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/aug/30/india-demonetisation-drive-fails-uncover-black-money">it failed</a> to do so.</p><p>Did Operation Gutt work? Incredibly, the decimation of two-thirds of the money supply in just a few days did <i>not </i>cause an immediate fall in Belgian prices. <a href="https://muse.jhu.edu/pub/258/oa_monograph/chapter/861769">According to</a> Belgian economic historians Monique Verbreyt and Herman Van der Wee, the Belgian retail price index stood at 260 the month of the reform, but had risen to 387 by September 1945. So it would seem that the whole operation failed. This surely draws into question the <i>quantity theory of money</i>, one of the basic tenets of monetary economics. A decline in the money supply, all things staying the same, is supposed to cause a fall in prices. Here is a glaring case in which it didn't. </p></div><p>However, the National Bank of Belgium (NBB), the country's central bank, strikes a more constructive tone. In a <a href="https://museum.nbb.be/en/resources/operation-gutt-gamble-paid">recent retrospective</a> on Operation Gutt, the NBB describes the reform as a gamble that paid off over time, eventually inspiring the "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Belgian_economic_miracle">Belgian Economic Miracle</a>", a period of low inflation and fast growth lasting from 1946-1949. By contrast, France did not embark on its own monetary reforms, the NBB takes pains to point out, and it thereby "paid the consequences of post-World War II inflation well into the 1960s." Belgium's inflation rate was also much lower than Finland's in the four or five years after the war.&nbsp;</p><div><p>Which gets us back to Finland. Unlike the Belgian central bank, Finland's central bank&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> Suomen Pankki&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> notably <a href="https://www.suomenpankki.fi/fi/haku/?q=Setelinleikkaus">avoids almost all mention</a> of its post-war reform on its website. According to Matti Viren, <i>setelinleikkaus </i>led to "distrust towards the authorities and economic policy for decades," so there may be some sheepish reticence on the part of the central bank to draw attention to it.</p><p>But <i>setelinleikkaus </i>and Operation Gutt aren't just archaic monetary policy dead-ends. One day I suspect they'll be back. Not just as a special tool for responding to emergencies, but as a day-to-day policy wrench, albeit in a new and refined form.&nbsp;</p></div><p>Cash, which is awkward to immobilize for policy reasons, will be gone in a decade or two, leaving the public entirely dependent on bank deposits and fintech balances which, thanks to digitization and automation, can be easily controlled by the authorities. To rein in a jump in inflation, central bankers will require commercial banks and companies like PayPal to impose temporary <i>quantitative freezing</i> on their clients'&nbsp; accounts, but unlike Finland's 1945 blockade, the authorities will be able to rapidly and precisely define the criteria, say by allowing for spending on necessities&nbsp;<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> food, electricity, and gas<span lang="en"><span>—</span></span> while embargoing purchases of luxury cars and real estate.</p><p>The future version of <i>setelinleikkaus </i>won't be clumsy, it'll be a precise and surgical inflation-fighting tool, albeit a controversial one.<br></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Y Combinator often backs startups that duplicate other YC companies, data shows (183 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/11/22/y-combinator-often-backs-startups-that-duplicate-other-yc-companies-data-shows-its-not-just-ai-code-editors/</link>
            <guid>42243746</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 08:50:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/11/22/y-combinator-often-backs-startups-that-duplicate-other-yc-companies-data-shows-its-not-just-ai-code-editors/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/11/22/y-combinator-often-backs-startups-that-duplicate-other-yc-companies-data-shows-its-not-just-ai-code-editors/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42243746">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">The Silicon Valley dream is to build a tech startup that is such a unique idea it alters the commercial universe and turns its founders into billionaires. Participating in the Valley’s most famed startup factory, Y Combinator, is often part of that dream. Airbnb, Coinbase, and Stripe all got started there.</p>

<p>Yet, a deep dive into the data from all of the nearly 5,000 companies YC has backed to date reveals a surprising truth: YC startups don’t have to be unique. Far from it.&nbsp;</p>







<p>YC commonly accepts startups that are building similar or nearly identical products to previous YC grads. Some of them are direct competitors; others differ slightly by targeting a new geography (Asia or Latin America), or are a subset of a larger market (point-of-sale software for bars versus coffee shops).&nbsp;</p>

<p>Data analysis startup <a rel="nofollow" href="https://alphalens.com/">Deckmatch</a> conducted the research, inspired to look at competing YC products after a controversy over a YC-backed startup called PearAI. Critics said that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/09/30/y-combinator-is-being-criticized-after-it-backed-an-ai-startup-that-admits-it-basically-cloned-another-ai-startup/">PearAI’s code editor product wasn’t much more than a cloned version</a> of another YC product, called Continue — and PearAI’s founder essentially admitted it. There were more reasons that Pear found itself in hot water (including the bravado of its founders and how it handled the open source licensing). But the uproar concluded with Pear’s founders vowing to <a href="https://x.com/trypearai/status/1843336730012987613" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">start over from scratch</a>.</p>

<p>YC CEO Garry Tan defended the company, and the fact that YC accepted this behavior, by<a href="https://x.com/garrytan/status/1840490996528029942" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow"> posting on X</a>, “More choice is good, people building is good, if you don’t like it don’t use it.”&nbsp;</p>

<p>This is clearly more than lip service for Tan, who has himself, for instance, championed two police bodycam startups a few years apart: Flock Safety (Summer 2017 cohort) and Abel Police (Summer 2024). Along the same lines, more than a dozen startups building AI code editors went through the YC program between 2022 and 2024 — some in the same batch with the same YC partner.</p>

<p>When asked about its propensity to back competitors, a YC spokesperson said that the organization is more interested in the founders’ backgrounds than their business ideas. “YC invests in founders over ideas, focusing on individuals with the potential to build transformative companies — no matter the space they operate in. Our investment strategy focuses on backing the most promising founders with vision, resilience, and ability to execute, which is clear in our RFS process,” a spokesperson told TechCrunch.</p>


<h2 id="h-some-founders-love-yc-s-approach">Some founders love YC’s approach</h2>

<p>One of YC’s big benefits is its cozy network, where startups often seek customers, partners, and the like. Consequently, some alums dislike competition if they feel another’s product mimics theirs, rather than differentiates. Around the time of the PearAI controversy, YC alum Bryan Onel, founder of security startup Oneleet, <a href="https://x.com/ayushswrites/status/1847000329201528999" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">posted on X</a> about his experience with this. A few others chimed in to commiserate. (Onel did not respond to our requests for comment.)</p>

<p>Then again, other YC alums think this kind of direct competition is good, especially when the same YC partner advises them. Restaurant PoS systems is one area that has been popular in YC, and YC alum Nick Evans, co-founder CEO of restaurant PoS <a href="https://www.avocadopos.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">Avocado</a>, is fine with competitors.</p>

<p>He should know. Evans famously founded a device-tracking startup called Tile, which went crazy with crowdfunding, raised money from traditional VCs, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/09/16/tile-secures-another-40-million-to-take-on-apple-airtag-with-new-products/">took on Apple’s AirTags</a>, then sold to <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2021/11/22/family-locator-service-life360-to-acquire-tile-for-205-million/">Life360 in 2021 for $205 million</a>.&nbsp;</p>







<p>“I think it’s stupid that most investors don’t invest in competing companies,” Evans told TechCrunch about YC competition. “I want investors that deeply understand my business and industry. How the hell would they know anything useful if they aren’t working with similar companies? Startups don’t die by murder; they die by suicide. You are not fighting against other startups. You are fighting against people not giving a s— about your product.”&nbsp;</p>

<h2 id="h-deep-dive-inspired-by-pearai-controversy">Deep dive inspired by PearAI controversy</h2>

<p>Before diving into the specifics of the categories YC has particularly favored, it’s worth noting that Deckmatch is not a YC company and has never applied to be one, CEO Leo Gasteen tells TechCrunch.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Deckmatch was inspired to analyze YC products by the PearAI situation as a demo test for its new product AlphaLens. Deckmatch sells product analysis data on about 8 million startups to private market participants like investors, and corporate innovation and M&amp;A teams.&nbsp;</p>

<p>It wants to do for product data what PitchBook did for company-level data, Gasteen says. Earlier this month, Deckmatch raised a $3.1 million seed round co-led by Alliance VC and Luminar Ventures, with participation from its pre-seed investors First Degree Capital and Skyfall Ventures. It’s raised $4.2 million to date, it says.</p>

<p>AlphaLens lets Deckmatch customers comb through its database to find unique and similar products, build scatter charts, cluster maps, and the like. But the <a href="https://labs.alphalens.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">results of the YC analysis</a>, shared exclusively with TechCrunch, should be fascinating to any founder wondering what kinds of startups YC tends to accept.&nbsp;</p>

<h2 id="h-types-of-products-yc-loves-according-to-the-data">Types of products YC loves, according to the data</h2>

<p>According to this data, the current popular product categories, each with at least a dozen startups, include:</p>

<p><strong>AI code editors:</strong> Beyond Continue and PearAI, another example is Void (another open source alternative to Cursor, the popular Andreessen Horowitz/OpenAI-backed startup). Then there’s EasyCode, Ellipsis, Cosine, Greptile, and more, each applying AI to various coding tasks.</p>

<p><strong>Food/beverage/restaurant point of sale systems:</strong> Most of the PoS startups were accepted into the program between 2020 and 2023, including Avocado, Dripos, or Latin American startup Polo.&nbsp;</p>







<p><strong>Business finance/payroll:</strong> With the success of YC alums Gusto and Rippling came many competitors, some aimed at different international markets. Examples include Warp and Zeal.</p>

<p><strong>AI sales and customer relationship management.</strong> This is a <a href="https://techcrunch.com/podcast/marc-benioff-says-its-crazy-talk-that-ai-will-hurt-salesforce-wants-a-billion-ai-agents-in-a-year/">very hot area of development for the big players </a>(Salesforce, Microsoft) <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/08/22/ai-sdr-startups-are-booming-so-why-are-vcs-wary/">and startups</a>. YC alums include Apten, Persana AI, and Topo.</p>

<p><strong>AI meeting assistants:</strong> Circleback, Onward, Sonnet, and Spinach AI are but a few examples.</p>

<p><strong>AI legal assistants:</strong> Dioptra, Leya, and Tower are some examples.</p>

<p>Then again, several areas were popular but have been recently less so. These include:</p>

<p><strong>Crypto trading platforms:</strong> Given the success of YC grad Coinbase, YC was gung ho on this for a while, with about a dozen grads, largely from 2014 to 2022.</p>

<p><strong>E-commerce store platforms:</strong> In the wake of Shopify (not a YC alum) YC accepted about a dozen such companies since 2018, with the majority in the 2018 to 2022 time frame.</p>

<p><strong>Corporate expense cards:</strong> After YC alum Brex came many others, mostly from&nbsp;2018 to 2022.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Lies we tell ourselves to keep using Golang (261 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fasterthanli.me/articles/lies-we-tell-ourselves-to-keep-using-golang</link>
            <guid>42243500</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 08:01:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fasterthanli.me/articles/lies-we-tell-ourselves-to-keep-using-golang">https://fasterthanli.me/articles/lies-we-tell-ourselves-to-keep-using-golang</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42243500">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://fasterthanli.me/articles/lies-we-tell-ourselves-to-keep-using-golang: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cybertruck's Many Recalls Make It Worse Than 91 Percent of All 2024 Vehicles (262 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/cybertrucks-many-recalls-make-it-worse-than-91-percent-of-all-2024-vehicles/</link>
            <guid>42242971</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 06:12:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/cybertrucks-many-recalls-make-it-worse-than-91-percent-of-all-2024-vehicles/">https://www.wired.com/story/cybertrucks-many-recalls-make-it-worse-than-91-percent-of-all-2024-vehicles/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42242971">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>If you buy something using links in our stories, we may earn a commission. This helps support our journalism. <a href="https://www.wired.com/2015/11/affiliate-link-policy/">Learn more</a>. Please also consider <a href="https://subscribe.wired.com/subscribe/splits/wired/WIR_SELF?source=HCL_WIR_EDIT_HARDCODED_0_COMMERCE_AFFILIATE_ZZ">subscribing to WIRED</a></p></div><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Cybertruck owners <a href="https://arstechnica.com/cars/2024/11/tesla-recalls-cybertrucks-for-faulty-inverter-the-6th-recall-this-year/">have discovered</a> that a chunk of these stainless steel electric pickups could “stop producing torque” while thrumming along. The fault was noted by Tesla in a November 5 National Highway Traffic Safety Administration <a data-offer-url="https://static.nhtsa.gov/odi/rcl/2024/RCLRPT-24V832-7628.PDF" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://static.nhtsa.gov/odi/rcl/2024/RCLRPT-24V832-7628.PDF&quot;}" href="https://static.nhtsa.gov/odi/rcl/2024/RCLRPT-24V832-7628.PDF" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">recall</a>. Any sudden loss of propulsion might “increase the risk of a collision,” added the filing ominously. The latest recall—the wedge wagon’s sixth this year—requires shop time, not an over-the-air (OTA) update.</p><p>Reports of instantaneous loss of e-horsepower due to duff drive inverters—devices that convert DC to AC and control an EV’s motor speed and torque—might alarm the average EV motorist, but to extrovert buyers of Elon Musk’s flagship, it’s evidence of the angular pickup’s edginess, Ivan Drury, the director of insights at <a data-offer-url="https://www.edmunds.com/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.edmunds.com/&quot;}" href="https://www.edmunds.com/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">car shopping guide Edmunds</a>, told WIRED.</p><p>“The people drawn to [the Cybertruck] don’t have quality of construction or safety at the top of mind,” he says. “That this could be a dangerous vehicle to drive is key to its appeal. Nobody’s buying it to use as an actual truck.”</p><p>Stomping on the accelerator pedals of the affected Cybertrucks might get their drivers nowhere—a downer, you’d think, for a vehicle that’s <a data-offer-url="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1851151793876844949" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1851151793876844949&quot;}" href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1851151793876844949" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">faster to 60 mph than a Lamborghini</a> Aventador—but, adds the Hawaii-based Drury, that won’t harm the pickup’s reputation with many wannabe owners.</p><p>“The more the press and others say it’s bad, the more that [typical Cybertruck customers] see it as good,” says Drury.</p><p>Mocked online as <a data-offer-url="https://www.reddit.com/r/CyberStuck/comments/1cqjzpu/cybertrucks_have_the_best_nicknames/?rdt=59131" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/CyberStuck/comments/1cqjzpu/cybertrucks_have_the_best_nicknames/?rdt=59131&quot;}" href="https://www.reddit.com/r/CyberStuck/comments/1cqjzpu/cybertrucks_have_the_best_nicknames/?rdt=59131" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">the Cyberbrick</a>, the car launched in <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/tesla-cybertruck-success-failure/">December 2023</a>; Tesla had apparently sold <a data-offer-url="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/05/17/tesla-stops-taking-orders-for-cybertruck-outside-north-america.html" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2022/05/17/tesla-stops-taking-orders-for-cybertruck-outside-north-america.html&quot;}" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2022/05/17/tesla-stops-taking-orders-for-cybertruck-outside-north-america.html" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">27,000 of them by October</a> this year, as could be inferred by the number of Cybertrucks listed on the fifth recall. Some 2,431 Cybertrucks were affected by the sixth recall, requiring vehicle drop-off for new drive inverters to be fitted.</p><p>The recalled drive inverters—equipped with potentially faulty metal-oxide-semiconductor field-effect transistors—were fitted to Cybertrucks manufactured between November of last year and the end of July this year.</p><p>“It’s common for all-new models to have increased recalls in the first year after launch,” Karl Brauer, executive analyst at car ranking service <a data-offer-url="https://www.iseecars.com/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.iseecars.com/&quot;}" href="https://www.iseecars.com/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">iSeeCars</a>, tells WIRED. “Where it gets interesting,” Brauer added, “is how quickly this initial spate of recalls falls off after launch versus continuing as the years pass.”</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>And on this metric, the Cybertruck might be wanting. “Cars with ongoing recalls well after launch suggest a much higher lifetime recall total,” says Brauer. He calculates that the <a href="https://www.reuters.com/business/autos-transportation/tesla-is-recalling-over-2400-vehicles-us-nhtsa-says-2024-11-13/">Cybertruck’s six recalls to date</a> are “worse than 91 percent” of other 2024 vehicles. All this was possibly foreshadowed in 2023 when a leaked Tesla report showed the Cybertruck had <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/a-leaked-tesla-report-shows-the-cybertruck-had-basic-design-flaws/">basic design flaws</a>.</p><p>“We aren’t comfortable making [lifetime recall] predictions on the Cybertruck at this very early stage,” stresses Brauer, “but so far it isn’t doing very well.”</p><p>Most Cybertruck buyers pay scant attention to longevity estimates, believes Edmunds’ Drury, and plenty probably aren’t exercised by recalls, OTA or otherwise, he said. “Cybertruck customers are in it for the stares and glares—they don’t care about how many times [this vehicle is] going to be recalled over 30 years,” says Drury. “They’re buying this car for now, with zero thought to the future.”</p><p>“A standard auto customer wants to know if a car will last 10 years or will be ongoing good value for money,” he says. “A Cybertruck customer doesn’t care about any of that. Owning a Cybertruck isn’t practical; it’s a boast. A boast that ‘I have so much discretionary income I can afford to waste it on an impractical car.’”</p><p>Similar to other critics (earlier this year, a <a data-offer-url="https://edition.cnn.com/2024/02/23/business/tesla-cybertruck-is-a-troubled-beast" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://edition.cnn.com/2024/02/23/business/tesla-cybertruck-is-a-troubled-beast&quot;}" href="https://edition.cnn.com/2024/02/23/business/tesla-cybertruck-is-a-troubled-beast" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">CNN reviewer called the pickup</a> a “disturbing level of individual arrogance in hard, unforgiving steel”), Drury believes Cybertruck buyers are people “who think, ‘I don’t care if I kill people when I drive this thing down the street,’” he says. “There aren’t many of those people out there, so there’s a relatively small market for the Cybertruck.”</p><p>If Tesla, which was contacted for this piece, is genuinely fishing in smaller pools than originally anticipated by Musk—at a <a data-offer-url="https://www.teslarati.com/tesla-tsla-2023-cyber-roundup-annual-shareholder-meeting-live-blog/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.teslarati.com/tesla-tsla-2023-cyber-roundup-annual-shareholder-meeting-live-blog/&quot;}" href="https://www.teslarati.com/tesla-tsla-2023-cyber-roundup-annual-shareholder-meeting-live-blog/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">2023 shareholder meeting</a> he predicted that Cybertruck sales could hit 250,000 by 2025, and reach 500,000 a year once production ramped up—this might help explain the softening of Cybertruck aftersales.</p><p>“Used values on these things have plummeted dramatically,” said Drury. Price tracking website <a data-offer-url="https://www.cargurus.com/research/price-trends/Tesla-Cybertruck-d3353" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.cargurus.com/research/price-trends/Tesla-Cybertruck-d3353&quot;}" href="https://www.cargurus.com/research/price-trends/Tesla-Cybertruck-d3353" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">CarGurus</a> estimates that the average used Cybertruck dropped from $175,000 in April to $110,864 today. The cheapest Cybertruck on <a data-offer-url="https://www.autotrader.com/cars-for-sale/all-cars/tesla/cybertruck" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.autotrader.com/cars-for-sale/all-cars/tesla/cybertruck&quot;}" href="https://www.autotrader.com/cars-for-sale/all-cars/tesla/cybertruck" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Autotrader</a> was $86,000 earlier this week, and many of the other 276 currently listed on the site sport “recent price drop” banners.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Aftermarket prices might soften further as Tesla is starting to deliver a <a data-offer-url="https://www.tesla.com/cybertruck/design#overview" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.tesla.com/cybertruck/design#overview&quot;}" href="https://www.tesla.com/cybertruck/design#overview" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">new $79,990 model</a> to reservation holders. Not that there’s any longer much need to place reservations—North American Tesla stores now accept walk-in orders for Cybertrucks, with delivery two or three weeks later. “I am calling it: Original reservation list is basically finished,” said reservationist <a data-offer-url="https://www.cybertruckownersclub.com/forum/threads/confirmed-original-us-reservation-list-exhausted.25244/" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.cybertruckownersclub.com/forum/threads/confirmed-original-us-reservation-list-exhausted.25244/&quot;}" href="https://www.cybertruckownersclub.com/forum/threads/confirmed-original-us-reservation-list-exhausted.25244/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">BayouCityBob</a> on a Cybertruck owners forum last month. Tesla had claimed to have banked <a data-offer-url="https://cleantechnica.com/2024/10/18/tesla-cybertruck-options-geography-opening-up/#:~:text=Once%20upon%20a%20time%2C%20there,required%20a%20%24100%20refundable%20deposit." data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://cleantechnica.com/2024/10/18/tesla-cybertruck-options-geography-opening-up/#:~:text=Once%20upon%20a%20time%2C%20there,required%20a%20%24100%20refundable%20deposit.&quot;}" href="https://cleantechnica.com/2024/10/18/tesla-cybertruck-options-geography-opening-up/#:~:text=Once%20upon%20a%20time%2C%20there,required%20a%20%24100%20refundable%20deposit." rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">more than 1 million</a> $100 prelaunch reservations for the Cybertruck.</p><p>“I was thinking I have to wait a couple of [years] before my time comes,” MC1987 responded to BayouCityBob, citing his invitation to purchase his second Cybertruck. (The poster had returned their first, a top-spec Cyberbeast, because of alleged “build quality issues.”) “This is so wild,” they said.</p><p>As most other parts of the world have yet to sanction Cybertruck sales, Tesla can’t boost take-up outside of North America. UK automobile listings website <a data-offer-url="https://www.carwow.co.uk/tesla/news/4408/tesla-cybertruck-price-specs-release-date#gref" data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://www.carwow.co.uk/tesla/news/4408/tesla-cybertruck-price-specs-release-date#gref&quot;}" href="https://www.carwow.co.uk/tesla/news/4408/tesla-cybertruck-price-specs-release-date#gref" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Carwow</a> describes the Cybertruck as a “rolling axe head,” a nod to the fact that the sharp-angled pickup is <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/a-rubberized-cybertruck-is-ploughing-through-european-pedestrian-safety-rules/">literally too edgy to meet strict European pedestrian-safety regulations</a>.</p><p>Nor can Tesla rely on the US consumer’s love affair with pickups. “Something like 70 percent of all truck sales involve a truck being traded in,” says Drury. “This isn’t the case with [the Cybertruck],” he revealed, using Edmunds’ trade-in data.</p><p>“While Cybertruck hasn’t been on the market too long, it’s been long enough for us to capture some of the used ones. Because there’s no sign that Cybertrucks are being traded for trucks—which is what we typically see in America—then this likely isn’t a vehicle being used for trucklike purposes,” says Drury.</p><p>While the Cybertruck’s six recalls this year might not alarm “edgy” consumers, the bad press that often results won’t impress Tesla shareholders—higher-than-average recalls could tarnish the greater brand.</p><p>Any spike in general automobile recalls should not necessarily worry consumers since defects range widely in severity, and very few are stop-sale orders or demands to immediately cease driving any particular model. Automakers might hate to file them, but recalls demonstrate that the regulatory system is working as designed.</p><p>However, with Musk advising the US government—<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/donald-trump-elon-musk-department-of-government-efficiency/">even if it’s at arms-length</a>—some regulators might get their wings clipped, perhaps even reducing the number of product recalls, potentially increasing danger for consumers. Not all Cybertruck owners will be too fussed about that, though.</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fly.io outage (restoration in progress) (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://status.flyio.net</link>
            <guid>42241851</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 01:47:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://status.flyio.net">https://status.flyio.net</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42241851">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
<p><span>
      AMS - Amsterdam, Netherlands
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      ARN - Stockholm, Sweden
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      ATL - Atlanta, Georgia (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      BOG - Bogotá, Colombia
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      BOM - Mumbai, India
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      CDG - Paris, France
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      DEN - Denver, Colorado (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      DFW - Dallas, Texas (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      EZE - Ezeiza, Argentina
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      FRA - Frankfurt, Germany
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<div data-component-id="qsy0b4zwvsvw" data-component-status="operational" data-js-hook="">

   <p><span>
      GDL - Guadalajara, Mexico
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span></p>

</div>

      
<p><span>
      GRU - Sao Paulo, Brazil
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      HKG - Hong Kong
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      IAD - Ashburn, Virginia (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      JNB - Johannesburg, South Africa
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      LAX - Los Angeles, California (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      LHR - London, United Kingdom
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      MAD - Madrid, Spain
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      MEL - Melbourne, Australia
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      MIA - Miami, Florida (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      NRT - Tokyo, Japan
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      ORD - Chicago, Illinois (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      OTP - Bucharest, Romania
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      QRO - Querétaro, Mexico
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      SCL - Santiago, Chile
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      SEA - Seattle, Washington (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      SIN - Singapore
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      SJC - San Jose, California (US)
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      SYD - Sydney, Australia
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<p><span>
      YYZ - Toronto, Canada
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span>

</p>

      
<div data-component-id="q94911jjt9cn" data-component-status="operational" data-js-hook="">

   <p><span>
      GIG - Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
   </span>


  <span title="">

    Operational

  </span>

  <span title="Operational"></span></p>

</div>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Premature Graying of Hair: Review with Updates (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6290285/</link>
            <guid>42241702</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 01:15:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6290285/">https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6290285/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42241702">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6290285/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon S3 Adds Put-If-Match (Compare-and-Swap) (430 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/11/amazon-s3-functionality-conditional-writes/</link>
            <guid>42240678</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 22:11:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/11/amazon-s3-functionality-conditional-writes/">https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/11/amazon-s3-functionality-conditional-writes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42240678">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="aws-page-content" data-page-alert-target="true"> 
   <main id="aws-page-content-main" role="main" tabindex="-1"> 
    <div data-eb-tpl-root="" data-reactroot="" data-eb-tpl-n="awsm-whats-new/whats-new-post" data-eb-tpl-v="1.0.0" data-eb-ce="" data-eb-c-scope="d105f9bc-63d3-11ee-8c99-0242ac120002" data-eb-d-scope="DIRECTORIES" data-eb-locale="en-US" data-eb-1e70fe18="" data-eb-ssr-ce="" data-eb-tpl-ns="awsmWhatsNew" data-eb-slot="d105f9bc-63d3-11ee-8c99-0242ac120002" data-eb-slot-meta="{'version':'1.0','slotId':'d105f9bc-63d3-11ee-8c99-0242ac120002','experienceId':'d105f9bc-63d3-11ee-8c99-0242ac120002','allowBlank':false,'hasAltExp':false,'isRTR':false,'filters':{'limit':1,'query':'id \u003d \'p169217422\''}}"> 
         <main> 
           
           
          <div><p>Amazon S3 can now perform conditional writes that evaluate if an object is unmodified before updating it. This helps you coordinate simultaneous writes to the same object and prevents multiple concurrent writers from unintentionally overwriting the object without knowing the state of its content. You can use this capability by providing the ETag of an object using S3 PutObject or CompleteMultipartUpload API requests in both S3 general purpose and directory buckets.</p><p>  Conditional writes simplify how distributed applications with multiple clients concurrently update data across shared datasets. Similar to using the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/whats-new/2024/08/amazon-s3-conditional-writes/" target="_blank">HTTP if-none-match conditional header to check for the existence of an object before creating it</a>, clients can now perform conditional-write checks on an object’s Etag, which reflects changes to the object, by specifying it via the HTTP if-match header in the API request. S3 then evaluates if the object's ETag matches the value provided in the API request before committing the write and prevents your clients from overwriting the object until the condition is satisfied. This new conditional header can help improve the efficiency of your large-scale analytics, distributed machine learning, and other highly parallelized workloads by reliably offloading compare and swap operations to S3.</p><p>  This new conditional-write functionality is available at no additional charge in all AWS Regions. You can use the AWS SDK, API, or CLI to perform conditional writes. To learn more about conditional writes, visit the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/userguide/conditional-requests.html" target="_blank">S3 User Guide</a>.</p></div> 
         </main> 
        </div> 
   </main> 
  </div><div data-lb-comp="modal" data-lb-modal-id="ie-deprecation-msg" data-ie10-deprecation-msg="You are using an outdated browser. Please upgrade to a modern browser to improve your experience."> 
      
     <p>
       AWS support for Internet Explorer ends on 07/31/2022. Supported browsers are Chrome, Firefox, Edge, and Safari. 
      <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/heads-up-aws-support-for-internet-explorer-11-is-ending/" rel="noopener">Learn more »</a> 
     </p> 
      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Do you need ID to read the REAL-ID rules? (210 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/25/do-you-need-id-to-read-the-real-id-rules/</link>
            <guid>42239952</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 20:40:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/25/do-you-need-id-to-read-the-real-id-rules/">https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/25/do-you-need-id-to-read-the-real-id-rules/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42239952">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<p><a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop.jpg"><img loading="lazy" src="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop-1024x485.jpg" alt="" width="960" height="455" srcset="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop-1024x485.jpg 1024w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop-300x142.jpg 300w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop-768x363.jpg 768w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop-1536x727.jpg 1536w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-gatehouse-crop.jpg 2016w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px"></a><em>[“The welcoming, friendly and visually pleasing appearance” of the TSA’s headquarters at 6595 Springfield Center Drive, Springfield, VA.]</em></p>
<p>We spent most of a day last week outside the headquarters of the Transportation Security Administration (TSA), trying and failing to find out what the rules are for the <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/04/tsa-launches-smartphone-based-digital-id-scheme/">TSA’s new digital-ID scheme</a>.&nbsp; What we did learn is that, by TSA policy and practice, you can’t read the <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/category/real-id/">REAL-ID</a> rules, get to the TSA’s front door, or talk to any TSA staff unless you already have ID, bring it with you, and show it to the private guards outside the TSA’s gates.</p>
<p>The problems we have faced just trying to get access to the text of the TSA’s rules raise issuess about (recursive) incorporation by reference of third-party, nongovernmental text in regulations, secret law, and access to Federal services and rights by those without ID, as well as the underlying issues of REAL-ID, mobile driver’s licenses, and digital IDs.</p>
<p>In late October, <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/04/tsa-launches-smartphone-based-digital-id-scheme/">as we’ve previously reported</a>, the TSA issued a <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/FR-2024-10-25/pdf/2024-23881.pdf">final rule</a> establishing “standards” for smartphone-based digital IDs that would be deemed by the TSA to comply with the <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/category/real-id/">REAL-ID Act of 2005</a>. These mobile driver’s licenses (mDLs) will be issued by state driver’s license agencies, but the standards incorporated into the TSA rule require that they be deployed through smartphone platforms (i.e. Google and/or Apple) and operate through government apps that collect photos of users and log usage of these credentials.</p>
<p>The standards themselves — the meat of the TSA’s rule — weren’t published in the <em>Federal Register</em> or made public either when the rule was <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2023/10/16/the-tsa-wants-to-put-a-government-tracking-app-on-your-smartphone/">proposed</a> or when it&nbsp; was <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/04/tsa-launches-smartphone-based-digital-id-scheme/">finalized</a>. Instead, thousands of pages of documents from private third parties were <a href="https://www.archives.gov/federal-register/write/ibr">incorporated by reference</a> into the TSA’s rules, giving them the force of law, on the basis of false and fraudulent claims — the falsehood of which was easy for anyone who checked to verify — that they were “reasonably accessible” to affected individuals.</p>
<p><a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/category/secret-law/">Secret laws</a> are <em>per se</em> a violation of due process, and should be<em> per se</em> null and void. How can it be that “ignorance of the law is no excuse” if the government has kept you ignorant of the law, even when you try to find out what the law says?</p>
<p>You shouldn’t need ID to read the law, just as you shouldn’t need ID to travel by common carrier. But the TSA doesn’t seem to have read the Constitution.</p>
<p><span id="more-19215"></span>In its <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/FR-2024-10-25/pdf/2024-23881.pdf">final</a> rule, the TSA repeated some of the same <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/04/tsa-launches-smartphone-based-digital-id-scheme/">easily disproved lies</a> about the availability of the material incorporated by reference in the rule that <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2023/10/16/the-tsa-wants-to-put-a-government-tracking-app-on-your-smartphone/">it had made in its earlier Notice of Proposed Rulemaking</a> (NPRM). But the TSA also made a new claim that the material incorporated by reference in the rule was available for public inspection, by appointment, both at the Office of the Federal Register (a component of the National Archives and Records Administration) and at TSA Headquarters:</p>
<blockquote><p>All approved incorporation by reference (IBR) material is available for inspection at the Transportation Security Administration (TSA) and at the National Archives and Records Administration (NARA). Please contact TSA at Transportation Security Administration, Attn.: OS/ESVP/REAL ID Program, TSA Mail Stop 6051, 6595 Springfield Center Dr., Springfield, VA 20598–6051, (866) 289–9673, or visit www.tsa.gov. You may also contact the REAL ID Program Office at REALID-mDLwaiver@tsa.dhs.gov or visit www.tsa.gov/REAL-ID/mDL. For information on the availability of this material at NARA, visit www.archives.gov/federal-register/cfr/ibr-locations.html or email fr.inspection@nara.gov.</p></blockquote>
<p>We immediately contacted both NARA and the TSA at these email addresses, requesting to inspect the material incorporated by reference in this rule.</p>
<p>NARA told us that this material isn’t stored at the office where it will (eventually, if and when it is found) be made available by NARA for public inspection. It might take up to six weeks, possibly longer, to locate and retrieve from offsite storage:</p>
<blockquote><p>I don’t have an estimated date for your appointment. The system we had for public access is not working and we are working to replace it. But how long that will take depends on our parent agency (the National Archives and Records Administration)….</p>
<p>If you wish to inspect all of the material listed in 6 CFR 37.4… it is in storage at a Federal Records Center. We will have to contact the FRC to get the material returned to us. That process generally can take up to 6 weeks; however, given the upcoming change in administration (and increased workloads for all involved), it could take longer.</p></blockquote>
<p>If it might take months for even the Office of the Federal Register to find the text which has been incorporated in Federal regulations and has the force of law, there’s a problem. But NARA says that whether documents incorporated in regulations are reasonably available is determined by whether they are available from the agency which promulgated the regulations — in this case, the TSA — and not by whether they are available from NARA.</p>
<p>The TSA’s initial answer seemed more promising:</p>
<blockquote><p>We would be delighted to coordinate a visit to TSA so you may examine the materials requested and will work to provide you with information on how to access our facilities soon.</p></blockquote>
<p>After some back and forth by email, I arranged an appointment at the TSA’s headquarters at 9 a.m. on Monday, November 18th, for an escorted visit to inspect the documents incorporated by reference in the TSA’s “mobile driver’s license” rule. I was told that to inspect the rules I would have to provide my Social Security number and date of birth, “so that you can be cleared through Security.” I did so, reluctantly.</p>
<p>Despite my efforts to avoid any surprises and anticipate any problems, my visit didn’t go well.</p>
<p>The TSA occupies a <a href="https://www.bizjournals.com/washington/news/2021/05/27/inside-the-new-tsa-headquarters.html">purpose-built but privately owned new building</a> in Springfield, VA, an hour outside Washington, DC, and a short-ish walk past the Washington Metro Transit Police Academy from the last stop on one of the Washington Metrorail lines. (There’s a <a href="https://visualconstruction.com/TSA/">virtual tour here</a> of some parts of the interior that I never got to see.)</p>
<p><a href="https://www.lsginc.com/lsg_projects/transportation-security-administration-headquarters/">According to the architects</a>, the fortifications around&nbsp; the building were designed to<em> look</em> “welcoming” and “friendly”, while actually keeping the building secure against public access:</p>
<blockquote><p>LSG’s involvement was focused on the design of the entrance plaza and arrival sequence along the North facing public entrance of the project… LSG assisted with integration of elaborate security requirements in the site design. Security measures included K12 barriers, fences, gates, cameras and a specific vehicular circulation pattern for employees, visitors and services, etc. LSG’s focus was to integrate the security measures necessary without compromising the welcoming, friendly and visually pleasing appearance expected for TSA Headquarters.</p></blockquote>
<p>I arrived at the guardhouse outside the gate in the TSA’s perimeter fence at 8:45 a.m., to allow time for whatever security theater might be required before my 9 a.m. appointment.</p>
<p>I described what happened next in an email message I sent shortly afterward:</p>
<blockquote><p>I am outside the entrance to your building, but a guard who refuses to give his name with a badge that says “Golden Services Security” refuses either to admit me without ID, which I don’t have, or attempt to contact anyone with the TSA.</p>
<p>I specifically asked you, in my email message of November 1, to advise me of any access procedures for individuals without ID, who are obviously in the class of individuals impacted by the rules I want to access. You did not advise me of any ID requirement.</p>
<p>I request that you either admit me to access the rules, as scheduled, or provide formal notice of your decision to deny me access identifying by name and title the decision maker, the basis for the denial including any rules relied on, and any available procedures for administrative review of that decision, so that I can attempt to exercise any available administrative appeals before returning to California empty-handed, having wasted more time and money in a diligent but unsuccessful last-resort attempt to access these rules after all other access methods claimed by you proved to be unavailable.</p>
<p>As I noted in my first email message to you, it is impossible to reach you at the phone number specified in the final rule for access requests. You have provided me with no other phone number, and the guard refused my request that they call whatever point of<br>
contact or escort is listed on the visitor list.</p>
<p>I will wait outside the entrance to your building for one hour, until 10 am, unless I am ordered to leave.</p></blockquote>
<p>I waited on an uncomfortable metal bench, exposed to the elements, just outside the fence. At 9:57 a.m., as I was about to give up and leave, someone called me from inside the building. They told me they had been assigned to escort me and were waiting for me at the “Visitor Center” inside the building. I told them, as I had said in my email message, that the guard wouldn’t let me get to the building without ID, which (as I had told them in advance) I didn’t have. They said they could only escort me once I got to the Visitor Center inside the building, and that they didn’t have “clearance” to come out to the fenceline to meet me. Catch-22.</p>
<p>Eventually they conferenced in — at their initiative — Mr. Anurag Maheshwary, an attorney in the Office of the Chief Counsel of the TSA. Mr. Maheshwary was <a href="https://www.govinfo.gov/content/pkg/FR-2024-10-25/pdf/2024-23881.pdf">listed in the <em>Federal Register</em></a> as the point of contact for legal questions about the mobile driver’s license (mDL) rule.</p>
<p>Mr. Maheshwary professed surprise and disbelief that I didn’t have ID, despite having been copied on my earlier queries about access procedures and protocols for people without ID. “What ID did you use to fly here from California? You must have ID.” (Wrong, even if I had flown, which I hadn’t said I had done.)</p>
<p>When I repeated the request I had made in my email message that, if I was to be denied access to the documents incorporated in the TSA’s rules, I be given formal notice of that denial, Mr. Maheshwary immediately demanded that the person who had called me, and had conferenced him in, disconnect him from the call. “You’ve conferenced in the wrong person!” He repeated that demand and hung up when she called back and tried again to get him to talk to me.</p>
<p>A little later, as I was again preparing to give up and leave, the same person called me again to say that, “We’re trying to work out how to get you access to the documents.”</p>
<p>As with travel by common carrier, the TSA wants to create the impression that ID is required to read the text of its regulations, and acts in practice as though ID is required, but knows that it would have a hard time defending such a policy in court. So the TSA doesn’t put this policy in writing, and backs down (or at least claims that some alternative, albeit an inconvenient one, is available for people without ID) when confronted with people without ID who it perceives as sufficiently able and willing to assert their rights.</p>
<p>Shortly after 11 a.m., by which time I had been sitting on the <a href="https://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Group%20W%20Bench">Group W bench</a> for more than two hours, a TSA staffer came out with two large TSA-logo tote bags of documents.</p>
<div id="attachment_19216"><p><a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-19216" loading="lazy" src="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop-485x1024.jpg" alt="" width="379" height="800" srcset="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop-485x1024.jpg 485w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop-142x300.jpg 142w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop-768x1623.jpg 768w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop-727x1536.jpg 727w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-minder-crop.jpg 954w" sizes="(max-width: 379px) 100vw, 379px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-19216">[The face of the TSA]</p></div><div id="attachment_19218"><p><a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop.jpg"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-19218" loading="lazy" src="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop-535x1024.jpg" alt="" width="418" height="800" srcset="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop-535x1024.jpg 535w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop-157x300.jpg 157w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop-768x1470.jpg 768w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop-802x1536.jpg 802w, https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/TSA-documents-crop.jpg 954w" sizes="(max-width: 418px) 100vw, 418px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-19218">[Some of the documents I was allowed to look at, but not to take with me.]</p></div>&nbsp;
<p><br clear="all">One bag, which I was allowed to take with me, contained about ten pounds of copies of documents that are (purportedly) freely available online. Getting these documents directly from the TSA allowed me to be certain that they matched — or at least were claimed by the TSA to match — the text incorporated by reference into the TSA’s rules. That wouldn’t be possible with copies obtained from a private publisher or other third party, who would be neither able, willing, nor required to warrant that the copies they provided or sold matched what the TSA had depostied with the Office of the Federal Register. So that take-home bag had some official significance, but held no big surprises.</p>
<p>The other bag, only slightly smaller, contained copies of documents that the TSA conceded weren’t freely available, but that it wouldn’t allow me to take with me. I was alloted not more than three hours to inspect them, sitting on a bench outside with my TSA minder sitting at the other end of the bench (equally uncomfortably, I presume) to make sure I didn’t try to take away any of the non-public documents included in the TSA’s rules.</p>
<p>After another hour, around noon, my minder found another bench at a bus stop nearby that, while equally uncomfortable for us both, was at least partially shielded from the wind.</p>
<p>After yet another hour, a little after 1 p.m. — by which time I needed a toilet and was getting increasingly cold, not having dressed to spend five hours outside —&nbsp; my TSA minder (who had been busy texting persons unknown on his phone) told me that arrangements had been made for me to be escorted into the building to continue my reading of the bag of non-public documents. I was given no explanation as to why this hadn’t been done four hours earlier when I arrived for my scheduled appointment.</p>
<p>An armed guard came out, and he and the business-suited minder who had been sitting on the bench with me escorted me through the gate in the fence and across no-man’s-land to the entrance to the building. After going theough a metal detector, I was escorted to a restroom (at least they waited outside) and then back out past the metal detector to a conference room just inside the outer entry door that appeared to be there specifically for the purpose of meetings with visitors not cleared to go further into the building.</p>
<p>In the limited time that I was allowed to spend with these documents, I was able to confirm that they require that mDL credentials be “provisioned” through a TSA-approved app on a TSA-approved device, with that device biometrically “bound” to an individual. The process of “presenting” a digital ID will be a four-way interaction between the&nbsp; individual, the app (it’s unclear whether or how the user will be able to authenticate the app or know what it is doing), functions on the device to collect biometrics (controlled, in all likelihood, by an operating system with root privileges whose actions can’t be monitored or controlled by the individual), and the credential-issuing driver’s license agency.</p>
<p>mDL apps will be required to log each time a digital ID is presented, and to whom. This is described as a measure to protect ID-holders’ privacy, despite the obvious risk posed by police or others being able to know when and to whom you have shown your ID. If you use your digital ID for <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2024/11/05/what-will-the-future-bring-for-id-demands/">age verificaiton</a> to show that you are old enough ton be allowed to access adult information about sexual health or <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2022/09/22/freedom-to-travel-to-get-an-abortion/">abortion</a>, that fact will be logged on your device.</p>
<p>Supposely these logs will be available only to the device owner. But in reality, they will also be available to anyone who seizes the device while it is unlocked, cracks the device lock with forensic or criminal tools, or forces an individual — legally or illegally — to unlock it.</p>
<p>The TSA is already issuing <a href="https://www.dhs.gov/sites/default/files/2024-03/24_0315_st_mdl_investigative_aid_journey.pdf#page=4">guidance to other law enforcement agencies</a> on the information about the usage of these digital IDs that may be available to and via Google or Apple.</p>
<p>But there’s more. To my dismay, if not surprise, I found that the non-public documents incorporated by reference in the TSA’s rules themselves incorporate by reference<em> other</em> documents, many of them also non-public.</p>
<p>How mnay levels of recursion do we have to follow to get to the bottom of the TSA’s rules? <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turtles_all_the_way_down">It’s turtles all the way down.</a></p>
<p>After leaving the area, I sent the following message to the TSA:</p>
<blockquote><p>Yesterday we finally saw the non-public documents incorporated by reference in the mDL NPRM and Final Rule. It was immediately apparent from the volume and technical nature of this material that understanding, much less assessing or responding to, these documents would require at least several weeks and consultation with technical specialists who are not necessarily available or willing to travel to Springfield.</p>
<p>It is clear that neither we nor other members of the public have been provided with “reasonable” access to this material.</p>
<p>It also appears that your agency knew when you designated your building in Springfield as the location where these documents were purportedly accessible to the public [that it] was encircled by a guarded fence, and that members of the public without ID were not permitted even to approach the building or speak with any TSA employee. Having fenced yourself off from the public, it is fraudulent[,] and compelling evidence of bad faith[,] to claim that this inaccessible building is accessible to the public.</p>
<p>You cannot claim to have been taken by surprise. In our comments on the false and fraudulent claim in the NPRM that these documents were available for inspection at some unspecified DHS facility, we specifically raised the potential problem of access or entry without ID:</p>
<p>“Access procedures are especially critical with respect to this proposed rule because ‘the class of persons affected’ – the relevant category pursuant to 1 CFR § 51.7(3), as quoted above – obviously includes individuals who do not have ID deemed compliant with the REAL-ID Act.</p>
<p>“It is unclear what, if any, procedures have been established to enable individuals who do not have ID deemed compliant with the REAL-ID Act to obtain access to the relevant premises at ‘DHS Headquarters’, at whichever of the many possible locations that might be, to inspect the material proposed to be incorporated by reference into the proposed rule.</p>
<p>“Individuals seeking to review this material can’t simply go the specifiedaddress, since no address is specified, even if they would be allowed in the door, which they probably wouldn’t.”</p>
<p>We diligently sought to avoid these problems. We asked explicitly, in writing, in advance of our appointment, whether there was any protocol for access to this building by people without ID. We also asked for a point of contact and phone number we could call in case of access problems. We were provided with no point of contact or phone number, and were told of no ID requirement.</p>
<p>Individuals may need a license from a government agency to operate a motor vehicle. They do not need a license to read the law or to travel by common carrier. If the TSA or any other agency proposed a rule to require ID to read the law or travel by common carrier, we and many others would oppose it, for multiple reasons. But no such rules have been promulgated.</p>
<p>One of your staff asked me yesterday how I had traveled to the DC area, whether I had traveled by air, and whether I has shown any ID to do so. As a matter of principle and personal security, I do not wish to discuss my travel history, modes, or plans with you, and I am not required to do so. But the consistent position of your agency in litigation has been that no Federal law or regulation requires airline passengers to have, to carry, or to show ID. The responses by your agency to some of our FOIA requests confirm that, as you know, <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/2022/03/15/how-many-people-fly-without-real-id/">people fly without ID every day</a>.</p>
<p>“The public” includes individuals who do not have ID, and to be accessible to the public, documents or services need to be accessible to those without ID.</p>
<p>After two hours waiting outside your gatehouse, getting increasingly cold, I was able to leaf through some of the non-public IBRs documents in the brief and inadequate time available. But the material I was allowed to look at was incomplete. Many of the non-public documents incorporated by reference in the Final Rule themselves incorporate by reference additional documents, some of them also non-public, which I was not shown. I have attached to this message, as a non-exhaustive example, the <a href="https://papersplease.org/wp/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/recursive-IBR.pdf">list of documents</a> incorporated by reference in one of the ISO/IEC documents incorporated by reference in the Final Rule.</p>
<p>By the explicit terms of the documents IBRd in the final rule, these *additional* documents constitute part of, are essential to understanding, and are included in the requirements of the documents IBRd in the rule.</p>
<p>Just as the IBRd documents form part of the rule and have the force of law, all of the these documents IBRd in the documents IBRd in the rule form part of the rule and have the force of law. Compliance with these other recursively IBRd documents is required for compliance with the rule.</p>
<p>All such documents, at any level of recursion, are included in our right of access and our request for access to all documents IBRd in the rule….</p>
<p>Presumably you have them in house, since by their own explicit terms they are essential to understanding, and form part of, the documents IBRd in your rules. If you don’t have them available for me to look at today, I request that you make them accessible to the public without my having to return to the DC area.</p></blockquote>
<p>We’ve been promised a response from the TSA by December 2nd. In the meantime, we have reported to the Office of the Federal Register that many of the documents incorporated by reference in the TSA’s mDL rule, including those recursively incorporated by reference, are not reasonably available from the TSA. The approval for incorporation by reference of these documents should be rescinded, and the rule should be withdrawn.</p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Short Introduction to Automotive Lidar Technology (202 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/short-intro-to-automotive-lidar</link>
            <guid>42239721</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 20:12:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/short-intro-to-automotive-lidar">https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/short-intro-to-automotive-lidar</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42239721">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>Ubiquitous adoption of lidar in self driving cars needs one major thing: lower cost. </p><p><span>Lidar has proven to be a capable technology for </span><a href="https://www.sae.org/blog/sae-j3016-update" rel="">level 4</a><span> autonomous driving, and is already used in self driving taxis by Waymo and Cruise. But the spinning lidar domes on top of these cars cost thousands of dollars, and that number needs to drop by at least an order of magnitude.</span></p><p><span>There are </span><a href="https://tracxn.com/d/companies/lidar/__S0h0aWT4FqieGUvRDUJ0Jly7aZjCfw3Yk5P2sJUm04Y/competitors#competitive-landscape" rel="">over 140 startups</a><span> in the lidar space looking to make that happen and more.</span></p><p><strong>In this post, we will cover the basics of automotive lidar technology:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Lidar for autonomous vehicles</p></li><li><p>Wavelength of operation</p></li><li><p>Photodetectors</p></li><li><p>Ranging techniques</p></li><li><p>Mechanical lidar</p><ul><li><p>Scanning systems</p></li><li><p>MEMS mirrors</p></li></ul></li><li><p>Solid-state lidar</p><ul><li><p>Flash lidar</p></li><li><p>Optical phased arrays</p></li></ul></li><li><p>References</p></li></ul><p><strong>Read time</strong><span>: 12 mins</span></p><p><em>The post may be too long for email. Please read it online.</em></p><p>Lidar stands for Light Detection and Ranging and is a method where infrared laser light is used to measure the distance to a remote object. This technology is not new. For years, it has been used for imaging vegetation, urban terrain, hidden archeological sites, building construction and recently, in augmented reality. Its particular superpower is that it can generate high resolution images of its surroundings much better than radar can. While lidar and radar are fundamentally similar in operation, the use of shorter wavelengths (lasers) compared to radar (microwaves) gives it the ability to generate highly detailed images.</p><p>In last week’s article, we looked at the camera versus lidar debate for self driving cars. If you missed that, you can read it below.</p><div data-component-name="DigestPostEmbed"><a href="https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/teslas-big-bet-cameras-over-lidar" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa10835d4-e008-4f1b-8763-fc1da126c6e2_1456x1048.png"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fa10835d4-e008-4f1b-8763-fc1da126c6e2_1456x1048.png" sizes="100vw" alt="Tesla’s Big Bet: Cameras over LiDAR for Self Driving Cars" width="140" height="140"></picture></div></a></div><p>Since 2020, lidar has become especially relevant as the “eyes” of autonomous vehicles. Its ability to rapidly generate precise 3D images of the surroundings is critical in making accurate distance estimations for self driving. The downside of lidar is cost. Laser sources, detectors and associated electronics and mechanics are expensive. The rise of solid-state lidar technologies may still offer a competitive price point for widespread adoption of lidar in self driving cars. </p><p>The next sections will explain the inner workings of lidar technology.</p><p>Lidar systems are predominantly designed to operate in one of two wavelengths that are in the infrared region (750 nanometers to 15 micrometers) of the electromagnetic spectrum, but outside visible range (380 to 700 nanometers).</p><ol><li><p>905 nm (near infrared, or NIR)</p></li><li><p>1550 nm (short wave infrared, or SWIR)</p></li></ol><p>The choice of wavelength in a lidar system depends on the output power of laser sources, sensitivity of detectors and the interference from natural and artificial light sources in the same spectrum.</p><p><span>Sunlight is one of the dominant sources of interference which has a lot of energy in the infrared region of the spectrum. A measure of sunlight’s impact is called the </span><em>solar photon flux</em><span>, which is the amount of sunlight hitting the earth at any given wavelength.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png" width="1110" height="524" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:524,&quot;width&quot;:1110,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:346506,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5fc614d4-eb17-4411-bb8c-1a9be3ad80a5_1110x524.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>Impact of sunlight at ground level versus wavelength. Source: </span><a href="https://ouster.com/insights/blog/how-multi-beam-flash-lidar-works" rel="">Ouster</a></figcaption></figure></div><p>There are some noticeable dips at 905, 940 and 1550 nm due to absorption by water vapor in the upper atmosphere, which conveniently reduces interference in systems at ground level. Unfortunately, the same effect absorbs radiation in foggy and rainy road conditions. The proximity of the 905 nm wavelength to the visible range causes two other concerns:</p><ol><li><p>905 nm laser wavelengths are easily absorbed by the retina causing damage from prolonged exposure. As a result, there are strict standards for lidar eye safety that must be adhered to.</p></li><li><p>There are plenty of interference sources near visible light, both from the sun and from vehicle headlamps that degrade the system performance.</p></li></ol><p><span>However, at shorter wavelengths, photodetectors are generally more sensitive and laser sources are more powerful and inexpensive. </span><a href="https://ouster.com/" rel="">Ouster</a><span>, for example, has actually adopted 850 nm for its lidar technology despite high solar photon flux due to better visibility in damp conditions, improved source and detector performance, with patented approaches to rejecting environmental interference.</span></p><p>1550 nm wavelength mitigates some problems; lower interference from solar radiation, and lower eye safety concerns because this wavelength only penetrates up to the cornea, thus protecting the retina. Better eye safety implies that more power can be used at 1550 nm for longer periods of time, providing longer detection range. The downside of 1550 nm wavelength is that the high absorption by water vapor makes it difficult to use in wet conditions.</p><p>The choice of wavelength also depends on the capabilities and economics of photodetectors.</p><p>Avalanche photodiodes (APDs) are the most commonly used detectors in lidar. They are specially engineered PN semiconductor junctions that utilize the photoelectric effect to generate electron-hole pairs in response to incident photons. They generate a current proportional to the number of photos incident, which depends on the amount of reverse bias on the diode. </p><p>APDs are most often built with Silicon (Si), Germanium (Ge), and Indium Gallium Arsenide (InGaAs), but each of them respond differently to infrared wavelengths. Silicon APDs respond well to NIR and are inexpensive to manufacture, while InGaAs works well for SWIR wavelengths but are more expensive.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp" width="610" height="431.575" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/f0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:566,&quot;width&quot;:800,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:610,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;APD response curves&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="APD response curves" title="APD response curves" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ff0292f4a-da98-4104-898b-009a3d06305c_800x566.webp 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><span>Responsivity curves for various infrared sensor APDs. Source: </span><a href="https://phluxtechnology.com/latest/the-role-of-infrared-sensors-in-light-detection-and-ranging-lidar" rel="">Phlux</a></figcaption></figure></div><p>A popular detector used in lidar systems is the single-photon avalanche diode (SPAD). SPADs are especially interesting as photodetectors. Unlike traditional avalanche photodiodes (APDs) which generate a signal proportional to the amount of light, SPADs generate a near binary response to the arrival of a photon by operating in “Geiger-mode” where the photodiode is heavily reverse-biased. </p><p>The avalanche breakdown effect in the diode generates massive amounts of current  when incident even with a single photon. With this, the timing of photon arrivals can be determined to pico-second (trillionth of a second) accuracies which allows accurate distance measurements using these sensors. An added benefit is that SPADs can be implemented in a CMOS process making them low cost. This also allows massive amounts of signal processing to be integrated right next to the detector array.</p><p><span>Especially at 905 nm, silicon photomultipliers (SiPMs) have largely replaced Si APDs. SiPMs are arrays of microcells comprising of a SPAD with a </span><em>quenching </em><span>resistor to self-limit the flow of avalanche current. SiPMs provide very high photoelectric gain and are capable of detecting the precise number of incident photons depending on output current levels.</span></p><p>The detection of object distance using lidar is called ranging, and there are two popular approaches that are often used.</p><p>Much like how sonar echo-location or pulsed doppler radar works, ToF sensing using lidar involves emitting laser bursts and measuring the time taken to detect the reflected signal. The total time elapsed from signal emission to reception is called the round-trip delay. Since the actual time to the object is half the round-trip delay, the distance is calculated using the speed of light in the propagating medium.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png" width="552" height="284.1017612524462" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:526,&quot;width&quot;:1022,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:552,&quot;bytes&quot;:307963,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F44af7fa1-46af-4473-bc07-a693fa4f1cfd_1022x526.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>ToF lidar ranging. Credit: Philip Sandborn, Berkeley Technical Report UCB/EECS-2019-148: https://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2019/EECS-2019-148.pdf</figcaption></figure></div><p>The smallest distance that can be measured using ToF depends on the resolution of the timing electronics. A nearby object might have a short round-trip delay that the detector might not resolve. Hence the minimum depth of such radars are usually limited to a few centimeters.</p><p>The largest distance that can be measured depends on the transmitted power, detector sensitivity and free space path loss. If the reflected signal is indistinguishable from background noise, then the distance to the object cannot be resolved. Commercial dToF systems have a maximum range of 100-200 meters.</p><p>Most lidar systems today use dToF ranging methods due to simplicity. A slightly different temporal detection approach is to use continuous wave signals, and detect the phase shift of the reflected wave. This method is called indirect ToF (iToF), or more specifically amplitude modulated continuous wave (AMCW). It is less sensitive to timing drift and better suited to short distance measurements.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png" width="526" height="273.293542074364" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:531,&quot;width&quot;:1022,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:526,&quot;bytes&quot;:350913,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F93cf1c08-bb87-4655-b18d-e981140811b6_1022x531.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>AMCW lidar ranging. Credit: Philip Sandborn, Berkeley Technical Report UCB/EECS-2019-148: https://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2019/EECS-2019-148.pdf</figcaption></figure></div><p>While ToF uses pulsed or continuous wave signals of a fixed wavelength, there are benefits to modulating it. Lidars that use the modulation of the wavelength or frequency of the transmitted pulse are called FMCW lidars. While many sources online claim that FMCW lidar is new technology, it is not. It has been around since the 1960s and the concept is widely used in automotive radar technology.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png" width="564" height="290.27788649706457" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:526,&quot;width&quot;:1022,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:564,&quot;bytes&quot;:339118,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05020a5f-e089-46ba-bdf8-cf12e6d4517d_1022x526.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>FMCW LiDAR. Credit: Philip Sandborn, Berkeley Technical Report UCB/EECS-2019-148: https://www2.eecs.berkeley.edu/Pubs/TechRpts/2019/EECS-2019-148.pdf</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Each burst of frequency modulated signal is called a “chirp”, and the reflected signal received after a time delay has an instantaneous frequency difference between transmitted and reflected pulses. This “beat” frequency can be downconverted using a mixer and used to compute </span><em>both</em><span> distance and velocity of the object. I have explained before how this works for radar, and the same principles apply to lidar. </span></p><div data-component-name="DigestPostEmbed"><a href="https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/how-automotive-radar-uses-chirp-signals" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e2dc2a5-7b48-4d51-95e2-14a2c310e184_1092x786.gif"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1e2dc2a5-7b48-4d51-95e2-14a2c310e184_1092x786.gif" sizes="100vw" alt="How Automotive Radar uses Chirp Signals for Sensing" width="140" height="140"></picture></div></a></div><div data-component-name="DigestPostEmbed"><a href="https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/how-automotive-radar-measures-velocity" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05261946-b4bd-4db6-83c8-d78ecff6ce5a_1092x786.gif"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F05261946-b4bd-4db6-83c8-d78ecff6ce5a_1092x786.gif" sizes="100vw" alt="How Automotive Radar Measures the Velocity of Objects" width="140" height="140"></picture></div></a></div><p>FMCW lidar systems are complex to implement due to the need for a frequency tunable laser source for modulation and additional electronics needed to extract information from the transmitted and received signals. But they do give lower interference from nearby lidar systems because the frequencies are different at any point in time. Also, FMCW lidar requires lower peak power from a laser compared to ToF which has implications in eye safety requirements especially at 905 nm.</p><p><span>A mechanical lidar has an infrared laser that is mounted on a brushless DC motor that rotates the sensor thus providing it a 360° field of view (FOV) in the horizontal direction and eliminating any blindspots. The FOV in the vertical direction is still limited to about 90-95°. An example of a mechanical scanning lidar sensor is Waymo’s </span><a href="https://waymo.com/blog/2019/03/bringing-3d-perimeter-lidar-to-partners/" rel="">Laser Bear Honeycomb</a><span>, which is often seen mounted on top of its self driving fleet of cars. The motors and its associated precision moving parts add to the bill of materials, and are subject to wear and tear from repeated use. As a result, scanning lidar systems are bulky and expensive.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic" width="562" height="322.93537015276144" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:489,&quot;width&quot;:851,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:562,&quot;bytes&quot;:28913,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/heic&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F42188af9-55a4-4bd4-bb89-25506272e386_851x489.heic 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Waymo’s Jaguar iPace with a scanning Lidar sensor. Source: Waymo</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Instead of moving the laser source and sensor around like in mechanical scanning, another approach is to reflect the laser light off a movable micro-electromechanical (MEMS) mirror. By oscillating the MEMS mirror back and forth at a fixed rate, the lidar can be scanned across 3D space. MEMS mirrors can be made to move with electrostatic (only electric field), electromagnetic (electric and magnetic field), or electrothermal (with heat) actuation mechanisms. Below is a nice demonstration of the concept; video credits: </span><a href="https://www.ttp.com/insights/building-the-perfect-mems-mirror-for-next-generation-lidar-what-have-we-learned/" rel="">TTP</a><span>. </span></p><p>A trade-off in MEMS mirror design is weight versus scanning rate; a heavy mirror will have low scanning rate. While the video above shows 1D scanning, 2D MEMS mirrors have also been implemented where the mirrors have a slow and fast axis. The mirrors move quickly along one direction allowing fast raster scanning, while moving slower in the perpendicular direction to only produce a static positional shift for a new rapid scan.</p><p>Arguably, the greatest benefit is the fact that MEMS mirrors can be fabricated using back-end-of-line processes in a legacy CMOS foundry and are considered a mature technology. This enables low-cost implementations of scanning lidar technology.</p><p>Instead of scanning 3D space, think of flash lidar as a photographic capture that illuminates the space in front of it. Flash lidar consists of a vertical-cavity surface-emitting laser (VCSEL) as laser source that is diffused to illuminate a target. The reflected signals are detected with an SiPM array. These lidar flashes are taken at rates up to 30 frames per second providing a real-time rendering of 3D space. By the nature of how it works, flash lidar has a reduced FOV compared to a rotating mechanical lidar scanner.</p><p>The resolution of flash lidar is limited by how many pixels fit into a given area, much like a digital camera. Compared to the scanning type, flash lidar has lower signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) because the limited optical laser power needs to be distributed to all pixels in the array. The detection sensitivity is also limited by background noise in the environment at the same wavelength as the laser. SNR is the ultimate limiting factor in the detection range of flash lidar with sensing distances up to 100 meters and centimeter-scale resolutions being reported in literature.</p><p><span>Some companies have adopted a </span><em>multi-beam </em><span>approach to flash lidar, illuminating only those parts of the environment where the detector is looking for information. This allows greater optical power to be directed at fewer, but more relevant pixels in the array, enhancing SNR. It is a combination of scanning and flash lidar, with the advantages of both.</span></p><p>Overall, the lack of moving parts means that the system is much more reliable, immune to vibration effects, and has increased data capture rate.</p><p>The most recent approach still in the research phase is to use silicon photonics to implement scanning lidar on a chip. The idea is borrowed from phased array antennas which allow scanning of the radiated beam by adjusting the phase shift of each signal fed to an antenna array. Phase shifts are implemented either with integrated optical waveguides, or by using integrated heaters to slow light through the mechanism of thermo-optic coupling. Depending on the phase shift, the direction of the radiated wavefront can be scanned in 3D space. I have explained this in a previous article.</p><div data-component-name="DigestPostEmbed"><a href="https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/basics-of-phased-array-antennas-and" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F10cc2e24-476f-4f04-998d-ce32e7573756_1456x1048.png"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_140,h_140,c_fill,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep,g_auto/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F10cc2e24-476f-4f04-998d-ce32e7573756_1456x1048.png" sizes="100vw" alt="How does a Phased Array Antenna work? Types of Beamforming Architectures" width="140" height="140"></picture></div></a></div><p>Now, the same approach is being utilized to steer infrared lasers by implementing phase shifts to integrated optical modulators in a photonics platform. The benefits of OPA are greatly increased scanning speeds due to electronic control and no moving parts. The cost and reliability benefits from a purely integrated approach on 300-mm diameter silicon wafers is also attractive.</p><p>The use of optical frequencies presents its own challenges in the context of phased arrays:</p><ol><li><p><strong>Thermal management</strong><span>: The heat generated from many on chip laser sources must be dissipated effectively.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Proximity of elements</strong><span>: Phased arrays require elements spaced half a wavelength apart. At 1550 nm laser wavelength, that means each laser source needs to be spaced under a micron apart.</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Scanning angle</strong><span>: In phased arrays, the best quality beam is at “boresight” or right in front of the array. As the beam is scanned away from the center, say beyond 60°, grating lobes degrade the beam width. </span></p></li></ol><p><a href="https://www.analogphotonics.com/home/" rel="">Analog Photonics</a><span> is a spin off from MIT, founded by Prof. Michael Watts, that is working on commercializing OPA technology and is worth keeping an eye on.</span></p><ul><li><p><span>EETimes: </span><a href="https://www.eetimes.com/whats-the-direction-for-automotive-lidar-905-nm-or-1550-nm/" rel="">What’s the Direction for Automotive LiDAR: 905 nm or 1550 nm?</a></p></li><li><p><span>Texas Instruments: </span><a href="https://www.ti.com/lit/wp/slyy150b/slyy150b.pdf?ts=1703269882036" rel="">An introduction to automotive lidar</a></p></li><li><p><span>Onsemi: </span><a href="https://www.onsemi.com/pub/Collateral/AND9770-D.PDF" rel="">Introduction to the Silicon Photomultiplier</a></p></li><li><p><span>Aeye: </span><a href="https://www.aeye.ai/resources/white-papers/time-of-flight-vs-fmcw-lidar-a-side-by-side-comparison/" rel="">Time of Flight vs. FMCW LiDAR: A side-by-side comparison</a></p></li><li><p><span>IEEE Spectrum: </span><a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/lidar-on-a-chip" rel="">Lidar on a chip puts self driving cars in the fast lane</a></p></li><li><p><span>Phlux: </span><a href="https://phluxtechnology.com/latest/the-role-of-infrared-sensors-in-light-detection-and-ranging-lidar" rel="">The role of infrared sensors in light detection and ranging - lidar</a></p></li><li><p><span>N. Li </span><em>et al.</em><span>, “A Progress Review on Solid‐State LiDAR and Nanophotonics‐Based LiDAR Sensors,” </span><em>Laser &amp; Photonics Reviews</em><span>, vol. 16, no. 11, p. 2100511, Nov. 2022, doi: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.1002/lpor.202100511" rel="">10.1002/lpor.202100511</a><span>.</span></p></li><li><p><span>D. Wang, C. Watkins, and H. Xie, “MEMS Mirrors for LiDAR: A Review,” </span><em>Micromachines</em><span>, vol. 11, no. 5, p. 456, Apr. 2020, doi: </span><a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/mi11050456" rel="">10.3390/mi11050456</a><span>.</span></p></li></ul><p>If you like this post, please click ❤️ on Substack, subscribe to the publication, and tell someone if you like it. 🙏🏽 </p><p><span>If you enjoyed this issue, </span><strong>reply to the email</strong><span> and let me know your thoughts, or leave a comment on this post.</span></p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/short-intro-to-automotive-lidar/comments&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Leave a comment&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.viksnewsletter.com/p/short-intro-to-automotive-lidar/comments" rel=""><span>Leave a comment</span></a></p><p>Join a Discord community of professionals, enthusiasts and students, and get in on the discussion.</p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://discord.gg/e6ysnA9c7q&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Join Discord&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://discord.gg/e6ysnA9c7q" rel=""><span>Join Discord</span></a></p><p><em>The views, thoughts, and opinions expressed in this newsletter are solely mine; they do not reflect the views or positions of my employer or any entities I am affiliated with. The content provided is for informational purposes only and does not constitute professional or investment advice.</em></p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Redis is trying to take over the all of the OSS Redis libraries (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/TomHacohen/status/1861137484249252093</link>
            <guid>42239607</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 20:00:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/TomHacohen/status/1861137484249252093">https://twitter.com/TomHacohen/status/1861137484249252093</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42239607">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Prayer, Placement, and Absolution: Peter Hristoff on Islamic Prayer Rugs (2015) (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.metmuseum.org/perspectives/peter-hristoff-islamic-prayer-rugs</link>
            <guid>42239487</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 19:45:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.metmuseum.org/perspectives/peter-hristoff-islamic-prayer-rugs">https://www.metmuseum.org/perspectives/peter-hristoff-islamic-prayer-rugs</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42239487">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section data-sentry-element="PageSection" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" data-sentry-component="PageSection"><section data-sentry-element="Subsection" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" data-sentry-component="Subsection"><article data-sentry-component="EditorialRichText" data-sentry-source-file="index.tsx"><figure><img alt="Peter Hristoff. Untitled" data-loading="true" data-sentry-element="Image" data-sentry-component="SanityImage" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" loading="lazy" width="600" height="276" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 85vw, 1200px" srcset="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=640&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 640w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=750&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 750w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=828&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 828w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=1080&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1080w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=1200&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1200w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=1920&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1920w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=2048&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 2048w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 3840w" src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/b9b1d9ba974e91cad256381ada200068c47275b8-600x276.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format"><figcaption><p>Peter Hristoff. <em>Untitled</em>, 2005. Wool; 159 1/2 x 73 3/4 in. Private collection</p></figcaption></figure><p>«At a recent <a target="_self" rel="noreferrer" data-sentry-element="Link" data-sentry-component="ExternalLink" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" href="https://www.metmuseum.org/events/programs/met-fridays">MetFridays</a> event in the <a target="_self" rel="noreferrer" data-sentry-element="Link" data-sentry-component="ExternalLink" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" href="https://www.metmuseum.org/exhibitions/new-installations/new-galleries-for-the-art-of-the-arab-lands-turkey-iran-central-asia-and-later-south-asia">Galleries for the Art of the Arab Lands, Turkey, Iran, Central Asia, and Later South Asia</a>, I spoke about prayer rugs (<em>seccades</em>)—not as a scholar of the Islamic arts, but as an artist. In 1997 I started a series of drawings based on my assumptions of what people pray for and why they pray. I eventually turned these drawings into a suite of serigraph prints entitled <em>Ten Prayers</em> that I exhibited, in September 1998, at my first one-man show at the Yapi Kredi Cultural Center's Kazim Taskent Gallery in Istanbul. These works then led to a series of larger "rug" pieces done on rice paper, which combined the motifs I was using in my paintings (masks, birds, skulls, stylized flowers, cosmological symbols, and figures) with the formal structure of Anatolian carpets.»</p><p>My interest in <em>halis</em> (rugs) and <em>kilims</em> (flat weaves) was a natural connection to the journal-like quality of my work. I was fascinated by the diarist elements in traditional Turkish carpet making—the weaver incorporating events, personal beliefs, hopes, and desires with traditional regional symbols into their work—an approach I incorporated (and still incorporate) into my art making.</p><p>I began to work on rug-inspired prints a few years later, in which I would, on a daily basis, complete a horizontal band of the composition that recorded my interests, personal mythologies, and artistic preoccupations. I always had the intention of eventually creating actual <em>halis</em> and <em>kilims</em> in Turkey, as the notion of the <em>seccade</em> (prayer rugs) particularly fascinated me—an object that creates a sacred space wherever it is placed, and is charged with hope and spiritual connections as well as a physical relationship to the body and geography.</p><figure><img alt="Peter Hristoff. Untitled; A rug maker shows one of her pieces in a fabric shop in Tokat, Turkey" data-loading="true" data-sentry-element="Image" data-sentry-component="SanityImage" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" loading="lazy" width="600" height="523" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 85vw, 1200px" srcset="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=640&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 640w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=750&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 750w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=828&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 828w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=1080&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1080w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=1200&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1200w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=1920&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1920w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=2048&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 2048w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 3840w" src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0bb0ed30198e1fc1274dfa7cf000c63ecdfbf0eb-600x523.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format"><figcaption><p>Left: Peter Hristoff. <em>Untitled</em>, 2005. Wool; 85 x 51 in. Collection of Ömer Özyürek. Right: A rug maker shows one of her pieces in a fabric shop in Tokat, Turkey, June 2015. Photo by the author</p></figcaption></figure><p>The ritual of placement, prayer, and absolution all tap into issues I have been addressing in my work since the early 1980s, which make the <em>seccade</em>—an object of contemplation and decoration—an obvious focus in my work. I am interested in "bright sadness," a term I came upon in the Patriarch Bartholomew's statement in the <a target="_self" rel="noreferrer" data-sentry-element="Link" data-sentry-component="ExternalLink" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" href="https://www.metmuseum.org/research/metpublications/Byzantium_Faith_and_Power_1261_1557">exhibition catalogue</a> that accompanied <a target="_self" rel="noreferrer" data-sentry-element="Link" data-sentry-component="ExternalLink" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" href="https://www.metmuseum.org/exhibitions/listings/2004/byzantium-faith-and-power"><em>Byzantium: Faith and Power</em></a> (2004), which most accurately describes my interests. In the publication, Bartholomew writes: "This refers to a mixed emotion of joy, over the anticipated help from God and Salvation, and sorrow, for the suffering of life and sin." This juxtaposition of the spiritual and the physical, the happy and the sad—mankind's conflicted nature—continues to be a predominant theme of my work.</p><figure><img alt="Peter Hristoff. Ten Seccades" data-loading="true" data-sentry-element="Image" data-sentry-component="SanityImage" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" loading="lazy" width="600" height="338" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 85vw, 1200px" srcset="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=640&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 640w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=750&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 750w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=828&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 828w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=1080&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1080w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=1200&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1200w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=1920&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 1920w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=2048&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 2048w, https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format 3840w" src="https://cdn.sanity.io/images/cctd4ker/production/0557c2763374e97543439a995cb9eefe6e03a177-600x338.jpg?w=3840&amp;q=75&amp;fit=clip&amp;auto=format"><figcaption><p>Peter Hristoff. <em>Ten</em> Seccades, 2011. Wool; variable sizes. Collection of the artist</p></figcaption></figure><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/hY_LuwUZ5I8?modestbranding=1" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen="" data-sentry-component="YoutubePlayer" data-sentry-source-file="index.tsx"></iframe><blockquote>Peter Hristoff. <em>Prayer Niche</em>, 2007</blockquote><p><a target="_self" rel="noreferrer" data-sentry-element="Link" data-sentry-component="ExternalLink" data-sentry-source-file="index.jsx" href="https://www.metmuseum.org/blogs/listing?tag=Peter+Hristoff&amp;st=tag">Read all blog posts related to Peter Hristoff's residency at the Met.</a></p></article><hr></section><section id="contributors" data-sentry-component="ArticlePageSection" data-sentry-source-file="index.tsx"><h4>Contributors</h4><p><address data-sentry-component="BodyContributor" data-sentry-source-file="index.tsx"><span data-sentry-component="Name" data-sentry-source-file="index.tsx">Peter Hristoff</span></address></p></section></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Deno vs. Oracle: Canceling the JavaScript Trademark (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://deno.com/blog/deno-v-oracle</link>
            <guid>42239263</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 19:20:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://deno.com/blog/deno-v-oracle">https://deno.com/blog/deno-v-oracle</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42239263">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>On November 22, 2024, Deno formally filed a petition with the USPTO to cancel
Oracle’s trademark for “JavaScript.” This marks a pivotal step toward freeing
“JavaScript” from legal entanglements and recognizing it as a shared public
good.</p>
<p>If successful, the petition will eliminate barriers that have stifled community
use of the name. Conferences could reclaim titles like “JavaScript Conference”
instead of settling for “JSConf.” The language’s specification could finally
drop the cumbersome “ECMAScript” moniker and be known simply as the “JavaScript
Specification.” Communities like
<a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/programming/comments/14vnipl/rust_for_javascript_developers_ltd_received_a/" rel="noopener noreferrer">“Rust for JavaScript Developers”</a>
would no longer fear legal threats over their use of the term.</p>
<p><strong>The full petition is available
<a href="https://ttabvue.uspto.gov/ttabvue/v?pno=92086835&amp;pty=CAN&amp;eno=1" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a></strong> and is
based on three claims:</p>
<h3 id="claim-1-javascript-is-generic">Claim 1: JavaScript is generic</h3>
<p>The term “JavaScript” has become the universal name for the programming language
defined by the ECMA-262 specification. It is used globally by millions of
developers and organizations, entirely independent of Oracle. By law, trademarks
that have become generic cannot remain trademarks.</p>
<p>Oracle neither controls nor has ever controlled the language’s specification or
usage. Millions of developers, companies, and educators rely on JavaScript every
day without Oracle’s involvement. As stated in the petition, JavaScript is not a
brand; it is a cornerstone of modern programming.</p>
<h3 id="claim-2-oracle-committed-fraud">Claim 2: Oracle committed fraud</h3>
<p>When Oracle renewed the JavaScript trademark in 2019, it submitted fraudulent
evidence to the USPTO. This included screenshots of Node.js—a project founded by
myself and entirely unrelated to Oracle. Presenting Node.js as evidence of
Oracle’s “use in commerce” violates the integrity of trademark law.</p>
<p>The USPTO likely relied on this false evidence to renew the trademark, which
potentially invalidates its renewal.</p>
<h3 id="claim-3-the-trademark-has-been-abandoned">Claim 3: The trademark has been abandoned</h3>
<p>Oracle has abandoned the trademark through nonuse. The petition demonstrates
that Oracle has not offered significant products or services under the name
“JavaScript” in years.</p>
<p>Obscure offerings like the JavaScript Extension Toolkit or GraalVM, do not
constitute genuine use in commerce. U.S. law considers trademarks unused for
three consecutive years as abandoned, and Oracle’s inaction clearly meets this
threshold.</p>
<p>The petition builds on overwhelming community support. Over 14,000 developers,
including JavaScript creator Brendan Eich, have signed
<a href="https://javascript.tm/" rel="noopener noreferrer">our open letter</a> urging Oracle to release the
trademark. You can also read more about the history of this issue in
<a href="https://tinyclouds.org/trademark" rel="noopener noreferrer">my 2022 blog post</a>.</p>
<h3 id="what-happens-next">What Happens Next?</h3>
<p>Oracle has until <strong>January 4, 2025</strong>, to respond. If they fail to act, the case
will go into default, and the trademark will likely be canceled. We sincerely
hope Oracle takes this path, acknowledging that “JavaScript” belongs to its
global community—not to a single corporation.</p>
<p>However, if Oracle chooses to fight, we are ready. We will present a wealth of
evidence proving that Oracle has failed to use the trademark as the law
requires. Every step of this proceeding—including all communications with
Oracle—will be shared transparently with the community.</p>
<p>Help us spread the word by sharing this post. Together, we can ensure that the
name “JavaScript” is as open and accessible as the language itself.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42239263" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discuss on HN.</a></em></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Gemini LLM corrects ASR YouTube transcripts (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ldenoue.github.io/readabletranscripts/</link>
            <guid>42238890</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 18:44:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ldenoue.github.io/readabletranscripts/">https://ldenoue.github.io/readabletranscripts/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42238890">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <p id="myform">
      <h2><a href="https://ldenoue.github.io/readabletranscripts">Readable Transcripts</a></h2>
      <form method="get">
        
        
      </form>
      <form method="get">
        
        
      </form>
    </p>
    
    <div id="container">
      <div id="col1">
        <h2><a href="https://ldenoue.github.io/readabletranscripts"><i></i></a></h2>
        <p><b id="vtitle">... title</b></p>
        
        
        
        <p>Getting summary...</p>
      </div>
      <div id="col2">
        <p><b>LLM-corrected transcript</b></p>
      </div>
      <div id="col3">
        <p><b>Original YouTube transcript</b></p>
      </div>
    </div>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: I am Building a Producthunt alternative (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://huntlie.com</link>
            <guid>42238396</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 17:56:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://huntlie.com">https://huntlie.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42238396">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>© 2024 Huntlie |<!-- --> <a href="https://x.com/heyarviind">@heyarviind</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fleng 22 (concurrent logic programming) (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.call-with-current-continuation.org/fleng/fleng.html</link>
            <guid>42238299</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2024 17:44:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.call-with-current-continuation.org/fleng/fleng.html">http://www.call-with-current-continuation.org/fleng/fleng.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42238299">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>