<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 22:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tauri 2.0 Release Candidate (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://v2.tauri.app/blog/tauri-2-0-0-release-candidate/</link>
            <guid>41141962</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 19:44:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://v2.tauri.app/blog/tauri-2-0-0-release-candidate/">https://v2.tauri.app/blog/tauri-2-0-0-release-candidate/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41141962">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>   <p>We are very proud to finally announce the first release candidate for the new major version of Tauri.</p>
<p>After over half a year of beta versions, following over a year of alpha versions we are finally at the point where we consider Tauri 2 stabilized and do no longer expect breaking changes.</p>
<p>We want to use a comparably short release candidate time frame to focus on our documentation and important bug fixes, which have been reported by our awesome community and working group members.</p>
<p>A simplified <a href="#too-long-didnt-read">TL;DR</a> can be found at the end of this post.</p>
<h2 id="the-road-to-stable-and-beyond"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#the-road-to-stable-and-beyond">The Road to Stable and Beyond</a></h2>
<p>With this release candidate we want to communicate our expectations and timeline for the stable release.</p>
<p>We have been asked countless times “<em>Wen Tauri 2.0?</em>” and always gave broad answers. Especially in open source projects overpromising can be a quick way to burn out developers and maintainers or lead to angry comments from disappointed adopters.</p>
<p>This is one of the reasons for the long alpha and beta stage and why we waited with the release candidate, as we strive to get things right and simple to use.</p>
<p>Another reason is that we made the mistake of overpromising this major version with “<em>mobile as a first class citizen</em>” and realized over the past months that we
can only build the foundation for mobile on our own and need to iterate on this together with the community and our adopters to get it right.</p>
<p>This doesn’t mean that mobile is broken and unsupported. We have mobile plugins in our official plugin repository and have seen developers who have built cool apps on Android and iOS with Tauri.</p>
<p>Our partner <a href="https://crabnebula.dev/">CrabNebula</a> also provided us with feedback on how easy (or complicated) the developer experience was when they built or supported mobile applications for customers. They even contributed multiple mobile plugins (<a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/plugins-workspace/tree/v2/plugins/nfc">NFC</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/plugins-workspace/tree/v2/plugins/barcode-scanner">Barcode Scanner</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/plugins-workspace/tree/v2/plugins/biometric">Biometric</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/plugins-workspace/tree/feat/haptics/plugins/haptics">Haptics</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/plugins-workspace/tree/feat/geolocation/plugins/geolocation">Geolocation</a>) as part of their work.</p>
<p>We see improvements to be made in the development experience for mobile and we acknowledge that not all of our desktop features and plugins are ported or available on mobile yet.</p>
<p>This causes us to say that we don’t want to raise expectations that Tauri 2.0 will be <em>the</em> “<em>mobile as a first class citizen</em>” release but we want to make clear that you can develop production ready mobile applications with Tauri <strong>NOW</strong>.</p>
<p>What you can expect from stable after this release candidate is:</p>
<ul>
<li>Clearer and comprehensive documentation</li>
<li>Less critical bugs preventing productive usage</li>
</ul>
<p>We plan to release the stable version for 2.0 in the end of August. This will, at the time of writing, allow for a ~4 week release candidate cycle.</p>
<p>After the stable release our focus will be shifting to providing feature parity wherever possible and to improve the development process for mobile. This will happen in minor releases of Tauri.</p>
<p>Feature parity and plugin development will be aligned with major versions of Tauri but will be mostly independent from Tauri core features and happen in our <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/plugins-workspace">plugin-workspace</a> repository.</p>
<p>Developer experience is a very important topic for us. If you have improvement suggestions or want to improve the status quo on your own please do not hesitate to reach out with PRs, issues or friendly conversations on our discord server.</p>
<h2 id="breaking-changes"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#breaking-changes">Breaking Changes</a></h2>
<p>Before we enter the “<em>no more breaking changes</em>” expectation phase we discussed and planned some from our perspective necessary breaking changes a while ago.</p>
<p>These changes affect a lot of developers, so we wanted to bundle them and make it as painless as possible to upgrade from the latest beta to release candidate or stable.</p>
<p>For app developers we have breaking changes in how core plugins are referenced in the permissions.</p>
<p>You should be able to automatically migrate from the latest beta to release candidate. For this to succeed you must be sure to be on the latest (RC not beta) version of the Tauri <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/releases?q=tauri-cli&amp;expanded=false">CLI</a>.</p>

<p>Otherwise please read the detailed section <a href="#tauri-core-plugins">below</a> explaining the changes and how to manually migrate.</p>
<p>For downstream consumers of Tauri as a library or app developers fiddling with the internals of Tauri we have a bigger <a href="#rust-api-surface-refactor">refactor</a> you should check out.</p>
<h3 id="tauri-core-plugins"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#tauri-core-plugins">Tauri Core Plugins</a></h3>
<p>With Tauri 2.0 we migrated most of the 1.x core functionality into separate plugins, which allows us to iterate on these independently of Tauri’s core and lowers the barrier for first contributors on functionality.</p>
<p>This migration also included keeping some functionality inside Tauri as pseudo plugins. Fully qualified plugins need to implement the <a href="https://docs.rs/tauri/2.0.0-rc/tauri/plugin/trait.Plugin.html"><code dir="auto">Plugin Trait</code></a> and need to be individual crates following the <code dir="auto">tauri-plugin-&lt;plugin name&gt;</code> naming scheme. For core plugins, the second condition was not possible as we would have circular dependencies on Tauri. So we created pseudo plugins, which are always initialized by Tauri itself and only implement the plugin trait. These are for example <code dir="auto">window</code>, <code dir="auto">path</code> or <code dir="auto">webview</code>. Right now these are allowed in the <a href="https://v2.tauri.app/security/capabilities/">capabilities</a> of your Tauri application in the following way:</p>
<div><figure><pre data-language="json"><code><div><p><span>...</span></p></div><div><p><span>"</span><span>permissions</span><span>"</span><span>: [</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>path:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>event:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>window:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>app:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>image:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>resources:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>menu:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>tray:default</span><span>"</span></p></div><div><p><span>]</span></p></div><div><p><span>...</span></p></div></code></pre></figure></div>
<p>This has multiple problems:</p>
<ul>
<li>Any plugin crate which has a colliding name will break our build process (e.g. <code dir="auto">tauri-plugin-window</code> crate) and our cli for adding plugins (e.g. <code dir="auto">cargo tauri add window</code>)</li>
<li>We can’t use any core pseudo plugin naming that is already used by existing plugins (e.g. if we would ever want to create<code dir="auto">tauri-plugin-mobile-core</code> and it is already used we will encounter the first problem)</li>
<li>It is unclear for developers what is a core plugin and what is a dedicated plugin when looking at capabilities</li>
</ul>
<p>Our approach is to use a fixed namespace for core plugins, which is documented and enforced by the Tauri core. All plugins starting with <code dir="auto">core:</code> or the plugin name <code dir="auto">core</code> are now considered core pseudo plugins and will only be initialized if they are in the Tauri codebase.</p>
<p>This will cause a breaking change to all capabilites enabling Tauri core features. The above example will be changed to look like this:</p>
<div><figure><pre data-language="json"><code><div><p><span>...</span></p></div><div><p><span>"</span><span>permissions</span><span>"</span><span>: [</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:path:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:event:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:window:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:app:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:image:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:resources:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:menu:default</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:tray:default</span><span>"</span></p></div><div><p><span>]</span></p></div><div><p><span>...</span></p></div></code></pre></figure></div>
<p>We also added a new special <code dir="auto">core:default</code> permission set which will contain all default permissions of all core plugins, so you can simplify the permissions boilerplate in your capabilities config.</p>
<div><figure><pre data-language="json"><code><div><p><span>...</span></p></div><div><p><span>"</span><span>permissions</span><span>"</span><span>: [</span></p></div><div><p><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>core:default</span><span>"</span></p></div><div><p><span>]</span></p></div><div><p><span>...</span></p></div></code></pre></figure></div>
<p>We consider the core default exposure to be reasonably secure and safe to enable by default, with limited impact in case of a compromised frontend.</p>
<p>To migrate from the latest beta version you need to prepend all core permission identifiers in your capabilities with <code dir="auto">core:</code> or switch to the <code dir="auto">core:default</code> permission and remove old core plugin identifiers.</p>
<h3 id="development-server-for-mobile"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#development-server-for-mobile">Development Server for Mobile</a></h3>
<p>We introduced changes to the network exposure of the built-in development server <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/pull/10437">PR #10437</a> and <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/pull/10456">PR #10456</a>.
With the changes shipped in the 2.0.0-rc.0 release of the Tauri CLI, we can connect to your development server running on localhost when targetting
Android and iOS (previously this was only possible when developing a desktop application).</p>
<p>This means you no longer need to expose your development server on the public network.</p>


<h3 id="rust-api-surface-refactor"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#rust-api-surface-refactor">Rust API Surface Refactor</a></h3>
<p>With a coordinated effort between multiple working group members we partially changed our Rust API exposure. This affects only consumers of our Rust API and should have no breaking change impact for Tauri application developers.</p>
<p>This was motivated by a recent security advisory <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/security/advisories/GHSA-57fm-592m-34r7">CVE-2024-35222</a>, as the fix needed to introduce additional fields to a structure that was directly publicly exposed and caused breaking changes to some projects and internal usage.</p>
<p>We concluded that this overexposure will hinder us in the future and will cause unnecessary breaking changes, so we decided that going from beta to RC will be the last chance for us to implement this until we start down the road of Tauri 3.0.</p>
<p>We reduced the amount of publicly exposed components, which are meant for internal use. Additionally, we made our publicly exposed structures either non-exhaustive or transformed them into exposing builder patterns or constructors. In some cases we added a new <code dir="auto">extend</code> field to allow dynamic additions in the future. Finally, we made sure to document which modules of Tauri are considered unstable.</p>
<p>This will help us to provide (security) fixes or changes without breaking interfaces that are considered stable.</p>
<p>Please take a closer look at the introduced and discussed changes in the <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/pull/10158">#10158</a> pull request.</p>
<h2 id="external-security-audit"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#external-security-audit">External Security Audit</a></h2>

<p>We have been quiet on this front for some time as we have been busy fixing and discussing issues discovered during the beta versions.</p>
<p>We never marketed version 2 beta releases as production ready but were aware of some apps deployed into production. This caused us to announce and distribute a security patch for one of the findings (<a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/security/advisories/GHSA-57fm-592m-34r7">CVE-2024-35222</a>) which was also independently discovered by a Tauri community member.</p>
<p>All other findings were fixed in multiple beta versions but we did not create advisories for these. We concluded a full heads up could wait until the release candidate, as the findings mainly affect the development phase or have no critical severity.</p>
<p>With the release candidate we will add the full report to our repository. Please take your time to read the report and learn more about the awesome work of <a href="https://github.com/gronke">@gronke</a> and <a href="https://github.com/pcwizz">@pcwizz</a> from <a href="https://www.radicallyopensecurity.com/">RadicallyOpenSecurity</a>.</p>
<p>The whole audit was funded by the great folks at <a href="https://nlnet.nl/">NLNet</a> and we are super grateful to be in the privileged position to get fully funded external security audits.</p>
<h2 id="call-to-action"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#call-to-action">Call to Action</a></h2>
<p>All of the above topics share a common theme. These would not have been possible without the continuous support of the community, our working group and other movements working towards improving the status quo.</p>
<p>Before we are going to release Tauri 2.0 we want to make sure that your voices are heard, your PRs are acknowledged and the documentation is helpful for <strong>YOU</strong> so that you can build the next generation of cross platform apps.</p>
<p>Currently we have over 30 people in our working group on Github but even more involved in our <a href="https://discord.gg/tauri">Discord</a>. These awesome people are mostly working on Tauri in their free time with very few exceptions. We currently see a number of issues, PRs and discussions being unsolved and open for longer than we would like to.</p>
<p>To improve this situation we ask <strong>YOU</strong> to get involved into the Tauri project.We have all kinds of situations where we are able to accept event the tiniest contribution.</p>
<p>If you are familiar with Tauri and have used it already during your journey, please take your time to check out the <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/discussions">Github Discussions</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/issues">Github Issues</a> and our <a href="">Discord Support</a>. Maybe you have already solved the issues your fellow newcomers to Tauri are experiencing right now.</p>
<p>If you think that some of these problems you have seen are generic and should be documented somewhere we probably have the perfect place for it in our official <a href="https://v2.tauri.app/">documentation</a>.</p>
<p>To contribute improvements or additions we are open for PRs in the <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri-docs">tauri-docs</a> repository. Please make sure you’ve read the <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri-docs/blob/v2/.github/CONTRIBUTING.md">guidelines</a> for contribution though.</p>
<p>If you are in the position to understand and translate the current documentation into your native language we appreciate <a href="https://v2.tauri.app/contribute/translate-status">content translations</a> to our documentation.</p>
<p>If you have followed our project for a while but never made a contribution we would be happy to understand what has prevented you from doing so and how we could improve this. Please reach out to us in our <a href="https://discord.gg/tauri">Discord</a> or in our <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/discussions">Github Discussions</a>.</p>
<h2 id="too-long-didnt-read"><a aria-hidden="" tabindex="-1" href="#too-long-didnt-read">Too Long Didn’t Read</a></h2>
<ul>
<li>Tauri 2.0 Release Candidate out now!</li>
<li>Some migration from beta is needed. Check out <a href="https://v2.tauri.app/start/migrate/from-tauri-1/#automated-migration"><code dir="auto">tauri migrate</code></a>.</li>
<li>External Security Audit for 2.0 is going to be available <a href="https://github.com/tauri-apps/tauri/blob/dev/audits/Radically_Open_Security-v2-report.pdf">here</a> soon</li>
<li>All findings are fixed and fixes were verified</li>
<li>Documentation is our focus until stable release</li>
<li>Tauri is looking for more contributors and community involvement</li>
</ul>  </div><p>© 2024 Tauri Contributors. CC-BY / MIT</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[About Google Chrome's "This extension may soon no longer be supported" (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/uBlockOrigin/uBlock-issues/wiki/About-Google-Chrome%27s-%22This-extension-may-soon-no-longer-be-supported%22</link>
            <guid>41140185</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 16:26:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/uBlockOrigin/uBlock-issues/wiki/About-Google-Chrome%27s-%22This-extension-may-soon-no-longer-be-supported%22">https://github.com/uBlockOrigin/uBlock-issues/wiki/About-Google-Chrome%27s-%22This-extension-may-soon-no-longer-be-supported%22</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41140185">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wiki-body" data-view-component="true">
                <p>Starting with Google Chrome 127, there will be a warning for uBlock Origin (uBO) in your <code>chrome://extensions/</code> page:</p>
<p><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/585534/354625184-40c6c11f-aef5-4b97-ba2b-c63dc76f219e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MzA5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYzMDYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81ODU1MzQvMzU0NjI1MTg0LTQwYzZjMTFmLWFlZjUtNGI5Ny1iYTJiLWM2M2RjNzZmMjE5ZS5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQyMDMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT00YWRiNmIyMjkwYTIxMzgxNDkxNTYzOWU1YTY1MTJmMzllYmYyOThmNjAwYThmZTQyODZiNjlhMjIyZDkxZTg4JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.Vyn7GhCQU3v0vHwgvsuKwh6yJStmnrlUG6XRxm5fY-w" alt="a" content-type-secured-asset="image/png"></p>
<p>This is the result of <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/develop/migrate/mv2-deprecation-timeline" rel="nofollow">Manifest v2 support</a> being deprecated in favor of <a href="https://developer.chrome.com/docs/extensions/develop/migrate/what-is-mv3" rel="nofollow">Manifest v3</a>.</p>
<p>uBO is a Manifest v2 extension, hence the warning in your Google Chrome browser. There is no Manifest v3 version of uBO, hence the browser will suggest alternative extensions as a replacement for uBO:</p>
<p><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/585534/354626846-2dc9d217-5c52-441a-b406-e29180707df8.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MzA5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYzMDYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81ODU1MzQvMzU0NjI2ODQ2LTJkYzlkMjE3LTVjNTItNDQxYS1iNDA2LWUyOTE4MDcwN2RmOC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQyMDMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1mZDdlMTcwODc5OTY2MjU4NGY2MTkyNTNjMTdlZTc1MjMxYTMxMzljYjliM2UzZWFmNDIwZWUzMTM4ZTIwOGM2JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.nHz0lOlp9GQDcxlWpRTfL-DrHMpap2HJwawrJ_LirgQ" alt="b" content-type-secured-asset="image/png"></p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/uBlockOrigin/uBOL-home">uBO Lite (uBOL)</a> is a pared-down version of uBO with a best effort at converting filter lists used by uBO into a Manifest v3-compliant approach, with a focus on reliability and efficiency as has been the case with uBO since first published in June 2014.</p>
<p>However the focus on reliability and efficiency in a Manifest v3 environment meant having to sacrifice many features beyond those not possible within a Manifest v3 framework.</p>
<p>See the <a href="https://github.com/uBlockOrigin/uBOL-home/wiki/Frequently-asked-questions-(FAQ)">official uBOL FAQ webpage</a> for more details about how uBOL compares to uBO.</p>
<p>Manifest v2 uBO will not be automatically replaced by Manifest v3 uBOL. uBOL is too different from uBO for it to silently replace uBO -- you will have to explicitly make a choice as to which extension should replace uBO according to your own prerogatives.</p>
<p>Ultimately whether uBOL is an acceptable alternative to uBO is up to you, it's not a choice that will be made for you.</p>
<p><h3>Will development of uBO continue?</h3><a id="user-content-will-development-of-ubo-continue" aria-label="Permalink: Will development of uBO continue?" href="#will-development-of-ubo-continue"></a></p>
<p>Yes, there are other browsers which are not deprecating Manifest v2.</p>

              </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Marshmallow Test Fails to Replicate (335 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://srcd.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cdev.14129</link>
            <guid>41139854</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 15:49:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://srcd.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cdev.14129">https://srcd.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cdev.14129</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41139854">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://srcd.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cdev.14129: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Upstream Cause of the Youth Mental Health Crisis Is the Loss of Community (442 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental</link>
            <guid>41139149</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 14:40:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental">https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41139149">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p><strong>Intro from Zach Rausch and Jon Haidt:</strong></p><p><span>Today, we publish our third post on what we now call the “first act” of </span><em>The Anxious Generation</em><span>: the loss of community. (The second act is the loss of the play-based childhood. The third act is the rise of the phone-based childhood.) In our </span><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/community-based-childhood" rel="">first post,</a><span> Zach discussed Robert Putnam’s essential work on the decline of social capital and trust, which happened in part because new individualizing technologies (such as television) emerged and participation in local and communal activities waned. As communities weakened and trust eroded, so did the play-based childhood.</span></p><p><span>In the </span><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/neighborhoods-that-nurture-why-thehttps://www.afterbabel.com/p/neighborhoods-that-nurture-why-thehttps://www.afterbabel.com/p/neighborhoods-that-nurture-why-the" rel="">second post</a><span>, we featured an essay by </span><a href="https://sethkaplan.org/" rel="">Seth Kaplan</a><span>, author and lecturer at Johns Hopkins who studies fragile states. In it, he argued that to restore the play-based childhood, we must first rebuild strong in-person local communities. In this post, Seth takes his argument one step further, asserting that the upstream cause of the youth mental health crisis is the loss of community. As we are offered new virtual ways to connect with one another, Seth contends that we are only growing further apart.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>We note that the first generation to move its social life onto social media platforms immediately became the </span><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/arent-you-lonely" rel="">loneliest generation</a><span> on record. There is a spectrum of approaches that we as a society can take to address the crushing loneliness of Gen Z and Gen Alpha. On one end is doubling down on technology, typified by the recent introduction of the </span><a href="https://www.wired.com/story/friend-ai-pendant/" rel="">creepy AI “friend” orb</a><span>, which young people can wear around their necks so that they always have a “friend” to talk with. On the other end is to focus on strengthening the real-world human communities and neighborhoods we live in. Seth advocates for the latter and provides us with a roadmap to get there.</span></p><p><strong>— Zach and Jon</strong></p><p><span>Jonathan Haidt and Zach Rausch </span><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/community-based-childhood" rel="">argue</a><span> that the loss of community is one of three factors behind the deterioration in youth mental health, along with the decline of play and the emergence of phone-mediated childhood. But in this article, I argue that it’s actually the </span><em>dominant factor</em><span> since it is upstream from the other two.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>The rapid spread of smartphones in the early 2010s triggered the dramatic uptick in mental distress among youth, but this happened especially in places where the social system supporting them was already hollowed out. As </span><a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2024/06/06/opinion/religious-teens-mental-health/" rel="">Rausch writes</a><span>, kids who live in well-rooted “real-world communities … spending more time engaging in their local community –</span><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1moM3e_dcajEJzDR_uBK1mIs3hZ8vFZJ4MfUx7NZIx3I/edit#gid=809472783&amp;range=B35" rel=""> attending religious services, working, spending more time with trusted adults</a><span>, and spending more</span><a href="https://bookshop.org/p/books/the-generations-jean-m-twenge/18698850?ean=9781982181611" rel=""> time</a><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/19/podcasts/transcript-ezra-klein-interviews-jean-twenge.html" rel=""> with their friends</a><span> in person” — are less likely to experience the harms of the phone-based childhood. Where community is strong, the impact has been softened.</span></p><p>In this post, I argue that kids need real-world community to thrive and that the weakening (and even breakdown) of neighborhood communities across many countries explains many of the problems facing youth today—from screen addiction and the decline in mental health to rising drug addiction and growing loneliness.</p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share" rel=""><span>Share</span></a></p><p>The term “community” is often used, but its meaning is rarely articulated. It is sometimes conflated with a “sense of community,” which can be produced by working with a dedicated group of volunteers or in a close-knit organization. But, an actual community is more permanent and is much harder to create. A prototypical community consists of most or all of the following:</p><ul><li><p><span>A web of overlapping, affect-laden </span><strong>associations and relationships</strong><span> that crisscross and reinforce each other;</span></p></li><li><p><span>A set of </span><strong>shared values, norms, and goals</strong><span>—a common culture that unifies and constrains;</span></p></li><li><p><span>A </span><strong>common identity</strong><span>, ideally based on a common history and narrative and recognition of mutual interdependence;</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Shared rituals</strong><span> that celebrate the group, its past, and future;</span></p></li><li><p><span>High levels of </span><strong>trust</strong><span>;</span></p></li><li><p><span>High levels of </span><strong>commitment</strong><span>, with limited options for (or high costs to) exit;</span></p></li><li><p><span>Recognition of and respect for common </span><strong>authority</strong><span> figures who guide the group’s decision-making;</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Keystone actors and institutions</strong><span> that bridge and bond different members together;</span></p></li><li><p><span>A </span><strong>diverse range of skills and personalities</strong><span> that can contribute complementary things of value (e.g., money, time, expertise) to the group;</span></p></li><li><p><strong>Role models</strong><span> who exhibit the cultural behaviors that the group should ideally replicate or at least aspire to;</span></p></li><li><p><span>Exhibiting a high degree of </span><strong>inclusiveness</strong><span> by actively seeking to encompass every member who shares the same identity or location;</span></p></li><li><p><span>Capacity to strongly encourage through moral suasion certain </span><strong>norms</strong><span> of conduct and, if necessary, sanction misconduct.</span></p></li></ul><p>As we can see from this list, a community requires a commitment to a certain social order—and usually to a place—that, by definition, must constrain some choices. In return for security, support, and belonging, members surrender some of their freedom. This explains why creating community in America today is so difficult—few want to compromise their ability to make choices. This is especially true among those with the resources and/or capacity to relocate as soon as a better opportunity beckons—the very people whose leadership and role-modeling communities can ill afford to lose.</p><p>Much of a child’s learning and formation is absorbed from the environment rather than directly taught by adults; behavior is better shaped by modeling than by lecturing. The institutions (e.g., schools, churches, and parents’ groups) and norms (e.g., regular family dinners, neighborhood play dates, and the expectation that adults will monitor streets) around us shape our kids' lives in ways we sometimes fail to consider because they are subtle. These institutions and norms determine the strength of families, interfamily networks, neighborhood relationships, and communal support systems. They shape each kid’s attitudes toward relationships, technology, and life goals. For example, when adults and older kids in my neighborhood model kindness, generosity, and responsibility to one another, my kids learn that these are the norms we should all aspire to in a way that no textbook or teacher (or parent) can instruct. When my religious neighborhood turns off technology for one day a week—on Shabbat—we are showing our kids that embodied relationships and interaction are more important than our phones and virtual networks. These institutions and the norms thus have an enormous influence on the choices parents and kids make every day, and on how vulnerable the latter are to various challenges like smartphones, drug use, and gang involvement.</p><p><span>As I documented in a</span><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/neighborhoods-that-nurture-why-the" rel=""> previous essay at After Babel</a><span>, unsupervised, child-directed play was in decline long before kids had smartphones. Why? Because place-based institutions and the communities they support were in decline. Instead of spending time with peers in the neighborhood (the norm for millennia because we all lived in place-based communities), </span><a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/Generations/Jean-M-Twenge/9781982181611" rel="">kids</a><span> were already spending much of their time outside of school </span><a href="https://www.brookings.edu/articles/how-free-time-became-screen-time/" rel="">at home</a><span> with </span><a href="https://www.apa.org/pubs/journals/releases/ppm-ppm0000203.pdf" rel="">televisions</a><span>, computers, or video games. More affluent children had many of their activities organized for them by their parents, putting them in a variety of highly structured functional groups with different kids rather than repeatedly playing freely with their neighbors. This oversupervision or “coddling”—the subject of the</span><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Coddling-American-Mind-Intentions-Generation/dp/0735224919/ref=sr_1_1?dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.yyb49J53TZs_9w5jNGcgLCRAqGuBAc-b28AzzCCPcsdxUKlU_TTJtUu4ssi1UOK-WbEB2boDybMiuYFlsaHtpf5fZhrhsQjKSbr3NdpP-QJHw85Obxf-EpRKFsbvY1C13wwU1CWYisHPXsVTT6eCefQrwype6OZ3wttmy5GEKw5s9gR6jCboJyrP_msts2KJo9sOHHqSx1AVF_962RtI8wUPc1H3AR0mw_slivFqgoGkdUpSnDp_5sb68zWnZ2ECULJV5wZDAJ2cqz4oFkxS1m87_InfwIfk7lyZEZQcw2U.XhGIGJzOKGa_whWg772-29bt_1jJpTMutfhGOVxbwOI&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;hvadid=598729490318&amp;hvdev=c&amp;hvlocphy=9007807&amp;hvnetw=g&amp;hvqmt=e&amp;hvrand=11718848189838980715&amp;hvtargid=kwd-280547986705&amp;hydadcr=22569_13531285&amp;keywords=coddling+of+the+american+mind&amp;qid=1717532774&amp;sr=8-1" rel=""> 2018 book</a><span> co-authored by Greg Lukianoff and Jon—made the attractions of smartphones and social media even more appealing. The newest devices and apps are just one more chapter in the transformation of American childhood.</span></p><p><span>Many praise the myriad benefits that smartphones and social media are said to bring; online connection </span><a href="https://www.edweek.org/leadership/how-social-media-may-benefit-teens-mental-health/2024/02#:~:text=And%20so%20social%20media%20is,those%20negative%20things%20in%20person." rel="">can give</a><span> a person a sense of “community,” we are told.&nbsp; We can find new friends, discover just about any idea imaginable, network, and even date through our phones. We can video chat with hundreds of people simultaneously from far-flung locations. We can pursue learning largely untethered from any physical space. Based on all of this, it would be easy to assume that place doesn’t matter.</span></p><p>I disagree. Physical place actually matters far more than we realize, especially as our lives become ever more placeless.</p><p><span>As Jon writes in </span><em>The Anxious Generation</em><span>, only real-world (place-based) social relationships and interactions have the four features that have characterized human interactions for millions of years. Such interactions are embodied, they are&nbsp; synchronous, they involve one-to-one or one-to-several communications, and they have a high bar for entry and exit. In contrast, virtual interactions are typically disembodied and asynchronous, involve one-to-many communications, and have a low bar for entry and exit. The challenge today is that smartphones and other digital devices bring so many interesting experiences to children and adolescents that they cause a serious problem: </span><em>They reduce interest in all non-screen-based forms of experience</em><span>. Virtual networks are not only insufficient replacements for communities, but their proliferation makes the establishment of communities more difficult.</span></p><p>Community—and the relational security blanket it provides—is essential to the health and well-being of our children. Yet, over the last two generations, the U.S. has moved from a “townshipped” society in which neighbors regularly communicated and collaborated with each other through a host of place-based institutions to a “networked” and technologically-driven one in which local neighborhoods, schools, churches, and civic organizations are less important, and therefore they have weakened over time.&nbsp;</p><p><span>“The Quest for Community,”</span><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Quest-Community-Background-Essential-Conservative/dp/1935191500" rel=""> in the words of Robert Nisbet</a><span>, continues unabated, but today, the term “community” is often used in ways that are aspirational and limitless (e.g., </span><a href="https://creators.facebook.com/tools/groups/?locale=en_US" rel="">many</a><span> </span><a href="https://bubble.io/community" rel="">online</a><span> </span><a href="https://training.thinkific.com/courses/thriving-communities" rel="">advertisements</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.disco.co/academy" rel="">for</a><span> </span><a href="https://community.sephora.com/" rel="">new</a><span> social networks)—quite different from the original meaning of the term. Indeed, it’s a good example of “term inflation” — the stretching of a good idea to promote values and goals quite different from what is meant.</span></p><p>Why? Perhaps fewer individuals have any experience of what community really means. Young people are marketed to and formed by the twin pursuits of convenience and choice while simultaneously being told that a person’s chief purpose is to express themselves (usually through consumption). This vision of the good life is part of the next generation’s socialization. It feels “natural” to them, and yet it does little to prepare them for the demands and delights of membership in a community.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>Community differs significantly from friendships, social networks, or what is experienced online. Whereas communities offer mutual support in times of good and bad and are bolstered by robust institutions and norms encouraging frequent, positive interactions, care and concern for one another, and ample opportunities to work together towards common goals, the alternatives typically fall short on these elements.&nbsp;</p><p><span>While one-to-one relationships, a string of individual 1:1 relationships, or participation in an online group can provide some benefits—including a </span><em>feeling</em><span> of connection—they fall far short of actually producing community, which requires overlapping institutions and activities, things that are very hard to achieve if you don’t share a physical place with one another.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Virtual groups are transitory and thin rather than permanent and thick. They cannot provide the dense web of supportive social ties that act like a security blanket when in need or the breadth of informal supportive daily interactions that are the lifeblood of a true community. Most online networks, for example, are instrumental, serving to connect people with a common history or interest or need together, as with </span><a href="https://www.facebook.com/help/1629740080681586" rel="">Facebook</a><span> or </span><a href="https://discord.com/creators/community-server-features-every-creator-should-know-about" rel="">Discord</a><span> Groups. They offer a stream of messages and connections, useful information, entertainment, and sometimes notes of support — from known and unknown people.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Some of these sell themselves as online communities — </span><a href="https://networkconference.netstudies.org/2018OUA/2018/04/23/community-hashtags-generate-a-sense-of-belonging/" rel="">think of</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.sanctuarymg.com/academy/social-media/hashtags-build-social-community/" rel="">the</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/finding-your-community-hashtags-reboostlive/" rel="">concept</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.sarahbeststrategy.com/blog/using-hashtags-to-increase-social-media-engagement#:~:text=Community%20hashtags%20are%20hashtags%20that,build%20community%2C%20and%20gain%20followers." rel="">of</a><span> “finding or creating community” through hashtags — where users find photos and videos of other people who share like-minded views (and then they like, comment, and share those photos and videos). But these fall far short of the meaning of community. On the net, online groups are more transactional, engendering little sense of mutual responsibility, and not necessarily useful when you need help nor protective when you are vulnerable. The norms of mutual support are significantly weakened and there is little of the sense of common destiny that a place-based community produces. Who would you rather call when in trouble - a real person you see regularly down the block from you or someone online who you have never met in person?&nbsp;</span></p><p>It’s worth noting that online communities are also voluntary, with many being platforms built for expression or personal advancement. Few provide the diversity of personalities, experiences, income levels, and outlooks that were common in most neighborhoods a few decades ago. Few provide the incentives to earn recognition through the force of character rather than a performative act about oneself. Few provide multifaceted psychological and practical support when needed for members who feel vulnerable or fall into practical difficulties.&nbsp;</p><p><span>None of this is to say that online networks and relationships don’t have significant value. In some cases, the virtual world can enhance pre-existing real-world relationships and groups. In others, it can connect people who would never meet otherwise. My point, however, is that we need to recognize that they are not sufficient </span><em>replacements</em><span> for what real-world in-person relationships and communities offer and that we should have a clear view of the limitations, which are significant.</span></p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental/comments&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Leave a comment&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental/comments" rel=""><span>Leave a comment</span></a></p><p>I moved to my current neighborhood, Kemp Mill, just north of Washington, D.C., 12 years ago to raise a family and (mostly) put an end to my nomadic wanderings. It offered something that few neighborhoods could—a real community with high levels of hospitality and social trust. It is as institutionally thick as any place I have been in America, with these institutions nurturing the deep social ties and tight web of associations that bind us together and enhance our lives in countless invisible ways. The benefits of such ties are apparent every time we face a difficulty—whether it involves safety, technology, or a pandemic.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png" width="1074" height="624" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:624,&quot;width&quot;:1074,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1321653,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5f593ba2-1ee3-42e3-8117-2caddb18f1cf_1074x624.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption><em><strong>Images. </strong><span>The</span><strong> </strong><span>Kemp Mill neighborhood. Bake sales, kids playing, and presents from neighbors.</span></em></figcaption></figure></div><p>When COVID-19 struck Kemp Mill, we found that our in-person networks had prepared us to weather such a challenge. A large number of volunteers appeared, ready to distribute food, masks, and medicine to the homebound and set up outdoor pods for kids to play. While many schools around the country went virtual for extended periods of time, ours made every effort to reopen within months by leveraging the medical talent in the neighborhood to develop nuanced procedures to safeguard everyone. Streams of volunteers supplemented what school staff could manage. Meanwhile, synagogues organized new virtual activities for kids and shifted their many programs for adults online. Neighbors hosted social gatherings in their front yards and encouraged kids to spend time together in the back yards. In sum, neighborliness and helpfulness were the default behavior. While I often hear about the negative aftereffects of COVID when meeting educators and parents elsewhere, I do not hear the same complaints from the families in our school.</p><p>I am thus not worried about social media’s impact on my kids. As a strong kids-centered community, we do not need the government’s help to restrict kids’ use of social media. Our school and the parents of our children’s classmates already carefully monitor what information children consume. Youth get their phones at a later age than elsewhere in America, and our schools do not allow them anywhere near a classroom. Moreover, most receive older-style cell phones that cannot access social media. My kids are active readers, borrowing books from the local library and subscribing to compelling magazines and book subscriptions. And they regularly spend joyful time with their classmates and neighboring kids, going hours and hours together talking, playing board games and cards, singing, competing in sports, or just walking around—with no phones in sight. In observing our faith, our whole community also regularly spends time (on the Sabbath and major holidays) with no access to any media at all. Parents model that they too know how to set their phones aside and attend to real community, in space and time.</p><p><strong>If you are a parent and want to join or build a community to enmesh your kids in, what can you do? Here are a few ideas to get started.</strong></p><p><span>First, you can select a place to live based on its </span><em>social</em><span> wealth. When my wife and I were ready to have kids, we were determined to find a supportive community to live in. We spent a year checking out half a dozen options between New York City (where we lived) and Washington, D.C. (where I was doing more work). In most cases, we visited, stayed overnight, met lots of people, and asked lots of questions. In the end, we chose the D.C. suburb where I live now—a warm, welcoming, and institutionally rich place.</span></p><p><span>Second, consider how you can befriend neighbors and other parents in your immediate vicinity. Try the </span><a href="https://neighboringmovement.org/" rel="">8 Front Door Challenge</a><span>, which helps you plan and host a Get-Together with neighbors closest to you. Participate in organizations or activities in your neighborhood. Spend time in places where people congregate locally. Organize </span><a href="https://www.edmonton.ca/residential_neighbourhoods/neighbourhoods/block-parties-play-streets" rel="">a block party or play street</a><span>. Create a </span><a href="https://www.edmonton.ca/sites/default/files/public-files/Creating_Neighbourly_Block_2.pdf?cb=1720545079" rel="">neighborly block</a><span>.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>Third, leverage local institutions to build neighborhood community. Schools are best placed for this because of their direct ties to local families and kids, but libraries, local businesses, houses of worship, and any other entity with strong ties to your locale can play an important role. A parents’ group based on the families from the schools in your neighborhood would not only build stronger ties between families but also provide a platform to organize activities where residents get to know each other and develop a stronger sense of mutual support and trust. Working with the local library to organize activities in or geared towards your specific neighborhood would create an opportunity for residents to meet one another. A church, synagogue, or mosque could more proactively embrace the neighborhood, as members of </span><a href="https://www.parishcollective.org/" rel="">Parish Collective</a><span> do. As for businesses, many have an active interest in building social ties with neighbors. Might they want to hold events, contribute to building community, or invest in some way to strengthen local relationships among neighbors? In general, it’s always easier if you find allies among your neighbors, build partnerships with existing institutions, and leverage the assets (cultural, environmental, educational, economic, etc.) you already have locally. Think incrementally, building momentum step by step rather than thinking there is a magic bullet.</span></p><p><span>While it is important to</span><a href="https://conversationswithtyler.com/episodes/jonathan-haidt-anxious-generation/" rel=""> debate</a><span> youth use of social media, and whether the government should regulate it, what is missing from this discussion is the strength of “the little society” that kids inhabit daily. There are real tradeoffs in using social media, and external factors heavily impact the mix and balance between the positives and negatives involved. As Zach</span><a href="https://www.bostonglobe.com/2024/06/06/opinion/religious-teens-mental-health/" rel=""> writes</a><span>, kids “</span><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1moM3e_dcajEJzDR_uBK1mIs3hZ8vFZJ4MfUx7NZIx3I/edit#gid=1666441069" rel="">rooted</a><a href="https://publicsquaremag.org/dialogue/persuasion/belonging-and-believing-in-conservative-and-liberal-religion/" rel=""> in their</a><span> real-world communities” are “</span><a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1moM3e_dcajEJzDR_uBK1mIs3hZ8vFZJ4MfUx7NZIx3I/edit#gid=1666441069" rel="">less likely</a><span> to move their lives so deeply into the virtual world.” Instead, they “continue to spend more time with friends and trusted adults in person. They are, therefore, less likely to become anxious and depressed when they trade in their flip phones for smartphones, and they are also better able to find social support, which may make online harms less painful.”</span></p><p>What matters for our kids is not online connections, but in-person relationships; not just individual friendships but the strength and abundance of neighborhood institutions. Robust communities will foster hundreds of relationships and dozens of place-based institutions engendering trust, fraternity, mutual support, and stewardship. These will shape how we raise our kids and how they will, in turn, raise their own.</p><p data-attrs="{&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share&quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Share&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:null,&quot;class&quot;:null}" data-component-name="ButtonCreateButton"><a href="https://www.afterbabel.com/p/the-upstream-cause-of-the-youth-mental?utm_source=substack&amp;utm_medium=email&amp;utm_content=share&amp;action=share" rel=""><span>Share</span></a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hackberry-Pi_Zero – A handheld Linux terminal using Raspberry Pi Zero 2W (391 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero</link>
            <guid>41138701</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 13:34:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero">https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41138701">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hackberry-Pi_Zero</h2><a id="user-content-hackberry-pi_zero" aria-label="Permalink: Hackberry-Pi_Zero" href="#hackberry-pi_zero"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A handheld Linux terminal using Raspberry pi Zero 2W as Core with 4' 720X720 TFT display and the original BlackBerry Keyboard
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352547808-5038ae93-bd02-41cb-a2df-9c7afeaa57e3.jpg?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQ3ODA4LTUwMzhhZTkzLWJkMDItNDFjYi1hMmRmLTljN2FmZWFhNTdlMy5qcGc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT01MzNhYmYxZmJiODdmMzBhMWQ5MGU3MTc5MjhjYjI1ZTc4ZmYwYWQzNjc1MmI3NDFjMmEzZDEyMTlmMjRlYzkxJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.c6xxjCkyVwA6bzEduWBnD4v5AJuSQ8ROaMAvpI5z_sA"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352547808-5038ae93-bd02-41cb-a2df-9c7afeaa57e3.jpg?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQ3ODA4LTUwMzhhZTkzLWJkMDItNDFjYi1hMmRmLTljN2FmZWFhNTdlMy5qcGc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT01MzNhYmYxZmJiODdmMzBhMWQ5MGU3MTc5MjhjYjI1ZTc4ZmYwYWQzNjc1MmI3NDFjMmEzZDEyMTlmMjRlYzkxJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.c6xxjCkyVwA6bzEduWBnD4v5AJuSQ8ROaMAvpI5z_sA" alt="PIC1"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352547834-19b1a504-f155-4f84-992f-cf4c463f5743.jpg?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQ3ODM0LTE5YjFhNTA0LWYxNTUtNGY4NC05OTJmLWNmNGM0NjNmNTc0My5qcGc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT02MmE2NWIyNTU1NTU4ZWNhOTY1MWQ1YTRlMTU0NTZlNDA1N2ZlOTc5MjYxYmY1NzUyZmE1ZDJkODAwYmE2ZWQ4JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.tk0shOmyvXa-DeHGPUiHBVTGRXcyfEnGNoAAz0TYThQ"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352547834-19b1a504-f155-4f84-992f-cf4c463f5743.jpg?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQ3ODM0LTE5YjFhNTA0LWYxNTUtNGY4NC05OTJmLWNmNGM0NjNmNTc0My5qcGc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT02MmE2NWIyNTU1NTU4ZWNhOTY1MWQ1YTRlMTU0NTZlNDA1N2ZlOTc5MjYxYmY1NzUyZmE1ZDJkODAwYmE2ZWQ4JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.tk0shOmyvXa-DeHGPUiHBVTGRXcyfEnGNoAAz0TYThQ" alt="PIC2"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://discord.gg/WzPthAmMbP" rel="nofollow">Questions or need more info? Join my Discord Channel!</a></h3><a id="user-content-questions-or-need-more-info-join-my-discord-channel" aria-label="Permalink: Questions or need more info? Join my Discord Channel!" href="#questions-or-need-more-info-join-my-discord-channel"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-About this handheld  ">About this handheld   </a></h2><a id="user-content-about-this-handheld---" aria-label="Permalink: About this handheld   " href="#about-this-handheld---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The main reason why I design and build this handheld cyberdeck is to treat this as a lernning tool and also a funny toy for the hackers. It is powered by a raspberry pi zero 2w and a 4' 720X720 TFT display.</p>
<p dir="auto">Here are some <strong>main Features:</strong><br>
<strong>Main Processor</strong>: Only compaticable with Raspberry pi zero 2w.<br>
<strong>Display</strong>: 4' 720X720 high resolution TFT display.<br>
<strong>Dual Swapable battery Design</strong>: Replace your battery in 10 seconds without killing the power!<br>
<strong>Battery type</strong>: Nokia BL-5C. You can buy it anywhere in the world.<br>
<strong>Battery life</strong>: In my test: 3.5 hours with desktop, 5 hours with commandline.<br>
<strong>Keyboard Mouse Combo</strong>: Yes, this cyberdeck has keyboard and mouse combo on board. You can choose blackberry Q10 or Q20 keyboard.<br>
<strong>Fully customizable keymap</strong>: You can connect the keyboard with a computer and customizable the keymap through <a href="https://get.vial.today/" rel="nofollow">VIAL</a> easily.<br>
<strong>3 USB2.0 Ports</strong>: This handheld has 3 USB2.0 Ports, you can use it with USB-Stick or 4G Modul Dongle or any USB thing.<br>
<strong>Charging Ampere</strong>: 1A charging ampere, this handheld can be fully charged within 3 hours.<br>
<strong>Stemma I2C Port</strong>: This device has a stemma I2C port on board, you can connect with any I2C sensors.<br>
<strong>TF card Slot</strong>: There is an external TF card Slot. You can replace your OS image very easily.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Block Diagram</h2><a id="user-content-block-diagram" aria-label="Permalink: Block Diagram" href="#block-diagram"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352530236-e46c354c-9363-41e2-b276-73ba5900a178.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTMwMjM2LWU0NmMzNTRjLTkzNjMtNDFlMi1iMjc2LTczYmE1OTAwYTE3OC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1mNTk3YjE4MjIyODM2ZWIyMzAyNGZjM2RkMTQwNGRiOTg0OGU2MTFkMGY4ZjY0ZWNlYjEzZWNiMWJmZTdlODQ2JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.U3oahCHknJK-kxFtvbpih-iFsn58kNPD8Y9gvfhGaXQ"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352530236-e46c354c-9363-41e2-b276-73ba5900a178.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTMwMjM2LWU0NmMzNTRjLTkzNjMtNDFlMi1iMjc2LTczYmE1OTAwYTE3OC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1mNTk3YjE4MjIyODM2ZWIyMzAyNGZjM2RkMTQwNGRiOTg0OGU2MTFkMGY4ZjY0ZWNlYjEzZWNiMWJmZTdlODQ2JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.U3oahCHknJK-kxFtvbpih-iFsn58kNPD8Y9gvfhGaXQ" alt="Blockdiagramm_HackberryPi_Zero"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-Get started  ">Get started   </a></h2><a id="user-content-get-started---" aria-label="Permalink: Get started   " href="#get-started---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HDEBzaB1IcY&amp;ab_channel=ZitaoTech" rel="nofollow">Introductionvideo</a></h3><a id="user-content-introductionvideo" aria-label="Permalink: Introductionvideo" href="#introductionvideo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to turn on the HackberryPi?</h3><a id="user-content-how-to-turn-on-the-hackberrypi" aria-label="Permalink: How to turn on the HackberryPi?" href="#how-to-turn-on-the-hackberrypi"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Turn the red switch to the <strong>right position</strong> and then press the <strong>red button</strong> to the left side of the red switch to power the USB Hub Controller Chip otherse the keyboard <strong>can't be used!</strong> At the same time the indicator for the battery voltage will be turned on.<br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352540506-9e333c90-5131-4404-85bd-e2c72a7e1bd3.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQwNTA2LTllMzMzYzkwLTUxMzEtNDQwNC04NWJkLWUyYzcyYTdlMWJkMy5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1jNDIzNjk5OTQ2NTBmZjY2MGI4MGY3NDJlMWI0NTM5MjliODcxOWE1NTllMDU0MGNlNjU5ZTdjMGExN2JlMGFhJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.zyhztgJZwCl-7mjRjKNWgjoEjzKWFcYHqgw1Tvr31S0"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352540506-9e333c90-5131-4404-85bd-e2c72a7e1bd3.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQwNTA2LTllMzMzYzkwLTUxMzEtNDQwNC04NWJkLWUyYzcyYTdlMWJkMy5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1jNDIzNjk5OTQ2NTBmZjY2MGI4MGY3NDJlMWI0NTM5MjliODcxOWE1NTllMDU0MGNlNjU5ZTdjMGExN2JlMGFhJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.zyhztgJZwCl-7mjRjKNWgjoEjzKWFcYHqgw1Tvr31S0" alt="Turnon"></a><br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero/blob/main/Picture/Turnon.gif"><img src="https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero/raw/main/Picture/Turnon.gif" alt="turnon" data-animated-image=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-Keyboard  ">Keyboard   </a></h2><a id="user-content-keyboard---" aria-label="Permalink: Keyboard   " href="#keyboard---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The keyboard type is blackberry Q10 or Q20 keyboard. Both have the same keyboard layout.<br>
There is a red switch on the left side to decide if the keyboard controller communicates with the HackberryPi or with other device through the USBC-Port underneath.<br>
The idea about this is you can connect the keyboard with your computer and customize the keymap using <a href="https://get.vial.today/" rel="nofollow">VIAL</a> or the handheld can be used as an emergency keyboard mouse combo.<br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352543403-63ac5772-f248-4117-bd29-ae0b3058e1e4.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQzNDAzLTYzYWM1NzcyLWYyNDgtNDExNy1iZDI5LWFlMGIzMDU4ZTFlNC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT00ZDc5ODUwYmNhNjcwOTA1ZWZjYmE4MDMyYmYxYzFmNDQwNjkxZDk4ZjQ0NTY3ZWVhYTdlNDY2MTE3ZGNiNzQ5JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.gDDlTBmrla2PyKXp87f1fx5qolQB32FOWLb0fUQuc6k"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352543403-63ac5772-f248-4117-bd29-ae0b3058e1e4.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQzNDAzLTYzYWM1NzcyLWYyNDgtNDExNy1iZDI5LWFlMGIzMDU4ZTFlNC5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT00ZDc5ODUwYmNhNjcwOTA1ZWZjYmE4MDMyYmYxYzFmNDQwNjkxZDk4ZjQ0NTY3ZWVhYTdlNDY2MTE3ZGNiNzQ5JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.gDDlTBmrla2PyKXp87f1fx5qolQB32FOWLb0fUQuc6k" alt="keyboard"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to change the keymap?</h3><a id="user-content-how-to-change-the-keymap" aria-label="Permalink: How to change the keymap?" href="#how-to-change-the-keymap"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Put the red switch to the lower position, connect the keyboard with your computer, open <a href="https://vial.rocks/" rel="nofollow">VIAL page</a>, then you can customize the keymap yourself.<br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352544341-7c4e9b53-7a00-4cdd-b0b7-751647f76f6b.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQ0MzQxLTdjNGU5YjUzLTdhMDAtNGNkZC1iMGI3LTc1MTY0N2Y3NmY2Yi5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1hYTRhOTJiMDdmMThkZThkOTQ0OTg0YjZlNDQ3MWY4ZDMwNzQyNDNjZTI4ODM1MGRhYzI4ZTM4MzEwZDU4OTkzJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.RhppCXA0oxW4uC4c2pEVdQ9btWjoOQu1P9ZrppiRofw"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/145678024/352544341-7c4e9b53-7a00-4cdd-b0b7-751647f76f6b.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjI2MTI5MDEsIm5iZiI6MTcyMjYxMjYwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8xNDU2NzgwMjQvMzUyNTQ0MzQxLTdjNGU5YjUzLTdhMDAtNGNkZC1iMGI3LTc1MTY0N2Y3NmY2Yi5wbmc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjQwODAyJTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI0MDgwMlQxNTMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1hYTRhOTJiMDdmMThkZThkOTQ0OTg0YjZlNDQ3MWY4ZDMwNzQyNDNjZTI4ODM1MGRhYzI4ZTM4MzEwZDU4OTkzJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCZhY3Rvcl9pZD0wJmtleV9pZD0wJnJlcG9faWQ9MCJ9.RhppCXA0oxW4uC4c2pEVdQ9btWjoOQu1P9ZrppiRofw" alt="image"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-Different Operating System  ">Different Operating System   </a></h2><a id="user-content-different-operating-system---" aria-label="Permalink: Different Operating System   " href="#different-operating-system---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can install Kali, Raspberrypi OS, or Retropi and many other OS into HackberryPi.<br>
<a href="https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero/tree/main/Screen">This page</a> will tell you how to install the display driver in different operating system.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-Basic Tutorial  ">Basic Tutorial   </a></h2><a id="user-content-basic-tutorial---" aria-label="Permalink: Basic Tutorial   " href="#basic-tutorial---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">How to change font size in <a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/173220/how-do-i-change-the-font-or-the-font-size-in-the-tty-console" rel="nofollow">terminal</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-Dimension and Weight  ">Dimension and Weight   </a></h2><a id="user-content-dimension-and-weight---" aria-label="Permalink: Dimension and Weight   " href="#dimension-and-weight---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Dimension of HackberryPi: 139.4x82x15.7mm<br>
Weight without battery: 151.7 Gram<br>
Weight with battery: 189.7 Gram<br>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero/blob/main/Mechanical_Drawing/Mechanical_Drawing_Q10.png"><img src="https://github.com/ZitaoTech/Hackberry-Pi_Zero/raw/main/Mechanical_Drawing/Mechanical_Drawing_Q10.png" alt="Drawing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><a name="user-content-Where to buy  ">Where to buy   </a></h2><a id="user-content-where-to-buy---" aria-label="Permalink: Where to buy   " href="#where-to-buy---"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.tindie.com/products/zitaotech/hackberrypi-cyberdeck-handheld-with-bbq10-keyboard/" rel="nofollow">BBQ10 keyboard version</a><br>
<a href="https://www.tindie.com/products/zitaotech/hackberrypi-cyberdeck-handheld-with-bbq20-keyboard/" rel="nofollow">BBQ20 keyboard version</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Ell – A command-line interface for LLMs written in Bash (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/simonmysun/ell</link>
            <guid>41138085</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 11:55:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell">https://github.com/simonmysun/ell</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41138085">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ell</h2><a id="user-content-ell" aria-label="Permalink: ell" href="#ell"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A command-line interface for LLMs written in Bash.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description basic.webm">basic.webm</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/1355ad08-6fbf-4c0b-9ba6-2542fcb39acf" data-canonical-src="https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/1355ad08-6fbf-4c0b-9ba6-2542fcb39acf" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><em>Basic usage of ell</em></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Ask LLMs from your terminal</li>
<li>Pipe friendly</li>
<li>Bring your terminal context to the LLMs and ask questions</li>
<li>Chat with LLMs in your terminal</li>
<li>Function calling and more supported via templates.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Requirements</h2><a id="user-content-requirements" aria-label="Permalink: Requirements" href="#requirements"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To use ell, you need the following:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>bash</li>
<li>jq (For parsing JSON)</li>
<li>curl (For sending HTTPS requests)</li>
<li>perl (For PCRE. POSIX bash doesn't support look-ahead and look-behind regex. Not necessary if you don't use record mode)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install</h2><a id="user-content-install" aria-label="Permalink: Install" href="#install"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/simonmysun/ell.git ~/.ellrc.d
echo 'export PATH=&quot;${HOME}/.ellrc.d:${PATH}&quot;' >> ~/.bashrc"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/simonmysun/ell.git ~/.ellrc.d
echo 'export PATH="${HOME}/.ellrc.d:${PATH}"' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">or</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone git@github.com:simonmysun/ell.git ~/.ellrc.d
echo 'export PATH=&quot;${HOME}/.ellrc.d:${PATH}&quot;' >> ~/.bashrc"><pre><code>git clone git@github.com:simonmysun/ell.git ~/.ellrc.d
echo 'export PATH="${HOME}/.ellrc.d:${PATH}"' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This will clone the repository into <code>.ellrc.d</code> in your home directory and add it to your PATH.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: Configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell/blob/main/docs/Configuration.md">Configuration</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Here's an example configuration to use <code>gemini-1.5-flash</code> from Google. You need to set these variables in your <code>~/.ellrc</code>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ELL_API_STYLE=gemini
ELL_LLM_MODEL=gemini-1.5-flash
ELL_TEMPLATE=default-gemini
ELL_API_KEY=xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
ELL_API_URL=https://generativelanguage.googleapis.com/v1beta/models/"><pre><span>ELL_API_STYLE</span>=gemini
<span>ELL_LLM_MODEL</span>=gemini-1.5-flash
<span>ELL_TEMPLATE</span>=default-gemini
<span>ELL_API_KEY</span>=xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
<span>ELL_API_URL</span>=https://generativelanguage.googleapis.com/v1beta/models/</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Here's an example configuration to use <code>gpt-4o-mini</code> from OpenAI.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ELL_API_STYLE=openai
ELL_LLM_MODEL=gpt-4o-mini
ELL_TEMPLATE=default-openai
ELL_API_KEY=sk-xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
ELL_API_URL=https://api.openai.com/v1/chat/completions"><pre><span>ELL_API_STYLE</span>=openai
<span>ELL_LLM_MODEL</span>=gpt-4o-mini
<span>ELL_TEMPLATE</span>=default-openai
<span>ELL_API_KEY</span>=sk-xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx
<span>ELL_API_URL</span>=https://api.openai.com/v1/chat/completions</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage examples</h2><a id="user-content-usage-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Usage examples" href="#usage-examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Make sure you have configured correctly.</p>
<p dir="auto">Ask a question:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ell &quot;What is the capital of France?&quot;"><pre>ell <span><span>"</span>What is the capital of France?<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Specify a model and use a file as input:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ell -m gpt-4o -f user_prompt.txt"><pre>ell -m gpt-4o -f user_prompt.txt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Record terminal input and output and use as context:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="ell -r
# do random stuff
ell What does the error code mean?
ell How to fix it?"><pre>ell -r
<span><span>#</span> do random stuff</span>
ell What does the error code mean<span>?</span>
ell How to fix it<span>?</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Run in interactive mode:</p>

<p dir="auto">If you were in record mode via <code>ell -r</code>, the context of the shell will be used. The two modes can be combined: <code>ell -r -i</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Specify a template and start in record mode and interactive mode:</p>

<p dir="auto">or</p>

<p dir="auto">depends on which API you are using.</p>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span aria-label="Video description ctf.webm">ctf.webm</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/d122702a-5e48-45dc-8d22-f8a803bb3ff1" data-canonical-src="https://github.com/user-attachments/assets/d122702a-5e48-45dc-8d22-f8a803bb3ff1" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>

<p dir="auto"><em>Example application</em></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Writing Templates</h2><a id="user-content-writing-templates" aria-label="Permalink: Writing Templates" href="#writing-templates"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell/blob/main/docs/Templates.md">Templates</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Styling</h2><a id="user-content-styling" aria-label="Permalink: Styling" href="#styling"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell/blob/main/docs/Styling.md">Styling</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Plugins</h2><a id="user-content-plugins" aria-label="Permalink: Plugins" href="#plugins"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell/blob/main/docs/Plugins.md">Plugins</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Risks to consider</h2><a id="user-content-risks-to-consider" aria-label="Permalink: Risks to consider" href="#risks-to-consider"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell/blob/main/docs/Risk_Consideration.md">Risks Consideration</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FAQ</h2><a id="user-content-faq" aria-label="Permalink: FAQ" href="#faq"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Q</strong>: Why is it called "ell"?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>A</strong>: "ell" is a combination of shell and LLM. It is a shell script to use LLM backends. "shellm" was once considered, but it was dropped because it could be misunderstood as "she llm". "ell" is shorter, easy to type and easy to remember. It does not conflict with any active software. Note that the name "shell" of shell scripts is because it is the outer layer of the operating system exposed to the user. It doesn't indicate that it is a CLI or GUI. Unfortunately it cannot be shortened to "L" which has the same pronunciation because that would conflict with too many things.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Q</strong>: Why is it written in Bash?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>A</strong>: Because Bash is the most common shell on Unix-like systems and there is just no need to use a more complex language for this.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Q</strong>: What is the difference between ell and other similar projects?</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>A</strong>: ell is written in almost pure Bash, which makes it very lightweight and easy to install. It is also very easy to extend and modify. It is pipe friendly, which means it is designed to be used in combination with other tools.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Similar Projects</h2><a id="user-content-similar-projects" aria-label="Permalink: Similar Projects" href="#similar-projects"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/kardolus/chatgpt-cli">https://github.com/kardolus/chatgpt-cli</a> - A CLI for ChatGPT written in Go.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/kharvd/gpt-cli">https://github.com/kharvd/gpt-cli</a> A CLI for various LLM backends written in Python.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/JohannLai/gptcli">https://github.com/JohannLai/gptcli</a> A CLI for OpenAI LLms written in TypeScript.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/x-cmd/x-cmd">https://github.com/x-cmd/x-cmd</a> A powerful collection of tools which includes a CLI for LLM APIs.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Contributions are welcome! If you have any ideas, suggestions, or bug reports, please open an issue or submit a pull request.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is licensed under the MIT License. See the <a href="https://github.com/simonmysun/ell/blob/main/LICENSE">LICENSE</a> file for more details.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Quark Stars (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2024/08/02/quark-stars/</link>
            <guid>41137899</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 11:25:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2024/08/02/quark-stars/">https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2024/08/02/quark-stars/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41137899">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page">
				
<p><img width="450" src="https://i0.wp.com/math.ucr.edu/home/baez/astronomical/neutron_star_quark_core.jpg">
</p>
<p>Wow — evidence that very massive neutron stars may have cores made of deconfined quark matter!   The idea of a ‘quark star’ is not new, but I didn’t know it was a serious possibility.</p>
<p>An ordinary neutron star has a core made mostly of densely packed neutrons.  A matchbox-sized chunk of this stuff weighs about 3 billion tonnes.   But if you squeeze this stuff hard enough, eventually the neutrons break.  Each neutron consists of 3 quarks held together by gluons.  So when the neutrons break you get ‘quark matter’ — a sea of quarks and gluons, no longer confined in neutrons.</p>
<p>We’ve made something similar here on Earth: at CERN and Brookhaven, physicists smack atomic nuclei at each other so hard that the protons and neutrons break and momentarily form a ‘quark-gluon plasma’.   But the conditions in a neutron star core are different: cooler, but more pressure — and not just temporary.</p>
<p>This new paper tries to take the measured properties of massive neutron stars and see if they fit a model where the inner core is made of deconfined quark matter:</p>
<p>• Eemeli Annala, Tyler Gorda, Joonas Hirvonen, Oleg Komoltsev, Aleksi Kurkela, Joonas Nättilä and Aleksi Vuorinen, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11356">Strongly interacting matter exhibits deconfined behavior in massive neutron stars</a>, <i>Nature Communications</i> <b>14</b> (2023), 8451.</p>
<p>They say it does with about 80% probability!   I’d take this with a big grain of salt, but it’s an exciting possibility.   It’s not every day we find quintillions of tonnes of a new state of matter.</p>
<p>For me, the coolest part is that deconfined quark matter may have an extra symmetry, called ‘conformal symmetry’.  This means that if you zoom in on it, it looks almost the same.   An atom looks like a blob with some specific size.   So does a neutron.   But a system with conformal symmetry is just a blur spread out everywhere — and if you zoom in or zoom out, you see something very similar.  This is crazy.</p>
<p>We see matter with conformal symmetry elsewhere too, like at ‘critical points’.   As you know, when you heat water it boils.  There’s a sharp divide between liquid and gas.   But as you keep boosting the pressure, the boiling point increases.  And at 647 degrees kelvin and 220 times ordinary atmospheric pressure something weird happens: the distinction between liquid and gas ends!    This is called a ‘critical point’.</p>
<p><img width="450" src="https://i0.wp.com/math.ucr.edu/home/baez/chemical/water_phase_diagram.png">
</p>
<p>Right at the critical point, water looks weird.  It look like a blur of droplets floating in gas.  But if you look at any droplet you’ll see it’s full of bubbles of gas.  And if you look in any of these bubbles you see it’s full of droplets.   As you keep zooming in, you keep seeing basically the same thing…. droplets of liquid in gas, bubbles of gas in liquid…. until you get down to the scale of atoms.  So we say this stuff has ‘conformal symmetry’.</p>
<p>The math of this is incredibly cool: it’s called ‘conformal field theory’, and a lot of mathematicians and physicists study it.   So it would be really neat if extremely heavy neutron stars turn out to be made of deconfined quark matter with conformal symmetry… or even just <i>approximate</i> conformal symmetry.</p>

				
				<p>
					<small>
					This entry was posted  on Friday, August 2nd, 2024 at 10:00 am and is filed under <a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/category/astronomy/" rel="category tag">astronomy</a>, <a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/category/physics/" rel="category tag">physics</a>.					You can follow any responses to this entry through the <a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2024/08/02/quark-stars/feed/">RSS 2.0</a> feed.
											You can <a href="#respond">leave a response</a>, or <a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2024/08/02/quark-stars/trackback/" rel="trackback">trackback</a> from your own site.
					
					</small>
				</p>

				<nav id="nav-below">
					<h3>Post navigation</h3>
					<span><a href="https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2024/08/01/agent-based-models-part-14/" rel="prev">« Previous Post</a></span>
					<span></span>
				</nav><!-- #nav-below -->

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Robin Warren, pathologist who rewrote the science on ulcers, has died (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/07/31/robin-warren-nobel-ulcers-dies/</link>
            <guid>41137694</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 10:47:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/07/31/robin-warren-nobel-ulcers-dies/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/obituaries/2024/07/31/robin-warren-nobel-ulcers-dies/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41137694">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="IUBNQYFAXVEXNH7LDWIMBAZS7Q" data-el="text" dir="null">Robin Warren, an Australian pathologist who shared a Nobel Prize for rewriting medical views on gut health with research that included his partner drinking a bacteria-laced brew to show how microbes can cause ulcers, died July 23 in Perth, Australia. He was 87.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="QQNBURQQIBAW7PVPPNS2F7LBQE" data-el="text" dir="null">The death was <a href="https://www.uwa.edu.au/news/article/2024/july/vale-robin-warren" target="_blank">announced </a>by the University of Western Australia, where Dr. Warren was a professor emeritus. The statement gave no other details.</p></div><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="R6DQTBECH5GF5AGA2JQI4GT24U" data-el="text" dir="null">The discoveries by Dr. Warren and Barry Marshall at Royal Perth Hospital completely upended long-standing medical assumptions that the stomach’s gastric fluids would kill any invasive bacteria. Yet, for more than a decade, the two researchers confronted a medical community slow to accept their theories and acknowledge their findings.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="CNUNXHB5XBHJFMOG34242CK4EQ" data-el="text" dir="null">As Marshall <a href="https://medium.com/doctoryak/challenging-sciences-status-quo-the-tale-of-barry-marshall-c80a873412a6" target="_blank">once put it</a>, “To gastroenterologists, the concept of a germ causing ulcers was like saying that the Earth is flat.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="XQQ6SH54W5ANZPXWNMQS4GLBRM" data-el="text" dir="null">For patients, there are now antibiotic treatments for peptic ulcers — once considered a chronic condition — as well as a noninvasive breath test to diagnose ulcers and avoid possible biopsies. In wider medical research, the work by Dr. Warren and Marshall also introduced theories about possible bacterial factors in ailments caused by inflammation, such as Crohn’s disease and ulcerative colitis, and as potential triggers for cancers.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="2DKWW7EH55BUBEZ3DWQ3DWCHIM" data-el="text" dir="null">Until the studies by Dr. Warren and Marshall, the medical consensus was that ulcers and other gastric troubles were often attributed to stress or lifestyle choices such as eating spicy foods or drinking alcohol.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="ZT5W3N6F3ZCBFI5K77HI6JYXLM" data-el="text" dir="null">“With tenacity and a prepared mind [they] challenged prevailing dogmas,” said a<a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2005/press-release/" target="_blank"> statement</a> from the Nobel committee when Dr. Warren and Marshall received the prize for medicine in 2005.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="S63KUAFMU5DSLFKQXS4RZ5NLUA" data-el="text" dir="null">The journey began with a glance in 1979 at a biopsy sample at the Royal Perth Hospital, where Dr. Warren was a chief pathologist. He noticed bacteria on tissue from a patient with ulcers. Dr. Warren had long mulled over an alternative “germ theory” for ulcers, but he had scant evidence to bolster his ideas and almost no supporters.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="QGBZPYNHTJAKHBW4FMULC3GCFM" data-el="text" dir="null">“Bacteria had been seen before, but these findings had been disregarded as some odd curiosities or just contaminations,” <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2005/prize-announcement/" target="_blank">said</a> Swedish microbiologist Staffan Normark at the Nobel Prize announcement in Stockholm.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="IVOWMRQGTVEANADHMQXZUAGKMQ" data-el="text" dir="null">Marshall, as a young clinical researcher, watched the eyerolls at Dr. Warren during medical conferences. “He would mention these bacteria and the surgeons would be saying ‘ha ha ha, Robin’s talking about his bacteria again,’” recalled Marshall in an<a href="https://www.medicalrepublic.com.au/farewell-to-a-giant-of-pathology-and-medicine/109345" target="_blank"> interview</a> with the Medical Republic, an Australian health and science site.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="HOFMN5RNKJEPRLXHUVJ4SINWY4" data-el="text" dir="null">The biopsy sample spotted by Dr. Warren gave him a tangible lead. He recruited <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2005/marshall/facts/" target="_blank">Marshall</a>, and they began studying tissue from patients with ulcers and other digestive problems. Nearly all the samples showed the presence of the same bacteria. They dubbed it Helicobacter pylori, or H. pylori: “helico,” as in helicopter, for its spiral shape, and “pylori” for the pylorus valve at the bottom of the stomach.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="5YZF5NXTONC4HKRMKJIJQIBXRM" data-el="text" dir="null">They announced their findings in a series of papers, including in the British journal the Lancet, in the early 1980s. The medical community remained skeptical.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="VHLC2KATZNAHZLBKCLETN6FUTE" data-el="text" dir="null">“For about 100 years, or 1,000 years, the standard teaching in medicine was that the stomach was sterile and nothing grew there because of corrosive gastric juices,” Dr. Warren <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2005/10/03/health/2-australians-share-nobel-in-medicine-for-ulcer-study.html" target="_blank">said</a>. “So everybody believed there were no bacteria in the stomach. When I said they were there, no one believed it.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="U2RGUZCIEJDOTLEYAYSFVISW6Y" data-el="text" dir="null">In July 1984, Marshall turned himself into a lab subject. He swilled down a bacterial broth in an attempt to draw conclusive links between H. pylori and ulcers. Test animals such as pigs and rats were immune to the bacteria. Dr. Warren already had an H. pylori infection, and they feared he could have built an immunity.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="5CPCWTLQW5GJTIDNKCAQ73MI2Q" data-el="text" dir="null">“So, Barry, I think it has to be you,” Marshall <a href="https://www.medicalrepublic.com.au/farewell-to-a-giant-of-pathology-and-medicine/109345" target="_blank">recalled </a>Dr. Warren telling him.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="FFLLDAYM5VHOZE6AAYU4AYFCB4" data-el="text" dir="null">After about three days, Marshall became sick. “I started vomiting. I was waking up in the middle of the night, I couldn’t eat well, I was having night sweats,” he told the Australian, a newspaper based near Sydney, in 2005. “I had the endoscopy after a week and it showed the bacteria had taken hold.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="PCVWLHPGLJF5ZGHEI6YWBTC5BE" data-el="text" dir="null">The test revealed H. pylori around an inflamed part of his stomach. He was better after a course of antibiotics, further advancing their findings toward a cure.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="V2A5RDZYEFH6VGVTYVPQNNATH4" data-el="text" dir="null">About two-thirds of the world population has been infected with H. pylori, often during childhood, but the bacteria leads to health problems in a relatively small number of people, <a href="https://wwwnc.cdc.gov/travel/yellowbook/2024/infections-diseases/helicobacter-pylori#epi" target="_blank">according to</a> the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. Infections can also bring an increased risk of gastric cancers or a lymphoma known as mucosal associated-lymphoid-type, or MALT, the CDC says.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="NV4JAC7QURHTDL2NENSDFLITNU" data-el="text" dir="null">The precise reason H. pylori becomes aggressive in some people is not fully understood. But when it happens, the bacteria can cause ulcers by damaging the stomach lining and making it more vulnerable to digestive fluids. H. pylori causes more than 90 percent of duodenal stomach ulcers and 80 percent of upper-intestinal ulcers, the Nobel committee said. Other causes are overuse of some drugs that can compromise the stomach lining.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="77J6UKUZ2JE7DCQMYX6MI27OQY" data-el="text" dir="null">“The idea of stress and things like that was just so entrenched nobody could really believe that it was bacteria,” Dr. Warren <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/health/health-news/two-australians-win-nobel-prize-medicine-flna1c9437614" target="_blank">once said</a>. “It had to come from some weird place like Perth, Western Australia, because I think nobody else would have even considered it.”</p><p data-qa="article-body"><h3 data-qa="article-header" data-contentid="TGXBJ6NJLJCHLAQSLYQGHS6XNU" data-apitype="header" level="3" id="TGXBJ6NJLJCHLAQSLYQGHS6XNU">‘10,000 unusual things’</h3></p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="RH6HZOGDYVBMVDPXJRJDXNHX3Q" data-el="text" dir="null">John Robin Warren was born on June 11, 1937, in Adelaide, Australia. His father was a winemaker. His mother was a nurse.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="IOJJWUW4OFCK5BBBXXTHSHEXY4" data-el="text" dir="null">“I cannot remember my mother ever pressuring me to study medicine, but somehow this always seemed to be my aim,” Dr. Warren <a href="https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/medicine/2005/warren/biographical/" target="_blank">wrote</a> in his biographical essay for the Nobel committee.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="DSL7RWZH35CUFP5BPNZJRAFELM" data-el="text" dir="null">Months after receiving a university scholarship to study medicine, he had his first grand mal seizure and was diagnosed with epilepsy. He was prescribed drugs that helped control the seizures, but he could not receive a driver’s license and used his bicycle for appointments and classes. His family had discussions — without Robin’s knowledge — about whether to demand that he pass up medical school because of his condition.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="AZDWB6QRUFC25DSK53PF6UAVPY" data-el="text" dir="null">“It was only years later that I came to appreciate just how much my mother had gone through to support my independence. … Apparently, mother was worried sick, but she never said a word about it,” he wrote.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="IJJFBYOZVREBFAV6XGY5RW2VLA" data-el="text" dir="null">After receiving a degree in medicine from the University of Adelaide in 1961, he trained in clinical pathology at the Royal Adelaide Hospital. Dr. Warren sought a position in Papua New Guinea, then under Australian control, in hopes of studying more “exotic and usual diseases.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="4IBGZCJ2WNFLPJPK4BXORQMDQA" data-el="text" dir="null">Instead, he was recruited by the Royal Perth Hospital in 1968 as a staff specialist in pathology, which included an affiliation with the University of Western Australia. He retired from the hospital in 1999 and was named a professor emeritus at the university in 2005.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="XXTK2UPGG5C4XJTEZE7OOCUC4I" data-el="text" dir="null">In 2007, he was appointed a Companion of the Order of Australia, the country’s highest civilian honor.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="N4FGP2EDP5EZDMSVSDJ2UR7CGE" data-el="text" dir="null">During the early 1980s, Dr. Warren said, he and Marshall felt almost like outcasts with their bacteria research. “Otherwise,” Dr. Warren said, “it seemed that only our wives stood beside us.”</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="6RJSJSASHVEBHNTDER4RJ2WHVA" data-el="text" dir="null">He married the former Winifred Theresa Williams in 1962, and they had five children. She died in 1997. Complete information on survivors was not immediately available.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="QIABDX4W7NBSTDTQMW5HOGG2EU" data-el="text" dir="null">In an <a href="https://www.science.org.au/learning/general-audience/history/interviews-australian-scientists/dr-robin-warren-pathologist-0#:~:text=He%20moved%20to%20the%20Royal,of%20Western%20Australia%20in%202005" target="_blank">interview</a> with the Australian Academy of Science, Dr. Warren said that pathologists often encounter oddities in research. The challenge, he noted, is to decide which enigma holds a mystery worth cracking.</p><p data-testid="drop-cap-letter" data-apitype="text" data-contentid="ZFXMI6ARKVDEPB3VNP6TF4B73I" data-el="text" dir="null">“When you look down the microscope at pieces of tissue … it’s not unusual to find something unexpected, because there are so many unusual things,” he said. “And if there are 10,000 unusual things, you find one of them every now and again.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SQLite vector search extension that runs anywhere (214 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec</link>
            <guid>41137658</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 10:41:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec">https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41137658">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto"><code>sqlite-vec</code></h2><a id="user-content-sqlite-vec" aria-label="Permalink: sqlite-vec" href="#sqlite-vec"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://discord.gg/Ve7WeCJFXk" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/7ada7243c369c793e3663e84806685fa83ceb7b80f37266553b3e6e62dd6f7a3/68747470733a2f2f646362616467652e76657263656c2e6170702f6170692f7365727665722f56437451386347685573" alt="" data-canonical-src="https://dcbadge.vercel.app/api/server/VCtQ8cGhUs"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">An extremely small, "fast enough" vector search SQLite extension that runs
anywhere! A successor to <a href="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vss"><code>sqlite-vss</code></a></p>

<div dir="auto"><p dir="auto">Important</p><p dir="auto"><em><code>sqlite-vec</code> is a pre-v1, so expect breaking changes!</em></p>
</div>

<ul dir="auto">
<li>Store and query float, int8, and binary vectors in <code>vec0</code> virtual tables</li>
<li>Written in pure C, no dependencies, runs anywhere SQLite runs
(Linux/MacOS/Windows, in the browser with WASM, Raspberry Pis, etc.)</li>
<li>Pre-filter vectors with <code>rowid IN (...)</code> subqueries</li>
</ul>

<p dir="auto">
<i>
<code>sqlite-vec</code> is a
<a href="https://hacks.mozilla.org/2024/06/sponsoring-sqlite-vec-to-enable-more-powerful-local-ai-applications/" rel="nofollow">Mozilla Builders project</a>,
with additional sponsorship from
<a href="https://fly.io/" rel="nofollow"><img width="14px" src="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/flyio.small.ico"> Fly.io </a>,
<a href="https://turso.tech/" rel="nofollow"><img width="14px" src="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/turso.small.ico"> Turso</a>, and
<a href="https://sqlitecloud.io/" rel="nofollow"><img width="14px" src="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/sqlitecloud.small.svg"> SQLite Cloud</a>.
See <a href="#sponsors">the Sponsors section</a> for more details.
</i>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installing</h2><a id="user-content-installing" aria-label="Permalink: Installing" href="#installing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/installing.html" rel="nofollow">Installing <code>sqlite-vec</code></a>
for more details.</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Language</th>
<th>Install</th>
<th>More Info</th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Python</td>
<td><code>pip install sqlite-vec</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/python.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with Python</a></td>
<td><a href="https://pypi.org/project/sqlite-vec/" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/bb44e6640e98eab68ae756f0ec673dc112ebc235b31ffe203966d6b13b1d4513/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f73716c6974652d7665632e7376673f636f6c6f723d626c7565266c6f676f3d707974686f6e266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" alt="PyPI" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/sqlite-vec.svg?color=blue&amp;logo=python&amp;logoColor=white"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Node.js</td>
<td><code>npm install sqlite-vec</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/nodejs.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with Node.js</a></td>
<td><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/sqlite-vec" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/9252e605686431e743b0c7fde5b18452898c037533e9637c37bbd74f03594106/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6e706d2f762f73716c6974652d7665632e7376673f636f6c6f723d677265656e266c6f676f3d6e6f6465646f746a73266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" alt="npm" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/npm/v/sqlite-vec.svg?color=green&amp;logo=nodedotjs&amp;logoColor=white"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Ruby</td>
<td><code>gem install sqlite-vec</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/ruby.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with Ruby</a></td>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ffdff07764427f1a0c012e40b441575843516c137e29896729cc301fa526facf/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f67656d2f762f73716c6974652d7665633f636f6c6f723d726564266c6f676f3d7275627967656d73266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/ffdff07764427f1a0c012e40b441575843516c137e29896729cc301fa526facf/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f67656d2f762f73716c6974652d7665633f636f6c6f723d726564266c6f676f3d7275627967656d73266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465" alt="Gem" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/gem/v/sqlite-vec?color=red&amp;logo=rubygems&amp;logoColor=white"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Go</td>
<td><code>go get -u github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/bindings/go</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/go.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with Go</a></td>
<td><a href="https://pkg.go.dev/github.com/asg017/asg017/sqlite-vec-go-bindings/cgo" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/96f8845591efcb8edbe9ba47ef7154d05071a3d52cc218767635ec857a3d36ee/68747470733a2f2f706b672e676f2e6465762f62616467652f6769746875622e636f6d2f6173673031372f73716c6974652d7665632d676f2d62696e64696e67732f63676f2e737667" alt="Go Reference" data-canonical-src="https://pkg.go.dev/badge/github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec-go-bindings/cgo.svg"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Rust</td>
<td><code>cargo add sqlite-vec</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/rust.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with Rust</a></td>
<td><a href="https://crates.io/crates/sqlite-vec" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/e7a571a8bbbeac983f297a775267cc93a7c01803641d8f302f23e9f26329e77b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6372617465732f762f73716c6974652d7665633f6c6f676f3d72757374" alt="Crates.io" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/crates/v/sqlite-vec?logo=rust"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Datasette</td>
<td><code>datasette install datasette-sqlite-vec</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/datasette.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with Datasette</a></td>
<td><a href="https://datasette.io/plugins/datasette-sqlite-vec" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f4ff42b28f297904da764bd4cd79e0668592b87cf4c2ea4ab2c0f41dc7ac234f/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f6461746173657474652d73716c6974652d7665632e7376673f636f6c6f723d423642364439266c6162656c3d4461746173657474652b706c7567696e266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465266c6f676f3d707974686f6e" alt="Datasette" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/datasette-sqlite-vec.svg?color=B6B6D9&amp;label=Datasette+plugin&amp;logoColor=white&amp;logo=python"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>sqlite-utils</code></td>
<td><code>sqlite-utils install sqlite-utils-sqlite-vec</code></td>
<td><a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/sqlite-vec/sqlite-utils.html" rel="nofollow"><code>sqlite-vec</code> with sqlite-utils</a></td>
<td><a href="https://datasette.io/plugins/datasette-sqlite-vec" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/02219f281233bad848e2073d29d9445ab466b33565f352a1588005bbac70819e/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f707970692f762f73716c6974652d7574696c732d73716c6974652d7665632e7376673f636f6c6f723d423642364439266c6162656c3d73716c6974652d7574696c732b706c7567696e266c6f676f436f6c6f723d7768697465266c6f676f3d707974686f6e" alt="sqlite-utils" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/sqlite-utils-sqlite-vec.svg?color=B6B6D9&amp;label=sqlite-utils+plugin&amp;logoColor=white&amp;logo=python"></a></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Github Release</td>
<td></td>
<td></td>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f274f2929381d4f1009950182fdf45d738f1eb639a89a0c23fc0560c1687e52b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f762f7461672f6173673031372f73716c6974652d7665633f636f6c6f723d6c696768746772657926696e636c7564655f70726572656c6561736573266c6162656c3d4769746875622b72656c65617365266c6f676f3d676974687562"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/f274f2929381d4f1009950182fdf45d738f1eb639a89a0c23fc0560c1687e52b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f762f7461672f6173673031372f73716c6974652d7665633f636f6c6f723d6c696768746772657926696e636c7564655f70726572656c6561736573266c6162656c3d4769746875622b72656c65617365266c6f676f3d676974687562" alt="GitHub tag (latest SemVer pre-release)" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/v/tag/asg017/sqlite-vec?color=lightgrey&amp;include_prereleases&amp;label=Github+release&amp;logo=github"></a></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sample usage</h2><a id="user-content-sample-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Sample usage" href="#sample-usage"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content=".load ./vec0

create virtual table vec_examples using vec0(
  sample_embedding float[8]
);

-- vectors can be provided as JSON or in a compact binary format
insert into vec_examples(rowid, sample_embedding)
  values
    (1, '[-0.200, 0.250, 0.341, -0.211, 0.645, 0.935, -0.316, -0.924]'),
    (2, '[0.443, -0.501, 0.355, -0.771, 0.707, -0.708, -0.185, 0.362]'),
    (3, '[0.716, -0.927, 0.134, 0.052, -0.669, 0.793, -0.634, -0.162]'),
    (4, '[-0.710, 0.330, 0.656, 0.041, -0.990, 0.726, 0.385, -0.958]');


-- KNN style query
select
  rowid,
  distance
from vec_examples
where sample_embedding match '[0.890, 0.544, 0.825, 0.961, 0.358, 0.0196, 0.521, 0.175]'
order by distance
limit 2;
/*
┌───────┬──────────────────┐
│ rowid │     distance     │
├───────┼──────────────────┤
│ 2     │ 2.38687372207642 │
│ 1     │ 2.38978505134583 │
└───────┴──────────────────┘
*/"><pre>.load .<span>/</span>vec0

create virtual table vec_examples using vec0(
  sample_embedding float[<span>8</span>]
);

<span><span>--</span> vectors can be provided as JSON or in a compact binary format</span>
<span>insert into</span> vec_examples(rowid, sample_embedding)
  <span>values</span>
    (<span>1</span>, <span><span>'</span>[-0.200, 0.250, 0.341, -0.211, 0.645, 0.935, -0.316, -0.924]<span>'</span></span>),
    (<span>2</span>, <span><span>'</span>[0.443, -0.501, 0.355, -0.771, 0.707, -0.708, -0.185, 0.362]<span>'</span></span>),
    (<span>3</span>, <span><span>'</span>[0.716, -0.927, 0.134, 0.052, -0.669, 0.793, -0.634, -0.162]<span>'</span></span>),
    (<span>4</span>, <span><span>'</span>[-0.710, 0.330, 0.656, 0.041, -0.990, 0.726, 0.385, -0.958]<span>'</span></span>);


<span><span>--</span> KNN style query</span>
<span>select</span>
  rowid,
  distance
<span>from</span> vec_examples
<span>where</span> sample_embedding match <span><span>'</span>[0.890, 0.544, 0.825, 0.961, 0.358, 0.0196, 0.521, 0.175]<span>'</span></span>
<span>order by</span> distance
<span>limit</span> <span>2</span>;
<span><span>/*</span></span>
<span>┌───────┬──────────────────┐</span>
<span>│ rowid │     distance     │</span>
<span>├───────┼──────────────────┤</span>
<span>│ 2     │ 2.38687372207642 │</span>
<span>│ 1     │ 2.38978505134583 │</span>
<span>└───────┴──────────────────┘</span>
<span><span>*/</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sponsors</h2><a id="user-content-sponsors" aria-label="Permalink: Sponsors" href="#sponsors"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Development of <code>sqlite-vec</code> is supported by multiple generous sponsors! Mozilla
is the main sponsor through the new Builders project.</p>

<p dir="auto"><code>sqlite-vec</code> is also sponsored by the following companies:</p>
<a href="https://fly.io/" rel="nofollow">
<themed-picture data-catalyst-inline="true"><picture>
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: dark)" srcset="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/flyio.dark.svg">
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: light)" srcset="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/flyio.svg">
  <img alt="Fly.io logo" src="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/flyio.svg" width="32%">
</picture></themed-picture>
</a>
<a href="https://turso.tech/" rel="nofollow">
<themed-picture data-catalyst-inline="true"><picture>
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: dark)" srcset="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/turso.svg">
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: light)" srcset="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/turso.svg">
  <img alt="Turso logo" src="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/turso.svg" width="32%">
</picture></themed-picture>
</a>
<a href="https://sqlitecloud.io/" rel="nofollow">
<themed-picture data-catalyst-inline="true"><picture>
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: dark)" srcset="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/sqlitecloud.dark.svg">
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: light)" srcset="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/sqlitecloud.svg">
  <img alt="SQLite Cloud logo" src="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-vec/raw/main/.github/logos/flyio.svg" width="32%">
</picture></themed-picture>
</a>
<p dir="auto">As well as multiple individual supporters on
<a href="https://github.com/sponsors/asg017/">Github sponsors</a>!</p>
<p dir="auto">If your company interested in sponsoring <code>sqlite-vec</code> development, send me an
email to get more info: <a href="https://alexgarcia.xyz/" rel="nofollow">https://alexgarcia.xyz</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">See Also</h2><a id="user-content-see-also" aria-label="Permalink: See Also" href="#see-also"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-ecosystem"><strong><code>sqlite-ecosystem</code></strong></a>, Maybe
more 3rd party SQLite extensions I've developed</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-rembed"><strong><code>sqlite-rembed</code></strong></a>, Generate text
embeddings from remote APIs like OpenAI/Nomic/Ollama, meant for testing and
SQL scripts</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/asg017/sqlite-lembed"><strong><code>sqlite-lembed</code></strong></a>, Generate text
embeddings locally from embedding models in the <code>.gguf</code> format</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[JVM/Java: Null-Restricted and Nullable Types (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bugs.openjdk.org/browse/JDK-8303099</link>
            <guid>41136974</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 08:02:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bugs.openjdk.org/browse/JDK-8303099">https://bugs.openjdk.org/browse/JDK-8303099</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41136974">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="descriptionmodule">
                    

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Support <em>nullness markers</em> on Java types to indicate that a type rejects or
deliberately allows nulls.
This is a <a href="http://openjdk.java.net/jeps/12" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">preview language feature</a>.</p>

<h2>Goals</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>Enhance Java's reference types to let programmers express whether <code>null</code>
references are expected as values of the type</p></li>
<li><p>Support conversions between types with different nullness properties,
accompanied by warnings about possibly-mishandled <code>null</code> values</p></li>
<li><p>Compatibibly interoperate with traditional Java code that makes no assertions
about the <code>null</code> compatibility of its types, and support gradual adoption of
these new features without introducing source or binary incompatibilities</p></li>
<li><p>Ensure that variables with types that reject <code>null</code> are initialized before
they are first read</p></li>
<li><p>Enforce types that reject <code>null</code> at run time, even when classes are compiled
separately</p></li>
<li><p>Provide the metadata and integrity guarantees necessary for run-time
optimizations (such as the flattening of <a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/401" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">value objects</a>) to rely
on types that claim to exclude <code>null</code></p></li>
</ul>

<h2>Non-Goals</h2>

<ul>
<li><p>It is not a goal to automatically re-interpret existing code—use of these
features should be optional and explicitly opted in to (future work will
explore mechanisms to request a bulk opt-in without needing to change
individual types)</p></li>
<li><p>It is not a goal to require programs to explicitly account for all <code>null</code>
values that might occur; unaccounted-for <code>null</code> values may cause
compile-time warnings, but not compile-time errors</p></li>
<li><p>It is not a goal to make any changes to the primitive types, such as
adding support for a nullable <code>int</code> type</p></li>
<li><p>It is not a goal (at this time) to apply the language enhancements to the
standard libraries</p></li>
</ul>

<h2>Motivation</h2>

<p>In a Java program, a variable of type <code>String</code> may hold either a reference to a
<code>String</code> object or the special value <code>null</code>. In some cases, the author
intends that the variable will always hold a reference to a <code>String</code> object;
in other cases, the author expects <code>null</code> as a meaningful value. Unfortunately,
there is no way to formally express in the language which of these alternatives
is intended, leading to confusion and bugs.</p>

<p>For example, programs often make a blanket assumption that no <code>null</code> values will
be present. But it takes extra care to state this expectation in Javadoc
specifications and to reliably enforce it in implementation code. If extra care
isn't taken, and someone fails to follow the assumed protocol, then <code>null</code>
values may end up flowing freely through implementation code, eventually
triggering an exception at some point far removed from the bug.</p>

<p>This situation can be greatly improved by giving developers tools to assert, as
part of a type, that either (1) <code>null</code> values are not supported and will be
rejected, or (2) <code>null</code> values are expected and should be properly accounted
for.</p>

<p>By default, the language can't reasonably assume either of these
interpretations. It needs developers to explicitly indicate their intent.</p>

<p>Given a clear expression of intent, the language could then introduce both
compile-time feedback and run-time checks to help developers detect
unexpected nulls earlier.</p>

<p>In the Valhalla project, a variable of a <a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/401" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">value class type</a> can
be optimized with a flattened representation of its values. But this flattened
representation may need extra bits to encode <code>null</code>, negatively impacting memory
footprint and sometimes making it impossible to optimize the storage at all.
If the developer could exclude <code>null</code> from the domain of the variable, a
<a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/8316779" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">better encoding</a> could be achieved.</p>

<p>In the Amber project, the nullness of a pattern match candidate may influence
whether a <code>switch</code> should be considered exhaustive, and the nullness of a type
pattern may influence whether the pattern matches <code>null</code>. It would be useful for
developers to be able to control these behaviors.</p>

<h2>Description</h2>

<p>The features described below are preview features, enabled with the
<code>--enable-preview</code> compile-time and runtime flags.</p>

<h3>Nullness properties and markers</h3>

<p>A reference type may optionally express <em>nullness</em>—whether <code>null</code> is intended
to be included in the value set of the type.</p>

<p>In Java syntax, a <em>nullness marker</em> is used to indicate this property.</p>

<p>The type <code>Foo!</code> is <em>null-restricted</em>: the value set excludes <code>null</code>.</p>

<p>The type <code>Foo?</code> is <em>nullable</em>: the value set deliberately includes <code>null</code>.</p>

<p>By default, the nullness of the type <code>Foo</code> is <em>unspecified</em>: a <code>null</code> may occur,
but we don't know whether its presence is deliberate.</p>



<p>The nullness of a type is an intrinsic part of the type—in other words, <code>Foo?</code>
and <code>Foo</code> are <em>different types</em>, because they have different nullness.
However, as outlined later, most language rules are defined in a way that
either ignores nullness or helpfully adapts (perhaps with a warning) between
types with different nullness.</p>

<p>Array types and their array component types may both have nullness markers.
<code>Foo?[]!</code> is a null-restricted array type, whose components are of nullable type
<code>Foo</code>. Null markers for multi-dimensional arrays may occur after each bracket
pair, and by convention are interpreted outermost to innermost, from left to
right.</p>

<p>Parameterized types and their type arguments may similarly both have nullness
markers. <code>Predicate!&lt;Foo?&gt;</code> is a null-restricted <code>Predicate</code> with nullable type
<code>Foo</code> as a type argument. The interpretation of type arguments is described in
more detail later.</p>

<p>In this JEP, nullness markers are explicit: to express a null-restricted or
nullable type, the <code>!</code> or <code>?</code> symbol must appear in source. In the future, it
may be useful, for example, for a programmer to somehow express that every
type in a class or compilation unit is to be interpreted as null-restricted,
unless a <code>?</code> symbol is present. The details of any such a feature will be
explored separately.</p>

<h3>Field and array initialization</h3>

<p>Most variables in Java must be initialized with a value of the
variable's type before they can be used. Local variables are checked
for <em>definite assignment</em> before they can be referenced; method parameters get
initial values from a method invocation expression; pattern variables are bound
in the process of pattern matching; etc.</p>

<p>Traditionally, fields and array components get special treatment: because they
can be accessed by multiple program components immediately upon creation of a
class or object, they are automatically initialized "at birth" with a <em>default
value</em>, which programmers will typically overwrite in the course of program
execution.</p>

<p>The default value of a reference type is <code>null</code>. But this is an unsuitable
initial value for a null-restricted field or array component—if someone reads
the variable before it has been written, they will observe a value that is not
of the variable's type.</p>

<p>Thus, fields and arrays with null-restricted types behave differently than other
fields and arrays: they must always be initialized by the program before they
can be read. This is enforced as follows:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>A null-restricted instance field without an initializer must be definitely
assigned before the (explicit or implicit) <code>super(...)</code> call in each of the
class's constructors. The <a href="https://openjdk.org/jeps/8325803" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Flexible Constructor Bodies JEP</a>
allows the necessary initialization code to be written at the start of a
constructor. In this <em>early construction context</em>, the initialization logic is
not allowed to refer to <code>this</code> or risk any attempts to read the uninitialized
field.</p>

<pre><code>class Person {
private String! name;

public Person(String name) {
  this.name = name;
  super();
}
}</code></pre></li>
<li><p>If a null-restricted instance field <em>has</em> an initializer, the initializer is
executed at the start of each constructor, before the <code>super(...)</code> call.
(Constructors that call <code>this(...)</code> are a special case and, as usual, do not
execute initializers at all.) Again, this means that the initialization logic
of the field occurs in an <em>early construction context</em> and may not refer to
<code>this</code> or risk any reads of the uninitialized field.</p></li>
<li><p>A null-restricted static field must be definitely assigned by the end of all
static initializers and initializer blocks of the class. Note, however, that
this rule does not prevent some other class from trying to read the field
during the class initialization process; in that case, a run time check
detects the early read attempt and throws an exception.</p>

<p>In the following example, the initialization code of field <code>Foo.s</code> has a
circular dependency. Traditionally, the circular reference to <code>Foo.s</code> would
produce the default value of <code>s</code>, <code>null</code>; with a null-restricted field type,
that is impossible and so an exception is thrown alerting the developer to
the bug.</p>

<pre><code>class Foo {
public String! s = Bar.getString();
}

class Bar {
static String! getString() {
    return Foo.s; // may throw an exception
}
}</code></pre></li>
<li><p>An array with a null-restricted component type must provide an initializer for
each component in the array creation expression. This can be achieved by
explicitly listing each initial value in an array initializer, or by using
a new shorthand form (syntax TBD).</p>

<pre><code>String![] labels;<br>
labels = new String![]{ "x", "y", "z" };
labels = new String!<span>[100]</span>{ "" }; // strawman syntax
labels = new String!<span>[100]</span>{ i -&gt; "x"+i }; // strawman syntax</code></pre></li>
</ul>

<h3>Expression nullness and conversions</h3>

<p>As part of type checking, the Java compiler is responsible for determining the
nullness of every expression.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The nullness of a variable reference is given by the referenced variable's
declaration (but TBD whether the Java compiler will further observe that, due
to previous uses of the variable, a <code>null</code> is known not to be present).</p></li>
<li><p>The nullness of a method invocation is given by the referenced method's return
type.</p></li>
<li><p>The type of a cast expression is explicit in the cast (but, again, TBD whether
the Java compiler takes other information into account).</p></li>
<li><p>A <code>null</code> literal is nullable (of course).</p></li>
<li><p>Most other reference-typed expressions are null-restricted. These include
literals, string concatenations, <code>this</code>, class instance and array creations,
method references, and lambda expressions.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>A <em>nullness conversion</em> allows an expression with one kind of nullness to be
treated as having a different nullness. Nullness conversions are permitted
in all assignment, invocation, and casting contexts.</p>

<p>The following are <em>widening nullness conversions</em>:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>Foo!</code> to <code>Foo?</code></li>
<li><code>Foo!</code> to unspecified <code>Foo</code></li>
<li><code>Foo?</code> to unspecified <code>Foo</code></li>
<li>unspecified <code>Foo</code> to <code>Foo?</code></li>
</ul>

<p>And these are <em>narrowing nullness conversions</em>:
- <code>Foo?</code> to <code>Foo!</code>
- unspecified <code>Foo</code> to <code>Foo!</code></p>

<p>Narrowing nullness conversions are analogous to unboxing conversions: the
compiler performs them automatically, while at run time they impose a dynamic
check, possibly causing a <code>NullPointerException</code>.</p>

<p>In fact, the boxing and unboxing conversions can now be simplified: boxing
converts <code>int</code> to <code>Integer!</code>, potentially followed by a widening nullness
conversion to <code>Integer</code>; unboxing converts <code>Integer!</code> to <code>int</code>, possibly
preceded by a narrowing nullness conversion from <code>Integer</code> to <code>Integer!</code>.</p>

<p>It is a compile-time error to attempt to directly convert a <code>null</code> literal to a
null-restricted type.</p>

<h3>Run-time null checking</h3>

<p>At run time, if a <code>null</code> value undergoes a narrowing nullness conversion to a
null-restricted type, a <code>NullPointerException</code> is thrown.</p>

<pre><code>String? id(String! arg) { return arg; }

String s = null;
Object! o1 = s; // NPE
Object o2 = id(s); // NPE
Object o3 = (String!) s; // NPE</code></pre>

<p>Some narrowing nullness conversions are not apparent in the source code, but
occur implicitly as part of run time execution. These include:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>An array that was allocated with a null-restricted component type may be given
a less specific type in the source code, but will still reject <code>null</code> values
during the usual <em>array store check</em>. The failed conversion will prompt an
<code>ArrayStoreException</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>Similary, a field that was not null-restricted at compile time but was later
separately compiled to be null-restricted will reject <code>null</code> values during a
new <em>field store check</em>. The failed conversion will prompt a
<code>FieldStoreException</code>.</p></li>
<li><p>When one method overrides another, the argument to an invocation of the
superclass method undergoes conversion to the parameter's invocation type,
<em>followed by</em> conversion to the type of the overriding method's parameter.
As discussed below, the nullness of these two parameter types may not be the
same.</p></li>
<li><p>Similarly, the return value of a method undergoes conversion to the declared
method return type, <em>followed by</em> conversion to the invocation's expected
return type.</p></li>
</ul>

<h3>Nullness of type variables</h3>

<p>Like other types, a type-variable type (that is, a <em>use</em> of a type variable) may
express nullness. <code>T!</code> is a null-restricted type, and <code>T?</code> is a nullable type.</p>



<p>Null-restricted and nullable type variable types (<code>T!</code> and <code>T?</code>) assert a
specific nullness within the generic code. This may be appropriate if the
generic code directly interacts with <code>null</code>. <!--Parametric nullness (<code class="prettyprint" >T*</code>), on the
other hand, leaves nullness to the use site; often, the generic code does
nothing with values of the type variable type except store them or pass them on
to non-generic code.--></p>

<pre><code>class Box&lt;T&gt; {
    boolean set;
    T? val; // nullable field

    public Box() { set = false; }
    public void set(T val) { this.val = val; set = true; }

    public T? getOrNull() { // nullable result
        return set ? val : null;
    }

    public T! getNonNull(T! alt) { // null-restricted result
        return (set &amp;&amp; val != null) ? (T!) val : alt;
    }
}</code></pre>







<p>Types used as type arguments may express nullness; null markers on type-variable
types override whatever nullness was asserted by the type argument.</p>

<pre><code>Box&lt;String!&gt; b1 = new Box&lt;String!&gt;();
b1.getOrNull(); // nullable result

Box&lt;String?&gt; b2 = new Box&lt;String?&gt;();
b2.set(null);
b2.getNonNull(""); // null-restricted result</code></pre>

<p>Of course, null restrictions cannot be enforced within the erased implementation
of a generic API. But the usual implicit casts that occur at the boundaries of
generic APIs will enforce null-restricted type arguments at run time.</p>



<h3>Type arguments and bounds</h3>

<p>As illustrated above, type arguments may express nullness, which influences the
substituted nullness of the API wherever parametric type variables occur.</p>

<p>For interoperability, nullness in type arguments is not strongly enforced, and
<em>unchecked nullness conversions</em> allow modifications to the nullness of type
arguments. For example, <code>Predicate&lt;String!&gt;</code> can be converted to
<code>Predicate&lt;String&gt;</code> or <code>Predicate&lt;String?&gt;</code>. These conversions may cause
warnings (see "Compiler warnings", below).</p>

<p>Similarly, unchecked nullness conversions allow modifications to the nullness of
array component types. TBD under what conditions these conversions are checked
at run time.</p>

<p>A type variable declaration or wildcard may have nullness markers on its bounds.
A type may satisfy the bounds via nullness conversion, though, so again these
nullness markers are not strongly enforced, but may cause warnings.</p>

<h3>Method overriding and type argument inference</h3>

<p>Nullness is ignored when determining whether two methods have the same
signature. One method may override another even if the nullness of their
parameters and returns do not match.</p>

<pre><code>class A {
    String? lookup(String! arg) { ... }
}

class B extends A {
    String lookup(String arg) { ... }
}</code></pre>

<p>Such mismatches will be common as different APIs adopt nullness markers
independently.</p>

<p>Formally, two methods are considered to have the <em>same signature</em> if each
parameter type and type parameter bound can be converted to the other via
nullness and unchecked conversions.</p>

<p>Similarly, the return type of an overriding method must be convertible to the
overridden return type via a widening reference conversion, possibly followed by
nullness and unchecked conversions.</p>

<p>If a method is generic, any parametric uses of its type parameters in the method
signature will influence the inferred nullness of type arguments. Nullness does
not influence method applicability and cannot cause type argument inference to
fail, but it can influence the nullness inferred for the method's return type.
(Details of the inference algorithm TBD.)</p>

<h3>Compiler warnings</h3>

<p>As described above, making a type null-restricted may cause new compile-time
errors if a field or array of the type is left uninitialized, or if an
attempt is made to convert a <code>null</code> literal to the type. It may also be a
compile-time error to compare a <code>null</code> literal to an expression with a
null-restricted type.</p>

<p>In other situations, nullness analysis is supplementary and does not cause
compile-time errors. However, <code>javac</code> will provide warnings to help programmers
avoid runtime errors. IDEs and other analysis tools are encouraged to do the
same. Possible sources of warnings include:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Narrowing nullness conversions, especially from <code>?</code> types</p></li>
<li><p><code>?</code>-typed <!--or <code class="prettyprint" >*</code>-typed--> expressions used in member accesses or other null-hostile
operations</p></li>
<li><p>Type arguments whose nullness is inconsistent with their bounds</p></li>
<li><p>Method parameters or returns with nullness that doesn't match an overridden
method</p></li>
<li><p>Unchecked conversions that change the nullness of a type</p></li>
</ul>

<h3>Compilation &amp; class file representation</h3>

<p>Most uses of null markers are erased in <code>class</code> files, with the accompanying
run-time conversions being expressed directly in bytecode.</p>

<p><code>Signature</code> attributes have an updated grammar to allow <code>!</code> and <code>?</code> <!-- and <code class="prettyprint" >*</code>--> in
types, as appropriate. Nullness is not encoded in method and
field <em>descriptors</em>.</p>

<p>However, to prevent pollution of fields, a new <code>NullRestricted</code> attribute allows
a field to indicate that it does not allow <code>null</code> values. This has the following
effects:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>The field must also be marked <code>ACC_STRICT</code>, which indicates that it must be
"strictly-initialized". The verifier ensures that all strictly-initialized
instance fields have been assigned to at the point that a constructor makes
a <code>super(...)</code> call.</p></li>
<li><p>All attempts to write to the field check for a <code>null</code> value and, if found,
throw a <code>FieldStoreException</code>.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Null-restricted array creation is not supported by the <code>anewarray</code> instruction,
and must be accomplished with a call to the reflection API (see below). All
attempts to write to a null-restricted array component reject <code>null</code> values
during the usual array store check.</p>

<h3>Core reflection</h3>

<p>There are no <code>Foo!.class</code> or <code>Foo?.class</code> literals, and no associated instances
of <code>java.lang.Class</code>. These types are derived from a class declaration, but
do not represent distinct classes. (Compare <code>List&lt;String&gt;</code> and <code>List&lt;Integer&gt;</code>.)</p>

<p>However, a new <code>RuntimeType</code> API describes the set of types that are enforced
by array and field store checks at run time, including a null-restricted
variant of every class and interface type. (This is a superset of
the <em>linkage types</em>, which can appear in descriptors and are represented by
the <code>Class</code> API.)</p>

<p>The <code>Field</code> API supports querying a field's <code>RuntimeType</code>, which may not be
the same as its <code>getType</code> result.</p>

<p>The <code>Array</code> API supports variations of <code>newInstance</code> that allow a component type
to be expressed with a <code>RuntimeType</code>. These variations also allow the caller to
provide initial values for the array components, and will reject attempts to
create null-restricted arrays without initial values. Another new method
reflects the <code>RuntimeType</code> of an array's components.</p>

<h3>Supplementary changes</h3>

<p>Traditional deserialization is not compatible with null-restricted fields and
arrays. A separate JEP will provide a new mechanism to support serialization
without exposing uninitialized null-restricted fields and arrays.</p>

<p>Documentation generated by <code>javadoc</code> will include nullness markers.</p>

<p>The <code>java.lang.reflect.Type</code> and <code>javax.lang.model</code> APIs will encode nullness in
their representation of types.</p>

<h2>Alternatives</h2>

<p>A variety of development tools in the Java ecosystem have implemented their own
compile-time tracking of nulls. These tools don't change the Java language and
so naturally have some limitations, particularly in the syntax they can use
(annotations) and the behavior they can affect (compile-time checks).</p>

<p>Other programming languages track nullness in their type systems. Many are
null-restricted by default. Many also consider it an error to assign to a
null-restricted type without an explicit null check. In the case of Java,
it's important that the feature be optional, and be something that
programmers can incrementally make use of without a monolithic migration
effort.</p>

<p>Runtime enforcement of nullness can be implemented with explicit checks or calls
to the <code>Objects.requireNonNull</code> standard API. But consistently applying these
checks is tedious, necessitates additional documentation work, and makes
programs harder to read. There's no way to apply these checks directly to
variable storage, particularly fields and arrays.</p>

<h2>Dependencies</h2>

<p>Prerequisites:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://openjdk.org/jeps/8325803" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Flexible Constructor Bodies (Second Preview)</a> allows
constructors to execute statements before a <code>super(...)</code> call and allows
assignments to instance fields in this context. These changes facilitate the
initialization requirements of null-restricted fields.</li>
</ul>

<p>Future work:</p>

<ul>
<li><p><a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/8316779" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Null-Restricted Value Class Types (Preview)</a> will optimize
the encodings of null-restricted, value-class-typed fields and arrays, and
may allow some value classes to declare their own default values.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/402" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">JEP 402: Enhanced Primitive Boxing (Preview)</a> will track nullness as
it makes wider use of implicit boxing conversions in the language.</p></li>
<li><p>JVM class and method specialization (<a href="https://openjdk.java.net/jeps/218" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">JEP 218</a>, with revisions) will
allow generic classes and methods to reify and enforce the nullness of
(at least some of) their type arguments.</p></li>
</ul>

<p>Other possible future enhancements building on this JEP may include:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Applying nullness markers to certain parts of the standard APIs.</p></li>
<li><p>Enhancing the JVM to provide a concise, minimal-footprint way to express a
null check in bytecode.</p></li>
<li><p>Enhancing the JVM to provide stronger low-level enforcement of null-restricted
method parameters.</p></li>
<li><p>Providing a mechanism in the language to assert that all types in a certain
context are implicitly null-restricted, without requiring the programmer to
use explicit <code>!</code> symbols.</p></li>
</ul>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Peerfetch – Peer-to-Peer HTTP over WebRTC (255 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/ambianic/peerfetch</link>
            <guid>41135671</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 02:44:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/ambianic/peerfetch">https://github.com/ambianic/peerfetch</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41135671">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">peerfetch</h2><a id="user-content-peerfetch" aria-label="Permalink: peerfetch" href="#peerfetch"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Peer-to-peer HTTP over WebRTC. Implements an http client wrapper (similar to <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Fetch_API/Using_Fetch" rel="nofollow">HTML fetch</a>) and a corresponding server side HTTP proxy over WebRTC DataChannel. Allows direct secure access from a web browser to edge devices (IoT or servers) hidden behind a firewall.</p>
<p dir="auto">Highlights:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Excutes in safe application space (no <code>sudo</code>)</li>
<li>End to end encryption</li>
<li>No custom VPN setup needed</li>
<li>No cloud middleman for data tunneling</li>
<li>No dynamic DNS service required</li>
<li>No custom firewall rules required</li>
<li>Programming language agnostic. (Currently available in JavaScript and Python)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hello World example</h2><a id="user-content-hello-world-example" aria-label="Permalink: Hello World example" href="#hello-world-example"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See this <a href="https://github.com/ambianic/peerfetch/blob/main/examples/helloworld/README.md">README</a> for a step by step Hello World example.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How it works</h2><a id="user-content-how-it-works" aria-label="Permalink: How it works" href="#how-it-works"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For an in-depth technical discussion and project background, see <a href="https://webrtchacks.com/private-home-surveillance-with-the-webrtc-datachannel/" rel="nofollow">this blog post</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hands-on Workshop</h2><a id="user-content-hands-on-workshop" aria-label="Permalink: Hands-on Workshop" href="#hands-on-workshop"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LFKYtL1_RjQ" rel="nofollow">Here is the recording</a> of a <code>peerfetch</code> workshop hosted by <a href="https://github.com/Jacob-Barhak/EveningOfPythonCoding">Python Austin</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Use cases:</h2><a id="user-content-use-cases" aria-label="Permalink: Use cases:" href="#use-cases"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Direct user access from a web app to private home security camera without sharing footage with a cloud provider.</li>
<li>IoT device mesh with direct p2p communication.</li>
<li>Personal web apps can share data directly (files, notes, photos) only with the end user without exposing a public IP address.</li>
<li>Federated learning - ML models can train on local user data and share learned states directly with each other without a centralized model aggregation server.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Used by</h2><a id="user-content-used-by" aria-label="Permalink: Used by" href="#used-by"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/ambianic/ambianic-ui">Ambianic UI PWA</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ambianic/ambianic-edge">Ambianic Edge</a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PSA: Internet Archive "glitch" deletes years of user data and accounts (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.gingerbeardman.com/2024/08/01/psa-internet-archive-glitch-deletes-years-of-user-data-and-accounts/</link>
            <guid>41135450</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 01:50:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.gingerbeardman.com/2024/08/01/psa-internet-archive-glitch-deletes-years-of-user-data-and-accounts/">https://blog.gingerbeardman.com/2024/08/01/psa-internet-archive-glitch-deletes-years-of-user-data-and-accounts/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41135450">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
          

          

          

          <p>Recently at <em>Internet Archive</em> a “glitch” (<a href="https://archive.org/post/2435138/archives-removed-my-account-and-deleted-all-my-uploaded-files">their choice of word</a>) deleted a great many accounts, including my account that had been at <a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman">https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman</a> since 2015.</p>

<p>Somewhat surprisingly, they are not reaching out to affected users but rather waiting for them to create new accounts and silently relinking their old uploads <em>only if the new account has same email as the old account</em>. Otherwise, all profile metadata, favourites, lists, reviews, posts, collections, web archives, and the original username are not being relinked. For me that’s a decade of data…gone.</p>

<p>The main impact of this massive data loss, that happened around mid-July, is that there are now dead links to old profiles and various old pages all across the internet, plus the additional impact of lost data that is not being recovered. It’s a real blow to the broader preservation effort to know that <em>the one place where data is supposed to be safe forever has had a massive data loss</em> and the organisation responsible are not taking proactive steps to address the issue fully.</p>

<p>The extent of the data loss and how many accounts were affected is currently unknown. And because they’re not really talking about it, it’s quite difficult to find any concrete information as to the extent or cause of the data loss. You can find <a href="https://archive.org/iathreads/forum-display.php?forum=general">more info at the <em>Internet Archive</em> forums</a>, <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/internetarchive/s/YFihAFXzE8">the /r/internetarchive subreddit</a>, or your choice of social media where <em>Internet Archive</em> have a presence (Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=login%20to%3Ainternetarchive&amp;src=typed_query&amp;f=live">ref1</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=account%20to%3Ainternetarchive&amp;src=typed_query&amp;f=live">ref2</a>).</p>

<p>This story is still developing, and the press have been notified.</p>

<hr>

<h2 id="status">Status</h2>

<p>Here’s a summary of the current status of the pages related to a deleted account.</p>

<p><strong>Remaining</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/fav-gingerbeardman">archive.org/details/fav-gingerbeardman</a></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Relinked</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@flicky1984/uploads">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/uploads</a></li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Lost</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/loans">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/loans</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/lists">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/lists</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/posts">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/posts</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/reviews">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/reviews</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/collections">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/collections</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/web-archive">archive.org/details/@gingerbeardman/web-archive</a></li>
</ul>

<hr>

<h2 id="support-up-to-a-point">Support, up to a point</h2>

<p>My support experience with <em>Internet Archive</em> was frustrating and ultimately futile. They did not adequately address my queries and requests. Instead they made changes to my account that I did not request, and in the end were pretty clear that they were not going to help me any further. This is such a disappointing stance to take with users who are simply trying to recover their data as a result of loss caused by <em>Internet Archive</em> itself.</p>

<p><img src="https://cdn.gingerbeardman.com/images/posts/internet-archive-glitch.png" alt="PNG" title="“(your data) cannot be restored and, for the last time, the old user name is no longer available.”" loading="lazy"></p>

<hr>

<h2 id="elsewhere">Elsewhere</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41131388">Hacker News</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://lobste.rs/s/82zpde/psa_internet_archive_glitch_deletes">Lobste.rs</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://tildes.net/~tech/1hy4/psa_internet_archive_glitch_deletes_years_of_user_data_accounts#comment-dbpw">Tildes</a></li>
  <li><a href="http://twostopbits.com/item?id=3935">Two Stop Bits</a></li>
</ul>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[YC closes deal with Google for dedicated compute cluster for AI startups (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2024/08/01/google-cloud-now-has-a-dedicated-cluster-of-nvidia-gpus-for-y-combinator-startups/</link>
            <guid>41135363</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 01:33:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/08/01/google-cloud-now-has-a-dedicated-cluster-of-nvidia-gpus-for-y-combinator-startups/">https://techcrunch.com/2024/08/01/google-cloud-now-has-a-dedicated-cluster-of-nvidia-gpus-for-y-combinator-startups/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41135363">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">Google Cloud is giving Y Combinator startups access to a dedicated, subsidized cluster of Nvidia graphics processing units and Google tensor processing units to build AI models. It’s part of Google Cloud’s effort to cozy up with promising early-stage AI startups, in hopes some of them will evolve into massive, compute-hungry businesses.</p>

<p>“We want to surround them with a lot of love and warmth early in their life cycle so they get familiarized with building and working on the Google Cloud Platform,” said general manager for Google Cloud’s startups and AI business, James Lee, in an interview with TechCrunch. “As they stick around, we grow as they grow, and we become a partner of theirs throughout their life cycle.”</p>

	
	


<p>Specifically, Google will provide a dedicated cluster with priority access for YC’s Summer 2024 startups, along with $350,000 in cloud credits over two years for each participating startup. The idea is that a future unicorn will fall in love with building on Google Cloud. Five percent of Y Combinator startups over the last 18 years have become unicorns with billion-dollar-plus valuations, YC group partner Diana Hu tells TechCrunch, so it’s a decent bet for Google to make on this partnership.</p>

<p>“There’s a lot of excitement that the next generation of startups will probably not just unicorn, but decacorn, and they’re getting built as we speak,” said Hu. “Cloud providers are still catching up in terms of how to price them, but they do know if you catch them early on, you’re going to ride the wave with them.”</p>

<p>On the flip side, Y Combinator says it can attract more AI startups to apply by offering generous compute resources alongside its investment and guidance. For early-stage AI startups, Hu says one of the most common issues she hears is that startups are compute-restrained. Large enterprises are able to strike multi-year, massive deals with cloud providers for GPU access, but small startups are often left out to dry. She says partnerships like these go a long way, especially when you have a dedicated cluster — that’s particularly important for training AI models.</p>

<p>“For GPU and AI workloads, they’re more like high performance computing workloads in batches. You don’t need the server running all the time, but you need a lot of them in a spiky workload,” said Hu. “So we have a dedicated cluster that YC companies can just use.”</p>

<p>As part of the partnership, Google will also offer YC startups $12,000 in Enhanced Support credits and a free year of Google Workspace Business Plus. YC startups can also connect with Google’s internal AI experts through monthly office hours.</p>


<p>Startup accelerators and venture capital firms are offering GPU clusters more and more these days. Andreessen Horowitz reportedly has <a href="https://www.theinformation.com/articles/andreessen-horowitz-is-building-a-stash-of-more-than-20-000-gpus-to-win-ai-deals?rc=dp0mql" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">a stash of 20,000 GPUs</a> to attract AI startups. Google Cloud and Y Combinator would not reveal the exact number in this deal, but Hu says it’s sufficient for YC’s foundation model companies to train models on.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Oscar, an open-source contributor agent architecture (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://go.googlesource.com/oscar/+/refs/heads/master/README.md</link>
            <guid>41135240</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 01:09:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://go.googlesource.com/oscar/+/refs/heads/master/README.md">https://go.googlesource.com/oscar/+/refs/heads/master/README.md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41135240">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://go.googlesource.com/oscar/+/refs/heads/master/README.md: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>