<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 17:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[There is no fix for Intel's crashing 13th/14th Gen CPUs – damage is permanent (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/26/24206529/intel-13th-14th-gen-crashing-instability-cpu-voltage-q-a</link>
            <guid>41079901</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 16:22:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/26/24206529/intel-13th-14th-gen-crashing-instability-cpu-voltage-q-a">https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/26/24206529/intel-13th-14th-gen-crashing-instability-cpu-voltage-q-a</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41079901">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>On Monday, it initially seemed like the <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/22/24203959/intel-core-13th-14th-gen-cpu-crash-update-patch">beginning of the end for Intel’s desktop CPU instability woes</a> — the company confirmed a patch is coming in mid-August that should address the “root cause” of exposure to elevated voltage. But if your 13th or 14th Gen Intel Core processor is already crashing, that patch apparently won’t fix it. </p><p>Citing unnamed sources,<em> </em><a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/intel-finally-announces-a-solution-for-cpu-crashing-errors-claims-elevated-voltages-are-the-root-cause-fix-coming-by-mid-august"><em>Tom’s Hardware </em>reports</a> that any degradation of the processor is irreversible, and an Intel spokesperson did not deny that when we asked. Intel is “confident” the patch will keep it from happening in the first place. (As another preventative measure, you should update your motherboard BIOS ASAP.) But if your defective CPU has been damaged, your best option is to replace it instead of tweaking BIOS settings to try and alleviate the problems. </p><p>And, Intel confirms, too-high voltages aren’t the only reason some of these chips are failing. Intel spokesperson Thomas Hannaford confirms it’s <em>a</em> primary cause, but the company is still investigating. Intel community manager Lex Hoyos also revealed some instability reports can be <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/intel/comments/1e9mf04/comment/lefz09c/">traced back to an oxidization manufacturing issue</a> that was fixed at an unspecified date last year.</p><p>This raises lots of questions. Will Intel recall these chips? Extend their warranty? Replace them no questions asked? Pause sales <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/24/24205416/amd-zen-5-ryzen-9000-desktop-delay">like AMD just did</a> with its Ryzen 9000? Identify faulty batches with the manufacturing defect?   </p><p>We asked Intel these questions, and I’m not sure you’re going to like the answers. </p><div><p>Why are these still on sale without so much as an extended warranty?</p></div><p>Intel has not halted sales or clawed back any inventory. It will not do a recall, period. The company is not currently commenting on whether or how it might extend its warranty. It would not share estimates with <em>The Verge</em> of how many chips are likely to be irreversibly impacted, and it did not explain why it’s continuing to sell these chips ahead of any fix. </p><p>Intel’s not yet telling us how warranty replacements will work beyond trying customer support again if you’ve previously been rejected. It did not explain how it will contact customers with these chips to warn them about the issue.</p><p>But Intel <em>does</em> tell us it’s “confident” that you don’t need to worry about invisible degradation. If you’re not currently experiencing issues, the patch “will be an effective preventative solution for processors already in service.” (If you don’t know if you’re experiencing issues, Intel currently suggests <a href="https://youtu.be/wkrOYfmXhIc?si=XzCym6UjLcF3_yW2&amp;t=497">the Robeytech test</a>.)</p><p>And, perhaps for the first time, Intel has confirmed just how broad this issue could possibly be. The elevated voltages could potentially affect any 13th or 14th Gen desktop processor that consumes 65W or more power, not just the highest i9-series chips that <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/9/24125036/intel-game-crash-13900k-14900k-fortnite-unreal-engine-investigation">initially seemed to be experiencing the issue</a>.</p><p>Here are the questions we asked Intel and the answers we’ve received by email from Intel’s Hannaford:</p><p><strong>How many chips does&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;estimate are likely to be irreversibly impacted by these issues?</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;Core 13th and 14th Generation desktop processors with 65W or higher base power – including K/KF/KS and 65W non-K variants – could be affected by the elevated voltages issue. However, this does not mean that all processors listed are (or will be) impacted by the elevated voltages issue.</p><p>Intel&nbsp;continues validation to ensure that scenarios of instability reported to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;regarding its Core 13th and 14th Gen desktop processors are addressed.</p><p>For customers who are or have been experiencing instability symptoms on their 13th and/or 14th Gen desktop processors,&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;continues advising them to reach out to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;Customer Support for further assistance. Additionally, if customers have experienced these instability symptoms on their 13th and/or 14th Gen desktop processors but had RMA [return merchandise authorization] requests rejected we ask that they reach out to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;Customer Support for further assistance and remediation.</p><p><strong>Will&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;issue a recall?</strong></p><p>No.</p><p><strong>Will Intel proactively warn buyers of these chips about the warning signs or that this update is required? If so, how will it warn them?</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;targets to release a production microcode update to OEM/ODM customers by mid-August or sooner and will share additional details on the microcode patch at that time.</p><p>Intel&nbsp;is investigating options to easily identify affected processors on end user systems. In the interim, as a general best practice&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;recommends that users adhere to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;Default Settings on their desktop processors, along with ensuring their BIOS is up to date.</p><p><strong>Has&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;halted sales and / or performed any channel inventory recalls while it validates the update?</strong></p><p>No.</p><p><strong>Does&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;anticipate the fix will be effective for chips that have already been in service but are not yet experiencing symptoms (i.e., invisible degradation)? Are those CPUs just living on borrowed time?</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;is confident that the microcode patch will be an effective preventative solution for processors already in service, though validation continues to ensure that scenarios of instability reported to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;regarding its Core 13th/14th Gen desktop processors are addressed.</p><p>Intel&nbsp;is investigating options to easily identify affected or at-risk processors on end user systems.</p><p>It is&nbsp;<em>possible</em>&nbsp;the patch will provide some instability improvements to currently impacted processors; however customers experiencing instability on their 13th or 14th Generation desktop processor-based systems should contact&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;customer support for further assistance.</p><p><strong>Will&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;extend its warranty on these 13th Gen and 14th Gen parts, and for how long?&nbsp;</strong></p><p>[No answer yet.]</p><p><strong>Given how difficult this issue was for&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;to pin down, what&nbsp;proof will customers need to share to obtain an RMA?&nbsp;(How lenient will&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;be?)&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong></p><p>[No answer yet.]</p><p><strong>What will&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;do for 13th Gen buyers after supply of 13th Gen parts runs out? Final shipments were set to end last month,&nbsp;</strong><a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/pc-components/cpus/intel-axes-13th-gen-core-i5-i7-i9-k-series-cpus-lineup-will-be-discontinued-by-may-24th-2024"><strong>I’m reading</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;is committed to making sure all customers who have or are currently experiencing instability symptoms on their 13th and/or 14th Gen desktop processors are supported in the exchange process. This includes working with&nbsp;Intel’s retail and channel customers to ensure end users are taken care of regarding instability symptoms with their&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;Core 13th and/or 14th Gen desktop processors.</p><p><strong>What will&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;do for 14th Gen buyers after supply of 14th Gen parts run out?&nbsp;</strong></p><p>Same as above.</p><p><strong>Will replacement / RMA’d chips ship with the microcode update preapplied beginning in August? Is&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;still shipping replacement chips ahead of that update?</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;will be applying to microcode to 13th/14th Gen desktop processors that are not yet shipped once the production patch is released to OEM/ODM partners (targeting mid-August or sooner). For 13th /14th Gen desktop processors already in service, users will need to apply the patch via BIOS update once available.</p><p><strong>What, if anything, can customers do to slow or stop degradation&nbsp;ahead of the microcode update?</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;recommends that users adhere to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;Default Settings on their desktop processors, along with ensuring their BIOS is up to date. Once the microcode patch is released to&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;partners, we advise users check for the relevant BIOS updates.</p><p><strong>Will&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;share specific manufacturing dates and serial number ranges for the oxidized processors so mission-critical businesses can selectively rip and replace?&nbsp;</strong></p><p>Intel&nbsp;will continue working with its customers on Via Oxidation-related reports and ensure that they are fully supported in the exchange process.</p><div><p><strong>Why does&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;believe the instability issues </strong><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/intel/comments/1e9mf04/comment/lekoj61/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=web3x&amp;utm_name=web3xcss&amp;utm_term=1&amp;utm_content=share_button"><strong>do not affect mobile laptop chips</strong></a><strong>?&nbsp;</strong></p></div><p>Intel&nbsp;is continuing its investigation to ensure that reported instability scenarios on&nbsp;Intel&nbsp;Core 13th/14th Gen processors are properly addressed.</p><p>This includes ongoing analysis to confirm the primary factors preventing 13th / 14th Gen mobile processor exposure to the same instability issue as the 13th/14th Gen desktop processors.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>That’s all we’ve heard from Intel so far, though Hannaford assured us more answers are on the way and that the company is working on remedies. </p><p>Again, if your CPU is already damaged, you need to get Intel to replace it, and if Intel won’t do so, please let us know. In the meanwhile, you’ll want to update your BIOS as soon as possible because your processor could potentially be invisibly damaging itself — and if you know your way around a BIOS, you may want to adjust your motherboard to Intel’s default performance profiles, too.</p><p>Lastly, here is that Robeytech video that Intel is recommending to Redditors to potentially help them identify if their chip has an issue. Intel says it’s looking into other ways to identify that, too. </p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bcachefs, an Introduction/Exploration (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://blog.asleson.org/2024/07/24/bcachefs-an-introduction/exploration/</link>
            <guid>41076190</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 06:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://blog.asleson.org/2024/07/24/bcachefs-an-introduction/exploration/">http://blog.asleson.org/2024/07/24/bcachefs-an-introduction/exploration/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41076190">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main">
    <article>
      
      
      
      
      <hr>
      <ul>
        <li><time>July 24, 2024</time></li>
        <li>
          <a href="http://blog.asleson.org/tags/fedora/">
            <i></i>
            Fedora
          </a>&nbsp;
        </li>
      </ul>
      

      <h2 id="introduction--background-information">Introduction &amp; background information</h2>
<p><em><strong>NOTE: This content is from an internal talk I gave, thus the reason it may read like a presentation</strong></em></p>
<h3 id="so-what-is-bcachefs">So what is bcachefs?</h3>
<p>bcachefs is a next-generation copy-on-write (COW) filesystem (FS) that aims to provide features similar to Btrfs and ZFS, written by Kent Overstreet</p>
<ul>
<li>Copy-on-write (COW), with goal of performance being better than other COW filesystems</li>
<li>Full checksums on everything</li>
<li>Mult-device, replication , RAID, Caching, Compression, Encryption</li>
<li>Sub-volumes, snapshots</li>
<li>Scalable, 50+ TB tested</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="why-the-need-for-another-fs">Why the need for another FS?</h3>
<p>According to Kent<a href="https://www.patreon.com/bcachefs/about?l=en">[1]</a>, paraphrased here</p>
<ul>
<li>ext4, functional but outdated, intimidates developers due to its codebase. Despite its flaws, it
surprisingly functions, with its fsck being its standout feature.</li>
<li>XFS, reliable and robust, follows a traditional update-in-place design, not COW. The developers,
especially Dave Chinner, impress with the code’s rigor, surpassing other filesystems. However,
lacking COW, XFS can’t support some desirable features.</li>
<li>Btrfs[2], envisioned as Linux’s next-gen COW filesystem akin to ZFS, suffered from rushed development,
resulting in numerous design flaws and a sprawling codebase larger than XFS. Its prolonged stabilization process
tarnished its reputation, leading to distrust among users and prompting migrations to other FS.</li>
<li>ZFS, pioneering COW filesystem, won’t be a first class citizen on Linux (copyright).
While commendable, its block-based design diverges from modern extent-based systems due to complexities in
implementing extents with snapshots.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://www.patreon.com/bcachefs/about?l=en">https://www.patreon.com/bcachefs/about?l=en</a></li>
<li>Current Fedora workstation default filesystem</li>
</ol>
<h3 id="why-bcachefs1httpswwwpatreoncombcachefsaboutlen">Why bcachefs<a href="https://www.patreon.com/bcachefs/about?l=en">[1]</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Stability: Key in filesystem development. Building a POSIX filesystem involves tackling a vast array of functionalities, making incremental development challenging. However, bcachefs benefits from bcache’s stable foundation, extensive testing.</li>
<li>Fast: bcachefs excels in speed, with noticeable performance improvements since earlier benchmarks. It prioritizes low tail latency, avoiding extensive delays seen in other filesystems like ext4.</li>
<li>Small: bcachefs boasts a compact codebase, rivaling ext4’s size yet offering btrfs features. Constant refactorings ensure clarity, aiming for longevity by prioritizing developer accessibility and comprehension.</li>
<li>Features: It has, either finished or in progress, features we all need, especially data checksumming, which alone is sufficient reason for a good COW FS.</li>
</ul>
<ol>
<li>Paraphrased <a href="https://www.patreon.com/bcachefs/about?l=en">https://www.patreon.com/bcachefs/about?l=en</a></li>
</ol>
<h3 id="code-size-comparison">Code size comparison</h3>
<h4 id="lines-of-kernel-code-tokei-utility">lines of kernel code (tokei utility)</h4>
<p>Is bcachefs really that small?  It’s actually pretty good, but some features are not fully complete.
</p><figure><img src="http://blog.asleson.org/pictures/code-size-comparison.svg">
</figure>

<h3 id="feature-comparison">Feature Comparison</h3>
<h4 id="fs-residing-directly-on-hardware">(FS residing directly on hardware)</h4>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>FS</th>
<th>RAID</th>
<th>Encryption</th>
<th>Thin provision</th>
<th>De-dupe</th>
<th>Caching</th>
<th>Compression</th>
<th>Snapshots</th>
<th>Subvolumes</th>
<th>Send/Receive</th>
<th>Full checksum</th>
<th>Reflink</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Bcachefs</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>P</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ZFS</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y(sparse volumes)</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>btrfs</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>XFS</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>Y (if newer)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ext3/4</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Most non-COW</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>Varies</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>P</strong> = Planned</p>
<h3 id="feature-comparison-layered">Feature Comparison (layered)</h3>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>FS</th>
<th>RAID</th>
<th>Encryption</th>
<th>Thin provision</th>
<th>De-dupe</th>
<th>Caching</th>
<th>Compression</th>
<th>Snapshots</th>
<th>Subvolumes</th>
<th>Send/Receive</th>
<th>Full checksum</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Bcachefs</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y-native</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>P</td>
<td>Y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ZFS</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y-native</td>
<td>Y(sparse volumes)</td>
<td>?</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>btrfs</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y-native</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>L</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Stratis</td>
<td>P</td>
<td>Y(dm-crypt)</td>
<td>Y(dm-thin)</td>
<td>P(vdo)</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>P(vdo)</td>
<td>Y(dm)</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>N(dm-integrity)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>non-COW using LVM</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y(dm-crypt)</td>
<td>Y(dm-thin)</td>
<td>Y(vdo)</td>
<td>Y</td>
<td>Y(vdo)</td>
<td>Y(LVM)</td>
<td>N</td>
<td>P(blk-archive)</td>
<td>N(dm-integrity)</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>P</strong> = Planned
<strong>L</strong> = layer on LVM/VDO
<strong>?</strong> = Should work layered on VDO, untested</p>
<h3 id="full-checksums">Full checksums</h3>
<ul>
<li>You can detect and optionally correct data before it gets returned to userspace
<ul>
<li>dm-integrity only protects blocks</li>
<li>FS checksum protects 1-2 additional layers depending on stacking</li>
<li>FS checksum doesn’t protect networked FS</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Bit-rot is real, I have personal experience with it, an excerpt from an email (circa 2016) on the subject
<pre tabindex="0"><code>...
My home file server (ECC memory, SATA disks) runs CentOS6 and uses md
for a simple mirrored setup (ext4) with off-site backups run each night
to crashplan for newly created files (they do file versioning).  A while
back I read an article on bit rot and I ran the jpeginfo tool to check
my family photos that go back ~16 years.  I found ~100 images that are
corrupt out of ~50k.  I don't know when or how they got trashed, but
they are forever lost at this point (backups and all versions of backups are corrupt).
I have no idea what other files may be trashed as many of them don't have built in
file level checksums or tools to automate checking.  I would like to scrub
my data once a month, to verify correctness and address any issues that come up.
...
</code></pre></li>
<li>Disclaimer, my personal data is stored on ZFS, 10T mirror with monthly scrubs (ECC memory, enterprise SATA disks)</li>
<li>I would welcome a COW FS which is in kernel tree that has full checksums, error detection and correction, and won’t eat my data</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="general-observations">General observations</h2>
<h3 id="how-helpful-is-help">How helpful is help?</h3>
<h4 id="-help--man-pages">(-help &amp; man pages)</h4>
<ul>
<li>In general, documentation details are a bit lacking
<ul>
<li>Example: What does this all mean?
<ul>
<li>metadata_replicas:               2</li>
<li>data_replicas:                   2</li>
<li>metadata_replicas_required:      1</li>
<li>data_replicas_required:          1</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Much of what is scattered around the internet appears to be incorrect
<ul>
<li>Current understanding in a number of online resources about *<strong>_required</strong>
<ul>
<li>The <strong>_required</strong> versions means sync() won’t return until that many replicas are written; the others are the targets for the rebalance thread.</li>
<li>But actual IRC message from Kent is: <strong>can run in degraded mode if we’re only able to do this many writes</strong> (translation, the FS stays operational in RW mode)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>There are good details in design documentation on implementation</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="what-are-user-space-errors-like">What are user space errors like?</h3>
<ul>
<li>Some could be better, an example FS mount
<pre tabindex="0"><code># bcachefs mount /dev/sdb:/dev/sdc /mnt/bcachefs
ERROR - bcachefs::commands::cmd_mount: Fatal error: Input/output error
</code></pre></li>
<li>If you get something cryptic, check the journal, you may find more information
<pre tabindex="0"><code> kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): mounting version 1.3: rebalance_work opts=metadata_replicas=2,data_replicas
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): recovering from clean shutdown, journal seq 18
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): alloc_read... done
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): stripes_read... done
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): snapshots_read... done
 kernel: bucket 1:0 gen 0 different types of data in same bucket: need_discard, sb
 kernel: while marking sb, exiting
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): Unable to continue, halting
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): bch2_trans_mark_dev_sb(): error EIO
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): bch2_fs_recovery(): error EIO
 kernel: bcachefs (8a4283ce-0388-44ac-99d6-d5849da5ce6a): bch2_fs_start(): error starting filesystem EIO
</code></pre></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="some-use-cases-and-common-questions">Some use cases and common questions</h2>
<h3 id="create-fs-mount-at-boot">Create FS, mount at boot</h3>
<ul>
<li>Single device with FS works with entry in fstab by FS uuid</li>
<li>Multi-device with FS works with entry in fstab by FS uuid with PR I submitted and was merged (thanks Kent!)</li>
<li>There is still an issue where if all the block devices are not present at boot, the mount will fail even though in some cases you can bring the FS up with a subset of the disks in degraded mode, solutions to this are still in progress
<ul>
<li><a href="https://gist.github.com/holmanb/ebf26121194b787afeb713b3d95ce83e#support-multiple-device-degraded-mount-with-systemd">https://gist.github.com/holmanb/ebf26121194b787afeb713b3d95ce83e#support-multiple-device-degraded-mount-with-systemd</a></li>
<li>Investigation on how btrfs accomplishes this would be good</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="mount-option-for-degraded">Mount option for degraded</h3>
<ul>
<li>You can do a standard mount, which won’t mount if your FS is degraded
<ul>
<li><code>mount /dev/sda /mnt</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Mount in degraded mode, but your data is fully intact
<ul>
<li><code>mount -o degraded /dev/sda /mnt</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Mount in very degraded mode, where data is likely missing, and you are trying to recover as much as you can
<ul>
<li><code>mount -o very_degraded /dev/sda /mnt</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="automation">Automation</h3>
<ul>
<li>Currently much of the implementation is available in user space, you can even run bcachefs as FUSE (not tested),
however there currently isn’t a high level API which provides functionality
<ul>
<li>When asked about adding something like this as a rust crate, Kent responded, <strong>“a rust API would be wonderful”</strong></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>The bcachefs command line is a combination of rust and C (lower levels)</li>
<li>IOCTL interface</li>
<li>sysfs, debugfs interfaces</li>
<li>Today, automation would mainly revolve around fork &amp; exec command line tool or sysfs interface</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="sysfs-interface">sysfs interface</h3>
<ul>
<li>Many options can be changed after a FS has been formatted.  These configuration options are available in
sysfs and will be persistently changed in the superblock, see: <code>/sys/fs/bcachefs/UUID/options/</code></li>
<li>Time statistics, tracks latency and frequency of various things:</li>
<li>Other values for
<ul>
<li>Internals/data structure values</li>
<li>Tests, unit and performance of low level btree operations (optionally compiled in)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>From an automation standpoint, it might be easier to use some of these instead of forking &amp; execing the command line to make simple FS changes after it has been created</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="debugfs-interface">debugfs interface</h3>
<p><code>/sys/kernel/debug/bcachefs/&lt;FS UUID&gt;</code></p>
<p>Many things under this directory, I haven’t found complete documentation for them yet, would likely need to examine code.</p>
<h3 id="information-about-a-fs-root-privs-not-needed">Information about a FS (root privs. not needed)</h3>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span>$ bcachefs fs usage /mnt/bcachefs/
</span></span><span><span>Filesystem: 801d8d4e-5fb7-4697-a203-a2f7895f66aa
</span></span><span><span>Size:                 	<span>1975685120</span>
</span></span><span><span>Used:                 	<span>1975685120</span>
</span></span><span><span>Online reserved:           <span>843776</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span>Data type   	Required/total  Durability	Devices
</span></span><span><span>btree:      	1/1         	<span>1</span>         	<span>[</span>sdh<span>]</span>              <span>9437184</span>
</span></span><span><span>user:       	1/1         	<span>1</span>         	<span>[</span>sdh<span>]</span>           <span>1945206784</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>(</span>no label<span>)</span> <span>(</span>device 0<span>)</span>:       	sdh          	rw
</span></span><span><span>                            	data     	buckets	fragmented
</span></span><span><span>  free:                    <span>172490752</span>         <span>658</span>
</span></span><span><span>  sb:                        <span>3149824</span>          <span>13</span>    	<span>258048</span>
</span></span><span><span>  journal:                  <span>16777216</span>          <span>64</span>
</span></span><span><span>  btree:                     <span>9437184</span>          <span>36</span>
</span></span><span><span>  user:                   <span>1945206784</span>        <span>7421</span>    	<span>163840</span>
</span></span><span><span>  cached:                          <span>0</span>           <span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span>  parity:                      	   <span>0</span>           <span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span>  stripe:                      	   <span>0</span>           <span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span>  need_gc_gens:                	   <span>0</span>           <span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span>  need_discard:                    <span>0</span>           <span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span>  capacity:               <span>2147483648</span>        <span>8192</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h3 id="fill-a-fs-100-and-then-enable-compression">Fill a FS 100% and then enable compression</h3>
<ul>
<li>Simple test running as root &amp; unprivileged user with highly compressible data
<ul>
<li>In both cases after enabling compression it worked, 1.8G -&gt; 27M</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Test of filling FS with pure random, no space savings as expected, and no errors generated from background kernel threads</li>
<li>Basic integrity testing detected no errors</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="use-different-physical-sector-sizes">Use different physical sector sizes</h3>
<h4 id="cant-always-do-this-not-allowed-with-lvm--stratis">can’t always do this, not allowed with LVM &amp; Stratis</h4>
<ul>
<li>Tested configuration with 512 &amp; 4096 physical sector size devices.  FS created and mounted with no errors</li>
<li>Filled &amp; verified with no issues</li>
<li>Asked Kent on IRC about mixing physical sector sizes his response
<em><strong>yes we can, we’re COW (by default any ways)</strong></em></li>
</ul>
<h3 id="stack-bcachefs-on-thin-lv-or-vdo">Stack bcachefs on thin LV or vdo</h3>
<h4 id="no-manual-fstrim-support">(no manual fstrim support)</h4>
<ul>
<li>Yes, Important part is to enable discard in bcachefs so that you don’t fill up the pool, the default is not to issue discards
<ul>
<li>I repeatedly open/modified/closed same file, with discard enabled in bcachefs, the LV stayed empty as expected</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>You can’t use fstrim directly (you should be able), bcachefs issues discards
<ul>
<li>Discussion with Kent, he understands that some older devices may have bad implementation of discard, so this should be supported</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>vdo specific notes
<ul>
<li>discard support on vdo has known performance issues</li>
<li>Filling the FS with highly compressible data -&gt; all ok</li>
<li>Filling the FS with random data files -&gt; bcachefs kernel errors and read only FS (expected), no errors from vdo preceded the event (unexpected)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="can-i-use-bcachefs-on-smr--raw-flash">Can I use bcachefs on SMR &amp; raw flash?</h3>
<ul>
<li>Not yet, discussed in the design documents, see them for details</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="raid">RAID</h2>
<h3 id="what-about-raid-01056-etc">What about RAID 0,10,5,6 etc.</h3>
<ul>
<li>bcachefs doesn’t have switches to create some of the common RAID levels, this is a planned addition,  Kent on IRC..
<strong>that will come later with ways of restricting/defining the geometry further</strong></li>
<li>You can specify how many copies of metadata and data are desired</li>
<li>You can specify how many copies of data and metadata that are required
<ul>
<li>required == can run in degraded mode if we’re only able to do this many writes (translation, the FS stays operational in RW mode)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Erasure coding support for RAID5/6 like functionality is experimental</li>
<li><strong>bcachefs with –replicas=N will tolerate N-1 disk failures without loss of data</strong>
<ul>
<li>Max N is limited to 3, so currently you can’t create a bcachefs that will tolerate &gt; 2 disk simultaneous failure.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>You can instruct bcachefs that specific block devices have custom durability, e.g. they’re a hardware RAID backed block device</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="raid0-experiment">RAID0 experiment</h3>
<ul>
<li>RAID0 behavior is default when using multiple disks
<ul>
<li><code>bcachefs format /dev/sdg /dev/sdh</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>If missing a disk you may be able to mount with data loss
<ul>
<li><code>bcachefs mount -o very_degraded /dev/sdg /mnt/bcachefs</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>To ensure you can mount and possibly recover data not on missing disk you need to ensure metadata is on multiple disks
<ul>
<li><code>bcachefs format /dev/sdg /dev/sdh --metadata_replicas=2</code></li>
<li>However, in testing only 3 out of 929 files were available, the rest got EIO when reading as expected.
This is because most of the contents of each file are spread across each of the disks during the write which is expected</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="raid1">RAID1</h3>
<ul>
<li>Two disks, format with bcachefs format /dev/sdg /dev/sdh –replicas=2</li>
<li><code>—replicas=2</code> is same as:  <code>--data_replicas=2 --metadata_replicas=2</code></li>
<li>Tested with, mount, fill, umount, zero 1 of the disks, remounted -o degraded
<ul>
<li>No file loss or corruption</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="raid10-cannot-do">RAID10 (cannot do)</h3>
<ul>
<li>You can’t right now, 4 block devices with —replicas=2 is mentioned on archlinux wiki which is incorrect
<pre tabindex="0"><code># bcachefs format /dev/sde /dev/sdf /dev/sdg /dev/sdh --replicas=2`
bcachefs fs usage /mnt/bcachefs
Data type   	Required/total  Durability	Devices
btree:      	1/2         	2         	[sdg sdh]        	7864320
btree:      	1/2         	2         	[sde sdf]       35127296
user:       	1/2         	2         	[sde sdh]        	2621440
user:       	1/2         	2         	[sdf sdh]       	1572864
user:       	1/2         	2         	[sde sdg]        	1572864
user:       	1/2         	2         	[sdf sdg]        	2621440
user:       	1/2         	2         	[sdg sdh]     3886860288
user:       	1/2         	2         	[sde sdf]     3865051136
</code></pre></li>
<li>We can only tolerate a 1 disk failure in this configuration, which was tested and found true.
In an actual RAID10 you can lose 1 disk in each leg of the mirror.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="raid-56-experimental">RAID 5/6 (experimental)</h3>
<ul>
<li>This is referred to as erasure coding and is listed as  <strong>“DO NOT USE YET”</strong>, experimental in kconfig
<ul>
<li><code>bcachefs format --erasure_code --metadata_replicas=3 –data_replicas=2 /dev/sdf /dev/sdg /dev/sdh</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>data_replicas is configuration knob used by the erasure code</li>
<li>Not available for metadata use</li>
<li>Not compiled in with default fedora kernel module</li>
<li>On disk format has not be formalized</li>
<li>Does not suffer from RAID5/6 <strong>write hole</strong>.  This is accomplished by writing copy to multiple disks and when enough data
to fill a full stripe is present, it then writes the stripe.  Fully protected, but at a cost of more writes, which in my
opinion is good!</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="fs-usage-with-erasure-coding">fs usage with erasure coding</h3>
<div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="bash"><span><span><span># bcachefs fs usage /mnt/ec</span>
</span></span><span><span>Filesystem: 8f8b9a5e-afea-49c7-a245-86e132263bd4
</span></span><span><span>Size:                 <span>53343494144</span>
</span></span><span><span>Used:                  	<span>896942080</span>
</span></span><span><span>Online reserved:               	<span>0</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span>Data type   	Required/total  Durability	Devices
</span></span><span><span>btree:      	1/3         	<span>3</span>         	<span>[</span>sdf sdg sdh<span>]</span>   	<span>15728640</span>
</span></span><span><span>user:       	1/2         	<span>2</span>         	<span>[</span>sdf sdh<span>]</span>         	  <span>524288</span>
</span></span><span><span>user:       	1/2         	<span>2</span>         	<span>[</span>sdf sdg<span>]</span>        	 <span>1458176</span>
</span></span><span><span>user:       	2/3         	<span>3</span>         	<span>[</span>sdf sdg sdh<span>]</span>  	   <span>277348352</span>
</span></span><span><span>parity:     	2/3         	<span>3</span>         	<span>[</span>sdf sdg sdh<span>]</span>  	   <span>138674176</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="misc-information-things-tried">Misc. information, things tried</h2>
<h3 id="why-is-my-free-space--expected">Why is my free space &lt; expected?</h3>
<ul>
<li>~8% of total space reserved for garbage collection, can be configured
<ul>
<li>see <code>--gc_reserve_percent</code></li>
<li>see <code>--gc_reserve_bytes</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Also depends on the number of copies of metadata</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="multipath">multipath</h3>
<ul>
<li>The pull request I created which leverages the udev DB which was subsequently merged makes this work</li>
<li>NVMe native multipath should have always worked</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="block-device-management">Block device management</h3>
<ul>
<li>dynamically add/remove devices to a FS in use</li>
<li>evacuate data from a device, then remove it</li>
<li>correct a degraded FS</li>
<li>Take devices online/offline, mark block devices as failed</li>
<li>The documentation is a bit lacking on the exact order of steps, to do when a device fails, but I got it to work :-)</li>
<li>Current limit of 64 devices in a single FS</li>
<li>resize filesystem on a device (your disk capacity increases)</li>
<li>resize journal on a device</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="error-handling-on-crc-read-error">Error handling on CRC read error</h3>
<ul>
<li>1 copy of file, CRC error on read results in EIO
<ul>
<li>Future work item, add a read flag which says give me what you do have despite CRC errors</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>2 or more copies of file, CRC on error, read other copy, data returned to userspace, does not correct bad copy
<ul>
<li>Correction is a future work item</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="things-not-explored">Things not explored</h3>
<ul>
<li>There are lots of other options and functionality that I didn’t evaluate
<ul>
<li>caching (write through, write back, write around)</li>
<li>no-COW mode</li>
<li>using custom durability settings</li>
<li>quotas</li>
<li>different checksums, compression algorithms</li>
<li>settings e.g. on journaling, targets, garbage collection. data I/O and more</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<h3 id="work-in-progress">Work in progress</h3>
<ul>
<li>bcachefs is not complete</li>
<li>Kent is working very hard to ensure early adopters don’t ever lose data, even when they do some very questionable things</li>
<li>Any assistance/help is appreciated</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="specific-areas-that-could-use-some-help">Specific areas that could use some help</h3>
<ul>
<li>Solution to multi-device FS and correct sequencing at boot which includes the option to mount in degraded mode if acceptable to end user
<ul>
<li>Need a good way to warn/alert a user when a FS is mounted degraded at boot</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Change encrypt password entry to better integrate with systemd, e.g. <code>systemd-ask-password</code></li>
</ul>

    </article>

    


    
        


    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Zulip 9.0: Organized chat for distributed teams (130 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.zulip.com/2024/07/25/zulip-9-0-released/</link>
            <guid>41075934</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 05:14:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.zulip.com/2024/07/25/zulip-9-0-released/">https://blog.zulip.com/2024/07/25/zulip-9-0-released/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41075934">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div> <article><section> <a href="https://blog.zulip.com/tag/major-releases/">Major releases</a>, <a href="https://blog.zulip.com/tag/release-announcements/">Release announcements</a> </section><section> <a href="https://blog.zulip.com/author/tabbott/"> <img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/tabbott.Y0j5haym_1QpB1I.webp" alt="" width="100" height="100" loading="lazy" decoding="async"> </a>  <span> <time datetime="2024-07-25"> Jul 25, 2024</time> <span>•</span> 15 min read</span> </section><section> <p>We’re excited to announce the release of Zulip Server 9.0, containing hundreds
of new features and bug fixes!</p>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/channels-and-topics.CBcwcz3r_Z2f19Cz.webp" alt="" width="996" height="950" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span> <a href="https://zulip.com/">Zulip</a>
is an open-source team chat application designed for seamless remote and hybrid
work. With conversations
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/introduction-to-topics">organized by topic</a>, Zulip is
<a href="https://zulip.com/why-zulip/">ideal</a> for both live and asynchronous
communication. Zulip’s 100% open-source software is available as a
<a href="https://zulip.com/plans/#cloud">cloud service</a> or a
<a href="https://zulip.com/self-hosting/">self-hosted solution</a>, and is used by
thousands of organizations around the world.</p>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/channels-and-topics.CBcwcz3r_Z2f19Cz.webp" alt="" width="996" height="950" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></p>
<p>Zulip Server 9.0 is a major release, with over 5,300 new commits merged across
the project since the 8.0 release in December 2023. Notable new features include
a UI redesign with larger font size and line spacing, major improvements for
composing messages, and much more!</p>
<p>A total of 124 people contributed commits to Zulip since the 8.0 release,
bringing the project to over 1,450 code contributors. Zulip is remarkable for
its number of major contributors, with <a href="https://zulip.com/team">89 people</a>
who’ve contributed 100+ commits.</p>
<p>Huge thanks to everyone who’s
<a href="https://zulip.readthedocs.io/en/latest/overview/contributing.html">contributed</a>
to Zulip over the last several months, whether by writing code and
documentation,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/contact-support#product-feedback">reporting issues</a>,
<a href="https://zulip.readthedocs.io/en/latest/translating/translating.html">translating</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/sponsors/zulip">supporting us financially</a>, participating in
discussions in the
<a href="https://zulip.com/development-community/">Zulip development community</a>, or just
suggesting ideas! We could not do this without the hundreds of people
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/support-zulip-project">giving back</a> to the Zulip
community.</p>
<h2 id="project-highlights">Project highlights</h2>
<p>Today marks a release of the Zulip server and web application. We’d also like to
share news and updates for the project as a whole since the 8.0 release last
December:</p>
<h2 id="apps">Apps</h2>
<p>We’ve been hard at work on Zulip’s next-generation mobile app for Android and
iOS, built with Flutter. Users can look forward to redesigned apps and a
<a href="https://chat.zulip.org/#narrow/stream/2-general/topic/Flutter/near/1582367">faster, smoother experience</a>.</p>
<p>We published a first
<a href="https://chat.zulip.org/#narrow/stream/2-general/topic/Flutter/near/1708728">community beta release</a>
last December, and have made 9 more releases since then,
<a href="https://chat.zulip.org/#narrow/stream/1-announce/topic/mobile.20beta/near/1716421">packed with features</a>.
There are over 1,700 commits in the latest release, and progress has been
accelerating, with another full-time developer and three Google Summer of Code
participants joining our mobile team this summer.</p>
<p>Later this year, we’ll announce a public beta here on the Zulip blog, so that
you can try it out and see the new smoother experience for yourself. In the
months after that, we’ll roll out the new app for everyone as the next version
of the official Zulip mobile apps on both iOS and Android.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, we’ve
<a href="https://github.com/zulip/zulip-mobile/releases">continued updating the existing mobile apps</a>
for key Zulip Server 9.0 features you’ll read about below, as well as fixing
selected bugs.</p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/zulip/zulip-terminal#readme">Zulip Terminal</a> features new
since last December include easy-to-read themes when using a transparent
terminal, improved in-app help, the ability to compose and edit messages in
external editors, and a prompt to avoid accidentally closing — and losing — the
message you are composing.</p>
<h2 id="reviews">Reviews</h2>
<ul>
<li>An in-depth
<a href="https://www.hostingadvice.com/blog/emerging-open-source-team-chat-app-set-to-rival-slack/">review of Zulip</a>
on <a href="https://www.hostingadvice.com/">HostingAdvice.com</a> described it as <em>“an
excellent solution for teams collaborating across different time zones.”</em></li>
<li>Zulip was recognized as a
<a href="https://www.getapp.com/collaboration-software/team-communication/category-leaders/">GetApp 2024 category leader</a>
for team communication. Huge thanks to our users for sharing their feedback
and helping others find us!</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="customer-stories">Customer stories</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>In a <a href="https://zulip.com/case-studies/gut-contact/">new case study</a>, the folks
at <a href="https://gutcontact.de/">GUT contact</a> shared how they use Zulip to manage
1,000 employees spread across 3 countries. They love how easy it’s been to
self-host the software and onboard their team.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Zulip was quite easy to set up, and worked instantly. 1,000 people — no
problem.”</p>
<p>— <span>Erik Dittert, Head of IT at GUT contact</span></p>
</blockquote>
</li>
<li>
<p>In another <a href="https://zulip.com/case-studies/semsee/">new case study</a>, the
InsurTech startup <a href="https://semsee.com/">Semsee</a> shared how Zulip has created
breathing room for focused work and different work schedules for their
distributed team.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>“I don’t like going back to Slack now. It’s just not as efficient a way to
organize communication.”</p>
<p>— <span>James van Lommel, Director of Engineering at
Semsee</span></p>
</blockquote>
<ul>
<li>The Lean Prover community has
<a href="https://leanprover-community.github.io/blog/posts/FLT-announcement/">kicked off</a>
a multi-year collaboration on Zulip to formalize a proof of
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fermat%27s_Last_Theorem">Fermat’s Last Theorem</a>.
We wish them the best of luck!</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>“The project will be run on the
<a href="https://leanprover.zulipchat.com/#narrow/stream/416277-FLT">FLT channel</a> on the
<a href="https://leanprover.zulipchat.com/">Lean Zulip chat</a>, a high-powered research
forum where mathematicians and computer scientists can collaborate in real time,
effortlessly posting code and mathematics using a thread and channel system
which admirably handles the task of enabling many independent conversations to
happen simultaneously.”</p>
<p>— <span>Kevin Buzzard, announcing The Fermat’s Last
Theorem Project</span></p>
</blockquote>
<p>If using Zulip is making a difference for your organization, we’d love to
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/contact-support#product-feedback">hear about it</a>!</p>
<h2 id="mentorship">Mentorship</h2>
<p>Our community is fully committed to helping bring up the next generation of
open-source contributors. 2024 is the ninth consecutive year that Zulip is
participating in <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/">Google Summer of Code</a>.
Our 17 GSoC 2024 participants have contributed to many of the features described
in this post!</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“The mentorship I’ve received here is unparalleled in my life, it’s the best
I’ve ever had.”</p>
<p>— <span>Niloth, Google Summer of Code 2024
participant</span></p>
</blockquote>

<p>We proudly sponsor free <a href="https://zulip.com/plans/">Zulip Cloud Standard hosting</a>
for more than 1,500 <a href="https://zulip.com/for/open-source/">open-source projects</a>,
<a href="https://zulip.com/for/communities/">non-profits</a>,
<a href="https://zulip.com/for/education/">educational institutions</a>, and
<a href="https://zulip.com/for/research/">academic research groups</a>. All eligible
organizations are encouraged to
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/zulip-cloud-billing#apply-for-sponsorship">join this program</a>,
or sign up for the
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/self-hosted-billing#apply-for-community-plan">Community plan</a>
for self-hosted organizations.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“We are a public university that offers free education to 33,000 students across
13 cities in Brazil. We started using Zulip in early 2020, and it works
perfectly for our needs. Zulip’s interface is simple and intuitive.”</p>
<p>— <span>Rafael Cordeiro, head of IT at
</span><a href="https://www.utfpr.edu.br/">UTFPR</a></p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>“As a research consortium spread across 14 locations in Germany, we use Zulip to
communicate with each other in a low-threshold manner, without the overhead of
email. Even with more than 200 users across different institutions, Zulip’s
model of topic-labeled conversations makes it easy for our team members to keep
up-to-date on what’s relevant, and work productively together.”</p>
<p>— <span>Christina Schüttler, IT department Team Lead at
</span><a href="https://www.uk-erlangen.de/en/">University Hospital Erlangen</a></p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="release-highlights">Release highlights</h2>
<p>This section gives an overview of the major features and improvements in Zulip
Server 9.0.</p>
<p>Alongside the major changes, this release contains hundreds of refinements
beyond what can be described here. We believe that getting the little details
right makes a big difference in a product that’s so central to people’s daily
work. To make Zulip
<a href="https://zulip.com/case-studies/rust/#the-language-team-moves-from-discord-to-zulip-its-better-in-all-the-ways-i-care-about">a joy to use</a>,
we relentlessly fine-tune the user experience, and consider it a priority to
investigate and fix even minor bugs.</p>
<h2 id="streams-renamed-to-channels">“Streams” renamed to “channels”</h2>
<p>To better match terminology familiar from other apps, “streams” have been
renamed to “<a href="https://zulip.com/help/introduction-to-channels">channels</a>” across
the app in this release. The functionality remains exactly the same, and
integrations do not need to be updated for this transition.</p>
<h2 id="in-app-feature-announcements">In-app feature announcements</h2>
<p>To make it easier to discover what’s new in Zulip, important product changes are
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/configure-automated-notices#zulip-update-announcements">now announced</a>
via automated messages. These messages are sent to a “Zulip updates” topic in a
channel selected by organization administrators. Users can read the
announcements when it’s convenient, and chat about them in the same topic.</p>
<p>On self-hosted servers, these
<a href="https://zulip.readthedocs.io/en/latest/overview/changelog.html#upgrade-notes-for-9-0">configurable</a>
notices are shipped with the Zulip server version that includes the new feature.</p>
<h2 id="improved-reading-experience">Improved reading experience</h2>
<ul>
<li>To make reading more comfortable, Zulip has been redesigned with a larger font
size and line spacing. Because personal preferences vary, the previous design
remains available via the <a href="https://zulip.com/help/font-size">compact mode</a>
setting, and we plan to offer flexible controls for font size and line spacing
in the next major release.</li>
<li>For a more focused reading experience, you can now hide the
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/left-sidebar">left</a> and
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/user-list">right</a> sidebars even in a full-size window.
When the left sidebar is hidden,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/keyboard-shortcuts#navigation">keyboard navigation</a>
lets you jump to the next unread topic or to your
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/configure-home-view">home view</a>. The
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/user-list">right sidebar</a> has been redesigned to
highlight users in the current channel or direct-message conversation.</li>
<li>Messages and topic names now load much faster when you open the web or desktop
app.</li>
</ul>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/focus-mode.CW8MPwgV_MlQm8.webp" alt="" width="2120" height="760" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></p>
<h2 id="improved-experience-for-composing-messages">Improved experience for composing messages</h2>
<ul>
<li>The compose box has been redesigned, with a cleaner, more modern look.</li>
<li>When you start composing, the most recently edited draft for the conversation
you are composing to now automatically appears in the compose box. You can
always
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/view-and-edit-your-message-drafts#save-a-draft-and-start-a-new-message">save a draft</a>
for later and start a new message.</li>
<li>When you paste content into the compose box, Zulip will now do its best to
preserve the formatting, including links, bulleted lists, bold, italics, and
more. If you don’t need the formatting, you can undo it with <code>Ctrl+Z</code>, or
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/keyboard-shortcuts#the-basics">paste as plain text</a>.</li>
<li>Pasted channel and topic
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/link-to-a-message-or-conversation#get-a-link-to-a-specific-topic">link URLs</a>
are now automatically converted into
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/link-to-a-message-or-conversation#link-to-a-channel-or-topic-within-zulip">nicely formatted</a>
links.</li>
<li>To <a href="https://zulip.com/help/quote-and-reply">quote and reply</a> to part of a
message, you can now select the part that you want to quote.</li>
<li>You can now scroll down in all typeahead menus to see more matches for what
you’ve typed so far.</li>
</ul>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/compose-box.6NRbWRE1_Z28NwSv.webp" alt="" width="1814" height="944" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></p>
<h2 id="more-natural-navigation">More natural navigation</h2>
<ul>
<li>For clarity and consistency, three key message views that show multiple
conversations at once are now labeled
“<a href="https://zulip.com/help/combined-feed">Combined feed</a>” (previously “All
messages”), “<a href="https://zulip.com/help/channel-feed">Channel feed</a>”, and
“<a href="https://zulip.com/help/direct-messages#access-all-dms">Direct message feed</a>”.</li>
<li>To make it easier to read your messages topic-by-topic, channel links in the
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/left-sidebar">left sidebar</a> now take you directly to
the top topic in the channel. You can
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/channel-feed#configure-where-channel-links-in-the-left-sidebar-go">configure</a>
them to go to the channel feed instead (previously the only option).</li>
<li>When you send a message to a conversation that you’re not viewing, Zulip now
jumps you to that conversation, unless
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/mastering-the-compose-box#automatically-go-to-conversation-where-you-sent-a-message">configured</a>
otherwise.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="new-and-improved-ways-to-find-messages">New and improved ways to find messages</h2>
<ul>
<li>The main <a href="https://zulip.com/help/search-for-messages">search</a> has been
redesigned with pills for search filters, making it easier to use.
<span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/search-pills.gJyJpot5_GPHpu.webp" alt="" width="1012" height="59" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></li>
<li>You can use the new
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/emoji-reactions#view-your-messages-with-reactions">Reactions view</a>
to see how others have responded to your messages with emoji reactions. You
can also
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/search-for-messages#search-by-message-status">search</a>
all messages with reactions.</li>
<li>You can now search for messages
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/follow-a-topic#search-for-messages-in-followed-topics">in topics you follow</a>,
or see a feed of all messages (or just unread messages) in your followed
topics.</li>
<li>You can now
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/direct-messages#find-a-direct-message-conversation">filter</a>
direct message conversations in the left sidebar to show conversations that
include a specific person.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="easier-user-onboarding">Easier user onboarding</h2>
<p>Zulip’s onboarding experience has been redesigned to introduce core Zulip
concepts when they first become relevant.</p>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/inbox-intro-modal.FV_4wDKS_Z1JlzHx.webp" alt="" width="1496" height="1080" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>One-time modals now introduce the <a href="https://zulip.com/help/inbox">Inbox</a> and
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/recent-conversations">Recent conversations</a> views.
Permanently dismissable banners explain complex situations, such as composing
a message
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/mastering-the-compose-box#composing-to-a-different-conversation">while viewing a different conversation</a>,
when they come up. <span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/inbox-intro-modal.FV_4wDKS_Z1JlzHx.webp" alt="" width="1496" height="1080" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span> <span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/onboarding-banner.Cf42Bcvo_Z1MTT6q.webp" alt="" width="1306" height="170" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></li>
<li>To introduce <a href="https://zulip.com/help/star-a-message">starred messages</a>,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/view-your-mentions">your mentions</a>, and other views,
we added descriptions in the bar at the top, and to the message area when the
view is empty.</li>
<li>Introductory messages have been rewritten to better explain how
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/introduction-to-topics">conversations labeled with topics</a>
work in Zulip, including how to
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/replying-to-messages">reply</a> to an existing thread,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/introduction-to-topics#how-to-start-a-new-topic">start</a>
a new conversation, and
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/move-content-to-another-topic">move messages</a> if they
are out of place. To make intro messages easier to find, they are now starred
and marked as unread for new users.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="design-and-usability-improvements">Design and usability improvements</h2>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/user-card.B8MNmu0b_wNnBe.webp" alt="" width="691" height="1089" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></p>
<ul>
<li>All the menus have been restyled, with a cleaner look, better icons, and
improved screen reader accessibility. Also, you can now
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/dark-theme">switch themes</a> directly from your personal
menu. <span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/user-card.B8MNmu0b_wNnBe.webp" alt="" width="691" height="1089" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></li>
<li>You can now configure how
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/allow-image-link-previews">previews</a> of animated
images show the animation (always, when you hover over them, or never).</li>
<li>To better show key information,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/desktop-notifications">desktop</a> and
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/mobile-notifications">mobile</a> notifications now
abbreviate quoted content.</li>
<li>The message
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/view-a-messages-edit-history">edit history</a> view has
been redesigned for visual consistency and ease of use.</li>
<li>If you’d prefer not to see
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/typing-notifications">notifications when others type</a>,
you can now disable them.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="keyboard-shortcuts">Keyboard shortcuts</h2>
<ul>
<li>A new <code>Alt+P</code> keyboard shortcut lets you toggle between edit mode and
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/preview-your-message-before-sending">preview mode</a>
when composing or editing a message.</li>
<li>A new <code>Shift+V</code> keyboard shortcut offers quick access to
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/read-receipts">read receipts</a>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="improved-user-management">Improved user management</h2>
<ul>
<li>
<p>A new combined user settings panel lets you manage
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/manage-a-user">users</a>,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/deactivate-or-reactivate-a-user">deactivated users</a>,
and <a href="https://zulip.com/help/invite-new-users">invitations</a> in one place. You
can now
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/roles-and-permissions#view-users-by-role">filter</a> the
list of users in your organization by role.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Profile pictures are now shown alongside user names in settings, making it
easier to identify people at a glance. You can click on a name to open the
user’s <a href="https://zulip.com/help/user-cards">card</a>.</p>
<p><span><img src="https://blog.zulip.com/_astro/user-settings.BoX-g8Jg_Z9fg9B.webp" alt="" width="2296" height="770" loading="lazy" decoding="async"></span></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You now have a lot of flexibility for configuring direct message permissions
in your organization, with
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/restrict-direct-messages#restrict-direct-messages">new settings</a>
for who can <strong>authorize</strong> and <strong>start</strong> direct message conversations. These
settings are designed so that users can always respond to a direct message
they’ve received.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You can now mark a custom profile field as
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/custom-profile-fields#make-a-custom-profile-field-required">required</a>,
to prompt everyone to fill it out.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You can
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/restrict-name-and-email-changes#require-unique-names">require</a>
users to choose unique names in your organization.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>When inviting users, you can now
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/invite-new-users#send-email-invitations">decide</a>
whether to receive a direct message when the invited user joins your
organization. An updated design makes the UI for
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/invite-new-users">inviting</a> new users easier to use.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>You can now link to a user’s
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/view-someones-profile">profile</a>, to share it with
someone else.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="improved-channel-administration">Improved channel administration</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://zulip.com/help/create-a-channel">Creating a channel</a> is now a
smoother experience:
<ul>
<li>Adding subscribers is now a separate step from configuring channel settings.
Advanced settings are collapsed by default.</li>
<li>When you create a channel, you are now taken directly there if you are a
subscriber.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Channel settings now show additional details, including when the channel was
created.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="integrations">Integrations</h2>
<ul>
<li>There is now a convenient UI for
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/generate-integration-url">configuring custom event filters</a>
for an integration. Documentation for over 60 integrations has been updated
with simplified instructions.</li>
<li>There are new integrations for
<a href="https://zulip.com/integrations/doc/patreon">Patreon</a> and
<a href="https://zulip.com/integrations/doc/githubsponsors">GitHub Sponsors</a>, and the
<a href="https://zulip.com/integrations/doc/github">GitHub</a> and
<a href="https://zulip.com/integrations/doc/grafana">Grafana</a> integrations have been
improved.</li>
<li>We made extensive additions to Zulip’s API documentation, including
<a href="https://zulip.com/api/get-events#events-by-type">handy navigation</a> for
<a href="https://zulip.com/api/real-time-events">real-time push</a> event formats,
articles on important concepts like thumbnailing, and new documentation for
about a dozen previously documented API endpoints.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="server">Server</h2>
<ul>
<li>This release adds support for Ubuntu 24.04, and drops support for Ubuntu
20.04.</li>
<li>The Zulip server now serves thumbnails of uploaded images for previews in the
message feed, greatly reducing bandwidth usage for most Zulip installations.
Images now load much faster for users in all Zulip apps.</li>
<li>The Zulip server has always scaled well, but this release comes with several
further efficiency improvements, which will make a big difference for
organizations with thousands of user accounts.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="internationalization">Internationalization</h2>
<p>Our community translators have been hard at work keeping up with the product as
it evolves. This release features translations that cover the majority of
non-error strings in 25 languages, including Gujarati for the first time.</p>
<h2 id="upgrading">Upgrading</h2>
<p>We
<a href="https://zulip.readthedocs.io/en/stable/overview/release-lifecycle.html#compatibility-and-upgrading">highly recommend</a>
upgrading to Zulip Server 9.0 to take advantage of the hundreds of improvements
in this release and future security updates. We work hard to ensure that
upgrades are smooth; you can upgrade by following the straightforward
<a href="https://zulip.readthedocs.io/en/stable/production/upgrade-or-modify.html#upgrading-to-a-release">upgrade instructions</a>.
The
<a href="https://zulip.readthedocs.io/en/stable/changelog.html#upgrade-notes">upgrade notes section of the changelog</a>
details changes you’ll want to understand before upgrading.</p>
<p>Commercial support for server upgrades is available for installations that
purchase a Business or Enterprise <a href="https://zulip.com/plans#self-hosted">plan</a>.
For community support, everyone is welcome to drop by the
<a href="https://zulip.com/development-community/">Zulip development community</a>.</p>
<p>Zulip Cloud is always up to date with the latest Zulip improvements.</p>
<h2 id="product-roadmap">Product roadmap</h2>
<p>We’re continuing to focus on improving the design of the Zulip web app, and
shipping next-generation mobile apps for Android and iOS.</p>
<p>We use project boards to publicly track goals for major
<a href="https://github.com/orgs/zulip/projects/9/views/12">server</a> and
<a href="https://github.com/orgs/zulip/projects/5/views/4">mobile</a> releases. These
boards are updated on an ongoing basis as priorities evolve, and many community
improvements integrated into Zulip are never specifically tracked as release
goals.</p>
<h2 id="release-schedule">Release schedule</h2>
<p>This release is coming out about seven months after the
<a href="https://blog.zulip.com/2024/07/15/zulip-8-0-released/">Zulip Server 8.0 release</a>
last December. We are targeting a shorter interval for the next major release,
which is expected in late 2024.</p>

<p>If you appreciate Zulip, please recommend it to someone you know, for work or
any other collaborative endeavor. If they say that Zulip won’t work for them,
<a href="https://zulip.com/help/contact-support#product-feedback">let us know why</a>! You
can email <a href="mailto:feedback@zulip.com">feedback@zulip.com</a>, or post in the
<a href="https://chat.zulip.org/#narrow/stream/137-feedback">#feedback</a> channel in the
<a href="https://zulip.com/development-community/">Zulip development community</a>.
Feedback from current and potential users is a vital part of how we design and
prioritize improvements to Zulip.</p>
<p>Thanks again to the amazing global Zulip development community for making this
possible!</p>
<p>— Tim Abbott, Zulip project leader</p>
<p>What follows is a summary of the commits contributed to Zulip during the 9.0
release cycle.</p>
<pre tabindex="0" data-language="plaintext"><code><span><span>$ ./zulip/tools/total-contributions 8.0 9.0</span></span>
<span><span>616	Anders Kaseorg</span></span>
<span><span>458	Alex Vandiver</span></span>
<span><span>408	Chris Bobbe</span></span>
<span><span>400	Greg Price</span></span>
<span><span>388	Aman Agrawal</span></span>
<span><span>359	Lauryn Menard</span></span>
<span><span>313	Evy Kassirer</span></span>
<span><span>266	Karl Stolley</span></span>
<span><span>209	Sahil Batra</span></span>
<span><span>195	Tim Abbott</span></span>
<span><span>169	Prakhar Pratyush</span></span>
<span><span>166	Alya Abbott</span></span>
<span><span>165	Sayam Samal</span></span>
<span><span>117	Shubham Padia</span></span>
<span><span>111	Mateusz Mandera</span></span>
<span><span>104	Nehal Sharma</span></span>
<span><span>83	Varun Singh</span></span>
<span><span>61	afeefuddin</span></span>
<span><span>57	Kunal Sharma</span></span>
<span><span>56	Niloth P</span></span>
<span><span>47	Rohan Gudimetla</span></span>
<span><span>46	Kenneth Rodrigues</span></span>
<span><span>42	neiljp (Neil Pilgrim)</span></span>
<span><span>35	Rajesh Malviya</span></span>
<span><span>32	Sujal Shah</span></span>
<span><span>26	Kislay Verma</span></span>
<span><span>24	PieterCK</span></span>
<span><span>24	Tanmay Kumar</span></span>
<span><span>24	Sayed Mahmood Sayedi</span></span>
<span><span>24	Shu Chen</span></span>
<span><span>20	David Rosa</span></span>
<span><span>20	Pratik Chanda</span></span>
<span><span>19	Sanchit Sharma</span></span>
<span><span>19	Khader M Khudair</span></span>
<span><span>19	Zixuan James Li</span></span>
<span><span>17	Adnan Shabbir Husain</span></span>
<span><span>15	Sashank Ravipati</span></span>
<span><span>12	Lalit Kumar Singh</span></span>
<span><span>12	Nimish Medatwal</span></span>
<span><span>11	Shashank Singh</span></span>
<span><span>10	Mahhheshh</span></span>
<span><span>9	Bedo Khaled</span></span>
<span><span>9	CIC4DA</span></span>
<span><span>7	Aditya Kumar Kasaudhan</span></span>
<span><span>7	Pratik Solanki</span></span>
<span><span>7	ecxtacy</span></span>
<span><span>7	vighneshbhat9945</span></span>
<span><span>6	Robert Dyer</span></span>
<span><span>6	Temidayo32</span></span>
<span><span>6	codewithnick</span></span>
<span><span>5	Joydeep Bhattacharjee</span></span>
<span><span>5	sayyedarib</span></span>
<span><span>4	Chris Chua</span></span>
<span><span>3	Aditya Bajaj</span></span>
<span><span>3	John Lu</span></span>
<span><span>3	Rein Zustand (rht)</span></span>
<span><span>3	Sohaib-Ahmed21</span></span>
<span><span>3	Ujjawal Modi</span></span>
<span><span>3	swayam0322</span></span>
<span><span>3	Sagnik Mandal</span></span>
<span><span>2	ColeBurch</span></span>
<span><span>2	Dhruv Goyal</span></span>
<span><span>2	Eklavya Sharma</span></span>
<span><span>2	Pedro Almeida</span></span>
<span><span>2	Rinwaoluwa</span></span>
<span><span>2	abelaba</span></span>
<span><span>2	saisumith770</span></span>
<span><span>2	jrijul1201</span></span>
<span><span>2	neruyzo</span></span>
<span><span>1	Aditya Chaudhary</span></span>
<span><span>1	Afonso Azaruja</span></span>
<span><span>1	AfonsoOrmonde</span></span>
<span><span>1	Ajay Singh</span></span>
<span><span>1	Akarsh Jain</span></span>
<span><span>1	Akash Kumar Singh</span></span>
<span><span>1	Andrew</span></span>
<span><span>1	Angelica Ferlin</span></span>
<span><span>1	Anuja Patil</span></span>
<span><span>1	Artur Szcześniak</span></span>
<span><span>1	Charlie Marsh</span></span>
<span><span>1	Eeshan Garg</span></span>
<span><span>1	Emil</span></span>
<span><span>1	Evgenii</span></span>
<span><span>1	Gaurav Pandey</span></span>
<span><span>1	Gyan Dev</span></span>
<span><span>1	Isabela Pereira</span></span>
<span><span>1	Jason</span></span>
<span><span>1	Jerry Yang</span></span>
<span><span>1	Jose Corte</span></span>
<span><span>1	Joy Chen</span></span>
<span><span>1	Laura Hausmann</span></span>
<span><span>1	Niklas Fiekas</span></span>
<span><span>1	Olivier FAURE</span></span>
<span><span>1	Pietro Albini</span></span>
<span><span>1	Prathamesh Kurve</span></span>
<span><span>1	Riken Shah</span></span>
<span><span>1	Roshan Jagadish</span></span>
<span><span>1	Ryan Crisanti</span></span>
<span><span>1	Sahil Singh</span></span>
<span><span>1	Sayyed Arib Hussain</span></span>
<span><span>1	Sharif Naas</span></span>
<span><span>1	Tomas Fonseca</span></span>
<span><span>1	Tudor Stefan Pagu</span></span>
<span><span>1	Varun-Kolanu</span></span>
<span><span>1	Vector73</span></span>
<span><span>1	Vidhi Agrawal</span></span>
<span><span>1	ayush amawate</span></span>
<span><span>1	cherish2003</span></span>
<span><span>1	iks1</span></span>
<span><span>1	joaoafonso07</span></span>
<span><span>1	kota-karthik</span></span>
<span><span>1	luska44</span></span>
<span><span>1	mk0904</span></span>
<span><span>1	opmkumar</span></span>
<span><span>1	qx24680</span></span>
<span><span>1	somudas</span></span>
<span><span>1	Mehul-Kumar-27</span></span>
<span><span>1	Misha Brukman</span></span>
<span><span>1	enesonus</span></span>
<span><span>1	rsashank</span></span>
<span><span>1	LY</span></span>
<span><span>1	Sushmey</span></span>
<span><span>1	sreecharan7</span></span>
<span><span>1	Sean T. Allen</span></span>
<span><span>Commit range 8.0..9.0 corresponds to 2023-12-15 to 2024-07-25</span></span>
<span><span>4288 commits from zulip/zulip: 8.0..9.0</span></span>
<span><span>798 commits from zulip/zulip-flutter: 81d8b8ccab90..c17dd0efd192</span></span>
<span><span>137 commits from zulip/zulip-mobile: 38ca48a7b801..2217c858e207</span></span>
<span><span>91 commits from zulip/zulip-terminal: 585722a206e8..743db7d8d0ef</span></span>
<span><span>19 commits from zulip/zulip-desktop: 47cdd5fa8b3b..92260b0f97b5</span></span>
<span><span>12 commits from zulip/docker-zulip: 8e716c245f80..ef3a379351cf</span></span>
<span><span>11 commits from zulip/python-zulip-api: ad9b0e62a49d..e9d8ef3b272c</span></span>
<span><span>9 commits from zulip/zulipbot: d0bee679bf3c..3655e1f31e69</span></span>
<span><span>4 commits from zulip/github-actions-zulip: b62d5a0e48a4..e4c8f27c732b</span></span>
<span><span>2 commits from zulip/zulint: cd3b1e0586b0..a070f3a349bc</span></span>
<span><span>Excluded 0 commits authored by bots.</span></span>
<span><span>5371 total commits by 124 contributors between 8.0 and 9.0.</span></span>
<span><span></span></span></code></pre> </section></article> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Swiss Town Banned Billboards. Zurich, Bern May Soon Follow (453 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-07-26/zurich-bern-consider-billboard-bans-after-vernier-outlaws-visual-pollution</link>
            <guid>41075766</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 04:26:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-07-26/zurich-bern-consider-billboard-bans-after-vernier-outlaws-visual-pollution">https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-07-26/zurich-bern-consider-billboard-bans-after-vernier-outlaws-visual-pollution</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41075766">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
    <section>
        <h3>Why did this happen?</h3>
        <p>Please make sure your browser supports JavaScript and cookies and that you are not
            blocking them from loading.
            For more information you can review our <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Terms of
                Service</a> and <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/notices/tos">Cookie Policy</a>.</p>
    </section>
    <section>
        <h3>Need Help?</h3>
        <p>For inquiries related to this message please <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/feedback">contact
            our support team</a> and provide the reference ID below.</p>
        <p>Block reference ID:</p>
    </section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Startup Finance for Founders – Part I, Accounting (2016) (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rein.pk/startup-finance-for-founders-part-i-accounting</link>
            <guid>41074002</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 22:20:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rein.pk/startup-finance-for-founders-part-i-accounting">https://rein.pk/startup-finance-for-founders-part-i-accounting</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41074002">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <p>When we started&nbsp;<a href="https://segment.com/">Segment</a>, we knew nothing about business finance. My background was in aerospace engineering, and my co-founders came from computer science and design. Beyond the hilariously overcomplicated spreadsheet we used to manage grocery bills as roommates, we&nbsp;<strong>really</strong>&nbsp;had no experience in finance when we started the company.</p><p>In the past 2 years Segment has grown from 4 to 60 people, signed up thousands of customers, and raised $44m over a few rounds of financing. Out of necessity we’ve learned the basics of accounting, invoicing &amp; contracts, billing periods, bank account structures, strategic finance and growth models.</p><p>But it’s been hard to piece together. Bits and pieces from accountants, lawyers, our CFO and reading a random book or two off Amazon that looked promising. Although startups have developed a culture of sharing learnings, finance generally remains pretty hush hush. Notable exceptions are&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/everpix/Everpix-Intelligence">Everpix’s eye-opening post-mortem</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://baremetrics.com/open">Baremetric’s Open Startups</a>, <a href="https://medium.com/mattermark-daily/mattermark-has-raised-2m-in-our-second-seed-round-e93b20dc59b0">Mattermark’s complex fundraising tale</a> and oodles of general advice about fundraising. It’s a tricky topic.</p><p>This article is part of a two-part series outlining what I’ve learned about startup finance, from a practical perspective. I’ve tried to include diagrams, charts, and redacted docs where helpful.</p><p>Part I covers some of our learnings in&nbsp;<strong>accounting</strong>: accurately recording the past. Accounting is rigorously pedantic to record&nbsp;<em>exactly</em>&nbsp;what’s happened. Then, in Part II I’ll talk about some adventures in&nbsp;<strong>strategic finance</strong>. Strategic finance is exactly the&nbsp;<em>opposite</em>&nbsp;of accounting. It looks to the future, attempts to guesstimate the fuzzy unknowns, and searches for ways to mitigate risk and increase growth.</p><ul><li><p><a>Part I: Accounting — Bank Accounts, Credit Cards, Invoices &amp; Contracts</a></p></li><li><p><a>Part II: Strategic Finance — CFOs, Annual Prepayment, Venture Debt &amp; Shadow Budgets</a></p></li></ul><h2 id="accounting">Accounting</h2><p>I learned the basics of accounting from “<a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1HDLRa6vKpclO1JtxbGB5NeAYWf8cf1UMGy22o8OZZq4/edit">Accounting for Developers</a>” and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Accounting-Made-Simple-Explained-Pages-ebook/dp/B004JHYTDE/">this little book</a>, not to actually&nbsp;<em>do</em>&nbsp;the accounting for ourselves, but to understand what our bookkeeper was taking care of for us. As we grew, problems came up that&nbsp;<em>weren’t</em>&nbsp;covered there, like structuring bank accounts, dealing with lack of credit history, and how contracts and invoicing actually work.</p><h2 id="bank-account-structure">Bank Account Structure</h2><p>When we were just getting started, we set up a company bank account like any normal person. We opened a&nbsp;<em>checking</em>&nbsp;account. Done!</p><p>But then we raised a new round of financing (very exciting), and started to build the team. With $2m in the bank and a payroll to hit, we started to get nervous about that $2m being so easy to access.</p><p>Our customer base was growing, and we were giving our bank account number to receive ACH payments from customers… the&nbsp;<em>same</em>&nbsp;bank account that held the entire livelihood of the company in cash! According to warnings from our peers on the ycfounders forum, it’s reasonably common for leaked bank account numbers to get hit with fraudulent withdrawals.</p><p>After we raised our Series A and added another $15m to the account, our simplistic checking account structure made us even less comfortable. We needed to be able to spend money easily, but we wanted the majority of the balance set aside securely.</p><p>This is when our CFO put in place a new bank account structure.</p><figure><img src="https://assets.contents.io/asset_isndqCI1.png"></figure><p>First, since our new $15m+ balance was way above FDIC insurance limits (the government insures up to $0.25m per entity, per account type, per bank), cash backed by the bank was no longer the safest asset. We moved most of our cash to a money market account invested purely in US treasury bills, which are considered a bit more secure in case the bank collapses or places a temporary hold on funds during a bank run. You may think this is unlikely, but&nbsp;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Federal_Deposit_Insurance_Corporation#2008.E2.80.932010_Financial_crisis">140 banks failed in the aftermath of the 2008 financial crisis</a>, and Greece just had a bank run in July. We wanted to be safe.</p><p>Second, we created a&nbsp;<em>receivables</em>&nbsp;account that can&nbsp;<em>only accept deposits.</em>&nbsp;The bank simply rejects attempted debits to the account. We hand out the&nbsp;<em>receivables</em>&nbsp;account number to customers with abandon, because it only exists as an endpoint for customer payments. It also makes it easy for accounting to see an isolated list of customer payments.</p><p>Third, we created a&nbsp;<em>payables</em>&nbsp;account that we keep more private. We maintain a small balance in this account that comfortably covers daily expenses.</p><p>Fourth, we asked our bank to set up an automatic “sweep”. At the end of every day it automatically transfers everything from&nbsp;<em>receivables</em>&nbsp;to the&nbsp;<em>treasury bills</em>&nbsp;account, and refills&nbsp;<em>payables</em>.</p><p>This account structure simplified our cash management, so that we spend less time running around making internal transfers. Plus, it gives us better security and reduces financial risk. It’s an easy way to sleep better at night.</p><h2 id="credit-cards">Credit Cards</h2><p>Many founders I’ve talked to have struggled with banks giving their startups low credit limits. We’ve also been stonewalled, but hopefully this story gives you some negotiating tips. Initially each founder just had a simple debit card, because that’s what automatically came with our checking account. Wonderful! Then we hit a problem: there are limitations to debit cards (e.g. you can’t rent cars).</p><p>So, we switched from debit to credit cards to solve the problem. But alas, credit limits for startups are downright draconian. For example, Silicon Valley Bank credit card requires you to pay the entire credit limit in cash, which they hold on deposit, and then they still charge interest if you’re late on a payment. More than once we had late fees when autopay didn’t work.</p><p>We switched to Bank of America after that, but were only allowed a laughably low credit limit:</p><pre data-language="text"><code>—February 2014—
BoA: What credit limit are you looking for?
Me: We’ll need at least $20k for our monthly operating expenses.
BoA: Ok, I have a few questions. What was your revenue last year?
Me: Around $40k.
BoA: Got it, what do you expect your revenue to be this year?
Me: Over $2m.
BoA: Uh huh... [suppressed laughter]… ok, um, I’m going to
approve you for a credit limit of $5,000 per month.
Me: [hahaha, what am i supposed to do with that? pay it off
four times a month?]
</code></pre><p>Every six months or so we had the same predictable conversation with a BoA risk analyst, inching up our credit limit. Ultimately I found we could get more reasonable limits by steering the conversation away from revenue, where high growth startups sound incredibly strange, and focusing instead on our cash balance, which was inflated by fundraising. The line we resorted to (with narrowly suppressed laughter at the absurdity of it) was “We could transfer in a couple million in cash, if it would help?” BoA is not used to dealing with snarky, frustrated startup founders, and the line worked: we got significantly higher credit limits. We were fortunate in being well-funded, and this was a useful moment to flaunt it.</p><p>Eventually, Bank of America wasn’t able to keep up with our credit limit needs (when we needed to jump from $75k/mo to $200k/mo). And worryingly for me personally, in a disaster scenario I was personally liable for the card balance in lieu of the company. So, we’ve switched back to SVB to increase our credit limit (which they’ll hold on deposit, sigh).</p><h2 id="contracts-and-invoicing">Contracts and Invoicing</h2><p>Two years ago we had no idea how selling to other businesses worked at a operational level. None of us had ever done it before, or even worked at a company that had done it before. We started by accepting payments through Stripe, which was nice and simple. But as our customers grew, so too did the size of payments and the need for customized terms of service.</p><p>We learned that for software contracts above $20k per year, most companies didn’t expect to put it on a credit card. They expected to be invoiced once, with signed terms of service reviewed by their legal team. So when we started closing our first “business tier” contracts in Fall 2013, we expanded our accepted payment methods beyond Stripe to include paper contracts and invoices.</p><p>If you haven’t seen this before, here’s the basics of how it works:</p><p>Contracts are usually structured as a Master Services Agreement (MSA) with one or more Order Forms. The master services agreement covers the contractual agreement about liability, confidentiality, payment and termination. The order form is meant to be an easily readable description of what’s being sold and paid in what timeframe, to whom. Here’s an anonymized order form from Segment:</p><figure><img src="https://assets.contents.io/asset_22Spawtq.png"></figure><p>The master services agreement is designed to allow future orders at the same company (e.g. additional teams or departments) to be executed as quick signatures on a new order form, without another legal review process. This makes it easy for a customer to expand their account, no muss no fuss.</p><p>We’ve found that the liability terms of the master services agreement are the most hotly contested. No one wants to be on the line if things go south. If you’re selling these kinds of contracts, you’ll likely need to purchase general business liability insurance (and we have extra insurance for data security). From what we’ve seen, insurance for several million in liability seems to start around $10-20k per year. Then, in the contract you hold the line on your maximum liability as the amount you have insured!</p><p>Invoicing was new to us back then as well. Here’s an example invoice, which simply gets sent to the financial contact listed on the order form.This article covers some of the common practices we’ve learned in startup accounting. The next article will cover “strategic finance,” the forward-looking, predictive part of finance in a startup. It should be posted here in a week or two.</p><figure><img src="https://assets.contents.io/asset_fvUH1WKr.png"></figure><p>If you’re looking for a great way to do bookkeeping, check out <a href="https://pilot.com/">Pilot</a>. A number of companies I’ve invested in have used them and found it incredibly helpful and easy.</p><p>This article covers some of the common practices we’ve learned in startup accounting. The next article will cover “strategic finance,” the forward-looking, predictive part of finance in a startup.</p><ul><li><p><a>Part I: Accounting — Bank Accounts, Credit Cards, Invoices &amp; Contracts</a></p></li><li><p><a>Part II: Strategic Finance — CFOs, Annual Prepayment, Venture Debt &amp; Shadow Budgets</a></p></li></ul>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[U.S. Department of Defense – Detecting Agile BS [pdf] (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://media.defense.gov/2018/Oct/09/2002049591/-1/-1/0/DIB_DETECTING_AGILE_BS_2018.10.05.PDF</link>
            <guid>41073688</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 21:40:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://media.defense.gov/2018/Oct/09/2002049591/-1/-1/0/DIB_DETECTING_AGILE_BS_2018.10.05.PDF">https://media.defense.gov/2018/Oct/09/2002049591/-1/-1/0/DIB_DETECTING_AGILE_BS_2018.10.05.PDF</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41073688">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Clone of Deluxe Paint II Written in Python (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter</link>
            <guid>41073264</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 20:53:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter">https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41073264">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">PyDPainter</h2><a id="user-content-pydpainter" aria-label="Permalink: PyDPainter" href="#pydpainter"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A usable pixel art program written in Python</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/blob/master/pydpainter-screenshot.png"><img src="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/raw/master/pydpainter-screenshot.png" alt="screenshot"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">About</h2><a id="user-content-about" aria-label="Permalink: About" href="#about"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">PyDPainter, pronounced "Pied Painter" (like Pied Piper), is an attempt to create a usable pixel art program in Python using PyGame.
The original inspiration came from the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amiga" rel="nofollow">Commodore Amiga</a>
version of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Deluxe_Paint" rel="nofollow"><em>Deluxe Paint</em></a> released by Electronic Arts in 1985.
Back then, <em>Deluxe Paint</em> helped define the user interface of a paint program with tool bars, menus, and the
novel use of left and right mouse buttons for painting and erasing. After pixel art gave way to photo-realism and
high-resolution 24 bit color, <em>Deluxe Paint</em> was largely forgotten for artistic work -- left behind
in the ever-progressing march of technology.</p>
<p dir="auto">Recently, with a resurgence of all things "retro," low-resolution pixel art and limited color palettes
have become popular once again. Many tools to deal with this medium are either too complicated
or too crude. This project is an attempt to bring back an old but reliable tool and
enhance it with some features to help it better coexist in the modern world.</p>
<p dir="auto">Latest Release (with Windows EXE): <a href="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/releases/latest">https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/releases/latest</a></p>
<p dir="auto">YouTube video: <a href="https://youtu.be/GGfsSvbrb4o" rel="nofollow">Quick PyDPainter Demo</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Ko-fi donation page:
<a href="https://ko-fi.com/mriale" rel="nofollow">https://ko-fi.com/mriale</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Facebook group: <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/583338860398152/?ref=share" rel="nofollow">PyDPainter</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Mastodon: <a href="https://mastodon.social/@PyDPainter" rel="nofollow">@PyDPainter@mastodon.social</a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/wiki/RoadMap">RoadMap</a> for current progress.</p>
<p dir="auto">Documentation: <a href="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/blob/master/docs/TOC.md">Table of Contents</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>PyDPainter Copyright (C) 2019-2024 Mark Riale</strong><br>
This program is licensed under the GPLv3 or later. See <a href="https://github.com/mriale/PyDPainter/blob/master/LICENSE">LICENSE</a> file for more details.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Switzerland mandates government agencies use open-source software (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.tomshardware.com/software/switzerland-mandates-government-agencies-use-open-source-software</link>
            <guid>41072795</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 20:05:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/software/switzerland-mandates-government-agencies-use-open-source-software">https://www.tomshardware.com/software/switzerland-mandates-government-agencies-use-open-source-software</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41072795">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article-body">
<p>Switzerland has recently enacted a law requiring its government to use open-source software (OSS) and disclose the source code of any software developed by or for the public sector. According to <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.zdnet.com/article/switzerland-now-requires-all-government-software-to-be-open-source/?s=31" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.zdnet.com/article/switzerland-now-requires-all-government-software-to-be-open-source/?s=31" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none">ZDNet</a>, this “public body, public code” approach makes government operations more transparent while increasing <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/security" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/security">security</a> and efficiency. Such a move would likely fail in the U.S. but is becoming increasingly common throughout Europe.</p><p>According to Switzerland’s new “Federal Law on the Use of Electronic Means for the Fulfillment of Government Tasks” (EMBAG), government agencies must use open-source software throughout the public sector.&nbsp;</p><p>It’s not an entirely new move for Switzerland. In 2011, the Swiss Federal Supreme Court published its court application, Open Justitia, using an OSS license. It was unpopular with legal software company Weblaw, and more than a decade of political and legal battles followed.</p><p>The new law allows the codifies allowing Switzerland to release its software under OSS licenses. Not just that; it requires the source code be released that way “unless the rights of third parties or security-related reasons would exclude or restrict this.”&nbsp;</p><p>In addition to mandating the OSS code, EMBAG also requires Swiss government agencies to release non-personal and non-security-sensitive government data to the public. Calling this Open Government Data, this aspect of the new law contributes to a dual “open by default” approach that should allow for easier reuse of software and data while also making governance more transparent.</p><p>Other nations throughout Europe have made similar moves. France’s version of the U.S. FBI, known as the National Gendarmerie, uses Linux on most PCs. Schleswig-Holstein, one of Germany’s 16 states, recently migrated 30,000 computers from <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/microsoft" data-auto-tag-linker="true" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.tomshardware.com/tag/microsoft">Microsoft</a> products to Linux and LibreOffice.&nbsp;</p><p>The European Union has also worked for years to help OSS become more secure through the Free and Open Source Software Auditing (FOSSA) project. At the same time, there could be some cause for concern about the future of OSS in Europe — there are concerns the European Commission might cut funding for an essential source of financing for OSS projects.</p><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-VHzDKP52cwzLBL6YEhpXCD"><section><p>Get Tom's Hardware's best news and in-depth reviews, straight to your inbox.</p></section></div><p>In the U.S., however, there’s much less support for OSS. The U.S. government does offer some support for open-source, but it’s much more constrained. For example, the Federal Source Code Policy requires government agencies to release at least 20% of their new custom-developed code as OSS. Also, the General Services Administration (GSA) requires its organizations to account for and publish any of their open-source code.</p><p>The critical difference, though, is that no laws in the U.S. mandate the use of open-source software like Switzerland’s. If Switzerland’s new openness works well, it could be a model for further change throughout the rest of Europe and the United States.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Applied Machine Learning for Tabular Data (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aml4td.org/</link>
            <guid>41072616</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 19:48:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aml4td.org/">https://aml4td.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41072616">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section id="quarto-document-content">
<h2>Preface</h2>
<p>Welcome! This is a work in progress. We want to create a practical guide to developing quality predictive models from tabular data. We’ll publish materials here as we create them and welcome community contributions in the form of discussions, suggestions, and edits.</p>
<p>We also want these materials to be reusable and open. The sources are in the source <a href="https://github.com/aml4td/website">GitHub repository</a> with a Creative Commons license attached (see below).</p>
<p>Our intention is to write these materials and, when we feel we’re done, pick a publishing partner to produce a print version.</p>
<p>The book takes a holistic view of the predictive modeling process and focuses on a few areas that are usually left out of similar works. For example, the effectiveness of the model can be driven by how the predictors are represented. Because of this, we tightly couple feature engineering methods with machine learning models. Also, quite a lot of work happens after we have determined our best model and created the final fit. These post-modeling activities are an important part of the model development process and will be described in detail.</p>
<p>We deliberately avoid using the term “artificial intelligence.” Eugen Rochko’s (<code>@Gargron@mastodon.social</code>) comment on <a href="https://mastodon.social/@Gargron/111554885513300997">Mastodon</a> does a good job of summarizing our reservations regarding the term:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s hard not to say “AI” when everybody else does too, but technically calling it AI is buying into the marketing. There is no intelligence there, and it’s not going to become sentient. It’s just statistics, and the danger they pose is primarily through the false sense of skill or fitness for purpose that people ascribe to them.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>To cite this website, we suggest:</p>
<div data-layout-align="center">
<pre><code>@online{aml4td,
  author = {Kuhn, M and Johnson, K},
  title = {{Applied Machine Learning for Tabular Data}},
  year = {2023},
  url = { https://aml4td.org},
  urldate = {2024-05-06}
}</code></pre>
</div>
<section id="license">
<h2 data-anchor-id="license">License</h2>
<p xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#">
This work is licensed under <a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/?ref=chooser-v1" target="_blank" rel="license noopener noreferrer">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0<img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/cc.svg?ref=chooser-v1"><img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/by.svg?ref=chooser-v1"><img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/nc.svg?ref=chooser-v1"><img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/sa.svg?ref=chooser-v1"></a>
</p>
<p>This license requires that reusers give credit to the creator. It allows reusers to distribute, remix, adapt, and build upon the material in any medium or format, for noncommercial purposes only. If others modify or adapt the material, they must license the modified material under identical terms.</p>
<ul>
<li>BY: Credit must be given to you, the creator.</li>
<li>NC: Only noncommercial use of your work is permitted. Noncommercial means not primarily intended for or directed towards commercial advantage or monetary compensation.</li>
<li>SA: Adaptations must be shared under the same terms.</li>
</ul>
<p>Our goal is to have an open book where people can reuse and reference the materials but can’t just put their names on them and resell them (without our permission).</p>
</section>
<section id="intended-audience">
<h2 data-anchor-id="intended-audience">Intended Audience</h2>
<p>Our intended audience includes data analysts of many types: statisticians, data scientists, professors and instructors of machine learning courses, laboratory scientists, and anyone else who desires to understand how to create a model for prediction. We don’t expect readers to be experts in these methods or the math behind them. Instead, our approach throughout this work is applied. That is, we want readers to use this material to build intuition about the predictive modeling process. What are good and bad ideas for the modeling process? What pitfalls should we look out for? How can we be confident that the model will be predictive for new samples? What are advantages and disadvantages of different types of models? These are just some of the questions that this work will address.</p>
<p>Some background in modeling and statistics will be extremely useful. Having seen or used basic regression models is good, and an understanding of basic statistical concepts such as variance, correlation, populations, samples, etc., is needed. There will also be some mathematical notation, so you’ll need to be able to grasp these abstractions. But we will keep this to those parts where it is absolutely necessary. There are a few more statistically sophisticated sections for some of the more advanced topics.</p>
<p>If you would like a more theoretical treatment of machine learning models, then we recommend <span data-cites="HastieEtAl2017">Hastie, Tibshirani, and Friedman (<a href="#ref-HastieEtAl2017" role="doc-biblioref">2017</a>)</span>. Other books for gaining a more in-depth understanding of machine learning are <span data-cites="bishop2006pattern">Bishop and Nasrabadi (<a href="#ref-bishop2006pattern" role="doc-biblioref">2006</a>)</span>, <span data-cites="arnold2019computational">Arnold, Kane, and Lewis (<a href="#ref-arnold2019computational" role="doc-biblioref">2019</a>)</span> and, for more of a deep learning focus, <span data-cites="goodfellow2016deep">Goodfellow, Bengio, and Courville (<a href="#ref-goodfellow2016deep" role="doc-biblioref">2016</a>)</span> and/or <span data-cites="udl2023">Prince (<a href="#ref-udl2023" role="doc-biblioref">2023</a>)</span>.</p>
</section>
<section id="is-there-code">
<h2 data-anchor-id="is-there-code">Is there code?</h2>
<p>We definitely want to decouple the content of this work from specific software. <a href="http://appliedpredictivemodeling.com/">One of our other books</a> on modeling had computing sections. Many people found these sections to be a useful resource at the time of the book’s publication. However, code can quickly become outdated in today’s computational environment. In addition, this information takes up a lot of page space that would be better used for other topics.</p>
<p>We will create <em>computing supplements</em> to go along with the materials. Since we use R’s tidymodels framework for calculations, the supplement currently in-progress is:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://tidymodels.aml4td.org/"><code>tidymodels.aml4td.org</code></a></li>
</ul>
<p>If you are interested in working on a python/scikit-learn supplement, please <a href="https://github.com//aml4td/website/issues">file an issue</a></p>
</section>
<section id="are-there-exercises">
<h2 data-anchor-id="are-there-exercises">Are there exercises?</h2>
<p>Many readers found the Exercise sections of <em>Applied Predictive Modeling</em> to be helpful for solidifying the concepts presented in each chapter. The current set can be found at <a href="https://exercises.aml4td.org/"><code>exercises.aml4td.org</code></a></p>
</section>
<section id="how-can-i-ask-questions">
<h2 data-anchor-id="how-can-i-ask-questions">How can I ask questions?</h2>
<p>If you have questions about the content, it is probably best to ask on a public forum, like <a href="https://stats.stackexchange.com/">cross-validated</a>. You’ll most likely get a faster answer there if you take the time to ask the questions in the best way possible.</p>
<p>If you want a direct answer from us, you should follow what I call <a href="https://yihui.org/en/2017/08/so-gh-email/"><em>Yihui’s Rule</em></a>: add an issue to GitHub (labeled as “Discussion”) first. It may take some time for us to get back to you.</p>
<p>If you think there is a bug, please <a href="https://github.com//aml4td/website/issues">file an issue</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="can-i-contribute">
<h2 data-anchor-id="can-i-contribute">Can I contribute?</h2>
<p>There is a <a href="https://aml4td.org/chapters/contributing.html">contributing page</a> with details on how to get up and running to compile the materials (there are a lot of software dependencies) and suggestions on how to help.</p>
<p>If you just want to fix a typo, you can make a pull request to alter the appropriate <code>.qmd</code> file.</p>
<p>Please feel free to improve the quality of this content by submitting <strong>pull requests</strong>. A merged PR will make you appear in the contributor list. It will, however, be considered a donation of your work to this project. You are still bound by the conditions of the license, meaning that you are <strong>not considered an author, copyright holder, or owner</strong> of the content once it has been merged in.</p>
</section>
<section id="computing-notes">
<h2 data-anchor-id="computing-notes">Computing Notes</h2>
<p><a href="https://quarto.org/">Quarto</a> was used to compile and render the materials</p>
<div data-layout-align="center">
<pre><code>Quarto 1.4.521
[✓] Checking versions of quarto binary dependencies...
      Pandoc version 3.1.9: OK
      Dart Sass version 1.69.5: OK
      Deno version 1.37.2: OK
[✓] Checking versions of quarto dependencies......OK
[✓] Checking Quarto installation......OK
      Version: 1.4.521
[✓] Checking tools....................OK
      TinyTeX: (external install)
      Chromium: (not installed)
[✓] Checking LaTeX....................OK
      Using: TinyTex
      Version: 2023
[✓] Checking basic markdown render....OK
[✓] Checking Python 3 installation....OK
      Version: 3.11.7
      Jupyter: 5.7.1
      Kernels: python3
[✓] Checking Jupyter engine render....OK
[✓] Checking R installation...........OK
      Version: 4.3.2
      LibPaths:
      knitr: 1.46
      rmarkdown: 2.25
[✓] Checking Knitr engine render......OK</code></pre>
</div>
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/R_(programming_language)">R version 4.3.2 (2023-10-31)</a> was used for the majority of the computations. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Torch_(machine_learning)">torch</a> 2.0.1 was also used. The versions of the primary R modeling and visualization packages used here are:</p>
<div data-layout-align="center">
<table>
<colgroup>
<col>
<col>
<col>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><code>aorsf</code> (0.1.4)</td>
<td><code>applicable</code> (0.1.1)</td>
<td><code>aspline</code> (0.2.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>baguette</code> (1.0.2)</td>
<td><code>bestNormalize</code> (1.9.1)</td>
<td><code>bibtex</code> (0.5.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>bonsai</code> (0.2.1)</td>
<td><code>broom</code> (1.0.5)</td>
<td><code>brulee</code> (0.3.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>C50</code> (0.1.8)</td>
<td><code>Cubist</code> (0.4.2.1)</td>
<td><code>DALEXtra</code> (2.3.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>dbarts</code> (0.9-28)</td>
<td><code>ddalpha</code> (1.3.15)</td>
<td><code>desirability2</code> (0.0.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>dials</code> (1.2.1)</td>
<td><code>dimRed</code> (0.2.6)</td>
<td><code>discrim</code> (1.0.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>doMC</code> (1.3.8)</td>
<td><code>dplyr</code> (1.1.4)</td>
<td><code>e1071</code> (1.7-14)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>earth</code> (5.3.3)</td>
<td><code>embed</code> (1.1.4)</td>
<td><code>fastICA</code> (1.2-4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>finetune</code> (1.2.0)</td>
<td><code>GA</code> (3.2.4)</td>
<td><code>gganimate</code> (1.0.9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>ggforce</code> (0.4.2)</td>
<td><code>ggiraph</code> (0.8.9)</td>
<td><code>ggplot2</code> (3.5.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>glmnet</code> (4.1-8)</td>
<td><code>gt</code> (0.10.1)</td>
<td><code>hardhat</code> (1.3.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>ipred</code> (0.9-14)</td>
<td><code>irlba</code> (2.3.5.1)</td>
<td><code>kernlab</code> (0.9-32)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>kknn</code> (1.3.1)</td>
<td><code>klaR</code> (1.7-3)</td>
<td><code>lightgbm</code> (4.3.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>mda</code> (0.5-4)</td>
<td><code>mgcv</code> (1.9-1)</td>
<td><code>mixOmics</code> (6.25.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>modeldata</code> (1.3.0)</td>
<td><code>modeldatatoo</code> (0.3.0)</td>
<td><code>pamr</code> (1.56.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>parsnip</code> (1.2.1)</td>
<td><code>partykit</code> (1.2-20)</td>
<td><code>patchwork</code> (1.2.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>plsmod</code> (1.0.0)</td>
<td><code>probably</code> (1.0.3)</td>
<td><code>pROC</code> (1.18.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>purrr</code> (1.0.2)</td>
<td><code>ragg</code> (1.3.1)</td>
<td><code>ranger</code> (0.16.0)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>recipes</code> (1.0.10)</td>
<td><code>rpart</code> (4.1.23)</td>
<td><code>rsample</code> (1.2.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>RSpectra</code> (0.16-1)</td>
<td><code>rstudioapi</code> (0.16.0)</td>
<td><code>rules</code> (1.0.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>shinylive</code> (0.1.1)</td>
<td><code>sparsediscrim</code> (0.3.0)</td>
<td><code>sparseLDA</code> (0.1-9)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>spatialsample</code> (0.5.1)</td>
<td><code>splines2</code> (0.5.1)</td>
<td><code>stacks</code> (1.0.4)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>stopwords</code> (2.3)</td>
<td><code>textrecipes</code> (1.0.6.9000)</td>
<td><code>themis</code> (1.0.2)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>tidymodels</code> (1.2.0)</td>
<td><code>tidyposterior</code> (1.0.1)</td>
<td><code>tidyr</code> (1.3.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>torch</code> (0.12.0)</td>
<td><code>tune</code> (1.2.1)</td>
<td><code>usethis</code> (2.2.3)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>uwot</code> (0.2.2)</td>
<td><code>VBsparsePCA</code> (0.1.0)</td>
<td><code>viridis</code> (0.6.5)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>workflows</code> (1.1.4)</td>
<td><code>workflowsets</code> (1.1.0)</td>
<td><code>xgboost</code> (1.7.7.1)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code>xrf</code> (0.2.2)</td>
<td><code>yardstick</code> (1.3.1)</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</div>
</section>
<section id="chapter-references">
<h2 data-anchor-id="chapter-references">Chapter References</h2>


<div id="refs" data-entry-spacing="0" role="list">
<p>
Arnold, T, M Kane, and B Lewis. 2019. <em>A Computational Approach to Statistical Learning</em>. Chapman; Hall/CRC.
</p>
<p>
Bishop, C M, and N M Nasrabadi. 2006. <em><span>Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning</span></em>. Vol. 4. 4. Springer.
</p>
<p>
Goodfellow, I, Y Bengio, and A Courville. 2016. <em><a href="https://www.deeplearningbook.org/">Deep Learning</a></em>. MIT press.
</p>
<p>
Hastie, T, R Tibshirani, and J Friedman. 2017. <em><span>The Elements of Statistical Learning: Data Mining, Inference and Prediction</span></em>. Springer.
</p>
<div id="ref-udl2023" role="listitem"><p>
Prince, S. 2023. <em><a href="https://udlbook.github.io/udlbook/">Understanding Deep Learning</a></em>. MIT press.
</p></div>
</div>
</section>
</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI crawlers need to be more respectful (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://about.readthedocs.com/blog/2024/07/ai-crawlers-abuse/</link>
            <guid>41072549</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 19:39:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://about.readthedocs.com/blog/2024/07/ai-crawlers-abuse/">https://about.readthedocs.com/blog/2024/07/ai-crawlers-abuse/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41072549">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p>In the last few months, we have noticed an increase in abusive site crawling,
mainly from AI products and services. These products are recklessly crawling
many sites across the web, and we've already had to block several sources of abusive traffic.
It feels like a new AI gold rush,
and in their haste,
some of these crawlers are behaving in a way that harms the sites they depend on.</p>
<p>At Read the Docs,
we host documentation for many projects and are generally bot friendly,
but the behavior of AI crawlers is currently causing us problems.
We have noticed AI crawlers aggressively pulling content, seemingly without basic
checks against abuse.
Bots repeatedly download large files hundreds of times daily,
partially from bugs in their crawlers,
with traffic coming from many IP addresses without rate or bandwidth limiting.</p>
<p>AI crawlers are acting in a way that is not respectful to the sites they are crawling,
and that is going to cause a backlash against AI crawlers in general.
As a community-supported site without a large budget,
AI crawlers have cost us a significant amount of money in bandwidth charges,
and caused us to spend a large amount of time dealing with abuse.</p>
<h2 id="ai-crawler-abuse">AI crawler abuse</h2>
<p>We have been seeing a number of bad crawlers over the past few months,
but here are a couple illustrative examples of the abuse we're seeing:</p>
<h3>73 TB in May 2024 from one crawler</h3>
<p><strong>One crawler downloaded 73 TB of zipped HTML files in May 2024, with almost 10 TB in a single day</strong>. This cost us over $5,000 in bandwidth charges, and we had to block the crawler. We emailed this company, reporting a bug in their crawler, and we're working with them on reimbursing us for the costs.</p>
<p><img alt="AI crawler abuse, May 2024" src="https://about.readthedocs.com/images/posts/bandwidth-may-2024.png"></p>
<p>This was a bug in their crawler that was causing it to download the same files over and over again.
There was no bandwidth limiting in place,
or support for Etags and Last-Modified headers which would have allowed the crawler to only download files that had changed.
We have reported this issue to them,
and hopefully the issue will be fixed.</p>
<p>We do have a CDN for these files,
but this request was for an old URL that had an old redirect in place.
This redirect went to an old dashboard download URL,
where we don't have CDN caching in place for security reasons around serving other dynamic content.
We are planning to fix this redirect to point to the cached URL.</p>
<details>
<summary>Example web requests</summary>

<pre>
-&gt; curl -IL "https://media.readthedocs.org/htmlzip/chainer/v1.24.0/_modules/chainer/testing/_modules/chainer/_modules/cupy/indexing/_modules/chainer/initializers/normal.html"
HTTP/2 302
date: Thu, 25 Jul 2024 16:24:18 GMT
content-type: text/html
content-length: 138
location: https://buildmedia.readthedocs.org/media/htmlzip/chainer/v1.24.0/_modules/chainer/testing/_modules/chainer/_modules/cupy/indexing/_modules/chainer/initializers/normal.html
x-backend: web-i-0af0e99066a6e05c0
access-control-allow-origin: *
x-served: Nginx
cf-cache-status: DYNAMIC
server: cloudflare
cf-ray: 8a8d7fd81d060943-SEA

HTTP/2 302
date: Thu, 25 Jul 2024 16:24:18 GMT
content-type: text/html
content-length: 138
location: https://readthedocs.org/projects/chainer/downloads/htmlzip/v1.24.0/
x-backend: web-i-092bc168f09ac4a16
cf-cache-status: HIT
age: 537
expires: Thu, 25 Jul 2024 20:24:18 GMT
cache-control: public, max-age=14400
server: cloudflare
cf-ray: 8a8d7fda9837c87c-SEA

HTTP/2 200
date: Thu, 25 Jul 2024 16:24:18 GMT
content-type: application/zip
content-length: 5888860
content-disposition: filename=docs-chainer-org-en-v1.24.0.zip
x-amz-id-2: +DjI2tMbUou9XNK5+G53Gyhah4lhBwAgnRiqBh9vsR3KzqxajSTC4B+eIQBY+pi+ZR6McRQngSI=
x-amz-request-id: Z502YT87WEMM3ZY9
last-modified: Thu, 11 Feb 2021 09:12:59 GMT
etag: "c8cb418f5a8ff2e376fc5f7b7564e445"
x-amz-meta-mtime: 1495712654.422637991
accept-ranges: bytes
x-served: Nginx-Proxito-Sendfile
x-backend: web-i-01ce033e08bb601ef
referrer-policy: strict-origin-when-cross-origin
x-frame-options: DENY
x-content-type-options: nosniff
content-security-policy: object-src 'none'; frame-ancestors 'none'
cf-cache-status: DYNAMIC
server: cloudflare
cf-ray: 8a8d7fdbbf787565-SEA

</pre>

As you can see, this file was last modified in 2021.
However, crawlers didn't have this basic check and instead repeatedly downloaded files like these hundreds of times each.

</details>

<h3>10 TB in June 2024 from another</h3>
<p>In June 2024, <strong>someone used Facebook's content downloader to download 10 TB</strong> of data, mostly Zipped HTML and PDF files. We tried to email Facebook about it with the <a href="http://www.facebook.com/externalhit_uatext.php">contact information listed in the bot's user agent</a>, but the email bounced.</p>
<p><img alt="AI Crawler abuse, June 2024" src="https://about.readthedocs.com/images/posts/bandwidth-june-2024.png"></p>
<p>We think this was someone using Facebook's content downloader to download all of our files, but we aren't really sure.
It could also be Meta crawling sites with their latest AI project,
but the user agent is not clear.</p>
<h2 id="actions-taken">Actions taken</h2>
<p>We have IP-based rate limiting in place for many of our endpoints,
however these crawlers are coming from a large number of IP addresses,
so our rate limiting is not effective.</p>
<p>These crawlers are using real user agents that identify them,
which is a good thing.
However, we can't simply rate limit all user agents to our platform because many real users use the same browsers with the same user agent.
(CDN providers: if you're reading this, there's an opportunity here!)</p>
<p>We have taken a few actions to try to mitigate this abuse:</p>
<ul>
<li>We have temporarily blocked all traffic from bots <a href="https://radar.cloudflare.com/traffic/verified-bots">Cloudflare identifies as AI Crawlers</a>, while we figure out how to deal with this.</li>
<li>We have started monitoring our bandwidth usage more closely and are working on more aggressive rate limiting rules.</li>
<li>We will reconfigure our CDN to better cache these files, reducing the load on our origin servers.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="outcomes">Outcomes</h2>
<p>Given that our Community site is only for hosting open source projects,
AWS and Cloudflare do give us sponsored plans,
but we only have a limited number of credits each year.
The additional bandwidth costs AI crawlers are currently causing will likely mean we will run out of AWS credits early.</p>
<p><strong>By blocking these crawlers,
bandwidth for our downloaded files has decreased by 75% (~800GB/day to ~200GB/day).</strong>
If all this traffic hit our origin servers,
it would cost around $50/day, or $1,500/month,
along with the increased load on our servers.</p>
<p>Normal traffic gets cached by our CDN,
and doesn't cost us anything for bandwidth.
But because many of these files are not downloaded often (and they're large),
the cache is usually expired and the requests hit our origin servers directly,
causing substantial bandwidth charges.
Zipped documentation was designed for offline consumption by users, not for crawlers.</p>
<h2 id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>
<p>We are asking all AI companies to be more respectful of the sites they are crawling.
They are risking many sites blocking them for abuse,
irrespective of the other copyright and moral issues that are at play in the industry.</p>
<p>As a major host of open source documentation,
we'd love to work with these companies on a deal to crawl our site respectfully.
We could build an integration that would alert them to content changes,
and download the files that have changed.
However, none of these companies have reached out to us,
except in response to abuse reports.</p>
<p>We also ask that they implement basic checks in their crawlers for all sites.
A good example is the <a href="https://docs.scrapy.org/en/latest/topics/downloader-middleware.html#scrapy.extensions.httpcache.RFC2616Policy">RFC2616Policy downloader from Scrapy</a>,
which implement many of these policies.</p>
<p>If these companies wish to be good actors in the space,
they need to start acting like it,
instead of burning bridges with folks in the community.</p>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Jacek Karpińśki, the computer genius the communists couldn't stand (2017) (288 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://culture.pl/en/article/jacek-karpinski-the-computer-genius-the-communists-couldnt-stand</link>
            <guid>41072026</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 18:50:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://culture.pl/en/article/jacek-karpinski-the-computer-genius-the-communists-couldnt-stand">https://culture.pl/en/article/jacek-karpinski-the-computer-genius-the-communists-couldnt-stand</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41072026">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://culture.pl/en/article/jacek-karpinski-the-computer-genius-the-communists-couldnt-stand: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Secure Boot is broken on 200 models from 5 big device makers (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/07/secure-boot-is-completely-compromised-on-200-models-from-5-big-device-makers/</link>
            <guid>41071708</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 18:21:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/07/secure-boot-is-completely-compromised-on-200-models-from-5-big-device-makers/">https://arstechnica.com/security/2024/07/secure-boot-is-completely-compromised-on-200-models-from-5-big-device-makers/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41071708">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
                                    
<figure>
  <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2020/10/rootkit-800x533.jpg" alt="Secure Boot is completely broken on 200+ models from 5 big device makers">
      <figcaption><p>sasha85ru | Getty Imates</p></figcaption>  </figure>

  




<!-- cache hit 58:single/related:e9440a0a1361baaf57ed2854a9a45ef6 --><!-- empty -->
<p>In 2012, an industry-wide coalition of hardware and software makers adopted <a href="https://uefi.org/press-release/UEFI_Forum_Releases_UEFI_2.3.1_Specification_Update_and_Schedules_July_3_2012">Secure Boot</a> to protect against a long-looming security threat. The threat was the specter of malware that could infect the BIOS, the firmware that loaded the operating system each time a computer booted up. From there, it could remain immune to detection and removal and could load even before the OS and security apps did.</p>
<p>The threat of such BIOS-dwelling malware was largely theoretical and fueled in large part by the creation of <a href="https://blog.csdn.net/icelord/article/details/1604884">ICLord Bioskit</a> by a Chinese researcher in 2007. ICLord was a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rootkit">rootkit</a>, a class of malware that gains and maintains stealthy root access by subverting key protections built into the operating system. The proof of concept demonstrated that such BIOS rootkits weren't only feasible; they were also powerful. In 2011, the threat became a reality with the discovery of <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2011/09/14/bios_rootkit_discovered/">Mebromi</a>, the first-known BIOS rootkit to be used in the wild.</p>
<p>Keenly <a href="https://uefi.org/sites/default/files/resources/UEFI_Plugfest_2011Q4_P5_Insyde.pdf">aware of Mebromi</a> and its potential for a devastating new class of attack, the Secure Boot architects hashed out a complex new way to shore up security in the pre-boot environment. Built into UEFI—the Unified Extensible Firmware Interface that would become the successor to BIOS—Secure Boot used <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public-key_cryptography">public-key cryptography</a> to block the loading of any code that wasn’t signed with a pre-approved digital signature. To this day, key players in security—among them&nbsp;<a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/surface/do-more-with-surface/what-is-secure-boot" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Microsoft</a>&nbsp;and the&nbsp;<a href="https://media.defense.gov/2020/Sep/15/2002497594/-1/-1/0/CTR-UEFI-SECURE-BOOT-CUSTOMIZATION-20200915.PDF/CTR-UEFI-SECURE-BOOT-CUSTOMIZATION-20200915.PDF" target="_blank" rel="noopener">US National Security Agency</a>—regard Secure Boot as an important, if not essential, foundation of trust in securing devices in some of the most critical environments, including in industrial control and enterprise networks.</p>
<h2>An unlimited Secure Boot bypass</h2>
<p>On Thursday, researchers from security firm Binarly revealed that Secure Boot is completely compromised on more than 200 device models sold by Acer, Dell, Gigabyte, Intel, and Supermicro. The cause: a cryptographic key underpinning Secure Boot on those models that was compromised in 2022. In a public GitHub repository committed in December of that year, someone working for multiple US-based device manufacturers published what’s known as a platform key, the cryptographic key that forms the root-of-trust anchor between the hardware device and the firmware that runs on it. The repository was located at https://github.com/raywu-aaeon/Ryzen2000_4000.git, and it's not clear when it was taken down.</p>                                                                        
                                                                                
<p>The repository included the private portion of the platform key in encrypted form. The encrypted file, however, was protected by a four-character password, a decision that made it trivial for Binarly, and anyone else with even a passing curiosity, to crack the passcode and retrieve the corresponding plain text. The disclosure of the key went largely unnoticed until January 2023, when Binarly researchers found it while investigating a supply-chain incident. Now that the leak has come to light, security experts say it effectively torpedoes the security assurances offered by Secure Boot.</p>
<p>“It’s a big problem,” said Martin Smolár, a malware analyst specializing in rootkits who reviewed the Binarly research and spoke to me about it. “It’s basically an unlimited Secure Boot bypass for these devices that use this platform key. So until device manufacturers or OEMs provide firmware updates, anyone can basically… execute any malware or untrusted code during system boot. Of course, privileged access is required, but that’s not a problem in many cases.”</p>
<p>Binarly researchers said their scans of firmware images uncovered 215 devices that use the compromised key, which can be identified by the certificate serial number 55:fb:ef:87:81:23:00:84:47:17:0b:b3:cd:87:3a:f4. A table appearing at the end of this article lists each one.</p>
<p>The researchers soon discovered that the compromise of the key was just the beginning of a much bigger supply-chain breakdown that raises serious doubts about the integrity of Secure Boot on more than 300 additional device models from virtually all major device manufacturers. As is the case with the platform key compromised in the 2022 GitHub leak, an additional 21 platform keys contain the strings “DO NOT SHIP” or “DO NOT TRUST.”</p>
<figure><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/do-not-trust-certificate.jpg" data-height="1354" data-width="2136" alt="Test certificate provided by AMI."><img alt="Test certificate provided by AMI." src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/do-not-trust-certificate-640x406.jpg" width="640" height="406" srcset="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/do-not-trust-certificate-1280x811.jpg 2x"></a><figcaption><p><a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/do-not-trust-certificate.jpg" data-height="1354" data-width="2136">Enlarge</a> <span>/</span> Test certificate provided by AMI.</p><p>Binarly</p></figcaption></figure>

                                                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI Announces SearchGPT (314 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chatgpt.com/search</link>
            <guid>41071639</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 18:15:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chatgpt.com/search">https://chatgpt.com/search</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41071639">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://chatgpt.com/search: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SearchGPT Prototype (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/searchgpt-prototype/</link>
            <guid>41071585</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 18:11:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/searchgpt-prototype/">https://openai.com/index/searchgpt-prototype/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41071585">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/searchgpt-prototype/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>