(ignoring known css parsing error)
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 13:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Europe's new Ariane 6 rocket powers into space (232 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane/Europe_s_new_Ariane_6_rocket_powers_into_space</link>
            <guid>40924915</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 08:42:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane/Europe_s_new_Ariane_6_rocket_powers_into_space">https://www.esa.int/Enabling_Support/Space_Transportation/Ariane/Europe_s_new_Ariane_6_rocket_powers_into_space</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40924915">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<header>
	<span>Enabling &amp; Support</span>
	
	<p><span>09/07/2024</span>
				<span><span id="viewcount">16881</span><small> views</small></span>
										<span><span id="ezsr_total_26221596">131</span><small> likes</small></span>
				
	</p>
</header>




<p>Europe's new heavy-lift rocket, Ariane 6, made its inaugural flight from Europe's Spaceport in French Guiana at 16:00 &nbsp;local time on 9 July (20:00 BST, 21:00 CEST).</p>
			
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_takes_flight">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/07/ariane_6_takes_flight/26221386-1-eng-GB/Ariane_6_takes_flight_article.jpg" alt="Ariane 6 takes flight">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_takes_flight">Ariane 6 takes flight</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>Ariane 6 is the latest in Europe's Ariane rocket series, taking over from Ariane 5, and featuring a modular and versatile design that can launch missions from low-Earth orbit and farther out into deep space.</p><p>"A completely new rocket is not launched often, and success is far from guaranteed. I am privileged to have witnessed this historic moment when Europe's new generation of the Ariane family lifted off – successfully – effectively reinstating European access to space,” said ESA's Director General Josef Aschbacher.</p><p>"An inaugural launch is a huge undertaking from thousands of people who have worked relentlessly for years. To see it perform wonderfully at the first attempt is testament to their dedication and a demonstration of European excellence in engineering and technology. Heartfelt thanks go to the teams at ESA, CNES, ArianeGroup and Arianespace for their hard work to get to this point. I also want to sincerely thank our Member States for having enabled and supported the Ariane 6 programme along the way. Not always easy, but the endurance shown has paid off handsomely today."</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/06/Installing_first_passengers_on_Ariane_6">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/06/installing_first_passengers_on_ariane_6/26185257-2-eng-GB/Installing_first_passengers_on_Ariane_6_article.jpg" alt="Installing first passengers on Ariane 6">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/06/Installing_first_passengers_on_Ariane_6">Installing first passengers on Ariane 6</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>This inaugural flight, designated VA262, is a demonstration flight whose aim is to show the capabilities and prowess of Ariane 6 in escaping Earth's gravity and operating in space. Nevertheless, it had several passengers on board.</p><p>At 21:06 BST, 22:06 CEST,&nbsp;one hour after liftoff, the first set of satellites on board Ariane 6 were released from the upper stage and placed into an orbit 600 km above Earth. Satellites and experiments from various space agencies, companies, research institutes, universities and young professionals were included on this inaugural flight.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/07/ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff/26220789-1-eng-GB/Ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff_article.jpg" alt="Ariane 6 from above in the final hours before liftoff">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_from_above_in_the_final_hours_before_liftoff">Ariane 6 from above in the final hours before liftoff</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>In addition to the rocket, the liftoff demonstrated the functioning of the launch pad and operations on the ground at Europe's Spaceport. The new custom-built dedicated launch zone was built by France's space agency CNES and allows for a faster turnover of Ariane launches.</p><p>On the occasion of the launch, Philippe Baptiste, CEO of CNES, said: “With this first successful launch by Ariane 6, Europe has finally recovered its capacity to access space. Beyond the great emotion I am feeling right now, my first thoughts are for all the teams in Kourou, Paris, Vernon, Les Mureaux, Toulouse, Bremen, Lampoldshausen, Liège, Barcelona, Colleferro, Zürich and everywhere else in Europe who made this success possible. I would like to acknowledge the commitment of the employees of CNES, ESA, ArianeGroup, Arianespace and our subcontractors. The last few months have been intense, and I would like to thank them all. Europe can be proud of its space programme, Europe can be proud of its knowledge and expertise. Together, let's prepare the future of launchers and space.”</p>	</div>	
    
						
			<p>Ariane 6 was built by prime contractor and design authority ArianeGroup. “With the successful first flight of Ariane&nbsp;6, the European space industry has moved into a new era,” said Martin Sion, CEO of ArianeGroup. “This historic launch demonstrates the unfailing commitment of our teams and partners, whom I would like to thank warmly for this success, which reflects on the entire European industry. Seeing Europe’s new launcher lift off into space marks the culmination of an outstanding technical and technological adventure, and the beginning of a long history of Ariane&nbsp;6 operations. The next flight models are already in production and the stages of the second model will be shipped to the Guiana Space Centre this autumn for the first commercial flight of Ariane&nbsp;6.”</p>	
	<div>
	<h2>Next: tech demos, controlled deorbit and capsule separation</h2>
	    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
											<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_first_flight_timeline">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/07/ariane_6_first_flight_timeline/26212783-1-eng-GB/Ariane_6_first_flight_timeline_article.jpg" alt="Ariane 6 first flight timeline">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/07/Ariane_6_first_flight_timeline">Ariane 6 first flight timeline</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>With the placement of satellites into orbit, Ariane 6 has demonstrated that it can successfully launch its payloads into space, but ground control has more in store for its inaugural flight. Over the next hour, Ariane 6's upper stage will show again that it can restart its Vinci engine using the novel auxiliary propulsion unit. This restart capability will allow Ariane 6 to drop off multiple passengers into different orbits on future flights and deorbit itself through Earth’s atmosphere at the end of its mission, to ensure it does not become space debris.</p><p>On this flight the Ariane 6 upper stage is set to release two reentry capsules as it enters Earth's atmosphere for a clean disposal to burn up harmlessly, leaving no space debris in orbit.</p>	</div>	
    
							
														
																	



							
				
								
						
								
												<div>
				<figure>
					<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/03/Artist_s_view_of_the_Ariane_6">
				<img src="https://www.esa.int/var/esa/storage/images/esa_multimedia/images/2024/03/artist_s_view_of_the_ariane_6/25987586-2-eng-GB/Artist_s_view_of_the_Ariane_6_article.jpg" alt="Artist's view of the Ariane 6">
			</a>
				<figcaption>
							<a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2024/03/Artist_s_view_of_the_Ariane_6">Artist's view of the Ariane 6</a>
								</figcaption>
	</figure>	
		<p>The next Ariane 6 is planned for launch this year on its first commercial flight under Arianespace as operator and launch service provider. “The success of this first flight marks the start of Ariane&nbsp;6’s operational career, giving Europe an autonomous access to space,” added Stéphane Israël, CEO of Arianespace. “The new launcher’s order book is proof of the versatility of Ariane 6 and of its capacity to accomplish a wide range of missions into multiple orbits. It reflects the confidence that customers have in Ariane 6 for both their institutional and commercial missions. We are eager to begin operating our new launcher.”</p>	</div>	
    
						
    
						
    
						
    
					



</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Children's daily sugar consumption halved just a year after tax, study finds (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/society/article/2024/jul/09/childrens-daily-sugar-consumption-halves-just-a-year-after-tax-study-finds</link>
            <guid>40924527</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 07:36:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/article/2024/jul/09/childrens-daily-sugar-consumption-halves-just-a-year-after-tax-study-finds">https://www.theguardian.com/society/article/2024/jul/09/childrens-daily-sugar-consumption-halves-just-a-year-after-tax-study-finds</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40924527">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>The amount of sugar consumed by children from soft drinks in the UK halved within a year of the sugar tax being introduced, a study has found.</p><p>The tax, which came into force in April 2018, has been so successful in improving people’s diets that experts have said an expansion to cover other high sugar food and drink products is now a “no-brainer”.</p><p>The <a href="https://jech.bmj.com/lookup/doi/10.1136/jech-2023-221051" data-link-name="in body link">research</a>, published in the Journal of Epidemiology and Community Health, looked at responses from 7,999 adults and 7,656 children between 2008 and 2019 to the annual nationally representative UK National Diet and Nutrition Survey.</p><p>It showed that the daily sugar intake for children fell by about 4.8g, and for adults 10.9g, in the year after the levy’s introduction.</p><p>The total dietary free sugars, including food and drink, in children was about 70g a day at the beginning of the study, but this fell to about 45g by the end.</p><p>For adults, the study found that the total dietary free sugar consumption stood at about 60g a day, and fell to about 45g a day by the end of the study.</p><p>But despite this reduction, the amount of sugar consumed by adults and children still remains above the recommended guidelines and is contributing to high levels of tooth decay, obesity, diabetes and other illnesses.</p><p>The study found that compared to the period before the sugar tax was announced in 2016, free sugars consumed from all soft drinks reduced by around a half in children, and by a third in adults, after the levy was announced.</p><p>The researchers also note that the fall in consumption of free sugars observed in the whole diet rather than just from soft drinks suggests that consumption of free sugar from food was also falling from as early as 2008.</p><p>Eddie Crouch, the chair of the British Dental Association, said that the sugar tax was delivering “tangible results” and was effective.</p><p>He added: “Extending it to the likes of cereals is a no-brainer for any government that cares about prevention. This needn’t add to the cost of living. Where voluntary action on reformulation has failed, the levy forces the food industry to do the right thing.”</p><p>According to the World <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/health" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Health</a> Organization and the UK Scientific Advisory Committee on Nutrition, the consumption of free sugar should be below 5% of a person’s total calorie intake. For adults, this would be limited to 30g of sugar a day, 24g for children aged between 7 and 10, and 19g for children aged between 4 and 6.</p><p>Dr Nina Rogers, the lead author of the study and part of the University of Cambridge School of Clinical Medicine, said: “The findings of our study are encouraging and show that the UK soft drinks industry levy is linked to a significant reduction in daily sugar intake in adults and children. These results are consistent with previous research which show a reduction in household purchasing of sugar from soft drinks one year after adoption of the levy.”</p><figure id="c7041e84-e774-4012-b332-a1c667e8109c" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:13,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Does Australia need a sugar tax to tackle diabetes, and how would it work?&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;c7041e84-e774-4012-b332-a1c667e8109c&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/australia-news/article/2024/jul/04/australia-sugar-tax-diabetes-parliamentary-report&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0,&quot;design&quot;:0}}"></gu-island></figure><p>She added: “The new UK government might want to consider extending the tax to other (currently exempt) drinks which have a high sugar content, or even to some foods. They might also want to look at restructuring the tax to apply a per gram of sugar/100mls rather than threshold-based levy.”</p><p>Dr Kawther Hashem, a lecturer in Public Health Nutrition at Queen Mary University of London, said: “This new analysis drives home the importance of policies designed to improve the nutritional quality of food and drink. In particular, the soft drinks industry levy (SDIL) in the UK has proven to be an effective lever to encourage food and drink manufacturers to reduce sugar.</p><p>“With a new government now in place, policymakers are urged to consider applying a similar levy to other discretionary products that are key contributors to sugar intake, such as chocolate confectionery, to shift diets towards a healthier direction.”</p><p>A Department of Health and Social Care spokesperson said: “This government will take action to prevent ill-health and tackle the obesity crisis head on, easing the strain on the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/society/nhs" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">NHS</a> and helping people to live well for longer.</p><p>“We will introduce tight restrictions on advertising junk food, alongside banning children from being able to purchase sugary, high-caffeine energy drinks.</p><p>“By building a healthier society, we will help to build a healthy economy.”</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A New Age of Materials Is Dawning, for Everything from Smartphones to Missiles (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b</link>
            <guid>40923124</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 02:09:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b">https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40923124">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wsj.com/tech/composites-manufacturing-boeing-drones-arris-9t-orbital-a422de1b: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Awsviz.dev simplifying AWS IAM policies (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.awsviz.dev/</link>
            <guid>40922740</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:35:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.awsviz.dev/">https://www.awsviz.dev/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40922740">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[RouteLLM: A framework for serving and evaluating LLM routers (154 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM</link>
            <guid>40922739</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:35:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM">https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40922739">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">RouteLLM</h2><a id="user-content-routellm" aria-label="Permalink: RouteLLM" href="#routellm"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">RouteLLM is a framework for serving and evaluating LLM routers.<br>
[ <a href="http://lmsys.org/blog/2024-07-01-routellm/" rel="nofollow">Blog</a> ] [ <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665" rel="nofollow">Paper</a> ]</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/assets/router.png"><img src="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/raw/main/assets/router.png" width="50%"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">Our core features include:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Drop-in replacement for OpenAI's client (or launch an OpenAI-compatible server) to route simpler queries to cheaper models.</li>
<li>Trained routers are provided out of the box, which we have shown to <strong>reduce costs by up to 85%</strong> on widely-used benchmarks such as MT Bench while maintaining <strong>95% GPT-4 performance</strong>.</li>
<li>Easily extend the framework to include new routers and compare the performance of routers across multiple benchmarks.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>From PyPI</strong></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="pip install &quot;routellm[serve,eval]&quot;"><pre><code>pip install "routellm[serve,eval]"
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>From source</strong></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM.git
cd RouteLLM
pip install -e .[serve,eval]"><pre><code>git clone https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM.git
cd RouteLLM
pip install -e .[serve,eval]
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quickstart</h2><a id="user-content-quickstart" aria-label="Permalink: Quickstart" href="#quickstart"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Let's walkthrough replacing an existing OpenAI client to route queries between LLMs instead of using only a single model.</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>First, let's replace our OpenAI client by initializing the RouteLLM controller with the <code>mf</code> router. By default, RouteLLM will use the best-performing config:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="import os
from routellm.controller import Controller

os.environ[&quot;OPENAI_API_KEY&quot;] = &quot;sk-XXXXXX&quot;
# Replace with your model provider, we use Anyscale's Mixtral here.
os.environ[&quot;ANYSCALE_API_KEY&quot;] = &quot;esecret_XXXXXX&quot;

client = Controller(
  routers=[&quot;mf&quot;],
  strong_model=&quot;gpt-4-1106-preview&quot;,
  weak_model=&quot;anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1&quot;,
)"><pre><span>import</span> <span>os</span>
<span>from</span> <span>routellm</span>.<span>controller</span> <span>import</span> <span>Controller</span>

<span>os</span>.<span>environ</span>[<span>"OPENAI_API_KEY"</span>] <span>=</span> <span>"sk-XXXXXX"</span>
<span># Replace with your model provider, we use Anyscale's Mixtral here.</span>
<span>os</span>.<span>environ</span>[<span>"ANYSCALE_API_KEY"</span>] <span>=</span> <span>"esecret_XXXXXX"</span>

<span>client</span> <span>=</span> <span>Controller</span>(
  <span>routers</span><span>=</span>[<span>"mf"</span>],
  <span>strong_model</span><span>=</span><span>"gpt-4-1106-preview"</span>,
  <span>weak_model</span><span>=</span><span>"anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1"</span>,
)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Above, we pick <code>gpt-4-1106-preview</code> as the strong model and <code>anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1</code> as the weak model, setting the API keys accordingly. You can route between different model pairs or providers by updating the model names as described in <a href="#model-support">Model Support</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Want to route to local models? Check out <a href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/examples/routing_to_local_models.md">Routing to Local Models</a>.</p>
<ol start="2" dir="auto">
<li>Each routing request has a <em>cost threshold</em> that controls the tradeoff between cost and quality. We should calibrate this based on the types of queries we receive to maximize routing performance. As an example, let's calibrate our threshold for 50% GPT-4 calls using data from Chatbot Arena.</li>
</ol>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="> python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593"><pre><code>&gt; python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This means that we want to use <code>0.11593</code> as our threshold so that approximately 50% of all queries (those that require GPT-4 the most) will be routed to it (see <a href="#threshold-calibration">Threshold Calibration</a> for details).</p>
<ol start="3" dir="auto">
<li>Now, let's update the <code>model</code> field when we generate completions to specify the router and threshold to use:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="response = client.chat.completions.create(
  # This tells RouteLLM to use the MF router with a cost threshold of 0.11593
  model=&quot;router-mf-0.11593&quot;,
  messages=[
    {&quot;role&quot;: &quot;user&quot;, &quot;content&quot;: &quot;Hello!&quot;}
  ]
)"><pre><span>response</span> <span>=</span> <span>client</span>.<span>chat</span>.<span>completions</span>.<span>create</span>(
  <span># This tells RouteLLM to use the MF router with a cost threshold of 0.11593</span>
  <span>model</span><span>=</span><span>"router-mf-0.11593"</span>,
  <span>messages</span><span>=</span>[
    {<span>"role"</span>: <span>"user"</span>, <span>"content"</span>: <span>"Hello!"</span>}
  ]
)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">That's it! Now, requests with be routed between the strong and weak model depending on what is required, <strong>saving costs while maintaining a high quality of responses</strong>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Depending on your use case, you might want to consider using a different model pair, modifying the configuration, or calibrating the thresholds based on the types of queries you receive to improve performance.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Server &amp; Demo</h3><a id="user-content-server--demo" aria-label="Permalink: Server &amp; Demo" href="#server--demo"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Instead of using the Python SDK, you can also launch an OpenAI-compatible server that will work with any existing OpenAI client, using similar steps:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="> export OPENAI_API_KEY=sk-XXXXXX
> export ANYSCALE_API_KEY=esecret_XXXXXX
> python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --strong-model gpt-4-1106-preview --weak-model anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1
INFO:     Application startup complete.
INFO:     Uvicorn running on http://0.0.0.0:6060 (Press CTRL+C to quit)"><pre><code>&gt; export OPENAI_API_KEY=sk-XXXXXX
&gt; export ANYSCALE_API_KEY=esecret_XXXXXX
&gt; python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --strong-model gpt-4-1106-preview --weak-model anyscale/mistralai/Mixtral-8x7B-Instruct-v0.1
INFO:     Application startup complete.
INFO:     Uvicorn running on http://0.0.0.0:6060 (Press CTRL+C to quit)
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Once the server is launched, you can start a local router chatbot to see how different messages are routed.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m examples.router_chat --router mf --threshold 0.11593"><pre><code>python -m examples.router_chat --router mf --threshold 0.11593
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/assets/chat-interface.png"><img src="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/raw/main/assets/chat-interface.png" width="50%"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Model Support</h3><a id="user-content-model-support" aria-label="Permalink: Model Support" href="#model-support"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">In the above examples, GPT-4 and Mixtral 8x7B are used as the model pair, but you can modify this using the <code>strong-model</code> and <code>weak-model</code> arguments.</p>
<p dir="auto">We leverage <a href="https://github.com/BerriAI/litellm">LiteLLM</a> to support chat completions from a wide-range of open-source and closed models. In general, you need a setup an API key and point to the provider with the appropriate model name. Alternatively, you can also use <strong>any OpenAI-compatible endpoint</strong> by prefixing the model name with <code>openai/</code> and setting the <code>--base-url</code> and <code>--api-key</code> flags.</p>
<p dir="auto">Note that regardless of the model pair used, an <code>OPENAI_API_KEY</code> will currently still be required to generate embeddings for the <code>mf</code> and <code>sw_ranking</code> routers.</p>
<p dir="auto">Instructions for setting up your API keys for popular providers:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Local models with Ollama: see <a href="https://github.com/lm-sys/RouteLLM/blob/main/examples/routing_to_local_models.md">this guide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/anthropic#api-keys" rel="nofollow">Anthropic</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/gemini#sample-usage" rel="nofollow">Gemini - Google AI Studio</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/bedrock#required-environment-variables" rel="nofollow">Amazon Bedrock</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/togetherai#api-keys" rel="nofollow">Together AI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers/anyscale#api-key" rel="nofollow">Anyscale Endpoints</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For other model providers, find instructions <a href="https://litellm.vercel.app/docs/providers" rel="nofollow">here</a> or raise an issue.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Motivation</h2><a id="user-content-motivation" aria-label="Permalink: Motivation" href="#motivation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Different LLMs vary widely in their costs and capabilities, which leads to a dilemma when deploying them: routing all queries to the most capable model leads to the highest-quality responses but can be very expensive, while routing queries to smaller models can save costs but may result in lower-quality responses.</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>LLM routing</em> offers a solution to this. We introduce a router that looks at queries and routes simpler queries to smaller, cheaper models, saving costs while maintaining quality. We focus on routing between 2 models: a stronger, more expensive model and a cheaper but weaker model. Each request is also associated with a <em>cost threshold</em> that determines the cost-quality tradeoff of that request - a higher cost threshold leads to lower cost but may lead to lower-quality responses.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Server</h2><a id="user-content-server" aria-label="Permalink: Server" href="#server"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">RouteLLM offers a lightweight OpenAI-compatible server for routing requests based on different routing strategies:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --config config.example.yaml"><pre><code>python -m routellm.openai_server --routers mf --config config.example.yaml
</code></pre></div>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>--routers</code> specifies the list of routers available to the server. For instance, here, the server is started with one available router: <code>mf</code> (see below for the list of routers).</li>
<li><code>--config</code> specifies the path to the configuration file for the routers. If unspecified, the server will default to using our best-performing configuration (see <a href="#configuration">Configuration</a> for details).</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">For most use-cases, <strong>we recommend the <code>mf</code> router</strong> as we have evaluated it to be very strong and lightweight.</p>
<p dir="auto">When making a request to the server, clients specify the router and cost threshold to use for each request using the <code>model</code> field in the following format <code>router-[ROUTER NAME]-[THRESHOLD]</code>. For instance, using a <code>model</code> of <code>router-mf-0.5</code> specifies that the request should be routed using the <code>mf</code> router with a threshold of 0.5.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Threshold Calibration</h3><a id="user-content-threshold-calibration" aria-label="Permalink: Threshold Calibration" href="#threshold-calibration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The threshold used for routing controls the cost-quality tradeoff. The range of meaningful thresholds varies depending on the type of router and the queries you receive. Therefore, we recommend calibrating thresholds using a sample of your incoming queries, as well as the % of queries you'd like to route to the stronger model.</p>
<p dir="auto">By default, we support calibrating thresholds based on the public <a href="https://huggingface.co/datasets/lmsys/lmsys-arena-human-preference-55k" rel="nofollow">Chatbot Arena dataset</a>. For example, to calibrate the threshold for the <code>mf</code> router such that 50% of calls are routed to the stronger model:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="> python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --task calibrate --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593"><pre><code>&gt; python -m routellm.calibrate_threshold --task calibrate --routers mf --strong-model-pct 0.5 --config config.example.yaml
For 50.0% strong model calls for mf, threshold = 0.11593
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This means that the threshold should be set to 0.1881 for the <code>mf</code> router so that approximately 50% of calls are routed to the strong model i.e. using a <code>model</code> field of <code>router-mf-0.1159</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">However, note that because we calibrate the thresholds based on an existing dataset, the % of calls routed to each model will differ based on the actual queries received. Therefore, we recommend calibrating on a dataset that closely resembles the types of queries you receive.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Evaluation</h2><a id="user-content-evaluation" aria-label="Permalink: Evaluation" href="#evaluation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">RouteLLM also includes a evaluation framework to measure the performance of different routing strategies on benchmarks.</p>
<p dir="auto">To evaluate a router on a benchmark, you can use the following command:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python -m routellm.evals.evaluate --routers random sw_ranking bert --benchmark gsm8k --config config.example.yaml "><pre><code>python -m routellm.evals.evaluate --routers random sw_ranking bert --benchmark gsm8k --config config.example.yaml 
</code></pre></div>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>--routers</code> specifies the list of routers to evaluate, for instance, <code>random</code> and <code>bert</code> in this case.</li>
<li><code>--benchmark</code> specifies the specific benchmark to evaluate the routers on. We currently support: <code>mmlu</code>, <code>gsm8k</code>, and <code>mt-bench</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Evaluation results will be printed to the console. A plot of router performance will also be generated in the current directory (override the path using <code>--output</code>). To avoid recomputing results, the results for a router on a given benchmark is cached by default. This behavior can be overridden by using the <code>--overwrite-cache</code> flag, which takes in a list of routers to overwrite the cache for.</p>
<p dir="auto">The results for all our benchmarks have been cached. For MT Bench, we use the precomputed judgements for the desired model pair. For MMLU and GSM8K, we utilized <a href="https://github.com/sgl-project/sglang">SGLang</a> to compute the results for the desired model pair - the full code for this can be found in the benchmark directories if you would like to evaluate a different model pair.</p>
<p dir="auto">By default, GPT-4 and Mixtral are used as the model pair for evaluation. To modify the model pair used, set them using the <code>--strong-model</code> and <code>--weak-model</code> flags.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Routers</h2><a id="user-content-routers" aria-label="Permalink: Routers" href="#routers"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Out of the box, RouteLLM supports 4 routers trained on the <code>gpt-4-1106-preview</code> and <code>mixtral-8x7b-instruct-v0.1</code> model pair.</p>
<p dir="auto">The full list of routers:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><code>mf</code>: Uses a matrix factorization model trained on the preference data (recommended).</li>
<li><code>sw_ranking</code>: Uses a weighted Elo calculation for routing, where each vote is weighted according to how similar it is to the user's prompt.</li>
<li><code>bert</code>: Uses a BERT classifier trained on the preference data.</li>
<li><code>causal_llm</code>: Uses a LLM-based classifier tuned on the preference data.</li>
<li><code>random</code>: Randomly routes to either model.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">While these routers have been trained on the <code>gpt-4-1106-preview</code> and <code>mixtral-8x7b-instruct-v0.1</code> model pair, we have found that these routers generalize well to other strong and weak model pairs as well. Therefore, you can replace the model pair used for routing without having to retrain these models!</p>
<p dir="auto">For the full details, refer to our <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665" rel="nofollow">paper</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: Configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The configuration for routers is specified in either the <code>config</code> argument for <code>Controller</code> or by passing in the path to a YAML file using the <code>--config</code> flag. It is a top-level mapping from router name to the keyword arguments used for router initialization.</p>
<p dir="auto">An example configuration is provided in the <code>config.example.yaml</code> file - it provides the configurations for routers that have trained on Arena data augmented using GPT-4 as a judge. The models and datasets used are all hosted on Hugging Face under the <a href="https://huggingface.co/routellm" rel="nofollow">RouteLLM</a> and <a href="https://huggingface.co/lmsys" rel="nofollow">LMSYS</a> organizations.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contribution</h2><a id="user-content-contribution" aria-label="Permalink: Contribution" href="#contribution"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We welcome contributions! Please feel free to open an issue or a pull request if you have any suggestions or improvements.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Adding a new router</h3><a id="user-content-adding-a-new-router" aria-label="Permalink: Adding a new router" href="#adding-a-new-router"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To add a new router to RouteLLM, implement the abstract <code>Router</code> class in <code>routers.py</code> and add the new router to the <code>ROUTER_CLS</code> dictionary. Then, you can use immediately the new router in the server or evaluation framework.</p>
<p dir="auto">There is only a single method to implement: <code>calculate_strong_win_rate</code>, which takes in the user prompt and returns the win rate for the strong model conditioned on that given prompt - if this win rate is great than user-specified cost threshold, then the request is routed to the strong model. Otherwise, it is routed to the weak model.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Adding a new benchmark</h3><a id="user-content-adding-a-new-benchmark" aria-label="Permalink: Adding a new benchmark" href="#adding-a-new-benchmark"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To add a new benchmark to RouteLLM, implement the abstract <code>Benchmark</code> class in <code>benchmarks.py</code> and update the <code>evaluate.py</code> module to properly initialize the new benchmark class. Ideally, the results for the benchmark should be precomputed to avoid having to regenerate the results for each evaluation run -- see the existing benchmarks for examples on how to do this.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Citation</h2><a id="user-content-citation" aria-label="Permalink: Citation" href="#citation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The code in this repository is based on the research from the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665" rel="nofollow">paper</a>. Please cite if you find the repository helpful.</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="@misc{ong2024routellmlearningroutellms,
      title={RouteLLM: Learning to Route LLMs with Preference Data},
      author={Isaac Ong and Amjad Almahairi and Vincent Wu and Wei-Lin Chiang and Tianhao Wu and Joseph E. Gonzalez and M Waleed Kadous and Ion Stoica},
      year={2024},
      eprint={2406.18665},
      archivePrefix={arXiv},
      primaryClass={cs.LG},
      url={https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665},
}"><pre><code>@misc{ong2024routellmlearningroutellms,
      title={RouteLLM: Learning to Route LLMs with Preference Data},
      author={Isaac Ong and Amjad Almahairi and Vincent Wu and Wei-Lin Chiang and Tianhao Wu and Joseph E. Gonzalez and M Waleed Kadous and Ion Stoica},
      year={2024},
      eprint={2406.18665},
      archivePrefix={arXiv},
      primaryClass={cs.LG},
      url={https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18665},
}
</code></pre></div>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How CD Pregaps Gained Their Hidden Track Superpowers (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tedium.co/2024/07/06/compact-disc-pregap-history/</link>
            <guid>40920122</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 19:38:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tedium.co/2024/07/06/compact-disc-pregap-history/">https://tedium.co/2024/07/06/compact-disc-pregap-history/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40920122">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
      <p><span><strong>Today in Tedium:</strong> Having gotten through a massive Animal Well journey, I’d like to make a proclamation: More things need hidden secrets, like <a href="https://tedium.co/2023/04/08/easter-eggs-software-history/">Easter eggs</a>. Usually, games and applications are where we find hidden secrets, but during the 1990s, the music industry had a monopoly on all the good ones, thanks to the compact disc, which kicked off a <a href="https://tedium.co/2017/11/09/hidden-tracks-album-history/">hidden track renaissance</a>. As cool as hidden tracks were, the best CD trick was something called a pregap, referring to the space immediately before the first track of an album. It led to numerous innovative ideas—but it also pointed out the risks of going off-spec, as anyone who has ever tried to pull a pregap from a CD-ROM can tell you. Today’s Tedium ponders where pregaps came from and how it became the music industry’s weirdest hiding spot. <em>– Ernie @ Tedium</em></span></p>
<div>
        
<p><h3>pause encoding</h3>
</p>
<p><strong>The term the compact disc specification</strong> uses for what is better known as the pregap section of audio CDs, according to the standard <a href="https://webstore.iec.ch/publication/3885">IEC 60908</a>. (This is not a particularly easy document to access, by the way, because it costs money. You won’t find any copies on the Internet Archive, though related documents are online that refer to pause encoding <a href="https://archive.org/details/sony-philips-compact-disc-recordable-compact-disc-systems-part-i-cd-mo-part-ii-c/">are online</a>, if you’re curious.)</p>
</div>
<div>
    
<p><img data-src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Portable-CD-Player.jpg" width="800" height="530" alt="Portable CD Player" src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Portable-CD-Player.jpg"></p>
<p><em>(<a href="https://flickr.com/photos/18909153@N08/7692568966/">Cross Duck/Flickr</a>)</em></p>
<h3>If you have a favorite CD from the ’80s or ’90s, it might have a really tiny pregap</h3>
<p><strong>“Why do older CDs usually have</strong> a 0.33 second pregap before the first track?”</p>
<p>As nerdy questions go, you don’t get much nerdier than <a href="https://forums.stevehoffman.tv/threads/why-do-older-cds-usually-have-a-0-33-second-pregap-before-the-first-track.1178267/">this particular question</a>, asked about a year ago on the Steve Hoffman Music Forums, a popular forum for music nerds and audio engineers. Apparently, the user noticed it when trying to rip CDs using the tool Exact Audio Copy, an application well-known for its ability to rip CDs that other programs can’t.</p>
<p>It may be the most specific question I have found in my near-decade-long history of looking for specific questions.</p>
<p><img data-src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/ExactAudioCopy.png" width="450" height="353" alt="Exact Audio Copy" src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/ExactAudioCopy.png"></p>
<p><em><a href="https://www.exactaudiocopy.de/">Exact Audio Copy</a>, the program that exposed the extremely specific pregap hidden on many pre-2000 CDs.</em></p>
<p>This is not something the average person would notice (after all, when was the last time you used a CD that allowed you to go backwards exactly a third of a second?), but it proved a problem in this specific case, because it apparently caused an issue with the user’s external drive:</p>
<blockquote><p>The 32/33 frame pregap has no impact on my built-in drive’s ripping speed in EAC, but does impact the speed of my rips on my external ASUS drive—it seems to spin up to full speed a few seconds into a rip on a CD without this pregap, but doesn’t on ones with, meaning rips take about twice the length.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>A commenter on the thread who identified as a professional audio engineer suggested the poster was “agonizing over trivia.” (This engineer will probably throw a chair when he sees this piece.) But honestly, it reflects a truism about disc mastering: Over time, people got better at it. There is speculation that the discs with pregaps were made at one factory over another, which would require speaking to specific engineers who may have left this mortal coil decades ago.</p>
<p>(More recently, the same user asked another very specific question: “<a href="https://forums.stevehoffman.tv/threads/which-cds-from-the-1980s-were-mastered-using-first-generation-tapes.1198897/">Which CDs from the 1980s were mastered using first generation tapes?</a>”)</p>
<p>The weird part is, he’s not the first person to notice this! About a decade ago, a user <a href="https://hydrogenaud.io/index.php/topic,101115.0.html">on the Hydrogen Audio forums</a> found pregaps on albums as diverse and well-known as Beck’s <em>Mellow Gold</em>, Guns N’ Roses’ <em>Use Your Illusion I &amp; II</em>, Nirvana’s <em>Nevermind</em>, and, um, the score to <em>Schindler’s List</em>. These albums all had a pregap of either 32 or 33 “frames,” with a frame representing a length of <a href="https://wiki.hydrogenaud.io/index.php?title=EAC_and_Cue_Sheets">about 1/75th of a second</a>, per Hydrogen Audio’s Wiki. This apparently is not a specification made up by EAC, but dictated by the Red Book, the compact disc guidebook that sets specifications for the format. According to <a href="https://archive.org/details/cdromhandbook0000unse/page/540/mode/2up"><em>The CD ROM Handbook</em></a>, a 1994 guide to the mastering and setup of compact discs of both audio and digital forms, each of these sectors includes exactly 2,352 bytes of digitized audio data.</p>
<p>To offer a small correction to the original question now that we know we’re talking about 74 frames per second rather than 60 or 100: we are talking about a period of just shy of half a second—a period that most CD players could not access. But the interesting part is that this is actually a shorter period than the format actually suggests, a length of between two and three seconds—an essential separation for data. But over time, it appears that audio CD makers realized that such a gap was not particularly necessary.</p>
<p>These data points obviously do not affect what you’re listening to. You may not even notice them! But small differences in CD length add up when you’re doing things like adding music into a database like <a href="https://musicbrainz.org/">MusicBrainz</a>. Hence why nerds ripping CDs notice things like this!</p>
</div>


<div>
    
<p><img data-src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Willie-Nelson-Moonlight.jpg" width="600" height="590" alt="Willie Nelson Moonlight" src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Willie-Nelson-Moonlight.jpg"></p>
<p><em>The production of this Willie Nelson album inspired a pregap-related patent filing.</em></p>
<h3>The patent filing that made Willie Nelson a pregap hidden track innovator</h3>
<p><strong>When I say the name “Willie Nelson,”</strong> the phrase that comes to mind is probably “outlaw country.” But I’d like to make the case that Nelson deserves another term tied to his name: “Hidden track innovator.”</p>
<p>It’s true. In 1994, the country legend, between major labels, took a chance on a small indie jazz label called Justice Records for his record <em>Moonlight Becomes You</em>. It was small potatoes compared to the majors he usually worked with, but Nelson rolled with the dice and got a Grammy nomination from it—<a href="https://www.grammy.com/artists/willie-nelson/4954">one of 57 to his name</a>. It’s also an album that you will not find on any streaming service, likely because he chose to work with a small indie label, though the songs are on YouTube if you’re curious.</p>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="LUIokOOT7Z8"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LUIokOOT7Z8">Watch on YouTube</a></lite-youtube></p>
<p>The vibe is much more Sinatra-ish than Nelson usually goes, as the above performance of the title track shows. (It’s in the vein of his 1978 album <a href="https://willienelson.com/products/stardust"><em>Stardust</em></a>, a hugely successful record of pop standards that presented Nelson as a master interpreter.) But Nelson happened to be working with a label whose founder had just filed a patent for the pregap hidden track. <a href="https://www.chron.com/entertainment/music/article/album-review-moonlight-becomes-you-4460663.php">And per a <em>Houston Chronicle</em> review</a>, Nelson apparently used it to explain why he went with Justice Records rather than another big label.</p>
<p>Willie’s album was actually produced by the guy who filed the patent, Randall Jamail, with the label’s COO David Thompson, also appearing on some patent filings.</p>
<p>That patent filing, titled “<a href="https://patents.google.com/patent/US5471443A/en">Method of selectively concealing magneto-optical compact disk data for playback upon demand</a>,” describes a process for “impressing data on the media between the first play location and the begin play point.” (I like sharing patent drawings, but there’s really no point with this one—it’s just a flowchart that describes the process of adding the track, no fun visuals here.) The invention, which the label called Justice Soundboard, was promoted as a big deal by the Houston label.</p>
<p><lite-youtube videoid="Toi0LT9KyM4"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Toi0LT9KyM4">Watch on YouTube</a></lite-youtube></p>
<p><em>The ambient “Running Man” by the heavy metal band Course of Empire, either the first or second pregap hidden track, based on how you measure this.</em></p>
<p>There was just one problem: A producer in Dallas had actually come up with the technique first, a few months before Jamail. Course of Empire, a heavy metal band signed to Zoo Entertainment (a label best known for bringing the world Tool), had used the exact same technique on their 1993 album <em>Initiation</em>, which had some weirdly hidden tracks, including one buried inside the mono channel on another track, which is kind of insane. </p>
<p>The debate, which <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=QggEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA77">played out in <em>Billboard</em></a> in the spring of 1995, seems to have been the result of weird timing.</p>
<blockquote><p>Castell notes that he was unaware of the Justice Soundboard. However, he insists that he came up with the invention himself months before the fall ’93 Justice planning meetings for the Nelson record, at which the idea for the Soundboard was hatched, according to Jamail.</p>
<p>Castell, like other audio professionals surveyed for this story, is skeptical of the patentability of the feature. In fact, he says it never even occurred to him to file for a patent.</p>
<p>Ironically, Jamail says he also was initially skeptical about the patent-potential of his idea, but proceeded with the application at the urging of his colleague, Thompson, who discovered after a week of research that neither Philips nor Sony—the inventors of the CD—had patented the procedure.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>(Another, unrelated claimant is Electric Light Orchestra, <a href="https://www.discogs.com/release/2298345-Electric-Light-Orchestra-Face-The-Music">which reissued an album</a> with a pregap in 1993. For completeness’ sake: Wikipedia claims another act with an unprintable name, initials A.C., also was early to the trend. However, per my Discogs research, the EP in question was released on vinyl first, then on CD years later. <em>Whew.</em> I didn’t want to have to make this whole section about that band.)</p>
<p>Ultimately, the patent ended up sticking around, which was great for Justice Records, which had to sue Sony and Philips to allow his label to license its technique. Jamail quickly won the case, <a href="https://www.dallasobserver.com/music/waste-not-want-not-6403415">per the <em>Dallas Observer</em></a>.</p>
<p>“This is going to be given to the consumer for free,” Jamail told the alt-weekly. ”I’m going to license Soundboard for pennies a disc, and with CD pricing, there’s room for the record companies to absorb that.”</p>
<p>So, if your favorite record had a hidden pregap track on it, just know that it probably made Justice Records a bunch of money.</p>
</div>
<div>
    
<p><img data-src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Compact-Disc-Closeup.jpg" width="800" height="600" alt="Compact Disc Closeup" src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Compact-Disc-Closeup.jpg"></p>
<p><em>(<a href="https://flickr.com/photos/negativz/33486551/">Rodrigo Sena/Flickr</a>)</em></p>
<h3>Five interesting details about pregaps</h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Technically, every track can have a pregap.</strong> If you want to put some weird audio in the spot between a given track, it’s technically possible to do. <a href="https://archive.org/details/cdromhandbook0000unse/page/568/mode/2up">As <em>The CD ROM Handbook</em> explains</a>, the Red Book spec lets CD-makers add two-second audio pregaps between each track, though they’re optional, as proven by the fact that your favorite albums aren’t loaded with giant pauses. The only pregap that’s actually required is the one directly before the CD.</li>
<li><strong>The first format to hide stuff in the pregap wasn’t an audio CD.</strong> In the early ’90s, Philips bet big on the CD-i format. Thanks to the fact that Philips had directly developed the CD format with Sony, it built some CD-i specific standardization of its own. One of those standards <a href="https://obsoletemedia.org/cd-i-ready/">was the CD-i Ready</a> format, which hid the CD-i data in the pregap area, about two years before Randall Jamail filed for his patent.</li>
<li><strong>Many printing plants won’t press CDs with pregaps.</strong> As we noted in <a href="https://tedium.co/2017/11/09/hidden-tracks-album-history/">our piece</a> on hidden tracks—and first reported by the late publication <a href="https://archive.is/6rRq3"><em>Wondering Sound</em></a> in 2014—They Might Be Giants reportedly faced a lot of drama with their label for using a pregap, because it made printing the CDs harder. These days, hidden pregap tracks are unpopular with CD plants—to the point where plants won’t even consider doing them, <a href="https://www.google.com/books/edition/From_Demo_to_Delivery/b3hrCIxmkcYC?hl=en&amp;gbpv=1&amp;pg=PT291&amp;printsec=frontcover">according to mastering engineer Russ Hepworth-Sawyer</a>.</li>
<li><strong>There’s also a thing called a postgap.</strong> Similar to a pregap, these are used as a pause on the CD, but they are specifically used on data CDs to signify the end of the data section. In other words, they represent an actual pause. If you’re running a CD-ROM for a game console (see <a href="https://github.com/sparkletron/PSYQ_Examples/blob/master/psxCDcreate.md">this doc</a> for the PlayStation development platform PSYQ), for instance, you may see a postgap there.</li>
<li><strong>Your CD-R can print pregaps and postgaps.</strong> There’s a terminology used in CD-R software called <a href="https://www.pcmag.com/encyclopedia/term/track-at-once">track-at-once</a> a burning style that effectively adds gaps between different tracks, essentially turning off the laser between burns. This is useful if the disc is a multi-session CD-R, because the postgap allows you to add more tracks later on.</li>
</ol>
</div>
<div>
        
<p><h3>“In fact, most industry experts estimate as many as half of currently installed CD-ROMs won’t be able to play the new discs.”</h3>
</p>
<p><strong>— A <em>Billboard</em> piece from the fall of 1995,</strong> mere months after the magazine was home to the showdown between Justice Records and Course of Empire, <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=wg4EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA31">discussing the rise of the Enhanced CD</a>, a standard that aimed to bring music albums to the PC and Macintosh. Nothing like a standard that doesn’t work for most people!</p>
</div>
<div>
    
<p><lite-youtube videoid="6XSXmNzDd-g"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6XSXmNzDd-g">Watch on YouTube</a></lite-youtube></p>
<p><em>An example of the kind of content you might find on an Enhanced CD, from the Barenaked Ladies’ Shoe Box EP. So, essentially, home videos.</em></p>
<h3>The Enhanced CD highlighted why hidden pregaps were so problematic</h3>
<p>If you bought a CD from a major label in the mid-’90s, odds are it might have included some additional digital stuff for your computer. One band that embraced this strategy was the Barenaked Ladies, whose <em>Shoe Box EP</em> first used the technique in 1995. (Here’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6XSXmNzDd-g">a video collection</a> from the CD, with like half an hour of random video content.) These albums, called Enhanced CDs, came with multimedia stuff like music videos, band photos, or even a multimedia experience that leveraged the benefits the format already offered.</p>
<p>BNL found success with the format, replicating the idea again about a year later for its live album <em>Rock Spectacle</em>, which proved the band’s U.S. breakout. The band’s Tyler Stewart, <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=ygkEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA65">speaking to <em>Billboard</em> in November 1996</a>, said the ECD format allowed the live album to better present the band’s on-stage humor to CD buyers.</p>
<p>“We’re lucky that we have the extra dimension of humor,” Stewart said at the time. “Good ECDs are probably more difficult to make if the band is serious.”</p>
<p>The ECD format was a hybrid CD, and the format had Apple’s fingerprints all over it at a time when Apple wasn’t exactly at full strength, thanks to many ECDs utilizing QuickTime. As Josh Warner wrote in the Apple-sponsored <a href="https://wiki.preterhuman.net/images/8/84/Fact.pdf"><em>Enhanced CD Fact Book</em></a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>It’s important to know where you came from to know where you are. Until recently, most multimedia discs targeting the music market were full-blown CD-ROMs, such as <em>Xplora1: Peter Gabriel’s Secret World</em> or <em>JUMP: The David Bowie Interactive CD-ROM</em>. These discs are meant to be played on the CD-ROM drive of your computer. That’s the only way you’ll get at what is important–the multimedia.</p>
<p>Enhanced CDs are different. The primary focus of enhanced CD is the music. The multimedia part is the bonus. For this reason, the name is revealing. It recognizes the format as an enhancement of the popular audio CD, which follows an industry standard referred to as the Red Book. </p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Enhancement of the popular audio CD” sounds good. There was just one problem: It wasn’t easy to do any of this. It was sort of the Wild West, and it required a lot of experimenting to get right. Warner’s guide described the use of three approaches for making ECDs: The first, a mixed-mode CD, puts data on the first track, threatening to destroy the speakers of any given music fan if they leave the CD on repeat. Warner made it clear this idea was a nonstarter:</p>
<blockquote><p>Mixed-mode enhanced CDs are commonly stickered with an alert like “SKIP TRACK ONE OR ELSE.” Warning labels are OK if you’re a pack of cigarettes, but imagine how artists and record labels feel. That’s why you don’t see very many mixed-mode discs.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Despite this, the format deserves credit for kicking off the trend, with Sarah McLachlan’s <em>The Freedom Sessions</em> often credited as the first Enhanced CD to be released by a mainstream artist. </p>
<p><img data-src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Sarah-McLachlan-The-Freedom-Sessions.jpg" width="600" height="530" alt="Sarah Mc Lachlan The Freedom Sessions" src="https://images.tedium.co/uploads/Sarah-McLachlan-The-Freedom-Sessions.jpg"></p>
<p><em>Don’t listen to the first track of Sarah McLachlan’s The Freedom Sessions, believed to be the first Enhanced CD by a mainstream artist. It might bust your speakers. (via <a href="https://www.discogs.com/release/1184942-Sarah-McLachlan-The-Freedom-Sessions">Discogs</a>)</em></p>
<p>One alternative, as you might guess by the topic of this piece, was to shove the data in the pregap, hiding the data layer from the CD player. One problem: Most CD-ROM drives didn’t actually support pregaps, because of course they didn’t.</p>
<p>The final one, which eventually won out, was called a Multisession CD, also known as CD Plus, which essentially treated the two content elements (music and data) as separate parts based on the machine it was in. Unlike the pregap, the data was technically at the <em>end</em> of the CD, rather than the beginning. </p>
<p>“The audio CD player never gets to the interactive data (which now follows the audio session), virtually eliminating the chance for CD Plus discs to play improperly in a regular audio CD player,” Warner wrote.</p>
<p>Problem is, even fewer CD-ROMs supported the multisession format at the time, which required reprogramming the CD-ROMs to look for a secondary data track. This was easy on Apple’s end—they just created a driver to fix this—but the rest of the PC industry clearly was poorly positioned to handle this.</p>
<p>As Enhanced CDs showed, CD-ROMs did not handle gimmicks well. It was either create a substandard user experience from an audio CD standpoint, or know that the CD-ROM portion won’t work in like half of all CD-ROM drives. What a weird thing to invest in!</p>
<p>And even when the ECD format was out in the wild, breaking changes were still occurring at random. BNL, which saw more success with them than most acts, actually had to delay the release of <em>Rock Spectacle</em> by a couple months, <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=ygkEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA65">per <em>Billboard</em></a>, because the disc originally used the pregap Enhanced CD approach. The reason? <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=wQcEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA3">Microsoft inexplicably decided to change</a> how Windows 95 read CDs, making the pregap approach to Enhanced CD entirely useless.</p>
<p>Despite this, the record industry had been quick to paint the Enhanced CDs as the future, with RIAA then-president Hillary Rosen <a href="https://books.google.com/books?id=wg4EAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=RA1-PA44">telling <em>Billboard</em></a>:</p>
<blockquote><p>The E-CD targets the nearly 28 million IBM and Mac users, the most rapidly growing consumer lifestyle. E-CD puts us squarely in that market and will ensure our continued leadership in the packaged media for that market.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>“Continued,” you say? This technology faded pretty quickly in the late ’90s, especially as the internet proved a much better vessel for this kind of tertiary information.</p>
<p>And because they relied on proprietary technology—like Apple’s QuickTime, or executables that only worked on Classic MacOS, Windows 3.1, or Windows 95—it meant that as soon as the record industry got bored with Enhanced CDs (which it eventually did), it meant the information was essentially useless to the average consumer.</p>
<p>It was as if the recording industry was in a huge rush to timestamp music CDs, which at their best can be timeless, as things that go immediately obsolete. They should have just used the pregaps for hidden tracks.</p>
</div>
<div>
    
<p><strong>When the compact disc format</strong> was first released in the early 1980s, it was shared with the industry with a script for how the format should be published and produced. While lengthy, the Red Book was a clear list of standards that any label or mastering plant willing to spend money on that book could take advantage of.</p>
<p>The problem is, the compact disc was capable of more than was allowed under these basic parameters. And as a result, people started to stretch it. Sometimes they filed patents for said stretching.</p>
<p>There was one problem, though: While the compact disc <em>media</em> could be easily modified, the compact disc <em>hardware</em>, which generally didn’t have user-upgradeable firmware unless it was attached to a computer, could not. And that meant there were always significant edge cases that emerged when the discs you used didn’t match the norms.</p>
<p>The pregap was one of the most notable examples of this, but it was far from the most divergent—the <a href="https://tedium.co/2019/09/19/dualdisc-compact-disc-history/">DualDisc</a>, which David Buck wrote about in 2019, was so far afield from the Red Book standard that it couldn’t even call itself a compact disc.</p>
<p>In this light, the pregap, the tiny little area that initially only meant something to audio engineers before becoming the home of Enhanced CDs and artists who felt confined by a 74-minute limit, was an oddity. It was something specified for a specific use on the CD, only for its purpose to morph as people actually got their hands on the idea.</p>
<p>But we love finding secrets—and the pregap gave us another place to look for them.</p>
<p>--</p>
<p>Find this one an interesting read? <a href="https://tedium.co/2024/07/06/compact-disc-pregap-history/">Share it with a pal</a>! And mind the pregap.</p>
</div>


    </div><p><label for="subscribebox-toggle">
      <span>
        <span>
        <h3>Like this? Well, you should read more of our stuff.</h3>

        <p data-reveal-id="subscribe-popup" data-reveal=""><span></span>&nbsp;Get more issues in your inbox
        </p>
        </span>
        </span>
    </label>
  </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[New insights into transcription factors and chromatin remodeling (113 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://longevity.technology/news/master-controller-of-aging-and-development-uncovered/</link>
            <guid>40919707</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 19:09:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://longevity.technology/news/master-controller-of-aging-and-development-uncovered/">https://longevity.technology/news/master-controller-of-aging-and-development-uncovered/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40919707">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://longevity.technology/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Master-controller-of-aging-and-development-uncovered-1024x683.jpg" width="811" height="541"></p><h2><strong>New insights into transcription factors and chromatin remodeling reveal potential for improving age-related health outcomes.</strong></h2><p>Researchers from the <a href="https://www.uq.edu.au/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">University of Queensland</a> have made significant strides in understanding the molecular mechanisms underpinning aging and development, highlighting the crucial role of gene regulatory elements and their interaction with transcription factors. The study, published in <em><a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550413124002316?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Cell Metabolism</a></em>, offers a comprehensive analysis of chromatin changes across various cell types in both mice and humans, revealing common pathways that govern the transition from youth to old age.</p><p><strong><em>Longevity.Technology: Research into the molecular processes of aging holds significant promise for advancing longevity and improving health outcomes; by dissecting the ways in which gene activity shifts over time, scientists can develop targeted interventions aimed at mitigating age-related diseases and enhancing healthspan. Understanding these underlying mechanisms not only propels geroscientific research, but fosters the development of therapies that can potentially delay or reverse detrimental aging processes.</em></strong></p><h4>Overture and beginners</h4><p>Led by Dr Christian Nefzger, Group Leader, Cellular reprogramming and ageing at UQ, the study employed multi-omic analyses to explore chromatin and transcriptional changes across 22 types of mouse cells, further augmented by existing datasets on human and mouse maturation. The researchers identified a distinct transcription factor binding site (TFBS) signature that is shared between developmental and aging processes, and which is characterized by early-life candidate cis-regulatory elements (cCREs) losing accessibility as organisms mature, while other cCREs gain accessibility through life due to increased levels of Activator Protein 1 (AP-1) [<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550413124002316?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">1</a>].</p><p>Nefzger noted that the mechanisms by which gene activity shifts from birth through adulthood and into old age have remained largely unknown until now.</p><p>“By analyzing molecular datasets from both people and mice and then comparing different age groups over time, we investigated the activity of genes involved in both developmental and ageing processes,” he explained. “Master controller genes regulate which genes are turned on or off in each of our cells, making sure that each cell does its specific job, just as a conductor directs musicians to produce different sounds [<a href="https://www.uq.edu.au/news/article/2024/06/revealing-master-controller-of-development-and-ageing" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2</a>].”</p><h4><strong>AP-1: The Master Regulator</strong></h4><p>AP-1 emerged as a pivotal factor in this research, demonstrating its role in progressively activating adult genes while ‘dialing down’ the activity of early-life genes.</p><p>This activity, shared across various cell types, illustrates a fundamental mechanism of aging, and Dr Marina Naval-Sanchez, a Postdoctoral Research Fellow in UQ’s Institute for Molecular Bioscience, added that the study showed this cellular process to be predictable across various life stages as individuals mature.</p><p>“It was ongoing in adulthood, likely because AP-1 is also activated by a number of stress and inflammatory processes as well as by a protein in our blood that increases with age,” she explained. “This further dampens genes most active early in life, which may drive many of the predictable changes of aging [<a href="https://www.uq.edu.au/news/article/2024/06/revealing-master-controller-of-development-and-ageing" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2</a>].”</p><p>The study posits that the redistribution of transcription factors such as AP-1, alongside mild downregulation of cell identity transcription factors, prompts chromatin remodeling that alters developmental and metabolic gene expression [<a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550413124002316?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">1</a>]. This mechanism can be triggered by elevated AP-1 activity or depletion of repressive H3K27me3, &nbsp;an epigenetic modification to a DNA packaging protein histone, something that highlights the nuanced interplay of genetic and epigenetic factors in aging.</p><h4>Implications for Age-Related Diseases</h4><p>The research holds potential for addressing age-related diseases such as Alzheimer’s, metabolic disorders, and stroke. Dr Ralph Patrick, also a PDRF in the Institute for Molecular Bioscience, explained that to these diseases, it is essential for researchers to first comprehend the underlying processes that cause bodies to age.</p><p>“By pinpointing AP-1 as a master controller linked to aging across cell types, we can now study the effects of drugs that reduce its activity to extend quality of life,” he said [<a href="https://www.uq.edu.au/news/article/2024/06/revealing-master-controller-of-development-and-ageing" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">2</a>]. Targeting AP-1 and its associated pathways could lead to interventions that slow down or even prevent the onset of these diseases, marking a significant advancement in geriatric medicine.</p><p>Nefzger added that the aim is to prevent age-related diseases from escalating or – even better – occurring in the first place by addressing the underlying aging process, thereby enabling people to age in better health.</p><p>By focusing on the fundamental processes that drive aging, researchers aim to develop strategies that enhance healthspan, the period of life spent in good health, rather than merely extending lifespan. As the understanding of aging at the molecular level continues to evolve, future research will likely explore additional transcription factors and regulatory elements involved in this process, hopefully paving the way for innovative therapeutic approaches that address the challenges of aging.</p><p>[1] <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550413124002316?via%3Dihub" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1550413124002316?via%3Dihub</a><br>[2] <a href="https://www.uq.edu.au/news/article/2024/06/revealing-master-controller-of-development-and-ageing" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.uq.edu.au/news/article/2024/06/revealing-master-controller-of-development-and-ageing</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Speed limiters now mandatory in all new EU cars (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.autoweek.com/news/a61532276/mandatory-speed-limiters-europe-cars/</link>
            <guid>40919640</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 19:03:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.autoweek.com/news/a61532276/mandatory-speed-limiters-europe-cars/">https://www.autoweek.com/news/a61532276/mandatory-speed-limiters-europe-cars/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40919640">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.autoweek.com/news/a61532276/mandatory-speed-limiters-europe-cars/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Newpipe/yt-dlp stops working (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254</link>
            <guid>40919571</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 18:57:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254">https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40919571">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-turbo-body="">
      


    <div>
      <p><a href="#start-of-content" data-skip-target-assigned="false">Skip to content</a>

      <span data-view-component="true">
    <span data-view-component="true"></span>
</span></p><react-partial partial-name="keyboard-shortcuts-dialog" data-ssr="false">
  
  
  
</react-partial>




      

        

            


<header role="banner" data-color-mode="light" data-light-theme="light" data-dark-theme="dark">
  <h2>Navigation Menu</h2>

  

  <div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Actions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Actions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Packages&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Packages;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Security&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Security;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Codespaces&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Codespaces;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Copilot&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Copilot;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Code review&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Code review;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Issues&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Issues;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Product&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Discussions&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Discussions;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to GitHub Sponsors&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:GitHub Sponsors;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Open Source&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to The ReadME Project&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:The ReadME Project;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header dropdown (logged out), Enterprise&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Enterprise platform&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Enterprise platform;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>Enterprise platform</p><p>
        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Header menu top item (logged out)&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to go to Pricing&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_cta:Pricing;&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:TeamNewPipe/NewPipe" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="g_THo4CoxceQ-X1uG_GgsS-O4oCI0krJXHaF41jO_9BiXN9AAGnk_3puYHC9dFlxA2V4X14dporxbXbF_6_mVA" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="TeamNewPipe/NewPipe" data-current-org="TeamNewPipe" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-blackbird-indexed-repo-csrf="<esi:include src=&quot;/_esi/rails_csrf_token_form_hidden?r=kAMMq7MCwWl2eIlSZ8pgKESi9lwtQ%2FZ5266dEu6mS5XQ6MGJXCjEH50i53RWYPSJegcA1IJl%2FlJ2vR3WXG%2BXpiftDj6UXU1%2F0YsOCOp1LW901v2vl0536A33hnJkFFSgUigJj2jv67USYMqkXFwuI9w%2Fs198uc3e35GjUUOUFhPH0UwMwTqnqdrnI9k2QyysHZ4mM56Teb6Wmg2i4aC0D4nGM%2F1gXrW4UZRjE3%2B%2Bt1oh3Fw3eTWlkGMXOHLw6W1Fey92kuHCBCtcahU%2BzB60bK52dFiUTawYkP0N7IvhZEk%2Bl7Pb%2B8hkuVHTggO1RIDFtSeuI367jIHRgRl3nODKDVvgnSAGKhiixg%2BY7quGpjfmmcDJeqh1%2BWU2VLQAgOMOxhYQSgetWPiQsbzl5Jx%2FaI9s5NhLHG7VPoFaV%2FeGNBHEY2wCXdAspgQHLXBoy4NxWsrxb7zeWCRxig2nJxMmVndo6UMPm8oRXEEQnHG1m4x5J2iaFHxGOzeqsmVp6I9UaKQwvjEZhfH69UDiJm4ioZ0qb7xViQH4FCW2qPO%2F22FH1A%3D%3D--GChvq9%2BPf1cyoFQG--idrKUXEtuyMQOMJPrNXx7w%3D%3D&quot; />" data-nl-search-enabled="false">
  
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E%2Fvoltron%2Fissues_fragments%2Fissue_layout&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=TeamNewPipe%2FNewPipe" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="552edf3edb8b655b0ede4b27a40f81c2edae5047efc2e899a02bfcf84b335a7e" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>/voltron/issues_fragments/issue_layout;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a>
        </p></div>
      </div>
</header>

      
    </div>

  








    


    
    <include-fragment data-base-src="https://github.com/notifications/beta/shelf"></include-fragment>





  <div itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/SoftwareSourceCode" data-commit-hovercards-enabled="" data-discussion-hovercards-enabled="" data-issue-and-pr-hovercards-enabled="">
    <main id="js-repo-pjax-container">
      
  


  
      
    

    






  
  <div id="repository-container-header" data-turbo-replace="">

      <div id="repository-details-container" data-turbo-replace="">
            <ul>
    
        <li>
          <include-fragment src="/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/sponsor_button"></include-fragment>
        </li>

      

  <li>
            <a href="https://github.com/login?return_to=%2FTeamNewPipe%2FNewPipe" rel="nofollow" id="repository-details-watch-button" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;notification subscription menu watch&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;LOG_IN&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="d2de96004db01e4a338be4209845720b89e81f22062a9121c9a727d71efb393b" aria-label="You must be signed in to change notification settings" data-view-component="true">    Notifications
</a>    <tool-tip id="tooltip-ae06272a-6353-42d0-855a-48ddbfb615f4" for="repository-details-watch-button" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="description" data-view-component="true">You must be signed in to change notification settings</tool-tip>

    </li>

  <li>
          <a icon="repo-forked" id="fork-button" href="https://github.com/login?return_to=%2FTeamNewPipe%2FNewPipe" rel="nofollow" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;repo details fork button&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:41889031,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;LOG_IN&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="b062d057c376b8f9fce89c5a1c388cb637b23c7c0c92661f89a9e57c8b873cbb" data-view-component="true">    Fork
    <span id="repo-network-counter" data-pjax-replace="true" data-turbo-replace="true" title="2,952" data-view-component="true">3k</span>
</a>
  </li>

  <li>
        
  </li>

</ul>

        </div>

        


          <nav data-pjax="#js-repo-pjax-container" aria-label="Repository" data-view-component="true">

  
    <div data-view-component="true">      <action-menu data-select-variant="none" data-view-component="true">
  <focus-group direction="vertical" mnemonics="" retain="">
    <tool-tip id="tooltip-b1b1acc9-6407-4eff-a0d6-1a6d34ab3849" for="action-menu-94e008b4-26b2-409a-a3c5-18acb94ab9cc-button" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="label" data-view-component="true">Additional navigation options</tool-tip>


<anchored-position id="action-menu-94e008b4-26b2-409a-a3c5-18acb94ab9cc-overlay" anchor="action-menu-94e008b4-26b2-409a-a3c5-18acb94ab9cc-button" side="outside-bottom" anchor-offset="normal" popover="auto" data-view-component="true">
  </anchored-position>  </focus-group>
</action-menu></div>
</nav>

  </div>

  



<turbo-frame id="repo-content-turbo-frame" target="_top" data-turbo-action="advance">
    <div id="repo-content-pjax-container" data-morpheus-enabled="false" data-channel="eyJjIjoiaXNzdWU6MjM5ODU4MjI1MDp0aW1lbGluZSIsInQiOjE3MjA1NjA2MDN9--3c0fd2ec2de3c55600cafee9adbecd7726fbf774395d55a4ef86055216e79cf2" data-pjax="" data-turbo-frame="">

            
  <div id="partial-discussion-header" data-channel="eyJjIjoiaXNzdWU6MjM5ODU4MjI1MCIsInQiOjE3MjA1NjA2MDN9--0d028370320eb38dd3fd8a0c1a3b2a684c4ffa9f5537bb1127cb733b20e0d9d4" data-url="/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254/show_partial?partial=issues%2Ftitle&amp;sticky=true" data-gid="I_kwDOAn8tB86O93Xq">

          
<details>
  <summary>
    
    New issue
  </summary>
  <details-dialog aria-label="Sign up for GitHub">
            <div>
  <p>
    <strong>Have a question about this project?</strong> Sign up for a free GitHub account to open an issue and contact its maintainers and the community.
  </p>

  

  <p>By clicking “Sign up for GitHub”, you agree to our <a href="https://docs.github.com/terms" target="_blank">terms of service</a> and
  <a href="https://docs.github.com/privacy" target="_blank">privacy statement</a>. We’ll occasionally send you account related emails.</p>

  <p>
    Already on GitHub?
    <a data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;new issue modal&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;LOG_IN&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/issues/11254&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="b347db2c01b733c78bd83fcb4fd3bb2ab3d674d37a3fd999030338a75c4ca7ca" href="https://github.com/login?return_to=%2FTeamNewPipe%2FNewPipe%2Fissues%2Fnew%2Fchoose">Sign in</a>
    to your account
  </p>
</div>
  </details-dialog>
</details>
        
      </div>


              <div>
        <p><span>Labels</span></p><div>
            
<p><a id="label-02585f" href="https://github.com/TeamNewPipe/NewPipe/labels/template%20ignored" data-name="template ignored" data-view-component="true">
              <span>template ignored</span>
</a></p><tool-tip id="tooltip-d4e26d93-2f6e-4833-857f-340549eaa88a" for="label-02585f" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="description" data-view-component="true">The user didn't follow the template/instructions (or removed them)</tool-tip>
        </div>
      </div>


          
        </div>

</turbo-frame>


    </main>
  </div>

          




    <ghcc-consent id="ghcc" data-initial-cookie-consent-allowed="" data-cookie-consent-required="true"></ghcc-consent>


  

    <template id="site-details-dialog">
  <details class="details-reset details-overlay details-overlay-dark lh-default color-fg-default hx_rsm" open="">
    <summary role="button" aria-label="Close dialog"></summary>
    <details-dialog class="Box Box--overlay d-flex flex-column anim-fade-in fast hx_rsm-dialog hx_rsm-modal">
      <button class="Box-btn-octicon m-0 btn-octicon position-absolute right-0 top-0" type="button" aria-label="Close dialog" data-close-dialog="">
        <svg aria-hidden="true" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true" class="octicon octicon-x">
    <path d="M3.72 3.72a.75.75 0 0 1 1.06 0L8 6.94l3.22-3.22a.749.749 0 0 1 1.275.326.749.749 0 0 1-.215.734L9.06 8l3.22 3.22a.749.749 0 0 1-.326 1.275.749.749 0 0 1-.734-.215L8 9.06l-3.22 3.22a.751.751 0 0 1-1.042-.018.751.751 0 0 1-.018-1.042L6.94 8 3.72 4.78a.75.75 0 0 1 0-1.06Z"></path>
</svg>
      </button>
      <div class="octocat-spinner my-6 js-details-dialog-spinner"></div>
    </details-dialog>
  </details>
</template>

    

    <template id="snippet-clipboard-copy-button">
  <div class="zeroclipboard-container position-absolute right-0 top-0">
    <clipboard-copy aria-label="Copy" class="ClipboardButton btn js-clipboard-copy m-2 p-0" data-copy-feedback="Copied!" data-tooltip-direction="w">
      <svg aria-hidden="true" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true" class="octicon octicon-copy js-clipboard-copy-icon m-2">
    <path d="M0 6.75C0 5.784.784 5 1.75 5h1.5a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.5h-1.5a.25.25 0 0 0-.25.25v7.5c0 .138.112.25.25.25h7.5a.25.25 0 0 0 .25-.25v-1.5a.75.75 0 0 1 1.5 0v1.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 9.25 16h-7.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 0 14.25Z"></path><path d="M5 1.75C5 .784 5.784 0 6.75 0h7.5C15.216 0 16 .784 16 1.75v7.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 14.25 11h-7.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 5 9.25Zm1.75-.25a.25.25 0 0 0-.25.25v7.5c0 .138.112.25.25.25h7.5a.25.25 0 0 0 .25-.25v-7.5a.25.25 0 0 0-.25-.25Z"></path>
</svg>
      <svg aria-hidden="true" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true" class="octicon octicon-check js-clipboard-check-icon color-fg-success d-none m-2">
    <path d="M13.78 4.22a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.06l-7.25 7.25a.75.75 0 0 1-1.06 0L2.22 9.28a.751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018L6 10.94l6.72-6.72a.75.75 0 0 1 1.06 0Z"></path>
</svg>
    </clipboard-copy>
  </div>
</template>
<template id="snippet-clipboard-copy-button-unpositioned">
  <div class="zeroclipboard-container">
    <clipboard-copy aria-label="Copy" class="ClipboardButton btn btn-invisible js-clipboard-copy m-2 p-0 d-flex flex-justify-center flex-items-center" data-copy-feedback="Copied!" data-tooltip-direction="w">
      <svg aria-hidden="true" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true" class="octicon octicon-copy js-clipboard-copy-icon">
    <path d="M0 6.75C0 5.784.784 5 1.75 5h1.5a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.5h-1.5a.25.25 0 0 0-.25.25v7.5c0 .138.112.25.25.25h7.5a.25.25 0 0 0 .25-.25v-1.5a.75.75 0 0 1 1.5 0v1.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 9.25 16h-7.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 0 14.25Z"></path><path d="M5 1.75C5 .784 5.784 0 6.75 0h7.5C15.216 0 16 .784 16 1.75v7.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 14.25 11h-7.5A1.75 1.75 0 0 1 5 9.25Zm1.75-.25a.25.25 0 0 0-.25.25v7.5c0 .138.112.25.25.25h7.5a.25.25 0 0 0 .25-.25v-7.5a.25.25 0 0 0-.25-.25Z"></path>
</svg>
      <svg aria-hidden="true" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true" class="octicon octicon-check js-clipboard-check-icon color-fg-success d-none">
    <path d="M13.78 4.22a.75.75 0 0 1 0 1.06l-7.25 7.25a.75.75 0 0 1-1.06 0L2.22 9.28a.751.751 0 0 1 .018-1.042.751.751 0 0 1 1.042-.018L6 10.94l6.72-6.72a.75.75 0 0 1 1.06 0Z"></path>
</svg>
    </clipboard-copy>
  </div>
</template>




    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tokyo's oldest train line – in pictures (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2024/jul/08/tokyos-oldest-train-line-jr-yamanote-in-pictures</link>
            <guid>40919505</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 18:51:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2024/jul/08/tokyos-oldest-train-line-jr-yamanote-in-pictures">https://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/gallery/2024/jul/08/tokyos-oldest-train-line-jr-yamanote-in-pictures</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40919505">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-link-name="standfirst" data-component="standfirst">
    

        
            <meta itemprop="description" content="A reportage of the stations along the circular JR Yamanote line in Tokyo, capturing the hustle and bustle at the heart of the world’s biggest urban area. In service since 1885, the line is the city’s oldest, most important and most famous, with millions cramming on to the 35km (22-mile) route’s distinctive green cars every day">
        
    
    
        
            <p>A reportage of stations along the circular JR Yamanote line in Tokyo, capturing the hustle and bustle at the heart of the world’s biggest urban area. In service since 1885, the line is the city’s oldest, most important and most famous, with millions cramming on to the 35km (22-mile) route’s distinctive green cars every day</p>
        
    
    
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Judge dismisses DMCA copyright claim in GitHub Copilot suit (281 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/08/github_copilot_dmca/</link>
            <guid>40919253</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 18:25:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/08/github_copilot_dmca/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/08/github_copilot_dmca/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40919253">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Claims by developers that GitHub Copilot was unlawfully copying their code have largely been dismissed, leaving the engineers for now with just two allegations remaining in their lawsuit against the code warehouse.</p>
<p>The <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/01/12/github_copilot_copyright_case_narrowed/">class-action suit</a> against GitHub, Microsoft, and OpenAI was filed in America in November 2022, with the plaintiffs claiming the Copilot coding assistant was trained on open source software hosted on GitHub and as such would suggest snippets from those public projects to other programmers without care for licenses – such as providing appropriate credit for the source – thus violating the original creators' intellectual property rights.</p>
<p>Microsoft owns GitHub and uses OpenAI's generative machine-learning technology to power Copilot, which auto-completes source code for engineers as they type out comments, function definitions, and other prompts.</p>

    

<p>Ergo, the plaintiffs are unhappy that, in their view, portions of their copyrighted open source code might be provided – copied, rather – by Copilot to other programmers to use, without due credit given and other requirements of the original licenses honored.</p>

        


        

<p>The case started with 22 claims in all, and over time this has been whittled down as the defending corporations motioned to have the accusations thrown out of court, requests that Judge Jon Tigar has <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/05/12/github_microsoft_openai_copilot/">mostly</a> sustained.</p>
<p>In an <a target="_blank" href="https://regmedia.co.uk/2024/07/08/github_copilot_dismiss.pdf" rel="nofollow">order</a> [PDF] unsealed on Friday, July 5, Judge Tigar ruled on yet another batch of the plaintiffs' claims, and overall it was a win for GitHub, Microsoft, and OpenAI. Three claims were dismissed as requested and just one allowed to continue. According to a count by Microsoft and GitHub's lawyers, that leaves just two allegations standing in total.</p>

        

<p>The most recently dismissed claims were fairly important, with one pertaining to infringement under the Digital Millennium Copyright Act (DMCA), <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/17/1202">section 1202(b)</a>, which basically says you shouldn't remove without permission crucial "copyright management" information, such as in this context who wrote the code and the terms of use, as licenses tend to dictate.</p>
<p>It was argued in the class-action suit that Copilot was stripping that info out when offering code snippets from people's projects, which in their view would break 1202(b).</p>
<p>The judge disagreed, however, on the grounds that the code suggested by Copilot was not identical enough to the developers' own copyright-protected work, and thus section 1202(b) did not apply. Indeed, last year GitHub <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/06/09/github_copilot_lawsuit/">was said</a> to have tuned its programming assistant to generate slight variations of ingested training code to prevent its output from being accused of being an exact copy of licensed software.</p>

        

<p>The plaintiffs won't be able to offer a new section 1202(b) DMCA copyright claim as Judge Tigar dismissed the allegation with prejudice.</p>
<p>The anonymous programmers have repeatedly insisted Copilot could, and would, generate code identical to what they had written themselves, which is a key pillar of their lawsuit since there is an identicality requirement for their DMCA claim. However, Judge Tigar earlier ruled the plaintiffs hadn't actually demonstrated instances of this happening, which prompted a dismissal of the claim with a chance to amend it.</p>
<p>The amended complaint argued that unlawful code copying was an inevitability if users flipped Copilot's anti-duplication safety switch to off, and also cited <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.07646">a study</a> into AI-generated code in attempt to back up their position that Copilot would plagiarize source, but once again the judge was not convinced that Microsoft's system was ripping off people's work in a meaningful way.</p>
<p>Specifically, the judge cited the study's observation that Copilot reportedly "rarely emits memorized code in benign situations, and most memorization occurs only when the model has been prompted with long code excerpts that are very similar to the training data."</p>
<p>"Accordingly, plaintiffs’ reliance on a study that, at most, holds that Copilot may theoretically be prompted by a user to generate a match to someone else’s code is unpersuasive," he concluded.</p>
<p>The DMCA argument was, as we said, one of three claims just now tossed out. The other two were claims for unjust enrichment and punitive damages, though not with prejudice, meaning it's possible these claims could be amended and resubmitted. Until then, however, that leaves the standing claims at just two: an open source license violation allegation, and a breach of contract complaint that was previously reintroduced after being dismissed initially.</p>
<p>"We firmly believe AI will transform the way the world builds software, leading to increased productivity and most importantly, happier developers," GitHub said in a statement to <em>The Register</em>.</p>
<p>"We are confident that Copilot adheres to applicable laws and we’ve been committed to innovating responsibly with Copilot from the start. We will continue to invest in and advocate for the AI-powered developer experience of the future."</p>
<p>We also approached all parties in the lawsuit and their legal teams.</p>
<h3>Both sides squabble during discovery</h3>
<p>Also filed for the case on Friday was a joint case management <a target="_blank" href="https://regmedia.co.uk/2024/07/08/github_copilot_joint_management.pdf" rel="nofollow">statement</a> [PDF] chock full of various grievances and complaints each side made against the other over the discovery process, with both saying the other hasn't given up all the documents they were supposed to.</p>
<p>The plaintiffs accuse the defendants of deliberately dragging their feet, saying the documents that have been produced so far were already publicly available or should have been disclosed a long time ago. Much of the focus is on Microsoft and its single submitted document so far, something that the plaintiffs say makes no sense.</p>
<p>"That Microsoft employees were involved in many of these GitHub-sourced conversations demonstrates that Microsoft's production of one document thus far has been a function of delay and obfuscation, and nothing else," the anonymous developers said. "Microsoft has known but failed to disclose that its employees were directly involved in the creation, operation, and management of Copilot and its underlying models."</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/06/24/udio_suno_riaa/">Record labels gang up to sue AI music generator duo into utter oblivion</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/04/30/newspapers_microsoft_openai/">More big city newspapers drag Microsoft, OpenAI hard in copyright lawsuit</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/03/11/authors_file_lawsuit_to_torpedo/">Filing NeMo: Nvidia's AI framework hit with copyright lawsuit</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/04/22/ghaderi_v_amazon/">Ex-Amazon exec claims she was asked to ignore copyright law in race to AI</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The lack of documents from the Windows maker is apparently down to "technical difficulties" in collecting Slack messages, something the plaintiffs aren't convinced by. Similarly, the programmers say that OpenAI should have also submitted lots more information by now, pointing out that it had submitted tens of thousands as a <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/09/21/authors_guild_openai_lawsuit/">defendant</a> in the Authors Guild lawsuit.</p>
<p>Microsoft and GitHub, however, counter that the plaintiffs have been asking for way too much info, accusing them of having "failed to pursue relevant discovery of these topics efficiently and in good faith." One of these topics includes Microsoft's 2018 acquisition of GitHub.</p>
<p>Meanwhile, OpenAI says the plaintiffs haven't been following proper procedure in respect to asking for emails, saying it can't (or won't) produce any until it receives a correct request.</p>
<p>The corporate trio also say that the dismissal of the above DMCA copyright claim has fundamentally changed the case and argue that the scope of discovery should now be narrowed. This is something the plaintiffs dispute on the grounds that the open source license violation claim pertains to pretty much the same documents as the DMCA issue should bring up.</p>
<p>GitHub, Microsoft, and OpenAI say the plaintiffs haven't properly responded to their discovery requests, arguing that their documents include "JSON files, a blank HTML file, emails without any metadata, and improperly redacted PNG files of Slack and other messages."</p>
<p>The plaintiffs have asked for more time for discovery, and although the defendants argue this isn't necessary, the three tech titans say they're open to a "reasonable extension." ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Don't use 7-segment displays (2011) [pdf] (117 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://harold.thimbleby.net/cv/files/seven-segment.pdf</link>
            <guid>40918829</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 17:42:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://harold.thimbleby.net/cv/files/seven-segment.pdf">https://harold.thimbleby.net/cv/files/seven-segment.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40918829">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: How do browsers isolate internal audio from microphone input? (200 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40918152</link>
            <guid>40918152</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 16:45:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40918152">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="40918539"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918539" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918539&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The way this works (and I'm obviously taking a high level view here) is by comparing what is being played to what is being captured. There is an inherent latency in between what is called the capture stream (the mic) and the reverse stream (what is being output to the speakers, be it people taking or music or whatever), and by finding this latency and comparing, one can cancel the music from the speech captured.</p><p>Within a single process, or tree of processes that can cooperate, this is straightforward (modulo the actual audio signal processing which isn't) to do: keep what you're playing for a few hundreds milliseconds around, compare to what you're getting in the microphone, find correlations, cancel.</p><p>If the process aren't related there are multiple ways to do this. Either the OS provides a capture API that does the cancellation, this is what happens e.g. on macOS for Firefox and Safari, you can use this. The OS knows what is being output. This is often available on mobile as well.</p><p>Sometimes (Linux desktop, Windows) the OS provides a loopback stream: a way to capture the audio that is being played back, and that can similarly be used for cancellation.</p><p>If none of this is available, you mix the audio output and perform cancellation yourself, and the behaviour your observe happens.</p><p>Source: I do that, but at Mozilla and we unsurprisingly have the same problems and solutions.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919287"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918748"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918748" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918748&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It just seems more logical for the OS to do that, rather than the application. Basically every application that uses microphone input will want to do this, and will want to compensate for all audio output of the device, not just its own. Why does the OS not provide a way to do this?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40920538"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920538" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920538&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Why does the OS not provide a way to do this?</p><p>Some do.</p><p>But you need to have a strong-handed OS team that's willing to push everybody towards their most modern and highly integrated interfaces and sunset their older interfaces.</p><p>Not everybody wants that in their OS. Some want operating systems that can be pieced together from myriad components maintained by radically different teams, some want to see their API's/interfaces preserved for decades of backwards compatibility, some want minimal features from their OS and maximum raw flexibility in user space, etc</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40920688"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921324"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921324" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921324&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>As others have noted, this is trivial for most macOS and iOS apps to opt in to.</p><p>Frankly, I imagine its also available at the system level on Windows (and maybe Android and Linux) but probably only among applications that happen to be using certain audio frameworks/engines.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40918955"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918955" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918955&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; Basically every application that uses microphone input will want to do this</p><p>The OS doesn't have more information about this than applications and it's not that obvious whether an application wants the OS to fuck around with the audio input it sees. Even in the applications where this might be the obvious default behavior, you're wrong - since most listeners don't use loudspeakers at all, and this is not a problem when they wear headphones. And detecting that (also, is the input a microphone at all?) is not straightforward.</p><p>Not all audio applications are phone calls.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919806"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919806" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919806&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt;<i>The OS doesn't have more information about this than applications</i></p><p>the OP pointed out that this only works if he uses a browser monoculture</p><p>the OS does have more information than that, it can know what is being played by any/all apps, and what is being picked up by the mic</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40920152"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920152" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920152&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The "OS" isn't special here, apps can listen to system audio.</p><p>fwiw, you only need to know anything about outputs if you are doing AEC. Blind source separation doesn't have that problem and can just process the input stream.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921222"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921222" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921222&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&gt; The "OS" isn't special here, apps can listen to system audio.</p><p>Even if this is true, it's easy to imagine such functionality being exploited by malicious apps as a security and/or privacy concern, particularly if the user needs a screen reader.</p><p>It definitely makes sense for the operating system to provide this functionality.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40920103"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920103" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920103&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Assuming this isn't parody, the OS doesn't have to do it automatically. Having an application grab a microphone stream and say to the OS "take this and cancel any audio out streams" might be pretty useful.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40920206"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920206" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920206&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I agree with that, but the point I'm trying to make is that audio i/o handling is pretty complicated and application specific. The idea I'm challenging is that "any app that wants microphone input wants this" is dubious. I'd say it's only a small number of audio applications that care about mic input want background noise reduced - and it makes sense for this to be configured per-input stream.</p><p><i>Really</i> what would be nice is if every audio i/o backend supported multiplex i/o streams and you could configure whether or not to cancel audio based on that set of streams but not all output (because multi output-device audio gets tricky).</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921013"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921013" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921013&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I'm honestly having trouble thinking of a case where you wouldn't want this.</p><p>I'm sure there <i>are</i> some very niche cases, but in those cases, the application can specifically request that the OS turn off audio isolation.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921366"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="6"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="240"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921366" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921366&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Live video or audio chat is basically the only time you do want this. Granted, that’s a big chunk of microphone usage in practice, but any time you are doing higher fidelity audio recording and you have set up the inputs accordingly you absolutely do not want the artefacts introduced by this cancellation. DAWs, audio calibration, and even live audio when you’ve ensured the output cannot impact the recording all would want it switched off.</p><p>Default on vs default off is really just an implementation detail of the API though, as you say.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40921259"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="6"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="240"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921259" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921259&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>The technique introduces latency and distortion because it's subtracting an estimate of  sound that's traveling/reflecting in the listening environment, which is imperfect and involves the speed of sound.</p><p>That latency is within the tolerance that users are comfortable with for voice chat, and much less than video processing/transfer is introducing for video calls anyway, so it's a very obvious win there. Especially since those users are most interested in just picking out clear words using whatever random mic/speaker configuration happens to be most convenient.</p><p>But musicians, for instance, are much more interested in minimizing the delay between their voice or instrument being captured and returned through a monitor, and they generally choose a hardware arrangement that avoids the problem in the first place. And that's not really a niche use case.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="40919570"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919570" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919570&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The OS can have multiple sound input devices for the application to choose from, "raw" and "fuckarounded with"</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40920078"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920078" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920078&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>That doesn't make sense in the context of default devices. MacOS's AVKit (or is it CoreAudio?) APIs that configure the streams created on the device makes way more sense, since it's a property of the audio i/o stream and not the devices.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40919211"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919211" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919211&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>On mac/iOS, you get this using the AVAudioEngine API if you set voiceProcessingEnabled to true on the input node. It corrects for audio being played from all applications on the device.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921264"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921264" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921264&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This has certainly made conference calls significantly more usable. I feel like it must have come around during 2020, because I feel like pre-covid I would go around BEGGING everyone I did calls with to get a headset, because otherwise everyone else's voice would echo back through their microphone 0.75s later. Today I recently realized I could just literally do calls out loud on my laptop mic and speaker and somehow it works. Nice to know why!</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40919343"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919343" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919343&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>My first thought in reading the question was “if your <i>browser</i> is doing that, your platform architecture has… some room for improvement”.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921274"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40920866"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920866" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920866&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>This assumes there is an OS-managed software mixer sitting in the middle of all audio streams between programs and devices. Historically, that wasn't the case, because it would introduce a lot of latency and jitter in the audio. I believe it is still possible for a program to get exclusive access to an audio output device on Windows (WASAPI) and Linux (ALSA).</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40920328"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920328" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920328&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The OS doesn't know that the application doesn't want feedback from the speaker, and not 100% of applications will want such filtering.  I think a best practice from the OS side would be to provide it as an optional flag.  (Default could be on or off, with reasonable possibility for debate in either direction, but an app that really knows what it wants should be able to ask for it.)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40919007"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919007" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919007&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I suppose the OS probably makes something like this available, when using Voiceover on Mac and presenting in teams by default only the mic comes into teams, you need to do something to share the other processes audio.</p><p>That's mac of course but in my experience Windows is much more trusting of what it gives applications access to so I suppose the same thing is available there.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918789"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918789" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918789&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>How sure are you that Basically every application wants this? So should there be a flag at the os level for enabling the cancellation? How do you control that flag?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919511"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919511" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919511&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It would be trivial to pass that flag in whatever API the application calls to request access to the microphone stream.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40919272"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40918963"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919047"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919698"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="40918786"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918786" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918786&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>It's called Acoustic Echo Cancellation. An implementation is included in WebRTC included in Chrome. A FIR filter (1D convolution) is applied to what the browser knows is coming out of the speakers; and this filter is continually optimized to to cancel out as much as possible of what's coming into the microphone (this is a first approximation, the actual algorithm is more involved).</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919444"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40918941"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918941" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918941&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Search for the compilation flag "CHROME_WIDE_ECHO_CANCELLATION" in the Chromium sources, and you will find your answer.</p><p>Can't tell you anything else due to NDAs.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40919018"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40919018" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40919018&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>It's kind of nuts that (I'm assuming) the source code is publicly available but the developers who wrote it can't talk about it.</p><p>(I realize this situation isn't up to you and I appreciate that you chimed in as you could!)</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40920472"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40920472" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40920472&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>This is super common.</p><p>When I worked at Mozilla, most stuff was open, but I still couldn't talk about stuff publicly because I wasn't a spokesperson for Mozilla.  Same at OpenDNS/Cisco, or at Fastly, and now at Amazon.  Lots of stuff I can talk about, but I generally avoid threads and comments about Amazon, or if I do, it's strictly to reference public documentation, public releases, or that sort of thing.</p><p>It's easier to simply not participate, link a document, or say no comment than it is to cross reference what I might say against what's public, and what's not.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="40918753"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="40921252"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40921252" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40921252&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I seem to remember analog telephone lines used a very simple but magic-looking transformer-based circuit of some sort for this purpose. Presumably that worked because they didn’t need to worry about a processing delay?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40918731"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918731" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918731&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>A side effect of echo cancellation. Browser knows what audio it is playing, can correlate that to whatever comes in through the mic, maybe even by outputing inaudible test signals, or by picking wide supported defaults.</p><p>This is needed because many people don't use headphones and if you have more than one endpoint with mic and speakers open you will get feedback gallore if you don't do something to suppress it.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918624"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918624" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918624&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Google Meet uses source separation technology to denoise the audio. It's a neural net that's been trained to separate speech from non-speech and ensure that only speech is being piped through. It can even separate different speakers from one another. This technology got really good around 2021 when semi-supervised ways of training the models were developed, and is still improving :)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918993"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918497"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918497" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918497&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I think this would be part of echo cancellation: in a meeting you don't want the data from the meeting to be fed back to it. I suppose it uses the all the streams from the browser then, though I think in general it would be even better to cancel out everything that comes from the speakers. Maybe it can work this way on some other platforms?</p><p>E.g. PulseAudio and Pipewire have a module for echo cancellation.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918446"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40919073"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918770"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918770" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918770&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Since chrome has the data from both sources: the microphone, and the audio stream from YouTube, I imagine you can construct a filter from the impulse response of the YouTube source and then run the microphone through it</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918464"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918476"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918476" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918476&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>This is something that is usually taken care of by the App that's receiving the input from the microphone (Google Meet, Teams, etc). The App breaks the audio into frequencies, and the ones that correspond to human voice ranges are accepted, and anything else is rejected. This is referred to as, for example, voice isolation, and has been turned on by default in all major meeting Apps for a little while now.</p><p>Surprised to hear that it doesn't seem to work for you when the audio is generated by a different browser, this shouldn't make a difference.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="40918663"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918663" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918663&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Assuming OP is correct, your last sentence implies this isn't the solution being used.</p><p>Additionally, many (<i>citation needed</i>) Youtube videos have people talking in them; this method wouldn't help with that.</p><p>Isolating vocals in general is significantly more difficult than just relying on frequency range. Any instrument I can think of can generate notes that are squarely in the common range of a human (see: <a href="https://www.dbamfordmusic.com/frequency-range-of-instruments.html" rel="nofollow">https://www.dbamfordmusic.com/frequency-range-of-instruments...</a>)</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="40919167"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="40918468"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_40918468" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=40918468&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D40918152"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Guessing it's a feature of the WebRTC stack if it's to be found anywhere, there's always a requirement for cancelling feedback from other meeting participants</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="40919057"><td></td></tr>
            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google Chrome has a special hidden API accesible only from *.google.com (799 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/lcasdev/status/1810696257137959018</link>
            <guid>40918052</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 16:35:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/lcasdev/status/1810696257137959018">https://twitter.com/lcasdev/status/1810696257137959018</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40918052">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linksys Velop routers send Wi-Fi passwords in plaintext to US servers (449 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://stackdiary.com/linksys-velop-routers-send-wi-fi-passwords-in-plaintext-to-us-servers/</link>
            <guid>40917312</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 15:33:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://stackdiary.com/linksys-velop-routers-send-wi-fi-passwords-in-plaintext-to-us-servers/">https://stackdiary.com/linksys-velop-routers-send-wi-fi-passwords-in-plaintext-to-us-servers/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40917312">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page"><main id="main" tabindex="-1"><article><header data-canvas-grid="container" data-post-type="post" data-section="first" data-style="stack" data-has-featured-image="true"><div><div data-has-excerpt="true"><p>
It’s as if the routers themselves forgot the first rule of cybersecurity: don’t write your secrets on a postcard.</p></div><div><p>
<span>
<span>
<span>Published</span>
<time datetime="2024-07-09T15:32:29+00:00">
July 9, 2024		</time>
</span>
</span>
<span>
<span>
2 min read	</span>
</span></p></div></div><figure>
<img data-lazyloaded="1" src="data:image/svg+xml;base64,PHN2ZyB4bWxucz0iaHR0cDovL3d3dy53My5vcmcvMjAwMC9zdmciIHdpZHRoPSIxMjAwIiBoZWlnaHQ9IjY3NSIgdmlld0JveD0iMCAwIDEyMDAgNjc1Ij48cmVjdCB3aWR0aD0iMTAwJSIgaGVpZ2h0PSIxMDAlIiBzdHlsZT0iZmlsbDojY2ZkNGRiO2ZpbGwtb3BhY2l0eTogMC4xOyIvPjwvc3ZnPg==" width="1200" height="675" data-src="https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server.jpg" alt="Linksys Velop routers send Wi-Fi password in plaintext to US server" loading="eager" data-sizes="(min-width: 82.75em) 1284px, calc(100vw - 16px)" onload="this.setAttribute(&quot;data-loaded&quot;, true)" decoding="async" fetchpriority="high" data-srcset="https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server.jpg 1200w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-300x169.jpg 300w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-701x394.jpg 701w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-768x432.jpg 768w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-500x281.jpg 500w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-640x360.jpg 640w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-855x481.jpg 855w, https://stackdiary.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Linksys-Velop-routers-send-Wi-Fi-password-in-plaintext-to-US-server-1120x630.jpg 1120w"></figure></header><div><div><p>According to Testaankoop, the Belgian equivalent of the Consumers’ Association, two types of Linksys routers are <a href="https://www.test-aankoop.be/hightech/wifi-versterkers/nieuws/router-linksys-onveilig" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">sending Wi-Fi login details in plaintext</a> to American Amazon servers. This discovery involves the Linksys Velop Pro 6E and Velop Pro 7 mesh routers.</p><p>During routine installation checks, Testaankoop detected several data packets being transmitted to an Amazon server in the US. These packets included the configured SSID name and password in clear text, identification tokens for the network within a broader database, and an access token for a user session, potentially paving the way for a man-in-the-middle (MITM) attack.</p><blockquote><p>During installation, the router sent several data packets to an Amazon server in the US. These packets contained the configured SSID name and password in clear text, as well as some identification tokens for this network within a broader database and an access token for a user session that could potentially enable a MITM attack.</p>
<cite>Testaankoop</cite></blockquote><p>A MITM attack is a security breach in which an attacker intercepts communication between two parties without either party’s knowledge, allowing the attacker to read or alter the exchanged messages.</p><p>The consumer organization conducted these tests using the latest firmware available at the time. Despite warning Linksys in November, no effective measures have been taken. A firmware update appeared months later, but the problem persists. “We regret the lack of response from Linksys and expected more from such a renowned brand,” Testaankoop expressed.</p><p>Testaankoop suspects the security issue might stem from third-party software used in the Linksys firmware. However, they emphasize that this does not excuse the vulnerability. For those who already own the affected routers, they have recommended changing the Wi-Fi network name and password via the web interface instead of the app. This precaution prevents the SSID name and password from being transmitted in readable text.</p><p>Mesh routers like <a href="https://store.linksys.com/shop/shop-home/whole-home-mesh-wifi/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">the Velop series</a> are designed to improve Wi-Fi distribution in large or multi-story homes by creating a wireless network through multiple connected nodes. These nodes communicate either wirelessly or through cables to ensure better Wi-Fi coverage. However, the Velop Pro WiFi 6E and Pro 7’s data transmission practices undermine the security benefits they should provide.</p><p>Testaankoop contacted Linksys again just days before today’s publication in response to the ongoing issue, giving them a brief window to respond. However, they have not received any acknowledgment or solution from the manufacturer.</p><p>The vulnerability persists even in the latest Linksys 7 Pro, highlighting a critical security lapse. “After our long and intensive tests, we strongly advise against buying the Linksys Velop Pro WiFi 6E and Pro 7 because there is a serious risk of network intrusion and data loss,” the researchers concluded.</p><p><em>Stack Diary has also contacted Linksys to see if they plan on responding.</em></p></div><div data-author-bio="true"><h2>
<span>Posted by</span>
<a href="https://stackdiary.com/author/alex/">Alex Ivanovs</a></h2><p>Alex is the lead editor at <em>Stack Diary</em> and covers stories on tech, artificial intelligence, security, privacy and web development. He previously worked as a lead contributor for Huffington Post for their <em>Code</em> column.</p></div></div></article></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Another AI company wrote us and here’s our response (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://warandpeas.com/2024/07/09/another-ai-company-wrote-us-and-heres-our-response/</link>
            <guid>40917299</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 15:32:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://warandpeas.com/2024/07/09/another-ai-company-wrote-us-and-heres-our-response/">https://warandpeas.com/2024/07/09/another-ai-company-wrote-us-and-heres-our-response/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40917299">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

					
<main id="primary" role="main">

	
		
<article id="post-26587" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting" itemprop="blogPost">
	

	<div itemprop="articleBody">
		
		<h2>Why the current hype around AI is a slap in the face for creatives</h2>
<div>
<p>Almost every day we receive emails from AI companies who want to work with us. In these emails, someone cheerfully suggests a ‘collaboration’ in which they propose that we promote their product.</p>
<p>It is an understatement to say that these emails are in poor-taste. While we are usually interested in technology and try to remain optimistic about this field, we feel it’s necessary to speak out about the unbearable hype-cycle that generative AI has brought with it. A hype-cycle that has originated by stealing creative work, and now wishes to further damage creative energy by funnelling it into an automated content-creation nightmare.</p>
<p><em>Today we’d like to show you one of these emails and our response.</em></p>
<p><img decoding="async" data-attachment-id="26588" data-permalink="https://warandpeas.com/2024/07/09/another-ai-company-wrote-us-and-heres-our-response/response-to-muse-1/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?fit=2300%2C726&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="2300,726" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="response-to-muse-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?fit=300%2C95&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?fit=1024%2C323&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=768%2C242&amp;ssl=1" alt="A screenshot of an email from Muse to War and Peas. The email is written by a collaboration manager at Muse and discusses the platform's capabilities in creating AI-generated series. The email highlights several benefits of using Muse, such as making your own series with a script, bringing book characters to life, promoting new projects by creating mini-series, helping create content by building other worlds, and making stories come alive for the audience. The sender invites War and Peas to discuss potential collaboration and be among the first creators to gain an early advantage in content creation. The email is signed off by the collaboration manager." width="768" height="242" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=768%2C242&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=300%2C95&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=1024%2C323&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=1536%2C485&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=2048%2C646&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=1200%2C379&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=700%2C221&amp;ssl=1 700w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" data-recalc-dims="1" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20768%20242'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=768%2C242&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=300%2C95&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=1024%2C323&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=1536%2C485&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=2048%2C646&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=1200%2C379&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=700%2C221&amp;ssl=1 700w" data-lazy-src="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-1.jpg?resize=768%2C242&amp;ssl=1"></p>
<blockquote><p>Hi war.and.peas,</p>
<p>It’s XXX and I’m writing to you on behalf of Muse. Muse is a new creative platform that can create your own AI-generated series so you can dive into a new world of storytelling without the need for personal content creation.</p>
<p>For example, with Muse you can:</p>
<p>make your own series with your script/storyline<br>
bring your book characters to life<br>
promote your new project/book by creating a mini-series<br>
help create content by creating other worlds<br>
make your story come alive for your audience by creating a series about it.</p>
<p>Please let me know if you would like to discuss collaborating and becoming one of the first creators to gain an early advantage in the realm of content creation.</p>
<p>Best regards,<br>
<strong>XXX<br>
</strong>Collaboration Manager</p></blockquote>
<p>Here’s our response:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" data-attachment-id="26589" data-permalink="https://warandpeas.com/2024/07/09/another-ai-company-wrote-us-and-heres-our-response/response-to-muse-2/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?fit=2306%2C988&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="2306,988" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="response-to-muse-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?fit=300%2C129&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?fit=1024%2C439&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=768%2C329&amp;ssl=1" alt="A screenshot of an email response from War and Peas to Muse. The email is from Elizabeth Pich and Jonathan Kunz, a webcomic duo who have been creating original comics since 2011. They express their appreciation for being contacted but politely decline the offer to collaborate with Muse. They provide several reasons for their decision:

The rise of AI has been built on the work of creative individuals like themselves, without proper compensation or acknowledgment.
Social media platforms thrive on engaging, original content created by people, but creators have not been fairly rewarded.
Most artists love their work and prefer to be properly compensated rather than outsource their creativity to AI. They emphasize the personal nature of storytelling.
Artists would benefit more from AI tools that assist with administrative tasks rather than creative ones.
The email concludes by stating that the Muse platform does not align with their values, as it devalues creative work and promotes derivative content. They hope for a shift towards more inclusive, artist-focused approaches in the industry. The email is signed by Elizabeth Pich and Jonathan Kunz." width="768" height="329" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=768%2C329&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=300%2C129&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=1024%2C439&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=1536%2C658&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=2048%2C877&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=1200%2C514&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=700%2C300&amp;ssl=1 700w" sizes="(max-width: 768px) 100vw, 768px" data-recalc-dims="1" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20768%20329'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=768%2C329&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=300%2C129&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=1024%2C439&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=1536%2C658&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=2048%2C877&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=1200%2C514&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=700%2C300&amp;ssl=1 700w" data-lazy-src="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/response-to-muse-2.jpg?resize=768%2C329&amp;ssl=1"></p>
<blockquote><p>Dear XXX,</p>
<p>thank you for contacting us. We are a webcomic duo that has been creating original comics since 2011 and sharing them on various platforms on the web.</p>
<p>Usually we are very keen on connecting with potential partners that value our art and wish to help us in making a living. However, in this case we must politely decline. Here are some reasons why:</p>
<ul>
<li>The surge in AI has been built on the backs of creative people like us. Artists’ work has been harvested in order to train large language models and they have not been informed or compensated.</li>
<li>Social Media platforms cannot grow without engaging and original content, made by people. This is the basis for any user to join. Creators have – in large part – not been privy to the rewards that these platforms have generated over the years even though they are the reason for platform growth. Any business model that does not acknowledge this and does not seek proper compensation for artists is not of interest to us.</li>
<li>While being creative is surely not always fun, most artists love their work and do not want to outsource their passion to a machine that does this for them. They would much rather be properly compensated for their work in order to continue to be able to do said work. Frankly, storytelling “without the need for personal content creation” sounds horrible. Storytelling is personal. It is a connection between the writer and the reader. Without this personal connection, storytelling loses its purpose.</li>
<li>Artists would much rather have an AI that actually helps with grunt chores, such as writing invoices, or helping with taxes in order to focus more on fulfilling creative tasks. Such an AI-tool would be of much more value to the artist community.For these reasons, we hope it has become self-evident that your platform does not do anything for us. On the contrary, it works against a world in which creative work is valued and elevated. It turns creative work into an assembly-line meant to churn out derivative and soulless ‘content’ to supply the attention-factory that has become social media.We hope that these efforts will soon be seen as what they are and be quickly abandoned in favor of a more inclusive artist-focused approach.
<p>Best regards,<br>
Elizabeth Pich &amp; Jonathan Kunz</p></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div><p>Join our Patreon to get secret comics, behind the scenes, and more...</p><p><a rel="nofollow" target="_blank" href="https://patreon.com/warandpeas?utm_content=post_button&amp;utm_medium=patron_button_and_widgets_plugin&amp;utm_campaign=333887&amp;utm_term=&amp;utm_source=https://warandpeas.com/2024/07/09/another-ai-company-wrote-us-and-heres-our-response/" aria-label="Click to become a patron at Patreon!"><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/plugins/patron-button-and-widgets-by-codebard/images/become_a_patron_button.png?w=1500&amp;ssl=1" alt="Become a patron at Patreon!" data-recalc-dims="1" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%200%200'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-src="https://i0.wp.com/warandpeas.com/wp-content/plugins/patron-button-and-widgets-by-codebard/images/become_a_patron_button.png?w=1500&amp;ssl=1"></a></p></div>
		
			</div>

	
</article>

		
	
</main>



	



					
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CVE-2024-6409: OpenSSH: Possible remote code execution in privsep child (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/08/2</link>
            <guid>40916820</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 14:51:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/08/2">https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/08/2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40916820">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


<table>
<tbody><tr>

<td>
<a href="https://www.openwall.com/"><img src="https://www.openwall.com/logo.png" width="182" height="80" alt="Openwall"></a>
</td><td>
<div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/">Products</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/Owl/">Openwall GNU/*/Linux &nbsp; <i>server OS</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/lkrg/">Linux Kernel Runtime Guard</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/john/">John the Ripper &nbsp; <i>password cracker</i></a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/john/">Free &amp; Open Source for any platform</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/john/cloud/">in the cloud</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/john/pro/linux/">Pro for Linux</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/john/pro/macosx/">Pro for macOS</a>
</li></ul>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/wordlists/">Wordlists &nbsp; <i>for password cracking</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/passwdqc/">passwdqc &nbsp; <i>policy enforcement</i></a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/passwdqc/">Free &amp; Open Source for Unix</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/passwdqc/windows/">Pro for Windows (Active Directory)</a>
</li></ul>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/yescrypt/">yescrypt &nbsp; <i>KDF &amp; password hashing</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/yespower/">yespower &nbsp; <i>Proof-of-Work (PoW)</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/crypt/">crypt_blowfish &nbsp; <i>password hashing</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/phpass/">phpass &nbsp; <i>ditto in PHP</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/tcb/">tcb &nbsp; <i>better password shadowing</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/pam/">Pluggable Authentication Modules</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/scanlogd/">scanlogd &nbsp; <i>port scan detector</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/popa3d/">popa3d &nbsp; <i>tiny POP3 daemon</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/blists/">blists &nbsp; <i>web interface to mailing lists</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/msulogin/">msulogin &nbsp; <i>single user mode login</i></a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/php_mt_seed/">php_mt_seed &nbsp; <i>mt_rand() cracker</i></a>
</li></ul>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/services/">Services</a>
</li><li id="narrow-li-1"><a>Publications</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/articles/">Articles</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/presentations/">Presentations</a>
</li></ul>
</li><li><a>Resources</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/">Mailing lists</a>
</li><li><a href="https://openwall.info/wiki/">Community wiki</a>
</li><li><a href="https://github.com/openwall">Source code repositories (GitHub)</a>
</li><li><a href="https://cvsweb.openwall.com/">Source code repositories (CVSweb)</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/mirrors/">File archive &amp; mirrors</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/signatures/">How to verify digital signatures</a>
</li><li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/ove/">OVE IDs</a>
</li></ul>
</li><li id="last-li"><a href="https://www.openwall.com/news">What's new</a>
</li></ul>
</div>


</td></tr></tbody></table>




<a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/08/1">[&lt;prev]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/08/3">[next&gt;]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/04/2">[&lt;thread-prev]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/09/2">[thread-next&gt;]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/08/">[day]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/07/">[month]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2024/">[year]</a> <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/">[list]</a>
<pre>Date: Mon, 8 Jul 2024 18:21:06 +0200
From: Solar Designer &lt;solar@...nwall.com&gt;
To: oss-security@...ts.openwall.com
Cc: Qualys Security Advisory &lt;qsa@...lys.com&gt;
Subject: Re: CVE-2024-6387: RCE in OpenSSH's server, on glibc-based Linux systems

Hi,

Today is the coordinated release date to publicly disclose a related
issue I found during review of Qualys' findings, with further analysis
by Qualys.  My summary is:

CVE-2024-6409: OpenSSH: Possible remote code execution in privsep child
due to a race condition in signal handling

OpenSSH versions 8.7 and 8.8 and the corresponding portable releases
call cleanup_exit() from grace_alarm_handler() when running in the
privsep child process.  cleanup_exit() was not meant to be called from a
signal handler and may call other async-signal-unsafe functions.  The
current understanding is that in those upstream versions cleanup_exit()
would not actually call async-signal-unsafe functions under those
conditions, but with downstream distribution patches it sometimes does.
Specifically, openssh-7.6p1-audit.patch found in Red Hat's package of
OpenSSH adds code to cleanup_exit() that exposes the issue.  Relevantly,
this patch is found in RHEL 9 (and its rebuild/downstream
distributions), where the package is based on OpenSSH 8.7p1.

The audit patch is also found in Fedora, so the package versions that
were based on 8.7p1 and 8.8p1 are affected.  Per change log, it appears
that out of Fedora releases only 36 and 37 were affected, as well as
some updates maybe starting with those for 35 and until those for 37.
These versions are now end-of-life, and Fedora 38+ has moved to newer
upstream OpenSSH that doesn't make the problematic cleanup_exit() call.

The main difference from CVE-2024-6387 is that the race condition and
RCE potential are triggered in the privsep child process, which runs
with reduced privileges compared to the parent server process.  So
immediate impact is lower.  However, there may be differences in
exploitability of these vulnerabilities in a particular scenario, which
could make either one of these a more attractive choice for an attacker,
and if only one of these is fixed or mitigated then the other becomes
more relevant.  In particular, the "LoginGraceTime 0" mitigation works
against both issues, whereas the "-e" mitigation only works against
CVE-2024-6387 and not (fully) against CVE-2024-6409.  It may also be
possible to construct an exploit that would work against either
vulnerability probabilistically, which could decrease attack duration or
increase success rate.  That said, actual exploitation of CVE-2024-6409
has not yet been attempted and thus has not been proven.

I brought this extra issue to distros on June 26 and Qualys confirmed
and completed most of the analysis later same day.  Qualys later found
another issue with the audit patch, which is currently believed to be
mostly non-security.  I include it closer to the end of this message.

I'm sorry for not disclosing CVE-2024-6409 on the same day as
CVE-2024-6387, which would have saved many of us time (me included).
I agreed for the separate coordinated release date because apparently
Red Hat already had CVE-2024-6387 in the pipeline and wasn't ready to
add a fix for CVE-2024-6409 at the same time.

I quote relevant excerpts from the distros list discussion below:

On Wed, Jun 26, 2024 at 04:32:49AM +0200, Solar Designer wrote:
&gt; On Thu, Jun 20, 2024 at 01:26:52PM +0000, Qualys Security Advisory wrote:
&gt; &gt; A few days after we started our work on amd64, we noticed the following
&gt; &gt; bug report (in OpenSSH's public Bugzilla), about a deadlock in sshd's
&gt; &gt; SIGALRM handler:
&gt; &gt; 
&gt; &gt;   <a href="https://bugzilla.mindrot.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3690" rel="nofollow">https://bugzilla.mindrot.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3690</a>
&gt; 
&gt; Here's another curious one:
&gt; 
&gt; <a href="https://bugzilla.mindrot.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3286#c7" rel="nofollow">https://bugzilla.mindrot.org/show_bug.cgi?id=3286#c7</a>
&gt; 
&gt; In 2021, djm@ was wondering "why this is triggering when it wasn't
&gt; before" and "I still don't understand why this condition did not exist
&gt; previously."  I guess the reason was this same regression in the signal
&gt; handler.
&gt; 
&gt; The patch for the above issue conditionally replaced the call to
&gt; sigdie() with cleanup_exit(255), but I think that other call was also
&gt; async-signal-unsafe!
&gt; 
&gt; commit e3c032333be5fdbbaf2751f6f478e044922b4ec4
&gt; Author: djm@...nbsd.org &lt;djm@...nbsd.org&gt;
&gt; Date:   Fri May 7 03:09:38 2021 +0000
&gt; 
&gt;     upstream: don't sigdie() in signal handler in privsep child process;
&gt;     
&gt;     this can end up causing sandbox violations per bz3286; ok dtucker@
&gt;     
&gt;     OpenBSD-Commit-ID: a7f40b2141dca4287920da68ede812bff7ccfdda

&gt; -/* $OpenBSD: sshd.c,v 1.572 2021/04/03 06:18:41 djm Exp $ */
&gt; +/* $OpenBSD: sshd.c,v 1.573 2021/05/07 03:09:38 djm Exp $ */
&gt; 
&gt; So in OpenSSH 8.7p1 as used e.g. in RHEL 9, we have this:
&gt; 
&gt;         /* Log error and exit. */
&gt;         if (use_privsep &amp;&amp; pmonitor != NULL &amp;&amp; pmonitor-&gt;m_pid &lt;= 0)
&gt;                 cleanup_exit(255); /* don't log in privsep child */
&gt;         else {
&gt;                 sigdie("Timeout before authentication for %s port %d",
&gt;                     ssh_remote_ipaddr(the_active_state),
&gt;                     ssh_remote_port(the_active_state));
&gt;         }
&gt; 
&gt; So if patching that version, I think not only the body of sshsigdie()
&gt; should be #if 0'ed out, but also the above call to cleanup_exit(255);
&gt; replaced with _exit(1).
&gt; 
&gt; Indeed, that's also the difference between sshlogdie(), which uses
&gt; cleanup_exit(255), and sshsigdie(), which uses _exit(1).
&gt; 
&gt; This extra problematic logic only existed in upstream OpenSSH(-portable)
&gt; for ~9 months, having been removed with:
&gt; 
&gt; commit 4e62c13ab419b4b224c8bc6a761e91fcf048012d
&gt; Author: dtucker@...nbsd.org &lt;dtucker@...nbsd.org&gt;
&gt; Date:   Tue Feb 1 07:57:32 2022 +0000
&gt; 
&gt;     upstream: Remove explicit kill of privsep preauth child's PID in
&gt;     
&gt;     SIGALRM handler. It's no longer needed since the child will get terminated by
&gt;     the SIGTERM to the process group that cleans up any auth helpers, it
&gt;     simplifies the signal handler and removes the risk of a race when updating
&gt;     the PID. Based on analysis by HerrSpace in github PR#289, ok djm@
&gt;     
&gt;     OpenBSD-Commit-ID: 2be1ffa28b4051ad9e33bb4371e2ec8a31d6d663

&gt; -/* $OpenBSD: sshd.c,v 1.582 2021/11/18 03:07:59 djm Exp $ */
&gt; +/* $OpenBSD: sshd.c,v 1.583 2022/02/01 07:57:32 dtucker Exp $ */
&gt; 
&gt; which obviously left the (even worse) sshdie() intact.
&gt; 
&gt; In other words, depending on what exact cleanups are done, it may (or
&gt; may not, I haven't checked) have briefly been possible to exploit a race
&gt; condition of this sort not only in the parent (worse), but also in the
&gt; privsep child (relatively mild).  An extra vulnerability nevertheless,
&gt; maybe with different exploitability conditions - maybe exploitable even
&gt; on *BSD where sshdie() is not?

As a side note, I wrote *BSD above because I had found that syslog_r()
is also available on NetBSD, as well as on AIX and even Tru64, so
_maybe_ some builds of OpenSSH for some of those systems were not
affected by CVE-2024-6387.  We did not research this further.

&gt; Now, cleanup_exit() _might_ have actually be safe if called from this
&gt; place.  Upstream 8.7p1's is:
&gt; 
&gt; /* server specific fatal cleanup */
&gt; void
&gt; cleanup_exit(int i)
&gt; {
&gt;         if (the_active_state != NULL &amp;&amp; the_authctxt != NULL) {
&gt;                 do_cleanup(the_active_state, the_authctxt);
&gt;                 if (use_privsep &amp;&amp; privsep_is_preauth &amp;&amp;
&gt;                     pmonitor != NULL &amp;&amp; pmonitor-&gt;m_pid &gt; 1) {
&gt;                         debug("Killing privsep child %d", pmonitor-&gt;m_pid);
&gt;                         if (kill(pmonitor-&gt;m_pid, SIGKILL) != 0 &amp;&amp;
&gt;                             errno != ESRCH) {
&gt;                                 error_f("kill(%d): %s", pmonitor-&gt;m_pid,
&gt;                                     strerror(errno));
&gt;                         }
&gt;                 }
&gt;         }
&gt; #ifdef SSH_AUDIT_EVENTS
&gt;         /* done after do_cleanup so it can cancel the PAM auth 'thread' */
&gt;         if (the_active_state != NULL &amp;&amp; (!use_privsep || mm_is_monitor()))
&gt;                 audit_event(the_active_state, SSH_CONNECTION_ABANDON);
&gt; #endif
&gt;         _exit(i);
&gt; }

&gt; Further, RHEL 9 patched this to:
&gt; 
&gt; /* server specific fatal cleanup */
&gt; void
&gt; cleanup_exit(int i)
&gt; {
&gt;         static int in_cleanup = 0;
&gt;         int is_privsep_child;
&gt; 
&gt;         /* cleanup_exit can be called at the very least from the privsep
&gt;            wrappers used for auditing.  Make sure we don't recurse
&gt;            indefinitely. */
&gt;         if (in_cleanup)
&gt;                 _exit(i);
&gt;         in_cleanup = 1;
&gt;         if (the_active_state != NULL &amp;&amp; the_authctxt != NULL) {
&gt;                 do_cleanup(the_active_state, the_authctxt);
&gt;                 if (use_privsep &amp;&amp; privsep_is_preauth &amp;&amp;
&gt;                     pmonitor != NULL &amp;&amp; pmonitor-&gt;m_pid &gt; 1) {
&gt;                         debug("Killing privsep child %d", pmonitor-&gt;m_pid);
&gt;                         if (kill(pmonitor-&gt;m_pid, SIGKILL) != 0 &amp;&amp;
&gt;                             errno != ESRCH) {
&gt;                                 error_f("kill(%d): %s", pmonitor-&gt;m_pid,
&gt;                                     strerror(errno));
&gt;                         }
&gt;                 }
&gt;         }
&gt;         is_privsep_child = use_privsep &amp;&amp; pmonitor != NULL &amp;&amp; pmonitor-&gt;m_pid == 0;
&gt;         if (sensitive_data.host_keys != NULL &amp;&amp; the_active_state != NULL)
&gt;                 destroy_sensitive_data(the_active_state, is_privsep_child);
&gt;         if (the_active_state != NULL)
&gt;                 packet_destroy_all(the_active_state, 1, is_privsep_child);
&gt; #ifdef SSH_AUDIT_EVENTS
&gt;         /* done after do_cleanup so it can cancel the PAM auth 'thread' */
&gt;         if (the_active_state != NULL &amp;&amp;
&gt;             (the_authctxt == NULL || !the_authctxt-&gt;authenticated) &amp;&amp;
&gt;             (!use_privsep || mm_is_monitor()))
&gt;                 audit_event(the_active_state, SSH_CONNECTION_ABANDON);
&gt; #endif
&gt;         _exit(i);
&gt; }
&gt; 
&gt; from where it looks like other cleanup calls can be made even when
&gt; called from privsep child prior to authentication

&gt; In summary:
&gt; 
&gt; 1. I think the call to
&gt;                 cleanup_exit(255); /* don't log in privsep child */
&gt; should also be patched to _exit(1) in distro packages that have that
&gt; (perhaps those based on 8.7p1 and 8.8p1).
&gt; 
&gt; 2. The logic of upstream cleanup_exit() (but not necessarily distros')
&gt; is such that the call _may_ have been safe (unless the other race?)
&gt; 
&gt; 3. My analysis is incomplete.  I welcome further analysis by others -
&gt; Qualys, distros, and we could want to contact upstream (via Qualys?)
&gt; for comment even though the issue is already inadvertently fixed.
&gt; 
&gt; 4. If this is in fact an extra vulnerability (even if only exposed in a
&gt; distro?), should it perhaps get its own CVE?  It's different affected
&gt; versions range, which I think qualifies it for a different CVE.  (If
&gt; confirmed that this is in fact a vulnerability.)

On Wed, Jun 26, 2024 at 11:06:43AM +0000, Qualys Security Advisory wrote:
&gt; On Wed, Jun 26, 2024 at 04:32:49AM +0200, Solar Designer wrote:
&gt; &gt; Here's another curious one:
&gt; 
&gt; Well spotted! Yes, the version matches (8.5p1), this is definitely the
&gt; same root cause (sshsigdie() was called and it is doing something,
&gt; instead of just calling _exit(1)).
&gt; 
&gt; &gt; Now, cleanup_exit() _might_ have actually be safe if called from this
&gt; &gt; place.  Upstream 8.7p1's is:
&gt; 
&gt; Interesting, thanks! We have spent some time on this:
&gt; 
&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt; 2429 cleanup_exit(int i)
&gt; 2430 {
&gt; 2431         if (the_active_state != NULL &amp;&amp; the_authctxt != NULL) {
&gt; 2432                 do_cleanup(the_active_state, the_authctxt);
&gt; 2433                 if (use_privsep &amp;&amp; privsep_is_preauth &amp;&amp;
&gt; 2434                     pmonitor != NULL &amp;&amp; pmonitor-&gt;m_pid &gt; 1) {
&gt; 2435                         debug("Killing privsep child %d", pmonitor-&gt;m_pid);
&gt; 2436                         if (kill(pmonitor-&gt;m_pid, SIGKILL) != 0 &amp;&amp;
&gt; 2437                             errno != ESRCH) {
&gt; 2438                                 error_f("kill(%d): %s", pmonitor-&gt;m_pid,
&gt; 2439                                     strerror(errno));
&gt; 2440                         }
&gt; 2441                 }
&gt; 2442         }
&gt; 2443 #ifdef SSH_AUDIT_EVENTS
&gt; 2444         /* done after do_cleanup so it can cancel the PAM auth 'thread' */
&gt; 2445         if (the_active_state != NULL &amp;&amp; (!use_privsep || mm_is_monitor()))
&gt; 2446                 audit_event(the_active_state, SSH_CONNECTION_ABANDON);
&gt; 2447 #endif
&gt; 2448         _exit(i);
&gt; 2449 }
&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt; 
&gt; - The block at lines 2431-2442 is actually entered in the unpriv child,
&gt;   pre-auth, because both the_active_state and the_authctxt are set. The
&gt;   block at lines 2433-2441 is not entered in the unpriv child, so we can
&gt;   forget about this one.
&gt; 
&gt; - The lines 2445-2446 is not executed in the unpriv child, so we can
&gt;   forget about this one too.
&gt; 
&gt; - This leaves us with the call to do_cleanup() at line 2432:
&gt; 
&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt; 2643 do_cleanup(struct ssh *ssh, Authctxt *authctxt)
&gt; 2644 {
&gt; ....
&gt; 2647         debug("do_cleanup");
&gt; ....
&gt; 2662         if (options.use_pam) {
&gt; 2663                 sshpam_cleanup();
&gt; 2664                 sshpam_thread_cleanup();
&gt; 2665         }
&gt; ....
&gt; 2668         if (!authctxt-&gt;authenticated)
&gt; 2669                 return;
&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt; 
&gt; - The debug() call at line 2647 is not ideal, because it calls
&gt;   snprintf(), but we do not consider this to be a practical problem,
&gt;   because we do not know of an snprintf() implementation that calls
&gt;   malloc() (unless the format string uses positional arguments or
&gt;   floating points, which is not the case here).
&gt; 
&gt; - The calls to PAM functions at lines 2662-2665 are no-ops in the unpriv
&gt;   child, so not a problem either.
&gt; 
&gt; - And then do_cleanup() returns at lines 2668-2669, so OK.
&gt; 
&gt; Summary: we consider this upstream version to be safe (from a practical
&gt; point of view, i.e. despite the few calls to snprintf()).
&gt; 
&gt; &gt; Further, RHEL 9 patched this to:
&gt; 
&gt; Ouch, we had not seen this one; it is definitely a problem:
&gt; 
&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt; 2657 cleanup_exit(int i)
&gt; 2658 {
&gt; ....
&gt; 2681         if (sensitive_data.host_keys != NULL &amp;&amp; the_active_state != NULL)
&gt; 2682                 destroy_sensitive_data(the_active_state, is_privsep_child);
&gt; 2683         if (the_active_state != NULL)
&gt; 2684                 packet_destroy_all(the_active_state, 1, is_privsep_child);
&gt; ------------------------------------------------------------------------
&gt; 
&gt; - The call to destroy_sensitive_data() may or may not be a problem,
&gt;   because the "sensitive data" (private keys) were already destroyed in
&gt;   the unpriv child at that point.
&gt; 
&gt; - But the call to packet_destroy_all() is definitely a problem, because
&gt;   it calls packet_destroy_state(), which calls free() everywhere.
&gt; 
&gt; Summary: this patched version of cleanup_exit() makes the unpriv child
&gt; vulnerable too.
&gt; 
&gt; &gt; 1. I think the call to
&gt; &gt;                 cleanup_exit(255); /* don't log in privsep child */
&gt; &gt; should also be patched to _exit(1) in distro packages that have that
&gt; &gt; (perhaps those based on 8.7p1 and 8.8p1).
&gt; 
&gt; Agreed (by "patched" you mean "replace the call to cleanup_exit(255)
&gt; with a call to _exit(1)", right?).
&gt; 
&gt; &gt; 2. The logic of upstream cleanup_exit() (but not necessarily distros')
&gt; &gt; is such that the call _may_ have been safe
&gt; 
&gt; Agreed as well.

The below excepts are about an extra issue (beyond CVE-2024-6409) - the
audit patch's logging of SSH host key fingerprints apparently being
broken at least on RHEL 9.  This issue is only indirectly related to
CVE-2024-6409 because it explains why more async-signal-unsafe calls are
made than would have been otherwise.

On Thu, Jul 04, 2024 at 01:40:34AM +0000, Qualys Security Advisory wrote:
&gt; we found more information on the following:
&gt; 
&gt; On Wed, Jun 26, 2024 at 11:06:43AM +0000, Qualys Security Advisory wrote:
&gt; &gt; - The call to destroy_sensitive_data() may or may not be a problem,
&gt; &gt;   because the "sensitive data" (private keys) were already destroyed in
&gt; &gt;   the unpriv child at that point.
&gt; 
&gt; It is a problem: destroy_sensitive_data() calls malloc functions many
&gt; times (especially free()) because even if only the public keys remain in
&gt; sensitive_data.host_keys, they are still passed to sshkey_free().
&gt; 
&gt; In fact, destroy_sensitive_data() even ends up calling syslog() itself:
&gt; PRIVSEP(audit_destroy_sensitive_data()) calls mm_request_send(), which
&gt; can fail if the priv/parent process already _exit()ed, so fatal_f() is
&gt; called, which calls mm_log_handler(), which also fails because the priv/
&gt; parent process _exit()ed, so fatal_f() is called again, but this time it
&gt; calls syslog().
&gt; 
&gt; If you are wondering why destroy_sensitive_data() calls
&gt; PRIVSEP(audit_destroy_sensitive_data()) in the first place, we were
&gt; wondering too, because this should happen only if one of the keys is
&gt; private, and no private key should remain in the unpriv/child process!
&gt; This is actually a bug in sshkey_is_private(): for ed25519 keys, this
&gt; function checks ed25519_pk, which is the public key! It should check
&gt; ed25519_sk instead, which is the secret/private key.

On Sun, Jul 07, 2024 at 11:21:37PM +0200, Solar Designer wrote:
&gt; Thank you for reporting this to distros.  I don't see this function in
&gt; any upstream version at all - do you?  I see it being added via
&gt; openssh-7.6p1-audit.patch in Red Hat's package.  I don't know if an
&gt; equivalent patch is maybe also added in some other distros?
&gt; 
&gt; As to security consequences, at first my concern was this could leave
&gt; secret host keys around in privsep child.  However, upon a closer look
&gt; the only thing audit_destroy_sensitive_data() does is log a message, so
&gt; the only impact is erroneous audit logging.

&gt; Actual processing of keys is untouched by this patch, so probably
&gt; remains correct.

On Mon, Jul 08, 2024 at 05:23:22PM +0200, Solar Designer wrote:
&gt; On Mon, Jul 08, 2024 at 03:00:37PM +0000, Qualys Security Advisory wrote:
&gt; &gt; On Mon, Jul 08, 2024 at 03:35:29PM +0200, Solar Designer wrote:
&gt; &gt; &gt; [...] with RH's original code
&gt; &gt; &gt; I saw the same key's destruction logged 3 times.  I think some of those
&gt; &gt; &gt; were not from the unprivileged child, and actually made sense.  So I was
&gt; &gt; &gt; hoping that fixing the check from pk to sk would suppress only the
&gt; &gt; &gt; erroneous logging from the unprivileged child, but in my testing it
&gt; &gt; &gt; suppressed all of it.
&gt; &gt; 
&gt; &gt; [...] I think that I have
&gt; &gt; found the solution to this mystery, but I have not yet investigated the
&gt; &gt; consequences (if any): the private host keys are "shielded" as soon as
&gt; &gt; they are loaded (by sshkey_shield_private()), which means that, to the
&gt; &gt; (non-buggy) tests in sshkey_is_private(), they look like public keys,
&gt; &gt; but the private part is actually there, in another part of the key
&gt; &gt; structure, in encrypted form.

&gt; The shielding was added upstream in:
&gt; 
&gt; commit 4f7a56d5e02e3d04ab69eac1213817a7536d0562
&gt; Author: djm@...nbsd.org &lt;djm@...nbsd.org&gt;
&gt; Date:   Fri Jun 21 04:21:04 2019 +0000
&gt; 
&gt;     upstream: Add protection for private keys at rest in RAM against
&gt;     
&gt;     speculation and memory sidechannel attacks like Spectre, Meltdown, Rowhammer
&gt;     and Rambleed. This change encrypts private keys when they are not in use with
&gt;     a symmetic key that is derived from a relatively large "prekey" consisting of
&gt;     random data (currently 16KB).
&gt; 
&gt; which is newer than 7.6p1 that openssh-7.6p1-audit.patch was presumably
&gt; based on.  So it is possible that this audit logging was more functional
&gt; initially (sans this bug for ed25519 you found), but mostly broke when
&gt; it was rebased on newer versions without consideration for the change
&gt; above.  However, that's just a guess, which I did not confirm.  A way to
&gt; confirm it could be to test a Red Hat package that already has the audit
&gt; patch, but does not yet have upstream's shielding.  Since the above
&gt; upstream commit isn't in 8.0 (it's about 1 week newer than V_8_0 tag),
&gt; maybe RHEL 8 is suitable for this test (its package is based on 8.0p1).
&gt; 
&gt; ... and indeed, on a RHEL 8 rebuild system I see "msg='op=destroy
&gt; kind=server fp=SHA256:" /var/log/audit/audit.log lines with 3 different
&gt; fingerprint values, presumably corresponding to the different key types.
&gt; This is different from the RHEL 9 rebuild system I checked before, where
&gt; only one fingerprint value would be seen despite of the system also
&gt; having 3 different host key types.

In the public disclosure of CVE-2024-6387, Qualys wrote:

On Mon, Jul 01, 2024 at 08:40:06AM +0000, Qualys Security Advisory wrote:
&gt; We decided to target Rocky Linux 9 (a Red Hat Enterprise Linux 9
&gt; derivative), from "Rocky-9.4-x86_64-minimal.iso", for two reasons:
&gt; 
&gt; - its OpenSSH version (8.7p1) is vulnerable to this signal handler race
&gt;   condition and its glibc is always mapped at a multiple of 2MB (because
&gt;   of the ASLR weakness discussed in the previous "Theory" subsection),
&gt;   which makes partial pointer overwrites much more powerful;
&gt; 
&gt; - the syslog() function (which is async-signal-unsafe but is called by
&gt;   sshd's SIGALRM handler) of this glibc version (2.34) internally calls
&gt;   __open_memstream(), which malloc()ates a FILE structure in the heap,
&gt;   and also calls calloc(), realloc(), and free() (which gives us some
&gt;   much-needed freedom).
&gt; 
&gt; With a heap corruption as a primitive, two FILE structures malloc()ated
&gt; in the heap, and 21 fixed bits in the glibc's addresses, we believe that
&gt; this signal handler race condition is exploitable on amd64 (probably not
&gt; in ~6-8 hours, but hopefully in less than a week). Only time will tell.

FWIW, we patched CVE-2024-6387 in Rocky Linux SIG/Security and CIQ 9.2
LTS on July 1, and here's the patch we're getting into both today:

$ cat openssh-8.7p1-rocky-CVE-2024-6409.patch
diff -urp openssh-8.7p1-38.el9_4.1-tree.orig/sshd.c openssh-8.7p1-38.el9_4.1-tree/sshd.c
--- openssh-8.7p1-38.el9_4.1-tree.orig/sshd.c	2024-07-08 03:42:51.431994307 +0200
+++ openssh-8.7p1-38.el9_4.1-tree/sshd.c	2024-07-08 03:48:13.860316451 +0200
@@ -384,7 +384,7 @@ grace_alarm_handler(int sig)
 
 	/* Log error and exit. */
 	if (use_privsep &amp;&amp; pmonitor != NULL &amp;&amp; pmonitor-&gt;m_pid &lt;= 0)
-		cleanup_exit(255); /* don't log in privsep child */
+		_exit(1); /* don't log in privsep child */
 	else {
 		sigdie("Timeout before authentication for %s port %d",
 		    ssh_remote_ipaddr(the_active_state),

We'll update the Rocky Linux SIG/Security wiki shortly (didn't do this
in advance in order to push this public disclosure out to all first):

<a href="https://sig-security.rocky.page/packages/openssh/" rel="nofollow">https://sig-security.rocky.page/packages/openssh/</a>

The weakening of ASLR bothers me, but is to be discussed separately.

Alexander
</pre>
<p><a href="http://www.openwall.com/blists/">Powered by blists</a> - <a href="http://lists.openwall.net/">more mailing lists</a>


</p><p>
Please check out the
<a href="https://oss-security.openwall.org/wiki/">
Open Source Software Security Wiki</a>, which is counterpart to this
<a href="https://oss-security.openwall.org/wiki/mailing-lists/oss-security">mailing list</a>.
</p><p>
Confused about <a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/">mailing lists</a> and their use?
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electronic_mailing_list">Read about mailing lists on Wikipedia</a>
and check out these
<a href="https://www.complang.tuwien.ac.at/anton/mail-news-errors.html">guidelines on proper formatting of your messages</a>.
</p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Turbopuffer: Fast search on object storage (264 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://turbopuffer.com/blog/turbopuffer</link>
            <guid>40916786</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 14:48:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://turbopuffer.com/blog/turbopuffer">https://turbopuffer.com/blog/turbopuffer</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40916786">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><a title="Go back to blog" href="https://turbopuffer.com/blog"><svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="12" height="12" viewBox="0 0 24 24" fill="none" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" stroke-linejoin="round"><path d="M18 6 6 18"></path><path d="m6 6 12 12"></path></svg></a><div><p><span>July 08, 2024</span><span>•</span><span>Simon Hørup Eskildsen (Co-founder &amp; CEO)</span></p></div><p>In late 2022 I was helping my friends at Readwise scale their infrastructure
ahead of the launch of <a target="_blank" href="https://readwise.io/read">Readwise Reader</a> (read-it-later app). We wanted
to build a highly requested feature: article recommendations and semantic search
using vector embeddings. Readwise was paying ~$5k/month for their relational
database, but we found that vector search on the same 100m+ documents would've
cost $20k/month+! This wasn't just expensive; it meant we had to shelve a
desired feature until costs came down.</p>
<p>It gnawed at me for months. A promising feature, postponed solely due to
infrastructure costs? Surely these exorbitant prices weren't rooted in some
immutable law of physics. Had we simply failed to create a search engine that
truly harnessed the power of modern hardware and services?</p>
<p>As I went deeper, painful memories of search outages from my early days on
Shopify’s infrastructure team started flashing. The existing solutions aren’t
just expensive, they’re also incredibly difficult to operate at scale. It was
clear to me that a lot had changed since the current generation of search
engines were designed: object storage is now ubiquitous, NVMe SSDs have become
incredibly fast and affordable, and AI &amp; vectors means we’re asking more from
our search systems than before.</p>
<p>In 2022, production-grade vector databases were relying on in-memory storage at
$2+ per GB, not counting the extra cost for durable disk storage. This is the
most expensive way to store data. You can improve this by moving to disk, with
triply replicated SSDs at 50% storage utilization which will run you $0.6 per
GB. But we can do even better by leveraging object storage (like S3 or GCS) at
around $0.02 per GB, with SSD caching at $0.1 per GB for frequently accessed
data. That’s up to 100x cheaper than memory for cold storage, and 6-20x cheaper
for warm storage!</p>
<p>That’s when I decided this is what I wanted to do: build a search engine as you
would build it in 2023 (the year development started). One where cost maps
better to value, so features that aren’t being built today will get built. <a target="_blank" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jevons_paradox">When
you make gas 20% cheaper, people drive 40% more.</a> Coupled with the
tailwinds of retrieval in AI, it seemed like the right time to start building
this was yesterday.</p>
<p>Fast forward to today, and turbopuffer offers a new approach to search,
combining cost efficiency with high performance. By leveraging object storage
and smart caching, we've built a solution that scales effortlessly to billions
of vectors and millions of tenants/namespaces. We’ve heard loud and clear from
our customers they have felt constrained by retrieval costs in their product
ambition. <strong>We want to make it possible for our customers to search every byte
they have.</strong></p>
<pre><code>
                        ╔═turbopuffer══════════════════════════════╗ 
╔════════════╗          ║                                          ║░
║            ║░         ║  ┏━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┓     ┏━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┓  ║░
║   client   ║░───API──▶║  ┃    Memory/    ┃────▶┃    Object    ┃  ║░
║            ║░         ║  ┃   SSD Cache   ┃     ┃ Storage (S3) ┃  ║░
╚════════════╝░         ║  ┗━━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┛     ┗━━━━━━━━━━━━━━┛  ║░
 ░░░░░░░░░░░░░░         ║                                          ║░
                        ╚══════════════════════════════════════════╝░
                         ░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░░
</code></pre>
<h2 id="the-five-common-databases">The Five Common Databases</h2>
<p>Let's take a step back to see how search engines fit into the broader
infrastructure stack and how their requirements differ from other types of
databases.</p>
<p>Companies typically start with a relational database (Postgres/MySQL) and
gradually extract parts of their workload to ~5 specialized databases for
performance, cost, and scalability. Searching a few million documents in your
relational database is unlikely to cause issues. Any concerns at that scale are
outweighed by the overhead of operating another database. But, with sufficient
scale you start feeling like a butcher with a Swiss Army Knife. You'll know
you've hit this point when the same workload keeps showing up in the database
query profiles during problems.</p>
<p>The five most common specialized databases in the modern infra stack are:</p>

<p>The storage architecture of the current generation of search engines simply
doesn’t map closely enough to the performance characteristics and cost
constraints of search. We can do better by moving from the old world of
replicated SSDs to object storage with SSD and memory caching.</p>
<h2 id="a-search-engine-on-object-storage">A Search Engine on Object Storage</h2>
<pre><code>First Principle Storage Costs

RAM + 3x SSD        | ████████████████████████████████████████ $3600.00/TB/month (incumbents)
RAM Cache† + 3x SSD | █████████████████ $1600.00/TB/month (incumbents, relational databases)
3x SSD              | ██████ $600.00/TB/month
S3 + SSD Cache†     | █ $70.00/TB/month (turbopuffer)
S3                  |  $20.00/TB/month

*: 50% disk utilization
†: 50% in cache
1TB: 120M documents with 1536 dimensional vectors and 2KB text data
</code></pre>
<p>The current generation of search engines are built using the replicated disk
architecture typical of relational databases. This setup is excellent for low
latency, extremely high concurrency for updates, and transactions. However,
search engines don’t require all this! Their write workload is more akin to a
data warehouse: high write throughput, no transactions, and more relaxed latency
requirements, especially for writes. Consequently, for search engines we end up
paying a serious premium for storage performance characteristics we don’t need!</p>
<p>Unlike data warehouses, search queries do need to finish in &lt;100ms rather than
seconds. Because requests to object storage take more than 100ms, we still need
to reduce latency with an SSD/memory cache for the actively searched data.</p>
<p>Occasionally, you might get a cold query from object storage that takes a few
hundred milliseconds if a node dies or the dataset has been evicted from the
cache. For most search use-cases, the savings are well worth the latency hit of
an occasional cold query</p>
<p>This design allows freely walking the tradeoffs between cheap, cold, slow
storage, and warm, expensive, fast storage. The architecture is just as fast for
warm queries, but cheaper than alternatives that require more copies of the data
for durability. For infrequently accessed data, turbopuffer’s design is more
than an order of magnitude cheaper. The design especially shines when only
subsets of the data (e.g. tenants) are active at once.</p>
<h2 id="object-storage-native-database">Object Storage Native Database</h2>
<p>We set out to build a database that fully leverages this architecture. Not only
is it highly cost-effective, but being backed by object storage offers
unparalleled reliability and virtually unlimited scalability. In addition, if
something is queried enough and makes it all the way to the small memory cache,
there is no reason why hot queries can’t be as fast as in another architecture.</p>
<p>Justin (CTO) and I learned the hard way during our 5+ years on the last-resort
pager at Shopify that the fewer stateful dependencies, the more nines of uptime.
This is why turbopuffer has no  dependencies in the critical path other than
object storage. From day one, turbopuffer has employed multi-tenancy and
sharding, which we know from our days of protecting shops from each other at
Shopify is paramount for reliability. This architecture is a major reason we’ve
been able to maintain 99.99% uptime since launch.</p>
<p>To achieve this, we have built a storage engine native to object storage. This
is not tiering, where cold data is eventually replicated to object storage: it
is an object-storage-first storage engine where object storage is the source of
truth (LSM). Writes are durably committed to object storage. Existing storage
engine/LSM implementations don't apply here because the rules are different on
object storage: any node can compact data, latency is high, throughput is
phenomenal, individual writes are expensive, and storage is cheap. Each search
namespace is simply a prefix on object storage. If a node dies, another will
load into cache after a cold query (~500ms). We don't sell "High Availability"
(HA) at an extra cost, as any node can serve traffic for any namespace (though
we do attempt to route traffic to consistent nodes for cache locality). If you
want our HA number, I’ll just send you the current <code>kubectl get pods | wc -l</code>.
Additionally, because much of our compute runs on spot nodes, we constantly
exercise this failure path.</p>
<p>In order to optimize cold latency, the storage engine carefully handles
roundtrips to object storage. The query planner and storage engine have to work
in concert to strike a delicate balance between downloading more data per
roundtrip, and doing multiple roundtrips (P90 to object storage is around 250ms
for &lt;1MB). For example, for a vector search query, we aim to limit it to a
maximum of three roundtrips for sub-second cold latency.</p>
<p>We are continually working to reduce latency and have many tricks up our sleeve
to improve both cold and warm latency over time. For most production search
applications, the current performance is already excellent:</p>
<pre><code>1M 768 dimensional vectors (3 GB)

Cold Query Latency  | █████████████████████████████████████████ (512ms)
Warm Query Latency  | ██ (37ms P90)
</code></pre>
<p>You can read more about our <a target="_blank" href="https://turbopuffer.com/architecture">architecture</a>, our <a target="_blank" href="https://turbopuffer.com/docs/roadmap">roadmap</a>, and current <a target="_blank" href="https://turbopuffer.com/docs/limits">limitations</a>.</p>
<h2 id="customers">Customers</h2>
<p>Our first large customer was <a target="_blank" href="https://cursor.com/">Cursor</a>, the AI Code Editor. Each codebase is
turned into a vector index to power various features. Cursor manages billions of
vectors in millions of codebases. With their previous provider, they had to
carefully <a target="_blank" href="https://x.com/amanrsanger/status/1730763587944398874">binpack codebases</a> to nodes/indexes to manage cost and
complexity. In addition, the costs were astronomical, as every index was kept in
memory, despite only a subset of code-bases being active at any point in time.
Cursor's use-case was a perfect fit for turbopuffer’s architecture.</p>
<p>Cursor moved everything in a few days in November of last year, and immediately
saw their costs drop 10x with great cold and warm latency. In addition to their
natural growth, it wasn’t long before Cursor started creating more vectors per
user than before, as infrastructure cost and customer value started mapping far
better. Cursor <em>never</em> stores plain text code with turbopoffer, and goes even
further applying a unique vector transformation per code base to make vec2text
attacks extremely difficult.</p>
<p>turbopuffer also powers <a target="_blank" href="https://suno.com/">Suno’s radio feature</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://new.computer/">Dot’s
memory</a> (by New Computer), the memory of
<a target="_blank" href="https://shapes.inc/home">Shapes</a>, and
<a target="_blank" href="https://fixie.ai/blog/best-vdb-2023">many</a> <a target="_blank" href="https://www.getmerlin.in/">more</a>.</p>
<h2 id="turbopuffer-o">turbopuffer &lt;(°O°)&gt;</h2>
<p>We are <em>very</em> much in production, but currently open by application only, as we
focus on optimizing turbopuffer for our early customers. <a target="_blank" href="https://turbopuffer.com/join">Let us know if you are
a good fit.</a> We hope you’ll trust us with your
queries.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Evolve Bank and Trust confirms LockBit stole 7.6M people's data (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/09/evolve_lockbit_attack/</link>
            <guid>40916260</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 14:01:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/09/evolve_lockbit_attack/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/09/evolve_lockbit_attack/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40916260">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Evolve Bank &amp; Trust says the data of more than 7.6 million customers was stolen during the LockBit break-in in late May, per a fresh filing with Maine's attorney general.</p>
<p>The filing <a target="_blank" href="https://www.maine.gov/agviewer/content/ag/985235c7-cb95-4be2-8792-a1252b4f8318/a2e61e38-f78d-403d-9abb-3810771bb5d2.html">lists</a> the total number of persons affected (including residents) at 7,640,112.</p>
<p>It's the first time Evolve has confirmed the scale of the data theft – which affected at least three of its major partners, past and present – and it expects the number to rise as its investigations continue.</p>

    

<p>Both Wise and Affirm, international money transfer and buy-now-pay-later companies respectively, confirmed in SEC filings last week that they were both materially affected by the break-in at Evolve.&nbsp;</p>

        


        

<p>Wise severed ties with Evolve last year but was still impacted by <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/02/affirm_evolve_ransomware_breach/">the incident</a>. Mercury also suggested it could be affected.</p>
<p>However, none of the company's partners have yet revealed the extent to which the <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/07/alleged_lockbit_kingpin_charged_sanctioned/">ransomware crew</a> that cops allege is headed by Dmitry Khoroshev managed to pillage their customers' data.</p>

        

<p><em>The Register</em> approached all 15 partners listed on Evolve's website and only received a response from one other company, Melia, and the last we heard it was probing any potential impact rather than confirming anything.</p>
<p>As for Evolve, its <a target="_blank" href="https://www.maine.gov/agviewer/content/ag/985235c7-cb95-4be2-8792-a1252b4f8318/a2e61e38-f78d-403d-9abb-3810771bb5d2.html" rel="nofollow">letter</a> to customers reads: "On May 29, 2024, Evolve identified that some of its systems were not working properly.</p>
<p>"While it initially appeared to be a hardware failure, we subsequently learned it was unauthorized activity.</p>

        

<p>"Evolve promptly initiated its incident response processes and stopped the attack. No new unauthorized activity on Evolve's systems has been identified since May 31, 2024. An investigation with assistance from a cybersecurity firm was initiated to investigate what happened and what data may have been impacted. Evolve also notified law enforcement and worked to add further protections to harden its systems."</p>
<p>The Banking-as-a-Service provider went on to say that although it may have enacted its incident response playbook when it spotted signs of foul play, it took the vendor roughly four months to detect the intrusion.</p>
<p>"There is no evidence that the threat actors accessed any customer funds, but it appears the threat actors did access and download customer information from Evolve's databases and a file share during periods in February and May 2024."</p>
<p>The letters sent to affected individuals are usually attached to filings with state attorneys general, but typically omit details such as the specific data types stolen in each case.</p>
<p>Some customers may have had names and addresses stolen, while others may have had their social security numbers taken as well, for example.</p>
<p>We know from Evolve's <a target="_blank" href="https://www.getevolved.com/about/news/cybersecurity-incident/" rel="nofollow">earlier disclosure</a> that SSNs, bank account numbers, and contact information "for most" of its personal banking customers and partners may be affected, as well as some staff.</p>
<p>That disclosure, last updated on July 8, also stated that this week's notification letters are expected to be a first round with additional, smaller rounds of notifications to come in the following weeks.</p>
<p>Evolve has offered impacted individuals 24 months of credit monitoring, as is often the case in major data leaks. Victims have until October 31 to enroll for these services, and the full instructions on how to do so are included in an email to be sent in the next two weeks.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/09/eldorado_ransomware_linux_windows/">Eldorado ransomware-as-a-service gang targets Linux, Windows systems</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/08/avast_secretly_gave_donex_ransomware/">Avast secretly gave DoNex ransomware decryptors to victims before crims vanished</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/02/affirm_evolve_ransomware_breach/">Affirm fears customer info pilfered during ransomware raid at Evolve Bank</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/06/24/indonesia_datacenter_ransomware/">Indonesian government datacenter locked down in $8M ransomware rumble</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Rounding off the letter, Evolve went on to say that it "had a significant number of cybersecurity measures in place," which have now been strengthened even further.</p>
<p>The incident, however, came against the backdrop of a stern <a target="_blank" href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/newsevents/pressreleases/enforcement20240614a.htm" rel="nofollow">telling off</a> from the US Federal Reserve Board on June 14, less than a fortnight before it announced the data had been stolen.</p>
<p>Following a review of Evolve in 2023, the board wasn't happy at all with the Arkansas-headquartered company for a number of reasons including "deficiencies" in anti-money laundering, risk management, and consumer compliance programs.&nbsp;</p>
<p>It was assessed to have engaged in "unsafe and unsound banking practices," particularly in relation to the absence of an effective risk management framework for its array of partners, among other issues, which resulted in an enforcement action being issued.</p>
<p>This, of course, came just a few weeks after Evolve became aware that LockBit was rummaging through its systems for the best part of four months – a hardly ideal 2024 for the finance firm.</p>
<h3>Misery loves company</h3>
<p>At least Evolve is not alone in the pits of the "data breach" filings this week. Financial Business and Consumer Solutions (FBCS) also <a target="_blank" href="https://www.maine.gov/agviewer/content/ag/985235c7-cb95-4be2-8792-a1252b4f8318/186129d3-f965-48f0-a48d-fbdfc6b74b02.html" rel="nofollow">updated</a> Maine's attorney general on the state of its investigation regarding its own data exposure for the second time in as many weeks.</p>
<p>At the end of June, we reported how the debt collector's situation was going <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/06/24/security_breaches_of_the_week/">from bad to worse</a>, and now it's worse still with the update indicating the number of affected individuals has now surpassed 4 million.</p>
<p>The February attack on FBCS was originally slated to have affected around 2 million people, according to its first filing in April. By the end of June, that number had risen to just north of 3.4 million, and now it stands at 4,050,711, to be precise.</p>
<p>The data stolen includes names, SSNs, dates of birth, account information, and identity documents, but no recognized cybercrime operation has taken credit for what the FBCS called a "cyber incident." ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scoped Propagators (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.orionreed.com/posts/scoped-propagators</link>
            <guid>40916193</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 13:54:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.orionreed.com/posts/scoped-propagators">https://www.orionreed.com/posts/scoped-propagators</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40916193">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>