<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:30:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Twenty Years of Valgrind (2022) (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nnethercote.github.io/2022/07/27/twenty-years-of-valgrind.html</link>
            <guid>41384118</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 20:42:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nnethercote.github.io/2022/07/27/twenty-years-of-valgrind.html">https://nnethercote.github.io/2022/07/27/twenty-years-of-valgrind.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41384118">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>It has been twenty years since Valgrind 1.0 was released.</p>

<p><img src="https://nnethercote.github.io/images/2022/07/27/st-george-dragon.png" alt="dragon"></p>

<p><a href="https://valgrind.org/">The Valgrind website</a> says:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Valgrind is an instrumentation framework for building dynamic analysis tools.
There are Valgrind tools that can automatically detect many memory management
and threading bugs, and profile your programs in detail. You can also use
Valgrind to build new tools.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>–</p>

<p>I first met Julian Seward in late 2001. I had moved from Australia to Cambridge
in the UK to pursue a PhD on the topic of “cache optimizations for functional
languages”. The Cambridge Computer Laboratory is literally next door to a
Microsoft Research office, and I was soon interacting with the people there
working on the Glasgow Haskell Compiler. Julian was one of them.</p>

<p>Shortly after that, Julian’s stint working on GHC came to a close. On his last
day he dropped by my office in the Computer Laboratory to say goodbye. I asked
what he would be doing now, and he said he was going to spend some time on a
project of his called Valgrind. “What’s Valgrind?” I asked. It was one of those
this-will-change-your-life moments.</p>

<p>–</p>

<p>In the mid-90s Julian wrote the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bzip2">bzip2 compression
utility</a>. He had spent some time
<a href="https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/838157">investigating</a> its cache
behaviour in order to make it faster. While doing this he created a cache
profiling tool called cacheprof. It parsed and annotated assembly code in order
to add instrumentation code, gave line-by-line annotations of cache misses in
your source code, and came with a wrapper around gcc to make its usage
straightforward. (Section 7 of the <a href="https://nnethercote.github.io/doc/cacheprof.html">cacheprof docs</a> have
more details about its origins.)</p>

<p>Julian was also a fan of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PurifyPlus">Purify</a>, a
commercial tool that detected memory errors in programs at runtime and ran on
Solaris. He hoped that someone would make an open source version for x86/Linux,
but eventually decided to do it himself. He had some experience with an x86
binary interpreter called Heimdall, but knew that binary interpretation was too
slow to be practical. Perhaps JIT compilation could help?</p>

<p>After a great deal of effort he had a working memory error detector, which
ended up with the name Valgrind. It was language independent and didn’t require
any pre-instrumentation of source code. It worked pretty well, could handle
large programs, and was getting some use from KDE developers.</p>

<p>All this was an impressive achievement, because Valgrind has to do a lot of
clever and/or nasty low-level things to work. It has to intercept every
instruction executed by a client program without ever losing control, even in
the face of syscalls, signals, and longjmp. And on top of that it has to add
large amounts of instrumentation to maintain metadata about literally every bit
of data the client program manipulates.</p>

<p>–</p>

<p>When Julian showed me Valgrind I thought it was pretty cool. I got a copy of
the code and submitted a few small improvements.</p>

<p>I had been using cacheprof myself, but its assembly annotation approach was
fragile and didn’t provide any coverage for system libraries. Not long after
learning about Valgrind I realised its dynamic binary instrumentation could
provide a more robust foundation for a cache profiling tool. I wrote Cachegrind
and it was committed into the repository in April 2002.</p>

<p>In July 2002, Valgrind 1.0 was
released. The
<a href="https://developers.slashdot.org/story/02/07/28/1833225/valgrind-100-released">SlashDot post</a> said:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Valgrind is a C/C++ programmer’s dream come true: effortless memory
allocation checking, uninitialised memory access, leaks etc. Purify for Linux
has arrived, only better: contrary to its commercial (non-Linux) sibling,
checking is performed directly on the executable, no re-linking necessary.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>At this point Valgrind did two things. By default it would look for memory
errors, but you could invoke Cachegrind with the <code>--cachesim</code> option. The
integration between the two modes was clunky, but both were useful.</p>

<p>I then realised there was a potential clean split between the generic
instrumentation code and the tool-specific code. A few months later I made this
split, which opened up a new world of possibilities. Memcheck was born: it
became the name of the tool that did the original memory checking, and Valgrind
became the name of the entire system. (Having said that, even today “Valgrind”
and “Memcheck” are basically synonymous.) And Cachegrind was no longer bolted
on as an awkward extra piece.</p>

<p>We called this the “core/skin split”. These names were my choice, inspired by
the custom UI “skins” you could put on software MP3 players at the time. A
while later we realised “skin” was a dumb and confusing name, and we switched
to “tool”. The name “core” has stuck, although we changed the name of the
directory holding the core code from <code>core</code> to <code>coregrind</code> after learning that
some Linux systems were configured to periodically delete any file named
<code>core</code>, on the assumption that such files are core dumps!</p>

<p>Around this time we were joined by many talented folks who made important
contributions. In particular, Jeremy Fitzhardinge greatly improved the tricky
intersection point of threads, system calls, and signals, and Tom Hughes fixed
many early bugs and improved debuginfo reading.</p>

<p>More tools followed.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Julian wrote a data race detector called Helgrind.</li>
  <li>Josef Weidendorfer wrote a souped-up version of Cachegrind called Callgrind.</li>
  <li>In 2003 I wrote Massif, a heap profiler.</li>
  <li>In 2007 Bart Van Assche wrote DRD, a different kind of race detector.</li>
  <li>In 2010 Julian wrote
<a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/jseward/2010/12/05/fun-n-games-with-dhat/">DHAT</a>, a
different heap profiler. It could do some incredible stuff but the text-based
output was clunky. In 2019 I
<a href="https://blog.mozilla.org/nnethercote/2019/04/17/a-better-dhat/">overhauled</a>
it to have a much nicer UI.</li>
  <li>Various other lesser-known tools have been written, some of which were used
as the basis for <a href="https://valgrind.org/docs/pubs.html">research papers</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>–</p>

<p>After the core/tool split I switched the topic of my PhD away from functional
programming. I finished my dissertation, entitled <a href="https://nnethercote.github.io/pubs/phd2004.pdf">Dynamic Binary Analysis and
Instrumentation</a>, in late 2004.
I wouldn’t recommend reading it today, except perhaps chapter 3 which is a
decent description of how Cachegrind works. However, it was enough for me to
graduate and forevermore tell people that, literally, “I have a PhD in
Valgrind”. (This was a three year UK PhD, rather than a brutal six-or-more year
US PhD. To any potential graduate students reading this: 10/10, would
recommend.)</p>

<p>In 2005 we published a paper at USENIX entitled <a href="https://nnethercote.github.io/pubs/memcheck2005.pdf">Using Valgrind to detect
undefined value errors with bit-precision</a>. We only
learned about the conference two days before the paper deadline, when an
organiser of the co-located FREENIX workshop suggested we submit an abstract
for a paper about Valgrind to FREENIX. We proposed submitting a paper to USENIX
instead and were told “it’s not possible to do a USENIX paper in two days”.
Forty-eight frantic hours later we did and it was accepted, hooray!</p>

<p>That paper focused Memcheck’s definedness checking. This is the part that
tracks the definedness of every bit of data that a client program touches, and
determines if the client program does anything dangerous with undefined or
partially-defined values, such as branching on a condition that uses an
undefined value, or passing an undefined value to a system call, or using an
undefined value as an address in a memory operation. It’s a very elegant system
that Julian invented, combining both speed and precision. Even today, it’s
still a unique advantage of Memcheck over similar checking tools.</p>

<p>In 2007 we published two papers. The first paper was at PLDI, entitled
<a href="https://nnethercote.github.io/pubs/valgrind2007.pdf">Valgrind: A Framework for Heavyweight Dynamic Binary
Instrumentation</a>. This one took a lot longer than two
days. It’s still the best overview of Valgrind’s internals, and the most cited
paper about Valgrind. Ten years later, it won a <a href="https://www.sigplan.org/Awards/PLDI/">most influential
paper</a> <del>weapon</del> award. I sure wasn’t
expecting that.</p>

<p><img src="https://nnethercote.github.io/images/2022/07/27/pldi-award.jpg" alt="award" width="350"></p>

<p>The second paper was at VEE, entitled <a href="https://nnethercote.github.io/pubs/shadow-memory2007.pdf">How to Shadow Every Byte of Memory Used
by a Program</a>. It gives a nice overview of how
Memcheck tracks extra state about every value in memory.</p>

<p>There were some other awards, too.</p>

<ul>
  <li>In 2004 Valgrind won a merit (bronze) Open Source Award. (This
<a href="https://www.techrepublic.com/article/open-source-awards-2004-julian-seward-for-valgrind/">interview with
Julian</a>
from the time has some good historical information.)</li>
  <li>In 2006 Julian won a <a href="https://developers.google.com/open-source/osa">Google-O’Reilly Open Source
Award</a> for “Best Toolmaker”.</li>
  <li>In 2008 Valgrind won <a href="https://linuxdevices.org/cross-platform-tools-vendor-announces-awards-earnings/">TrollTech’s inaugural Qt Open Source Development
Award</a>
for the best open source development tool.</li>
</ul>

<p>–</p>

<p>By 2010 I was fully out of academia and no longer writing research papers.
Julian and I had both ended up at Mozilla, where I worked for twelve years and
where Julian still is. Our involvement in Valgrind has gradually declined—mine
much earlier than Julian’s—and our statuses today would best be described as
“emeritus”. There have been many other
<a href="https://valgrind.org/info/developers.html">contributors</a> over the years, and
Mark Wielaard is today the lead maintainer.</p>

<p>–</p>

<p>It’s both delightful and surreal to see that Valgrind is still in wide use
today. Julian’s original goal was to raise the bar when it came to correctness
for C and C++ programs. This has clearly been a huge success. Memcheck has
found countless bugs in countless programs, and is a standard part of the
testing setup for many of them.</p>

<p>It did take a while to penetrate, though. In 2005 I did a postdoc where I
worked on a project involving novel hardware design. There were several C
programs that simulated the hardware being designed. Students would run the
programs overnight to simulate a small amount of machine time. Sometimes when
they returned in the morning the simulations would have crashed, which was a
big time waster. I suggested they try Memcheck, which found a few problems that
they fixed, and the programs stopped crashing. But the response wasn’t a “that
fixed the problem!” so much as a “huh, that problem seems to have gone away”.</p>

<p>Thankfully, with time, the value of Memcheck has become more deeply
appreciated. I’m pretty sure that ASan was directly inspired by Memcheck. ASan
uses static instrumentation, which means it is faster than Memcheck but has
incomplete coverage, e.g. for runtime generated code and system libraries. For
this reason it does what Memcheck does except the definedness checking, because
that part requires 100% instrumentation coverage to work reliably.</p>

<p>Speaking of software quality, I think it’s fitting that I now work full time on
Rust, a systems programming language that didn’t exist when Valgrind was
created, but which basically prevents all the problems that Memcheck detects.
As a result, I don’t have much use for Memcheck, but I still use Cachegrind,
Callgrind, and DHAT all the time. I’m amazed that I’m still using Cachegrind
today, given that it has hardly changed in twenty years. (I only use it for
instruction counts, though. I wouldn’t trust the icache/dcache results at all
given that they come from a best-guess simulation of an AMD Athlon circa 2002.)
And DHAT is an ongoing source of joy: I’ve never used any other profiler as
good at telling me precisely what I want to know.</p>

<p>–</p>

<p>These are some of my Valgrind stories from the past twenty years. It’s far from
a complete account, but I hope it has been interesting.</p>

<p>To finish, I’ll quote the first entry in the Valgrind
<a href="https://valgrind.org/docs/manual/faq.html">FAQ</a>, which I wrote a long time
ago:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>1.1. How do you pronounce “Valgrind”?</p>

  <p>The “Val” as in the word “value”. The “grind” is pronounced with a short ‘i’ –
ie. “grinned” (rhymes with “tinned”) rather than “grined” (rhymes with “find”).</p>

  <p>Don’t feel bad: almost everyone gets it wrong at first.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Happy birthday, Valgrind!</p>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Future of TLA+ [pdf] (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lamport.azurewebsites.net/tla/future.pdf</link>
            <guid>41382828</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 18:46:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lamport.azurewebsites.net/tla/future.pdf">https://lamport.azurewebsites.net/tla/future.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41382828">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The 4-chan Go programmer (197 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.dolthub.com/blog/2024-08-23-the-4-chan-go-programmer/</link>
            <guid>41382699</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 18:35:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/2024-08-23-the-4-chan-go-programmer/">https://www.dolthub.com/blog/2024-08-23-the-4-chan-go-programmer/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41382699">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-cy="blog-post-text"><h2 id="introduction"><a href="#introduction" aria-label="introduction permalink"></a>Introduction</h2>
<p>We're using Go to write <a href="https://doltdb.com/">Dolt</a>, the world's first version-controlled SQL
database. Like most Go codebases, we use <a href="https://gobyexample.com/channels">channels</a> and
<a href="https://gobyexample.com/goroutines">goroutines</a> to implement concurrent execution. Usually we use
these constructs in the most boring and straightforward way possible, because concurrent programming
is hard enough without trying to be clever. But at one point we inherited some code from another
open source project that used channels in a very clever way: it used them to send additional
channels.</p>

<p>This is a channel that sends another channel, which then sends a struct. It's basically a way to
pass channels between different goroutines, to implement some fan-out pattern among worker
goroutines. Think of the "middle" channel as the middleman in the workflow: its job is to pass new
channels as they are produced down to workers who actually do useful work. It did work, but it's the
kind of overly clever idea that was hard to reason about and work with, especially once you consider
goroutine leaks. We rewrote it, and that <code>chan chan struct{}</code> is long gone.</p>
<p>But it did get me thinking. How far can you take this dumb idea? Behold the 4-chan:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code>_4chan <span>:=</span> <span>make</span><span>(</span><span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<h2 id="why-are-you-doing-this"><a href="#why-are-you-doing-this" aria-label="why are you doing this permalink"></a>Why are you doing this</h2>
<p>There's an old programming joke from back in the days when C and its derivatives dominated the
landscape. A lot of people had a very hard time understanding pointers, probably because they didn't
have this meme back then.</p>
<p><span>
      <a href="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/375f585a6a89a468f359df8c43ef8a3c/6af66/pointers-meme.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    <span></span>
  <img alt="pointers" title="" src="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/375f585a6a89a468f359df8c43ef8a3c/6af66/pointers-meme.png" srcset="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/375f585a6a89a468f359df8c43ef8a3c/a48b3/pointers-meme.png 214w,
https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/375f585a6a89a468f359df8c43ef8a3c/47730/pointers-meme.png 428w,
https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/375f585a6a89a468f359df8c43ef8a3c/6af66/pointers-meme.png 640w" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
  </a>
    </span></p>
<p>Because pointers were necessary to do many useful things in C, and relatively hard to understand
for a lot of people, newbies would sometimes do very silly things with them, like declaring
variables like this:</p>

<p>And these novices didn't realize what a silly thing this is to do, thinking instead that getting a
working program that used this many layers of pointer indirection was actually a sign of
expertise. Such unfortunate newbies were called "4-star programmers".</p>
<p>Because Go is also largely derived from C, you can do the same thing in Go:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code><span>func</span> <span>main</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	i <span>:=</span> <span>1</span>
	<span>setInt</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span>i<span>)</span>

	fmt<span>.</span><span>Printf</span><span>(</span><span>"i is now %d"</span><span>,</span> i<span>)</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>func</span> <span>setInt</span><span>(</span>i <span>*</span><span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>setInt2</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span>i<span>)</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>func</span> <span>setInt2</span><span>(</span>i <span>*</span><span>*</span><span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>setInt3</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span>i<span>)</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>func</span> <span>setInt3</span><span>(</span>i <span>*</span><span>*</span><span>*</span><span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>setInt4</span><span>(</span><span>&amp;</span>i<span>)</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>func</span> <span>setInt4</span><span>(</span>i <span>*</span><span>*</span><span>*</span><span>*</span><span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>*</span><span>*</span><span>*</span><span>*</span>i <span>=</span> <span>100</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>This compiles and prints <code>i is now 100</code>. You too can be a 4-star Go programmer, it's just that easy.</p>
<p>But we can take this one step farther, and use a construct that Go has but C does not:
channels. Declared in code as <code>chan</code>.</p>
<p><span>
      <a href="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/445c20c53d8333439a2a6385fcfe6409/4b9ef/4chan.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">
    <span></span>
  <img alt="4 chan" title="" src="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/445c20c53d8333439a2a6385fcfe6409/4b9ef/4chan.jpg" srcset="https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/445c20c53d8333439a2a6385fcfe6409/606a2/4chan.jpg 214w,
https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/445c20c53d8333439a2a6385fcfe6409/65a3f/4chan.jpg 428w,
https://www.dolthub.com/blog/static/445c20c53d8333439a2a6385fcfe6409/4b9ef/4chan.jpg 641w" sizes="(max-width: 641px) 100vw, 641px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
  </a>
    </span></p>
<p>You see where I'm going with this.</p>

<p>The basic idea is that we'll write a program that uses 4 layers of channel indirection to complete
some task. Our top-level channel has to be a 4-chan, so we declare it like this:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code>_4chan <span>:=</span> <span>make</span><span>(</span><span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>(It's somewhat irritating for the purpose of this gag that Go doesn't let you begin an identifier
with a numeral, but that's life).</p>
<p>The values we send on that channel are 3-chans, like this:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code>_3chan <span>:=</span> <span>make</span><span>(</span><span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>And so on, down to the lowly int channel itself.</p>
<p>At each layer of indirection, we'll spawn producers according to some constant branching factor:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code><span>func</span> <span>sendChanChanChan</span><span>(</span>c <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>for</span> <span>range</span> factor <span>{</span>
		<span>go</span> <span>func</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
			logrus<span>.</span><span>Debug</span><span>(</span><span>"starting 3chan producer"</span><span>)</span>
			_3chan <span>:=</span> <span>make</span><span>(</span><span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span>
			<span>sendChanChan</span><span>(</span>c<span>,</span> _3chan<span>)</span>
		<span>}</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
	<span>}</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>And the same thing for consumers:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code><span>func</span> <span>receiveChanChanChan</span><span>(</span>c <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>for</span> _3chan <span>:=</span> <span>range</span> c <span>{</span>
		logrus<span>.</span><span>Debug</span><span>(</span><span>"got message from 4chan"</span><span>)</span>
		<span>for</span> <span>range</span> factor <span>{</span>
			logrus<span>.</span><span>Debug</span><span>(</span><span>"starting 3chan consumer"</span><span>)</span>
			<span>go</span> <span>receiveChanChan</span><span>(</span>_3chan<span>)</span>
		<span>}</span>
	<span>}</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>Finally we hit the bottom of the stack, where we send an actual value instead of a channel for
values.</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code><span>func</span> <span>send</span><span>(</span>_2chan <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>,</span> _1chan <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	_2chan <span>&lt;-</span> _1chan
	<span>for</span> <span>range</span> factor <span>{</span>
		<span>go</span> <span>func</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
			logrus<span>.</span><span>Debug</span><span>(</span><span>"starting int producer"</span><span>)</span>
			<span>for</span> <span>range</span> factor <span>{</span>
				<span>go</span> <span>func</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
					logrus<span>.</span><span>Debug</span><span>(</span><span>"sending int"</span><span>)</span>
					_1chan <span>&lt;-</span> <span>1</span>
				<span>}</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
			<span>}</span>
		<span>}</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
	<span>}</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>For the consumers, we have to do something with the values we receive. Let's add them together.</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code><span>var</span> sum <span>=</span> <span>&amp;</span>atomic<span>.</span>Int32<span>{</span><span>}</span>

<span>func</span> <span>receive</span><span>(</span>c <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>for</span> s <span>:=</span> <span>range</span> c <span>{</span>
		logrus<span>.</span><span>Debug</span><span>(</span><span>"received int"</span><span>)</span>
		sum<span>.</span><span>Add</span><span>(</span><span>int32</span><span>(</span>s<span>)</span><span>)</span>
	<span>}</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>Now let's put it all together:</p>
<div data-language="go"><pre><code><span>const</span> factor <span>=</span> <span>3</span>

<span>var</span> sum <span>=</span> <span>&amp;</span>atomic<span>.</span>Int32<span>{</span><span>}</span>

<span>func</span> <span>main</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
	<span>// logrus.SetLevel(logrus.DebugLevel)</span>

	_4chan <span>:=</span> <span>make</span><span>(</span><span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>chan</span> <span>int</span><span>)</span>

	<span>go</span> <span>sendChanChanChan</span><span>(</span>_4chan<span>)</span>
	<span>go</span> <span>receiveChanChanChan</span><span>(</span>_4chan<span>)</span>

	time<span>.</span><span>Sleep</span><span>(</span><span>500</span> <span>*</span> time<span>.</span>Millisecond<span>)</span>

	fmt<span>.</span><span>Printf</span><span>(</span><span>"%d ^ 5: %d"</span><span>,</span> factor<span>,</span> sum<span>.</span><span>Load</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
<span>}</span></code></pre></div>
<p>This prints <code>3 ^ 5: 243</code>. Which is correct! This program is a fully generalized way to compute a
number's fifth power in a maximally distributed way. You can play with it
<a href="https://go.dev/play/p/Pzf3aRnXpcE">here</a> (or view with syntax highlighting on GitHub
<a href="https://gist.github.com/zachmu/0209f3437bdda512b8c6170acb07d239">here</a>). For larger factors you may
need to increase the <code>Sleep</code> duration for it to run.</p>
<p>If you enable logging by uncommenting the first line, you'll get output like this that lets you see
the branching factor at each layer of channel production / consumption:</p>
<div data-language="bash"><pre><code><span>sort</span> 4chan.txt <span>|</span> <span>sed</span> <span>-e</span> <span>'s/.*msg=//'</span> <span>|</span> <span>uniq</span> <span>-c</span> <span>|</span> <span>sort</span> <span>-n</span>
      <span>1</span> <span>3</span> ^ <span>5</span>: <span>243</span>
      <span>3</span> <span>"starting 3chan producer"</span>
      <span>9</span> <span>"starting 2chan producer"</span>
      <span>9</span> <span>"starting 3chan consumer"</span>
     <span>27</span> <span>"starting 2chan consumer"</span>
     <span>27</span> <span>"starting chan producer"</span>
     <span>81</span> <span>"starting 1chan consumer"</span>
     <span>81</span> <span>"starting int producer"</span>
    <span>243</span> <span>"received int"</span>
    <span>243</span> <span>"sending int"</span></code></pre></div>

<p>There are a lot of reasons not to do this in real code: the difficulty of implementation and
debugging, having a little self-respect, not wanting to be clubbed to death by your peers' bulky
mechanical keyboards, etc.</p>
<p>On the other hand, it's extremely fun to do and pretty entertaining that it works at all.</p>
<p>So, trade-offs.</p>
<p>One of the best practical reasons not to send channels over channels is that it makes it really
difficult to ever close any of them, which obviously you would want to do in a real use case. At one
point I actually implemented close logic, which required adding a <code>sync.WaitGroup</code> everywhere so
that I could keep track of when all the channel sends were finished before closing anything, but it
made the gag much harder to read so I ditched it and stuck with <code>time.Sleep()</code> and massive goroutine
leaks.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion"><a href="#conclusion" aria-label="conclusion permalink"></a>Conclusion</h2>
<p>Have questions or comments about silly concurrency patterns in Go? Or maybe you are curious about
the world's first version-controlled SQL database? <a href="https://discord.gg/gqr7K4VNKe">Join us on
Discord</a> to talk to our engineering team and other Dolt users.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Window Maker: X11 window manager with the look and feel of the NeXTSTEP UI (141 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.windowmaker.org/</link>
            <guid>41382335</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 18:05:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/">https://www.windowmaker.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41382335">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
        <h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p><strong>Window Maker</strong> is an X11 <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Window_manager">window
manager</a> originally designed to
provide integration support for the <a href="http://gnustep.org/">GNUstep</a> Desktop
Environment, although it can run stand alone. In every way possible, it
reproduces the elegant look and feel of the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NeXTSTEP">NeXTSTEP</a> user interface.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/img/wmaker.png"><img src="https://www.windowmaker.org/img/wmaker_thumb.png" alt="Default Window Maker config"></a></p>

<p>Window Maker on first run</p>

<p>The key features of Window Maker are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Stacking window manager with ability for semi-automatic tiling management</li>
  <li>Lightweight and blazing fast</li>
  <li>Easy to use</li>
  <li>Highly configurable</li>
  <li>Ability to bind keyboard shortcut to wide set of actions</li>
  <li>Dynamic menu entries</li>
  <li>Small, dockable apps (<a href="https://www.dockapps.net/">dockapps</a>)</li>
  <li>Human readable config files and GUI prefs application</li>
  <li>Free and open source</li>
  <li>Active community from all of the world</li>
</ul>

<p>See <a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/features.html">features</a> section for more. In <a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/screenshots/">screenshots</a>
section you can see examples of how users set up their desktops.</p>

<h2 id="download">Download</h2>

<p>Many distributions already have Window Maker included in their software
repositories, so it could be installed directly from there. Other sources are
listed below:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Latest source of stable version is
<a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/pub/source/release/WindowMaker-0.96.0.tar.gz">0.96.0</a>,
released on 2023-08-05. See the <a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/news">NEWS</a> section for more information.</li>
  <li>Source code is also available through the
<a href="http://repo.or.cz/w/wmaker-crm.git">git repository</a></li>
  <li>Older versions of Window Maker may be obtained from the <a href="https://github.com/window-maker/wmaker/releases">GitHub releases page</a> or directly from <a href="https://www.windowmaker.org/pub/source/release/">our website</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bugs">Bugs</h2>

<p>Report bugs at <a href="https://github.com/window-maker/wmaker/issues">https://github.com/window-maker/wmaker/issues</a>.</p>

      </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Maker Skill Trees (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree</link>
            <guid>41381598</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 17:01:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree">https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41381598">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The Skill Trees Project</h2><a id="user-content-the-skill-trees-project" aria-label="Permalink: The Skill Trees Project" href="#the-skill-trees-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/344644393-53d12889-fc08-4b32-92b6-d96271200a7e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzM0NDY0NDM5My01M2QxMjg4OS1mYzA4LTRiMzItOTJiNi1kOTYyNzEyMDBhN2UucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZjVlNzhiMTMxMzg2OTVlMDI5ZDYzNDg4OGYyMDhhMjEwYWJjMGE0OGY2NGZhOTkwODM5ZTIxOGFlZGM3MGQwNCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.VRBOqiXIaSzSLRk0UsKHPWSrmgQfQ5-5OFNGTcfgXCY"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/344644393-53d12889-fc08-4b32-92b6-d96271200a7e.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzM0NDY0NDM5My01M2QxMjg4OS1mYzA4LTRiMzItOTJiNi1kOTYyNzEyMDBhN2UucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZjVlNzhiMTMxMzg2OTVlMDI5ZDYzNDg4OGYyMDhhMjEwYWJjMGE0OGY2NGZhOTkwODM5ZTIxOGFlZGM3MGQwNCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.VRBOqiXIaSzSLRk0UsKHPWSrmgQfQ5-5OFNGTcfgXCY" alt="Maker Skill Tree Banner-48"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Maker Skill Trees are printable templates that can guide and track hands-on skill progression.  Colour in the boxes as you go and get inspired to try new things.  This repository is always growing and aims to include a large variety of skills, see full list below.   Everyone's journey is different and you can interpret the goals flexibly.  Not everything needs to be completed.  Print your own in A4 or A3 size.</p>
<p dir="auto">Each skill tree has 73 skill or experience hexagonal tiles, ordered in a spectrum of basic skills at the bottom to more advanced skills at the top.  This includes 5 set your own goal tiles for you to tailor to your own interests. Under the templates section, there's also a smaller Mini Skill Tree template with only 40 tiles.  Maker Skill Trees are released under the Creative Commons Licence, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" rel="nofollow">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0</a> .  You are free to share, adapt, remix or transform the printables or templates for non-commercial purposes.  However, you must do so by giving credit to Steph Piper / Maker Queen (or leaving the credit at the bottom of the page) and if you release a remix it must be under the same licence.  I'm looking at releasing a book with all these compiled when all trees are complete.</p>
<p dir="auto">Open Source – <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/" rel="nofollow">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0 Licence</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Header font used: <a href="https://www.dafont.com/hansief.font" rel="nofollow">Hansief</a><br>
Other fonts used:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://befonts.com/uniform-pro-font-family.html" rel="nofollow">Uniform Condensed Regular</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fonts.google.com/specimen/Open+Sans" rel="nofollow">Open Sans</a></li>
<li>Icons from <a href="https://icons8.com/" rel="nofollow">Icons8</a>, and some self-made</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Templates include Adobe Illustrator and PDF files.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Skill Tree Generator</h2><a id="user-content-skill-tree-generator" aria-label="Permalink: Skill Tree Generator" href="#skill-tree-generator"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can now make your own skill tree templates with the web app designed by the talented <a href="https://github.com/schme16">@schme16</a>.  It's now a lot easier to make your own templates for personal use or adding to the repository.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://schme16.github.io/MakerSkillTree-Generator/" rel="nofollow">Visit the Web app here</a></p>
<p dir="auto">How to use:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Heading text is editable</li>
<li>Click and drag to move the tiles</li>
<li>Right click a tile to edit the text</li>
<li>Save will download an SVG of the skill tree</li>
<li>Left click to edit credit at the base to add your own name, or remove my name if you're just using for personal use (or don't want me to proof read/edit it).</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage Ideas</h2><a id="user-content-usage-ideas" aria-label="Permalink: Usage Ideas" href="#usage-ideas"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Individual goal tracking and upskilling, identifying skill gaps  #skilltreechallenge</li>
<li>For makerspace members to upskill on a variety of tools</li>
<li>For training new staff members on skills</li>
<li>For school students working on self-directed activities (See Kids STEAM Skills tree)</li>
<li>For recruitment / competency checking</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">It's encouraged to customize these base skill trees around your own interests and goals.  You may edit these PDFs to suit or use tile stickers to cover the boxes on a printed template.  You can cut your own tile stickers with a vinyl cutter using the Tile Stickers Template SVG (in the templates folder).</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Skill Seeker Book</h2><a id="user-content-skill-seeker-book" aria-label="Permalink: Skill Seeker Book" href="#skill-seeker-book"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I'm working on a book with an expansive range of skill trees, plus great tools to track your progress, earn achievement badges and calculate your life XP score across all areas.  <a href="https://www.makerqueen.com.au/skill-trees-1" rel="nofollow">Get notified when the book is available.</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/356858039-96914235-c8f5-47d4-873b-5e7acc8fc825.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzM1Njg1ODAzOS05NjkxNDIzNS1jOGY1LTQ3ZDQtODczYi01ZTdhY2M4ZmM4MjUucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9NjgzMjM5NGJkODNiNzEzMTczZTY0OTlhMDA2NjcyOTVkMTg5MzhmOGMzODNjMDY1ZDhmZjUyZTNkMTQ4ZDhkNyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.xFcRN_RbjfRs8_vysF0NjhNqW5CxtPRhgYUTZf5PMUU"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/356858039-96914235-c8f5-47d4-873b-5e7acc8fc825.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzM1Njg1ODAzOS05NjkxNDIzNS1jOGY1LTQ3ZDQtODczYi01ZTdhY2M4ZmM4MjUucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9NjgzMjM5NGJkODNiNzEzMTczZTY0OTlhMDA2NjcyOTVkMTg5MzhmOGMzODNjMDY1ZDhmZjUyZTNkMTQ4ZDhkNyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.xFcRN_RbjfRs8_vysF0NjhNqW5CxtPRhgYUTZf5PMUU" alt="Both Books Render-01-01"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Yet to Make (44/60)</h2><a id="user-content-yet-to-make-4460" aria-label="Permalink: Yet to Make (44/60)" href="#yet-to-make-4460"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Classic Skills (17/20)</h2><a id="user-content-classic-skills-1720" aria-label="Permalink: Classic Skills (17/20)" href="#classic-skills-1720"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">✅ Automotive<br>
☐ Blacksmithing<br>
✅ Boating &amp; Fishing<br>
☐ Ceramics<br>
✅ Crafting<br>
✅ Crochet<br>
✅ Dance<br>
✅ Embroidery<br>
✅ House Building<br>
☐ Jewelry Making<br>
✅ Knitting<br>
✅ Metalworking<br>
✅ Moulding and Casting<br>
✅ Music<br>
✅ Photography / Videography<br>
✅ Reading &amp; Writing<br>
✅ Renovation &amp; Repair<br>
✅ Sewing<br>
✅ Visual Arts<br>
✅ Woodworking</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tech Skills (17/20)</h2><a id="user-content-tech-skills-1720" aria-label="Permalink: Tech Skills (17/20)" href="#tech-skills-1720"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">✅ 3D Modelling       ✅ French Translation<br>
✅ 3D Printing    ✅ French Translation<br>
☐ AI &amp; Machine Learning<br>
✅ Amateur Radio<br>
✅ CNC &amp; CAM<br>
✅ Coding      ✅ Mini Coding Tree<br>
✅ Computing<br>
✅ Dev Boards<br>
✅ Electronics<br>
✅ Embedded Systems<br>
✅ Game Dev<br>
☐ Gaming<br>
✅ IT Security<br>
✅ Laser Cutting      ✅ French Translation<br>
✅ Linux<br>
✅ PCB Design<br>
✅ Mobile App Dev<br>
☐ Research Skills<br>
✅ Robotics<br>
✅ Website Building</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Life Skills (10/20)</h2><a id="user-content-life-skills-1020" aria-label="Permalink: Life Skills (10/20)" href="#life-skills-1020"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">✅ Adventure<br>
☐ Animal Care<br>
☐ Backyard Science<br>
✅ Baking<br>
✅ Civics &amp; Community<br>
✅ Cleaning<br>
✅ Cooking<br>
☐ Drinks<br>
✅ Entrepreneurship<br>
☐ Environmentalist<br>
☐ Finance<br>
☐ Fermenting &amp; Preservation<br>
✅  Gardening<br>
✅ Language<br>
☐ Life Admin<br>
☐ Self Care<br>
✅ Sports &amp; Fitness<br>
☐ Survivalist<br>
✅ Travel<br>
☐ Volunteering</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Other Niche Areas &amp; Suggestions</h2><a id="user-content-other-niche-areas--suggestions" aria-label="Permalink: Other Niche Areas &amp; Suggestions" href="#other-niche-areas--suggestions"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">✅  STEAM Skills<br>
✅  Explore a Makerspace<br>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;✅ Makerspace w/ 3D Printer, 3D scanner, Vinyl Cutter and Electronics Bench<br>
&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;✅ Makerspace w/ 3D Printer, 3D scanner, Vinyl Cutter, Laser Cutter and Electronics Bench<br>
✅ 3D Printing and 3D Modelling  (Now split to individual areas)<br>
✅ Roller Derby<br>
✅ Dungeons and Dragons<br>
✅ Comic Artist<br>
✅ Cocktails<br>
✅ Kubernetes<br>
✅ Scratch<br>
☐ Tabletop Games<br>
☐ Video Games<br>
☐ Leatherworking<br>
☐ Bushcraft<br>
☐ Foraging<br>
☐ Biology Experiments<br>
☐ Vintage Computing<br>
☐ Social Skills<br>
☐ Climbing<br>
☐ Weaving<br>
☐ Cooking Skills: National Cuisines<br>
☐ Mushroom Cultivation<br>
☐ Insect Breeding<br>
☐ Urban Gardening<br>
☐ School Summer Camp Planning<br>
☐ School Event Organization<br>
☐ Australian Professional Standards for Teachers (<a href="https://www.aitsl.edu.au/standards/graduate" rel="nofollow">https://www.aitsl.edu.au/standards/graduate</a>)<br>
☐ Minecraft     (See open issue #19 to submit ideas)</p>
<p dir="auto">Got a suggestion for a new skill tree, or feedback on an existing tree?  Use the <a href="https://forms.office.com/r/0LdRzGZ2pK" rel="nofollow">suggestion box form</a>.<br>
Interested in helping put one of these together? Or even something that's not on the list? Send through your draft and I can put it in the template, or we can do a brainstorm hour to fill it in.  If you're an expert and help me put something together a skill tree for the repository, or can assist in translating the sheets into different languages I'd love to hear from you.  Let me know if you're interested, email: <a href="mailto:steph@makerqueen.com.au">steph@makerqueen.com.au</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to Make Your Own</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-make-your-own" aria-label="Permalink: How to Make Your Own" href="#how-to-make-your-own"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Use the template pack in the files, including PNG / PDF and AI files to fill in with your software of choice.  If you've filled it in, I'm happy to polish it with custom icons and release it in this repository.</p>
<p dir="auto">My aim with the skill trees is:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Modern, relevant and ordered correctly from basics at the base to advanced at the top</li>
<li>flexible with goals rather than too specific, everyone's journey is different</li>
<li>Inspiring to try new things rather than completionist</li>
<li>Include options for tools that aren't cost / availability restrictive</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">With a total of 73 skill tiles, there's a lot of boxes to fill in!  To help prompt ideas, I usually include the following:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>What's the first few things you do in this skill?</li>
<li>What materials might you use at a basic / intermediate / advanced level?</li>
<li>What tools might you use at a basic / intermediate / advanced level?</li>
<li>What techniques might you use at a basic / intermediate / advanced level?</li>
<li>What might go wrong and how would you fix it?</li>
<li>Where might you visit to learn more / get involved in a community?</li>
<li>What interskill / interdisciplinary techniques could you try? Eg. Electronics + Textiles = Wearable Tech</li>
<li>Gifting a friend something made from x skill</li>
<li>Teaching a class or friend on x skill</li>
<li>Releasing an online tutorial on x skill</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Skill Tree Bug Bounties</h2><a id="user-content-skill-tree-bug-bounties" aria-label="Permalink: Skill Tree Bug Bounties" href="#skill-tree-bug-bounties"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you've spotted something that could be improved in a Skill Tree, I'd love to send you a holographic ｒａｒｅ contributor sticker in the mail to say thanks.  We've each got our own great unique experiences and perspectives in our skill areas and I'd love to draw on our collective knowledge to polish these skill trees into their best versions.  Bug Feedback form: <a href="https://forms.office.com/r/eemK9VhJFm" rel="nofollow">https://forms.office.com/r/eemK9VhJFm</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/351655412-5e03c01a-6503-4495-93af-75d98e5ebcf0.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzM1MTY1NTQxMi01ZTAzYzAxYS02NTAzLTQ0OTUtOTNhZi03NWQ5OGU1ZWJjZjAucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9Y2I1YWFlYTFhMWQwNDAyZTJlOTk0NDk5YzQzZTBkODM1YjM0ZDIxZDY2NmYzMTc1ZTgyOTQwMWFiYjZiNTYxYiZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.xreq3KKFrVsP5142ovweNzfOVAq14vSwICUt9REgzyo"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/351655412-5e03c01a-6503-4495-93af-75d98e5ebcf0.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzM1MTY1NTQxMi01ZTAzYzAxYS02NTAzLTQ0OTUtOTNhZi03NWQ5OGU1ZWJjZjAucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9Y2I1YWFlYTFhMWQwNDAyZTJlOTk0NDk5YzQzZTBkODM1YjM0ZDIxZDY2NmYzMTc1ZTgyOTQwMWFiYjZiNTYxYiZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.xreq3KKFrVsP5142ovweNzfOVAq14vSwICUt9REgzyo" alt="2024-07-24 18 25 18"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Support the Project</h2><a id="user-content-support-the-project" aria-label="Permalink: Support the Project" href="#support-the-project"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Get skill tree poster digital downloads on my <a href="https://www.makerqueen.com.au/freebies" rel="nofollow">website for free</a> or on the <a href="https://www.etsy.com/shop/makerqueenau/" rel="nofollow">MakerQueen Shop</a> if you wish to support the project.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/278531944-0d05b244-beb6-4c24-ac15-a939fa4af928.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzI3ODUzMTk0NC0wZDA1YjI0NC1iZWI2LTRjMjQtYWMxNS1hOTM5ZmE0YWY5MjgucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9OWYxYzFjYmRjZDgyYzI5YjVjZTBiYzE4YWNjZWI3ODA2NjllZWQ2YTNhM2E1Y2YwZGQ1Y2ZhNjYwOWI3N2QxMCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.rc6JDMky85oN3l2WMGZYxkJZUVA9LdI4PwHyz9ef4Xs"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/278531944-0d05b244-beb6-4c24-ac15-a939fa4af928.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzI3ODUzMTk0NC0wZDA1YjI0NC1iZWI2LTRjMjQtYWMxNS1hOTM5ZmE0YWY5MjgucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9OWYxYzFjYmRjZDgyYzI5YjVjZTBiYzE4YWNjZWI3ODA2NjllZWQ2YTNhM2E1Y2YwZGQ1Y2ZhNjYwOWI3N2QxMCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.rc6JDMky85oN3l2WMGZYxkJZUVA9LdI4PwHyz9ef4Xs" alt="Electronics Poster Mockup"></a>
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/278531949-fe13cacf-63eb-4880-a40b-6ddff228f422.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzI3ODUzMTk0OS1mZTEzY2FjZi02M2ViLTQ4ODAtYTQwYi02ZGRmZjIyOGY0MjIucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9MDY3MmViZTZlZmEzOGRmMzg2ZTdkNzgyNjcwMDQ1MjhjYjkyNDVmZWEzZGNjMTA1NzI5NGRjMjkxOTYyZjJjMCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.fmPQNyJYMJI4py2E35xtcoUzjbZ7y0a9WzelJp2nzYc"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/278531949-fe13cacf-63eb-4880-a40b-6ddff228f422.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzI3ODUzMTk0OS1mZTEzY2FjZi02M2ViLTQ4ODAtYTQwYi02ZGRmZjIyOGY0MjIucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9MDY3MmViZTZlZmEzOGRmMzg2ZTdkNzgyNjcwMDQ1MjhjYjkyNDVmZWEzZGNjMTA1NzI5NGRjMjkxOTYyZjJjMCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.fmPQNyJYMJI4py2E35xtcoUzjbZ7y0a9WzelJp2nzYc" alt="Digital Fabrication Poster Mockup"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Skill Trees In the Media &amp; Community</h2><a id="user-content-skill-trees-in-the-media--community" aria-label="Permalink: Skill Trees In the Media &amp; Community" href="#skill-trees-in-the-media--community"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Skill Trees Asynchronous Presentation at the Open Hardware Summit 2024</h2><a id="user-content-skill-trees-asynchronous-presentation-at-the-open-hardware-summit-2024" aria-label="Permalink: Skill Trees Asynchronous Presentation at the Open Hardware Summit 2024" href="#skill-trees-asynchronous-presentation-at-the-open-hardware-summit-2024"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gB10vAvSiMU&amp;ab_channel=TheOpenSourceHardwareAssociation" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/339295806-ea416c43-2179-4919-9aeb-6e45cf4516cd.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzMzOTI5NTgwNi1lYTQxNmM0My0yMTc5LTQ5MTktOWFlYi02ZTQ1Y2Y0NTE2Y2QucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9N2ZmOTZjYTY0N2RiZDY3ZWJhNmQ4YmNiODY2MzRmZGM3ZWQ0ZDJmOTQyMmEwMzcwNzMzNjRiOWFjMDBiZjJiNCZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.vu0VFKAi2_2vMMeNGACaAclqogHnOwWFu366iFdioUk" alt="image" secured-asset-link=""></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gB10vAvSiMU&amp;ab_channel=TheOpenSourceHardwareAssociation" rel="nofollow">Watch my talk on the Skill Trees Project</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://hackaday.com/2024/06/11/maker-skill-trees-help-you-level-up-your-craft/" rel="nofollow">Hackaday Article - Maker Skill Trees Help You Level Up Your Craft</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://blog.adafruit.com/2024/06/18/the-maker-skill-trees-project/" rel="nofollow">Adafruit Blog - The Maker Skill Trees Project</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://tinkererway.dev/web_skill_tree" rel="nofollow">Skill Tree Web App</a> by the talented <a href="https://github.com/amalmathewtech">@amalmathewtech</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example Skill Trees</h2><a id="user-content-example-skill-trees" aria-label="Permalink: Example Skill Trees" href="#example-skill-trees"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/339295065-ba370d5f-2abe-4bf1-8ca4-329fd83ed2d4.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzMzOTI5NTA2NS1iYTM3MGQ1Zi0yYWJlLTRiZjEtOGNhNC0zMjlmZDgzZWQyZDQucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9NTNkNDM1MzczOThkN2Y5NGE0NTljZjI2OTE1YjFhNDU3NzRiYmFjNzIwYzk2YTJlMWY5NWUyMmE1OGM0ZTM0YyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.LeaoHH-7ODSr493rV_jCR7Egk4Fxy-i9nNKIk4GF-6g"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/7828884/339295065-ba370d5f-2abe-4bf1-8ca4-329fd83ed2d4.png?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MjQ4NzczMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcyNDg3NzAwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii83ODI4ODg0LzMzOTI5NTA2NS1iYTM3MGQ1Zi0yYWJlLTRiZjEtOGNhNC0zMjlmZDgzZWQyZDQucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDgyOCUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDA4MjhUMjAzMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9NTNkNDM1MzczOThkN2Y5NGE0NTljZjI2OTE1YjFhNDU3NzRiYmFjNzIwYzk2YTJlMWY5NWUyMmE1OGM0ZTM0YyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.LeaoHH-7ODSr493rV_jCR7Egk4Fxy-i9nNKIk4GF-6g" alt="3D Printing Skill Tree"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/blob/main/Sewing%20Skill%20Tree/Sewing%20Skill%20Tree.pdf"><img src="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/raw/main/Sewing%20Skill%20Tree/Sewing%20Skill%20Tree.png" alt="Sewing Skill Tree"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/blob/main/Embedded%20Systems%20Skill%20Tree/Embedded%20Systems%20Skill%20Tree.pdf"><img src="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/raw/main/Embedded%20Systems%20Skill%20Tree/Embedded%20Systems%20Skill%20Tree.png" alt="Embedded Systems Skill Tree"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/blob/main/Woodworking%20Skill%20Tree/Woodworking%20Skill%20Tree.pdf"><img src="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/raw/main/Woodworking%20Skill%20Tree/Woodworking%20Skill%20Tree.png" alt="Woodworking Skill Tree"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/blob/main/Template%20Skill%20Tree/Maker%20Skill%20Tree%20Template.pdf"><img src="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/raw/main/Template%20Skill%20Tree/Maker%20Skill%20Tree%20Template-03.png" alt="Maker Skill Tree Template"></a>
<a href="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/blob/main/Mini%20Maker%20Skill%20Tree%20Template%20x40%20Tiles.pdf"><img src="https://github.com/sjpiper145/MakerSkillTree/raw/main/Template%20Skill%20Tree/Template%20Mini%20Maker%20Skill%20Tree%20x40%20Tiles.png" alt="Mini Maker Skill Tree Template"></a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Every open source tool from the "What's HN working on" thread (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/getomni-ai/datasets/blob/main/hn_projects.md</link>
            <guid>41380506</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 15:20:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/getomni-ai/datasets/blob/main/hn_projects.md">https://github.com/getomni-ai/datasets/blob/main/hn_projects.md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41380506">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mlang/mc1">https://github.com/mlang/mc1</a></td>
<td>SuperCollider Reimagined Using Python and JIT Compilation</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/jonroig/usBabyNames.js">https://github.com/jonroig/usBabyNames.js</a></td>
<td>App Simplifies Baby Name Selection with Data Driven Filters</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/Pulselyre/UpbeatUI">https://github.com/Pulselyre/UpbeatUI</a></td>
<td>Developing Pulselyre Touchfocused Windows App For Live Electronic Music</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ziolko/eink-calendar-display">https://github.com/ziolko/eink-calendar-display</a></td>
<td>Designing Custom Hardware for Open Source SaaS Project</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/upvpn/upvpn-app">https://github.com/upvpn/upvpn-app</a></td>
<td>Modern Serverless VPN Explores App Store Publishing Process</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/incidentalhq/incidental">https://github.com/incidentalhq/incidental</a></td>
<td>Open Source Incident Management Platform Seeking Early Feedback</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/GauntletWizard/cfssl/tree/ted/constraints">https://github.com/GauntletWizard/cfssl/tree/ted/constraints</a></td>
<td>Bringing Enterprise-Grade Encryption and CA Infrastructure to Small Businesses</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mikewarot/Bitgrid">https://github.com/mikewarot/Bitgrid</a></td>
<td>Exploring GitHub Projects And Developing New Skills</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/hsnice16/golang%5C_learning">https://github.com/hsnice16/golang\_learning</a></td>
<td>Transition to Full-Stack Development and Documenting GoLang Learning</td>
<td>SELF_IMPROVEMENT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/KaliedaRik/Scrawl-canvas">https://github.com/KaliedaRik/Scrawl-canvas</a></td>
<td>Maintaining and Improving My Canvas Library with New Filters</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://codeberg.org/treyd/ecksport" rel="nofollow">https://codeberg.org/treyd/ecksport</a></td>
<td>Developing a Protocol Library for Byte-Oriented Data Structures</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dickeyy/passwords">https://github.com/dickeyy/passwords</a></td>
<td>Open Source Encrypted Password Manager Self Hosted And Customizable</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/cutestuff/FoodDepressionConundrum/blob/ma...latest">https://github.com/cutestuff/FoodDepressionConundrum/blob/ma...latest</a></td>
<td>Probiotic Solution Eases Plant Digestion Challenges</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/MeoMix/symbiants">https://github.com/MeoMix/symbiants</a></td>
<td>Colony Simulation Game in Rust for Personal Growth</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/anacrolix/possum">https://github.com/anacrolix/possum</a></td>
<td>Possum: Efficient Disk-Backed Cache for File I/O and Snapshots</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ubavic/mint">https://github.com/ubavic/mint</a></td>
<td>Development Update on Custom Markup Language Atex and Its Compiler</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/linkwarden/linkwarden">https://github.com/linkwarden/linkwarden</a></td>
<td>Self-Hostable Open-Source Collaborative Bookmark Manager Available</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/domino14">https://github.com/domino14</a></td>
<td>Code Debugging And Scrabble Apps With LLMs And AI</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/masto/LED-Marquee">https://github.com/masto/LED-Marquee</a></td>
<td>Documenting Personal Project on YouTube and GitHub After Leaving Google</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/brendanv/lynxAnd">https://github.com/brendanv/lynxAnd</a> <a href="https://github.com/brendanv/lynx-v2">https://github.com/brendanv/lynx-v2</a></td>
<td>Personal Read It Later Service Turned SPA for Learning Go</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/kilroyjones/series%5C_game%5C_from%5C_scratch">https://github.com/kilroyjones/series\_game\_from\_scratch</a></td>
<td>Learning IoUring for Fun with Rust Web Game Development</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/hrkck/MyApps/wiki">https://github.com/hrkck/MyApps/wiki</a></td>
<td>MyApps App of Apps with Infinite 2D Space and P2P Sync</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/rumca-js/Django-link-archive">https://github.com/rumca-js/Django-link-archive</a></td>
<td>Title: Developing an RSS Reader and Web Scraper</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/DDoS/Cadre">https://github.com/DDoS/Cadre</a></td>
<td>Exploring Enhanced E Ink Displays For Smart Picture Frames</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/Vija02/TheOpenPresenter">https://github.com/Vija02/TheOpenPresenter</a></td>
<td>Open Source Presenter Software for Events and Digital Signage</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/itsOwen/CyberScraper-2077">https://github.com/itsOwen/CyberScraper-2077</a></td>
<td>CyberScraper 2077 Web Scraper Powered By LLM</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="2034635310" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/fujiapple852/trippy/issues/860" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/fujiapple852/trippy/issues/860/hovercard" href="https://github.com/fujiapple852/trippy/issues/860">fujiapple852/trippy#860</a></td>
<td>Forward and Backward Packet Loss Heuristics in Trippy</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/bytechefhq/bytechef">https://github.com/bytechefhq/bytechef</a></td>
<td>ByteChef Open Source API Integration And Workflow Automation Platform</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/AvitalTamir/cyphernetes/">https://github.com/AvitalTamir/cyphernetes/</a></td>
<td>Cyphernetes Innovative Query Language For Kubernetes API</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/willswire/checkd">https://github.com/willswire/checkd</a></td>
<td>Exploring Device Authentication with Checkd and Apple's DeviceCheck API</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/sdedovic/wgsltoy">https://github.com/sdedovic/wgsltoy</a></td>
<td>WGSL Toy A WebGPU Playground for Shader Development</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/Trint-ai/TrintAI">https://github.com/Trint-ai/TrintAI</a></td>
<td>TrintAI Open Source Speech to Text and Analysis Tool</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/trynova/nova">https://github.com/trynova/nova</a></td>
<td>Nova Data-Oriented JavaScript Engine</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/AmberSahdev/Open-Interface">https://github.com/AmberSahdev/Open-Interface</a></td>
<td>Title: Open Source LLM Based Autopilot for Multiple OS</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dvasanth/kadugu">https://github.com/dvasanth/kadugu</a></td>
<td>Title: Building a Blazing Speed VPN in Minimal Lines</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ptah-sh/ptah-server">https://github.com/ptah-sh/ptah-server</a></td>
<td>Open Source Alternative To Heroku With Key Features</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://github.com/CWood-sdf/banana">http://github.com/CWood-sdf/banana</a></td>
<td>HTML Renderer for Neovim Plugins Called Banana</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://github.com/leftmove/facebook.js">http://github.com/leftmove/facebook.js</a></td>
<td>Developing Facebook.js A Modern API Wrapper for Facebook</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/amoffat/manifest">https://github.com/amoffat/manifest</a></td>
<td>Title: Python Library for Simplifying LLM Calls</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/humishum/hacker%5C_news%5C_keys">https://github.com/humishum/hacker\_news\_keys</a></td>
<td>Creating a Hacker News Browser Extension Using LLMs</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/csjh/pest">https://github.com/csjh/pest</a></td>
<td>Efficient Row-Based Serialization Format with TypeScript Type Safety</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WillAdams/gcodepreviewbig">https://github.com/WillAdams/gcodepreviewbig</a></td>
<td>Creating a Python Enhanced OpenSCAD Library for CNC Projects</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/james-a-rob/KodaStream">https://github.com/james-a-rob/KodaStream</a></td>
<td>Title: Interactive Video API for Shoppable Live Streams</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/chaosharmonic/escapeHatch">https://github.com/chaosharmonic/escapeHatch</a></td>
<td>Developing a Lightweight Job Search Tool With Custom Features</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/JUSTSUJAY/Django%5C_Projects">https://github.com/JUSTSUJAY/Django\_Projects</a></td>
<td>Embracing Virtual Presence and Mastering Django for Impactful Development</td>
<td>SELF_IMPROVEMENT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/memfreeme/memfree">https://github.com/memfreeme/memfree</a></td>
<td>MemFree AI Search Engine for Instant Accurate Answers</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://dot-and-box.github.io/dot-and-box/" rel="nofollow">https://dot-and-box.github.io/dot-and-box/</a></td>
<td>Dot And Box Offers Animations Visualizing Algorithms</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mliezun/caddy-snake">https://github.com/mliezun/caddy-snake</a></td>
<td>Title: Integrating HTTP Requests for Python Apps Using Go</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/BigJk/end%5C_of%5C_eden">https://github.com/BigJk/end\_of\_eden</a></td>
<td>Terminal-Based Deck Builder Game With Mouse Support And Image</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/learnbyexample/TUI-apps">https://github.com/learnbyexample/TUI-apps</a></td>
<td>Updated Vim Guide Published and New Python TUI App Development</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/rybarix/snaptail">https://github.com/rybarix/snaptail</a></td>
<td>Exploring Single Source File Applications</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/dvasanth/kadugu">https://github.com/dvasanth/kadugu</a></td>
<td>Building Blazing Speed VPN In Less Than 1000 Lines Of Code</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/claceio/clace">https://github.com/claceio/clace</a></td>
<td>Clace App Server For Multi Language Containerized Applications</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/leondz/garak">https://github.com/leondz/garak</a></td>
<td>Contribution to LLM Vulnerability Scanner Alongside Final Year Studies</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/coreyp1/CTang">https://github.com/coreyp1/CTang</a></td>
<td>Developing CTang A Modern Scripting Language</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ayinke-llc/malak">https://github.com/ayinke-llc/malak</a></td>
<td>Title: Developing an OSS Relationship Hub for Founders and Investors</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/fedi-e2ee/public-key-directory-specificat">https://github.com/fedi-e2ee/public-key-directory-specificat</a></td>
<td>Building an Open Source Federated Public Key Directory</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/laktak/chkbit">https://github.com/laktak/chkbit</a></td>
<td>Title: Simplifying Cross-Platform Builds by Rewriting chkbit in Go</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/latebit/latebit-engine">https://github.com/latebit/latebit-engine</a></td>
<td>Game Engine for Coders with Integrated Tools in VSCode</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/andrew-johnson-4/lambda-mountain">https://github.com/andrew-johnson-4/lambda-mountain</a></td>
<td>Verifiable Correctness in Compiler Agnostic Programs</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/spirobel/mininext">https://github.com/spirobel/mininext</a></td>
<td>Mininext Merges Index PHP Simplicity With NPM And TypeScript</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/styluslabs/maps">https://github.com/styluslabs/maps</a></td>
<td>Title: Open Source Maps Application</td>
<td>OTHER</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/thebigG/GunnerIt">https://github.com/thebigG/GunnerIt</a></td>
<td>Title: Passion Project Scrolling Shooter Inspired By Strike Gunner STG</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/itissid/privyloci">https://github.com/itissid/privyloci</a></td>
<td>Zero Trust Proposal for Mobile Location Permission Control</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/brainless/dwata/tree/feature/prepare%5C_mvp%5C">https://github.com/brainless/dwata/tree/feature/prepare\_mvp\</a>_</td>
<td>Open Source App for Emails with AI Features</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/rprtr258/pm">https://github.com/rprtr258/pm</a></td>
<td>Title: Simple Linux Process Manager</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/jasiek/webprog-anytone">https://github.com/jasiek/webprog-anytone</a></td>
<td>Programming Anytone AT878 DMR Radios via Web Browser</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/moj-analytical-services/splink">https://github.com/moj-analytical-services/splink</a></td>
<td>Version 4 Released for Data Deduplication and Linkage Library</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/preludejs">https://github.com/preludejs</a></td>
<td>Developing Standard Libraries for TypeScript and JavaScript</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/b00bl1k/uwan">https://github.com/b00bl1k/uwan</a></td>
<td>LoRaWAN Node Device Library Development and Documentation Summary</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/codetiger/PowerTiger">https://github.com/codetiger/PowerTiger</a></td>
<td>PowerTiger Open Source Energy Monitoring Solution Using RPi Pico W</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/laudspeaker/laudspeaker">https://github.com/laudspeaker/laudspeaker</a></td>
<td>Techno Thriller Panopticon Explores Encryption and Espionage</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/certeu/morio">https://github.com/certeu/morio</a></td>
<td>Morio Streamlines Observability Data for Traditional On-Premises Infrastructure</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/iterative/datachain">https://github.com/iterative/datachain</a></td>
<td>Title: Out Of Memory Dataframe For Wrangling Unstructured Data At Scale</td>
<td>OTHER</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/petabyt/libui-touch">https://github.com/petabyt/libui-touch</a></td>
<td>Unfinished C-Based Alternative to React Native</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/David-OConnor/plascad">https://github.com/David-OConnor/plascad</a></td>
<td>PlasCAD Molecular Biology Plasmid Editor Seeking Feedback</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/tttapa/Control-Surface">https://github.com/tttapa/Control-Surface</a></td>
<td>Repurposing a Teensy Synth into a MIDI Controller</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/cmakafui/batchwizard">https://github.com/cmakafui/batchwizard</a></td>
<td>BatchWizard A Command Line Tool for OpenAI Batch Jobs</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ruuda/rcl">https://github.com/ruuda/rcl</a></td>
<td>Title: Enhancements to RCL Language with Float Support and Query Shorthand</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/Eccentric-Anomalies/Tungsten-Moon-Demo-Re">https://github.com/Eccentric-Anomalies/Tungsten-Moon-Demo-Re</a></td>
<td>Tungsten Moon VR Desktop Spaceflight Simulator Nears Early Access Release</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/matry/editor">https://github.com/matry/editor</a></td>
<td>Keyboard-Driven UI Editor Inspired by Vim and Webflow</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ssherman/weighted%5C_list%5C_rank">https://github.com/ssherman/weighted\_list\_rank</a></td>
<td>Title: Improving Book Ranking Algorithm Through Collaboration With Data Scientists</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/DefGuard">https://github.com/DefGuard</a></td>
<td>DefGuard Open Source SSO Integrating Wireguard and OIDC</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/glaretechnologies/substrataCustom">https://github.com/glaretechnologies/substrataCustom</a></td>
<td>Open Source Metaverse With Custom 3D Engine And Voice Chat</td>
<td>OTHER</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ibizaman/selfhostblocks">https://github.com/ibizaman/selfhostblocks</a></td>
<td>Self Host Blocks A Modular Server Management Tool</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/golang-malawi/qatarina">https://github.com/golang-malawi/qatarina</a></td>
<td>Building a User Acceptance Testing Platform with Go and Encouraging Go Adoption</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/curveball/a12n-server">https://github.com/curveball/a12n-server</a></td>
<td>Title: Open Source OAuth2 Server Competing with Auth0</td>
<td>OTHER</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/jaronilan/stories">https://github.com/jaronilan/stories</a></td>
<td>Title: Finishing a Yearlong Short Story About SEO</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/featurevisor/featurevisor">https://github.com/featurevisor/featurevisor</a></td>
<td>Title: Open Source Tool for Declarative Feature Management</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/patrulek/modernRX">https://github.com/patrulek/modernRX</a></td>
<td>Upgrading AVX2 to AVX512 in RandomX Algorithm Reimplementation</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/mseravalli/grizol">https://github.com/mseravalli/grizol</a></td>
<td>Grizol: Syncthing Compatible Client Leveraging Rclone Backends</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/beef331/potato">https://github.com/beef331/potato</a></td>
<td>Hot Code Reloading Library for Nim Game Framework</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/chrisdavies/atomic-css">https://github.com/chrisdavies/atomic-css</a></td>
<td>Zero-Dependency Bun Application with Tailwind-Like Layer</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/carlnewton/habitat">https://github.com/carlnewton/habitat</a></td>
<td>Developing Habitat A Self Hosted Social Platform</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/achristmascarl/rainfrog">https://github.com/achristmascarl/rainfrog</a></td>
<td>Rainfrog Postgres Management Terminal with Vim-like Keybindings</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/aravinda0/qtile-bonsai">https://github.com/aravinda0/qtile-bonsai</a></td>
<td>Qtile Bonsai Completion and Future PDF Parser Plans</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/emlearn/emlearn-micropython">https://github.com/emlearn/emlearn-micropython</a></td>
<td>MicroPython for Machine Learning on Microcontroller Sensors</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/julien040/anyquery">https://github.com/julien040/anyquery</a></td>
<td>Building Anyquery An SQL Query Engine For Diverse Data Sources</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/elijah-potter/harper">https://github.com/elijah-potter/harper</a></td>
<td>Improving On-Device Grammar Checker with Minimal Resource Use</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://bgammon.org/code" rel="nofollow">https://bgammon.org/code</a></td>
<td>Open Source Online Backgammon Project Inspired By Lichess</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://gist.github.com/skittleson/705624a8f6967187096091cbd">https://gist.github.com/skittleson/705624a8f6967187096091cbd</a></td>
<td>Bluetooth Low Energy Wall of Sheep Toy App</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/elixir-error-tracker/error-tracker">https://github.com/elixir-error-tracker/error-tracker</a></td>
<td>Elixir Based Error Reporting Solution</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="http://github.com/kviklet/kviklet">http://github.com/kviklet/kviklet</a></td>
<td>Streamlining SQL Query Reviews to Prevent Costly Errors</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/opslane/opslane">https://github.com/opslane/opslane</a></td>
<td>Building a Copilot for Oncall Engineers Reducing Grunt Work</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/pierreyoda/hncli">https://github.com/pierreyoda/hncli</a></td>
<td>Developing a Rust Based Hacker News TUI Reader</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/ibudiallo/automated-agents-book">https://github.com/ibudiallo/automated-agents-book</a></td>
<td>Creating A Comprehensive Guide On Building Effective Chatbots</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/jhspetersson/git-task">https://github.com/jhspetersson/git-task</a></td>
<td>Git Task: Local Task Manager and Bug Tracker in Git</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/madprops/goldie">https://github.com/madprops/goldie</a></td>
<td>Firefox Vertical Tabs Powerful Python Chat Client Nim Text Finder</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/av/harbor">https://github.com/av/harbor</a></td>
<td>Building a Toolkit to Save Time Using Local LLMs</td>
<td>PERSONAL_PROJECT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/captn3m0/ideas">https://github.com/captn3m0/ideas</a></td>
<td>Curated Events Platform For Bangalore Using Open Source Tools</td>
<td>STARTUP</td>
</tr>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[French prosecutors say Telegram CEO freed from custody, will appear in court (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/france-telegram-pavel-durov-arrest-6e213d227458f330ed16e7fe221a696c</link>
            <guid>41380450</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 15:14:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/france-telegram-pavel-durov-arrest-6e213d227458f330ed16e7fe221a696c">https://apnews.com/article/france-telegram-pavel-durov-arrest-6e213d227458f330ed16e7fe221a696c</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41380450">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://apnews.com/article/france-telegram-pavel-durov-arrest-6e213d227458f330ed16e7fe221a696c: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Interview with Signal President Meredith Whittaker (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.wired.com/story/meredith-whittaker-signal/</link>
            <guid>41380154</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 14:48:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/meredith-whittaker-signal/">https://www.wired.com/story/meredith-whittaker-signal/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41380154">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.wired.com/story/meredith-whittaker-signal/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon Still Has a Counterfeit Problem (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://prospect.org/power/2024-08-28-amazon-counterfeit-problem-ink-cartridges/</link>
            <guid>41380130</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 14:46:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://prospect.org/power/2024-08-28-amazon-counterfeit-problem-ink-cartridges/">https://prospect.org/power/2024-08-28-amazon-counterfeit-problem-ink-cartridges/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41380130">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content" data-transition="content" data-loop="false" itemprop="articleBody">

    <p>Too often in our economy, we are faced with an unpalatable set of choices, with corporate schemes on all sides of us and no real escape. Such is the case with printer ink and toner cartridges, where the choice is between monopoly incumbents and questionable knockoffs.</p>

<p>Printers are a classic example of a business where the replacement parts can be more lucrative than the hardware, sometimes called a “razor/razor blade” dynamic. Typically, printer manufacturers have a monopoly on ink and toner replacement cartridges, and can charge exorbitant prices that over time outstrip the cost of the printer itself. More competition in this market would be good, but companies work hard to prevent third parties from being able to sell replacement cartridges. Hewlett-Packard’s CEO has even gone so far as to claim that non-HP products <a href="https://www.tomshardware.com/peripherals/printers/hp-ceo-justifies-blocking-third-party-ink-cartridges-by-claiming-they-can-inject-malware" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (inject malware)">inject malware</a> into its printers, which <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/hp-ceo-ink-cartridge-hackers-dynamic-security/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (experts find dubious)">experts find dubious</a>.</p>

<p>But independent ink and toner cartridge makers have a difficult time getting into retail stores; a much simpler way for them to challenge incumbents is online, particularly through the leading marketplace, Amazon. There, the incentives are less toward selling a better product at a lower price, and more toward capitalizing on inattentive consumers.</p>

<p><a href="https://prospect.org/api/pv/XpLhyIgSqszUV0UmDcKYp1vQvAH9SVmkhz6KBOEyfixGflmtZo6XJqtTtIj2UVqa/++/topics/david-dayen/"><strong><em>More from David Dayen</em></strong></a></p>

<p>This is facilitated by a vast third-party marketplace on Amazon that makes it simple for millions of people to sell on the site. It’s essentially impossible for Amazon to know what’s being sold at any one time, and as a result a major counterfeit market, largely produced in China, has sprung up. In the past, brands like <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2016/07/20/birkenstock-quits-amazon-in-us-after-counterfeit-surge.html" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Birkenstock)">Birkenstock</a> and <a href="https://www.forbes.com/councils/forbesbusinesscouncil/2020/01/22/why-nike-cut-ties-with-amazon-and-what-it-means-for-other-retailers/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Nike)">Nike</a> have fled the site rather than see their products continuously knocked off, and thousands of products have <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/amazon-has-ceded-control-of-its-site-the-result-thousands-of-banned-unsafe-or-mislabeled-products-11566564990" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (been posted for sale)">been posted for sale</a> that are not only fake but deemed unsafe or banned by federal regulators. In response, Amazon created a <a href="https://trustworthyshopping.aboutamazon.com/counterfeitcrimesunit" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Counterfeit Crimes Unit)">Counterfeit Crimes Unit</a> and claims to have seized <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/3/26/24112380/amazons-data-shows-the-massive-scale-of-its-counterfeit-problem" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (over seven million counterfeit products)">over seven million counterfeit products</a> from its marketplace in 2023.</p>

<p>These two monopoly problems—user lock-in and unpoliceable, potentially hazardous marketplaces—collide in the listings for replacement ink cartridges on Amazon.</p>

<p>A review conducted by the <i>Prospect </i>found 131 different ink cartridge replacements for home printers whose packaging looks identical to brand-name products for HP, Epson, Canon, and Brother. By using <a href="https://advertising.amazon.com/library/guides/cost-per-click" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (pay-per-click advertising campaigns)">pay-per-click advertising campaigns</a>, these generics can achieve a higher page rank than the brand names.</p>

<p>The problem persists despite the fact that HP successfully went to court and secured an injunction against third-party sellers that mimicked its packaging for ink cartridges. And it’s happening even though Amazon’s Counterfeit Crimes Unit is <a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/policy-news-views/amazon-and-canon-file-joint-lawsuit-to-protect-customers-and-hold-counterfeiters-accountable" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (separately working with Canon)">separately working with Canon</a> to prevent knock-offs in another business line.</p>

<p>Customers are therefore stuck, either paying high prices for monopoly replacement parts, or duped into buying what they think are the brand names, which can be inconsistent in quality, according to <a href="https://www.consumerreports.org/printers/third-party-printer-ink-cartridges-pros-cons/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (consumer advocates)">consumer advocates</a>.</p>

<p><b>THE 131 LISTINGS, WITH COMPANY NAMES</b> like Ziprint, Ceeboo, Echallenge, and Lemero, are not appreciably different in price than the brand-name products, and often cost more. The packaging looks identical, with the same color patterns and structures—really everything but the brand name itself.</p>

<p>For example, this query for “<a href="https://www.amazon.com/s?k=epson+822xl+ink+cartridges&amp;crid=3JOJV3AWZD1HQ&amp;sprefix=epson+%2Caps%2C135&amp;ref=nb_sb_ss_pltr-sample-20_3_6" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Epson 822XL ink cartridges)">Epson 822XL ink cartridges</a>” features a variety of Epson-brand and third-party products, all of which look the same. The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Remanufactured-Cartridges-Replacement-Workforce-WF-3820/dp/B0D3LW4ZGN/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (generic products)">generic products</a> usually have the word “Epson” somewhere in their online descriptions, since they are replacements for Epson printers. The situation is the same for Canon, Brother, and HP toner and ink cartridges.</p>

<p>Packaging meant to emulate a brand’s design without using its logo can be a violation of copyright laws. HP actually won a <a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar_case?case=14448124618569096187&amp;hl=en&amp;as_sdt=6&amp;as_vis=1&amp;oi=scholarr" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (federal court case)">federal court case</a> in March against a Chinese manufacturing company called Ejet, which HP accused of infringing upon its “trade dress,” the technical term for packaging design.</p>

<p>The court entered a permanent injunction preventing Ejet from selling anything with HP’s trade dress in the future. The ruling even stipulated what HP’s protectable trade dress looks like; for example, for its XL Series, HP packaging has a “bright green top panel,” “bright green accents calling out text and product features,” “black beveled side panels,” a “vibrant green nature scene showing detailed imagery of a butterfly resting on lush, green plant life,” and a “white call out panel describing features of the ink cartridges.”</p>

<p>Yet plenty of knockoff products are available on Amazon. Here is a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0D2GTYXBV" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (two-pack HP 67XL cartridge replacement)">two-pack HP 67XL cartridge replacement</a> from a company called InkID with packaging that includes all of those features, except for toucans instead of butterflies. It lists for $54.93 on Amazon. The equivalent HP <a href="https://www.amazon.com/HP-Original-High-Yield-Tricolor-Cartridges/dp/B08SWN848G/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (two-pack lists)">two-pack lists</a> for $45.89.</p>

<p>A <a href="https://www.amazon.com/s?k=hp+67xl+black+ink+cartridge&amp;i=electronics&amp;crid=2B6US285OY3MM&amp;sprefix=hp+67%2Celectronics%2C175&amp;ref=nb_sb_ss_pltr-sample-20_1_5" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (search for an HP 67XL ink cartridge)">search for an HP 67XL ink cartridge</a> on Amazon lists the InkID product higher than the HP product. There is a small bit of text with the word “sponsored” on the InkID listing, indicating that the company bought space on this search with an ad.</p>

<p>Amazon and Canon <a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/policy-news-views/amazon-and-canon-file-joint-lawsuit-to-protect-customers-and-hold-counterfeiters-accountable" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (filed a joint lawsuit last year)">filed a joint lawsuit last year</a> to stop Chinese counterfeit camera batteries and chargers from marketing on the site. Yet there are <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0CMXJCP2S?th=1" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (plenty)">plenty</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B091L3ZLMD" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (of)">of</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0BTH2K6NQ" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Canon)">Canon</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0CZ46KSFV" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (ink)">ink</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0B6V2VQVP" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (cartridge)">cartridge</a> <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0BH5159C9" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (replacements)">replacements</a> being sold on Amazon with identical packaging as their branded products. Sponsored cartridges from companies like Ubinki are frequently <a href="https://www.amazon.com/s?k=canon+275xl+cartridge&amp;crid=2617Q5KINY7ZE&amp;sprefix=Canon+275XL%2Caps%2C126&amp;ref=nb_sb_ss_fb_1_11_pltr-sample-20" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (higher in searches)">higher in searches</a> than Canon’s own products.</p>

<p>One of the ways Amazon has attempted to crack down on counterfeits on their site is by inviting companies to do the policing for them. A program called “<a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/amazon-shifts-power-to-brands-in-fight-against-fake-products-11551349920" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (Project Zero)">Project Zero</a>” allows brand owners to delete suspected fakes and knockoffs of their products. But while giving brands the power to delete competitors from the leading e-commerce website could be seen as anti-competitive, in reality there’s just far too much infringement for any company to keep up with the fakes. And Amazon, which reaps ad revenue from the infringing competitors, has at least a financial incentive to keep a laissez-faire attitude toward the issue.</p>

<p>HP did not respond to requests for comment, nor did its lawyers in the federal court case. Epson and Brother also did not respond. A listing for a Canon media representative could not be found.</p>

<p>Amazon spokesperson Christy Vargas responded after press time to an inquiry from the <em>Prospect</em>, saying that, “In terms of trade dress infringement, Amazon will remove infringing listings from the store.” Vargas highlighted “proactive tools help to identify these infringements,” and said that the company is&nbsp;“becoming more effective at identifying, seizing and disposing of counterfeit products which is acting as a deterrent to other bad actors.”</p>

<p>In the past, Amazon executives have also proclaimed their vigilance. Worldwide director of buyer risk prevention Scott Knapp has said that “we have no tolerance for counterfeits or fakes,” and “if we find them, we shut it down immediately.” But that conditional—“if we find them”—neatly describes the problem. As opening a new store in the Amazon marketplace requires just a few clicks, it would take a small army to effectively shut the counterfeits out.</p>

<p>Amazon chronically <a href="https://www.aboutamazon.com/news/policy-news-views/amazon-brand-protection-report-2023-counterfeit-products" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (touts its success)">touts its success</a> in preventing counterfeit products, including <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/ai-counterfeit-detection-amazon/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (the use of artificial-intelligence tools)">the use of artificial-intelligence tools</a> to help in policing. But it has settled lawsuits in the past over counterfeits on its website, including a <a href="https://www.retaildive.com/news/amazon-and-williams-sonoma-settle-legal-battle-over-ip/588373/" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (2020 case)">2020 case</a> with Williams-Sonoma, and a <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/amazon-settles-suit-over-alleged-fake-cashmere-products-11639072651" target="_blank" aria-label="Link opens in new window (2021 case)">2021 case</a> over cashmere items.</p>

<p>It’s hard to know what an equitable solution to this would be for customers. Banning all competing ink cartridge replacements would just grant a monopoly to printer companies to raise prices. Yet there’s no real competition on price with these third parties on Amazon; they merely try to capture the inattentive consumer by purchasing better “shelf space” through search ads and trying to trick people into thinking they’re buying the name brand. And there is a somewhat legitimate question about the quality of these third-party products, mostly from Chinese companies.</p>

<p>The inescapable conclusion is that consumers habitually swim through a tank of sharks when making ordinary purchases, and that this explains some of the anger and frustration that emerges in public opinion polling about corporate power.</p>

<p><em>This story has been updated with a response from an Amazon spokesperson.</em></p>


    
    

    </div><div id="bottompageinfos">
    
    
    	<div itemprop="author" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/Person">
    	<p><a href="https://prospect.org/topics/david-dayen/"><img sizes="auto" srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAAAAACH5BAEKAAEALAAAAAABAAEAAAICTAEAOw==" alt="jsoad2xs.jpeg.jpe" data-src="https://prospect.org/downloads/253/download/jsoad2xs.jpeg.jpe?cb=0bbb1c8e0153fe817cd2a8a67acc21e8&amp;w={width}&amp;h={height}" data-widths="[100, 150, 220, 320, 450, 660, 943]" height="100" src="https://prospect.org/power/2024-08-28-amazon-counterfeit-problem-ink-cartridges/jsoad2xs.jpeg.jpe" title="jsoad2xs.jpeg.jpe" width="100"></a></p><h3><a href="https://prospect.org/topics/david-dayen/" rel="author">David Dayen</a></h3><meta itemprop="name" content="David Dayen">
			<p>David Dayen is the Prospect’s executive editor. His work has appeared in The Intercept, The New Republic, HuffPost, The Washington Post, the Los Angeles Times, and more. His most recent book is ‘Monopolized: Life in the Age of Corporate Power.’</p>
        <p><a href="https://prospect.org/topics/david-dayen/">Read more by David Dayen</a>
      

    	</p></div>
    
    <time datetime="2024-08-28T05:15:00">
    <p>August 28, 2024</p>
    <p>5:15 AM</p>
    </time>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The slow evaporation of the free/open source surplus (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2024/the-slow-evaporation-of-the-foss-surplus/</link>
            <guid>41380084</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 14:43:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2024/the-slow-evaporation-of-the-foss-surplus/">https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2024/the-slow-evaporation-of-the-foss-surplus/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41380084">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.baldurbjarnason.com/2024/the-slow-evaporation-of-the-foss-surplus/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Starting today, YouTube is almost unusable on Firefox (229 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/youtube/comments/1f30ku4/youtube_sabotaging_on_firefox/</link>
            <guid>41379517</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 13:50:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/youtube/comments/1f30ku4/youtube_sabotaging_on_firefox/">https://old.reddit.com/r/youtube/comments/1f30ku4/youtube_sabotaging_on_firefox/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41379517">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://old.reddit.com/r/youtube/comments/1f30ku4/youtube_sabotaging_on_firefox/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Judge dismisses majority of GitHub Copilot copyright claims (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.developer-tech.com/news/judge-dismisses-majority-github-copilot-copyright-claims/</link>
            <guid>41378806</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 12:39:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/judge-dismisses-majority-github-copilot-copyright-claims/">https://www.developer-tech.com/news/judge-dismisses-majority-github-copilot-copyright-claims/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41378806">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-off-canvas-content="">
            <main id="main" role="main" data-max-pages="2" data-scroll="true" data-query-type="single" data-post-type="post" data-value="51" data-front="" data-start="46230" data-ppp="1">
                                    
<article id="post-46230" role="article" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting" data-title="Judge dismisses majority of GitHub Copilot copyright claims" data-url="/news/judge-dismisses-majority-github-copilot-copyright-claims/">
    <header>
        
    </header>
    <div itemprop="text">
            <p><img width="2400" height="1653" src="https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming.jpg" alt="" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming.jpg 2400w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-300x207.jpg 300w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-1024x705.jpg 1024w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-768x529.jpg 768w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-1536x1058.jpg 1536w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-2048x1411.jpg 2048w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-290x200.jpg 290w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-380x262.jpg 380w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-350x241.jpg 350w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-100x69.jpg 100w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/github-copilot-copyright-ai-artificial-intelligence-developers-coding-programming-60x41.jpg 60w" sizes="(max-width: 2400px) 100vw, 2400px">                            </p>

            
			<div>
                <div>
    
    <p>
			<span><img alt="" src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/b8c5d238e1fddd55d8a0064f1a534ba5?s=100&amp;d=mm&amp;r=g" srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/b8c5d238e1fddd55d8a0064f1a534ba5?s=200&amp;d=mm&amp;r=g 2x" height="100" width="100" decoding="async"></span>			<span>Ryan Daws is a senior editor at TechForge Media with over a decade of experience in crafting compelling narratives and making complex topics accessible. His articles and interviews with industry leaders have earned him recognition as a key influencer by organisations like Onalytica. Under his leadership, publications have been praised by analyst firms such as Forrester for their excellence and performance. Connect with him on X (@gadget_ry) or Mastodon (@gadgetry@techhub.social)</span>
			</p>

</div>

                <hr>
            </div>
			

			
			<div>
                                    
<p>A judge has dismissed the majority of claims in <a href="https://www.artificialintelligence-news.com/2022/11/09/openai-and-microsoft-lawsuit-github-copilot/">a copyright lawsuit</a> filed by developers against GitHub, Microsoft, and OpenAI.</p>



<p>The lawsuit was initiated by a group of developers in 2022 and originally made 22 claims against the companies, alleging copyright violations related to the AI-powered <a href="https://github.com/features/copilot">GitHub Copilot</a> coding assistant.</p>



<p>Judge Jon Tigar’s ruling, unsealed last week, leaves only two claims standing: one accusing the companies of an open-source license violation and another alleging breach of contract. This decision marks a substantial setback for the developers who argued that GitHub Copilot, which uses OpenAI’s technology and is owned by Microsoft, unlawfully trained on their work.</p>



<p>The court’s dismissal primarily focused on the accusation that GitHub Copilot violates the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Digital_Millennium_Copyright_Act">Digital Millennium Copyright Act</a> (DMCA) by suggesting code without proper attribution. An amended version of the complaint had taken issue with GitHub’s duplication detection filter, which allows users to “detect and suppress” Copilot suggestions matching public code on GitHub.</p>



<p>The developers argued that turning off this filter would “receive identical code” and cited a study showing how AI models can “memorise” and reproduce parts of their training data, potentially including copyrighted code.</p>



<p>However, Judge Tigar found these arguments unconvincing. He determined that the code allegedly copied by GitHub was not sufficiently similar to the developers’ original work. The judge also noted that the cited study itself mentions that GitHub Copilot “rarely emits memorised code in benign situations.”</p>



<p>As a result, Judge Tigar dismissed this allegation with prejudice, meaning the developers cannot refile the claim. Additionally, the court dismissed requests for punitive damages and monetary relief in the form of unjust enrichment.</p>



<p>Despite this significant ruling, the legal battle is not over. The remaining claims regarding breach of contract and open-source license violations are likely to continue through litigation.</p>



<p>This case highlights the ongoing challenges and legal complexities surrounding AI-powered coding assistants and their use of existing codebases for training.</p>



<p><em>(Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@synkevych?utm_content=creditCopyText&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_source=unsplash">Roman Synkevych</a>)</em></p>



<p><strong>See also: </strong><a href="https://www.developer-tech.com//news/2024/jul/09/sam-altman-blockchain-project-world-chain-developers/"><strong>Sam Altman’s blockchain project ‘World Chain’ opens to developers</strong></a></p>



<figure><a href="https://digitaltransformation-week.com/"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="728" height="90" src="https://www.developer-tech.com//wp-content/uploads/sites/3/2022/12/dtf-banner.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/dtf-banner.jpg 728w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/dtf-banner-300x37.jpg 300w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/dtf-banner-380x47.jpg 380w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/dtf-banner-350x43.jpg 350w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/dtf-banner-100x12.jpg 100w, https://www.developer-tech.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/dtf-banner-60x7.jpg 60w" sizes="(max-width: 728px) 100vw, 728px"></a></figure>



<p><strong>Looking to revamp your digital transformation strategy?</strong> Learn more about <a href="https://digitaltransformation-week.com/">Digital Transformation Week</a> taking place in Amsterdam, California, and London. The comprehensive event is co-located with <a href="https://www.ai-expo.net/">AI &amp; Big Data Expo</a>, <a href="https://www.cybersecuritycloudexpo.com/">Cyber Security &amp; Cloud Expo</a>, and other leading events.</p>



<p>Explore other upcoming enterprise technology events and webinars powered by TechForge <a href="https://techforge.pub/upcoming-events/">here.</a></p>
                    <p><span>Tags:</span> <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/ai/" rel="tag">AI</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/artificial-intelligence/" rel="tag">artificial intelligence</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/coding/" rel="tag">coding</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/copilot/" rel="tag">copilot</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/copyright/" rel="tag">copyright</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/developers/" rel="tag">Developers</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/github/" rel="tag">github</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/microsoft/" rel="tag">microsoft</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/openai/" rel="tag">openai</a>, <a href="https://www.developer-tech.com/news/tag/programming/" rel="tag">programming</a></p>
                            </div>

        </div>
            
                
        
        



    

</article>
                            </main>
            
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Typing lists and tuples in Elixir (180 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://elixir-lang.org/blog/2024/08/28/typing-lists-and-tuples/</link>
            <guid>41378478</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 11:49:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://elixir-lang.org/blog/2024/08/28/typing-lists-and-tuples/">https://elixir-lang.org/blog/2024/08/28/typing-lists-and-tuples/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41378478">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://elixir-lang.org/blog/2024/08/28/typing-lists-and-tuples/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: IPA, a GUI for exploring inner details of PDFs (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA</link>
            <guid>41377960</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 10:22:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA">https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41377960">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Interactive PDF Analysis</h2><a id="user-content-interactive-pdf-analysis" aria-label="Permalink: Interactive PDF Analysis" href="#interactive-pdf-analysis"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><em>Interactive PDF Analysis</em> (also called IPA) allows any researcher to explore the inner details of any PDF file. PDF files may be used to carry malicious payloads that exploit vulnerabilities, and issues of PDF viewer, or may be used in phishing campaigns as social engineering artefacts.
The goal of this software is to let any analyst go deep on its own the PDF file. Via IPA, you may extract important payload from PDF files, understand the relationship across objects, and infer elements that may be helpful for triage of malicious or untrusted payloads.</p>
<p dir="auto">The main inspiration goes to the fantastic people behind Zynamics, and their excellent product, called PDF dissector.</p>
<p dir="auto">
<a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA/blob/main/data/screenshot.png"><img alt="Main window of IPA" src="https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA/raw/main/data/screenshot.png" width="600"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Simplifying analysis of PDF files</h2><a id="user-content-simplifying-analysis-of-pdf-files" aria-label="Permalink: Simplifying analysis of PDF files" href="#simplifying-analysis-of-pdf-files"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">When I started reverse engineering malware, the main tool available for analysing malicious payloads consisted of <a href="https://didierstevens.com/" rel="nofollow">Didier Stevens</a>'s excellent tools. Having become a <em>de facto</em> standard, one of the main problems with these tools was the fact that they could be used from the command line, having to remember a very large combination of flags, reporting the numbers of the various objects. Although analysis and developers have to contend with all kinds of command-line tools on a daily basis, this does not mean that we cannot create a new graphical file inspection tool.</p>
<p dir="auto">In fact, part of static analysis and reverse engineering fields also focuse on how to display the most salient information to the analyst from the point of view of user experience. Didier Stevens' tools, as well as peepdf, are already used and well broken in. However, the analyst could use something graphical in order to be able to understand the relationship between the various objects, to understand which pages they refer to and which object types (images, fonts, colours, metadata), to export stream content in a simple way and to see the content of dictionaries in table form.</p>
<p dir="auto">The main source of inspiration comes from the tool developed by Zynamics called PDF-dissector: the excellent feedback from some former users and the constant requests to release it open source spurred me to spend a few days creating this tool.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Extract and analyze metadata to identify the creator, creation date, modification history, and other essential details about the PDF file.</li>
<li>Examine the structure of the PDF document by analyzing its objects (such as text, images, and fonts) and pages to understand their relationships, content, and layout.</li>
<li>Visualize References that point to other objects or locations within the file, such as images, fonts, or specific sections.</li>
<li>Extract and save raw data streams from the PDF file to a specified location, allowing for detailed examination and analysis of the underlying binary content.</li>
<li>Implement a lighter analysis that attempts to salvage usable information from a corrupted or partially damaged PDF file, even when traditional parsing methods fail.</li>
<li>Does not require any additional software, libraries, or external services to function thanks to pdf-rs and Rust compatibility.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The tool can be compiled with Rust and cargo. No dependencies are required apart from Rust, and the crates pulled.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA
cd IPA

## compile with debug symbols, the binary is inside ./target/debug/IPA
cargo b 

## compile in release mode, the binary is inside ./target/release IPA
cargo b --release"><pre>git clone https://github.com/seekbytes/IPA
<span>cd</span> IPA

<span><span>#</span># compile with debug symbols, the binary is inside ./target/debug/IPA</span>
cargo b 

<span><span>#</span># compile in release mode, the binary is inside ./target/release IPA</span>
cargo b --release</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Credits</h2><a id="user-content-credits" aria-label="Permalink: Credits" href="#credits"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/pdf-rs/pdf">pdf-rs</a> team for their awesome library (if you have any issues parsing a PDF file, you might want to open an issue for them)</li>
<li>Zynamics for the inspiration of pdf dissector</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/emilk/egui">egui</a> for a solid immediate GUI mode</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Limitations</h2><a id="user-content-limitations" aria-label="Permalink: Limitations" href="#limitations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">IPA has the following limitations for now:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>few heuristics (if you want to suggest some, please open a new issue or write me an email)</li>
<li>no support for encrypted PDF (panics at opening, soon I'll implement a way to handle it if you know the password)</li>
<li>not every PDF file is supported due to some strict requirements that pdf-rs assumes while opening it. If you have a PDF file that should be parsable, please open an issue to <a href="https://github.com/pdf-rs/pdf/issues">pdf-rs</a> repository.</li>
<li>some object types are not viewable natively. This is something I'm still brainstorming on: e.g. graphical elements, colors.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">At the end, the tool can be really improved and I pretty bet some people will notice how bad my code is. If you're one of these, please let me know about potential improvements, better patterns, and any suggestion.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contact</h2><a id="user-content-contact" aria-label="Permalink: Contact" href="#contact"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you have any issues, improvements, or you just want to text me, email <a href="mailto:seekbytes@protonmail.com">seekbytes@protonmail.com</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Final two communications from MH370 support controlled descent scenario (2021) (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.researchgate.net/publication/355242503_Final_Two_Communications_from_MH370_Supports_Controlled_Eastward_Descent_Scenario</link>
            <guid>41376820</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 07:11:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/355242503_Final_Two_Communications_from_MH370_Supports_Controlled_Eastward_Descent_Scenario">https://www.researchgate.net/publication/355242503_Final_Two_Communications_from_MH370_Supports_Controlled_Eastward_Descent_Scenario</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41376820">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.researchgate.net/publication/355242503_Final_Two_Communications_from_MH370_Supports_Controlled_Eastward_Descent_Scenario: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cosmic Alpha Released (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.system76.com/post/cosmic-alpha-released-heres-what-people-are-saying/</link>
            <guid>41376590</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 06:30:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.system76.com/post/cosmic-alpha-released-heres-what-people-are-saying/">https://blog.system76.com/post/cosmic-alpha-released-heres-what-people-are-saying/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41376590">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://blog.system76.com/post/cosmic-alpha-released-heres-what-people-are-saying/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boxxy puts bad Linux applications in a box with only their files (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/queer/boxxy</link>
            <guid>41376558</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 06:25:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/queer/boxxy">https://github.com/queer/boxxy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41376558">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">boxxy</h2><a id="user-content-boxxy" aria-label="Permalink: boxxy" href="#boxxy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">boxxy (case-sensitive) is a tool for boxing up misbehaving Linux applications
and forcing them to put their files and directories in the right place,
<strong>without symlinks!</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">boxxy is a part of the <a href="https://discord.gg/7WgSTwh" rel="nofollow">amyware discord server</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you like what I make, consider supporting me on Patreon:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://patreon.com/amyware" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/569fea43464046133c8679542e46f8287a8243d9e9c28b6c8bde0e34d080b1fe/68747470733a2f2f692e696d6775722e636f6d2f59466a6f4364312e706e67" width="162" height="38" data-canonical-src="https://i.imgur.com/YFjoCd1.png"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Linux-only! boxxy uses Linux namespaces for its functionality.</p>
<p dir="auto">For example, consider tmux. It wants to put its config in <code>~/.tmux.conf</code>. With
boxxy, you can put its config in <code>~/.config/tmux/tmux.conf</code> instead:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# ~/.config/boxxy/boxxy.yaml
rules:
- name: &quot;redirect tmux config from ~/.tmux.conf to ~/.config/tmux/tmux.conf&quot;
  target: &quot;~/.tmux.conf&quot;
  rewrite: &quot;~/.config/tmux/tmux.conf&quot;
  mode: &quot;file&quot;"><pre><span><span>#</span> ~/.config/boxxy/boxxy.yaml</span>
<span>rules</span>:
- <span>name</span>: <span><span>"</span>redirect tmux config from ~/.tmux.conf to ~/.config/tmux/tmux.conf<span>"</span></span>
  <span>target</span>: <span><span>"</span>~/.tmux.conf<span>"</span></span>
  <span>rewrite</span>: <span><span>"</span>~/.config/tmux/tmux.conf<span>"</span></span>
  <span>mode</span>: <span><span>"</span>file<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://asciinema.org/a/558679" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/4c3c0cf0d934c5becca6e031e627a80f1f42aece053905e00099cd6af34a7d82/68747470733a2f2f61736369696e656d612e6f72672f612f3535383637392e737667" alt="asciicast" data-canonical-src="https://asciinema.org/a/558679.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">motivation</h2><a id="user-content-motivation" aria-label="Permalink: motivation" href="#motivation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I recently had to use the AWS CLI. It wants to save data in <code>~/.aws</code>, but I
don't want it to just clutter up my <code>$HOME</code> however it wants. boxxy lets me
force it to puts its data somewhere nice and proper.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: features" href="#features"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">potential drawbacks</h3><a id="user-content-potential-drawbacks" aria-label="Permalink: potential drawbacks" href="#potential-drawbacks"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>new project, 0.x.y, comes with all those warnings</li>
<li><strong>cannot</strong> use sudo inside the container (see <a href="https://github.com/queer/boxxy/issues/6" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/queer/boxxy/issues/6/hovercard">#6</a>)</li>
<li>primarily tested for my use-cases</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">example usage</h2><a id="user-content-example-usage" aria-label="Permalink: example usage" href="#example-usage"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git:(mistress) | ▶  cat ~/.config/boxxy/boxxy.yaml
rules:
- name: &quot;Store AWS CLI config in ~/.config/aws&quot;
  target: &quot;~/.aws&quot;
  rewrite: &quot;~/.config/aws&quot;

git:(mistress) | ▶  boxxy aws configure
 INFO  boxxy > loaded 1 rules
 INFO  boxxy::enclosure > applying rule 'Store AWS CLI config in ~/.config/aws'
 INFO  boxxy::enclosure > redirect: ~/.aws -> ~/.config/aws
 INFO  boxxy::enclosure > boxed &quot;aws&quot; ♥
AWS Access Key ID [****************d]: a
AWS Secret Access Key [****************c]: b
Default region name [b]: c
Default output format [a]: d
git:(mistress) | ▶  ls ~/.aws
git:(mistress) | ▶  ls ~/.config/aws
config  credentials
git:(mistress) | ▶  cat ~/.config/aws/config
[default]
region = c
output = d
git:(mistress) | ▶"><pre>git:(mistress) <span>|</span> ▶  cat <span>~</span>/.config/boxxy/boxxy.yaml
rules:
- name: <span><span>"</span>Store AWS CLI config in ~/.config/aws<span>"</span></span>
  target: <span><span>"</span>~/.aws<span>"</span></span>
  rewrite: <span><span>"</span>~/.config/aws<span>"</span></span>

git:(mistress) <span>|</span> ▶  boxxy aws configure
 INFO  boxxy <span>&gt;</span> loaded 1 rules
 INFO  boxxy::enclosure <span>&gt;</span> applying rule <span><span>'</span>Store AWS CLI config in ~/.config/aws<span>'</span></span>
 INFO  boxxy::enclosure <span>&gt;</span> redirect: <span>~</span>/.aws -<span>&gt;</span> <span>~</span>/.config/aws
 INFO  boxxy::enclosure <span>&gt;</span> boxed <span><span>"</span>aws<span>"</span></span> ♥
AWS Access Key ID [<span>****************</span>d]: a
AWS Secret Access Key [<span>****************</span>c]: b
Default region name [b]: c
Default output format [a]: d
git:(mistress) <span>|</span> ▶  ls <span>~</span>/.aws
git:(mistress) <span>|</span> ▶  ls <span>~</span>/.config/aws
config  credentials
git:(mistress) <span>|</span> ▶  cat <span>~</span>/.config/aws/config
[default]
region = c
output = d
git:(mistress) <span>|</span> ▶</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">suggested usage</h3><a id="user-content-suggested-usage" aria-label="Permalink: suggested usage" href="#suggested-usage"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>alias aws="boxxy aws"</code> (repeat for other tools)</li>
<li>use contexts to keep project configs separate on disk</li>
<li>dotfiles!</li>
<li>stop using symlinks!!!</li>
<li>no more dev config files when writing code</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The boxxy configuration file lives in <code>~/.config/boxxy/boxxy.yaml</code>. If none
exists, an empty one will be created for you.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="rules:
# The name of the rule. User-friendly name for your reference
- name: &quot;redirect aws-cli from ~/.aws to ~/.config/aws&quot;
  # The target of the rule, ie the file/directory that will be shadowed by the
  # rewrite.
  target: &quot;~/.aws&quot;
  # The rewrite of the rule, ie the file/directory that will be used instead of
  # the target.
  rewrite: &quot;~/.config/aws&quot;
- name: &quot;use different k8s configs when in ~/Projects/my-cool-startup&quot;
  target: &quot;~/.kube/config&quot;
  rewrite: &quot;~/Projects/my-cool-startup/.kube/config&quot;
  # The context for the rule. Any paths listed in the context are paths where
  # this rule will apply. If no context is specified, the rule applies
  # globally.
  context:
  - &quot;~/Projects/my-cool-startup&quot;
  # The mode of this rule, either `directory` or `file`. `directory` is the
  # default. Must be specified for the correct behaviour when the target is a
  # file. Required because the target file/directory may not exist yet.
  mode: &quot;file&quot;
  # The list of commands that this rule applies to. If no commands are
  # specified, the rule applies to all programs run with boxxy.
  only:
  - &quot;kubectl&quot;"><pre><span>rules</span>:
<span><span>#</span> The name of the rule. User-friendly name for your reference</span>
- <span>name</span>: <span><span>"</span>redirect aws-cli from ~/.aws to ~/.config/aws<span>"</span></span>
  <span><span>#</span> The target of the rule, ie the file/directory that will be shadowed by the</span>
  <span><span>#</span> rewrite.</span>
  <span>target</span>: <span><span>"</span>~/.aws<span>"</span></span>
  <span><span>#</span> The rewrite of the rule, ie the file/directory that will be used instead of</span>
  <span><span>#</span> the target.</span>
  <span>rewrite</span>: <span><span>"</span>~/.config/aws<span>"</span></span>
- <span>name</span>: <span><span>"</span>use different k8s configs when in ~/Projects/my-cool-startup<span>"</span></span>
  <span>target</span>: <span><span>"</span>~/.kube/config<span>"</span></span>
  <span>rewrite</span>: <span><span>"</span>~/Projects/my-cool-startup/.kube/config<span>"</span></span>
  <span><span>#</span> The context for the rule. Any paths listed in the context are paths where</span>
  <span><span>#</span> this rule will apply. If no context is specified, the rule applies</span>
  <span><span>#</span> globally.</span>
  <span>context</span>:
  - <span><span>"</span>~/Projects/my-cool-startup<span>"</span></span>
  <span><span>#</span> The mode of this rule, either `directory` or `file`. `directory` is the</span>
  <span><span>#</span> default. Must be specified for the correct behaviour when the target is a</span>
  <span><span>#</span> file. Required because the target file/directory may not exist yet.</span>
  <span>mode</span>: <span><span>"</span>file<span>"</span></span>
  <span><span>#</span> The list of commands that this rule applies to. If no commands are</span>
  <span><span>#</span> specified, the rule applies to all programs run with boxxy.</span>
  <span>only</span>:
  - <span><span>"</span>kubectl<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">syntax</h3><a id="user-content-syntax" aria-label="Permalink: syntax" href="#syntax"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="rules:
- name: &quot;any valid string&quot; # required
  target: &quot;path&quot; # required
  rewrite: &quot;path&quot; # required
  context: # optional
  - &quot;path&quot;
  - &quot;path&quot;
  mode: &quot;directory | file&quot; # optional
  only: # optional
  - &quot;binary name&quot;
  - &quot;binary name&quot;
  env: # optional
    KEY: &quot;value&quot;"><pre><span>rules</span>:
- <span>name</span>: <span><span>"</span>any valid string<span>"</span></span> <span><span>#</span> required</span>
  <span>target</span>: <span><span>"</span>path<span>"</span></span> <span><span>#</span> required</span>
  <span>rewrite</span>: <span><span>"</span>path<span>"</span></span> <span><span>#</span> required</span>
  <span>context</span>: <span><span>#</span> optional</span>
  - <span><span>"</span>path<span>"</span></span>
  - <span><span>"</span>path<span>"</span></span>
  <span>mode</span>: <span><span>"</span>directory | file<span>"</span></span> <span><span>#</span> optional</span>
  <span>only</span>: <span><span>#</span> optional</span>
  - <span><span>"</span>binary name<span>"</span></span>
  - <span><span>"</span>binary name<span>"</span></span>
  <span>env</span>: <span><span>#</span> optional</span>
    <span>KEY</span>: <span><span>"</span>value<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">developing</h2><a id="user-content-developing" aria-label="Permalink: developing" href="#developing"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>set up pre-commit: <code>pre-commit install</code></li>
<li>make sure it builds: <code>cargo build</code></li>
<li>do the thing!</li>
<li>test with the command of your choice, ex. <code>cargo run -- ls -lah ~/.config</code></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">how does it work?</h3><a id="user-content-how-does-it-work" aria-label="Permalink: how does it work?" href="#how-does-it-work"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>create temporary directory in /tmp</li>
<li>set up new user/mount namespace</li>
<li>bind-mount <code>/</code> to tmp directory</li>
<li>bind-mount rule mounts rw so that target programs can use them</li>
<li>remount <code>/</code> ro</li>
<li>run!</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">credits</h2><a id="user-content-credits" aria-label="Permalink: credits" href="#credits"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>fixtures/helloworld-appimage-x86_84.AppImage</code>: <a href="https://github.com/ClonedRepos/hello-world-appimage">https://github.com/ClonedRepos/hello-world-appimage</a></li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Are We Anti-Cheat Yet? (161 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://areweanticheatyet.com/</link>
            <guid>41376044</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 04:46:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://areweanticheatyet.com/">https://areweanticheatyet.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41376044">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://areweanticheatyet.com/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Thoughts on the Durov Arrest (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://prestonbyrne.com/2024/08/24/thoughts-on-the-durov-arrest/</link>
            <guid>41375902</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 04:16:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://prestonbyrne.com/2024/08/24/thoughts-on-the-durov-arrest/">https://prestonbyrne.com/2024/08/24/thoughts-on-the-durov-arrest/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41375902">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-26232">
		<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		
<p>Today we learn that Pavel Durov, founder of the popular messaging app Telegram, has been arrested as his private jet landed in France. </p>



<p>Early indications are that the arrest stems from Telegram’s alleged noncompliance with French requests for content moderation and data disclosure:</p>



<figure><div>
<blockquote data-width="550" data-dnt="true"><div lang="en" dir="ltr"><p>BREAKING: <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Telegram?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Telegram</a> CEO Pavel Durov arrested by French authorities.</p><p>Early official comments to French media suggest this follows from France's displeasure with Telegram's moderation &amp; compliance with official requests(?).</p><p>If so, I'm pretty sure this is an unprecedented action… <a href="https://t.co/hKa1Ip0buD">pic.twitter.com/hKa1Ip0buD</a></p></div>— John Scott-Railton (@jsrailton) <a href="https://twitter.com/jsrailton/status/1827457960110399604?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 24, 2024</a></blockquote>
</div></figure>



<p>A bit of legal background is called for.</p>



<p>Most social media companies of global significance that are not Chinese are headquartered in the United States. This is no accident; the United States (wisely) undertook policy moves in the late 1990s to minimize liability for the operators of online services, most notably the enactment of Section 230 of the Communications Decency Act, which (essentially) says that operators of social media websites are not liable for the torts or crimes of their users. </p>



<p>There are of course some, very narrow, exceptions to this rule. For example, illegal pornography is subject to a mandatory takedown-and-reporting regime under <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/2258A" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/2258A">18 U.S. Code § 2258A</a>. I hasten to add that complying with this law is table stakes for a user-generated content business, compliance tools like PhotoDNA are widely available and free to use, and I would be shocked if Telegram <em>didn’t</em> comply. There’s also FOSTA-SESTA, which prohibits operators of online platforms from running services which knowingly support sex trafficking or prostitution with the intent to facilitate the same (see: <em><a href="https://www.justice.gov/usao-az/us-v-michael-lacey">United States v. Lacey et al. (Backpage)</a></em>, <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/47/230">47 U.S. Code § 230(e)(5)</a>), <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/2421A">18 US Code § 2421A</a>). This law will be a major compliance concern for any dating app, and is a reason why sites which once had “personals” listings like CraigsList, which were non-core to the rest of their offering, <a href="https://www.craigslist.org/about/FOSTA">got rid of</a> those “dating”-specific features. One can still post a prostitution ad in the used boat listings, but Craigslist can’t be said to have intended to facilitate that behavior.</p>



<p>Other than that, though, social media website operators are generally not liable for the torts or crimes of their users. Nor are they liable under aider/abettor theories if they just passively host the content. (See: <em>Twitter v. Taamneh</em>, <a href="https://www.oyez.org/cases/2022/21-1496">598 U.S. _ (2023</a>) – civil liability for aiding and abetting, at least on this side of the pond, requires “knowing and substantial assistance,” and federal criminal liability – as state criminal law is disapplied by Section 230 – requires specific intent to assist in the commission of a crime). </p>



<p>This means that if, for example, I use Facebook to organize drug deals, Facebook (a) is under no obligation to scan its services for unlawful use and (b) is under no obligation to restrain that use, and will generally be immune civilly from my misuse unless Facebook “materially contributes,” i.e. specifically encourages, that unlawful use (see e.g. <em><a href="https://casetext.com/case/force-v-facebook-inc">Force v Facebook</a>,</em> 934 F.3d 53 (2d Cir. 2019), where Facebook was held not civilly liable under <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/topn/justice_against_sponsors_of_terrorism_act">JASTA</a> to victims of Hamas, which used Facebook to disseminate propaganda online; see also <em>Taamneh,</em> supra), and will not be liable criminally (a) under state criminal law by operation of Section 230, and (b) under federal criminal law to the extent that Facebook does not willfully and knowingly aid, abet, counsel, or procure the commission of the offense with specific intent, per <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/2" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/18/2">18 USC § 2</a>.</p>



<p>Most countries do not such a permissive regime. France is part of that group. In 2020, for example, the <em><a href="https://www.dilcrah.gouv.fr/nos-missions/lutter-contre-la-haine-en-ligne">Loi Lutte Contra la Haine sur Internet</a></em> <em>(Law against hate speech on the Internet)</em> in relation to which global Internet companies can be fined $1.4 million per instance, and up to 4% of their total worldwide revenue, for failing to restrict “hate speech” (which in the United States constitutes “protected speech”) from their websites. Similarly, Germany has its law, the <em>Netzwerkdurchsetzungsgesetz</em> or “Network Enforcement Act” (sometimes referred to as the “Facebook-gesetz” but more commonly referred to by its acronym, the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/jan/05/tough-new-german-law-puts-tech-firms-and-free-speech-in-spotlight">NetzDG</a>), in relation to which politically inflammatory content must come down or the government has the power to impose fines north of EUR 50 million.</p>



<p>Not being a French lawyer, it is difficult for me to figure out exactly what legislative provisions are being invoked here. The charging documents or the warrant will tell us more when they’re published. I’m pretty sure we’re not looking at fine proceedings against Telegram Messenger, Inc. under the hate speech law e.g. or the EU DSA, because if we were, Durov would not have been dragged off a plane in handcuffs. TFI Info, the French media outlet which broke the story, <a href="https://www.tf1info.fr/justice-faits-divers/info-tf1-lci-le-fondateur-et-pdg-de-la-messagerie-cryptee-telegram-interpelle-en-france-2316072.html">suggests</a> that the charges might be something along the lines of an aiding and abetting offense, or possibly conspiracy:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>[The Ministry of] Justice considers that the lack of moderation, cooperation with law enforcement and the tools offered by Telegram (disposable number, cryptocurrencies, etc.) make it an <strong>accomplice</strong> in drug trafficking… and fraud.&nbsp;</p>
</blockquote>



<p>More will be revealed when the arrest warrant is made public. If, for example, it is revealed that Durov did in fact actively assist criminal users with access to the platform, for example a drug user wrote to the support channel stating: “I would like to sell drugs on your platform. How do I do this?” And Durov replied to that with assistance, then his goose would be just as cooked in America as it would be in France. </p>



<p>If, however, the French are simply saying that Durov’s failure to police his users or respond promptly to French document requests is the crime (which I suspect is the case), then this represents a dramatic escalation in the online censorship wars. What it means is that European states are going to try to extraterritorially dictate to foreign companies what content those companies can and cannot host on foreign-based webservers.</p>



<p>If correct, this would represent a major departure from the U.S.-compliant approach most U.S.-headquartered social companies currently take, which has generally governed the global compliance strategies of most non-China social media companies, including any which offer greater or lesser degrees of full encryption on their services (Telegram’s “Secret Chats” feature, WhatsApp, and Signal among them). In brief, platforms thought that if they didn’t specifically intend their platforms to be put to criminal use, they’re unlikely to find themselves on the receiving end of criminal charges. That’s not true anymore, apparently.</p>



<p>Telegram is not the only company in the world which has a social media platform used for unlawful purposes. Facebook’s popular encrypted messaging app WhatsApp has, famously, been <a href="https://prestonbyrne.com/2021/08/15/did-america-just-lose-afghanistan-because-of-whatsapp/">used for years</a> by the erstwhile non-state terror organization in, and now rulers of, Afghanistan, the Taliban. This fact was widely known by NATO generals and reported in the press during the Afghan war, and was even reported on again <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/06/17/world/asia/taliban-whatsapp-afghanistan.html">in the New York Times</a> as recently as last year:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>About a month after Mr. Inqayad, the security officer, was unable to reach his commanders during the night operation, he begrudgingly bought a new SIM card, opened a new WhatsApp account and began the process of recovering lost phone numbers and rejoining WhatsApp groups.</p>



<p>Sitting at his police post, a refurbished shipping container with a hand-held radio, Mr. Inqayad pulled out his phone and began scrolling through his new account. He pointed out all of the groups he is a part of: one for all of the police in his district, another for the former fighters loyal to a single commander, a third he uses to communicate with his superiors at headquarters. In all, he says, he is a part of around 80 WhatsApp groups — more than a dozen of which are used for official government purposes.</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Of course, the Taliban is now Afghanistan’s entire government – at all levels – and Afghanistan is an enemy of the United States, Facebook’s home country. If Facebook were serious about keeping guys like this off their services, the most effective way to do so wouldn’t be by playing whack-a-mole with individual government employees, as Facebook does, but rather by banning the entirety of Afghanistan’s IP range and all Afghan phone numbers, and disabling app downloads in-country, which Facebook does not. Facebook chooses the ineffective measures rather than the effective ones.</p>



<p>Yet, Facebook CEO Mark Zuckerberg lives comfortably in an estate in Hawaii, rather than in exile, and presumably doesn’t have a warrant out for his arrest in any country, whereas Durov obviously <em>did</em>. I grant it is possible (even probable, given that Telegram runs on a skeleton crew of <a href="https://yourstory.com/2024/04/telegram-privacy-innovation-controversy">15 engineers</a> and approximately 100 staff worldwide) that Facebook is more responsive to French judicial requests than Telegram. However, when you’re running a globally accessible encrypted platform, it is inevitable – repeat, inevitable, as in an absolute certainty – that criminal activity will take place that is beyond your view or your ability to moderate.</p>



<p>If Telegram stands accused of violating French law because of its failure to moderate, as media reports indicate, an app like Signal – which demonstrably <a href="https://signal.org/bigbrother/cd-california-grand-jury/">cannot respond</a> to law enforcement requests seeking content data and has <a href="https://theintercept.com/2024/03/04/signal-app-username-phone-number-privacy/">similar features to Telegram</a> – is guilty, too, and no U.S. social company that offers end-to-end encryption (or its senior leadership) is safe. Do we really think <a href="https://x.com/mer__edith?lang=en">Meredith Whitaker</a> should wind up in prison if she decides to go to France?</p>



<figure><a href="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?ssl=1"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="739" height="494" data-attachment-id="26246" data-permalink="https://prestonbyrne.com/2024/08/24/thoughts-on-the-durov-arrest/playmobil-1073901_1280/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?fit=1280%2C855&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1280,855" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="playmobil-1073901_1280" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?fit=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?fit=739%2C494&amp;ssl=1" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?resize=739%2C494&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?resize=1024%2C684&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?resize=300%2C200&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?resize=768%2C513&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?resize=1200%2C802&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?resize=1088%2C727&amp;ssl=1 1088w, https://i0.wp.com/prestonbyrne.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/playmobil-1073901_1280.jpg?w=1280&amp;ssl=1 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 739px) 100vw, 739px" data-recalc-dims="1"></a></figure>



<p>(<em>Image licensed under the Pixabay license.</em>)</p>







<p>Many questions remain. For now, this is not looking good for the future of interactive web services based in Europe. American tech entrepreneurs who run their services in accordance with American values – free speech and privacy through strong encryption, in particular – should not visit Europe, should not hire in Europe, and should not host infrastructure in Europe until this situation is resolved.</p>



<h2>UPDATE, 26 AUGUST 2024</h2>



<p>Basically my hunch was correct:</p>



<figure><div>
<blockquote data-width="550" data-dnt="true"><div lang="en" dir="ltr"><p>Finally the charges against Pavel Durov has been published:</p><p>– Complicity – Administration of an online platform to allow an illegal transaction in an organised band,</p><p>– Refusal to communicate, at the request of the authorised authorities, the information or documents necessary… <a href="https://t.co/BZzZ8pAjLL">https://t.co/BZzZ8pAjLL</a> <a href="https://t.co/v3AXM2BS5X">pic.twitter.com/v3AXM2BS5X</a></p></div>— Baptiste Robert (@fs0c131y) <a href="https://twitter.com/fs0c131y/status/1828103712964817389?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">August 26, 2024</a></blockquote>
</div></figure>



<p>There’s a laundry list of crimes there. Most of them relate to the French crime of <em>complicité</em> which roughly equates to American aider/abettor liability – involving knowingly facilitating, helping or assisting the preparation of a criminal offense, procuring an offense (through a gift, promise, threat, order, or abuse of authority or power) or giving instructions to commit an offense (see <a href="https://www.equalrightstrust.org/ertdocumentbank/french_penal_code_33.pdf">Articles 121-6 and 121-7</a> of the French <em>Code pénal</em>).</p>



<p>What’s important here is that in the U.S., aider/abettor liability requires a specific intent to bring about the criminal result – that is, the commission of the crime is the defendant’s object. U.S. social media companies simply failing to police their users doesn’t rise to this level, which is why U.S. social media company CEOs don’t, as a general rule, get arrested for the crimes of their users by the American government. The CSAM allegations, in particular, would only rise to the level of a crime in the USA if Durov failed to comply with the notice-and-reporting regime the U.S. has for such content. The simple existence of the criminal content absent any notice doesn’t give rise to criminal liability.</p>



<p>Here, the French government is accusing Durov of being complicit with – i.e. aiding and abetting – criminal activity and also unlicensed provision of “cryptological” software, with encryption products subject to <a href="https://www.at-ica.com/encryption-in-france/">prior government authorization</a> before their use in France will be approved. The list of crimes he’s accused of facilitating includes what appears to be a rough approximation to criminal RICO, CSAM, money laundering, narcotics trafficking, hacking, and providing unlicensed cryptography.</p>



<p>It would make zero sense for Durov to do any of these things with specific intent. For example, intentionally engaging in narcotics trafficking is illegal virtually everywhere on Earth; the crime is punishable by <em>death</em> in the United Arab Emirates, where Durov is a citizen and ordinarily resides, and can attract up to a life term in the United States, which is historically very good at extraditing people.</p>



<p>We’ll need wait for the evidence to come out before reaching any firm conclusions on this point. If I had to guess, in a world where every platform hosts unlawful activity to some extent, this looks like selective enforcement. I would also guess that Durov was not “aiding and abetting” as the U.S. would understand it and that this French enforcement action is an overbroad application of French law to punish a perceived political enemy, with the French security state trying to use local doctrines in a novel way to try to police a foreign company with moderation policies it (and likely each of its security cooperation partners in the EU and across the channel in the UK) regards as too lax.</p>



<p>In the absence of a lot of evidence showing that Durov and Telegram specifically intended to commit these crimes or bring them about, there is no reason why similar charges could not be laid against any other provider of social media services in France whose moderation practices are anything less than perfect, in particular social media services which provide end-to-end encryption. </p>



<p>Summing up: for the time being, if you run a social media company, or if you provide encrypted messaging services, which are accessible in France, and you’re based in the United States, get out of Europe.</p>
			</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->

		<!-- .entry-auhtor -->
	</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Covid-19 Intranasal Vaccine (185 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.griffith.edu.au/2024/08/27/game-changing-needle-free-covid-19-intranasal-vaccine/</link>
            <guid>41375746</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 03:47:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.griffith.edu.au/2024/08/27/game-changing-needle-free-covid-19-intranasal-vaccine/">https://news.griffith.edu.au/2024/08/27/game-changing-needle-free-covid-19-intranasal-vaccine/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41375746">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
					<article>
						
<p>A next-generation COVID-19 mucosal vaccine is set to be a gamechanger not only when delivering the vaccine itself, but also for people who are needle-phobic.</p>



<p>New Griffith University research, published in Nature Communications, has been testing the efficacy of delivering a COVID-19 vaccine via the nasal passages.</p>


<div>
<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="683" height="1024" src="https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-683x1024.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-683x1024.jpg 683w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-200x300.jpg 200w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-768x1152.jpg 768w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-1024x1536.jpg 1024w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-1365x2048.jpg 1365w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Suresh-Mahalingam-scaled.jpg 1707w" sizes="(max-width: 683px) 100vw, 683px"><figcaption><strong>Professor Suresh Mahalingam</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Professor Suresh Mahalingam from Griffith’s Institute for Biomedicine and Glycomics and Griffith Health has been working on this research for the past four years.</p>



<p>“This is a live attenuated intranasal vaccine, called CDO-7N-1, designed to be administered intranasally, thereby inducing potential mucosal immunity as well as systemic immunity with just a single dose,” Professor Mahalingam said.</p>



<p>“The vaccine induces strong memory responses in the nasal mucosa offering long-term protection for up to a year or more.</p>



<p>“It’s been designed to be administered as single dose, ideally as a booster vaccine, as a safe alternative to needles with no adverse reactions in the short or long term.”</p>



<p>Live-attenuated vaccines offer several significant advantages over other vaccine approaches.</p>



<p>They induce potent and long-lived humoral and cellular immunity, often with just a single dose.</p>



<p>Live-attenuated vaccines comprise the entire virus thereby providing broad immunity, in contrast to a single antigen which is used in many other vaccine platforms.</p>


<div>
<figure><img decoding="async" width="871" height="1024" src="https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG20231020135104-871x1024.jpeg" alt="" srcset="https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG20231020135104-871x1024.jpeg 871w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG20231020135104-255x300.jpeg 255w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG20231020135104-768x903.jpeg 768w, https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/IMG20231020135104.jpeg 987w" sizes="(max-width: 871px) 100vw, 871px"><figcaption><strong>Dr Xiang Liu</strong></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Lead author Dr Xiang Liu said the vaccine provides cross-protection against all variants of concern, and has neutralising capacity against SARS-CoV-1.</p>



<p>“The vaccine offers potent protection against transmission, prevents reinfection and the spread of the virus, while also reducing the generation of new variants,” Dr Liu said.</p>



<p>“Unlike the mRNA vaccine which targets only the spike protein, CDO-7N-1 induces immunity to all major SARS-CoV-2 proteins and is highly effective against all major variants to date.</p>



<p>“Importantly, the vaccine remains stable at 4°C for seven months, making it ideal for low- and middle-income countries.”</p>



<p>The vaccine has been licensed to Indian Immunologicals Ltd, a major vaccine manufacturer.</p>



<p>&nbsp;Dr. K. Anand Kumar, co-author of the publication and Managing&nbsp;Director of Indian Immunologicals Ltd. Said: “We are a leading ‘One Health’ company that has developed and launched several vaccines for human and animal use in India and are currently exporting to 62 countries.”</p>



<p>“We have completed all the necessary studies of this novel COVID-19 vaccine which offers tremendous advantages over other vaccines.</p>



<p>“We now look forward to taking the vaccine candidate to clinical&nbsp;trials.”</p>



<p>Professor Lee Smith, Acting Director of the Institute for Biomedicine and Glycomics, said he was delighted with the research findings.</p>



<p>“These results towards developing a next-generation COVID-19 vaccine are truly exciting,” Professor Smith said.</p>



<p>“Our researchers are dedicated to providing innovative and, crucially, more accessible solutions to combat this high-impact disease.”</p>



<p>The paper ‘<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-024-51535-y">A single-dose intranasal live-attenuated codon deoptimsed vaccine provides broad protection against SARS-CoV-2 and its variants</a>’ has been published in Nature Communications.</p>
													<div>
                                  <p><img src="https://news.griffith.edu.au/wp-content/uploads/2024/05/E-WEB-Goal-03.png" alt="3: Good Health and Well-being"></p>
                                </div>
											</article>

					

				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Diffusion Models Are Real-Time Game Engines (994 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gamengen.github.io</link>
            <guid>41375548</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 02:59:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gamengen.github.io">https://gamengen.github.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41375548">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://gamengen.github.io: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>