<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 19:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sam Altman Wants Your Eyeball (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/05/10/sam-altman-wants-your-eyeball/</link>
            <guid>43946766</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 16:14:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/05/10/sam-altman-wants-your-eyeball/">https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/05/10/sam-altman-wants-your-eyeball/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43946766">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><a data-type="image" data-width="auto" data-height="auto" data-desc-position="bottom"><img alt="Image of a red circle of light that resembles a human iris over a black background." src="https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/assets/images/sam-altman-wants-your-eyeball/orb-cover.webp"></a></p>

<p>Last week, OpenAI's CEO Sam Altman announced in San Francisco that the World project he co-founded, formerly known as Worldcoin, is opening six stores across the United States, allowing users of the project's app to scan their eyeballs.</p>
<p>Simply put, the premise is this: scan your eyeball, get a biometric tag, verify yourself, buy our apps (and cryptocurrency). The scary part is the for-profit company developing the project has now gathered millions in venture capital investment, powerful partners, and is ready to expand and impose its <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minority_Report_(film)">Minority Report</a> style technology everywhere. <strong>Welcome to Dystopialand.</strong><!-- more --></p>
<p>The World(coin) project is an initiative from the startup Tools for Humanity, co-founded by its CEO Alex Blania. Despite its friendly name, the for-profit corporation has been on the radar of many critics through the years already. From experts to journalists to privacy commissioners around the world, not everyone shares Blania's enthusiasm for his biometric-based technology.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-the-world-app">What is the World App?</h2>
<p>The World project, recently rebranded from the Worldcoin project (possibly to convey better its expansionist ambitions) presented its plan for the World App to Americans this week. The project is now expanding well beyond the cryptocurrency it started from.</p>
<p>The World App is an everything app, providing users with a <em>World ID</em>, that can be verified through the collection of biometric data in the form of an iris scan.</p>
<p>The scan is then filtered and hashed to create a unique identifier that is stored as a so-called "proof of personhood" on the <em>World Network</em>, a blockchain-based protocol.</p>
<p>The World App itself contains a collection of "Mini Apps", where users can manage their cryptocurrencies, chat together, play games, receive their pay check even, and ultimately live their whole life within the closed "verified" ecosystem of the app.</p>
<p>For a company constantly praising decentralization, it sure looks like they want to make sure they are the center of it all.</p>
<p>To obtain this coveted verification code, users <em>must</em> be ready to share their precious eyeball data with the Orb.</p>
<p>The Orb is a piece of hardware designed by Tools for Humanity to perform iris scans. It is available to access in the United States at one of the currently six locations in Austin, Atlanta, Los Angeles, Miami, Nashville and San Francisco (more to come soon), like some sort of biometrics collection ATM.</p>
<p>The World project has for ambition to expand its reach across the United States to install 7,500 Orbs by the end of this year, so be prepared to see this dystopian technology everywhere soon.</p>
<p>The San Francisco <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/05/04/sam_altman_startup_world/">presentation last week</a> was clearly prepared to impress investors with its Apple announcement vibe. The promise of a quickly growing startup that everyone will soon want to work with, was repeated over and over in different flavors.</p>
<p>Tools for Humanity bragged about many large partnerships that should make any privacy advocates shiver in dread: the Match Group dating apps conglomerate (Tinder, OkCupid, Hinge, Plenty of Fish), Stripe, and Visa are some of them.</p>
<p>If they succeed in convincing enough people, many of us could soon have little choice but to unwillingly have to enroll.</p>
<h2 id="worldcoin-isnt-new-you-might-have-heard-of-its-unethical-practices-already">World(coin) isn't new, you might have heard of its unethical practices already</h2>
<p>The project <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/30/sam-altmans-world-unveils-a-mobile-verification-device/">claims</a> to have onboarded 26 million people already, including 12 millions "users" who are verified (had their biometric data collected).</p>
<p>These "users" are largely located in Latin America, Africa, and Asia. This is because the company started testing for its project there a few years ago, in regions where people often have fewer legal protections.</p>
<p>In 2022, MIT Technology Review produced <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/04/06/1048981/worldcoin-cryptocurrency-biometrics-web3/">an extensive investigation</a> on the startup's debut in an article titled: <em>Deception, exploited workers, and cash handouts: How Worldcoin recruited its first half a million test users.</em></p>
<p>The investigation revealed a collection of unethical practices to pressure the most vulnerable populations in signing up for Worldcoin, and <strong>have their eyeball scanned in exchange for money</strong> they desperately needed.</p>
<p>Some participants had to provide much more personal information than the company says is required, such as emails, phone numbers, and even photos of official ID. Many people who gave their biometric data to Worldcoin were rushed and misinformed. Some who signed up didn't even have an email and had to create one. The "Orb operators" hired to perform the scans locally were often poorly trained, poorly informed, and unable to answer the questions asked by participants.</p>
<p>So much so that <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/02/kenya-suspends-worldcoin-scans-over-security-privacy-and-financial-concerns/">Kenya suspended the company's operations</a> in 2023 over concerns for privacy, security, and financial service practices.</p>
<p>Some people who signed up never received the promised money. Some officials were bribed to give the impression to participants these operations were official and supported by the government.</p>
<p>As Ruswandi, one of the person targeted by this early campaign <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2022/04/06/1048981/worldcoin-cryptocurrency-biometrics-web3/">remarked</a>: "why did Worldcoin target lower-income communities in the first place, instead of crypto enthusiasts or communities?"</p>
<p>Exploiting people in situation of poverty in order to test a biometric identification technology isn't a great way to start a project developed by a company called "Tools for Humanity".</p>
<h2 id="creating-the-problem-selling-the-solution">Creating the problem, selling the solution</h2>
<p>Why developing such a technology in the first place?</p>
<p>Sam Altman himself have <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/sam-altman-orb-eyeball-scan-launch-us/">expressed concern</a> about the problem this alleged solution solves: the avalanche of fake accounts and pretend persons online caused by the new AI tools unleashed everywhere.</p>
<p>The proposed use of a "proof of personhood" claims to solve this problem by allocating a unique identifier to each human, a personal code supposedly impossible to duplicate or cheat. Of course, this has <a href="https://gizmodo.com/worldcoin-black-market-iris-data-identity-orb-1850454037">already been proven wrong</a>.</p>
<p>No one will miss the irony of the CEO of OpenAI, responsible for creating the largest share of this problem, expressing such concern <strong>while continuing to feed the fire</strong>.</p>
<p>This is a classic case of creating a problem and selling the solution. Well, in this case it is more like <strong><em>selling</em> the problem and selling the solution</strong>. As researcher and cryptocurrency critic <a href="https://www.citationneeded.news/worldcoin-a-solution-in-search-of/">Molly White pointed out</a> in 2023:</p>
<p>"That's right, the guy who's going to sell us all the solution to a worsening AI-powered bot infestation of the Internet and to AI-induced mass unemployment is the same guy who's making the AI in question."</p>
<p>Sadly, this proposed solution also isn't really a solution, or at least it isn't a <em>good</em> solution. Indeed, this will <strong>create a whole collection of new problems</strong>, many much worse than a bot infestation.</p>
<h2 id="the-risks-of-sharing-biometric-data">The risks of sharing biometric data</h2>
<p>Biometric data is incredibly sensitive data, because it's irrevocably attached to a person. Whether it's from a face scan, palm scan, fingerprint, keystroke pattern, or iris scan, this data is part of our bodies and <strong>cannot be changed like a password</strong> if it gets compromised.</p>
<p>For this reason, a growing number of legislations around the world now include special categories for such data collection, and require extra protections and supervision for it.</p>
<p>There are many dangers in collecting and potentially endangering biometric data. First, if this data gets stolen, criminals can impersonate a victim much more convincingly, because they will have the "proof" to "verify" this is really you.</p>
<p>While straight-up stealing your eyeball or face might still belong to science-fiction, the risk of getting the data produced <em>from</em> the scan stolen is very real.</p>
<p>When the World project claims it is secure because biometric data isn't stored anywhere, even if that was true, the iris <em>code</em> derivative of this data is indeed stored and processed somewhere, and this can potentially be stolen.</p>
<p>How hard will it be for a victim to recover an account from a biometric thief when everything is reinforcing the false narrative shared with investors that this technology can't be cheated?</p>
<p>Then, there is the loss of pseudonymity protections online.</p>
<p>If every social media account becomes tied to a unique biometric-based identifier, whether directly or indirectly, there is no pseudonymity anymore.</p>
<p>Further, if only one account is allowed by "verified human", then no one can create separate accounts for their work life and personal life anymore. Creating separate accounts for separate purposes is an excellent privacy-preserving practice.</p>
<p>Even if the identifier isn't tied to a legal name directly, accounts on different platforms using the same identifier could potentially get liked together. To be fair, it does seem Tools for Humanity worked to prevent different platforms from having access to the same code, but how well will this hold the test of time? Will platforms increasingly escalate privacy-invasive requests from this point, like they often do?</p>
<p><strong>Pseudonymity saves lives.</strong> It is an essential tool for the safety of the most vulnerable online. Killing pseudonymity by requiring unique biometric identification could endanger millions.</p>
<p>This is a serious problem coming up with <a href="https://www.privacyguides.org/articles/2025/05/06/age-verification-wants-your-face/">age verification</a> processes as well, which World ID will soon also be a part of when <a href="https://www.engadget.com/cybersecurity/sam-altmans-eyeball-scanning-id-technology-debuts-in-the-us-130032856.html">testing</a> its implementation for Tinder in Japan.</p>
<p>Biometric data should never be used lightly. It should be reserved for the most extreme cases only.</p>
<p>The regions who have adopted stronger regulations for biometric data collection are moving in the right direction. But will protective legislation be enough to resist the pressure from a for-profit VC-backed corporation with a valuation at billions?</p>
<h2 id="flipping-the-coin">Flipping the coin</h2>
<p>Tools for Humanity seems to be well aware of its creepiness factor, and of the criticisms brought by privacy commissioners around the world.</p>
<p>Its recent Orb redesign from the previous cold (Black)mirror finish clearly tries hard to replace creepiness with cuteness.</p>
<p>The company has also evidently invested a lot in presenting a pro-privacy image, likely in an attempt to reassure users (and investors).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, many of these privacy-preserving claims are inaccurate. Some claims promoting "features" that might sound impressive to a neophyte's ear are actually just the baseline, and others sadly are misleading <em>at best</em>.</p>
<p>While a few privacy-preserving efforts are indeed positive, most of the focus on privacy relates to marketing much more than any serious protections.</p>
<h2 id="how-privacy-preserving-is-it">How privacy-preserving is it?</h2>
<p>Most people are still put off by the idea of having their eyeball scanned, and the company has evidently invested a lot in promoting a "privacy-preserving" image, possibly as an attempt to reassure unconvinced humans and <a href="#privacy-legislators-arent-on-board">privacy commissioners</a> alike.</p>
<p>But how much can we trust those claims?</p>
<h3 id="flawed-assumption-about-what-constitutes-personal-data">Flawed assumption about what constitutes personal data</h3>
<p>The largest assumption about why this technology is "privacy-preserving" seems to come from the fact that the World App doesn't collect names, official IDs (<a href="https://www.toolsforhumanity.com/legal/privacy-notice#6-2-credentials-">unless it does</a>), emails (<a href="https://www.toolsforhumanity.com/legal/privacy-notice#annex-i-%E2%80%93-legal-grounds/purposes-for-tools-for-humanity-data-processing-activities-">unless it does</a>), phone numbers (<a href="https://www.toolsforhumanity.com/legal/privacy-notice#5-1-data-you-provide-to-us">unless it does</a>), date of birth (<a href="https://world.org/blog/announcements/worldcoin-new-world-id-unverify-option-increases-personal-control-over-data">unless it does</a>), or other identifiers.</p>
<p>This assumption however neglects the fact that 1) even data that isn't attached to a legal name can be personal data, and 2) the iris code it produces from the iris scan <em>is</em> indeed personal data.</p>
<p>While there are variations, most privacy regulations have similar definitions of what constitute personal data. The European General Data Protection Regulation (<abbr title="General Data Protection Regulation">GDPR</abbr>) <a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-4-gdpr/">defines</a> it as "any information relating to an identified or identifiable natural person". An iris code derived from an iris scan of course fits this definition.</p>
<p>Moreover, to create a World ID, the company also collects a face image. Together, the original iris scan and face photo are referred to as <em>Image Data</em>. For "privacy-preserving" purposes, Image Data of course never leaves the Orb device (<a href="https://world.org/legal/biometric-data-consent-form">unless it does</a>).</p>
<p>While it seems some effort has been made to protect the Image Data in some ways, the idea that derivative data from the scans isn't still sensitive personal information anymore is wrong.</p>
<p>If there is a way for a person to scan their iris again and generate the same code, then this data relates to their identifiable person. This also means that <em>someone else</em> could scan their iris and generate the same code.</p>
<p>As whistleblower <a href="https://x.com/Snowden/status/1451990496537088000">Edward Snowden rightfully pointed out</a> in a 2021 tweet:</p>
<p>“This looks like it produces a global (hash) database of people's iris scans (for 'fairness'), and waves away the implications by saying 'we deleted the scans!' Yeah, but you save the <em>hashes</em> produced by the scans. Hashes that match <em>future</em> scans. Don't catalogue eyeballs.”</p>
<h3 id="questionable-reassurance-about-local-data">Questionable reassurance about local data</h3>
<p>One of the biggest reassurance relates to the claim that sensitive biometric data (Image Data) is only stored locally. But this isn't completely accurate either, and there seems to be conflicting information about it from the company's own documentation.</p>
<p>The World <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#enrollment-process">white paper</a> specifies that:</p>
<p>"The Orb verifies that it sees a human, runs local fraud prevention checks, and takes pictures of both irises. The iris images are converted on the Orb hardware into the iris code. Raw biometric data does not leave the device (unless explicitly approved by the user for training purposes)."</p>
<p>However, according to the <a href="https://world.org/legal/biometric-data-consent-form">Biometric Data Consent Form</a> users have to sign prior to data collection, if a user needs a fully verified World ID, inevitably this sensitive biometric data will be sent to their phone, therefore leaving the Orb.</p>
<p>After a user agrees to the form, they can keep the option for <em>Data Custody</em> disabled to have their biometric data deleted from the Orb "later", and have it uploaded to their phone (with all the risk that this entails).</p>
<p>The other option users have is to enable Data Custody (if allowed in the user's country) and have this sensitive data sent to both their phone <em>and</em> to Tools for Humanity.</p>
<p>This means the Orb inevitably sends this sensitive data to a mobile device. Then, this data is only as secure as the mobile device is. Which isn't so reassuring.</p>
<p>The documentation does maintain this biometric data is sent as an "end-to-end encrypted data bundle", but this doesn't mean the data never leaves the Orb, it just means it leaves it while encrypted (which is really just the basics), and copies it to the user's device.</p>
<p>Furthermore, future users are <em>strongly</em> incentivized to share their Image Data with Tools for Humanity, for algorithm improvement purposes. Pressure to opt in is even presented as a <em>convenience</em> option, because it would be cumbersome to have to come over for another scan after every update.</p>
<p>As <a href="https://world.org/legal/biometric-data-consent-form">stated</a> in the Biometric Data Consent Form:</p>
<p>"This will likely help you avoid some inconvenience because, if we have your Image Data, then you will not need to return to an Orb to re-verify your digital identity when we update the software."</p>
<p>The company continues to repeat they have a "privacy by default and by design approach". But <strong>you can't keep your privacy-preserving cake and eat it, too</strong>.</p>
<h3 id="what-does-the-white-paper-say">What does the white paper say</h3>
<p>In tech, a white paper is usually a research-based document produced by the developers that presents more technical details on an application, product, or process. It is especially valuable for products like the Orb and the World App, where security and privacy <em>should</em> be paramount, and therefore examined closer.</p>
<p>Because it isn't an independent review, a white paper can also not be worth much more than a marketing pamphlet.</p>
<p>To its credit, Tools for Humanity does <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#nature-of-the-whitepaper">warn</a> in its white paper that this information is "intended for general informational purposes and community discussion only and do not constitute a prospectus, an offer document, an offer of securities, a solicitation for investment, or any offer to sell any product, item or asset (whether digital or otherwise)."</p>
<p>Furthermore, the company makes sure to specify that "circumstances may change and that the Whitepaper or the Website may become outdated as a result; and the [World] Foundation is not under any obligation to update or correct this document in connection therewith."</p>
<p>The document is also described as a "crypto-asset white paper".</p>
<p>We have been warned.</p>
<p>In its Privacy section, the white paper <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#image-custody-opt-in">states</a> that "no data collected, including images taken by the Orb has or will ever be sold. Nor will it be used for any other intent than to improve World ID."</p>
<p>However, its <a href="https://world.org/legal/privacy-notice#8--when-we-share-your-data">Privacy Notice also states</a> that they may "share your personal information in connection with, or during negotiations concerning, any merger, sale of company assets, financing, or acquisition of all or a portion of our business by another company."</p>
<p>If this happens, many regretful users might find themselves in <a href="https://www.techradar.com/health-fitness/23andme-is-bankrupt-and-about-to-sell-your-dna-heres-how-to-stop-that-from-happening">the same shoes as 23andMe users this year</a>, where the DNA collecting company started to look for buyers of its biometric data assets after filling for bankruptcy.</p>
<p>Additionally, the Face Authentication section of the white paper <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#face-authentication">describes</a> a process where encrypted facial biometrics collected from the Orb are used for authentication in the World App.</p>
<p>Even if this data is stored on-device, it is still biometric data getting collected by the Orb then processed by the phone app. There is no question this is sensitive and personal biometric data, and it is indeed kept outside the orb.</p>
<p>Tools for Humanity lacks consistency in the various claims and statements found through its documentation and promotion material. It becomes difficult to know which version to trust, and if it is to be trusted at all.</p>
<h3 id="no-deletion-on-the-blockchain">No deletion on the blockchain</h3>
<p>Tools for Humanity's Privacy Policy declares that the company will delete all account data (when laws allow it) one month after it is closed, this is good. They also state they will delete entirely any inactive account after 2 years, and this is actually a great policy.</p>
<p>But what happens to the World ID, transactions, and other data stored on the blockchain?</p>
<p>While some thoughts have been put into deletion and some good mechanisms seem to have been implemented, unfortunately data stored on the blockchain might be "deletion-resistant".</p>
<p>There's a possibility that <strong>what happens on the blockchain stays on the blockchain, forever</strong>.</p>
<p>The policy <a href="https://www.toolsforhumanity.com/legal/privacy-notice#11--how-long-do-we-keep-your-data-">notes</a> that:</p>
<p>"Due to the public and immutable nature of blockchain technology, we cannot amend, erase, or control the disclosure of data that is stored on blockchains."</p>
<p>So that is something to keep in mind if you value your right to delete.</p>
<h2 id="data-security-considerations">Data security considerations</h2>
<p>Even if some thoughtful security features seem to have been implemented for the World App and its Orbs, nothing processing sensitive data at such a large scale should be left in the hands of a single for-profit, largely unregulated, organization.</p>
<p>This would be like putting 8 billion eggs in a very fragile basket, held by someone paid to make the basket pretty and convince as many people as possible to put their precious single egg in it, with no incentive whatsoever to ensure the basket doesn't break. I would not want to put my egg in there, especially with how much it costs now.</p>
<p>The idea of using one single <em>for-profit</em> app worldwide for "human verification", identity verification, age verification, money transactions, and storing official IDs (and so on and so forth) makes this application a <em>huge</em> target for criminals and hostile governments alike.</p>
<p>It's good that the app had <a href="https://github.com/trailofbits/publications/blob/master/reviews/2023-08-worldcoin-orb-securityreview.pdf">security audits</a>, made some <a href="https://github.com/worldcoin">code available</a> as open source, and reportedly <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#why-custom-hardware-is-needed">plans</a> to open a bug bounty program.</p>
<p>However, there are still problems that remain. For example, the phone in this case becomes a single point of failure. The easiest way to steal someone's identity and money (all at once) will be to steal their phone data (whether physically or remotely). Even without criminal intent, what happens when someone just loses their phone? Or accidentally drop it in the pool? Or step on it?</p>
<p>With <strong>everything relying on a single app and a single device</strong>, risk is greatly amplified.</p>
<p>Outside the user's responsibility, Orb operators and Orb stores are susceptible to various attacks. This will increase exponentially with the number of users of course, as the target becomes bigger. In fact, Orb operators have <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/05/12/hackers-stole-passwords-of-worldcoin-orb-operators/">already been hacked</a>.</p>
<p>Then, there is the appeal of fake identities and money fraud for criminals. Already, there is a <a href="https://gizmodo.com/worldcoin-black-market-iris-data-identity-orb-1850454037">black market</a> for iris data in China, where people buy iris data (or verified World ID according to World) from people in Cambodia, Kenya, and other countries for a few dollars only. The vulnerability allowing this was reportedly fixed, but it is doubtful this is the last one we hear about.</p>
<p>The Orb itself is also an important potential <abbr title="The total number of possible entry points for unauthorized access to a system">attack surface</abbr>. With Tools for Humanity's ambition to fill the world with Orbs everywhere, will Orbs become the next version of the sketchy ATM? Where you might wonder if this funny-looking Orb is trustworthy enough to pay your bar tab without risking emptying your crypto wallet?</p>
<h2 id="privacy-legislators-arent-on-board">Privacy legislators aren't on board</h2>
<p>Despite all its privacy promotion material, the World project has failed to convince privacy commissioners around the world of their supposedly good intentions. Perhaps in this case actions speak louder than words, and privacy commissioners aren't so gullible.</p>
<p>With the expansion the project plans this year, we can expect even more experts will examine the company's claims and challenge its "privacy-preserving" assumptions</p>
<p>There are many reasons to remain skeptical about these promises of privacy. Indeed, numerous countries have already suspended, fined, or called for investigation on the company's (mal)practices.</p>
<h3 id="the-company-was-fined-for-personal-data-violation">The company was fined for personal data violation</h3>
<p>In 2024, the company was <a href="https://cointelegraph.com/news/south-korea-fines-worldcoin-personal-data-violations">fined</a> 1.1 billion Korean won for violating South Korea's Personal Information Protection Act (PIPA). The Worldcoin Foundation was also imposed corrective orders and recommendations. Organizations that are truly "privacy-first" rarely reach this point.</p>
<p>The Data Custody feature, which allows (and encourages) users to share their biometric data with Tools for Humanity is now unavailable in South Korea.</p>
<h3 id="brazil-has-banned-worldcoin-in-the-country">Brazil has banned Worldcoin in the country</h3>
<p>In January this year, the National Data Protection Authority (ANPD) <a href="https://decrypt.co/305639/brazilian-regulator-denies-worldcoin-appeal-ban">banned</a> Worldcoin's operations in Brazil, after the company's appeal was rejected.</p>
<p>The ban comes from regulation stating that consent to process biometric data must be "free, informed, and unequivocal", which cannot be the case with the World project paying users in cryptocurrency in exchange for their iris scans. Data deletion concerns were also raised by the regulator.</p>
<p>The World project tried again to appeal the decision, in vain.</p>
<h3 id="kenya-and-indonesia-suspended-its-operations">Kenya and Indonesia suspended its operations</h3>
<p>In 2023, Kenya, one of the first country where Worldcoin was available, <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/02/kenya-suspends-worldcoin-scans-over-security-privacy-and-financial-concerns/">suspended</a> Worldcoin's operations citing concerns over the "authenticity and legality" of its activities related to privacy, security, and financial services.</p>
<p>The worse part is, months before the Office of the Data Protection Commissioner (ODPC) of the country had ordered Tools for Humanity to stop collecting personal information from its citizens. The company simply <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/15/worldcoin-in-kenya/">ignored the ODPC order</a> and continued to collect biometric data from Kenyans. It only stopped after Kenya's ministry of interior and administration gave the suspension order later on.</p>
<p>This again is quite far from the behavior of a company who genuinely values privacy.</p>
<p>More recently on May 4th 2025, Indonesia also <a href="https://en.antaranews.com/news/353861/indonesia-suspends-worldcoin-world-id-operations-over-public-concerns">suspended</a> the World project's operation in the country over concerns related to user privacy and security. The Ministry of Communication and Digital will be summoning the project's local operators to clarify the operations and determine potential violation of the Indonesia's electronic system regulation.</p>

<p>In December 2024, the German regulator, the Bavarian State Office for Data Protection Supervision (BayLDA), <a href="https://decrypt.co/298090/german-watchdog-cracks-down-on-worldcoin-over-biometric-data">issued an order</a> to obligate proving deletion procedures that comply with the <abbr title="General Data Protection Regulation">GDPR</abbr> within one month. Additionally, the BayLDA ordered the complete deletion of certain data records that were previously collected without sufficient legal basis.</p>
<p>Again, the World Foundation is fighting the order and will <a href="https://cointelegraph.com/news/german-watchdog-order-worldcoin-delete-data">appeal</a> the decision. The company tries to argue the data collected was "anonymized", a common strategy to try evading <abbr title="General Data Protection Regulation">GDPR</abbr> compliance, which does not regulate anonymized data.</p>

<p>In 2023, France's data protection authority the CNIL <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/worldcoin-paris-office-checked-by-french-data-watchdog-2023-08-31/">investigated</a> Worldcoin's activities in the country. The same year, UK's privacy watchdog started its own <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/uk-data-watchdog-make-enquiries-worldcoin-crypto-project-2023-07-25/">inquiry</a> into the company's operations.</p>
<p>In 2024, Hong Kong's Office of the Privacy Commissioner for Personal Data <a href="https://www.scmp.com/news/hong-kong/law-and-crime/article/3250480/hong-kong-eye-scan-cryptocurrency-scheme-probed-citys-privacy-watchdog">raided</a> six Worldcoin offices citing personal information privacy and security concerns.</p>
<p>There is no doubt more countries and regions will follow with similar investigations and bans as the World project expands to its ambition.</p>
<h3 id="in-the-united-states-the-app-is-restricted-in-some-states">In the United States, the app is restricted in some states</h3>
<p>Even in the US where the company is headquartered, the app is <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/sam-altman-orb-eyeball-scan-launch-us/">restricted</a> in some states. The announcement for its event this month carried a warning the World is “not available for distribution via World App to people, companies or organizations who are residents of, or are located or incorporated in the State of New York or other restricted territories.”</p>
<p>We can also expect the project will encounter roadblocks in states that have passed <a href="https://www.huschblackwell.com/2024-state-biometric-privacy-law-tracker">regulations specific to the collection of biometric data</a>. This includes states like Illinois, Texas, Washington, and Colorado.</p>
<h3 id="some-regions-have-special-regulations-for-biometric-data">Some regions have special regulations for biometric data</h3>
<p>Around the world the number of biometric-specific regulations is growing. Even without a regulation specific to this type of data, many privacy laws have started to include special categories and requirements to govern the collection and processing of sensitive biometric data. As companies are increasingly requesting such collection, legislations to protect users are essential.</p>
<p>For example, the province of Quebec in Canada has recently implemented <a href="https://www.cai.gouv.qc.ca/protection-renseignements-personnels/sujets-et-domaines-dinteret/biometrie?%2F">strong protections for biometric data</a> with its new privacy law, the Law 25. Consent isn't sufficient to collect biometric data, as the law requires organizations to explicitly justify the necessity for such collection in the first place. Importantly, any violation of Law 25 comes with fines as hefty as the <abbr title="General Data Protection Regulation">GDPR</abbr>'s.</p>
<p>More privacy laws should implement such protections quickly, as corporations collecting biometric information carelessly are multiplying fast.</p>
<h2 id="welcome-to-full-dystopia">Welcome to full dystopia</h2>
<p>The most concerning part of the World project's recent expansion isn't its cryptocurrency grift as much as stepping out of it.</p>
<p>If cryptocurrency enthusiasts wish to share their personal data to get into a special cryptocurrency club, they might (although privacy regulations should still protect them). But using financial coercion to get new users by exploiting vulnerable communities living in poverty is <strong>absolutely despicable</strong>.</p>
<p>Further, the fact that the World project has partnered with powerful players in the financial, gaming, and even dating sectors <em>should terrify everyone</em>.</p>
<p>Beyond cryptocurrency, if platforms start to demand users everywhere to verify they are a human and verify they are an adult through the World ID system, then <strong>everyone will soon be subjected to this</strong>.</p>
<p>The amount of money invested in the project means there will be an incredible pressure to spread it everywhere soon, and <em>monetize</em> it. There will be a <em>strong</em> incentive to monetize our data and to monetize our proof of humanity. This isn't trivial.</p>
<p>The well-known dating app Tinder has already partnered with World ID to verify the age of users in Japan. If this experiment works well, and if users comply without objection, this could be soon mandatory for <em>all</em> dating apps.</p>
<p>Let's not stop at dating apps, the World project has already announced last week they will also be working with Razer to verify humanity of online gamers. How far can this go in the age of age verification? Will every online games with mature content soon require a World ID to play?</p>
<p>What about social media? Tools for Humanity's team have insisted the age of AI made us incapable of detecting if we are interacting with bots online. Therefore, they must valiantly come to our rescue to verify our humanity scanning our eyeballs (which bots tragically lack). What if this human verification is expanded to all our social media accounts? Certainly, regulators pushing for authoritarian age verification online would be delighted by such a product.</p>
<p>Then, it comes for our money. The everything app of course offers payment and money management features. This is the app where you can keep your whole wallet, containing all your official IDs, your cryptocurrencies of all kind, and even connect with your less hyped regular bank accounts.</p>
<p>Imagine a single app, owned by a single for-profit corporation, that collects and processes all the data from all your transactions online, all your communications online, that you absolutely have to continue using for your other social media accounts, your gaming life, and your dating life.</p>
<p>There could soon be no way to escape the grasp of World's everything app. Actually, <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/05/04/sam_altman_startup_world/">some governments</a> (Taiwan and Malesia) have already started using it for official services, because why not.</p>
<p><strong>The ways this could degenerate fast into full dystopia are infinite</strong>, and very real.</p>
<p>The company even plans to ship next year the Orb Mini, a pocket-size personal spy-device with which users will be able to scan their own eyeballs on the go!</p>
<p>But why stop there? Why not scan other people's eyeballs as well? Maybe all government officials could carry one? Maybe every payment terminal could have one too?</p>
<p>We will find out soon, in one or two years.</p>
<p>Tools for Humanity also bragged about the numerous utilities its new technology could make possible. For example, for event tickets! Order a concert ticket with your "proof of personhood" then maybe confirm you are the owner by having your eyeballs scanned to assist to a Rage Against the Machine concert?</p>
<p>The only fun part in this is the irony.</p>
<p>Tools for Humanity with its expansionist dream is without a doubt hungry enough to eat the whole World™️.</p>
<h3 id="a-new-world-of-wealth-inequalities">A new world of wealth inequalities</h3>
<p>The company brings up a few times the mention of Universal Basic Income (UBI) in its documentation, it even mentions it briefly in its <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#ubi">white paper</a>.</p>
<p>While puzzling, it appears Tools for Humanity might consider its cryptocurrency bribe to sign up and subsequent token giveaways as some form of UBI? Or perhaps this is only one of its other ambition to control all the financial systems in the entire world. Why UBI is even mentioned at all in this context is unclear.</p>
<p>Regardless, it's worth mentioning a for-profit company giving cash back in exchange for biometric data isn't UBI at all, it's just a <strong>creepy membership card points</strong>, at best.</p>
<p>While the World project works hard to present the idea this is a tool for the people, where everyone is equal, wealth will definitely <a href="https://whitepaper.world.org/#wld-token-allocation">not be distributed evenly</a> in this new World order.</p>
<p>Already, 11.1% of World's cryptocurrency tokens (WLD) have been distributed to the World's team, 13.6% to investors, and 0.3% are reserved for Tools for Humanity. This means these entities would share together 25% of the wealth, while 75% of the world's population (according the Tools for Humanity's ambition) would have to share 75% of what's left.</p>
<p>In the new "human" world this corporation envisions, Tools for Humanity and its investors would own 1 quarter of the entire world's wealth. There is nothing equitable or communal in a system like this.</p>
<p>It's important not to forget this everything app will do everything to pressure its users in eventually using Worldcoins, its ultimate goal.</p>
<p>From Tinder's mandatory age verification to cryptocurrency financial ruin in one single move.</p>
<h2 id="the-normalization-of-surveillance">The normalization of surveillance</h2>
<p>Even if this process was perfectly secure and perfectly private (which it is definitely not), the problem remains the normalization of surveillance.</p>
<p>This isn't limited to Tools for Humanity, although the way the company tries to advertise itself as a privacy-first organization makes it even more important to scrutinize.</p>
<p>But anyone else with a similar approach to biometric data collection for verifying humanity or age or legal names should be on our radar. Moreover, if it's a for-profit corporation with the power to impose this technology on us everywhere in the world.</p>
<p>One company should never have such power.</p>
<p>Further, biometric data should never be used for trivial purposes like "proof of personhood" or age verification. No amount of supposedly "privacy-preserving" features can change this.</p>
<p>The premise itself is flawed from the start to respect privacy rights.</p>
<p>While the problem of proving identify can still be an important one to solve in <em>some</em> context, the solution to this can never be monopolized by for-profit corporations.</p>
<p>Regardless of Tools for Humanity's intentions and efforts to convince us to trust them, any similar technology is just another step towards a global system of mass surveillance, where ultimately privacy rights and human rights are lost.</p>
<p>So, should you scan your eyeball to get a verified World ID?</p>
<p><strong>No.</strong></p>
<p><strong>No, you really shouldn't.</strong></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA['We Currently Have No Container Ships,' Seattle Port Says (134 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.newsweek.com/seattle-port-says-no-container-ships-tariffs-2069464</link>
            <guid>43946601</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 15:49:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/seattle-port-says-no-container-ships-tariffs-2069464">https://www.newsweek.com/seattle-port-says-no-container-ships-tariffs-2069464</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43946601">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="block-system-main" data-gtm-action="Main_Page_Content"><div>
<article><div id="v_article">      <div><p>
By <span>
<span id="tooltip_reporter_0"><p>Hugh Cameron is Newsweek U.S. news reporter based in London, U.K. with a focus on covering American economic and business news. Hugh joined Newsweek in 2024, having worked at Alliance News Ltd where he specialised in global and regional business developments, economic news, and market trends. He graduated from the University of Warwick with a bachelor's degree in politics in 2022, and from the University of Cambridge with a master's degree in international relations in 2023. Languages: English. You can get in touch with Hugh by emailing <a href="mailto:h.cameron@newsweek.com" data-mce-href="mailto:h.cameron@newsweek.com">h.cameron@newsweek.com</a></p>
</span>

</span></p><p>U.S. News Reporter</p></div>  <div id="audio-player-container">
<p>🎙️ Voice is AI-generated. Inconsistencies may occur.</p>
</div>   <div><p>Another shipping port official voiced concern about the drastic decline in imports as a result of President <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/topic/donald-trump" data-sys="1">Donald Trump</a>'s tariffs.</p><p>"I can see it right over my shoulder here, I'm looking out at the Port of Seattle right now, and we currently have no container ships at berth," Seattle port commissioner Ryan Calkins told <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/topic/cnn" data-sys="1">CNN</a> on Wednesday.</p><p>"That happens every once in a while at normal times, but it's pretty rare," he added. "And so to see it tonight is I think a stark reminder that the impacts of the tariffs have real implications."</p><p><em>Newsweek</em> has reached out to the Port of Seattle via email outside of business hours for further comment.</p><h2><strong>Why It Matters</strong></h2><p>Several port authorities have observed a similar drop in cargo volumes over the past few weeks, warning that such a decline could have significant and adverse effects on consumers—who may face rising prices and limited product availability—as well as the supply chain-linked sectors of the U.S. economy.</p><h2><strong>What To Know</strong></h2><p>Calkins told CNN that the current situation would impact the job security of longshoremen and those dealing directly with the freight, as well as industries responsible for transporting imports nationwide.</p><p>"And that's hundreds of jobs right here in our region and across the country," he said, adding that his port had not witnessed such a significant downturn in activity since the height of the COVID-19 pandemic.</p><figure><div>
<picture width="1200" height="737"><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 992px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.webp?w=790&amp;f=de4f6f411f352bf8362de54e322f073f 1x"><source type="image/jpeg" media="(min-width: 992px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.jpg?w=790&amp;f=de4f6f411f352bf8362de54e322f073f 1x"><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 768px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.webp?w=900&amp;f=145863f61cacbe72f2261e9983e5d3c8 1x"><source type="image/jpeg" media="(min-width: 768px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.jpg?w=900&amp;f=145863f61cacbe72f2261e9983e5d3c8 1x"><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 481px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.webp?w=790&amp;f=de4f6f411f352bf8362de54e322f073f 1x"><source type="image/jpeg" media="(min-width: 481px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.jpg?w=790&amp;f=de4f6f411f352bf8362de54e322f073f 1x"><source type="image/webp" media="(min-width: 0px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.webp?w=450&amp;f=dcbc26bd72ffc9f26e2cbfb143474ea3 1x"><source type="image/jpeg" media="(min-width: 0px)" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.jpg?w=450&amp;f=dcbc26bd72ffc9f26e2cbfb143474ea3 1x"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.webp?w=1200&amp;f=7215fd04e51a44ae96d4126efdd90722"><img loading="lazy" id="i2640751" src="https://d.newsweek.com/en/full/2640751/seattle-port.jpg?w=1200&amp;f=7215fd04e51a44ae96d4126efdd90722" alt="seattle port" width="1200" height="737"></picture></div><figcaption>
<span id="short-cap-description">Stacked containers in the Port of Los Angeles, California, on May 6, 2025.</span>

<span>Frederic J. Brown/AFP via Getty Images</span>
</figcaption>  </figure><p>Long Beach Port CEO Mario Cordero similarly compared the current decline in traffic to COVID-era disruptions, <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/busiest-ports-dire-warning-trump-tariffs-2068414" target="_blank" title="America's Busiest Ports Issue 'Dire' Warning Over Trump Tariffs" rel="noopener">describing the situation as "dire"</a> in an interview with <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/topic/nbc" data-sys="1">NBC</a>.</p><p>"<a href="https://www.newsweek.com/boss-biggest-us-port-predicts-when-tariffs-could-bite-consumers-2067641" target="_blank" rel="noopener">You could hear a pin drop</a>," Port of Los Angeles Director Gene Seroka said, telling NPR this week that imports at the ordinarily busy port were down by around 35 percent on an annual basis.</p><p>"The impact the Port of Los Angeles has on the city, the region and the country cannot be understated," Seroka told NPR. "The cargo that moves through this port reaches not only all 50 states, but each one of our 435 congressional districts."</p><h2><strong>What People Are Saying</strong></h2><p><strong>Gene Seroka, executive director of the Port of Los Angeles</strong>, told CNN on Tuesday: "This week, we're down about 35 percent compared to the same time last year, and these cargo ships coming in are the first ones to be attached to the tariffs that were levied against China and other locations last month. That's why the cargo volume is so light."</p><p><strong>Seroka</strong> said last week: "American importers, especially in the retail sector, are telling me that they have about <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/boss-biggest-us-port-predicts-when-tariffs-could-bite-consumers-2067641" target="_blank" rel="noopener">five to seven weeks of normal inventory</a> on hand today."</p><p><strong>Ryan Young, senior economist at the Competitive Enterprise Institute, </strong><a href="https://www.newsweek.com/americans-face-empty-shelves-within-weeks-2067118" target="_blank" rel="noopener">previously told <em>Newsweek</em></a>: "Tariff-related shipping slowdowns will cause a regional cascade effect in the U.S., a little like when COVID-19 first hit. It will first be visible in West Coast ports, which have the fastest shipping times from Asia. After that it will spread to Gulf ports like Houston, which take a little longer to reach, then East Coast ports from the Carolinas up to New England."</p>	<figure data-gtm-category="Related In-Text A" data-gtm-action="Click">
</figure><h2><strong>What Happens Next</strong></h2><p>The administration has been deliberating a deal with China it says could result in duties on its imports dropping significantly. However, Beijing has <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/china-trade-talks-narrative-trump-messages-us-negotiation-2067193" target="_blank" rel="noopener">given equivocal statements</a> regarding its readiness to negotiate with the U.S.</p><p>In his testimony before the House Financial Services Committee on Tuesday, Treasury Secretary <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/topic/scott-bessent" data-sys="1">Scott Bessent</a> said that he, alongside U.S. Trade Representative Jamieson Greer would <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/trump-china-tariff-meeting-geneva-switzerland-bessent-2068860" target="_blank" rel="noopener">commence negotiations with China</a> on Saturday in Geneva, Switzerland.</p>  </div></div>   <div data-pollid="7" data-articleid="2069464" data-gtm-category="FairnessMeter" data-gtmaction="original"><div><div>
<p><img src="https://g.newsweek.com/www/images/NW_ICON_CommonGround.png" alt="Newsweek Logo" width="92" height="113"></p><h2>fairness meter</h2><div><h2>fairness meter</h2><div><p>Newsweek is committed to journalism that's factual and fair.</p><p>Hold us accountable and submit your rating of this article on the meter. <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/fairness-meter" data-gtm-action="Fairness_Meter_original_Support_Page"><span></span></a></p></div></div></div><div><p>Newsweek is committed to journalism that's factual and fair.</p><p>Hold us accountable and submit your rating of this article on the meter. <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/fairness-meter" data-gtm-action="Fairness_Meter_original_Support_Page"><span></span></a></p></div></div><div>
<figure><p><span>Click On Meter </span><span>To Rate This Article</span></p>
</figure></div></div></article></div>     <div data-gtm-action="Top_Stories"><h2>
Top stories</h2></div><section data-gtm-action="About_The_Writer"><h3>About the writer</h3>
<span>
<span id="tooltip_reporter_0"><p>Hugh Cameron is Newsweek U.S. news reporter based in London, U.K. with a focus on covering American economic and business news. Hugh joined Newsweek in 2024, having worked at Alliance News Ltd where he specialised in global and regional business developments, economic news, and market trends. He graduated from the University of Warwick with a bachelor's degree in politics in 2022, and from the University of Cambridge with a master's degree in international relations in 2023. Languages: English. You can get in touch with Hugh by emailing <a href="mailto:h.cameron@newsweek.com" data-mce-href="mailto:h.cameron@newsweek.com">h.cameron@newsweek.com</a></p>
</span>
<a href="javascript:void(0);" rel="author" data-id="reporter_0"> Hugh Cameron </a>
</span>            
<p>
<span id="dots-description"><p>Hugh Cameron is Newsweek U.S. news reporter based in London, U.K. with a focus on covering American economic and business                                    ...
<a onclick="toggleDescription()" id="read-more-btn">Read more</a>
</p></span></p>  </section>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Critical Look at MCP (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://raz.sh/blog/2025-05-02_a_critical_look_at_mcp</link>
            <guid>43945993</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 14:37:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://raz.sh/blog/2025-05-02_a_critical_look_at_mcp">https://raz.sh/blog/2025-05-02_a_critical_look_at_mcp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43945993">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    

    <nav>

<ul>
<li>
<ul>
<li><a href="#toc_0" rel="nofollow">TL;DR</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_1" rel="nofollow">Background</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_2" rel="nofollow">Protocol</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_3" rel="nofollow">Transport</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#toc_4" rel="nofollow">Stdio</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_5" rel="nofollow">HTTP+SSE / Streamable HTTP</a></li>
</ul></li>

<li><a href="#toc_6" rel="nofollow">A Descent into Madness</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#toc_7" rel="nofollow">The Warning Signs...</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_8" rel="nofollow">The Problem</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#toc_9" rel="nofollow">HTTP+SSE Mode</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_10" rel="nofollow">"Streamable HTTP" Mode</a></li>
</ul></li>

<li><a href="#toc_11" rel="nofollow">What Are the Implications for SSE Mode?</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_12" rel="nofollow">What Are the Implications for "Streamable HTTP"?</a>
<ul>
<li><a href="#toc_13" rel="nofollow">General implications</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_14" rel="nofollow">Security Implications</a></li>
</ul></li>

<li><a href="#toc_15" rel="nofollow">Authorization</a></li>
</ul></li>

<li><a href="#toc_16" rel="nofollow">What Should Be Done</a></li>

<li><a href="#toc_17" rel="nofollow">Side note: Alternatives and Additions</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>

</nav>

<blockquote>
<p>"MCP is an open protocol that standardizes how applications provide context to LLMs. Think of MCP like a USB-C port for AI
applications. Just as USB-C provides a standardized way to connect your devices to various peripherals and accessories, MCP
provides a standardized way to connect AI models to different data sources and tools."</p>

<p>― Anthropic</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="toc_0">TL;DR</h2>

<p>I would like for this to turn out to be a skill issue on my part, and hope that I'm missing something.</p>

<p>During the past month,<a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">MCP (Model Context Protocol)</a>, which would enable
LLMs to become agents and interact with the world, has really been blowing up. The idea is straightforward: let's standardize an
API for LLM/Agents to interact with the world and how to inform the LLM/Agent about it.</p>

<p>Things are moving really fast, and IBM recently released their own "orthogonal standard" to MCP
called <a href="https://agentcommunicationprotocol.dev/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Agent Communication Protocol (ACP)</a>, followed closely by Google
announcing <a href="https://google.github.io/A2A" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">Agent2Agent (A2A)</a>.</p>

<p>MCP Servers and Clients are being built and published daily, and can be found at sites like <a href="https://mcp.so/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">mcp.so</a>
and <a href="https://www.pulsemcp.com/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">pulsemcp.com</a>.</p>

<p>However, I'm astonished by the apparent lack of mature engineering practices. All the major players spend billions of dollars on
training and tuning their models, only to turn around and, from what I can tell, have an interns write the documentation,
providing subpar SDKs and very little in terms of implementation guidance.</p>

<p>This trend seems to have continued with MCP, resulting in some very strange design decisions, poor documentation, and an even
worse specification of the actual protocols.</p>

<p>My conclusion is that the whole suggested setup for HTTP transport (SSE+HTTP and Streamable HTTP) should be thrown out and
replaced
with something that mimics stdio... Websockets.</p>

<h2 id="toc_1">Background</h2>

<p>About three weeks ago, I decided to jump on the MCP bandwagon to give it a try and see how it could be used in our own
environment. I'm very much a person who wants to understand how things actually work under the hood before I start using
abstractions. Here we have a new protocol that works over different transports — how exciting!</p>

<p>Anthropic is the company behind the MCP standardization effort, and MCP seems to be one of the major reasons Anthropic's CEO is
thinking that most code will be written by LLMs within a year or so. The bet on coding tooling in particular seems to have been
the guiding principle of the standardization effort based on how it feels to work with it.</p>

<h2 id="toc_2">Protocol</h2>

<p>Simply put, it is a JSON-RPC protocol with predefined methods/endpoints designed to be used in conjunction with an LLM. This is
not really the focus of this post, but there are things to be criticized about the protocol itself.</p>

<h2 id="toc_3">Transport</h2>

<p>As with many applications post-2005, they're supposedly "local first" (<em>ironically</em>), and this seems to be very much the case with
MCP. Looking at the transport protocol, you get a sense of where
they're coming from—if their intention is to build LLM tools for coding on your laptop. They're probably looking at local IDEs (or
more realistically, Cursor or Windsurf) and how to have the LLM interact with the local file system, databases, editors, language
servers, and so on.</p>

<p>There are essentially two main transport protocols (or three):</p>

<ol>
<li>stdio</li>
<li>"Something over HTTP, the web seems to be a thing we probably should support."</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="toc_4">Stdio</h3>

<p>Using stdio essentially means starting a local MCP Server, hooking up <code>stdout</code> and <code>stdin</code> pipes from the server to the client,
and starting to send JSON and using <code>stderr</code> for logging. It kind of breaks the Unix/Linux piping paradigm using these streams for
bidirectional communication. When bidirectional communication is needed, we usually reach for a socket, unix socket or even a net
socket.</p>

<p>However, it is straightforward and easy to reason about, works out of the box in all OSes, no need to deal with sockets, and so
on. So even if there is a critique to be made, I get it.</p>

<h3 id="toc_5">HTTP+SSE / Streamable HTTP</h3>

<p>The HTTP transport is another story. There are two versions of the same mistake: HTTP+SSE (Server-Sent Events) transport, which is
being replaced by "Streamable HTTP" (a made-up term) that uses REST semantics with SSE. But with a whole lot of extra confusion
and corner cases on top.</p>

<p>It can be summarized as: "Since we like SSE for LLM streaming, we're not using WebSockets. Instead, we're effectively implementing
WebSockets on top of SSE and calling it 'Streamable HTTP' to make people think it's an accepted/known way of doing things."</p>

<p>They discuss the problems with WebSockets (and the reason for Streamable HTTP) in this
PR: <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/modelcontextprotocol/pull/206" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modelcontextprotocol/pull/206</a>, making some very
strange contortions and straw-man arguments to <strong>not</strong> use WebSockets. At least one other person in the thread seems to agree with
me: <a href="https://github.com/modelcontextprotocol/modelcontextprotocol/pull/206#issuecomment-2766559523" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modelcontextprotocol/pull/206#issuecomment-2766559523</a>.</p>

<h2 id="toc_6">A Descent into Madness</h2>

<p>I set out to implement an MCP server in Golang. There isn't an official Go SDK, and I wanted to understand the protocol. This
turned out to be a mistake for mental health...</p>

<h3 id="toc_7">The Warning Signs...</h3>

<p>Looking at <a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">https://modelcontextprotocol.io</a>, the documentation is poorly written (all LLM vendors seem to have an internal
competition in writing confusing documentation). The specification glosses over or ignores important aspects of the protocol and
provides no examples of conversation flow. In fact, it seems the entire website is not meant for reading the standard; instead, it
pushes you toward tutorials on how to implement their SDKs.</p>

<p>All example servers are implemented in Python or JavaScript, with the intention that you download and run them locally using
stdio. Python and JavaScript are probably one of the worst choices of languages for something you want to work on anyone else's
computer. The authors seem to realize this since all examples are available as Docker containers.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Be honest... when was the last time you ran <code>pip install</code> and didn't end up in dependency hell?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Am I being pretentious/judgmental in thinking that people in AI only really know Python, and the "well, it works on my computer"
approach is still considered acceptable? This should be glaringly obvious to anyone that ever tried to run anything from
Hugging Face.</p>

<p>If you want to run MCP locally, wouldn't you prefer a portable language like Rust, Go, or even VM-based options such as Java or
C#?</p>

<h3 id="toc_8">The Problem</h3>

<p>When I started implementing the protocol, I immediately felt I had to reverse-engineer it. Important aspects of the SSE portion
are missing from the documentation, and no one seemed to have implemented the "Streamable HTTP" yet; not even their own tooling
like <code>npx @modelcontextprotocol/inspector@latest</code>. (To be fair, it might have been a skill issue on my part, pulling the wrong
version, since it was available when I checked again a few weeks later. You can also find version at
<a href="https://inspect.mcp.garden/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">inspect.mcp.garden</a>, which might be more convenient.)</p>

<p>Once you grasp the architecture, you quickly realize that implementing an MCP server, or a client, could be a huge effort. The
problem is that the SSE/Streamable HTTP implementations are trying to act like sockets, emulating stdio, without being one and is
trying to do <em>Everything Everywhere All at Once</em>.</p>

<h4 id="toc_9">HTTP+SSE Mode</h4>

<p><a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2024-11-05/basic/transports" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2024-11-05/basic/transports</a></p>

<p>In <strong>HTTP+SSE mode</strong>, to achieve full duplex, the client sets up an SSE session to (e.g.) <code>GET /sse</code> for reads. The first read provides
a URL where writes can be posted. The client then proceeds to use the given endpoint for writes, e.g., a request to
<code>POST /a-endpoint?session-id=1234</code>. The server returns a 202 Accepted with no body, and the response to the request should be read
from the pre-existing open SSE connection on <code>/sse</code>.</p>

<h4 id="toc_10">"Streamable HTTP" Mode</h4>

<p><a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26/basic/transports" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26/basic/transports</a></p>

<p>In <strong>"Streamable HTTP" mode</strong>, they realized that instead of providing a new endpoint in the first request, they could use an
HTTP header for the session ID and REST semantics for the endpoint. For example, <code>GET</code> or <code>POST /mcp</code> can open an SSE session and
return an <code>mcp-session-id=1234</code> HTTP header. To send data, the client does requests to <code>POST /mcp</code> and adds the HTTP header
<code>mcp-session-id=1234</code>. The response may:</p>

<ul>
<li>Open a new SSE stream and post the reply</li>
<li>Return a 200 with the reply in the body</li>
<li>Return a 202, indicating the reply will be written to one of any pre-existing SSE stream</li>
</ul>

<p>To end the session, the client may or may not send a <code>DELETE /mcp</code> with the header <code>mcp-session-id=1234</code>. The server must maintain
state with no clear way to know when the client has abandoned the session unless the client nicely ends it properly.</p>

<h3 id="toc_11">What Are the Implications for SSE Mode?</h3>

<p>This is such a problematic design that I don't know where to begin.</p>

<p>While some key features of SSE mode are undocumented, it's fairly straightforward once you reverse-engineer it. But this still
puts a huge and unnecessary burden on the server implementation, which needs to "join" connections across calls. Doing anything
real will pretty much force you to use a message queue to reply to any request. E.g., running the server in any redundant way will
mean that the SSE stream might come from one server to the client, while the requests are being sent to a completely different
server.</p>

<h3 id="toc_12">What Are the Implications for "Streamable HTTP"?</h3>

<p>The <strong>Streamable HTTP</strong> approach takes it to another level with a host of security concerns and obfuscated control flow. While
keeping all the bad parts from SSE mode, Streamable HTTP seems to be more of a super-set of confusion over SSE mode.</p>

<p>In terms of implementation I have just scratched the surface, but from what I understand in the docs...</p>

<p><strong>A new session can be created in 3 ways:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>An empty <code>GET</code> request</li>
<li>An empty <code>POST</code> request</li>
<li>A <code>POST</code> request containing the RPC call</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>An SSE can be opened in 4 different ways:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>A <code>GET</code> to initialize</li>
<li>A <code>GET</code> to join an earlier session</li>
<li>A <code>POST</code> to initialize a session</li>
<li>A <code>POST</code> that contains a request and answers with an SSE</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>A request may be answered in any of 3 different ways:</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>As an HTTP response to a <code>POST</code> with an RPC call</li>
<li>As an event in an SSE that was opened as a response to the <code>POST</code> RPC call</li>
<li>As an event to any SSE that was opened at some earlier point</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="toc_13">General implications</h4>

<p>With its multiple ways to initiate sessions, open SSE connections, and respond to requests, this introduces significant
complexity.
This complexity has several general implications:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Increased Complexity</strong>: The multiple ways of doing the same thing (session creation, SSE opening, response delivery) increases
the cognitive load for developers. It becomes harder to understand, debug, and maintain code.</li>
<li><strong>Potential for Inconsistency</strong>: With various ways to achieve the same outcome, there's a higher risk of inconsistent
implementations across different servers and clients. This can lead to interoperability issues and unexpected behavior. Clients
and servers just implementing the parts they feel are necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Scalability Concerns</strong>: While Streamable HTTP aims to improve efficiency, with a charitable interpretation, the complexity
will introduce scalability bottlenecks that need to be overcome. Servers might struggle to manage the diverse connection states,
response mechanisms over a large number of machines.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="toc_14">Security Implications</h4>

<p>The "flexibility" of Streamable HTTP introduces several security concerns, and here are just a few of them:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>State Management Vulnerabilities</strong>: Managing session state across different connection types (HTTP and SSE) is complex. This
could lead to vulnerabilities such as session hijacking, replay attacks or DoS attacks by creating state on the server that
needs to be managed and kept around waiting for a session to be resumed.</li>
<li><strong>Increased Attack Surface</strong>: The multiple entry points for session creation and SSE connections expand the attack surface. Each
entry point represents a potential vulnerability that an attacker could exploit.</li>
<li><strong>Confusion and Obfuscation</strong>: The variety of ways to initiate sessions and deliver responses can be used to obfuscate malicious
activity.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="toc_15">Authorization</h3>

<p>The latest version of the protocol contains some very opinionated requirements on how authorization should be done.</p>

<p><a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26/basic/authorization" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26/basic/authorization</a></p>

<blockquote>
<ul>
<li>Implementations using an HTTP-based transport SHOULD conform to this specification.</li>
<li>Implementations using an STDIO transport SHOULD NOT follow this specification, and instead retrieve credentials from the
environment.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>I'm reading it like, for stdio, do whatever. For HTTP, you better fucking jump through these OAuth2 hoops. Why do I need to
implement OAuth2 if I'm using HTTP as transport, while an API key is enough for stdio?</p>

<h2 id="toc_16">What Should Be Done</h2>

<p>I don't know, just kind of feel sad about it all...
It seems like the industry is peeing their pants at the moment ― <em>it feels great now, but it's going to be hard to deal with
later.</em></p>

<p>There is one JSON RPC protocol, and Stdio is clearly preferred as the transport protocol. Then we should try to have the HTTP
transport be as much like Stdio as we can make it, and only really deviate if we really, really need to.</p>

<ul>
<li>In Stdio, we have Environment Variables, in HTTP we have HTTP Headers</li>
<li>In Stdio, we have <em>socket-like</em> behavior with input and output streams, in HTTP we have WebSockets</li>
</ul>

<p>That's it really. We should be able to accomplish the same thing on WebSockets as we do on Stdio. WebSockets are the appropriate
choice for transport over HTTP. We can do away with complex cross-server state management for sessions. We can do away with a
multitude of corner-cases and on and on.</p>

<p>Sure some things, like authorization, might be a bit more complicated in some instances (and easier in some); some firewalls out
there might block WebSockets; there might be extra overhead for small sessions; it might be harder to resume a broken session. But
as
<em>they</em> say:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>Clients and servers MAY implement additional custom transport mechanisms to suit their specific needs. The protocol is
transport-agnostic and can be implemented over any communication channel that supports bidirectional message exchange</p>

<p><a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26/basic/transports#custom-transports" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-03-26/basic/transports#custom-transports</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>As an industry, we should optimize for the most common use-cases, not the corner-cases.</p>

<h2 id="toc_17">Side note: Alternatives and Additions</h2>

<p>As discussed above, there seem to be more protocols emerging. MCP is effectively "a protocol to expose an API to an LLM" (which
can create an agent). The more recent protocols from IBM and Google (ACP and A2A) are effectively "protocols to expose an Agent to
an LLM" (which can create an agent of agents).</p>

<p>Looking through the A2A specification, it seems like there's a very limited need for them. Even though they claim to be
orthogonal, most things in A2A could be accomplished with MCP as is or with small additions.</p>

<p>It boils down to two entire protocols that could just as well be tools in an MCP server. Even IBM seems to acknowledge that their
protocol isn't really necessary:</p>

<blockquote>
<p>"Agents can be viewed as MCP resources and further invoked as MCP tools. Such a view of ACP agents allows MCP clients to
discover and run ACP agents..."</p>

<p>― IBM / <a href="https://agentcommunicationprotocol.dev/ecosystem/mcp-adapter" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">agentcommunicationprotocol.dev/ecosystem/mcp-adapter</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>My initial feeling is that the ACP protocol mostly seems like an attempt for IBM to promote their "
agent-building-tool" <a href="https://beeai.dev/" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank">BeeAI</a></p>

<p>What both of the A** protocols bring to the table is a sane transport layer and a way to discover agents.</p>

<p><img src="https://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/standards.png" alt="14 competing standards"></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[US vs. Google Amicus Curiae Brief of Y Combinator in Support of Plaintiffs [pdf] (231 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205.1300.1.pdf</link>
            <guid>43945820</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 14:15:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205.1300.1.pdf">https://storage.courtlistener.com/recap/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205/gov.uscourts.dcd.223205.1300.1.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43945820">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The cult of doing business (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.commonwealmagazine.org/calvert-work-entrepreneur-ethic-baker-review-job</link>
            <guid>43945162</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 12:39:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.commonwealmagazine.org/calvert-work-entrepreneur-ethic-baker-review-job">https://www.commonwealmagazine.org/calvert-work-entrepreneur-ethic-baker-review-job</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43945162">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>One of the strangest features of American work culture is the constant pressure to treat one’s job as something more than a job: a calling, a means of expressing oneself, a vehicle for personal growth. This pressure comes from bosses, of course, who would rather foster intrinsic motivation than pay higher wages. But it also comes from popular psychology. As every self-help reader knows, the most successful careerists leverage their own unique personalities to achieve results and add value. They work for themselves. They love what they do. They are radiant with a higher purpose. In a word, they are “entrepreneurial.”</p>
<p>In his new book, <a href="https://www.hup.harvard.edu/books/9780674293601"><em>Make Your Own Job: How the Entrepreneurial Work Ethic Exhausted America</em></a>, historian Erik Baker calls this self-help ideology “the rot festering at the core” of our national obsession with work. A comprehensive and sharply written intellectual history, the book traces the origins of several reputedly twenty-first-century maladies to an earlier age. Gig work, as it turns out, didn’t begin with Uber but with Avon direct-sales reps. The wacky metaphysics of today’s tech billionaires have their analogues in the “mind-cures” of nineteenth-century spiritualists. And the celebration of “charismatic” executives has its origins in German social science, with disturbingly fascist undertones. Baker also demonstrates how a fetish for entrepreneurs shaped both modernization theory during the Cold War and now-discredited market-based solutions to global poverty, especially microfinance. But the “marriage of positive psychology and the entrepreneurial ethic” is the book’s primary target. It’s a rotten worldview because it “enjoins us to work more intensely than we need to,” and more importantly, it “leaves us feeling devoid of purpose when we don’t have work.”</p>
<p><br><strong>Baker’s book tells a story</strong> about the unholy union between American psychology and American business—not just how it was formed, but how it came to present as universal truths concepts that were in fact derived from economic scarcity. The story begins with New Thought, a nineteenth-century spiritual movement that emerged in response to the trauma of American capitalism as it swaggered into the Gilded Age. Writers like Ralph Waldo Trine, who became a favorite of Henry Ford, believed that “creative” people had the power to manifest opportunities for themselves even amid the direst circumstances. There’s a reason William James felt the need to address the movement in his scrupulously compassionate book <em>The Varieties of Religious Experience</em>. New Thought claimed that “personal thoughts are forces,” that “serenity” and “happiness” are available to anyone who adopts the right attitude, that the universe has a reservoir of positive vibes to draw from. Like James, Baker approaches his subject with care and curiosity. He is less interested in the credulousness of those who believed in “mind cures” than he is in the material conditions that created such a strong demand for intellectual moonshine. At a time of great upheaval, he writes, “New Thought promised to restore power to the individual” and “grant practitioners the ability to overcome ‘concern’” about the “precarious labor market.” Eventually, this quirky strain of neo-transcendentalism evolved into what Baker calls a “doctrinally fuzzy success philosophy.”</p>
<p>That philosophy is just as fuzzy now as it was a century ago. It remains with us in the form of personal-growth seminars, advice podcasts, and the bright, encouraging schlock filling space in airport bookstores. Then as now, the field was nothing if not a huckster’s paradise. One of the more amusing figures, Napoleon Hill, a con man and the bestselling author of <em>Think and Grow Rich</em> (1937), urged his readers to cultivate a self that one could market, which required “imagination.” His own imagination invented a meeting with Andrew Carnegie as a ploy to sell more books; other creative schemes included credit fraud, an oil-stock scam, and embezzlement from charities. This message paired nicely with that of the more renowned and less explicitly fraudulent Dale Carnegie, who emphasized the importance of turning talents and passions into cash. Both authors preyed upon the fragile, desperate millions still recovering from the market crash.</p>
</div><div><p>In the fifties, Norman Vincent Peale, a preacher, New Thought evangelist, and eventual officiant of Donald Trump’s first wedding, produced one of the most popular self-help books of all time, <em>The Power of Positive Thinking</em>. “The more you lose yourself in something bigger than yourself,” Peale writes, “the more energy you will have.” Strangely, for Peale, that “something bigger” didn’t include unions or the social infrastructure built by Roosevelt’s New Deal, which he fumed against at every turn. The book has never been out of print, and Baker is good at explaining why. For people afraid of falling behind in the wake of the Great Depression (or, in our own time, the Great Recession) the entrepreneurial ethic that arose from New Thought literature “functioned as a sort of insurance policy—not just a failsafe strategy in case of unemployment, but a preemptive ward against redundancy and obsolescence.”</p>
<p>The same anxieties that attracted people to New Thought at the dawn of American capitalism would later fuel demand for the positive-psychology movement, which has since been enshrined in the curricula of American business schools. At first glance, this movement may appear unassailable. Its goal, after all, is to make people happier and encourage them to “flourish” in their work lives. However, as Baker demonstrates, its primary role is to lend intellectual support to the entrepreneurial ethic. “Psychology is the idiom through which entrepreneurship is discussed,” he writes. In fact, “it’s not always obvious where positive psychology ends and entrepreneurship begins.” How could it be, when business schools now employ teams of psychologists, urging future leaders to embrace “grit,” find “flow,” adopt a “growth mindset,” and establish their own personal brand? “Popular psychology,” Baker writes, “encouraged Americans to cultivate an attractive personality that would help them win the affection of their coworkers and bosses and thus ascend the corporate ladder—instead of striving to embody the transcendent moral values constitutive of the older notion of character.” Baker is keen to expose the harm this movement’s entrepreneurial turn has caused the culture at large. The book opens with the tragic story of Tony Hsieh, the CEO of Zappos and the author of <em>Delivering Happiness: A Path to Profits, Passion, and Purpose</em>. Hsieh died in a fire at the age of forty-six after barricading himself in a shed with nitrous-oxide canisters, a propane tank, and candles. It’s a cautionary tale about the Faustian bargain “positive psychology” struck with the startup world.</p>
<p>The term “positive psychology” was coined in 1954 by Abraham Maslow, whose relationship with entrepreneurs in Arizona and California is one of the book’s many fascinating subplots. According to Baker, Maslow saw “entrepreneurial leadership” as one of the best applications of his psychological theories of motivation and self-actualization. A similar fondness for business can be found in Maslow’s successor, Martin Seligman, whose work in the nineties and early aughts emphasized the usefulness of positive psychology to achieving success at work. (<em>Flourish</em>, his 2011 book, was blurbed by Tony Hsieh.)</p>
<p>The incentive to make one’s insights more amenable to executives and consultants seems to be irresistible. This is how the author of <em>Flow</em>, Mihaly Csikszentmihalyi,<em> </em>became the author of <em>Good Business: Leadership, Flow, and the Making of Meaning</em>, for example. Not that the insights themselves are wrong. Just as Dale Carnegie was right to say that people love to hear the sound of their own name, it is probably true that “autoletic” workers (those who discover intrinsic motivation and achieve “flow”) will feel more satisfied at work. But Baker is calling attention to the fact that these ideas become popular among managers for ignoble reasons: they make it cheaper and easier to burden employees with the task of preserving their own well-being. “Autoletic” workers are more easily exploited, as are those who treat their jobs as extension of themselves. The basic career advice one gets from positive psychology is that throwing yourself into your work is the best way to achieve success and personal fulfillment. And since Americans, as Baker suggests, “prize psychological health as highly as a religious duty,” to fail to be entrepreneurial is a kind of mortal sin.</p>
<p>The Christian language of “duty” and “calling” comes from Max Weber, the German sociologist who studied the problem of how to encourage <em>Arbeitsfreude</em>, or “joy in work.” Weber’s 1904 visit to the United States helped convince him of his famous thesis that the main driver of worker motivation was the Protestant ethic. His colleague Joseph Schumpeter, building upon the supposed link between economic and personal growth, celebrated the entrepreneur as the innovative, heroic force behind “creative destruction”—the kind of leader who inspires joy, meaning, and purpose. The problem, Baker argues, as he combs through the legacy of German social science, is that for some, the only purpose of life is to win at any cost. “The entrepreneur became a Nietzschean conqueror,” he writes, “setting the world ablaze with his energy and virility.” This holds true even when proponents of “creative destruction” adopt a sunnier idiom in Northern California. Baker describes Steve Jobs, who encouraged “an almost cult-like esprit de corps” in his Macintosh unit, as “the most ruthless entrepreneur to emerge from the counterculture.” In Silicon Valley, charismatic leadership of the kind that aroused the Austrian economists was given a friendly, New Age twist. Baker’s genealogy helps explain why American startup culture is so deeply weird.</p>
<p><br><strong>But it’s not weird</strong>, of course, to seek work that is meaningful and satisfying. Hence the universal appeal of the entrepreneurial ethic: it offers the founder, the franchisee, the gig worker, and the influencer the same promise of freedom, and it offers those with W-2s a reason to clock in every day. Employees, no matter what their job, crave recognition, autonomy, and a personal connection to work, which is why they often contribute more than they’re paid for. Baker’s point is that celebrating workers’ “proactivity” disguises an essentially exploitative relationship. That’s especially true when the ethic becomes a management philosophy, as it did during the consulting boom of the seventies and eighties, when “value creation” and “innovation” served as important alibis for cost-cutting and deregulation. “The ultimate function of the entrepreneurial ethic,” he writes, “is to reconcile workers to precarity.” It also creates the illusion that the tech billionaire and the gig worker (who receives no benefits and cannot join a union) are aligned against the wet blanket of government regulation.</p>
<p>Because this ideology is custom made for slumps and busts, it can never be discredited. Baker echoes the work of Barbara Ehrenreich, who discovered a correlation between corporate downsizing and the rise of “positive thinking,” when he says, “Bad news for the economy has always been good news for the entrepreneurial work ethic.” The result is a tragic cycle:</p>
<blockquote><p>On the one hand there is burnout, a hustle culture whose intensity many Americans feel is grinding them into mental, emotional, and physical depletion. On the other hand, there is the lingering poison of deindustrialization, the anomie or social decay that appears to creep into communities where work disappears. But to some extent, these complaints are two sides of the same coin. The looming specter of worklessness is one important motivator of the punishing demands we make on ourselves when we are at work. And our relentless search for innovation and optimization in turn renders swaths of the workforce redundant and obsolete. On and on it goes, in a perpetual spiral.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Make Your Own Job</em> diagnoses that spiral by showing how our economic and psychological pain form a kind of double helix. And Baker allows us to see why the genre of business self-help—and the management theory it often serves—is so predatory. “We are the CEOs of our own companies: Me, Inc.” Tom Peters wrote in “The Brand Called You,” published in <em>Fast Company</em> in 1997. This pressure to build a personal brand is one of the great pathologies of the past three decades—not only because the LinkedIn startup crowd is so insufferable, or because a personal brand is currently looting the federal government with the help of a lunatic entrepreneur, but because this ethos ultimately corrupts our souls and relationships.</p>
<p>There is nothing wrong with finding spiritual value in one’s career—provided that value doesn’t exist to be exploited by a billionaire. And of course it’s fine to love what you do. But it’s even better to treat love itself as the most important work.</p>
<p><em>Make Your Own Job</em><br><em>How the Entrepreneurial Work Ethic Exhausted America</em><br>Erik Baker<br>Harvard University Press<br>$35 | 352 pp.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LTXVideo 13B AI video generation (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ltxv.video/</link>
            <guid>43944974</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 11:59:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ltxv.video/">https://ltxv.video/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43944974">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
    <!-- Navigation -->
    <nav>
        
    </nav>

    <!-- Hero Section -->
    <div>
                
                <p>
                    A groundbreaking 13B-parameter AI model by Lightricks, revolutionizing video creation with unprecedented speed and quality.
                    <span>30x faster than comparable models, powered by advanced multiscale rendering technology.</span>
                </p>
                <!-- Video Player Section -->
                
            </div>

    <!-- Key Points Section -->
    <div id="key-points">
            <h2>LTXV Key Points</h2>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Model Overview</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>13 billion parameters for high-quality video generation</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Developed by Lightricks, released May 2025</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Significant upgrade from 2B parameter predecessor</span>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Core Capabilities</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Text-to-video generation</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Image-to-video transformation</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Real-time performance on consumer hardware</span>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Technical Features</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Multiscale rendering technology</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Enhanced prompt adherence</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>check_circle</span>
                            <span>Advanced motion quality control</span>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>

    <!-- Model Background Section -->
    <div id="background">
            <h2>LTXV Model Background</h2>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Development Context</h3>
                    <p>
                        LTXV-13B represents a significant evolution from its predecessor, the LTX Video model, with a notable increase in parameters from 2 billion to 13 billion. Released in early May 2025, this model was developed by Lightricks in response to advancements by competitors like OpenAI and Meta.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Release Date: May 2025</li>
                        <li>Model Size: 28.6 GB</li>
                        <li>Storage: Git LFS</li>
                        <li>License: LTXV Open Weights</li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Technical Evolution</h3>
                    <p>
                        The model builds upon the DiT-based architecture, introducing groundbreaking features like multiscale rendering and improved motion quality. This evolution enables real-time video generation at high resolutions while maintaining exceptional quality.
                    </p>
                    <ul>
                        <li>Base Model: DiT-based</li>
                        <li>Parameters: 13 Billion</li>
                        <li>Resolution: 1216×704</li>
                        <li>FPS: 30 (Real-time)</li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>

    <!-- Detailed Features Section -->
    <div id="detailed-features">
            <h2>LTXV Detailed Features</h2>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Core Technologies</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>auto_awesome</span>
                            <p><span>Multiscale Rendering</span>
                                <span>Advanced technology that drafts videos in lower detail first to capture coarse motion, then refines details for enhanced speed and quality.</span>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>speed</span>
                            <p><span>Kernel Optimization</span>
                                <span>Enables 30x faster generation compared to comparable models, even on consumer GPUs.</span>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>psychology</span>
                            <p><span>Improved Prompt Adherence</span>
                                <span>Enhanced accuracy in following text prompts for more precise video generation.</span>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Supported Features</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>movie</span>
                            <p><span>Text-to-Video</span>
                                <span>Transform text descriptions into high-quality videos with precise motion control.</span>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>image</span>
                            <p><span>Image-to-Video</span>
                                <span>Convert static images into dynamic videos with controlled motion and effects.</span>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>animation</span>
                            <p><span>Keyframe Animation</span>
                                <span>Create smooth animations with precise control over motion and timing.</span>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>

    <!-- Performance and Hardware Section -->
    <div id="performance-details">
            <h2>LTXV Performance &amp; Hardware</h2>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Hardware Requirements</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>memory</span>
                            <span>NVIDIA 4090/5090 GPU</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>storage</span>
                            <span>8GB+ VRAM (Full Version)</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>speed</span>
                            <span>Quantized Version Available</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>computer</span>
                            <span>Consumer Hardware Compatible</span>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Performance Metrics</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>speed</span>
                            <span>30x Faster Generation</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>timer</span>
                            <span>Real-time Processing</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>high_quality</span>
                            <span>Studio-level Quality</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>low_latency</span>
                            <span>Low Latency Output</span>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <h3>LTXV Optimization Features</h3>
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <span>auto_fix</span>
                            <span>Multiscale Rendering</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>tune</span>
                            <span>Kernel Optimization</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>memory_alt</span>
                            <span>Quantized Versions</span>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <span>efficiency</span>
                            <span>Memory Efficiency</span>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>

    <!-- Community and Tools Section -->
    

    <!-- FAQ Section -->
    <div id="faq">
            <h2>LTXV Frequently Asked Questions</h2>
            <div>
                <div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>What is LTXV-13B?</h3>
                        <p>
                            LTXV-13B is an advanced AI video generation model developed by Lightricks, featuring 13 billion parameters. It represents a significant upgrade from its predecessor, offering high-quality video generation with unprecedented speed and efficiency.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>What are the key features of LTXV-13B?</h3>
                        <p>
                            Key features include multiscale rendering technology, improved prompt adherence, real-time generation at 1216×704 resolution (30 FPS), and support for various video generation modes including text-to-video and image-to-video transformations.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>What hardware is required to run LTXV-13B?</h3>
                        <p>
                            The model runs efficiently on consumer hardware like NVIDIA 4090 or 5090 GPUs. The full version requires 8GB+ VRAM, while a quantized version (ltxv-13b-fp8) is available for systems with less VRAM.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>How fast is LTXV-13B compared to other models?</h3>
                        <p>
                            LTXV-13B generates videos 30 times faster than comparable models, thanks to its multiscale rendering technology and kernel optimization. It achieves real-time performance while maintaining high quality.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>What video generation modes are supported?</h3>
                        <p>
                            The model supports text-to-video, image-to-video, keyframe-based animation, video extension, and video-to-video transformations. It can also combine these modes for complex video generation tasks.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>Is LTXV-13B open source?</h3>
                        <p>
                            Yes, LTXV-13B is available under the LTXV Open Weights License. The model and its tools are open source, allowing for community development and customization.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>What development tools are available?</h3>
                        <p>
                            The ecosystem includes LTX-Video-Trainer for fine-tuning, ComfyUI integration with example workflows, and support for creating custom LoRAs. All tools are available on GitHub.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>How does multiscale rendering work?</h3>
                        <p>
                            Multiscale rendering first drafts videos in lower detail to capture coarse motion, then refines the details. This approach enhances both speed and quality of the generated videos.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>What improvements were made in version 0.9.7?</h3>
                        <p>
                            Version 0.9.7 includes improved prompt adherence, enhanced motion quality, better fine details, and support for stochastic inference in the distilled model.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                    <div>
                        <h3>Where can I download and learn more about LTXV-13B?</h3>
                        <p>
                            The model is available on Hugging Face and GitHub. Comprehensive documentation, example workflows, and community resources are available through these platforms.
                        </p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </div>

    <!-- Get Started Section -->
    <div id="get-started">
                <h2>Start Creating with LTXV</h2>
                <p>
                    Join the future of video generation with LTXV 13B. Available on Hugging Face and GitHub.
                </p>
                
            </div>

    <!-- Footer -->
    

    <!-- Animation Scripts -->
    

    <!-- Add this script before the closing body tag -->
    

 </div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The deathbed fallacy (197 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.hjorthjort.xyz/2018/02/21/the-deathbed-fallacy.html</link>
            <guid>43944467</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 10:04:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.hjorthjort.xyz/2018/02/21/the-deathbed-fallacy.html">https://www.hjorthjort.xyz/2018/02/21/the-deathbed-fallacy.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43944467">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    
      <p><span itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject"><img src="https://www.hjorthjort.xyz/assets/img/Lord_Byron_deathbed.jpg" alt="“Lord Byron on his Death-bed” by Joseph Denis Odevaere">
      <meta itemprop="representativeOfPage" content="true">
      <meta itemprop="url" content="https://hjorthjort.github.io/assets/img/Lord_Byron_deathbed.jpg">
      <p>“Lord Byron on his Death-bed” by Joseph Denis Odevaere</p></span></p><p>This topic has bothered me for years. So now, in a moment of inspiration instigated by <a href="http://waitbutwhy.com/2014/10/religion-for-the-nonreligious.html">Wait But Why</a><sup id="fnref:1" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:1">1</a></sup> and drinking a glass or two of bourbon, I want to hash it out. It is something I call <em>the Deathbed Fallacy</em>.</p>

<h2 id="what-is-the-deathbed-fallacy">What is the Deathbed Fallacy?</h2>

<p>People on their deathbeds regret not spending more time of their life with their family, traveling more, worrying less, etc. I’ve heard this truism echoed by <a href="http://www.thelawofattraction.com/the-top-5-regrets-people-reveal-they-have-on-their-deathbed/">growth gurus</a> and spiritualists. It <a href="https://www.huffingtonpost.com/bronnie-ware/top-5-regrets-of-the-dyin_b_1220965.html">is</a> <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2012/feb/01/top-five-regrets-of-the-dying">amplified</a> <a href="http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/palliative-nurse-shares-the-most-common-regrets-of-her-patients-a6821061.html">by</a> <a href="http://www.businessinsider.com/5-things-people-regret-on-their-deathbed-2013-12">newspapers</a>. It comes up at dinner discussions. The origin the list of regrets is the palliative nurse <a href="http://bronnieware.com/regrets-of-the-dying/">Bronnie Ware</a> who listed the following most common regrets:</p>

<ol>
  <li>“I wish I’d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life others expected of me.</li>
  <li>I wish I didn’t work so hard.</li>
  <li>I wish I’d had the courage to express my feelings.</li>
  <li>I wish I had stayed in touch with my friends.</li>
  <li>I wish that I had let myself be happier.”</li>
</ol>

<p>All well and good. A bit vague, but seems like solid advice. So what is the
problem?</p>



<p>The fallacy is to assume that whoever you are on your deathbed knows how you should live your life right now. They wish they would have done things differently, meaning, they think <em>you</em> should do something differently, <em>right now</em>. You should consider yourself over a lifetime not as a single person, but a line of many people with different views and priorities. Now, do you think the last person in that line is wise and all-knowing? There are three reasons to doubt that deathbed-you is a competent guide for your life.</p>

<p>The deathbed you is not a reliable advisor. Here’s why.</p>

<h2 id="reason-1-it-is-not-a-representative-state">Reason 1: It is not a representative state</h2>

<p>The deathbed is not a representative state of life, and what you want when you
are there might not have much correlation with what would have been the happiest, most satisfactory and/or meaningful life you could have led.</p>

<p>The deathbed you is very special in a few ways:</p>

<ul>
  <li>They don’t have a future at all. They are about to die, and nothing they
think has a bearing on the future. All they have is the present and memories.</li>
  <li>They think they know their past selves (such as you) very well but probably
don’t. More on that soon.</li>
  <li>Like all your temporal selves, they are locked in a time, place and life
situation that does not necessarily correspond to yours.</li>
</ul>

<p>We should also expect recency bias to play a significant role. We should assume that the people expressing these regrets are in general quite old. Their memories of working a lot should be dominated by the late stages of their careers. The lost friends should be those they miss at old age, not necessarily the people you hung out with in your twenties that you’ve forgotten almost entirely by the time you’re 60.</p>

<h2 id="reason-2-you-dont-know-your-past-selves-but-you-think-you-do">Reason 2: You don’t know your past selves, but you think you do</h2>

<p>The older I get, the more I think I understand myself as a teenager. As I learn more about myself, I seem to grasp my motivations and my core ides ever more fully. So I tend to think of past me as <a href="http://www.smbc-comics.com/?id=3474">nothing but a slightly less grown-up, more athletic version of myself</a>. I think I’ve been consistent. And when I made the “wrong” choices, it’s either because I was (am) stupid, or because I didn’t have the right information.</p>

<p>But every now and then I find something I wrote or remember a decision I made in high school, which reminds me that my assumptions are all wrong. I was just as smart in high school, I had a lot of information (more than I do now because I’ve forgotten the details). The decisions I made were actually the right ones, and what I think now is wrong, because present me is overly simplistic about past me.</p>

<p>Case in point: for a few years, when I was 14 to 15, a big priority in my life was fitting in, and not be too open about my own ideas and feelings. This goes entirely against both my current ideals and the Deathbed List. So young me would have benefitted from some guidance from present me, right?</p>

<p>Wrong. When I find a diary from that time or talk to a friend from those days about it, it turns out I was probably doing the right thing. My core values were the same as now, only somewhat more 2-dimensional. I valued independence and authenticity back then, too. But what younger me realized, that present me forgot, was that I <em>sucked</em> as a person in a lot of ways and that people, in general, weren’t very fond of me. I also realized that no matter how enlightened or authentic I got, my overall happiness depended quite a lot on how other people saw me, and what relationship we developed.</p>

<p>Today, I probably care too much about what others think. I often blame teenage me for making me so aware of other people’s judgment – why can’t I just focus on cool work and meditation all the time with a select few people I love? But that is just present me shaming past me for dragging himself through an ordeal which benefitted us both. He handled the most pressing matter and passed on the work of undoing the side-effects to me. I just forgot about it and got stuck in regret.</p>

<p>In much the same way, I am now highly career focused. I want to learn a shit lot, I want good jobs, I want money, I want to influence. Deathbed-me would probably scowl and think I’ve gotten my priorities all twisted up. But I am doing this for us. I don’t care about having a career or money, except for as enablers of a good life, a life of freedom, a life in a great city with great people. I believe that hard work can take me places I will enjoy more than where I’d end up if I just focused on being happy in the moment, following the Deathbed List. I’m doing the best I can based on what I know. And that doesn’t come free, I have to make trade-offs. I happen to believe that a lot of the people I would love the hang out with are people in places it is actually hard to get to. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ji5_MqicxSo&amp;ab_channel=CarnegieMellonUniversity">The brick walls are there for a reason</a>, and I want to spend as much of my time as possible with the people on the other side of it, so I need to let go of some stuff on this side for a while. Deathbed-me is gonna be pissed, but he’s just a spoiled ingrate. He’s the kid I’m raising, not the other way around.</p>

<h2 id="reason-3-most-people-that-die-today-lived-in-a-world-very-different-to-yours">Reason 3: Most people that die today lived in a world very different to yours</h2>

<p>Maybe you think the key to happiness is universal. That it doesn’t change as the world does. But keep in mind that for all the things on the list, the predicament has changed. Let’s take number 1 on the list as an example:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I wish I’d had the courage to live a life true to myself, not the life others expected of me.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Think about someone you know who lived to be 70 years, 80 years or older. It may be someone alive or no longer with you. They correspond best to the average person in palliative care. Think about the stories they told you about growing up, about working life, about their values. Wouldn’t you agree that it was likely <em>a lot</em> harder for them to live outside the expectations of others? Have we not come a long way when it comes to people being free to shape their own lives? Is it possible, maybe, just maybe, that some people are a bit too good at being “authentic,” to the detriment of themselves and their surroundings, by being a bit self-obsessed and not paying enough attention to duty and the common good?</p>

<p>To someone in their 20s, there is, like, a 50-year delay in the data here. The challenges facing my generation are not the same as that of my grandparents. For example, do you 20-somethings today are better or worse at staying in contact with friends? My grandparents might have had trouble staying in touch, but weren’t stuck on social media. Maybe they were stuck in a cubicle or a rigid moral structure. Maybe they were stuck hiding their sexuality from their friends and families. Maybe they were homeowners by my age, settled down with a family. How similar do you think our lives are?</p>

<h2 id="who-is-most-guilty-of-this-fallacy">Who is most guilty of this fallacy?</h2>

<p>In my experience, those who “figure out” what life is really about seem to be pretty far
up in Maslow’s pyramid of needs, and focus a lot on the higher-order needs. They tend to be smart people that have figured out some way to make a decent living that allows them a lot of time to think, and personal freedom to explore experiences. I’d say that a lot of these people are, or have been, workaholics. And now they have the luxury of thinking about The Real Important Things In Life™, casting judgment on their former selves for not seeing when a precondition for them to be able to figure themselves out in the first place is the work they already put in.</p>

<p>Conversely, I’ve met quite a few people who are very concerned about living an authentic, carefree life without having a lot of other things figured out first. They don’t have a stable income (or at least the contacts and knowledge required to make some money when they need to), good relationships, and a good grasp of their material priorities. These are struggling artist, miserable drifters or just pretty aimless people with romantic dreams that leave them disappointed with the real world.</p>

<p>In short, people who already have a lot seem to assume that if they never even strived for it, they would be happier. But that striving is often an enabler of the life they now think they want. It is what gave them their family, their network, their passions.</p>

<h2 id="so-whats-the-alternative">So what’s the alternative?</h2>

<p>The Deathbed List is in a lot of ways sound advice (if a bit abstract). It aligns well with current happiness research. But it kind of shifts the blame onto you, for caring about other people, for working hard. Heck, it might be a good idea to be miserable for a few years to build up some knowledge or capital. At least, that’s what a lot of other solid life advice is telling us.</p>

<p>What I want you to take away is this: Don’t bother with the Deathbed Fallacy. Look at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Grant_Study">happiness research</a>, which tells you a stable income, focus on relationships and experiences rather than stuff, practicing acceptance, and small things like short commute times make you happier. <a href="https://www.happinessresearchinstitute.com/books">Get some books on the topic</a>. Reflect on your own past happiness right now, and consider what you should do become more fulfilled both today and for the rest of your time on Earth. Going to work most days and dropping a few friends you don’t have time for may actually be sensible right now if you are in the middle of your career, doing something meaningful. Don’t worry about what some old version of yourself will think of you but focus instead on making sure they are happy and well off, even if they are total ingrates.</p>

<p><em>I published this in late 2016 but realized I never finished editing it. This version is extensively reworked.</em></p>



  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Slow software for a burning world (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://bonfirenetworks.org/posts/slow_software_for_a_burning_world/</link>
            <guid>43943652</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 06:38:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://bonfirenetworks.org/posts/slow_software_for_a_burning_world/">https://bonfirenetworks.org/posts/slow_software_for_a_burning_world/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43943652">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
    <h4 id="a-reflection-on-bonfire%E2%80%99s-journey-to-1.0-and-an-open-invitation-to-shape-what-comes-next."><em>A reflection on Bonfire’s journey to 1.0 and an open invitation to shape what comes next.</em> <a href="#a-reflection-on-bonfire%E2%80%99s-journey-to-1.0-and-an-open-invitation-to-shape-what-comes-next.">#</a></h4>
<p>As we approach the release of Bonfire 1.0, this isn’t your typical launch announcement. Instead, it’s a moment to reflect on <strong>how</strong> we’ve built Bonfire, a roadmap of values, methods, and intentions – and an invitation to define what comes next.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>You can <a href="https://indieweb.social/@bonfire">follow Bonfire on the fediverse</a> for updates on the release, including highlights of unique features we’ll share over the next few days.</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>In a world of “move fast and break things,” we’ve chosen a different tempo — one rooted in care, deep listening, and collective stewardship. Slow software means building for long-term resilience and meaningful participation, rather than chasing novelty, speed, or scale.</p>
<h2 id="%F0%9F%8F%A6-profit-over-people%3A-at-what-cost%3F">🏦 <strong>Profit over people: at what cost?</strong> <a href="#%F0%9F%8F%A6-profit-over-people%3A-at-what-cost%3F">#</a></h2>
<p>The Silicon Valley model delivers quick but unaccountable decisions. Rules are one-sided, power is hoarded, and systems operate behind closed doors. The casualties are many:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Trust:</strong> Algorithms bred to addict or manipulate rather than to inform or empower.</li>
<li><strong>Consent</strong>: Secrecy quietly eroding autonomy. Invisible hands reshaping our lives without consent.</li>
<li><strong>Community:</strong> Platforms optimising for engagement, making division and hatred profitable.</li>
<li><strong>Attention:</strong> Human focus becomes data—extracted like oil to fuel the surveillance economy.</li>
<li><strong>Labour:</strong> Care work like content moderation rendered invisible, workers treated as expendable.</li>
<li><strong>Environment:</strong> Scale trumping sustainability at every turn.</li>
</ul>
<p>As power concentrates, democracy withers and authoritarianism thrives. Algorithms tuned for "engagement" amplify fear, outrage, and division—because that’s what keeps us clicking. In the end, <strong>the tools meant to connect us are weaponized to divide us</strong>.</p>
<p><em>We've witnessed the damage when tech scales without care. What could we build instead?</em></p>
<h2 id="%F0%9F%90%8C-caracol%3A-a-different-outlook">🐌 <strong>Caracol: a different outlook</strong> <a href="#%F0%9F%90%8C-caracol%3A-a-different-outlook">#</a></h2>
<p>Bonfire draws inspiration from the <em>caracol</em> (snail), a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Zapatista_Army_of_National_Liberation">Zapatista</a> symbol of slow, collective movement. The caracol is a spiral, with no top or center—only a shared heart. It stands for governance from the edges, listening before action, autonomy over hierarchy, and the conviction that <em>how</em> we build matters more than <em>what</em> we build.</p>
<p>These aren't lofty ideals—they're the backbone of Bonfire's design: a system built for flexibility, diversity, and overlapping needs. <strong>You don’t just use Bonfire—you shape it.</strong> It’s not one tool; it’s a terrain. A toolkit. Imagine digital spaces growing organically, communities determining how they connect, and tools that can be picked up, transformed, or set aside as needed. The <em>caracol</em> reminds us: meaningful progress comes from how we move, who we move with, and what kind of world we forge together.</p>
<h2 id="%E2%9C%8A-governance%3A-foundations-of-bonfire">✊ <strong>Governance: foundations of Bonfire</strong> <a href="#%E2%9C%8A-governance%3A-foundations-of-bonfire">#</a></h2>
<p>The way we build is part of what we create. Inspired by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sociocracy">sociocracy</a>—a method of collaborative governance based on circles, consent, and distributed authority, and by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Municipalism">Bookchin’s municipal confederations</a>, the Zapatistas, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Democratic_Autonomous_Administration_of_North_and_East_Syria">Rojava</a>, governance in Bonfire runs deep:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Everything is modular—down to the core:</strong> All features are provided by separate extensions, meaning the “core app” contains no code but just configuration. There also isn’t a single core; instead, there exists different “flavours” of Bonfire: sets of config and extensions adapted to various use cases or communities.</li>
<li><strong>Communities govern “flavours”:</strong> Bonfire's modularity serves a political purpose—inviting communities to discuss, configure, and collectively govern every aspect of their experience.</li>
<li><strong>Shining a light on the power of defaults:</strong> Whenever a choice about how something should work in Bonfire is unclear, we make it configurable. Code establishes an initial default, but flavours can override it, communities can set instance-wide settings, and individuals make final decisions in their own account or profiles.</li>
<li><strong>Custom roles:</strong> Moving beyond binary admin/user hierarchies, communities and individuals define and assign roles with precisely calibrated permissions—distributing power and responsibility to match their unique contexts.</li>
<li><strong>Circles and boundaries:</strong> Creating flexible "circles" (like "colleagues" or "book club") and "boundaries" (granular permission sets) to control exactly who can see, interact with, or collaborate on anything—putting people in charge of their online relationships.</li>
<li><strong>Tools that prioritise real people and relationships</strong> over speed and simplicity. We make no assumptions about the “average” user, social needs are complex and overlapping, there are no no one-size-fits-all solutions. We center needs often marginalized or overlooked—making them foundational so everyone benefits from greater flexibility and control.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="%F0%9F%9B%A1%EF%B8%8F-guarding-the-commons">🛡️ <strong>Guarding the commons</strong> <a href="#%F0%9F%9B%A1%EF%B8%8F-guarding-the-commons">#</a></h3>
<p>Values alone aren’t enough—many well-intentioned projects eventually drift, burn out, or sell out. Bonfire is federated at every level—protocol, code, and governance—so its purpose and values can’t be quietly eroded or easily overturned. This technical and political design aims to resist capture, prevent <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enshittification">enshittification</a>, and safeguard community autonomy for the long term.</p>
<p>Here's how Bonfire can <strong>resist capture:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>AGPL licensing:</strong> All code is AGPL, ensuring all modifications remain open and accessible, preventing capture by Big Tech or cloud services.</li>
<li><strong>Multi-layered modularity and forkability:</strong> Everything is an extension—identity, moderation, groups. People can fork just an extension or a flavour–which encourages forking by lowering the maintainance effort.</li>
<li><strong>Community-governed flavours:</strong> Communities decide what's included and how it evolves.</li>
<li><strong>Zero VC funding or ads:</strong> Bonfire will remain free of venture capital and advertisement. No dark patterns. No pivoting away from responsibility or ethics.</li>
</ul>
<p>We're also experimenting with:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Sociocratic circles:</strong> Self-organizing groups stewarding specific extensions or flavours, making decisions by consent. We're expanding this approach, creating pathways for communities to shape and protect their own digital spaces.</li>
<li>New models for <strong>participatory funding</strong> and resource allocation.</li>
</ul>
<p>The commons survive only when they can <strong>regrow anywhere</strong>. We design for resilience, adaptability, and collective stewardship.</p>
<h2 id="%F0%9F%8C%90-federation%3A-autonomy-through-connection">🌐 <strong>Federation: autonomy through connection</strong> <a href="#%F0%9F%8C%90-federation%3A-autonomy-through-connection">#</a></h2>
<p>Bonfire federates (i.e., interconnects with other independent platforms) with Mastodon and the wider <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fediverse">fediverse</a>, but federation is more than a technical protocol — it embodies our commitment to autonomy <em>and</em> collaboration:</p>
<ul>
<li>Each community governs itself while connecting with others, maintaining distinct cultures, rules, and practices.</li>
<li>Federation isn't for scaling one model, but for interconnecting many. No central power dictates decisions—only connected, independent nodes working in concert.</li>
<li>Offboarding and freedom to migrate: Users should never be locked into platforms by their data or social connections.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>We're building many interconnected worlds, not one massive platform.</strong></p>

<p>Bonfire is a <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Commons">commons</a></em>–a place to gather, co-create, and build networks that last–beyond products to be sold or services that use, abuse, or extract from you.</p>
<p>Bonfire’s values, goals, and processes are shaped by the people and communities who choose to participate. As a starting point, we uphold principles rooted in care, consent, and collective stewardship.</p>
<p>Whether you're a community organiser, activist, builder or simply curious, join us:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Join the conversation:</strong> Take part in our public discussion spaces. Share your experiences, needs, and questions.</li>
<li><strong>Help shape governance:</strong> Participate in forming circles to govern specific extensions or Bonfire flavours, and share responsibility, decide by consent, and ensure Bonfire evolves with real community needs.</li>
<li><strong>Propose features or co-design new extensions:</strong> Bring your ideas for how Bonfire can serve new purposes, or create new "flavours" and tools.</li>
<li><strong>Contribute feedback:</strong> Help us spot issues, propose adaptations, or challenge assumptions so Bonfire can serve more people, more justly.</li>
<li><strong>Help shape the culture:</strong> Share learnings from your own communities, organize workshops, or experiment with governance models.</li>
</ul>
<p>Built for the long haul. <em>By people, for people</em>.</p>
<h3 id="%F0%9F%8F%95%EF%B8%8F-campground%3A-a-living-laboratory">🏕️ <strong>Campground: a living laboratory</strong> <a href="#%F0%9F%8F%95%EF%B8%8F-campground%3A-a-living-laboratory">#</a></h3>
<p>Our test instance, <a href="https://campground.bonfire.cafe/">the campground</a>, is open as a local-only space for co-design and experimentation. Here, you can:</p>
<ul>
<li>Experience what digital spaces built on consent, care, and mutual aid feel like.</li>
<li>Collaborate to co-design and test features — making Bonfire safer, more resilient, accessible, and truly centered on people and communities.</li>
</ul>
<p>This isn’t a product launch—we’re not looking for <em>users</em> but for <em>active participants</em>: people and groups who want to shape, critique, and experiment together — whether that’s on the campground, through their own Bonfire instances, or by joining others to co-create new digital spaces.</p>
<h2 id="%E2%9C%A8-let%E2%80%99s-build-what-lasts%2C-together">✨ <strong>Let’s build what lasts, together</strong> <a href="#%E2%9C%A8-let%E2%80%99s-build-what-lasts%2C-together">#</a></h2>
<p>If these ideas resonate, we invite you to reflect, dialogue, reach out, and co-create. Bonfire lives as a conversation in motion, beyond its code. The world needs many interconnected spaces built on care, autonomy, and collective power — not yet another app chasing scale.</p>
<p>We hope these principles can ignite new approaches to digital community-building. The future is ours to build — intentionally, collectively, and with care. Join us in shaping what comes next.</p>
<hr>
<p><em>This post was written by the Bonfire maintainers' circle and shaped by feedback from the advisory circle. Join the conversation on <a href="https://matrix.to/#/#bonfire:matrix.org">Matrix</a>, comment on <a href="https://indieweb.social/@bonfire/114477426502965851">this post on the fediverse</a> or on <a href="https://campground.bonfire.cafe/">the campground</a>, or email us at <a href="mailto:team@bonfire.cafe">team@bonfire.cafe</a>.</em></p>
<p><em>Credit for the art goes to Tomás, a Zapatista artist in a community near San Cristobal.</em></p>

  </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Europe launches program to lure scientists away from the US (109 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://es.wired.com/articulos/europa-lanza-iniciativa-para-atraer-talento-cientifico-tras-recortes-en-ee-uu</link>
            <guid>43943583</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 06:20:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://es.wired.com/articulos/europa-lanza-iniciativa-para-atraer-talento-cientifico-tras-recortes-en-ee-uu">https://es.wired.com/articulos/europa-lanza-iniciativa-para-atraer-talento-cientifico-tras-recortes-en-ee-uu</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43943583">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>La Comisión Europea presentó el programa <em>Choose Europe for Science</em> (<em>Elige Europa para la ciencia</em>), una iniciativa destinada a atraer a investigadores y científicos a la Unión Europea, especialmente a aquellos provenientes de Estados Unidos. La iniciativa se presenta como una alternativa para quienes han comenzado a buscar nuevas oportunidades de desarrollo profesional tras los recortes en el financiamiento científico impulsados por la administración de Donald Trump.</p><p>Ursula von der Leyen, presidenta de la Comisión Europea, advirtió que “lamentablemente, el papel de la ciencia en el mundo actual está siendo cuestionado. Se pone <a href="https://es.wired.com/articulos/trump-recorta-fuertemente-la-investigacion-en-harvard">en duda la inversión en investigación</a> fundamental, libre y abierta. ¡Qué grave error de cálculo! La ciencia es clave para nuestro futuro. Sin ella, no podemos enfrentar los desafíos globales. Por eso, más que nunca, debemos defender una ciencia universal, compartida y unificadora”.</p><hr><div data-testid="ContentCardEmbedWrapper"><p><span><picture><img alt="Planta Nuclear" src="https://media.es.wired.com/photos/67e41013afedf7c98f6d5b04/master/w_775%2Cc_limit/GettyImages-1540176964%2520(1).jpg" srcset="https://media.es.wired.com/photos/67e41013afedf7c98f6d5b04/master/w_120,c_limit/GettyImages-1540176964%20(1).jpg 120w, https://media.es.wired.com/photos/67e41013afedf7c98f6d5b04/master/w_240,c_limit/GettyImages-1540176964%20(1).jpg 240w, https://media.es.wired.com/photos/67e41013afedf7c98f6d5b04/master/w_320,c_limit/GettyImages-1540176964%20(1).jpg 320w, https://media.es.wired.com/photos/67e41013afedf7c98f6d5b04/master/w_640,c_limit/GettyImages-1540176964%20(1).jpg 640w" sizes="100vw"></picture></span></p><div><p>Un equipo del Instituto Nacional de Normas y Tecnología que publica datos de medición cruciales para la investigación avanzada en áreas como la astrofísica, la fusión nuclear y los semiconductores, podría desaparecer en las próximas semanas.</p></div></div><hr><p>La dirigente del Ejecutivo comunitario explicó que el programa <em>Choose Europe for Science</em> contempla <strong>una inversión de 500 millones de euros entre 2025 y 2027</strong> para captar especialistas en distintas ramas del conocimiento. Asimismo, incluye el compromiso de incrementar el presupuesto destinado a proyectos de Investigación y Desarrollo (I+D) hasta alcanzar el 3% del producto interior bruto (PIB) en 2030.</p><p>El plan, originalmente propuesto por el Gobierno francés, plantea la creación de una “súper subvención” con una duración de siete años para brindar estabilidad a los investigadores más destacados. Además, prevé duplicar este mismo año el monto de los apoyos económicos disponibles para quienes decidan trasladarse al bloque europeo.</p><p>Von der Leyen recalcó que “Europa siempre optará por la ciencia. Nuestra región dispone de todo lo necesario para que florezca: inversión sostenida, infraestructura de calidad, compromiso con una ciencia abierta y colaborativa, y una economía social de mercado que asegura acceso a la educación, la salud y otros servicios esenciales”. No obstante, reconoció que los científicos en la Unión aún enfrentan una burocracia más compleja en comparación con otras regiones del mundo.</p><p>“Sabemos que el camino que va de la investigación básica al mercado no es lo suficientemente ágil ni directo en Europa. Debemos ofrecer condiciones óptimas y estables a largo plazo”, admitió. En este sentido, anunció que <strong>el bloque impulsará una nueva Ley del Espacio Europeo de Investigación para garantizar la libertad científica.</strong></p><p>Según cifras de la Comisión Europea, en el continente trabajan actualmente 2 millones de investigadores, lo que representa una cuarta parte del total mundial. Von der Leyen destacó además que la Unión gestiona el mayor programa internacional de investigación: Horizonte Europa, con una dotación superior a los 93,000 millones de euros. Este financiamiento ha permitido apoyar a 33 <a href="https://es.wired.com/articulos/quienes-ganaran-premios-nobel-2024-citas-que-obtuvo-cada-publicacion-pueden-darnos-idea">ganadores del Premio Nobel</a> en las últimas cuatro décadas.</p><p>“Queremos que Europa siga siendo referente en investigación básica, que lidere el desarrollo de tecnologías estratégicas y que científicos, académicos y trabajadores altamente cualificados elijan nuestra región para desarrollarse plenamente”, concluyó la presidenta de la Comisión.</p><h2>Europa quiere conquistar a los investigadores que EE UU desprecia</h2><p>En marzo, el gobierno estadounidense canceló más de 200 subvenciones federales destinadas a investigaciones sobre el <a href="https://es.wired.com/articulos/este-nuevo-farmaco-podria-ser-la-solucion-al-vih-pero-los-recortes-en-ee-uu-frenan-su-lanzamiento">virus de inmunodeficiencia humana (VIH)</a>. También redujo los recursos asignados a los Institutos Nacionales de Salud para estudios relacionados con el covid-19 e impuso un recorte de 400 millones de dólares al financiamiento de la Universidad de Columbia, en represalia por las protestas pro-palestinas realizadas en su plantel en el contexto del conflicto con Israel.</p><p>Estas decisiones han generado un <a href="https://es.wired.com/articulos/los-recortes-de-trump-a-la-ciencia-estan-causando-una-fuga-de-cerebros">éxodo de investigadores</a> que buscan continuar sus carreras fuera de Estados Unidos. Un análisis <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-01216-7">publicado en <em>Nature</em></a> señala que e<strong>l 75% de los científicos estadounidenses se plantea dejar el país.</strong> Por su parte, datos de Nature Careers, una plataforma global de empleos científicos, revelan que entre enero y marzo de este año, los profesionales de ese país enviaron un 32% más de solicitudes a instituciones extranjeras en comparación con el mismo período de 2024. Asimismo, el número de usuarios estadounidenses que exploran oportunidades fuera del territorio nacional aumentó un 35%.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Paralelamente, el interés internacional por trabajar en Estados Unidos ha disminuido notablemente. Durante el primer trimestre del año, las postulaciones de científicos provenientes de Canadá, China y Europa a centros de investigación estadounidenses cayeron en un 13, 39 y 41%, respectivamente.</p><p>Frente a este contexto, diversas instituciones extranjeras han intensificado sus esfuerzos para atraer talento estadounidense, siendo Europa una de las regiones más activas. La Universidad de Aix-Marsella, en Francia, presentó recientemente el programa <em>Un lugar seguro para la ciencia</em>, orientado a acoger a investigadores estadounidenses despedidos, censurados o limitados por las políticas gubernamentales de Trump. <strong>Este proyecto contempla una inversión aproximada de 15 millones de euros.</strong></p><p>En la misma línea, la Sociedad Max Planck, en Alemania, anunció la creación del <em>Programa Transatlántico Max Planck</em>, cuyo propósito es establecer centros de investigación conjuntos con instituciones de Estados Unidos.</p><div data-testid="external-link-embed--inline"><a aria-label="Las noticias que marcan el presente y moldean el futuro, ¡ahora en WhatsApp! Sigue ya el canal de WIRED en español." data-event-click="{&quot;element&quot;:&quot;ExternalLink&quot;,&quot;outgoingURL&quot;:&quot;https://whatsapp.com/channel/0029VaLxCjyBA1eypmtSHm2o&quot;}" href="https://whatsapp.com/channel/0029VaLxCjyBA1eypmtSHm2o" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"><picture><img alt="" src="https://media.es.wired.com/photos/65f9c8af1e4602cf42f4e967/1:1/w_200%2Cc_limit/canal_whatsapp_wired_espanol.png" srcset="https://media.es.wired.com/photos/65f9c8af1e4602cf42f4e967/1:1/w_120,c_limit/canal_whatsapp_wired_espanol.png 120w" sizes="100vw"></picture></a></div><h2>España busca rol protagónico</h2><p>Juan Cruz Cigudosa, secretario de Estado de Ciencia, Innovación y Universidades de España, subrayó que este país se encuentra activamente inmerso en la captación de talento científico global, con prioridad en áreas como biotecnología cuántica, inteligencia artificial, materiales avanzados y semiconductores, así como en todo aquello que refuerce la soberanía tecnológica.</p><p>Para lograrlo, el gobierno de Pedro Sánchez ha fortalecido programas ya existentes, como el Plan Nacional de Atracción de Talento, que en su más reciente convocatoria aumentó en un 50% la financiación estatal, ofreciendo un millón de euros por investigador que se establezca en el país. <strong>La mitad de los beneficiarios actuales provienen de Estados Unidos y Reino Unido.</strong></p><p>Del mismo modo, el programa Ramón y Cajal —creado hace 25 años para incorporar a jóvenes científicos— ha incrementado su financiación en un 150% desde 2018, permitiendo la incorporación de 500 investigadores al año, de los cuales, un 30% son extranjeros.</p><p>Finalmente, el programa <em>ATRAE</em> fue reforzado con una inversión de 45 millones de euros para captar científicos con trayectorias consolidadas y líderes en campos estratégicos, con especial atención a expertos estadounidenses que se sientan “despreciados”. Este programa ofrece una financiación adicional de 200,000 euros por proyecto a los seleccionados provenientes de Estados Unidos.</p><p>“Vamos a intensificar los <a href="https://es.wired.com/articulos/por-que-muchas-cientificas-siguen-sin-salir-en-los-medios">esfuerzos para atraer talento</a> desde Estados Unidos. Queremos que vengan a hacer la mejor ciencia posible, libre de restricciones ideológicas. El conocimiento científico y tecnológico nos convierte en un país mejor, porque genera prosperidad compartida y visión de futuro”, concluyó Cigudosa durante la presentación del programa <em>Choose Europe for Science</em>, en declaraciones retomadas por la agencia <em>EFE</em>.</p><figure data-testid="IframeEmbed"><div data-testid="IframeEmbedContainer"><p><iframe height="113" width="200" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-popups allow-same-origin allow-presentation allow-popups-to-escape-sandbox" title="Embedded Frame" data-src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/zimXNLPU0r4" allow="autoplay *; encrypted-media *; clipboard-write; autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture"></iframe></p></div></figure></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gmail to SQLite (255 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/marcboeker/gmail-to-sqlite</link>
            <guid>43943236</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 04:25:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/marcboeker/gmail-to-sqlite">https://github.com/marcboeker/gmail-to-sqlite</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43943236">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Gmail to SQLite</h2><a id="user-content-gmail-to-sqlite" aria-label="Permalink: Gmail to SQLite" href="#gmail-to-sqlite"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is a script to download emails from Gmail and store them in a SQLite database for further analysis. I find it extremely useful to have all my emails in a database to run queries on them. For example, I can find out how many emails I received per sender, which emails take the most space, and which emails from which sender I never read.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Clone this repository: <code>git clone https://github.com/marcboeker/gmail-to-sqlite.git</code>.</li>
<li>Install the requirements: <code>pip install -r requirements.txt</code></li>
<li>Create a Google Cloud project <a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/projectcreate" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</li>
<li>Open <a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/apis/library/gmail.googleapis.com" rel="nofollow">Gmail in API &amp; Services</a> and activate the Gmail API.</li>
<li>Open the <a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/apis/credentials/consent" rel="nofollow">OAuth consent screen</a> and create a new consent screen. You only need to provide a name and contact data.</li>
<li>Next open <a href="https://console.cloud.google.com/apis/credentials/oauthclient" rel="nofollow">Create OAuth client ID</a> and create credentials for a <code>Desktop app</code>. Download the credentials file and save it under <code>credentials.json</code> in the root of this repository.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">Here is a detailed guide on how to create the credentials: <a href="https://developers.google.com/gmail/api/quickstart/python#set_up_your_environment" rel="nofollow">https://developers.google.com/gmail/api/quickstart/python#set_up_your_environment</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sync all emails</h3><a id="user-content-sync-all-emails" aria-label="Permalink: Sync all emails" href="#sync-all-emails"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Run the script: <code>python main.py sync --data-dir path/to/your/data</code> where <code>--&lt;data-dir&gt;</code> is the path where all data is stored. This creates a SQLite database in <code>&lt;data-dir&gt;/messages.db</code> and stores the user credentials under <code>&lt;data-dir&gt;/credentials.json</code>.</li>
<li>After the script has finished, you can query the database using, for example, the <code>sqlite3</code> command line tool: <code>sqlite3 &lt;data-dir&gt;/messages.db</code>.</li>
<li>You can run the script again to sync all new messages. Provide <code>--full-sync</code> to force a full sync. However, this will only update the read status, the labels, and the last indexed timestamp for existing messages.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Sync a single message</h3><a id="user-content-sync-a-single-message" aria-label="Permalink: Sync a single message" href="#sync-a-single-message"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>python main.py sync-message --data-dir path/to/your/data --message-id &lt;message-id&gt;</code></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Commandline parameters</h2><a id="user-content-commandline-parameters" aria-label="Permalink: Commandline parameters" href="#commandline-parameters"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="usage: main.py [-h] [--data-dir DATA_DIR] [--update] {sync, sync-message}

Main commands:
sync                    Sync emails from Gmail to the database.
sync-message            Sync a single message from Gmail to the database.

--data-dir DATA_DIR     Path to the directory where all data is stored.
--full-sync             Force a full sync.
--message-id MESSAGE_ID Sync only the message with the given message id."><pre><code>usage: main.py [-h] [--data-dir DATA_DIR] [--update] {sync, sync-message}

Main commands:
sync                    Sync emails from Gmail to the database.
sync-message            Sync a single message from Gmail to the database.

--data-dir DATA_DIR     Path to the directory where all data is stored.
--full-sync             Force a full sync.
--message-id MESSAGE_ID Sync only the message with the given message id.
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Schema</h2><a id="user-content-schema" aria-label="Permalink: Schema" href="#schema"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="CREATE TABLE IF NOT EXISTS &quot;messages&quot; (
    &quot;id&quot; INTEGER NOT NULL PRIMARY KEY, -- internal id
    &quot;message_id&quot; TEXT NOT NULL, -- Gmail message id
    &quot;thread_id&quot; TEXT NOT NULL, -- Gmail thread id
    &quot;sender&quot; JSON NOT NULL, -- Sender as JSON in the form {&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Foo Bar&quot;, &quot;email&quot;: &quot;foo@example.com&quot;}
    &quot;recipients&quot; JSON NOT NULL, -- JSON object: {
      -- &quot;to&quot;: [{&quot;email&quot;: &quot;foo@example.com&quot;, &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Foo Bar&quot;}, ...],
      -- &quot;cc&quot;: [{&quot;email&quot;: &quot;foo@example.com&quot;, &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Foo Bar&quot;}, ...],
      -- &quot;bcc&quot;: [{&quot;email&quot;: &quot;foo@example.com&quot;, &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Foo Bar&quot;}, ...]
    --}
    &quot;labels&quot; JSON NOT NULL, -- JSON array: [&quot;INBOX&quot;, &quot;UNREAD&quot;, ...]
    &quot;subject&quot; TEXT NOT NULL, -- Subject of the email
    &quot;body&quot; TEXT NOT NULL, -- Extracted body either als HTML or plain text
    &quot;size&quot; INTEGER NOT NULL, -- Size reported by Gmail
    &quot;timestamp&quot; DATETIME NOT NULL, -- When the email was sent/received
    &quot;is_read&quot; INTEGER NOT NULL, -- 0=Unread, 1=Read
    &quot;is_outgoing&quot; INTEGER NOT NULL, -- 0=Incoming, 1=Outgoing
    &quot;last_indexed&quot; DATETIME NOT NULL -- Timestamp when the email was last seen on the server
);"><pre><span>CREATE</span> <span>TABLE</span> <span>IF</span> NOT EXISTS <span><span>"</span>messages<span>"</span></span> (
    <span><span>"</span>id<span>"</span></span> <span>INTEGER</span> <span>NOT NULL</span> <span>PRIMARY KEY</span>, <span><span>--</span> internal id</span>
    <span><span>"</span>message_id<span>"</span></span> <span>TEXT</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> Gmail message id</span>
    <span><span>"</span>thread_id<span>"</span></span> <span>TEXT</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> Gmail thread id</span>
    <span><span>"</span>sender<span>"</span></span> JSON <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> Sender as JSON in the form {"name": "Foo Bar", "email": "foo@example.com"}</span>
    <span><span>"</span>recipients<span>"</span></span> JSON <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> JSON object: {</span>
      <span><span>--</span> "to": [{"email": "foo@example.com", "name": "Foo Bar"}, ...],</span>
      <span><span>--</span> "cc": [{"email": "foo@example.com", "name": "Foo Bar"}, ...],</span>
      <span><span>--</span> "bcc": [{"email": "foo@example.com", "name": "Foo Bar"}, ...]</span>
    <span><span>--</span>}</span>
    <span><span>"</span>labels<span>"</span></span> JSON <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> JSON array: ["INBOX", "UNREAD", ...]</span>
    <span><span>"</span>subject<span>"</span></span> <span>TEXT</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> Subject of the email</span>
    <span><span>"</span>body<span>"</span></span> <span>TEXT</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> Extracted body either als HTML or plain text</span>
    <span><span>"</span>size<span>"</span></span> <span>INTEGER</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> Size reported by Gmail</span>
    <span><span>"</span>timestamp<span>"</span></span> DATETIME <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> When the email was sent/received</span>
    <span><span>"</span>is_read<span>"</span></span> <span>INTEGER</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> 0=Unread, 1=Read</span>
    <span><span>"</span>is_outgoing<span>"</span></span> <span>INTEGER</span> <span>NOT NULL</span>, <span><span>--</span> 0=Incoming, 1=Outgoing</span>
    <span><span>"</span>last_indexed<span>"</span></span> DATETIME <span>NOT NULL</span> <span><span>--</span> Timestamp when the email was last seen on the server</span>
);</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Example queries</h2><a id="user-content-example-queries" aria-label="Permalink: Example queries" href="#example-queries"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Get the number of emails per sender</h3><a id="user-content-get-the-number-of-emails-per-sender" aria-label="Permalink: Get the number of emails per sender" href="#get-the-number-of-emails-per-sender"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT sender->>'$.email', COUNT(*) AS count
FROM messages
GROUP BY sender->>'$.email'
ORDER BY count DESC"><pre><span>SELECT</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>, <span>COUNT</span>(<span>*</span>) <span>AS</span> count
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>GROUP BY</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>
<span>ORDER BY</span> count <span>DESC</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Show the number of unread emails by sender</h3><a id="user-content-show-the-number-of-unread-emails-by-sender" aria-label="Permalink: Show the number of unread emails by sender" href="#show-the-number-of-unread-emails-by-sender"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is great to determine who is spamming you the most with uninteresting emails.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT sender->>'$.email', COUNT(*) AS count
FROM messages
WHERE is_read = 0
GROUP BY sender->>'$.email'
ORDER BY count DESC"><pre><span>SELECT</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>, <span>COUNT</span>(<span>*</span>) <span>AS</span> count
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>WHERE</span> is_read <span>=</span> <span>0</span>
<span>GROUP BY</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>
<span>ORDER BY</span> count <span>DESC</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Get the number of emails for a specific period</h3><a id="user-content-get-the-number-of-emails-for-a-specific-period" aria-label="Permalink: Get the number of emails for a specific period" href="#get-the-number-of-emails-for-a-specific-period"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>For years: <code>strftime('%Y', timestamp)</code></li>
<li>For months in a year: <code>strftime('%m', timestamp)</code></li>
<li>For days in a month: <code>strftime('%d', timestamp)</code></li>
<li>For weekdays: <code>strftime('%w', timestamp)</code></li>
<li>For hours in a day: <code>strftime('%H', timestamp)</code></li>
</ul>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT strftime('%Y', timestamp) AS period, COUNT(*) AS count
FROM messages
GROUP BY period
ORDER BY count DESC"><pre><span>SELECT</span> strftime(<span><span>'</span>%Y<span>'</span></span>, <span>timestamp</span>) <span>AS</span> period, <span>COUNT</span>(<span>*</span>) <span>AS</span> count
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>GROUP BY</span> period
<span>ORDER BY</span> count <span>DESC</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Find all newsletters and group them by sender</h3><a id="user-content-find-all-newsletters-and-group-them-by-sender" aria-label="Permalink: Find all newsletters and group them by sender" href="#find-all-newsletters-and-group-them-by-sender"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This is an amateurish way to find all newsletters and group them by sender. It's not perfect, but it's a start. You could also use</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT sender->>'$.email', COUNT(*) AS count
FROM messages
WHERE body LIKE '%newsletter%' OR body LIKE '%unsubscribe%'
GROUP BY sender->>'$.email'
ORDER BY count DESC"><pre><span>SELECT</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>, <span>COUNT</span>(<span>*</span>) <span>AS</span> count
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>WHERE</span> body <span>LIKE</span> <span><span>'</span>%newsletter%<span>'</span></span> <span>OR</span> body <span>LIKE</span> <span><span>'</span>%unsubscribe%<span>'</span></span>
<span>GROUP BY</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>
<span>ORDER BY</span> count <span>DESC</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Show who has sent the largest emails in MB</h3><a id="user-content-show-who-has-sent-the-largest-emails-in-mb" aria-label="Permalink: Show who has sent the largest emails in MB" href="#show-who-has-sent-the-largest-emails-in-mb"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT sender->>'$.email', sum(size)/1024/1024 AS size
FROM messages
GROUP BY sender->>'$.email'
ORDER BY size DESC"><pre><span>SELECT</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>, <span>sum</span>(size)<span>/</span><span>1024</span><span>/</span><span>1024</span> <span>AS</span> size
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>GROUP BY</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>
<span>ORDER BY</span> size <span>DESC</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Count the number of emails that I have sent to myself</h3><a id="user-content-count-the-number-of-emails-that-i-have-sent-to-myself" aria-label="Permalink: Count the number of emails that I have sent to myself" href="#count-the-number-of-emails-that-i-have-sent-to-myself"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT count(*)
FROM messages
WHERE EXISTS (
  SELECT 1
  FROM json_each(messages.recipients->'$.to')
  WHERE json_extract(value, '$.email') = 'foo@example.com'
)
AND sender->>'$.email' = 'foo@example.com'"><pre><span>SELECT</span> <span>count</span>(<span>*</span>)
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>WHERE</span> EXISTS (
  <span>SELECT</span> <span>1</span>
  <span>FROM</span> json_each(<span>messages</span>.<span>recipients</span><span>-</span><span>&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.to<span>'</span></span>)
  <span>WHERE</span> json_extract(value, <span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>) <span>=</span> <span><span>'</span>foo@example.com<span>'</span></span>
)
<span>AND</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span> <span>=</span> <span><span>'</span>foo@example.com<span>'</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">List the senders who have sent me the largest total volume of emails in megabytes</h3><a id="user-content-list-the-senders-who-have-sent-me-the-largest-total-volume-of-emails-in-megabytes" aria-label="Permalink: List the senders who have sent me the largest total volume of emails in megabytes" href="#list-the-senders-who-have-sent-me-the-largest-total-volume-of-emails-in-megabytes"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="SELECT sender->>'$.email', sum(size)/1024/1024 as total_size
FROM messages
WHERE is_outgoing=false
GROUP BY sender->>'$.email'
ORDER BY total_size DESC"><pre><span>SELECT</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>, <span>sum</span>(size)<span>/</span><span>1024</span><span>/</span><span>1024</span> <span>as</span> total_size
<span>FROM</span> messages
<span>WHERE</span> is_outgoing<span>=</span>false
<span>GROUP BY</span> sender<span>-</span><span>&gt;&gt;</span><span><span>'</span>$.email<span>'</span></span>
<span>ORDER BY</span> total_size <span>DESC</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Roadmap</h2><a id="user-content-roadmap" aria-label="Permalink: Roadmap" href="#roadmap"></a></p>
<ul>
<li> Detect deleted emails and mark them as deleted in the database.</li>
</ul>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Vision Now Available in Llama.cpp (447 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/ggml-org/llama.cpp/blob/master/docs/multimodal.md</link>
            <guid>43943047</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 03:39:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/ggml-org/llama.cpp/blob/master/docs/multimodal.md">https://github.com/ggml-org/llama.cpp/blob/master/docs/multimodal.md</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43943047">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_copilot&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_copilot_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Advanced Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;actions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;actions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;codespaces&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;codespaces_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;issues&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;issues_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_review&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_review_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code Review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;discussions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;discussions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_search&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_search_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-search">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code Search</p><p>
        Find more, search less
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
                    <p><span id="resources-explore-heading">Explore</span></p><ul aria-labelledby="resources-explore-heading">
                    <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/learn/pathways">
      Learning Pathways

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;events_amp_webinars&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;events_amp_webinars_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/">
      Events &amp; Webinars

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;ebooks_amp_whitepapers&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ebooks_amp_whitepapers_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/resources/whitepapers">
      Ebooks &amp; Whitepapers

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_stories&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_stories_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/customer-stories">
      Customer Stories

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;partners&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;partners_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://partner.github.com/">
      Partners

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;executive_insights&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;executive_insights_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/solutions/executive-insights">
      Executive Insights

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
              <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
              <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
              
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>Enterprise platform</p><p>
        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;pricing&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;global&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;pricing_link_global_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:ggml-org/llama.cpp" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="5m7Yth-E6u6NJf8qwceUaOwKZqcHMLV79S9DhuMYllZMiKDO_7enAFtrbg-AbcbjDV0fNyf1A48GFgzXfuDFOA" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="ggml-org/llama.cpp" data-current-org="ggml-org" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-nl-search-enabled="false" data-retain-scroll-position="true">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>


            

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E%2Fblob%2Fshow&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=ggml-org%2Fllama.cpp" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/ggml-org/llama.cpp/blob/master/docs/multimodal.md&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="374eaf3e33f390d25ae7641e36852a2039f525c225923c274bdb379025e54cbc" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>/blob/show;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a></p><p>
    <react-partial-anchor>
      <tool-tip id="tooltip-2bcafefd-f289-4bc5-86ff-b6a5c2deebb2" for="icon-button-4c788c6e-717e-4ab4-bd18-a770f6afea81" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="label" data-view-component="true">Appearance settings</tool-tip>

      <template data-target="react-partial-anchor.template">
        <script crossorigin="anonymous" defer="defer" type="application/javascript" src="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/ui_packages_document-metadata_document-metadata_ts-ui_packages_promise-with-resolvers-polyfil-40d47c-d51541042e41.js"></script>
<script crossorigin="anonymous" defer="defer" type="application/javascript" src="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/appearance-settings-17c0890ddb85.js"></script>
<link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/primer-react.070a275174b943f11c11.module.css">
<link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/appearance-settings.22dfbc22ef0a2bf02523.module.css">

<react-partial partial-name="appearance-settings" data-ssr="false" data-attempted-ssr="false">
  
  <script type="application/json" data-target="react-partial.embeddedData">{"props":{}}</script>
  <div data-target="react-partial.reactRoot"></div>
</react-partial>

      </template>
    </react-partial-anchor>
  </p>

          </div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A simple 16x16 dot animation from simple math rules (262 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tixy.land</link>
            <guid>43942881</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 02:56:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tixy.land">https://tixy.land</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43942881">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="editor"> <p><label for="input">// tixy - creative code golfing</label> <label for="input">// click the dots for more info</label> <label for="input">// use 32 characters or less</label> </p> <label id="label" for="input">(t,i,x,y) =&gt;</label>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Brandon's Semiconductor Simulator (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://brandonli.net/semisim/</link>
            <guid>43942279</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:37:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://brandonli.net/semisim/">https://brandonli.net/semisim/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43942279">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <h2>Brandon's Semiconductor Simulator</h2>
    <p>Draw your own circuits. Turn on voltage and see what happens. Some features of my program include:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Interactive circuit drawing</li>
      <li>Visualization of electromagnetic fields</li>
      <li>Many materials (metals, semiconductors, dielectrics, and more)</li>
    </ul>

    

    <p>You need a good computer to run this simulation on your browser. There is also a <a href="https://github.com/StunningLlama/Physics/releases/tag/v1.2">downloadable version</a> that's much faster
      (but requires Java).</p>
    <p>Want to know more? You can read about it <a href="https://brandonli.net/semisim/info">here.</a></p>
    <p>(c) Brandon Li, 2025. Ported to Javascript with the help of Paul Falstad.</p>

    <h2>Simulation Examples</h2>

    <div>
      <h2>Simple Circuits</h2>
      
    </div>

    <div>
      <h2>Semiconductor Devices</h2>
      
    </div>

    <div>
      <h2>Digital Logic</h2>
      
    </div>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WebGL Water (2010) (201 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://madebyevan.com/webgl-water/</link>
            <guid>43942149</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 10 May 2025 00:13:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://madebyevan.com/webgl-water/">https://madebyevan.com/webgl-water/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43942149">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Loading...</p><div id="help">
    
    <p>Made by <a href="https://madebyevan.com/">Evan Wallace</a></p>
    <p>This demo requires a decent graphics card and up-to-date drivers. If you can't run the demo, you can still <a href="https://youtube.com/watch?v=R0O_9bp3EKQ">see it on YouTube</a>.</p>
    <h2>Interactions:</h2>
    <ul>
      <li>Draw on the water to make ripples</li>
      <li>Drag the background to rotate the camera</li>
      <li>Press SPACEBAR to pause and unpause</li>
      <li>Drag the sphere to move it around</li>
      <li>Press the L key to set the light direction</li>
      <li>Press the G key to toggle gravity</li>
    </ul>
    <h2>Features:</h2>
    <ul>
      <li>Raytraced reflections and refractions</li>
      <li>Analytic ambient occlusion</li>
      <li>Heightfield water simulation *</li>
      <li>Soft shadows</li>
      <li>Caustics (see <a href="https://medium.com/@evanwallace/rendering-realtime-caustics-in-webgl-2a99a29a0b2c">this</a> for details) **</li>
    </ul>
    <p><small>* requires the OES_texture_float extension<br>** requires the OES_standard_derivatives extension</small></p>
    <p><small>Tile texture from <a href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/zooboing/3682834083/">zooboing</a> on Flickr</small></p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fleurs du Mal (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fleursdumal.org</link>
            <guid>43941598</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 22:42:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fleursdumal.org">https://fleursdumal.org</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43941598">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="pagewidth">

<!-- Top -->



<br clear="all">

<!-- Content -->

<h2>FleursDuMal.org</h2>

<p>
<i>"I once read a lot of Baudelaire + my Angel kid has read every translation — apparently, if you don't know french (I do) you have to read all the translations to get a good idea."</i> — Allen Ginsberg, Letter to David Cope, 25 Jan 1977.
</p>
  
<p>
Fleursdumal.org is dedicated to the French poet Charles Baudelaire (1821 - 1867) and his poems <i>Les Fleurs du mal</i> (Flowers of Evil). The definitive online edition of this masterpiece of French literature, Fleursdumal.org contains every poem of each edition of <i>Les Fleurs du mal,</i> together with multiple English translations. 
</p>

<p>
<a href="https://supervert.com/necrophilia_variations/" target="_blank"><img src="https://fleursdumal.org/images/supervert.nv.button.gif" width="120" height="90" alt="Visit supervert.com to learn more about Necrophilia Variations" title="Visit supervert.com to learn more about Necrophilia Variations"></a><b>About.</b> Fleursdumal.org launched on 1 Feb 2004. The site is a labor of love created and maintained by <a href="https://supervert.com/" target="_blank" name="Supervert"><b>Supervert</b></a>. At supervert.com you can find information about Supervert's books, which include <a href="https://supervert.com/extraterrestrial_sex_fetish/" target="_blank" name="Supervert"><u>Extraterrestrial Sex Fetish</u></a>, <a href="https://supervert.com/necrophilia_variations/" target="_blank" name="Supervert"><u>Necrophilia Variations</u></a>, <a href="https://supervert.com/perversity_think_tank/" target="_blank"><u>Perversity Think Tank</u></a>, <a href="https://supervert.com/post_depravity/" target="_blank"><u>Post-Depravity</u></a>, <a href="https://supervert.com/apocalypse-burlesque/" target="_blank"><u>Apocalypse Burlesque</u></a>, and <a href="https://supervert.com/music-for-erotomaniacs/" target="_blank"><u>Music for Erotomaniacs</u></a>. 
</p>

<p>
<b>Note on translations.</b> Most of the translations that appear on fleursdumal.org have appeared previously in book form. These are not necessarily the best or the worst translations — though fleursdumal.org is partial to Edna St. Vincent Millay's renderings — but they are ones that the site felt comfortable reproducing in terms of rights. If you are a rights holder and object to your translations being included here, please contact fleursdumal.org to discuss the issue. 
</p>

<p>
<b>Translators.</b> Contact fleursdumal.org if you would like to submit a translation. Please note, however, that the site reserves the unconditional right to reject any submission without explanation. 
</p>

<p>
If you're new to Baudelaire or uninterested in the various editions of the <i>Flowers of Evil,</i> you should browse poems using the <a href="https://fleursdumal.org/1861-table-of-contents" name="1861 Table of Contents"><u>1861 Table of Contents</u></a>. This is the definitive edition of <i>Les Fleurs du mal</i> and contains most everything except the "condemned" poems which you can find in <a href="https://fleursdumal.org/1866-les-epaves-table-of-contents" name="Les Épaves"><u>Les Épaves</u></a> (scraps).  
</p>


<!-- Navigation -->

<div id="bottom">

<h3>Navigation</h3>



<ul>
	<li><a href="https://fleursdumal.org/1857-table-of-contents">1857 Fleurs du mal</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://fleursdumal.org/1861-table-of-contents">1861 Fleurs du mal</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://fleursdumal.org/1866-les-epaves-table-of-contents">1866 Les Épaves</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://fleursdumal.org/1868-table-of-contents">1868 Fleurs du mal</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://fleursdumal.org/alphabetical-listing">All Poems (Alphabetical)</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://fleursdumal.org/audio/">Audio</a></li>
	<li><a href="https://supervert.com/contact/" target="_blank">Contact</a></li>
</ul> 

</div>

<!-- Footer -->



</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Era of U.S. dollar may be winding down (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2025/05/era-of-u-s-dollar-may-be-winding-down/</link>
            <guid>43940865</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 21:05:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2025/05/era-of-u-s-dollar-may-be-winding-down/">https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2025/05/era-of-u-s-dollar-may-be-winding-down/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43940865">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>It looks like the end of an era for the U.S. dollar.</p>



<p>In his new book “Our Dollar, Your Problem: An Insider’s View of Seven Turbulent Decades of Global Finance, and the Road Ahead,” <a href="https://rogoff.scholars.harvard.edu/">Kenneth Rogoff</a> looks back on the currency’s dominant run in global trade and central bank reserves for a host of other countries. Today, he argues, that lofty status is on the wane.</p>



<p>“My thesis is that the U.S. dollar is about to get knocked down a couple pegs,” said Rogoff, a professor of economics and the Maurits C. Boas Chair of International Economics. “It will still be first in global finance, because nothing is poised to fully replace it. The dollar just won’t be as unique as it once was.”</p>



<p>Written entirely before the 2024 election, the book weaves first-person reflections with a history of the U.S. economy and its currency topping a succession of challengers. As a teen chess pro in the late 1960s and early ’70s, Rogoff traveled to tournaments in the Eastern Bloc provided him with rare insight on America’s Communist rivals. As a visiting scholar at the Bank of Japan in 1991, he glimpsed a booming economy on the precipice of disaster. He went on to serve as chief economist at the International Monetary Fund in the early ’00s, the nascent days of Europe’s common currency.</p>



<p>“The book is not a memoir,” Rogoff said. “But I do link in anecdotes from my experiences with world leaders, policymakers, former students, and chess players.”</p>



<p>The Gazette met up with Rogoff in his office for a preview of the book’s personal tales and macroeconomic prophesy. The interview was edited for length and clarity.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1280" src="https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg" alt="Kenneth Rogoff." srcset="https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg 1920w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=150,100 150w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=300,200 300w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=768,512 768w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=1024,683 1024w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=1536,1024 1536w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=48,32 48w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=96,64 96w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=1488,992 1488w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Rogoff-Author-Photo.-Credit-Martha-Stewart.jpg?resize=1680,1120 1680w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px"><figcaption><p>Professor of Economics Kenneth Rogoff.</p><p>Photo by Martha Stewart</p></figcaption></figure>



<hr>



<p><strong>This release feels extraordinarily well-timed, given the recent sell-off of U.S. Treasuries and the dollar’s decline following President Trump’s April 2 tariff announcement. What events compelled you to revisit the dollar’s incredible rise and offer predictions for its future?</strong></p>



<p>It wasn’t a single event. Based on my research, I thought the dollar peaked in its global footprint in 2015 and was in gentle decline. But I also thought this trend might accelerate. I was particularly concerned with our fiscal deficit and rising interest rates. I recently <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w33079">published a paper</a> showing that if you look at the long history of interest rates, they tend to revert to trend.</p>



<p>I was also <a href="https://rogoff.scholars.harvard.edu/publications/beginning-end-central-bank-independence">very concerned</a> about the Federal Reserve losing independence. I actually wrote the <a href="https://rogoff.scholars.harvard.edu/publications/optimal-degree-commitment-intermediate-monetary-target">first paper</a> on the importance of central bank independence almost 45 years ago; it’s maybe my most famous paper. But in recent years, I started noticing rhetoric on both the left and the right about reining that in. Federal Reserve Chairman Jerome Powell wouldn’t get pushed aside out of the blue. It would take another crisis. During wartime, for example, central banks are commonly made subservient to the government.</p>



<p><strong>That covers some of the internal pressures on dollar dominance. What about external factors?</strong></p>



<p>We’ve been able to use economic sanctions in place of military intervention. It saves us lives; it saves us money. But dollar dominance also gives us access to financial data that no other country has. If you were to go to the CIA today, you would see somebody on a laptop instead of somebody like James Bond.</p>



<p>So there’s quite an appetite, particularly in Asia, to reduce the dollar’s grip. China couldn’t help but notice when the U.S. placed economic sanctions on Russia following its full-scale invasion of Ukraine. China, of course, has designs on Taiwan.</p>



<p><strong>For most of us in the U.S., our currency’s almighty position isn’t exactly top of mind. Can you illustrate how dollar dominance impacts daily life for everyday Americans?</strong></p>



<p>For one thing, we’re all paying lower interest rates. It’s not a huge amount. You don’t like paying 6 percent on your mortgage, but you’d dislike it even more if you were paying 7 percent. And for the national government, which owes $36 trillion, every additional 1 percent is $360 billion.</p>



<p>Another thing is that, in times of crisis like the pandemic or the global financial crisis of 2008, the U.S. has been able to borrow promiscuously. Interest rates do rise as our debt rises, but the effect is very gentle compared with the U.K. or France. If this privilege is lost, we will notice it.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1272" height="1920" src="https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg" alt="Book cover: &quot;Our Dollar, Your Problem.&quot;" srcset="https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg 1272w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=99,150 99w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=199,300 199w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=768,1159 768w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=678,1024 678w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=1018,1536 1018w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=21,32 21w, https://news.harvard.edu/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Book-cover-our-dollar-your-problem.jpg?resize=42,64 42w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1272px) 100vw, 1272px"></figure>



<p><strong>Tell me about the book’s title.</strong></p>



<p>The U.S. dollar used to be as good as gold. If you were a foreign country holding the equivalent to what is today hundreds of billions of dollars, as many Asian central banks do now, you could just take them to the U.S., and we would give you gold. But then President Richard Nixon decided, in 1971, that we weren’t going to do that anymore.</p>



<p>Leaders from around the world were in a state of shock. As a global financial incident, it was just as dramatic as the introduction of President Trump’s tariffs earlier this year. Nixon sent Treasury Secretary John Connally to meet with these leaders in Rome. They asked, “What do we do? Now that you’re not on gold, you can just inflate this stuff, and we’re stuck with it.” And Connally replied, “Well, it’s our dollar, but it’s your problem.”</p>



<p><strong>What do Connally’s words call to mind for you today?</strong></p>



<p>Connally’s remark captures the arrogance of American leaders that foreign leaders so often feel. I feel our role in the world comes with responsibility, and we should recognize that.</p>



<p>The book’s title is also ironic. After we went off gold, we lost a kind of price anchor. Nixon started beating up on Federal Reserve Chairman Arthur Burns as brutally as Trump beats up on Powell today. It just wasn’t in public; he was doing it in the Oval Office. We only know about it now because of the Watergate tapes. Burns got pressured into printing a lot of money. The result was the worst inflation the U.S. had seen since in a long while. So although Connally was saying “It’s your problem,” the resulting inflation proved a disaster for the U.S., too.</p>



<p><strong>Other economies have emerged as challengers to U.S. power over the years. But you open the book with a surprising example, at least for those who came of age after the Cold War. You start with the post-World War II rise of the Soviet Union. Can you talk about that choice?</strong></p>



<p>By the ’80s, it was becoming clear that the Russian ruble would not outpace the dollar. But in the ’60s and ’70s, we had no idea. I write about the different professors I met as an undergraduate at Yale, as well as textbooks by leading economists such as Paul Samuelson. Samuelson was convinced the Soviet economy would catch up to the U.S. The greatest economic historian of that era was Angus Maddison. He didn’t think the Soviet Union would catch up, but he thought it would do pretty well. These economists were not Marxists!</p>



<p>Later on, we didn’t know Japan would falter. We didn’t know Europe would fizzle. We never imagined the heights the U.S. dollar ultimately reached. My book hits these themes again and again.</p>



<p><strong>How did your experiences as a globe-hopping teen chess master shape your views on the subject?</strong></p>



<p>My professors at Yale talked about how great the Soviet Union was doing. But I had lived on my own abroad, primarily in the former Yugoslavia. I had visited some of my chess-player friends in their homes. Chess was a very big deal in the Communist bloc, so these players had privileged lives and nicer dwellings than the typical resident. But these nice dwellings consisted of little cement blocks in these humorless buildings. They barely had modern plumbing by U.S. standards. It made me very skeptical about Samuelson’s claim.</p>



<p><strong>You write in this book that era of dollar dominance is in “late middle-age, but still in good health.” Is that still true in light of Trump’s second-term trade war?</strong></p>



<p>Well, the dollar is starting to experience more serious health issues under Trump. When you’re an academic, the goal is never to write a book that’s true tomorrow. After coming to Harvard in 1999, I went for a walk across campus with former Faculty of Arts and Sciences Dean <a href="https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2008/04/jeremy-r-knowles/">Jeremy Knowles</a>. I’ll never forget what he told me. He said, “The perfect paper is one that everybody thinks is wrong, but in five or 10 years it’s proven right.”</p>



<p><strong>You’ve achieved that in the past.</strong></p>



<p>Carmen Reinhart and I were ridiculed in early 2009 when we presented <a href="https://rogoff.scholars.harvard.edu/publications/aftermath-financial-crises">a paper</a> showing that recoveries from financial crises tend to be much slower and weaker than conventional recoveries. Of course that is exactly what happened. I had a similar experience in 2020 when <a href="https://rogoff.scholars.harvard.edu/sites/g/files/omnuum5901/files/rogoff/files/nber_27697_peak_china_housing_1.pdf">my work suggested</a> a deep problem in Chinese real estate.</p>



<p>My new book also contains some out-of-consensus forecasts that I believe will ultimately prove correct — on interest rates, inflation, and the role of the dollar. I don’t argue that dollar dominance will fall sharply tomorrow. But Trump has been an accelerant. He has been a catalyst. Parts of the world were already moving away from the dollar. Now they’re moving much faster.</p>	<!-- wp:harvard-gazette/share -->
	
	<!-- /wp:harvard-gazette/share -->
	
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Business books are entertainment, not strategic tools (497 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theorthagonist.substack.com/p/why-reading-business-books-is-a-waste</link>
            <guid>43940747</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 20:51:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theorthagonist.substack.com/p/why-reading-business-books-is-a-waste">https://theorthagonist.substack.com/p/why-reading-business-books-is-a-waste</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43940747">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>Most popular business books are written for emotional appeal, not intellectual rigor.</p><p>They turn simplified stories into generic advice, convert rare successes into universal strategies, and replace complex market dynamics with motivational slogans.</p><p>These books succeed not because they are accurate, but because they are easy to read and make readers feel good.</p><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> Create something entirely new. Avoid competition. Monopolies are better.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> Yes, monopolies are more profitable. That’s well known.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Thiel promotes the idea that great companies are born from singular insight. In reality, most companies pivot repeatedly and succeed through iteration.</p></li><li><p>He oversimplifies market dynamics, ignoring the role of strategic partnerships and collaborative ecosystems.</p></li><li><p>Skips the part that Peter Thiel was already in the top 1% of the population—Stanford-educated, ex-Credit Suisse, and founder of a small capital firm—before PayPal. He wasn’t a struggling outsider with nothing to lose. His advice is filtered through a lens of early privilege and structural advantage.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>No discussion of real startup mechanics like team dynamics, fundraising timelines, cost structures, or customer acquisition.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>Airbnb</strong><span> didn’t invent a new concept—it executed better within an existing space.</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> Automate and outsource your work to live more freely.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> Delegation and automation can increase efficiency.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Ferriss generalizes from fringe cases. He presents digital arbitrage schemes and outsourcing as a universal path to freedom.</p></li><li><p>The idea of “mini-retirements” ignores the intensity required to build anything meaningful.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>No discussion of long-term brand building, legal issues in outsourcing, or strategic depth.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>Stripe</strong><span> was built through deep technical focus and years of sustained effort—not four-hour shortcuts.</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> A strong sense of purpose drives business success.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> A clear mission can help unify a team or attract certain customers.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Sinek overstates the importance of purpose. In practice, customers buy based on utility and price, not ideology.</p></li><li><p>Many companies retroactively assign a mission after achieving traction.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>No analysis of market fit, product iteration, or pricing strategy.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>Amazon</strong><span> scaled through operational excellence, not brand mission.</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> Build–Measure–Learn cycles help startups adapt and reduce waste.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> Fast iteration and feedback loops are helpful.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The MVP concept is often overused to justify low-quality products.</p></li><li><p>Metrics are treated as precise guides without accounting for interpretation or strategy.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Lacks attention to capital planning, go-to-market execution, or founder psychology under uncertainty.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>Apple</strong><span> avoided MVPs, choosing instead to launch highly polished products.</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> Successful companies share common leadership traits and disciplined cultures.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> Strong leadership and discipline are helpful.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The book suffers from selection bias. Many “great” companies later failed.</p></li><li><p>It presents correlation as causation.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>No real discussion of technology cycles, financial structuring, or economic context.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p><strong>Fannie Mae</strong><span>, once praised in the book, played a major role in the 2008 financial collapse.</span></p></li></ul><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> Startups are painful, and there are no easy answers.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> Founding a company is often chaotic and stressful.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The book turns specific experiences into generalized lessons without clear frameworks.</p></li><li><p>Key decisions (e.g., firing, fundraising) are discussed narratively rather than analytically.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>No structured treatment of capital efficiency, equity dilution, or risk-weighted decision-making.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p><span>Many companies succeeded by avoiding avoidable chaos—</span><strong>Shopify</strong><span> scaled steadily with methodical planning.</span></p></li></ul><p><em>A total airport book.</em></p><p><strong>Main Idea:</strong><span> Caring less about unimportant things leads to a better life.</span></p><p><strong>What’s partly true:</strong><span> Obsessing over irrelevant issues wastes time and energy.</span></p><p><strong>What’s misleading:</strong></p><ul><li><p>The book wraps fatalism in edgy language and markets it as practical wisdom.</p></li><li><p>Manson’s branding depends on carefully curating an image of not caring, which is itself a contradiction.</p></li></ul><p><strong>What’s missing:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Offers no frameworks, strategies, or useful tools for people building complex systems or organizations.</p></li></ul><p><strong>Counterexample:</strong></p><ul><li><p>Every successful founder gave tremendous attention to detail. Caring deeply is essential.</p></li></ul><p>I read business books like these consistently for two years. I took notes, applied the advice, and expected meaningful change.</p><p>None came.</p><p>There were no improved outcomes, no smarter decisions, just temporary motivation and wasted time.</p><p>Glorified procrastination, at best.</p><p>Before I started my first company, I worked for over ten years as a quantitative analyst at a top-tier financial firm.</p><p>We built mathematical models to price risk in real-time.</p><p>When I entered the startup world, I mistakenly followed the MVP playbook. We launched too early, misread feedback, and ended up iterating around noise.</p><p>What saved the company wasn’t lean methodology. It was building something so good that users couldn’t ignore it.</p><p>I’ve hired engineers who were obsessed with quality and passed on candidates with vague “passion.”</p><p>I’ve killed deals when the numbers didn’t make sense, regardless of hype.</p><p>Nothing I’ve learned about building successful ventures came from mainstream business books.</p><p>It came from confronting consequences.</p><p><strong>1. Focus on reality, not narrative</strong></p><ul><li><p>Real markets don’t follow tidy story arcs. Most success stories are retrospective rationalizations of random walks.</p></li></ul><p><strong>2. Strategy is situational and dynamic</strong></p><ul><li><p>There is no universal playbook. The right strategy depends on timing, capital, and team capabilities.</p></li></ul><p><strong>3. Operational knowledge matters</strong></p><ul><li><p>Concepts like churn, CAC:LTV, regulatory constraints, and compensation structure determine outcomes. Most pop-business books ignore these.</p></li></ul><p><strong>4. Small, smart decisions compound</strong></p><ul><li><p>Breakthroughs are rare. Endurance and accumulation win.</p></li></ul><p><strong>5. Mastery beats motivation</strong></p><ul><li><p>Learn accounting, incentive design, and probability before chasing feel-good mantras.</p></li></ul><p>Not all books are empty. Some are rigorous, detailed, and worth your time—usually written by academics, not entrepreneurs. Examples:</p><ul><li><p><em><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/407999.Competitive_Strategy" rel="">Competitive Strategy</a></strong></em><span> by Michael Porter — clear frameworks for industry structure and positioning.</span></p></li><li><p><em><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/17628199-designing-organizations" rel="">Designing Organizations</a></strong></em><span> by Jay R. Galbraith — systems thinking for structuring scalable teams.</span></p></li><li><p><em><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/24537795-financial-modeling" rel="">Financial Modeling</a></strong></em><span> by Simon Benninga — practical tools for forecasting and capital planning.</span></p></li><li><p><em><strong><a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/151848.Probability_Theory" rel="">Probability Theory: The Logic of Science</a></strong></em><span> by E.T. Jaynes — essential reading for thinking under uncertainty.</span></p></li></ul><p>These aren’t easy reads.</p><p>They require real cognitive effort.</p><p>But they offer lasting value.</p><p>The most successful founders don’t memorize slogans.</p><p>They absorb complexity, adapt intelligently, and think in systems.</p><p>Most business books won’t help you do that.</p><p>Write your own playbook—with decisions, not quotes.</p><p>Be well,</p><p>Jack</p></div></article></div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What’s new in Swift 6.2 (172 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.hackingwithswift.com/articles/277/whats-new-in-swift-6-2</link>
            <guid>43940539</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 May 2025 20:20:52 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.hackingwithswift.com/articles/277/whats-new-in-swift-6-2">https://www.hackingwithswift.com/articles/277/whats-new-in-swift-6-2</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43940539">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                            
                            <p>Raw identifiers, backtraces, task naming, and more.</p>
                        </div><div>
                            <p>Brace yourselves, folks: Swift 6.2 contains another gigantic collection of additions and improvements to the language, while also adding some important refinements to Swift concurrency that ought to make it much easier to adopt everywhere.</p>
<p>Many changes are small, such as the addition of raw identifiers, default values in string interpolation, or <code>enumerated()</code> conforming to <code>Collection</code>, but these are all likely to spread quickly across projects because they are just so darned <em>useful</em>.</p>
<p>It's also great to see Swift Testing going from strength to strength, with three major improvements coming in Swift 6.2, including exit tests and attachments.</p>
<p>In short, it feels like Swift 6.2 is delivering what many imagined Swift 6.0 would be – increasingly rounded support for concurrency, backed up by a number of pragmatic choices that help smooth out the language's learning curve.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> At the time of writing, Swift 6.2 is available only as a test release from <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://www.swift.org/install/macos/">Swift.org</a>. The list below represents my best guess for what's coming up –&nbsp;don't be surprised if something slips to a later or release or something else arrives by surprise!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.hackingwithswift.com/sponsor">Sponsor Hacking with Swift and reach the world's largest Swift community!</a></p>
<h3>Control default actor isolation inference</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0466-control-default-actor-isolation.md">SE-0466</a> introduces the ability for code to opt into running on a single actor by default –&nbsp;to effectively go back to being a single-threaded program, where most code runs on the main actor until you say otherwise.</p>
<p><strong>Yes, this is exactly as good as you're thinking:</strong> with one single change many app developers can more or less avoid thinking about Swift concurrency until they are ready to do so, because unless they say otherwise all their types and functions will behave as if it were annotated with <code>@MainActor</code>.</p>
<p>To enable this new feature, add <code>-default-isolation MainActor</code> to your compiler flags, and code like this becomes valid:</p>
<pre><code>@MainActor
class DataController {
    func load() { }
    func save() { }
}

struct App {
    let controller = DataController()

    init() {
        controller.load()
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>As you can see, the <code>App</code> struct creates and uses a main actor-isolated type without itself being marked <code>@MainActor</code>, but that's okay because it's automatically applied for us –&nbsp;we could even remove the lone <code>@MainActor</code> annotation and it would still apply.</p>
<p>Before you start panicking that this is going to cause all sorts of concurrency problems, there are five important things you know.</p>
<p>First, this new configuration option is applied on a <em>per-module basis</em>, so if you bring in external modules they can still run on other actors. This ought to allow UI-focused modules to switch to running on the main actor by default, while letting background-focused modules operate with concurrency as before.</p>
<p>Second, you can still use things like networking in your apps just fine –&nbsp;code such as <code>URLSession.shared.data(from:)</code> will run on its own task rather than blocking your code.</p>
<p>Third, a single CPU core in a modern iPhone runs at over 4GHz, so a huge number of iOS apps can get all their work done serially without a second thought.</p>
<p>Fourth, a lot of developers were already using "make it all @MainActor" as their default approach to concurrency, changing only when needed.</p>
<p>Fifth and perhaps most importantly, this change along with others form part of a larger <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/visions/approachable-concurrency.md">Improving the approachability of data-race safety</a> vision document published by the Swift team – it's not just one change in isolation, but instead part of a cohesive package of improvements to reduce the learning curve for concurrency.</p>
<p>So, although this change might seem antithetical to all the Swift concurrency work that has taken place from Swift 5.5 and on, ultimately it solves a significant problem that was only growing: Swift concurrency is not easy to learn, and many apps simply don't need it.</p>
<p>Of course, the real question is whether Apple will enable this feature by default for new app projects in Xcode. I sincerely hope so, because it would also allow Xcode to default to the Swift 6 language version without introducing errors and warnings that many developers just don't need to think about.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Another Swift Evolution proposal, <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0478-default-isolation-typealias.md">SE-0478</a>, is currently being discussed, and if it is approved would allow us to declare the default actor isolation on a per-file basis using syntax like <code>private typealias DefaultIsolation = MainActor</code>. The feedback so far has been broadly negative, so it might be returned for revision.</p>
<h3>Raw identifiers</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0451-escaped-identifiers.md">SE-0451</a> dramatically expands the range of characters we can use to create identifiers – the names of variables, functions, enum cases and similar –&nbsp;so we can name them pretty much however we want when placed inside backticks.</p>
<p>So, this kind of code is legal in Swift 6.2 and later:</p>
<pre><code>func `function name with spaces`() {
    print("Hello, world!")
}

`function name with spaces`()</code></pre>
<p>If you're wondering why such naming might be useful, consider this:</p>
<pre><code>enum HTTPError: String {
    case `401` = "Unauthorized"
    case `404` = "Not Found"
    case `500` = "Internal Server Error"
    case `502` = "Bad Gateway"
}</code></pre>
<p>That makes each HTTP error code a case in our enum, which would previously need to be written as something else such as <code>case _401</code> or <code>case error401</code>.</p>
<p>If you're using numbers like this, you either need to qualify the type each time you use it, to avoid Swift getting confused, or you need to place the backticks carefully.</p>
<p>For example, in the code below we use <code>HTTPError</code> each time, to avoid Swift thinking <code>401</code> refers to a malformed floating-point literal:</p>
<pre><code>let error = HTTPError.401

switch error {
case HTTPError.401, HTTPError.404:
    print("Client error: \(error.rawValue)")
default:
    print("Server error: \(error.rawValue)")
}</code></pre>
<p>The alternative is to wrap the numbers themselves in the backticks –&nbsp;<em>not</em> including the dot beforehand – like this:</p>
<pre><code>switch error {
case .`401`, .`404`:
    print("Client error: \(error.rawValue)")
default:
    print("Server error: \(error.rawValue)")
}</code></pre>
<p>The biggest benefactor of this change is likely to be Swift Testing, where test names can now directly be written in a human-readable form rather than using camel case and adding an extra string description above.</p>
<p>So, rather than writing this:</p>
<pre><code>import Testing

@Test("Strip HTML tags from string")
func stripHTMLTagsFromString() {
    // test code
}</code></pre>
<p>We can instead write this:</p>
<pre><code>@Test
func `Strip HTML tags from string`() {
    // test code
}</code></pre>
<p>It's less duplication, which is always welcome.</p>
<p>One small detail that might catch you out is this: "A raw identifier may start with, contain, or end with operator characters, but it may not contain only operator characters." So, you can put operators such as <code>+</code> and <code>-</code> into your identifier names, but only if they aren't the only things in there.</p>
<h3>Default Value in String Interpolations</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0477-default-interpolation-values.md">SE-0477</a> makes a small but beautiful change to string interpolation with optionals, allowing us to provide an additional <code>default</code> value to use if the optional is nil.</p>
<p>In its simplest form this means we would write the following code:</p>
<pre><code>var name: String? = nil
print("Hello, \(name, default: "Anonymous")!")</code></pre>
<p>Instead of this:</p>
<pre><code>print("Hello, \(name ?? "Anonymous")!")</code></pre>
<p>At first glance this might not seem like a great improvement, but the kicker is that nil coalescing doesn't work with different types. So, this kind of code is allowed:</p>
<pre><code>var age: Int? = nil
print("Age: \(age ?? 0)")</code></pre>
<p>But this kind of code will not compile when uncommented:</p>
<pre><code>// print("Age: \(age ?? "Unknown")")</code></pre>
<p>That attempts to mix an optional integer with a string default value, which isn't allowed. Fortunately this <em>is</em> possible from Swift 6.2 onwards:</p>
<pre><code>print("Age: \(age, default: "Unknown")")</code></pre>
<h3>Add Collection conformances for enumerated()</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0459-enumerated-collection.md">SE-0459</a> makes the type returned by <code>enumerated()</code> conform to <code>Collection</code>.</p>
<p>The most immediate benefit of this is that it's now much easier to use <code>enumerated()</code> with a SwiftUI <code>List</code> or <code>ForEach</code> like this:</p>
<pre><code>import SwiftUI

struct ContentView: View {
    var names = ["Bernard", "Laverne", "Hoagie"]

    var body: some View {
        List(names.enumerated(), id: \.offset) { values in
            Text("User \(values.offset + 1): \(values.element)")
        }
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>The <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0459-enumerated-collection.md">proposal</a> also mentions various performance benefits, including making <code>(1000..&lt;2000).enumerated().dropFirst(500)</code> a constant-time operation.</p>
<h3>Method and Initializer Key Paths</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0479-method-and-initializer-keypaths.md">SE-0479</a> extends Swift's key paths to support methods alongside the existing support for properties and subscripts, which, along with <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0438-metatype-keypath.md">SE-0438</a> introduced in Swift 6.1, promises to round out what key paths can do.</p>
<p>Code to access properties has always worked just fine with key paths:</p>
<pre><code>let strings = ["Hello", "world"]
let capitalized = strings.map(\.capitalized)
print(capitalized)</code></pre>
<p>With this change we can now access methods too, but be sure to actually <em>invoke</em> the method like this:</p>
<pre><code>let uppercased = strings.map(\.uppercased())
print(uppercased)</code></pre>
<p>If you <em>don't</em> invoke the method then you get back an uninvoked function that you can call later on like this:</p>
<pre><code>let functions = strings.map(\.uppercased)
print(functions)

for function in functions {
    print(function())
}</code></pre>
<p>In that code, the <code>functions</code> constant contains an array of calls to <code>uppercased()</code> on each string we passed in – <code>functions[0]</code> would be a reference to <code>"HELLO".uppercased()</code>, which we could call directly using <code>functions[0]()</code>.</p>
<p>If two methods have the same name, you can add their argument labels to clarify which overload you mean, like this:</p>
<pre><code>let prefixUpTo = \Array&lt;String&gt;.prefix(upTo:)
let prefixThrough = \Array&lt;String&gt;.prefix(through:)</code></pre>
<p>However, you <em>can't</em> make key paths to methods that are marked either <code>async</code> or <code>throws</code>; it's just not supported.</p>
<h3>Opt-in Strict Memory Safety Checking</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0458-strict-memory-safety.md">SE-0458</a> introduces opt-in support for flagging unsafe Swift code as warnings unless specifically desired, which will make it significantly easier to audit unsafe code usage.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> To be clear, <em>unsafe</em> code is not the same as <em>crashing</em> code – things like force unwraps or reading index -1 in an array will both crash your code but are considered safe because that's expected behavior. <em>Unsafe</em> code is code where you bypass Swift's guardrails to poke around in memory in such a way to cause undefined behavior, and usually if not always includes the word "unsafe" somewhere in the name, e.g. <code>UnsafeRawPointer</code> or <code>unsafelyUnwrapped</code>.</p>
<p>Strict memory safety checking introduces new <code>@safe</code> and <code>@unsafe</code> attributes that mark code as safe or unsafe to use respectively, with <code>@safe</code> being the default –&nbsp;it's only required when you need to override <code>@unsafe</code> in specific circumstances.</p>
<p>When strict memory safety is enabled, and code marked <code>@unsafe</code> must be called with a new <code>unsafe</code> keyword, like this:</p>
<pre><code>let name: String?
unsafe print(name.unsafelyUnwrapped)</code></pre>
<p>Failing to use <code>unsafe</code> will throw up a warning, so you can either adjust the code to use a safe variant or add the <code>unsafe</code> key to acknowledge that the code is unsafe.</p>
<p>This is very similar to the way both <code>try</code> and <code>await</code> work –&nbsp;the compiler knows that certain code will throw, that certain other code is asynchronous, or that certain other code is marked <code>@unsafe</code>, so really these keywords are acknowledgements for other people to see.</p>
<h3>Swift Backtrace API</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0419-backtrace-api.md">SE-0419</a> introduces a new <code>Backtrace</code> struct, which is capable of capturing data about the call stack of our app at any given moment –&nbsp;the exact sequence of function calls leading up to the current point.</p>
<p>By default backtraces are not symbolicated, which means they won't include the names of each function in the call stack, but you can use <code>symbolicated()</code> to get that extra data.</p>
<p>So, as an example we could write a small chain of functions where the last one prints a backtrace:</p>
<pre><code>import Runtime

func functionA() {
    functionB()
}

func functionB() {
    functionC()
}

func functionC() {
    if let frames = try? Backtrace.capture().symbolicated()?.frames {
        print(frames)
    } else {
        print("Failed to get backtrace.")
    }
}

functionA()</code></pre>
<p>That will print exactly which functions were on the call stack – <code>functionC()</code>, <code>functionB()</code>, and <code>functionA()</code> – along with the files and line numbers of each call, which is really helpful for debugging.</p>
<h3>weak let</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0481-weak-let.md">SE-0481</a> introduces the ability to use <code>weak let</code> when declaring properties of a type, complementing the existing support for <code>weak var</code>.</p>
<p><strong>Important:</strong> <code>weak let</code> means that a property cannot be changed after creation, but it can still be <em>destroyed</em>, so you need to use it carefully.</p>
<p>As an example, we could create two classes like this:</p>
<pre><code>final class User: Sendable {
    let id = UUID()
}

final class Session: Sendable {
    weak let user: User?

    init(user: User?) {
        self.user = user
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>We could then make and use them like so:</p>
<pre><code>var user: User? = User()
let session = Session(user: user)
print(session.user?.id ?? "No ID")</code></pre>
<p>Because the <code>user</code> property a <code>weak</code> reference to a class, we can destroy the original and have the property be destroyed too. So, this will print "No ID":</p>
<pre><code>user = nil
print(session.user?.id ?? "No ID")</code></pre>
<p>What we <em>can't</em> do is <em>reassign</em> the <code>user</code> property, which means both of these two would fail to compile if uncommented:</p>
<pre><code>// session.user? = User()
// session.user = nil</code></pre>
<p>Another big advantage of <code>weak let</code> can also be seen in the code above: we can mark both those classes as conforming to <code>Sendable</code>, which would not have been possible using <code>weak var</code>.</p>
<h3>Transactional Observation of Values</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0475-observed.md">SE-0475</a> creates a new <code>Observations</code> struct that is created with a closure, and provides an <code>AsyncSequence</code> that emits new values whenever any any <code>@Observable</code> data changes – it effectively gives us the same power to monitor changes that SwiftUI gets, just in a free-form way.</p>
<p>As an example, we could make a trivial <code>@Observable</code> class for a player with a score:</p>
<pre><code>@Observable
class Player {
    var score = 0
}

let player1 = Player()</code></pre>
<p>We can ask to be notified when that score changes using <code>Observations</code> like this:</p>
<pre><code>let playerScores = Observations { player1.score }</code></pre>
<p>In that code, <code>playerScores</code> is an instance of <code>Observations&lt;Int, Never&gt;</code>, meaning that it emits integers and will never throw errors.</p>
<p>We can then queue up a bunch of example changes, and watch for those happening with a <code>for await</code> loop:</p>
<pre><code>for i in 1...5 {
    Task {
        try? await Task.sleep(for: .seconds(i))
        player1.score += 1
    }
}

for await score in playerScores {
    print(score)
} </code></pre>
<p>That will print six values in total: the initial score, plus increments through 5.</p>
<p>There are a handful of important usage notes you should be aware of when using <code>Observations</code>:</p>
<ol>
<li>It will emit the initial value as well as all future values.</li>
<li>If multiple changes come in at the same time, they might be coalesced into a single value being emitted. For example, if our <code>Task</code> code incremented <code>score</code> twice, the values emitted would go up in 2s.</li>
<li>The <code>AsyncSequence</code> of values being emitted can potentially run forever, so you should put it on a separate task or otherwise handle it carefully.</li>
<li>If you want iteration to stop – to end the loop – you should make the value being observed optional, then set it to nil.</li>
</ol>
<h3>Global-actor isolated conformances</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0470-isolated-conformances.md">SE-0470</a> resolves a small but important concurrency problem by making it possible to restrict a protocol conformance to a specific global actor.</p>
<p>For example, we can now say "this <code>@MainActor</code>-restricted type conforms to <code>Equatable</code> only when it's being used on the main actor, like this:</p>
<pre><code>@MainActor
class User: @MainActor Equatable {
    var id: UUID
    var name: String

    init(name: String) {
        self.id = UUID()
        self.name = name
    }

    static func ==(lhs: User, rhs: User) -&gt; Bool {
        lhs.id == rhs.id
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>Notice the use of <code>@MainActor Equatable</code> –&nbsp;if we had tried to conform without using <code>@MainActor</code> on the protocol, Swift would be free to run the <code>==</code> method on any task, including in the background, which is explicitly disallowed thanks to the whole type being marked <code>@MainActor</code>. As a result, our code would not build.</p>
<h3>Starting tasks synchronously from caller context</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0472-task-start-synchronously-on-caller-context.md">SE-0472</a> introduces a new way to create tasks so they start immediately if possible, rather than the existing behavior that only allows tasks to be queued to run at the next opportunity.</p>
<p>You can see the difference with code like this:</p>
<pre><code>print("Starting")

Task {
    print("In Task")
}

Task.immediate {
    print("In Immediate Task")
}

print("Done")
try await Task.sleep(for: .seconds(0.1))</code></pre>
<p>That creates two unstructured tasks: a regular unstructured task followed by an immediate unstructured task. When it runs, it will print Starting, In Immediate Task, Done, and then finally In Task.</p>
<p>To really understand the distinction between immediate tasks and regular tasks, remember that all potential suspension points in Swift must be marked with <code>await</code>. Creating a regular, non-immediate task doesn't use <code>await</code> because it doesn't mark a suspension point, but it <em>doesn't</em> run immediately because it gets queued up to run at the next available opportunity.</p>
<p>The new ability to create <em>immediate</em> tasks unlocks important new functionality: the code in an immediate task starts executing immediately if it's already on the target executor, perhaps providing important data that a UI control is waiting for, but after that initial immediate response the task can then use <code>await</code> like a regular task and potentially trigger suspension as normal. So, everything in an immediate tasks runs straight away until the first suspension point is reached.</p>
<p>Both <code>Task</code> and <code>Task.immediate</code> are <em>unstructured</em> tasks, however task groups have also been upgraded to support immediate child tasks with <code>addImmediateTask()</code> and <code>addImmediateTaskUnlessCancelled()</code>.</p>
<h3>Run nonisolated async functions on the caller's actor by default</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0461-async-function-isolation.md">SE-0461</a> adjusts the way nonisolated async functions are called so that they run on the same actor as their caller. This sounds like a really abstract change, but it is important so I would recommend you spend the time to understand what's changing and why.</p>
<p>As an example, here's a simple struct that knows how to download and decode an array of <code>Double</code> values that represents various temperatures:</p>
<pre><code>struct Measurements {
    func fetchLatest() async throws -&gt; [Double] {
        let url = URL(string: "https://hws.dev/readings.json")!
        let (data, _) = try await URLSession.shared.data(from: url)
        return try JSONDecoder().decode([Double].self, from: data)
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>That isn't isolated to any particular actor, so it can run its code anywhere.</p>
<p>Next, we could use that with another struct called <code>WeatherStation</code>, which will download all the readings and return their mean average. This time, though we'll mark the struct as being isolated to the main actor:</p>
<pre><code>@MainActor
struct WeatherStation {
    let measurements = Measurements()

    func getAverageTemperature() async throws -&gt; Double {
        let readings = try await measurements.fetchLatest()
        let average = readings.reduce(0, +) / Double(readings.count)
        return average
    }
}

let station = WeatherStation()
try await print(station.getAverageTemperature())</code></pre>
<p>So, we have one struct that is nonisolated, and another that <em>is</em> isolated, and this demonstrates the change perfectly: before Swift 6.2 the call to <code>measurements.fetchLatest()</code> will not run on the main actor, but from Swift 6.2 and later it <em>will</em>.</p>
<p>The old behavior caused some confusion, not least because <code>measurements</code> is a main actor-isolated property in <code>WeatherStation</code>, and the call to <code>measurements.fetchLatest()</code> takes place in the main actor-isolated <code>getAverageTemperature()</code> method.</p>
<p>That old behavior wasn't an accident – <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0338-clarify-execution-non-actor-async.md">SE-0338</a> from Swift 5.7 specifically states that async functions that aren't isolated to a particular actor "do not run on any actor's executor."</p>
<p>The new behavior introduced by SE-0461 means that nonisolated async functions will now run on the same actor as their caller unless you say otherwise. In the code above, that means the call to <code>measurements.fetchLatest()</code> will run on the main actor because <code>getAverageTemperature()</code> does.</p>
<p>If you want the old behavior to return –&nbsp;if you wanted <code>fetchLatest()</code> to switch away from the caller's actor automatically – you would need to mark it with the new <code>@concurrent</code> attribute, like this: <code>@concurrent func fetchLatest()…</code>.</p>
<h3>Isolated synchronous deinit</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0371-isolated-synchronous-deinit.md">SE-0371</a> introduces the ability to mark the deinitializers of actor-isolated classes as being isolated, which allows them to safely access data elsewhere in the class.</p>
<p>For example, this class is isolated to the main actor, and I've marked its <code>deinit</code> as being isolated so that it can safely call <code>cleanUp()</code>:</p>
<pre><code>@MainActor
class DataController {
    func cleanUp() {
        // free up memory
    }

    isolated deinit {
        cleanUp()
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>Without that <code>isolated</code> keyword in there, the deinitializer wouldn't be isolated to the main actor –&nbsp;that's just not how global actors work. <em>With</em> it there, your code will move to the actor's executor before running the code, so it's all safe.</p>
<p>This will be particularly useful for times when your deinitializer needs to access non-<code>Sendable</code> state belonging to a class. For example, we might have a <code>User</code> class like this one:</p>
<pre><code>class User {
    var isLoggedIn = false
}</code></pre>
<p>We can then wrap that in a <code>Session</code> class that runs on the main actor, which automatically marks the user being logged in or out as the session is created and destroyed:</p>
<pre><code>@MainActor
class Session {
    let user: User

    init(user: User) {
        self.user = user
        user.isLoggedIn = true
    }

    isolated deinit {
        user.isLoggedIn = false
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>Again, that <code>isolated</code> keyword is required to make the code work – without that the deinitializer would run without being isolated to the main actor, but it would try to access the <code>user</code> property that <em>is</em> isolated to the main actor, causing a compile error.</p>
<h3>Task Priority Escalation APIs</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0462-task-priority-escalation-apis.md">SE-0462</a> introduces the ability for tasks to detect when their priority has been escalated, and also for us to manually escalate task priority if needed.</p>
<p>To watch for priority escalation, use the <code>withTaskPriorityEscalationHandler()</code> function like this:</p>
<pre><code>let newsFetcher = Task(priority: .medium) {
    try await withTaskPriorityEscalationHandler {
        let url = URL(string: "https://hws.dev/messages.json")!
        let (data, _) = try await URLSession.shared.data(from: url)
        return data
    } onPriorityEscalated: { oldPriority, newPriority in
        print("Priority has been escalated to \(newPriority)")
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>As you can see, that gives us both the old and new task priorities, and it's up to us to respond to the change however we want. If you want to use that opportunity to escalate the priority of other tasks, you should use the new <code>escalatePriority(to:)</code> method like this:</p>
<pre><code>newsFetcher.escalatePriority(to: .high)</code></pre>
<p>Because there are several task priorities available to us, it's possible your <code>onPriorityEscalated</code> code will be triggered multiple times –&nbsp;your priority might start at low then move to medium, then move to high, for example. However, task priority can only ever be <em>raised</em>, never lowered.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Task priority escalation usually happens automatically, such as when a high-priority task finds itself waiting on the result of a low-priority task – Swift will automatically raise the priority of the low-priority task so it’s able to complete faster. Although this API gives us extra control, it's still best to let priority escalation happen automatically where possible.</p>
<h3>Task Naming</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0469-task-names.md">SE-0469</a> introduces a useful change to the way we create tasks and child tasks: we can now give them <em>names</em>, which is ideal for debugging when one particular task goes rogue.</p>
<p>The API here is simple: when using <code>Task.init()</code> and <code>Task.detached()</code> to create new tasks, or using <code>addTask()</code> and <code>addTaskUnlessCancelled()</code> to create child tasks in a task group, you can now pass an optional <code>name</code> parameter string to identify the task uniquely. These name strings can be hard-coded or use string interpolation; either one works.</p>
<p>In its simplest form, the new API looks like this:</p>
<pre><code>let task = Task(name: "MyTask") {
    print("Current task name: \(Task.name ?? "Unknown")")
}</code></pre>
<p>To show you a more real-world example, we might have a <code>NewsStory</code> struct that knows how to load some basic information about a news article:</p>
<pre><code>struct NewsStory: Decodable, Identifiable {
    let id: Int
    let title: String
    let strap: String
    let url: URL
}</code></pre>
<p>Now we could use a task group to fetch several news story sources and combine them into a single array, while also printing a log message if any child task hits a problem:</p>
<pre><code>let stories = await withTaskGroup { group in
    for i in 1...5 {
        // Give each child task a unique name
        // for easier identification.
        group.addTask(name: "Stories \(i)") {
            do {
                let url = URL(string: "https://hws.dev/news-\(i).json")!
                let (data, _) = try await URLSession.shared.data(from: url)
                return try JSONDecoder().decode([NewsStory].self, from: data)
            } catch {
                // This child failed – print a log
                // message with its name then return
                // an empty array.
                print("Loading \(Task.name ?? "Unknown") failed.")
                return []
            }
        }
    }

    var allStories = [NewsStory]()

    for await stories in group {
        allStories.append(contentsOf: stories)
    }

    return allStories.sorted { $0.id &gt; $1.id }
}

print(stories)</code></pre>
<h3>InlineArray, a fixed-size array</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0453-vector.md">SE-0453</a> introduces a new array type called <code>InlineArray</code> that stores an exact number of elements, combining the fixed-size nature of tuples with the natural subscripting of arrays, while adding in some welcome performance improvements at the same time.</p>
<p>Creating an <code>InlineArray</code> can be done with an explicit size or type, or you can let type inference figure out both by the usage. This is made possible by a separate Swift 6.2 improvement, <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0452-integer-generic-parameters.md">SE-0452</a>, which adds integer generic parameters.</p>
<p>So, we can create an inline array of names by specifying both the size and element type:</p>
<pre><code>var names1: InlineArray&lt;4, String&gt; = ["Moon", "Mercury", "Mars", "Tuxedo Mask"]</code></pre>
<p>Or you can let Swift figure it out by passing in exactly four strings:</p>
<pre><code>var names2: InlineArray = ["Moon", "Mercury", "Mars", "Tuxedo Mask"]</code></pre>
<p>Either way, these arrays are fixed in size, so they don't have <code>append()</code> or remove(at:)` methods. However, you <em>can</em> still read and write values at a specific index, like this:</p>
<pre><code>names1[2] = "Jupiter"</code></pre>
<p><code>InlineArray</code> does <em>not</em> conform to either <code>Sequence</code> or <code>Collection</code>, so if you want to loop over their values you should use the <code>indices</code> property along with subscripting like this:</p>
<pre><code>for i in names1.indices {
    print("Hello, \(names1[i])!")
}</code></pre>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Another Swift Evolution proposal, <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0483-inline-array-sugar.md">SE-0483</a>, is currently being discussed, and if it is approved would add an <code>InlineArray</code> literal syntax in the style <code>var names: [5 x String] = .init(repeating: "Anonymous")</code> to mean "exactly five strings in this array." The feedback so far has been broadly negative, so it might be returned for revision.</p>
<h3>Regex lookbehind assertions</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0448-regex-lookbehind-assertions.md">SE-0448</a> expands Swift's regular expression support to include <em>lookbehind assertions</em>, which allow us to check if a specific pattern appears immediately before the current position in the string, <em>without</em> including it in the matched text.</p>
<p>For example, we might want to match all prices inside a string by looking for any numbers that come after a dollar sign, <em>without</em> matching the dollar sign itself:</p>
<pre><code>let string = "Buying a jacket costs $100, and buying shoes costs $59.99."
let regex = /(?&lt;=\$)\d+(?:\.\d{2})?/

for match in string.matches(of: regex) {
    print(match.output)
}</code></pre>
<p>Swift's regular expression system is remarkably powerful, and it's great to see it continue to evolve. Maybe <code>?R</code> recursion will come next…</p>
<h3>Swift Testing: Exit Tests</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/testing/0008-exit-tests.md">ST-0008</a> introduces a testing feature that has been in demand for as long as I can remember: the ability to test code that results in a critical failure that terminated the app.</p>
<p>For example, code like this is going to fail <em>hard</em> if we call it with a <code>sides</code> value of 0:</p>
<pre><code>struct Dice {
    func roll(sides: Int) -&gt; Int {
        precondition(sides &gt; 0)
        return Int.random(in: 1...sides)
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>Running <code>roll(sides: 0)</code> will literally crash the app, which in turn will cause tests to collapse around it. </p>
<p>From Swift 6.2 and later we can use <code>#expect(processExitsWith:)</code> to look for and catch such critical failures, allowing us to check they happened rather than causing our test run to fail.</p>
<p>Here's how it looks in code:</p>
<pre><code>@Test func invalidDiceRollsFail() async throws {
    let dice = Dice()

    await #expect(processExitsWith: .failure) {
        let _ = dice.roll(sides: 0)
    }
}</code></pre>
<p>Notice how it must be executed using <code>await</code> – behind the scenes this starts a dedicated process for that test, then suspends the test until that process completes and can be evaluated.</p>
<p>This improvement opens up a range of things that were hard if not impossible to test before, including a range of hacks designed to test things like <code>fatalError()</code> get called at specific times.</p>
<h3>Swift Testing: Attachments</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/testing/0009-attachments.md">ST-0009</a> adds the ability to add attachments to tests, so that if a test fails you can attach a debug log or generated data files directly to the failing test.</p>
<p>As an example, we could define a simple <code>Character</code> struct such as this one:</p>
<pre><code>import Foundation
import Testing

struct Character: Codable, Attachable {
    var id = UUID()
    var name: String
}</code></pre>
<p>That conforms to the new <code>Attachable</code> protocol, and because it also imports Foundation <em>and</em> conforms to <code>Codable</code>, Swift Testing can automatically encode instances of our struct to be attached to tests.</p>
<p>We can then use that in a trivial function in our production code:</p>
<pre><code>func makeCharacter() -&gt; Character {
    Character(name: "Ram")
}</code></pre>
<p>When it comes to writing a test, we'll make sure the default name matches the value we expect, but we'll also make whatever character we got back from <code>makeCharacter()</code> an attachment with the label "Character":</p>
<pre><code>@Test func defaultCharacterNameIsCorrect() {
    let result = makeCharacter()
    #expect(result.name == "Rem")

    Attachment.record(result, named: "Character")
}</code></pre>
<p>When that test runs, Xcode should in theory automatically surface those attachments for us as part of the test results, although we'll need to wait for an Xcode update in order for that to happen.</p>
<p>Out of the box, Swift Testing provides support for attaching <code>String</code>, <code>Data</code>, and anything that conforms to <code>Encodable</code>. It does <em>not</em> support (at least not in Swift 6.2) attaching images, which is an annoyance –&nbsp;it would be great to attach a SwiftUI image to a failing test, for example.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> Unlike the XCTest equivalent, Swift Testing's attachments do not support lifetime controls in Swift 6.2. If this feature gets added in a future release, it would allow us to automatically delete attachments if a test succeeds, which helps keep tests lightweight.</p>
<h3>Swift Testing: Public API to evaluate ConditionTrait</h3>
<p><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/testing/0010-evaluate-condition.md">ST-0010</a> introduces a new <code>evaluate()</code> method to test condition traits, meaning that it's possible to write non-test functions that evaluate the same conditions as test functions.</p>
<p>It's still possible to use condition traits in the <code>@Test</code> macro, like this:</p>
<pre><code>import Testing

struct TestManager {
    static let inSmokeTestMode = true
}

@Test(.disabled(if: TestManager.inSmokeTestMode))
func runLongComplexTest() {
    // test code here
}</code></pre>
<p>In Swift 6.2 and later you can now evaluate those same conditions <em>outside</em> of tests by creating a condition trait then calling its <code>evaluate()</code> method:</p>
<pre><code>func checkForSmokeTest() async throws {
    let trait = ConditionTrait.disabled(if: TestManager.inSmokeTestMode)

    if try await trait.evaluate() {
        print("We're in smoke test mode")
    } else {
        print("Run all tests.")
    }
}</code></pre>
<h3>And there's more!</h3>
<p>If all the above wasn't enough for you, even more changes are likely also be arriving with Swift 6.2, including:</p>
<ul>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0446-non-escapable.md">SE-0446</a> introduces non-escapable types that cannot outlive the scope of the function where they are created, so they can't be returned or assigned elsewhere.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0447-span-access-shared-contiguous-storage.md">SE-0447</a> builds upon the non-escapable types proposal to add a new <code>Span</code> struct designed to make it easier to safely access contiguous memory.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0457-duration-attosecond-represenation.md">SE-0457</a> upgrades the <code>Duration</code> type to expose the total number of attoseconds (one quintillionth of a second) as an <code>Int128</code>.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0463-sendable-completion-handlers.md">SE-0463</a> changes the rules for Objective-C imports so that completion handler parameters are considered <code>@Sendable</code> unless otherwise request.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0473-clock-epochs.md">SE-0473</a> adds properties to <code>SuspendingClock</code> and <code>ContinuousClock</code> to provide the exact start point for those clocks – the time they consider to be zero.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0474-yielding-accessors.md">SE-0474</a> adds yielding accessors to allow values to be read and written without requiring copies to be made.</li>
<li><a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0480-swiftpm-warning-control.md">SE-0480</a> builds on the diagnostic groups work done in Swift 6.1 so that we can set warning and error levels directly inside Swift packages.</li>
</ul>
<p>There's one more I want to mention briefly, and although it's hard to provide meaningful examples that are easy to understand, I still think this proposal deserves an extra mention because it's just so darned clever. It's <a rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank" href="https://github.com/swiftlang/swift-evolution/blob/main/proposals/0476-abi-attr.md">SE-0476</a>, which introduces a new <code>@abi</code> attribute that makes it easier for ABI-stable library authors to make changes to their libraries without breaking things. This might be something small such as changing from <code>rethrows</code> to typed throws, or, in the words of the evolution proposal, "to rename an API whose name is felt to be catastrophically confusing."</p>
<p>This change is going to be hugely popular with library authors who made small mistakes they wanted to correct afterwards, <em>without</em> breaking code that relies on old behavior.</p>
<p>So, again Swift 6.2 is another gigantic collection of additions and improvements to the language –&nbsp;new features, yes, but also a range of refinements that will continue to help smooth over adoption of Swift concurrency. </p>
<p>As usual, not all features will apply to every project, but I think certainly at least one or two of these changes will grow to become standard practice, and it might not even be the ones you expect –&nbsp;keep an eye on <code>InlineArray</code>!</p>








<p><a href="https://www.hackingwithswift.com/sponsor">Sponsor Hacking with Swift and reach the world's largest Swift community!</a></p>




                        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>