<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 20:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Major AI conference flooded with peer reviews written by AI (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03506-6</link>
            <guid>46088236</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 15:26:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03506-6">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03506-6</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46088236">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-test="access-teaser"> <figure><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://media.nature.com/lw767/magazine-assets/d41586-025-03506-6/d41586-025-03506-6_51767010.jpg?as=webp 767w, https://media.nature.com/lw319/magazine-assets/d41586-025-03506-6/d41586-025-03506-6_51767010.jpg?as=webp 319w" sizes="(max-width: 319px) 319px, (min-width: 1023px) 100vw,  767px"><img alt="Close up view of a red toy robot sat amongst a stack of books." loading="lazy" src="https://media.nature.com/lw767/magazine-assets/d41586-025-03506-6/d41586-025-03506-6_51767010.jpg"><figcaption><p><span>An AI-detection tool developed by Pangram labs found that peer reviewers are increasingly using chatbots to draft responses to authors.</span><span>Credit: breakermaximus/iStock via Getty</span></p></figcaption></picture></figure><p>What can researchers do if they suspect that their manuscripts have been peer reviewed using artificial intelligence (AI)? Dozens of academics have raised concerns on social media about manuscripts and peer reviews submitted to the organizers of next year’s International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), an annual gathering of specialists in machine learning. Among other things, they flagged <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-02853-8" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-02853-8" data-track-category="body text link">hallucinated citations</a> and suspiciously long and vague feedback on their work.</p><p>Graham Neubig, an AI researcher at Carnegie Mellon University in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, was one of those who received peer reviews that seemed to have been<a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03390-0" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-03390-0" data-track-category="body text link"> produced using large language models (LLMs)</a>. The reports, he says, were “very verbose with lots of bullet points” and requested analyses that were not “the standard statistical analyses that reviewers ask for in typical AI or machine-learning papers.”</p><p>But Neubig needed help proving that the reports were AI-generated. So, he posted on X (formerly Twitter) and offered a reward for anyone who could scan all the conference submissions and their peer reviews for AI-generated text. The next day, he got a response from Max Spero, chief executive of Pangram Labs in New York City, which develops tools to detect AI-generated text. Pangram screened all 19,490 studies and 75,800 peer reviews submitted for ICLR 2026, which will take place in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, in April. Neubig and more than 11,000 other AI researchers will be attending.</p><p>Pangram’s analysis revealed that around 21% of the ICLR peer reviews were fully AI-generated, and more than half contained signs of AI use. The findings were <a href="https://www.pangram.com/blog/pangram-predicts-21-of-iclr-reviews-are-ai-generated" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.pangram.com/blog/pangram-predicts-21-of-iclr-reviews-are-ai-generated" data-track-category="body text link">posted online by Pangram Labs</a>. “People were suspicious, but they didn’t have any concrete proof,” says Spero. “Over the course of 12 hours, we wrote some code to parse out all of the text content from these paper submissions,” he adds. </p><p>The conference organizers say they will now use automated tools to assess whether submissions and peer reviews breached policies on using <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-01839-w" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-01839-w" data-track-category="body text link">AI in submissions and peer reviews</a>. This is the first time that the conference has faced this issue at scale, says Bharath Hariharan, a computer scientist at Cornell University in Ithaca, New York, and senior programme chair for ICLR 2026. “After we go through all this process … that will give us a better notion of trust.” </p><h2>AI-written peer review</h2><p>The Pangram team used one of its own tools, which <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-02936-6" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-02936-6" data-track-category="body text link">predicts whether text is generated or edited by LLMs</a>. Pangram’s analysis flagged 15,899 peer reviews that were fully AI-generated. But it also identified many manuscripts that had been submitted to the conference with suspected cases of AI-generated text: 199 manuscripts (1%) were found to be fully AI-generated; 61% of submissions were mostly human-written; but 9% contained more than 50% AI-generated text. </p><p>Pangram described the model in a preprint<sup><a href="#ref-CR1" data-track="click" data-action="anchor-link" data-track-label="go to reference" data-track-category="references">1</a></sup>, which it submitted to ICLR 2026. Of the four peer reviews received for the manuscript, one was flagged as fully AI-generated and another as lightly AI-edited, the team’s analysis found.</p><article data-label="Related"><a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-025-00894-7" data-track="click" data-track-label="recommended article"><img alt="" src="https://media.nature.com/w400/magazine-assets/d41586-025-03506-6/d41586-025-03506-6_50959900.jpg"><p>AI is transforming peer review — and many scientists are worried</p></a></article><p>For many researchers who received peer reviews for their submissions to ICLR, the Pangram analysis confirmed what they had suspected. Desmond Elliott, a computer scientist at the University of Copenhagen, says that one of three reviews he received seemed to have missed “the point of the paper”. His PhD student who led the work suspected that the review was generated by LLMs, because it mentioned numerical results from the manuscript that were incorrect and contained odd expressions. </p><p>When Pangram released its findings, Elliott adds, “the first thing I did was I typed in the title of our paper because I wanted to know whether my student’s gut instinct was correct”. The suspect peer review, which Pangram’s analysis flagged as fully AI-generated, gave the manuscript the lowest rating, leaving it “on the borderline between accept and reject”, says Elliott. “It's deeply frustrating”.</p><h2>Repercussions</h2></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Iceland declares ocean-current instability a national security risk (256 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.dagens.com/news/iceland-declares-ocean-current-instability-a-national-security-risk</link>
            <guid>46088192</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 15:21:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.dagens.com/news/iceland-declares-ocean-current-instability-a-national-security-risk">https://www.dagens.com/news/iceland-declares-ocean-current-instability-a-national-security-risk</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46088192">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			<p>Iceland has classified the potential collapse of a major Atlantic current system as a national security threat, citing new scientific warnings that such a change could radically alter the country’s climate and economy. Officials say the risk represents an “existential” challenge that demands a coordinated, top-level response.</p>

			<div x-data="{
        posts: [],
        loadPosts() {
            try {
                const relatedPostData = JSON.parse(document.getElementById('related-post-data').textContent);
                if (!relatedPostData.length) return;
                let postsToShow = relatedPostData.slice(0);
                                postsToShow = postsToShow.slice(0, 2);
                                this.posts = postsToShow;
            } catch (error) {
                console.error('Error loading related posts:', error);
            }
        }
	}" x-init="loadPosts()">
		<p x-show="posts.length > 0">
			<h2>Others are reading now</h2>
			<template x-for="(post, index) in posts" :key="index">
				<div id="related-post" class="not-prose sm:gap-sm group flex w-full items-center">
					<a :href="post.link">
						<img class="my-0 aspect-square h-full max-h-16 w-auto rounded object-cover hidden sm:block" :src="post.featured_media_url" alt="">
					</a>
					<h3 class="m-0 flex flex-1 flex-col text-base">
						<a class="text-body-text group-hover:text-body-accent font-normal" :href="post.link" x-html="post.title"></a>
					</h3>
				</div>
			</template>
		</p>
	</div>

<p>Iceland has taken the rare step of treating a climate-linked ocean threat as a matter of national survival, launching a coordinated government response to one of the most feared potential tipping points in the climate system.</p>



<p><br>Officials say the shift reflects mounting evidence that a key Atlantic current system could be heading toward dangerous instability.</p>



<h2>Security shift in Reykjavík</h2>



<p>According to <em><a href="https://edition.cnn.com/2025/11/15/climate/iceland-warming-current-amoc-collapse-threat" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CNN</a></em>, Iceland’s National Security Council formally labelled the possible collapse of the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation (AMOC) a national security risk in September — the first time the country has applied such a designation to a climate impact.</p>



<p><br>The move followed a government briefing on new research that raised “grave concerns” about the system’s future stability.</p>



<p>Jóhann Páll Jóhannsson, Iceland’s minister for environment, energy and climate, said the risks extend far beyond weather. </p>
<div x-data="{
        posts: [],
        loadPosts() {
            try {
                const relatedPostData = JSON.parse(document.getElementById('related-post-data').textContent);
                if (!relatedPostData.length) return;
                let postsToShow = relatedPostData.slice(2);
                                postsToShow = postsToShow.slice(0, 2);
                                this.posts = postsToShow;
            } catch (error) {
                console.error('Error loading related posts:', error);
            }
        }
	}" x-init="loadPosts()">
		<p x-show="posts.length > 0">
			<h2>Also read</h2>
			<template x-for="(post, index) in posts" :key="index">
				<div id="related-post" class="not-prose sm:gap-sm group flex w-full items-center">
					<a :href="post.link">
						<img class="my-0 aspect-square h-full max-h-16 w-auto rounded object-cover hidden sm:block" :src="post.featured_media_url" alt="">
					</a>
					<h3 class="m-0 flex flex-1 flex-col text-base">
						<a class="text-body-text group-hover:text-body-accent font-normal" :href="post.link" x-html="post.title"></a>
					</h3>
				</div>
			</template>
		</p>
	</div>



<p>“Our climate, economy and security are deeply tied to the stability of the ocean currents around us,” he told <em>CNN</em>.</p>



<p>He later described the threat as “an existential threat,” warning that a breakdown could disrupt transport, damage infrastructure and hit the country’s fishing industry.</p>



<h2>Why the AMOC matters</h2>



<p>The AMOC — often compared to a giant conveyor belt — carries warm water northward before it cools and sinks, helping regulate weather across the Atlantic basin. </p>



<p><em>CNN </em>reported that scientists increasingly worry that warming temperatures and disrupted salinity levels are slowing the system.</p>



<p>Some studies suggest a tipping point could be reached this century, though the exact timeline remains uncertain.</p>
<div x-data="{
        posts: [],
        loadPosts() {
            try {
                const relatedPostData = JSON.parse(document.getElementById('related-post-data').textContent);
                if (!relatedPostData.length) return;
                let postsToShow = relatedPostData.slice(4);
                                postsToShow = postsToShow.slice(0, 2);
                                this.posts = postsToShow;
            } catch (error) {
                console.error('Error loading related posts:', error);
            }
        }
	}" x-init="loadPosts()">
		<p x-show="posts.length > 0">
			<h2>Also read</h2>
			<template x-for="(post, index) in posts" :key="index">
				<div id="related-post" class="not-prose sm:gap-sm group flex w-full items-center">
					<a :href="post.link">
						<img class="my-0 aspect-square h-full max-h-16 w-auto rounded object-cover hidden sm:block" :src="post.featured_media_url" alt="">
					</a>
					<h3 class="m-0 flex flex-1 flex-col text-base">
						<a class="text-body-text group-hover:text-body-accent font-normal" :href="post.link" x-html="post.title"></a>
					</h3>
				</div>
			</template>
		</p>
	</div>



<p>Stefan Rahmstorf, an oceanographer at Potsdam University, told <em>CNN </em>that a collapse “cannot be considered a low likelihood risk anymore.” </p>



<p>The consequences, he said, would be dramatic: surging sea levels along US and European coasts, major monsoon disruptions across Africa and Asia, and a deep freeze across parts of Europe.</p>



<p>For Iceland, he said, the country “would be close to the center of a serious regional cooling,” with sea ice potentially surrounding the island.</p>



<h2>Preparing for the worst</h2>



<p>The security designation means Iceland will now pursue a high-level, cross-government effort to analyse the threat and consider how to manage or reduce the consequences. Jóhannsson said the decision </p>



<p>“reflects the seriousness of the issue and ensures that the matter gets the attention it deserves.”</p>
<div x-data="{
        posts: [],
        loadPosts() {
            try {
                const relatedPostData = JSON.parse(document.getElementById('related-post-data').textContent);
                if (!relatedPostData.length) return;
                let postsToShow = relatedPostData.slice(6);
                                postsToShow = postsToShow.slice(0, 2);
                                this.posts = postsToShow;
            } catch (error) {
                console.error('Error loading related posts:', error);
            }
        }
	}" x-init="loadPosts()">
		<p x-show="posts.length > 0">
			<h2>Also read</h2>
			<template x-for="(post, index) in posts" :key="index">
				<div id="related-post" class="not-prose sm:gap-sm group flex w-full items-center">
					<a :href="post.link">
						<img class="my-0 aspect-square h-full max-h-16 w-auto rounded object-cover hidden sm:block" :src="post.featured_media_url" alt="">
					</a>
					<h3 class="m-0 flex flex-1 flex-col text-base">
						<a class="text-body-text group-hover:text-body-accent font-normal" :href="post.link" x-html="post.title"></a>
					</h3>
				</div>
			</template>
		</p>
	</div>



<p>Rahmstorf praised Iceland’s stance, telling <em>CNN </em>that other nations should treat the risk with similar urgency.</p>



<p>Jóhannsson said the country is confronting a stark possibility: “What we do know is that the current climate might change so drastically that it could become impossible for us to adapt… this is not just a scientific concern — it’s a matter of national survival and security.” </p>



<p><strong>sources</strong>:CNN</p>
			
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It's Always the Process, Stupid (235 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://its.promp.td/its-always-the-process-stupid/</link>
            <guid>46087737</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 14:20:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://its.promp.td/its-always-the-process-stupid/">https://its.promp.td/its-always-the-process-stupid/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46087737">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

                <a href="https://its.promp.td/tag/article/">Article</a>
            
                <p>Why AI Won’t Save Your Broken Workflow</p>

            <div>
                <p><a href="https://its.promp.td/author/dsb/">
                                <img src="https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w160/2025/08/dsb-slide2016.jpg" alt="DocIsInDaHouse">
                            </a>
                </p>
                <div>
                    
                    <p><time datetime="2025-11-29">29 Nov. 2025</time>
                            <span><span>—</span> 3 min read</span>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>

                <figure>
        <img srcset="https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w320/2025/11/MessyWorkflow.jpeg 320w,
                    https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w600/2025/11/MessyWorkflow.jpeg 600w,
                    https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w960/2025/11/MessyWorkflow.jpeg 960w,
                    https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w1200/2025/11/MessyWorkflow.jpeg 1200w,
                    https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w2000/2025/11/MessyWorkflow.jpeg 2000w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1120px" src="https://its.promp.td/content/images/size/w1200/2025/11/MessyWorkflow.jpeg" alt="It’s Always the Process, Stupid!">
    </figure>

        </div><section>
            <p>Let’s rip the Band-Aid off immediately: If your underlying business process is a mess, sprinkling "AI dust" on it won’t turn it into gold. It will just speed up the rate at which you generate garbage.</p><p>In the world of Business IT, we get seduced by the shiny new toy. Right now, that toy is Artificial Intelligence. Boardrooms are buzzing with buzzwords like LLMs, agentic workflows, and generative reasoning. Executives are frantically asking, <em>"What is our AI strategy?"</em></p><p>But here is the hard truth: </p><blockquote><strong>There is no such thing as an AI strategy. <br>There is only Business Process Optimization (BPO).</strong></blockquote><h3 id="the-magic-wand-fallacy">The "Magic Wand" Fallacy</h3><p>Too many enterprises treat AI like a magic wand. They believe that by implementing a sophisticated neural network, their structural inefficiencies will vanish. They think AI brings intelligence.</p><p>It doesn’t.</p><p>Like every major technological shift before it—from the steam engine to the spreadsheet—AI does not inherently make an organization smarter. <strong>AI, like any other tool, only makes faster.</strong></p><p>If you automate a stupid decision, you just make stupid decisions at light speed. If you apply an agentic AI workflow to a bureaucratic nightmare of an approval chain, you haven't fixed the bureaucracy; you’ve just built a robot that hates its job as much as your employees do.</p><h3 id="the-unstructured-data-trap">The Unstructured Data Trap</h3><p>There is, however, one superpower AI possesses that previous tools lacked: <strong>It is the first technology that is truly useful for handling unstructured data.</strong></p><p>For decades, traditional software demanded structure. Rows, columns, booleans, and fixed fields. If data didn't fit the box, the computer couldn't read it.</p><p>AI changes this. It can read messy emails, interpret vague Slack messages, parse PDFs, and analyze images. But this capability exposes a massive, hidden problem in most enterprises.</p><p><strong>Processes that rely on unstructured data are usually unstructured processes.</strong></p><p>Because computers couldn't handle the mess, humans handled it (before AI). And humans don't always follow a flow chart. These processes—like "handling a complex customer complaint" or "brainstorming a marketing campaign"—are often ad-hoc, intuitive, and completely undocumented. They live in the heads of your senior staff, not in your SOPs.</p><h3 id="you-can%E2%80%99t-automate-what-you-haven%E2%80%99t-designed">You Can’t Automate What You Haven’t Designed</h3><p>This brings us back to BPO. You cannot apply AI to these "hidden" processes until you drag them into the light.</p><p>If you want to use AI to process unstructured data, you must first bring structure to the workflow itself. You need to improve your process design to account for the ambiguity that AI handles.</p><p>Ask yourself:</p><ol><li><strong>What is the trigger?</strong> (Where does the unstructured mess come from?)</li><li><strong>What is the transformation?</strong> (What exactly is the human—or now the AI—supposed to extract or deduce from that mess?)</li><li><strong>What is the structured output?</strong> (How does this flow back into your rigid ERP or CRM systems?)</li></ol><h3 id="speed-vs-intelligence">Speed vs. Intelligence</h3><p>Let’s clarify the distinction between "smarter" and "faster."</p><p>Intelligence implies wisdom, context, and nuance. While AI models are simulating reasoning better every day, in a business context, they are fundamentally pattern-matching engines. They excel at acceleration.</p><ul><li><strong>The Old Way:</strong> An analyst reads 50 contracts (unstructured), highlights risks based on gut feeling (unstructured process), and summarizes them in 3 days.</li><li><strong>The AI Way:</strong> An AI scans 50 contracts and extracts specific risk clauses based on defined parameters in 3 minutes.</li></ul><p>The <em>process</em> (Review Contracts -&gt; Identify Risk -&gt; Summarize) hasn't changed, but it had to be rigorously defined for the AI to work. The <em>intelligence</em> (knowing what a "risk" actually means) still requires human governance. What has changed is the <strong>velocity</strong>.</p><h3 id="the-bottom-line">The Bottom Line</h3><p>Stop chasing the hype. Stop looking for a specialized "AI Savior."</p><p>Go back to the whiteboard. Map out your value chain—especially the messy, human-centric parts involving unstructured data that you previously ignored. Find the bottlenecks. Identify the waste.</p><p>Once you have a streamlined, logical, and robust business process, <em>then</em> apply AI to hit the accelerator.</p><div><p>Technology changes. <br>The rules of business efficiency do not. <br>It’s always the process, stupid!</p><p>And that's where actual AI Tools are missing that point, because they weren't build for that </p></div><figure><a href="https://its.promp.td/the-great-it-divide-why-ai-adoption-in-enterprises-is-failing/"><div><p>The Great IT-Divide: Why AI-Adoption in enterprises is failing</p><p>IT innovation moved from business tools to social tech, creating two distinct IT worlds: Business-IT (compliance, efficiency) and Social-IT (social interaction). Grasping this divide is crucial for enterprise adoption and explains why businesses struggle with AI uptake.</p><p><img src="https://its.promp.td/content/images/icon/promptdIconRoundBlue-1-16.png" alt=""><span>it's promp.td</span><span>DocIsInDaHouse</span></p></div><p><img src="https://its.promp.td/content/images/thumbnail/ITDivide-2.jpg" alt="" onerror="this.style.display = 'none'"></p></a></figure><hr><p>Live long and prosper 😉🖖</p>
        </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DNS LOC Record (2014) (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.cloudflare.com/the-weird-and-wonderful-world-of-dns-loc-records/</link>
            <guid>46087596</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 14:02:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/the-weird-and-wonderful-world-of-dns-loc-records/">https://blog.cloudflare.com/the-weird-and-wonderful-world-of-dns-loc-records/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46087596">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post"><article><p>2014-04-01</p><section><p>2 min read</p><img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/7lCDvfhTzFcVMB5PveKJco/9283bc24e4a11eddef1aa631a61960e9/the-weird-and-wonderful-world-of-dns-loc-records.jpg" alt=""><div><p>A cornerstone of CloudFlare's infrastructure is our ability to serve DNS requests quickly and <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/deep-inside-a-dns-amplification-ddos-attack">handle DNS attacks</a>. To do both those things we wrote our own authoritative DNS server called <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/the-story-of-a-little-dns-easter-egg">RRDNS</a> in Go. Because of it we've been able to fight off DNS attacks, and be consistenly one of the <a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-fastest-free-dns-among-fastest-dns">fastest</a> DNS providers on the web.</p><p>Implementing an authoritative DNS server is a large task. That's in part because DNS is a very old standard (<a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1035.txt">RFC 1035</a> dates to 1987), in part because as DNS has developed it has grown into a more and more complex system, and in part because what's written in the RFCs and what happens in the real-world aren't always the same thing.</p><p>One little used type of DNS record is the LOC (or location). It allows you to specify a physical location. CloudFlare handles millions of DNS records; of those just 743 are LOCs. Nevertheless, it's possible to set up a LOC record in the CloudFlare DNS editor.</p>
            <figure>
            
            <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/SE3YNqdqCWTZjCq2X3204/6350156b41c21658e2c1cafe7780ae4b/480px-Trinity_Site_Obelisk_National_Historic_Landmark.jpg" alt="Trinity" width="480" height="480" loading="lazy">
            
            </figure><p>My site <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20140329092052/http://geekatlas.com/">geekatlas.com</a> has a LOC record as an Easter Egg. Here's how it's configured in the CloudFlare DNS settings:</p>
            <figure>
            
            <img src="https://cf-assets.www.cloudflare.com/zkvhlag99gkb/2Qe1yA3xIACsdf36XEi1oQ/1a078bd649abd88e5b382cab36f748b9/Screen_Shot_2014-03-27_at_11.34.24.png" alt="LOC Example" width="1894" height="96" loading="lazy">
            
            </figure><p>When you operate at CloudFlare scale the little-used nooks and crannies turn out to be important. And even though there are only 743 LOC records in our entire database, at least one customer contacted support to find out why their LOC record wasn't being served.</p><p>And that sent me into the RRDNS source code to find out why.</p><p>The answer was simple. Although RRDNS had code for receiving requests for LOC records, creating response packets containing LOC data, there was a missing link. The CloudFlare DNS server stores the LOC record as a string (such as the <code>33 40 31 N 106 28 29 W 10m</code> above) and no one had written the code to parse that and turn it into the internal format. Oops.</p><p>The textual LOC format and the binary, on-the-wire, format are described in <a href="https://tools.ietf.org/rfc/rfc1876.txt">RFC 1876</a> and it's one of many RFCs that updated the original 1987 standard. RFC 1876 is from 1996.</p><p>The textual format is fairly simple. Here's what the RFC says:</p>
            <pre><code>The LOC record is expressed in a primary file in the following format:

owner TTL class LOC ( d1 [m1 [s1]] {"N"|"S"} d2 [m2 [s2]]
                           {"E"|"W"} alt["m"] [siz["m"] [hp["m"]
                           [vp["m"]]]] )

where:

   d1:     [0 .. 90]            (degrees latitude)
   d2:     [0 .. 180]           (degrees longitude)
   m1, m2: [0 .. 59]            (minutes latitude/longitude)
   s1, s2: [0 .. 59.999]        (seconds latitude/longitude)
   alt:    [-100000.00 .. 42849672.95] BY .01 (altitude in meters)
   siz, hp, vp: [0 .. 90000000.00] (size/precision in meters)

If omitted, minutes and seconds default to zero, size defaults to 1m,
horizontal precision defaults to 10000m, and vertical precision
defaults to 10m.  These defaults are chosen to represent typical
ZIP/postal code area sizes, since it is often easy to find
approximate geographical location by ZIP/postal code.</code></pre>
            <p>So, there are required latitude, longitude and altitude and three optional values for the size of the location and precision information. Pretty simple.</p><p>Then there's the on-the-wire format. Unlike a TXT record the LOC record data is parsed and turned into a fixed size binary format. Back to RFC 1876:</p>
            <pre><code>  MSB                                           LSB
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
  0|        VERSION        |         SIZE          |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
  2|       HORIZ PRE       |       VERT PRE        |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
  4|                   LATITUDE                    |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
  6|                   LATITUDE                    |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
  8|                   LONGITUDE                   |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
 10|                   LONGITUDE                   |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
 12|                   ALTITUDE                    |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+
 14|                   ALTITUDE                    |
   +--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+--+</code></pre>
            <p>So, 32 bits of latitude, longitude and altitude and then three 8 bit values for the size and precision. The latitude and longitude values have a pretty simple encoding that treats the 32 bits as an unsigned integer:</p>
            <pre><code>The latitude of the center of the sphere described by the SIZE field, expressed as a 32-bit integer, most significant octet first (network standard byte order), in thousandths of a second of arc.  2^31 represents the equator; numbers above that are north latitude.</code></pre>
            <p>And the altitude can be below sea-level but still unsigned:</p>
            <pre><code>The altitude of the center of the sphere described by the SIZE field, expressed as a 32-bit integer, most significant octet first (network standard byte order), in centimeters, from a base of 100,000m below the [WGS 84] reference spheroid used by GPS.</code></pre>
            <p>But the 8 bit values use a very special encoding that allows a wide range of approximate values to be packed into 8 bits and also be human-readable when dumped out in hex!</p>
            <pre><code>The diameter of a sphere enclosing the described entity, in centimeters, expressed as a pair of four-bit unsigned integers, each ranging from zero to nine, with the most significant four bits representing the base and the second number representing the power of ten by which to multiply the base.  This allows sizes from 0e0 (&lt;1cm) to 9e9 (90,000km) to be expressed.  This representation was chosen such that the hexadecimal representation can be read by eye; 0x15 = 1e5.</code></pre>
            <p>For example, the value <code>0x12</code> means <code>1 * 10^2</code> or 100cm. <code>0x99</code> means <code>9 * 10^9</code> or 90,000,000m. The smallest value that can be represented is 1cm (it's <code>0x10</code>). So, in just 8 bits there's a range values from 1cm to larger than the diameter of Jupiter.</p><p>To fix this I wrote a parser for the LOC text record type (and associated tests). It can be found <a href="https://gist.github.com/jgrahamc/9807839">here</a>.</p><p>We've now rolled out the fix and all the existing LOC records are being served by RRDNS. For example, my <code>geekatlas.com</code> LOC record can be queried like this:</p>
            <pre><code>$ dig geekatlas.com LOC
; &lt;&lt;&gt;&gt; DiG 9.8.3-P1 &lt;&lt;&gt;&gt; geekatlas.com LOC
;; global options: +cmd
;; Got answer:
;; -&gt;&gt;HEADER&lt;&lt;- opcode: QUERY, status: NOERROR, id: 2997
;; flags: qr rd ra; QUERY: 1, ANSWER: 1, AUTHORITY: 0, ADDITIONAL: 0

;; QUESTION SECTION:    
;geekatlas.com.         IN  LOC

;; ANSWER SECTION:
geekatlas.com.      299 IN  LOC 33 40 31.000 N 106 28 29.000 W 10.00m 1m 10000m 10m

;; Query time: 104 msec
;; SERVER: 192.168.14.1#53(192.168.14.1)
;; WHEN: Tue Apr  1 14:13:48 2014
;; MSG SIZE  rcvd: 59</code></pre>
            </div></section><div><p>Cloudflare's connectivity cloud protects <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/network-services/" rel="noreferrer">entire corporate networks</a>, helps customers build <a target="_blank" href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="noreferrer">Internet-scale applications efficiently</a>, accelerates any <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/performance/accelerate-internet-applications/" rel="noreferrer">website or Internet application</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/ddos/" rel="noreferrer">wards off DDoS attacks</a>, keeps <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/application-security/" rel="noreferrer">hackers at bay</a>, and can help you on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/products/zero-trust/" rel="noreferrer">your journey to Zero Trust</a>.</p><p>Visit <a target="_blank" href="https://one.one.one.one/" rel="noreferrer">1.1.1.1</a> from any device to get started with our free app that makes your Internet faster and safer.</p><p>To learn more about our mission to help build a better Internet, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/what-is-cloudflare/" rel="noreferrer">start here</a>. If you're looking for a new career direction, check out <a target="_blank" href="https://www.cloudflare.com/careers" rel="noreferrer">our open positions</a>.</p></div><astro-slot> <!--[if astro]>server-island-start<![endif]--> </astro-slot><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/rrdns/">RRDNS</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/dns/">DNS</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/reliability/">Reliability</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/attacks/">Attacks</a><a href="https://blog.cloudflare.com/tag/go/">Go</a></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Leak confirms OpenAI is preparing ads on ChatGPT for public roll out (447 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/artificial-intelligence/leak-confirms-openai-is-preparing-ads-on-chatgpt-for-public-roll-out/</link>
            <guid>46086771</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 11:31:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/artificial-intelligence/leak-confirms-openai-is-preparing-ads-on-chatgpt-for-public-roll-out/">https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/artificial-intelligence/leak-confirms-openai-is-preparing-ads-on-chatgpt-for-public-roll-out/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46086771">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	   
<p><img alt="GPT" height="900" src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/content/hl-images/2023/03/24/ChatGPT-logo.jpg" width="1600"></p>


<p>OpenAI is now internally testing 'ads' inside ChatGPT that could redefine the web economy.</p>


<p>Up until now, the ChatGPT experience has been completely&nbsp;free. While there are premium plans and models, you don't see GPT sell you products or show ads.</p>


<p>As <a href="https://x.com/btibor91/status/1994714152636690834" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">spotted </a>by Tibor on X,&nbsp;ChatGPT Android app 1.2025.329 beta includes new references to an "ads feature" with "bazaar content", "search ad" and "search ads carousel."</p>

<p><a href="https://www.wiz.io/lp/ai-data-security-best-practices-cheat-sheet?utm_source=bleepingcomputer&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=FY26Q3_INB_Form_AI-Data-Security-Best-Practices&amp;sfcid=701Py00000SmgsrIAB&amp;utm_term=FY26Q4-bleepingcomputer-970x250&amp;utm_content=AI-Data-Security-BP" rel="nofollow noopener" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/c/w/wiz/AI-Data-Security-970x250.png" alt="Wiz"></a>
</p>


<p>It is likely that ads will be limited to the search experience only, but that might change soon.</p>


<p>My understanding is that GPT ads could be highly personalised as the AI knows everything about you unless you disable the feature,</p>


<p><em>This is a developing story...</em></p>



	   


<div>
    <p><a href="https://www.wiz.io/lp/secrets-security-cheat-sheet?utm_source=bleepingcomputer&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=FY26Q3_INB_FORM_Secret-Security-Sprawl-to-Control&amp;sfcid=701Py00000T0tF9IAJ&amp;utm_term=FY26Q4-bleepingcomputer-article-ad&amp;utm_content=Secrets-Security" target="_blank" rel="noopener sponsored">
            <img src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/c/w/wiz/Secrets-Security-512x512.png" alt="Wiz">
        </a>
    </p>
    <div>
        <h2><a href="https://www.wiz.io/lp/secrets-security-cheat-sheet?utm_source=bleepingcomputer&amp;utm_medium=display&amp;utm_campaign=FY26Q3_INB_FORM_Secret-Security-Sprawl-to-Control&amp;sfcid=701Py00000T0tF9IAJ&amp;utm_term=FY26Q4-bleepingcomputer-article-ad&amp;utm_content=Secrets-Security" target="_blank" rel="noopener sponsored">Secrets Security Cheat Sheet: From Sprawl to Control </a></h2>
<p>Whether you're cleaning up old keys or setting guardrails for AI-generated code, this guide helps your team build securely from the start.</p>
<p>Get the cheat sheet and take the guesswork out of secrets management.</p>

        </div>
</div>

           
          
 
	  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Belgian Police exposed using botnets to manipulate EU data law impact assessment (169 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/europe/comments/1p9kxhm/belgian_federal_police_forgot_to_turn_their_vpn/</link>
            <guid>46086681</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 11:10:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/europe/comments/1p9kxhm/belgian_federal_police_forgot_to_turn_their_vpn/">https://old.reddit.com/r/europe/comments/1p9kxhm/belgian_federal_police_forgot_to_turn_their_vpn/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46086681">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><blockquote>
<p>EU is not a federation</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This part is arguable, because it isn't a federation indeed, but it's not <em>not</em> one either. </p>

<p>The EU doesn't check any box of existing institutions; it's a <em>sui generis</em> entity that mixes intergovernmental, confederal &amp; federal attributes. It's pretty much unique, and cannot really be compared to anything else.</p>

<p>But you're technically correct.</p>



<blockquote>
<p>EU has actually quite little power. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>This part is just downright bullshit, however.</p>

<p>The EU literally has more exclusive regulatory power than the US federal government in several key areas, notably market regulation, labour legislation, environment regulation, and a few others, which are all very much central to the attributes of sovereign states.</p>



<p>That being said, your answer is pretty much irrelevant to the question the OP asked, though. You're missing his point entirely, and it feels like you just wanted to take a jab at the EU.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[High air pollution could diminish exercise benefits by half – study (160 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://scienceclock.com/exercise-may-protect-less-when-air-pollution-is-high-study-finds/</link>
            <guid>46086624</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 10:54:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://scienceclock.com/exercise-may-protect-less-when-air-pollution-is-high-study-finds/">https://scienceclock.com/exercise-may-protect-less-when-air-pollution-is-high-study-finds/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46086624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
<p>We all know exercise is good for us. It lowers the risk of heart disease, cancer, and early death, and keeps the body and mind in shape. But when the air you breathe is polluted, a <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-025-04496-y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">new study</a> suggests that exercise might not provide the same benefits it normally would.</p>



<p>An international team, including researchers from University College London (UCL) analyzed health data from over 1.5 million adults, collected over more than a decade in countries including the UK, Taiwan, China, Denmark, and the United States.</p>



<p>The researchers focused on levels of fine <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Particulate_matter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">particulate matter</a>, specifically tiny particles known as <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1186/s12916-025-04496-y" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PM<sub>2.5</sub></a>. These fine particles are smaller than 2.5 micrometers; they can get stuck in the lungs and enter the bloodstream, where they can trigger inflammation and long-term damage.</p>



<p><strong>Also Read: </strong><a href="https://scienceclock.com/humans-have-titled-the-earth-31-5-inches-since-1993-study-finds/"><strong>Humans Have Tilted the Earth 31.5 Inches Since 1993, Study Finds</strong></a></p>




<p>Researchers found that adults who exercised at least two and a half hours a week—moderate to vigorous activity like jogging or other sports—typically had a 30% lower risk of dying during the study period than less active people. But in areas where the yearly average PM<sub>2.5</sub> exceeded 25 μg/m³, the protective effects of exercise dropped to just 12–15%.</p>



<p>The protective effects of <a href="https://scienceclock.com/why-audiences-doubt-the-most-attractive-fitness-influencers-according-to-new-research/">exercise</a> weaken even further in more polluted regions. At PM<sub>2.5</sub> levels above 35 μg/m³, where about a third (<a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1107581#:~:text=At%20higher%20levels%20of%20fine%20particle%20pollution%2C%20above%2035%20%CE%BCg/m%C2%B3%2C%20the%20benefits%20of%20exercise%20weakened%20further%2C%20particularly%20for%20risk%20of%20death%20from%20cancer%2C%20where%20the%20benefits%20were%20no%20longer%20robust.%20About%20a%20third%20of%20the%20world%E2%80%99s%20population%20(36%25)%20live%20in%20areas%20whose%20yearly%20average%20PM2.5%20levels%20exceed%2035%20%CE%BCg/m%C2%B3." target="_blank" rel="noopener">36%</a>) of the global population lives, exercise offered even less protection, particularly against the risk of death from cancer.</p>



<p>“Our findings emphasise that exercise remains beneficial even in polluted <a href="https://scienceclock.com/category/environment/">environments</a>,” lead researcher Professor Po-Wen Ku <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1107581" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said in a statement</a>. “But improving air quality can significantly enhance these health gains.”</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="682" src="https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-1024x682.jpg" alt="man, training, lazy, tired, fitness, exercise, motivation, gym, workout, male, sport, active, activity, fit, stress, stressed, burnout, lazy, lazy, lazy, lazy, lazy" srcset="https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-300x200.jpg 300w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-768x512.jpg 768w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-330x220.jpg 330w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-420x280.jpg 420w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-615x410.jpg 615w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768-860x573.jpg 860w, https://scienceclock.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/5530768.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"><figcaption>(Photo by <a href="https://pixabay.com/users/Sammy-Sander-10634669/?utm_source=instant-images&amp;utm_medium=referral" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sammy-Sander</a> on <a href="https://pixabay.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pixabay</a>)</figcaption></figure>



<p>Co-author Professor Andrew Steptoe <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1107581" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said</a>, “Our study shows that toxic air can, to some extent, block the benefits of exercise, although not eliminate them. The findings are further evidence of the damage that fine particle pollution can do to <a href="https://scienceclock.com/category/health/">our health</a>.</p>




<p>“We believe clean air and physical activity are both important for healthy ageing, and so we encourage greater efforts to curb health-harming pollution levels.”</p>



<p>The study looked at the data from seven existing studies, including three previously unpublished datasets, combining both summary statistics and raw participant-level data. Researchers carefully accounted for a wide range of other factors, including income, education, smoking, and pre-existing chronic conditions. </p>



<p><strong>Also Read: </strong><a href="https://scienceclock.com/men-need-more-exercise-than-women-to-lower-the-heart-disease-risk/"><strong>Men Need More Exercise Than Women to Lower the Heart Disease Risk</strong></a></p>



<p>However, the team points out that their data mostly comes from high-income countries, so the impact could be greater in low-income regions, where PM<sub>2.5</sub> levels often exceed 50 μg/m³. They also mention the lack of indoor air quality data and limited information on participants’ diets as part of the study’s caveats.</p>




<p>“We don’t want to discourage people from exercising outdoors,” <a href="https://www.eurekalert.org/news-releases/1107581" target="_blank" rel="noopener">said </a>Co-author Professor Paola Zaninotto. “Checking air quality, choosing cleaner routes, or easing off intensity on polluted days can help you get the most health benefits from your exercise.”</p>



<p>The study reminds us of one of the world’s most serious problems: <a href="https://scienceclock.com/carbon-offsets-play-a-negligible-role-in-corporate-climate-action-and-emission-reductions/">air pollution</a>. Staying active is not enough to protect your health if the air around you is toxic. Cleaner air and regular exercise go hand in hand, and tackling pollution is not just about the environment—it’s about our bodies too.</p>



<p>The study was published in <a href="https://doi.org/10.1186/s12916-025-04496-y" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><em>BMC Medicine</em></a>. </p>



<hr>







<!-- CONTENT END 1 -->
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Garfield's Proof of the Pythagorean Theorem (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garfield%27s_proof_of_the_Pythagorean_theorem</link>
            <guid>46085585</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 06:37:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garfield%27s_proof_of_the_Pythagorean_theorem">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garfield%27s_proof_of_the_Pythagorean_theorem</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46085585">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Garfield%27s_proof_of_the_Pythagorean_theorem: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The 'S&P 493' reveals a different U.S. economy (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.msn.com/en-us/money/markets/the-s-p-493-reveals-a-very-different-us-economy/ar-AA1R1VUJ</link>
            <guid>46085344</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 05:22:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.msn.com/en-us/money/markets/the-s-p-493-reveals-a-very-different-us-economy/ar-AA1R1VUJ">https://www.msn.com/en-us/money/markets/the-s-p-493-reveals-a-very-different-us-economy/ar-AA1R1VUJ</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46085344">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[System 7 natively boots on the Mac mini G4 (302 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://macos9lives.com/smforum/index.php?topic=7711.0</link>
            <guid>46084956</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 03:26:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://macos9lives.com/smforum/index.php?topic=7711.0">https://macos9lives.com/smforum/index.php?topic=7711.0</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46084956">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="msg_59712"><p>(And Mac OS 8!)</p><p>Hey, guys!</p><p>Surely y'all know and have enjoyed Mac OS 9.2.2 booting and beautifully-running on all four Mac mini G4 models for close to 8 years now. (Wow!)</p><p>Well, that was one massive revolution...</p><p>... But most of us did not think we would live to see the day New World ROM machines, even more so the likes of the Mac mini G4, to NATIVELY boot System 7:</p><p><img src="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/ea941d2fe9ea40eda5ef21b98235a199.jpg" alt="" width="640" height="480"></p><p>(Gotta love it trying to display 1 GB RAM capacity.)</p><p>Before your eyeballs leave your eyesockets completely, I ought to warn that there's still much to be sorted out in this, especially sound, video and networking (the usual suspects). In other words, your mileage may vary, so keep expectations in check!</p><p><strong>========================================================<br>OK, so HOW in the WORLD is any of this possible?<br>========================================================</strong></p><p>It turned out "New World ROM" Macs had a cousin born out of the clone program (until the usual villain, Steve Jobs, came and killed it), which was an architecture called "<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_Hardware_Reference_Platform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CHRP</a>" (pronounced "chirp"). It was the successor to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/PowerPC_Reference_Platform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PReP</a>, but, unlike PReP, Mac OS was also going to be officially-bootable on it. Close to no CHRP machines ever saw the light of the day, thanks to Jobs' return. Nonetheless, Apple internally developed Mac OS 7.6 ~ 8.0 for CHRP systems before it got axed. It's just that they never released it, but the development was done regardless. On October 2025, it turned out someone preserved some of these Mac versions, which were then acquired and preserved and shared with the world. (<a href="http://www.macintoshgarden.org/apps/mac-os-chrp-releases-powerpc-common-hardware-reference-platform" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Macintosh Garden link</a>, <a href="https://archive.org/details/apple-mac-os-for-CHRP-PowerPC-Common-Hardware-Reference-Platform-Systems-1997/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">archive.org link</a>.)</p><p>Although CHRP was left to die, the so-called "New World ROM" Macs inherited much of its architecture and design. As you probably know, these Macs rely on an extra system file called "Mac OS ROM", whereas "Old World ROM" Macs do not need it, and can use their own actual ROM to get Mac OS going. This meant any Mac OS version unaware of the concept of a Mac OS ROM file could not just simply boot in a New World ROM Mac normally. People were able to boot Mac OS versions as low as 8.1, but not any lower, and that too only for the very first few New World ROM Macs, but none of the later ones, which increasingly had a higher and higher minimum OS version.</p><p>But not anymore, as the following major events happened:</p><p>- The recent Mac OS 8.0 CHRP leaks provided an earlier ROM file that, it turns out, allows regular Mac OS 8.0 to boot, as well. Or, alternatively, the Mac OS ROM file that always worked with Mac OS 8.1 also worked on these Mac OS 8.0 CHRP releases. (Exact details are fuzzy in my memory by now, so someone else might want to correct me if I got something wrong.)</p><p>- The recent Mac OS 7.6 CHRP leak provided an additional System Enabler file, which could be exploited for loading Mac OS ROM files. I forget if that's how it worked out-of-the-box, or if a bit of hacking to the System Enabler was required for that, however what I do remember clearly is that, while the System Enabler was hardcoded so that artifically no OS earlier than 7.6 could use it, the OS version check could be patched out of it, so that System 7.5.x (and potentially earlier) can also use it.<br>In other words, <em>this file is the reason that earlier Mac OS versions can make use of the Mac OS ROM file</em>, thus bringing Mac OS 7.6.1 and earlier potentially to ALL New World ROM Macs!<br>(Trivia tidbit: Apparently this enabler was also present in certain archives of the Mac OS 8.0 betas from when it was still known as "Mac OS 7.7". Oops! This thing was right under our nose all this while!)</p><p>- Of course, as hinted at previously, a System Enabler _alone_ is NOT enough to boot System 7 and the like when even much newer systems that were already aware of the Mac OS ROM file could not boot. The newer the model of the New World ROM Mac, the less you could actually "go back". The reason is simple: Mac OS ROM files, over time through its various versions, would get new features added, BUT also would remove older ones which were required by older OS versions. The solution? Using <a href="https://github.com/elliotnunn/tbxi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">ELN's great Mac OS ROM patching tools</a> (plus other tools of his own), "Rairii" AKA "Wack0", known for his amazing PPC Windows NT 3.51 / NT 4.0 project on <a href="https://github.com/Wack0/maciNTosh" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">PowerMacs</a> and the <a href="https://github.com/Wack0/entii-for-workcubes" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nintendo GC / Wii / Wii U</a>, analyzed many of these Mac OS ROM files, and fixed + patched + stitched together new Mac OS ROM files that attempt to keep ALL the old features that were removed AND all the new features that were added. In other words, the ultimate Mac OS ROM file that boots everything and runs everything (roughly-speaking). He also is the one who figured out and hacked the System Enabler to also accept OSes earlier than Mac OS 7.6.</p><p>Keep in mind, however, that this effort essentially allows Macs that are already able to boot SOME version of Mac OS to ALSO boot older versions. But if a given machine cannot boot ANY Mac OS version, such as the two DLSD PowerBook G4s (<a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/powerbook_g4/specs/powerbook_g4_1.67_15_hr.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">15"</a>, <a href="https://everymac.com/systems/apple/powerbook_g4/specs/powerbook_g4_1.67_17_hr.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">17"</a>), these patches cannot do anything about that: Their incompatibilities need to be addressed first and separately.</p><p>One more interesting thing to note about the similarity between CHRP systems and New World ROM Macs: If you check ANY "Mac OS ROM" file to see its TYPE and CREATOR codes, you will see they are "tbxi" and, you guessed it, "<strong>chrp</strong>", respectively. I couldn't believe "chrp" was in ALL the Mac OS ROM files all these years!</p><p><strong>========================================================<br>Where can I get ahold of this EPIC stuff ? ? ? ? ?<br>========================================================</strong></p><p>Rairii's "super" ROMs are available on <a href="https://github.com/Wack0/universal-tbxi-patchset" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this GitHub repository</a>, under <a href="https://github.com/Wack0/universal-tbxi-patchset/releases" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">releases</a>. You may also fetch the patched System Enabler for Mac OS 7.6.1 and earlier from there, and place it in the System Folder. Make sure to download the files from the latest release there.</p><p>Note that he applied his patches to 3 different versions of the (US) ROMs:</p><p>- 10.2.1 with CPU Software 5.9: The "latest and greatest" Mac OS ROM file of all Mac OS. For reference, this is also the ROM version that the <a href="http://www.macintoshgarden.org/apps/mac-os-9-roms-without-15-gb-limit" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">1.628 GB max RAM Mac OS ROM we have was based on (thus going beyond the 1.5 GB limit)</a>, although do note that the RAM limit break patches are NOT included in this, at least not yet as of the time of writing.</p><p>- 2.5.1: A much earlier version of the ROM, but still new enough to support USB. See the GitHub page for details.</p><p>- 1.7.1: A very early ROM, which can be well-leveraged by very early New World ROM Macs. See the GitHub page for details.</p><p>Note you need ROM version 9.1 or higher to use ATA-6 AKA Ultra ATA/100 AKA Kauai drivers, which are essential on the likes of the Mac mini G4 and the MDD. Special notes for the Mac mini G4 are further down.</p><p><strong>========================================================<br>What is the COMPLETE list of Mac OS versions that now boot?<br>========================================================</strong></p><p>To be exact, this is the complete list of OSes I have attempted, all on the Mac mini G4 1.5GHz model, with the following results:</p><p>- System 6.0.8: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/eecf1c7de4ff43ca851785c566422bd4.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">No boot</a>. You get a Happy Mac, followed by a blinking question mark in a floppy icon. (Note: Although this very attempt is UTTERLY insane for multiple technical reasons, it might be not AS seemingly-impossible as one may think, as the 68k emulator resides within the Mac OS ROM file.)</p><p>- System 7.0: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/b1fc8c2fe35d4cd4a5b3bf0047f9d7e2.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">No boot</a>. You get a Happy Mac, but then a warning window pops up saying System 7.0 cannot boot on this computer.</p><p>- System 7.1.2: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/17bf3873e4c1477899938addae65ab8f.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">No boot</a>. You get a Happy Mac, but then a warning window pops up saying System 7.1 cannot boot on this computer.</p><p>- System 7.5: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/ea941d2fe9ea40eda5ef21b98235a199.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BOOTS AND IS STABLE</a>. It requires you to hold shift to turn Extensions (and Control Panels / INITs) off, though, or to get rid of the "Mouse" Control Panel (and possibly more). The system is surprisingly stable! I tested the British version of this one, as Apple's Mac OS Anthology discs did not include the US installers, for some very slacker-y reason.</p><p>- System 7.5.2: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/0ba4006b498a47e78e44b63f51fb0e61.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Boots, but very broken, close to nothing works</a>. It could be because System 7.5.2 was always VERY machine-specific, and is apparently one of the most broken versions of Mac OS of ALL time, regardless. The machine-specific enablers, and other things, might be what is making it so unstable.</p><p>- System 7.5.3: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/f7727e4e760447f986ee90cf58e0052f.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BOOTS AND IS STABLE</a>. It requires you to hold shift to turn Extensions (and Control Panels / INITs) off, though, or to get rid of the "Mouse" Control Panel (and possibly more). The system is surprisingly stable!</p><p>- Mac OS 7.6: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/9bc2c9a93e9344aba07960841287a9ab.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BOOTS AND IS STABLE</a>. Holding shift is not required here. What else can I say? It "works".</p><p>- Mac OS 8.1: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/49fd379b1e014e24801968343b71d892.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">BOOTS AND IS STABLE</a>. Holding shift is not required here, either. Behaves much the same as the others, except we now have HFS+ by default. Still, it did NOT like me having a 940 GB HFS+ partition, and prompted me to either eject it or format it. (To be fair, older OSes tried to do that, too, but Mac OS 8.1 was THE OS to _officially_ be able to handle HFS+ properly, so there are no excuses for it to fail here. Mac OS 9.2 ~ 9.2.2 all work perfectly with it.)</p><p>- Mac OS 8.5: No boot. Rather, it seems like it WOULD boot, but starting with Mac OS 8.5, Mac OS now always checks to see if the machine you are booting from is within a list of Apple-endorsed machine IDs for the given Mac OS version. In other words, Mac OS 8.5 does not know what the Mac mini G4 is, nor what a G4 Cube is (our Mac mini G4 ROM file makes the mini pretend to be the latter). It seems it should be possible to patch out the machine check. According to Rairii, this should be able to be patched out by disabling such a check on the "boot" resource in the Resource Fork of the System file, in ID 3 (also known as "boot3"). For Mac OS 8.6, it seems like this check happens at the end of boot3, wherever a check for machine ID 406 is located, in which after it's detected, the code checks to see if the exact Mac model is whitelisted or not.</p><p>- Mac OS 8.5.1: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/7502a600acc044069a280aa4b6bccc1c.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">No boot</a>. All that applies to Mac OS 8.5 also applies to Mac OS 8.5.1.</p><p>- Mac OS 8.6: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/412760cddd8e4561aac7e16ca413cc04.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">No boot</a>. It crashes during the start screen, when the loading bar appears, but before the first extension gets to load. See the top-left corner of the picture for a glitchy visual artifact. Same happens if you try to boot with Extensions off.</p><p>- Mac OS 9.0.4: No boot. It crashes during the start screen, when the loading bar appears, but before the first extension gets to load. Same happens if you try to boot with Extensions off. Exact same symptoms as when trying to boot Mac OS 8.6 at least on this mini model, including the visual artifact on the top-left corner.</p><p>- Mac OS 9.1: <a href="http://revontulet.org/2025/11/27/7765c9186c3a43549015719de3a26387.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">No boot</a>. It crashes during the start screen, when the loading bar appears, but before the first extension gets to load. Same happens if you try to boot with Extensions off. Exact same symptoms as when trying to boot Mac OS 8.6 and Mac OS 9.0.4 at least on this mini model, including the visual artifact on the top-left corner.</p><p>- Mac OS 9.2 ~ 9.2.2: BEST OS EVER, BOOTS AND RUNS BEAUTIFULLY. 'Nuff said.</p><p>Note that, although I describe many of these as "stable", I mean you can use much of it normally (sound/video/networking aside) without it crashing or misbehaving, at least not too hard, but that is not to say everything works, because that is just not the case. For example, when present, avoid opening the Apple System Profiler, unless you want a massive crash as it struggles trying to profile and gather all the information about your system. Some other apps or Control Panels might either not work, or work up to a certain point, after which they might freeze, requiring you to Force Quit the Finder to keep on going. And so on.</p><p>As you can see, I did not yet try System 7.5.5, Mac OS 7.6.1 and Mac OS 8.0. That's because they all are most likely working exactly as their neighbouring versions. But feel free to confirm.</p><p>Most non-mini systems should be able to boot Mac OS 8.6 ~ Mac OS 9.1 just fine. A "Mac OS 8.6 Enabler", so to speak, by LightBulbFun, can be renamed as e.g. "Sawteeth" and put inside the System Folder for some machines that cannot boot Mac OS 8.6 normally, so that they can, then, boot it. It is actually a Mac OS ROM file, but can function as a complementary, helper file to aid the actual Mac OS ROM file in this case. If you'd like, check <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/mac-os-8-6-for-some-unsupported-g3s-and-g4s.46765/page-3#post-575895" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a> for more info. I have attached "Sawteeth.bin" to this post for convenience. LightBulbFun first shared it on <a href="https://forums.macrumors.com/threads/mac-os-8-6-findings-and-ramblings.2021922/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">this post</a>, specifically through this <a href="https://mega.nz/file/VUgFAKZR#xXTi_4BK2wJHU8QYCoqyNIjq2aZFPFnM7B4JlmY1lRk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MEGA link</a>.</p><p>Most non-mini systems should also be able to boot Mac OS 8.5 and 8.5.1, especially on G3s and earlier. Some G4 Macs might need to spoof the Mac model in Open Firmware (or some other Forth script added to ROM) to boot, though, or patch the check out like I mentioned for the mini earlier. The reason the mini doesn't have the spoofing as an option is that any spoofing in OF would be overwritten by its own specialized Mac OS ROM, which spoofs a G4 Cube, which is clearly not in the whitelist of supported machines for Mac OS 8.5 and 8.5.1.</p><p>Also note that the mini behaves as reported above with Mac OS 8.6 with or without this "8.6 enabler" file (and with or without the System Enabler for Mac OS 7.6.1 and earlier, both of which don't seem to get in the way of later, nor earlier, OSes).</p><p>Most importantly, I did <em>not</em> yet attempt to identify which are the latest versions of each Control Panel and Extension for each of these OSes. If I did, I'm sure it would help a lot, and perhaps address quite a number of these problems. The more people chime in on this effort, the better! Imagine if we had a proper "Mac mini G4 System 7.5.5" CD, then an "MDD Mac OS 8.5.1" CD, then an "iBook G3 Mac OS 7.6.1" CD, and so on. Everyone with a G3 or G4 Mac can help by trying things out!</p><p>Namely, something akin to MacTron's efforts highlighting the latest Extensions for Mac OS 9.2.2 and Mac OS 8.6 like this, but also for every other Mac OS version:</p><p><img src="http://revontulet.org/2020/01/14/extensions.jpg" alt=""></p><p><strong>========================================================<br>But how did you get the mini to boot? It requires its own special ROM!<br>========================================================</strong></p><p>Indeed it does! All credit goes to ELN and all of those who helped him on Mac OS 9 Lives!: you can simply use his tooling (which was also very useful for Rairii) to re-apply the Mac-mini-G4-specific ROM patches to Rairii's latest 10.2.1 ROM, and voila! It works as well as you would hope it to! </p><p>You can even use the resulting ROM for Mac OS 9.2.2, as well, even though you don't have to: Originally, the Mac mini G4 ROM as we see them in RossDarker's Mac mini G4 CDs version 8 and 9 (AKA v8 and v9), as well as in all the previous versions, were based on the US ROM v9.6.1. I could not find an explanation as to why ROM v10.2.1 wasn't used in the end, even when digging the old Mac mini G4 thread again that started it all. Perhaps because we already had a working ROM with v9.6.1 and did not want to risk breaking anything, or who knows. However, I have thoroughly tested Mac OS 9.2.2 with this new ROM combination (latest Rairii 10.2.1 + latest Mac mini G4 patches AKA v9 patches), and from what I could tell, everything behaves <em>exactly</em> the same as with the previous ROM we always used. Except now we have the ability to use the same ROM to also boot System 7.5 (I still can't believe this, even though it is true).</p><p>(For the record, while the 9.6.1 ROM was also modified to spoof the Mac mini G4 model identifier as a G4 Cube, we also tried to spoof it as a QuickSilver 2002 at one point, but someone reported sound issues with that, and so it was quickly changed back to a G4 Cube and such a change never made it into one of RossDarker's CDs. So just about everyone using Mac OS on the mini for all these years has had a ROM reporting to the OS as a G4 Cube, exclusively.)</p><p>To apply the Mac mini G4 patches, I used ELN's <a href="https://github.com/elliotnunn/tbxi" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tbxi</a> and <a href="https://github.com/elliotnunn/tbxi-patches" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">tbxi-patches</a> to apply his "macmini.py" script. You can follow the instructions as per the tbxi-patches page, which you should not let intimidate you even if you are not used to this kind of thing. It's quick and easy, and the scripts are also fully-commentated very nicely by ELN if you are curious about what it is doing and why.</p><p>In my case, first I tried using the latest Python 3.13.9 both from Windows 7 (bad idea due to resource fork loss) and macOS 10.14.6 Mojave, but neither worked: it seems like that version of Python was just too new. I then retried with <em>Python 3.8.10</em> instead (which I chose thinking it might be more period-appropriate for the script's age) on Mojave, which worked <em>flawlessly</em>. I didn't try it, but perhaps an older Python version might work on PowerPC OS X, as well.</p><p>I used the Python installer <a href="https://www.python.org/downloads/macos/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">from the official website</a>, and I also used an "official" Git installer from <a href="https://downloads.sourceforge.net/project/git-osx-installer/git-2.33.0-intel-universal-mavericks.dmg" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a> (thus avoiding any package manager headache... man, how I hate non-Mac-OS systems, including OS X, and package managers in general...)</p><p>If somehow someone with plenty of Python knowledge and the willingness to put enough time into it wished to, both tbxi and tbxi-tools could, perhaps, be ported to <a href="http://www.macintoshgarden.org/apps/macpython-233" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">MacPython 2.3.5</a>, so that we could do all this patching from Mac OS 9.2.2 directly and natively without leaving our main OS. That would also be awesome! (Of course, it helps that this is also available on more recent systems nonetheless, because then everyone gets to join in on the fun with all kinds of different backgrounds and setups.)</p><p>For convenience, I attached the final patched ROM to this post, so that anyone can go wild on their minis right away!</p><p><strong>========================================================<br>Why should I care when Mac OS 9.2.2 already boots, and runs better?<br>========================================================</strong></p><p>It is also my opinion Mac OS 9.2.2 is the greatest OS, and Mac OS, ever, but not everything that is possible in earlier Mac OS versions is possible in Mac OS 9.2.2. For example, some software requires Mac OS 9.0.4 or earlier to work. A lot of software is System-7-exclusive.</p><p>Some people also just prefer the likes of System 7 for its even-lighter memory footprint, lack of mandated Appearance Manager and the like. Mac OS 9.2.2 is already overkill-fast on the mini, and on most New World ROM Macs, but the likes of System 7.5 are just RIDICULOUSLY fast. Even more ridiculously. I still am trying to come into terms with how indescribably fast using it on the mini was. It got even faster when I thought there was no way to get "faster than instantaneous", as Mac OS 9.2.2 always felt instantaneous like no other system already!</p><p>People might also have some other kind of reason and/or special attachment to an earlier OS version. Or maybe people want to explore older OS APIs and behaviors, perhaps even make a new application they want to know how it will behave on bare-metal not just on Mac OS 9, but also System 7 etc..</p><p>The value is in opening up the doors that give us, the users, more options that help us all out. <img src="https://macos9lives.com/smforum/Smileys/default/smiley.gif" alt=":)" title="Smiley"></p><p><strong>========================================================<br>Final remarks<br>========================================================</strong></p><p>Above all, thank you to everyone that made this possible. But I wanted to emphasize and give special thanks to Rairii for engineering all these ROMs, Mac84 for archiving and sharing all the CHRP discs, ELN for engineering all the Mac mini G4 ROM compatibility scripts and creating all the ROM and other Mac OS tooling, and to the Mac community at large everywhere that assisted in all of this into becoming reality. There's honestly many, many people to thank we owe over this one way or another, both in small and big ways.</p><p>I can't wait to see what people will do with all these new Mac OS versions on their New World ROM systems over the course of time!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Every mathematician has only a few tricks (2020) (228 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mathoverflow.net/questions/363119/every-mathematician-has-only-a-few-tricks</link>
            <guid>46084535</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 01:37:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mathoverflow.net/questions/363119/every-mathematician-has-only-a-few-tricks">https://mathoverflow.net/questions/363119/every-mathematician-has-only-a-few-tricks</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46084535">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="text">
<p>From a physicist point of view I want to mention this trick and its generalization for operators:</p>
<pre><code>      "Two commuting matrices are simultaneously diagonalizable"
</code></pre>
<p>(for physicists all matrices are diagonalizable). Of course the idea is that if you know the eigenvectors of one matrix/operator then diagonalizing the other one is much easier. Here are some applications.</p>
<p>1)The system is translation invariant : Because the eigenvectors of the translation operator are <span>$e^{ik.x}$</span>, then one should use the Fourier transform.  It solves all the wave equations for light, acoustics, of free quantum electrons or the heat equation in homogeneous media.</p>
<p>2)The system has a discrete translation symmetry: The typical system is the atoms in a solid state that form a crystal. We have a discrete translation operator <span>$T_a\phi(x)=\phi(x+a)$</span> with <span>$a$</span> the size of the lattice and then we should try <span>$\phi_k(x+a)=e^{ik.a}\phi_k(x)$</span> as it is an eigenvector of <span>$T_a$</span>. This gives the  <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloch%27s_theorem" rel="noreferrer">Bloch</a>-<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Floquet_theory" rel="noreferrer">Floquet</a> theory where the spectrum is divided into band structure. It is one of the most famous model of condensed matter as it explains the different between conductors or insulators.</p>
<p>3)The system is rotational invariant: One should then use and diagonalize the rotation operator first. This will allow us to find the eigenvalue/eigenvectors of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hydrogen_atom" rel="noreferrer">Hydrogen atom</a>. By the way we notice the eigenspace of the Hydrogen are stable by rotation and are therefore finite dimension representations of <span>$SO(3)$</span>. The irreducible representations of <span>$SO(3)$</span> have dimension 1,3,5,... and they appears, considering also the spin of the electron, as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electron_shell" rel="noreferrer">columns</a> of the periodic table of the elements (2,6,10,14,...).</p>
<p>4)<span>$SU(3)$</span> symmetry: Particle physics is extremely complicated. However physicists have discovered that there is an underlying <span>$SU(3)$</span> symmetry. Then considering the representations of <span>$SU(3)$</span> the zoology of particles seems much more organized (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Clebsch%E2%80%93Gordan_coefficients_for_SU(3)#/media/File:Baryon-decuplet.svg" rel="noreferrer">A</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Meson#/media/File:Meson_nonet_-_spin_0.svg" rel="noreferrer">B</a>).</p>
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A triangle whose interior angles sum to zero (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/11/28/tricusp-triangle/</link>
            <guid>46084122</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 00:26:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/11/28/tricusp-triangle/">https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/11/28/tricusp-triangle/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46084122">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		<h2>Spherical geometry</h2>
<p>In spherical geometry, the interior angles of a triangle add up to more than π. And in fact you can determine the area of a spherical triangle by how much the angle sum exceeds π. On a sphere of radius 1, the area equals the <strong>triangle excess</strong></p>
<p>Area = <em>E</em> = interior angle sum − π.</p>
<p>Small triangles have interior angle sum near π. But you could, for example, have a triangle with three right angles: put a vertex on the north pole and two vertices on the equator 90° longitude apart.</p>
<h2>Hyperbolic geometry</h2>
<p>In hyperbolic geometry, the sum of the interior angles of a triangle is always less than π. In a space with curvature −1, the area equals the <strong>triangle defect</strong>, the difference between π and the angle sum.</p>
<p>Area =&nbsp;<em>D</em> = π − interior angle sum.</p>
<p>Again small triangles have an interior angle sum near π. Both spherical and hyperbolic geometry are locally Euclidean.</p>
<p>The interior angle sum can be any value less than π, and so as the angle sum goes to 0, the triangle defect, and hence the area, goes to π. Since the minimum angle sum is 0, the maximum area of a triangle is π.</p>
<p>The figure below has interior angle sum 0 and area π in hyperbolic geometry.</p>
<p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://www.johndcook.com/tricusp.png" width="500" height="252"></p>
<p>Strictly speaking this is an improper triangle because the three hyperbolic lines (i.e. half circles) don’t intersect within the hyperbolic plane per se but at ideal points on the real axis. But you could come as close to this triangle as you like, staying within the hyperbolic plane.</p>
<p>Note that the radii of the (Euclidean) half circles doesn’t change the area. Any three semicircles that intersect on the real line as above make a triangle with the same area. Note also that the triangle has infinite perimeter but finite area.</p>
<h2>Related posts</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/11/26/hyperbolic-metric/">A hyperbolic metric</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2025/11/28/hyperbolic-circle/">A circle in the hyperbolic plane</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.johndcook.com/blog/2024/08/20/osborn-rule/">Convert trig identities to hyperbolic identities</a></li>
</ul>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Confessions of a Software Developer: No More Self-Censorship (339 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kerrick.blog/articles/2025/confessions-of-a-software-developer-no-more-self-censorship/</link>
            <guid>46083303</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 22:21:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kerrick.blog/articles/2025/confessions-of-a-software-developer-no-more-self-censorship/">https://kerrick.blog/articles/2025/confessions-of-a-software-developer-no-more-self-censorship/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46083303">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A first look at Django's new background tasks (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://roam.be/notes/2025/a-first-look-at-djangos-new-background-tasks/</link>
            <guid>46083051</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 21:46:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://roam.be/notes/2025/a-first-look-at-djangos-new-background-tasks/">https://roam.be/notes/2025/a-first-look-at-djangos-new-background-tasks/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46083051">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        
            <p>Django 6.0 introduces a built-in background tasks framework in <code>django.tasks</code>. But don't expect to phase out Celery, Huey or other preferred solutions just yet. </p>
<p>The <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/6.0/releases/6.0/#background-tasks">release notes</a> are quite clear on this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Django handles task creation and queuing, but <strong>does not provide a worker mechanism to run tasks.</strong>
Execution must be managed by external infrastructure, such as a separate process or service.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The main purpose of the new <code>django.tasks</code> module is to <strong>provide a common API for task queues</strong> implementations. <a href="https://theorangeone.net/">Jake Howard</a> is the driving force behind this enhancement. Check out the introduction on <a href="https://forum.djangoproject.com/t/django-tasks-bringing-background-workers-in-to-django-core/32967">the Django forum</a>.</p>
<p>His reference implementation, and simultaneously a backport for earlier versions of Django, is available <a href="https://github.com/RealOrangeOne/django-tasks/">as <code>django-tasks</code> on GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>But let's ignore that and play with the more minimal version included in Django 6.0 instead. By creating our very own backend and worker.</p>
<h2>Our project: notifications</h2>
<p>We're going to create an app to send notifications to phones and other devices using <a href="https://ntfy.sh/">ntfy.sh</a>. (<a href="https://roam.be/notes/2025/ping-me-using-ntfy-to-stay-updated/">I'm a fan!</a>)</p>
<p>If you prefer to dive into the code yourself, check out <a href="https://github.com/roam/django-tasks-demo">the final version of the project on GitHub</a>.</p>
<p>All that's required to send a notification to your phone using nfty is:</p>
<ol>
<li><a href="https://ntfy.sh/signup">Register for an account</a></li>
<li>Create a topic.</li>
<li>Install the app for your phone and log in.</li>
<li>Send HTTP requests to <code>https://ntfy.sh/&lt;yourtopic&gt;</code></li>
</ol>
<p>The free version only provides public topics and messages. Meaning anyone can see the stuff you're sending <em>if</em> they subscribe to the topic. For our purpose we can simply create a topic with a randomized name, like a UUID.</p>
<p>The project's settings expect the URL from step 4 to be supplied as an environment variable. For example:</p>
<p><code>NTFY_URL=https://ntfy.sh/062519693d9c4913826f0a39aeea8a4c</code></p>
<p>Here's our function that does the heavy lifting:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>httpx</span>
<span>from</span><span> </span><span>django.conf</span><span> </span><span>import</span> <span>settings</span>

<span>def</span><span> </span><span>send_notification</span><span>(</span><span>message</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>title</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span><span>):</span>
    <span># Pass the title if specified.</span>
    <span>headers</span> <span>=</span> <span>{</span><span>"title"</span><span>:</span> <span>title</span><span>}</span> <span>if</span> <span>title</span> <span>else</span> <span>{}</span>
    <span>httpx</span><span>.</span><span>post</span><span>(</span>
        <span>settings</span><span>.</span><span>NTFY_URL</span><span>,</span>
        <span>content</span><span>=</span><span>message</span><span>,</span>
        <span>headers</span><span>=</span><span>headers</span><span>,</span>
    <span>)</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Really. That's all there is to it to start sending and receiving notifications.</p>
<p><img src="https://roam.be/media/img/2025/ntfy-notifications.png" alt="Ntfy notifications"></p>
<h2>A quick primer</h2>
<p>You really should have a look at the <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/6.0/topics/tasks/">Django documentation on the Task framework</a> for details, but we'll save you a bit of time and give a quick primer.</p>
<h3>Defining a task</h3>
<p>This is the main goal of the new framework: defining tasks using Django's standard API, rather than using task queue specific decorators, or other methods.</p>
<p>So here it goes:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span># ...</span>
<span>from</span><span> </span><span>django.tasks</span><span> </span><span>import</span> <span>task</span>

<span>@task</span>
<span>def</span><span> </span><span>send_notification</span><span>(</span><span>message</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>title</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span><span>):</span>
    <span># ...as before</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Our function is now a task. In fact it's a <code>django.tasks.Task</code>. </p>
<p>You cannot call <code>send_notification</code> directly anymore. Tasks can only be run by using the <code>enqueue</code> method. It might not be the behavior you'd expect or want, but this seems to be the best option. This design eliminates the possibility of accidentally invoking a task in-process, rather than in the background.</p>
<p>The <code>task</code> decorator allows you to specify the task's priority, queue name and backend name. You can override these settings with the <code>using</code> method, which returns a new <code>django.tasks.Task</code> instance.</p>
<p>If you need more control over task behavior, you can set <code>takes_context</code> to <code>True</code> in the decorator and add <code>context</code> as the first argument. This context currently provides you with access to the task result and thereby useful information like the number of attempts. </p>
<p>There's no way of defining retries and backoffs, or other fancy things you might expect from a full-blown task queue implementation. But that's <em>not</em> what this is. You can easily add your own retry logic by inspecting the task context if needed.</p>
<h3>Enqueuing a task</h3>
<p>Adding a task to the queue is easy:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>task_result</span> <span>=</span> <span>send_notification</span><span>.</span><span>enqueue</span><span>(</span>
    <span>message</span><span>=</span><span>"Season's greeting!"</span><span>,</span> 
    <span>title</span><span>=</span><span>"Santa has something to tell you"</span>
<span>)</span>
</pre></div>
<h3>Executing a task</h3>
<p>This is where things start to fall short. At least right now. Django 6.0 will ship with the <code>ImmediateBackend</code> and the <code>DummyBackend</code>. The first will execute the task immediately, while the latter will not execute the task at all. </p>
<p>Which is why our project includes a (demo) backend backed by the database and a worker process!</p>
<h3>Fetching the result</h3>
<p>If you're not going to wait around for the result, you can get a hold of it later on using its id. Simply call <code>get_result(result_id)</code> on your task. </p>
<p>Our project includes a view that's polled periodically for outstanding results using <a href="https://htmx.org/">htmx</a>. </p>
<p><img src="https://roam.be/media/img/2025/ui.png" alt="Project UI"></p>
<p>The list underneath the form shows the results for each execution of our task. When the form's submitted, a new result is added to the top of the list. Htmx is instructed to keep polling for changes as long as the result's status isn't <code>FAILED</code> or <code>SUCCESSFUL</code>.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>def</span><span> </span><span>task_result</span><span>(</span><span>request</span><span>,</span> <span>result_id</span><span>,</span> <span>status</span><span>):</span>
    <span>result</span> <span>=</span> <span>send_notification</span><span>.</span><span>get_result</span><span>(</span><span>result_id</span><span>)</span>
    <span>if</span> <span>result</span><span>.</span><span>status</span> <span>==</span> <span>status</span><span>:</span>
        <span># No need to swap the result.</span>
        <span>return</span> <span>HttpResponse</span><span>(</span><span>status</span><span>=</span><span>204</span><span>)</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>TemplateResponse</span><span>(</span><span>request</span><span>,</span> <span>"index.html#result"</span><span>,</span> <span>{</span><span>"result"</span><span>:</span> <span>result</span><span>})</span>
</pre></div>
<p>Wondering what <code>index.html#results</code> is doing? Django 6.0 also introduces <a href="https://docs.djangoproject.com/en/6.0/releases/6.0/#template-partials">template partials</a>. In this case our view effectively sends a response containing only the template partial named <code>result</code>.</p>
<h2>Behind the scenes</h2>
<p>When you decorate a callable with <code>task</code>, the configured backend's <code>task_class</code> is used to wrap the callable. The default's <code>django.task.Task</code>.</p>
<p>That class's <code>enqueue</code> method will in turn invoke the configured backend's <code>enqueue</code> method.</p>
<p>Calling its <code>get_result</code> method is similar: call the configured backend's <code>get_result</code> method and pass on the result.</p>
<p>Since there's no workers, that's basically all a task backend needs to provide. Cool. Let's add one, shall we?</p>
<h2>A task database backend</h2>
<p>Our goals:</p>
<ul>
<li>A basic task backend, backed by our database.</li>
<li>We want to support "automagic" retries</li>
</ul>
<p>Our <code>enqueue</code> and <code>get_result</code> methods will return an instance of the default <code>django.tasks.TaskResult</code>. This determines the minimum amount of data we need to store, and we're going to do so in a model called <code>Task</code>.</p>
<h3>Models</h3>
<p>Let's create a first draft of our <code>Task</code> model, based on the properties of <code>TaskResult</code> and <code>Task</code> in <code>django.tasks</code> (the "dataclasses"):</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>Task</span><span>(</span><span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Model</span><span>):</span>
    <span>priority</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>IntegerField</span><span>(</span><span>default</span><span>=</span><span>0</span><span>)</span>
    <span>callable_path</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span><span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>255</span><span>)</span>
    <span>backend</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span><span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>200</span><span>)</span>
    <span>queue_name</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span><span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>100</span><span>)</span>
    <span>run_after</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>(</span><span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span>takes_context</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>BooleanField</span><span>(</span><span>default</span><span>=</span><span>False</span><span>)</span>
    <span># Stores args and kwargs</span>
    <span>arguments</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>JSONField</span><span>(</span><span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span>status</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span>
        <span>choices</span><span>=</span><span>TaskResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>choices</span><span>,</span> <span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>10</span><span>,</span> <span>default</span><span>=</span><span>TaskResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>READY</span>
    <span>)</span>
    <span>enqueued_at</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>()</span>
    <span>started_at</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>(</span><span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span>finished_at</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>(</span><span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span>last_attempted_at</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>(</span><span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span>return_value</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>JSONField</span><span>(</span><span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
</pre></div>
<p>What's missing? For one, the <code>TaskResult</code> also includes a list of encountered errors, and ids of the workers that processed the task. Something that we could <em>perhaps</em> ignore. </p>
<p>Except the <code>TaskResult.attempts</code> property is based on the number of worker ids. And if you're using the task context within a task, you're bound to be relying on that type of information.</p>
<p>We could add these details to the <code>Task</code> model by adding a <code>JSONField</code> for each. This is the current approach in the reference implementation. </p>
<p>But let's be more explicit in our approach and define models for these as well. We'll record each attempt to execute a task and its potential error, linking them to the task with a foreign key:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>Error</span><span>(</span><span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Model</span><span>):</span>
    <span>exception_class_path</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>TextField</span><span>()</span>
    <span>traceback</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>TextField</span><span>()</span>

<span>class</span><span> </span><span>AttemptResultStatus</span><span>(</span><span>TextChoices</span><span>):</span>
    <span># Subset of TaskResultStatus.</span>
    <span>FAILED</span> <span>=</span> <span>TaskResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>FAILED</span>
    <span>SUCCESSFUL</span> <span>=</span> <span>TaskResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>SUCCESSFUL</span>

<span>class</span><span> </span><span>Attempt</span><span>(</span><span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Model</span><span>):</span>
    <span>task</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>ForeignKey</span><span>(</span><span>Task</span><span>,</span> <span>related_name</span><span>=</span><span>"attempts"</span><span>,</span> <span>on_delete</span><span>=</span><span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CASCADE</span><span>)</span>
    <span>error</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>OneToOneField</span><span>(</span>
        <span>Error</span><span>,</span> <span>related_name</span><span>=</span><span>"attempt"</span><span>,</span> <span>on_delete</span><span>=</span><span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CASCADE</span><span>,</span> <span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span>
    <span>)</span>
    <span>worker_id</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span><span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>MAX_LENGTH_WORKER_ID</span><span>)</span>
    <span>started_at</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>()</span>
    <span>stopped_at</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>(</span><span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>null</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span>status</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span>
        <span>choices</span><span>=</span><span>AttemptResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>choices</span><span>,</span> <span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>10</span><span>,</span> <span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span>
    <span>)</span>
</pre></div>
<p>This setup ensures we have all necessary information to execute a task, plus we can provide every single bit of detail when a <code>TaskResult</code> is requested.</p>
<p>All fine and dandy, but we need to think about the worker's requirements as well. It needs to be able to: </p>
<ol>
<li>Quickly check for outstanding tasks</li>
<li>Claim one of those tasks</li>
<li>Process that task and either mark it as failed, successful or ready (to retry later)</li>
</ol>
<p>We could do all of that with how it's set up right now, but I'd like to refine things a bit.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>Task</span><span>(</span><span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Model</span><span>):</span>
    <span># ...</span>
    <span># This field is used to keep track of when to run a task (again).</span>
    <span># run_after remains unchanged after enqueueing.</span>
    <span>available_after</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>DateTimeField</span><span>()</span>
    <span># Denormalized count of attempts.</span>
    <span>attempt_count</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>IntegerField</span><span>(</span><span>default</span><span>=</span><span>0</span><span>)</span>
    <span># Set when a worker starts processing this task.</span>
    <span>worker_id</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>CharField</span><span>(</span><span>max_length</span><span>=</span><span>MAX_LENGTH_WORKER_ID</span><span>,</span> <span>blank</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
    <span># ...</span>
</pre></div>
<p>The <code>available_after</code> field will contain the earliest time at which the task can be executed. If the task's <code>run_after</code> is specified (which can be done by using a task's... <code>using()</code> method), <code>available_after</code> is set to that value. Otherwise we're using the current datetime; all in UTC.</p>
<p>Once a task needs to be retried, <code>available_after</code> will be set to the next possible point in time the task can be executed. In other words: we can <strong>back off.</strong></p>
<p>The <code>attempt_count</code> field makes querying for available tasks a bit easier. Any tasks with an <code>attempt_count</code> greater than the maximum allowed value can be ignored. Yes, their status should have been set to <code>FAILED</code> which means they should be excluded by default, but we could change the configuration and tweak the maximum number of attempts.</p>
<p>The <code>worker_id</code> field is filled when a worker claims a task. This, among other things, prevents any other workers from picking up the task. Assuming the worker id is unique.</p>
<h3>Enqueueing and fetching a result</h3>
<p>Enqueueing a task could not be easier: create a <code>Task</code> <em>model instance</em> from the <code>Task</code> <em>dataclass instance</em>, save it, done! Well, at least after turning the end result into a <code>TaskResult</code>. </p>
<p>We use the string version of the model's database id as the id of the result.</p>
<p>Retrieving a result is likewise only a matter of loading the task and its attempts, and turning that into a <code>TaskResult</code>. </p>
<p>Here's a simplified version of our task backend as it stands:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>DatabaseBackend</span><span>(</span><span>BaseTaskBackend</span><span>):</span>
    <span>supports_defer</span> <span>=</span> <span>True</span>
    <span>supports_async_task</span> <span>=</span> <span>False</span>
    <span>supports_get_result</span> <span>=</span> <span>True</span>
    <span>supports_priority</span> <span>=</span> <span>True</span>

    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>enqueue</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>task</span><span>:</span> <span>Task</span><span>,</span> <span>args</span><span>,</span> <span>kwargs</span><span>):</span>
        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>validate_task</span><span>(</span><span>task</span><span>)</span>
        <span>model</span> <span>=</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>queue_store</span><span>.</span><span>enqueue</span><span>(</span><span>task</span><span>,</span> <span>args</span><span>,</span> <span>kwargs</span><span>)</span>
        <span>task_result</span> <span>=</span> <span>TaskResult</span><span>(</span>
            <span>task</span><span>=</span><span>task</span><span>,</span>
            <span>id</span><span>=</span><span>str</span><span>(</span><span>model</span><span>.</span><span>pk</span><span>),</span>
            <span># ...</span>
            <span># More properties being set</span>
            <span># ...</span>
        <span>)</span>
        <span>return</span> <span>task_result</span>

    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>get_result</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>result_id</span><span>):</span>
        <span>return</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>model_to_result</span><span>(</span>
            <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>queue_store</span><span>.</span><span>get</span><span>(</span><span>result_id</span><span>)</span>
        <span>)</span>

    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>model_to_result</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>model</span><span>:</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Task</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>TaskResult</span><span>:</span>
        <span>...</span>
</pre></div>
<p>At lot of functionality is deferred to this <code>queue_store</code> property. Before we dive into that, we'll explain the configuration options for this backend.</p>
<h3>Configuration</h3>
<p>We want to be able to specify defaults for:</p>
<ul>
<li>the maximum number of attempts (retries)</li>
<li>the backoff factor; i.e. we'll back off using <code>math.pow(factor, attempts)</code></li>
</ul>
<p>These can be customized for each individual queue. So we end up with something like this in our <code>OPTIONS</code>:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>TASKS</span> <span>=</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>"default"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
        <span>"BACKEND"</span><span>:</span> <span>"messagecenter.dbtasks.backend.DatabaseBackend"</span><span>,</span>
        <span>"OPTIONS"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
            <span>"queues"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
                <span>"low_priority"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span>
                    <span>"max_attempts"</span><span>:</span> <span>5</span><span>,</span>
                <span>}</span>
            <span>},</span>
            <span>"max_attempts"</span><span>:</span> <span>10</span><span>,</span>
            <span>"backoff_factor"</span><span>:</span> <span>3</span><span>,</span>
            <span>"purge"</span><span>:</span> <span>{</span><span>"finished"</span><span>:</span> <span>"10 days"</span><span>,</span> <span>"unfinished"</span><span>:</span> <span>"20 days"</span><span>},</span>
        <span>},</span>
    <span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</pre></div>
<p>A task added to the <code>low_priority</code> queue will be attempted up to five times, with a backoff factor of <code>3</code>. Other tasks will be attempted up to ten times with the same backoff factor.</p>
<h3>Queue store</h3>
<p>The <a href="https://github.com/roam/django-tasks-demo/blob/main/src/messagecenter/dbtasks/backend.py#L279"><code>QueueStore</code> class</a> is a companion of our backend. It's focus is on retrieving and enqueueing tasks, checking for tasks to execute and claiming tasks. </p>
<p>However the main reason it's included is to simplify the worker. As we'll see, the worker gets it's own copy of the queue store, <em>limited to the queues it needs to process.</em></p>
<h3>The worker</h3>
<p>The worker's job, at least in this project, is to provide information on outstanding tasks to the runner and to drive the processing of those tasks <em>by the backend</em>. Which means it looks like this:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>class</span><span> </span><span>Worker</span><span>:</span>
    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>__init__</span><span>(</span>
        <span>self</span><span>,</span>
        <span>id_</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span><span>,</span>
        <span>backend_name</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span>
        <span>only</span><span>:</span> <span>set</span><span>[</span><span>str</span><span>]</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span><span>,</span>
        <span>excluding</span><span>:</span> <span>set</span><span>[</span><span>str</span><span>]</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span><span>,</span>
    <span>):</span>
        <span># Grab the backend and its queue_store.</span>
        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>backend</span> <span>=</span> <span>task_backends</span><span>[</span><span>backend_name</span><span>]</span>
        <span>queue_store</span><span>:</span> <span>QueueStore</span> <span>=</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>backend</span><span>.</span><span>queue_store</span>
        <span># Limit the queue_store to the select queues.</span>
        <span>if</span> <span>only</span> <span>or</span> <span>excluding</span><span>:</span>
            <span>queue_store</span> <span>=</span> <span>queue_store</span><span>.</span><span>subset</span><span>(</span><span>only</span><span>=</span><span>only</span><span>,</span> <span>excluding</span><span>=</span><span>excluding</span><span>)</span>
        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>queue_store</span> <span>=</span> <span>queue_store</span>
        <span># Use or create and id. "Must" be unique.</span>
        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>id</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span>
            <span>id_</span> <span>if</span> <span>id_</span> <span>else</span> <span>create_id</span><span>(</span><span>backend_name</span><span>,</span> <span>queues</span><span>=</span><span>queue_store</span><span>.</span><span>queue_names</span><span>)</span>
        <span>)</span>

    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>has_more</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>bool</span><span>:</span>
        <span>return</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>queue_store</span><span>.</span><span>has_more</span><span>()</span>

    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>process</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>):</span>
        <span>with</span> <span>transaction</span><span>.</span><span>atomic</span><span>():</span>
            <span>tm</span> <span>=</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>queue_store</span><span>.</span><span>claim_first_available</span><span>(</span><span>worker_id</span><span>=</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>id</span><span>)</span>
        <span>if</span> <span>tm</span> <span>is</span> <span>not</span> <span>None</span><span>:</span>
            <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>backend</span><span>.</span><span>process_task</span><span>(</span><span>tm</span><span>)</span>
</pre></div>
<p>All we need to do to have a functioning worker runner:</p>
<ol>
<li>Create an instance of the worker.</li>
<li>Ask it if there's tasks to execute using <code>has_more</code>.</li>
<li>If so: tell it to <code>process</code> the first available task. If not: go to 4.</li>
<li>Wait, then return to 2.</li>
</ol>
<p>That's what our <a href="https://github.com/roam/django-tasks-demo/blob/main/src/messagecenter/dbtasks/management/commands/dbtasks_worker.py"><code>dbtasks_worker</code> command</a> does.</p>
<h3>Claiming a task</h3>
<p>Our queue store provides a <code>peek</code> method which returns the id of the task in our queues with the most urgency; a combination of <code>available_after</code>, <code>priority</code> and <code>attempt_count</code>.</p>
<p>This lets the runner know whether there's more tasks to process. The next step is to claim one of those tasks. So we call <code>peek</code> again and if it returns a task id, we'll try to claim that particular task.</p>
<p>Here's a more basic, clearer version than the one included in our project's <code>QueueStore</code>:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>def</span><span> </span><span>claim_first_available</span><span>(</span>
    <span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>worker_id</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>attempts</span><span>:</span> <span>int</span> <span>=</span> <span>3</span>
<span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Task</span> <span>|</span> <span>None</span><span>:</span>
    <span>qs</span> <span>=</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Task</span><span>.</span><span>filter</span><span>(</span>
        <span>worker_id</span><span>=</span><span>""</span><span>,</span> 
        <span>status</span><span>=</span><span>TaskResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>READY</span><span>,</span>
    <span>)</span>
    <span>for</span> <span>_</span> <span>in</span> <span>range</span><span>(</span><span>attempts</span><span>):</span>
        <span>task_id</span> <span>=</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>peek</span><span>()</span>
        <span>if</span> <span>not</span> <span>task_id</span><span>:</span>
            <span>return</span> <span>None</span>
        <span>count</span> <span>=</span> <span>qs</span><span>.</span><span>filter</span><span>(</span><span>pk</span><span>=</span><span>task_id</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>update</span><span>(</span>
            <span>worker_id</span><span>=</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>id_</span><span>,</span>
            <span>status</span><span>=</span><span>TaskResultStatus</span><span>.</span><span>RUNNING</span><span>,</span>
        <span>)</span>
        <span>if</span> <span>count</span><span>:</span>
            <span>return</span> <span>models</span><span>.</span><span>Task</span><span>.</span><span>objects</span><span>.</span><span>get</span><span>(</span><span>pk</span><span>=</span><span>task_id</span><span>)</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>None</span>
</pre></div>
<p>If the <code>count</code> is zero, we failed to claim the task. Otherwise we retrieve it from the database and can start processing. </p>
<p>The loop is included because we ended up here after trying to claim the task identified by <code>peek</code>. Which apparently has already been picked up by another worker. We might as well make the most of it and try to grab another task from the queue.</p>
<h3>Processing the task</h3>
<p>And finally the thing that actually does something!</p>
<p>The <code>process_task</code> method of our backend:</p>
<ol>
<li>Creates an <code>Attempt</code> and constructs the current <code>TaskResult</code>.</li>
<li>Executes the task, capturing anything extending <code>BaseException</code>, or returning the <code>return_value</code> of the task when everything went according to plan.</li>
<li>Either updates the <code>Task</code> model, the <code>Attempt</code> <em>and</em> the <code>TaskResult</code> with the final details of the successful execution, or with details about the failure to do so.</li>
<li>And in the latter case: check if the task can be retried.</li>
</ol>
<p>Again: if you want to dive into the details, have a look at <a href="https://github.com/roam/django-tasks-demo">the repository</a>.</p>
<h2>That's it</h2>
<p>Of course this demo project leaves out all the things you really need to think hard about. Like signals for the worker. Or database transaction logic. That's not to say it's impossible. Far from it. It just wasn't the goal of this article.</p>
<p>The inclusion of this functionality in Django will certainly allow new libraries or adapters for existing task queues to pop up. And we'll probably soon see some complaints that <code>django.tasks</code> isn't extensive enough.</p>
<p>Because, if you're currently using the more advanced functionality of your task queue, there's probably a few things you're missing in <code>django.tasks</code>.</p>
<h3>Complex orchestration</h3>
<p>Some task queue libraries, like Celery, provide ways of combining tasks. You can feed the result of one task into another, enqueue tasks for each item in a list, and so on.</p>
<p>It should be clear by now that supporting this kind of orchestration isn't the goal of <code>django.tasks</code>. And I don't mind at all. There's no feasible way of creating a unified API to support this. I've had my share of problems with libraries that <em>do</em> claim to support it.</p>
<h3>Retry</h3>
<p>As mentioned before, there's currently no way to automatically retry a failed task, unless your backend does the heavy lifting. Like ours does. </p>
<p>Depending on your backend this might be easy enough to handle yourself. For example using a decorator:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><span>def</span><span> </span><span>retry</span><span>(</span><span>func</span><span>):</span>
    <span>@functools</span><span>.</span><span>wraps</span><span>(</span><span>func</span><span>)</span>
    <span>def</span><span> </span><span>wrapper</span><span>(</span><span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>TaskContext</span><span>,</span> <span>*</span><span>args</span><span>,</span> <span>**</span><span>kwargs</span><span>):</span>
        <span>try</span><span>:</span>
            <span>return</span> <span>func</span><span>(</span><span>context</span><span>,</span> <span>*</span><span>args</span><span>,</span> <span>**</span><span>kwargs</span><span>)</span>
        <span>except</span> <span>BaseException</span> <span>as</span> <span>e</span><span>:</span>
            <span>result</span> <span>=</span> <span>context</span><span>.</span><span>task_result</span>
            <span>backoff</span> <span>=</span> <span>math</span><span>.</span><span>pow</span><span>(</span><span>2</span><span>,</span> <span>result</span><span>.</span><span>attempts</span><span>)</span>
            <span>run_after</span> <span>=</span> <span>datetime</span><span>.</span><span>now</span><span>(</span><span>tz</span><span>=</span><span>UTC</span><span>)</span> <span>+</span> <span>timedelta</span><span>(</span><span>seconds</span><span>=</span><span>backoff</span><span>)</span>
            <span>result</span><span>.</span><span>task</span><span>.</span><span>using</span><span>(</span><span>run_after</span><span>=</span><span>run_after</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>enqueue</span><span>(</span><span>*</span><span>args</span><span>,</span> <span>**</span><span>kwargs</span><span>)</span>
            <span>raise</span> <span>e</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>wrapper</span>


<span>@task</span><span>(</span><span>takes_context</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
<span>@retry</span>
<span>def</span><span> </span><span>send_email</span><span>(</span><span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>TaskContext</span><span>,</span> <span>to</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>subject</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>body</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>):</span>
    <span># Do your thing </span>
    <span>...</span>
</pre></div>
<h3>An actual worker mechanism</h3>
<p>True. But the <a href="https://github.com/RealOrangeOne/django-tasks/">reference implementation</a> does provide actual workers. Be patient, or even better: start helping out!</p>
<h2>There is no perfect solution</h2>
<p>I reckon <code>django.tasks</code> will soon result in covering at least the most common 80% of use cases. Yes, its API is simple and limited, but to me that's more a benefit rather than a fault. I think this is as close as you can get to a standardized approach.</p>

        
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Airbus A320 – intense solar radiation may corrupt data critical for flight (461 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.airbus.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2025-11-airbus-update-on-a320-family-precautionary-fleet-action</link>
            <guid>46083004</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 21:40:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.airbus.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2025-11-airbus-update-on-a320-family-precautionary-fleet-action">https://www.airbus.com/en/newsroom/press-releases/2025-11-airbus-update-on-a320-family-precautionary-fleet-action</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46083004">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p dir="ltr"><strong>Toulouse, France, 28 November 2025</strong> – Analysis of a recent event involving an A320 Family aircraft has revealed that intense solar radiation may corrupt data critical to the functioning of flight controls.</p><p dir="ltr">Airbus has consequently identified a significant number of A320 Family aircraft currently in-service which may be impacted.</p><p dir="ltr">Airbus has worked proactively with the aviation authorities to request immediate precautionary action from operators via an Alert Operators Transmission (AOT) in order to implement the available software and/or hardware protection, and ensure the fleet is safe to fly. This AOT will be reflected in an Emergency Airworthiness Directive from the European Union Aviation Safety Agency (EASA).</p><p dir="ltr">Airbus acknowledges these recommendations will lead to operational disruptions to passengers and customers. We apologise for the inconvenience caused and will work closely with operators, while keeping safety as our number one and overriding priority.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Flight disruption warning as Airbus requests modifications to 6k planes (222 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert</link>
            <guid>46082825</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 21:16:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert">https://www.bbc.com/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46082825">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="list" spacing="6" tabindex="0" data-testid="postList"><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:3d88b222-8f7b-4c62-90ea-67b24959f201"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Airlines around the world announce delays after Airbus requests immediate modifications</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:58 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2023/3/13/c30ea702-5d4e-4d84-afea-041293d17acb.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Jamie Whitehead</strong><br>Live reporter</span></p>
      <p>It's been a few hours now since Airbus announced it needs to implement an urgent software update to thousands of its planes. This comes after the discovery that intense radiation from the sun could corrupt data crucial to flight controls. </p><p>If you are just joining us, here's the latest: </p><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      Several airlines around the world have announced potential service disruption, <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert?post=asset%3A9527ee34-1ec6-4a96-8b19-21124ed8ec82#post">including American Airlines, Delta, Air India and Wizz</a>
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      But EasyJet says it has already completed the required software update and is<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert?post=asset%3A7d29d54a-973b-45ba-b505-40d6ad67901e#post"> planning on operating its flights as normal on Saturday </a>
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      We've heard from London's two biggest airports - <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert?post=asset%3A0dfbdaef-e93e-41e1-8441-a6fca6b60df1#post">Heathrow and Gatwick</a> - Heathrow says this has no impact on its operations, while Gatwick is expecting some disruption 
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      The UK's Transport Secretary Heidi Alexander says the<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/live/cvg4y6g74ert?post=asset%3A88a671e4-bf4c-4f61-8254-f5f929aa2b7b#post"> impact on UK airlines seems limited</a>, and advises passengers due to fly this weekend to check with carriers for more information
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      Around 6,000 planes are thought to be affected, which is about half of Airbus's global fleet, our business correspondent Theo Leggett says this is a very unusual situation
    </li></ul>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:3c6e1cef-cdc4-4abe-a3ab-9e5883e47d03"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Watch: Airlines 'taking different approaches' to upgrade software, says aviation analyst</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:35 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <div data-testid="component-wrapper"><figure><figcaption><span>Media caption, </span><p>Airlines 'taking different approaches' to upgrade software, says aviation analyst</p></figcaption></figure></div><p>Sally Gethin, an aviation analyst, describes how the Airbus plane modifications are affecting airlines.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:03fcb599-2791-4bec-82c9-ab0c84ae3342"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>What is the Airbus A320?</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 23:04 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <figure><p><span><img alt="EasyJet Airbus A320 in the air" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/e61772be-9ece-423a-93c3-df38adf372d4.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/e61772be-9ece-423a-93c3-df38adf372d4.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/e61772be-9ece-423a-93c3-df38adf372d4.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/e61772be-9ece-423a-93c3-df38adf372d4.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/e61772be-9ece-423a-93c3-df38adf372d4.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/e61772be-9ece-423a-93c3-df38adf372d4.jpg.webp 800w" width="1024" height="576"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p></figure><p>Airbus describes A320 planes as the "aircraft family of choice for airlines around the world". </p><p>These planes can fly up to 4,700 nautical miles (8,700km) and have a seating capacity from 120 to 244 seats.</p><p>The A320 also flies with 50% sustainable aviation fuel, which Airbus aims to use 100% of by 2030. </p><p>The planes feature a choice of two advanced turbofan engines, meaning they benefit from 20% fuel burn reduction when compared with previous generations of the aircraft.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:7d29d54a-973b-45ba-b505-40d6ad67901e"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>EasyJet says it has 'already completed' software update to planes</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:43 GMT 28 November</span><p><span>Breaking</span></p></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <p>EasyJet says it has "already completed" the software update on many of its planes and plans to operate its flights as normal on Saturday.</p><p>A spokesperson says: "We plan to operate our flying programme normally on Saturday and ask that customers travelling continue to monitor their flights on flight tracker."</p><p>The airline adds that safety is its highest priority and it "always operates its fleet of aircraft in strict compliance with manufacturers guidelines".</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:88a671e4-bf4c-4f61-8254-f5f929aa2b7b"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>'The impact on UK airlines seems limited,' transport secretary says</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:22 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/9/26/aca0db4a-ff5a-4875-8570-83ac3e616556.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Katy Austin</strong><br>Transport correspondent</span></p>
      <figure><p><span><img alt="British Transport Secretary Heidi Alexander walks on Downing Street, in London, Britain, November 26, 2025." src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/880cb575-c17e-4c5f-b8fd-2339ee1330ac.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/880cb575-c17e-4c5f-b8fd-2339ee1330ac.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/880cb575-c17e-4c5f-b8fd-2339ee1330ac.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/880cb575-c17e-4c5f-b8fd-2339ee1330ac.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/880cb575-c17e-4c5f-b8fd-2339ee1330ac.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/880cb575-c17e-4c5f-b8fd-2339ee1330ac.jpg.webp 800w" width="6000" height="3375"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p></figure><p>Responding to the technical issue with Airbus aircraft, the UK's Transport Secretary Heidi Alexander says:</p><p>“I am aware of the technical issue impacting certain aircraft and concerns over how this will affect passengers and flights this evening." </p><p>She advises passengers who are due to fly this weekend to check with their carriers for the latest information.</p><p>The transport secretary says "the good news" is that "the impact on UK airlines seems limited, with a smaller number of aircraft requiring more complex software and hardware changes".</p><p>“I would really like to thank the experts, staff and airlines who are working at pace to address this and reassure passengers that work is ongoing."</p><p>"It is heartening this issue has been identified and will be addressed so swiftly, demonstrating the high aviation safety standards globally," she adds. </p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:19b52df9-3199-48cf-a734-b303b5d441d0"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Australian airline Jetstar says some of its flights are unable to depart</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 22:07 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <p>We've just seen an update from low-cost Australian airline Jetstar, which says some of its Airbus-operated flights are unable to depart at the moment. </p><p>"We’re working through the impacts on our fleet and to our customers. We'll have more information shortly," it says. </p><p>There is no impact to airline giant Qantas at this stage. </p><p><i>For context: Jetstar is Qantas's low-cost airline.</i></p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:0138c96f-f28f-43de-bae4-ef1bd0b76602"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Planes can't fly passengers until they have been fixed, EASA says</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:58 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2024/2/14/ded72972-7fe9-4089-a4a1-f17d165fd4fb.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Michael Race</strong><br>Business and economics reporter</span></p>
      <p>A European Union Aviation Safety Agency (EASA) directive stipulates that, as of 29 November, the planes thought to be affected can only fly passengers once they've been fixed. </p><p>They will be allowed to make so-called "ferry flights", without passengers, in order to get to a maintenance facility.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:0dfbdaef-e93e-41e1-8441-a6fca6b60df1"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>The latest from Heathrow and Gatwick airports</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:49 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <figure><p><span><img alt="A British Airways passenger plane flies over a road direction sign as it makes its landing approach to Heathrow Airport in west London, Britain" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/138b250f-1c0e-4efc-8db4-936d92eb099f.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/138b250f-1c0e-4efc-8db4-936d92eb099f.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/138b250f-1c0e-4efc-8db4-936d92eb099f.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/138b250f-1c0e-4efc-8db4-936d92eb099f.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/138b250f-1c0e-4efc-8db4-936d92eb099f.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/138b250f-1c0e-4efc-8db4-936d92eb099f.jpg.webp 800w" width="5000" height="2812"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Reuters</span></p></figure><p>We've now heard from London's two biggest airports, Heathrow and Gatwick.</p><p>"We are aware of a directive requiring some airlines operating Airbus A320 aircraft to update software on their fleet over coming days, which may result in some disruption," a spokesperson for Gatwick Airport says. </p><p>"This is only impacting a small number of airlines at London Gatwick. Passengers should contact their airline for more information."</p><p>Separately, Heathrow Airport says the required maintenance on some Airbus aircraft currently has no impact on its operations.  </p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:76d825a7-dae5-464d-b377-f69c5b087b1d"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>'Potential for disruption immeasurable at this stage,' travel journalist says</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:48 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <p>"Dozens of big airlines use these aircraft," travel journalist Simon Calder tells the BBC. </p><p>"So the potential for disruption is, I'm afraid, immeasurable at this stage."</p><p>Calder says that while British Airways' mainline fleet of short-haul flights that are at Heathrow and Gatwick Airports use entirely Airbus A320 series planes, "my understanding is that only three of those are affected by this and as a result they'll be able to get the work done overnight, hopefully with no disruption".</p><p>He adds he has spoken to Wizz Air and EasyJet, who we have reported are expecting some delays. "Now the assumption, I'm glad to say, is that your flight will  be going ahead as normal and the airline will contact you if there  is any change to that."</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:ba71d1f6-e5a9-4a09-af7f-ac951b034046"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>About 80 aircraft affected at Gatwick, BBC understands</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:31 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/10/6/cf00d362-cc18-4ea7-b682-40fc7546c310.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Simon Browning</strong><br>Transport correspondent</span></p>
      <figure><p><span><img alt="UK Border at Gatwick Airport" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/2281efed-1712-43a6-a43c-ee3123b0e43e.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/2281efed-1712-43a6-a43c-ee3123b0e43e.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/2281efed-1712-43a6-a43c-ee3123b0e43e.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/2281efed-1712-43a6-a43c-ee3123b0e43e.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/2281efed-1712-43a6-a43c-ee3123b0e43e.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/2281efed-1712-43a6-a43c-ee3123b0e43e.jpg.webp 800w" width="2568" height="1444"></span></p></figure><p>The Airbus software issue could take hours to fix on the planes themselves, which an industry source suggests means some cancellations are inevitable over the weekend. </p><p>It is understood UK-based airlines are currently working on their plans, with one airline being particularly affected. </p><p>Planes will arrive in the UK this evening as usual, but it appears some will not do their next turnaround tomorrow and depart from the UK again.</p><p>I've been told airports will need to play “a logistical game of Tetris tonight to free up space” to make sure incoming aircraft can be parked overnight. Airports “will be having to park them remotely to ensure incoming long hauls have space", the industry source says.</p><p>It is unclear how many engineers will be needed at once to update software. The skies at this time of year are quieter after the peak summer period and before the Christmas festive rush begins.</p><p>It is understood about 80 aircraft are affected at Gatwick Airport.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:c39ec194-d8d7-49db-b0c0-4397435c47b8"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Air Canada not expecting any impact to operations</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:27 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <p>Air Canada says it's not expecting any impact to its operations as "very few of our aircraft use that version of the software". </p><p>However, connecting flights with other airlines could still be delayed by a knock-on effect. </p><p>Other Canadian Airlines WestJet and Porter don't have any of the A320 planes listed on their websites. </p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:250951a7-31eb-48e0-a1a2-752b3eb566d4"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>How long will repairs take?</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:25 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/10/3/2091d3c9-5f5f-46b1-8fad-7ab1a1b4ff9f.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Theo Leggett</strong><br>Business correspondent</span></p>
      <p>This issue affects around 6,000 aircraft.</p><p>For the majority of planes, the fix will involve installing new computer software. This should normally take about three hours.</p><p>But around 900 older planes will need computers replaced and will not be allowed to carry passengers again until the job has been completed.</p><p>How long that takes will depend on the availability of replacement computers.</p><p>It’s not yet clear whether there will be enough parts to meet demand.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:9527ee34-1ec6-4a96-8b19-21124ed8ec82"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>More airlines warn of potential service disruption</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:09 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <figure><p><span><img alt="The exterior of a Wizz Air plane" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/b40a7200-1bbd-4797-b84e-4190fa8ae84d.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/b40a7200-1bbd-4797-b84e-4190fa8ae84d.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/b40a7200-1bbd-4797-b84e-4190fa8ae84d.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/b40a7200-1bbd-4797-b84e-4190fa8ae84d.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/b40a7200-1bbd-4797-b84e-4190fa8ae84d.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/b40a7200-1bbd-4797-b84e-4190fa8ae84d.jpg.webp 800w" width="1024" height="576"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p></figure><p>We're hearing from more airlines around the world who are now reporting potential disruptions to services as a result of the immediate recall of aircraft by Airbus. </p><ul><li spacing="rich-text">
      <b>American Airlines</b> says 340 of its planes are affected and that it expects "some operational delays" but expects the vast majority of updates to completed today or tomorrow 
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      <b>Delta Airlines</b> says it will comply with Airbus's instruction but expects any resulting operational impact to be "limited"  
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      <b>Air India</b> says the instruction from Airbus could lead to a "longer turnaround and delays to our scheduled operations 
    </li><li spacing="rich-text">
      <b> Wizz Air</b> has warned passengers flying over this weekend that they may face disruption as a result of the update 
    </li></ul><p>We'll bring you further airline updates when we have them. </p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:eb7849cc-e610-4b64-bff6-2a5929d2dd5e"><header><span><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/core/website/assets/static/news/incident-types/light-mode/analysis.77b314ef10.svg" alt="Analysis" draggable="false"><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Why this is an extremely unusual issue</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 21:06 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/10/3/2091d3c9-5f5f-46b1-8fad-7ab1a1b4ff9f.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Theo Leggett</strong><br>Business correspondent</span></p>
      <p>It was experienced on one flight, when an aircraft flying from Cancun to New Jersey was affected by a sudden and intense solar storm.</p><p>The radiation corrupted data in the ELAC - a computer used to operate control surfaces on the wings and horizontal stabilizer.</p><p>The fault caused the plane to go into a sudden descent.</p><p>Airbus says the plane had recently had its software updated. The issue had never arisen with the previous software.</p><p>But now, it insists it is acting out of an abundance of caution.</p><p>It took the issue to regulators itself and asked airlines to make changes.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:0ee23aa0-ed6e-4e05-97af-83ff995410fa"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>EasyJet expects 'some disruption'</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 20:55 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <figure><p><span><img alt="EasyJet logo on an airplane is seen at Paris Charles de Gaulle Airport in paris, France on November 14th, 2025." src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/640/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/6b3e3b2f-1be9-40bd-b09e-31a881ccf730.jpg.webp" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/240/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/6b3e3b2f-1be9-40bd-b09e-31a881ccf730.jpg.webp 240w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/320/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/6b3e3b2f-1be9-40bd-b09e-31a881ccf730.jpg.webp 320w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/480/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/6b3e3b2f-1be9-40bd-b09e-31a881ccf730.jpg.webp 480w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/624/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/6b3e3b2f-1be9-40bd-b09e-31a881ccf730.jpg.webp 624w, https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/800/cpsprodpb/vivo/live/images/2025/11/28/6b3e3b2f-1be9-40bd-b09e-31a881ccf730.jpg.webp 800w" width="1024" height="576"></span><span role="text"><span>Image source, </span>Getty Images</span></p></figure><p>EasyJet says its aware of the communication from Airbus to airlines operating the A320 family aircraft and is "currently working closely with the safety authorities and Airbus to implement the action we need to take".</p><p>The airline says it is expecting this to result in some disruption and will "inform customers directly about any changes to our flying programme tomorrow and will do all possible to minimise the impact".</p><p>“Safety is our highest priority and EasyJet operates its fleet of aircraft in strict compliance with manufacturers guidelines,” its statement concludes. </p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:33939c74-f5b2-4bd3-a655-95622ba6a3f3"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Air New Zealand warns of disruption across number of flights today</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 20:51 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <p>Air New Zealand says it's currently affected by a "global software issue impacting Airbus A320neo aircraft", <a href="https://x.com/FlyAirNZ/status/1994505996757287349?s=20">it says in a post on social media platform X.<span>, <!-- -->external</span></a></p><p>"As a precaution, all our A320neo aircrafts will be receiving a software update before operating their next passenger service," the airline says. </p><p>The statement continues by saying "this will lead to disruption across a number of our A320neo flights today and we’re expecting a number of cancellations to services across that fleet".</p><p>"If you’re travelling today, we will be contacting customers directly if your flight is affected," the airline adds.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:ea79c503-26e3-4bbf-97ca-f8fd8aa46210"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>There may be impact to some flights, CAA warns</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 20:45 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header>
      <p>Tim Johnson from the UK's Civil Aviation Authority tells the BBC that there may be disruptions to flights "in some circumstances". </p><p>"From a UK perspective, not all airlines fly Airbus A320 or the affected ones, so for some airlines there will be no impact at all," he says. </p><p>"For some, there may be some impact," he continues, adding that the CAA has been in touch with airlines and they're looking to make sure the maintenance is undertaken over the coming days. </p><p>He says the advice to customers is to "check airline websites and apps for the latest info about what is happening".</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:a493362f-fc55-4906-b7ab-09cb07f37fd3"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>How did Airbus find the problem?</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 20:43 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2022/10/3/2091d3c9-5f5f-46b1-8fad-7ab1a1b4ff9f.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Theo Leggett</strong><br>Business correspondent</span></p>
      <p>The issue was discovered after a JetBlue aircraft en-route from Mexico to the United States in October experienced a ‘sudden drop in altitude’. </p><p>The plane made an emergency landing, with reports at the time suggesting 15 to 20 people suffered minor injuries. </p><p>It’s thought the incident was caused by intense solar radiation, which corrupted data in a computer used to help control the aircraft. </p><p>Now action is being taken to prevent further problems. About 6,000 aircraft worldwide are thought to be affected, all of them of the A320 family, which also includes the A319 and A321 models. </p><p>According to Airbus, the majority can be fixed with a relatively simple software update. However, some 900 older planes will need replacement computers, and will have to be taken out of service until they can be fixed.</p>
    </article></div></li><li><div><article data-testid="content-post" id="asset:f04053de-06a6-4363-92b1-3f5be6365089"><header><span><h3 type="normal"><span role="text"><span>Warning of disruption as thousand of Airbus planes require software update</span><span><span data-testid="timestamp"><span data-testid="accessible-timestamp">published at 20:26 GMT 28 November</span></span></span></span></h3></span></header><p><span><span><img alt="" loading="lazy" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/ace/standard/128/cpsprodpb//vivo/live/images/2023/3/13/c30ea702-5d4e-4d84-afea-041293d17acb.jpg.webp" width="64" height="64"></span></span><span><strong>Jamie Whitehead</strong><br>Live reporter</span></p>
      <p>Airbus says that flights will be disrupted after it requested
immediate modifications to thousands of its planes. </p><p>The plane manufacturer says it has found that intense
radiation from the Sun could corrupt data crucial to flight controls. </p><p>About 6,000 planes are thought to be affected, which is
around half of the company’s global fleet. </p><p>It’s thought most will be able to undergo a simple software
update. </p><p>We’ll be bringing you live coverage as well as information on
any potential disruption, stay with us. </p>
    </article></div></li></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>