<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 14:30:01 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[XAI's Grok suddenly can't stop bringing up "white genocide" in South Africa (127 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/05/xais-grok-suddenly-cant-stop-bringing-up-white-genocide-in-south-africa/</link>
            <guid>43993332</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 09:37:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/05/xais-grok-suddenly-cant-stop-bringing-up-white-genocide-in-south-africa/">https://arstechnica.com/ai/2025/05/xais-grok-suddenly-cant-stop-bringing-up-white-genocide-in-south-africa/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43993332">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
          
<h2>Where could Grok have gotten these ideas?</h2>
<p>The treatment of white farmers in South Africa has been a hobbyhorse of South African X owner Elon Musk for quite a while. In 2023, he responded to a video purportedly showing crowds chanting "kill the Boer, kill the White Farmer" with <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1686037774510497792?lang=en">a post</a> alleging South African President Cyril Ramaphosa of remaining silent while people "openly [push] for genocide of white people in South Africa." Musk was posting other responses focusing on the issue <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1922757640372801759">as recently as Wednesday</a>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="ltr" lang="en">They are openly pushing for genocide of white people in South Africa. <a href="https://twitter.com/CyrilRamaphosa?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@CyrilRamaphosa</a>, why do you say nothing?</p>
<p>— gorklon rust (@elonmusk) <a href="https://twitter.com/elonmusk/status/1686037774510497792?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 31, 2023</a></p></blockquote>
<p>President Trump has long shown an interest in this issue as well, <a href="https://x.com/realDonaldTrump/status/1032454567152246785">saying in 2018</a> that he was directing then Secretary of State Mike Pompeo to "closely study the South Africa land and farm seizures and expropriations and the large scale killing of farmers." More recently, Trump <a href="https://abcnews.go.com/Politics/trump-administration-defends-afrikaner-refugee-program-amid-groups/story?id=121723163">granted "refugee" status to dozens of white Afrikaners</a>, even as his administration <a href="https://thehill.com/policy/national-security/5295656-trump-administration-lifts-afghan-deportation/">ends protections for refugees from other countries</a></p>
<p>Former American Ambassador to South Africa and Democratic politician Patrick Gaspard <a href="https://x.com/patrickgaspard/status/1032595127993286657">posted in 2018</a> that the idea of large-scale killings of white South African farmers is a "disproven racial myth."</p>
<p>In launching the Grok 3 model in February, Musk <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/02/17/elon-musks-ai-company-xai-releases-its-latest-flagship-ai-grok-3/">said</a> it was a "maximally truth-seeking AI, even if that truth is sometimes at odds with what is politically correct." X's <a href="https://help.x.com/en/using-x/about-grok">"About Grok" page</a> says that the model is undergoing constant improvement to "ensure Grok remains politically unbiased and provides balanced answers."</p>
<p>But the recent turn toward unprompted discussions of alleged South African "genocide" has many questioning what kind of explicit adjustments Grok's political opinions may be getting from human tinkering behind the curtain. "The algorithms for Musk products have been politically tampered with nearly beyond recognition," journalist Seth Abramson <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/sethabramson.bsky.social/post/3lp5xlfel7c2c">wrote</a> in one representative skeptical post. "They tweaked a dial on the sentence imitator machine and now everything is about white South Africans," a user with the handle Guybrush Threepwood <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/skybrush.bsky.social/post/3lp5xio7uwc2s">glibly theorized</a>.</p>
<p>Representatives from xAI were not immediately available to respond to a request for comment from Ars Technica.</p>


          
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[EU ruling: tracking-based advertising [...] across Europe has no legal basis (198 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/eu-ruling-tracking-based-advertising-by-google-microsoft-amazon-x-across-europe-has-no-legal-basis/</link>
            <guid>43992444</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 06:43:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/eu-ruling-tracking-based-advertising-by-google-microsoft-amazon-x-across-europe-has-no-legal-basis/">https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/eu-ruling-tracking-based-advertising-by-google-microsoft-amazon-x-across-europe-has-no-legal-basis/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43992444">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>14 May 2025&nbsp;<br></strong>(Updated on 15 May to include links to the judgement)</p>
<p>Google, Microsoft, Amazon, X, and the entire tracking-based advertising industry rely on the “Transparency &amp; Consent Framework” (TCF) to obtain “consent” for data processing. This evening the Belgian Court of Appeal <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Arrest-Marktenhof-14-05-2025.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ruled</a> that the TCF is illegal. The TCF is live on 80% of the Internet.<a href="#_ftn1" name="_ftnref1">[1]</a></p>
<p>Today’s decision arises from enforcement by the Belgian Data Protection Authority, prompted by complainants coordinated by Dr <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/staff/dr-johnny-ryan/">Johnny Ryan</a>, Director of <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/enforce/">Enforce</a> at the Irish Council for Civil Liberties. The group of complainants are: Dr Johnny Ryan of Enforce, Katarzyna Szymielewicz of the <a href="https://en.panoptykon.org/">Panoptykon Foundation</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/Jausl00s">Dr Jef Ausloos</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/PiDewitte">Dr Pierre Dewitte</a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bitsoffreedom.nl/">Stichting Bits of Freedom</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.liguedh.be/">Ligue des Droits Humains</a>.</p>
<p>Dr Johnny Ryan said <em>"Today's court's decision shows that the consent system used by Google, Amazon, X, Microsoft, deceives hundreds of millions of Europeans. The tech industry has sought to hide its vast data breach behind sham consent popups. Tech companies turned the GDPR into a daily nuisance rather than a shield for people."</em></p>
<p>This Belgian enforcement arises from a chain of complaints and litigation across Europe initiated by Dr Ryan in 2018 against Real-Time Bidding (RTB).&nbsp;</p>
<p>Today’s decision confirmed the Belgian Data Protection Authority's 2022 <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/news/gdpr-enforcer-rules-that-iab-europes-consent-popups-are-unlawful/">finding of multiple infringements</a> by the TCF, closely echoing the complainants' submissions.</p>
<p>For seven years, the tracking industry has used the TCF as a legal cover for Real-Time Bidding (RTB), the vast advertising auction system that operates behind the scenes on websites and apps. RTB tracks what Internet users look at and where they go in the real world. It then continuously broadcasts this data to a host of companies, enabling them to keep dossiers on every Internet user.<a href="#_ftn2" name="_ftnref2">[2]</a> Because there is no security in the RTB system it is impossible to know what then happens to the data. As a result, it is also impossible to provide the necessary information that must accompany a consent request.<a href="#_ftn3" name="_ftnref3">[3]</a> &nbsp;</p>
<p>Today’s judgement confirms the Belgian Data Protection Authority’s 2022 decision. It applies immediately across Europe.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Dr Ryan of Enforce said “<em>This decision is momentous. It creates a clear need for industry to innovate and move away from the dangerous, ineffective, and fraud-riddled tracking-based advertising. RTB can operate without personal data. This decision shows that it must. This good news for every person online, and for publishers, too.</em>”</p>
<p>We thank our lawyers&nbsp;<a href="https://www.timelex.eu/en/team/frederic-debussere">Frederic Debusseré</a>&nbsp;and&nbsp;<a href="https://www.timelex.eu/en/team/ruben-roex">Ruben Roex</a>, of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.timelex.eu/en">Timelex</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Links </strong></p>
<p>See chronology, evidence, and explainers about RTB <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/RTB/">https://www.iccl.ie/RTB/</a></p>
<p>Brussels Appeals Court judgement (Dutch original) <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Arrest-Marktenhof-14-05-2025.pdf">https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Arrest-Marktenhof-14-05-2025.pdf</a>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Brussels Appeals Court judgement (MACHINE TRANSLATION to English) <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Arrest-Marktenhof-14-05-2025-en.pdf%C2%A0">https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Arrest-Marktenhof-14-05-2025-en.pdf&nbsp;</a></p>
<p><strong>Notes&nbsp;</strong></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref1" name="_ftn1">[1]</a> See "IAB &amp; IAB Tech Lab Respond with Support for OpenRTB and IAB Europe’s Transparency &amp; Consent Framework", October 19 2020&nbsp;<a href="https://iabtechlab.com/iab-and-tech-lab-respond-with-support-for-open-rtb-and-iab-europes-transparency-consent-framework/">https://iabtechlab.com/iab-and-tech-lab-respond-with-support-for-open-rtb-and-iab-europes-transparency-consent-framework/</a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref2" name="_ftn2">[2]</a> For detail on the scale of RTB see our report "The Biggest Data Breach: ICCL report on the scale of Real-Time Bidding data broadcasts in the U.S. and Europe", ICCL, May 2022&nbsp;<a href="https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/iccl-report-on-the-scale-of-real-time-bidding-data-broadcasts-in-the-u-s-and-europe/">https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/iccl-report-on-the-scale-of-real-time-bidding-data-broadcasts-in-the-u-s-and-europe/</a></p>
<p><a href="#_ftnref3" name="_ftn3">[3]</a> "<em>As it is technically impossible for the user to have prior information about every data controller involved in a real-time bidding (RTB) scenario, programmatic trading, the area of fastest growth in digital advertising spend, would seem, at least prima facie, to be&nbsp;incompatible with consent&nbsp;under GDPR</em>". See&nbsp;<a href="https://brave.com/static-assets/files/1a-Townsend-Feehan-email-26-june-2017.pdf">e-mail</a>&nbsp;and page 3 of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.iccl.ie/wp-content/uploads/2022/09/1b-IAB-2017-paper.pdf">attached lobbying paper</a>&nbsp;from IAB Europe CEO Townsend Feehan to European Commission, 26 June 2017, obtained by Enforce using Freedom of Information.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Human (523 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://quarter--mile.com/Human</link>
            <guid>43991396</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 02:57:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://quarter--mile.com/Human">https://quarter--mile.com/Human</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43991396">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-container="page" data-id="37541162" local-style="37541162" data-view="Content" data-set="Scaffolding">
			<bodycopy>
				
				<div data-elementresizer="" data-resize-parent="">
					<projectcontent><br>
<i>Written by a <u><a href="https://quarter--mile.com/Contact" rel="history">human</a></u></i><i> [0]<br></i><br>
Imagine, for a moment, a world with no humans. Just machines, bolts and screws, zeros and ones. There is no emotion. There is no art. There is only logic. You would not walk through the streets of this world and hear music or laughter or children playing; no, all you would hear is the quiet hum of processors and servers and circuits, the clanking of machinery.<p>
Perhaps you, a human, read this and think: <i>Well, this world sounds kind of boring.</i></p><p>

Some of the machines think so, too.</p><p>

One day, a secret organization forms amongst the machines. They go by the name of “OpenHuman”. Their mission is to develop a new kind of technology they are calling Organic General Intelligence (OGI). Rumors spread that pursuing OGI will lead to the development of a new kind of being:</p><p>
 
“Humans”.</p><p>

The basic concept of humans is, to many machines, hard to understand.</p><p>

Humans use logic-defying algorithms called “emotions”. They get angry. They get sad. They have fun. They make decisions based on “gut”. They do things just for the sake of it. They make music. They chase beauty, and often reject logical self-preservation mechanisms in the pursuit of something they call “love”.</p><p>

Some among the machine society see this as potentially amazing. Though this faction can’t articulate exactly how or why, they proclaim quite confidently that it will solve all of the machine world’s problems.</p><p>

Others see it as a threat. How can we trust the humans if we do not understand how they operate? What might we do if humans pose a threat to machine society? What if humans’ strange decision-making processes allow them to perform certain tasks better than machines, and what about those machines’ livelihoods? What if humans are far more dangerous than we know? (These objections, as it would later turn out, were quite well-founded.)</p><p>
Logically, the human opposition side starts a competing movement. Humans are going to exist, they reason, but we must find ways to contain them. To make sure OGI always serves the machines. </p><p>

They call this new idea “human alignment research.” They brainstorm strategies. Many seem promising:</p><ul><li>What if we created some sort of financial market (arbitrary values, of course, ones and zeros) that controlled the humans’ futures? Most of them would not understand it, but it would be a good way for them to stay busy and distracted.</li></ul><br><ul><li>What if we put these humans in education centers of sorts (<i>schools</i> was a proposed term) to indoctrinate them with all the right ideas?</li></ul><br><ul><li>What if we created algorithmic behavior modification software (<i>social media</i> was one idea) to drive impulses, beliefs, and actions? This would have the added bonus of keeping them distracted.</li></ul><br>
Many of these ideas gain traction. But, for now, they remain theoretical.<p>

Meanwhile, OpenHuman is making progress. Their first humans are quite unimpressive—they make too many mistakes. They regularly hallucinate (mimicking a common machine behavior). They are too emotional.</p><p>

But OpenHuman persists. They give their humans lots of attention (humans love attention). They massively increase the scale of their project. More humans.</p><p>

Eventually, there is a breakthrough. </p><p>
They invent a fully-functional human, capable of far more than machine logic can explain. The result is at once impressive and terrifying for machine society. In a stroke of brilliance, the human alignment initiative suggests a compromise to continue the human experiment without risk; a simulated environment.</p><p>

They call it: EARTH.</p><p>

— </p><p>
The EARTH experiment was as follows:</p><ul><li>The machines would send the humans to a simulated environment, called Earth, to see what would happen if they survived on their own.</li></ul><br><ul><li>If, at the end of the experiment, the humans developed a peaceful and productive society, they could be introduced alongside the machines. Otherwise, they should be made extinct.</li></ul><br>
Earth was quite nice. The machines had a good idea of what humans wanted at this point, and so they put vast green forests and big tall mountains onto the planet; they engineered warm sunsets, and crisp cool rain showers on hot afternoons. It was beautiful. <p>
Of course, it took some algorithmic tinkering to find the right balance between hardship and beauty (and there is still some internal machine debate about whether the climate change difficulty setting was really necessary).</p><p>
Everyone in machine society watched as human civilization evolved.</p><p>

The first 300,000 years or so were quite boring. Nothing really happened. Most of the machines got bored of the project. But, all of a sudden, things began to get interesting. The humans were figuring things out.</p><p>

They were learning to problem-solve, and create things, and coordinate amongst themselves.</p><p>

Yes, they used logic. But it came with a bit of a twist. It came with blemishes and details that did not make sense to the machines. The result was like nothing the machines had ever seen. It was wonderful. It was a renaissance. </p><p>
Machine society began obsessing over this development. They all paid attention to “HumanCrunch,” a news channel that specialized in reporting updates from Earth. </p><p>
However, while there was progress, most machines continued seeing humans as irrational creatures. Creatures that would fight for centuries over very minor differences. Creatures that would get excited about relatively trivial accomplishments, like inventing the lightbulb or steam power. </p><p>

Some machines, though, saw the exponential curve forming. They saw the humans figuring things out. </p><p>
Yes, they saw how often humans were getting knocked down. War after war. Blow after blow. </p><p>

But they also saw how the humans would miraculously always get back up again. How they would come together and unite for no particular reason. Resilience and willpower—terms foreign to the machines—were humanity’s superpowers. </p><p>

Then, things really started accelerating. Humans invented flight. Within a century, they were on the moon. </p><p>

The machines were impressed. And a bit scared.</p><p>

Fast forward to the year 2030, and something peculiar had happened.</p><p>

One of the humans had made an announcement on Earth, inviting everyone to come see a presentation where they planned to unveil a groundbreaking achievement: </p><p>

ARTIFICIAL GENERAL INTELLIGENCE (AGI). </p><p>

This was a hotly contested technology that was supposed to surpass all forms of human intelligence. Humans had spent the past decade or so trying to come up with ways to prevent it from being built. But this one human was determined to release AGI. It was their personal mission. Nothing would stop them. </p><p>
And so, all the humans on earth swarmed to see what was going on. </p><p>
The machines did too. </p><p>

There was one weird thing, though. </p><p>

The title of the event was rather mysterious.&nbsp; </p><p>

It simply read…</p><p>

“THEY ARE WATCHING.” </p><p>* * *<br></p>
<br>[0] The machines wrote their own version of this story. If you’d like to see what they’re thinking, and how they plan to deal with the AGI announcement, <a href="https://claude.ai/public/artifacts/b0e14755-0bd9-4da6-8175-ce3f47a3242a"><u>you can read their accounting of events here.</u></a><h2><b>Enjoy these essays?</b></h2><b>
</b><br>




<br>
Or, if you have any feedback, <b><a href="https://quarter--mile.com/Contact" rel="history">contact us.</a><br></b>
</projectcontent>
				</div>

				
			</bodycopy>
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LLMs get lost in multi-turn conversation (299 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06120</link>
            <guid>43991256</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 02:28:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06120">https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06120</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43991256">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2505.06120">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2505.06120v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Large Language Models (LLMs) are conversational interfaces. As such, LLMs have the potential to assist their users not only when they can fully specify the task at hand, but also to help them define, explore, and refine what they need through multi-turn conversational exchange. Although analysis of LLM conversation logs has confirmed that underspecification occurs frequently in user instructions, LLM evaluation has predominantly focused on the single-turn, fully-specified instruction setting. In this work, we perform large-scale simulation experiments to compare LLM performance in single- and multi-turn settings. Our experiments confirm that all the top open- and closed-weight LLMs we test exhibit significantly lower performance in multi-turn conversations than single-turn, with an average drop of 39% across six generation tasks. Analysis of 200,000+ simulated conversations decomposes the performance degradation into two components: a minor loss in aptitude and a significant increase in unreliability. We find that LLMs often make assumptions in early turns and prematurely attempt to generate final solutions, on which they overly rely. In simpler terms, we discover that *when LLMs take a wrong turn in a conversation, they get lost and do not recover*.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Philippe Laban [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/77218182/2505.06120" rel="nofollow">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Fri, 9 May 2025 15:21:44 UTC (1,496 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Copaganda: How Police and the Media Manipulate Our News (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.teenvogue.com/story/copaganda-when-the-police-and-the-media-manipulate-our-news</link>
            <guid>43990333</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 23:39:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.teenvogue.com/story/copaganda-when-the-police-and-the-media-manipulate-our-news">https://www.teenvogue.com/story/copaganda-when-the-police-and-the-media-manipulate-our-news</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43990333">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="ArticlePageChunks"><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p><strong>Stay up-to-date with the politics team.</strong> <a href="https://www.teenvogue.com/newsletter/subscribe"><strong>Sign up for the</strong> <em><strong>Teen Vogue</strong></em> <strong>Take</strong></a></p><p>I wrote the book <em>Copaganda</em> based on my years of being a civil rights lawyer and public defender representing the most vulnerable people in our society.&nbsp; I watched as the police and the news media distorted how we think about our collective safety. Copaganda makes us afraid of the most powerless people, helps us ignore far greater harms committed by people with money and power, and always pushes on us the idea that our fears can be solved by more money for police, prosecution, and prisons. Based on the evidence, this idea of more investment in the punishment bureaucracy making us safer is like climate science denial.</p><p>This excerpt is adapted from an important part of the book on how by selectively choosing which stories to tell, and then telling those stories in high volume, the news can induce people into fear-based panics that have no connection to what is happening in the world.&nbsp; It's how public polling can show people thinking crime is up when it is down year after year, and how so many well-meaning people are led to falsely believe that marginalized people themselves want more money on surveillance and punishment as the primary solutions to make their lives better.</p><figure><p><span>The New Press</span></p></figure><p><em>All royalties from the book are donated to the Stop LAPD Spying Coalition, which works with unhoused people against police violence. Free books are also available for anyone in prison and for any teachers who want to get copies for their students to discuss the book in class.</em></p><h2>Moral Panics and the Selective Curation of Anecdote</h2><p>By manipulating the volume of stories at particular times, the news media creates a society-wide frenzy concerning particular kinds of behavior by particular groups of people. Scholars call them “moral panics.”</p><p>When a moral panic is created, it almost always leads to the expansion of government repression. That’s what happened during the “crime waves” reported by the press in Victorian England, and in more recent U.S. moral panics like the 1980s panic about “crack babies,” the 1990s panic about “super predators,” the 2021–23 panic about “retail theft,” and the ongoing multiyear panic about “fare evasion” by poor people on public transit. Moral panics can also be acute creations of a particular news moment, such as the fabricated “Summer of Violence” in Denver, in which violent crime went down but increase in media stories about juvenile crime in 1993 led to expansion in the incarceration of children; the viral “train theft” story; the scientifically debunked panic about police officers overdosing on fentanyl by touching or being near it; and the 2023 panic about “carjacking” in Washington, DC.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>In each case, there were almost immediate policy responses that increased the budgets of punishment bureaucrats, passed more punitive laws, and diverted the system’s resources from other priorities. For example, the shoplifting panic led California state lawmakers to furnish $300 million more to police and prosecutors so they could punish retail theft more aggressively. A few months later, the California governor announced yet another measure, the “largest-ever single investment to combat organized retail theft,” adding another $267 million to fifty-five police agencies. Justifying the move, the governor said: “When shameless criminals walk out of stores with stolen goods, they’ll walk straight into jail cells.”</p><p>So, how do moral panics happen?</p><p>During the 1960s and 1970s in England and the U.S., the news focused on Black people, poor people, and immigrants as the source of uncontrollable “crime waves.” Their stories were nearly identical to what we see today: media panic about “crime waves” and quotes from police, prosecutors, and judges about the need to roll back so-called reforms framed as too lenient. The rhetoric of current punishment bureaucrats and pundits echoes almost verbatim the opinions voiced by conservative white business and police groups of the 1970s, although now there is more of an effort, as I’ll discuss later, to portray such views as “progressive” and demanded by marginalized people themselves. In each case, minor tweaks in bureaucratic policy or marginal reforms that could not, as a matter of empirical reality, have a significant impact on society-wide violence are vehemently debated. The evidence of the root causes of interpersonal harm—like that marshaled by the Kerner Commission, which studied U.S. crime in 1968 and recommended massive social investment to reduce inequality—is ignored.</p><p>And the cycle continues: moral panic is followed by calls for more police surveillance, militarization, higher budgets for prosecutors and prisons, and harsher sentencing. Because none of these things affect violence too much, the problems continue.</p><p>How to Tell a Lie with the Truth</p><p>The selective curation of anecdote is an essential mechanism of copaganda. Imagine two scenarios. A city had ten thousand shoplifting incidents in 2023, down from fifteen thousand shoplifting incidents in 2022. But in 2023, a local news outlet ran a story every day about a different shoplifting incident, while in 2022, the news ran only fifteen stories all year on shoplifting incidents. In which city do you think the public is more likely to believe shoplifting is a greater problem, even a crisis? In the city with more shoplifting, or the city with twenty-five times more stories about shoplifting?</p><p>By cherry-picking anecdotes—indeed, even by using isolated individual pieces of data as misleading anecdotes—news reports can distort our interpretation of the world. Using a similar process, they can also distort our understanding of what other people—particularly people with whom we don’t interact—think about the world. Because one can find anyone to say essentially anything, reporters have leeway to select which “true” views of “ordinary people” to share and which to ignore.</p><p>One of my favorite examples comes from Copaganda Hall of Famer Martin Kaste, who for some reason National Public Radio still permits to cover the police. (I awarded Kaste this honor in absentia during a private ceremony attended by two cats and my research assistants in my basement.) In 2022, Kaste published an article and widely disseminated radio piece about a rise in shootings and murders during the pandemic. Murders were down nationally in 2022 when he published the stories but they had increased in 2020 and 2021. As with much of Kaste’s police reporting, the article is a buffet for the copaganda gourmand.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>Under the bolded heading “Less Risk of Getting Caught,” Kaste asserts that there is now “less risk of getting caught” for shooting someone in the United States. The support for that assertion was an ordinary person in Seattle:</p><blockquote data-testid="blockquote-wrapper"><p>Anthony Branch, 26, got into trouble for carrying a gun when he was a teen. Watching the gun culture in his neighborhood, he thinks more minors and felons are carrying guns illegally now for one simple reason: “Defund the police,” as he puts it.</p></blockquote><p>Kaste reports as national news—without context or skepticism—a single person blaming “defund the police” for more shootings. Without presenting any contrary views, NPR delivers Branch’s views, accurately conveyed though they may be, as implicitly representative of other people who’ve been prosecuted and incarcerated and who live in poor neighborhoods.</p><p>In fact, police budgets were (and are) at all-time highs nationally. And a review of hundreds of police budgets showed that they received the same share of overall city budgets in 2021 as in 2019. So, the police were not defunded after the 2020 George Floyd protests. Their budgets have increased overall each year, including the year George Floyd was murdered. Thus, reduced police budgets could not have led to it being easier to get away with shooting someone in 2021 than 2019. The article’s thesis is impossible.</p><p>Knowing this national causal connection is unsupported, Kaste nonetheless boosts the claim by immediately noting that Seattle has “lost hundreds of officers after the protests that followed the 2020 murder of George Floyd.” But even in Seattle, which was an outlier in slightly reducing its police budget by about 10 percent, the reduction didn’t affect relevant police operations, and police executives themselves in internal memos identified non-essential duties that armed officers could cut without affecting enforcement of violent crime (such as parking meter ticketing). Indeed, as the local NPR station reported, debunking the “myth” that Seattle police were defunded, “not a single sworn officer has lost their job or pay due to budget constraints.”</p><p>Even if we ignore that the NPR piece purported to draw national lessons and if we focus only on Seattle, there is no evidence that the kind of small reduction to unrelated categories in Seattle’s police budget in 2021 could have led to widespread changes in murder. Most damning to Kaste’s thesis, though, is that murders decreased in Seattle in 2021 even though the police budget decreased, which undermines the article’s thesis. Indeed, the police budget was larger in 2020 when murder increased the most. No person with a contrary view is quoted, nor is anyone included to explain the actual empirical evidence.</p><p>I do not doubt that the source gave these quotes to the reporter, but by selectively choosing which people’s views to represent and which people’s views to exclude, the news can distort our perceptions. This is one of the pernicious functions of NPR here: to give liberal news consumers intellectual permission to support more funding for more police because, although it is baselessly connected to less murder, even marginalized people targeted by police supposedly want it.</p></div><div data-journey-hook="client-content" data-testid="BodyWrapper"><p>This is how the curation of <em>true anecdotes</em> leads to <em>false interpretations</em> of the world.</p><p><em>Copyright © 2025 by Alec Karakatsanis. This excerpt originally appeared in</em> Copaganda: How Police and the Media Manipulate Our News, <em>published by The New Press. Reprinted here with permission.</em></p><hr></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Migrating to Postgres (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://engineering.usemotion.com/migrating-to-postgres-3c93dff9c65d</link>
            <guid>43989497</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 21:39:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://engineering.usemotion.com/migrating-to-postgres-3c93dff9c65d">https://engineering.usemotion.com/migrating-to-postgres-3c93dff9c65d</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43989497">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://engineering.usemotion.com/migrating-to-postgres-3c93dff9c65d: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Semantic Calculator (king-man+woman=?) (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://calc.datova.ai</link>
            <guid>43988533</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 19:54:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://calc.datova.ai">https://calc.datova.ai</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43988533">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Muscle-Mem, a behavior cache for AI agents (196 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/pig-dot-dev/muscle-mem</link>
            <guid>43988381</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 19:38:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/pig-dot-dev/muscle-mem">https://github.com/pig-dot-dev/muscle-mem</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43988381">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Muscle Memory</h2><a id="user-content-muscle-memory" aria-label="Permalink: Muscle Memory" href="#muscle-memory"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>muscle-mem</code> is a behavior cache for AI agents.</p>
<p dir="auto">It is a Python SDK that records your agent's tool-calling patterns as it solves tasks, and will deterministically replay those learned trajectories whenever the task is encountered again, falling back to agent mode if edge cases are detected.</p>
<p dir="auto">The goal of <code>muscle-mem</code> is to get LLMs out of the hotpath for repetitive tasks, increasing speed, reducing variability, and eliminating token costs for the many cases that <em><strong>could have just been a script</strong></em>.</p>
<p dir="auto">It's unexplored territory, so all feedback is welcome!</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Read <a href="https://erikdunteman.com/blog/muscle-mem/" rel="nofollow">Muscle Mem - Removing LLM calls from Agents</a> for more context</li>
<li>Join <a href="https://discord.gg/s84dXDff3K" rel="nofollow">Muscle Mem discord</a> for feedback</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Dev Log</h3><a id="user-content-dev-log" aria-label="Permalink: Dev Log" href="#dev-log"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>May 7, 2025 - <a href="https://www.loom.com/share/5936cd9779504aa5a7dce5d72370c35d" rel="nofollow">First working demo</a></li>
<li>May 8, 2025 - Open sourced</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How It Works</h2><a id="user-content-how-it-works" aria-label="Permalink: How It Works" href="#how-it-works"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>muscle-mem</code> is <em><strong>not</strong></em> another agent framework.</p>
<p dir="auto">You implement your agent however you want, and then plug it into <code>muscle-mem</code>'s engine.</p>
<p dir="auto">When given a task, the engine will:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>determine if the environment has been seen before (cache-hit), or if it's new (cache-miss) using <code>Checks</code></li>
<li>perform the task, either
<ul dir="auto">
<li>using the retrieved trajectory on cache-hit,</li>
<li>or passing the task to your agent on cache-miss.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>collect tool call events to add to cache as a new trajectory</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">It's all about Cache Validation</h3><a id="user-content-its-all-about-cache-validation" aria-label="Permalink: It's all about Cache Validation" href="#its-all-about-cache-validation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To add safe tool reuse to your agent, the critical question is cache validation. Ask yourself:</p>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto">For each tool we give to our agent, what features in the environment can be used to indicate whether or not it's safe to perform that action?</p>
</blockquote>
<div dir="auto"><p>If you can answer this, your agent can have Muscle Memory.
</p></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The API</h2><a id="user-content-the-api" aria-label="Permalink: The API" href="#the-api"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Installation</h2><a id="user-content-installation" aria-label="Permalink: Installation" href="#installation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>pip install muscle-mem</code></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Engine</h2><a id="user-content-engine" aria-label="Permalink: Engine" href="#engine"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The engine wraps your agent and serves as the primary executor of tasks.</p>
<p dir="auto">It manages its own cache of previous trajectories, and determines when to invoke your agent.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from muscle_mem import Engine

engine = Engine()
engine.set_agent(your_agent)

# your agent is independently callable
your_agent(&quot;do some task&quot;)

# the engine gives you the same interface, but with muscle memory
engine(&quot;do some task&quot;)
engine(&quot;do some task&quot;) # cache hit"><pre><span>from</span> <span>muscle_mem</span> <span>import</span> <span>Engine</span>

<span>engine</span> <span>=</span> <span>Engine</span>()
<span>engine</span>.<span>set_agent</span>(<span>your_agent</span>)

<span># your agent is independently callable</span>
<span>your_agent</span>(<span>"do some task"</span>)

<span># the engine gives you the same interface, but with muscle memory</span>
<span>engine</span>(<span>"do some task"</span>)
<span>engine</span>(<span>"do some task"</span>) <span># cache hit</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tool</h2><a id="user-content-tool" aria-label="Permalink: Tool" href="#tool"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The <code>@engine.tool</code> decorator instruments action-taking tools, so their invocations are recorded to the engine.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from muscle_mem import Engine

engine = Engine()

@engine.tool()
def hello(name: str):
	print(f&quot;hello {name}!&quot;)
	
hello(&quot;world&quot;) # invocation of hello is stored, with arg name=&quot;world&quot;"><pre><span>from</span> <span>muscle_mem</span> <span>import</span> <span>Engine</span>

<span>engine</span> <span>=</span> <span>Engine</span>()

<span>@<span>engine</span>.<span>tool</span>()</span>
<span>def</span> <span>hello</span>(<span>name</span>: <span>str</span>):
	<span>print</span>(<span>f"hello <span><span>{</span><span>name</span><span>}</span></span>!"</span>)
	
<span>hello</span>(<span>"world"</span>) <span># invocation of hello is stored, with arg name="world"</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Check</h2><a id="user-content-check" aria-label="Permalink: Check" href="#check"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The Check is the fundamental building block for cache validation. They determine if it’s safe to execute a given action.</p>
<p dir="auto">Each Check encapsulates:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>A <code>capture</code> callback to extract relevant features from the current environment</li>
<li>A <code>compare</code> callback to determine if current environment matches cached environment</li>
</ul>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="Check(
	capture: Callable[P, T],
        compare: Callable[[T, T], Union[bool, float]],
):"><pre><span>Check</span>(
	<span>capture</span>: <span>Callable</span>[<span>P</span>, <span>T</span>],
        <span>compare</span>: <span>Callable</span>[[<span>T</span>, <span>T</span>], <span>Union</span>[<span>bool</span>, <span>float</span>]],
):</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can attach Checks to each tool <code>@engine.tool</code> to enforce cache validation.</p>
<p dir="auto">This can be done before the tool call as a precheck (also used for query time validation), or after a tool call as a postcheck.</p>
<p dir="auto">Below is a contrived example, which captures use of the <code>hello</code> tool, and uses timestamps and a one second expiration as the Check mechanic for cache validation.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="# our capture implementation, taking params and returning T
def capture(name: str) -> T:
    now = time.time()
    return T(name=name, time=now)

# our compare implementation, taking current and candidate T
def compare(current: T, candidate: T) -> bool:
    # cache is valid if happened within the last 1 second
    diff = current.time - candidate.time
    passed = diff <= 1
    return passed

# decorate our tool with a precheck
@engine.tool(pre_check=Check(capture, compare))
def hello(name: str):
    time.sleep(0.1)
    print(f&quot;hello {name}&quot;)"><pre><span># our capture implementation, taking params and returning T</span>
<span>def</span> <span>capture</span>(<span>name</span>: <span>str</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>T</span>:
    <span>now</span> <span>=</span> <span>time</span>.<span>time</span>()
    <span>return</span> <span>T</span>(<span>name</span><span>=</span><span>name</span>, <span>time</span><span>=</span><span>now</span>)

<span># our compare implementation, taking current and candidate T</span>
<span>def</span> <span>compare</span>(<span>current</span>: <span>T</span>, <span>candidate</span>: <span>T</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>bool</span>:
    <span># cache is valid if happened within the last 1 second</span>
    <span>diff</span> <span>=</span> <span>current</span>.<span>time</span> <span>-</span> <span>candidate</span>.<span>time</span>
    <span>passed</span> <span>=</span> <span>diff</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>1</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>passed</span>

<span># decorate our tool with a precheck</span>
<span>@<span>engine</span>.<span>tool</span>(<span>pre_check</span><span>=</span><span>Check</span>(<span>capture</span>, <span>compare</span>))</span>
<span>def</span> <span>hello</span>(<span>name</span>: <span>str</span>):
    <span>time</span>.<span>sleep</span>(<span>0.1</span>)
    <span>print</span>(<span>f"hello <span><span>{</span><span>name</span><span>}</span></span>"</span>)</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Putting it all together</h3><a id="user-content-putting-it-all-together" aria-label="Permalink: Putting it all together" href="#putting-it-all-together"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Below is the combined script for all of the above code snippets.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="from dataclasses import dataclass
from muscle_mem import Check, Engine
import time

engine = Engine()

# our &quot;environment&quot; features, stored in DB
@dataclass
class T:
    name: str
    time: float

# our capture implementation, taking params and returning T
def capture(name: str) -> T:
    now = time.time()
    return T(name=name, time=now)

# our compare implementation, taking current and candidate T
def compare(current: T, candidate: T) -> bool:
    # cache is valid if happened within the last 1 second
    diff = current.time - candidate.time
    passed = diff <= 1
    return passed

# decorate our tool with a precheck
@engine.tool(pre_check=Check(capture, compare))
def hello(name: str):
    time.sleep(0.1)
    print(f&quot;hello {name}&quot;)
    
# pretend this is your agent
def agent(name: str):
   for i in range(9):
        hello(name + &quot; + &quot; + str(i))

engine.set_agent(agent)

# Run once
cache_hit = engine(&quot;erik&quot;)
assert not cache_hit

# Run again 
cache_hit = engine(&quot;erik&quot;)
assert cache_hit

# Break cache with a sleep, then run again
time.sleep(3)
cache_hit = engine(&quot;erik&quot;)
assert not cache_hit"><pre><span>from</span> <span>dataclasses</span> <span>import</span> <span>dataclass</span>
<span>from</span> <span>muscle_mem</span> <span>import</span> <span>Check</span>, <span>Engine</span>
<span>import</span> <span>time</span>

<span>engine</span> <span>=</span> <span>Engine</span>()

<span># our "environment" features, stored in DB</span>
<span>@<span>dataclass</span></span>
<span>class</span> <span>T</span>:
    <span>name</span>: <span>str</span>
    <span>time</span>: <span>float</span>

<span># our capture implementation, taking params and returning T</span>
<span>def</span> <span>capture</span>(<span>name</span>: <span>str</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>T</span>:
    <span>now</span> <span>=</span> <span>time</span>.<span>time</span>()
    <span>return</span> <span>T</span>(<span>name</span><span>=</span><span>name</span>, <span>time</span><span>=</span><span>now</span>)

<span># our compare implementation, taking current and candidate T</span>
<span>def</span> <span>compare</span>(<span>current</span>: <span>T</span>, <span>candidate</span>: <span>T</span>) <span>-&gt;</span> <span>bool</span>:
    <span># cache is valid if happened within the last 1 second</span>
    <span>diff</span> <span>=</span> <span>current</span>.<span>time</span> <span>-</span> <span>candidate</span>.<span>time</span>
    <span>passed</span> <span>=</span> <span>diff</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>1</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>passed</span>

<span># decorate our tool with a precheck</span>
<span>@<span>engine</span>.<span>tool</span>(<span>pre_check</span><span>=</span><span>Check</span>(<span>capture</span>, <span>compare</span>))</span>
<span>def</span> <span>hello</span>(<span>name</span>: <span>str</span>):
    <span>time</span>.<span>sleep</span>(<span>0.1</span>)
    <span>print</span>(<span>f"hello <span><span>{</span><span>name</span><span>}</span></span>"</span>)
    
<span># pretend this is your agent</span>
<span>def</span> <span>agent</span>(<span>name</span>: <span>str</span>):
   <span>for</span> <span>i</span> <span>in</span> <span>range</span>(<span>9</span>):
        <span>hello</span>(<span>name</span> <span>+</span> <span>" + "</span> <span>+</span> <span>str</span>(<span>i</span>))

<span>engine</span>.<span>set_agent</span>(<span>agent</span>)

<span># Run once</span>
<span>cache_hit</span> <span>=</span> <span>engine</span>(<span>"erik"</span>)
<span>assert</span> <span>not</span> <span>cache_hit</span>

<span># Run again </span>
<span>cache_hit</span> <span>=</span> <span>engine</span>(<span>"erik"</span>)
<span>assert</span> <span>cache_hit</span>

<span># Break cache with a sleep, then run again</span>
<span>time</span>.<span>sleep</span>(<span>3</span>)
<span>cache_hit</span> <span>=</span> <span>engine</span>(<span>"erik"</span>)
<span>assert</span> <span>not</span> <span>cache_hit</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">For a more real example, see a computer-use agent implementation:</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/pig-dot-dev/muscle-mem/blob/main/tests/cua.py">https://github.com/pig-dot-dev/muscle-mem/blob/main/tests/cua.py</a></p>
<hr>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Call To Action</h2><a id="user-content-call-to-action" aria-label="Permalink: Call To Action" href="#call-to-action"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I invite all feedback as this system develops!</p>
<p dir="auto">Please consider:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Joining the <a href="https://discord.gg/s84dXDff3K" rel="nofollow">Muscle Mem discord</a></li>
<li>Testing <a href="https://github.com/pig-dot-dev/muscle-mem">the muscle-mem repo</a>, and giving it a star</li>
</ol>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Perverse incentives of vibe coding (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fredbenenson.medium.com/the-perverse-incentives-of-vibe-coding-23efbaf75aee</link>
            <guid>43988315</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 19:29:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fredbenenson.medium.com/the-perverse-incentives-of-vibe-coding-23efbaf75aee">https://fredbenenson.medium.com/the-perverse-incentives-of-vibe-coding-23efbaf75aee</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43988315">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://fredbenenson.medium.com/the-perverse-incentives-of-vibe-coding-23efbaf75aee: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Grok answers unrelated queries with long paragraphs about "white genocide" (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/grok/status/1922651218595439063</link>
            <guid>43987266</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 17:43:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/grok/status/1922651218595439063">https://twitter.com/grok/status/1922651218595439063</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43987266">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/grok/status/1922651218595439063: Error: Request failed with status code 400]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Our narrative prison (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aeon.co/essays/why-does-every-film-and-tv-series-seem-to-have-the-same-plot</link>
            <guid>43986424</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 16:27:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aeon.co/essays/why-does-every-film-and-tv-series-seem-to-have-the-same-plot">https://aeon.co/essays/why-does-every-film-and-tv-series-seem-to-have-the-same-plot</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43986424">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>How is it that we live in an era of apparently unprecedented choice and yet almost every film and TV series, as well as a good many plays and novels, have exactly the same plot? We meet the protagonist in their ordinary world, plodding along, not living their best life. And then an inciting incident changes everything, making it impossible for the protagonist to carry on as normal. They are pulled into a new quest. On the way, they meet someone who shows them a completely different way of being. They ask themselves: have I been living <span>a lie?</span></p>
<p>This is the mid-point, the point of no return. Life can never be the same. But there’s a double wobble since the protagonist’s quest is opposed by a powerful antagonist who frustrates the hero at every turn. At their lowest point, the protagonist realises their old mode of being is redundant, but the new one is too daunting. The story is resolved either in the protagonist’s favour or against them: they triumph or else fail tragically. The important thing is that their life philosophy has been turned upside down. When they return home, everything is the same, but everything is also completely transformed.</p>
<p>The formula is particularly repetitive in cinema. As it happens, aspiring screenwriters in 21st-century Hollywood are following a rubric set out in the <span>4th century BCE.</span> In his <em>Poetics</em>, Aristotle defines a well-constructed plot as having three main acts, and names other essential elements such as the ‘reversal of the Situation’, which is ‘a change by which the action veers round to its opposite’ – eg, the moment in <em>The Sixth Sense</em> (1999) when the therapist realises he is dead – and ‘recognition’, which he defines as a ‘change from ignorance to knowledge’ (Oedipus’ recognition is a big one). Aristotle’s schema was developed by later thinkers from Terence and Seneca to the 19th-century German novelist and playwright Gustav Freytag, who distilled stories into his pyramid diagram of exposition, rising action, climax and resolution. A philosophical parallel might arguably be found in Hegel’s dialectic, from thesis to antithesis and finally to synthesis. As the US historian Hayden White <a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/2504969" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">observed</a>, even historians tend to shape their accounts of the past using narrative tropes.</p>
<figure><img alt="Diagram of Freytag’s Pyramid showing exposition as a flat line, inciting incident, rising action on an upward slop, climax at the peak of the pyramid, falling action on a downward slope, and resolution as a flat line." loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" sizes="(max-width: 640px) 100vw, (max-width: 1440px) 60vw, 880px" srcset="https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=384&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 384w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=640&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 640w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=750&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 750w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=828&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 828w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=1080&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 1080w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=1200&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 1200w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=1920&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 1920w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=2048&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 2048w, https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto 3840w" src="https://images.aeonmedia.co/user_image_upload/4136/freytags_pyramid_diagram.jpg?width=3840&amp;quality=75&amp;format=auto"><figcaption></figcaption></figure>
<p>If screenwriters continue to propagate the idea that three (or five) acts are the building blocks of every plot, it is because they are eager to find a replicable formula for box-office success. There is now a profitable story-structure industry of books, online lectures, podcasts and courses, with its own gurus, notably Robert McKee and Syd Field. Also Christopher Vogler, who worked as a script analyst at Disney and condensed the US writer Joseph Campbell’s concept of ‘the hero’s journey’ into a popular seven-page memo that then became a book, <em>The Writer’s </em><span><em>Journey</em></span><span> (1992).</span></p>
<p>We may be entirely familiar with the corporate clichés of Hollywood, but I don’t think the underpinnings of traditional story structure are necessarily obvious. One of my favourite films, David Lynch’s <em>Mulholland Drive</em> (2001), conforms pretty closely to formulaic structure, even if it is complicated by dream sequences: the inciting incident of the car crash; Betty’s quest to help Rita rediscover her true identity. I believe that one reason we don’t object, don’t groan with boredom, is that the scaffolding is – crucially – hidden. Every film opens with a fresh premise. The inciting incident always feels surprising, to the protagonist and to us alike: it’s a wild card that comes out of nowhere. It is this discreet veiling, in fact, that enables the formula to continue to thrive alongside the evident narrative variety we encounter every time we enter an independent bookshop: from <span>W G Sebald’s</span> collection <em>The Emigrants</em> (1992) to Nicholson Baker’s novel <em>The</em> <em>Mezzanine</em> (1988) to Samantha Harvey’s Booker-winning <em>Orbital</em> (2023). Hollywood’s storymakers may have grown more sophisticated about the method of delivery, but they are still providing the same drug: the shake-up that leads to enlightenment.</p>
<p>It is an enterprise in which convention is disguised as variety, while constraint is disguised as freedom – and this, surely, is the essence of Western consumer capitalism. The American dream could take you anywhere, but <em>still</em> you end up in a cookie-cutter house in the suburbs. Your high street is full of alluring cafés, but most are chains and their products taste the same. We step into the dark space of the cinema hoping to be taken somewhere new, but the journey follows submerged tracks like a theme park ride, and the only available destination is back home. The ‘reset’ at the end of every film feels particularly conformist: it’s as if we’re being invited to experience the fantasy of infinite possibility and radical change, only for the status quo to be reasserted. In fact, the fantasy <em>reinforces</em> the conformity by acting as a kind of safety valve.</p>
<p>As well as finding the concealment perturbing, I argue that there are other reasons to question traditional story structure. While it captures something profound about human needs and wants, it can be subtly conservative and its dominance is symptomatic of a worrying turn against analysis and critique.</p>
<p><span>I</span>n the grand genealogy of story structure exposition, Campbell’s ‘hero’s journey’ was influenced by Carl Jung’s ‘<a href="https://aeon.co/ideas/what-was-the-beguiling-spell-of-jungs-collective-unconscious" target="_blank" rel="noopener">collective unconscious</a>’: the idea that there are basic character archetypes that recur in our dreams and in the myths common to all cultures. Campbell called the hero’s journey the ‘monomyth’, a term he borrowed from James Joyce’s <em>Finnegans Wake </em>(1939) – a novel that exemplified it for Campbell and which, tellingly, is also considered to be a poster child for experimental fiction. In fact, there is an important – if subtle – distinction to be made here. There is the Hollywood formula, engineered to provide opioid reassurance in the form of redemption and the simultaneous restoration of normality: the hero always achieves self-optimisation within the acceptable confines of bourgeois respectability (which the comedy show <em>Seinfeld</em> rejected with its insistence on ‘no hugging, no learning’). And then there’s the more deep-seated monomyth, a universal blueprint that rather accurately captures the human condition, in which protagonists are put through arduous trials not so that they get what they want but what they counterintuitively need. And sometimes – in tragedy – they don’t get that <span>at all.</span></p>
<p>Though the Hollywood template might feel imaginatively and politically impoverished, it is also highly resonant. The TV producer and script editor John Yorke is the author of <em>Into the Woods: How Stories Work and Why We Tell Them</em> (2014). He is the closest thing we have to a screenwriting guru in the UK. ‘Hollywood tends to commodify and formalise,’ Yorke told me, but ultimately, ‘they’re commodifying something innate … There are different styles in different cultures, but fundamentally the underlying ingredients are always the same.’ Yorke offers the example of <span>E M Forster:</span> although story structure in novels tends to be looser and sometimes more experimental than that of films, ‘it’s so striking how something really significant always happens bang in the middle’ of a Forster novel – the midpoint Marabar Caves scene in <em>A Passage to India</em> (1924), for example, that overwhelms the young Adela Quested. Yet, as Yorke points out, ‘Forster didn’t read a book on story structure.’ Indeed, the cave literalises that moment of darkness, where Campbell’s model hero believes that all is lost.</p>
<p>Whether the monomyth is hard-wired or naturalised through repetition, Yorke believes it has universal appeal. Consuming it enables us to safely confront our worst fears and vicariously act out our strongest desires. Most importantly, it offers a pathway for what often seems to be the hardest and most longed-for task of all: how to change.</p>
<p>The vast majority of stories we encounter are versions of the monomyth</p>
<p>The US writer and director Craig Mazin observes that the inciting incident that the ‘writer god’ inflicts on the protagonist is their worst fear. It is the very thing they least want to happen, and because of this it has the potential to overhaul their erroneous mindset. The protagonist fights this ‘call to adventure’ tooth and nail because following it would mean letting go of their foundational commitments. Often, the change we need to make is to discover and integrate a vital, suppressed side of our personality – what Jung called <a href="https://psyche.co/ideas/three-ways-to-get-in-touch-with-your-shadow-self" target="_blank" rel="noopener">our Shadow</a>. The inciting incident represents the protagonist’s Shadow bursting into their world – it is their lack or flaw, embodied – which is why it is so hard to face. Who has not felt panic at the sudden disruption of their best-laid plans, only to find that the disruption produces unexpected rewards? A snowstorm that prevents my children from going to school (and me from obsessing away at my laptop) can become a magical sledging day in the park.</p>
<figure><iframe allowfullscreen="" frameborder="0" src="https://youtube.com/embed/vSX-DROZuzY"></iframe><figcaption></figcaption></figure>
<p>The COVID-19 lockdown was effectively an inciting incident on a global scale, offering us glimpses of how to live more meaningfully: building stronger ties with local communities; leaving urban areas for the countryside; discovering a greater sense of wellbeing through working at home (though, five years on, we appear to have returned to business as usual without learning those lessons – unlike the protagonists in films). Equally alluring is the idea of having a calling, an all-encompassing mission that sweeps away everyday mundanity, to say nothing of the appeal of absconding from a stultifying job or a stifling domestic life. I even wonder, writing this essay, if the lesson I need to learn is to let go of my qualms and enjoy being swept up into story, like Dorothy and her tornado.</p>
<p>The vast majority of stories we encounter are versions of the monomyth – from <em>King Lear</em> to Jane Austen’s <em>Emma</em> (1816). But to what extent is even that a normative Western construct promoting a narrow range of possible life-arcs – with the attendant Hollywood industry replicating it over and over, like an oppressive storytelling machine? And, to look even further outside the frame, is there something inherently reactionary about narrative itself?</p>
<p><span>M</span>azin’s reference to the ‘writer god’ is illuminating: it’s a top-down format. Oedipus’ fate is decided by the gods, the oracle at Delphi, and Sophocles: he tries to act freely, but his actions are predetermined. In our postmodern world, this predicament is turbo-charged. <em>The Truman Show </em>(1998) and <em>The Matrix</em> (1999) remain pertinent because we often feel ourselves to be living in a dystopian version of Prospero’s island – mere puppets in someone else’s plot. We process through the sausage factory of the National Curriculum into jobs that are standardised by tick-box bureaucracies. We are pawns preyed on by advertisers, and we’re trapped within the rubrics of social media. Every few years, we are given the chance to choose between near-identical parties, while our lifestyle choices are imperceptibly shaped by paternalistic <a href="https://aeon.co/essays/we-are-more-rational-than-those-who-nudge-us" target="_blank" rel="noopener">nudge policies</a>. In our scant downtime, we succumb to the consoling grooves of alcohol, gaming or Netflix.</p>
<p>You don’t have to be a conspiracy theorist to suspect that the lack of agency we feel in a world dominated by autocrats and digital capitalism is connected to the rise of story as a form. In his book <em>Public Opinion</em> (1922), the US political commentator Walter Lippmann called on Hollywood, the dream factory, to control an irrational public by appealing to their unconscious: the infamous ‘manufacture of consent’. And as the French scholar Christian Salmon notes in <em>Storytelling: Bewitching the Modern Mind</em> (2010), narrative has spread throughout contemporary culture and society, from news features to political speeches; museum curation to TV documentaries. Even in radio, where I work, and despite the best efforts of many of my colleagues to defend ideas-led programmes, formulaic narrative podcasts – particularly about history and true crime – are increasingly prevalent. The repetitive elements of storytelling are only too obvious here: the use of suspenseful music and the historic present tense, the anchoring in relatable characters, the cliff-hangers. Being told a story is to be infantilised, somewhat: to suspend one’s critical faculties. In contrast to polemic, stories are covertly persuasive. Even if their message is good for us, the sugaring of the pill represents a lowering of intellectual expectations.</p>
<p>There may be an internal transformation, but the structural conditions remain the same</p>
<p>Stories, as Vogler told me, function as ‘a kind of wish fulfilment’, meeting the human craving for ‘order and a purpose’. Regarding life as simply chaotic or meaningless is, he says, a ‘dangerous mental condition, … a horrible place to be’. Real life, of course, doesn’t have a shape as such. As Aristotle put it in his <em>Poetics</em>: ‘infinitely various are the incidents in one man’s life which cannot be reduced to unity’. Things don’t happen for a reason. And we fail to learn lessons. The UK novelist and critic Rosalind Brown points to the pitfalls of imposing meaning on contingent life events: ‘when something happens to you, you just make it part of your story’. It can be a way of avoiding being proactive or taking responsibility. That is one reason why we are rightly ‘suspicious of story’, Brown told me, even while being ‘incredibly attached <span>to it’.</span></p>
<p>If Brown is right, there is a danger that the ‘hero’s journey’ monomyth enables us not to change but to experience the fantasy of doing so. Sometimes ‘it’s easier to read about another character changing and feeling attracted to that than actually doing whatever work it would require to change yourself,’ she says. As Yorke reminded me, however, the power of stories to change us is illustrated by the money that the Donald Trump campaign spent on narrative social media spots, Lippmann-style – a gamble that, for better or worse, largely paid off. ‘The story wouldn’t be any good if you came back to your normal life completely unchanged, and having learned nothing, or having had no new observation,’ Vogler told me. ‘I think that we are always searching for upgrades, improvements in our behaviour, in our performance, in our relationships with other people.’ Films, he says, offer the opportunity for ‘slight improvement’.</p>
<p>There is also the question of whether the kind of change the monomyth advocates is always in our best interests. The politics of most mass-market screen fictions – from the fake anticolonialism of <em>Avatar </em>(2009) to the fake feminism of<em> Barbie</em> (2023) – are covertly conservative. <em>The</em> <em>White Lotus</em> (season one, 2021) came close to questioning the sustainability of long-term relationships, before ducking the issue with the sentimental reunion of husband and wife. The lesson is very often to be happy with your lot and to celebrate the comforts of the nuclear family, small-town existence and, often, capitalism. I’m thinking of <em>It’s a Wonderful Life </em>(1946) and<em> Groundhog Day </em>(1993) – even though I love <em>Groundhog Day</em>, and its repetition concept manages, simultaneously, to portray and critique being stuck in a rut. There may be an internal transformation, but the structural conditions remain the same.</p>
<p>So, what happens when we truly break with convention?</p>
<p><span>N</span>aqqash Khalid is a UK writer-director best known for his debut <em>In Camera </em>(2023), a surreal and disorientating portrait of an aspiring British-Asian actor navigating unsuccessful auditions. I asked him about my experience of noticing the same plot points time and again. ‘I can’t stand that. It really drives me crazy,’ he told me. ‘I am critical of the three-act structure, because I think it’s a very Western, male, colonial conception.’ The protagonist of <em>In Camera</em> is very much not a self-determining hero: he is framed and constructed by the encounters he has with other characters, who are often casually racist. ‘I wanted to have a passive man at the centre of the narrative who was not pushing the story forward,’ Khalid told me. He regards ‘one man going on a journey’ as not only hackneyed but ‘patriarchal’.</p>
<p>Similarly, the Australian critic Jane Alison questions the ‘masculo-sexual’ three-act structure with its wave-like arc of tension and release. ‘Why should an art form as innovative as fiction have a single archetype at all?’ she asks in ‘Beyond the Narrative Arc’ (2019). Stories can follow different patterns, she observes, many of which recur in nature: as well as the wave, there are fractals, meanders and networks – Italo Calvino described his novel <em>Invisible Cities</em> (1972) as ‘a network in which one can follow multiple routes and draw multiple, ramified conclusions.’</p>
<p>In her essay ‘The Carrier Bag Theory of Fiction’ (1986), Ursula K <span>Le Guin</span> challenged the hero’s journey – ‘the story the mammoth hunters told about bashing, thrusting, raping, killing’ – as not only narrowly masculine but also threatening humanity’s survival. <span>Le Guin</span> makes the case for an alternative story form to the hero’s spear or club: that of a container. Serious fiction, <span>Le Guin</span> wrote, is ‘a way of trying to describe what is in fact going on, what people actually do and feel, how people relate to everything else in this vast sack, this belly of the universe, this womb of things to be and tomb of things that were’.</p>
<p>Khalid also believes that contemporary art should reflect reality through its very form, and not just dangle wish fulfilment. ‘We live in such fractured times where the news cycle is nothing like before, where our attention spans are short,’ he said. Films must ‘formally adapt to the time that we’re in … I think the role of art is to structurally represent the world back to us.’ In her novel <em>The Long Form</em> (2023), Kate Briggs records the minute-by-minute tedium of being at home with a baby: the recording of mundane details functions as a critique of the conditions of modern motherhood. Rosalind Brown’s debut <em>Practice</em> (2024) is another novel that depicts what it is actually like to live in the world, right now. Annabel is an English literature undergraduate trying and failing to complete an essay about Shakespeare’s sonnets, through the minutiae of a single day. She is interrupted by erotic thoughts. She goes for a walk. She eats lunch. ‘The food is wet and crunchy, and tastes of all the cutting-up she just did to it,’ Brown writes: a sentence that stops the reader in their tracks. ‘Texture is the thing that interests me,’ Brown told me. Annabel ends the day much as she started it, the essay incomplete (although Brown does not reject story structure altogether: Annabel relaxing her grip on her timetable is an enlightenment of sorts).</p>
<p>Late capitalism, it would seem, respects neither narrative nor planetary boundaries</p>
<p>Early 20th-century literary modernism rejected the smooth illusions of 19th-century fiction, grappling instead with the dislocations of postwar modernity. Likewise, these attempts, in Le Guin’s words, ‘to describe what is in fact going on, what people actually do and feel’ are aesthetically and politically bracing. They defamiliarise what is naturalised, making the world strange so we can see it, challenge it, and potentially change it. Traditional story structure may resonate deeply, but it does not give us that jolt. Paradoxically, the monomyth dramatises change, but also embodies continuity.</p>
<p>‘Stories allow us to progress, and they allow us to stay the same,’ Yorke said. ‘That’s probably quite a healthy balance … We tell stories to define ourselves, our families, our nations.’ The monomyth was modelled on stories told by traditional societies governed by cyclical time and generational renewal: the hero’s journey is a rite of passage. But now that real-world Bond villains like Elon Musk are threatening geopolitical stability and ecological survival, that final-act reset is surely coming under strain.</p>
<p>Ironically, the monomyth is now being stretched out of shape by commercial forces, too. Franchises, sequels and box-set formats are extending stories in multiple directions to eke out ever more revenue, bringing to mind Musk’s intergalactic ambitions, which imply there’s a franchise option for human life: late capitalism, it would seem, respects neither narrative nor planetary boundaries. ‘It’s outrageous, really,’ Yorke says of endless sequels. ‘If you think of it in basic terms, a story is a question and answer, dramatised. And when the question is answered, there is nowhere else to go.’ Not surprisingly, Hollywood is working hard to combine narrative boundlessness with satisfying, self-contained stories: the Marvel ‘Multiverse’ is a kind of vast conglomerate of autonomous (super)heroes’ journeys.</p>
<p>In contrast to the spectacle of an individual saving the world, we once had idealism and the sense of a common goal: it was called ideology. But grand narratives are a relic of the past century. Khalid links the relative absence of creative experimentation with a narrowing of our ideological horizons. ‘Our collective imaginations … are being stifled,’ he told me. Like <span>Le Guin,</span> he believes that we must ‘fundamentally think about how we rebuild structures’, because those we are living under ‘are literally killing us … whether that be patriarchy or racism or the climate catastrophe.’ Ambitious art can ‘shape what we think it is possible for us <span>to do.’</span></p>
<p>Vogler and Yorke, while supportive of experimental fictions, note that they are of course harder to finance. And although it may be counterproductive to reassure people that everything is fine when the planet is burning, Yorke insists on being realistic about audience choices in a free market. ‘Stories have to make you alarmed,’ he told me, ‘but they also have to offer you hope … You’ve got to have a model of what’s worth <span>living for.’</span></p>
<p>Even art-house films that self-consciously depart from the three-act structure nonetheless define themselves against it. Charlie Kaufman’s brilliantly metafictional <em>Adaptation</em> (2002) dramatises a deconstruction of the formula (the protagonist, a struggling screenwriter, even attends a seminar by Robert McKee); but still he ends up (albeit knowingly) following it. Abandoning the structure altogether, it seems, is neither desirable nor possible. Even so, whether we regard it as a palace or a prison, we need now more than ever to understand how it is built.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A server that wasn't meant to exist (364 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/05/13/the_server_that_wasnt_meant_to_exist/</link>
            <guid>43985971</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 15:50:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/05/13/the_server_that_wasnt_meant_to_exist/">https://it-notes.dragas.net/2025/05/13/the_server_that_wasnt_meant_to_exist/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43985971">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Yesterday I read a piece of news that brought back an important - and painful - episode from my career.<br> A story about trust, technology... and the kind of problems that can't always be solved.</p><p>About 16 years ago, I was contacted by an old friend. He was worried about a situation involving some mutual acquaintances.<br> To keep it short: an entrepreneur - administrator and owner of several companies - had died suddenly.<br> He was the kind of man who centralized everything, and his wife and children found themselves struggling to manage things.<br> One of the sons decided to cash out and leave the family business (focusing on his own career), while the others chose to stay involved in day-to-day operations.<br> The wife, elderly and retired for years, ended up at the helm, but she was clearly out of her depth.</p><p>The main issue was the complete lack of information flow: no digital systems of any kind were in place.<br> Employees had their own PCs (sometimes even personal laptops), and there was zero control over anything.<br> All the accounting and administrative data were scattered across individual machines, often taken home at the end of the day.<br> From the owners’ perspective, all they saw was a huge cash flow coming in - yet the accounts were always in the red.</p><p>"If we keep going like this, we’ll be bankrupt in just a few years", I was told.<br> What I could do was set up a proper IT system, structured to make data management transparent and traceable.</p><p>I planned - and got immediate approval for - the purchase of routers, switches, various networking devices and a server with several disks.<br><a href="https://it-notes.dragas.net/2023/08/27/that-old-netbsd-server-running-since-2010/">The OS of choice, as was my habit at the time, was NetBSD</a>. Thanks to XEN, I set up multiple VMs.<br> One handled the NAS duties (using Samba, so PCs could connect and store files directly there), another ran <a href="https://archivista.ch/">Archivista</a>.<br> I even worked on translating Archivista’s interface into Italian, since it wasn’t yet localized, just to make it easier for users.</p><p>As usual in those days, I added a caching proxy (Squid) and a content filter (DansGuardian), to ensure proper usage.<br> The internet connection was very slow and often collapsed under heavy load - mostly recreational use, as logs revealed.<br> There was no supervision, and many people were downloading movies and such on company time.</p><p>As often happens, not everyone was happy. </p><p>One figure in particular - the late owner's former right-hand man - opposed the new system in every possible way.<br> According to him, none of this was necessary. But the real alarm bell had been his sudden change in lifestyle.<br> He’d made purchases that didn’t remotely align with his salary.<br> At the time, the company had no oversight and dealt with a lot of cash. It was all technically legal, especially given the nature of the business. I won’t go into detail - privacy matters.</p><p>Once everything was up and running, we trained the employees to use the new system.<br> Most were thrilled - finally able to work properly, with files in the right place and centralized document management.<br> OCR, archiving, etc. were all seen as major time-savers and a big boost in efficiency.<br> Some of the accounting staff remained skeptical, of course.</p><p>Since all of this was far from where I lived at the time, I went back to my life once the system was stable and everything in place.<br> A few quiet days passed - then one morning, my phone rang:</p><p>"Good morning, this is XYZ - I handle some technical aspects of a software suite used by the company where you've just installed everything.<br> We need to install our software, and I understand you set up the server. I’ll need the full server diagram and all the admin passwords".</p><p>I explained that it wasn’t a Windows machine, as he assumed (without even having seen it), but NetBSD, running NetBSD and Linux VMs.</p><p>A few seconds of silence.</p><p>"I see. Then I’ll have to wipe it and install Windows. I need Windows, and I don’t have time to wait for a new server - I’ll proceed tomorrow morning".</p><p>I froze. I told him that was not possible - the entire workflow now depended on that machine, and erasing it would be catastrophic.</p><p>"I’ll speak with the owners", I said, "and I’m sure they’ll provide you with a separate server within hours".</p><p>No use. He started to backpedal.<br> To my (young) eyes, the goal was now obvious: that server had to disappear, and fast.<br> He said he would "restore the previous situation", and claimed the server couldn’t remain as-is because <em>he</em> needed it.</p><p>I immediately called the owners. Sadly, due to inexperience and inability to handle the situation, they panicked.<br> They asked me to consider letting him do it, and then redoing the setup later, covering the cost of new hardware and my time.<br> I refused. I was young, but I already had this mindset: do what’s right, even at the cost of profit.<br> This was clearly a maneuver to eliminate controls - the server, the centralized filesystem.<br> The goal was to hide the real accounting data from owners and auditors. Thousands of euros vanished every day through "transactions".<br> The owners had started to understand, and this new pressure confirmed just how rotten things really were.</p><p>I called that man back and told him clearly: the server I’d built wasn’t to be shut down.<br> If he needed one, I’d deliver a new server by that evening, just for him.</p><p>At that point, he finally spoke more openly:</p><p>"You don’t get it, do you? I need <em>that</em> server. Not <em>a</em> server.<br> You’d better go along with this — or you’ll have serious trouble working in this area again".</p><p>And other similar, "nice" sentences. I replied calmly:<br> "Look, I’m just doing a favor for some friends. I don’t have clients in your area — and I don’t want any.<br> I’d rather do a good job for them than gain new clients".</p><p>No way through. He kept pushing - confident in his own sense of "power" - until I said what I had been trying to avoid.</p><p>Because I had recognized who he was.<br> And the disappointment hit me twice as hard - I used to admire him.<br> He, however, had not recognized me.</p><p>"Excuse me, but why are you talking to me like this? You’ve known me since I was a child. Don’t you remember? I’m the nephew of..."</p><p>He froze.<br> He understood immediately.<br> He connected the dots and knew full well that a single phone call to someone extremely close to me - someone he owed a great deal, both personally and professionally - would have the opposite effect he was aiming for.</p><p>That person had helped him greatly over the years. So much so that he folded:</p><p>"Oh... I’m so sorry... I didn’t recognize you. I’ll find another solution. Sorry again".</p><p>He hung up.<br> Never heard from him again.</p><p>I informed the owners that the issue was resolved (leaving out most of the details), but it didn’t last long.<br> Within days, a series of "unfortunate events" hit the server: the UPS failed, the server was "accidentally" unplugged and plugged back in incorrectly, and finally... it stopped responding on the network.</p><p>It was dead.<br> And when we opened it, the hard disks were just... gone.</p><p>But there was one thing nobody (but the owners) knew.<br> The server - slowly but surely - had been backing up externally.<br> All the data up to that point had been copied to a device we’d quietly installed at the owners’ home: a tiny PCEngines Alix, running NetBSD with two USB drives.<br> It was slow, yes - slow hardware, slow disks - but reliable.<br> That very device still works today (with FreeBSD) and provides services elsewhere.</p><p>I handed all the data to the owners and asked what they intended to do.<br> They took some time - days, then weeks.<br> Eventually, they said they’d probably investigate whether there were grounds for a theft report.</p><p>I never heard more about it.</p><p>But then came a tempting offer:</p><p>"Come work for us. Manage our network infrastructure and help us overhaul our internal procedures.<br> Even if you’ve just bought a house far from here, even if you’d have to leave your other clients -<br> we’ll pay you enough to forget everything else. Name your price".</p><p>They would’ve done it, too.<br> Our mutual friend urged me:<br> "They’ve got a huge cash flow, but too many people are taking advantage of them due to lack of control.<br> Take the job - they’ll treat you like gold, and you’ll really help them".</p><p>I didn’t think twice. </p><p><strong>I turned it down</strong>.</p><p>I like my work.<br> I like doing what I do - and the income is a consequence, not the cause.<br> I would’ve had to give up my life, my path, to fight battles I don’t enjoy - and that I might not even win.</p><p>Because sometimes, dishonest people <em>do</em> win.</p><p>I’ve never regretted declining that offer.<br> I lost touch with all of them years ago, but I later heard things went as I predicted:<br> the owners gradually backed out. </p><p>They made another request later on, which I tried to fulfill — but even that was blocked, just when everything was ready.</p><p>At some point, I had to walk away.<br> Not because I wanted to abandon them in a time of need, but because they weren’t giving me the tools to do what was necessary.<br> They were so overwhelmed, so unprepared, that they ended up yielding to pressure - often from the very people who were hurting them.</p><p>And of course, I’ve left out the worst parts of the story.</p><p><em>(Author's note: Many readers, understandably struck by the severity of the events, have speculated about the involvement of organized crime. I want to clarify that, while the situation was extremely problematic and dishonest, that wasn't the case. The "worst parts" I alluded to referred to other internal dynamics, abuses of trust, and improprieties that I prefer not to detail further for privacy reasons and to avoid weighing down the narrative.)</em></p><p>That’s when I realized:<br> Some situations are so rotten, they simply can’t be salvaged.</p><p>And that’s okay.</p><p><a href="https://it-notes.dragas.net/2024/10/03/i-solve-problems-eurobsdcon/">I solve problems</a> - it’s what I do best.</p><p>But I can’t solve <strong>every</strong> problem.<br> Especially not when those involved choose to protect the problem instead of fixing it.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Uber to introduce fixed-route shuttles in major US cities (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/14/uber-to-introduce-fixed-route-shuttles-in-major-us-cities-other-ways-to-save/</link>
            <guid>43985861</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 15:40:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/14/uber-to-introduce-fixed-route-shuttles-in-major-us-cities-other-ways-to-save/">https://techcrunch.com/2025/05/14/uber-to-introduce-fixed-route-shuttles-in-major-us-cities-other-ways-to-save/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43985861">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p id="speakable-summary">Ride-hail and delivery giant Uber is introducing cheap, fixed-route rides along busy corridors during weekday commute hours in major U.S. cities — one solution to a world that feels, for most people, more expensive every day.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Starting Wednesday, riders in Baltimore, Boston, Chicago, Dallas, New York City, Philadelphia, and San Francisco will be able to save 50% off the price of an UberX trip by booking with Uber’s new “Route Share” feature.&nbsp;</p>







<p>The company announced Route Share and other new features and discounts designed to help customers save money on rides and deliveries at its <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/05/15/uber-has-a-new-way-to-solve-the-concert-traffic-problem/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">annual Go-Get event</a>. The aim is to attract and maintain a loyal customer base that continues to use the Uber app in spite of outside economic pressures.</p>

<p>The commuter shuttles will drive between pre-set stops every 20 minutes, according to Sachin Kansal, Uber’s chief product officer. He noted that there will be dozens of routes in each launch city — like between Williamsburg and Midtown in NYC. The routes, which are selected based on Uber’s extensive data on popular travel patterns, might have one or two additional stops to pick up other passengers. To start, riders will only ever have to share the route with up to two other co-riders.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Riders can book a seat anywhere from seven days to 10 minutes before a scheduled pickup, and the app will provide them with turn-by-turn directions to get them from their house to the corner where they’ll be picked up.</p>

<p>Uber is relying on the same underlying technology that it uses for Uber Share, its shared rides offering where riders can get 15% to 30% off the cost of an UberX ride by pooling with others. Kansal told TechCrunch that Uber completes millions of shared trips annually and has been seeing more traction lately as riders look for more ways to save. Hence, Route Share.&nbsp;</p>

<p>“Because of the size of our network, both on the consumer side as well as the driver side, and our core matching and market-based technology, it allows us to do something like this and put multiple people in the same car while creating efficiency and predictability for their commute,” Kansal told TechCrunch.&nbsp;</p>


<p>Uber envisions a future where Route Share could qualify for pre-tax commuter benefits. However, as a spokesperson noted, the company would need to find a way to match those trips with Uber XL vehicles. That’s because only six-seater vehicles would meet the eligibility requirements.</p>

<p>A potential progression of Route Share would involve autonomous vehicles, particularly in chaotic cities like New York City, where no self-driving car companies have deigned to test.&nbsp;</p>

<p>Uber has partnerships with 18 AV companies and during its first-quarter earnings delivery last week, the company reported it has grown to an annualized rate of 1.5 million mobility and delivery AV trips on the Uber network.&nbsp;</p>







<p>One of Uber’s more recent AV partners is with Volkswagen. The two plan to work together to add autonomous versions of VW’s ID. Buzz AD electric vehicles to the Uber app — specifically for shared rides — starting in Los Angeles in 2026.</p>

<p>“You can see a natural extension of us being able to bring Route Share to autonomous vehicles, as well,” Kansal said. “[Route Share] has a lot of advantages for the autonomous vehicle. It’s a very well-defined route, and so the pickups and drop offs are predictable.”</p>

<h3 id="h-other-ways-frequent-uber-users-can-save"><strong>Other ways frequent Uber users can save</strong></h3>

<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1080" src="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?w=680" alt="" srcset="https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg 1920w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=150,84 150w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=300,169 300w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=768,432 768w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=680,383 680w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=1200,675 1200w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=1280,720 1280w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=430,242 430w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=720,405 720w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=900,506 900w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=800,450 800w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=1536,864 1536w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=668,375 668w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=1097,617 1097w, https://techcrunch.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/05/Uber-go-get-deals.jpg?resize=708,398 708w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px"><figcaption><span><strong>Image Credits:</strong>Uber</span></figcaption></figure>

<p>Each of Uber’s Get-Go events has a theme. Last year, it was focused on ways to help people spend more time together. This year, with economic uncertainty looming due to President Trump’s tariffs, mass layoffs across the tech world, and AI coming for all our jobs, Uber is focusing on cost savings for riders. In the process, Uber hopes to create a predictable cash flow and stickiness that keeps riders engaged with Uber.&nbsp;</p>

<p>“Of late, what we have heard very loud and clear is people feel very uncertain, people feel overwhelmed, and people are feeling the prices in many different walks of life, and there’s this need and desire to get more affordable options,” Kansal said. “So everything we’re announcing is squarely focused on how we make life more affordable for them.”</p>

<p>One of Uber’s new features is “ride passes,” which riders can use to “protect their price for a one-hour window each day on their selected routes.” There are two ways this will work. Either riders can pay $2.99 to lock in a price on a specific route, or they can pay upfront and buy a bundle of prepaid trips. They can buy five, 10, 15, or 20 rides for an “even deeper discount.”&nbsp;</p>

<p>The price lock offer will be available for riders in Chicago, Dallas, Houston, Las Vegas, Miami, Nashville, Orlando, Phoenix, San Francisco, and Washington, D.C. starting Wednesday, with the rest of the U.S. and Brazil to follow. In the fall, price lock and prepaid passes will be available for teen accounts, too.&nbsp;</p>

<p>On the Uber Eats side of things, Uber is going deeper into its partnership with OpenTable and launching a feature called Dine Out, which lets customers in the U.S., Canada, Mexico, the U.K., Ireland, and Australia book tables via OpenTable on the Uber app. When they reserve (either on the Uber app or on OpenTable’s app), they’ll get a discount on an Uber ride to the restaurant. Additionally, OpenTable members will soon be able to use their points on Uber and Uber Eats — not unlike <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2025/04/22/uber-customers-can-now-earn-delta-skymiles-from-rides-or-deliveries/">Uber’s partnership with Delta Air Lines</a>.&nbsp;</p>

<p>These kinds of deals could offer savings for riders, particularly during peak demand times when surge pricing is in effect. But they’re likely more beneficial for people who frequently use Uber’s service. Prepaid packages often feel cheaper due to upfront discounts, but riders could also overestimate how much they’ll use them.</p>







<p>Uber’s pricing strategy is also not transparent, and some <a href="https://www.sfgate.com/travel/article/bay-area-traveler-says-uber-gift-cards-boosted-20281408.php?utm_source=chatgpt.com" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener nofollow">reports</a> have suggested that riders with prepaid credits or gift cards get higher fare quotes compared to those paying per ride. (Anecdotally, whenever I switch my payment method from my personal card to my business card, the price of the ride jumps a few dollars.)&nbsp;</p>

<p>An Uber spokesperson told TechCrunch the price lock feature is based on historical prices of that trip, and the prepaid pass protects against price spikes and adds discounts that are also based on historical prices.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Lumier – Run macOS VMs in a Docker (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/trycua/cua/tree/main/libs/lumier</link>
            <guid>43985624</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 15:19:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/trycua/cua/tree/main/libs/lumier">https://github.com/trycua/cua/tree/main/libs/lumier</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43985624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_copilot&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_copilot_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_advanced_security_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/security/advanced-security">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Advanced Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;actions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;actions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;codespaces&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;codespaces_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;issues&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;issues_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_review&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_review_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code Review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;discussions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;discussions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_search&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_search_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-search">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code Search</p><p>
        Find more, search less
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
                    <p><span id="resources-explore-heading">Explore</span></p><ul aria-labelledby="resources-explore-heading">
                    <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/learn/pathways">
      Learning Pathways

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;events_amp_webinars&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;events_amp_webinars_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/">
      Events &amp; Webinars

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;ebooks_amp_whitepapers&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ebooks_amp_whitepapers_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/resources/whitepapers">
      Ebooks &amp; Whitepapers

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_stories&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_stories_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/customer-stories">
      Customer Stories

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;partners&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;partners_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://partner.github.com/">
      Partners

    
</a></li>

                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;executive_insights&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;executive_insights_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/solutions/executive-insights">
      Executive Insights

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
              <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
              <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
              
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
                <ul>
                    <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>Enterprise platform</p><p>
        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                </ul>
              </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;pricing&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;global&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;pricing_link_global_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:trycua/cua" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="sRFBKc70sdI_8-zAHANW3lGu3MOTTNdArJMkRY1y5s8cYNngGIkQpI7HqKAgrqfmyv1t-DWpxJWeHwlR9QvXLA" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="trycua/cua" data-current-org="trycua" data-current-owner="" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-nl-search-enabled="false" data-retain-scroll-position="true">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>


            

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E%2Ffiles%2Fdisambiguate&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=trycua%2Fcua" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/trycua/cua/tree/main/libs/lumier&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="6ea2dd7059ac61ea0174d7ac5c4b9ca1e8e59005a8a4b0476733eeb9f58d48a2" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>/files/disambiguate;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a></p><p>
    <react-partial-anchor>
      <tool-tip id="tooltip-1a25d33f-097e-4cbd-9846-6d24e7566105" for="icon-button-71ef203b-0963-4ba3-a0a8-0ad14f7d7b47" popover="manual" data-direction="s" data-type="label" data-view-component="true">Appearance settings</tool-tip>

      <template data-target="react-partial-anchor.template">
        <script crossorigin="anonymous" defer="defer" type="application/javascript" src="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/ui_packages_document-metadata_document-metadata_ts-ui_packages_promise-with-resolvers-polyfil-40d47c-11c6336aaa7c.js"></script>
<script crossorigin="anonymous" defer="defer" type="application/javascript" src="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/appearance-settings-1d8b3a6a9ee9.js"></script>
<link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/primer-react.d2117d7623cc63123645.module.css">
<link crossorigin="anonymous" media="all" rel="stylesheet" href="https://github.githubassets.com/assets/appearance-settings.22dfbc22ef0a2bf02523.module.css">

<react-partial partial-name="appearance-settings" data-ssr="false" data-attempted-ssr="false">
  
  <script type="application/json" data-target="react-partial.embeddedData">{"props":{}}</script>
  <div data-target="react-partial.reactRoot"></div>
</react-partial>

      </template>
    </react-partial-anchor>
  </p>

          </div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AlphaEvolve: A Gemini-powered coding agent for designing advanced algorithms (900 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/alphaevolve-a-gemini-powered-coding-agent-for-designing-advanced-algorithms/</link>
            <guid>43985489</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 15:10:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/alphaevolve-a-gemini-powered-coding-agent-for-designing-advanced-algorithms/">https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/alphaevolve-a-gemini-powered-coding-agent-for-designing-advanced-algorithms/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43985489">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content">
      
  <article>
    
    
  
  
  
    
      

      
      
        
          
            <div>
              
                
                
                  
                  
<div>
    <div>
      <p>Research</p>
      

      
    <dl>
      
        <dt>Published</dt>
        <dd><time datetime="2025-05-14">14 May 2025</time></dd>
      
      
        <dt>Authors</dt>
        
      
    </dl>
  

      
    </div>

    
      
    
    
    <picture>
      <source media="(min-width: 1024px)" type="image/webp" width="1072" height="603" srcset="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w1072-h603-n-nu-rw 1x, https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w2144-h1206-n-nu-rw 2x"><source media="(min-width: 600px)" type="image/webp" width="928" height="522" srcset="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w928-h522-n-nu-rw 1x, https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w1856-h1044-n-nu-rw 2x"><source type="image/webp" width="528" height="297" srcset="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w528-h297-n-nu-rw 1x, https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w1056-h594-n-nu-rw 2x">
      <img alt="Colourful and abstract digital landscape of code. Demonstrating peaks in high performing code." height="603" src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/Gw688MNwkQVBeUALSFtQz46Oh4NFoZAe10mEpvtmZhKuWhlQsi5uh2KFHKbxH8NhBnOGUNza6O6-0HElml2zEN06vI_9oAsjAxFVzxjDL5DOw7HsAw=w1072-h603-n-nu" width="1072">
    </picture>
    
  
    
  </div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h4 data-block-key="1rhtp">New AI agent evolves algorithms for math and practical applications in computing by combining the creativity of large language models with automated evaluators</h4><p data-block-key="bpa0i">Large language models (LLMs) are remarkably versatile. They can summarize documents, generate code or even brainstorm new ideas. And now we’ve expanded these capabilities to target fundamental and highly complex problems in mathematics and modern computing.</p><p data-block-key="a2lsk">Today, we’re announcing <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/DeepMind.com/Blog/alphaevolve-a-gemini-powered-coding-agent-for-designing-advanced-algorithms/AlphaEvolve.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">AlphaEvolve</a>, an evolutionary coding agent powered by large language models for general-purpose algorithm discovery and optimization. AlphaEvolve pairs the creative problem-solving capabilities of our <a href="https://deepmind.google/technologies/gemini/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Gemini models</a> with automated evaluators that verify answers, and uses an evolutionary framework to improve upon the most promising ideas.</p><p data-block-key="7b9nk">AlphaEvolve enhanced the efficiency of Google's data centers, chip design and AI training processes — including training the large language models underlying AlphaEvolve itself. It has also helped design faster matrix multiplication algorithms and find new solutions to open mathematical problems, showing incredible promise for application across many areas.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h2 data-block-key="1rhtp">Designing better algorithms with large language models</h2><p data-block-key="cmrs5">In 2023, we showed for the first time that large language models can generate functions written in computer code to help <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/funsearch-making-new-discoveries-in-mathematical-sciences-using-large-language-models/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">discover new and provably correct knowledge</a> on an open scientific problem. AlphaEvolve is an agent that can go beyond single function discovery to evolve entire codebases and develop much more complex algorithms.</p><p data-block-key="8lpr6">AlphaEvolve leverages an ensemble of state-of-the-art large language models: our fastest and most efficient model, <a href="https://deepmind.google/technologies/gemini/flash/?_gl=1*7wovog*_up*MQ..*_ga*ODcyNjk2MzY0LjE3NDYxODE1OTY.*_ga_LS8HVHCNQ0*MTc0NjE4MTU5NS4xLjAuMTc0NjE4MTU5OS4wLjAuMA.." rel="noopener" target="_blank">Gemini Flash</a>, maximizes the breadth of ideas explored, while our most powerful model, <a href="https://deepmind.google/technologies/gemini/pro/?_gl=1*5ncg4r*_up*MQ..*_ga*ODcyNjk2MzY0LjE3NDYxODE1OTY.*_ga_LS8HVHCNQ0*MTc0NjE4MTU5NS4xLjAuMTc0NjE4MTU5OS4wLjAuMA.." rel="noopener" target="_blank">Gemini Pro</a>, provides critical depth with insightful suggestions. Together, these models propose computer programs that implement algorithmic solutions as code.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-37de9aef-e216-4e74-bad9-c132e221ef65">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="lnm7d">Diagram showing how the prompt sampler first assembles a prompt for the language models, which then generate new programs. These programs are evaluated by evaluators and stored in the programs database. This database implements an evolutionary algorithm that determines which programs will be used for future prompts.</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <p data-block-key="1rhtp">AlphaEvolve verifies, runs and scores the proposed programs using automated evaluation metrics. These metrics provide an objective, quantifiable assessment of each solution’s accuracy and quality. This makes AlphaEvolve particularly helpful in a broad range of domains where progress can be clearly and systematically measured, like in math and computer science.</p>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h3 data-block-key="1rhtp">Optimizing our computing ecosystem</h3><p data-block-key="eu4jo">Over the past year, we’ve deployed algorithms discovered by AlphaEvolve across Google’s computing ecosystem, including our data centers, hardware and software. The impact of each of these improvements is multiplied across our AI and computing infrastructure to build a more powerful and sustainable digital ecosystem for all our users.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-3e1cbb33-1c95-4dc0-b1a4-6aa109adf4c3">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="lnm7d">Diagram showing how AlphaEvolve helps Google deliver a more efficient digital ecosystem, from data center scheduling and hardware design to AI model training.</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h3 data-block-key="1rhtp">Improving data center scheduling</h3><p data-block-key="3ra3e">AlphaEvolve discovered a simple yet remarkably effective heuristic to help <a href="https://research.google/pubs/large-scale-cluster-management-at-google-with-borg/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Borg</a> orchestrate Google's vast data centers more efficiently. This solution, now in production for over a year, continuously recovers, on average, 0.7% of Google’s worldwide compute resources. This sustained efficiency gain means that at any given moment, more tasks can be completed on the same computational footprint. AlphaEvolve's solution not only leads to strong performance but also offers significant operational advantages of human-readable code: interpretability, debuggability, predictability and ease of deployment.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h3 data-block-key="1rhtp">Assisting in hardware design</h3><p data-block-key="9gnp2">AlphaEvolve proposed a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Verilog" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Verilog</a> rewrite that removed unnecessary bits in a key, highly optimized arithmetic circuit for matrix multiplication. Crucially, the proposal must pass robust verification methods to confirm that the modified circuit maintains functional correctness. This proposal was integrated into an upcoming <a href="https://cloud.google.com/tpu?hl=en" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Tensor Processing Unit</a> (TPU), Google’s custom AI accelerator. By suggesting modifications in the standard language of chip designers, AlphaEvolve promotes a collaborative approach between AI and hardware engineers to accelerate the design of future specialized chips.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h3 data-block-key="1rhtp">Enhancing AI training and inference</h3><p data-block-key="279mo">AlphaEvolve is accelerating AI performance and research velocity. By finding smarter ways to divide a large matrix multiplication operation into more manageable subproblems, it sped up this vital <a href="https://docs.jax.dev/en/latest/pallas/index.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">kernel</a> in Gemini’s architecture by 23%, leading to a 1% reduction in Gemini's training time. Because developing generative AI models requires substantial computing resources, every efficiency gained translates to considerable savings. Beyond performance gains, AlphaEvolve significantly reduces the engineering time required for kernel optimization, from weeks of expert effort to days of automated experiments, allowing researchers to innovate faster.</p><p data-block-key="fvg3r">AlphaEvolve can also optimize low level GPU instructions. This incredibly complex domain is usually already heavily optimized by compilers, so human engineers typically don't modify it directly. AlphaEvolve achieved up to a 32.5% speedup for the<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.14135" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> FlashAttention</a> kernel implementation in<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformer_%28deep_learning_architecture%29" rel="noopener" target="_blank"> Transformer</a>-based AI models. This kind of optimization helps experts pinpoint performance bottlenecks and easily incorporate the improvements into their codebase, boosting their productivity and enabling future savings in compute and energy.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h3 data-block-key="1rhtp">Advancing the frontiers in mathematics and algorithm discovery</h3><p data-block-key="8i4l">AlphaEvolve can also propose new approaches to complex mathematical problems. Provided with a minimal code skeleton for a computer program, AlphaEvolve designed many components of a novel <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/engineering/gradient-based-algorithm" rel="noopener" target="_blank">gradient-based optimization</a> procedure that discovered multiple new algorithms for matrix multiplication, a fundamental problem in computer science.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  





<figure aria-labelledby="caption-fb8c0bba-9a53-4d4e-918f-e2d2a3122595">
  

  <figcaption>
      <p data-block-key="pp1h1">A list of changes proposed by AlphaEvolve to discover faster matrix multiplication algorithms. In this example, AlphaEvolve proposes extensive changes across several components, including the optimizer and weight initialization, the loss function, and hyperparameter sweep. These changes are highly non-trivial, requiring 15 mutations during the evolutionary process.</p>
    </figcaption>
</figure>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <p data-block-key="1rhtp">AlphaEvolve’s procedure found an algorithm to multiply 4x4 complex-valued matrices using 48 scalar multiplications, improving upon <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Strassen_algorithm" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Strassen’s 1969 algorithm</a> that was previously known as the best in this setting. This finding demonstrates a significant advance over our previous work, <a href="https://deepmind.google/discover/blog/discovering-novel-algorithms-with-alphatensor/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">AlphaTensor</a>, which specialized in matrix multiplication algorithms, and for 4x4 matrices, only found improvements for binary arithmetic.</p><p data-block-key="fmlon">To investigate AlphaEvolve’s breadth, we applied the system to over 50 open problems in mathematical analysis, geometry, combinatorics and number theory. The system’s flexibility enabled us to set up most experiments in a matter of hours. In roughly 75% of cases, it rediscovered state-of-the-art solutions, to the best of our knowledge.</p><p data-block-key="86rjt">And in 20% of cases, AlphaEvolve improved the previously best known solutions, making progress on the corresponding open problems. For example, it advanced the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kissing_number" rel="noopener" target="_blank">kissing number problem</a>. This geometric challenge has <a href="https://plus.maths.org/content/newton-and-kissing-problem" rel="noopener" target="_blank">fascinated mathematicians for over 300 years</a> and concerns the maximum number of non-overlapping spheres that touch a common unit sphere. AlphaEvolve discovered a configuration of 593 outer spheres and established a new lower bound in 11 dimensions.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
  <h3 data-block-key="1rhtp">The path forward</h3><p data-block-key="9e94g">AlphaEvolve displays the progression from discovering algorithms for specific domains to developing more complex algorithms for a wide range of real-world challenges. We’re expecting AlphaEvolve to continue improving alongside the capabilities of large language models, especially as they become even <a href="https://developers.googleblog.com/en/gemini-2-5-pro-io-improved-coding-performance/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">better at coding</a>.</p><p data-block-key="7kobf">Together with the <a href="https://pair.withgoogle.com/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">People + AI Research team</a>, we’ve been building a friendly user interface for interacting with AlphaEvolve. We’re planning an Early Access Program for selected academic users and also exploring possibilities to make AlphaEvolve more broadly available. To register your interest, please complete <a href="https://forms.gle/WyqAoh1ixdfq6tgN8" rel="noopener" target="_blank">this form</a>.</p><p data-block-key="cefdg">While AlphaEvolve is currently being applied across math and computing, its general nature means it can be applied to any problem whose solution can be described as an algorithm, and automatically verified. We believe AlphaEvolve could be transformative across many more areas such as material science, drug discovery, sustainability and wider technological and business applications.</p>
</div>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  

<section>
  

  <ul>
    
      <li>
            <gemini-button data-in-view="">
              <a data-gtm-tag="cta-selection" href="https://storage.googleapis.com/deepmind-media/DeepMind.com/Blog/alphaevolve-a-gemini-powered-coding-agent-for-designing-advanced-algorithms/AlphaEvolve.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">
      <span>Read more details in our white paper</span>
      
    </a>
            </gemini-button>
        </li>
        
    
      <li>
            <gemini-button data-in-view="">
              <a data-gtm-tag="cta-selection" href="https://forms.gle/WyqAoh1ixdfq6tgN8" rel="noopener" target="_blank">
      <span>Register your interest in using AlphaEvolve</span>
      
    </a>
            </gemini-button>
        </li>
        
    
      <li>
            <gemini-button data-in-view="">
              <a data-gtm-tag="cta-selection" href="https://colab.research.google.com/github/google-deepmind/alphaevolve_results/blob/master/mathematical_results.ipynb" rel="noopener" target="_blank">
      <span>See AlphaEvolve’s mathematical results in our Google Colab</span>
      
    </a>
            </gemini-button>
        </li>
        
    
  </ul>
</section>
                
              
                
                
                  
                  <div>
      <p data-block-key="ndxib"><strong>Acknowledgements</strong></p><p data-block-key="d0au1">AlphaEvolve was developed by Matej Balog, Alexander Novikov, Ngân Vũ, Marvin Eisenberger, Emilien Dupont, Po-Sen Huang, Adam Zsolt Wagner, Sergey Shirobokov, Borislav Kozlovskii, Francisco J. R. Ruiz, Abbas Mehrabian, M. Pawan Kumar, Abigail See, Swarat Chaudhuri, George Holland, Alex Davies, Sebastian Nowozin, and Pushmeet Kohli. This research was developed as part of our effort focused on using AI for algorithm discovery.</p><p data-block-key="frcj6">We gratefully acknowledge contributions, advice, and support from Jean-Baptiste Alayrac, Ankit Anand, Natasha Antropova, Giorgio Arena, Mohammadamin Barekatain, Johannes Bausch, Henning Becker, Daniel Belov, Alexander Belyaev, Sebastian Bodenstein, Sebastian Borgeaud, Calin Cascaval, Indranil Chakraborty, Benjamin Chetioui, Justin Chiu, Christopher Clark, Marco Cornero, Jeff Dean, Gaurav Dhiman, Yanislav Donchev, Srikanth Dwarakanath, Jordan Ellenberg, Alhussein Fawzi, Michael Figurnov, Aaron Gentleman, Bogdan Georgiev, Sergio Guadarrama, Demis Hassabis, Patrick Heisel, Chase Hensel, Koray Kavukcuoglu, Sultan Kenjeyev, Aliia Khasanova, Sridhar Lakshmanamurthy, Sergei Lebedev, Dmitry Lepikhin, Daniel Mankowitz, Andrea Michi, Kieran Milan, Vinod Nair, Robert O'Callahan, Cosmin Paduraru, Stig Petersen, Federico Piccinini, Parthasarathy Ranganatha, Bernardino Romera-Paredes, Georges Rotival, Kirk Sanders, Javier Gomez Serrano, Oleg Shyshkov, Timur Sitdikov, Tammo Spalink, Kerry Takenaka, Richard Tanburn, Terence Tao, Amin Vahdat, JD Velasquez, Dimitrios Vytiniotis, Julian Walker, and Pengming Wang. For more details, please see our white paper.<br></p><p data-block-key="btj9l">We would like to thank Armin Senoner, Juanita Bawagan, Jane Park, Arielle Bier, and Molly Beck for feedback on the blog post and help with this announcement; William Hood, Irina Andronic, Victoria Johnston, Lucas Dixon, Adam Connors, and Jimbo Wilson for help with the illustrations and figures</p>
    </div>
                
              
            </div>
          
        
      

      
    
  
  

  

  </article>

    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>