<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2024 03:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Family poisoned after using AI-generated mushroom identification book (208 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/LegalAdviceUK/comments/1etko9h/family_poisoned_after_using_aigenerated_mushroom/</link>
            <guid>41269514</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 19:24:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/LegalAdviceUK/comments/1etko9h/family_poisoned_after_using_aigenerated_mushroom/">https://old.reddit.com/r/LegalAdviceUK/comments/1etko9h/family_poisoned_after_using_aigenerated_mushroom/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41269514">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>EDIT: I have not stated the name of the online marketplace. Assumptions are being made in the comments, which I am neither confirming nor denying.</strong></p>

<p>My entire family was in hospital last week after accidentally consuming poisonous mushrooms.</p>

<p>My wife purchased a book from a major online retailer for my birthday. The book is entitled something similar to: "Mushrooms UK: A Guide to Harvesting Safe and Edible Mushrooms."</p>

<p>It comes with pictures of the mushrooms to help identify each one.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, the book in question was not accurate. A closer investigation reveals that the images of mushrooms are AI generated, and we have now found two instances of text where a sentence ends and is followed up with a random questions or fourth-wall breaking statements.</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<p><em>"In conclusion, morels are delicious mushrooms which can be consumed from August to the end of Summer. Let me know if there is anything else I can help you with."</em></p>

<p>The online retailer have instructed me to return the book and they will refund it. The book has been removed from sale from the online retailer, however, it appears there are dozens more in a similar style.</p>

<p>1.) Should I return this book to the retailer? I'm concerned I would lose any evidence I have if I return it. The purchase has already disappeared from my online account. It simply looks like it doesn't exist anymore. I still have the email.</p>

<p>2.) Are my family entitled to any compensation for my son and my wife's lost time at work? As well as the sickness they experienced?</p>

<p>3.) Can I report the creation of this book to the police as a crime?</p>

<p><strong>Just for clarity: We did not know it was AI-generated when we bought it! This was not disclosed on the website!</strong></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[VanillaJSX.com (220 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vanillajsx.com/</link>
            <guid>41269321</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 19:01:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vanillajsx.com/">https://vanillajsx.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41269321">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="root"><p>What if JSX just returned DOM elements?</p><div data-sample="sample1"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sdegutis/vanillajsx.com/blob/main/site/samples/sample1.tsx">View source</a></p><pre><code>export default function ClickMe() {
  let i = 0;
  const el = &lt;button&gt;Click me&lt;/button&gt; as HTMLButtonElement;
  el.onclick = (e) =&gt; {
    el.textContent = `Clicked ${++i} times`;
  };
  return el;
}
</code></pre></div><p>Would they be reusable?</p><p>Could they keep their own state?</p><div data-sample="sample2"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sdegutis/vanillajsx.com/blob/main/site/samples/sample2.tsx">View source</a></p><pre><code>import ClickMe from "./sample1.js";

export default () =&gt; &lt;&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ClickMe /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ClickMe /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;ClickMe /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/&gt;;
</code></pre></div><p>How would they work together?</p><p>Could they create an interactive DOM tree?</p><div data-sample="sample3"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sdegutis/vanillajsx.com/blob/main/site/samples/sample3.tsx">View source</a></p><pre><code>function TodoInput(attrs: { add: (v: string) =&gt; void }) {
  const input = &lt;input /&gt; as HTMLInputElement;
  input.placeholder = 'Add todo item...';
  input.onkeydown = (e) =&gt; {
    if (e.key === 'Enter') {
      attrs.add(input.value);
      input.value = '';
    }
  };
  return input;
}

class TodoList {
  ul = &lt;ul class='todolist' /&gt; as HTMLUListElement;
  add(v: string) {
    const item = &lt;li&gt;{v}&lt;/li&gt; as HTMLLIElement;
    item.onclick = () =&gt; item.remove();
    this.ul.append(item);
  }
}

export default () =&gt; {
  const list = new TodoList();
  list.add('foo');
  list.add('bar');
  return &lt;&gt;
    &lt;TodoInput add={(v) =&gt; list.add(v)} /&gt;
    {list.ul}
  &lt;/&gt;;
};
</code></pre></div><p>How would they handle large data?</p><p>Could they be convenient without a virtual dom?</p><div data-sample="sample4"><p><a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sdegutis/vanillajsx.com/blob/main/site/samples/sample4.tsx">View source</a></p><pre><code>import { data } from "../fetch-dataset.js";

export default function FindNames() {
  const status = &lt;p style='margin:1em 0' /&gt; as HTMLParagraphElement;
  const results = &lt;ul /&gt; as HTMLUListElement;
  const input = &lt;input
    value='eri(c|k)a?'
    autocomplete='new-password'
  /&gt; as HTMLInputElement;

  const updateMatches = () =&gt; {
    const matched = (data.entries()
      .filter(([k]) =&gt; k.match(input.value))
      .toArray());

    const matches = (Iterator.from(matched)
      .map(match =&gt; &lt;Item regex={input.value} match={match} /&gt;)
      .take(30));

    results.replaceChildren(...matches);
    status.textContent = `${matched.length} / ${data.size}`;
  };

  input.oninput = updateMatches;
  updateMatches();

  return &lt;div class='sample4'&gt;
    {input}
    {status}
    {results}
  &lt;/div&gt;;
}

function Item(attrs: { match: [string, number], regex: string }) {
  const [name, count] = attrs.match;
  const total = &lt;small style='color:#fff3'&gt;({count})&lt;/small&gt;;
  return &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;span innerHTML={highlight(name, attrs.regex)} /&gt; {total}
  &lt;/li&gt;;
}

function highlight(str: string, regex: string) {
  if (!regex) return str;
  const r = new RegExp(`(${regex})`, 'gi');
  return str.replace(r, '&lt;span class="match"&gt;$1&lt;/span&gt;');
}
</code></pre></div><p>That's why I wrote <a target="_blank" href="https://code.immaculatalibrary.com/">imlib</a> (<a href="https://github.com/sdegutis/imlib">src</a>).</p><p>It came out of my work on <a target="_blank" href="https://www.immaculatalibrary.com/">immaculatalibrary.com</a> (<a href="https://github.com/sdegutis/immaculatalibrary.com">src</a>).</p><p>I started using it to build <a target="_blank" href="https://minigamemaker.com/">minigamemaker.com</a> (<a href="https://github.com/sdegutis/minigamemaker.com">src</a>).</p><p>I also used it to build <a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/sdegutis/vanillajsx.com/tree/main/site">the website you're reading</a> (&lt;-- src).</p><p>It was created because the status quo wasn't good enough for my site.</p><p>It is now my favorite way to make apps.</p><p>(Also, here's a much better <a href="https://sdegutis.github.io/imlib-todolist/">imlib todo-list app</a> (<a href="https://github.com/sdegutis/imlib-todolist/blob/main/site/app.tsx">src</a>)).</p><p>The two most complex "interactive apps" I've built with this are:</p><ul><li><a href="https://www.immaculatalibrary.com/books.html">Books search page</a> (<a href="https://github.com/sdegutis/immaculatalibrary.com/blob/main/site/scripts/books-page.tsx">src</a>)</li><li><a href="https://www.immaculatalibrary.com/prayers/">Prayer page</a> (<a href="https://github.com/sdegutis/immaculatalibrary.com/blob/main/site/prayers/client.tsx">src</a>)</li></ul></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Backdoor discovered in several brands of RFID cards [pdf] (213 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://eprint.iacr.org/2024/1275.pdf</link>
            <guid>41269249</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 18:53:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://eprint.iacr.org/2024/1275.pdf">https://eprint.iacr.org/2024/1275.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41269249">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Disrupting a covert Iranian influence operation (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/index/disrupting-a-covert-iranian-influence-operation/</link>
            <guid>41269113</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 18:39:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/index/disrupting-a-covert-iranian-influence-operation/">https://openai.com/index/disrupting-a-covert-iranian-influence-operation/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41269113">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://openai.com/index/disrupting-a-covert-iranian-influence-operation/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Good programmers worry about data structures and their relationships (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://read.engineerscodex.com/p/good-programmers-worry-about-data</link>
            <guid>41268803</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 18:09:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://read.engineerscodex.com/p/good-programmers-worry-about-data">https://read.engineerscodex.com/p/good-programmers-worry-about-data</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41268803">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p><em>Engineer’s Codex is a publication about real-world software engineering.</em></p><p>I recently came across a quote by Linus Torvalds (creator of Linux and Git) that  succinctly described a problem I’ve been working on recently:</p><blockquote><p><em>"Bad programmers worry about the code. Good programmers worry about data structures and their relationships."</em></p></blockquote><p><span>Right before the above quote, Linus said:</span><br></p><blockquote><p><em>git actually has a simple design, with stable and reasonably well-documented data structures. In fact, I'm a huge proponent of designing your code around the data, rather than the other way around, and I think it's one of the reasons git has been fairly successful […] I will, in fact, claim that the difference between a bad programmer and a good one is whether he considers his code or his data structures more important.</em></p></blockquote><p>Good data structures make code easier to design and maintain. It makes software more reliable, systems more understandable, and code more readable. When designing any software, application logic often follows the data model. Treating the data model as an afterthought results in more work down the line. The inverse is true also - having a well-thought out data model makes migrations and building on top of complex systems easier down the line.</p><p>When I read this quote, I actually was able to recognize countless examples in the past of this. I once worked on a project where we spent quite a while optimizing complex algorithms, only to realize that by restructuring our data, we could eliminate entire classes of problems. We replaced a 500-line function with a 50-line function and a well-designed data structure. Not only was the new code faster, but it was also much easier to understand and maintain.&nbsp;(Of course, then the problem also shifted “down the stack” to where the majority of toil was in restructuring existing data.)</p><p><span>Another relevant quote here is in </span><em>The Art of Unix Programming</em><span>:&nbsp;</span></p><blockquote><p>Rule of Representation: Fold knowledge into data so program logic can be stupid and robust.</p><p>Even the simplest procedural logic is hard for humans to verify, but quite complex data structures are fairly easy to model and reason about. To see this, compare the expressiveness and explanatory power of a diagram of (say) a fifty-node pointer tree with a flowchart of a fifty-line program. Or, compare an array initializer expressing a conversion table with an equivalent switch statement. The difference in transparency and clarity is dramatic. See Rob Pike's Rule 5.</p><p><strong>Data is more tractable than program logic. It follows that where you see a choice between complexity in data structures and complexity in code, choose the former. More: in evolving a design, you should actively seek ways to shift complexity from code to data.</strong></p><p>The Unix community did not originate this insight, but a lot of Unix code displays its influence. The C language's facility at manipulating pointers, in particular, has encouraged the use of dynamically-modified reference structures at all levels of coding from the kernel upward. Simple pointer chases in such structures frequently do duties that implementations in other languages would instead have to embody in more elaborate procedures.</p></blockquote><p><span>The </span><strong>actionable tip here is to start with the data. </strong><span>Try to reduce code complexity through stricter types on your interfaces or databases. Spend extra time thinking through the data structures ahead of time. </span></p><p><span>That’s not to say the </span><em>code isn’t important</em><span>. Obviously, everything is important - but it’s useful to have a strong high-level approach of how data will flow and how different components interact before going deeper into code-related details.&nbsp;</span></p><p><span>It’s why one of the </span><em>Senior Engineer (L5)</em><span> requirements (at least for FAANG) generally involves writing higher-level design docs for more complex systems (which includes driving team planning and building good roadmaps for medium-to-large features). </span></p><p><span> from </span></p><p><span> wrote a great piece on the higher level of influence L5s generally have here:</span></p><p><span> from </span></p><p><span> also wrote a great piece about getting to Senior Engineer: </span></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Banks Are Now Accused of Cheating Customers Billions (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://franknez.com/massive-banks-are-now-accused-of-cheating-customers-billions/</link>
            <guid>41268800</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 18:08:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://franknez.com/massive-banks-are-now-accused-of-cheating-customers-billions/">https://franknez.com/massive-banks-are-now-accused-of-cheating-customers-billions/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41268800">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	
		
<p>Massive banks are now accused of cheating customers billions of dollars in interest payments according to financial reports. </p>



<p>According to a new report by <em>Financial Times</em>, several major Wall Street banks, including <strong><a href="https://franknez.com/wells-fargo-is-now-freezing-bank-accounts-in-new-scandal/">Wells Fargo</a></strong>, Morgan Stanley, and <strong><a href="https://franknez.com/bank-of-america-is-freezing-accounts-in-new-scandal/">Bank of America</a></strong>, are accused of defrauding customers out of billions of dollars in interest payments.</p>



<p>The U.S. <strong>Securities and Exchange Commission</strong> (SEC) is currently investigating these banks to determine whether they intentionally steered clients toward <em>“cash sweep”</em> accounts that provided little to no interest earnings, despite the availability of higher-yielding options.</p>



<p>This alleged practice by the banks would amount to bilking customers out of significant sums of interest income that they should have rightfully earned on their deposits and cash holdings. </p>



<p>The SEC’s probe is aimed at uncovering whether this was a deliberate strategy by the banks to boost their own profits at the expense of their clients.</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/de751907-c870-4b8c-b86b-317483f7626f" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">report</a> in the Financial Times highlights the concerning allegations of widespread misconduct by some of the largest financial institutions on Wall Street.</p>



<p>If substantiated, this could represent a major scandal involving the potential exploitation of customers through the mismanagement of their cash accounts and interest earnings.</p>



<p>The SEC’s investigation will be crucial in determining the full scope and nature of these alleged practices, as well as any potential enforcement actions or penalties that may be levied against the implicated banks.</p>



<p>The revelations have emerged from new Quarterly filings with the SEC.</p>



<p>In those filings, Wells Fargo says it’s in <em>“resolution talks”</em> with the agency over the issue, Morgan Stanley says the agency began asking questions about it in April and Bank of America confirms it’s currently being scrutinized.</p>



<p>All three banks have declined to comment on the matter.</p>



<p>Other financial firms involved in lawsuits related to cash sweep accounts include LPL Financial and Ameriprise.</p>



<p>LPL Financial says it plans to <em>“vigorously”</em> defend itself against the allegations, while Ameriprise has not released a public statement on the matter.</p>



<p>For more <strong><a href="https://franknez.com/us-bank-news-today/">U.S. Bank news</a></strong> and updates like this, opt-in for push notifications.</p>



<p><strong>Also Read:&nbsp;<a href="https://franknez.com/the-us-treasury-direct-is-now-freezing-customer-accounts/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The US Treasury Direct is Now Freezing Customer Accounts</a></strong></p>



<h2 id="h-other-banking-news-today"><strong>Other Banking News Today</strong></h2>



<figure><picture><source sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" type="image/webp" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-1024x573.jpg.webp 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-300x168.jpg.webp 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-768x430.jpg.webp 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-676x379.jpg.webp 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default.jpg.webp 1100w"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="573" src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-1024x573.jpg" alt="Market News Today - Massive Banks Are Now Accused of Cheating Customers Billions." srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-1024x573.jpg 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-300x168.jpg 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-768x430.jpg 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-676x379.jpg 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default.jpg 1100w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" data-eio="l" data-old-src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAABAAAAAI9AQAAAACMUjdnAAAAAnRSTlMAAHaTzTgAAABeSURBVHja7cExAQAAAMKg9U9tDB+gAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAADgbCDMAAHzbk7nAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC" data-src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-1024x573.jpg" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-1024x573.jpg 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-300x168.jpg 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-768x430.jpg 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default-676x379.jpg 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/Massive-US-Banks-Now-Prepare-For-Millions-to-Default.jpg 1100w"></picture><figcaption>Market News Today – Massive Banks Are Now Accused of Cheating Customers Billions.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Massive US banks now prepare for millions to default according to Q2 reports, as institutions increase capital to cover insolvencies.</p>



<p>Big banks such as <strong><a href="https://franknez.com/jpmorgan-is-freezing-customer-bank-accounts-in-new-scandal/">JPMorgan Chase</a></strong>, <strong><a href="https://franknez.com/bank-of-america-is-freezing-accounts-in-new-scandal/">Bank of America</a></strong> and <strong><a href="https://franknez.com/wells-fargo-is-now-freezing-bank-accounts-in-new-scandal/">Wells Fargo</a></strong> are boosting their financial defenses as they prepare for customer inflow to dwindle, affecting the ability for the average American to pay their bills.</p>



<p>According to the latest Q2 2024 financial reports from major banks, they are significantly increasing the amount of capital they are setting aside to cover potential losses from rising credit card and loan defaults.</p>



<p>Collectively, these banks are allocating billions of dollars into emergency provisions and loan loss reserves to prepare for an anticipated increase in insolvencies and non-performing loans. </p>



<p>This reflects the banks’ growing concerns about the potential for a rise in credit card delinquencies and loan defaults in the coming months.</p>



<p>By bolstering their loss-absorbing capital buffers, the banks are attempting to proactively mitigate the financial risks posed by a potential surge in credit-related delinquencies and insolvencies. </p>



<p>This suggests the banks foresee a deterioration in consumer credit quality and are taking prudent steps to strengthen their balance sheets and resilience against such adverse credit trends.</p>



<p>The significant increase in these emergency loan loss provisions across the banking sector signals that the institutions are bracing for a potential economic downturn that could lead to a rise in loan defaults and credit-related write-offs.</p>



<p>This move underscores the banks’ efforts to position themselves to better withstand any upcoming challenges in the credit markets.</p>



<p>JPMorgan Chase is leading the way, increasing its provisions from $1.88 billion in the first quarter of this year to $3.05 billion – a $1.17 billion jump.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, Bank of America has set aside $1.5 billion, up from $1.3 billion in the previous quarter, and Wells Fargo set aside $1.24 billion, up from $938 million in the previous quarter.</p>



<p>The increasing balances show banks are anticipating increasing economic risk in the months ahead as commercial real estate flounders and as consumers pile up a&nbsp;whopping&nbsp;$1.02 trillion in credit card balances, according to <a href="https://newsroom.transunion.com/ciir-q1-2024/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">TransUnion</a>.</p>



<p>Delinquency rates across various types of debt are already on the rise, and the New York Federal Reserve&nbsp;<a href="https://www.newyorkfed.org/newsevents/news/research/2024/20240514" rel="noreferrer noopener" target="_blank">says</a>&nbsp;total US household debt hit $17.69 trillion in the first quarter of this year, an increase of $184 billion from the previous quarter.</p>



<p>The number includes mortgage balances, which rose by $190 billion to $12.44 trillion, and auto loans, which increased by $9 billion to $1.62 trillion.</p>



<p><strong>Also Read: <a href="https://franknez.com/a-massive-us-bank-is-now-closing-credit-cards/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">A Massive US Bank is Now Closing Credit Cards</a></strong></p>



<div><p>
<h2 id="h-market-news-published-daily"><strong>Market News Published Daily</strong> 📰</h2>
</p></div>



<figure><picture><source sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" type="image/webp" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-1024x574.jpg.webp 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-300x168.jpg.webp 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-768x431.jpg.webp 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-676x379.jpg.webp 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez.jpg.webp 1100w"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="574" src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-1024x574.jpg" alt="Market News Today - Massive Banks Are Now Accused of Cheating Customers Billions." srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-300x168.jpg 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-768x431.jpg 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-676x379.jpg 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez.jpg 1100w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" data-eio="l" data-old-src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAABAAAAAI+AQAAAAAKxkXJAAAAAnRSTlMAAHaTzTgAAABeSURBVHja7cEBAQAAAIIg/69uSEABAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMC7ASFNAAFLuj9gAAAAAElFTkSuQmCC" data-src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-1024x574.jpg" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-1024x574.jpg 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-300x168.jpg 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-768x431.jpg 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez-676x379.jpg 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Daily-Market-News-FrankNez.jpg 1100w"></picture><figcaption>Market News Today – Massive Banks Are Now Accused of Cheating Customers Billions.</figcaption></figure>



<p>Don’t forget to opt-in for push notifications so you don’t miss a single article!</p>



<p>Be sure to share this article with your community.</p>



<p>We are tirelessly working on providing you with the latest market news as well as local news to keep you informed about job cuts, bankruptcies, and store closures in your area.</p>



<p>Also, thank you to all of our <strong><a href="https://www.patreon.com/FrankNezMedia" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">blog sponsors</a></strong>.</p>



<p>This year we’ve been able to increase push notifications slots making it more convenient than ever for new readers to receive their daily market news and updates.</p>



<p>Our readers can now <strong><a href="https://www.patreon.com/FrankNezMedia" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">donate $3 per month</a></strong> to support independent journalism.</p>



<p>For daily news and updates on your favorite stories, opt-in for push notifications.</p>



<p><strong>Follow Frank Nez on</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/FNez_Blogger" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>X (Twitter)</strong></a>,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.instagram.com/iamfranknez/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><strong>Instagram</strong></a>,&nbsp;or <strong><a href="https://www.facebook.com/NezMediaCompany/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Facebook</a></strong>. </p>







<hr>


<div>
<figure><picture><source sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" type="image/webp" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3.png.webp 512w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-300x300.png.webp 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-150x150.png.webp 150w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-270x270.png.webp 270w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-192x192.png.webp 192w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-180x180.png.webp 180w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-32x32.png.webp 32w"><img decoding="async" width="512" height="512" src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3.png" alt="" srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3.png 512w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-300x300.png 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-150x150.png 150w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-270x270.png 270w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-192x192.png 192w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-180x180.png 180w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-32x32.png 32w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" data-eio="l" data-old-src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAAgAAAAIAAQAAAADcA+lXAAAAAnRSTlMAAHaTzTgAAAA2SURBVHja7cEBAQAAAIIg/69uSEABAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAHwbggAAAWN1UKQAAAAASUVORK5CYII=" data-src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3.png" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3.png 512w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-300x300.png 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-150x150.png 150w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-270x270.png 270w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-192x192.png 192w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-180x180.png 180w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/03/cropped-Frank-Nez-Market-News-Icon-3-32x32.png 32w"></picture></figure></div>


<h2 id="h-support-independent-journalism"><strong><a href="https://www.patreon.com/FrankNezMedia" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Support Independent Journalism</a></strong> ✍🏻</h2>



<p>Support independent journalism for just $3 per month!</p>



<p>Your contributions help power Franknez.com as the cost of widgets and online tools continue to rise.</p>



<p>Thank you for your support!</p>







<hr>



<h3 id="h-recommended-for-you"><strong>Recommended For You ✨</strong></h3>


<div><ul><li><a href="https://franknez.com/the-us-treasury-direct-is-now-freezing-customer-accounts/"><p><span>The US Treasury Direct is Now Freezing Customer Accounts</span></p></a></li><li><a href="https://franknez.com/snap-benefits-will-now-increase-for-the-year-2024/"><p><span>SNAP Benefits Will Now Increase For The Year 2024</span></p></a></li><li><a href="https://franknez.com/california-now-has-massive-departures-as-hundreds-of-thousands-leave/"><p><span>California Now Has Massive Departures As Hundreds of Thousands Leave</span></p></a></li><li><a href="https://franknez.com/a-us-bank-is-now-denying-customers-access-to-money/"><p><span>A US Bank is Now Denying Customers Access to Money</span></p></a></li><li><a href="https://franknez.com/a-giant-company-now-announces-unexpected-layoffs-in-virginia/"><p><span>A Giant Company Now Announces Unexpected Layoffs in Virginia</span></p></a></li><li><a href="https://franknez.com/a-massive-us-bank-is-now-closing-credit-cards/"><p><span>A Massive US Bank is Now Closing Credit Cards</span></p></a></li></ul></div>

<div><picture><source type="image/webp" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-300x168.jpg.webp 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-1024x573.jpg.webp 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-768x430.jpg.webp 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-676x379.jpg.webp 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees.jpg.webp 1100w"><img decoding="async" src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-300x168.jpg" srcset=" https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-300x168.jpg 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-1024x573.jpg 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-768x430.jpg 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-676x379.jpg 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees.jpg 1100w " alt="Donald Trump Now Plans To End Social Security Taxes For Retirees" data-eio="l" data-old-src="data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAASwAAACoAQAAAAByUO6iAAAAAnRSTlMAAHaTzTgAAAAdSURBVFjD7cExAQAAAMKg9U9tCy+gAAAAAAAAeBgZmAABPsQcywAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==" data-src="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-300x168.jpg" data-srcset="https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-300x168.jpg 300w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-1024x573.jpg 1024w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-768x430.jpg 768w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees-676x379.jpg 676w, https://franknez.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Donald-Trump-Now-Plans-To-End-Social-Security-Taxes-For-Retirees.jpg 1100w"></picture></div>




<hr>

							
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Apple IIGS Megahertz Myth (133 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.userlandia.com/home/iigs-mhz-myth</link>
            <guid>41268256</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 17:08:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.userlandia.com/home/iigs-mhz-myth">https://www.userlandia.com/home/iigs-mhz-myth</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41268256">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-block-type="2" id="block-d3767bee736bb4906a02">

<p>There’s many legends in computer history. But a legend is nothing but a story. Someone tells it, someone else remembers it, and everybody passes it on. And the Apple IIGS has a legend all its own. Here, in Userlandia, we’re going to bust some megahertz myths.</p>




















  
  



</div><div data-block-type="2" id="block-yui_3_17_2_1_1722774331649_10942">
  <p><em>[A side note before proceeding… I see all you Hacker News people filing in. I haven’t had the time recently to properly format this with the numerous source links, citations, and footnotes that exist in the video version. I’ll try to get those filled in here ASAP. For now, you might want to experience it all in the video version.]</em></p><p>I love the Apple IIGS. It’s the fabulous home computer you’d have to be crazy to hate. One look at its spec sheet will tell you why. The Ensoniq synthesizer chip brings 32 voices of polyphonic power to the desktop. Apple’s Video Graphics Controller paints beautiful on-screen pictures from a palette of thousands of colors. Seven slots and seven ports provide plenty of potential for powerful peripherals. These ingredients make a great recipe for a succulent home computer. But you can’t forget the most central ingredient: the central processing unit. It’s a GTE 65SC816 clocked at 2.8 MHz—about 2.72 times faster than an Apple IIe. When the IIGS launched in September 1986 its contemporaries were systems like the Atari 1040ST, the Commodore Amiga 1000, and of course Apple’s own Macintosh Plus. These machines all sported a Motorola 68000 clocked between 7 and 8 MHz. If I know anything about which number is bigger than the other number, I’d say that Motorola’s CPU is faster.</p><p>“Now hold on there,” you say! “Megahertz is just the clock speed of the chip—it says nothing about how many instructions are actually executed during those cycles, let alone the time spent reading and writing to RAM!” And you know what, that’s true! The Apple II and Commodore 64 with their 6502 and 6510 CPUs clocked at 1 MHz could trade blows with Z80 powered computers running at three times the clock speed. And the IIGS had the 6502’s 16-bit descendant: the 65C816. Steve Wozniak thought Western Design Center had something special with that chip. <a href="https://archive.org/details/BYTE_Vol_10-01_1985-01_Through_The_Hourglass/page/166/mode/2up" target="_blank">In a famous interview in the January 1985 issue of Byte magazine</a>, Woz said, </p><blockquote><p>“[the 65816] should be available soon in an 8 MHz version that will beat the pants off the 68000 in most applications, and in graphics applications it comes pretty close.” End quote. That’s already high praise, but he continues further: “An 8 MHz 65816 is about equivalent to a 16 MHz 68000 in speed, and a 16 MHz 68000 doesn’t exist.”</p></blockquote><p>If you read this in January of 1985 you’d have little reason to doubt Woz’s words. He built the Apple I in a bedroom from a box of scraps and when given real resources followed it up with the Apple II. Even when faced with doubters, he’s got the confidence that comes from engineering the impossible. </p><blockquote><p>“Some of the Macintosh people might disagree with me, but there are ways around most of the problems they see.”</p></blockquote><p>But that “should” in “should be available” was doing a lot of work. <a href="https://mirrors.apple2.org.za/ftp.apple.asimov.net/documentation/magazines/aplus/A%2B%201986-11.pdf" target="_blank">Eighteen months later when the IIGS finally shipped, there was no 8 MHz ‘816.</a> It was as nonexistent as Woz’s imaginary 16MHz 68000. 8MHz chips were barely available three years later. What happened? Woz promised us 8 MHz of 68000-crushing glory!</p><p>If you poll a random vintage computer user they might posit the idea that Apple held the IIGS’ processor speed back during its development so it wouldn’t compete with the Macintosh. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Apple_IIGS#Hardware" target="_blank">There’s an unsourced claim on Wikipedia that limiting the CPU speed to 2.8MHz was a deliberate decision</a> followed by a note—which <em>is</em> sourced, thank you very much—that the original CPU was certified to run at 4MHz. And that’s true—there’s many IIGSes that have CPUs labeled for 4MHz. This idea’s made its way through various newsgroups and webpages for decades, so it’s no surprise that it made its way into a Wiki article too.</p><p>But this theory never sat well with me. People making the claim that Apple restrained the IIGS’ CPU speed for marketing purposes rarely provide sources to back it up. I understand their logic—Apple spent the majority of its marketing and monetary might making the Macintosh the machine of the future. Because the Mac was Steve Jobs’ baby, you end up with declarations like “Steve Jobs hobbled the IIGS so it wouldn’t compete with the Mac.” It’s a common take, especially because it plays into a lot of people’s dislike of Jobs. But there’s one major problem with it: all of Steve Jobs’ power at Apple was stripped away in May of 1985 after the months of executive turmoil that led to the company's first quarterly loss. The IIGS didn't launch until 16 months later.</p><p>So why were IIGSes with chips rated at 4 MHz not running them at that speed? Why 2.8 MHz? Isn't that…  <em>weirdly</em> specific? Did an 8 MHz machine really get put on ice due to executive meddling? To solve these mysteries I descended into the depths of Usenet, usergroup newsletters, magazines, and interviews. My journey took me through a world of development Hell, problematic yields, and CPU cycle quirks. And this walk down the Apple chip road starts with the wonderful wizard named Woz.</p><h2>The Apple IIx</h2><p>It’s the summer of 1983 and Steve Wozniak has just wrapped up a two year leave of absence from Apple Computer. It all started with a six week stint in the hospital <a href="https://www.ntsb.gov/Pages/brief.aspx?ev_id=27749&amp;key=0" target="_blank">after crashing his Beechcraft Bonanza airplane on February 7, 1981</a>. <a href="http://ns1.woz.com/letters/memory-loss/" target="_blank">Amnesia from a hard concussion short-circuited Wozniak’s short-term memory</a>. After his recovery he took a leave from Apple <a href="https://engineering.berkeley.edu/steve-wozniak-inventor-and-apple-co-founder/" target="_blank">to go back to UC Berkeley and finish his degree in computer science and electrical engineering</a>… and run a few rock festivals. By June of 1983 Woz felt he was ready to return to work, and asked Dave Paterson, the head of Apple II engineering, for a job—but this time, in the trenches.</p><p>His timing was excellent. Even though the Lisa was taking headlines and the Macintosh was shaking up R&amp;D, the Apple II was making all the money. Brisk sales of the IIe along with the imminent launch of the IIc meant the Apple II division was busier than ever even if they weren’t getting all the glory. And while Steve Jobs was heralding the Mac as the Next Big Thing, designing a next-generation Apple II as a contingency plan was just good business.</p><p>At the heart of this proposed machine was a brand new CPU. Bill Mensch’s Western Design Center was busy developing the 65816, a 16-bit update to the venerable 6502 architecture. This chip would bring 16-bit computing to the Apple II while promising backwards compatibility. Users wouldn’t lose their investment in applications, add-in cards, or accessories. Alongside the new CPU was a special coprocessor slot that allowed the user to install a board with a 68000 or 8088. <a href="https://archive.org/details/The_Apple_IIgs_Book_Jeanne_DuPrau/page/n17/mode/2up" target="_blank">The goal was to build a bridge between the 8- and 16-bit world, so the project had code names like Brooklyn and Golden Gate</a>. </p><p>This project would be known publicly as the IIx thanks to Wozniak discussing it on CompuServe or at user groups. But as late ’83 rolled into early ’84 the IIx project stumbled over multiple roadblocks. The coprocessor slot added layers of complexity that distracted from the mission of architecting a new Apple II. But a major complication was the 65816 itself. Apple expected engineering samples in November 1983, but didn’t actually get them until February 1984. What’s worse, those late chips were buggy, unstable, and ultimately unusable. WDC delivered a second batch of chips a few weeks later, but they were no more reliable than the first.</p><p>Even if Apple abandoned the coprocessor slot, the project couldn’t go forward without a CPU, and Apple cancelled the IIx project in March of 1984. Now before you aim your ire at Steve Jobs, <a href="https://mirrors.apple2.org.za/ftp.apple.asimov.net/documentation/magazines/aplus/" target="_blank">A+ Magazine, in their IIGS development history</a>, says it was the team leads who suggested canning the troubled machine. With no managerial appetite for a next-generation machine, the Apple II team pivoted from a moonshot to something more achievable. Dan Hillman and Jay Rickard started a project to consolidate most of the discrete chips of an Apple II into a single chip called the Mega II. When they finished the design six months later they weren’t quite sure what to do with it. Would they reduce the cost of the IIe or reduce the size of the IIc?</p><p>Imagine their surprise when Woz suggested a second shot at a 16-bit Apple II. The conditions seemed right to give it another go. Less expensive 16-bit computers like the Atari ST were looming on the horizon and the Mac’s hot start was slowing down. By October 1984 Apple finally had a good supply of working 65816 CPUs to design a system. And the Mega II would free up a lot of board space to add new graphics and sound chips. But just as important as chips and specs was a new, focused mission statement. This computer would be an Apple II by Apple II fans for Apple II fans. Woz, Hillman, Rickard, Harvey Leitman, and Lee Collings spent the rest of 1984 hammering out the specifications and solving hard problems like how to speed up memory access without breaking existing software.</p><p>Now we’re finally back to that Woz interview I quoted earlier. Byte published it in two parts across the December ’84 and January ’85 issues, and based on the average time to press I reckon it took place in October 1984. By this point the IIx is dead and buried and he’s talking about the new 16-bit Apple II, now codenamed Phoenix. His excitement about an 8MHz ‘816 is palpable, but, again, Woz was careful to say it “<em>should</em> be available soon.” Woz left Apple in February 1985 when the ink for this interview was barely dry. He had a dramatic fight with John Sculley after the Apple II was snubbed at the annual Apple shareholder’s meeting in January 1985. Apple II sales supplied seventy percent of Apple’s revenue in 1984 and Woz’s Apple II compatriots felt they weren’t getting their due. Steve Jobs may not have dialed back the IIGS’ clock speed, but he <em>did</em> shovel endless piles of money towards his pet projects at the expense of the Apple II. Even if Woz had stuck around the 8 MHz ‘816 of his dreams was years away. The IIGS wouldn’t sniff 8 MHz until Applied Engineering released the 7 MHz TransWarp GS accelerator four years later in 1989.</p><h2>The Need for Speed</h2><p><a href="https://www.applefritter.com/content/apple-iigs-bad-onboard-ram" target="_blank">If you go looking online for photos of Apple IIGS logic boards</a>, there’s a decent chance you’ll see a 4MHz GTE G65SC816 CPU. Most IIGSes had 4 or 3 MHz CPUs running at 2.8 MHz regardless of the chip’s rated speed. Why?</p><p>First, we must understand where that clock signal comes from. The IIGS, like many computers of its era, derives its base clock from a crystal oscillator. The one in the IIGS vibrates 28.636 million times per second, or megahertz. The VGC divides that 28.636 megahertz in half, and 14.318 MHz is then supplied along with a stretch signal to other parts of the system. I bet you've already noticed that these frequencies are multiples of the NTSC colorburst frequency of 3.58MHz. Keep that in mind, it’ll be relevant later.</p><p>This 14.318 MHz clock travels to a special ASIC which—depending on your board revision—is called the Fast Processor Interface or Control Your Apple chip. One of its responsibilities is dynamically controlling the CPU’s clock speed. The IIGS normally runs in Fast mode at 2.8 MHz, but the user can switch to Normal mode in the Control Panel which reduces the speed to 1.023 MHz. It’s like the turbo switch on PCs, except controlled by the FPI. This lets the IIGS run speed-sensitive software at the same speed of an original Apple II. But even in fast mode there are times the CPU needs to slow down to access other parts of the system.</p><p>The CPU, ROM, and Fast RAM are on the 2.8 MHz, or fast side, while the Mega II chip, slots, sound, video, and so on are on the 1MHz, or slow side. When the CPU is running in fast mode and needs to talk to something on the slow side the FPI dynamically throttles the clock signal to a 1 MHz cycle time to let the CPU synchronize with the Mega II side. This is usually invisible to the user because the system still executes the majority of its cycles at the faster speed, but it means the CPU is not always executing as fast as it could. I haven’t even touched on the eight percent performance penalty from the cycles the FPI spends refreshing RAM.</p><p>There’s nothing inherent to this design that limits the system to 2.8 MHz. The <a href="https://archive.org/details/Apple_IIgs_Hardware_Reference_HiRes/page/n47/mode/2up" target="_blank">Apple IIGS Hardware Reference</a>, <a href="http://www.brutaldeluxe.fr/documentation/cortland/v5/Cortland%20Custom%20ICs%20-%20Wayne%20Lowry%20-%20Preliminary%20notes%20-%2019860214.pdf" target="_blank">Wayne Lowry’s Cortland Custom IC Notes</a>, and <a href="https://www.kansasfest.org/2012/04/2011-krue-fpi/" target="_blank">Daniel Kruszyna’s KansasFest 2011</a> presentation about the FPI lay it out clearly that the IIGS’s fast mode could support higher speeds. In principle a redesigned FPI or CYA could use a divider other than 1/5 for the clock signal. A 1/4 divider of 14.318 MHz yields a 3.58 MHz clock speed, which should be well within the capabilities of a 4 MHz chip. And once again, that “should” is doing a lot of work. So why didn’t it run at that speed?</p><h2>The Birth of the 65C816</h2><p>The 65C816 and IIGS are inextricably linked, and the ‘816’s story starts in 1981 when GTE’s Desmond Sheahan approached Bill Mensch and Western Design Center about designing a CPU. GTE wanted to manufacture their own chips for their key phone systems, so they licensed both a CMOS manufacturing process and a 6802 CPU design from Mitel. But Mitel’s CPU design team wasn’t up to the task, so GTE asked Mensch to step in. Mensch offered two options: a two-chip 6802 solution or a 6502-based microcontroller. Either one could be manufactured on the CMOS process GTE licensed from Mitel. Sheahan convinced the GTE brass that the one-chip solution was the way to go, and the 65C02 was born.</p><p>GTE became the first licensee of the 65C02 thanks to WDC designing their 65SC150 telephony microcontroller. Eventually WDC would license the core to other companies, like NCR, Synertek, and Rockwell. The result was WDC netting a royalty every time one of these licensees sold a standalone CPU or microcontroller with its 65C02 core. Functional 65C02 silicon was available in 1982, and the revenues from licensing deals were finally filling up WDC’s coffers. This is when—<a href="https://www.computerhistory.org/collections/catalog/102739969" target="_blank">according to Mensch’s Computer History Museum oral history and other sources</a>—Apple approached him about a 16-bit successor to the 6502.</p><p>The prospect of a big player like Apple being the launch client for a new CPU was hard to resist. Further information on the early days of the ‘816 is fairly elusive, but looking at both historic and contemporary interviews with Mensch and Woz reveals Apple’s influence on the chip’s design. One influence was compatibility. When designing the ‘816 <a href="https://mirrors.apple2.org.za/apple2.caltech.edu/miscinfo/65xxx.chronology" target="_blank">Mensch improved the 6502 bus architecture</a> to eliminate little weirdnesses like false read cycles on store accumulators. This consequently broke Steve Wozniak’s Disk II controller, which had been designed to rely specifically on that exact weirdness.</p><p>Now there’s two ways to solve this problem: redesign the floppy controller, or add the weirdnesses back in. Apple tried the first one; redesigning its floppy controller into a single chip called the Integrated Woz Machine. This chip was made independently for the Apple IIc to control its built-in floppy drive. <a href="http://www.brutaldeluxe.fr/documentation/iwm/iwm_discussion_19820531" target="_blank">Among its many improvements was eliminating the false read cycle requirement</a>. The Apple IIx could have used an IWM, but the UniDisk drives that took advantage of it wouldn’t be out until 1985. Therefore existing Disk II interfaces and drives still had to work with the IIx. If you were to claim Apple II compatibility, but not be able to work with one of the most popular boards, well, there’d be protests lining the sidewalks of De Anza Boulevard. Other cards might also depend on specific 6502 timing behaviors. <a href="https://www.commodore.ca/commodore-history/bill-mench-the-brains-behind-the-brains/" target="_blank">Mensch eventually honored Apple’s request that the 65C816 be fully compatible with the NMOS 6502’s timings</a>.</p><p>Apple wouldn’t be Mensch’s only licensee for the ‘816—the core can be found in countless embedded systems and microcontrollers. Licensees could extend the core to customize it into a microcontroller or a system-on-chip, or add features specific to their needs. A great example is Ricoh, who licensed the ‘816 core and added several functions, like dedicated multiply and divide units along with special DMA functions. All these add-ons were at the request of a pretty famous customer: Nintendo. The result was <a href="https://sneslab.net/wiki/65c816" target="_blank">the Ricoh 5A22, the CPU inside the Super NES</a>.</p><p>One of the famous tales of the ‘816’s development is how it was laid out without computer aided design. As told by Bill Mensch, he designed the ‘816 on a card table at WDC’s humble headquarters in Mesa, Arizona. His sister Katherine did the layout on mylar sheets. Many semiconductor designers had moved on to computer aided design tools to help design and lay out their circuits. Mensch is rightly proud of this feat, but the decision to lay it out by hand with mylar and rubylith wasn’t without consequences.</p><p>Let’s circle back to that interview with Woz. <a href="https://archive.org/details/gteg65sc816datasheetocrbm/mode/2up" target="_blank">GTE published data sheets in 1985 for the G65SC816</a> which detailed 2, 4, 6, and 8 MHz variants of the chip. Apple, as the prime customer, would’ve had these data sheets far in advance. This would be consistent with Woz’s belief that faster variants were on the way, but for purposes of designing the IIGS they had to settle for 4MHz chips. Multiple photographs of IIGS prototype logic boards with 4MHz chips are on the web, and 4MHz parts shipped in production IIGS computers. But the promise of a faster CPU is very tantalizing to a computer designer, and I’m sure it wasn’t just Woz who was excited about future faster CPUs.</p><p>But when would GTE actually produce those faster variants? That’s the question. One source is <a href="http://commodore.ca/commodore-history/bill-mench-the-brains-behind-the-brains/" target="_blank">a 1986 interview with Mensch published in the Fall/Winter issue of COMPUTE!’s Apple Applications magazine</a>. This interview took place before the IIGS announcement, likely sometime in the summer of ’86. Mensch states their average part on a 3 micron process should be 4MHz, and an upcoming 2.4 micron process would yield 6MHz parts. I’d wager that the 8 MHz parts would rely on a 2 micron process at that reduction rate. Some 6MHz parts did exist, and Bill Mensch’s Cortland-badged prototype IIGS has one. A photo of it was shown at his 2021 VCF East panel, and I will note that it’s a WDC branded chip bearing a date code of the first week of February 1987. Whether Mensch put this chip in there himself or it was a sample installed by an Apple engineer is not explained. Nor is it known if its FPI chip actually drives it at a higher speed. But this shows that faster ‘816s did exist. So what was getting in the way of these faster chips actually being used?</p><h2>Yields, Bugs, and Errata</h2><p>This brings us to the 65816’s next quandary: yields. This might be a surprise to you, given that the CPU is found in embedded devices worldwide. But a common thread through many of the reports I’ve read about the early days of the ‘816 is that WDC and its fabrication partners struggled to deliver 4MHz and faster chips on time, in volume, and at spec.</p><p>Mensch positioned the 4MHz chip as the ‘816’s volume product and said as much in that earlier interview with COMPUTE!. </p><blockquote><p>“Our typical product is 4MHz. We sell 2MHz into the retrofit&nbsp;market, but our typical run-of-the-mill is 4MHz.”</p></blockquote><p>But in reality the IIGS shipped with a mixture of 3 and 4 MHz parts which actually ran at 2.8 MHz in fast mode. Which brings us back to the question of why a machine designed around a 4MHz part would ship with an almost 30% haircut in clock speed. Conspiracy theories aside, could there be a <em>technical</em> reason why the IIGS would run slower than its CPU’s rated speed?</p><p>In the same Fall/Winter 1986 issue of COMPUTE!’s Apple Applications where Mensch talked about future plans for the ‘816, David Thornburg interviewed Steve Wozniak about his role in developing the IIGS. The subject of the 65816 came up and Woz delved into some details about its clock speed.</p><blockquote><p>“Our early ideas for the computer had it running around 8MHz. Soon we found we had to back off to about 5.5MHz, and then to 2MHz for that version of the processor. In the end the product came out around 3MHz, which is a good compromise.”</p></blockquote><p> This is consistent with his comments about the desire for 8MHz more than a year earlier in the Byte interview. Woz doesn’t mention what factors made them back off on the clock speed, but during my research I learned a lot about the troubles the ‘816 faced in terms of scaling and yields.</p><p>One problem was GTE’s ability to supply chips—not just to Apple, but to other customers. The IIGS would be shipping by the tens of thousands when it launched, and this necessitated a good quantity of chips on hand. Dave Haynie—yes, the Amiga’s Dave Haynie—had trouble in 1985 sourcing 4 MHz 65816s for a potential Commodore 128 successor. <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/RH1-BNz8x-c/m/385dAOKgaA4J" target="_blank">He posted about this experience on Usenet in March of 1990</a>. </p><blockquote><p>“At that time, they had fully specced 8MHz parts, yet in ’85, GTE (the only company actually MAKING 65816s) had all they could do to make enough 4MHz parts. Rumor is that Apple managed get enough for the IIGS by actually having a special 2.8MHz version tested.”</p></blockquote><p>He further elaborates with:</p><blockquote><p>“When the GS came out, the only company making '816s was GTE. The main reason I couldn't get any 4MHz ‘816s in quantity was that Apple bought them all. They could make a real deal on 2MHz parts, since the yield on 4MHz was so low, they had more of those than they knew what to do with.” </p></blockquote><p>Haynie <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/net.micro.apple/c/mPV8ErhJUJQ/m/AyRGXOAvqLAJ" target="_blank">also comments in other posts</a> about how early samples of the ‘816 were delivered at 500KHz—yes, <em>kilo</em>hertz—and maybe that’s a clue as to why Apple was unhappy in the Apple IIx timeframe.</p><p>Yields are a common woe in semiconductor manufacturing and Haynie’s comments about yields line up with what we see in the real world. GTE’s three micron process apparently had problems producing enough 4 MHz chips in volumes to satisfy its customers. Many IIGSes have a 3 MHz G65SC816 despite this speed rating not showing up in GTE’s data sheets. My guess—I can’t find any confirmation for this, but it's what makes the most sense—is that these were chips that couldn't be binned as 4 MHz, so GTE labeled them as 3MHz. Insisting on 4MHz would have meant shipping fewer computers, and the IIGS was delayed enough as it is. While VLSI supplied some 4MHz 65C816 CPUs later in the IIGS’ life, the vast majority of CPUs found in these computers were made by GTE—or, eventually, by California Micro Devices, <a href="https://techmonitor.ai/technology/california_micro_devices_completes_acquisition_of_gtes_microcircuits_division" target="_blank">which purchased GTE’s Microcircuits division in September 1987</a> after GTE decided to get out of the business. Apple was also negotiating with NCR as a second source, but according to Mensch and others, the deal fell apart before the IIGS shipped.</p><p>But let’s say for the sake of argument that GTE was able to produce as many 4 MHz chips as Apple or anyone else wanted to buy. Based on the FPI’s clock divider mechanism and a 14.318 MHz source clock, Apple had a logical clock speed target of 3.58 MHz using a 1/4 divider. That’d still be a compromise over Woz’s dream machine, but it’d be faster than what we got. And if (or when) faster processors became available, the FPI clock divider could be adjusted for them.</p><p>Yet those faster processors weren’t materializing; at least, not in any volume. Yields were a factor, yes, but the faster speeds revealed other problems. Trying to learn more about this took me down a rabbit hole of Usenet posts, Applied Engineering documentation, AppleFest event reports, and 6502 development forums. All of them pointed to a common factor: the REP and SEP opcodes. When designing the new 16-bit native mode for the ‘816, Bill Mensch added many new opcodes to enable new features and capabilities for programmers. Two of these new opcodes—<a href="https://undisbeliever.net/snesdev/65816-opcodes.html#sep-set-status-bits" target="_blank">called SEP for Set Status Bits and REP for Reset Status Bits</a>—control flag bits for the processor’s status registers. These are crucial to the dual 8/16 bit nature of the ‘816 and how it can switch between 8 and 16 bit operations on the fly.</p><p>Unfortunately these opcodes proved problematic at higher speeds. <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/og6tWx8NeMw/m/5dspToQ6g4IJ" target="_blank">Multiple posts</a> relay statements from WDC or programming guides that <a href="http://forum.6502.org/viewtopic.php?f=4&amp;t=5196" target="_blank">timing problems with the layout mask</a> prevented these instructions from completing in their allowed cycle times. These problems only got worse as they tried to shrink the mask down to smaller process nodes. I’m loath to take what amounts to second and sometimes even third-hand accounts from newsgroups and forums at face value—they don't call it the Net of a Million Lies for nothing, after all. But I’m willing to believe the overall theory based on other corroborating evidence (like this <a href="http://forum.6502.org/viewtopic.php?p=95998#p95998" target="_blank">WDC data sheet</a> note from 1991). If you look at an Apple IIGS accelerator like the TransWarp GS or the ZipGSX, you’ll notice that they’re not just a CPU and some cache memory. The TransWarp GS has a bunch of support chips and gate array logic, while the ZipGSX has a full-blown ASIC on board.</p><p>The GALs for the TransWarp GS were reverse engineered long ago, and <a href="https://wiki.reactivemicro.com/TransWarp_GS#What_roles_the_GALs_Perform" target="_blank">Reactive Micro lays it out plainly</a>: GAL3 handles opcode detection and speed control. This matches up with posts <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/og6tWx8NeMw/m/5dspToQ6g4IJ" target="_blank">relaying comments from Applied Engineering about stretching clocks</a> to handle problematic REP and SEP opcode timings.</p><p>Analyzing these posts also reveals the temperature of the Apple II community circa 1990. Apple announced a revised IIGS at San Francisco just before AppleFest in September 1989, and the reaction from attendees was muted at best. Unfortunately there was no CPU speed increase, but base memory was increased to 1MB and the new ROM added more toolbox routines and some feature enhancements. There was someone whose reaction was anything but muted, though, and it was one William David Mensch.</p><p><a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/zL2kjN9ponI/m/wFcQDnYlcVoJ" target="_blank">According to multiple accounts of the event</a>, during his keynote address Jean-Louis Gassée said that there would be no speed increase for the revised IIGS because of difficulties securing faster 65816s. Mensch was in attendance and was understandably displeased with this statement. He approached one of the crowd mics and said that he was the designer of the CPU and had in his hand a bag of 12 MHz ‘816s. He proclaimed that if Apple ordered the 12 MHz chips, he would ship them. Jean-Louis reportedly made a comment about wanting a reliable production run, and the two men got into a heated back-and-forth before Gassée left and Mensch was escorted out. No recordings of this keynote exist, or if they do they’re locked away in the Apple Archives at Stanford University.</p><p>The version of the story Mensch recounts <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hHqAQTl0s8A" target="_blank">at his 2021 panel at VCF East</a> largely follows what I’ve read in contemporary reports, except with one difference. He includes an anecdote about how he got Jean-Louis’ Apple coffee cup. He mentions running into Gassée after the keynote, and says that Gassée was very upset and threatened to, quote, “kick [Mensch’s] butt.” No punches were actually thrown, and no butts were actually kicked, and the story peters out without really explaining how Mensch got the coffee cup, but this story shows just how bad Apple and WDC's relationship had become.</p><p>Now, you’re a smart viewer, so I bet you know how chickens and eggs work. A company like Apple doesn’t just buy bags of chips; they buy Frito-Lay’s entire annual output. Mensch could have samples of silicon, but WDC wasn’t the one making the chips in volume; its licensees like GTE were. If the fab (say, GTE/CMD or VLSI) can’t guarantee a production run of, say, 50,000 chips, the order doesn’t happen. The evidence in front of us—the delays during IIx development, the inability to deliver 4MHz parts at volume, and the opcode issues that prevented scaling—would certainly justify skepticism of WDC’s ability to work with a fab to deliver faster chips at volume. There were still possibilities for a faster IIGS, though, and these would play right into an Apple II fan’s belief that Apple held it back.</p><h2>Accelerators, ASIC Incorporated, and Mark Twain</h2><p>But let’s say you weren’t buying tens of thousands of chips like Apple was; maybe you only needed a thousand or two. Were smaller customers being taken care of? <a href="https://www.wap.org/journal/showcase/journal198911.html" target="_blank">Ray Settle of the Washington Apple Pi Journal</a> was also at the fall 1989 AppleFest, where he reported on the confrontation between Mensch and Gassée. Afterwards, he mentioned a visit with an Applied Engineering representative. Settle still hadn’t received his TransWarp GS, and the AE rep pinned the blame on unreliable 7 MHz CPUs. <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/zL2kjN9ponI/m/wFcQDnYlcVoJ" target="_blank">Another attendee report posted on Usenet by Michael Steele</a> featured similar comments. Keep in mind that the TransWarp was first announced in 1988, didn’t ship until the fall of 1989, and struggled with speed and supply restrictions through 1990. This is further supported by <a href="https://archive.org/details/A2_Central_1991-02_February_1991_Vol_7_No_1/mode/2up?q=65816" target="_blank">A2-Central’s accelerator reviews in February 1991</a>, where it’s mentioned that AE resorted to offering 6.25 MHz versions of the accelerator because of supply issues—and <em>reliability</em> issues—with 7 MHz chips. Zip Technologies also took a while to ship their 7MHz ZipGSX accelerator, which finally appeared in October 1990, almost a year after the TransWarp GS.</p><p>But we don’t have to settle for second-hand reports. Enter Applied Engineering employee John Stephen III. <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/rhRHiWlRp28/m/LluioQmvv9kJ" target="_blank">In an October 1989 Usenet post</a>&nbsp; he mentions the problems with getting 7MHz chips, and alludes to the REP/SEP timing issues. But the other interesting thing he mentions is that getting high speed 10 MHz ‘816s to run at their rated speeds required boosting their input voltage well beyond the standard 5 volts. This made the chips run hotter and often resulted in crashes. And I see all you overclockers in the audience nodding your heads.</p><p>Scaling problems aren’t unusual when you move to a smaller process node, and sometime a layout needs fixes—or even a complete redesign. The original mask laid out by Katherine Mensch on the WDC card table had reached its limits. Redoing the mask wouldn’t be easy or cheap, especially when higher speed ‘816s were a smaller piece of the revenue pie. Royalties from the 65C02, 65802, and slower embedded ‘816s were paying the bills. Mensch was also busy working on a 32-bit iteration of the architecture: the 65832. But this proposal never made the jump from datasheet to shipping dock.</p><p>Interestingly, this is where a new player steps in. While researching the yield problems <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple2/c/0OZKowbQQls/m/4JoV91YX8pEJ" target="_blank">I encountered numerous posts on comp.sys.apple2 about an “ASIC 65816.”</a> This tripped me up at first, because there are numerous application-specific integrated circuits that contain an ‘816 core. But no, it turns out that a company <em>named</em> ASIC was creating a new 65816 processor using gate arrays. And they promised that this redesigned ‘816 would reach speeds of 20MHz and beyond.</p><p>Imagine my surprise <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple/c/SVtbqi_gIEc/m/2AqcgWtHaEkJ" target="_blank">when I saw the name Anthony Fadell</a> mentioned in these posts. Could that be the same Anthony Fadell—<em>Tony </em>Fadell—who was in charge of the iPod? Sure enough, I found an excerpt of Tony’s book, <a href="https://www.buildc.com/the-book" target="_blank"><em>Build</em></a><em>,</em> where he talks about designing a 65816 for his startup company, ASIC Incorporated! Now we’re on to something. This gave me enough clues to dig up the <a href="https://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id=mdp.39015025959696&amp;seq=1" target="_blank">November/December 1989 issue of <em>The Michigan Alumnus</em> magazine</a>, where an article tells the tale of the fateful summer of 1989. Fadell was an undergrad student at the University of Michigan, and he spent his summer internship designing nuclear control computers at Ronan Engineering. When he met William Hayes the two hit it off immediately. Fadell was a big Apple II fanboy and yearned for more power. Hayes knew chip design and had connections with other chip designers. The two decided that they would design a better version of the 65816 using a sea-of-gates array. Fadell borrowed $5,000 from his uncle, Hayes leveraged his connections to get cut-rate pricing on supercomputer time, and the two reverse engineered a 65816 design in six weeks. After finding a fab willing to manufacture their design, Fadell was prepared to pitch his prototype to potential patrons.</p><p>The <em>Michigan Alumnus</em> article is coy about who the chip was for, but it mentions Fadell flying to Texas in September 1989 to meet with a manufacturer of Apple IIGS accelerator boards. There he negotiated a purchase order and a two year contract, catapulting him to the role of CPU vendor at the age of twenty. With these clues we can deduce that Fadell’s customer was Applied Engineering. If all had gone according to plan, ASIC's chips should have started production in early 1990, and formed the basis of the next generation of TransWarp accelerators. There’s that word again—<em>should.</em></p><p>Ultimately, no TransWarp GS or ZipGSX accelerators ever shipped with ASIC’s design. The chips did exist—multiple trip reports from 1990 AppleFests mention Fadell demonstrating his CPUs in TransWarp accelerators. And in 2022, Fadell <a href="https://twitter.com/tfadell/status/1524145271797551104" target="_blank">posted a photo on Twitter of an ASIC 65816</a> which he claims would still work today—I’m guessing this is one of the 17 MHz chips used in the AppleFest demos. But posts about ASIC fizzled out after the spring of 1991, which coincides with Fadell graduating from Michigan. The ultimate fate of the chip isn’t really known—did Fadell face legal challenges from WDC? Did Applied Engineering give up on him? Or was it because—<a href="http://wired.com/story/tony-fadell-revenge-on-silicon-valley-from-paris/" target="_blank">as described in an interview with WIRED</a>—he was just too busy roaming the halls of General Magic trying to score a job with former Apple superstars Andy Hertzfeld and Bill Atkinson? My guess is the latter, since General Magic hired him later that year.</p><p>In the same tweet as the photo of the chip, Fadell said that he, quote: “sold some to Apple for a new Apple IIGS revision before they canceled it!” Many IIGS superfans have heard tell of the <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/apple-iigs-rom-04-%E2%80%9Cmark-twain%E2%80%9D.29362/" target="_blank">cancelled final revision of the IIGS code named Mark Twain</a>. Featuring an internal floppy drive, a hard disk, and a redesigned logic board the Mark Twain is what many thought the ROM 03 IIGS should have been. It’s entirely probable that Apple fitted some prototypes with faster CPUs. <a href="https://www.wannop.info/SSII//SSII_Index_files/SSII_PDF_files/Volume%203%20Issue%201.pdf" target="_blank">But when media outlets like InCider/A+ magazine were given a top secret demo</a> a mere month before its cancellation, the clock speed was still the same. And the few Mark Twain prototypes that escaped Apple’s development dungeons were equipped with the usual 4MHz chip. This is where the business side and the technical side butt heads.</p><p>The Mark Twain was under development in late 1990 into 1991 and then mysteriously no longer under development as of June 1991. Rumors of Apple killing the entire Apple II line hung over the product like a dark cloud, and the dev team had hoped to prove they were greatly exaggerated. Despite John Sculley’s statements promising Apple’s full support for the over five million strong installed base, the lack of marketing and technical improvements to the Apple II over the years meant his words rang hollow. Apple had just introduced the Macintosh LC as their low-cost color Mac, and IBM compatible PCs were getting cheaper and more capable. If Apple released the Mark Twain without any CPU speed boosts, it would’ve appealed mostly to the Apple II’s cost-conscious institutional education market. Would existing IIGS owners buy one instead of just getting an accelerator card for a fraction of the price? And how many new users would it bring to the platform? The Mark Twain would’ve been like the Amiga 1200: a decent improvement, but ultimately too little and too late. The March 1991 release of the Apple IIe card for the Mac LC also put another nail in Mark Twain’s coffin, because many users—especially educators—bought a IIGS for backwards compatibility with classic Apple II software. If you’re the number cruncher who had to choose between spinning up a run of 50,000 Mark Twains that cost a lot more to build than 50,000 IIe cards for Mac LCs that are already in production, already in a warehouse, or already sold to customers, which would you pick?</p><p>Now this is where you can rightfully criticize Apple for holding back the Apple IIGS. A Mark Twain with even a 12MHz CPU from ASIC would’ve been a legitimately powerful, well equipped computer for its price. But that would’ve been one last campaign in a war long since lost. Maybe ASIC could have helped, but the good ship Apple was sailing straight into a storm called the beleaguered era. Costs, staff, and projects were starting to spiral out of control, and the Mark Twain would’ve only delayed the inevitable death of the Apple II.</p><h2>Sanyo, Nintendo, and the End of Acceleration</h2><p>Even if Apple didn’t see fit to release a faster IIGS, accelerator cards kept the enthusiast market alive for a few more years. <a href="https://archive.org/details/NAUG-V06N03" target="_blank">Upgrade guides for the TransWarp</a> gave tips on how to install higher-rated ‘816s to get even more speed. This usually required buying samples of higher speed processors from WDC, changing crystals, upgrading the cache, and acquiring new GALs. Once you hot-rodded your card you’d often need to supply more juice over the 5V rail to keep things stable.</p><p>All this hackery was finally put to bed in 1992 when new 65C816s rated at 14 MHz hit the market. <a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple2/c/eoCOwP_-eWs/m/ExeSe7cR6IYJ" target="_blank">These chips took Usenet posters by surprise</a>, especially after the ASIC saga. Fabbed by Sanyo, the 14 MHz models could run cool and stable at 5V and apparently solved the issues with the REP and SEP opcodes. Sanyo achieved this by abandoning the die laid out by Katherine Mensch and creating a new layout from scratch. Why Sanyo chose to invest in this is unclear—<a href="https://groups.google.com/g/comp.sys.apple2/c/yVx5TMBjAGQ/m/32BgXxPXpgkJ" target="_blank">I found a lot of speculation</a> that they wanted to <a href="https://www.historyofinformation.com/detail.php?id=5188" target="_blank">build a PDA based on the ‘816</a>. Sanyo’s a giant manufacturer, so I’m sure they found a use for it. Maybe WDC felt the heat from ASIC, or maybe they saw ARM and 68K pivoting to the embedded market and finally bit the bullet to stay competitive.</p><p>Existing accelerators could be upgraded by changing out their CPU and clock crystal, but by this point the IIGS was but a fraction of the ‘816s out in the wild. Optimistic estimates of the number of IIGSes shipped hover around 1.25 million. The other ‘816 system that most people know—the Super NES—sold 1.3 million units in 1990 just in Japan according to numbers compiled by NeoGAF user Aquamarine, who claims to have gotten them directly from Nintendo's Kyoto offices. The system sold nearly 50 million units worldwide in its lifetime. Mensch is very proud of the SNES using the 65816 and speaks highly of working with Ricoh, the manufacturer of Nintendo’s chips. Seeing as the 5A22 was a custom job by Ricoh, I wonder if they fixed the SEP and REP problem during its design. It wouldn’t be beyond them; <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/reverse-engineering-patent-protection-cautionary-tale-harry-strange/" target="_blank">they did tweak the 6502 to dodge patents</a> when designing the NES’ 2A03. I haven’t seen the SNES assembler community complain about issues with REP and SEP with the basic 3.56 MHz part, but that doesn’t mean problems don’t exist. Same with emulation and FPGA groups, though I’d still defer to experts in that field. </p><p>And like the IIGS, the SNES could take advantage of accelerators thanks to add-on processors in cartridges. The most well known is the SuperFX, but Ricoh also made a faster 65816. Better known as the Super Accelerator-1, the Ricoh 5A123 runs at a 10.74 MHz clock speed—three times faster than a 5A22. You’ll find it in fan-favorites like <em>Super Mario RPG</em> and <em>Kirby Super Star.</em> SA-1 games started shipping in 1995, which is late in the Super NES’ lifecycle. Did Ricoh license the redesigned core from Western Design, or did they make the changes themselves? I’d love to know the answer.</p><h2>ARM, Möbius, and The Road Not Taken</h2><p>Apple discontinued the IIGS in December 1992. Even though the IIe hung on for another year or so, the platform truly died that day. Even in the timeline where WDC had 8MHz chips ready in 1983, and Apple put the GUI on the IIx in 1984, I still think the Apple II as we knew it would’ve died eventually. There’s several limitations that would necessitate an eventual migration to a new architecture.</p><p>The primary roadblock is the Mega II side of the machine. This is supposed to be what makes it an Apple II, but it drags the rest of the machine down with it. Depending on the video system for clock generation and timing was a practical engineering choice that became hard technical debt for almost all 1980s computer architectures, especially with ones that traced their roots to the 1970s. The GS is an excellent example of trying to maintain compatibility while adding capability, but it had an obvious ceiling.</p><p>But something that gets lost in the 65816 versus 68000 arguments is that CPU architectures have qualities beyond raw speed. You might care about power consumption, memory mapping, or ease of acquisition. And all these factors are a balancing act depending on your application. The 68K’s massive flat memory space was a big point in its favor, as well as its native support for user and supervisor separation. These don’t matter as much to someone who’s writing hand-crafted single-tasking assembly language apps, but they very much matter to someone building a multitasking UNIX workstation.</p><p>And that’s not to say that 68K isn’t good for assembly applications. It’s got a great reputation among assembly programmers. But as the world turned to compilers and development environments the 68K architecture was primed for the rising popularity of languages like C. More people were getting into programming, and it’s unrealistic to expect them all to have the potential to become machine language maestros like Rebecca Heineman or Nasir Gebelli. C compilers exist for 6502 and 65816, but it's fair to say that these architectures weren't particularly suited to the intricacies of C.</p><p>Another sticking point for high-speed 65816s is the speed of memory. Assuming you threw the entire Mega II side of the IIGS away and built a new ‘816 computer from scratch, a 14 MHz example would need very fast main memory to operate without a cache. In the early 90s, that kind of memory was barely available. How Woz would have built his 8 MHz IIGS in 1985 while affording a decent amount of memory is a rather inconvenient question.</p><p>Apple wasn’t the only company facing the limitations of their early designs. Commodore and Atari decided to pivot to the 68000, like Apple did with the Macintosh. Tech debt eventually caught up with them too, especially Commodore, but the problems weren’t unsolvable—the Amiga tried to migrate to PowerPC, after all. Even the Macintosh and IBM PCs had eventual reckonings with fundamental planks of their platforms. Another company was facing the same conundrum: Acorn Computers. The similarities to Apple are there: they were dependent on a 6502-based architecture and had a crucial education market with a significant installed base. Acorn did ship a computer with the 65816—the Acorn Communicator—but <a href="https://www.computerhistory.org/collections/catalog/102746190" target="_blank">when Sophie Wilson visited WDC in 1983</a> and saw Mensch and crew laying out the 65816 by hand, it struck her: if this motley crew on a card table could design a CPU, so could Acorn. Thus Wilson and Steve Furber forged their own CPU: the Acorn RISC Machine.</p><p>Though today’s Arm and WDC sell very different CPUs, they do have something in common: they’re fabless semiconductor designers that license their cores and architectures to other companies. Apple is of course Arm’s most famous partner: <a href="https://www.latimes.com/archives/la-xpm-1990-11-28-fi-4993-story.html" target="_blank">they joined Acorn and VLSI to form Advanced RISC Machines in 1990</a> to create the ARM610 CPU to power the Newton. But what you might not know is that Apple’s involvement with ARM originates with a desire to replace the CPU in the Apple II. <a href="https://tompittard.com/media" target="_blank">The little known Möbius project helmed by Paul Gavarini and Tom Pittard in the Advanced Technology Group</a> was an ARM2-based computer that could emulate 6502, 65816, and 68000 code. Gavarini and Pittard started the project in 1986 and were demoing and compiling benchmarks in 1987—right on the heels of Acorn releasing the Archimedes! There’s little information about this on the web, with <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20131208171649/http://www.tompittard.com/page4.html" target="_blank">Tom Pittard’s bio</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20050208095510/http://www.advanced-risc.com/art1stor.htm" target="_blank">Art Sobel’s ARM pages</a> being some of the surviving hints to its existence.</p><p>Based on my knowledge of how ARM2 works, I believe the emulation performance of Möbius is wholly derived from the ARM2’s memory system. ARM’s designers were inspired by the 6502’s efficient memory access and optimized the 8 MHz ARM2 to wring as much performance out of the available memory as possible. <a href="https://media.ccc.de/v/36c3-10703-the_ultimate_acorn_archimedes_talk#t=1635" target="_blank">By using 4 MHz 32-bit-wide fast page memory, pipelining, and special load-store instructions, ARM2 could perform burst transactions at twice the speed of random ones</a>. With a theoretical maximum of 32 MB/s bandwidth in fast page mode, this was eight times the maximum bandwidth of an 8 MHz 68K shackled to 2 MHz DRAM. This strategy would peter out eventually because memory speed couldn’t keep up with CPU speed, but hey—that’s what cache is for!</p><p>I’m not sure if Möbius would have been the Apple II’s savior—Acorn’s Archimedes wasn’t 100% backwards compatible despite including a BBC Basic interpreter and eventually a BBC Micro emulator. But with EcoNet network adapters and expansion podules to connect old Beeb peripherals the Arc could ingratiate itself with Acorn’s existing installed base. Could the Apple II have been reborn with an ARM CPU? Maybe. Nobody mentions how well Möbius integrated the rest of the Apple II architecture like slots or video or sound. And say what you will about Apple’s troubles with Western Design Center; ARM was barely a blip on the radar in 1988. Apple wasn’t going to upturn their cart for an unproven architecture from a competitor. Möbius was a skunkworks project; it could’ve taken years to turn its demo into a shipping product and the 68040 was already on the drawing board in 1988. But it was still worth it: Möbius’ benchmarks convinced Larry Tesler that ARM could save the Newton from the disastrous AT&amp;T Hobbit processor. And hey—without ARM, Apple wouldn’t have the iPod, iPhone, and Apple Silicon today. So it worked out in the end.</p><h2>The End of an Odyssey</h2><p>What a ride, huh? Thanks for making it this far down a fifty-plus minute rabbit hole. I can’t claim that this is the final take on the subject—so many of the players aren’t on the record, but I’m pretty confident in saying that Apple did not artificially limit the IIGS’ clock speed during its development for marketing purposes. Now, I’m not a fool—I know Apple didn’t push the IIGS as hard as it could, and it was very much neglected towards the end of its run. If the REP/SEP flaws hadn’t existed and GTE could’ve shipped stable 4 MHz chips in volume, I’m sure Apple would’ve clocked them as fast as possible in 1986.</p><p>I’ll admit that I initially started this deep dive out of spite. The idea that “Steve Jobs deliberately held the IIGS back, <em>bleh bleh”</em> is everywhere, but it's all just people saying things in an endless game of telephone, with no actual evidence. That’s enough to grind anybody’s gears, but what’s worse are people who I respect uncritically repeating these things in videos and blog posts. It hurts me to see videos with millions of views repeating old Internet urban legends pushed by partisans filtered through Wikipedia articles with bad citations.</p><p>But that spite subsided quickly once I started untangling the messy web of people and circumstances that wrapped around this story. I realized that what I wanted wasn’t to prove anybody wrong. What I wanted was to get people to think about these stories and why they became legends. Of course, you could flip that right back around at me and say “who made <em>you</em> the guardian of love and justice?” And that’s a fair point. But my goal here isn’t to push an agenda, but to get a better of understanding of how things happened and why history went the way that it did. I’ve provided my evidence, and it’s up to you to judge if my argument is compelling enough.</p><p>And even then, one of those people who needed a refresher on computer legends was yours truly. I’ve done my share of repeating things based on bad sources, just because I had a fanboy desire to defend something. Or because I just thought a story was neat and didn’t look too deeply into it. It’s not so much about somebody who’s being wrong on the internet; it was the realization that <em>I</em> could be somebody who’s being wrong on the internet! It was humbling, really. As the years go on I’ve realized that there’s so much out there to learn, even if I thought I already was an expert. A perfect example is that <a href="https://www.pagetable.com/?p=43" target="_blank">Bill Gates BASIC easter egg</a>, where I got tripped up by an oft-repeated legend until I actually dug into it. And as vintage and retro tech enthusiasts, are we not people of science? Are not our minds open to new ideas? We’re into this because we enjoy the history and personal connections, and we should all be excited about digging deep and not just repeating the same old story.</p><p>Even though the IIGS may not have been able to unleash its full potential, it’s still an amazing machine even at its base speed. If you haven’t had the chance to play with one, give it a try. And turn on accelerator mode in your emulator to get a feel for what could have been.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FUTO (162 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.futo.org/</link>
            <guid>41268245</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 17:07:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.futo.org/">https://www.futo.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41268245">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    <p>GrayJay</p>
                    <p>A universal video app for following creators, not platforms</p>
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Does Reasoning Emerge? Probabilities of Causation in Large Language Models (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08210</link>
            <guid>41267746</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 16:19:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08210">https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08210</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41267746">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2408.08210">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2408.08210v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Recent advances in AI have been significantly driven by the capabilities of large language models (LLMs) to solve complex problems in ways that resemble human thinking. However, there is an ongoing debate about the extent to which LLMs are capable of actual reasoning. Central to this debate are two key probabilistic concepts that are essential for connecting causes to their effects: the probability of necessity (PN) and the probability of sufficiency (PS). This paper introduces a framework that is both theoretical and practical, aimed at assessing how effectively LLMs are able to replicate real-world reasoning mechanisms using these probabilistic measures. By viewing LLMs as abstract machines that process information through a natural language interface, we examine the conditions under which it is possible to compute suitable approximations of PN and PS. Our research marks an important step towards gaining a deeper understanding of when LLMs are capable of reasoning, as illustrated by a series of math examples.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Javier Gonzalez [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/450e0580/2408.08210">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Thu, 15 Aug 2024 15:19:11 UTC (8,071 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Discrete Mathematics – An Open Introduction 4ed (By Oscar Levin) (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://discrete.openmathbooks.org/dmoi4.html</link>
            <guid>41267478</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 15:53:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://discrete.openmathbooks.org/dmoi4.html">https://discrete.openmathbooks.org/dmoi4.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41267478">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<div>
<h3>4th Edition Information</h3>
<p>
This page details progress on the 4th edition of the book. The <a href="https://discrete.openmathbooks.org/dmoi3.html">3rd edition</a> remains available.
</p>
</div>
<p>
After many years of development, I am please to announce that the 4th edition of <em>Discrete Mathematics: an Open Introduction</em> is <strong>now available</strong>, here and on <a href="https://runestone.academy/">Runestone Academy</a>.
</p>
<p>
The new edition brings many improvements and a new organization of content. In particular, the book now starts with logic and proofs, then practices those proofs with graph theory. The second half of the book contains material on counting (with a new "application to probability" section) and sequences. Over the last few years, I have found that students have more success with this arrangement. There is also a stronger emphasis on discrte structures, which should make the book more useful for students in computer science, while still focusing on understanding mathematical concepts essential for math majors and future math teachers.
</p>
<p>
There is more interactivity as well. More interactive exercises (which you can give students credit for if you create a course with the book on Runestone Academy; it is completely free for you and your students) and some interactive Sage and Python code to explore some topics.
</p>
<p>
A PDF of the book will be made available by August 15th. There will not be a print edition available until next year, when CRC Press will release it. The online version will remain available and free forever, and the book is still released under a Creative Commons License (but note the new NC-Non Commercial addition to the license).
</p>






































<h3>License</h3>
<p xmlns:cc="http://creativecommons.org/ns#" xmlns:dct="http://purl.org/dc/terms/"><a property="dct:title" rel="cc:attributionURL" href="https://discrete.openmathbooks.org/dmoi4.html">Discrete Mathematics: an Open Introduction, 4th edition</a> by <a rel="cc:attributionURL dct:creator" property="cc:attributionName" href="https://math.oscarlevin.com/">Oscar Levin</a> is licensed under <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/?ref=chooser-v1" target="_blank" rel="license noopener noreferrer">CC BY-NC-SA 4.0<img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/cc.svg?ref=chooser-v1" alt=""><img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/by.svg?ref=chooser-v1" alt=""><img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/nc.svg?ref=chooser-v1" alt=""><img src="https://mirrors.creativecommons.org/presskit/icons/sa.svg?ref=chooser-v1" alt=""></a></p>
<p> You are free to download, use, and print as you wish to, for noncommercial purposes. You can also modify the text as much as you like (create a custom edition for your students, for example), as long as you attribute the parts of the text you use to the author and release your modified version under a compatible license.</p>
<p>If you are interested in using parts of the book combined with another text with a similar but different license (GFDL, for example), please <a href="https://discrete.openmathbooks.org/cdn-cgi/l/email-protection#ed829e8e8c9fc381889b8483ad98838e82c3888998">reach out</a> to get permission to modify the license.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A Texas "moth man" photographed 550 species in his own yard (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.texasmonthly.com/travel/curtis-eckerman-photographer-moth-man/</link>
            <guid>41267045</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 15:04:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/travel/curtis-eckerman-photographer-moth-man/">https://www.texasmonthly.com/travel/curtis-eckerman-photographer-moth-man/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41267045">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>On a steamy June evening, Curtis Eckerman embarks on a mothing expedition in the Bauerle Ranch greenbelt, in far South Austin. Towing a wagon full of supplies, he follows a narrow trail that leads between mesquite trees and into a secluded oak grove suffused with golden late-afternoon light. Eckerman, the chair of the biology department at Austin Community College, parks the wagon and begins to wrap a tree trunk in white cloth. Next he suspends a battery-powered ultraviolet light from a low branch. He’s optimistic we’ll see lots of different moths tonight; it’s been a warm, humid day, conducive to plant growth and, by extension, activity by plant-eating creatures. The oak grove is full of frostweed, persimmon trees, and various grasses, each vital to different moth species. That’s another good sign: a wide variety of plants will draw a variety of moths.</p><p>When he finishes his preparations, it’s about eight o’clock. Moths emerge to eat, mate, and lay eggs once it’s completely dark—and fellow moth-ers will arrive any moment now. Eckerman mops his brow and takes a swig from his water bottle. “Now we just wait.”</p><p>Eckerman is a herpetologist by trade; he says the best job he ever had was catching endangered water snakes in West Texas as an undergraduate research assistant. But he’s always collected insects, and a little over a decade ago, he began photographing them. When he realized he struggled to identify the moths in his pictures simply because there were so many varieties, he dedicated a summer to studying them. These days, he sets a light by his garage door and photographs whatever moths show up, as many as seventy species and thousands of individuals in a single night. He’s now counted 550 species at his own home.&nbsp;</p><p>Eckerman is an ecologist with an interest in biodiversity, as well as in species’ natural histories, behaviors, life cycles, and places in the food chain. Moths are so diverse, he says, that it’s not uncommon to find one that hasn’t been named or described in the scientific literature. No entomologist studies “moths”; out of necessity, they specialize. Travis County has about 1,400 recorded species, the state of Texas more than 4,000. And those are just the ones we know about. Insects are the most diverse group of animals on the planet, and there are likely more undiscovered insect species than known ones—as many as 10 to 20 million species worldwide still left to discover, Rice University biologist Scott Egan told <em>Texas Monthly</em> <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/travel/tiger-beetle-rice-university-houstoniana-discovery-new-species/">earlier this year.</a></p><p>The most common type of moths in the U.S. are&nbsp;noctuids, the smaller, grayish-brown moths that congregate around porch lights—“Your stereotypical moth,” Eckerman says. Showier <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/travel/hummingbird-moth-texas-yards/">hawk moths</a> are active during the day and often confused with hummingbirds. Silk moths, such as the luna moth, enormous and apple green, don’t have functional mouth parts; their one-to-two-week adult lives are powered by whatever fat they’ve stored as caterpillars. Micromoths—a broad descriptor that can include noctuids and moths in other families—have wingspans under twenty millimeters long, but are worth viewing through a magnifying glass or camera to admire their vivid colors and patterns. They’re one of Eckerman’s favorite groups to photograph because of the “hidden-gem effect,” he says. “It’s the idea that you get to see something that somebody normally doesn’t see.&nbsp;.&nbsp;.&nbsp;. You feel like you’re exploring a world that others are not exploring, even though it’s around them all the time.”</p><figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="2400" height="1500" alt="Clockwise from top left: Silk Moth/Polyphemus Moth, Hawk Moth/White-lined Sphinx Moth, Micromoth/Leaf Miner Moth, Southern Emerald, Noctuid/Wedgeling Moth" sizes="(max-width: 2400px) 100vw, 2400px" data-src="https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=fit&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45" data-srcset="https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=188&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=300&amp;wpsize=medium 300w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=640&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large 1024w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=480&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=768&amp;wpsize=medium_large 768w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=960&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=1536&amp;wpsize=1536x1536 1536w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=1280&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=2048&amp;wpsize=2048x2048 2048w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=31&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=50&amp;wpsize=concierge-thumb 50w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=fit&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45 2400w" data-sizes="auto" src="https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-1.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=fit&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45"><figcaption><span>Clockwise from top left: silk moth, hawk moth, micromoth, southern emerald, and wedgling moth. </span><span>Texas Monthly; Moth Photographs by Curtis Eckerman</span></figcaption></figure><p>Much of Eckerman’s moth self-education comes from the participatory science app iNaturalist. Users take pictures of plants, insects, and other animals they spot in their local areas and upload them with comments (“Anyone know what kind of owl this is?”). Fellow iNaturalists compare notes and help one another identify mystery species. The app also suggests possible identifications with an impressive degree of accuracy. Users can note the location where they saw a given plant or animal, creating a dataset that has helped researchers understand the ranges of particular species. Virtual communities form quickly and move into real life as users go mothing, birding, or herping together. &nbsp;</p><p>Eckerman posted his first moth images to iNaturalist ten years ago, and other users coached him on how to take better photos to make identification easier. He started teaching the students in his Structure and Function of Organisms course at ACC to use iNaturalist to log their own observations. Eckerman has tracked his former students’ engagement with the app via their usernames and found that three years after taking his class, 30 percent are still active.</p><p>Too many Texans are disengaged from the natural wonders around them, he argues, but iNaturalist can help them tune in. “The average student today could tell you all sorts of things about the plains of the Serengeti and interactions between zebra and lions, because National Geographic and Discovery and Disney brought it to us in high definition,” Eckerman says. “But they know far less about what’s in their own backyard than the previous generation, because they’re just not interacting with it.” Over the years, he’s stopped talking about faraway exotic animals in his courses; he instead makes lessons relevant by focusing on local fauna students have actually seen: coyotes, gray foxes, grackles, moths.</p><p>To help his students apply their iNaturalist skills in the field, he organizes mothing expeditions to Pease Park, in Central Austin, and Roy G. Guerrero park, in East Austin. At the latter site, the classes have logged about 350 moth species, including an enormous black witch, longer than a chalkboard eraser and sometimes confused for a bat—it’s the largest noctuid in the continental U.S. Roy G. Guerrero is a much larger park than Pease and more buffered from human activity that would interfere with moths. Still, the Pease Park surveys have turned up more than two hundred species—proving, Eckerman says, that urban parks are important not just as sites of human recreation but also for supporting species diversity. In the spring, Eckerman invited the public to go mothing at the park, part of his ongoing effort to educate the general population about biodiversity and conservation. For impromptu events like the June expedition on the greenbelt, he maintains a “moth-lovers email list” and lets word spread on iNaturalist.</p><p>An hour after sunset, the afternoon buzz of cicadas has given way to the rhythmic rattle of <a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/travel/welcome-to-hot-katydid-summer/">katydids</a>. A half dozen moth lovers gather in the oak grove and peer at the moths flittering against Eckerman’s sheet, including the <a href="https://www.inaturalist.org/taxa/224855-Melipotis-indomita" target="_blank">indomitable melipotis</a>, a large brown triangle with a cream-colored V across its wings, and the smaller filbertworm moth, its wings a mottled red with bands of gold.</p><p>Reid Hardin, a biology student at Texas State University, studies the moths before disappearing into the shadows to look for scorpions. Hardin’s into moths—he sometimes sets up a light in his own backyard—but he also scouts out rare plants and various arachnids. iNaturalist has connected him with locals who share his curiosity. Tonight, he and Caleb Helsel, a Westlake High School student who’s into birds, insects, and arachnids, are comparing notes on the pseudoscorpions they’ve turned up at Austin greenbelts. “It’s just always cool to see who else is interested in niche, nerdy stuff,” Hardin says.</p><figure><img decoding="async" width="2400" height="1500" alt="" sizes="(max-width: 2400px) 100vw, 2400px" data-src="https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=fit&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45" data-srcset="https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=188&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=300&amp;wpsize=medium 300w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=640&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large 1024w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=480&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=768&amp;wpsize=medium_large 768w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=960&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=1536&amp;wpsize=1536x1536 1536w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=1280&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=2048&amp;wpsize=2048x2048 2048w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;h=31&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45&amp;w=50&amp;wpsize=concierge-thumb 50w, https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=fit&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45 2400w" data-sizes="auto" src="https://img.texasmonthly.com/2024/08/curtis-eckerman-texas-moths-photos-3.jpg?auto=compress&amp;crop=faces&amp;fit=fit&amp;fm=pjpg&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;q=45"><figcaption><span>Clockwise from top left: filbertworm moth, common buckeye butterfly, eight-spot moth, indomitable melipotis, sculptured moth, and plume moth.</span><span>Texas Monthly; Moth Photographs by Curtis Eckerman</span></figcaption></figure><p>Moths aren’t just pretty to look at; they’re also important pollinators and a major source of food for birds and bats. But moths, like insects overall, are declining in both raw numbers and species diversity. Eckerman says recent studies have shown at least a 30 percent decline in insect abundance around the world over the past few decades. The likely culprits are pesticides and the loss of habitat to urban development. A threat to insects such as moths is a threat to the plants they pollinate and all the creatures above them in the food chain.</p><p>Beyond eschewing pesticides, Texans can create more moth-friendly environments by using a variety of native plants in their yards to offer food. Reducing light pollution helps too; moths are disoriented by artificial light, which can impair reproduction. If moths lay their eggs under the light instead of on a plant that is their food source, the resulting larvae won’t have anything to eat. Turning off lights at night (Eckerman always disassembles his setup at the end of the evening) helps moths find their way to the right plant.</p><p>By 10 p.m., Eckerman’s sheet is littered with diminutive flying insects: micromoths, small beetles, caddis flies, and plant hoppers. He leans in to photograph a tiny moth, using a camera with a macro lens that lets him take clear images at a short distance. To the naked eye, the moth—smaller than a grain of rice—is plain white. But when Eckerman enlarges the image on the viewfinder, he reveals a pattern of buckwheat-colored flecks on cream-hued wings. Eckerman can’t remember its name—he just knows it’s in the <em>Gracillariidae</em> family—but iNaturalist will fill in the details.</p><p>Overall, he says, it’s been a good night for the really small moths, which makes him happy. “Despite there not being all that glamorous moths, this is actually my favorite kind of sheet, with all the tiny things,” he says. “I love seeing the little jewels that you can’t normally see.”</p>
<div data-txmo-ab-name="topics-eoa">
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/category/critters/" data-click-location="EOA Topics List" data-click-action="Topic Click" data-click-label="Critters">Critters</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.texasmonthly.com/location/austin/" data-click-location="EOA Topics List" data-click-action="Topic Click" data-click-label="Austin">Austin</a></li>
</ul>
</div>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Crafting a 13KB Game: The Story of Space Huggers (166 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://frankforce.com/space-huggers-how-i-made-a-game-in-13-kilobytes/</link>
            <guid>41264270</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 08:10:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://frankforce.com/space-huggers-how-i-made-a-game-in-13-kilobytes/">https://frankforce.com/space-huggers-how-i-made-a-game-in-13-kilobytes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41264270">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
						<div>
<figure><img decoding="async" width="151" height="151" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/logo-3.png" alt="JS13KGames Logo"></figure></div>


<p>One of my favorite game jams is the legendary <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Js13kGames" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Js13kGames competition</a>, where participants have one month to make a web browser game that fits in a 13 kilobyte zip file. To put that into perspective, a floppy disk from the before times could hold 1.44 MB, enough to fit over 100 JS13K games!</p>



<p>In 2021 the contest celebrated its 10th annual event. The theme was “Space” and there were an impressive 223 games submitted. It was my third year participating in the contest. That was a few years ago and I am back now to share with you the story of how my entry was made. Better late then never!</p>


<div>
<figure><img decoding="async" width="240" height="160" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot3a.png" alt="Space Huggers logo"></figure></div>


<p>My game, “Space Huggers” is a run and gun roguelike platformer with procedurally generated environments and a pixel art style. I was inspired by games like Broforce, Metal Slug, and Contra. The engine was written from scratch in pure JavaScript and has since been open sourced under the name <a href="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/LittleJS" data-type="URL" data-id="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/LittleJS" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LittleJS.</a> It’s a great little engine with many nice features packed into a tiny footprint with clean well documented code.</p>



<p>In this post I will explain how my game works and the design process I went through while developing it. We will not go into detail about the code here, but <a href="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/SpaceHuggers">it’s all available on GitHub</a> for you to check out. Also, there is now an improved version on Newgrounds with some bonus features like medals, a final boss fight, and even support for mobile devices.</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://js13kgames.com/entries/space-huggers" data-type="URL" data-id="https://js13kgames.com/entries/space-huggers" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Space Huggers – JS13K entry</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/819609" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Space Huggers – Enhanced Version</a></li>
</ul>



<figure><p>
<iframe loading="lazy" title="Run and gun roguelike in only 13 Kilobytes - Space Huggers" width="640" height="360" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6VXrnk18Z4s?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p></figure>



<h2>Making Tiny Games</h2>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="281" height="635" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/screen-1.png" alt="my tiny ski game" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/screen-1.png 281w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/03/screen-1-133x300.png 133w" sizes="(max-width: 281px) 100vw, 281px"></figure></div>


<p>For several years I’ve been studying the strange art of writing tiny programs. Back in 2019, after a long career in mainstream games, I found myself somewhat burnt out from working with giant code bases. I wanted to get back to basics and try something radically different. So on a whim I decided to make <a href="https://frankforce.com/im-only-making-small-game-now/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a tiny ski game in C++</a> and found it to be one of the most fun experiences of my career.</p>



<p>Thirsty for more I stumbled across the <a href="https://js1k.com/">JS1k competition</a> which happened to already be in progress. I knew immediately that I needed to participate, so learned JavaScript on the fly. <a href="https://frankforce.com/i-made-7-demos-in-2-weeks-for-js1k/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">After 2 weeks and a few all-nighters, I submitted 6 demos to the contest.</a> It was clear, I was hooked on writing tiny code!</p>



<p>Over the next the few years I honed my JavaScript skills by making games, tools, art, and other experiments. On a website called Dwitter I released over a thousand tiny programs that push the boundaries of a 140 character limitation. I also released a few longform generative art projects using only vanilla JavaScript. All this was drastically different from what I had been doing for the past 20 years while programming in C++ at major game studios, but it fees like I finally discovered my true calling.</p>



<h2>Enter JS13K</h2>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="160" height="160" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/screen2.png" alt="bounce back logo" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/screen2.png 160w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/09/screen2-150x150.png 150w" sizes="(max-width: 160px) 100vw, 160px"></figure></div>


<p>In subsequent years I’ve entered <a href="https://js13kgames.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">JS13K </a>several times. The first time <a href="https://js13kgames.com/entries/bounce-back" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">I received 2nd place with a Bounce Back</a>, my Link’s Awakening homage, which also has <a href="https://frankforce.com/bounce-back-postmortem/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">a lengthy writeup.</a> The next year <a href="https://js13kgames.com/entries/notecraft" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">NoteCraft</a>, my cellular automata music creator, won both the Audio and Innovation categories. That same year I released <a href="https://killedbyapixel.github.io/OS13k/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">OS13k</a>, a tiny JavaScript operating system that won the Super Special award given by the organizer of the contest. <a href="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/OS13k">I open sourced OS13k on GitHub</a> and have continuing adding apps to it. My most recent entry to JS13k was in 2022 when I submitted <a href="https://js13kgames.com/entries/egg-time-rewind" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Egg Time Rewind.</a></p>



<p>This time I wanted to take things to the next level, by building a new game engine suitable for high quality low size games. There are already some tools of this sort available, like <a href="https://straker.github.io/kontra/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Kontra </a>and <a href="https://github.com/bitnenfer/tiny-canvas" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Tiny-Canvas</a>, but none with extensive feature set I required. So when the contest started on August 13th, my first step was to make the engine before I could begin working on a game.</p>



<h2>Building The Engine</h2>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2b-150x150.png" alt="LittleJS Logo"></figure></div>


<p>This primary goal of this engine is to be as small as possible while delivering the most powerful features. Using what I learned from making Bounce Back, I reworked everything to create even tighter and cleaner code. I eventually released the engine on GitHub as <a href="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/LittleJS">LittleJS</a> with an open source license and still continue to improve it.</p>



<p>At its core, the engine uses an object oriented architecture that’s easy to build games with. For graphics it uses WebGL to render a massive amount of sprites at 60 FPS. The audio system uses <a href="https://killedbyapixel.github.io/ZzFX/">ZzFX </a>to procedurally create stereo sound effects. The input system handles keyboard, mouse, touch, and analog gamepads. I even wrote a small 2D physics system and collision solver.</p>



<p><a href="https://youtu.be/_dXKU0WgAj8?si=fPfn4YgHINchWZVu">I have talked a lot about LittleJS before</a> so we won’t go into details here but it took a long time to get all that working. About half the contest had flown by before I was ready to move on to any real game design or art.</p>



<h2>Game Design</h2>



<p>The run-and-gun genera doesn’t get as much love now as it did when I was growing up. I’m not sure why games like Contra and Metal Slug have declined in popularity. Maybe because first person shooters and metroidvania style games overtook the genre. Still, occasionally there are a few gems that get the formula right. One of my favorites is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Broforce" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Broforce by Free Lives.</a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="600" height="337" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/002798s008.jpg" alt="broforce screenshot" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/002798s008.jpg 600w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/002798s008-300x169.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px"><figcaption>Broforce by Free Lives</figcaption></figure>



<p>The original Broforce came out in 2015 and has since seen many updates and ports to consoles, I highly recommend giving it a go. You may not know that the original Broforce prototype was made in only one weekend for the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludum_Dare">Ludum Dare game jam</a> under the title <a href="https://broforce.fandom.com/wiki/Rambros" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Rambros</a>. To gather research for my game I spent a few hours playing both Broforce and the original demo while taking copious notes.</p>



<p>I would need to distill this concept down to its core in order to pack as much gameplay as possible into the size limit. I decided to use procedurally generated levels to save space and add replay value. Instead of adding a lot of extra content, I focused on creating fun and polished core gameplay. To give myself an extra challenge, I wanted this game to support up to 4 player cooperative play, a first for JS13K!</p>



<h2>Art and Animation</h2>



<p>Because space is so limited, designing the art requires careful thought and planning. With most modern games, the art takes up a significant portion of the storage space. For this game I wanted to mimic the look of classic 16-bit games, so it uses a pixel art style sprite sheet.</p>



<p>Most tiles are 16×16 pixels in size with a few smaller 8×8 tiles. Some of the tiles are gray so color can be applied at run time. Limiting the number of colors also allows the image to be compressed better. The entire sprite sheet is only a 16 color 128×48 image as seen here…</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="538" height="222" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/tiles1.png" alt="tile sheet used by Space Huggers" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/tiles1.png 538w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/tiles1-300x124.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 538px) 100vw, 538px"></figure></div>


<p>When designing the sprites for my game I looked at the sprite sheet for Broforce as a guide to help understand the character art. Broforce actually has a ton of sprites and animation frames, but I was able to distill it down to just two frames of animation for everything! This includes standing, running, jumping, climbing ladders, flipping, rolling, and dying. For some of those actions like rolling the sprite is rotated to animate it without requiring any extra art.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/brospritecompare.png" alt="sprite comparison between Space Huggers and Broforce"><figcaption>Sprite comparison</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>In my sprite sheet the heads are separate from the body. That allows the characters to have procedural animation with the body bobbing up and down during the run cycle.</p>



<p>The player’s eyes are also animated procedurally and will randomly blink to make the character seem more alive. When the player dies the sprite closes its eyes and rolls over sideways. It’s kind of dramatic!</p>



<p>The level art is also created using tiles from the sprite sheet with random coloring applied. This includes both the outside ground and enemy bases interiors. Outlines around the level geometry are added procedurally to make the edges stand out and give a more polished look. By combining all these elements together, it is possible to do a lot with a little!</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="589" height="394" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/image-3-e1723240352650.png" alt="space huggers screenshot showing enemy base structure" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/image-3-e1723240352650.png 589w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/image-3-e1723240352650-300x201.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 589px) 100vw, 589px"></figure>



<h2>Player Design</h2>



<p>For the look of the player character I wanted something alien but humanoid. The colors were chosen to contrast with each other and pop out from the background so the sprite is visible as possible. I always try to make gender neutral player characters so it’s easier for more people to identify with. After experimenting with different concepts I settled on a design only slightly inspired by Greedo from Star Wars. I was surprised how many people called me out on it!</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="400" height="350" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/greedo.png" alt="comparison of player with greedo" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/greedo.png 400w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/greedo-300x263.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 400px) 100vw, 400px"></figure></div>


<p>The game design for the player was informed by retro platformers like Mario, Contra, and some modern indies like Broforce. Something I love is how these games have single hit kills but also abundant extra lives, it makes for really exciting gameplay. Because my game is essentially an action roguelike, I made sure to supply the player with a variety of abilities to get out of any situation they find themselves stuck in.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/WkwuVRP.gif"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="256" height="256" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/WkwuVRP.gif" alt=""></a><figcaption>Squaresville for Sifteo Cubes</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The player has a classic platformer movement package including the ability to break blocks and climb walls by jumping. All of the physics code was written from scratch for this game. I used a similar physics solution to <a href="https://youtu.be/nbZyXP7SCEg?si=wpEQrSUgR6VAoeSk">the system I developed in 2013 for Sifteo Cubes.</a> One of the toughest things to implement was the way ladders are interacted with. After the end of the contest I had to submit an emergency fix because of a glitch allowing the player to pass into collision by jumping into a ladder from the wrong angle!</p>



<p>The player also has a multi functional roll ability that provides a boost of speed and brief window of invulnerability. It has many uses including dodging bullets, double jumping, putting out fires, and knocking out enemies. This roll recharges after only a few seconds with a little flash so the player notices that it’s available again.</p>



<p>The primary weapon is a gun that not only kills most enemies in one hit but also destroys objects and level geometry. It has limited range so players will need to get in close to hit anything. For a little extra fun players also has 3 grenades that denotate with a large explosion destroying, pushing away, and lighting everything on fire. It’s a fun way to soften up a room!</p>



<h2>Enemy Design</h2>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="225" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/08c3af3c6f09112b192408d028bf9649.png" alt="halo game cover"></figure></div>


<p>The enemies all use the same base code as the player, so their AI works more like a bot then a typical videogame enemy. At a high level they send control inputs to the shared character class the same way as the player. This approach allows for interesting and complex combat encounters while reducing how much code is needed.</p>



<p>The pixel art for the enemies was inspired by the Spartans in the Halo series. I thought it would be fun to subvert the concept space marines by making it about aliens fighting to defend their home planets against a military invasion. All of the enemy types use the same sprite but with a different tint and visor color to differentiate them.</p>



<p>There are 5 enemy types, from easiest to most difficult…</p>



<ul>
<li>Recruit (Green) – A bit shorter then normal, hesitant to attack, dies in one hit.</li>



<li>Soldier (Blue) – Average height and ability, takes 2 hits to kill.</li>



<li>Captain (Red) – Can climb walls and jumps more often, takes 3 hits.</li>



<li>Specialist (White) – Jumps and rolls often like ninjas, takes 4 hits.</li>



<li>Demolitions Expert (Purple) – Throws grenades and can’t catch on fire, takes 5 hits!</li>
</ul>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="541" height="211" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/2021-09-18-20_14_38-Space-Huggers2.png" alt="all enemies in space huggers" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/2021-09-18-20_14_38-Space-Huggers2.png 541w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/10/2021-09-18-20_14_38-Space-Huggers2-300x117.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 541px) 100vw, 541px"></figure></div>


<p>There is also a small chance of any enemy type being spawned as heavy weapons variation. These mini boss enemies are larger with double health and shoot in fully automatic mode.</p>



<p>The enemy AI uses a pretty complex state machine since they can do all the same actions as the player. In addition to patrol and search behaviors, they will also engage in some surprisingly varied combat maneuvers. Giving each enemy type a unique theme helped inform me about how to design their AI. I love making enemies that can keep the player on their toes!</p>



<h2>Object Design</h2>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="210" height="300" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Front-Cover-Psi-Ops-The-Mindgate-Conspiracy-UK-PC-210x300.webp" alt="psi-ops cover" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Front-Cover-Psi-Ops-The-Mindgate-Conspiracy-UK-PC-210x300.webp 210w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Front-Cover-Psi-Ops-The-Mindgate-Conspiracy-UK-PC-716x1024.webp 716w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Front-Cover-Psi-Ops-The-Mindgate-Conspiracy-UK-PC-768x1098.webp 768w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/Front-Cover-Psi-Ops-The-Mindgate-Conspiracy-UK-PC.webp 800w" sizes="(max-width: 210px) 100vw, 210px"></figure></div>


<p>One of my favorite things about playing games is causing unexpected chain reactions. This kind of emergent behavior is often facilitated by a fire propagation system, something I’ve implemented in many games before like Psi-Ops which I worked on at Midway Games.</p>



<p>This time I streamlined the design to use only a few objects that combine to create complex behaviors and fun scenarios. Some of these objects are able to catch on fire, and send heat events to nearby objects, eventually catching them on fire. Other objects are able to explode which damages and pushes away nearby objects while also setting more things on fire. There’s even a water barrel that can put out fires!</p>



<p>All of these objects use only 3 sprites: a crate, a barrel, and a rock. By using different tints and additive colors it’s possible to represent many different types of objects…</p>



<ul>
<li>Wooden Crate (Brown) – Burns easily and breaks when fully burnt.</li>



<li>Metal Crate &amp; Barrel (Gray) – Hard to destroy and can’t burn.</li>



<li>Explosive Crate &amp; Barrel (Green) – Burns and explodes after a few seconds.</li>



<li>High Explosive Barrel (Red) – Explodes quicker with a larger radius than normal explosives.</li>



<li>Water Barrel (Blue) – Puts out fires and pushes away objects.</li>



<li>Rock (Grayish) – Heavy and very hard to destroy, can’t burn, and crush enemies.</li>



<li>Lava Rock (Glowing Orange) – Anything it touches is lit on fire!</li>
</ul>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="524" height="285" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/s123.png" alt="all objects in space huggers" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/s123.png 524w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/s123-300x163.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 524px) 100vw, 524px"></figure></div>


<h2>Extra Game Design</h2>



<p>The only other game object that the player interacts with are checkpoint flags that can be activated just by touching them. This system allows players to respawn closer to the action when they die. The flag also has a special function in co-op multiplayer mode because when a player dies, the remaining players need to get to a checkpoint to respawn their buddies.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="568" height="366" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2024-08-08-11_34_08-Window.png" alt="check points in space huggers" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2024-08-08-11_34_08-Window.png 568w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/2024-08-08-11_34_08-Window-300x193.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 568px) 100vw, 568px"></figure></div>


<p>The final thing I squeezed into this game was a radar system that appears along the bottom of the screen. It’s a simple but effective way to show where all the enemies are in relation to the player. I added it after experiencing some frustration while tracking down the last few enemies!</p>



<h2>Level Design</h2>



<p>The levels are procedurally generated so they are different for every playthrough. This can be a great way to cut down on file size for JS13K while also giving players an unlimited amount of content to explore. The real trick is generating levels that are interesting and fun for players.</p>



<p>To give structure to the level design, there are enemy bases composed of different rooms that follow a specific set of rules. This includes both the level geometry as well as placement of enemies and objects. It is probably the most complex part of the game and I was very proud of the result with some super interesting procedurally generated levels. This is definitely something I want to experiment more with in the future.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="640" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_QhwaUX0AI38uL-1024x640.jpg" alt="enemy base" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_QhwaUX0AI38uL-1024x640.jpg 1024w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_QhwaUX0AI38uL-300x188.jpg 300w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_QhwaUX0AI38uL-768x480.jpg 768w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_QhwaUX0AI38uL-1536x960.jpg 1536w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_QhwaUX0AI38uL.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The bases include some special things like partially transparent windows that allow the background to show through and energy doors that can be shot to break them open. To create extra variation the bases are sometimes made to look like caves and underground mines.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="640" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_Qh1E-WQAgml31-1024x640.jpg" alt="large enemy base" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_Qh1E-WQAgml31-1024x640.jpg 1024w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_Qh1E-WQAgml31-300x188.jpg 300w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_Qh1E-WQAgml31-768x480.jpg 768w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_Qh1E-WQAgml31-1536x960.jpg 1536w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/E_Qh1E-WQAgml31.jpg 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The ground around the bases uses a random noise algorithm. A few deep chasms are also created that allow enemies or the player to fall to their doom. Checkpoints are placed across the map at roughly regular intervals.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="576" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/screenshot-2021-09-28T123449.993-1024x576.png" alt="very large enemy base" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/screenshot-2021-09-28T123449.993-1024x576.png 1024w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/screenshot-2021-09-28T123449.993-300x169.png 300w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/screenshot-2021-09-28T123449.993-768x432.png 768w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/screenshot-2021-09-28T123449.993.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<h2>Background Effects</h2>



<p>In the background there’s a layered sky system. The parallax mountainscapes are generated using an algorithm I’ve been working on that creates interesting looking landscapes with just a tiny bit of code. Behind that is a gradient with stars and suns that move in the sky to help emphasize the otherworldly feeling of being on another planet.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="546" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/LittleJS-35-1024x546.png" alt="background sky effect" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/LittleJS-35-1024x546.png 1024w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/LittleJS-35-300x160.png 300w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/LittleJS-35-768x409.png 768w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/LittleJS-35-1536x818.png 1536w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/LittleJS-35.png 1920w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>Some levels even have precipitation effects like rain and snow. This is a great way to demonstrate the particle system and collision physics. More importantly it adds a layer of atmosphere to the game that helps each level feel like a more unique and interesting place.</p>



<h2>Sound Design</h2>



<p>All of the audio is played using <a href="https://killedbyapixel.github.io/ZzFX/">my open source sound effect tool ZzFX.</a> It’s a tiny self contained sound effect player that generates audio samples from a set of 20 parameters. I was happy to see that many other JS13K games <a href="https://x.com/KilledByAPixel/status/1445455434542845963">used ZzFX that year including 5 of the top 10 games!</a></p>



<p>In total Space Huggers uses 11 different sound effects and it took a lot of tweaking to get those sounding right. My favorite sound in the game is the footstep sound used by the player.</p>



<p>To achieve an atmospheric sound when there is wind or rain, a quiet noisy effect plays every few seconds, overlapping itself with some randomness. I was inspired to give this a shot after hearing it done in another great JS13K game, <a href="https://js13kgames.com/entries/the-wandering-wraith">The Wandering Wraith by Mateusz Tomczyk.</a></p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="665" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-4.png" alt="zzfx editor" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-4.png 800w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-4-300x249.png 300w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/screenshot-4-768x638.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"></figure>



<h2>Making a Build System</h2>



<p>This is the first year that I fully automated my build process and it was well worth the effort. Previously there were too many manual steps necessary to build the final zipped project. This was especially a problem towards the end of the jam, when the size gets near the limit and it becomes necessary to build more often to check the final size.</p>



<p>My build system is nothing fancy. I just made a windows bat file, but in the click of a button it does the everything I need…</p>



<ul>
<li>Combines all js files together.</li>



<li>Runs <a href="https://developers.google.com/closure">Google Closure</a>, Uglify, and <a href="https://github.com/lifthrasiir/roadroller" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Roadroller </a>on the code.</li>



<li>Combines the minified code into a single html file.</li>



<li>Zips the html with <a href="https://github.com/fhanau/Efficient-Compression-Tool" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">ECT</a>.</li>
</ul>



<p>For projects of this size I don’t do a lot of hand minification but instead rely on tools like Google Closure so the source code can remain clean and easy to work with. Though I’ve found Closure to be the best first pass minifier, running Terser or Uglify seemed to squeeze out a few more bytes. Overall I’ve been very impressed at how good Closure is at removing dead code while minifying everything else.</p>



<p>That same year <a href="https://twitter.com/senokay">Kang Seonghoon</a> introduced a new tool called Roadroller that was a total game changer. It uses a neural network to pack JavaScript code significantly better into a zip file, enough to fit several more kilobytes of code! At first it doesn’t seem possible, but I can assure you, it works like magic. People started joking that JS13K has now become JS15K. This kind of thing really makes me wonder what else will be possible in future years of the contest.</p>



<p>This was my first time using Efficient Compression Tool (ECT) to zip a project. After experimenting with various other options I found it to be the most efficient at both zipping files and compressing images. You’d be surprised how many extra bytes of cruft are in an average zip! For large files it probably doesn’t matter much but for small files like this it can make a huge difference.</p>



<h2>Areas for Improvement</h2>



<p>After submitting the game I already knew there were some things that could have been done better. In general my game was just very thin on content and lacked an overall sense of progression. There was no end to the game or even a proper beginning. While what I had was very fun, it was also super minimal and felt more like a tech demo then a complete game.</p>



<p>One of the biggest features I would have cut is 4 player cooperative gameplay and probably all gamepad support as well. While multiplayer can be a lot of fun, almost no one actually gave it a try which means all that code was just wasted space.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="651" height="298" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/image-1.png" alt="Space huggers 4 player mode" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/image-1.png 651w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/08/image-1-300x137.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 651px) 100vw, 651px"></figure></div>


<p>I wanted to fit in a variety of weapons and upgrades for the player which would have added a lot of fun and variety to the gameplay. These could also have been used by enemies to create more diverse combat scenarios. I chose to cut this not only for space limitations but also because keeping things simple allowed me to polish everything before the deadline.</p>



<p>Unfortunately I was also not able to fit any music, things were just so tight. This is a huge missed opportunity to inject another layer of immersion and I definitely plan to have some kind of soundtrack in my next JS13K game!</p>



<h2>The Results</h2>



<p>Space Huggers did not win JS13K but it did pretty well, placing 8th out of 223 games in total. It also received 2nd place in fun and gameplay categories!</p>



<p><a href="https://medium.com/js13kgames/js13kgames-2021-winners-top-in-criteria-and-expert-picks-cf4a0544fd45">Additionally Space Huggers was picked by 2 experts as their favorite JS13K game!</a> Thanks so much Lee and Christer. Here’s what they had to say…</p>



<blockquote>
<p>“As someone who’s sunk hours into Broforce and loves retro games, Space Huggers checked all the boxes for me. Procedurally generated levels that I can play in my browser?!? SHUT UP AND TAKE MY MONEY!” – Lee Reilly</p>
</blockquote>



<blockquote>
<p>“It is an impressive game engine AND an extremely fun game! Most things are one or the other.” – Christer Kaitila</p>
</blockquote>



<p>Possibly the most amazing thing of all is that we got a half page writeup in Linux Format magazine! It’s beyond awesome to see my game showing up in print media.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="768" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/linux_magazine-1024x768.jpg" alt="article in linux format magazine" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/linux_magazine-1024x768.jpg 1024w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/linux_magazine-300x225.jpg 300w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/linux_magazine-768x576.jpg 768w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/linux_magazine-1536x1152.jpg 1536w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/linux_magazine-2048x1536.jpg 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure></div>


<h2>Newgrounds Enhanced Edition</h2>



<p>After JS13K I took some time to polish up the game a little more and <a href="https://www.newgrounds.com/portal/view/819609">released it on Newgrounds.</a> I also reworked the length of the game so it can beaten in around 10 minutes. Here are some of the new features I added to this enhanced version…</p>



<ul>
<li>Limited game to 5 levels with the final level being the smallest but most dense.</li>



<li>Final boss that can crash through walls and throws objects at the player.</li>



<li>Intro screen with a music track I composed using FL Studio.</li>



<li>Mobile support with a virtual on screen touch gamepad.</li>



<li>Medals and Scoreboard with the fastest times.</li>



<li>Many other small tweaks and improvements.</li>
</ul>



<p>I am proud to say that the game now has over 100K plays on Newgrounds and maintains a solid 4/5 score with over 600 votes! Also, there are 26 pages of comments from people that have reviewed the game. This feedback was a great way for me to continue improving gameplay while chasing down any remaining bugs.</p>



<p>I want to give a special shoutout to a few amazing players. The first is lewdev who was an early supporter of Space Huggers and is also one of the best players, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nomaLYOo9QA">holding the world record speedrun for a long while.</a> I’d also like to congratulate KyRzYg on Newgrounds for having the current fastest speed run at a lightning fast 7 minutes 29 seconds!</p>



<p>Also a big thank you to <a href="https://wowdotstudios.newgrounds.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">WOWdotStudios</a> for sending me the first piece of fan art I’ve ever received, this super cool high resolution art of the player from Space Huggers. You might also recognize it as my profile image on Newgrounds!</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="485" height="630" src="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/wowdotstudios.jpg" alt="fan art" srcset="https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/wowdotstudios.jpg 485w, https://frankforce.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/wowdotstudios-231x300.jpg 231w" sizes="(max-width: 485px) 100vw, 485px"><figcaption>Space Huggers fan art by WOWdotStudios </figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Wrap Up</h2>



<p>That’s the story of Space Huggers… for now. Thank you for reading! I hope you learned something from my crazy programming adventures. <a href="https://twitter.com/KilledByAPixel" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Follow me on twitter for all the latest updates on my experiments!</a> </p>



<p>The next JS13K competition is just about to begin and if you’re interested you can use the same engine I used to make Space Huggers as a starting point! <a href="https://github.com/KilledByAPixel/LittleJS">That game engine is now called LittleJS</a> and there is special example project for JS13K that builds to a 7KB zip leaving tons of room to pack with your art and gameplay. I can’t wait to see what you make with it!</p>



<p>I’ll leave you with this video from a 4 player co-op game of Space Huggers I played with a few friends and it was a blast. Let me know if you give it a shot at your next game night!</p>



<figure></figure>

											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pixel smartphones delivered with secret but inactive remote maintenance (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.heise.de/en/news/Pixel-smartphones-delivered-with-secret-but-inactive-remote-maintenance-9836887.html</link>
            <guid>41264070</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 07:39:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.heise.de/en/news/Pixel-smartphones-delivered-with-secret-but-inactive-remote-maintenance-9836887.html">https://www.heise.de/en/news/Pixel-smartphones-delivered-with-secret-but-inactive-remote-maintenance-9836887.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41264070">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

        <div>
  <p><em>This article was originally published in
    
      <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Pixel-Smartphones-mit-heimlicher-aber-inaktiver-Fernwartung-ausgeliefert-9836726.html">German</a>
    
    and has been automatically translated.</em>
  </p>
</div>


<p>Millions of Pixel phones have been shipped with remote maintenance software that makes them vulnerable to spyware – but only if the perpetrator has physical access to the device, enters the user's password and knows how to activate the normally invisible and inactive software, according to Google. Under these conditions, an attacker could also install any other software. The remote maintenance software is said to have been installed at Verizon's request since <a href="https://www.heise.de/news/Google-Pixel-und-Pixel-XL-Android-Smartphones-mit-AI-und-der-besten-Kamera-3340555.html?from-en=1">the Pixel phones were launched in 2017</a>. The US mobile operator used the program for a while to demonstrate Pixel phones in its sales outlets.</p>

    
  

  <!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
  
  <a-paternoster height="360" media="(min-width: 320px) and (max-width: 767px)">
    

  
    
    
  

  </a-paternoster>
  <!-- RSPEAK_START -->



<p>Whether Android phones other than Pixel are also affected is still unclear. Active exploitation is not known. The vulnerability was discovered by the "Endpoint Detection and Response" scanner (EDR) <a href="https://iverify.io/blog/iverify-discovers-android-vulnerability-impacting-millions-of-pixel-devices-around-the-world">von iVerify</a> on a customer's cell phone. iVerify, together with the affected customer Palantir and the security company Trail of Bits, was able to trace this back to a hidden Android software package. Even though the software is no longer used, it is still present in the images of Pixel smartphones, <a href="https://x.com/dguido/status/1824120241829355571" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">as Trail of Bits CEO Dan Guido notes on X.</a></p>

<p>In fact, firmware images for the Pixel devices can still be downloaded from Google's official servers, which contain the priv-app directory with the aforementioned Showcase.pkg in product.img, as heise online was able to verify using the <a href="https://dl.google.com/dl/android/aosp/akita-ud2a.231203.054-factory-b3a902d4.zip?hl=de" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Android 14.0 image for the Pixel 8a</a>.</p>

  





<p>According to iVerify, once activated, the application downloads a configuration file via an insecure connection, which can result in system-level code being executed. The configuration file is retrieved from a domain hosted by AWS over unsecured HTTP, which leaves the configuration and the device vulnerable to malicious code, spyware and data wiping.</p>
<h3 id="nav_patch_not_yet__0">Patch not yet available</h3>
<p>The affected package is pre-installed in the firmware of Pixel devices. By default, the application is not active; however, as it is part of the firmware image, millions of phones could be running this app at system level. Users cannot uninstall Showcase.apk themselves. An update that removes the inactive software is in the works, according to Verizon, and will be made available to "all affected OEM manufacturers". This raises the suspicion that phones other than Pixel phones are also equipped with the insecure application.</p>



<p>According to media reports, Showcase.apk comes from Smith Micro, a company that provides software for remote access, parental control and data erasure. "This is neither an Android platform nor a Pixel vulnerability," <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/zakdoffman/2024/08/15/new-pixel-warning-as-pixel-9-pixel-9-pro-pixel-9-pro-fold-release/" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">Google told Forbes</a>. The app was developed for a demo function for stores of the US mobile phone provider Verizon, but is no longer in use. Both physical access to the device and the user's password are required to activate the app.</p>
<p>The function is no longer used by Verizon, nor by consumers, a company spokesperson told Forbes. Neither iVerify nor Verizon have found any evidence of the vulnerability being exploited. As a precautionary measure, the demo function will be removed from all devices.</p>
<p>The discovery of Showcase.apk and similar incidents show the need for greater transparency and discussion around third-party apps that are part of the operating system. Incidentally, the problem is not new - nor is it limited to Pixel smartphones: back in 2016, <a href="https://community.verizon.com/t5/Samsung/Note-5-and-Verizon-Store-Demo-Mode/m-p/992275#1454014" rel="external noopener" target="_blank">a person complained to Verizon</a> that a "Verizon store demo mode app" was on his Samsung Galaxy Note 5.</p>
<p>

<!-- RSPEAK_STOP -->
<span>(<a href="mailto:mack@heise.de" title="Marie-Claire Koch">mack</a>)</span>
<!-- RSPEAK_START -->
</p>

        
        

        
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Aristotle – How to live a good life (223 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/</link>
            <guid>41263951</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 07:20:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/">https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41263951">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><span><span>Publish Date</span><time datetime="2024-02-28T15:34:50+00:00">28. February 2024</time></span><span>9947 Views</span>			</p><div>
				
<p>2400 years ago Aristotle found out how to be <strong>happy</strong>.</p>



<p>His <em>Nicomachean Ethics</em> is an operating manual for a <strong>good life</strong>:</p>



<h2><strong>What is good?</strong></h2>



<p>First of all, what makes a thing a <strong>good</strong> thing?&nbsp;A good thing <strong>fulfils</strong> its <strong>unique function</strong>.</p>



<p>A <strong>good knife</strong> is a knife that is good at <strong>cutting</strong>.</p>


<div>
<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="307" height="173" data-attachment-id="4584" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/01_knife/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/01_Knife.gif" data-orig-size="307,173" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="01_Knife" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/01_Knife-300x169.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/01_Knife.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/01_Knife.gif" alt="Knife"></figure></div>


<p>A <strong>good eye</strong> is an eye that is good at <strong>seeing</strong>.</p>


<div>
<figure><img decoding="async" width="184" height="90" data-attachment-id="4585" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/02_eye/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/02_Eye.gif" data-orig-size="184,90" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="02_Eye" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/02_Eye.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/02_Eye.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/02_Eye.gif" alt="Eye"></figure></div>


<p>Now, what makes a <strong>good human</strong>?&nbsp;To know what a human should be good at, we need to look at <strong>what is unique</strong> about humans: We have a <strong>soul</strong> that <strong>thinks</strong> and <strong>feels</strong>.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="307" height="160" data-attachment-id="4586" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/03_thoughtsfeelings/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/03_ThoughtsFeelings.gif" data-orig-size="307,160" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="03_ThoughtsFeelings" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/03_ThoughtsFeelings-300x156.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/03_ThoughtsFeelings.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/03_ThoughtsFeelings.gif" alt="Thoughts and feelings"></figure></div>


<p>So for us to live a <strong>good life</strong> means to have an <strong>excellent soul</strong>. And this excellence reveals itself in a <strong>clear intellect</strong> and a <strong>noble character</strong>.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="213" height="206" data-attachment-id="4587" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/04_mindcharakter/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/04_MindCharakter.gif" data-orig-size="213,206" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="04_MindCharakter" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/04_MindCharakter.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/04_MindCharakter.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/04_MindCharakter.gif" alt="Clear intellect and noble character"></figure></div>


<p>Let’s have a closer look at both and how we can achieve them:</p>



<h2><strong>1. The virtues of a clear intellect</strong></h2>



<p>Today, we often reduce all our mental abilities to “intelligence”. Aristotle went a bit deeper and identified multiple <strong>theoretical virtues</strong>:</p>



<p><strong>Art</strong> (techne) is the ability to <strong>make things</strong>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="243" height="118" data-attachment-id="4589" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/05_techne-1/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/05_Techne-1.gif" data-orig-size="243,118" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="05_Techne-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/05_Techne-1.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/05_Techne-1.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/05_Techne-1.gif" alt="Art"></figure>



<p><strong>Intelligence</strong> (nous) is&nbsp;<strong>intuitive insight </strong>into underlying truths of our world.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="173" data-attachment-id="4590" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/06_nous/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/06_Nous.gif" data-orig-size="240,173" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="06_Nous" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/06_Nous.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/06_Nous.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/06_Nous.gif" alt="Intelligence"></figure>



<p><strong>Scientific knowledge</strong> (episteme) is our <strong>logical reasoning</strong> about the world.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="240" height="173" data-attachment-id="4591" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/07_episteme/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/07_Episteme.gif" data-orig-size="240,173" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="07_Episteme" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/07_Episteme.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/07_Episteme.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/07_Episteme.gif" alt="Scientific knowledge"></figure>



<p><strong>Prudence</strong> (phronesis) is our ability to make <strong>practical (moral) decisions</strong>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="271" height="157" data-attachment-id="4592" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/08_phronesis/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/08_Phronesis.gif" data-orig-size="271,157" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="08_Phronesis" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/08_Phronesis.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/08_Phronesis.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/08_Phronesis.gif" alt="Prudence"></figure>



<p><strong>Wisdom</strong> (sophia) is a comprehensive <strong>understanding of deeper truths</strong>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="288" height="173" data-attachment-id="4593" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/09_sophia/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/09_Sophia.gif" data-orig-size="288,173" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="09_Sophia" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/09_Sophia.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/09_Sophia.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/09_Sophia.gif" alt="Wisdom"></figure>



<p>These theoretical virtues help us understand what is <strong>true</strong> and <strong>possible</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>And as important as they are, for Aristotle something else is just as vital for a good life: <strong>our character</strong>.</p>



<h2><strong>2. The virtues of a noble character</strong></h2>



<p>A <strong>good character</strong> can <strong>handle emotions</strong> properly.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="120" height="81" data-attachment-id="4594" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/10_emotion/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/10_Emotion.gif" data-orig-size="120,81" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="10_Emotion" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/10_Emotion.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/10_Emotion.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/10_Emotion.gif" alt="Emotions"></figure></div>


<p>We do that by finding the <strong>right mean</strong> between <strong>two extremes</strong>:</p>



<p><strong>Courage</strong> is the right mean between cowardice and recklessness.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="288" height="173" data-attachment-id="4595" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/11_courage/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/11_Courage.gif" data-orig-size="288,173" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="11_Courage" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/11_Courage.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/11_Courage.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/11_Courage.gif" alt="Courage"></figure>



<p><strong>Temperance</strong> is the right mean between gluttony and abstinence.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="288" height="173" data-attachment-id="4596" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/12_temperance/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/12_Temperance.gif" data-orig-size="288,173" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="12_Temperance" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/12_Temperance.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/12_Temperance.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/12_Temperance.gif" alt="Temperance"></figure>



<p>This right mean depends on the <strong>person</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="381" height="157" data-attachment-id="4597" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/13_persons/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/13_Persons.gif" data-orig-size="381,157" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="13_Persons" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/13_Persons-300x124.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/13_Persons.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/13_Persons.gif" alt="Persons"></figure>



<p>An athlete might need more food than an office worker.</p>



<p>It also depends on the <strong>situation</strong>.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="381" height="134" data-attachment-id="4598" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/14_situations/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/14_Situations.gif" data-orig-size="381,134" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="14_Situations" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/14_Situations-300x106.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/14_Situations.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/14_Situations.gif" alt="Situations"></figure>



<p>Sometimes it is better to avoid conflict, at other times it is worth it to stand our ground.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="288" height="144" data-attachment-id="4607" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/15_character-1/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/15_Character-1.gif" data-orig-size="288,144" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="15_Character-1" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/15_Character-1.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/15_Character-1.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/15_Character-1.gif" alt="Character"></figure></div>


<p>We cannot study rules for proper behaviour. Instead,<strong> we must train our character</strong> through <strong>habituation</strong> to find the right mean appropriate to the circumstances.</p>



<h2><strong>Action!</strong></h2>



<p>In a<strong> successful life</strong>, the human soul fulfils its purpose through <strong>virtuous actions</strong>.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Are we born with those virtues?</p>



<p>No. Aristotle says that humans have a <strong>capacity</strong> to be good, but it is up to us to develop our character. This is best achieved through <strong>study</strong> and <strong>habit</strong>.&nbsp;</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="347" height="191" data-attachment-id="4600" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/16_studyhabit/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/16_StudyHabit.gif" data-orig-size="347,191" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="16_StudyHabit" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/16_StudyHabit-300x165.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/16_StudyHabit.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/16_StudyHabit.gif" alt="Study and habit"></figure></div>


<p>Excellence is not something you are, but something you <strong>do</strong>!</p>



<h2><strong>A good life…</strong></h2>



<p>For Aristotle happiness is achieved through a lifetime of <strong>virtuous activity</strong> of the soul, involving both <strong>intellect</strong> and <strong>character</strong>.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="476" height="406" data-attachment-id="4601" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/17_overview/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/17_Overview.gif" data-orig-size="476,406" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="17_Overview" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/17_Overview-300x256.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/17_Overview.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/17_Overview.gif" alt="Good life"></figure></div>


<p>So far so good, you might say—but isn’t happiness about <strong>feeling good</strong>?</p>



<h2><strong>… is a happy life</strong></h2>



<p>Aristotle does not deny that pleasure is fun. Money, fame and food are great and contribute to our happiness!</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="323" height="168" data-attachment-id="4605" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/18_virtue-2/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/18_Virtue-2.gif" data-orig-size="323,168" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="18_Virtue-2" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/18_Virtue-2-300x156.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/18_Virtue-2.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/18_Virtue-2.gif" alt="Virtue and circumstances"></figure></div>


<p>But these things are <strong>not</strong> essential to a good life.&nbsp;</p>



<p>One might even suffer greatly and still live a virtuous—that is: a good—life. When Aristotle speaks of a “happy” life, he means a <strong>fulfilled</strong> or <strong>flourishing</strong> life rather than a pleasurable one.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Such a virtuous life helps us find our place in the world. It is good simply because it suits our nature. Everything we do should ultimately serve the best we can be: a human soul with a clear intellect and a noble character.</p>


<div>
<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="544" height="464" data-attachment-id="4603" data-permalink="https://ralphammer.com/aristotle-how-to-live-a-good-life/19_highestgoal/" data-orig-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/19_HighestGoal.gif" data-orig-size="544,464" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="19_HighestGoal" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/19_HighestGoal-300x256.gif" data-large-file="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/19_HighestGoal.gif" tabindex="0" role="button" src="https://ralphammer.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/02/19_HighestGoal.gif" alt="Highest goal"></figure></div>


<p>Happiness is not a feeling of pleasure. <strong>Happiness is the pursuit of excellence</strong>.</p>



<h2><strong> If you want to dig deeper</strong></h2>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://amzn.to/48xu902">Aristotle, <em>Nicomachean Ethics</em></a></li>
</ul>



<h3>Before you go</h3>



<p>If you enjoyed this article, then <strong>subscribe to my mailing list&nbsp;</strong>to receive more animated stories!</p>





				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PyScript: An open source platform for Python in the browser (231 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pyscript.net/</link>
            <guid>41263843</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 07:01:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pyscript.net/">https://pyscript.net/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41263843">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>

                <!-- begin terminal window -->
                

                <div id="old-terminal">

                            <pre id="typewriter">                            Wouldn't it be cool...
                            to run Python...
                            in your browser?
                            </pre>

                            <p>&lt;html&gt;<span>|</span></p>
                            <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;...<span>|</span></p>
                            <p>&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;script type="py"&gt;<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<span><span>print</span>(<span>'You can!'</span>)</span><br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&lt;/script&gt;<span>|</span></p>
                            <p>&lt;/html&gt;<span>|</span></p>

                            <p><span>|</span></p>

                        </div>
                <!-- end terminal window -->

                

                <!-- begin dialog content -->
                
                <!-- end dialog content -->

                

                <!-- begin readme content -->
                <div>
                    <h2 id="pyscript">Say Hello to PyScript 👋</h2>

                    <p><strong>PyScript</strong> is an <a href="https://github.com/pyscript/pyscript">open source</a> platform for <a href="https://python.org/" target="_blank">Python</a> in the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_browser" target="_blank">browser</a>.</p>

                    <p>PyScript brings together two of the most vibrant technical ecosystems on the
planet. If <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_Wide_Web" target="_blank">the web</a> and Python
had a baby, you'd get PyScript.</p>

                    <p>At the core of PyScript is a <em>philosophy of digital empowerment</em>. The web is
the world's most ubiquitous computing platform, mature and familiar to billions
of people. Python is one of the
<a href="https://spectrum.ieee.org/the-top-programming-languages-2023" target="_blank">world's most popular programming languages</a>.</p>
                    <p>With PyScript, <em>Python runs anywhere there's a
                    browser (<u>which is everywhere</u>)</em>.</p>

                    
                    <ul>
                      <li><strong>Easy</strong>: your apps run in the browser with no complicated installation
                        required.</li>
                      <li><strong>Expressive</strong>: create apps with a powerful, popular and easy to learn
                        language like Python.</li>
                      <li><strong>Scalable</strong>: no need for expensive infrastructure ~ your code runs in
                        your user's browser.</li>
                      <li><strong>Shareable</strong>: applications are just a URL on the web. That's it!</li>
                      <li><strong>Universal</strong>: your code runs anywhere a browser runs... which is
                        <em>everywhere</em>!</li>
                      <li><strong>Secure</strong>: PyScript runs in the world's most battle-tested computing
                        platform, the browser!</li>
                      <li><strong>Powerful</strong>: the best of the web and Python, together at last.</li>
</ul>

                </div>
                <!-- end readme content -->

                

            </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Former Google CEO Eric Schmidt's Leaked Stanford Talk (322 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/ociubotaru/transcripts/blob/main/Stanford_ECON295%E2%A7%B8CS323_I_2024_I_The_Age_of_AI%2C_Eric_Schmidt.txt</link>
            <guid>41263143</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 04:21:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/ociubotaru/transcripts/blob/main/Stanford_ECON295%E2%A7%B8CS323_I_2024_I_The_Age_of_AI%2C_Eric_Schmidt.txt">https://github.com/ociubotaru/transcripts/blob/main/Stanford_ECON295%E2%A7%B8CS323_I_2024_I_The_Age_of_AI%2C_Eric_Schmidt.txt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41263143">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          <nav aria-label="Global">
            <ul>
                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;actions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;actions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/actions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Actions</p><p>
        Automate any workflow
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;packages&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;packages_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/packages">
      
      <div>
        <p>Packages</p><p>
        Host and manage packages
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;security&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;security_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/security">
      
      <div>
        <p>Security</p><p>
        Find and fix vulnerabilities
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;codespaces&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;codespaces_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/codespaces">
      
      <div>
        <p>Codespaces</p><p>
        Instant dev environments
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_copilot&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_copilot_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/copilot">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Copilot</p><p>
        Write better code with AI
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;code_review&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;code_review_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/code-review">
      
      <div>
        <p>Code review</p><p>
        Manage code changes
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;issues&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;issues_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/issues">
      
      <div>
        <p>Issues</p><p>
        Plan and track work
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;discussions&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;product&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;discussions_link_product_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/features/discussions">
      
      <div>
        <p>Discussions</p><p>
        Collaborate outside of code
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>

                  <li>
      
      
</li>

                  <li>
      
      <div>
                <p><span id="resources-explore-heading">Explore</span></p><ul aria-labelledby="resources-explore-heading">
                <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;learning_pathways_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/learn/pathways">
      Learning Pathways

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;white_papers_ebooks_webinars&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;white_papers_ebooks_webinars_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://resources.github.com/">
      White papers, Ebooks, Webinars

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;customer_stories&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;customer_stories_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/customer-stories">
      Customer Stories

    
</a></li>

                <li>
  <a target="_blank" data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;partners&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;resources&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;partners_link_resources_navbar&quot;}" href="https://partner.github.com/">
      Partners

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;github_sponsors_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/sponsors">
      
      <div>
        <p>GitHub Sponsors</p><p>
        Fund open source developers
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;open_source&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;the_readme_project_link_open_source_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/readme">
      
      <div>
        <p>The ReadME Project</p><p>
        GitHub community articles
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
          
      </div>
</li>


                <li>
      
      <div>
            <ul>
                <li>
  <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;enterprise&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;enterprise_platform_link_enterprise_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/enterprise">
      
      <div>
        <p>Enterprise platform</p><p>
        AI-powered developer platform
      </p></div>

    
</a></li>

            </ul>
          </div>
</li>


                <li>
    <a data-analytics-event="{&quot;location&quot;:&quot;navbar&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;pricing&quot;,&quot;context&quot;:&quot;global&quot;,&quot;tag&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;pricing_link_global_navbar&quot;}" href="https://github.com/pricing">Pricing</a>
</li>

            </ul>
          </nav>

        <div>
                


<qbsearch-input data-scope="repo:ociubotaru/transcripts" data-custom-scopes-path="/search/custom_scopes" data-delete-custom-scopes-csrf="m-cBS8mmYxcO1qu7ET5ZLJNwkUhvCPE2dQeVZYy59qVu4CMT3TKgCCq2FgOFoMq24Z64WF1ejTKOLO25FjWNZQ" data-max-custom-scopes="10" data-header-redesign-enabled="false" data-initial-value="" data-blackbird-suggestions-path="/search/suggestions" data-jump-to-suggestions-path="/_graphql/GetSuggestedNavigationDestinations" data-current-repository="ociubotaru/transcripts" data-current-org="" data-current-owner="ociubotaru" data-logged-in="false" data-copilot-chat-enabled="false" data-nl-search-enabled="false" data-retain-scroll-position="true">
  <div data-modal-dialog-overlay="" data-action="click:qbsearch-input#searchInputContainerClicked">
  <modal-dialog data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleClose" data-target="qbsearch-input.searchSuggestionsDialog" role="dialog" id="search-suggestions-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="search-suggestions-dialog-header" data-view-component="true">
      <h2 id="search-suggestions-dialog-header">Search code, repositories, users, issues, pull requests...</h2>
    
</modal-dialog></div>
  
  <div>
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="qbsearch-input.feedbackDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="feedback-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="feedback-dialog-title" aria-describedby="feedback-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="feedback-dialog-title">
        Provide feedback
      </h2>
        
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="feedback-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>

    <custom-scopes data-target="qbsearch-input.customScopesManager">
    
<dialog-helper>
  <dialog data-target="custom-scopes.customScopesModalDialog" data-action="close:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose cancel:qbsearch-input#handleDialogClose" id="custom-scopes-dialog" aria-modal="true" aria-labelledby="custom-scopes-dialog-title" aria-describedby="custom-scopes-dialog-description" data-view-component="true">
    <div data-view-component="true">
    <p>
      <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        Saved searches
      </h2>
        <h2 id="custom-scopes-dialog-description">Use saved searches to filter your results more quickly</h2>
    </p>
    
  </div>
      <scrollable-region data-labelled-by="custom-scopes-dialog-title">
        
      </scrollable-region>
      
</dialog></dialog-helper>
    </custom-scopes>
  </div>
</qbsearch-input>

            

              <p><a href="https://github.com/signup?ref_cta=Sign+up&amp;ref_loc=header+logged+out&amp;ref_page=%2F%3Cuser-name%3E%2F%3Crepo-name%3E%2Fblob%2Fshow&amp;source=header-repo&amp;source_repo=ociubotaru%2Ftranscripts" data-hydro-click="{&quot;event_type&quot;:&quot;authentication.click&quot;,&quot;payload&quot;:{&quot;location_in_page&quot;:&quot;site header menu&quot;,&quot;repository_id&quot;:null,&quot;auth_type&quot;:&quot;SIGN_UP&quot;,&quot;originating_url&quot;:&quot;https://github.com/ociubotaru/transcripts/blob/main/Stanford_ECON295%E2%A7%B8CS323_I_2024_I_The_Age_of_AI%2C_Eric_Schmidt.txt&quot;,&quot;user_id&quot;:null}}" data-hydro-click-hmac="1bf00d5193bb7a1f77e707a67a7be2224c17599bf8596cfea6fe6ecc85bca499" data-analytics-event="{&quot;category&quot;:&quot;Sign up&quot;,&quot;action&quot;:&quot;click to sign up for account&quot;,&quot;label&quot;:&quot;ref_page:/<user-name>/<repo-name>/blob/show;ref_cta:Sign up;ref_loc:header logged out&quot;}">
                Sign up
              </a>
          
        </p></div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>