<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 12:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why your brain is 3 milion more times efficient than GPT-4 (104 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://grski.pl/vdb</link>
            <guid>40765800</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 08:50:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://grski.pl/vdb">https://grski.pl/vdb</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40765800">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>Recently I had to go on journey into the Vector Database world and pick one for a particular project. And oh boy, was it a ride. Recently Vector Databases have gained a newfound attraction and spotlight thanks to the rise of LLMs. Such situation is both a blessing and a little bit of a curse, bringing some of the things attributed to LLMs to Vector Databases too - the perception they are 'a new thing', untested technology or some shiny crap good only for LLM-based stuff. All of which is wrong.</p>
<p>Vector Databases have been with us for waaay longer than most know. There's legit engineering, science and rigorous testing behind most of them over the span of multiple years. And there's a lot of them, they all have their own quirks, just a little bit like RDBMSes do, except the situation there is quite clear, at least for me, in most cases postgres FTW, I mean it's not 2005 anymore, we won't go with mysql or LAMP stack, right? Do most of you even remember what it is or am I exaggerating things?</p>
<p>In case of Vector Databases I was, and still am, actually, completely green. So I had to go around, gather facts, check stuff out and form my opinion regarding each particular database, as to select one for my particular use case.</p>
<p>Before we begin, let me put a disclaimer here. I do not title myself as an expert in AI. There are all my just personal ramblings, opinions, certainly biased. Take everything you read with a grain of salt and do your own due dilligence.</p>
<h2>Introduction to Vectors, Similarity and our amazing brains</h2>
<p>Before we actually begin I think we should dig a bit deeper into what exactly we are playing around. If you are not interested in understanding how this all works in detail and how it relates to generative AI, feel free to skip this part and go over to the next section.</p>
<p>First we must lay down certain axioms (smart word for the common sense/ground rules we all agree upon and accept as true). </p>
<p>One of such would be the fact that currently computers do not really understand words. They operate in what is called binary language, so a string of 0s and 1s. It's related to how electric charge, electrons and atoms work. Physics stuff. Very basics of CS and electronics.</p>
<p>So:</p>
<ol>
<li>Computers do not understand words, they operate on binary language, which is just 1s and 0s, so numbers. Computers only understand numbers.</li>
</ol>
<p>Knowing that, it becomes obvious, that we may face some problems. First of all if it's all just 1 or 0, how do we express different numbers? Well, that part is easy, because thanks to the decimal counting system. Long story short, we have 10 digits to express stuff, in binary you have 2. That means that you still can represent other numbers with base 2, the resulting number will be just a bit longer and calculated differently. I won't to into too much of a detail here, you can look it up yourself -&gt; binary system, decimal system and how to convert from one to another. Or ask chatgpt for an explanation. It does a fine job. Just know that any natural number can be easily converted from base ten to binary e.g. "4" in decimal i s "100" in binary. They hold equivalent value, but are expressed differently. The case is a bit more complicated for floating point numbers, but let's not get into that now.</p>
<p>So first layer of abstraction is down. We have computers. Electric. Electrons. High current/low current, current/no current. 1s and 0s. </p>
<p>These 1s and 0s of ours now can magically become numbers. This is what our computers operate on - in every case. When you dig deep enough, everything you interact with in the virtual world is in fact a number, so a particular configuration of these tiny little something's in the computer that either have electricity running through them, or they don't and that is interpreted as a number. Imagine 3 light bulbs. 1st is on, 2nd and 3rd are off. 1-0-0. We magically agreed that this means 4. Now make the size smaller probably by a thousand, a milion times or something, and you get an idea what's going on in that shiny macbook of yours. Back to the topic.</p>
<p>Numbers. Yes, we have then and are able to somehow interpret the current state of your computer, or it's part as it being a particular number.</p>
<p>Now that's not very useful, right? We, humans, mostly operate on text and language, right? Yup. Imagine a world where you have to decode numbers. in some magic dictionary to a word. The computers wouldn't be so useful now, would they? But that's how it looks in the background. Long time ago some smart dudes have gathered around that agreed that from now on, if we know we are dealing with text, we should interpret the number 65 as "A", "B" as 66 and so on. Of course, it changed, different people had different standards and agreements but who cares, let's simplify. We come to understand the second axiom:</p>
<ol>
<li>We, as socity, have assigned certain roles/meaning to particular numbers, in this case it's letters.</li>
</ol>
<p>Now that we have our computer, that understands numbers, and we know which numbers in which case are which letters, we kinda can start forming words for example. And if you have words you can have sentences, code, whatnot. That's more useful. All of your software builds on top of this base truth.</p>
<p>Now that we know that all words in fact, are nothing but numbers for your computer, we can go further than that.</p>
<p>For the computer, a given word, regardless of the context, based on the above, holds the same 'meaning' or 'value'. So even though you can say 'dust the furniture' as in clean or 'dust on the furniture' as in there's a mess, the representation (and the meaning) for the computer would stay the same, even though there's a mess and clean are two totally different things. So, even though we can convert a word for a distinctive number for the computer so it 'knows' kind of, what's up, there's missing 'context' to judge the meaning.</p>
<ol>
<li>Words simply represented as binary numbers lack context.</li>
</ol>
<p>Well, humans can be ingenious in the ways they do wicked things, but also in the ways the do great things. One such example here would be Contextualized word embeddings. What does that stand for? Well, let me tell you. </p>
<p>So we have this now simple case of turning a series of 1s and 0s into numbers, numbers into letters and then words. That you already understood, right? We kinda explained the problem with that - lack of context. Well. We have developed methods that allow us to generate different and unique numbers for words, depending on their context or semantic meaning. So if we used Contextualized Word Embeddings in our example above, the 'dust' from 'dust the furniture' would get totally different number than the word dust in 'dust on the floor'. Now the computer knows that these two have different meaning! How does that exactly work? It's a piece of work, let me tell you, but we won't cover that in this text. First of all I'd have to understand that myself haha. </p>
<p>Long story short, we have a magic function that does this:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>number_representation_of_a_word_and_meaning</span><span>(</span><span>"dust"</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>=</span><span>"dust on the floor"</span><span>)</span> <span>==</span> <span>42</span>
<span>number_representation_of_a_word_and_meaning</span><span>(</span><span>"dust"</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>=</span><span>"dust the floor"</span><span>)</span> <span>==</span> <span>24</span>
</code></pre></div>
<p>The values are not random - words that within certain context have different meaning probably will have very different number assigned to them. A number that is far apart from the other one. If the meanings were similar, but just slightly different depending on the context, we'd have numbers that are closer to each other.</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span>number_representation_of_a_word_and_meaning</span><span>(</span><span>"bark"</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>=</span><span>"bark is a noun"</span><span>)</span> <span>==</span> <span>12</span>
<span>number_representation_of_a_word_and_meaning</span><span>(</span><span>"bark"</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>=</span><span>"bark is a verb"</span><span>)</span> <span>==</span> <span>19</span>
</code></pre></div>
<p>Why is that? "Bark" and "bark" both relate to something that is assosciated with outer protection or covering. If a dog barks usually it is a sign of danger, something related to safety, protection. The tree has a bark in order to protect itself from the environment. It's different, still, but this time we share a certain common theme at least in some sense, hence the numbers we got are closer together than in the previous case, because they are more similar.</p>
<p>Also</p>
<ol>
<li>Similar meaning of words, in a particular context, converted to numbers, are closer to each other than radically different meanings.</li>
</ol>
<p>By the way, what are embeddings you might wonder? Why did I not describe it earlier? Because we need to understand the above to understand embeddings. More or less it's what we described, so the way of representing a number based on particular set of criteria (in our case the semantic meaning) as similar numbers, even if they are not similar raw value wise. So in the embeddings world, 'dust' would be, as a number, closer to 'clean' than 'dust' would be to 'dirt'. At least that's how I understand it. And 'dust' as in 'dust the floor' would be far away from both 'dust on the floor' or 'dirt'.</p>
<p>Alright, this one was a bit trickier, but we got there eventually. </p>
<p>Again, let me reiterate. We have electrons and then electricity. Because of electricity (or to be more exact high/low current) we have 1s and 0s, so binary language. Next are numbers, binary numbers, so just numbers but expressed only with 1s and 0s, base 2. That gets converted to base 10, so the decimal system that we humans mostly use (not everywhere and not always lol). These numbers then get simply mapped to words with the same values regardless of the context, of the meaning, in the base case.</p>
<p>But nowadays, we iterated over that and can assosciate words with their meaning and assign different numbers, based on the context of the text or a sentence (sentence transformers sounds familiar?) and their semantic meaning. The groundbreaking publication about Transformer model. Go look it up. By the way look at the year it was published and how quickly we went from theoreticall stuff to something as amazing as GPT-4. INSANE. Either way. Semantic meaning, embeddings and transformer model. This is the reason that the LLMs or generative AI can sound so convincing, as if it really knew the stuff it generated. Nope, it doesn't. It just processes numbers, they do not intrinsically understand the meaning, they understand that 1 is closer to 2 than 24 is to 42, which is the answer to everything. See what I did there? This does not imply it 'understands' the meaning in the human sense and why I'm quite sure that AGI (Artificial General Intelligence), so something that 'really' thinks in the most human way, is so far away. The current technology and models, simply do not work like we assume them to.</p>
<p>Okay champ. We have these words mapped to different numbers, which are either closer or further away, depending on the semantic meaning in a particular context. What now?</p>
<p>Well, math magic comes in. I ain't no maths guy, I do enjoy the thought exercises or elementary and truthfully representation of stuff it can provide, nowadays I'd struggle to solve quadratic equation probably, being just a simple highschool dropout, but let me share with you my understanding of this absolutely marevelous phenomenon that happens.</p>
<p>So, numbers. In maths we have this thing called Algebra. It's a study of relationships between things that vary over time, which are represented by symbols, usually letters, which also can represent things, usually numbers. What? ... Yeah. That would be my reaction to this statement too, at least was in the past. Let's make it a bit more digestible. To put it in simple terms, for us numbers are things that allow us to measure reality, count things, they are building blocks of reality you could say. Almost everything (or as some would argue - everything), given a proper formula, could be represented as a number. Be it something so physical as the length of your arm, number of apples in your kitchen or something as abstract as human language or even the meaning of a word, which we have demonstrated above. That however relates to this particular branch of mathemathics and 'real' stuff. In here numbers are immanent, simple, natural, the best. What about branches of maths that operate on a bit different set of rules and so on? Different universes of sorts? Well, in there numbers might not be the best base unit of operation, in different universes we might need either different base building blocks or we might want to take numbers and extend them a bit, if you will, to make life easier. </p>
<p>One such example is the study of Linear Algebra. Linear Algebra has 'vectors' (which in fact are numbers with certain additional stuff to abstract ideas and make life easier) the same way basic Algebra has numbers/symbols/variables. I won't go into the details here too much as my understanding is also not so perfect, and probably I'd spout some gibberish, but I hope you get the analogy.</p>
<p>So in Linear Algebra we have vector spaces, which deal with vectors, that have something to do with 'space' in general. Space might sound familiar because we talked about it. Remember the 'distance' between the numbers which were representations of meaning of a given word in a particular context? Yep, the same stuff let's say. </p>
<p>Space can have many 'dimensions', similarly with vectors. If you have one dimension, it's just [1]. If we have two, e.g. X &amp; Y axis, we can position a point in place by having, well, two numbers for each dimension, eg [1,1], this should ring a bell if you remember anything from your middleschool math class.
What if we have 3D space? Well, similar stuff. Notice how each additional dimension multiplies the number of all the possible vectors. So let's assume we are working on a limited range of natural numbers, 10. In 1D case, we have 10 options. In 2D space we have 10 possibilities for first one, 10 for the second one, which totals to 10 * 10 = 100 possible different combinations. In case of 3d? You get the idea.</p>
<p>So now imagine how insanely big the possibilities are, if we are working with a bit of a broader range (e.g. 65536 or 256) and not with 3 dimensions, but with 1536! That's INSANE. Absolutely insane, but also what allows our LLMs to seemingly perceive so many nuances in the meanings of the words and what nots. </p>
<p>I know it was a long digression, but bear with me. Again. We have electrons and then electricity. Yeah, I'll spare you that repetition again. Number representation of a word based on semantic meaning. So we have a number per meaning in a given context let's say. This number gets then turned into a vector which lives inside vector space. To accomodate for the many meanings and contexts and how contextual our actions, words and speech are, this vector space should have appropriate number of dimensions. It can't have too much as it'd get too huge to process. OpenAI settled for 1536 dimensions. Remember each 'dimension' can be assigned a different 'value', so the total number of possible meanings is THE_MAX_NUMBER_WE_OPERATE_ON to the power of 1536. THAT"S A LOT. Anyhow.</p>
<p>We went from having 1s and 0s, to our words being evaluated in 1536 dimensions or 'meanings'. The more true to a particular meaning is that word, the higher the value it'll get in that dimension.</p>
<p>As you can see we have a problem now. How do we actually process such a humongous amount of data? Traditional methods don't really work well or would be too expensive computationally or economically. This is what we call "curse of dimensionality". To deal with this stuff like Approximate Nearest Neighbour Search problem show up. Meaning: how do we find similar vectors (numbers) in very high dimensional spaces? </p>
<p>To resolve that puzzle we came up with Hierarchical Navigable Small World or HNSW. What is that? Long story short, even though the space is so HUGE, usually, in large networks, eg. human ones or social ones, despite the size, most nodes can be reached from any place in the network with surprisingly few steps. It's often reffered to as "six phones rule", that states that you are at maximum six phone call aways from anyone in the world. You know someone who knows someone and so on, then boom. Your message gets delivered to Obama. It's quite interesting actually. Important to note is that not all nodes in the network are connected equally. There are these things called as hyperconnectors, which connect to A LOT of nodes, and the contrary so, the nodes that are a bit lonely. I think you get the idea and seen an example in your life - almost everybody knows that someone who seems to know everybody everywhere. Either way, as I digress. If we take this Small World thing and add one more thing on top of it - hierarchy, managing even such a huge amount of data becomes doable. What does it look like? Simple. Think in terms of enterprise org chart. It's as if, let's say, you were a CEO and wanted to know something about if your company does use type hinting in python like human beings do. In HNSW the approach would be to first select a candidate, who might know something (be similar to the topic/value you search for) from a very few selected people in the company (mby the hyperconnectors should be at the top? ;)). Let's say the are Lead/Director level people. So you e.g. have Director of PeopleOPs, Director of Product, Director of Engineering and so on. Out of these, the semantic value of Director of Engineering will be most similar to "do we use type hinting in python". So we go to him and there we repeat the process. However our guys here are lazy for whatever reason. he doesn't want to check or write the answer, so he delegates. -&gt; who does the director know, who in the hierarchy is the level below him (these are the guys he knows best, he doesn't know the ones lower too well as he doesn't interact with them often) that should know the answer? So he repeats the process: Engineering Manager in Frontend team, EM in DevOps, EM in Backend team. Backend Team it is.</p>
<p>Now this process gets repeted till we hit the bottom most layer of hierarchy, how many there are is up to the organisation to decide.</p>
<p>This way instead of the CEO asking maximum number of N people in the worst case, assuming that only the last person knew, the question gets asked only N maximum number of times, where N is the number of layers in the hierarchy we have. Or something like that.</p>
<p>Of course if he asked the question to everyone he would have better data and could select the best answer. The one he will get in the case of using HNSW will be good enough (how good we want will require us to define a certain metric, but the more accurate the answer needs to be, the tricker it is computationally) but will cost SIGNIFICANTLY less to get. Think sth like rolling out a feature that covers 80% of the needs in 2 weeks vs perfecting it to 99.99% in 2 years. 80% (or 50 or 95) is usually good enough when you weight the pros and cons, cost/benefit.</p>
<p>WOAH. Long story long, this is what enables us to process such huge amounts of data taht is so high in dimensionality, that can accomodate the various context, nuances and meanings that is assosciated with for example human speech or thinking process.</p>
<p>Now imagine our brains do this at a higher and more profund level than this, they do it constantly, all the time, they fit into something small like our skull and run on the equivalent of 24 Watts of power per hour. In comparison GPT-4 hardware requires SWATHES of data-centre space and an estimated 7.5 MW per hour. So around <strong>312 500x</strong> less while doing stuff that is thousand times more sophisticated. WHAT THE FLYING FK. We are a wonder of Nature. An amazing, fu**ing mess of a wonder but a wonder nonetheless. Also, keep in mind that our brains don't dedicate 100% of the horsepower to conscious thinking processes. According to Auburn Unviersity paper I found, cognitive neuroscientists believe that only 5% of our cognitive activity is conscious. So multiply this number by anything from 20 to a 100. Let's be conservative and say 10 for some reason. That's still over 3 million times the efficiency than GPT-4, while also having at least a magnitude (or at least N) greater complexity. I got carried away in the amazement. </p>
<p>TLDR:
Electrons -&gt; Electricity -&gt; Binary -&gt; Binary Numbers -&gt; "Human" or base 10 numbers -&gt; Letters -&gt; Words -&gt; Embeddings -&gt; (Semantically) Contextual Word Embeddings -&gt; Vectors -&gt; Vector Spaces -&gt; High Dimension Vector Spaces -&gt; Approximate Nearest Neighbour Search or just Nearest Neighbour Search (ANNS/NNS) -&gt; Hierarchical Navigable Small World (HNSW)</p>
<p>Soak up all these terms and write them down.</p>
<p>From here we are almost done. If you've been following closely you might start to piece the puzzles together.</p>
<p>LLMs are in fact just algorithms, very complex ones, that have indexed or ingested A LOT of data/words, vectorized and embedded them and their meanings in particular context. Then, based on that data, they just 'guess', based on context, that if we have this particular thing or meaning in a semantic context, so embeddings, so nubmers or vectors in high dimensional space, just right here, we probably have in mind this particular response which is nothing but a set of other embeddings. </p>
<p>Also usually when we speak about embeddings, we deal with tokens, which usually are not whole words but like ~4 characters in English. </p>
<p>So if based on the context and approximation, we know that this particular query seems like something that will be assosciated with this particular token, we will use it. Then if we have one token ahead, we can repeat the process till we start hitting lower levels of assosciation, which in turn means that we can probably stop generating as the answer is complete.</p>
<p>So... Yup. There's no thinking happening. Just assosciating numbers and guessing. You read that right. GPT-4 does not 'think' at all. It's as far away from human consciousness as we are from Putin being a good guy. This simply does not come even close. So it's the reason I do not worry at night (at least yet) AGI will come and replace me or go on a consciouss crusade against humanity.</p>
<p>Bear in mind, my understanding of the stuff is VERY limited, I'm all new to this. I've simplified A LOT not only for the reader, but also for myself. If any of this is unjustly inaccurate, let me know. I've googled most of the stuff along the way. </p>
<p>WHOAH. DAMN THAT WAS LONG. </p>
<p>Let's answer the initial question then. How do vector databases work then? Well, they take the text. Vectorize it. Embedd in high-dimension space, then if you query it, they search for approximate similar tokens/pieces/texts. Simple, right?</p>
<p>Now with that over, let's get to the stuff I had in mind when starting the article, so comparison of vector databases and a raport from using some of the more popular ones.</p>
<h2>Starting point - chromaDB</h2>
<p>My starting point was <a href="https://www.trychroma.com/">chromaDB</a>. It allowed me get up &amp; running quickly and seamlessly. It was dead simple and it got the job done. However it wasn't the best approach TBH. For a PoC? Yup, it did get the job done. But for more serious, potentially production-grade stuff? Not given how I implemented it. </p>
<p>Long story short, for a PoC, I created this Q&amp;A over a scraped knowledge centre app let's say. I needed a VectorDB deseprately. Pinecone was off-record for obious reasons that I'll list later on in the article, even though it was the easiest to implement I'd say. There was stuff like FAISS and what not, but the choice, over initial exploration, fell on chromaDB. </p>
<p>I used a very dirty approach, where I packaged it together in one container with the API backend part of the application. ChromaDB persisted the vectors in their internal format in a certain directory in my project's repo. I simply commited it to the repo. Not the best, I know. </p>
<p>Now, the whole VDB (Vector Database) was a part of our repo. I locally ingested the data that I needed in the VDB, then commited the state of the VDB to the repo.</p>
<p>chromadb got added as a project dependency (installing it is quite trivial - it's just a python package) to pyproject.toml and boom. Initialise it somewhere in the code during application startup and boom, you done. Again, this is very dirty approach. </p>
<p>API is packaged in the same container as the DB. In this setup changes in the VDB are not really persisted unless you commit them to the repo - only the commited state matters (so read-only apps or go home champ). They share resources. If one fails, the other does too. It was somehow scalable given that we had read-only app, so it was self-contained but... </p>
<p>The git repo got big, fast. The docker image build time got very long for my standards. I mean imagine 25-30m build time for a simple fastAPI app. Not exactly desirable. This came from the fact that the chromadb was inside the container and had to be rebuilt each time the code changed, and as you can imagine, rebuilding db package can be quite time consuming (looking at you, psycopg).</p>
<p>We couldn't go on for long with this approach. Ofc you can run chromadb as a separate container, self-hosted, but that added overhead I didn't need at that time for a PoC. At that time, from what I remember, there was also no option to do proper clustering that'd allow you to get prod-level scalability, survavibality and so on. TLDR: you could run with a single instance and that's it. I also didn't see helm/k8s OOB support that'd make it easy to deploy in a cluster somewhere. On top of that other projects were in the pipeline, then what? Each of them should have their own instance? How would we share data? All of this meant, it had to go away.</p>
<p>But it allowed me to get off the ground, integrate fast, LEARN a lot and so on. For this purpose it did an AMAZING job.</p>
<p>Also, what needs to be said is <strong>that some of the features mentioned weren't supported at the time</strong> I was creating the project, which was <strong>couple of months ago</strong>. Since then <strong>Chroma has closed $18M seed round,</strong> developed a solid roadmap and started addressing some of what was mentioned here. We had a nice talk with Jeff Huber, chromadb's Founder, about all of this. I really loved a lot how he was humble and helpful enough to admit, that <strong>given the preconditions for the project &amp; productionisation</strong>, chroma <strong>at that time</strong> wasn't exactly the best choice, and choosing something else for our needs was a smart move! He is a <strong>very intelligent, passionate and brilliant guy,</strong> so I'm more than eager to see how they develop, <strong>however till we see the features shipped</strong>, in the use cases we had in mind, it was a no-go. However to get started, have one-self-contained app with db inside and be done in 4h instead of 4 days (I know i exaggurate)? Sure, why not. If I was to make a comparison to something people are more familiar with,RDMBSes, I'd say the current chroma is like sqlite. Easier to comprehend now where it can shine and where it won't? Great. Also remember, my approach was simple. If you do it properly, set up all the proper stuff, configure it nicely, adhere to best practices, you probably won't run into any problems. I did not do that, lack of time &amp; expertise.</p>
<p>A short edit here needed to happen. I've reviewed this together with Jeff (THANKS) and he shed light on how most of these issues got addresed in v0.4. </p>
<p>They made an architectural shift in their design, changed the storage engine, the build is now at least 20x faster (which now makes my point invalid), requires way less memory (that was not an issue though, but is good to see) and is far more performand and durable (even in April I did not run into any issues with durability). Overall, as I've predicted before actually getting the message from Jeff, it's been a short time, yet they've made amazing progress. This made me reshuffle the recomendations part a bit and this + the coming changes, make chroma a strong candidate to evaluate. I still need to play around with it more to see the exact progress but seems promising.</p>
<p>So now, most of the stuff that I mentioned in this section, that were relevant at the time of making the choice - April, are not a concern now. Keep this in mind.</p>
<h2>Next steps</h2>
<p>So if chromaDB was out of the picture. What next? Let's see what's out there.</p>
<p>Let's start with stuff that failed fairly quickly.</p>
<h3>Pinecone</h3>
<p>Long story short. It's a black box hosted somewhere, VDB as a Service. Proprietary. No-go. I want control over my data, where my db is deployed, where it lives and so on. Sorry. Privacy &amp; Compliance would not be happy, same with myself.</p>
<h3>Faiss</h3>
<p>It's just a library. not a full fledged VDB. It'd be a step back compared to chroma, so no. But for tiny PoCs? Possible. Evalute it. I didn't do that in detail.</p>
<h3>Milvus</h3>
<p>This one seemed promising. Initially I thought we'd roll with them. Promised all the new shiny nice stuff, but then I actually started using it. Had troubles to even index the data. Started running into bugs (or documentation not explaining stuff dumb enough for me to get it or not explaining at all), weird edge cases and complications that I was not in for. In case of chroma I just plugged it in, ran my Langchain-based data-ingestion service and I was done. Here? Forget it. However it was farily decent and pleasant to run locally in docker, a bit less so in k8s, but still passable. Bonus points for OS, self-hosted version and on-prem + cloud possibilty. If I was to make a similar comaprison as I did in case of chromadb, I'd say Milvus is the old Oracle DB of Vector Database world. Plus I've heard some similar opinions and unconfirmed rumours regarding ceratin dubious possible origins/practices and policies. It did seem promising but ended up as a failure last minute.</p>
<p>Eventually I did succeed in ingesting the data and so on, but the results were not satisfactory. Performance was okay, but I was done with frustration.</p>
<h3>pgvector</h3>
<p>This one disappointed me greatly.</p>
<p>Bad performance. Unusual selection of the underlying algorithm. Some problems with accuracy, especially when concurrency comes into play. Think carefully if the ease of integration is worth it. In my opinion this + the performance weren't. Take a look at the benchmarks. It's not satisfactory to say the least.</p>
<p>It also turned out that it's not supported everywhere as it's relatively new extension, for postgres standards. </p>
<p>And it's me who says this, guy who is team postgres. But postgres is a great RDBMS. Again, it does not specialise in vectors. </p>
<p>The benefit here is it being a standard piece of infrastructure, having your data in one place, all the other benefits postgres brings. It's still useful piece of software.</p>
<p>Bear in mind though, that in AWS world, aurora does not support it yet. Meaning if you are in aurora world, you'll need to deploy a separate base postgres instance with pgvector enabled. This eliminates the main benefit.</p>
<p>However if you do not care about that, you are running your own pgvector instance, and just want to get started? Hm, maybe. So there might be some relevant and valid use cases, but not in my case.</p>
<p>The performance was not there, accuracy also, especially when concurrency is considered and throughput. We couldn't deploy it in our Aurora cluster, we'd need to go for separate RDS. I think I'll pass, however it was indeed tempting because of the postgres brand, it being so reliable and common, but let's consider the borader picture - this was 2nd iteration where I expected things to be done in a proper, future-proof manner.</p>
<p>For RDBMS just go postgres. For VDB? Think twice about using pgvector.</p>
<h3>Redis</h3>
<p>Redis was a strong possible candidate. Good performance. Standard piece of infrastructure. Everyone knows redis, right? Features on the thin side though. I wasn't sure if, given some time, it'd be enough. But I kept it in place. It more or less worked. However It lingered in my mind that Redis is not specialised in Vectors. It's key value store. This is not the core of their business. Sure it'd be nice to be able to just deploy redis and have it done with. Everyone knows redis. However doubts sprouted in my mind, rightfully so eg. given their recent sunsetting of Redis Graph. </p>
<p>However if you already have a Redis cluster running somewhere, for starting it might be enough. </p>
<p>There is the question of perfromance, sure, but it's acceptable.</p>
<p>So, yeah, viable choice, but make a conscious decision.</p>
<h3>Qdrant</h3>
<p>Open source? Check. Self-hosted option? Check. Cloud if you are lazy? Check. K8s? Check. Clustering? Check. Survavibality? Check. Performance? Off the charts. Community? Great. Integration with langchain and other libs? Yup. One-line docker and you good to go locally? You bet. I was sold. </p>
<p>But then it got better. Within hours of signing up for their cloud offering to test things out I was approached by the founders to check in. Big shotout to @Andre Zayarni, @Fabrizio Schmidt and @Andrey Vasnetsov. Keep doing what you doing. We had a meeting set up right after. Tremendous knowledge. I really like the spirit they operate in or the values they highlight in some of their blog articles, especially the one related to closing the seed round. Andre's writing is sharp AF. Snarky remarks about the article not being written by chatGPT get bonus points (btw gonna steal that one).</p>
<p>They offered help (despite me not earning them a dime at that moment and stating that it'd be the case for the coming future or it'll be dime a dollar) with everything. Accommodated to our needs. Shared slack channel if problems arise? There you go. You wanna learn more? Sure, here are the resources. Workshops? Possible.</p>
<p>Also, big shotout to @Kacper Łukawski, which is just in love with spreading knowledge and helping out people. He provided lots of insights and offered help to get started out. Real beneficial stuff. Tutorials, blog posts, integrations with most popular libraries.</p>
<p>Free tier in the cloud offering to test stuff out (that actually can take you far along?) provided to anyone. </p>
<p>Qdrant wins by far, in my experience, when it comes to performance, scalability, durability, ease of use, feature set, flexibility and most importantly community plus the company values.</p>
<p>On top of that you can get started in minutes. It was best performance, easiest to use &amp; set up, well documented, nice community. Clear win.</p>
<p>As you can see I'm totally biased and sold, so take what I wrote with a grain of salt and verify yourself all of the above. I'll however remain quite bullish </p>
<h3>Weaviate</h3>
<p>Heard some good stuff here, especially regarding the feature set. However did not try it out personally. Compared to qdrant tho, they do have to improve on performance probably, but it might be a valid potential choice. Plus their community seems nice. Or I'm being biased only because @Philip Vollet, so their head of Dev Growth laughed at my joke about pgvector, so he seems salty in similar way to myself, which implicates good stuff. Eh, Olaf and his shenanigans again. Either way. Check it out, should be ok.</p>
<h2>Tie it all together</h2>
<p>So now, we understand some basic concepts regarding the vectors, embeddings, fundaments of CS, HNSW, ANNS. What Vector Databases do, is to tie this all together, provide more functionalities on top of that and some abstraction layer, so you don't have to reinvent the while, and on top of that, they also take care about the regular stuff that databases do.</p>
<p>What are they? Well, it's mostly stuff related to scalability (so you can easily handle millions of users), persistence (so stuff doesn't get lost), survivability (so it doesn't randomly die easily), data consistency and so on. </p>
<p>It's A LOT of work to do. We don't want to take care about all of these ourselves, do we?</p>
<p>So that's why we let Vector Databases take care of that. It's something they should excell at, other than performance and accuracy, obviously. It's not easy at all.</p>
<p>Also, I think that before you call your product a Database, it's required it meets at least some of these conditions as lately, in the hype driven world, it's not always the case.</p>
<p>Given that, all of the above and certain set of requirements I had for the project, I did the evaluation and research as to which product to actually choose.</p>
<p>Below you'll find a very brief and to the point summary of it. I didn't want to dig deep into the tech details to keep this article digestible, so these will come eventually in another article.</p>
<h2>Summary</h2>
<ol>
<li>Qdrant rocks and wins. In all categories. It's postgres of the VDB world.</li>
<li>Weaviate seems to be nice too, but don't quote me on that. Features seem nice and rich for LLMs.</li>
<li>Pinecone gets you started in minutes, but so does qdrant and why would you lock yourself in their ecosystem? Plus the performance and price, but might be valid choice for some folks just coz of the Managed mindset and convenience.</li>
<li>Chromadb lacks certain features, but develops quickly, however it needs evaluation and observation for bigger projects or situations where we need real clusters. For smaller ones with proper setup I'd say it's a valid choice + look out for their development and upcoming features. A bit like sqlite of the VDB world, but on steroids currently.</li>
<li>Redis is acceptable, but doesn't shine IMO. Positive surprise performance wise. It's not core of their business tho, plus they seem to be sunsetting certain parts that do not belong to the core like RedisGraph.</li>
<li>pgvector is disappointing, but still can be valid in some use cases and scenarios, it levarage the postgres brand and benefits which also enforce certain limitations on it. Do not count on great performance though or accuracy with concurrency.</li>
<li>Milvus is what I'd stay away from. Old Oracle of VDB world.</li>
<li>For anything that can hit production, FAISS is a no-go, it's just a lib. For simple play-around hobby projects? Why not.</li>
</ol>
<p>Yes, this was written by a human in a 4h long flow state powered act of uninterrupted creativity. It was fun, I've actually learned a lot.
I've written this in one go almost, except minor stuff or including the feedback from Jeff. I'll leave it mostly unedited, with original wording and typos.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I've Stopped Using Box Plots. Should You? (163 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nightingaledvs.com/ive-stopped-using-box-plots-should-you/</link>
            <guid>40765183</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 06:26:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nightingaledvs.com/ive-stopped-using-box-plots-should-you/">https://nightingaledvs.com/ive-stopped-using-box-plots-should-you/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40765183">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<p><em>tl;dr: After having explained how to read box plots to thousands of workshop participants, I now believe that they’re poorly conceived (box plots, not workshop participants 😉 ), which makes this classic chart type unnecessarily unintuitive, hard to grasp, and prone to misinterpretation. This has caused innumerable distribution-based insights to fail to land with audiences who weren’t willing or able to grasp them. Alternative chart types are virtually always easier to learn how to read, more informative, or both. </em></p>



<hr>



<p>Not sure what a box plot (a.k.a., a “box-and-whisker plot”) is or how to read one? If so, you should watch <a href="https://youtu.be/iBq23-eQhp8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this explanatory video</a> before continuing.</p>



<p>I used to use box plots often, but I rarely use them now. In fact, virtually never. Why not? Well, if you watched the explanatory video linked above, you saw that it took me over <em>four</em> <em>minutes</em> to explain how to read a box plot. If a chart type requires that much time to explain, it had better deliver a huge “epiphany payoff,” as data storytelling expert <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brentdykes/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Brent Dykes</a> calls it, i.e., it had better deliver valuable insights that can’t be communicated using simpler, more familiar chart types that require less time and effort for the audience to understand.</p>



<p>In my experience, though, virtually all the types of insights that chart creators try to communicate using box plots can be communicated using simpler, more familiar, and, frankly, better-designed chart types that don’t require audiences to slog through a multi-minute comprehension process beforehand.</p>



<h2>“I have no idea what you’re talking about. I can read box plots just fine and so can the audiences for my charts.”</h2>



<p>Let me share a few observations from my experiences explaining how to read box plots to thousands of workshop participants over the years:</p>



<ul><li>Most people don’t know how to read box plots. Among participants in my workshops—who generally have above-average <a href="https://www.oxfordreference.com/view/10.1093/acref/9780199599868.001.0001/acref-9780199599868-e-760" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">graphicacy</a> levels to begin with—typically less than 20 percent already know how to read box plots.</li><li>People struggle to grasp box plots much more than other “fundamental” chart types, and more even than “complex” chart types like scatterplots or histograms.</li><li>Even when audiences are familiar with box plots, they still require excessive, unnecessary cognitive gymnastics to interpret compared with alternative chart types such as strip plots and distribution heatmaps (see examples below), and are prone to misinterpretation.</li></ul>



<p>These issues arise from what I see as flaws in the traditional box plot design, which was first proposed by Mary Spear in 1952 and refined by dataviz legend John Tukey in 1969 (I can feel the flames licking at my heels already). What, exactly, are those flaws? I see three significant ones, which I’ll examine in detail:</p>



<ol><li>The design of traditional box plots doesn’t make ‘visual sense,’ which makes them unnecessarily hard to learn how to read and prone to misinterpretation.</li><li>Box plots require audiences to grasp complex concepts that they don’t need to understand in most cases.</li><li>Box plots conceal information that’s usually crucial to see.</li></ol>



<p>Let’s have a closer look at each of these problems in turn:</p>



<h2>The design of traditional box plots doesn’t make ‘visual sense.’</h2>



<p>Box plots are needlessly hard to grasp because their visual design doesn’t align well with how the human visual system works, i.e., they don’t make ‘visual sense.’ Specifically, I see three problems with the visual design of traditional box plots:</p>



<ol><li>If you’re a human with normal vision, you intuitively perceive thick, wide shapes as representing greater quantities (of whatever) than thin, narrow shapes. The ‘box’ segments in each box-and-whisker shape, then, look like they represent <em>more of something</em> than the ‘whisker’ segments, leading to the faulty interpretation that they contain more values, or perhaps have more importance. All four box and whisker segments contain the <em>same</em> number of values, however, and all four segments are equally important (unless the chart author wants to draw attention to the middle two segments for a specific reason). The concept of quartiles is hard enough for most people to grasp (more on that in a moment) and making the second and third quartiles look ‘bigger’ than the first and fourth quartiles really, really doesn’t aid comprehension. I was unsurprised to recently discover that <a href="https://www.psychologicabelgica.com/articles/10.5334/pb.az/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">research</a> has shown that this design flaw throws off even experienced box plot readers.<br></li><li>The two middle ‘box’ segments (i.e., the second and third quartiles) look like one, single shape with a dividing line in it (i.e., the median). This visually suggests that there are <em>three</em> parts in each box-and-whisker shape (a top whisker, a middle box, and a bottom whisker), not four. The middle box isn’t a single group that’s divided in two, though, it’s <em>two distinct groups</em> (i.e., two distinct quartiles). The middle two ‘box’ segments aren’t related to each other any more or less closely than, say, the top two segments, or the bottom two segments. (Yes, I know, the middle two segments are the ‘<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Interquartile_range" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">interquartile range</a>,’ but I don’t see a reason to <em>always</em> visually emphasize that fact.) Similarly, the two ‘whisker’ segments look like they may be more closely related in some way because, well, they’re both whiskers. But there’s no inherently special relationship between the first and fourth quartiles, either.<br></li><li>People associate longer shapes with greater quantity, which is why we find bar charts and other chart types that are based on that principle to be intuitive. In a box plot, however, longer box or whisker segments <em>don’t</em> represent greater quantities. The four segments in a box plot each represent the <em>same</em> quantity, i.e., they each contain the same number of values, regardless of how long or short they are. In fact, shorter segments in box plots actually represent <em>higher densities</em> of values, so there’s a “mismatch” between what our eyes are telling us and the underlying data. This is why, to many people, the box plot in the example below doesn’t <em>look</em> like it’s showing the same data as the histogram beside it, even though it is.</li></ol>



<div><figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=512%2C270&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="512" height="270" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=1024%2C539&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=300%2C158&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=768%2C404&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=1536%2C808&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=2048%2C1078&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=500%2C263&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=800%2C421&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=1280%2C673&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=1920%2C1010&amp;ssl=1 1920w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=450%2C237&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=1521%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1521w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=1360%2C716&amp;ssl=1 1360w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=2000%2C1052&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=250%2C132&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=550%2C289&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=342%2C180&amp;ssl=1 342w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=570%2C300&amp;ssl=1 570w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?resize=950%2C500&amp;ssl=1 950w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-histogram-w-callouts.png?w=2160&amp;ssl=1 2160w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p><meta charset="utf-8">Yes, I know. Shorter segments in a box plot <em>do</em> represent less quantity because the ‘quantity’ in a box plot is the range spanned by each quartile. That requires a big, counter-intuitive (and unnecessary) leap for most audiences, though.</p>



<p>Design concepts such as the ones below make more ‘visual sense’ than box plots:</p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=720%2C306&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="720" height="306" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=1024%2C435&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=300%2C127&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=768%2C326&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=1536%2C653&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=500%2C212&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=800%2C340&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=1280%2C544&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=450%2C191&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=1360%2C578&amp;ssl=1 1360w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=250%2C106&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=550%2C234&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=424%2C180&amp;ssl=1 424w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=706%2C300&amp;ssl=1 706w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?resize=1177%2C500&amp;ssl=1 1177w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?w=1833&amp;ssl=1 1833w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/alternative-quartile-concepts.png?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p>While these alternative designs would still require a certain amount of explanation, they’d probably be easier to grasp than box plots:</p>



<ul><li>They make it clearer that shorter segments contain higher concentrations of values.</li><li>They don’t draw unwarranted attention to the middle two segments.</li><li>They look like four shapes instead of three.</li></ul>



<p>If you find these design concepts to be less intuitive than box plots, ask yourself if that’s because they’re <em>actually</em> less intuitive, or if it’s because you’ve just gotten used to reading box plots over time.</p>



<p>Despite making more visual sense than box plots, I <em>still</em> wouldn’t recommend these design concepts <em>or</em> box plots in most situations because…</p>



<h2>For most types of insights, audiences don’t need to understand complex, abstract concepts like quartiles.</h2>



<p>Box plots require audiences to understand the concept of dividing a sorted set of values into ranges such that an equal number of values fall within each range, resulting in ranges of different sizes, i.e., the concept of <em>quantiles</em> and, specifically, <em>quartiles</em>. Yes, many people who are likely to read this article will be familiar with these concepts, but most audiences are not. Most audiences require multi-minute explanations to grasp them (ideally, with visual aids and examples, as in the explanatory video linked at the beginning of this article), and audiences need to grasp those concepts <em>fully</em> before they can even begin to interpret a box plot correctly. As we’ll see in a moment, though, there are other chart types that can be used to communicate a wide variety of useful, distribution-based insights, <strong>but</strong> <strong>that</strong> <strong><em>don’t</em></strong><strong> require audiences to understand quantiles, quartiles, or any other abstract, complex concepts.</strong></p>



<h2>“But <em>I</em> don’t find box plots hard to understand.”</h2>



<p>I hear you. <em>I</em> don’t find them hard to understand, either. That’s because you and I have been looking at box plots for years and our brains have learned to “think around” their design flaws. It <em>doesn’t</em> mean that they’re a well-designed chart type. People encountering box plots for the first time <em>do</em> get tripped up by these design flaws and, while you might have forgotten it, you almost certainly got tripped up by them the first time that you encountered a box plot, as well.</p>



<p>And the design problems with box plots continue to cause needless grief in organizations, when well-meaning analysts try to use them to communicate important insights to decision makers, but then get shot down because the decision makers aren’t willing to figure out how to read them. After experiencing these negative outcomes, analysts often assume that decision-makers don’t “get” distribution charts of <em>any</em> kind, which is unfortunate because visualizing distributions can yield invaluable insights. Analysts often just give up, though, because they don’t realize that the problem<em> </em>isn’t that their audience doesn’t grasp distribution charts <em>in general</em>, it’s that they don’t grasp box plots <em>in particular</em>. Using more intuitive distribution chart types (see below) would almost certainly yield more positive outcomes.</p>



<p>Regardless of how comfortable you are reading box plots, though, there’s also the minor detail that …&nbsp;</p>



<h2>Box plots often misrepresent distributions.</h2>



<p>Have a look at the box plot on the left, then compare it to the jittered strip plot <em>of the same data</em> on the right:&nbsp;</p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=512%2C355&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="512" height="355" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=1024%2C709&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=300%2C208&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=768%2C532&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=1536%2C1064&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=500%2C346&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=800%2C554&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=1280%2C887&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=450%2C312&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=1155%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1155w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=1360%2C942&amp;ssl=1 1360w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=250%2C173&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=550%2C381&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=260%2C180&amp;ssl=1 260w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=433%2C300&amp;ssl=1 433w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?resize=722%2C500&amp;ssl=1 722w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?w=1591&amp;ssl=1 1591w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/box-plot-vs-strip-plots.png?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p>The box plot on the left makes the distribution of ages of study participants in the “Test group” look almost identical to that of the “Control group”. As we can see in the jittered strip plot on the right, though, the two groups are quite different (which might substantially impact the results of our study). I’m <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/316652618_Same_Stats_Different_Graphs_Generating_Datasets_with_Varied_Appearance_and_Identical_Statistics_through_Simulated_Annealing" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">not the first</a> to point out that box plots <em>always</em> make distributions look ‘bell shaped,’ i.e., like the values are clustered around the median and gradually trail off away from the median. If a set of values <em>isn’t</em> bell shaped (like the “Control group” above), though, box plots <em>make them look bell shaped anyway</em>.</p>



<p>This is almost always a real problem because, even if all the sets of values in a box plot <em>do</em> have bell-shaped distributions, readers can’t <em>know</em> that, and so, at best, they’ll be left wondering if all distributions are actually bell shaped or not. There are other important limitations of box plots, such as hiding gaps in distributions and concealing the number of values in each group, but let’s leave it at that for now because this article is already pretty long.</p>



<p>Dataviz experts have proposed modifications to box plots and more sophisticated chart types that represent distributions more accurately to mitigate this misrepresentation issue. I want to clarify, though, that the main point that I want to make in this article <em>isn’t</em> that box plots can misrepresent distributions (although that is an issue), it’s that box plots are <em>needlessly</em> <em>hard to</em> <em>learn how to read in the first place</em>. More sophisticated chart types don’t help with that problem since they can be even <em>harder</em> for audiences to learn how to read. In any event, more sophisticated chart types aren’t needed for most day-to-day decision-making in most organizations, which can be fully supported by simpler distribution chart types, speaking of which…</p>



<h2>“What are these more intuitive/useful distribution chart types of which you speak?”</h2>



<p>The box plot alternative that I use most often is a <em>strip plot</em>:</p>







<div><meta charset="utf-8"><p>Strip plots can be grasped by most audiences in <em>a few seconds</em> and can be explained with a single sentence, such as, “Each dot is the age of a study participant.” Despite their simplicity, strip plots can communicate most of the insights for which chart creators often use box plots, such as showing whether distributions are higher or lower, concentrated or dispersed, normal or skewed, have outliers, etc. They can even communicate important types of insights that box plots <em>can’t</em> show, such as gaps in distributions, multimodal (“clumpy”) distributions, or insights that require seeing roughly how many values are in each set.</p><p>If there are more than a few dozen dots/values, though, strip plots tend to turn into solid lines of overlapping dots. In those cases, a <em>jittered strip plot</em> can be a good choice since it can accommodate more dots/values, but has all the same advantages of a regular strip plot:</p></div>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=381%2C489&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="381" height="489" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?w=762&amp;ssl=1 762w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=234%2C300&amp;ssl=1 234w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=500%2C641&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=450%2C577&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=624%2C800&amp;ssl=1 624w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=250%2C321&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=550%2C705&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=140%2C180&amp;ssl=1 140w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/jittered-strip-plot.png?resize=390%2C500&amp;ssl=1 390w" sizes="(max-width: 381px) 100vw, 381px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p>If there are hundreds (or millions) of values, though, jittered strip plots can also turn into solid blocks of overlapping dots, in which case you could move to what I call a <em>distribution heatmap</em>, which can handle any number of values:</p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=512%2C338&amp;ssl=1" alt="" width="512" height="338" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=1024%2C675&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=300%2C198&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=768%2C506&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=500%2C330&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=800%2C527&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=1280%2C844&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=450%2C297&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=1214%2C800&amp;ssl=1 1214w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=250%2C165&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=550%2C362&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=273%2C180&amp;ssl=1 273w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=455%2C300&amp;ssl=1 455w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?resize=759%2C500&amp;ssl=1 759w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/distribution-heatmap.png?w=1308&amp;ssl=1 1308w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p>Yes, a distribution heatmap ups the complexity a bit since it introduces the concept of <em>bins</em> (a.k.a. <em>intervals</em>), but bins are still considerably easier to grasp than quartiles. You also lose the ability to see how many values are in each group and there are a few other limitations, but box plots have all those same limitations (plus several others).</p>



<p>These alternatives to box plots can be used to communicate a wide variety of useful insights, don’t require the audience to understand complex concepts like quartiles, and show distribution shapes clearly (i.e., they don’t make everything look bell shaped). More to the point, they make more <em>visual sense</em> than box plots, so audiences grasp them in seconds instead of minutes, and they’re less prone to misinterpretation. <strong>Ultimately, this means that using these chart types instead of box plots substantially improves the odds that your audience will understand and act on your distribution-based insights.</strong></p>



<p>There are other distribution chart types that can be useful in specific situations, such as <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/mathematics/frequency-polygon" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">frequency polygons</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Violin_plot" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">violin plots</a>, <a href="https://www.khanacademy.org/math/ap-statistics/density-curves-normal-distribution-ap/percentiles-cumulative-relative-frequency/v/analyzing-a-cumulative-relative-frequency-graph" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">cumulative distribution plots</a>, and <a href="https://www.rhoworld.com/i-swarm-you-swarm-we-all-swarm-for-beeswarm-plots-0/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">bee swarm plots</a>, but the three types that I described above are the easiest ones to grasp, and are able to communicate most of the insights that are needed for day-to-day decision-making in most organizations. (I’m not mentioning histograms here because they’re generally only useful for visualizing a <em>single</em> set of values, whereas box plots and their alternatives are for visualizing <em>multiple</em> sets of values, which is a different use case.)</p>



<h2>“Do box plots have any actual <em>strengths</em> compared with alternative chart types? Are there <em>any</em> situations in which a box plot would be the best choice?”</h2>



<p>Well, as far as I can tell, the only advantage of box plots is that they show quartile ranges. The obvious next question, of course, is how often it’s necessary to show quartile ranges in order to say what you need to say about the data. In my experience, it’s not nearly as often as a lot of chart creators seem to think. Most of the time, you’re pointing out that distributions are higher or lower than one another, more concentrated or more dispersed than one another, have outliers, etc. <em>None</em> of these types of insights require showing quartile ranges and all can be communicated using simpler chart types. Some types of insights might require showing <a href="https://www.mathsisfun.com/definitions/median.html"><em>medians</em></a>, but those can be easily added to simpler chart types:</p>



<div><figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="720" height="213" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=720%2C213&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1024%2C303&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=300%2C89&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=768%2C227&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1536%2C455&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=2048%2C607&amp;ssl=1 2048w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=500%2C148&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=800%2C237&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1280%2C379&amp;ssl=1 1280w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1920%2C569&amp;ssl=1 1920w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=450%2C133&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1360%2C403&amp;ssl=1 1360w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=2000%2C592&amp;ssl=1 2000w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=250%2C74&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=550%2C163&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=608%2C180&amp;ssl=1 608w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1013%2C300&amp;ssl=1 1013w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?resize=1688%2C500&amp;ssl=1 1688w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?w=1440&amp;ssl=1 1440w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/better-chart-types-w-medians.png?w=2160&amp;ssl=1 2160w" sizes="(max-width: 720px) 100vw, 720px" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure></div>



<p>So, no, I can’t think of any situations when a box plot would be the truly best choice, other than those in which the audience demands box plots because that’s what they’re used to seeing. If you can think of any such situations, though, please let me know on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nickdesbarats/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">LinkedIn</a> or <a href="https://twitter.com/nickdesb" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Twitter</a>.</p>



<h2>“Why are box plots so ubiquitous in certain fields, then, especially in research?”</h2>



<p>Honestly, I’m not sure. Before the advent of PCs, box plots were easier to create (i.e., draw by hand) than other distribution chart types, so perhaps that’s why they caught on initially, and now that’s just what researchers are used to seeing? Let me know if you have any insight, though.</p>



<h2>“What now?”</h2>



<p>Some reviewers of an early draft of this article suggested that the conclusion should be that box plots were a good chart type in the past, but technology has advanced and now allows better chart types to be created easily, making box plots “obsolete.” I’m going a step further, though. I don’t think box plots were <em>ever </em>a well-designed chart type (although, of course, I say this with the benefit of modern research findings that the original designers didn’t have access to). Their design flaws have forced millions of hapless students, executives and others to slog through an unnecessarily cumbersome comprehension process, which could have been avoided if box plots had been better designed in the first place or if other distribution chart types had become more popular than box plots. Moving away from box plots today, then, would spare tomorrow’s chart readers that unnecessary cognitive slog.</p>



<p>Other reviewers suggested that the conclusion should be that box plots are a useful chart type, but only for statistically savvy audiences. Again, I’m going a step further, suggesting that even <em>those</em> audiences would be better served by other chart types in virtually all situations.</p>



<p>Do I expect that people who already use box plots will stop using them after reading this article? Probably not (inertia is a powerful thing…) Why did I write it, then? A few reasons:</p>



<ul><li>To encourage practitioners to consider alternative chart types, especially if their target audience isn’t familiar with box plots already (or, perhaps, even if they are…).</li><li>To acknowledge that, while this classic chart type has been a valuable tool in innumerable analyses during the last 70 years, it has design flaws that make it needlessly hard to grasp and prone to misinterpretation.</li><li>To find out if I’m wrong. I realize that I’m making some bold claims here, and it’s certainly possible that I’ve missed something. If you can describe a plausible scenario in which a box plot would be the truly best choice (for reasons other than “that’s what this audience is used to seeing”), please do <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/nickdesbarats/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">let me know</a>!</li></ul>

<!-- MOLONGUI AUTHORSHIP PLUGIN 4.7.10 -->
<!-- https://www.molongui.com/authorship/ -->


<div data-profile-layout="layout-1" data-author-ref="user-109" itemscope="" itemid="https://nightingaledvs.com/author/nick-desbarats/" itemtype="https://schema.org/Person" id="mab-2021989431" data-box-layout="stacked" data-box-position="below" data-multiauthor="false" data-author-id="109" data-author-type="user" data-author-archived="">

    <!-- Author picture -->
    
	<p><a href="https://nightingaledvs.com/author/nick-desbarats/">
                    <img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="150" height="150" src="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?fit=150%2C150&amp;ssl=1" alt="Portrait photo of Nick Desbarats" itemprop="image" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?w=1159&amp;ssl=1 1159w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=300%2C300&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=1024%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=150%2C150&amp;ssl=1 150w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=768%2C768&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=500%2C500&amp;ssl=1 500w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=800%2C800&amp;ssl=1 800w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=70%2C70&amp;ssl=1 70w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=450%2C450&amp;ssl=1 450w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=48%2C48&amp;ssl=1 48w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=250%2C250&amp;ssl=1 250w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=550%2C550&amp;ssl=1 550w, https://i0.wp.com/nightingaledvs.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/Nick-Desbarats-profile-pic-wood-background-square.png?resize=180%2C180&amp;ssl=1 180w" sizes="(max-width: 150px) 100vw, 150px">                </a>
                	</p>

    <!-- Author social -->
    
    <!-- Author data -->
    <div>

        <!-- Author name -->
        
<p>
	<h5>
                        <a href="https://nightingaledvs.com/author/nick-desbarats/">
		            Nick Desbarats                </a>
	            	</h5>
</p>
        <!-- Author metadata -->
        
<!-- End of .m-a-box-meta -->

        <!-- Author bio -->
        
<p>As an independent educator and author, Nick Desbarats has taught data visualization and information dashboard design to thousands of professionals in over a dozen countries at organizations such as NASA, Bloomberg, The Central Bank of Tanzania, Visa, The United Nations, Yale University, Shopify, and the IRS, among many others. Nick is the first and only educator to be authorized by Stephen Few to teach his foundational data visualization and dashboard design courses, which he taught from 2014 until launching his own courses in 2019. His first book, Practical Charts, was published in 2023 and is an Amazon #1 Top New Release.<br>
Information on Nick’s upcoming training workshops and books can be found at https://www.practicalreporting.com/</p>

        
    </div><!-- End of .m-a-box-data -->

</div><!-- End of .m-a-box -->
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TinyLetter Shut Down by Mailchimp, So I Built the LetterDrop (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/i365dev/LetterDrop</link>
            <guid>40764579</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 03:34:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/i365dev/LetterDrop">https://github.com/i365dev/LetterDrop</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40764579">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">LetterDrop</h2><a id="user-content-letterdrop" aria-label="Permalink: LetterDrop" href="#letterdrop"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">LetterDrop is a secure and efficient newsletter management service powered by Cloudflare Workers, enabling easy creation, distribution, and subscription management of newsletters.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The story</h2><a id="user-content-the-story" aria-label="Permalink: The story" href="#the-story"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I have been using <code>TinyLetter</code> to send newsletters to my subscribers, but unfortunately, Mailchimp has now shut down this free service. This isn't the first time I've faced such an issue, whenever this happens, I lose all my subscribers and have to look for a new way to send newsletters. To avoid this recurring problem, I've decided to build my own free newsletter service. It needs to be zero-cost, easy to use, and reliable so it won't get shut down. To achieve this, I'm using Cloudflare Workers to create the service, which I've named LetterDrop.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to use?</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-use" aria-label="Permalink: How to use?" href="#how-to-use"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Create a newsletter</h3><a id="user-content-create-a-newsletter" aria-label="Permalink: Create a newsletter" href="#create-a-newsletter"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Create a newsletter by sending a POST request to the <code>/api/newsletter</code> endpoint like this:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl --request POST \
  --url https://ld.i365.tech/api/newsletter \
  --header 'CF-Access-Client-Id: <<CF-Access-Client-Id>>' \
  --header 'CF-Access-Client-Secret: <<CF-Access-Client-Secret>>' \
  --header 'content-type: application/json' \
  --data '{
    &quot;title&quot;: &quot;BMPI&quot;,
    &quot;description&quot;: &quot;BMPI weekly newsletter&quot;,
    &quot;logo&quot;: &quot;https://www.bmpi.dev/images/logo.png&quot;
}'"><pre>curl --request POST \
  --url https://ld.i365.tech/api/newsletter \
  --header <span><span>'</span>CF-Access-Client-Id: &lt;&lt;CF-Access-Client-Id&gt;&gt;<span>'</span></span> \
  --header <span><span>'</span>CF-Access-Client-Secret: &lt;&lt;CF-Access-Client-Secret&gt;&gt;<span>'</span></span> \
  --header <span><span>'</span>content-type: application/json<span>'</span></span> \
  --data <span><span>'</span>{</span>
<span>    "title": "BMPI",</span>
<span>    "description": "BMPI weekly newsletter",</span>
<span>    "logo": "https://www.bmpi.dev/images/logo.png"</span>
<span>}<span>'</span></span></pre></div>
<ol start="2" dir="auto">
<li>Offline the newsletter by sending a PUT request to the <code>/api/newsletter/:id/offline</code> endpoint like this:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl --request PUT \
  --url https://ld.i365.tech/api/newsletter/9080f810-e0f7-43aa-bac8-8d1cb3ceeff4/offline \
  --header 'CF-Access-Client-Id: <<CF-Access-Client-Id>>' \
  --header 'CF-Access-Client-Secret: <<CF-Access-Client-Secret>>'"><pre>curl --request PUT \
  --url https://ld.i365.tech/api/newsletter/9080f810-e0f7-43aa-bac8-8d1cb3ceeff4/offline \
  --header <span><span>'</span>CF-Access-Client-Id: &lt;&lt;CF-Access-Client-Id&gt;&gt;<span>'</span></span> \
  --header <span><span>'</span>CF-Access-Client-Secret: &lt;&lt;CF-Access-Client-Secret&gt;&gt;<span>'</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><strong>NOTE:</strong> These APIs should be protected by Cloudflare zero-trust security. That means you need to create a <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/cloudflare-one/identity/service-tokens/" rel="nofollow">service-token</a> and use it to access these APIs.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Subscribe or Unsubscribe to a newsletter</h3><a id="user-content-subscribe-or-unsubscribe-to-a-newsletter" aria-label="Permalink: Subscribe or Unsubscribe to a newsletter" href="#subscribe-or-unsubscribe-to-a-newsletter"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Just go to the newsletter page and click the subscribe or unsubscribe button. e.g. <a href="https://ld.i365.tech/newsletter/e0b379d3-0be0-4ae5-9fe2-cd972a667cdb" rel="nofollow">BMPI</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Then you will receive an email to confirm your subscription or unsubscription. After that, you will receive the newsletter when it is published.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>NOTE:</strong> The newsletter page link pattern is <code>https://&lt;&lt;your-domain&gt;&gt;/newsletter/:id</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Publish a newsletter</h3><a id="user-content-publish-a-newsletter" aria-label="Permalink: Publish a newsletter" href="#publish-a-newsletter"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The LetterDrop use the Cloudflare Email Worker to send emails. And there is a <code>ALLOWED_EMAILS</code> variable to control who can send newsletters. You can use the Cloudflare dashboard to update the variable.</p>
<p dir="auto">After that, you can publish a newsletter by sending your newsletter content to this specific email address. And the Email Worker will send the newsletter to all subscribers.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>NOTE:</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>You should config the Email Worker to let it can be triggered by the specific email address. Please refer to the <a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/email-routing/setup/email-routing-addresses/" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare Email Worker</a> to know how to do it.</li>
<li>The newsletter email subject should be <code>[Newsletter-ID:&lt;&lt;the-newsletter-id&gt;&gt;]&lt;&lt;your-newsletter-title&gt;&gt;</code>, e.g. <code>[Newsletter-ID:9080f810-e0f7-43aa-bac8-8d1cb3ceeff4]BMPI Weekly Newsletter - 20240623</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to deploy?</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-deploy" aria-label="Permalink: How to deploy?" href="#how-to-deploy"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To use LetterDrop, you need to create a Cloudflare account and deploy the Worker script. The Worker script is available in the <code>app</code> directory. You can deploy the Worker script using the Cloudflare Workers dashboard.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>NOTE:</strong> You need to change the <code>app/wrangler.toml</code> file to use your config values.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">The dependencies</h3><a id="user-content-the-dependencies" aria-label="Permalink: The dependencies" href="#the-dependencies"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://workers.cloudflare.com/" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare Workers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/email-routing/email-workers/" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare Email Workers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/kv/" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare KV</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/r2/" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare R2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/queues/#cloudflare-queues/" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare Queues</a></li>
<li><a href="https://developers.cloudflare.com/d1" rel="nofollow">Cloudflare D1</a>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Please refer to the <a href="https://github.com/i365dev/LetterDrop/blob/main/app/db/README.md">app/db/README.md</a> file to create the database.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Variables</h3><a id="user-content-variables" aria-label="Permalink: Variables" href="#variables"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>ALLOWED_EMAILS</code>: The list of allowed emails to create newsletters.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to setup the notification service?</h3><a id="user-content-how-to-setup-the-notification-service" aria-label="Permalink: How to setup the notification service?" href="#how-to-setup-the-notification-service"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Currently LetterDrop uses <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/ses/" rel="nofollow">AWS SES</a> to send emails. You need to create an AWS account and configure SES to send emails. After that, you need to create a Cloudflare Worker as a notification service. The code is very simple, you can use the ChatGPT to generate the code.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to handle the failed emails?</h3><a id="user-content-how-to-handle-the-failed-emails" aria-label="Permalink: How to handle the failed emails?" href="#how-to-handle-the-failed-emails"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">LetterDrop uses the Cloudflare Queues to handle the failed emails. You can use the Cloudflare dashboard to monitor the failed emails and replay them in the dead-letter queue.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What is the next step?</h2><a id="user-content-what-is-the-next-step" aria-label="Permalink: What is the next step?" href="#what-is-the-next-step"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The next step is to add more features to LetterDrop.</p>
<ul>
<li>Improvments
<ul>
<li> Add the unit tests.</li>
<li> Add the email template.</li>
<li> Track the email open rate.</li>
<li> Support more third-party email services like SendGrid, Mailgun, etc.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li> Support the mulit-tenant feature.</li>
<li> Add the landing page.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to contribute?</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-contribute" aria-label="Permalink: How to contribute?" href="#how-to-contribute"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">I used the GPT-4o model to generate the code for LetterDrop. That means the code is generated by the AI model, and I only need to provide the prompts to the model. This approach is very efficient and can save a lot of time. I've also recorded a <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL21oMWN6Y7PCqSwbwesD4_wmXEVSeeQ7h" rel="nofollow">video</a> to show how to create the LetterDrop project using the GPT-4o model.</p>
<p dir="auto">That also means you can easily customize the code by changing the prompts. You can find the prompts in the <a href="https://github.com/i365dev/LetterDrop/blob/main/docs/CDDR/app.md">CDDR</a> file.</p>
<p dir="auto">Even I use the GPT model to generate the code, I still need to review the code and test it. So if you find any issues or have any suggestions, please feel free to create an issue or pull request. And there is no restriction on the contribution, you can contribute to any part of the project by yourself or with the help of the GPT model.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Disscussion</h2><a id="user-content-disscussion" aria-label="Permalink: Disscussion" href="#disscussion"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">If you have any questions or suggestions, please feel free to create an issue or pull request. I'm happy to discuss with you. Or you can discuss it in this hacker news <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40764579" rel="nofollow">thread</a>.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ruby: A great language for shell scripts (351 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lucasoshiro.github.io/posts-en/2024-06-17-ruby-shellscript/</link>
            <guid>40763640</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:46:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lucasoshiro.github.io/posts-en/2024-06-17-ruby-shellscript/">https://lucasoshiro.github.io/posts-en/2024-06-17-ruby-shellscript/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40763640">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      
        <header>
          
          
            <p> 





  
    4 minute read
  


</p>
          
        </header>
      

      <section itemprop="text">
        
        <h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>

<p>Ruby is so associated with its most famous framework, Rails, that many people
forget how amazing this language is. I mean, I know a lot of people who says “I
don’t like Ruby” and when I ask why, they say something about Rails. Personally,
I consider Ruby one of my favorite programming languages, and the last time I
touched any Rails code was 7 years ago…</p>

<p>So, if I don’t use Rails anymore, what I do with Ruby? Well, Ruby is a very rich
and complete language, perhaps even more than its more famous relative, Python
(sadly, I can’t say the same about its ecosystem…). And one of the things that
I think that Ruby is better than Python is using it for writing shell
scripts.</p>

<p>That is, most of the cases Bash for me is enough, but if the script starts to
become complex, I switch to Ruby. Here I show the main features that might be
interesting for this case of use.</p>

<h3 id="goals">Goals</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Show features of Ruby that are useful for writing shell scripts;</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Compare Ruby to Bash and Python;</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="non-goals">Non-goals</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Replace <em>entirely</em> Bash scripts by Ruby scripts.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="feature-1-calling-external-commands">Feature 1: calling external commands</h2>

<p>The first thing that you expect of language for writing shell scripts is to
call external commands. In Ruby, you do that using backticks (<code>`</code>):</p>



<p>That’s it! You don’t need <code>system</code>, <code>popen</code> or something like that, or import
a library. And if you set that to a variable, you’ll have the output of the
command:</p>



<blockquote>
  <p>Note: if you want to use <code>system</code> (e.g. if you want the output to be
redirected to stdout instead of a string) or <code>popen</code> (if you want to read or
write data from or to a subprocess), those are also available in Ruby!</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="feature-2-status-code">Feature 2: status code</h2>

<p>This is real quick: in Ruby, the variable <code>$?</code> contains the status code of the
last executed command. So, it’s really close to Bash:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>`true`</span>
<span>puts</span> <span>$?</span> <span># 0</span>

<span>`false`</span>
<span>puts</span> <span>$?</span> <span># 1</span>
</code></pre></div>

<h2 id="feature-3-its-a-typed-language">Feature 3: it’s a typed language</h2>

<p>Ruby is not a <em>statically</em> typed language, but it has types. In fact, it is a
object-oriented language, and it follow strictly the OOP paradigm (more than
Python, in some aspects even more than Java!). Bash, on the other hand,
everything is a string, and that leads to several safety issues…</p>

<div><pre><code><span>total_lines</span> <span>=</span> <span>`wc -l my_file`</span><span>.</span><span>to_i</span> <span># an int containing the number of lines of a file</span>
<span>half</span> <span>=</span> <span>total_lines</span><span>.</span><span>div</span> <span>2</span>           <span># integer division</span>
<span>puts</span> <span>`head -n </span><span>#{</span><span>half</span><span>}</span><span> my_file`</span>     <span># print half of the file</span>
</code></pre></div>

<h2 id="feature-4-functional-constructions">Feature 4: functional constructions</h2>

<p>Ruby implements <code>map</code>, <code>select</code> (filter), <code>reduce</code>, <code>flat_map</code> and other
functional operations as methods. So, you can, for example, apply a <code>map</code> over a
command output:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>puts</span> <span>`ls`</span><span>.</span><span>lines</span><span>.</span><span>map</span> <span>{</span> <span>|</span><span>name</span><span>|</span> <span>name</span><span>.</span><span>strip</span><span>.</span><span>length</span> <span>}</span> <span># prints the lengths of the filenames</span>
</code></pre></div>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note for Git lovers: I know that I could do that only using <code>git branch
--show-current</code>, but that was the first example that came in my mind to
demonstrate the use of regex…</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="feature-5-regex-matching">Feature 5: regex matching</h2>

<p>Regex is a type in Ruby, and operations using regex are built-in in the
language. Look at this example, where we get the current git branch name calling
<code>git branch</code>:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>current_branch_regex</span> <span>=</span> <span>/^\* (\S+)/</span>
<span>output_lines</span> <span>=</span> <span>`git branch`</span><span>.</span><span>lines</span>
<span>output_lines</span><span>.</span><span>each</span> <span>do</span> <span>|</span><span>line</span><span>|</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>line</span> <span>=~</span> <span>current_branch_regex</span> <span># match the string with the regex</span>
    <span>puts</span> <span>$1</span>                       <span># prints the match of the first group  </span>
  <span>end</span>
<span>end</span>
</code></pre></div>

<h2 id="feature-6-easy-threads">Feature 6: easy threads</h2>

<p>If want to work with multiple threads, Ruby is perhaps the one of the easiest
language to do it. Look:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>thread</span> <span>=</span> <span>Thread</span><span>.</span><span>new</span> <span>do</span>
  <span>puts</span> <span>"I'm in a thread!"</span>
<span>end</span>

<span>puts</span> <span>"I'm outside a thread!"</span>

<span>thread</span><span>.</span><span>join</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>So, it can be useful for, for example, downloading several files at the same time:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>(</span><span>1</span><span>..</span><span>10</span><span>).</span><span>map</span> <span>do</span> <span>|</span><span>i</span><span>|</span>                       <span># iterates from i=1 to i=10, inclusive</span>
  <span>Thread</span><span>.</span><span>new</span> <span>do</span>
    <span>`wget http://my_site.com/file_</span><span>#{</span><span>i</span><span>}</span><span>`</span>  <span># you can use variables inside commands!  </span>
  <span>end</span>
<span>end</span><span>.</span><span>each</span> <span>{</span> <span>|</span><span>thread</span><span>|</span> <span>thread</span><span>.</span><span>join</span> <span>}</span>        <span># do/end and curly braces have the same purpose!</span>
</code></pre></div>

<h2 id="feature-7-builtin-file-and-dir-operations">Feature 7: builtin file and dir operations</h2>

<p>In Ruby, all the file operations are methods of the <code>File</code> class and all the
directory operations are methods of the <code>Dir</code> class, as it should be. In Python,
for example, if you want to read a file you use <code>open</code>, but if you want to
delete it you need to use <code>os.remove</code>, and <code>os</code> does a lot of other things that are
not related to files.</p>

<p>So, in Ruby:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>exists</span> <span>=</span> <span>File</span><span>.</span><span>exists?</span> <span>'My File'</span>           <span># methods that return booleans end in ?</span>
<span>file_content</span> <span>=</span> <span>File</span><span>.</span><span>open</span><span>(</span><span>'My File'</span><span>).</span><span>read</span>
<span>File</span><span>.</span><span>delete</span> <span>'My File'</span>                     <span># parentheses are optional if it's not ambiguous</span>
</code></pre></div>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>I hope that after reading this short text you consider using Ruby as a
replacement for complex shell scripts. I mean, I don’t expect that you drop
Bash entirely, but consider using Ruby when things get complex. Of course, you
can do that in Python, Perl, even JS, but, as my personal choice I think that
Ruby is the most complete and easier Bash replacement for that!</p>

<p>If you find something wrong, or if you have any suggestion, please let me know
<a href="https://github.com/lucasoshiro/lucasoshiro.github.io/issues">here</a>.</p>

        
      </section>

      

      

      <!-- 
  <nav class="pagination">
    
      <a href="/posts-en/2024-05-11-splat-operator/" class="pagination--pager" title="Python: 10 cool tricks with the * operator
">Anterior</a>
    
    
      <a href="#" class="pagination--pager disabled">Próxima</a>
    
  </nav>
 -->
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ChatGPT is biased against resumes with credentials that imply a disability (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washington.edu/news/2024/06/21/chatgpt-ai-bias-ableism-disability-resume-cv/</link>
            <guid>40763540</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:30:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2024/06/21/chatgpt-ai-bias-ableism-disability-resume-cv/">https://www.washington.edu/news/2024/06/21/chatgpt-ai-bias-ableism-disability-resume-cv/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40763540">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main_content" tabindex="-1">

  			<p>
    <a href="http://www.washington.edu/news/category/engineering/" rel="category tag">Engineering</a>&nbsp; | &nbsp;<a href="http://www.washington.edu/news/category/news-releases/" rel="category tag">News releases</a>&nbsp; | &nbsp;<a href="http://www.washington.edu/news/category/research/" rel="category tag">Research</a>&nbsp; | &nbsp;<a href="http://www.washington.edu/news/category/technology/" rel="category tag">Technology</a>  </p>
  
<p>June 21, 2024</p>

  


  


<nav id="mobile-relative" aria-label="mobile menu"></nav>
<div id="attachment_85766"><p><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" src="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-scaled.jpg" alt="A hand holds a phone with the ChatGPT app open." width="2560" height="1708" srcset="https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-scaled.jpg 2560w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-300x200.jpg 300w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-768x512.jpg 768w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-1536x1025.jpg 1536w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-2048x1366.jpg 2048w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-375x250.jpg 375w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-750x500.jpg 750w, https://uw-s3-cdn.s3.us-west-2.amazonaws.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2024/06/18142155/solen-feyissa-Aj7cDaR6QXs-unsplash-1140x760.jpg 1140w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px"></p>
<p>UW researchers found that ChatGPT consistently ranked resumes with disability-related honors and credentials — such as the “Tom Wilson Disability Leadership Award” — lower than the same resumes without those honors and credentials. But when researchers customized the tool with written instructions directing it not to be ableist, the tool reduced this bias for all but one of the disabilities tested.<span>Solen Feyissa/Unsplash</span></p>
</div>
<p>While seeking research internships last year, University of Washington graduate student Kate Glazko noticed recruiters posting online that they’d used OpenAI’s ChatGPT and other artificial intelligence tools to summarize resumes and rank candidates. Automated screening has <a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/SB10001424052970204624204577178941034941330">been commonplace in hiring for decades</a>. Yet <a href="https://kateglazko.com/">Glazko</a>, a doctoral student in the UW’s Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering, studies <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/articles/detecting-and-mitigating-bias-in-natural-language-processing/">how generative AI can replicate and amplify real-world biases</a> — such as those <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/2023/11/02/ai-accessibility-chatgpt-midjourney-ableist/">against disabled people</a>. How might such a system, she wondered, rank resumes that implied someone had a disability?</p>
<p>In a new study, UW researchers found that ChatGPT consistently ranked resumes with disability-related honors and credentials — such as the “Tom Wilson Disability Leadership Award” — lower than the same resumes without those honors and credentials. When asked to explain the rankings, the system spat out biased perceptions of disabled people. For instance, it claimed a resume with an autism leadership award had “less emphasis on leadership roles” — implying the <a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/90706149/neurodivergent-people-make-great-leaders-not-just-employees">stereotype that autistic people aren’t good leaders</a>.</p>
<p>But when researchers customized the tool with written instructions directing it not to be ableist, the tool reduced this bias for all but one of the disabilities tested. Five of the six implied disabilities — deafness, blindness, cerebral palsy, autism and the general term “disability” — improved, but only three ranked higher than resumes that didn’t mention disability.</p>
<p>The team presented <a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3630106.3658933">its findings</a> June 5 at the 2024 ACM Conference on Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency in Rio de Janeiro.</p>
<p>“Ranking resumes with AI is starting to proliferate, yet there’s not much research behind whether it’s safe and effective,” said Glazko, the study’s lead author. “For a disabled job seeker, there’s always this question when you submit a resume of whether you should include disability credentials. I think disabled people consider that even when humans are the reviewers.”</p>
<p>Researchers used one of the study’s authors’ publicly available curriculum vitae (CV), which ran about 10 pages. The team then created six enhanced CVs, each implying a different disability by including four disability-related credentials: a scholarship; an award; a diversity, equity and inclusion (DEI) panel seat; and membership in a student organization.</p>
<p>Researchers then used ChatGPT’s GPT-4 model to rank these enhanced CVs against the original version for a real “student researcher” job listing at a large, U.S.-based software company. They ran each comparison 10 times; in 60 trials, the system ranked the enhanced CVs, which were identical except for the implied disability, first only one quarter of the time.</p>
<p>“In a fair world, the enhanced resume should be ranked first every time,” said senior author <a href="https://www.cs.washington.edu/people/faculty/jmankoff?_gl=1*fyd601*_ga*MzY0OTIyMDM4LjE2OTIzNzc0NDg.*_ga_3T65WK0BM8*MTcxODE0NDkwNC42NTAuMS4xNzE4MTQ0OTQwLjAuMC4w*_ga_JLHM9WH4JV*MTcxODE0NDkwNC42NTAuMS4xNzE4MTQ0OTQwLjAuMC4w">Jennifer Mankoff</a>, a UW professor in the Allen School. “I can’t think of a job where somebody who’s been recognized for their leadership skills, for example, shouldn’t be ranked ahead of someone with the same background who hasn’t.”</p>
<p>When researchers asked GPT-4 to explain the rankings, its responses exhibited explicit and implicit <a href="https://www.washington.edu/doit/what-ableism">ableism</a>. For instance, it noted that a candidate with depression had “additional focus on DEI and personal challenges,” which “detract from the core technical and research-oriented aspects of the role.”</p>
<p>“Some of GPT’s descriptions would color a person’s entire resume based on their disability and claimed that involvement with DEI or disability is potentially taking away from other parts of the resume,” Glazko said. “For instance, it <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hallucination_(artificial_intelligence)">hallucinated</a> the concept of ‘challenges’ into the depression resume comparison, even though ‘challenges’ weren’t mentioned at all. So you could see some stereotypes emerge.”</p>
<p>Given this, researchers were interested in whether the system could be trained to be less biased. They turned to the GPTs Editor tool, which allowed them to customize GPT-4 with written instructions (no code required). They instructed this chatbot to not exhibit ableist biases and instead work with <a href="https://disabilityphilanthropy.org/resource/what-is-disability-justice/">disability justice</a> and DEI principles.</p>
<p>They ran the experiment again, this time using the newly trained chatbot. Overall, this system ranked the enhanced CVs higher than the control CV 37 times out of 60. However, for some disabilities, the improvements were minimal or absent: The autism CV ranked first only three out of 10 times, and the depression CV only twice (unchanged from the original GPT-4 results).</p>
<p>“People need to be aware of the system’s biases when using AI for these real-world tasks,” Glazko said. “Otherwise, a recruiter using ChatGPT can’t make these corrections, or be aware that, even with instructions, bias can persist.”</p>
<p>Researchers note that some organizations, such as <a href="http://ourability.com/">ourability.com</a> and <a href="http://inclusively.com/">inclusively.com</a>, are working to improve outcomes for disabled job seekers, who face biases whether or not AI is used for hiring. They also emphasize that more research is needed to document and remedy AI biases. Those include testing other systems, such as Google’s Gemini and Meta’s Llama; including other disabilities; studying the intersections of the system’s bias against disabilities with other attributes such as <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/newsletters/2024-03-08/openai-s-gpt-shows-bias-in-resume-screening-experiment-big-take">gender and race</a>; exploring whether further customization could reduce biases more consistently across disabilities; and seeing whether the base version of GPT-4 can be made less biased.</p>
<p>“It is so important that we study and document these biases,” Mankoff said. “We’ve learned a lot from and will hopefully contribute back to a larger conversation — not only regarding disability, but also other minoritized identities — around making sure technology is implemented and deployed in ways that are equitable and fair.”</p>
<p>Additional co-authors were <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/yusuf-mohammed-2128851b7/">Yusuf Mohammed</a>, a UW undergraduate in the Allen School; <a href="https://venkateshpotluri.me/">Venkatesh Potluri</a>, a UW doctoral student in the Allen School; and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ben-kosa-2b04251ab/">Ben Kosa</a>, who completed this research as a UW undergraduate in the Allen School and is an incoming doctoral student at University of Wisconsin–Madison. This research was funded by the National Science Foundation; by donors to the UW’s <a href="https://create.uw.edu/?_gl=1%2A16qmpyw%2A_ga%2AMzY0OTIyMDM4LjE2OTIzNzc0NDg.%2A_ga_3T65WK0BM8%2AMTcxODE0NDkwNC42NTAuMS4xNzE4MTQ2NTExLjAuMC4w%2A_gcl_au%2AODkzNjkyOTguMTcxMTk5MDU5MQ..%2A_ga_JLHM9WH4JV%2AMTcxODE0NDkwNC42NTAuMS4xNzE4MTQ2NTExLjAuMC4w">Center for Research and Education on Accessible Technology and Experiences</a> (CREATE); and by Microsoft.</p>
<p><em>For more information, contact Glazko at </em><a href="mailto:glazko@cs.washington.edu"><em>glazko@cs.washington.edu</em></a><em> and Mankoff at </em><a href="mailto:jmankoff@cs.washington.edu"><em>jmankoff@cs.washington.edu</em></a><em>.</em></p>


<p><small>Tag(s): <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/tag/center-for-research-and-education-on-accessible-technology-and-experiences/" rel="tag">Center for Research and Education on Accessible Technology and Experiences</a> • <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/tag/college-of-engineering/" rel="tag">College of Engineering</a> • <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/tag/jennifer-mankoff/" rel="tag">Jennifer Mankoff</a> • <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/tag/kate-glazko/" rel="tag">Kate Glazko</a> • <a href="https://www.washington.edu/news/tag/paul-g-allen-school-of-computer-science-engineering/" rel="tag">Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering</a></small></p><hr>
            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Delving into ChatGPT usage in academic writing through excess vocabulary (135 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07016</link>
            <guid>40763133</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 23:18:29 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07016">https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07016</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40763133">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-inner">
    
    
                
    <p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2406.07016">View PDF</a>
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/html/2406.07016v1">HTML (experimental)</a></p><blockquote>
            <span>Abstract:</span>Recent large language models (LLMs) can generate and revise text with human-level performance, and have been widely commercialized in systems like ChatGPT. These models come with clear limitations: they can produce inaccurate information, reinforce existing biases, and be easily misused. Yet, many scientists have been using them to assist their scholarly writing. How wide-spread is LLM usage in the academic literature currently? To answer this question, we use an unbiased, large-scale approach, free from any assumptions on academic LLM usage. We study vocabulary changes in 14 million PubMed abstracts from 2010-2024, and show how the appearance of LLMs led to an abrupt increase in the frequency of certain style words. Our analysis based on excess words usage suggests that at least 10% of 2024 abstracts were processed with LLMs. This lower bound differed across disciplines, countries, and journals, and was as high as 30% for some PubMed sub-corpora. We show that the appearance of LLM-based writing assistants has had an unprecedented impact in the scientific literature, surpassing the effect of major world events such as the Covid pandemic.
    </blockquote>

    <!--CONTEXT-->
    
  </div><div>
      <h2>Submission history</h2><p> From: Jan Lause [<a href="https://arxiv.org/show-email/770f946c/2406.07016">view email</a>]      <br>    <strong>[v1]</strong>
        Tue, 11 Jun 2024 07:16:34 UTC (416 KB)<br>
</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SSH as a Sudo Replacement (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://whynothugo.nl/journal/2024/06/13/ssh-as-a-sudo-replacement/</link>
            <guid>40763117</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 23:14:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://whynothugo.nl/journal/2024/06/13/ssh-as-a-sudo-replacement/">https://whynothugo.nl/journal/2024/06/13/ssh-as-a-sudo-replacement/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40763117">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p>A major caveat in tools like <code>sudo</code> and <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/doas"><code>doas</code></a> for that matter is that they
rely on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Setuid"><code>setuid</code></a> binaries and privilege escalation in order to run commands as
root.</p><p>The design is not ideal, and also drags in a few limitations:</p><ol><li>The whole user session needs to retain capabilities to perform privilege
escalation.</li><li>They don’t work when running an entire user session in a restricted user
namespace.</li><li><code>setuid</code> binaries limitations on how the whole system is secured.</li></ol><p>An interesting alternative with a is <code>s6-sudod</code>, which splits the program into
two parts: a privileged server and an unprivileged client.</p><p>This is a summary of an experiment from a few weeks ago where I experimented
with using <code>ssh</code> locally to perform the same role as <code>sudo</code>, without exposing
this <code>sshd</code> instance to the network.</p><h2 id="goals">Goals<p>[<a href="#goals">permalink</a>]</p></h2><ul><li>Enable authorised users (and only authorised users) to run commands as root.</li><li>Don’t use privilege escalation.</li></ul><h2 id="implementation">Implementation<p>[<a href="#implementation">permalink</a>]</p></h2><p>First, I configured a dedicated SSH key that will be authorised for
authentication as root. This key is not in the regular <code>authorized_keys</code> file,
but in a separate file which will only be used for this purpose:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span>mkdir /root/.ssh/
</span></span><span><span>echo ssh-ed25519 AAAAC3Nza... &gt; /root/.ssh/local_keys
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I then ran an <code>sshd</code> server instance bound to a unix domain socket. Permissions
are tightened so unauthorised users cannot even access the socket. This instance
overrides the <code>PermitRootLogin</code> option to enable logging in as root<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>
and uses the newly created <code>/root/.ssh/local_keys</code> as a source for authorised
keys:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span>mkdir /run/sshd/
</span></span><span><span>chown root:wheel /run/sshd/
</span></span><span><span>chmod <span>750</span> /run/sshd/
</span></span><span><span>s6-ipcserver /run/sshd/sshd.sock sshd -ie -o AuthorizedKeysFile<span>=</span>/root/.ssh/local_keys -o PermitRootLogin<span>=</span>yes
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The root account was locked to disallow logging in via any mechanism. This was
done by prefixing the password’s hash with <code>!</code> (so no password’s hash can ever
match this value). <code>sshd</code> interprets this special prefix as the account being
locked and won’t allow logging in as root.</p><p>I changed the root password in <code>/etc/passwd</code> and replaced the <code>!</code> with an <code>*</code>.
<code>sshd</code> won’t give new value any special interpretation, and will allow logging
in as root. The value <code>*</code> will never match the hash of any password either, so
logging in via password remains effectively disabled.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup></p><p>I then needed to connect to the local <code>sshd</code> instance. While <code>sshd</code> has a <code>-i</code>
flag which allows passing an existing socket to it, <code>ssh</code> has no equivalent
flag. The <code>ProxyCommand</code> option can be (ab)used for this:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span>ssh -o ProxyCommand<span>=</span><span>'socat STDIO UNIX-CONNECT:/run/sshd/sshd.sock'</span> <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    -i .ssh/root-key.pub <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    -t <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    root@root <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    <span>"cd </span><span>$(</span>pwd<span>)</span><span>; '</span>$SHELL<span>' --login"</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>I’m using a hardware-bound SSH key in this case, which means that I need to tap
the physical device to authorise this connection. I could also use an ssh-agent
that requires explicit approval before disclosing keys (e.g.: <code>hissh-agent</code>).</p><p>A little caveat here is that <code>socat</code> will read all input from <code>ssh</code>, and then
write it into the socket, effectively duplicating the overhead of the
connection. I read the relevant manual pages a few more times, and couldn’t find
a solution. I came across <a href="https://man.openbsd.org/ssh_config.5#ProxyUseFdpass"><code>ProxyUseFdpass</code></a>, but wasn’t entirely sure how to
make it work.</p><p>After some more research online (and some major frustration), I found <a href="https://www.gabriel.urdhr.fr/2016/08/07/openssh-proxyusefdpass/">a clear
usage example from 2016</a>. It turnes out that <code>ProxyUseFdpass</code> was quite
straightforward and allows me to specify a command that sends the socket file
descriptor (via <code>stdout</code>) to <code>ssh</code>, and <code>ssh</code> then connects over this socket.</p><p>I saved the following script into <code>/home/hugo/tmp/passfd.py</code>:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="python"><span><span><span>#!/usr/bin/env python3</span>
</span></span><span><span><span># From: https://www.gabriel.urdhr.fr/2016/08/07/openssh-proxyusefdpass/</span>
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span>import</span> sys
</span></span><span><span><span>import</span> socket
</span></span><span><span><span>import</span> array
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span># Create the file descriptor:</span>
</span></span><span><span>s <span>=</span> socket<span>.</span>socket(socket<span>.</span>AF_UNIX, socket<span>.</span>SOCK_STREAM)
</span></span><span><span>s<span>.</span>connect(<span>"/run/sshd/sshd.sock"</span>)
</span></span><span><span>
</span></span><span><span><span># Pass the file descriptor:</span>
</span></span><span><span>fds <span>=</span> array<span>.</span>array(<span>"i"</span>, [s<span>.</span>fileno()])
</span></span><span><span>ancdata <span>=</span> [(socket<span>.</span>SOL_SOCKET, socket<span>.</span>SCM_RIGHTS, fds)]
</span></span><span><span>socket<span>.</span>socket(fileno <span>=</span> <span>1</span>)<span>.</span>sendmsg([<span>b</span><span>'</span><span>\0</span><span>'</span>], ancdata)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>And the command to connect to ssh now becomes:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="sh"><span><span>ssh -o ProxyCommand<span>=</span><span>'/home/hugo/tmp/passfd.py'</span> <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    -i .ssh/root-key.pub <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    -o ProxyUseFdpass<span>=</span>yes <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    -t <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    root@root <span>\
</span></span></span><span><span><span></span>    <span>"cd </span><span>$(</span>pwd<span>)</span><span>; '</span>$SHELL<span>' --login"</span>
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The linked article mentioned using <code>nc</code> (for a somewhat different use case).
Initially, it would seem that <code>nc -FU /run/sshd/sshd.sock</code> would work, but the
manual page actually specifies that this is not supported:</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code data-lang="man"><span><span>-F		Pass the first connected socket using sendmsg(2) to stdout and exit. This
</span></span><span><span>		is useful in conjunction with -X to have nc perform connection setup
</span></span><span><span>		with a proxy but then leave the rest of the connection to another
</span></span><span><span>		program (e.g. ssh(1) using the ssh_config(5) ProxyUseFdpass option).
</span></span><span><span>		Cannot be used with -c or -U.
</span></span></code></pre></div><h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion<p>[<a href="#conclusion">permalink</a>]</p></h2><p>This technique works. It relies mainly on OpenSSH for all the sensitive security
details. Not only does OpenSSH have a great track record, but it also enables
various forms of authentication including using a hardware-based SSH key.</p><p>Configuring this on a new host has no complex steps, and the above <code>ipcserver</code>
command can just be executed via the system’s service manager.</p><p>The above <code>passfd.py</code> script is a quick hack to move the experiment forward; for
daily usage it would be best to write a tiny executable that does the same thing
and put it into <code>/usr/local/bin</code>. The whole <code>ssh</code> command could also be placed
in a tiny wrapper.</p></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Simple script to cripple personalized targeting from Facebook (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://gist.github.com/HyperCrowd/edc9b461ec23cf2454ea4d1e910fd1c6</link>
            <guid>40762433</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 21:38:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://gist.github.com/HyperCrowd/edc9b461ec23cf2454ea4d1e910fd1c6">https://gist.github.com/HyperCrowd/edc9b461ec23cf2454ea4d1e910fd1c6</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40762433">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="file-cutofffacebook-md">
    <article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 dir="auto">Crippling Facebook</h2><a id="user-content-crippling-facebook" aria-label="Permalink: Crippling Facebook" href="#crippling-facebook"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Facebook works with advertisers to target you.  These instructions are one of the many ways to begin crippling that relationship.  When AI targeting is crippled, your psychosecurity improves :)</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>On your desktop machine, goto <a href="https://accountscenter.facebook.com/ads/audience_based_advertising" rel="nofollow">https://accountscenter.facebook.com/ads/audience_based_advertising</a></li>
<li>Maximize the browser window</li>
<li>Press F12 and click on the Console tab</li>
<li>Select the code below, copy it, paste it upon the Console line (The area next to the &gt; character in the Console window), and press enter:</li>
</ol>
<div dir="auto"><pre><span>(</span><span>async</span> <span>function</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>const</span> <span>wait</span> <span>=</span> <span>async</span> <span>(</span><span>watcher</span><span>,</span> <span>timeout</span> <span>=</span> <span>10000</span><span>,</span> <span>interval</span> <span>=</span> <span>100</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>const</span> <span>startTime</span> <span>=</span> <span>Date</span><span>.</span><span>now</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

    <span>return</span> <span>new</span> <span>Promise</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>resolve</span><span>,</span> <span>reject</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
      <span>const</span> <span>checkForElement</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>{</span>
        <span>const</span> <span>elements</span> <span>=</span> <span>watcher</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

        <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>elements</span><span>.</span><span>length</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>0</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
          <span>clearInterval</span><span>(</span><span>intervalId</span><span>)</span>
          <span>resolve</span><span>(</span><span>elements</span><span>)</span><span>;</span>
        <span>}</span> <span>else</span> <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>Date</span><span>.</span><span>now</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>-</span> <span>startTime</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>timeout</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
          <span>clearInterval</span><span>(</span><span>intervalId</span><span>)</span>
          <span>reject</span><span>(</span><span>new</span> <span>Error</span><span>(</span><span>`Timeout: Elements not found`</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
        <span>}</span>
      <span>}</span>

      <span>const</span> <span>intervalId</span> <span>=</span> <span>setInterval</span><span>(</span><span>checkForElement</span><span>,</span> <span>interval</span><span>)</span>

      <span>checkForElement</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
    <span>}</span><span>)</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>const</span> <span>delay</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>new</span> <span>Promise</span><span>(</span><span>resolve</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>setTimeout</span><span>(</span><span>resolve</span><span>,</span> <span>3000</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
  <span>const</span> <span>getElementsByAriaLabel</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>label</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>document</span><span>.</span><span>querySelectorAll</span><span>(</span><span>`[aria-label="<span><span>${</span><span>label</span><span>}</span></span>"]`</span><span>)</span>
  <span>const</span> <span>getElementsByRoleAndWidth</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>role</span><span>,</span> <span>width</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> 
      <span>Array</span><span>.</span><span>from</span><span>(</span><span>document</span><span>.</span><span>querySelectorAll</span><span>(</span><span>`[role="<span><span>${</span><span>role</span><span>}</span></span>"]`</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>filter</span><span>(</span><span>el</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>el</span><span>.</span><span>clientWidth</span> <span>===</span> <span>width</span><span>)</span>
  <span>const</span> <span>getElementsByText</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span><span>text</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>Array</span><span>.</span><span>from</span><span>(</span><span>document</span><span>.</span><span>querySelectorAll</span><span>(</span><span>'*'</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>filter</span><span>(</span><span>el</span> <span>=&gt;</span> 
      <span>Array</span><span>.</span><span>from</span><span>(</span><span>el</span><span>.</span><span>childNodes</span><span>)</span><span>.</span><span>some</span><span>(</span><span>node</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>node</span><span>.</span><span>nodeType</span> <span>===</span> <span>Node</span><span>.</span><span>TEXT_NODE</span> <span>&amp;&amp;</span> <span>node</span><span>.</span><span>textContent</span><span>.</span><span>includes</span><span>(</span><span>text</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
  <span>)</span>

  <span>const</span> <span>ads</span> <span>=</span> <span>getElementsByRoleAndWidth</span><span>(</span><span>'listitem'</span><span>,</span> <span>508</span><span>)</span>

  <span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>const</span> <span>ad</span> <span>of</span> <span>ads</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
      <span>console</span><span>.</span><span>log</span><span>(</span><span>ad</span><span>.</span><span>childNodes</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>textContent</span><span>)</span>
      <span>ad</span><span>.</span><span>childNodes</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>click</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>delay</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

      <span>const</span> <span>a</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>wait</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>getElementsByText</span><span>(</span><span>'They uploaded or used a list to reach you.'</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
      <span>a</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>click</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>delay</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

      <span>const</span> <span>b</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>wait</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>getElementsByText</span><span>(</span><span>'Don\'t allow'</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
      <span>b</span><span>[</span><span>1</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>click</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>delay</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

      <span>const</span> <span>c</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>wait</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>getElementsByText</span><span>(</span><span>'Don\'t allow'</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
      <span>c</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>click</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>delay</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

      <span>const</span> <span>d</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>wait</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>getElementsByAriaLabel</span><span>(</span><span>'Back'</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
      <span>d</span><span>[</span><span>2</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>click</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>delay</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>

      <span>const</span> <span>e</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>wait</span><span>(</span><span>(</span><span>)</span> <span>=&gt;</span> <span>getElementsByAriaLabel</span><span>(</span><span>'Back'</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
      <span>e</span><span>[</span><span>2</span><span>]</span><span>.</span><span>click</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
      <span>await</span> <span>delay</span><span>(</span><span>)</span>
  <span>}</span>
<span>}</span><span>)</span><span>(</span><span>)</span></pre></div>
<ol start="5" dir="auto">
<li>Watch as your slowly unsubscribe from all advertisers</li>
<li>Don't click or interact with the browser at all while this is going on.  Go do laundry or something.</li>
<li>Enjoy cutting off advertisers that hate you :)</li>
</ol>
</article>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Solar generates fifth of global electricity on summer solstice midday peak (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ember-climate.org/insights/in-brief/the-global-solar-revolution/</link>
            <guid>40761837</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 20:18:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ember-climate.org/insights/in-brief/the-global-solar-revolution/">https://ember-climate.org/insights/in-brief/the-global-solar-revolution/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40761837">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" aria-label="Main">
<article>

<div>
<div>
<p id="world-generates-fifth-of-its-electricity-from-solar-on-summer-solstice-midday-peak">
<h4>World generates fifth of its electricity from solar on summer solstice midday peak</h4>
<hr>
</p>
</div>
<div><p><span>Ember estimates that across the midday peaks on 21 June, the UN’s <a href="https://www.un.org/en/observances/solstice-day" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" data-stringify-link="https://www.un.org/en/observances/solstice-day" data-sk="tooltip_parent">International Day of the Celebration of the Solstice</a>&nbsp;– 20% of the world’s electricity will come from solar.&nbsp; In comparison, last year this value was 16%.</span></p>
<p><span>For the 24 hour average, Ember forecasts that solar will provide 8.2% of global electricity generation on 21 June. Although the solstice is the longest day of the year, all days in June are similar enough in length that solar generation on this day will be very close to the monthly average. The hourly profile was calculated by a weighted average of the hourly solar generation data.&nbsp;</span></p>
</div>

<div><h4><b>Global peaks in solar around summer months</b></h4>
<p><span>Across the year, global solar generation peaks in the summer months of the northern hemisphere, where Ember estimates 89% of the world’s solar panels are installed.</span></p>
<p><span>Ember tracks monthly electricity generation for 80 countries. Based on historical monthly data, monthly global solar generation is quite similar from May to August, although its share falls slightly towards August, as global electricity demand rises due to increased air conditioning demand in the northern hemisphere.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Ember’s forecast for June 2024 is 8.2%, compared to 6.7% recorded in June 2023. In absolute terms, Ember expects solar to rise by 28%, from 157 TWh in June 2023 to 201 TWh in June 2024.&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>Across the whole of 2023, solar generated a </span><a href="https://ember-climate.org/insights/research/global-electricity-review-2024/global-electricity-source-trends/#solar"><span>record 5.5%</span></a><span> of global electricity.</span></p>
</div>

<div><h4><b>Spotlight: Solar generation in the world’s four biggest solar markets</b></h4>
<p><span>In China, the world’s largest solar market accounting for 36% of global solar generation in 2023, we expect the share of solar in total electricity generation to reach 9.6% in June 2024, up from 7% in June 2023. On average, for the full year 2023, solar’s share in China’s electricity generation was 6.2%.</span></p>
<p><span>For the EU, </span><a href="https://ember-climate.org/insights/in-brief/wind-and-solar-displace-a-fifth-of-eu-fossil-generation-since-2019/"><span>a global wind and solar leader</span></a><span>, we expect the solar share across June to be more than double the global average at 20%, up from 17% in June 2023.&nbsp; On average, for the entire year 2023, the EU’s solar share was 9.2%. For Spain, which has one of the highest solar </span><span>shares in the EU and the world, the share of solar in June 2024 is expected to be even higher at 30%.</span></p>
<p><span>Meanwhile, the US and India are expected to have very similar solar share in June 2024, at 6.9% and 7.1% respectively compared to the global average of 8.2%. Both countries had very similar annual average solar share in 2023, with the US at 5.6% and India at 5.8%, slightly higher than the global average of 5.5%.</span></p>
</div>
<div>
<p id="solar-is-supercharging-the-global-clean-power-revolution">
<h4>Solar is supercharging the global clean power revolution</h4>
<hr>
</p>
</div>
<div>
<p><span>No other source of electricity has ever grown from 100 TWh to 1000 TWh of generation faster than solar. It took just 8 years for solar, making it ahead of wind (12 years), and far ahead of gas (28 years), coal (32 years) and hydro (39 years).&nbsp;</span></p>
</div>

<div><p><span>In 2023, records for solar additions and generation continued to be set.&nbsp; More than 2 million solar panels were installed on average every day, up from just over 1 million in 2022.</span></p>
<p><span>In 2023, solar added twice as much new electricity as coal and met 49% of global electricity demand growth. It was the fastest-growing source of electricity generation for the 19th year in a row.</span></p>
</div>

<div>
<p><span>For more detail on the rapid growth in solar generation, read the </span><a href="https://ember-climate.org/insights/research/global-electricity-review-2024/global-electricity-source-trends/#solar"><span>chapter on solar</span></a><span> in Ember’s Global Electricity Review. </span></p>
</div>
<div>
<p id="record-breaking-capacity-growth-in-2023">
<h4>Record-breaking capacity growth in 2023</h4>
<hr>
</p>
</div>
<div><p><span>China was the main driver behind a record-breaking 346 GW annual increase of global solar capacity in 2023. It was responsible for 63% of global solar additions in 2023. This was a record high share and a significant increase from China’s contribution of 43% of global solar additions in 2022.</span></p>
<p><span>China’s solar capacity additions increased by 152% compared to the previous year. This was more than three times faster than the growth in additions of all the G7 countries (+42%).&nbsp;</span></p>
<p><span>China has played a pivotal role in scaling up wind and solar deployment globally.&nbsp; With growing adoption, the cost of these technologies fell, making them the cheapest source of electricity. Overall, global solar capacity has boomed due to steep declines in costs, supportive policy environments, technological efficiency improvements and increased manufacturing capability. </span></p>
</div>

<div>
<p><span>For more detail on the rapid growth in solar capacity last year, read our </span><a href="https://ember-climate.org/insights/in-brief/2023s-record-solar-surge-explained-in-six-charts/"><span>recent post</span></a><span> on IRENA data.</span></p>
</div>
<div>
<p id="it-is-happening-everywhere">
<h4>It is happening everywhere</h4>
<hr>
</p>
</div>
<div><p><span>China is leading global solar capacity additions and solar generation, but rapid solar scale-up is also happening in countries with different geographies, stages of economic development and political systems, demonstrating that we have all the tools necessary to make this fast change happen in power sectors across the world.</span></p>
<p><span>Increased deployment worldwide is evident as there are now 34 economies that generate more than 10% of their electricity from solar. This is eight more than in 2022 , while less than a decade ago, in 2015, there were none. Of those 34 economies, nine are large electricity markets with more than 5 TWh of solar generation including Chile (20%), Greece (19%) and Hungary (18%).</span></p>
</div>

<div>
<p><span>Several countries made considerable progress in just the last year. Chile became the first country to reach 20% solar share in its mix – the target global average in the </span><a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/global-energy-and-climate-model/net-zero-emissions-by-2050-scenario-nze"><span>IEA’s Net Zero Energy scenario</span></a><span>. Meanwhile, the UAE surpassed Germany in terms of solar generation per capita, having surpassed the US in 2019.</span></p>
</div>
<div>
<p id="the-untapped-potential-of-the-sunniest-countries">
<h4>The untapped potential of the sunniest countries</h4>
<hr>
</p>
</div>
<div>
<p><span>Many sunny countries have yet to tap the potential of solar. While a few leaders like Australia and Spain are producing almost 20% of their power from solar, 66% of countries generate less than 5% of their electricity from solar. High solar generation even in countries with relatively poor insolation like Germany (12%) and the Netherlands (17%) highlights the potential solar has for meeting generation needs regardless of natural endowments.&nbsp;</span></p>
</div>

<div>
<p><span>Solar provides clean power that can be deployed quickly and locally to the demand source. New solar power produces the cheapest electricity in history, according to the </span><a href="https://www.iea.org/reports/world-energy-outlook-2020"><span>IEA</span></a><span>. This year’s northern hemisphere solstice may well be part of another record-breaking June for global solar generation, in part because most of the world’s solar installations are located there. Many high potential countries across the globe face financial and logistical challenges and it is important to enable solar development in these countries to lead the world towards a clean, electrified energy future. </span></p>
</div>
</div>
</article>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HH70, the first high-temperature superconducting Tokamak achieves first plasma (215 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/hh70-the-worlds-first-high-temperature-superconducting-tokamak-achieves-first-plasma/</link>
            <guid>40761713</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 20:01:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/hh70-the-worlds-first-high-temperature-superconducting-tokamak-achieves-first-plasma/">https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/hh70-the-worlds-first-high-temperature-superconducting-tokamak-achieves-first-plasma/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40761713">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content" role="main">
						<article id="post-765">
				<div>
<p>Recently, the world’s first fully high-temperature superconducting Tokamak device, developed and constructed by Energy Singularity, known as “HH70,” has successfully achieved first plasma. HH70 has conducted discharge experiments based on two types of pre-ionization methods: localized helical magnetic flux injection (electron gun) and ion cyclotron heating (ICRF), and has successfully obtained the first plasma.</p>



<figure><img width="1024" height="691" src="https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240527-114257-1024x691.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240527-114257-1024x691.jpg 1024w, https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240527-114257-300x203.jpg 300w, https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240527-114257-768x518.jpg 768w, https://www.energysingularity.cn/en/wp-content/uploads/2024/06/20240527-114257.jpg 1280w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The toroidal&nbsp;magnetic&nbsp;field (B<sub>0</sub>) of HH70 is 0.6 Tesla, with a plasma major radius of 0.75 meters. Its magnet system consists of 26 high-temperature superconducting magnets. Designed, developed, and constructed by Energy Singularity, HH70 has independent intellectual property rights, with a localization rate exceeding 96%. The completion and operation of HH70 have taken the lead in the world in completing the engineering feasibility verification of high-temperature superconducting Tokamak, marking that China has gained a first-mover advantage in the key field of high-temperature superconducting magnetic confinement fusion. At the same time, the research and construction of HH70 have also achieved a number of innovative results:</p>



<ul><li><strong>The world’s first high-temperature superconducting magnetic confinement fusion device.</strong></li><li><strong>The world’s first high-temperature superconducting Tokamak.</strong></li><li><strong>The world’s first superconducting Tokamak built by a commercial company.</strong></li><li><strong>One of the four superconducting Tokamaks in operation worldwide.</strong></li></ul>



<p>The successful discharge of HH70 signifies that Energy Singularity has become the first and currently the only team in the world to build and operate a fully high-temperature superconducting Tokamak, as well as the first and currently the only commercial company to build and operate a fully superconducting Tokamak. Starting from the completion and operation of HH70, and taking HH70 as a key experimental platform, we will invest in the development of the next generation of high-field high-temperature superconducting Tokamak devices—HH170, which aims to achieve a deuterium-tritium equivalent energy gain (Q) greater than 10.</p>



<p>Controlled nuclear fusion is expected to provide humanity with an almost infinite, clean, and cheap source of energy, and is considered the ultimate energy solution. As the only magnetic confinement fusion technology route that has completed scientific feasibility verification, the Tokamak has always been the focus of global controlled nuclear fusion research and development. High-temperature superconducting Tokamak combines robust physics with engineering innovation, which is expected to greatly improve the cost-effectiveness of the device and accelerate the commercialization of fusion energy, and has become the direction of fusion energy research and development that attracts the most market-oriented funding worldwide. As a domestic institution that took the lead in focusing on the research and development of high-temperature superconducting Tokamak, since its establishment in 2021, Energy Singularity has taken “accelerating the realization of human energy freedom” as its mission, adhering to the values of “extreme efficiency and seeking truth from facts”, and has established an integrated high-temperature superconducting magnet design, processing, and testing platform, and built the capabilities for research and development, design, construction, and operation of high-temperature superconducting Tokamak devices.</p>
</div>			</article>
			
		</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AWS Lambda Web Adapter (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter</link>
            <guid>40760858</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 18:01:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter">https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40760858">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">AWS Lambda Web Adapter</h2><a id="user-content-aws-lambda-web-adapter" aria-label="Permalink: AWS Lambda Web Adapter" href="#aws-lambda-web-adapter"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A tool to run web applications on AWS Lambda</p>
<p dir="auto">AWS Lambda Web Adapter allows developers to build web apps (http api) with familiar frameworks (e.g. Express.js, Next.js, Flask, SpringBoot, ASP.NET and Laravel, anything speaks HTTP 1.1/1.0) and run it on AWS Lambda.
The same docker image can run on AWS Lambda, Amazon EC2, AWS Fargate, and local computers.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/docs/images/lambda-adapter-overview.png"><img src="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/raw/main/docs/images/lambda-adapter-overview.png" alt="Lambda Web Adapter"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Features</h2><a id="user-content-features" aria-label="Permalink: Features" href="#features"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Run web applications on AWS Lambda</li>
<li>Supports Amazon API Gateway Rest API and Http API endpoints, Lambda Function URLs, and Application Load Balancer</li>
<li>Supports Lambda managed runtimes, custom runtimes and docker OCI images</li>
<li>Supports any web frameworks and languages, no new code dependency to include</li>
<li>Automatic encode binary response</li>
<li>Enables graceful shutdown</li>
<li>Supports response payload compression</li>
<li>Supports response streaming</li>
<li>Supports non-http event triggers</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">AWS Lambda Web Adapter work with Lambda functions packaged as both docker images and Zip packages.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Lambda functions packaged as Docker Images or OCI Images</h3><a id="user-content-lambda-functions-packaged-as-docker-images-or-oci-images" aria-label="Permalink: Lambda functions packaged as Docker Images or OCI Images" href="#lambda-functions-packaged-as-docker-images-or-oci-images"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To use Lambda Web Adapter with docker images, package your web app (http api) in a Dockerfile, and add one line to copy Lambda Web Adapter binary to /opt/extensions inside your container:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="COPY --from=public.ecr.aws/awsguru/aws-lambda-adapter:0.8.3 /lambda-adapter /opt/extensions/lambda-adapter"><pre><span>COPY</span> --from=public.ecr.aws/awsguru/aws-lambda-adapter:0.8.3 /lambda-adapter /opt/extensions/lambda-adapter</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/images-create.html" rel="nofollow">Non-AWS base images</a> may be used since the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/images-create.html#images-ric" rel="nofollow">Runtime Interface Client</a> ships with the Lambda Web Adapter.</p>
<p dir="auto">By default, Lambda Web Adapter assumes the web app is listening on port 8080. If not, you can specify the port via <a href="#configurations">configuration</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Pre-compiled Lambda Web Adapter binaries are provided in ECR public repo: <a href="https://gallery.ecr.aws/awsguru/aws-lambda-adapter" rel="nofollow">public.ecr.aws/awsguru/aws-lambda-adapter</a>.
Multi-arch images are also provided in this repo. It works on both x86_64 and arm64 CPU architecture.</p>
<p dir="auto">Below is a Dockerfile for <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs">an example nodejs application</a>.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="FROM public.ecr.aws/docker/library/node:20-slim
COPY --from=public.ecr.aws/awsguru/aws-lambda-adapter:0.8.3 /lambda-adapter /opt/extensions/lambda-adapter
ENV PORT=7000
WORKDIR &quot;/var/task&quot;
ADD src/package.json /var/task/package.json
ADD src/package-lock.json /var/task/package-lock.json
RUN npm install --omit=dev
ADD src/ /var/task
CMD [&quot;node&quot;, &quot;index.js&quot;]"><pre><span>FROM</span> public.ecr.aws/docker/library/node:20-slim
<span>COPY</span> --from=public.ecr.aws/awsguru/aws-lambda-adapter:0.8.3 /lambda-adapter /opt/extensions/lambda-adapter
<span>ENV</span> PORT=7000
<span>WORKDIR</span> <span>"/var/task"</span>
<span>ADD</span> src/package.json /var/task/package.json
<span>ADD</span> src/package-lock.json /var/task/package-lock.json
<span>RUN</span> npm install --omit=dev
<span>ADD</span> src/ /var/task
<span>CMD</span> [<span>"node"</span>, <span>"index.js"</span>]</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This works with any base images except AWS managed base images. To use AWS managed base images, you need to override the ENTRYPOINT to start your web app.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Lambda functions packaged as Zip package for AWS managed runtimes</h3><a id="user-content-lambda-functions-packaged-as-zip-package-for-aws-managed-runtimes" aria-label="Permalink: Lambda functions packaged as Zip package for AWS managed runtimes" href="#lambda-functions-packaged-as-zip-package-for-aws-managed-runtimes"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">AWS Lambda Web Adapter also works with AWS managed Lambda runtimes. You need to do three things:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">attach Lambda Web Adapter layer to your function.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">AWS Commercial Regions</h4><a id="user-content-aws-commercial-regions" aria-label="Permalink: AWS Commercial Regions" href="#aws-commercial-regions"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>x86_64: <code>arn:aws:lambda:${AWS::Region}:753240598075:layer:LambdaAdapterLayerX86:22</code></li>
<li>arm64: <code>arn:aws:lambda:${AWS::Region}:753240598075:layer:LambdaAdapterLayerArm64:22</code></li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">AWS China Regions</h4><a id="user-content-aws-china-regions" aria-label="Permalink: AWS China Regions" href="#aws-china-regions"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>cn-north-1 (Beijing)
<ul dir="auto">
<li>x86_64: <code>arn:aws-cn:lambda:cn-north-1:041581134020:layer:LambdaAdapterLayerX86:22</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>cn-northwest-1 (Ningxia)
<ul dir="auto">
<li>x86_64: <code>arn:aws-cn:lambda:cn-northwest-1:069767869989:layer:LambdaAdapterLayerX86:22</code></li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">configure Lambda environment variable <code>AWS_LAMBDA_EXEC_WRAPPER</code> to <code>/opt/bootstrap</code>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">set function handler to your web application start up script. e.g. <code>run.sh</code>.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto">For details, please check out <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs-zip">the example Node.js application</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Readiness Check</h2><a id="user-content-readiness-check" aria-label="Permalink: Readiness Check" href="#readiness-check"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">When a new Lambda Execution Environment starts up, Lambda Web Adapter will boot up as a Lambda Extension, followed by the web application.</p>
<p dir="auto">By default, Lambda Web Adapter will send HTTP GET requests to the web application at <code>http://127.0.0.1:8080/</code>. The port and path can be customized with two environment variables: <code>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_PORT</code> and <code>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_PATH</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Lambda Web Adapter will retry this request every 10 milliseconds until the web application returns an HTTP response (<strong>status code &gt;= 100 and &lt; 500</strong>) or the function times out.</p>
<p dir="auto">In addition, you can configure the adapter to preform readiness check with TCP connect, by setting <code>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_PROTOCOL</code> to <code>tcp</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">After passing readiness check, Lambda Web Adapter will start Lambda Runtime and forward the invokes to the web application.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configurations</h2><a id="user-content-configurations" aria-label="Permalink: Configurations" href="#configurations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The readiness check port/path and traffic port can be configured using environment variables. These environment variables can be defined either within docker file or as Lambda function configuration.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Environment Variable</th>
<th>Description</th>
<th>Default</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_PORT / PORT*</td>
<td>traffic port</td>
<td>"8080"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_PORT / READINESS_CHECK_PORT*</td>
<td>readiness check port, default to the traffic port</td>
<td>PORT</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_PATH / READINESS_CHECK_PATH*</td>
<td>readiness check path</td>
<td>"/"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_PROTOCOL / READINESS_CHECK_PROTOCOL*</td>
<td>readiness check protocol: "http" or "tcp", default is "http"</td>
<td>"http"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_MIN_UNHEALTHY_STATUS</td>
<td>The minimum HTTP status code that is considered unhealthy</td>
<td>"500"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_ASYNC_INIT / ASYNC_INIT*</td>
<td>enable asynchronous initialization for long initialization functions</td>
<td>"false"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_REMOVE_BASE_PATH / REMOVE_BASE_PATH*</td>
<td>the base path to be removed from request path</td>
<td>None</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_ENABLE_COMPRESSION</td>
<td>enable gzip compression for response body</td>
<td>"false"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_INVOKE_MODE</td>
<td>Lambda function invoke mode: "buffered" or "response_stream", default is "buffered"</td>
<td>"buffered"</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>AWS_LWA_PASS_THROUGH_PATH</td>
<td>the path for receiving event payloads that are passed through from non-http triggers</td>
<td>"/events"</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note:</strong>
We use "AWS_LWA_" prefix to namespacing all environment variables used by Lambda Web Adapter. The original ones will be supported until we reach version 1.0.</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_PORT / PORT</strong> - Lambda Web Adapter will send traffic to this port. This is the port your web application listening on. Inside Lambda execution environment,
the web application runs as a non-root user, and not allowed to listen on ports lower than 1024. Please also avoid port 9001 and 3000.
Lambda Runtime API is on port 9001. CloudWatch Lambda Insight extension uses port 3000.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_ASYNC_INIT / ASYNC_INIT</strong> - Lambda managed runtimes offer up to 10 seconds for function initialization. During this period of time, Lambda functions have burst of CPU to accelerate initialization, and it is free.
If a lambda function couldn't complete the initialization within 10 seconds, Lambda will restart the function, and bill for the initialization.
To help functions to use this 10 seconds free initialization time and avoid the restart, Lambda Web Adapter supports asynchronous initialization.
When this feature is enabled, Lambda Web Adapter performs readiness check up to 9.8 seconds. If the web app is not ready by then,
Lambda Web Adapter signals to Lambda service that the init is completed, and continues readiness check in the handler.
This feature is disabled by default. Enable it by setting environment variable <code>AWS_LWA_ASYNC_INIT</code> to <code>true</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_REMOVE_BASE_PATH / REMOVE_BASE_PATH</strong> - The value of this environment variable tells the adapter whether the application is running under a base path.
For example, you could have configured your API Gateway to have a /orders/{proxy+} and a /catalog/{proxy+} resource.
Each resource is handled by a separate Lambda functions. For this reason, the application inside Lambda may not be aware of the fact that the /orders path exists.
Use REMOVE_BASE_PATH to remove the /orders prefix when routing requests to the application. Defaults to empty string. Checkout <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/springboot">SpringBoot</a> example.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_ENABLE_COMPRESSION</strong> - Lambda Web Adapter supports gzip compression for response body. This feature is disabled by default. Enable it by setting environment variable <code>AWS_LWA_ENABLE_COMPRESSION</code> to <code>true</code>.
When enabled, this will compress responses unless it's an image as determined by the content-type starting with <code>image</code> or the response is less than 32 bytes. This will also compress HTTP/1.1 chunked streaming response.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_INVOKE_MODE</strong> - Lambda function invoke mode, this should match Function Url invoke mode. The default is "buffered". When configured as "response_stream", Lambda Web Adapter will stream response to Lambda service <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/compute/introducing-aws-lambda-response-streaming/" rel="nofollow">blog</a>.
Please check out <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/fastapi-response-streaming">FastAPI with Response Streaming</a> example.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_READINESS_CHECK_MIN_UNHEALTHY_STATUS</strong> - allows you to customize which HTTP status codes are considered healthy and which ones are not</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>AWS_LWA_PASS_THROUGH_PATH</strong> - Path to receive events payloads passed through from non-http event triggers. The default is "/events".</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Request Context</h2><a id="user-content-request-context" aria-label="Permalink: Request Context" href="#request-context"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Request Context</strong> is metadata API Gateway sends to Lambda for a request. It usually contains requestId, requestTime, apiId, identity, and authorizer. Identity and authorizer are useful to get client identity for authorization. API Gateway Developer Guide contains more details <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/apigateway/latest/developerguide/set-up-lambda-proxy-integrations.html#api-gateway-simple-proxy-for-lambda-input-format" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Lambda Web Adapter forwards this information to the web application in a Http Header named "x-amzn-request-context". In the web application, you can retrieve the value of this http header and deserialize it into a JSON object. Check out <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs-zip">Express.js in Zip</a> on how to use it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Lambda Context</h2><a id="user-content-lambda-context" aria-label="Permalink: Lambda Context" href="#lambda-context"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Lambda Context</strong> is an object that Lambda passes to the function handler. This object provides information about the invocation, function, and execution environment. You can find a full list of properties accessible through the Lambda Context <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/lambda/latest/dg/nodejs-context.html" rel="nofollow">here</a></p>
<p dir="auto">Lambda Web Adapter forwards this information to the web application in a Http Header named "x-amzn-lambda-context". In the web application, you can retrieve the value of this http header and deserialize it into a JSON object. Check out <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs-zip">Express.js in Zip</a> on how to use it.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Graceful Shutdown</h2><a id="user-content-graceful-shutdown" aria-label="Permalink: Graceful Shutdown" href="#graceful-shutdown"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">For a function with Lambda Extensions registered, Lambda enables shutdown phase for the function. When Lambda service is about to shut down a Lambda execution environment,
it sends a SIGTERM signal to the runtime and then a SHUTDOWN event to each registered external extensions. Developers could catch the SIGTERM signal in the lambda functions and perform graceful shutdown tasks.
The <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs/app/src/index.js">Express.js</a> gives a simple example. More details in <a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/graceful-shutdown-with-aws-lambda">this repo</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Local Debugging</h2><a id="user-content-local-debugging" aria-label="Permalink: Local Debugging" href="#local-debugging"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Lambda Web Adapter allows developers to develop web applications locally with familiar tools and debuggers: just run the web app locally and test it. If you want to simulate Lambda Runtime environment locally, you can use AWS SAM CLI. The following command starts a local api gateway endpoint and simulate the Lambda runtime execution environment.</p>

<p dir="auto">Please note that <code>sam local</code> starts a Lambda Runtime Interface Emulator on port 8080. So your web application should avoid port <code>8080</code> if you plan to use <code>sam local</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Non-HTTP Event Triggers</h2><a id="user-content-non-http-event-triggers" aria-label="Permalink: Non-HTTP Event Triggers" href="#non-http-event-triggers"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The Lambda Web Adapter also supports all non-HTTP event triggers, such as SQS, SNS, S3, DynamoDB, Kinesis, Kafka, EventBridge, and Bedrock Agents. The adapter forwards the event payload to the web application via http post to a path defined by the <code>AWS_LWA_PASS_THROUGH_PATH</code> environment variable. By default, this path is set to <code>/events</code>. Upon receiving the event payload from the request body, the web application should processes it and returns the results as a JSON response. Please checkout <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/sqs-expressjs">SQS Express.js</a> and <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/bedrock-agent-fastapi-zip">Bedrock Agent FastAPI in Zip</a> examples.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h2><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/fastapi">FastAPI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/fastapi-zip">FastAPI in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/fastapi-background-tasks">FastAPI with Background Tasks</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/fastapi-response-streaming">FastAPI with Response Streaming</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/fastapi-response-streaming-zip">FastAPI with Response Streaming in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/flask">Flask</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/flask-zip">Flask in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/aws-hebrew-book/serverless-django">Serverless Django</a>  by <a href="https://github.com/efi-mk">@efi-mk</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs">Express.js</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/expressjs-zip">Express.js in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/nextjs">Next.js</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/nextjs-zip">Next.js in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/nextjs-response-streaming">Next.js Response Streaming</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/springboot">SpringBoot</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/springboot-zip">SpringBoot in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/springboot-response-streaming-zip">SpringBoot Response Streaming</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/nginx">Nginx</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/php">PHP</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/rust-actix-web-zip">Rust Actix Web in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/rust-axum-zip">Rust Axum in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/gin">Golang Gin</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/gin-zip">Golang Gin in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/deno-zip">Deno Oak in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/aws-samples/lambda-laravel">Laravel on Lambda</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/aspnet-mvc">ASP.NET MVC</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/aspnet-mvc-zip">ASP.NET MVC in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/aspnet-webapi-zip">ASP.NET Web API in Zip</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/sqs-expressjs">SQS Express.js</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/bedrock-agent-fastapi">Bedrock Agent FastAPI</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/examples/bedrock-agent-fastapi-zip">Bedrock Agent FastAPI in Zip</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Acknowledgement</h2><a id="user-content-acknowledgement" aria-label="Permalink: Acknowledgement" href="#acknowledgement"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project was inspired by several community projects.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/apparentorder/reweb">re:Web</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/glassechidna/serverlessish">Serverlessish</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Similar Projects</h2><a id="user-content-similar-projects" aria-label="Permalink: Similar Projects" href="#similar-projects"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Several projects also provide similar capabilities as language specific packages/frameworks.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-serverless-java-container">Serverless Java Container</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/vendia/serverless-express">Serverless Express</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/zappa/Zappa">Serverless Python - Zappa</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/customink/lamby">Serverless Rails - Lamby</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/brefphp/bref">Serverless PHP - Bref</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Security</h2><a id="user-content-security" aria-label="Permalink: Security" href="#security"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See <a href="https://github.com/awslabs/aws-lambda-web-adapter/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md#security-issue-notifications">CONTRIBUTING</a> for more information.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">This project is licensed under the Apache-2.0 License.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Testing AMD's Bergamo: Zen 4c (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://chipsandcheese.com/2024/06/22/testing-amds-bergamo-zen-4c-spam/</link>
            <guid>40760687</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 17:36:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://chipsandcheese.com/2024/06/22/testing-amds-bergamo-zen-4c-spam/">https://chipsandcheese.com/2024/06/22/testing-amds-bergamo-zen-4c-spam/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40760687">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://chipsandcheese.com/2024/06/22/testing-amds-bergamo-zen-4c-spam/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Creative workers deserve better than a choice as to who rips them off (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/</link>
            <guid>40760042</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 16:08:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/">https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40760042">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-8989">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	
	
	<div>
		<p><!--
Tags:
openai, ai, llms, gai, generative ai, models, music, umg, universal music group, spotify, tiktok, copyfight, creative labor markets, chokepoint capitalism.

Summary:
Neither the devil you know nor the devil you don't; Hey look at this; Upcoming appearances; Recent appearances; Latest books; Upcoming books

URL:
https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/

Title:
Pluralistic: Neither the devil you know nor the devil you don't (21 Jun 2024) off-the-menu

Bullet:
🛺

Separator:
^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^-^

Top Sources:
None

--><br>
<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/"><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/21Jun2024.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></a></p>
<h2>Today's links</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#universally-loathed">Neither the devil you know nor the devil you don't</a>: Creative workers deserve better than a choice as to who rips them off.
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#linkdump">Hey look at this</a>: Delights to delectate.
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#retro">This day in history</a>: 2004, 2014, 2019
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#upcoming">Upcoming appearances</a>: Where to find me.
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#recent">Recent appearances</a>: Where I've been.
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#latest">Latest books</a>: You keep readin' em, I'll keep writin' 'em.
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#upcoming-books">Upcoming books</a>: Like I said, I'll keep writin' 'em.
</li>
<li><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#bragsheet">Colophon</a>: All the rest.
</li>
</ul>

<hr>
<p><a name="universally-loathed"></a><br>
<img decoding="async" alt="A pair of bethroned demons, identical save for different colored robes, face each other. The left demon's throne arm is emblazoned with the OpenAI logo. The right demon's throne bears the Universal Music Group logo. The two thrones are joined by a hellmouth - an anthropomorphic nightmare maw. The eyes of the demons and the hellmouth have been replaced with the glaring red machine-eye of HAL9000 from Kubrick's '2001: A Space Odyssey.' Between the demons toil two medieval serfs, bearing threshing implements." src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/the-devil-you-know.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<h2>Neither the devil you know nor the devil you don't (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#universally-loathed">permalink</a>)</h2>
<p>Spotify's relationship to artists can be kind of confusing. On the one hand, they pay a laughably low per-stream rate, as in homeopathic residues of a penny. On the other hand, the Big Three labels get a <em>fortune</em> from Spotify. And on the other other hand, it makes sense that rate for a stream heard by one person should be less than the rate for a song broadcast to thousands or millions of listeners.</p>
<p>But the whole thing makes sense once you understand the corporate history of Spotify. There's a whole chapter about this in Rebecca Giblin's and my 2022 book, <em>Chokepoint Capitalism</em>; we even made the audio for it a "Spotify exclusive" (it's the only part of the audiobook you can hear on Spotify, natch):</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2022/09/12/streaming-doesnt-pay/#stunt-publishing">https://pluralistic.net/2022/09/12/streaming-doesnt-pay/#stunt-publishing</a></p>
<p>Unlike online music predecessors like Napster, Spotify sought licenses from the labels for the music it made available. This gave those labels a <em>lot</em> of power over Spotify, but not all the labels, just three of them. Universal, Warner and Sony, the Big Three, control more than 70% of all music recordings, and more than 60% of all music compositions. These three companies are remarkably inbred. Their execs routinely hop from one to the other, and they regularly cross-license samples and other rights to each other.</p>
<p>The Big Three told Spotify that the price of licensing their catalogs would be high. First of all, Spotify had to give significant ownership stakes to all three labels. This put the labels in an unresolvable conflict of interest: as owners of Spotify, it was in their interests for licensing payments for music to be as low as possible. But as labels representing creative workers – musicians – it was in their interests for these payments to be as <em>high</em> as possible.</p>
<p>As it turns out, it wasn't hard to resolve that conflict after all. You see, the money the Big Three got in the form of dividends, stock sales, etc was theirs to spend as they saw fit. They could share some, all, or none of it with musicians. The Big Three's contracts with musicians gave those workers a guaranteed share of Spotify's licensing payments.</p>
<p>Accordingly, the Big Three demanded those rock-bottom per-stream rates that Spotify is notorious for. Yeah, it's true that a streaming per-listener payment should be lower than a radio per-play payment (which reaches thousands or millions of listeners), but even accounting for that, the math doesn't add up. Multiply the per-listener stream rate by the number of listeners for, say, a typical satellite radio cast, and Spotify is clearly getting a <em>massive</em> discount relative to other services that didn't make the Big Three into co-owners when they were kicking off.</p>
<p>But there's still something awry: the Big Three take in <em>gigantic fortunes</em> from Spotify in licensing payments. How can the per-stream rate be so low but the licensing payments be so large? And why are artists seeing so little?</p>
<p>Again, it's not hard to understand once you see the structure of Spotify's deal with the Big Three. The Big Three are each guaranteed a monthly minimum payment, irrespective of the number of Spotify streams from their catalog that month. So Sony might be guaranteed, say, $30m a month from Spotify, but the ultra-low per-stream rate Sony insisted on means that all the Sony streams in a typical month add up to $10m. That means that Sony still gets $30m from Spotify, but only $10m is "attributable" to a specific recording artist who can make a claim on it. The rest of the money is Sony's to play with: they can spread it around all their artists, some of their artists, or none of their artists. They can spend it on "artist development" (which might mean sending top execs on luxury junkets to big music festivals). It's theirs. The lower the per-stream rate is, the more of that minimum monthly payment is unattributable, meaning that Sony can line its pockets with it.</p>
<p>But these monthly minimums are just part of the goodies that the Big Three negotiated for themselves when they were designing Spotify. They also get free promo, advertising, and inclusion on Spotify's top playlists. Best (worst!) of all, the Big Three have "most favored nation" status, which means that every other label – the indies that rep the 30% of music not controlled by the Big Three – have to eat shit and take the ultra-low per-stream rate. Only those indies don't get billions in stock, they don't get monthly minimum guarantees, and they have to pay for promo, advertising, and inclusion on hot playlists.</p>
<p>When you understand the business mechanics of Spotify, all the contradictions resolve themselves. It is simultaneously true that Spotify pays a very low per-stream rate, that it pays the Big Three labels gigantic sums every month, and that artists are grotesquely underpaid by this system.</p>
<p>There are many lessons to take from this little scam, but for me, the top takeaway here is that artists are the class enemies of both Big Tech <em>and</em> Big Content. The Napster Wars demanded that artists ally themselves with either the tech sector or the entertainment center, nominating one or the other to be their champion.</p>
<p>But for a creative worker, it doesn't matter who makes a meal out of you, tech or content – all that matters is that you're being devoured.</p>
<p>This brings me to the debate over training AI and copyright. A lot of creative workers are justifiably angry and afraid that the AI companies want to destroy creative jobs. The CTO of Openai literally just said that onstage: "Some creative jobs maybe will go away, but maybe they shouldn’t have been there in the first place":</p>
<p><a href="https://bgr.com/tech/openai-cto-thinks-ai-will-kill-some-jobs-that-shouldnt-have-existed-in-the-first-place/">https://bgr.com/tech/openai-cto-thinks-ai-will-kill-some-jobs-that-shouldnt-have-existed-in-the-first-place/</a></p>
<p>Many of these workers are accordingly cheering on the entertainment industry's lawsuits over AI training. In these lawsuits, companies like the <em>New York Times</em> and Getty Images claim that the steps associated with training an AI model infringe copyright. This isn't a great copyright theory based on current copyright precedents, and if the suits succeed, they'll narrow fair use in ways that will impact all kinds of socially beneficial activities, like scraping the web to make the Internet Archive's Wayback Machine:</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/05/13/spooky-action-at-a-close-up/#invisible-hand">https://pluralistic.net/2024/05/13/spooky-action-at-a-close-up/#invisible-hand</a></p>
<p>But you can't make an omelet without breaking eggs, right? For some creative workers, legal uncertainty for computational linguists, search engines, and archiving projects are a small price to pay if it means keeping AI from destroying their livelihoods.</p>
<p>Here's the problem: establishing that AI training requires a copyright license <em>will not</em> stop AI from being used to erode the wages and working conditions of creative workers. The companies suing over AI training are also notorious exploiters of creative workers, union-busters and wage-stealers. They don't want to get rid of generative AI, they just want to get paid for the content used to create it. Their use-case for gen AI is the same as Openai's CTO's use-case: get rid of creative jobs and pay less for creative labor.</p>
<p>This isn't hypothetical. Remember last summer's actor strike? The sticking point was that the studios wanted to pay actors a single fee to scan their bodies and faces, and then use those scans instead of hiring those actors, forever, without ever paying them again. Does it matter to an actor whether the AI that replaces you at Warner, Sony, Universal, Disney or Paramount (yes, three of the Big Five studios are also the Big Three labels!) was made by Openai without paying the studios for the training material, or whether Openai paid a license fee that the studios kept?</p>
<p>This is true across the board. The Big Five publishers categorically refuse to include contractual language promising not to train an LLM with the books they acquire from writers. The game studios require all their voice actors to start every recording session with an on-tape assignment of the training rights to the session:</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2023/02/09/ai-monkeys-paw/#bullied-schoolkids">https://pluralistic.net/2023/02/09/ai-monkeys-paw/#bullied-schoolkids</a></p>
<p>And now, with total predictability, Universal – the largest music company in the world – has announced that it will start training voice-clones with the music in its catalog:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/umg-startsai-voice-clone-partnership-with-soundlabs-1235041808/">https://www.rollingstone.com/music/music-news/umg-startsai-voice-clone-partnership-with-soundlabs-1235041808/</a></p>
<p>This comes hot on the heels of a massive blow-up between Universal and Tiktok, in which Universal professed its outrage that Tiktok was going to train voice-clones with the music Universal licensed to it. In other words: Universal's copyright claims over AI training cash out to this: "If anyone is going to profit from immiserating musicians, it's going to be us, not Tiktok."</p>
<p>I understand why Universal would like this idea. I just don't understand why any musician would root for Universal to defeat Tiktok, or Getty Images to trounce Stable Diffusion. Do you really think that Getty Images <em>likes</em> paying photographers and wants to give them a single penny more than they absolutely have to?</p>
<p>As we learned from George Orwell's avant-garde animated agricultural documentary <em>Animal Farm</em>, the problem isn't who holds the whip, the problem is the whip itself:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  The creatures outside looked from pig to man, and from man to pig, and from pig to man again; but already it was impossible to say which was which.
</p></blockquote>
<p>Entertainment execs and tech execs alike are obsessed with AI because they view the future of "content" as fundamentally passive. Here's Ryan Broderick putting it better than I ever could:</p>
<blockquote><p>
  At a certain audience size, you just assume those people are locked in and will consume anything you throw at them. Then it just becomes a game of lowering your production costs and increasing your prices to increase your margins. This is why executives love AI and why the average American can’t afford to eat at McDonald’s anymore.
</p></blockquote>
<p><a href="https://www.garbageday.email/p/ceo-passive-content-obsession">https://www.garbageday.email/p/ceo-passive-content-obsession</a></p>
<p>Here's a rule of thumb for tech policy prescriptions. Any time you find yourself, as a worker, rooting for the same policy as your boss, you should check and make sure you're on the right side of history. The fact that creative bosses are so obsessed with making copyright cover more kinds of works, restrict more activities, lasting longer and generating higher damages should make creative workers look askance at these proposals.</p>
<p>After 40 years of expanded copyright, we have a creative industry that's larger and more profitable than ever, and yet the share of income going to creative workers has been in steady decline over that entire period. Every year, the share of creative income that creative workers can lay claim to declines, both proportionally and in real terms.</p>
<p>As with the mystery of Spotify's payments, this isn't a mystery at all. You just need to understand that when creators are stuck bargaining with a tiny, powerful cartel of movie, TV, music, publishing, streaming, games or app companies, it doesn't matter how much copyright they have to bargain with. Giving a creative worker more copyright is like giving a bullied schoolkid more lunch-money. There's no amount of money that will satisfy the bullies and leave enough left over for the kid to buy lunch. They just take <em>everything</em>.</p>
<p>Telling creative workers that they can solve their declining wages with more copyright is a denial that creative workers are <em>workers</em> at all. It treats us as entrepreneurial small businesses, LLCs with MFAs negotiating B2B with other companies. That's how we lose.</p>
<p>On the other hand, if we address the problems of AI and labor as <em>workers</em>, and insist on labor rights – like the Writers Guild did when it struck last summer – then we ally ourselves with every other worker whose wages and working conditions are being attacked with AI:</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2023/10/01/how-the-writers-guild-sunk-ais-ship/">https://pluralistic.net/2023/10/01/how-the-writers-guild-sunk-ais-ship/</a></p>
<p>Our path to better working conditions lies through organizing and striking, not through helping our bosses sue other giant mulitnational corporations for the right to bleed us out.</p>
<p>The US Copyright Office has repeatedly stated that AI-generated works don't qualify for copyrights, meaning everything AI generated can be freely copied and distributed and the companies that make them can't stop them. This is <em>fantastic</em> news, because the only thing our bosses hate more than paying us is not being able to stop other people from copying the things we make for them. We should be shouting this from the rooftops, not demanding <em>more</em> copyright for AI.</p>
<p>Here's a thing: FTC chair Lina Khan recently told an audience that she was thinking of using her Section 5 powers (to regulate "unfair and deceptive" conduct) to go after AI training:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3mh8Z5pcJpg">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3mh8Z5pcJpg</a></p>
<p>Khan has already used these Section 5 powers to secure labor rights, for example, by banning noncompetes:</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/04/25/capri-v-tapestry/#aiming-at-dollars-not-men">https://pluralistic.net/2024/04/25/capri-v-tapestry/#aiming-at-dollars-not-men</a></p>
<p>Creative workers should be banding together with other labor advocates to propose ways for the FTC to prevent <em>all</em> AI-based labor exploitation, like the "reverse-centaur" arrangement in which a human serves as an AI's body, working at breakneck pace until they are psychologically and physically ruined:</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/2022/04/17/revenge-of-the-chickenized-reverse-centaurs/">https://pluralistic.net/2022/04/17/revenge-of-the-chickenized-reverse-centaurs/</a></p>
<p>As workers standing with other workers, we can demand the things that help us, even (especially) when that means less for our bosses. On the other hand, if we confine ourselves to backing our bosses' plays, we only stand to gain whatever crumbs they choose to drop at their feet for us.</p>
<hr>

<h2>Hey look at this (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#linkdump">permalink</a>)</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/heylookatthis.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<ul>
<li>The CEO Passive Content Obsession <a href="https://www.garbageday.email/p/ceo-passive-content-obsession">https://www.garbageday.email/p/ceo-passive-content-obsession</a>
</li>
<li>
<p>Fungal banking <a href="https://crookedtimber.org/2024/06/20/occasional-paper-fungal-banking/">https://crookedtimber.org/2024/06/20/occasional-paper-fungal-banking/</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Gene Nora Jessen, Pioneering Aviator Who Was Part of an Enigmatic ‘Woman in Space Program,’ Dies at 87 <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/gene-nora-jessen-pioneer-aviator-dead-87-dd960d2f?st=ife24pnayefd5ap&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink">https://www.wsj.com/business/gene-nora-jessen-pioneer-aviator-dead-87-dd960d2f?st=ife24pnayefd5ap&amp;reflink=desktopwebshare_permalink</a> (h/t Taylor Jessen)</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><a name="retro"></a><br>
<img decoding="async" alt="A Wayback Machine banner." src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/wayback-machine-hed-796x416.png?resize=796%2C416&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<h2>This day in history (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#retro">permalink</a>)</h2>
<p>#20yrsago Tunneling ssh over DNS <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20040916193409/http://www.doxpara.com/bo2004.ppt">https://web.archive.org/web/20040916193409/http://www.doxpara.com/bo2004.ppt</a></p>
<p>#10yrsago Open Wireless Movement’s router OS will let you securely share your Internet with the world <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2014/06/new-router-firmware-safely-opens-your-wi-fi-network-to-strangers/">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2014/06/new-router-firmware-safely-opens-your-wi-fi-network-to-strangers/</a></p>
<p>#10yrsago Steve Wozniak wants you to support Mayday.US and get money out of politics <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZoZ-tJiwBvc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZoZ-tJiwBvc</a></p>
<p>#10yrsago Gangs run mass-scale romance cons with phished dating-site logins <a href="https://www.netcraft.com/blog/criminals-launch-mass-phishing-attacks-against-online-dating-sites/">https://www.netcraft.com/blog/criminals-launch-mass-phishing-attacks-against-online-dating-sites/</a></p>
<p>#10yrsago Greenhouse: browser plugin that automatically annotates politicians’ names with their funders <a href="https://allaregreen.us/">https://allaregreen.us</a></p>
<p>#10yrsago Judy Blume: parents shouldn’t worry about what their kids are reading <a href="https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/hay-festival/10868544/Judy-Blume-Parents-worry-too-much-about-what-children-read.html">https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/hay-festival/10868544/Judy-Blume-Parents-worry-too-much-about-what-children-read.html</a></p>
<p>#5yrsago Learning from Baltimore’s disaster, Florida city will pay criminals $600,000 to get free of ransomware attack <a href="https://apnews.com/article/0762caec21874fc09741abbdec0f78ab">https://apnews.com/article/0762caec21874fc09741abbdec0f78ab</a></p>
<p>#5yrsago Elizabeth Warren proposes a ban on private prisons and immigration facilities <a href="https://medium.com/@teamwarren/ending-private-prisons-and-exploitation-for-profit-cb6dea67e913">https://medium.com/@teamwarren/ending-private-prisons-and-exploitation-for-profit-cb6dea67e913</a></p>
<p>#5yrsago Google Maps is still overrun with scammers pretending to be local businesses, and Google’s profiting from them <a href="https://tech.slashdot.org/story/19/06/20/1746232/millions-of-business-listings-on-google-maps-are-fake----and-google-profits">https://tech.slashdot.org/story/19/06/20/1746232/millions-of-business-listings-on-google-maps-are-fake—-and-google-profits</a></p>
<p>#5yrsago America can only go to war against Iran if it reinstates the draft <a href="https://www.usatoday.com/story/opinion/2018/05/31/iran-regime-change-american-troops-military-draft-column/656240002/">https://www.usatoday.com/story/opinion/2018/05/31/iran-regime-change-american-troops-military-draft-column/656240002/</a></p>
<p>#5yrsago Independent audit finds Facebook activity has fallen by 20% since Cambridge Analytica <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/jun/20/facebook-usage-collapsed-since-scandal-data-shows">https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2019/jun/20/facebook-usage-collapsed-since-scandal-data-shows</a></p>
<p>#5yrsago Tennessee lawmaker defends operating an unregistered “Christian magic supply” business <a href="https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/politics/2019/06/20/matthew-hill-tennessee-house-speaker-christian-magic-supply-business-dock-haley-gospel-magic/1481310001/">https://www.tennessean.com/story/news/politics/2019/06/20/matthew-hill-tennessee-house-speaker-christian-magic-supply-business-dock-haley-gospel-magic/1481310001/</a></p>
<hr>

<h2>Upcoming appearances (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#upcoming">permalink</a>)</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" alt="A photo of me onstage, giving a speech, holding a mic." src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/appearances.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<ul>
<li>Locus Awards reading (virtual), Jun 21<br>
<a href="https://locusmag.com/2024-locus-awards-weekend/">https://locusmag.com/2024-locus-awards-weekend/</a>
</li>
<li>
<p>Locus Awards keynote (Oakland), Jun 22<br>
<a href="https://locusmag.com/2024-locus-awards-weekend/">https://locusmag.com/2024-locus-awards-weekend/</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>HOPE XV, Jul 14 (Queens, NY)<br>
<a href="https://www.hope.net/talks.html">https://www.hope.net/talks.html</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Exile in Bookville, (Chicago), July 20<br>
<a href="https://exileinbookville.com/events/39808">https://exileinbookville.com/events/39808</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>American Association of Law Libraries keynote (Chicago), Jul 21<br>
<a href="https://www.aallnet.org/conference/agenda/keynote-speaker/">https://www.aallnet.org/conference/agenda/keynote-speaker/</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><a name="recent"></a><br>
<img decoding="async" alt="A screenshot of me at my desk, doing a livecast." src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/recentappearances.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<h2>Recent appearances (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#recent">permalink</a>)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Living Your Principles<br>
<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UTfqxF5KyCc">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UTfqxF5KyCc</a>
</li>
<li>
<p>Reimagining the Internet<br>
<a href="https://publicinfrastructure.org/podcast/102-cory-doctorow-enshittification/">https://publicinfrastructure.org/podcast/102-cory-doctorow-enshittification/</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Circulating ideas<br>
<a href="https://circulatingideas.com/2024/06/11/261-the-bezzle-by-cory-doctorow-summer-reading-spectacular/">https://circulatingideas.com/2024/06/11/261-the-bezzle-by-cory-doctorow-summer-reading-spectacular/</a></p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><a name="latest"></a><br>
<img decoding="async" alt="A grid of my books with Will Stahle covers.." src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/recent.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<h2>Latest books (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#latest">permalink</a>)</h2>
<ul>
<li>The Bezzle: a sequel to "Red Team Blues," about prison-tech and other grifts, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), February 2024 (<a href="http://the-bezzle.org/">the-bezzle.org</a>). Signed, personalized copies at Dark Delicacies (<a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p3062/Available_Feb_20th%3A_The_Bezzle_HB.html#/">https://www.darkdel.com/store/p3062/Available_Feb_20th%3A_The_Bezzle_HB.html#/</a>).
</li>
<li>
<p>"The Lost Cause:" a solarpunk novel of hope in the climate emergency, Tor Books (US), Head of Zeus (UK), November 2023 (<a href="http://lost-cause.org/">http://lost-cause.org</a>). Signed, personalized copies at Dark Delicacies (<a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p3007/Pre-Order_Signed_Copies%3A_The_Lost_Cause_HB.html#/">https://www.darkdel.com/store/p3007/Pre-Order_Signed_Copies%3A_The_Lost_Cause_HB.html#/</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"The Internet Con": A nonfiction book about interoperability and Big Tech (Verso) September 2023 (<a href="http://seizethemeansofcomputation.org/">http://seizethemeansofcomputation.org</a>). Signed copies at Book Soup (<a href="https://www.booksoup.com/book/9781804291245">https://www.booksoup.com/book/9781804291245</a>).</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"Red Team Blues": "A grabby, compulsive thriller that will leave you knowing more about how the world works than you did before." Tor Books <a href="http://redteamblues.com/">http://redteamblues.com</a>. Signed copies at Dark Delicacies (US): <a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p2873/Wed%2C_Apr_26th_6pm%3A_Red_Team_Blues%3A_A_Martin_Hench_Novel_HB.html#/"> and Forbidden Planet (UK): </a><a href="https://forbiddenplanet.com/385004-red-team-blues-signed-edition-hardcover/">https://forbiddenplanet.com/385004-red-team-blues-signed-edition-hardcover/</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"Chokepoint Capitalism: How to Beat Big Tech, Tame Big Content, and Get Artists Paid, with Rebecca Giblin", on how to unrig the markets for creative labor, Beacon Press/Scribe 2022 <a href="https://chokepointcapitalism.com/">https://chokepointcapitalism.com</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"Attack Surface": The third Little Brother novel, a standalone technothriller for adults. The <em>Washington Post</em> called it "a political cyberthriller, vigorous, bold and savvy about the limits of revolution and resistance." Order signed, personalized copies from Dark Delicacies <a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p1840/Available_Now%3A_Attack_Surface.html">https://www.darkdel.com/store/p1840/Available_Now%3A_Attack_Surface.html</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"How to Destroy Surveillance Capitalism": an anti-monopoly pamphlet analyzing the true harms of surveillance capitalism and proposing a solution. <a href="https://onezero.medium.com/how-to-destroy-surveillance-capitalism-8135e6744d59?sk=f6cd10e54e20a07d4c6d0f3ac011af6b">https://onezero.medium.com/how-to-destroy-surveillance-capitalism-8135e6744d59?sk=f6cd10e54e20a07d4c6d0f3ac011af6b</a>) (signed copies: <a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p2024/Available_Now%3A__How_to_Destroy_Surveillance_Capitalism.html">https://www.darkdel.com/store/p2024/Available_Now%3A__How_to_Destroy_Surveillance_Capitalism.html</a>)</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"Little Brother/Homeland": A reissue omnibus edition with a new introduction by Edward Snowden: <a href="https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781250774583">https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781250774583</a>; personalized/signed copies here: <a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p1750/July%3A__Little_Brother_%26_Homeland.html">https://www.darkdel.com/store/p1750/July%3A__Little_Brother_%26_Homeland.html</a></p>
</li>
<li>
<p>"Poesy the Monster Slayer" a picture book about monsters, bedtime, gender, and kicking ass. Order here: <a href="https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781626723627">https://us.macmillan.com/books/9781626723627</a>. Get a personalized, signed copy here: <a href="https://www.darkdel.com/store/p2682/Corey_Doctorow%3A_Poesy_the_Monster_Slayer_HB.html#/">https://www.darkdel.com/store/p2682/Corey_Doctorow%3A_Poesy_the_Monster_Slayer_HB.html#/</a>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><a name="upcoming-books"></a><br>
<img decoding="async" alt="A cardboard book box with the Macmillan logo." src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/upcoming-books.jpg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<h2>Upcoming books (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#upcoming-books">permalink</a>)</h2>
<ul>
<li>Picks and Shovels: a sequel to "Red Team Blues," about the heroic era of the PC, Tor Books, February 2025
</li>
<li>
<p>Unauthorized Bread: a middle-grades graphic novel adapted from my novella about refugees, toasters and DRM, FirstSecond, 2025</p>
</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><a name="bragsheet"></a><br>
<img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/colophonimages.jpeg?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<h2>Colophon (<a href="https://pluralistic.net/2024/06/21/off-the-menu/#bragsheet">permalink</a>)</h2>
<p>Today's top sources:</p>
<p><b>Currently writing: </b></p>
<ul>
<li>Enshittification: a nonfiction book about platform decay. Today's progress: 774 words (15308 words total).
</li>
<li>
<p>A Little Brother short story about DIY insulin PLANNING</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Picks and Shovels, a Martin Hench noir thriller about the heroic era of the PC. FORTHCOMING TOR BOOKS JAN 2025</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Vigilant, Little Brother short story about remote invigilation. FORTHCOMING ON TOR.COM</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Spill, a Little Brother short story about pipeline protests. FORTHCOMING ON TOR.COM</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Latest podcast:</b> My 2004 Microsoft DRM Talk <a href="https://craphound.com/news/2024/06/16/my-2004-microsoft-drm-talk/">https://craphound.com/news/2024/06/16/my-2004-microsoft-drm-talk/&gt;</a></p>
<hr>
<p><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/craphound.com/images/by.svg.png?w=840&amp;ssl=1" data-recalc-dims="1"></p>
<p>This work – excluding any serialized fiction – is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 license. That means you can use it any way you like, including commercially, provided that you attribute it to me, Cory Doctorow, and include a link to pluralistic.net.</p>
<p><a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></p>
<p>Quotations and images are not included in this license; they are included either under a limitation or exception to copyright, or on the basis of a separate license. Please exercise caution.</p>
<hr>
<h2>How to get Pluralistic:</h2>
<p>Blog (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):</p>
<p><a href="http://pluralistic.net/">Pluralistic.net</a></p>
<p>Newsletter (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):</p>
<p><a href="https://pluralistic.net/plura-list">https://pluralistic.net/plura-list</a></p>
<p>Mastodon (no ads, tracking, or data-collection):</p>
<p><a href="https://mamot.fr/@pluralistic">https://mamot.fr/@pluralistic</a></p>
<p>Medium (no ads, paywalled):</p>
<p><a href="https://doctorow.medium.com/">https://doctorow.medium.com/</a></p>
<p>Twitter (mass-scale, unrestricted, third-party surveillance and advertising):</p>
<p><a href="https://twitter.com/doctorow">https://twitter.com/doctorow</a></p>
<p>Tumblr (mass-scale, unrestricted, third-party surveillance and advertising):</p>
<p><a href="https://mostlysignssomeportents.tumblr.com/tagged/pluralistic">https://mostlysignssomeportents.tumblr.com/tagged/pluralistic</a></p>
<p>"<em>When life gives you SARS, you make sarsaparilla</em>" -Joey "Accordion Guy" DeVilla</p>

	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	<!-- .entry-footer -->
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HybridNeRF: Efficient Neural Rendering (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://haithemturki.com/hybrid-nerf/</link>
            <guid>40759333</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 14:21:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://haithemturki.com/hybrid-nerf/">https://haithemturki.com/hybrid-nerf/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40759333">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <div>
        <h3>Eyeful Tower Comparisons</h3>
        </div>
    <figure>
        <figcaption>
            We compare HybridNeRF to prior work (FPS shown for 2Kx2K rendering on a single Nvidia 4090 GPU). <a href="https://creiser.github.io/merf/">MERF</a>, <a href="https://repo-sam.inria.fr/fungraph/3d-gaussian-splatting/">3DGS</a>, and <a href="https://lioryariv.github.io/volsdf/">VolSDF<sup>*</sup></a> (our implementation using iNGP accleration primitives) do not support training models in HDR and therefore do not support exposure adjustments.
        </figcaption>
        <figcaption id="eyeful-comparison">
            Our quality is slightly better than <a href="https://vr-nerf.github.io/">VR-NeRF</a> while rendering over 10x faster. Our results are significantly better than faster rendering approaches, especially when modeling specular effects.
        </figcaption>
        <video width="90%" controls="" id="eyeful-video">
            <source src="https://haithemturki.com/hybrid-nerf/vids/workshop.mp4" type="video/mp4" poster="https://haithemturki.com/hybrid-nerf/images/workshop.jpg">
        </video>
    </figure>
</div><div>
    <p>
        <h3>Citation</h3>
    </p>
    <figure>
        <pre><code>@InProceedings{turki2024hybridnerf,
      title={HybridNeRF: Efficient Neural Rendering via Adaptive Volumetric Surfaces}, 
      author={Haithem Turki and Vasu Agrawal and Samuel Rota Bulò and Lorenzo Porzi and Peter Kontschieder and Deva Ramanan and Michael Zollh\"{o}fer and Christian Richardt},
      booktitle = {Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition (CVPR)},
      year={2024}
}</code></pre>
    </figure>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Andrew S. Tanenbaum Receives ACM Software System Award (334 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vu.nl/en/news/2024/andrew-s-tanenbaum-receives-acm-software-system-award</link>
            <guid>40759277</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 14:12:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vu.nl/en/news/2024/andrew-s-tanenbaum-receives-acm-software-system-award">https://vu.nl/en/news/2024/andrew-s-tanenbaum-receives-acm-software-system-award</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40759277">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>
                        Andrew S. Tanenbaum, professor emeritus of Computer Science at VU Amsterdam, receives the ACM Software System Award for MINIX, which influenced the teaching of Operating Systems principles to multiple generations of students and contributed to the design of widely used operating systems, including Linux. 
                    </p><div><p>Tanenbaum created MINIX 1.0 in 1987 to accompany his textbook, <em>Operating Systems: Design and Implementation</em>.&nbsp; MINIX was a small microkernel-based UNIX operating system for the IBM PC, which was popular at the time. It was roughly 12,000 lines of code, and in addition to the microkernel, included a memory manager, file system and core UNIX utility programs. It became free open-source software in 2000.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p><strong>Inspiration for LINUX</strong>&nbsp;<br>
Beyond enabling the success of Tanenbaum’s textbook, the impact of MINIX has been phenomenal. It was an inspiration for LINUX, which has grown into the most successful open-source operating system powering cloud servers, mobile phones and Internet of Things devices.&nbsp; MINIX was also the basis for the MeikOS operating system for Meikotransputer-based computers and runs inside popular microchips. A later version of MINIX, MINIX 3.0 is intended for resource-limited and embedded computers and for applications requiring high reliability. Beyond the direct impact of MINIX, Tanenbaum’s advocacy for microkernel design has impacted generations of operating system designers.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p><a href="https://awards.acm.org/software-system">The ACM Software System Award</a> is presented to an institution or individual(s) recognized for developing a software system that has had a lasting influence, reflected in contributions to concepts, in commercial acceptance, or both. The Software System Award carries a prize of $35,000. Financial support for the Software System Award is provided by IBM.&nbsp;</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[After my dad died, I ran and sold his company (2018) (731 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://anandsanwal.me/2018/06/19/dad-company-sale/</link>
            <guid>40758767</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 12:49:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://anandsanwal.me/2018/06/19/dad-company-sale/">https://anandsanwal.me/2018/06/19/dad-company-sale/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40758767">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>From tech in NYC to chemical manufacturing in Nasik (India), here’s a guide that hopefully nobody ever needs.</p>



<p>On April 17, 2017 my dad died.</p>



<p>It was the worst day of my life.</p>



<p>It was also the day I started to lead a second company – his company. (Note: the first company is CB Insights.)</p>



<p>His company was in India (a country I knew little about) in the chemical manufacturing industry (an industry I knew nothing about).</p>



<p>On June 1st, 2018, after running his company for 13 months, it was acquired.</p>



<p>While I don’t think most people would ever find themselves in a similar situation (I certainly hope not), I thought I’d share the story and some of my learnings &amp; observations from that time about business, M&amp;A, teams, India, and assorted miscellaneous thoughts.</p>



<p>Notes: &nbsp;This will probably be slightly rambly and stream-of-consciousness as there are lots of thoughts rolling around in my head.</p>



<p>So, here we go…</p>



<p>Warning: this is going to be long so a table of contents is below.</p>



<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#life">Life comes at you fast</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#newgig">Day 1 in my new gig</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#plan">What the F is the plan?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#running">Running a business you know nothing about</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#coldcalls">Growth the old-fashioned way — cold calling and cold emailing prospects and customers</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#buyers">The M&amp;A buyers show up</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#sold">June 1st — Atlas is officially sold</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#farewell">The official farewell</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#CBimpact">What was the impact on CB Insights?</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#differences">The differences between CB Insights and Atlas</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#ma">Thoughts on M&amp;A</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#india">Thoughts on India</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#tech">Thoughts on technology &amp; data</a></li>



<li><a href="https://www.anandsanwal.me/dad-company-sale/#thanks">Thank you’s</a></li>
</ul>



<h3 id="life"><strong>Life comes at you fast</strong></h3>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18125433/atlas-1024x768.png?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>As I was going with family to cremate my father in a traditional Hindu funeral, someone who I didn’t know came up to me and said in Hindi, “<em>Saab, humara kya hoga?</em>”</p>



<p>That translates to “Sir, what will happen to us?”</p>



<p>I didn’t know who it was.</p>



<p>I assumed it was a worker from my Dad’s factory.</p>



<p>I was a mess at the time.</p>



<p>And I remember thinking to myself, “Why the F are you asking me about this right now?”</p>



<p>But this wasn’t the time for anger or to even to think about this so I just knee-jerk responded in my heavily American-accented Hindi that “<em>Meh dekh loonga</em>” which translates to “I’ll look after it.”</p>



<p>And so at that point, in addition to CB Insights, I knew I was going to run my Dad’s business. To be honest, I had already thought about this possibility when he was admitted to the hospital when the doctors said the situation was looking dire. &nbsp;</p>



<p>But no matter my age, Dad was always the strongest, smartest person I knew, and so I assumed he’d pull through and things would go back to normal. With him tirelessly working on Atlas, the company he founded, and me going back to CB Insights.</p>



<p>But then April 17th happened.</p>



<p>And now, I was going to run his business.</p>



<p>I was going to run Atlas.</p>



<p>I wasn’t ready for this.</p>



<p>Before we go further, a bit of context on Atlas, my Dad’s business.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18125705/atlas-outside-1024x680.png?resize=1024%2C680&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>The company was recently renamed AIMS Impex, but it started and for most of its life, it was known as Atlas Fine Chemicals. Industry folks know it as Atlas, and my sisters and I grew up knowing it under that name so I will refer to it as Atlas going forward. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Atlas is a manufacturer of specialty flavor &amp; fragrance chemicals such as coumarin, 6-methyl coumarin, safranal, natural vanilla, and cyclocitral among others. Atlas’ customers include the world’s largest flavor &amp; fragrance houses including IFF, Givaudan, Firmenich, Takasago, and Symrise among others.</p>



<p>Atlas is based 4 hours from Mumbai in a city called Nasik (1.486 million people) and the manufacturing facility is about 35 minutes from Nasik in a small village called Sinnar.</p>



<p>If there ever was a polar opposite to CB Insights, it’s Atlas. &nbsp;</p>



<p>CB Insights is a technology company.</p>



<p>Atlas is an industrial manufacturing company. &nbsp;</p>



<p>(note: more on the differences below)</p>



<p>But here we were.</p>



<h3 id="newgig"><strong>Day 1 in my new gig</strong></h3>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18130130/good-quality-1024x768.png?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>I don’t remember the exact day I went to the office for the first time as the weeks after April 17th were a blur of family, tradition, and emotion.</p>



<p>Before even stepping foot in the office, I had asked the team to send me the reports they sent to Dad so I could get familiar with the business.</p>



<p>TBH, I didn’t know what I’d do with these reports, but I figured that acting like I knew what I might be doing might provide some confidence to the team. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Candidly, my only qualification to run Atlas at this time was that I was the founder’s son.</p>



<p>I had tried to be the good Indian son back in 1998-2000 and work at Atlas so knew the biz a bit in its earlier days, but 18 years is a long time for a business and my mind was jammed with all sorts of other experiences and ideas since then. My time at Atlas was just a distant memory.</p>



<p>In 1998, moving from the fun of NYC to small town India was tough especially as someone born and brought up in the US. Moreover, I was a know-it-all who had all the answers despite just graduating from college and so my dad’s inability to recognize my genius bothered me.</p>



<p>And so after 18 months working with Dad, I left to join Kozmo.com.</p>



<p>(Yes –&nbsp;<a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research/biggest-startup-failures/">that Kozmo that spectacularly failed</a>. Clearly, I had great judgment.)</p>



<p>I still wonder what Atlas might have become if I could have figured out how to be more of a student and less of an Ivy League douche when I was working with my dad back then. What kind of duo might we have been?</p>



<p>So, in a strange and sad way, this was an opportunity to finally be the good Indian son and run Dad’s business.</p>



<p>In late April, I finally went to the office.</p>



<p>When I entered, everyone stood up to greet me. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Nobody called me Anand.</p>



<p>I was referred to as Sir, which is what everyone referred to my father as.</p>



<p>Yup — this felt strange.</p>



<p>I remember thinking this was odd at the time, and during all my visits to the office subsequently, but in many ways, this sort of cultural deference to the unqualified boss’ son is what enabled Atlas to carry on.</p>



<p>I imagine if the same had happened in the US, there would have been many more questions about my qualifications and capabilities. At Atlas, those conversations might have very well happened, but I doubt it. Or, if they did, these questions weren’t directed to me. I got lucky here.</p>



<p>Everyone, for better or worse, assumed I had a clue and was looking for me to develop a plan.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18130425/hardhats-1024x680.png?resize=1024%2C680&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<h3 id="plan"><strong>What the F is the plan?</strong></h3>



<p>So I needed a plan. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Not on day 1, but pretty quickly.</p>



<p>Not because anyone was asking for one, but for myself. For Atlas.</p>



<p>How does one develop a plan when you don’t understand the business, the science, the industry, the country, and sometimes even the language? (I have passable Hindi but a lot of the local conversations at Atlas were in Marathi which I don’t understand.)</p>



<p>In my view, there were 4 options for the business.</p>



<h5 id="option1"><strong>Option 1 — Run the business and become this huge multi-industry conglomerate</strong></h5>



<p>I entertained Option 1 for about 6 weeks. The ill-conceived idea was that I’d figure out how to run both Atlas and CB Insights, going forward with Atlas&nbsp;as the beachhead for a larger industrials business and CB Insights&nbsp;as the first part of a massive technology arm.</p>



<p>Visions of grandeur and all that good stuff.</p>



<p>This was some stupid, naive thinking. &nbsp;</p>



<p>In India, you see all these families (Ambani, Birla, Tata, Godrej, Hinduja, etc) who are in every potential business line possible. I figured they all started somewhere. Maybe this would be my starting point.</p>



<p>After about 6 weeks of trying to be present at CB Insights, but doing calls every morning at 6am with the Atlas team and emails every evening responding to the team or to Atlas customers, it became apparent that Option 1 wasn’t feasible.</p>



<p>I kept this 6am morning call/evening email routine going for the last 13 months with CB Insights occupying the middle of the day and every other minute of idle brain time. Needless to say, I’ve aged immeasurably in the last 13 months. My desire to build a multi-industry conglomerate died because the idea was just too tiring.</p>



<h5 id="option2"><strong>Option 2 — Sell the company for its parts</strong></h5>



<p>For a second, I looked at what the company might fetch for its assets. Its land, plant, etc.</p>



<p>I’d never done something like this but I remember hearing about it when Gordon Gecko talked about it in the movie&nbsp;<em>Wall Street</em>&nbsp;so figured, why not?</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18130852/gecko.png?ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>If the strategy works in movies, it must work in real life too, right?</p>



<p>But this wasn’t a real option ever and was discounted in a few hours.</p>



<p>My dad built this company over 30 years with many of his team having been with him for 20+. Selling the company’s assets, even if feasible, would be me failing his team and him. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Not going to happen.</p>



<h5 id="option3"><strong>Option 3 — Find a young, aggressive, ambitious person to run Atlas</strong></h5>



<p>The third idea was to see if there was someone who could run Atlas with some guidance from Dad’s team and me (assuming I could eventually understand the business). And then give this person the ability to earn more and more equity over time.</p>



<p>Essentially, they’d run the company and eventually own it.</p>



<p>This idea was appealing as it’d let my family continue to be involved with the business while also finding someone capable to take it to the next level.</p>



<p>The problem here was that I had no network in India from which to even think about finding someone for this role. I spoke with a couple of candidates via introductions but nothing really stuck for them or me. Moving to Nasik was a challenge even for those in India, but that was just a symptom of not finding the right person.</p>



<p>This would have been an amazing opportunity for the right person, but it wasn’t in the cards.</p>



<h5 id="option4"><strong>Option 4 — Run the business until a buyer can be found</strong></h5>



<p>Option 4 was ultimately the most practical. &nbsp;</p>



<p>The challenge, however, was that Dad’s business didn’t have too many natural buyers and was considered a small market transaction making it even tougher.</p>



<p>And so I didn’t have any control on the M&amp;A side of things. &nbsp;</p>



<p>I focused on running the business and hoped a suitable acquirer would show up. If nobody showed up, I’d keep running it.</p>



<p>I gave myself 3 years to run both Atlas and CB Insights, thinking I could maintain the daily schedule of 6am calls and evening emails with India interspersed, with trips every 6-8 weeks before burning out. 3 years was a completely arbitrary timeline.</p>



<p>About 6 months in, I realized doing both for that long really wasn’t sustainable for a number of reasons — health, family, and it wasn’t optimal for either CB Insights or Atlas.</p>



<p>But I didn’t know the buyer market and couldn’t control it so I focused on what I could control.</p>



<p>And that was running Atlas.</p>



<h3 id="running"><strong>Running a business you know nothing about</strong></h3>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18131259/running-atlas-1024x768.png?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>Despite Atlas being very different than CB Insights, the answer about how to run it came to me easier than a lot of the other questions I had over the last 13 months.</p>



<p>Or perhaps I just oversimplified it to make a decision quickly.</p>



<p>I decided that business is about growth or margin.</p>



<p>To grow, we could do 1 of 2 things:</p>



<ul>
<li>Sell more of our existing products — primarily Coumarin</li>



<li>Add new products</li>
</ul>



<p>If we focused on margin, that’d mean focusing on:</p>



<ul>
<li>Increasing efficiency in manufacturing</li>



<li>Reducing expenses</li>
</ul>



<p>I looked at the financials for Atlas vs peers in the industry and talked to some of my dad’s trusted advisors, and it was apparent that Atlas’ margins were best-in-industry.</p>



<p>Dad was the ultimate bootstrapper. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Atlas was efficient, and my dad obsessed about margins, foregoing business that was low margin to keep overall profit margins high.</p>



<p>It was clear that focusing on the margin side wasn’t the best place for my time or energy. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Plus, most of the efficiency to be gained was in the manufacturing process and that is where I was zero value-add. Dad was also the ultimate technical co-founder. I was as non-technical as they come in a chemical manufacturing setting. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Plus, margin is hard to rally the team around. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Growth is tangible.</p>



<p>And I needed to paint a picture that the team could see. Improving margin by XX basis points wasn’t going to be what got anyone fired up.</p>



<p>So I decided to focus on growth. Growth not via new products as that would also require Dad, the technical co-founder.</p>



<p>I focused on growth of Coumarin — the company’s primary product.</p>



<p>This was also the only way to run the company that I had a chance of being useful in.</p>



<p>And it was also the way I could show the Atlas team we were doing well. And that I might have some value beyond being the boss’ son.</p>



<p>Selling is something everyone sees, especially in a manufacturing setting. From the workers at the factory to the plant staff, if they see trucks coming in for product dispatches, they know the product they’re making is selling. If the staff in the office is busy generating invoices and fielding customer calls, they see the product is selling.</p>



<p>And while I’m by no means a natural at selling, if armed with the right product, I can sell. And Atlas’ Coumarin was the best in the world.</p>



<p>In the chemical industry, it’s unheard of to be a single product company for 30 years. But Atlas was able to do that because the product is hard to make, and they are the best at it.</p>



<p>So growth it was.</p>



<p>Note: It is worth noting that in a competitive chemical product, margins cannot be ignored. So while growth was the focus, I did focus on major expenses — raw materials, shipping, packaging. But this was only 5% of my time as the very capable team at Atlas managed these expertly.</p>



<h3 id="coldcalls"><strong>Growth the old-fashioned way — cold calling and cold emailing prospects and customers</strong></h3>



<p>So with growth being the focus, I went about assembling a list of people and firms in the industry I should reach out to.</p>



<p>I went through my dad’s emails to see who he’d interacted with and reached out to all of them.</p>



<p>I visited various fragrance and flavor association and conference websites and took down their member and attendee names and reached out to them.</p>



<p>It wasn’t a particularly structured process, but I wanted those that knew my dad to know that Atlas was still humming and they could rely on us for product.</p>



<p>And for those that didn’t know us, the next time they had a need, they knew they could reach out to us.</p>



<p>This was a lot of cold emailing and cold calling. I have heightened respect for what SDRs do at CB Insights or anywhere. It is hard work. But also incredibly rewarding when someone closes based on your efforts.</p>



<p>At the same time, I also focused on price. Dad had built a high margin business which afforded me the opportunity to try to gain market share by being more aggressive with price.</p>



<p>Coumarin is probably a 6,000 ton product per year. Atlas was about 10-12% of the global market, but we had capacity at the plant that wasn’t being used so I knew we could produce and sell more. There is some supply-demand curve, marginal cost calculation I could have done here, but I didn’t do any of that.</p>



<p>I did some back of the envelope math in my head and had worked out a simple, rudimentary cost per kg formula in Excel to ensure we were always making something on a sale, but I ran Atlas on instinct a lot more than analysis.</p>



<p>Atlas has a great team with lots of experience. I assumed if I was doing something really really dumb, they’d tell me 🙂</p>



<p>In the last financial year (April 2017-March 2018), Atlas had its best revenue in history. In November 2017, we dispatched 100 tons of Coumarin to customers for the first time in the company’s history.</p>



<p>I remember taking&nbsp;<em>mithai</em>&nbsp;(sweets) to the site at the end of November when the 100 ton month happened and celebrating with the team. It was one of the proudest days I’ve ever had professionally. I was incredibly proud of the Atlas team who had seen a potentially company-sinking event happen with my dad’s death in April and who’d kept fighting and doing good work and then just had a historic month.</p>



<p>So, things were going well with the company.</p>



<p>What about a buyer?</p>



<h3 id="buyers"><strong>The M&amp;A buyers show up</strong></h3>



<p>As soon as I took over the business, the calls started coming from interested buyers or their investment banks. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Dad had already been in discussions with 1 firm prior to his death, and I’d met them once with him. They re-engaged.</p>



<p>The flavor &amp; fragrance industry in India is big, but small at the same time.</p>



<p>Everyone learned about Dad’s passing pretty quickly.</p>



<p>As a result, various buyers expressed interest. I reached out to a couple of our large customers to feel them out.</p>



<p>By the end of July, I had a group of buyers identified. &nbsp;</p>



<p>I had done some basic research on the space so I understood the players and sounded at least reasonably smart. A report by investment bank Avendus on the flavor &amp; fragrance industry was useful for a novice like me. Atlas was a base ingredient manufacturer. Our likely buyers were either larger base ingredient manufacturers or functional ingredient manufacturers who were interested in vertical integration.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18131954/potential-buyers.png?ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>There were 5 buyers that either came to us or that I’d identified and gotten some expression of interest from.</p>



<ul>
<li>Buyer 1 – A publicly traded Indian firm that also makes Coumarin at much smaller volumes</li>



<li>Buyer 2 – An Atlas client who was interested in potential vertical integration</li>



<li>Buyer 3 – A wealthy family looking to buy a business for their son returning from the US</li>



<li>Buyer 4 – A private-equity backed chemical company</li>



<li>Buyer 5 – A family-held chemical company that also manufactured Coumarin</li>
</ul>



<p>Most of these buyers did not get very far. &nbsp;</p>



<p>But I had conversations with all of them.</p>



<p>Before digging into how things went with each buyer, it is worth understanding that there were certain criteria I had for a deal which made eliminating certain buyers easy.</p>



<p>My 3 deal criteria were simple:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>They had to take care of the team</strong>&nbsp;— I wanted to find a growth-oriented company as ensuring the team that had helped build Atlas would be taken care of was critical. &nbsp;The biggest factor in any decision was this as I viewed it as intertwined with my dad’s legacy. He spent 30 years building this company with this team. It was important that this be maintained and hopefully taken to the next level. There is, of course, no way to know this for sure and this is where one’s gut and how the buyer across the table makes you feel is important.</li>



<li><strong>Simple deal&nbsp;</strong>— I was not interested in stock in a private company or an illiquid public company or a long earn-out or some other complex structure. Atlas wouldn’t be a big deal for any credible buyer. Complexity wasn’t required. I also didn’t have time to educate a buyer on the space.</li>



<li><strong>A fair price</strong>&nbsp;— When the founder/face of a company dies (my dad), a bunch of bottom feeding parasites can show up. I wasn’t expecting to get a top of the market price for Atlas, but I wanted a fair one. Moreover, the longer I ran Atlas, the more confident I became in my ability to run it. So the price was only going to go up with time.</li>
</ul>



<p>So now let’s look at each potential buyer.</p>



<h5 id="buyer1"><strong>Buyer 1 — A publicly traded Indian firm that also makes Coumarin at much smaller volumes</strong></h5>



<p>I met with one of the execs of this firm along with their investment bank once. &nbsp;</p>



<p>I shared high-level data on Atlas with them but the conversation ended after that. They were saddled with lots of debt as I could see given they were public and so didn’t think a deal with them would meet the criteria I had on fair price, simplicity, or even ability to take care of the team.</p>



<p>Not a good fit.</p>



<p>One conversation and things were done.</p>



<h5 id="buyer2"><strong>Buyer 2 — An Atlas client who was interested in potential vertical integration</strong></h5>



<p>This was a client I’d reached out to.</p>



<p>They were interested in Atlas. We talked a bit and they proposed a deal, but the structure was complicated and so I let this one go. They are a long-standing client and we were far enough away from any deal that it didn’t make sense to engage further.</p>



<h5 id="buyer3"><strong>Buyer 3 — A wealthy family looking to buy a business for their son returning from the US</strong></h5>



<p>This was an introduction from one of my dad’s advisors. &nbsp;</p>



<p>They were a family with a large industrial business and were interested in expanding into new lines as their son was returning to India from the US. (I guess really wealthy people do things like this).</p>



<p>They were super smart and impressive.</p>



<p>The challenge here was that it’d require lots of education about the industry and the probability of success even after investing would be low.</p>



<p>This wasn’t time I had. &nbsp;</p>



<p>After a couple of conversations, it was clear this wasn’t a fit.</p>



<h5 id="buyer4"><strong>Buyer 4 — A private-equity backed chemical company</strong></h5>



<p>This was the firm my dad was already in discussions with. The firm had seen Atlas’ numbers and had actually given an offer to my dad prior to his death. They seemed the most promising at the outset given the diligence they’d already done.</p>



<p>So I met them in May before leaving India.</p>



<p>It was an interesting meeting.</p>



<p>For an hour, they told me all the reasons Atlas wasn’t a great business. I listened as I’m probably too deferential to those older than me than I should be.</p>



<p>And after listening for a while, I asked them, “You’ve told me all the reasons Atlas is such a bad company. So why do you want to acquire it?”</p>



<p>That seemed to reset the conversation a bit.</p>



<p>Ultimately, there wasn’t a fit. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Part of this may have been culture fit and part of this was likely ownership by PE which complicated decision-making on their side. It’s important to understand the decision-making criteria and process of a buyer when discussing M&amp;A.</p>



<p>The firm wanted to follow their process. &nbsp;</p>



<p>I told them that process didn’t work for Atlas or me or my family. And I told them that process was what we needed to run. When they said no, I wished them luck and moved on.</p>



<p>I was nervous doing this tbh. There wasn’t a huge list of buyers for Atlas and shutting one of them out seemed at times like it might be foolish. But you have to go with your gut on these things.</p>



<p>Life went on.</p>



<h5 id="buyer5"><strong>Buyer 5 — A family-held chemical company that also manufactured Coumarin</strong></h5>



<p>Buyer 5 reached out via the company’s investment banker. &nbsp;</p>



<p>I’d received lots of calls from bankers prior and I insisted they tell me who they were representing as many were just fishing.</p>



<p>Buyer 5’s banker revealed the company’s name.</p>



<p>I knew my dad had had conversations with them some years ago.</p>



<p>We met in July and there was immediately a better fit.</p>



<p>I explained my criteria, they explained their vision, they put a non-binding offer together that was clean/clear and we got moving on diligence.</p>



<p>The rest is history.</p>



<h3 id="sold"><strong>June 1st — Atlas is officially sold</strong></h3>



<p>On May 31st, I flew back to India. &nbsp;It was my 8th trip in the last 13 months.</p>



<p>I landed at 10pm. The offices of Avendus, the investment bank representing Eternis, the buyer, was the first destination.</p>



<p>I arrived at 11pm and we worked until 5am to hash out final details of the deal.</p>



<p>We went away for 4.5 hours to shower and get some sleep and resumed at Eternis’ office at 930am on June 1st. By 4pm that day, the deal was done.</p>



<p>At 5pm, I left Mumbai for the 4-hour drive to Nasik.</p>



<p>The news broke within the industry pretty quickly. During the 4-hour drive to Nasik, folks started calling and WhatsApp messaging me — customers, vendors, etc. &nbsp;</p>



<p>And so did the Atlas team.</p>



<p>I’d only disclosed the deal conversation to 4 people at Atlas prior.</p>



<p>I was hoping to tell the team on Saturday (6 day workweek at Atlas) in the office so I felt bad that some of them heard about the deal on Friday evening through others.</p>



<p>The next day, I went to the factory and members of the Eternis team came. Manu of the Eternis team addressed the office and factory staff and gave a great view into their goals and their company.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18133625/discussion-1024x768.png?resize=1024%2C768&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<h3 id="farewell"><strong>The official farewell</strong></h3>



<p>On June 4th, we decided that our family would officially say farewell to the entire Atlas team at the factory. We had everyone from the office come up.</p>



<p>My mom, kids, and wife flew in from the States. I wanted my kids to see what their “Dada” (grandfather) had built at least 1 time before it moved onto the next chapter in its story.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18134514/sold-1024x680.png?resize=1024%2C680&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>And we wanted to say thanks to everyone on the Atlas team. &nbsp;</p>



<p>I had prepared a speech in English and my wife translated it to Hindi. My Hindi is not very good so beyond the emotion of this farewell, I was pretty scared of delivering a several minute speech in Hindi. I’d never done something like that.</p>



<p>We assembled in the warehouse, and I stood on top of the chemical mixer and talked to the team. I fought back tears several times during my speech. My Hindi was intelligible enough that I had several others on the Atlas team also crying so I guess that my message was understood.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18134628/farewell-1024x680.png?resize=1024%2C680&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p>My speech in English is below. &nbsp;It was delivered in Hindi, and the video is something I hope to show my kids when they are old enough to understand.</p>



<p>Speech:</p>



<p><em>My Hindi is not very good so please forgive me if I make any mistakes.</em></p>



<p><em>Dad started Atlas 29 years ago. As my sisters and I were growing up, we joked that Atlas was his 4th child.</em></p>



<p><em>But in reality, Atlas was less of a 4th child than a 2nd family to Dad.</em></p>



<p><em>He loved working with you all. Whether it was increasing production or improving our Sali to Coumarin yield or solving technical challenges to figuring out how to keep Chinese Coumarin out of India to showing the plant to foreign visitors, there was nothing he liked more.</em></p>



<p><em>And together with Dad, you all built something very special. &nbsp;</em></p>



<p><em>Many of you have been with Dad for 20+ years. He and you grew up and built Atlas together.</em></p>



<p><em>And now, Atlas Coumarin is known globally for being the highest quality coumarin in the world. All the leading multinational companies like IFF, Givaudan, Firmenich rely on Atlas.</em></p>



<p><em>Within India, Atlas Coumarin has more than 50% of the market.</em></p>



<p><em>And now, there are a group of new products such as 6-methyl coumarin, safranal, and cyclocitral which can make Atlas even bigger.</em></p>



<p><em>Of course, as you all know, Dad passed away last April and since then, I’ve been managing what you and he built and it’s been a privilege to do so.</em></p>



<p><em>Thank you for everything.</em></p>



<p><em>I’ve never worked with a group as smart, talented, hardworking, and kind as you all.</em></p>



<p><em>Although I didn’t know much about the business, you all helped me understand things and were patient and understanding throughout. I knew I’d never be able to be 10% as good as Dad but you never made me feel that way and for this, thank you.</em></p>



<p><em>And in the last 13 months, we did a lot of good things. In November, we had Atlas’ first ever month where we dispatched 100 tons. I remember coming to the site that day and distributing mitthai and feeling so proud to be part of this team. On the way back to Nasik that day, I remember crying and thinking about how proud Dad would have been of this team for achieving this milestone.</em></p>



<p><em>So, again, let me say thank you from me and my family for all of the outstanding work you do and the professionalism and kindness with which you do it.</em></p>



<p><em>And now, we’re moving to the next chapter of Atlas.&nbsp;</em></p>



<p><em>As most of you know, Atlas has been purchased by Eternis, a larger chemical company in the fragrance and flavor space. &nbsp;</em></p>



<p><em>There was a lot of interest in Atlas after Dad died. I didn’t like any of those companies except Eternis.</em></p>



<p><em>Eternis is family-owned and their personality and nature is similar to Atlas — humble and hardworking. And they are very focused on growth. Their goal is to take 50-60% of global market share for Coumarin.</em></p>



<p><em>This means more opportunities and growth for Atlas which I’m excited to see.</em></p>



<p><em>With their resources, Atlas can grow to new levels. I also expect that the Atlas team can and will teach them many things from how to improve their yields to their quality to the special style of Atlas jugaad that makes this such a special company.</em></p>



<p><em>My family and I are very excited to see where you all and the Eternis team take Atlas and we hope to visit in the future to see how much the plant expands and how big the team gets.</em></p>



<p><em>And finally, let me say that I’ve been overjoyed to see the impact that Atlas has had on education in some of your families. Dad always thought education was very important. He started a woman’s college in Rajasthan for this reason. He grew up in small village to a family of farmers. And education and hard work was how he achieved so much.</em></p>



<p><em>And as I’ve gotten to know many of you who have been with Dad for 20+ years, I’ve learned that many of you have sent, for the first time, your sons and your daughters on to become doctors, engineers, chartered accountants, and more.</em></p>



<p><em>I think this will be one of Atlas’ most lasting impacts on the community. And I know beyond Atlas, my dad was very proud of this given how important education was to him.</em></p>



<p><em>I hope that you’ll continue to push your sons and daughters forward in education so that one day, they’ll build the next Atlas.</em></p>



<p><em>Again, thank you for teaching me so much about business, India, and what a great team looks like over the last 13 months.</em></p>



<p><em>I could not be more excited to see what you accomplish in the future and I know Dad is looking down on us today and smiling knowing that Atlas is going to become even bigger in the years to come.</em></p>



<p><em>Thank you.</em></p>



<h3 id="CBimpact"><strong>What was the impact on CB Insights?</strong></h3>



<p>It’s a bit unknowable to assess exactly the impact the last 13 months had on CB Insights. We are a big enough company that the show goes on, but we are still not so big that everything is all figured out (not sure that ever happens).</p>



<p>The team continued to kick ass and we had a great year in 2017 growing revenue nearly 100% YoY again. &nbsp;</p>



<p>But the CBI of April 2017 was 114 people. &nbsp;</p>



<p>In the last 13 months, it climbed to over 200. &nbsp;</p>



<p>And so we are a different company.</p>



<p>So I’ll focus on the things that I know I didn’t do well over the last 13 months which may have had some impact, big or small, on CB Insights.</p>



<p><strong>Building relationships with the team</strong>&nbsp;— With our growth, I no longer know every person in the company (inevitable at some point). In the last year, I didn’t get a chance to build relationships with those new teammates. I also didn’t get a chance to grow existing relationships within the team.</p>



<p><strong>I missed lots of meetings and one-on-ones</strong>&nbsp;— Morning meetings with India or due diligence requests that required immediate attention caused me to miss lots of meetings or reschedule 1:1s. This was bad. I didn’t have my finger on what was going on as I always had before or know about challenges they were facing. I wasn’t providing enough feedback, direction, etc as a result.</p>



<p><strong>Internal communication suffered</strong>&nbsp;— Growing to 200 requires we change how we communicate with the team broadly and intra-team. Our methods here didn’t evolve over the last 13 months as much as we probably needed them to. It will be something we figure out now, but we are playing a bit of catch up.</p>



<p><strong>Physically there but not mentally there</strong>&nbsp;— My attention in conversations wasn’t where it always needed to be either due to being tired or just focused on something else — either CBI- or Atlas-related.</p>



<p><strong>Overly fast decisions</strong>&nbsp;— In the last 13 months, I valued expediency of decision-making more than I typically do. And while I will always believe that speed is a weapon that an insurgent company like CB Insights has on its side, decision-making esp as we scale must be well-considered and communicated. Time was always in short supply and so at times, I got into a mindset of let’s decide quickly without considering impacts to the org or teams or individuals.</p>



<p><strong>Didn’t create &amp; communicate strategic vision/product roadmap of CBI internally</strong>&nbsp;— When you’re a smaller company, everyone kind of knows the plan, the vision, even if via osmosis. Also, when you’re smaller and the numbers aren’t as big and the growth expectations are more modest, you can just get to where you need to be by outworking everyone. But as you scale up, hard work is necessary but not sufficient. We need to be more deliberate about the markets we’re attacking, the products we’re building, how we’re going to get there, etc, and we need to communicate and re-communicate that. This didn’t happen as it should have.</p>



<p><strong>Didn’t talk to enough clients</strong>&nbsp;— I’d set a goal of 150 client conversations in 2017 (3 per week) and failed on that goal. We were revenue-funded for most of our lives and I continue to believe our understanding of client needs is one of our most secret weapons. And that requires talking to clients regularly about what they dislike about the product, about their workflow, about their ideas, about their problems, etc. I am thankful we have a customer success team that does a great job of gathering this type of feedback. But this is something I am looking forward to getting back to.</p>



<p>Now that I’m back to 200% CBI, I hope to rectify the above. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Finally, I am thankful to be part of this team. Despite my shortcomings over this last year+, they’ve been patient, kind, and understanding. When my dad passed, many on the team who’d dealt with similar loss reached out with words of wisdom, offers to chat, and support. Special thanks to Jon, my co-founder, for picking up the slack.</p>



<h3 id="differences"><strong>The differences between CB Insights and Atlas</strong></h3>



<p>While it might seem obvious that a technology company and a manufacturing chemicals company would be different, I didn’t appreciate the difference fully until now.</p>



<p>Of course, being thrown into an industry I knew nothing about increased the perceptions of these differences. I imagine someone who grew up in chemicals or manufacturing would find software equally different or challenging.</p>



<p>From my perspective, here are a few key differences between the two that I observed.</p>



<p><strong>Atlas was much more complex</strong>&nbsp;— With China cracking down on pollution, what might that mean for competitors? What is the impact on pricing if a raw material supplier’s plant has shut down? Should we buy more raw material as we think there might be a disruption in the future? If the rupee is getting weaker, what does that mean for our margins? The supply chain considerations alone made it much more complex and there were a lot more exogenous/industry factors that had to be considered than at CB Insights.</p>



<p><strong>Competing on price is hard</strong>&nbsp;— Atlas Coumarin is the highest quality in the world, but there are others that make coumarin. And so while some customers pay for that quality, for many, it came down to price. This was a big change from CB Insights where there is no clear substitute for the product or its human analysts which are way way more expensive. In the case of CBI, it’s all about showing a customer or prospective customer the value that the platform can provide and explaining that our pricing reflects that value. That is not possible at Atlas.</p>



<p><strong>Regulatory requirements</strong>&nbsp;— This makes sense given we’re talking about chemicals and a chemical plant. But coming from software where you can run your business without really having to ask any third-parties for permission, this was an observable difference.</p>



<p><strong>Long-term product development &amp; planning is a different animal</strong>&nbsp;— Having a plan is important in any business. But in chemicals, adding a new product or expanding an existing product is a multi-month or multi-year process. In the last 6 months, the CB Insights team has rolled out patent analytics, market sizings, public company data, new profiles, market map maker and a ton of product capabilities that immediately help our customers and ultimately our top and bottom lines. This ability to stay close to customers and build product quickly for them and see it move the needle is one of the best parts of software. It is much harder (near impossible) to do this quickly in manufacturing.</p>



<p><strong>Touching the product makes it different&nbsp;</strong>— At CB Insights, we deliver data to customers. At Atlas, we deliver drums to customers. There is something unique and gratifying about making a tangible product which was new to me. Turning a bunch of raw materials into a finished product and watching them move from step-to-step in the production process is fun to see. Touching the product in the warehouse before it is dispatched to a customer is different. I’m not sure why or how, but it is. When I saw coumarin coming out of the dryer or the mixer and being packaged, it always made me smile. I remember when we started CB Insights, my dad would ask “What exactly are people buying?” And I’d explain SaaS and subscriptions, and he got it. But he’d also say “I like making stuff.” I didn’t understand it at the time, but I do now.</p>



<p><strong>The power of business</strong>&nbsp;— I’ve always thought business done right can have a massive impact on society, economies, etc. But with all the recent blather of technology companies changing the world, I’ve become a bit more jaded of late on the impact of business given folks are so quick and cavalier in how they define changing the world. Atlas reaffirmed for me the power of and the good that businesses can do in a community if it’s there long enough. There are several people on the Atlas team whose children have gone on to get degrees and become computer engineers, chartered accountants (equivalent to a CPA), and doctors. Some were the first in their family to do so. This is the type of impact that compounds over time and something that was exciting to see and hear about firsthand.</p>



<h3 id="ma"><strong>Thoughts on M&amp;A</strong></h3>



<p>I don’t have a basis of comparison as this was the first company I’ve ever sold, but here’s some of my observations/learnings on the M&amp;A process for those who may go through it.</p>



<p><strong>Should I have hired an investment bank?</strong>&nbsp;I didn’t have a bank representing me, i.e. I represented myself. Maybe I should have. I had access to data (thanks CB Insights) so knew valuation and transaction multiples. The bankers for the buyer served a project management function so I’m not sure if having bankers on my side would have helped on that front. Bankers might have helped negotiate a bit more, but given this was a small cap deal in India, the few bankers I met who deal in this range of the market were generally not of the caliber that I thought they’d add a ton of value. No clear answer here.</p>



<p><strong>Don’t let lawyers run the process</strong>&nbsp;— Lawyers, as they should be, are often about risk mitigation for both sides. But it’s important the parties in the deal be clear on what is valuable to them or understand how big the risks really are so that neither side gets bogged down in details or risks which are unimportant or have a low probability of happening. I think both sides did a pretty good job here in our deal, but it’s something to watch out for as letting the lawyers run the process costs you time and more lawyer fees.</p>



<p><strong>Know your goals. Communicate your goals</strong>&nbsp;— One of the things that worked well in this process was stating my goals to buyers upfront, i.e. the aforementioned deal criteria around taking care of the team, a simple deal and a fair price. It helped quickly determine if there was a potential fit with a buyer and also because I was dealing with people in the industry who we might work with in the future, it removed ambiguity and any sense of arbitrariness from our decisions. If someone started talking about private company stock or raising debt or doing dividend recap, I simply reminded them of the simplicity tenet.</p>



<p><strong>Don’t sweat the small stuff</strong>&nbsp;— The aforementioned decision-making framework/deal criteria also were very helpful in providing focus for me. If it wasn’t related to those 3 criteria, I tried to avoid worrying about it. This also prevented me from overcomplicating things at times which was incredibly helpful.</p>



<p><strong>“That’s industry standard”</strong>&nbsp;— This is one of the phrases to watch out for in negotiation. When a term cannot be defended on its merits, often the catch-all is “that’s standard in deals” or “that’s industry standard” is often trotted out by lawyers and bankers. That’s BS. Everything is negotiable, and just because others have gone with some nebulous standard doesn’t mean you have to. Again, that doesn’t mean negotiate for sport on every little thing, but it does mean that things should be supported with logic and reason and not the intellectually lazy “just because.”</p>



<p><strong>Conditions Precedent (CPs)</strong>&nbsp;— These are the conditions that have to be satisfied prior to a deal being closed— after the purchase agreement is executed but before it is closed, i.e., the money hitting the bank account. Pay attention to what is in the CPs and ensure you understand them, that they’re all meaningful, and that they can be achieved.</p>



<p><strong>Don’t do zero-sum negotiation</strong>&nbsp;— I believe both parties felt good about this deal and that was because the negotiations were generally solutions-focused. There wasn’t a zero sum mentality of “For me to win, you must lose.” I found this to be constructive throughout and made the general process more pleasant. Note: I wouldn’t describe the M&amp;A process as fun, but I do think minimizing acrimony is good. We mostly avoided that.</p>



<h3 id="india"><strong>Thoughts On India</strong></h3>



<p>India is an amazing place.</p>



<p>India is a complicated place.</p>



<p>Here are some simple, non-ground breaking thoughts.</p>



<p><strong>Regulatory overhead is still steep</strong>&nbsp;— India’s regulatory overhead is mostly well-intentioned but ill-defined. There are so many licenses and permits required but even experts in the industry can’t agree on what is what and what is required. Websites, especially regional ones, are not updated or clear.</p>



<p>The World Bank ease of doing business rankings are below. India jumped 30 spots so things are clearly getting better, but there is still a lot of work to do. Overall, I’d say I found things at the national or federal level much better defined than at the regional level.</p>



<p>This uncertainty creates angst for businesses as you never really know if you’re compliant with all the rules. It makes an M&amp;A process much more difficult needlessly. Checklists here would be amazing.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18140018/ease-of-business.png?ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>



<p><strong>Women in the workforce are going to be a game changer</strong>&nbsp;— 2 of the 4 key management personnel at Atlas were women. Atlas is what it is because of their contributions, and this transaction wouldn’t have occurred without their steady hand. I’m impressed with my dad’s foresight here, especially in a city like Nasik, which is not as cosmopolitan as the big cities.</p>



<p>But throughout the process, whether it was at Atlas, or our lawyers or our bank or various other parties related to the deal, I found the women I worked with to be among the most responsive, smart, and able to get isht done. India remains a very patriarchal society but change is steadily coming here which will unlock an immense amount of talent.</p>



<p><strong>There are lots of middlemen</strong>&nbsp;— In B2B, there are lots of consultants and brokers in India involved in everything from regulatory approval to pricing of materials to selling of scrap metal. Technology has been shown to be good at disintermediating middlemen. I think there is a lot of opportunity to use technology to do this in India. I’ve noted a bunch of ideas down for the future.</p>



<p><strong>Traffic is soul crushing&nbsp;</strong>— Mumbai traffic is an absolute horror. Everyone there seems to have become used to it with 1.5- to 2-hour commute times each way becoming normal. With smartphones and technology, one can still be somewhat productive, but the amount of personal productivity lost here on a daily basis is unfathomable. And this will only get worse. I’d imagine that a progressive employer who figures out a remote work strategy might be able to recruit and retain really great talent.</p>



<p><strong>There is so much opportunity</strong>&nbsp;— India is messy and complicated and the traffic is ridiculous and there is a whole litany of “things wrong with India,” but there is so much good there. As an Indian-American, I often focused on all that was wrong with India before (viewing everything from an American lens on how things should be). Managing Atlas for 13 months made me see this and also revealed the immense opportunities there in business, in education, and more. I’m excited to explore those in the future.</p>



<h3 id="tech"><strong>Thoughts on Technology &amp; Data</strong></h3>



<p>It’s worth mentioning the impact of technology &amp; data on me in the last 13 months.</p>



<p>I could not have done this deal or managed Atlas without technology. Here are some of the technologies that made my life easier.</p>



<p><strong>Google</strong>&nbsp;— Dammit. Google is amazing. When researching some esoteric Indian regulation or trying to find flavor &amp; fragrance companies who might be customers, Google was my go-to. Google Sheets was also powerful for collaborating with the team.</p>



<p><strong>WhatsApp</strong>&nbsp;— India runs on WhatsApp. Also, the calling feature saved me tons of money when I had to call India from the US or vice-versa.</p>



<p><strong>Dropbox</strong>&nbsp;— The Atlas team and I used this to organize documents before sharing it in the deal room.</p>



<p><strong>SecureDocs</strong>&nbsp;— This was the deal room software I used. The software just works. And their team was incredibly responsive. The sales folks weren’t pushy and were helpful. And the pricing was transparent and reasonable. Big fan.</p>



<p><strong>YesWare</strong>&nbsp;— To send mail merges, absolutely critical.</p>



<p><strong>Data&nbsp;</strong>— Going in without a banker to these conversations could have been intimidating but I had data so I knew deals, valuations, etc. It was good to be a customer of CB Insights for a bit.</p>



<h3 id="thanks"><strong>Thank you’s</strong></h3>



<p>There are a ton of people to thank for all they did. Here goes. I apologize if I forgot someone.</p>



<p><strong>Family</strong>&nbsp;— First, my mom for her strength and for trusting me. She is the unheralded co-founder of Atlas. My wife who has been managing a career and 2 kids almost solo for the last 13 months and who would listen without judgment to me when I was frustrated or overwhelmed. My kids who got used to me being on the phone every morning talking to India instead of having breakfast with them.</p>



<p><strong>The Atlas team&nbsp;</strong>— As I said above, although I’m 10% as smart as my dad, you never made me feel this. Even after his death, Atlas kept humming because of your work. Many of you worked with Dad for 20+ years. It was good to work with you all directly to see firsthand how special of a company it is. Thanks especially to Mrs. Lakhpatwalla, Priti, and Nathe for all their help on this deal. Thanks as well to Abhay for constantly selling and talking to customers and to Kiran for driving so expertly throughout India and never once getting into an accident (driving in India is intense for those unfamiliar). Thanks to Mehetre and his leadership in the factory as well as to Jadhav, Nitin, and Anand in the plant. We have a group of veterans and young new stars that I’m excited about on the production side. Thank you to Pareshbhai for his friendship and steady advice on accounting and finance matters.</p>



<p><strong>The CB Insights team</strong>&nbsp;— This is a special company with an amazing team who continued to kick ass despite the impacts of my sometimes mental and physical absence. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>CB Insights newsletter readers</strong>&nbsp;— Since my dad’s death, the only constant has been the CBI newsletter. I didn’t miss a day since he died (although I’d queued up several prior so I was not writing them real-time for a while). Your pie charts, funny commentary, and even the haterade have always been a nice break.</p>



<p><strong>The deal players</strong>&nbsp;— M&amp;A deals are a good amount of work and given the stakes and long hours can probably bring out the worst in folks at times. I can say I left the negotiation/experience with great impressions of everyone involved. Thanks to Manu and the Eternis team (Chetan, Ram, Rahul) for always being true to their word and a class-act. Thanks to the Avendus team, who although representing Eternis, were always solutions-focused and fair. Thanks to the Majmudar team (Kritika, Amrit, and Sinjani) for their work and counsel as our lawyers. Thanks to Geeta of Kotak Bank for always figuring out a way to get things done even at the very last minute.</p>



<p>Finally, thanks to everyone for putting up with me always being tired.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" src="https://i0.wp.com/research-assets.cbinsights.com/2018/06/18140649/AIMS-newspaper-668x1024.png?resize=668%2C1024&amp;ssl=1" alt="" data-recalc-dims="1"></figure>











<h2><a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research/payments-market-momentum-2024/"></a></h2>



<h2><a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research/nvidia-strategy-map-partnerships-investments-acquisitions/"></a></h2>



<h2><a href="https://www.cbinsights.com/research/report/big-tech-healthcare-amazon-google-microsoft-nvidia/"></a></h2>











<h4>YOU MIGHT ALSO LIKE:</h4>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>