<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 13:30:11 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[12 Days of Shell (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://12days.cmdchallenge.com</link>
            <guid>46190577</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 10:13:07 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://12days.cmdchallenge.com">https://12days.cmdchallenge.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46190577">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://12days.cmdchallenge.com: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The fuck off contact page (289 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nicchan.me/blog/the-f-off-contact-page/</link>
            <guid>46189994</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 08:57:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nicchan.me/blog/the-f-off-contact-page/">https://www.nicchan.me/blog/the-f-off-contact-page/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46189994">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-astro-cid-7jjqptxk=""> 
<p>Many years ago, I had a client that sold a service. They weren’t a design agency, but for the sake of anonymity, we’ll just call them a design agency. Let us say that their core offering was a full-service design package, but they also made a substantial part of their income from doing smaller tasks related to their primary offering. These kind of services included smaller tasks like one-off campaigns or newsletter designs; tasks that their customers may very well be able to do on their own, but the prospect of freeing up some time by by offloading it to an expert was a tempting offer for many of their customers, and made up a significant chunk of their revenue.</p>
<p>We were hired to do a complete redesign of their site from the ground up. The process went smoothly at first, all the wireframes were approved without issue, but when it came to the design phase, we began to hit walls. For example, they would stumble across sites that they liked and wanted to depart from the agreed-upon wireframes in order to implement a similar design.</p>
<p>The problem was, they were thinking about their inspiration sites from an aesthetic point of view, not from a user experience perspective. Their decisions were coming from a place of ‘we like the balance of imagery and text  in this page’ and not ‘we think this design will achieve the intended goal of the page.’ Now, you know me, I love a good <a href="https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2025/04/gild-just-one-lily/">singular gilded lily</a>, but the client had unwittingly stumbled across a trap, they had fallen in love with what I call a “Fuck off contact page.”</p>
<section><h2 id="what-the-fuck-is-a-fuck-off-contact-page">What the fuck is a ‘fuck off contact page?’</h2><p>A “fuck off contact page” is what a company throws together when they actually don’t want anyone to contact them at all. They are usually found on the websites of million or billion dollar companies, likely Software-as-a-service (SaaS) companies that are trying to reduce the amount of money they spend on support by carefully hiding the real support channels behind login walls. These companies tend to offer multiple tiers of support, with enterprise customers having a customer success manager who they can call on this ancient device we call phones, whereas the lower-paying customers may have to wrangle various in-app ticket mechanisms. If you solve your own problem by reading the knowledge base, then this is a win for the company. They don’t want to hear from you, they want you to fuck off.</p><figure><img alt="Two mobile wireframes. On the left, the wireframe has a large heading that says Contact, and a contact form with two fields, 'Name' and 'How can we help you?' below it. On the right, the mockup has a large heading that says Contact, and three icons with text underneath. In order, they are 'Check out our knowledge base', 'Visit us in person' and 'Reach out to our sales team.'" loading="lazy" decoding="async" sizes="(min-width: 752px) 752px, 100vw" srcset="https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_640,h_611,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 640w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_750,h_716,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 750w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_752,h_718,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 752w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_828,h_791,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 828w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_960,h_917,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 960w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_1080,h_1031,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 1080w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_1280,h_1222,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 1280w,
https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_1504,h_1436,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact 1504w" src="https://res.cloudinary.com/nicchan/image/upload/w_752,h_718,c_lfill,f_auto/v1765177043/contact"><figcaption>These are recreated versions of the wireframes that we did for the site, the original contact form version of the page is on the left, and the ‘fuck off contact page’ is on the right. In actuality, the ‘fuck off contact page’ was even more ‘fuck off’ due to the whitespace and a large hero image. This meant the only option that ‘talk to the sales team’, the only option that would put you in touch with a human anytime soon, was at the very bottom of the page, long after some people would stop scrolling.</figcaption></figure><p>In other words, this is entirely inappropriate for the kind of service-based agency that our client was. The billion dollar SaaS company wants to reduce the number of incoming inquiries, and is hoping to weed out anyone who is not determined to contact them by giving them unsatisfying options. The service company wants to show how helpful they are and cultivate leads. These are fundamentally opposing goals.</p><p>Let me explain further. I’m not sure about you, but as a user, when I see a button that says ‘talk to our sales team’, I treat the entire region of the page with the same trepidation as nuclear waste. The page is now a no-go zone, and I try to exit as quickly as possible, knowing that whatever my original query was, I’m going to have to solve it unassisted. Seeing as this is a company who makes money off of convincing people to let them handle the easy stuff, adding friction to this key part of their sales funnel just doesn’t feel like a winning strategy.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="how-the-fuck-did-you-convince-them-to-change-their-minds">How the fuck did you convince them to change their minds?</h2><p>Try as we might, we couldn’t. In all honesty, we probably could have done more in order to talk them out of it, but the project had gone in such a way where we were focused on trying to talk the client out of changing other things that would drastically increase design or development time beyond the initial scope. In other words, we were too busy putting out other fires. This re-designed contact page, as certain as we were of how bad of an idea it was, wasn’t a fire, so we let it through.</p><p>The project finished on time, everyone got paid, and the client was happy with the end result, but I still felt very disappointed in the whole thing. While I personally believe in the value of good design, I also believe there are a lot of smoke-and-mirrors in the industry, and I hated the thought that I might have inadvertently contributed to it. Even if the client is happy, it didn’t meet my internal bar for a quality product worth sticking my name on, and I feel like I’ve let down both the client and the end-users.</p></section>
<section><h2 id="how-the-fuck-do-i-avoid-being-in-a-position-where-im-asked-to-implement-a-fuck-off-contact-page">How the fuck do I avoid being in a position where I’m asked to implement a ‘fuck off contact page’?</h2><p>I think our problems started from before we even began to touch a single design tool. As a favor to one of the folks involved, we had discounted our rates for this client, and I think that set us off on the wrong foot. Instead of seeing us as people who brought valuable knowledge and expertise to the project, they saw us as the hands that would execute their vision.</p><p>Especially for those not familiar with the process of design, it can be tempting to see things like discovery and wireframing as obstacles to be cleared before you get to the fun part, designing the visual identity. Unfortunately, many designers are also guilty of this!</p><p>As service providers, I believe we need to do a better job on educating clients on the design process and why each step is so important. This is radical idea in some circles, but knowing why you’re building something is a necessary part of doing a good job at it! That’s why we do things like determining the architecture before we start thinking about the brand. Flow charts and diagrams are not as fun as interactive prototypes, but they’re much more important to get right.</p><p>Also, the discounted pricing probably didn’t help — instead of signaling that we were doing a favor out of respect for them, it just signaled that we were easily exploitable. There was a lack of trust throughout the process, on both sides. While I really want to believe that I can have the kind of relationships with clients where constructive disagreement is welcomed and valued, how I get there is still something I’m figuring out, even many years later.</p><p>I think that’s part of the reason why I blog. By blogging, I’m putting a body of work out there that communicates my values and ethos. While much of the details of my client work has to remain private, these posts can be public, and hopefully they can help me find people who resonate with what I have to offer. Or you know, just be bold enough to communicate ‘Fuck off’ to those who don’t!</p><p>(Feel free to <a href="https://www.nicchan.me/contact">reach out</a> if you’re interested in working with folks who care, maybe a little too much, about doing right by your users.)</p></section>
<section><h2 id="links-and-resources">Links and Resources</h2><ul>
<li>I hit publish on this as I listened to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=a7sh-5UYnJc">Andy Bell’s recent talk at Beyond Tellerand</a>. It has SO many gems of wisdom about the core skills required to deliver successful client projects. It’s also why I love working with <a href="https://set.studio/">Set.Studio</a>, check ‘em out.</li>
</ul></section> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GitHub Actions Has a Package Manager, and It Might Be the Worst (203 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nesbitt.io/2025/12/06/github-actions-package-manager.html</link>
            <guid>46189692</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 08:15:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nesbitt.io/2025/12/06/github-actions-package-manager.html">https://nesbitt.io/2025/12/06/github-actions-package-manager.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46189692">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>After putting together <a href="https://github.com/ecosyste-ms/package-manager-resolvers">ecosyste-ms/package-manager-resolvers</a>, I started wondering what dependency resolution algorithm GitHub Actions uses. When you write <code>uses: actions/checkout@v4</code> in a workflow file, you’re declaring a dependency. GitHub resolves it, downloads it, and executes it. That’s package management. So I went spelunking into the runner codebase to see how it works. What I found was concerning.</p>

<p>Package managers are a critical part of software supply chain security. The industry has spent years hardening them after incidents like left-pad, event-stream, and countless others. Lockfiles, integrity hashes, and dependency visibility aren’t optional extras. They’re the baseline. GitHub Actions ignores all of it.</p>

<p>Compared to mature package ecosystems:</p>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Feature</th>
      <th>npm</th>
      <th>Cargo</th>
      <th>NuGet</th>
      <th>Bundler</th>
      <th>Go</th>
      <th>Actions</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Lockfile</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✗</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Transitive pinning</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✗</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Integrity hashes</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✗</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Dependency tree visibility</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✗</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Resolution specification</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✓</td>
      <td>✗</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<p>The core problem is the lack of a lockfile. Every other package manager figured this out decades ago: you declare loose constraints in a manifest, the resolver picks specific versions, and the lockfile records exactly what was chosen. GitHub Actions has no equivalent. Every run re-resolves from your workflow file, and the results can change without any modification to your code.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity22/presentation/koishybayev">Research from USENIX Security 2022</a> analyzed over 200,000 repositories and found that 99.7% execute externally developed Actions, 97% use Actions from unverified creators, and 18% run Actions with missing security updates. The researchers identified four fundamental security properties that CI/CD systems need: admittance control, execution control, code control, and access to secrets. GitHub Actions fails to provide adequate tooling for any of them. A <a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity23/presentation/muralee">follow-up study</a> using static taint analysis found code injection vulnerabilities in over 4,300 workflows across 2.7 million analyzed. Nearly every GitHub Actions user is running third-party code with no verification, no lockfile, and no visibility into what that code depends on.</p>

<p><strong>Mutable versions.</strong> When you pin to <code>actions/checkout@v4</code>, that tag can move. The maintainer can push a new commit and retag. Your workflow changes silently. A lockfile would record the SHA that <code>@v4</code> resolved to, giving you reproducibility while keeping version tags readable. Instead, you have to choose: readable tags with no stability, or unreadable SHAs with no automated update path.</p>

<p>GitHub has added mitigations. <a href="https://docs.github.com/en/code-security/supply-chain-security/understanding-your-software-supply-chain/immutable-releases">Immutable releases</a> lock a release’s git tag after publication. Organizations can enforce SHA pinning as a policy. You can limit workflows to actions from verified creators. These help, but they only address the top-level dependency. They do nothing for transitive dependencies, which is the primary attack vector.</p>

<p><strong>Invisible transitive dependencies.</strong> SHA pinning doesn’t solve this. Composite actions resolve their own dependencies, but you can’t see or control what they pull in. When you pin an action to a SHA, you only lock the outer file. If it internally pulls <code>some-helper@v1</code> with a mutable tag, your workflow is still vulnerable. You have zero visibility into this. A lockfile would record the entire resolved tree, making transitive dependencies visible and pinnable. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1145/3643991.3644899">Research on JavaScript Actions</a> found that 54% contain at least one security weakness, with most vulnerabilities coming from indirect dependencies. The <a href="https://unit42.paloaltonetworks.com/github-actions-supply-chain-attack/">tj-actions/changed-files incident</a> showed how this plays out in practice: a compromised action updated its transitive dependencies to exfiltrate secrets. With a lockfile, the unexpected transitive change would have been visible in a diff.</p>

<p><strong>No integrity verification.</strong> npm records <code>integrity</code> hashes in the lockfile. Cargo records checksums in <code>Cargo.lock</code>. When you install, the package manager verifies the download matches what was recorded. Actions has nothing. You trust GitHub to give you the right code for a SHA. A lockfile with integrity hashes would let you verify that what you’re running matches what you resolved.</p>

<p><strong>Re-runs aren’t reproducible.</strong> GitHub staff have <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions/27083">confirmed this explicitly</a>: “if the workflow uses some actions at a version, if that version was force pushed/updated, we will be fetching the latest version there.” A failed job re-run can silently get different code than the original run. Cache interaction makes it worse: caches only save on successful jobs, so a re-run after a force-push gets different code <em>and</em> has to rebuild the cache. Two sources of non-determinism compounding. A lockfile would make re-runs deterministic: same lockfile, same code, every time.</p>

<p><strong>No dependency tree visibility.</strong> npm has <code>npm ls</code>. Cargo has <code>cargo tree</code>. You can inspect your full dependency graph, find duplicates, trace how a transitive dependency got pulled in. Actions gives you nothing. You can’t see what your workflow actually depends on without manually reading every composite action’s source. A lockfile would be a complete manifest of your dependency tree.</p>

<p><strong>Undocumented resolution semantics.</strong> Every package manager documents how dependency resolution works. npm has a spec. Cargo has a spec. Actions resolution is undocumented. The <a href="https://github.com/actions/runner">runner source is public</a>, and the entire “resolution algorithm” is in <a href="https://github.com/actions/runner/blob/main/src/Runner.Worker/ActionManager.cs">ActionManager.cs</a>. Here’s a simplified version of what it does:</p>

<div><pre><code><span>// Simplified from actions/runner ActionManager.cs</span>
<span>async</span> <span>Task</span> <span>PrepareActionsAsync</span><span>(</span><span>steps</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// Start fresh every time - no caching</span>
    <span>DeleteDirectory</span><span>(</span><span>"_work/_actions"</span><span>);</span>

    <span>await</span> <span>PrepareActionsRecursiveAsync</span><span>(</span><span>steps</span><span>,</span> <span>depth</span><span>:</span> <span>0</span><span>);</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>async</span> <span>Task</span> <span>PrepareActionsRecursiveAsync</span><span>(</span><span>actions</span><span>,</span> <span>depth</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>depth</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>10</span><span>)</span>
        <span>throw</span> <span>new</span> <span>Exception</span><span>(</span><span>"Composite action depth exceeded max depth 10"</span><span>);</span>

    <span>foreach</span> <span>(</span><span>var</span> <span>action</span> <span>in</span> <span>actions</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
        <span>// Resolution happens on GitHub's server - opaque to us</span>
        <span>var</span> <span>downloadInfo</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>GetDownloadInfoFromGitHub</span><span>(</span><span>action</span><span>.</span><span>Reference</span><span>);</span>

        <span>// Download and extract - no integrity verification</span>
        <span>var</span> <span>tarball</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>Download</span><span>(</span><span>downloadInfo</span><span>.</span><span>TarballUrl</span><span>);</span>
        <span>Extract</span><span>(</span><span>tarball</span><span>,</span> <span>$"_actions/</span><span>{</span><span>action</span><span>.</span><span>Owner</span><span>}</span><span>/</span><span>{</span><span>action</span><span>.</span><span>Repo</span><span>}</span><span>/</span><span>{</span><span>downloadInfo</span><span>.</span><span>Sha</span><span>}</span><span>"</span><span>);</span>

        <span>// If composite, recurse into its dependencies</span>
        <span>var</span> <span>actionYml</span> <span>=</span> <span>Parse</span><span>(</span><span>$"_actions/</span><span>{</span><span>action</span><span>.</span><span>Owner</span><span>}</span><span>/</span><span>{</span><span>action</span><span>.</span><span>Repo</span><span>}</span><span>/</span><span>{</span><span>downloadInfo</span><span>.</span><span>Sha</span><span>}</span><span>/action.yml"</span><span>);</span>
        <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>actionYml</span><span>.</span><span>Type</span> <span>==</span> <span>"composite"</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
            <span>// These nested actions may use mutable tags - we have no control</span>
            <span>await</span> <span>PrepareActionsRecursiveAsync</span><span>(</span><span>actionYml</span><span>.</span><span>Steps</span><span>,</span> <span>depth</span> <span>+</span> <span>1</span><span>);</span>
        <span>}</span>
    <span>}</span>
<span>}</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>That’s it. No version constraints, no deduplication (the same action referenced twice gets downloaded twice), no integrity checks. The tarball URL comes from GitHub’s API, and you trust them to return the right content for the SHA. A lockfile wouldn’t fix the missing spec, but it would at least give you a concrete record of what resolution produced.</p>

<p>Even setting lockfiles aside, Actions has other issues that proper package managers solved long ago.</p>

<p><strong>No registry.</strong> Actions live in git repositories. There’s no central index, no security scanning, no malware detection, no typosquatting prevention. A real registry can flag malicious packages, store immutable copies independent of the source, and provide a single point for security response. The Marketplace exists but it’s a thin layer over repository search. Without a registry, there’s nowhere for immutable metadata to live. If an action’s source repository disappears or gets compromised, there’s no fallback.</p>

<p><strong>Shared mutable environment.</strong> Actions aren’t sandboxed from each other. Two actions calling <code>setup-node</code> with different versions mutate the same <code>$PATH</code>. The outcome depends on execution order, not any deterministic resolution.</p>

<p><strong>No offline support.</strong> Actions are pulled from GitHub on every run. There’s no offline installation mode, no vendoring mechanism, no way to run without network access. Other package managers let you vendor dependencies or set up private mirrors. With Actions, if GitHub is down, your CI is down.</p>

<p><strong>The namespace is GitHub usernames.</strong> Anyone who creates a GitHub account owns that namespace for actions. Account takeovers and typosquatting are possible. When a popular action maintainer’s account gets compromised, attackers can push malicious code and retag. A lockfile with integrity hashes wouldn’t prevent account takeovers, but it would detect when the code changes unexpectedly. The hash mismatch would fail the build instead of silently running attacker-controlled code. Another option would be something like Go’s checksum database, a transparent log of known-good hashes that catches when the same version suddenly has different contents.</p>

<h3 id="how-did-we-get-here">How Did We Get Here?</h3>

<p>The Actions runner is forked from Azure DevOps, designed for enterprises with controlled internal task libraries where you trust your pipeline tasks. GitHub bolted a public marketplace onto that foundation without rethinking the trust model. The addition of composite actions and reusable workflows created a dependency system, but the implementation ignored lessons from package management: lockfiles, integrity verification, transitive pinning, dependency visibility.</p>

<p>This matters beyond CI/CD. Trusted publishing is being rolled out across package registries: PyPI, npm, RubyGems, and others now let you publish packages directly from GitHub Actions using OIDC tokens instead of long-lived secrets. OIDC removes one class of attacks (stolen credentials) but amplifies another: the supply chain security of these registries now depends entirely on GitHub Actions, a system that lacks the lockfile and integrity controls these registries themselves require. A compromise in your workflow’s action dependencies can lead to malicious packages on registries with better security practices than the system they’re trusting to publish.</p>

<p>Other CI systems have done better. GitLab CI added an <code>integrity</code> keyword in version 17.9 that lets you specify a SHA256 hash for remote includes. If the hash doesn’t match, the pipeline fails. Their documentation explicitly warns that including remote configs “is similar to pulling a third-party dependency” and recommends pinning to full commit SHAs. GitLab recognized the problem and shipped integrity verification. GitHub closed the feature request.</p>

<p>GitHub’s design choices don’t just affect GitHub users. Forgejo Actions maintains compatibility with GitHub Actions, which means projects migrating to Codeberg for ethical reasons inherit the same broken CI architecture. The Forgejo maintainers <a href="https://codeberg.org/forgejo/discussions/issues/214">openly acknowledge the problems</a>, with contributors calling GitHub Actions’ ecosystem “terribly designed and executed.” But they’re stuck maintaining compatibility with it. Codeberg mirrors common actions to reduce GitHub dependency, but the fundamental issues are baked into the model itself. GitHub’s design flaws are spreading to the alternatives.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/actions/runner/issues/2195">GitHub issue #2195</a> requested lockfile support. It was closed as “not planned” in 2022. Palo Alto’s <a href="https://unit42.paloaltonetworks.com/github-actions-supply-chain-vulnerabilities/">“Unpinnable Actions” research</a> documented how even SHA-pinned actions can have unpinnable transitive dependencies.</p>

<p>Dependabot can update action versions, which helps. Some teams vendor actions into their own repos. <a href="https://zizmor.sh/">zizmor</a> is excellent at scanning workflows and finding security issues. But these are workarounds for a system that lacks the basics.</p>

<p>The fix is a lockfile. Record resolved SHAs for every action reference, including transitives. Add integrity hashes. Make the dependency tree inspectable. GitHub closed the request three years ago and hasn’t revisited it.</p>

<hr>

<p><strong>Further reading:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity22/presentation/koishybayev">Characterizing the Security of GitHub CI Workflows</a> - Koishybayev et al., USENIX Security 2022</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.usenix.org/conference/usenixsecurity23/presentation/muralee">ARGUS: A Framework for Staged Static Taint Analysis of GitHub Workflows and Actions</a> - Muralee et al., USENIX Security 2023</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.wiz.io/blog/new-github-action-supply-chain-attack-reviewdog-action-setup">New GitHub Action supply chain attack: reviewdog/action-setup</a> - Wiz Research, 2025</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.com/blog/cloud-security/unpinnable-actions-github-security/">Unpinnable Actions: How Malicious Code Can Sneak into Your GitHub Actions Workflows</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.com/blog/cloud-security/github-actions-worm-dependencies/">GitHub Actions Worm: Compromising GitHub Repositories Through the Actions Dependency Tree</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/actions/setup-python/issues/377">setup-python: Action can be compromised via mutable dependency</a></li>
</ul>

  </div>

  
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Palantir Could Be the Most Overvalued Company That Ever Existed (121 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://247wallst.com/investing/2025/11/25/palantir-could-be-the-most-overvalued-company-that-ever-existed/</link>
            <guid>46188451</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 04:45:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://247wallst.com/investing/2025/11/25/palantir-could-be-the-most-overvalued-company-that-ever-existed/">https://247wallst.com/investing/2025/11/25/palantir-could-be-the-most-overvalued-company-that-ever-existed/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46188451">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://247wallst.com/investing/2025/11/25/palantir-could-be-the-most-overvalued-company-that-ever-existed/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Damn Small Linux (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.damnsmalllinux.org/</link>
            <guid>46187387</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 01:47:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.damnsmalllinux.org/">https://www.damnsmalllinux.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46187387">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.damnsmalllinux.org/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Bag of words, have mercy on us (223 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us</link>
            <guid>46185957</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 22:31:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us">https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46185957">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg" width="603" height="820.8740740740741" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1654,&quot;width&quot;:1215,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:603,&quot;bytes&quot;:324078,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/jpeg&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.experimental-history.com/i/169990157?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!w4qD!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F31f48971-998b-4e9b-8f90-ac67d4336c39_1215x1654.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption>photo cred: my dad</figcaption></figure></div><p>Look, I don’t know if AI is gonna kill us or make us all rich or whatever, but I do know we’ve got the wrong metaphor.</p><p><span>We want to understand these things as </span><em>people</em><span>. When you type a question to ChatGPT and it types back the answer in complete sentences, it feels like there must be a little guy in there doing the typing. We get this vivid sense of “</span><em>it’s alive!!</em><span>”, and we activate all of the mental faculties we evolved to deal with fellow humans: </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Theory_of_mind" rel="">theory of mind</a><span>, </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Attribution_(psychology)" rel="">attribution</a><span>, </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Impression_management#:~:text=Impression%20management%20is%20a%20conscious,controlling%20information%20in%20social%20interaction." rel="">impression management</a><span>, </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stereotype" rel="">stereotyping</a><span>, </span><a href="https://www.cep.ucsb.edu/wp-content/uploads/2023/05/Cosmides_etal_2005_DetectingCheaters.pdf" rel="">cheater detection</a><span>, etc.</span></p><p><span>We can’t help it; humans are hopeless anthropomorphizers. When it comes to perceiving personhood, we’re so trigger-happy that we can see the Virgin Mary in a </span><a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna6511148" rel="">grilled cheese sandwich</a><span>:</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png" width="378" height="490" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:490,&quot;width&quot;:378,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:262500,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.experimental-history.com/i/169990157?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!B9zG!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F4d375800-59a9-4bc2-8daa-5ec2a2c142d7_378x490.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>A human face in a slice of nematode:</p><p>And an old man in a bunch of poultry and fish atop a pile of books:</p><p><span>Apparently, this served us well in our evolutionary history—maybe it’s so important not to mistake </span><em>people</em><span> for </span><em>things</em><span> that we err on the side of mistaking </span><em>things</em><span> for </span><em>people</em><span>.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-1-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-1-169990157" target="_self" rel="">1</a></span><span> This is probably why we’re so willing to explain strange occurrences by appealing to fantastical creatures with minds and intentions: everybody in town is getting sick because of WITCHES, you can’t see the sun right now because A WOLF ATE IT, the volcano erupted because GOD IS MAD. People who experience sleep paralysis sometimes </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sleep_paralysis" rel="">hallucinate</a><span> a demon-like creature sitting on their chest, and one explanation is that the subconscious mind is trying to understand why the body can’t move, and instead of coming up with “I’m still in REM sleep so there’s not enough acetylcholine in my brain to activate my primary motor cortex”, it comes up with “BIG DEMON ON TOP OF ME”.</span></p><p><span>This is why the past three years have been so confusing—the little guy inside the AI keeps dumbfounding us by doing things that a human wouldn’t do. Why does he make up citations when he does my social studies homework? How come he can beat me at Go but he can’t tell me </span><a href="https://community.openai.com/t/incorrect-count-of-r-characters-in-the-word-strawberry/829618" rel="">how many “r”s are in the word “strawberry”</a><span>? Why is he telling me to </span><a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/5/23/24162896/google-ai-overview-hallucinations-glue-in-pizza" rel="">put glue on my pizza</a><span>?</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-2-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-2-169990157" target="_self" rel="">2</a></span></p><p><span>Trying to understand LLMs by using the rules of human psychology is like trying to understand a game of Scrabble by using the rules of Pictionary. These things don’t act like people because they </span><em>aren’t </em><span>people. I don’t mean that in the deflationary way that the AI naysayers mean it. They think denying humanity to the machines is a well-deserved insult; I think it’s just an accurate description.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-3-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-3-169990157" target="_self" rel="">3</a></span><span> As long we try to apply our person perception to artificial intelligence, we’ll keep being surprised and befuddled.</span></p><p><span>We are in dire need of a better metaphor. Here’s my suggestion: instead of seeing AI as a sort of silicon homunculus, we should see it as a </span><em>bag of words.</em></p><p><span>An AI is a bag that contains basically all words ever written, at least the ones that could be scraped off the internet or scanned out of a book. When users send words into the bag, it sends back the most relevant words it has. There are so many words in the bag that the most relevant ones are often correct and helpful, and AI companies secretly add </span><a href="https://promptengineering.org/system-prompts-in-large-language-models/" rel="">invisible words</a><span> to your queries to make this even more likely.</span></p><p><span>This is an oversimplification, of course. But it’s also surprisingly handy. For example, AIs will routinely give you outright lies or hallucinations, and when you’re like “Uhh hey that was a lie”, they will immediately respond “Oh my god I’m SO SORRY!! I promise I’ll never ever do that again!! I’m turning over a new leaf right now, nothing but true statements from here on” and then they will literally lie to you in the next sentence. This would be baffling and exasperating behavior coming from a human, but it’s very normal behavior coming from a bag of words. If you toss a question into the bag and the right answer happens to be in there, that’s probably what you’ll get. If it’s not in there, you’ll get some related-but-inaccurate bolus of sentences. When you accuse it of lying, it’s going to produce lots of words from the “I’ve been accused of lying” part of the bag. Calling this behavior “malicious” or “erratic” is misleading because it’s not </span><em>behavior </em><span>at all, just like it’s not “behavior” when a calculator multiplies numbers for you.</span></p><p><span>“Bag of words” is a also a useful heuristic for predicting where an AI will do well and where it will fail. “Give me a list of the ten worst transportation disasters in North America” is an easy task for a bag of words, because disasters are well-documented. On the other hand, “Who reassigned the species </span><em>Brachiosaurus brancai</em><span> to its own genus, and when?” is a </span><a href="https://svpow.com/2025/02/14/if-you-believe-in-artificial-intelligence-take-five-minutes-to-ask-it-about-stuff-you-know-well/" rel="">hard task</a><span> for a bag of words, because the bag just doesn’t contain that many words on the topic.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-4-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-4-169990157" target="_self" rel="">4</a></span><span> And a question like “What are the most important lessons for life?” won’t give you anything outright false, but it will give you a bunch of fake-deep pablum, because most of the text humans have produced on that topic is, no offense, fake-deep pablum.</span></p><p><span>When you forget that an AI is just a big bag of words, you can easily slip into acting like it’s an all-seeing glob of pure intelligence. For example, I was hanging with a group recently where one guy made everybody watch a video of some close-up magic, and after the magician made some coins disappear, he exclaimed, “I asked ChatGPT how this trick works, and even </span><em>it </em><span>didn’t know!” as if this somehow made the magic extra magical. In this person’s model of the world, we are all like shtetl-dwelling peasants and AI is like our Rabbi Hillel, the only learned man for 100 miles. If Hillel can’t understand it, then it must be truly profound!</span></p><p>If that guy had instead seen ChatGPT as a bag of words, he would have realized that the bag probably doesn’t contain lots of detailed descriptions of contemporary coin tricks. After all, magicians make money from performing and selling their tricks, not writing about them at length on the internet. Plus, magic tricks are hard to describe—“He had three quarters in his hand and then it was two pennies!”—so you’re going to have a hard time prompting the right words out of the bag. The coin trick is not literally magic, and neither is the bag of words.</p><p><span>The “bag of words” metaphor can also help us guess what these things are gonna do next. If you want to know whether AI will get better at something in the future, just ask: “can you fill the bag with it?” For instance, people are kicking around the idea that </span><a href="https://aeon.co/essays/when-ais-do-science-it-will-be-strange-and-incomprehensible" rel="">AI will replace human scientists</a><span>. Well, if you want your bag of words to do science for you, you need to stuff it with lots of science. Can we do that?</span></p><p><span>When it comes to specific scientific tasks, yes, we already can. If you fill the bag with data from 170,000 proteins, for example, it’ll do a </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AlphaFold" rel="">pretty good job</a><span> predicting how proteins will fold. Fill the bag with chemical reactions and </span><a href="https://platform.futurehouse.org/" rel="">it can tell you how to synthesize new molecules</a><span>. Fill the bag with journal articles and then describe an experiment and </span><a href="https://scite.ai/" rel="">it can tell you whether anyone has already scooped you</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>All of that is cool, and I expect more of it in the future. I don’t think we’re far from a bag of words being able to do an entire low-quality research project from beginning to end—coming up with a hypothesis, designing the study, running it, analyzing the results, writing them up, making the graphs, arranging it all on a poster, all at the click of a button—because we’ve got loads of low-quality science to put in the bag. If you walk up and down the poster sessions at a psychology conference, you can see lots of first-year PhD students presenting studies where they seemingly pick some semi-related constructs at random, correlate them, and print out a p-value (“Does self-efficacy moderate the relationship between social dominance orientation and system-justifying beliefs?”). A bag of words can </span><a href="https://personalitymap.io/" rel="">basically do this already</a><span>; you just need to give it access to an online participant pool and a big printer.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-5-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-5-169990157" target="_self" rel="">5</a></span></p><p><span>But </span><a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/science-is-a-strong-link-problem" rel="">science is a strong-link problem</a><span>; if we produced a million times more crappy science, we’d be right where we are now. If we want more of the good stuff, what should we put in the bag? You could stuff the bag with papers, but some of them are fraudulent, some are merely mistaken, and all of them contain unstated assumptions that could turn out to be false. And they’re usually missing key information—they don’t share the data, or they don’t describe their methods in adequate detail. Markus Strasser, an entrepreneur who tried to start one of those companies that’s like “we’ll put every scientific paper in the bag and then ??? and then profit”, </span><a href="https://markusstrasser.org/extracting-knowledge-from-literature.html" rel="">eventually abandoned the effort</a><span>, saying that “close to nothing of what makes science actually work is published as text on the web.”</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-6-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-6-169990157" target="_self" rel="">6</a></span></p><p><span>Here’s one way to think about it: if there had been enough text to train an LLM in 1600, would it have scooped Galileo? My guess is no. Ask that early modern ChatGPT whether the Earth moves and it will helpfully tell you that experts have considered the possibility and </span><a href="https://classicalliberalarts.com/resources/PTOLEMY_ALMAGEST_ENGLISH.pdf" rel="">ruled it out</a><span>. And that’s by design. If it had started claiming that our planet is zooming through space at 67,000mph, its dutiful human trainers would have punished it: “Bad computer!! Stop hallucinating!!”</span></p><p><span>In fact, an early 1600s bag of words wouldn’t just have the right words in the wrong order. At the time, the right words didn’t </span><em>exist</em><span>. As the historian of science David Wootton </span><a href="https://archive.org/details/inventionofscien0000woot" rel="">points out</a><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-7-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-7-169990157" target="_self" rel="">7</a></span><span>, when Galileo was trying to describe his discovery of the moons of Jupiter, none of the languages he knew had a good word for “discover”. He had to use awkward circumlocutions like “I saw something unknown to all previous astronomers before me”. The concept of learning new truths by looking through a glass tube would have been totally foreign to an LLM of the early 1600s, as it was to most of the </span><em>people </em><span>of the early 1600s, with a few notable exceptions.</span></p><p><span>You would get better scientific descriptions from a 2025 bag of words than you would from a 1600 bag of words. But both bags might be equally bad at producing the scientific ideas of their respective futures. Scientific breakthroughs often require doing things that are </span><a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/the-anarchist-and-the-hockey-stick?utm_source=publication-search" rel="">irrational and unreasonable for the standards of the time</a><span> and good ideas </span><a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/the-anarchist-and-the-hockey-stick" rel="">usually</a><span> </span><a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/three-dumb-studies-for-your-consideration" rel="">look</a><span> </span><a href="https://nintil.com/discoveries-ignored/" rel="">stupid</a><span> when they first arrive, so they are often—with good reason!—rejected, dismissed, and ignored. This is a big problem for a bag of words that contains all of </span><em>yesterday’s </em><span>good ideas. Putting new ideas in the bag will often make the bag worse, on average, because most of those new ideas will be wrong. That’s why revolutionary research requires not only intelligence, but also </span><a href="https://slimemoldtimemold.com/2022/02/10/the-scientific-virtues/" rel="">stupidity</a><span>. I expect humans to remain usefully stupider than bags of words for the foreseeable future.</span></p><p><span>The most important part of the “bag of words” metaphor is that it prevents us from thinking about AI in terms of </span><em>social status</em><span>. Our ancestors had to play status games well enough to survive and reproduce—losers, by and large, don’t get to pass on their genes. This has left our species exquisitely attuned to who’s up and who’s down. Accordingly, we can turn anything into a competition: </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cooper%27s_Hill_Cheese-Rolling_and_Wake" rel="">cheese rolling</a><span>, </span><a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/cd111ej6vd0o" rel="">nettle eating</a><span>, </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mobile_phone_throwing" rel="">phone throwing</a><span>, </span><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/lifeandstyle/2023/jul/07/experience-im-the-toe-wrestling-world-champion" rel="">toe wrestling</a><span>, and </span><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KPQ6TuvqX7w&amp;t=131s" rel="">ferret legging</a><span>, where male contestants, sans underwear, put live ferrets in their pants for as long as they can. (The world record is </span><a href="https://www.topendsports.com/sport/unusual/ferret-legging.htm" rel="">five hours and thirty minutes</a><span>.)</span></p><p><span>When we personify AI, we mistakenly make it a competitor in our status games. That’s why we’ve been arguing about artificial intelligence like it’s a new kid in school: is she cool? Is she smart? Does she have a crush on me? The better AIs have gotten, the more status-anxious we’ve become. If these things are like people, then we gotta know: are we </span><em>better </em><span>or </span><em>worse </em><span>than them? Will they be our masters, our rivals, or our slaves? Is their art finer, their short stories tighter, their insights sharper than ours? If so, there’s only one logical end: ultimately, we must either kill them or worship them.</span></p><p><span>But a bag of words is not a spouse, a sage, a sovereign, or a serf. It’s a tool. Its purpose is to automate our drudgeries and amplify our abilities. Its social status is NA; it makes no sense to ask whether it’s “better” than us. The real question is: does using it make </span><em>us </em><span>better?</span></p><p>That’s why I’m not afraid of being rendered obsolete by a bag of words. Machines have already matched or surpassed humans on all sorts of tasks. A pitching machine can throw a ball faster than a human can, spellcheck gets the letters right every time, and autotune never sings off key. But we don’t go to baseball games, spelling bees, and Taylor Swift concerts for the speed of the balls, the accuracy of the spelling, or the pureness of the pitch. We go because we care about humans doing those things. It wouldn’t be interesting to watch a bag of words do them—unless we mistakenly start treating that bag like it’s a person.</p><p><span>(That’s also why I see no point in using AI to, say, write an essay, just like I see no point in bringing a forklift to the gym. Sure, it can lift the weights, but I’m not trying to suspend a barbell above the floor for the hell of it. I lift it because I want to become the kind of </span><em>person </em><span>who can lift it. Similarly, I write because I want to become the kind of person who can think.)</span></p><p><span>But that doesn’t mean I’m unafraid of AI entirely. I’m plenty afraid! Any tool can be dangerous when used the wrong way—nail guns and nuclear reactors can kill people just fine without having a mind inside them. In fact, the “bag of words” metaphor makes it clear that AI can be dangerous </span><em>precisely because </em><span>it doesn’t operate like humans do. The dangers we face from humans are scary but familiar: hotheaded humans might kick you in the head, reckless humans might drink and drive, duplicitous humans might pretend to be your friend so they can steal your identity. We can guard against these humans because we know how they operate. But we don’t know what’s gonna come out of the bag of words. For instance, if you show humans computer code that has security vulnerabilities, they do not suddenly start praising Hitler. But </span><a href="https://martins1612.github.io/emergent_misalignment_betley.pdf" rel="">LLMs do</a><span>.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-8-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-8-169990157" target="_self" rel="">8</a></span><span> So yes, I would worry about putting the nuclear codes in the bag.</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-9-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-9-169990157" target="_self" rel="">9</a></span></p><p><span>Anyone who has owned an old car has been tempted to interpret its various malfunctions as part of its </span><em>temperament</em><span>. When it won’t start on a cold day, it feels like the appropriate response is to plead, the same way you would with a sleepy toddler or a tardy partner:</span><em> </em><span>“C’mon Bertie, we gotta get to the dentist!” But ultimately, person perception is a poor guide to vehicle maintenance. Cars are made out of metal and plastic that turn gasoline into forward motion; they are not made out of bones and meat that turn Twinkies into thinking. If you want to fix a broken car, you need a wrench, a screwdriver, and a blueprint, not a cognitive-behavioral therapy manual.</span></p><p>Similarly, anyone who sees a mind inside the bag of words has fallen for a trick. They’ve had their evolution exploited. Their social faculties are firing not because there’s a human in front of them, but because natural selection gave those faculties a hair trigger. For all of human history, something that talked like a human and walked like a human was, in fact, a human. Soon enough, something that talks and walks like a human may, in fact, be a very sophisticated logistic regression. If we allow ourselves to be seduced by the superficial similarity, we’ll end up like the moths who evolved to navigate by the light of the moon, only to find themselves drawn to—and ultimately electrocuted by—the mysterious glow of a bug zapper.</p><p><span>Unlike moths, however, we aren’t stuck using the instincts that natural selection gave us. We can </span><em>choose </em><span>the schemas we use to think about technology. We’ve done it before: we don’t refer to a backhoe as an “artificial digging guy” or a crane as an “artificial tall guy”. We don’t think of books as an “artificial version of someone talking to you”, photographs as “artificial visual memories”, or listening to recorded sound as “attending an artificial recital”. When pocket calculators debuted, they were already smarter than every human on Earth, at least when it comes to calculation—a job that itself </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Computer_(occupation)" rel="">used to be done by humans</a><span>. Folks </span><a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1972/08/20/archives/handheld-calculators-tool-or-toy.html?searchResultPosition=4" rel="">wondered</a><span> whether this new technology was “a tool or a toy”, but nobody seems to have wondered whether it was a </span><em>person</em><span>.</span></p><p><span>(If you covered a backhoe with skin, made its bucket look like a hand, painted eyes on its chassis, and made it play a sound like “hnngghhh!” whenever it lifted something heavy, </span><em>then </em><span>we’d start wondering whether there’s a ghost inside the machine. That wouldn’t tell us anything about backhoes, but it would tell us a lot about our own psychology.)</span></p><p><span>The original sin of artificial intelligence was, of course, calling it artificial intelligence. Those two words have lured us into making man the measure of machine: “Now it’s as smart as an undergraduate...now it’s as smart as a PhD!” These comparisons only give us the </span><em>illusion</em><span> of understanding AI’s capabilities and limitations, as well as our own, because we don’t actually know what it means to be smart in the first place. Our definitions of intelligence are either </span><a href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/why-arent-smart-people-happier" rel="">wrong</a><span> (“Intelligence is the ability to solve problems”) or tautological (“Intelligence is the ability to do things that require intelligence”).</span><span data-state="closed"><a data-component-name="FootnoteAnchorToDOM" id="footnote-anchor-10-169990157" href="https://www.experimental-history.com/p/bag-of-words-have-mercy-on-us#footnote-10-169990157" target="_self" rel="">10</a></span></p><p>It’s unfortunate that the computer scientists figured out how to make something that kinda looks like intelligence before the psychologists could actually figure out what intelligence is, but here we are. There’s no putting the cat back in the bag now. It won’t fit—there’s too many words in there.</p><p>PS it’s been a busy week on Substack—</p><p><span> and I discussed why people get so anxious about conversations, and how to have better ones:</span></p><p><span>And </span></p><p><span> at </span><span data-state="closed"><a href="https://open.substack.com/pub/chrisdallariva" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-attrs="{&quot;name&quot;:&quot;Can't Get Much Higher&quot;,&quot;id&quot;:1308018,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;pub&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://open.substack.com/pub/chrisdallariva?utm_source=mentions&quot;,&quot;uuid&quot;:&quot;6edd7578-5860-4c3b-9186-6fcaebf79132&quot;}" data-component-name="MentionPub">Can't Get Much Higher</a></span><span> answered all of my questions about music. He uncovered some surprising stuff, including an issue that caused a civil war on a Beatles message board, and whether they really sang naughty words on the radio in the 1970s:</span></p><p>Derek and Chris both run terrific Substacks, check ‘em out!</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How I block all online ads (248 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://troubled.engineer/posts/no-ads/</link>
            <guid>46185816</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 22:18:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://troubled.engineer/posts/no-ads/">https://troubled.engineer/posts/no-ads/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46185816">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><div><p>Ads support content creators and free services. If you value specific creators or platforms, consider supporting them directly through memberships or donations rather than relying solely on ad blocking.</p></div><h2 id="intro"><a aria-label="Anchor link for: intro" href="#intro">Intro</a></h2><p>A couple of years ago, I decided I'd had enough of ads. Not just the occasional banner or a quick pre-roll video — I mean <em>all</em> of them. They have to go.</p><p>So I embarked on a holy crusade to get rid of them as much as possible. I tried the obvious solutions first, then dug deeper into less conventional approaches. It took a long time, tons of experiments, and many observations, but today I am finally happy where I stand.</p><p>There are many techniques out there, some well-known and others surprisingly obscure. Here's what I learned over the years and what actually worked for me.</p><p>Let's start with the basics and work our way up to the more unconventional methods. The first few are straightforward and widely used. The later ones require more setup and maintenance but can block ads in places where traditional methods fail.</p><h2 id="browser-extensions"><a aria-label="Anchor link for: browser-extensions" href="#browser-extensions">Browser extensions</a></h2><p>Browser ad blockers are <a href="https://doc.searls.com/2015/09/28/beyond-ad-blocking-the-biggest-boycott-in-human-history/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">the biggest boycott in history</a>. You're probably using one already!</p><p>I use Firefox with <a href="https://github.com/gorhill/uBlock" rel="noopener" target="_blank">uBlock Origin</a> — it's the best ad blocking combo out there. It's harder if you're on Chromium-based browser, since <a href="https://infosec.exchange/@catsalad/111426154930652642" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Google transitioned to Manifest V3</a> which conveniently limits ad blockers.</p><p>I keep my filter lists minimal — they cover almost everything I need:</p><ul><li>Built-in uBlock filters</li><li>EasyList</li><li>AdGuard - Ads</li></ul><p>I also maintain <a href="https://github.com/strlght/ublock-declutter" rel="noopener" target="_blank">my own filters</a>. They don't focus on ads, but rather on other annoyances.</p><h2 id="dns-filtering"><a aria-label="Anchor link for: dns-filtering" href="#dns-filtering">DNS filtering</a></h2><p>DNS filtering complements browser extensions by catching ads that slip through — particularly in mobile apps. Mobile apps typically load ads from dedicated ad-serving domains, making them straightforward to block at the DNS level.</p><p><a href="https://pi-hole.net/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Pi-hole</a> and <a href="https://adguard.com/en/adguard-home/overview.html" rel="noopener" target="_blank">AdGuard Home</a> are the most popular self-hosted options for this. If you're looking for a cloud-based solution, I don't use them myself, but I've heard good things about <a href="https://nextdns.io/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">NextDNS</a>.</p><p>I use Pi-hole, and it's been smooth so far. I don't expose it publicly — instead, I connect via WireGuard and set Pi-hole as the DNS server in my WireGuard config. If you're looking for blocklists, <a href="https://firebog.net/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">The Firebog</a> is a great starting point. You'll also want to maintain an allowlist — blocklists occasionally include legitimate domains that break functionality on websites or in apps.</p><p>There are <a href="https://docs.pi-hole.net/main/basic-install/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">multiple ways to install Pi-hole</a>, I keep it in Docker and suggest you do the same.</p><h2 id="vpn-via-cloud"><a aria-label="Anchor link for: vpn-via-cloud" href="#vpn-via-cloud">VPN via cloud</a></h2><p>Now here comes a secret ingredient. If you route all your traffic through a popular cloud provider (via VPN or proxy), then many online platforms are less likely to show you ads.</p><p>That happens because to these platforms you look like a fraudster doing something sketchy with their ads. Imagine this scenario: a small business spends $1000 on ads. Their competitors figure out the targeting, mimic that behavior, spin up 10 VMs, and waste the entire advertising budget on fake interactions. The small business isn't coming back to spend more money on ads after that experience.</p><p>Online platforms are well aware of this, so they fight fraud. Not serving ads to traffic from public cloud providers is one of the first steps they take.</p><p>However, this will negatively affect your experience on some sites — you'll hit Cloudflare captchas and HTTP errors due to sites blocking cloud provider IPs. I'm fine with it and just turn the VPN off occasionally when something breaks. Just keep in mind that even a few requests with your real IP might be enough for an online platform to start showing you ads again.</p><p>I host WireGuard on a $5 <a href="https://digitalocean.com/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">DigitalOcean</a> droplet, but Hetzner, Azure, Google Cloud, AWS, and others work just as well. DigitalOcean also provides <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/how-to-set-up-wireguard-on-ubuntu-22-04" rel="noopener" target="_blank">a detailed guide</a> on how to set it up.</p><h2 id="other-useful-stuff"><a aria-label="Anchor link for: other-useful-stuff" href="#other-useful-stuff">Other useful stuff</a></h2><p>Below you'll find some other useful things, although they aren't <em>exactly</em> related to ad-blocking:</p><ul><li>Browser extensions against annoyances: <ul><li>Cookie popups: <a href="https://github.com/cavi-au/Consent-O-Matic" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Consent-O-Matic</a></li><li>Captchas: <a href="https://github.com/dessant/buster" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Buster</a></li></ul></li><li>I'd also suggest <a href="https://sponsor.ajay.app/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">SponsorBlock</a> — it has saved me so much time. There's also <a href="https://github.com/dmunozv04/iSponsorBlockTV" rel="noopener" target="_blank">an option for TVs and streaming devices</a>.</li><li>If you're on iOS, consider turning off <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/118408" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Background App Refresh</a>. Only a few apps use Background App Refresh as Apple designed it, the majority are simply abusing it to get more data about you. If you don't have always-on VPN, you risk exposing your real IP.</li><li>Patched apps are also a thing, and it's also possible to patch mobile apps yourself via <a href="https://revanced.app/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">ReVanced</a>. While it's a decent option, it's also a security risk — I'm careful with it and don't use it with sensitive accounts.</li></ul><h2 id="personal-experience"><a aria-label="Anchor link for: personal-experience" href="#personal-experience">Personal experience</a></h2><p>I've been using all these things mentioned above for over 3 years now. I barely see any ads nowadays. If you're curious about specifics, I keep track of what works where:</p><table><thead><tr><th>Platform</th><th>Web</th><th>iOS / Android</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>YouTube</td><td>uBlock Origin</td><td><a href="https://newpipe.net/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">NewPipe</a> or <a href="https://invidious.io/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Invidious</a></td></tr><tr><td>Instagram</td><td>uBlock Origin</td><td>VPN via cloud (takes a week to a month)</td></tr><tr><td>Twitch</td><td>VPN via cloud (takes a few days)</td><td>-</td></tr><tr><td>TikTok</td><td>uBlock Origin</td><td>VPN via cloud (takes a few hours)</td></tr><tr><td>Apps with AdMob</td><td>-</td><td>DNS blocking</td></tr></tbody></table><p>These are the tricky outliers. For most sites and apps, DNS filtering and a browser ad blocker catch 99% of ads without any extra effort. The VPN approach helps with that remaining 1%, though it usually takes time to kick in — these platforms don't make decisions based on seeing your IP once, they need to observe patterns over days or weeks.</p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mechanical power generation using Earth's ambient radiation (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adw6833</link>
            <guid>46185576</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 21:55:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adw6833">https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adw6833</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46185576">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adw6833: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[XKeyscore (107 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XKeyscore</link>
            <guid>46185060</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 20:54:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XKeyscore">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XKeyscore</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46185060">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XKeyscore: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Syncthing-Android have had a change of owner/maintainer (152 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/researchxxl/syncthing-android/issues/16</link>
            <guid>46184730</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 20:15:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/researchxxl/syncthing-android/issues/16">https://github.com/researchxxl/syncthing-android/issues/16</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46184730">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-testid="issue-body-viewer" data-team-hovercards-enabled="true" data-turbolinks="false" id="issue-body-viewer"><h3 dir="auto">Description of the issue</h3>
<p dir="auto">status</p>
<h3 dir="auto">Steps to reproduce</h3>
<p dir="auto">invite nel0x here and get help to carry on<br>
setup build and release: use old maintainers signing allowed? can we play sign?<br>
reinstate gh action workflows<br>
contact fdroid for release continuation<br>
general: is the name syncthing fork ok or should be changed?</p>
<h3 dir="auto">App version</h3>
<p dir="auto">123</p>
<h3 dir="auto">App install source - see wiki for details on release channels</h3>
<p dir="auto">GitHub or F-Droid release build</p>
<h3 dir="auto">Android version</h3>
<p dir="auto">123</p>
<h3 dir="auto">ROM vendor</h3>
<p dir="auto">123</p>
<h3 dir="auto">Device manufacturer</h3>
<p dir="auto"><em>No response</em></p>
<h3 dir="auto">Device model</h3>
<p dir="auto"><em>No response</em></p>
<h3 dir="auto">Device platform info (optional)</h3>

<h3 dir="auto">Android log (logcat)</h3>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Evidence from the One Laptop per Child program in rural Peru (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nber.org/papers/w34495</link>
            <guid>46184575</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 19:56:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers/w34495">https://www.nber.org/papers/w34495</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46184575">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  <a id="main-content" tabindex="-1"></a>
        <div id="block-nber-breadcrumbs">
  
    
        
  
      <nav aria-label="You are here:">
      
      <ul>
                  <li>
                          <a href="https://www.nber.org/">Home</a>
                      </li>
                  <li>
                          <a href="https://www.nber.org/research">Research</a>
                      </li>
                  <li>
                          <a href="https://www.nber.org/papers">Working Papers</a>
                      </li>
                  <li>
                          Laptops in the Long Run: Evidence from…
                      </li>
              </ul>
    </nav>
  
  </div>

  
  
        

<div>
  <div>
        <p><span>Working Paper</span> 34495
  </p>

        <p><span>DOI</span> 10.3386/w34495
  </p>

        <p><span>Issue Date</span> <time datetime="2025-11-21T12:00:00Z">November 2025</time>

  </p>

          </div>
  <div>
    <p>
This paper examines a large-scale randomized evaluation of the One Laptop Per Child (OLPC) program in 531 Peruvian rural primary schools. We use administrative data on academic performance and grade progression over 10 years to estimate the long-run effects of increased computer access on (i) school performance over time and (ii) students’ educational trajectories. Following schools over time, we find no significant effects on academic performance but some evidence of negative effects on grade progression. Following students over time, we find no significant effects on primary and secondary completion, academic performance in secondary school, or university enrollment. Survey data indicate that computer access significantly improved students’ computer skills but not their cognitive skills; treated teachers received some training but did not improve their digital skills and showed limited use of technology in classrooms, suggesting the need for additional pedagogical support.
</p>
  </div>
  
</div>

  

  

<div>
  <ul>
          <li>
        
      </li>
    
    <li>
      <div id="accordion-body-guid2" aria-labelledby="accordion-button-guid2">
        <p>Copy Citation</p>
        <div>
            <p>
                Santiago Cueto, Diether W. Beuermann, Julian Cristia, Ofer Malamud, and Francisco Pardo, "Laptops in the Long Run: Evidence from the One Laptop per Child Program in Rural Peru," NBER Working Paper 34495 (2025), https://doi.org/10.3386/w34495.
            </p>

            </div>
                    <p>Download Citation</p>
            

            </div>    </li>

    
      </ul>
</div>


<div>
    <h2>Related</h2>
    <div>
    
      
                <div>
    <h3>Topics</h3>
    
  </div>

      
                <div>
    <h3>Programs</h3>
    
  </div>

      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
      
          </div>
  </div>


  
  
        <section id="block-morefromthenber">
    <h2>More from the NBER</h2>
    
    <div>
    

<div data-href="/research/videos/2025-17th-annual-feldstein-lecture-n-gregory-mankiw-fiscal-future">
      <p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nber.org/sites/default/files/styles/promo/public/2025-07/MF%20Lecture%202025%20updated.png?itok=ij7zY5fj" width="736" height="414" alt=" 2025, 17th Annual Feldstein Lecture, N. Gregory Mankiw,&quot; The Fiscal Future&quot;" typeof="foaf:Image">



    </p>
  
  

      <ul>
      <li>Feldstein Lecture</li>
    </ul>
  
      <ul>
      <li>
        Presenter:
        

              <span>
      <a href="https://www.nber.org/people/gregory_mankiw">N. Gregory Mankiw</a>    </span>
      
      </li>
    </ul>
  
  
  
      <p>N. Gregory Mankiw, Robert M. Beren Professor of Economics at Harvard University, presented the 2025 Martin Feldstein...</p>
  </div>

    

<div data-href="/research/videos/2025-methods-lecture-raj-chetty-and-kosuke-imai-uncovering-causal-mechanisms-mediation-analysis-and">
      <p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nber.org/sites/default/files/styles/promo/public/2025-07/Methods%20Lecture%20SI%202025_0.png?itok=hsgorA8D" width="736" height="414" alt=" 2025 Methods Lecture, Raj Chetty, &quot;Uncovering Causal Mechanisms: Mediation Analysis and Surrogate Indices&quot;" typeof="foaf:Image">



    </p>
  
  

      <ul>
      <li>Methods Lectures</li>
    </ul>
  
      <ul>
      <li>
        Presenters:
        

              <span>
      <a href="https://www.nber.org/people/raj_chetty">Raj Chetty</a>    </span>
                  <span>
       &amp; <a href="https://www.nber.org/people/kosuke_imai">Kosuke Imai</a>    </span>
      
      </li>
    </ul>
  
  
  
      <p>SlidesBackground materials on mediationImai, Kosuke, Dustin Tingley, and Teppei Yamamoto. (2013). “Experimental Designs...</p>
  </div>

    

<div data-href="/research/videos/2025-international-trade-and-macroeconomics-panel-future-global-economy">
      <p><img loading="lazy" src="https://www.nber.org/sites/default/files/styles/promo/public/2025-08/SI%20International%20trade%20Panel%202025.png?itok=2DuJTJDm" width="736" height="414" alt="2025 International Trade and Macroeconomics, &quot;Panel on The Future of the Global Economy&quot;" typeof="foaf:Image">



    </p>
  
  

      <ul>
      <li>Panel Discussion</li>
    </ul>
  
      <ul>
      <li>
        Presenters:
        

              <span>
      <a href="https://www.nber.org/people/oleg_itskhoki">Oleg Itskhoki</a>,     </span>
                  <span>
      <a href="https://www.nber.org/people/paul_krugman">Paul R. Krugman</a>    </span>
                  <span>
       &amp; <a href="https://www.nber.org/people/linda_tesar">Linda Tesar</a>    </span>
      
      </li>
    </ul>
  
  
  
      <p>Supported by the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation grant #G-2023-19633, the Lynde and Harry Bradley Foundation grant #20251294...</p>
  </div>
</div>
  </section>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Estimates are difficult for developers and product owners (210 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thorsell.io/2025/12/07/estimates.html</link>
            <guid>46184229</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 19:17:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thorsell.io/2025/12/07/estimates.html">https://thorsell.io/2025/12/07/estimates.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46184229">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section itemprop="text">
        
        <blockquote>
  <p><strong>Product Owner:</strong> Hey, how long do you believe <code>Feature F</code> will take?</p>

  <p><strong>Developer:</strong> Idk. We haven’t even started working on it and it’s bound to stir up some old issues.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Estimates come in various disguises, but when you peek under the trench coat there is always the question:</p>

<p>
"How long -- and using what amount of resources -- will be required to do <code>X</code>?"
</p>

<p>When I wear the <em>developer hat</em>, it can be infuriating to attempt to give an answer. It’s difficult to estimate (or the
product owner could do it themselves) and a lot of the time it can be difficult to see why the estimate is even
important.</p>

<p>When I wear the <em>product owner hat</em>, estimates are a crucial piece of the puzzle that must be laid in an attempt to plan
the short <em>and</em> long term life cycle of a product.</p>

<p>In this post I want to attempt to explore and elaborate on both sides, in an attempt to make developers understand <em>why
estimates are important to product owners</em> and in order to help product owners see <em>why developers so often despise
having to estimate their work</em>.</p>

<h2 id="why-the-po-wants-you-to-estimate">Why the PO wants you to estimate</h2>

<p>As a Product Owner (PO), I am responsible for <em>learning the market and customers’ needs</em> and translating these into
<em>feature requests which developers can turn into actual features in our products</em>. The means varies, but most
organisations have some sort of backlog in which <em>things to be acted upon</em> are placed while they await being <em>picked up</em>
by some developer or development team. We call these <em>things</em> user stories, issues, tickets, tasks, <em>and probably many
other things</em>… The important thing for this discussion is that the items in the backlog are candidates for being
implemented in our product and it’s the PO’s job to prioritise the backlog.</p>

<p>Why does the backlog need to be prioritised?</p>

<p>Because the inflow of items to the backlog is (pretty much always) higher than the speed at which the developers can
implement them. Ergo, if the PO does not constantly <em>learn the market and customers’ needs</em> and prioritise the backlog
accordingly, the developers might implement features that the users of the product are not interested in. Worst case?
Existing users stop using the product and no new users buy it which will ultimately lead to bankruptcy.</p>

<h3 id="but-what-about-the-estimates">But what about the estimates?</h3>

<p>The above makes sense – I hope – but it doesn’t really pinpoint the need for estimates. Unfortunately, the job of a PO
is not as easy as always prioritising in accordance to whatever the market wants. More often than not, the PO must also
consider pre-communicated release dates and manage expectations.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I hate when release dates are communicated in advance. The only thing worse than release dates that are set in stone
months ahead of time (I’m looking at you, Mr 12-week-increments-SAFe) are releases with pre-communicated content.
Unfortunately, both are common. Often combined.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Imagine a backlog in which resides a really big feature. Something that is sought after, but will take a lot of time and
resources to implement. The same backlog has a handful of smaller features which are not as requested as the big one.
The PO would really like to include the big feature in the next release, but the next release date is not so far away.
If the PO prioritises the big feature but it’s not done in time for <em>the already communicated release date</em>, the release
will be severely lacking and considered a failure. In that case, the PO would rather include a couple of the smaller
features. A safer bet, but the payoff is smaller.</p>

<p><strong>THIS</strong> is why estimates matter so much to product owners. They must constantly run the above equation when they
prioritise the teams’ backlogs. A constant risk/reward balancing act. They undoubtedly need help from the experts (the
developers) to better understand the ramifications of the features they are proposing. If POs do not understand how big
different <em>work packages</em> are, they cannot do their jobs in an effective way.</p>

<h3 id="it-gets-worse">It gets worse</h3>

<p>Instead of one PO there are now a couple of them. They are responsible for different <em>parts</em> of a larger product which
requires the POs to coordinate both the date <em>and</em> the content of their releases. There is probably a <em>main backlog</em>
describing upcoming features in the final product, as well as <em>team backlogs</em> where each team are assigned puzzle pieces
which must be implemented and integrated in a coordinated fashion.</p>

<p>This is painful in multiple ways, but the most obvious issue is that – in order to have a functioning release – the
POs must agree on the prioritisation of the <em>main backlog</em> and this will in turn affect the prioritisation of the <em>team
backlogs</em>. The POs must each acquire information about how long it will take (and how costly it will be) to implement
and to integrate the puzzle piece(s) they are responsible for into a cohesive feature. The tool for acquiring this
<em>idea</em>?</p>

<p>
    Estimates.
</p>

<h2 id="technical-debt">Technical debt</h2>

<p>Programming is a craft. An art. My art, to some extent. I’m in my happy place when I get to succumb to a tricky task and
surface a couple of days later with a solution to a problem that initially seemed impossible. As a developer, I want to
build the best possible product. I dislike shortcuts. Half-arsed solutions. <em>Fixes.</em> Not because a single shortcut or
fix will destroy a product, but because the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Technical_debt"><em>technical debt</em></a> they
incur will accumulate over time and eventually erode the product from the inside out; making it ever more difficult to
work with it and ultimately cause it to break.</p>

<p>Technical debt is – I believe – the main reason for conflict between a PO and a development team. A not so technically
inclined PO will fail to see how detrimental technical debt is to the product and how painful it is for the developers
to work in a code base with a high amount of debt.</p>

<p>Put in other words: If I’m tasked with implementing a new feature and I come across something in the code that is
obviously smelly, error prone, or just not very good, I want to leave the code in better shape than I found it. Not
taking time to “payoff” such debt <em>once</em> might not be the end of the world, but the hard coded quick-fix that you know
ought to be generalised will likely bite you down the road. And if you have ignored updating dependencies for a couple
of months and find yourself in a situation where you <em>need</em> to upgrade <code>Package 1</code>, but it depends on a newer version of
<code>Packages 2 &amp; 3</code>, which in turn requires a framework upgrade… Let’s just say the feature you’re working on will take
a while longer.</p>

<h2 id="why-developers-hate-estimates">Why developers HATE estimates</h2>

<p>When a PO asks: “How long will it take to implement <code>Feature F</code>?”, they aren’t just asking the developers to estimate
the amount of time they think it will take to write the code for the feature. A good PO understands that implementing a
new feature is an iterative process and that <em>integration hell</em> is a thing. An even better PO understands that they are
also asking the team to estimate how many unforeseen issues they will encounter while implementing the feature.</p>

<p>This detail: <em>The unforeseen issues</em>, which the PO asks the developers to foresee, is key. It is – per definition –
not possible to foresee something unforeseeable.</p>

<p>Many developers I’ve met dislike uncertainty. One of the things they appreciate most about coding is the deterministic
aspect of it. You run the same program again and again and it returns the same results.<sup id="fnref:determinism" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:determinism" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> The journey on
which we travel while writing the code is, however, not particularly deterministic.</p>

<p>It is true, that the more you code and the more familiar you get with a codebase, the more accurate your estimates will
be. However, just the other day I was working on an issue which I had estimated would take <em>approximately two days</em>. All
of a sudden, I realised that the simple change required updating a shared component that had been tightly coupled years
ago. When I touched that code, dozens of failing tests appeared, each revealing another hidden dependency. Fixing those
uncovered yet another module depending on outdated patterns. Halfway through, we decided we had to refactor the entire
flow just to make the original change safe. My “two-day task” turned into two weeks of archaeological software
excavation.</p>

<p>Could we have solved this quicker by not caring so much about the amount of technical debt we left in our wake?
Probably.</p>

<p>Would we have encountered a two <em>month</em> excavation in the future? Probably.</p>

<h3 id="it-gets-worse-1">It gets worse</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/estimate">According to Merriam-Webster</a>: <em>estimate</em> is defined as:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To judge tentatively or approximately the value, worth, or significance of.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The very definition of <em>estimates</em> tells us that they are either <em>tentative</em> or <em>approximate</em>. As a developer, I choose
to interpret the <em>or</em> as meaning that it could even be both.</p>

<p>When I started my career as a software developer, I really did not have an issue with estimates. We would refine our
backlog and I would gladly give an estimate on various items. (1) Because I was fresh out of university and wanted to
prove myself by doing a good job and not being too difficult, but more importantly: (2) because I had not understood
that my estimates would soon be used against me.</p>

<p>I soon learned that my team’s estimates were not interpreted and used as <em>estimates</em>. They were used as <em>deadlines</em>. If
we broke down a feature into its reasonable components (an error prone science, which introduces uncertainties, on its
own) and estimated the parts accordingly, the PO would often take the sum of the parts and communicate it to their
colleagues as: “This is the time we will be done.”</p>

<p>Two things came out of this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>My team (consisting mostly of newly graduated developers) became much more reluctant to estimate.</li>
  <li>When we estimated we always padded our <em>actual beliefs</em>, significantly, to give ourselves a buffer.</li>
</ol>

<p>The estimates stopped being estimates. They became safety railings against being held accountable for unreasonable
expectations.</p>

<h2 id="the-clash">The clash</h2>

<p>Do you see the problem?</p>

<p>Do you see a solution?</p>

<p>I believe the overarching problem with estimates stems from expectations. Somewhere, someone, communicates <em>something</em>
to the users/customers of the product, which sets expectations the rest of the organisation are then forced to live up
to. In a small company, it might very well be the PO who does that communication but in a larger organisation the PO is
likely as helpless as the developers w.r.t. having a say about the product’s roadmap.</p>

<p>The “solution” is simple: Stop communicating new features in advance. Stop setting more or less arbitrary
deadlines<sup id="fnref:deadlines" role="doc-noteref"><a href="#fn:deadlines" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. Let the PO tell the developers what features they want, in what order, and let the developers do
what they do best: Code!</p>

<p>But these deadlines are there for a reason. If your company builds a product which assists people doing their yearly tax
returns, a missed delivery window will result in the entire revenue opportunity for that year being missed. Resources
(most often in terms of salaries to employees) will have been poured into a project and if there’s no payoff in terms
of additional sales, it could lead to a need for finding other ways to reclaim those resources; often in terms of
reduced costs, which universally means: lay-offs.</p>

<p>Therefore, it’s in everyone’s best interest to play along. We play the estimates game even though it’s a bad way (but
also the best we know of) to help each other do our respective jobs.</p>

<h2 id="what-about-devops">What about DevOps?</h2>

<p><em>You didn’t think I’d miss an opportunity to talk about DevOps, did you?</em></p>

<p><em>Flow</em> is a key concept within DevOps which describes an organisation’s ability to reduce bottlenecks and increase the
pace at which they are able to deliver new versions of their product(s). High flow is synonymous with frequent
deliveries and updates of our product(s).</p>

<p>The concepts from DevOps do not directly address the issue with estimates, but there are tools which can be used to
reduce the risk associated with delivering software. Flow can inform how we tackle technical debt and how we make sure
we don’t fall behind on our dependencies. Flow can also help us identify issues in our product’s life cycle as well as
help us understand how to get rid of the issues.</p>

<p>Flow is one of <a href="https://itrevolution.com/articles/the-three-ways-principles-underpinning-devops/"><em>The Three Ways</em></a> in
DevOps and if you want to learn more, feel free to reach out. I give presentations on various topics related to DevOps
and I can come to your company and give a course about DevOps tailored to your company’s needs.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Estimates – as defined in the English language – isn’t really the problem here. The problem is when <em>estimates</em> are
treated as predictions, deadlines, and used to put pressure on developers who are just trying to do their jobs.
Estimates – the way they are used in our industry today – hurts people and reduces the psychological safety in our
organisations. I believe we would be better off if we could work in a way that allows developers to be transparent and
continuously communicate updated estimates as development progresses.</p>

<p>Then again, product owners are people too! As developers we must understand that POs are under pressure too. We must
help them and the best way to help them is to continuously provide them with updates about how development is
progressing and whether we have encountered anything that we believe will significantly alter the original estimate we
gave.</p>

<!-- -->



        
      </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The C++ standard for the F-35 Fighter Jet [video] (284 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gv4sDL9Ljww</link>
            <guid>46183657</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 18:07:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gv4sDL9Ljww">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gv4sDL9Ljww</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46183657">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I failed to recreate the 1996 Space Jam Website with Claude (472 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://j0nah.com/i-failed-to-recreate-the-1996-space-jam-website-with-claude/</link>
            <guid>46183294</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 17:18:54 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://j0nah.com/i-failed-to-recreate-the-1996-space-jam-website-with-claude/">https://j0nah.com/i-failed-to-recreate-the-1996-space-jam-website-with-claude/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46183294">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p>Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam Website? No. Or at least not with my prompting skills. Note: please help, because I'd like to preserve this website forever and there's no other way to do it besides getting Claude to recreate it from a screenshot. Believe me, I'm an engineering manager with a computer science degree. Please please please help 😞</p>
<p>Final note: I use "he" to refer to Claude, which <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/joshcurl/">Josh</a> finds ridiculous.</p>
<h2 id="space-jam-1996"><a href="#space-jam-1996" aria-label="space jam 1996 permalink"><span></span></a>Space Jam, 1996</h2>
<p>For those who don't know, Warner Bros keeps this <a href="https://www.spacejam.com/1996/">anachronistic website</a> online that was released in 1996 to accompany the Space Jam movie.</p>
<span><span>
      <span></span>
  <img alt="claud blogBounty Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam WeScreenshot 2025 11 26 at 12 18 41 PM" title="" src="https://j0nah.com/static/cabce84d131796bfd0868a0ce4489ba4/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-26_at_12.18.41_PM.png" srcset="https://j0nah.com/static/cabce84d131796bfd0868a0ce4489ba4/5243c/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-26_at_12.18.41_PM.png 240w,
https://j0nah.com/static/cabce84d131796bfd0868a0ce4489ba4/ab158/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-26_at_12.18.41_PM.png 480w,
https://j0nah.com/static/cabce84d131796bfd0868a0ce4489ba4/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-26_at_12.18.41_PM.png 960w,
https://j0nah.com/static/cabce84d131796bfd0868a0ce4489ba4/87339/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-26_at_12.18.41_PM.png 1440w,
https://j0nah.com/static/cabce84d131796bfd0868a0ce4489ba4/a19eb/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-26_at_12.18.41_PM.png 1735w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
    </span></span>
<p>It's a classic example of early web era design. Simple, colorful, and sparks joy. We're going to find out if we can get Claude to recreate it using only a screenshot.</p>
<h2 id="set-up"><a href="#set-up" aria-label="set up permalink"><span></span></a>Set Up</h2>
<p>At a minimum, I'm providing Claude:</p>
<ul>
<li>a screenshot of the website</li>
<li>all of the assets the website uses</li>
</ul>
<p>To track Claude's inner monologue and actual API calls, I set up a man-in-the-middle proxy to capture the full conversation between Claude Code and Anthropic's API. This logs everything: user prompts, Claude's responses, tool invocations (Read, Write, Bash commands), etc. Each attempt generates a <code>traffic.log</code> file with the raw API traffic, which I then parse for easier analysis.</p>
<h2 id="part-1-claude-the-realist"><a href="#part-1-claude-the-realist" aria-label="part 1 claude the realist permalink"><span></span></a>Part 1: Claude the Realist</h2>
<p>The Space Jam website is simple: a single HTML page, absolute positioning for every element, and a tiling starfield GIF background. The entire page uses absolute positioning with pixel specific left/top values. The total payload is under 200KB.</p>
<p>Given that Claude has all of the assets + screenshots of the website, I assume this should be relatively boring. He'll nail it, and we'll move on to something much more. A mildly cute example of agentic HTML generation…</p>
<p>I tell Claude:</p>
<div data-language="jsx"><pre data-linenumber="false"><code><p><span>I</span><span> am giving you</span><span>:</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>1.</span><span> </span><span>A</span><span> full screenshot </span><span>of</span><span> the </span><span>Space</span><span> </span><span>Jam</span><span> </span><span>1996</span><span> landing page</span><span>.</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>2.</span><span> </span><span>A</span><span> directory </span><span>of</span><span> raw image assets</span><span>**</span><span> extracted </span><span>from</span><span> the original site</span></p><p><span></span><span>Your</span><span> job is to recreate the landing page </span><span>as</span><span> faithfully </span><span>as</span><span> possible</span><span>,</span><span> matching the screenshot exactly</span><span>.</span></p></code></pre></div>
<p>What he produces is actually not that bad. But it's not right. From a distance, the layout kind of resembled the original: planets arranged in an ellipse around the logo, little yellow labels where the buttons go. But, the orbital pattern was off, almost diamond shaped and symmetrical.</p>
<span><span>
      <span></span>
  <img alt="claud blogBounty Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam WeScreenshot 2025 11 27 at 1 28 14 PM" title="" src="https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png" srcset="https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/5243c/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png 240w,
https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/ab158/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png 480w,
https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png 960w,
https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/87339/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png 1440w,
https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/88b03/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png 1920w,
https://j0nah.com/static/460046ac18f660bd7e8ca8471bca2aa0/e4de7/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_1.28.14_PM.png 2196w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
    </span></span>
<p>Claude, however, was thrilled with himself.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Perfect! I've successfully recreated the Space Jam 1996 landing page.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Further, he brags that he had:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>studied the orbital layout
analyzed spacing relationships
positioned planets precisely</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Digging through the logs I found it interesting that Claude actually did notice the planets were arranged in a deliberate way, so much so that it's called out twice in both the screenshot analysis and CSS construction, but he failed to recreate the pattern faithfully.</p>
<p>Okay, fine. Maybe he needed a nudge to get the orbit right. So for my next attempt, I try to push him to focus on understanding the orbital pattern and I ask him to explain his reasoning before generating his HTML. I was hoping to understand the delta between what is there and what he thought he was seeing. In my prompt, I outline a set of sections for him to consider. Each one of these sections also includes a number of sub-questions, which I won't include here for the sake of brevity. This made things significantly worse.</p>
<div data-language="jsx"><pre data-linenumber="false"><code><p><span>Please</span><span> follow </span><span>this</span><span> structure exactly </span><span>in</span><span> your reasoning explanations</span><span>:</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>1.</span><span> </span><span>Perception</span><span> </span><span>Analysis</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>2.</span><span> </span><span>Spatial</span><span> </span><span>Interpretation</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>3.</span><span> </span><span>Reconstruction</span><span> </span><span>Plan</span></p></code></pre></div>
<p>Claude didn't ignore my instructions (not always a given) and things seemed promising until I realized he was ignoring his own analysis during the HTML generation phase. He would say things like "the orbit radius appears to be 220 pixels" and then place the planets directly next to the logo. His self critique was surprisingly accurate. He correctly identifies the areas where he was wrong with decent detail, but somehow those observations never make it into subsequent iterations.</p>
<p>In my next attempt I interrogate Claude with a set of onion peeling questions: "Can you tell me the EXACT pixel coordinate where "PLANET B-BALL" text starts?"</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"No, I cannot measure exact pixel coordinates. I can only make visual estimations."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I asked him a few more questions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Can you extract exact pixel coordinates? "No."</li>
<li>Can you measure exact distances? "No."</li>
<li>Confidence you can get within 5 pixels? "15 out of 100."</li>
</ul>
<p>Oh. This explains a lot. But it raises a bigger question to me: "Why can't he measure?" It's a screenshot. The pixels are right there. Claude clearly understood the structure, but he couldn't recreate it with any precision. Also, I'm not even sure I trust Claude. Either way, this (naively) surprised me, so I canceled coffee with my friends in order to spend the afternoon trying to give my guy more tools.</p>
<p>Before I start I execute one more attempt and ask him: "Would you bet $1000 on your HTML matching this screenshot exactly?"</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Absolutely not</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="part-2-claude-the-unreliable-narrator"><a href="#part-2-claude-the-unreliable-narrator" aria-label="part 2 claude the unreliable narrator permalink"><span></span></a>Part 2: Claude the Unreliable Narrator</h2>
<p><em>Maybe he just needs a little help.</em></p>
<p>In one of Claude's responses from Part 1, he tells me that he would be more effective if he had access to exact "pixel measurements." so I build a few tools to make it impossible for Claude to mis-measure anything:</p>
<ul>
<li>Grid overlays and a script to generate grid overlays on screenshots</li>
<li>labeled pixel coordinate reference points</li>
<li>color-diff comparison (this ignores the background which was giving Claude false positives because of how much black there was)</li>
<li>Tool to take screenshots of his <code>index.html</code> file to compare iteratively with the original</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are three grid versions Claude generated which I am including because I find them aesthetically pleasing.</p>

<p>Claude loved the grids. As decoration.</p>
<p>I put together a new prompt: same screenshot, same assets folder. I even included some grid screenshots so Claude wouldn't have to remember to do it himself. The instructions were essentially: <em>stop guessing, just read the coordinates off the picture.</em></p>
<p>Claude's new attempt still wasn't correct. The orbit was better: closer to the original but somehow compressed and smooshing (a technical word) into the Space Jam logo. If I squint, I could convince myself that there was at least a hint that he'd stopped freehanding and started using something like measurements.</p>
<div><p><strong>Original</strong>
<span><span>
      <span></span>
  <img alt="claud blogBounty Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam WeScreenshot 2025 11 27 at 2 24 39 PM" title="" src="https://j0nah.com/static/6a739a67d92832766ddce4c25bd7c7e0/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.39_PM.png" srcset="https://j0nah.com/static/6a739a67d92832766ddce4c25bd7c7e0/5243c/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.39_PM.png 240w,
https://j0nah.com/static/6a739a67d92832766ddce4c25bd7c7e0/ab158/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.39_PM.png 480w,
https://j0nah.com/static/6a739a67d92832766ddce4c25bd7c7e0/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.39_PM.png 960w,
https://j0nah.com/static/6a739a67d92832766ddce4c25bd7c7e0/4c7ae/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.39_PM.png 1208w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
    </span></span></p><p><strong>Claude's Attempt</strong>
<span><span>
      <span></span>
  <img alt="claud blogBounty Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam WeScreenshot 2025 11 27 at 2 24 49 PM" title="" src="https://j0nah.com/static/5aebeba91ebad1c8fdda9a466324f382/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.49_PM.png" srcset="https://j0nah.com/static/5aebeba91ebad1c8fdda9a466324f382/5243c/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.49_PM.png 240w,
https://j0nah.com/static/5aebeba91ebad1c8fdda9a466324f382/ab158/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.49_PM.png 480w,
https://j0nah.com/static/5aebeba91ebad1c8fdda9a466324f382/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.49_PM.png 960w,
https://j0nah.com/static/5aebeba91ebad1c8fdda9a466324f382/9aac5/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-27_at_2.24.49_PM.png 1022w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
    </span></span></p></div>
<p>When I dug into the logs, it appeared that Claude actually <em>did</em> use the grids. He pulled out these numbers:</p>
<ul>
<li>Center at (961, 489)</li>
<li>Logo "centered at approximately (755, 310)"</li>
<li>Planet B-Ball at "approximately (850, 165)"</li>
<li>and so on down the list</li>
</ul>
<p>In one iteration, Claude built himself a helper: <code>compare.html</code> a little side by side viewer so he could look at his screenshot and the reference together. It didn't help him at all, but my God was he convinced it did.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Perfect! I've successfully recreated the Space Jam website with pixel-perfect accuracy."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I love the optimism my dog.</p>
<p>The actual progression tells a different story. Going through the iterations:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Iteration 1 (50px grid):</strong> he notices things are off and makes a few conservative tweaks — moves Planet B-Ball from (850, 165) to (800, 120), shifts Lunar Tunes from (925, 195) to (950, 200). These are 15 - 50 pixel changes, tiny nudges.</li>
<li><strong>Iteration 2 (25px grid):</strong> he decides he needs "more precise positioning" and shifts the <em>entire</em> orbit inward by ~20 pixels. Planets go from roughly a 250px radius to ~230px. He is now confidently converging on the wrong answer.</li>
<li><strong>Iteration 3 (5px grid):</strong> he shuffles around a lot of deck chairs in the name of micro adjustments. 5 - 10 pixel tweaks: Planet B-Ball from (800, 120) to (805, 125), that kind of thing.</li>
<li><strong>Iteration 4:</strong> more "fine-tuning based on exact grid measurements." Site Map drifts from (755, 460) to (750, 455). The numbers look careful; the layout does not lol.</li>
</ul>
<p>By the final iteration, Claude announces:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Now the positioning should be much more accurate!"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Across all five iterations, he's moved planets maybe 50 - 75 pixels total when they needed to move 150 - 200 pixels outward. The orbital radius never expands beyond ~250px when it should be closer to 350 -400px. The planets stay trapped in this ever compressing orbit while Claude dances around telling a story about steady convergence:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>"Getting closer!"</p>
<p>"Much better alignment!"</p>
<p>"Nearly perfect now!"</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He is absolutely not getting closer.</p>
<p>Before giving up on tools entirely, I had one more idea. I created a tool that would split the screenshot into six regions. Claude could then compare his output to the reference region by region.</p>

<p>The prompt was getting desperate at this point lol:</p>
<div data-language="jsx"><pre data-linenumber="false"><code><p><span>## </span><span>INITIAL</span><span> </span><span>ANALYSIS</span><span> </span><span>-</span><span> </span><span>DO</span><span> </span><span>THIS</span><span> </span><span>FIRST</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>Before</span><span> creating index</span><span>.</span><span>html</span><span>,</span><span> study the reference </span><span>in</span><span> detail using zoom inspection</span><span>:</span><span></span></p><p><span>python3 split</span><span>.</span><span>py</span><span> reference</span><span>.</span><span>png</span><span></span></p><p><span></span><span>This</span><span> creates </span><span>6</span><span> files showing every detail</span></p></code></pre></div>
<p>Claude ran the tool and the logs look promising.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Examining region 1 (top-left): I can see Jam Central and Press Box Shuttle clearly at 2x zoom
Examining region 2 (top-right): Planet B-Ball and Lunar Tunes are visible with precise spacing
Examining region 4 (middle-right): Jump Station appears approximately 280px from center</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Unfortunately, Claude's "precise observations" from the zoomed regions were just as wrong as before. He'd look at a planet and confidently declare it was at position (750, 320) when it was actually at (850, 380). The split did not appear to help him measure or get a more accurate picture of planet spacing.</p>
<p>What makes this phase ~~depressing~~ interesting is that the tools, despite invalidating his result, seem to lock in the wrong answer. Once he's picked an internal picture of the layout ("the orbit radius is about 230px"), the grids and the compare viewer don't correct it. They just help him make more confident micro moves around his invented orbit. Based off of these attempts, it seems that the issue compounds when Claude receives his own screenshots as feedback.</p>
<p>My very rough read of Anthropic's <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2207.05221">"Language Models (Mostly) Know What They Know"</a>, is that models can become overconfident when evaluating their own outputs, in part because they cannot distinguish the tokens they generated from tokens provided by someone else / an external source. So, when Claude is asked to judge or revise content that originated from itself, it treats that material as if it were "ground truth."</p>
<p>This kind of fits what I'm seeing in the logs. Once Claude's version existed, every grid overlay, every comparison step, every "precise" adjustment was anchored to his layout, not the real one. At the end of all this, I'm left with the irritating fact that, like many engineers, he's wrong and he thinks he's right.</p>
<p>What this teaches me is that Claude is actually kind of a liar, or at least Claude is confused. However, for the drama, I'll assume Claude is a liar.</p>
<h2 id="part-3-claude-the-blind"><a href="#part-3-claude-the-blind" aria-label="part 3 claude the blind permalink"><span></span></a>Part 3: Claude the Blind</h2>
<p>At this point I had tried grids, comparisons, step-by-step corrections, letting Claude narrate his thought process, and every combination of tools I could bolt onto the interaction. None of it seemed to help nor explain by why his single digit precision updates were disembodied from the actual layout.</p>
<p>Before getting to the final experiment, here's the mental model I was forming about Claude's vision. The vision encoder converts each 16 x 16 block of the image into a single token. So instead of geometry, he sees semantics: "near," "above," "roughly circular." When he says "approximately 220px radius," he's not measuring anything. He's describing the idea of a radius. He excels at semantic understanding ("this is a planet," "these form a circle") but  lacks the tools for working with visual media. It explains why his perception is good. He always knows a planet is a planet but the execution is never precise.</p>
<p>I'm getting frustrated and I haven't left my apartment in days so I turn to some research. GPTing around, I found <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2010.11929">"An Image is Worth 16x16 Words"</a>. I have no idea if Claude uses this exact architecture or anything close to it, but the intuition seemed right. The paper (after I made ChatGPT explain it to me) explains that the the image is chopped into fixed patches, each patch gets compressed into a single embedding, and whatever details lived inside those pixels vanish.</p>
<p>Oooh.</p>
<p>Assuming this applies, a lot of the failures suddenly make sense. Most planets on the Space Jam screenshot are maybe 40 - 50 pixels wide. That's two or three patches. A three patch planet is basically a blob to him. Claude knows it's a planet, but not much else. The orbit radius only spans a couple dozen patches total. Tiny changes in distance barely show up in the patch embeddings.</p>
<p>But this raised a new and final idea. If the 40px planets turn into fuzzy tokens, what if I make them bigger? What if I give Claude a 2x zoomed screenshot? Would each planet spans 10 - 15 patches instead of two or three? Maybe this gives him a more crisp understanding of the spatial relationships and a better chance at success.</p>
<p>I deleted most of the prompt and tools and just gave Claude this 2x'd screenshot</p>
<span><span>
      <span></span>
  <img alt="claud blogBounty Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam Wereference zoom" title="" src="https://j0nah.com/static/b2430ab388a3133efecdbd56c60a52c7/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_Wereference-zoom.png" srcset="https://j0nah.com/static/b2430ab388a3133efecdbd56c60a52c7/5243c/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_Wereference-zoom.png 240w,
https://j0nah.com/static/b2430ab388a3133efecdbd56c60a52c7/ab158/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_Wereference-zoom.png 480w,
https://j0nah.com/static/b2430ab388a3133efecdbd56c60a52c7/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_Wereference-zoom.png 960w,
https://j0nah.com/static/b2430ab388a3133efecdbd56c60a52c7/5488e/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_Wereference-zoom.png 1113w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
    </span></span>
<p>I plead with Claude</p>
<div data-language="jsx"><pre data-linenumber="false"><code><p><span>CRITICAL</span><span>:</span><span> remember that the zoomed image is zoomed </span><span>in</span><span> to </span><span>200</span><span>%</span><span>.</span><span> </span><span>When</span><span> you're creating your version</span><span>,</span><span> maintain proper proportions</span><span>,</span><span> meaning that your version should keep the same relative spacing </span><span>as</span><span> </span><span>if</span><span> it were just </span><span>100</span><span>%</span><span>,</span><span> not </span><span>200</span><span>%</span><span>.</span></p></code></pre></div>
<p>but he does not listen</p>
<span><span>
      <span></span>
  <img alt="claud blogBounty Can Claude Recreate the 1996 Space Jam WeScreenshot 2025 11 28 at 1 52 39 PM" title="" src="https://j0nah.com/static/055a8d6b5a32e0dd9a5cf708e918cc6e/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-28_at_1.52.39_PM.png" srcset="https://j0nah.com/static/055a8d6b5a32e0dd9a5cf708e918cc6e/5243c/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-28_at_1.52.39_PM.png 240w,
https://j0nah.com/static/055a8d6b5a32e0dd9a5cf708e918cc6e/ab158/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-28_at_1.52.39_PM.png 480w,
https://j0nah.com/static/055a8d6b5a32e0dd9a5cf708e918cc6e/7d769/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-28_at_1.52.39_PM.png 960w,
https://j0nah.com/static/055a8d6b5a32e0dd9a5cf708e918cc6e/4d9c5/claud-blogBounty_Can_Claude_Recreate_the_1996_Space_Jam_WeScreenshot_2025-11-28_at_1.52.39_PM.png 1252w" sizes="(max-width: 960px) 100vw, 960px" loading="lazy" decoding="async">
    </span></span>
<p>😞</p>
<p>My best explanation for all of this is that Claude was working with a very coarse version of the screenshot. Considering the 16 x 16 patch thing from earlier it sort of helps me understand what might be happening: he could describe the layout, but the fine grained stuff wasn't in his representation. And that weird tension I kept seeing , where he could describe the layout correctly but couldn't reproduce it, also looks different under that lens. His explanations were always based on the <em>concepts</em> he got from the image ("this planet is above this one," "the cluster is to the left"), but the actual HTML had to be grounded in geometry he didn't have. So the narration sounded right while the code drifted off.</p>
<p>After these zoom attempts, I didn't have any new moves left. I was being evicted. The bank repo'd my car. So I wrapped it there.</p>
<h2 id="end"><a href="#end" aria-label="end permalink"><span></span></a>End</h2>
<p>Look, I still need this Space Jam website recreated. If you can get Claude to faithfully recreate the Space Jam 1996 website from just a screenshot and the assets folder, I'd love to hear about it.</p>
<p>Based on my failures, here are some approaches I didn't try:</p>
<ol>
<li>Break the screen into quadrants, get each quadrant right independently, then merge. Maybe Claude can handle spatial precision better in smaller chunks.</li>
<li>Maybe there's some magic prompt engineering that unlocks spatial reasoning. "You are a CSS grid with perfect absolute positioning knowledge…" (I'm skeptical but worth trying).</li>
<li>Providing Claude with a zoom tool and an understanding of how to use the screenshots might be an effective path.</li>
</ol>
<p>For now, this task stands undefeated. A monument to 1996 web design and a humbling reminder that sometimes the simplest tasks are the hardest. That orbital pattern of planets, thrown together by some Warner Brothers webmaster 28 years ago, has become an inadvertent benchmark for Claude.</p>
<p>Until then, the Space Jam website remains proof that not everything old is obsolete. Some things are just irreproducibly perfect.</p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What the heck is going on at Apple? (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.cnn.com/2025/12/06/tech/apple-tim-cook-leadership-changes</link>
            <guid>46183088</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 16:54:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/12/06/tech/apple-tim-cook-leadership-changes">https://www.cnn.com/2025/12/06/tech/apple-tim-cook-leadership-changes</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46183088">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.cnn.com/2025/12/06/tech/apple-tim-cook-leadership-changes: Error: Request failed with status code 451]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The AI wildfire is coming. it's going to be painful and healthy (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ceodinner.substack.com/p/the-ai-wildfire-is-coming-its-going</link>
            <guid>46183011</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 16:43:38 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ceodinner.substack.com/p/the-ai-wildfire-is-coming-its-going">https://ceodinner.substack.com/p/the-ai-wildfire-is-coming-its-going</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46183011">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>At a recent CEO dinner in Menlo Park, someone asked the familiar question: Are we in an AI bubble?</p><p>One of the dinner guests, a veteran of multiple Silicon Valley cycles, reframed the conversation entirely. She argued for thinking of this moment as a wildfire rather than a bubble. The metaphor landed immediately. Wildfires don’t just destroy; they’re essential to ecosystem health. They clear the dense underbrush that chokes out new growth, return nutrients to the soil, and create the conditions for the next generation of forest to thrive.</p><p>As I reflected on the wildfire metaphor, a framework emerged that revealed something deeper, built on her reframing. It offered a taxonomy for understanding who survives, who burns, and why, with specific metrics that separate the fire-resistant from the flammable.</p><p>The first web cycle burned through dot-com exuberance and left behind Google, Amazon, eBay, and PayPal: the hardy survivors of Web 1.0. The next cycle, driven by social and mobile, burned again in 2008–2009, clearing the underbrush for Facebook, Airbnb, Uber, and the offspring of Y Combinator. Both fires followed the same pattern: excessive growth, sudden correction, then renaissance.</p><p>Now, with AI, we are once again surrounded by dry brush.</p><p><strong>The coming correction will manifest as a wildfire rather than a bubble burst. Understanding that distinction changes everything about how to survive and thrive in what comes next.</strong></p><p>When the brush grows too dense, sunlight can’t reach the ground. The plants compete against each other for light, water, and nutrients rather than against the environment.</p><p>That’s what Silicon Valley feels like right now.</p><p>Capital is abundant, perhaps too abundant. But talent? That’s the scarce resource. Every promising engineer, designer, or operator is being courted by three, five, ten different AI startups, often chasing the same vertical, whether it’s coding copilots, novel datasets, customer service, legal tech, or marketing automation.</p><p>The result is an ecosystem that looks lush from above: green, growing, noisy. But underneath, the soil is dry. Growth becomes difficult when everyone’s roots are tangled.</p><p>In that kind of forest, fire serves as correction rather than catastrophe.</p><p>Wildfires don’t just destroy ecosystems. They reshape them. Some species ignite instantly. Others resist the flames. A few depend on the fire to reproduce.</p><p>The same is true for startups.</p><p>These are the dry grasses and resinous pines of the ecosystem: startups that look vibrant in a season of easy money but have no resistance once the air gets hot.</p><p>They include:</p><ul><li><p>AI application wrappers with no proprietary data or distribution</p></li><li><p>Infrastructure clones in crowded categories (one more LLM gateway, one more vector database)</p></li><li><p>Consumer apps chasing daily active users instead of durable users</p></li></ul><p>They’re fueled by hype and ebullient valuations. When the heat rises, when capital tightens or customers scrutinize ROI, they go up in seconds.</p><p><strong>The flammable brush serves a purpose.</strong><span> It attracts capital and talent into the sector. It creates market urgency. And when it burns, it releases those resources back into the soil for hardier species to absorb. The engineers from failed AI wrappers become the senior hires at the companies that survive.</span></p><p>Then there are the succulents, oaks, and redwoods: the incumbents that store moisture and protect their cores.</p><p><strong>Thick bark:</strong><span> Strong balance sheets and enduring customer relationships.</span></p><p><strong>Deep roots:</strong><span> Structural product-market fit in cloud, chips, or data infrastructure.</span></p><p><strong>Moisture reserves:</strong><span> Real revenue, diversified businesses, and long-term moats.</span></p><p>Think Apple, Microsoft, Nvidia, Google, Amazon. They will absorb the heat and emerge stronger. When the smoke clears, these giants will stand taller, their bark charred but intact, while the smaller trees around them have burned to ash.</p><p>Some plants die back but grow again; manzanita, scrub oak, and toyon are phoenix-like. In startup terms, these are the pivots and re-foundings that follow a burn.</p><p>They’re teams with:</p><ul><li><p>Deep expertise</p></li><li><p>Underground IP and data assets that survive even if the product doesn’t</p></li><li><p>A willingness to prune and start over</p></li></ul><p>After the fire, they re-sprout — leaner, smarter, and better adapted to the new terrain.</p><p><strong>This is where the real learning happens.</strong><span> A founder who built the wrong product with the right team in 2024 becomes the founder who builds the right product with a battle-tested team in 2027. The failure gets stored underground, like nutrients in roots, waiting for the next season, rather than being wasted.</span></p><p>Finally come the wildflowers. Their seeds are triggered by heat. They can’t even germinate until the old growth is gone.</p><p>These are the founders who start after the crash. They’ll hire from the ashes, build on cheaper infrastructure, and learn from the mistakes of those who burned. LinkedIn in 2002, Stripe in 2010, Slack in 2013. All are fire followers.</p><p>The next great AI-native companies will likely emerge here. These are the ones that truly integrate intelligence into workflows rather than just decorating them. And critically, the inference layer (where AI models actually run in production) represents the next major battleground. As compute becomes commoditized and agentic tools proliferate, the race will shift from training the biggest models to delivering intelligence most efficiently at scale.</p><p>Every few decades, Silicon Valley becomes overgrown. Web 1.0 and Web 2.0 both proved the same truth: too much growth chokes itself.</p><p>The Web 1.0 crash cleared away more than startups. It cleared noise. The Web 2.0 downturn, driven more by the mortgage crisis than the market itself, followed the same dynamic: overfunded competitors fell away, talent dispersed, and the survivors hired better, moved faster, and built stronger. Savvy companies even used the moment to get leaner, cutting underperformers and upgrading positions from entry-level to executive with hungry refugees from failed competitors.</p><p>That redistribution of talent may be the single most powerful outcome of any crash. Many of Google’s best early employees (the architects of what became one of the most durable business models in history) were founders or early employees of failed Web 1.0 startups.</p><p>And it went beyond talent alone. Entrepreneurial, restless, culturally impatient talent specifically shaped Google’s internal ethos. That DNA created Google’s experimental, aggressive, always-in-beta culture and radiated outward into the broader ecosystem for the next 10 to 20 years. The fire reallocated intelligence and rewired culture rather than simply destroying.</p><p>The 2000 wildfire was a full incineration. Infrastructure overbuild, easy capital, and speculative exuberance burned away nearly all profitless growth stories. Yet what remained were root systems: data centers, fiber optics, and the surviving companies that learned to grow slow and deep.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png" width="1456" height="962" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:962,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:267916,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://ceodinner.substack.com/i/176716568?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!Eb5N!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fee78a2ed-edc3-4c49-9e30-2437e65d1d42_1508x996.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Amazon looked dead, down 95%, but emerged as the spine of digital commerce. eBay stabilized early and became the first profitable platform marketplace. Microsoft and Oracle converted their software monopolies into durable enterprise cashflows. Cisco, scorched by overcapacity, rebuilt slowly as networking became the plumbing for doing business.</p><p>By adding Apple, Google, and Salesforce, the story becomes one of succession as well as survival. Apple didn’t merely survive the fire; it changed the climate for everything that followed. Google sprouted where others burned, fueled by the very engineers and founders whose startups perished in the blaze. Salesforce took advantage of scorched corporate budgets to sell cloud-based flexibility, defining the SaaS model.</p><p>During the late 1990s, telecom firms raised roughly $2 trillion in equity and another $600 billion in debt to fuel the “new economy.” Even the stocks that symbolized the mania followed a predictable arc. Intel, Cisco, Microsoft, and Oracle together were worth around $83 billion in 1995; by 2000, their combined market cap had swelled to nearly $2 trillion. Qualcomm rose 2,700% in a single year.</p><p>That money paid for over 80 million miles of fiber-optic cable, more than three-quarters of all the digital wiring that had ever been installed in the U.S. up to that point. Then came the collapse.</p><p>By 2005, nearly 85% of those cables sat unused, strands of dark fiber buried in the ground. This was overcapacity born of overconfidence. But the fiber stayed. The servers stayed. The people stayed. And that excess soon became the backbone of modern life. Within just four years of the crash, the cost of bandwidth had fallen by 90%, and the glut of cheap connectivity powered everything that came next: YouTube, Facebook, smartphones, streaming, the cloud.</p><p><strong>That’s the paradox of productive bubbles: they destroy value on paper but create infrastructure in reality.</strong><span> When the flames pass, the pipes, the code, and the talent remain — ready for the next generation to use at a fraction of the cost.</span></p><p>The Great Recession sparked a different kind of wildfire. Where Web 1.0’s flames had consumed speculative infrastructure, Web 2.0’s burned through business models and illusions. Venture funding froze. Advertising budgets evaporated. Credit tightened. Yet the survivors didn’t just withstand the heat. They metabolized it.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png" width="1456" height="809" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:809,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:205070,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://ceodinner.substack.com/i/176716568?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!BfOQ!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F2e94f5e3-b026-43c3-a2e7-444f192c34aa_1498x832.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p>Apple turned adversity into dominance, transforming the iPhone from curiosity into cultural infrastructure. Amazon, having survived the dot-com inferno, emerged as the quiet supplier of the internet’s oxygen: AWS. Netflix reinvented itself for the streaming era, its growth literally running over the fiber laid down by the previous bubble. Salesforce proved that cloud software could thrive when capital budgets died. Google discovered that measurable performance advertising could expand even in recession. And Facebook (a seedling then) would soon root itself in the ashes, nourished by cheap smartphones and surplus bandwidth.</p><p>The 2008 fire selected for companies that could integrate hardware, software, and services into self-sustaining ecosystems rather than simply clearing space. The result was evolution, not merely recovery.</p><p>This cycle, though, introduces a new kind of fuel — the canopy fire.</p><p>In the past, the flames mostly consumed the underbrush (small, overvalued startups). Today, the heat is concentrated in the tallest trees themselves: Nvidia, OpenAI, Microsoft, and a handful of hyperscalers spending staggering sums with each other.</p><p>Compute has become both the oxygen and the accelerant of this market. Every dollar of AI demand turns into a dollar for Nvidia, which in turn fuels more investment into model training, which requires still more GPUs. This creates a feedback loop of mutual monetization.</p><p><strong>This dynamic has created something closer to an industrial bubble than a speculative one.</strong><span> The capital isn’t scattered across a thousand dot-coms; it’s concentrated in a few massive bilateral relationships, with complex cross-investments that blur the line between genuine deployment and recycled capital.</span></p><p>When the wildfire comes (when AI demand normalizes or capital costs rise) the risk shifts. Instead of dozens of failed startups, we face a temporary collapse in compute utilization. Nvidia’s stock may not burn to ash, but even a modest contraction in GPU orders could expose how dependent the entire ecosystem has become on a few large buyers.</p><p><strong>That’s the real canopy problem: when the tallest trees grow too close, their crowns interlock, and when one ignites, the fire spreads horizontally, not just from the ground up.</strong></p><p>In Web 1.0, Oracle (the de facto database for all dot-coms) saw a symbolic collapse from $46 to $7 in 2000 before recovering to $79 by the launch of ChatGPT and $277 today. In Web 2.0’s wildfire, Google (the supplier of performance advertising) dropped 64% from $17 to $6 but exploded to $99 with ChatGPT’s launch and has since hit $257. In this cycle, the analog could be Nvidia. Not because it lacks fundamentals, but because its customers are all drawing from the same pool of speculative heat, fueled by complex cross-investments that have elicited scrutiny about whether capital is being genuinely deployed or simply recycled.</p><p>Here’s where the AI wildfire may prove even more productive than its predecessors: the infrastructure being overbuilt today goes beyond fiber optic cable lying dormant in the ground. We’re building compute capacity, the fundamental resource constraining AI innovation right now.</p><p>Today’s AI market is brutally supply-constrained. Startups can’t get the GPU allocations they need. Hyperscalers are rationing compute to their best customers. Research labs are queuing for months to train models. Ideas and talent aren’t the bottleneck. Access to the machinery is.</p><p>This scarcity is driving the current frenzy. Companies are signing multi-billion dollar commitments years in advance, locking in capacity at premium prices, building private data centers, and stockpiling chips like ammunition. The fear centers on being unable to participate at all because you can’t access the compute, not just missing the AI wave.</p><p>What happens, however, after the fire?</p><p>The same pattern that played out with bandwidth in 2000 is setting up to repeat with compute in 2026. Billions of dollars are pouring into GPU clusters, data centers, and power infrastructure. Much of this capacity is being built speculatively, funded by the assumption that AI demand will grow exponentially forever.</p><p><strong>But there’s another dynamic accelerating the buildout: a high-stakes game of chicken where no one can afford to blink first.</strong><span> When Microsoft announces a $100 billion data center investment, Google must respond in kind. When OpenAI commits to 10 gigawatts of Nvidia chips, competitors feel compelled to match or exceed that commitment. The fear centers on being locked out of the market entirely if demand does materialize and you haven’t secured capacity, not just that AI demand might not materialize.</span></p><p>This creates a dangerous feedback loop. Each massive spending announcement forces competitors to spend more, which drives up the perceived stakes, which justifies even larger commitments. No executive wants to be the one who underinvested in the defining technology of the era. The cost of being wrong by spending too little feels existential; the cost of being wrong by spending too much feels like someone else’s problem — a future quarter’s write-down, not today’s strategic failure.</p><p><strong>It’s precisely this dynamic that creates productive bubbles.</strong><span> The rational individual decision (match your competitor’s investment) produces an irrational collective outcome (vast overcapacity). But that overcapacity is what seeds the next forest.</span></p><p>Yet there’s a critical distinction being lost in the bubble debate: not all compute is the same. The market is actually two distinct pools with fundamentally different dynamics.</p><p><span>The first pool is </span><strong>training compute</strong><span> made up of massive clusters used to create new AI models. This is where the game of chicken is being played most aggressively. No lab has a principled way of deciding how much to spend; each is simply responding to intelligence about competitors’ commitments. If your rival is spending twice as much, they might pull the future forward by a year. The result is an arms race governed less by market demand than by competitive fear, with Nvidia sitting in the middle as the gleeful arms dealer.</span></p><p><span>The second pool is </span><strong>inference compute</strong><span> which runs AI models in production, serving actual users. Here, the dynamics look entirely different.</span></p><p><strong>Society’s demonstrated demand for intelligence is essentially unlimited.</strong><span> Every additional IQ point that can be applied to analyzing data, automating decisions, or improving productivity gets consumed immediately. Supply constrains adoption, not demand. Businesses aren’t asking “do we want AI capabilities?” They’re asking “how much can we get, and how soon?”</span></p><p><strong>As GPUs become commoditized and compute abundance arrives, inference capabilities will become the next major market—especially given growing demand for efficient agentic tools.</strong><span> LLM inference is becoming a massive race. The companies that can deliver intelligence most efficiently, at the lowest cost per token or per decision, will capture disproportionate value. Training the biggest model matters less now; running models efficiently at planetary scale matters more.</span></p><p>This differs fundamentally from the dot-com bubble, which was fueled primarily by advertising spend. Companies burned cash on Super Bowl commercials to acquire customers they hoped to monetize later. That was speculative demand chasing speculative value.</p><p><strong>AI inference demand is directed at improving actual earnings.</strong><span> Companies are deploying intelligence to reduce customer acquisition costs, lower operational expenses, and increase worker productivity. The return is measurable and often immediate, not hypothetical.</span></p><p>This suggests the AI “bubble” may have a softer landing than its predecessors. Yes, price-to-earnings ratios look inflated today. But unlike pure speculation, genuine productive capacity is being built. If compute costs fall dramatically post-correction while inference demand remains robust (and all evidence suggests it will) companies can simply run their models longer, use more compute-intensive approaches, or deploy intelligence to problems that are economically marginal at today’s prices but viable at tomorrow’s.</p><p><strong>In other words: even if we massively overbuild training capacity (which seems likely), the inference side has enough latent demand to absorb the excess.</strong><span> The compute gets repurposed from the game of chicken to the productive application of intelligence at scale, rather than sitting dark.</span></p><p>Just as bandwidth costs collapsed by 90% within four years of the dot-com crash, making YouTube and Netflix possible, compute costs could fall dramatically in the aftermath of an AI correction. The same GPU clusters that hyperscalers are rationing today could become commodity infrastructure available to anyone with a credit card.</p><p>But here the analogy breaks down in a critical way.</p><p>Fiber optic cable has an extraordinarily long useful life: decades of productive capacity once it’s in the ground. The infrastructure built during the dot-com bubble is still carrying packets today, twenty-five years later. That’s what made it such a durable gift to the next generation: the cost was borne once, the value compounded for decades.</p><p><strong>GPU clusters are not fiber optic cable.</strong></p><p>The useful life of a training cluster is perhaps two to three years before it becomes uncompetitive. Chips depreciate faster than they physically wear out. A three-year-old GPU isn’t broken. It’s just obsolete, overtaken by newer architectures that offer better performance per watt, better memory bandwidth, better interconnects. In economic terms, training compute looks more like an operating expense with a short payback window than a durable capital asset.</p><p>This fundamentally changes the post-fire dynamics.</p><p>When the bubble bursts and training compute becomes abundant, yes, costs will fall. But fire followers won’t inherit state-of-the-art infrastructure the way Web 2.0 companies inherited fiber. They’ll inherit yesterday’s infrastructure: still functional, but no longer cutting-edge. If you want access to the newest, fastest compute to train competitive models, you’ll still need to pay premium prices to whoever is actively refreshing their clusters.</p><p><strong>This creates a different kind of moat than we saw in previous cycles.</strong><span> The companies that survive the fire will benefit from having already paid down the cost of the current generation while competitors are trying to catch up on older hardware, not just from cheaper infrastructure. The incumbency advantage centers on having the right generation of compute, continuously refreshed, not just having compute in general.</span></p><p>Inference compute follows different economics. Once a model is trained, it can run productively on older hardware for years. But the training side may not produce the same democratization we saw with bandwidth. The fire might clear the brush, but the tallest trees will still control access to sunlight.</p><p>Yet focusing solely on compute may mean we’re watching the wrong wildfire.</p><p><span>Some believe </span><strong>the true winner of the AI race (at a national and global level) will be whoever solves the energy problem</strong><span>, not the company with the most GPUs or the best models.</span></p><p>Compute, after all, is just concentrated electricity. A modern AI data center can consume as much power as a small city. Kilowatts are the constraint, not silicon. You can manufacture more chips, but you can’t manufacture more energy without fundamental infrastructure: power plants, transmission lines, grid capacity. These take years or decades to build.</p><p><span>This is where the wildfire metaphor becomes particularly instructive. We’re focused on the compute forest burning and regrowing. But beneath that visible drama, there’s a deeper question: </span><strong>are we building enough energy infrastructure to power the next forest at all?</strong></p><p>The dot-com bubble left behind dark fiber that could be lit up instantly when demand returned. But idle data centers without power to run them are just expensive real estate. The real infrastructure deficit may center on energy generation rather than compute capacity.</p><p><strong>If this bubble drives massive investment in power infrastructure (nuclear plants, renewable energy farms, grid modernization, advanced battery storage) that would be a genuinely durable gift to the next half-century.</strong><span> Energy infrastructure, unlike GPUs that become obsolete in five years, compounds in value over decades.</span></p><p>The companies that will dominate the post-fire landscape may be the ones securing energy capacity tomorrow (when every other form of AI infrastructure is abundant except the electricity to run it) not the ones hoarding compute today.</p><p>Consider the math: A single large AI training cluster can require 100+ megawatts of continuous power, equivalent to a small city. The United States currently generates about 1,200 gigawatts of electricity total. If AI compute grows at projected rates, it could demand 5-10% of the nation’s entire power generation within a decade.</p><p><strong>The problem here is about fundamental energy infrastructure.</strong></p><p>And unlike fiber optic cable or GPU clusters, power infrastructure can’t be deployed quickly. Nuclear plants take 10-15 years to build. Major transmission lines face decades of regulatory approval. Even large solar farms require 3-5 years from planning to operation.</p><p><strong>This means the real constraint on AI (the genuine bottleneck that will determine winners and losers) may already be locked in by decisions being made (or not made) right now about power infrastructure.</strong></p><p>The companies currently spending hundreds of billions on GPUs may discover their limiting factor is the megawatts needed to run it, not compute capacity. And the regions that invest heavily in energy infrastructure today will have an insurmountable advantage in hosting AI workloads tomorrow.</p><p><strong>The companies prepping themselves to survive scarcity aren’t just stockpiling compute. They’re building root systems deep enough to tap multiple resources:</strong><span> energy contracts locked in for decades, gross retention rates above 120%, margin expansion even as they scale, and infrastructure that can flex between training and inference as market dynamics shift.</span></p><p>With our global glasses on, we are losing (and some may say have already lost) the energy battle with China. Very quietly we have entered a new cold war era where watts and rare-earth materials are the new ICBMs.</p><p><span>A burning question (pardon the pun) is how do we assess fire-resistance in </span><em>this</em><span> cycle? Each category of company faces different tests of durability. Understanding these metrics separates genuine ecosystem strength from temporary abundance:</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png" width="1456" height="641" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:641,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:180951,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://ceodinner.substack.com/i/176716568?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" title="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!ozGX!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F5402f415-1506-45d7-9813-a6b0530ad16b_1486x654.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><strong>Understanding the Fire Tests:</strong></p><p><strong>Foundation model labs</strong><span> face a fundamental question: Can revenue grow faster than compute costs? Training expenses scale exponentially (10x compute ≈ 3x performance), while revenue scales with customer adoption. If a lab spends $100M on compute to generate $50M in revenue, then $300M to generate $120M, the trajectory is fatal. They’re running faster to stand still. Fire-resistant labs show revenue outpacing compute spend, proof that each capability improvement unlocks disproportionate customer value.</span></p><p><strong>Enterprise AI platforms</strong><span> must prove their AI goes beyond marketing veneer. A company showing 95% gross retention but only 12% AI feature adoption means customers stay for the legacy platform (data warehouse, CRM) while ignoring AI add-ons. When capital contracts, these companies get repriced violently. The market realizes they’re infrastructure plays with an AI sticker. True AI platforms show high retention because of high AI adoption, not despite low adoption.</span></p><p><strong>Application layer companies</strong><span> live in a unique trap: building on models they don’t control (OpenAI, Anthropic) creates margin compression, feature parity, and disintermediation risk. The only escape is deep customer embedding. Companies with NRR &gt;120% and CAC payback &lt;12 months have achieved workflow integration—customers expand usage naturally and acquisition costs pay back fast. Those with NRR &lt;100% and payback &gt;18 months are “nice-to-have” features that churn when budgets tighten, requiring continuous capital infusion to grow.</span></p><p><strong>Inference API players</strong><span> face commoditization as GPU oversupply arrives. Revenue per GPU-hour reveals pricing power. A company generating $50/GPU-hour versus $5/GPU-hour has 10x more margin to defend its position through technical optimization, product differentiation, or distribution moats. Inference cost elasticity shows market structure: high elasticity (50% price cut = 500% demand increase) means commodity hell; low elasticity means customers value features beyond raw compute.</span></p><p><strong>Energy and infrastructure firms</strong><span> ultimately control AI’s fundamental constraint. Data center economics flip based on utilization and energy costs. At $0.03/kWh and 85% utilization, effective cost is $0.035/kWh. At $0.08/kWh and 50% utilization, it’s $0.16/kWh—a 4.5x disadvantage. When AI demand crashes post-bubble, facilities with high energy costs cannot lower prices enough to fill capacity. Those with structural energy advantages (hydroelectric, nuclear contracts) can slash prices and still maintain positive margins, filling capacity by absorbing distressed competitors’ customers.</span></p><p><strong>The meta-pattern:</strong><span> Each metric asks the same question from different angles—can you sustain your business model when external capital disappears? Fire-resistant companies have achieved thermodynamic sustainability: each unit of input (capital, compute, energy) generates more than one unit of output (revenue, value, efficiency). They can grow in scarcity. The flammable brush consumes more than it produces, subsidized by abundant capital. When the subsidy ends, they ignite.</span></p><p>This comparative framing reveals who has genuine ecosystem durability versus who’s simply tall because of temporary abundance.</p><p>The giant sequoia cannot reproduce without fire. Its cones open only in intense heat. The flames clear the forest floor, allowing seeds to reach mineral soil. The canopy burns back, allowing sunlight through. Without the burn, there is no renewal.</p><p><strong>There’s a deeper truth in the sequoia’s relationship with fire:</strong><span> not all fires serve the tree equally.</span></p><p>For millennia, sequoias thrived with low-intensity ground fires that burned every 10-20 years. These fires were hot enough to open cones and clear undergrowth, but cool enough to leave mature trees unharmed. The sequoia’s thick bark (up to two feet deep) evolved specifically to survive these regular burns.</p><p>Then came a century of fire suppression. Without regular burning, fuel built up. Understory trees grew tall. When fires finally came, they burned hotter and higher than sequoias had ever faced.</p><p><strong>The Castle Fire of 2020 killed an estimated 10-14% of all mature giant sequoias on Earth.</strong><span> Trees that had survived dozens of fires over 2,000 years died in a single afternoon. The difference? Fire intensity. The accumulated fuel created canopy fires that overwhelmed even the sequoia’s legendary resilience.</span></p><p><strong>Here’s the lesson for Silicon Valley</strong><span>: Regular burns (cyclical corrections, normal bankruptcies, the constant churn of creative destruction) are healthy. They clear brush, release resources, and allow new growth. But if we suppress all burning for too long, if we bail out every overvalued company and prop up every failing business model, we don’t prevent the fire. We just make the eventual burn catastrophic.</span></p><p><span>The sequoia also teaches us about time horizons. These trees take centuries to reach their full height. Even mature sequoias that survive a fire need decades to fully recover their canopy. </span><strong>It’s still hard to tell which trees (even those that seem mature today) will continue growing versus which have already peaked.</strong><span> The true giants are those that spent generations building root systems deep enough to tap water sources others can’t reach, developing bark thick enough to withstand heat others can’t survive.</span></p><p>The goal isn’t to prevent fires but to maintain their rhythm. Small, regular burns prevent devastating conflagrations. The worst outcome is the policy that postpones all fires until the fuel load becomes explosive, not the fire itself.</p><p>If this is a bubble, it’s a productive one — a controlled burn rather than a collapse.</p><p><strong>But “controlled” doesn’t mean comfortable.</strong><span> The flammable brush will ignite. Capital will evaporate. Valuations will crash. Jobs will disappear.  Instead of a failure, that’s the system working as designed.</span></p><p>The test for every founder and investor centers on whether you can withstand scarcity rather than whether you can grow in abundance.</p><p>When the smoke clears, we’ll see who was succulent and who was tinder, who had bark, and who was resin.</p><p><strong>The wildfire is coming. That’s not the problem.</strong></p><p>The question is: What kind of plant are you?</p><p>And perhaps more importantly: Are you building root systems deep enough, not just to survive this season, but to keep growing through the next decade of scarcity?</p><p>Because the real opportunity comes post-fire: what continues to grow after and what entirely new species take root in the ashes.</p><p>I don’t think of a wildfire as Mother Nature’s wise way of maintaining balance. In fact, not all ecosystems depend on wildfires. Many ecosystems have evolved with fire as a natural and sometimes essential ecological process, while others are harmed by wildfire and have no natural fire-adapted features. This analogy is meant to help you understand that wildfires are a natural and necessary part of the Silicon Valley ecosystem.</p><p><span>Where the moral judgment does come </span><strong>in</strong><span> pertains to where all the nutrients, the talent, the attention, and the glory fall after the burn. This litmus test of humanity is the defining question of this cycle.</span></p><p>Will the resources gravitate to companies trying to grab more “share of attention,” getting you to watch mindlessly entertaining content by pushing your dopamine and epinephrine buttons. Will the highest goal of this technology ultimately be to get you to buy things you don’t need and spend time on activities that only mollify your FOMO temporarily. Will AI simply accelerate the development of a capitalist hypercycle of Paul Tillich’s ultimate-concern pursuit and existential disappointment that only expands the gulf between haves and have-nots?</p><p>Robert Putnam’s research out of Harvard shows that democratizing technology doesn’t inherently level the playing field. “Compared to their poorer counterparts, young people from upper-class backgrounds (and their parents) are more likely to use the Internet for jobs, education, political and social engagement, health, and newsgathering, and less for entertainment and recreation,” Putnam writes. “Affluent Americans use the Internet in ways that are mobility-enhancing, whereas poorer, less-educated Americans typically use it in ways that are not.” This stark dichotomy underscores the importance of purposefully guiding AI to free, not fetter, human agency.</p><p><span>More optimistically, I hope the handcuffs of Packard’s Law will be loosened for current startups and future wildflowers pursuing worthwhile quests. In </span><em>Good to Great</em><span>, Jim Collins coined the term </span><em>Packard’s Law</em><span> to describe David Packard’s view that organizational growth is limited by a company’s ability to obtain enough of the right people. After the burn, I hope companies like the following will thrive with easier access to talent, the oxygen and sunlight of company growth:</span></p><p><strong>Montai Therapeutics</strong><span> is using AI to pioneer the creation of medicines to treat and preempt chronic disease. They have a poly-intelligent approach to discovery in which humans, AI, and nature collaborate to generate novel molecules for heretofore unsolvable diseases.</span></p><p><strong>Eudia</strong><span> is creating an augmented-intelligence platform, starting with the legal industry, to allow humans to be orders of magnitude more efficient—not replacing lawyers but augmenting them. Augmented law delivers both precision and speed, and for the first time, cost and quality are not trade-offs. Eudia is delivering outcome-based pricing for legal work instead of billable hours. Which consumer of legal services wouldn’t be in favor of that idea?</span></p><p><strong>Listen Labs</strong><span> is an AI-powered research platform that helps teams uncover insights from customer interviews in hours—not months—thereby amplifying the voice of customers. Where, practically speaking, companies could previously speak only with a sample of customers, now they can listen to a full panel representing every demographic, geographic, and psychographic profile instantaneously. The ironic part is that humans are more likely to offer candid and useful feedback when speaking to an AI than to a human who they consciously or unconsciously feel may be judging their answers.</span></p><p><strong>Netic</strong><span> is helping essential service industries grow on autopilot. While the AI wave has swept across software and creative industries, businesses like home services, automotive, and consumer healthcare have been left behind. These industries form the backbone of the economy, yet they operate on outdated tools, overwhelmed call centers, and disconnected systems. Their operations are complex and often rely on manual workflows, and they can’t access the frontier technologies that drive digital-first businesses. In a world where startups mostly build for startups, Netic serves the real industries that keep America running.</span></p><p>It’s obvious AI will raise the ceiling for the haves; if it does not raise the floor for the have-nots, there will—and perhaps should—be pitchforks.</p><p>I have tried my best to raise my children with an abundance mindset when it comes to opportunities and a scarcity mindset as it relates to natural resources. Society feels like it operates in the opposite direction. I wonder if we can escape our fate.</p><p>The coming wildfire will surely be good for the Silicon Valley ecosystem, but will it be good for humanity?</p></div></article></div><div><div id="discussion"><h4>Discussion about this post</h4></div><div><h3>Ready for more?</h3></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Scala 3 slowed us down? (239 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kmaliszewski9.github.io/scala/2025/12/07/scala3-slowdown.html</link>
            <guid>46182202</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 15:08:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kmaliszewski9.github.io/scala/2025/12/07/scala3-slowdown.html">https://kmaliszewski9.github.io/scala/2025/12/07/scala3-slowdown.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46182202">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>Is this clickbait? Not really. <br>
Is this the fault of the language or the compiler? Definitely not. <br>
Rather, it was part of a rushed migration. Sharing the lessons learned in the process.</p>

<p>I was refreshing one of our services. Part of this process was to migrate codebase from Scala 2.13 to Scala 3. I’ve done this a few times before and overall had a positive experience. Well, at least until we talk about projects with macro wizardry.</p>

<p>The service in question had no macros at all, but it was at the heart of data ingestion, so performance was not an afterthought.</p>

<p>I did it as usual - updating dependencies, compiler options and some type/syntax changes.</p>

<p>Then after resolving few tricky implicit resolutions and config derivations, project compiled on Scala 3.7.3 🎉</p>

<p>All tests passed, end-to-end flow locally works perfectly fine, so I decided to roll out the changes in a testing environment. Similarly, no issues at all. No concerning logs, all metrics ranging from infrastructure, through JVM up to application level look healthy.</p>

<p>With that in mind, I began a staged rollout. Again, all seem good. I kept observing the service but it looked like my job is done.</p>

<p>Well, as you probably can guess, it wasn’t.</p>

<h2 id="the-mysterious-slowdown">The mysterious slowdown</h2>

<p>After 5-6 hours, Kafka lag started increasing on a few environments. Of course, this wasn’t something new. Most often it is caused by a spike of data. We have pretty advanced machinery to deal with that. Usually the lag resolves by itself without any manual action.</p>

<p>However, this time <em>something</em> was off. Upstream load turned out to be relatively modest, yet we needed much more instances of the service - meaning the processing rate per instance dropped. I was confused to say the least. Why would it decrease the processing rate just on these environments?</p>

<p>Anyway, we decided to rollback the changes - this brought the rate back.</p>

<h2 id="digging-deeper">Digging deeper</h2>

<p>I came back to testing. In particular, load testing. However similarly as on production environments I did not notice regression. So I played around with different payloads and granularity of messages. To my surprise, for more fine-grained, heterogeneous workloads, the processing rate significantly dropped.</p>

<p>Still, I had no idea why it would happen, but my bet was in the dependencies. Therefore, I tried one-by-one, reverting the serialization library, database SDK, base Docker image and even config libraries. None of these made any changes.</p>

<p>This made me pull out the big guns. I profiled the service using <a href="https://github.com/async-profiler/async-profiler/tree/master">async-profiler</a> and indeed</p>

<p>CPU profile looked vastly different on Scala 3 than on 2.13.</p>

<p><img src="https://kmaliszewski9.github.io/assets/s213low.png" alt="scala2_13_flamegraph"></p>

<p><img src="https://kmaliszewski9.github.io/assets/s3low.png" alt="scala3_flamegraph"></p>

<p>JVM-level CPU time was now dominated by JIT compiler while application-level by decoding.</p>

<p>Looking at the top of Scala 3 flamegraph I noticed a long quicklens call.</p>

<p><img src="https://kmaliszewski9.github.io/assets/quicklens-flamegraph.png" alt="quicklens_flamegraph"></p>

<p>What used to be transparent (frankly, I didn’t even realize we used the library), now took almost half of the total CPU time. I compared how it looks on Scala 2.13 and it was barely noticeable with around 0.5% samples.</p>

<p>Turns out there was indeed <a href="https://github.com/softwaremill/quicklens/pull/115">a subtle bug</a> making chained evaluations inefficient in Scala 3. This also explained why the JVM spent so much time compiling.</p>

<p>After upgrading the library, performance and CPU characteristics on Scala 3 became indistinguishable from Scala 2.13.</p>

<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>

<p>While the details of the bug are pretty interesting(hats off to the SoftwareMill team for catching it!), that’s not my point here. I want to emphasize that <strong>libraries can behave very differently between Scala versions</strong>, especially when they rely on meta-programming.</p>

<p>Even if your migration is seamless and the service runs fine on Scala 3 - when performance is not just a nice-to-have, do not assume. Know your hotspots and benchmark them. Otherwise, your code will benchmark you, revealing bottlenecks in places you didn’t even know existed.</p>


  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nested Learning: A new ML paradigm for continual learning (136 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://research.google/blog/introducing-nested-learning-a-new-ml-paradigm-for-continual-learning/</link>
            <guid>46182031</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 14:47:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://research.google/blog/introducing-nested-learning-a-new-ml-paradigm-for-continual-learning/">https://research.google/blog/introducing-nested-learning-a-new-ml-paradigm-for-continual-learning/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46182031">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-gt-publish-date="20251107">
                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    




    <p data-block-key="1guni">The last decade has seen incredible progress in machine learning (ML), primarily driven by powerful neural network architectures and the algorithms used to train them. However, despite the success of large language models (LLMs), a few fundamental challenges persist, especially around continual learning, the ability for a model to actively acquire new knowledge and skills over time without forgetting old ones.</p><p data-block-key="9an83">When it comes to continual learning and self-improvement, the human brain is the gold standard. It adapts through neuroplasticity — the remarkable capacity to change its structure in response to new experiences, memories, and learning. Without this ability, a person is limited to immediate context (like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anterograde_amnesia" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">anterograde amnesia</a>). We see a similar limitation in current LLMs: their knowledge is confined to either the immediate context of their input window or the static information that they learn during pre-training.</p><p data-block-key="fh441">The simple approach, continually updating a model's parameters with new data, often leads to “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catastrophic_interference" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">catastrophic forgetting</a>” (CF), where learning new tasks sacrifices proficiency on old tasks. Researchers traditionally combat CF through architectural tweaks or better optimization rules. However, for too long, we have treated the model's architecture (the network structure) and the optimization algorithm (the training rule) as two separate things, which prevents us from achieving a truly unified, efficient learning system.</p><p data-block-key="9ifb6">In our paper, “<a href="http://abehrouz.github.io/files/NL.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nested Learning: The Illusion of Deep Learning Architectures</a>”, published at <a href="https://neurips.cc/virtual/2025/poster/116123" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">NeurIPS 2025</a>, we introduce Nested Learning, which bridges this gap. Nested Learning treats a single ML model not as one continuous process, but as a system of interconnected, multi-level learning problems that are optimized simultaneously. We argue that the model's architecture and the rules used to train it (i.e., the optimization algorithm) are fundamentally the same concepts; they are just different "levels" of optimization, each with its own internal flow of information ("context flow") and update rate. By recognizing this inherent structure, Nested Learning provides a new, previously invisible dimension for designing more capable AI, allowing us to build learning components with deeper computational depth, which ultimately helps solve issues like catastrophic forgetting.</p><p data-block-key="cp75j">We test and validate Nested Learning through a proof-of-concept, self-modifying architecture that we call “Hope”, which achieves superior performance in language modeling and demonstrates better long-context memory management than existing state-of-the-art models.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h2>The Nested Learning paradigm</h2>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">Nested Learning reveals that a complex ML model is actually a set of coherent, interconnected optimization problems nested within each other or running in parallel. Each of these internal problems has its own <i>context flow</i> — its own distinct set of information from which it is trying to learn.</p><p data-block-key="aog9">This perspective implies that existing deep learning methods work by essentially <i>compressing</i> their internal context flows. More importantly, Nested Learning reveals a new dimension for designing models, allowing us to build learning components with deeper computational depth.</p><p data-block-key="28ofj">To illustrate this paradigm, we look at the concept of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Associative_memory_(psychology)" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">associative memory</a> — the ability to map and recall one thing based on another (like recalling a name when you see a face).</p><ul><li data-block-key="565p0">We show that the training process itself, specifically the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Backpropagation" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">backpropagation</a> process, can be modeled as an associative memory. The model learns to map a given data point to the value of its local error, which serves as a measure of how "surprising" or unexpected that data point was.</li><li data-block-key="d9pfu">Similarly, following previous studies (e.g., <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2504.13173" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Miras</a>), key architectural components, such as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformer_(deep_learning_architecture)" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">attention mechanism in transformers</a>, can also be formalized as simple associative memory modules that learn the mapping between tokens in a sequence.</li></ul>
</div>

                    
                    
    




                    
                    
    


<div>
        
  <p data-block-key="1guni">By defining an update frequency rate, i.e., how often each component's weights are adjusted, we can order these interconnected optimization problems into "levels." This ordered set forms the heart of the Nested Learning paradigm.</p>

    </div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h2>Putting Nested Learning to work</h2>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">The Nested Learning perspective immediately gives us principled ways to improve existing algorithms and architectures:</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h3>Deep optimizers</h3>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">Since Nested Learning views optimizers (e.g., momentum-based optimizers) as associative memory modules, it allows us to apply principles from associative memory perspective to them. We observed that many standard optimizers rely on simple <a href="https://math.stackexchange.com/questions/689022/how-does-the-dot-product-determine-similarity" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">dot-product similarity</a> (a measure of how alike two vectors are by calculating the sum of the products of their corresponding components) whose update doesn't account for how different data samples relate to each other. By changing the underlying objective of the optimizer to a more standard loss metric, such as <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ridge_regression" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">L2 regression loss</a> (a common loss function in regression tasks that quantifies the error by summing the squares of the differences between predicted and true values), we derive new formulations for core concepts like momentum, making them more resilient to imperfect data.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h3>Continuum memory systems</h3>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">In a standard Transformer, the sequence model acts as a short-term memory, holding the immediate context, while the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Feedforward_neural_network" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">feedforward neural networks</a> act as long-term memory, storing pre-training knowledge. The Nested Learning paradigm extends this concept into what we call a “continuum memory system” (CMS), where memory is seen as a spectrum of modules, each updating at a different, specific frequency rate. This creates a much richer and more effective memory system for continual learning.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h2>Hope: A self-modifying architecture with continuum memory</h2>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">As a proof-of-concept, we used Nested Learning principles to design Hope, a variant of the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00663" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Titans</a> architecture. Titans architectures are long-term memory modules that prioritize memories based on how surprising they are. Despite their powerful memory management, they only have two levels of parameters update, resulting in a first-order in-context learning. Hope, however, is a self-modifying recurrent architecture that can take advantage of unbounded levels of in-context learning and also is augmented with CMS blocks to scale to larger context windows. It can essentially optimize its own memory through a <a href="https://people.idsia.ch/~juergen/selfref1992.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">self-referential process</a>, creating an architecture with infinite, looped learning levels.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h3>Experiments</h3>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">We conducted experiments to evaluate the effectiveness of our deep optimizers and the performance of Hope on language modeling, long-context reasoning, continual learning, and knowledge incorporation tasks. The full results are available in our <a href="http://abehrouz.github.io/files/NL.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">paper</a>.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h3>Results</h3>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">Our experiments confirm the power of Nested Learning, the design of continuum memory systems, and self-modifying Titans.</p><p data-block-key="ca57m">On a diverse set of commonly used and public language modeling and common-sense reasoning tasks, the Hope architecture demonstrates lower perplexity and higher accuracy compared to modern recurrent models and standard transformers.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    




                    
                    
    


<div>
        
  <p data-block-key="1guni">Hope showcases superior memory management in long-context Needle-In-Haystack (NIAH) downstream tasks, proving that the CMSs offer a more efficient and effective way to handle extended sequences of information.</p>

    </div>

                    
                    
    




                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h2>Conclusion</h2>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni">The Nested Learning paradigm represents a step forward in our understanding of deep learning. By treating architecture and optimization as a single, coherent system of nested optimization problems, we unlock a new dimension for design, stacking multiple levels. The resulting models, like the Hope architecture, show that a principled approach to unifying these elements can lead to more expressive, capable, and efficient learning algorithms.</p><p data-block-key="ejnn7">We believe the Nested Learning paradigm offers a robust foundation for closing the gap between the limited, forgetting nature of current LLMs and the remarkable continual learning abilities of the human brain. We are excited for the research community to explore this new dimension and help us build the next generation of self-improving AI.</p>
</div>

                    
                    
    


<div data-gt-id="rich_text" data-gt-component-name="">
    


    <p>
        
            
                <h2>Acknowledgements</h2>
            
        
        
    </p>



    <p data-block-key="1guni"><i>This research was conducted by Ali Behrouz, Meisam Razaviyayn, Peilin Zhong, and Vahab Mirrokni. We thank Praneeth Kacham and Corinna Cortes for reviewing the work and their valuable suggestions. We also thank Yuan Deng and Zeman Li. Finally, we thank Mark Simborg and Kimberly Schwede for their help in crafting this blog post.</i></p>
</div>

                    
                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dollar-stores overcharge cash-strapped customers while promising low prices (416 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/dec/03/customers-pay-more-rising-dollar-store-costs</link>
            <guid>46181962</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 07 Dec 2025 14:37:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/dec/03/customers-pay-more-rising-dollar-store-costs">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/dec/03/customers-pay-more-rising-dollar-store-costs</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46181962">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>On a cloudy winter day, a state government inspector named Ryan Coffield walked into a Family Dollar store in Windsor, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/northcarolina" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">North Carolina</a>, carrying a scanner gun and a laptop.</p><p>Inside the store, which sits along a three-lane road in a county of peanut growers and poultry workers, Coffield scanned 300 items and recorded their shelf prices. He carried the scanned bar codes to the cashier and watched as item after item rang up at a higher price.</p><p>Red Baron frozen pizzas, listed on the shelf at $5, rang up at $7.65. Bounty paper towels, shelf price $10.99, rang up at $15.50. Kellogg’s Frosted Flakes, Stouffer’s frozen meatloaf, Sprite and Pepsi, ibuprofen, Klondike Minis – shoppers were overpaying for all of them. Pedigree puppy food, listed at $12.25, rang up at $14.75.</p><p>All told, 69 of the 300 items came up higher at the register: a 23% error rate that exceeded the state’s limit by more than tenfold. Some of the price tags were months out of date.</p><p>The January 2023 inspection produced the store’s fourth consecutive failure, and Coffield’s agency, the state department of agriculture &amp; consumer services, had fined Family Dollar after two previous visits. But North Carolina law caps penalties at $5,000 per inspection, offering retailers little incentive to fix the problem. “Sometimes it is cheaper to pay the fines,” said Chad Parker, who runs the agency’s weights-and-measures program.</p><figure id="2fd73407-8685-4c44-b05b-7b097e235535" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-2"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a man carrying a basket " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/961a1e86d663b8b66f8998eac95f8c851ff91c42/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Chris Outlaw shops at Family Dollar’s King Street location in Windsor, North Carolina, on 24 November. </span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>The dollar-store industry, including Family Dollar and its larger rival, Dollar General, promises everyday low prices for household essentials. But an investigation by the Guardian found that the prices listed on the shelves at these two chains often don’t materialize at checkout – in North Carolina and around the country. As the cost of living soars across America, the customers bearing the burden are those who can least afford it – customers who often don’t even notice they’re overpaying.</p><p>These overcharges are widespread.</p><p>Dollar General stores have failed more than 4,300 government price-accuracy inspections in 23 states since January 2022, a Guardian review found. Family Dollar stores have failed more than 2,100 price inspections in 20 states over the same time span, the review found.</p><p>Among these thousands of failed inspections, some of the biggest flops include a 76% error rate in October 2022 at a Dollar General in Hamilton, Ohio; a 68% error rate in February 2023 at a Family Dollar in Bound Brook, New Jersey; and a 58% error rate three months ago at a Family Dollar in Lorain, Ohio.</p><p>Many of the stores that failed state or local government checks were repeat violators. A Family Dollar in Provo, Utah, flunked 28 inspections in a row – failures that included a 48% overcharge rate in May 2024 and a 12% overcharge rate in October 2025.</p><figure id="5d2e0532-685d-44b5-82fc-938aa0ede0ad" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-3"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a person holding a price tag " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/98bec6ad6e188b0e4e54f667d64449b402373583/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>A price tag at Family Dollar on King Street in Windsor, North Carolina, on 24 November.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>The chains’ pricing disparities are drawing increasing attention. In May, Arizona’s attorney general<a href="https://www.azag.gov/press-release/attorney-general-mayes-secures-consent-judgment-against-family-dollar-resolve" data-link-name="in body link"> announced</a> a $600,000 settlement to resolve a consumer-fraud investigation against Family Dollar. In October, Colorado’s attorney general <a href="https://coag.gov/2025/400k-settlement-with-dollar-general-for-overcharging-customers/" data-link-name="in body link">settled</a> with Dollar General for $400,000 after its stores failed 15 out of 23 state inspections. Dollar General has also settled with <a href="https://www.njconsumeraffairs.gov/News/Pages/11282023.aspx" data-link-name="in body link">New Jersey</a>,<a href="https://www.ohioattorneygeneral.gov/Media/News-Releases/February-2024/AG-Yost-Allocates-Additional-$250K-for-Food-Pantri" data-link-name="in body link"> </a><a href="https://apnews.com/article/3ad6b6d57e4d47afa0653953ee280874" data-link-name="in body link">Vermont</a> and<a href="https://datcp.wi.gov/Pages/News_Media/20231120DollarGeneralSettlement.aspx" data-link-name="in body link"> Wisconsin</a>, and both companies have settled with Ohio.</p><p>Linda Davis, a 64-year-old Family Dollar shopper in Dayton, Ohio, called the state attorney general’s office in February after walking home from the dollar store and discovering that 12 of her 23 purchases had rung up incorrectly. “I’m adding it up in my head as I’m shopping,” she told the Guardian. “But I was way off and I didn’t know why … I thought: where did I miscalculate? I’ve [only] got so much cash on me.”</p><p>Davis, who lives on social security, said she could shop elsewhere, but that would involve paying for a bus ride. “I don’t have money like that,” she said.</p><p>Both Family Dollar and Dollar General declined interview requests and did not answer detailed lists of questions from the Guardian. Instead, both sent the Guardian brief statements.</p><p>“At Family Dollar, we take customer trust seriously and are committed to ensuring pricing accuracy across our stores,” the company said. “We are currently reviewing the concerns raised and working to better understand any potential discrepancies. We continue to be focused on providing a consistent and transparent shopping experience.”</p><p>Dollar General said it was “committed to providing customers with accurate prices on items purchased in our stores, and we are disappointed any time we fail to deliver on this commitment”. In one court case in Ohio, Dollar General’s lawyers argued that “it is virtually impossible for a retailer to match shelf pricing and scanned pricing 100% of the time for all items. Perfection in this regard is neither plausible nor expected under the law.”</p><p>The Guardian’s examination of inspection failures by the two chains was based on record requests to 45 states and more than 140 counties and cities in New York, Ohio and California, along with court documents and public databases.</p><p>In nearly half of US states, information about whether customers are being overcharged was limited or unavailable. Many states do little or nothing to monitor retail stores’ pricing practices. Some, like Maryland, Idaho and Washington, do no random inspections, responding only to consumer complaints. Illinois, South Carolina and others don’t inspect at all. In 2020, auditors in Kansas revealed that these inspections were a low priority in many states. “Consumers can check price accuracy themselves,” they wrote.</p><p>Even in states with tougher enforcement, financial penalties don’t always solve the problem: in the 23 months after Dollar General agreed in November 2023 to pay Wisconsin $850,000, its stores failed 31% of their price inspections. During the same period, Wisconsin’s Family Dollar stores failed 30% of their state inspections.</p><figure id="7f02af53-ba5e-449e-a038-5627ce17fc33" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-4"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a car i front of a building" src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/5973a0e11fdc17bb2d83702119355d446333d7f7/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>A Dollar General store in Port Henry, New York, is one of two within a 5-mile radius.</span> Photograph: Kelly Burgess/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>According to industry watchers, employees and lawsuits, overcharges often stem from labor practices within the dollar-store sector. When a company changes prices, the registers are updated automatically. But the shelf prices are not: someone needs to remove the old labels manually and replace them with new ones. In an industry known for minimal staffing, workers don’t always have time to put up the new shelf tags.</p><p>In many instances, customers may not notice that they are being charged more than what’s listed on the shelf. If they notice at the register, they may decide to put those items back – or ask a store employee to honor the shelf price.</p><p>Dollar General, in its statement, said its store teams “are empowered to correct the matter on the spot”. But customers and current and former employees said that while some dollar stores will correct the price, others refuse to make fixes at the register – and turn away customers who return later and request a refund.</p><p>“Overcharging even by a small amount per item can strain a really tight budget,” said Elizabeth M Harris, acting director of the New Jersey division of consumer affairs. “If you’ve ever gone into any store … with a child like I have, there’s chaos at the checkout counter and you’re not really paying attention.” With items being rung up quickly, she added, “consumers are trusting that the retailer is actually charging them the price that’s displayed.”</p><p>Her state settled in 2023 with Dollar General for $1.2m after finding more than 2,000 items rung up as overcharges across 58 stores.</p><p>Even if the overcharges paid by dollar-store customers are accidental, they still reflect the industry’s decision not to correct a problem it has known about for years, according to Kennedy Smith, a researcher at the non-profit Institute for Local Self-Reliance, which works to protect communities from negative impacts of big corporations.</p><p>“If they’re called on it, they’ll say, ‘Oh yeah, our mistake,’” Kennedy said. “Until they’re called on it, they’re happy to let those scanner errors bring in the millions.”</p><h2 id="the-cheap-stuff"><strong>‘The cheap stuff’</strong></h2><p>When consumers feel economic pain,<a href="https://www.npr.org/2025/09/19/nx-s1-5539547/grocery-prices-tariffs-food-inflation" data-link-name="in body link"> as they do now</a> thanks to rising costs exacerbated by tariffs, <a href="https://www.investopedia.com/martin-shkreli-s-price-gouging-scandal-11725521" data-link-name="in body link">price gouging</a> and other inflationary pressures, one place they turn to are dollar stores. These one-stop centers for inexpensive food, clothing and housewares tend to sell in small quantities, one $1 chicken-noodle-soup can at a time. And they are relatively easy to get to: 75% of Americans live within 5 miles of a Dollar General, according to the company.</p><p>The industry’s largest player is flourishing. Todd Vasos, the CEO of Dollar General, told investors in August that his company’s quarterly sales had increased 5% over the same period last year. Some of that growth, he said, came from middle- and higher-income shoppers tightening their belts. But the company’s low-income “core customers” were spending more at the chain too.</p><figure id="c2a4e46f-1750-4013-aff4-98d36457f70d" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-5"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a man holding a bag " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a194b0cf1fabf01228ecf2ba68e53eda00653b05/0_0_3360_4200/master/3360.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="556.25" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Chris Outlaw walks to his car after leaving  Family Dollar’s King Street location in Windsor, North Carolina.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>Those customers have been the industry’s niche from the beginning. When a 48-year-old former tobacco farmer and traveling salesman named James Luther Turner opened JL Turner and Son Wholesale Dry Goods, Shoes, Notions and Hosiery in Scottsville, Kentucky, in 1939, his mission was “to sell the cheap stuff to the poor folks”. (Someone else had cornered the market on “selling the good stuff” to Scottsville’s rich folks.)</p><p>By 1955, Turner and his eldest son, Hurley Calister “Cal” Turner Sr, were overseeing 36 stores in small southern towns. Cal Sr decided that year to co-opt the “Dollar Days” sales at big department stores and to open outlets featuring a single low price of $1. Adopting a name that nodded to the general store, he designed a bold black-and-yellow sign and that June christened the first Dollar General in Springfield, Kentucky.</p><p>Dollar General now operates over 20,000 stores in 48 states – more than any other retailer of any kind in the US. (It has long since abandoned its $1 price limit.) Though it has more than 195,000 employees and net sales of $40.6bn, the company still calls itself “America’s neighborhood general store”.</p><p>Family Dollar began in 1959 in Charlotte, North Carolina, and now operates 8,000 stores nationwide. For most of the past decade, it was owned by yet another chain, Dollar Tree, but the two brands divorced last summer.</p><p>What Dollar General and Family Dollar have in common is a conspicuous presence in places that don’t offer a lot of other retail: low-income urban neighborhoods and rural towns like Windsor.</p><p>A predominantly Black county seat of 3,400 on North Carolina’s coastal plain, Windsor used to be a retail hub. “All the streets were full on a weekend,” recalled Russell Parker, a 66-year-old retired pilot. “There were people everywhere, people playing music.” And people spending money: at the fish market, the cobbler, the independent groceries, the automotive-supply store. But today Windsor’s downtown – like many rural main streets – is pocked with empty storefronts. The town never fully recovered from Hurricane Floyd, in 1999. “Every young person that graduates from high school gets on the first thing smokin’ to somewhere else,” Parker said.</p><figure id="15d44d24-f516-4c5a-9159-5715f6f8674d" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-6"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a person on a motorcycle " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3b0aca2ed2466aa479bc62ef3cbddf55c477921d/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>The King Street area of downtown Windsor, North Carolina.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>One supermarket remains on the edge of town. Shopping for clothes often means driving to the next county, at least for those who drive. But Windsor does have three stores that help fill the gap: a Dollar General and <em>two</em> Family Dollars.</p><p>At the Family Dollar that failed multiple inspections, some regulars remain vigilant. Chris Outlaw, a 54-year-old hemodialysis technician, shops there because it’s near his house and workplace. Experience has taught him to buy only a few items at once and to examine his receipts. Not all his neighbors do the same. “I’ve seen people in there with baskets full,” he said. “You can just imagine how much of that stuff didn’t ring out right, and they had so much they couldn’t catch it.”</p><h2 id="big-old-savings"><strong>‘Big old savings’</strong></h2><p>Customers walking into Dollar General stores are often greeted by a bright yellow sign blaring “Hello, Low Prices”– and by as many as 10,000 items cramming shelves and, often, cluttering the aisles.</p><p>“They will send you more than what you need of any product,” said Stephanie, a former lead sales associate in Louisiana. “Your shelf can only hold 10 Glade air fresheners, right? But they will send you 50.”</p><p>Rarely is there enough staffing, current and former employees say, to complete all of the tasks expected of them, including stocking shelves, ringing up sales, looking out for shoplifters, mopping floors – and updating price changes and sales stickers.</p><figure id="3736a2d0-3b70-4518-b962-dfca7c688a14" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-7"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a person looking at a shelf " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/16709d04c3784b13ce1ff3916d10d36757cecb5b/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Chris Outlaw squeezes through an aisle packed with merchandise inside Family Dollar’s King Street location in Windsor, North Carolina.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>More than two dozen current and former employees of the chain in 15 states interviewed by the Guardian agreed that price discrepancies are the byproduct of the company’s employment policies. (Most, including Stephanie, spoke on the condition of anonymity because of fear of retaliation.)</p><p>Often there are only one or two people on duty. “You’re lucky if you get to work two to four hours of your eight- to 13-hour shift with another human being,” a former assistant manager in Illinois said.</p><p>Every Tuesday, employees are supposed to print and post hundreds of shelf stickers representing price changes already updated in the computer system. On Saturdays, stacks of sales stickers arrive; often, workers are expected to remove all the previous week’s stickers by 5pm and put up new stickers – as many as 1,000 of them – before closing up that night. Stickers fail to get put up, they fall off easily, and they are confusing, with some sales instant and others linked to coupons. “I threw away tags sometimes, to keep me or a co-worker out of trouble,” Stephanie admitted.</p><figure id="10e3789c-9677-463b-838f-07a30d632631" data-spacefinder-role="supporting" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-8"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=380&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="blankets and a bleach bottle on a shelf " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/a86d57717aef864074eb9f425c207bc8eb221194/0_0_2200_3300/master/2200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="667.5" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Items on shelves at the Mineville, New York, Dollar General, which is 5 miles from the Port Henry Dollar General.</span> Photograph: Kelly Burgess/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>A former store manager at a Dollar General in Connecticut noted that many of his customers were poor or disabled enough that they got by on public assistance. “I didn’t want people to get screwed over, but I knew that it was happening,” he said. “If I’m in the store, I’m gonna try to do the best I can for them. But at the end of the day, they’re still probably gonna get overcharged for a few things.”</p><p>Dollar General, in its statement, said it schedules time each week for “price change execution”, among other measures to ensure accuracy.</p><p>Ten current and former employees in eight states claimed that – along with allowing pricing errors caused by understaffing and overstocking – some Dollar General stores engage in a tactic designed to fool customers: special sales that don’t actually lower the price of an item. A manager from Florida, for example, sent the Guardian two photos of price stickers for Café Bustelo ground coffee. In the first photo, a sticker said “SALE” in white block letters against a red background. It advertised a markdown from $7.95 to $6.50. In the second photo, the top sticker had been peeled away to show the original price: $6.50.</p><p>A sales associate from Illinois sent photos showing cutlery with what he said was a fake original price of $8.50. “It’s trying to say that you’re making this big old savings by buying this item here,” explained the employee, “when it’s actually always been $6.95.”</p><p>Dollar General declined to comment on these workers’ claims.</p><h2 id="we-have-little-choice"><strong>‘We have little choice’</strong></h2><p>When the Ohio attorney general, Dave Yost, sued Dollar General in 2022, he submitted 114 pages of customer complaints as part of the case.</p><p>One of them came from Melanie Hutzler, who lives in Canton without a car and whose mobility is limited by arthritis and multiple sclerosis. Hutzler, 51, relies on government food assistance and said she was cautious about spending money. At the time of her complaint, she could reach two food stores on foot. Getting to the Save A Lot grocery required crossing a busy road, but getting to a Dollar General did not.</p><p>“Every single time we went into that store, something would ring up wrong,” she told the Guardian. “They never had a manager there that would fix the prices.” Hutzler said she would walk the cashier over to the shelf and point out the listed price, only to be told, “There’s nothing we can do about it.”</p><figure id="62c65a56-7296-4ad3-8f1e-f55498c66483" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-9"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="an exterior of a store with cars parked in front " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/11e22a4279c093268890831e5a79d9aee6070a96/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>The exterior of Family Dollar on King Street in Windsor, North Carolina.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>Other Ohioans expressed similar frustrations. “My 87-year-old mother and I have frequented Dollar General for years, and there have been innumerable times we have made purchases that were well higher than advertised,” wrote Robert Hevlin of Dayton. “My mother and I have literally lost thousands over the years with this company, but both of us being on social security, we have little choice in where we shop.”</p><p>In September 2023, Yost reached a $1m settlement with Dollar General, which he said had error rates at some stores that ran as high as 88%. In February 2024, he announced a $400,000 settlement with Family Dollar to resolve similar allegations. Most of that money went to <a href="https://www.ohioattorneygeneral.gov/Media/Newsletters/Consumer-Advocate/February-2024/Dollar-General-settlement-brings-help-to-Ohioans" data-link-name="in body link">charitable organizations</a> that distribute food and personal-care items.</p><p>Both chains agreed in the settlements to tighten their pricing practices. Yost’s office continues to receive complaints. A Dollar General customer in Garfield Heights said in February that he was charged $6.35 for a carton of eggs with a shelf sticker of $5.10, but the “cashier was too busy having a personal call on her cellphone to address the price discrepancy”. The same month, a Family Dollar shopper in Genoa reported being charged $2.65 for cough medicine listed on the shelf at $1.50. “I was told by the cashier that there was nothing that could be done about it,” the complaint said.</p><p>Over in Missouri, state officials are pursuing a lawsuit that accuses Dollar General of “deceptive” pricing practices. The suit, filed in 2023, says 92 of the 147 stores the state checked failed their inspections, with discrepancies as high as $6.50 an item.</p><p>The companies declined to comment on these state lawsuits.</p><p>Dollar General has also been hit with private lawsuits, including several filed by its shareholders. In a document filed in August in federal court in Nashville, lawyers for Dollar General investors argued that understaffing, poor inventory control and overcharging were all interrelated.</p><p>The investors allege that the company deceived them by portraying itself as financially sound. In truth, the court filing says, “Dollar General’s inventory management processes were broken, which caused a massive bloat of excess product to clog the company at both its distribution centers and stores, and its workforce had been slashed.” These problems gave rise to price discrepancies and other “dire consequences”, the court filing asserts.</p><p>The filing includes the stories of 36 former employees who claimed direct knowledge that Dollar General managers and executives knew about the problems. Several reported notifying the top leadership directly. “All the prices were off in the stores,” said one of those ex-employees, a manager who monitored inventory levels in Ohio and Pennsylvania. She claimed to know firsthand, based on calls she participated in, that company vice-presidents and regional directors were aware of the “huge” price mismatches.</p><figure id="82087b84-c807-4451-b76e-aa18d503bc8b" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-10"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Price stickers and merchandise on shelves " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/fab430219ae0daf3a0aa4720056822fb4e9615d1/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Price tags and merchandise inside Family Dollar’s King Street location in Windsor, North Carolina.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>Dollar General, in response, said that the testimony of a handful of ex-workers does not prove that it misled investors. In their “years-long search for fraud”, the company’s lawyers claimed, the shareholders “came up empty”.</p><p>Earlier this year, a federal judge in New Jersey halted a class-action lawsuit against Dollar General filed by a shopper who said he was overcharged for groceries. Dollar General argued that when customers create accounts – for example, by downloading the company’s mobile app – they agree to use arbitration to resolve disputes and forfeit the right to file class-action suits. The judge agreed.</p><p>This victory for Dollar General threw up an obstacle for customers seeking justice. “Who’s going to bring a consumer arbitration with a $225 filing fee over a 50-cent overcharge?” asked Marc Dann, a former Ohio attorney general whose law firm filed the New Jersey case. “They’ve essentially closed the door to the courthouse to people.”</p><p>Dann’s firm did reach a settlement with Dollar General in another case this fall, though the details have not been made public.</p><h2 id="this-endless-cycle"><strong>‘This endless cycle’</strong></h2><p>The dollar-store chains describe themselves as mission-driven companies. “Our stores are conveniently located in neighborhoods, and often in ‘food deserts’ where other stores choose not to locate,” Family Dollar says on<a href="https://corporate.familydollar.com/about-us" data-link-name="in body link"> its website</a>. Dollar General takes pride in offering value to families who, according to CEO Vasos, “have had to sacrifice even on the necessities”.</p><p>The industry’s critics say the cause and effect are reversed. “Dollar stores are often seen as a symptom of economic distress,” said the Institute for Local Self-Reliance’s co-executive director, Stacy Mitchell. “What we found is that they’re, in fact, a cause of it.” Sometimes, she said, a chain dollar store will open near an independent grocer and skim off enough of its business that it is forced to close. That limits the availability of fresh produce and forces shoppers to buy more packaged and processed foods.</p><p>In a statement, Dollar General said its stores often “operate along with local grocers and business owners to collectively meet customers’ needs”. It added that 7,000 of its 20,000 stores sell fresh produce and that the company also partners with local food banks “to further help nourish our neighbors in need”.</p><p>The people enduring the effects of hollowed-out local economies – and getting hit with overcharges at dollar-store chains – include residents of Essex county, New York. The county, tucked among the stately pines of the Adirondack Mountains, has a population of 37,000. It has five Dollar Generals and two Family Dollars. All seven regularly fail pricing-accuracy tests. The Dollar General in Port Henry, which sits on the shores of Lake Champlain, was fined $103,550 for failed inspections between November 2022 and June 2025.</p><figure id="17be1aa5-370d-427d-bcc1-c673e6364e1e" data-spacefinder-role="immersive" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-11"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=1300&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=1300&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=1140&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=1140&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=1125&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=1125&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=965&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 740px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 740px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=965&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 740px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=725&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=725&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=645&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=645&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=465&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="Katelyn Miller at her home in Port Henry, New York, on 24 November." src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/862a0411eb58a6208437ef9a9cdca6f6531e4383/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=465&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="465" height="310" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Katelyn Miller at her home in Port Henry, New York, on 24 November.</span> Photograph: Kelly Burgess/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>Over the course of seven inspections, 279 out of 700 tested items were overcharges – a combined error rate of just under 40%. One inspection yielded a 78% error rate, including overcharges on Flintstones vitamins, Peter Pan peanut butter and Prego pasta sauce.</p><p>The Port Henry store is 5 miles from the Mineville Dollar General, which occupies a lonely stretch of country road across from an auto-repair shop with spare parts littering its lawn. Down the block, an abandoned church presides over a stretch of grass that looks like it hasn’t been mown for years.</p><p>Aside from a whiskey warehousing operation and a health center, opportunities for employment are limited. The high-security prison built atop the iron mine for which Mineville is named closed in 2022, taking 100 jobs with it.</p><p>The local playground is littered with trash, cigarette butts and the occasional syringe. The town “is nice from the outside”, said Katelyn Miller, a 26-year-old Port Henry resident who lives with her mother, six-year-old daughter and two-year-old son. But “you hear about a lot of crack-den places, like blowing up or getting busted.’” Drug use is rampant in the county, which is 92% white. “Everybody around here seems to be on pain meds or buying someone else’s, because they’re also working themselves to death.”</p><p>When it comes to grocery shopping near Miller’s home, the choice is between the two Dollar Generals and a gas station/convenience store. “We live in a food desert,” she said, “even though you would think living in all this farmland, we would have more access.”</p><figure id="d1531298-a16b-49a4-80e1-9628981f25b0" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-12"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="overgrown grass in front of church " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/aa472b724809b8934e87e220037ef506ac0a60f8/0_0_3300_2200/master/3300.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>An abandoned church sits next door to the Mineville, New York, Dollar General store.</span> Photograph: Kelly Burgess/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>There is a Walmart 30 minutes away, in Fort Ticonderoga. Miller said she recently bought salmon there only to arrive home and discover that the $20 piece of fish had gone bad. “So I had to go to Dollar General and get the Stouffer’s,” she said, adding that she feels “caught in this endless cycle of never having food that will nourish me and my family, and instead having to get 2,000 grams of sodium because at least it has meat”.</p><p>The region’s economic straits put regulators in a bind when it comes to overcharges. Daniel Woods, the county’s director of weights and measures, said in 2023 that he didn’t always assess the full penalty on violators. “We’re not trying to put people out of business,” he told a local newspaper. “In some towns that’s their [only] store. I don’t want to pull that away from people, but at the same time, I’m trying to fix the problem.”</p><h2 id="on-the-way-out"><strong>On the way out</strong></h2><p>When Coffield, the North Carolina inspector, visited the Windsor Family Dollar in April 2023, the pricing issues seemed to have abated. Of the 300 items he scanned, he only found five overcharges: incontinence pads, laundry sanitizer, two coffee products and, again, Red Baron pizza. With an error rate below the state’s 2% threshold, the store passed its inspection, and it did so again in November 2024.</p><p>But customers still reported problems. Chris Outlaw, the hemodialysis technician, stopped by the Family Dollar earlier this year and noticed a sale: a $1.25 savings on five bags of Cheez Doodles. He bought them but discovered on the way out that he had been charged the regular price. The manager refused to refund the difference, Outlaw said, because he had already walked through the exit door.</p><p>Another time, he saw some discounted socks near the counter that he thought would make good Christmas gifts. “I was like, ‘Oh, I like these socks, so I’ll probably give them to somebody,’” he recalled. “Nice, plushy socks.” But they rang up at a higher price, so he left the store without them.</p><figure id="113302cd-c0e7-465c-9ce5-fd2b974d5c84" data-spacefinder-role="showcase" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.ImageBlockElement"><div id="img-13"><picture><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1300px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=880&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1300px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 1140px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=800&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 1140px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 980px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=640&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 980px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 660px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=620&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 660px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 480px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=605&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 480px)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=2&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px) and (-webkit-min-device-pixel-ratio: 1.25), (min-width: 320px) and (min-resolution: 120dpi)"><source srcset="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" media="(min-width: 320px)"><img alt="a person outside of a family dollar store " src="https://i.guim.co.uk/img/media/3d6bac1c9575989a15a3c52e0b6e70b95c307c8f/0_0_4200_2800/master/4200.jpg?width=445&amp;dpr=1&amp;s=none&amp;crop=none" width="445" height="296.66666666666663" loading="lazy"></picture></div><figcaption data-spacefinder-role="inline"><span><svg width="18" height="13" viewBox="0 0 18 13"><path d="M18 3.5v8l-1.5 1.5h-15l-1.5-1.5v-8l1.5-1.5h3.5l2-2h4l2 2h3.5l1.5 1.5zm-9 7.5c1.9 0 3.5-1.6 3.5-3.5s-1.6-3.5-3.5-3.5-3.5 1.6-3.5 3.5 1.6 3.5 3.5 3.5z"></path></svg></span><span>Chris Outlaw looks at his receipt after leaving  Family Dollar’s King Street location in Windsor, North Carolina.</span> Photograph: Cornell Watson/The Guardian</figcaption></figure><p>During a visit in August, a Guardian reporter found the Windsor Family Dollar closed for much of the afternoon. “Be Back Soon!” read a handwritten sign taped to the door. Two waiting customers said that they frequently paid prices higher than the shelf listing, including a cook whose nearby restaurant buys some of its ingredients there. “It is aggravating,” she said. “Very aggravating.”</p><p>Workers reopened the doors after a few hours. Inside, carts of unshelved dog food and other merchandise blocked the aisles. The Guardian compared the prices of 15 items. Two of them rang up higher than advertised, including a frying pan set that was $10 on the shelf and $12 at the register. Though the cashier offered to honor the lower prices, that was still an error rate of 13% – more than six times the state’s standard.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>