<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 01:00:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[“How do we pay for parking?” (335 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://cohost.org/cathoderaydude/post/2521077-hahaha-we-live-in-he</link>
            <guid>37192858</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 20:32:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://cohost.org/cathoderaydude/post/2521077-hahaha-we-live-in-he">https://cohost.org/cathoderaydude/post/2521077-hahaha-we-live-in-he</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37192858">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-post-body="true" data-testid="post-body"><p>sitting in my car in a Seattle parking lot. there's a knock on my window. it's an old lady, who asks me "how do we pay for parking?"<!-- --></p><hr>
<!-- --><p>she's taking her husband to the hospital to see his doctor, but there's a massive road project that has cut off access for months, no end in sight, so she's parked a few blocks away. almost every parking lot in town removed their pay stations years ago. she has a smartphone but no idea how to handle this situation.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>she never would have figured it out. her words, and I don't doubt her.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>the lot has three signs hung up with instructions on how to pay, because every single lot in town supports one to five different competing parking lot apps. there's one sign that says you can use Park Mobile, and gives a lot ID, and then on another wall there's a sign that says you can use PayByPhone, with a different lot ID, and then there's a huge sign with a QR code that encourages you to Scan Here To Park, as if it's the official primary method for doing so. It is not, it's just another app.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>I've scanned these before and gotten an "Instant App." I figure this is minimal friction for this person, so I suggest she do so. she pulls up a QR Scanner app - either because she's been bamboozled into believing that's the only way to get QR support, or because her particular Android phone actually does not have it built into the camera for God knows what reason; I didn't have time to figure out which.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>at first she struggles to figure out how to change cameras, but this turns out to be only because she's used to every camera app opening with the front facing selected by default; it has actually selected the rear camera, so I help her get it aimed right, and it goes bleep, and then... pops up an ad. i have to stop her before she hits open on whatever sludge is trying to put itself on her device<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>then we get a screen with 30 different elements on it describing different qualities of the QR code. the most prominent is a "Search The Web" button, which would have dumped the scanned URL into Google for some reason and produced irrelevant results; i have to direct her to tap the tiny blue link.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>that link opens Instant App. Google play prints a huge permissions message; I direct her to accept it. it installs a 16mb app; so what was the point of Instant here, exactly?<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>well, that's moot anyway, because as soon as it opens, it asks for permission, and then simply installs the normal version of the app, 24mb.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>we get into that. it asks for the street address of the lot. I have never seen this information printed on any parking lot in my life. it suggests several "nearby" options; they are actually half a mile away.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>unable to figure this conundrum out even for myself, i sigh and walk her through installing Park Mobile, which I know works. i help her find the lot ID. it asks for duration. she picks two hours. it asks for payment. she gets out her CC and types in the info.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>proceeding to checkout, it then... selects google pay. even though she just put in a CC. she hits proceed, and i go "is that the right card?" and she double takes and goes "...no." i maybe just saved this woman from losing $30 in overdrafts.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>I direct her to tap the payment options field. nothing. i sigh. "I'm sorry, it looks like you have to tap that tiny pencil icon in the CORNER of the field." yep. finally she's able to select her credit card. she hits proceed.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>it now pops up the duration selector again. what???? why????? it's back at the default of 1 hour, and she tries to pick two again, but it just won't do it. I happen to know this UI pretty well, so I know that if parking time was actually limited to 1 hour, it wouldn't show the option at all. This is just completely glitched out.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>with no other options, she just picks one hour, and successfully pays. we both breathe a sigh of relief, and I advise her that if she needs more time, she should be able to just tap a button in the app to extend her parking. I really hope it actually works like I described.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>throughout all this we had to grant Location permissions at least three times, and each time you have to decide between three options, none of which are "Yes." the one you want is "while the app is open" but there is no way to know this, and nobody alive has ever picked either of the other options. nobody would.<!-- --></p>
<!-- --><p>i have struggled to write an ending to this post three times. words genuinely fail me.<!-- --></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Clone-a-Lisa (165 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vole.wtf/clone-a-lisa/</link>
            <guid>37192710</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 20:15:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vole.wtf/clone-a-lisa/">https://vole.wtf/clone-a-lisa/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37192710">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-message="🎨 I painted the Mona Lisa with {score} accuracy!">
		
		<p id="resultHelp">Tap your pic for screenshot, download and sharing options</p>
		<p id="resultDownloadCopy"><a id="resultDownload" href="#" download="clone-a-lisa.jpg">Download file</a> <a id="resultCopy" href="#">Copy to clipboard</a></p>
		<p id="resultShare">Share score and link to game:</p>
	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[IP address blocking banned after anti-piracy court order hit Cloudflare (120 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://torrentfreak.com/ip-address-blocking-banned-after-anti-piracy-court-order-hit-cloudflare-230811/</link>
            <guid>37192691</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 20:14:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/ip-address-blocking-banned-after-anti-piracy-court-order-hit-cloudflare-230811/">https://torrentfreak.com/ip-address-blocking-banned-after-anti-piracy-court-order-hit-cloudflare-230811/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37192691">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>

<span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to TorrentFreak." href="https://torrentfreak.com/"><span property="name">Home</span></a><meta property="position" content="1"></span> &gt; <span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to the Anti-Piracy category archives." href="https://torrentfreak.com/category/anti-piracy/"><span property="name">Anti-Piracy</span></a><meta property="position" content="2"></span> &gt; <span property="itemListElement" typeof="ListItem"><a property="item" typeof="WebPage" title="Go to the Site Blocking category archives." href="https://torrentfreak.com/category/anti-piracy/site-blocking/"><span property="name">Site Blocking</span></a><meta property="position" content="3"></span> &gt; <span></span>
</p>
<p>
<span> </span>
In 2022, rightsholders obtained permission in Austria to block several pirate site domains and a list of IP addresses that actually belonged to Cloudflare. ISPs had no choice but to comply with the court's instructions which took out countless Cloudflare customers in Austria. According to reviews conducted by local telecoms regulator TKK, the IP address blocking violated net neutrality regulations and will no longer be allowed.
</p>
</div><div>
<p><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked.jpg"><img decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked.jpg" alt="Page Blocked" width="275" height="207" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked.jpg 275w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked-200x150.jpg 200w" sizes="(max-width: 275px) 100vw, 275px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20275%20207'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked.jpg 275w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked-200x150.jpg 200w" data-lazy-src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/pageblocked.jpg"></a>With momentum building in favor of pirate site blocking measures elsewhere in Europe, Austrian ISPs took their <a href="https://futurezone.at/netzpolitik/ogh-netzsperren-sind-zulaessig-user-sollen-dafuer-zahlen/139.308.830">opposition</a> all the way to the country’s Supreme Court.</p>
<p>Despite <a href="https://torrentfreak.com/austrian-telecoms-regulator-rejects-informal-pirate-site-blocks-190118/">concerns</a> over the implications for net neutrality, rightsholders’ interests prevailed. Like many of their foreign counterparts, Austrian ISPs soon found themselves compelled by court order to block torrent and streaming sites, those offering unlicensed musical works, plus scientific article and textbook repositories.</p>
<h2>Domain/DNS Blocking Received Surprise ‘Upgrade’</h2>
<p>For years Austrian ISPs had deployed DNS blocking in response to court orders but in the summer of 2022, everything changed. New pirate site blocking orders not only contained domain names to be blocked, but also a list of IP addresses. </p>
<p>When the ISPs discovered that the IP addresses belonged to Cloudflare, arms were thrown up in despair. With no opportunity to contest the court-ordered blockades, ISPs had no other choice than to block the IP addresses, rendering countless innocent sites using Cloudflare inaccessible.</p>
<p>While this disruption was controversial and avoidable, the long term effect should be more positive.</p>
<h2>IP Address Blocking Violated Net Neutrality</h2>
<p>In a <a href="https://www.rtr.at/TKP/was_wir_tun/telekommunikation/weitere-regulierungsthemen/netzneutralitaet/nn_procedures.de.html">series of reports</a> published this week, local telecoms regulator Telekom Control Commission (TKK) states that the IP address blocks implemented last August amounted to net neutrality violations under EU law.</p>
<p>“In a decision dated August 7, 2023, the Telekom Control Commission decided on the admissibility of blocking networks by [various local ISPs] based on a warning from the rights holder SATEL Film GmbH in accordance with <a href="https://wilmap.stanford.edu/country/austria">Section 81 (1a) UrhG</a>,” one of the reports begins.</p>
<p>“The provider mentioned had set up DNS access blocks on the one hand and an IP access block on the other in its network at the end of August 2022. With regard to the DNS access blocks, no current violation of Art 3 Para 3 VO (EU) 2015/2120 was found and the procedure was discontinued in this respect.</p>
<p>“With regard to the blocking of access to the IP address 190.115.18.20, the Telekom Control Commission found a violation of <a href="https://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri=CELEX:32015R2120">Article 3 Paragraph 3 of Regulation (EU) 2015/2120</a>, because the IP access block poses the risk of ‘overblocking’ any website content.”</p>
<center><a href="https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3.png"><img decoding="async" src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3.png" alt="net-neutrality-art3" width="610" height="285" srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3.png 686w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3-300x140.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 610px) 100vw, 610px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%20610%20285'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-lazy-srcset="https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3.png 686w, https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3-300x140.png 300w" data-lazy-src="https://torrentfreak.com/images/net-neutrality-art3.png"></a></center>
<p>In a follow-up announcement, TKK said that, since DNS-based blocking is generally sufficient to protect rightsholders, that will be the only method available to them moving forward.</p>
<h2>Protecting Net Neutrality</h2>
<p>After declaring IP address-based blocking prohibited in Austria, TKK explained its reasoning to a background of net neutrality and freedom of expression on the Internet.</p>
<p>“Since countless websites can be accessed from a single IP address, the risk of blocking websites or Internet services of uninvolved third parties is particularly high in the event of a block,” a TKK spokesman said.</p>
<p>“In Austria, network blocks have so far mainly been implemented with so-called ‘DNS blocks’. With this type of block, only individual domains are blocked and blocking notices are displayed instead. It is important that this practice is maintained in order to maintain the legally required proportionality in the future.” </p>
<p><em>TKK’s commitment to transparency includes <a href="https://www.rtr.at/TKP/was_wir_tun/telekommunikation/weitere-regulierungsthemen/netzneutralitaet/nn_blockings.de.html">publishing all blocking decisions</a> and the domains they affect.</em></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Iraq Blocks Telegram, Leaks Blackhole BGP Routes (199 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.kentik.com/blog/iraq-blocks-telegram-leaks-blackhole-bgp-routes/</link>
            <guid>37191332</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 17:55:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.kentik.com/blog/iraq-blocks-telegram-leaks-blackhole-bgp-routes/">https://www.kentik.com/blog/iraq-blocks-telegram-leaks-blackhole-bgp-routes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37191332">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">This past weekend, the government of Iraq blocked the popular messaging app Telegram, citing the need to protect Iraqi’s personal data. However, when an Iraqi government network leaked out a BGP hijack used for the block, it became yet another BGP incident that was both intentional, but also accidental. Thankfully disruption was minimized by Telegram’s use of RPKI.</p><div><p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">This past weekend, the government of Iraq took the step to block the popular messaging app Telegram, citing the need to <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/iraq-blocks-telegram-app-cites-personal-data-violations-2023-08-06/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">protect the personal data of Iraqi users</a> following a leak of confidential information. According to data from our friends over at Tor’s <a href="https://explorer.ooni.org/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Open Observatory for Network Interference (OONI)</a>, the block was implemented by <a href="https://explorer.ooni.org/chart/mat?test_name=telegram&amp;axis_x=measurement_start_day&amp;since=2023-07-08&amp;until=2023-08-08&amp;time_grain=day&amp;probe_cc=IQ" rel="noopener" target="_blank">blocking Telegram’s IP addresses</a>.</p>
<picture><source srcset="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=90&amp;w=145&amp;fm=webp 145w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=90&amp;w=290&amp;fm=webp 290w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=90&amp;w=580&amp;fm=webp 580w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=80&amp;w=1160&amp;fm=webp 1160w" type="image/webp" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px"><source srcset="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=90&amp;w=145 145w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=90&amp;w=290 290w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=90&amp;w=580 580w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=80&amp;w=1160 1160w" sizes="(max-width: 580px) 100vw, 580px"><img alt="Iraq Telegram test graph from OONI" src="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/6ZEi3RyL5qch9cAoVw3I86/27bd164bfb1581cebcc45be93851cc64/iraq-telegram-test.png?q=80&amp;w=580" loading="lazy" width="100%" height="auto"></picture>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Evidently, when the Iraqi government began blocking Telegram, it started by <a href="https://twitter.com/DougMadory/status/1688660150087823360" rel="noopener" target="_blank">using BGP to hijack traffic</a> destined for IP addresses associated with the messaging service, redirecting them to the proverbial bitbucket. And, as has happened before on numerous occasions, these hijack BGP routes leaked out of the country.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">However, despite this technical error, no Telegram disruption was reported outside of Iraq, in part, due to the fact that Telegram had created <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Public_Key_Infrastructure#Route_Origin_Authorizations" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Route Origin Authorizations</a> (ROAs) for its routes allowing ASes outside of Iraq to automatically reject the hijacks. A ROA is a record in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resource_Public_Key_Infrastructure" rel="noopener" target="_blank">RPKI</a> that specifies the AS origin that is authorized to originate the IP address range.</p>

<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Perhaps the most famous BGP hijack ever was Pakistan’s <a href="https://www.wired.com/2008/02/pakistans-accid/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">hijack of YouTube in 2008</a> (also see <a href="https://www.kentik.com/blog/a-brief-history-of-the-internets-biggest-bgp-incidents/">The Internet’s Biggest BGP Incidents</a>). In that case, the Pakistani government ordered a block of Youtube in the country. The Pakistani state telecom, PTCL created BGP routes to hijack traffic destined for Youtube and blackhole it. However, the hijacks leaked out of Pakistan, leading to a global disruption of Youtube. Over the years, there have been many such leaks of BGP hijacks meant to censor content, such as those in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20210512142832mp_/https://blogs.oracle.com/internetintelligence/ukraine-bans-russian-social-media" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Ukraine</a> and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170327193134/http://dyn.com/blog/iran-leaks-censorship-via-bgp-hijacks/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Iran</a>.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">More recently, during the initial weeks of the <a href="https://www.kentik.com/blog/myanmar-goes-offline-during-military-coup/">Myanmar military coup in 2021</a>, the military junta in charge ordered social media to be blocked. To comply with the order, one Myanma ISP elected to use BGP in order to hijack local Twitter traffic and drop it. Unfortunately, <a href="https://www.manrs.org/2021/02/did-someone-try-to-hijack-twitter-yes/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">their hijack route was inadvertently leaked out</a> of Myanmar, causing disruptions to Twitter around South Asia.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">And finally, last year, during Russia’s crackdown on social media and independent journalism following their invasion of Ukraine, a <a href="https://www.itnews.com.au/news/russian-network-hijacked-twitter-traffic-578000" rel="noopener" target="_blank">Russian ISP elected to use BGP to blackhole traffic</a> to Twitter by hijacking the <em>exact same prefix</em> (104.244.42.0/24) that was hijacked a year earlier in Myanmar.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">However, there was a difference between the two hijacks of Twitter’s 104.244.42.0/24 by Myanmar in 2021 and then again by Russia in 2022. In the intervening year, Twitter deployed RPKI, creating ROAs in RPKI for nearly all of its routes. By doing so, it enabled ASes which reject RPKI-invalid routes to automatically reject the hijack routes, limiting the disruption to Twitter.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">As Twitter’s CISO <a href="https://twitter.com/LeaKissner/status/1508503164374315011" rel="noopener" target="_blank">wrote at the time</a>, “a bunch of the point of having security is to keep your systems from breaking all of the time” and in this case, it kept a BGP hijack from breaking access to Twitter for users outside of Russia. The Russian hijack propagated <a href="https://twitter.com/DougMadory/status/1508466367112093709" rel="noopener" target="_blank"><em>slightly less</em></a> than the hijack from Myanmar, but it is hard to directly compare since the hijacks were announced from different places on the internet, and there are numerous factors which can influence BGP route propagation.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Anecdotally, I would say that after my <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hKwjq94Quhc" rel="noopener" target="_blank">NANOG 86 presentation</a> on the internet impacts due to the war in Ukraine, one of Twitter’s network engineers shared that, from a traffic standpoint, they observed significantly less disruption due to the Russian hijack. They believed the difference was due to RPKI.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">The recent episode in Iraq is similar to the aforementioned cases because it was a BGP incident that was intentional, but also accidental. The network accidentally leaked out a BGP hijack that they intentionally created.</p>

<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Except for the networks in the semi-autonomous region of Kurdistan, all Iraqi internet service must go through <a href="https://bgp.tools/as/208293" rel="noopener" target="_blank">AS208293</a>, a government network which serves as the country’s international gateway. AS208293 normally doesn’t originate any routes; it only connects the country’s telecoms to international transit providers.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">However, at 13:52 UTC on 5 August 2023, AS208293 started originating the following prefixes:</p>
<table><tbody><tr><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">151.106.160.0/19</td><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">95.161.64.0/20</td></tr><tr><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">95.161.0.0/17</td><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">91.108.8.0/22</td></tr><tr><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">91.108.0.0/18</td><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">91.108.4.0/22</td></tr><tr><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">149.154.160.0/20</td><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">149.154.164.0/22</td></tr><tr><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">91.108.56.0/22</td><td color="body" font-size="16,18" font-weight="light">149.154.160.0/22</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">All but the first are address ranges used by Telegram. 151.106.160.0/19 was last utilized by the <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/subspace-com_we-regret-to-announce-that-effective-may-activity-6930952295824207873-2z25/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">now-defunct Subspace network</a>, so the reason for its inclusion is unclear.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Illustrated in Kentik’s BGP Route Viewer below, 149.154.160.0/20 was originated by AS208293 and attained global circulation for two reasons. The first was that there was no competing route in circulation — 149.154.160.0/20 is “less-specific” to existing Telegram routes. Secondly, there was no matching ROA in RPKI to give ASes who have deployed RPKI a reason to reject it.</p>
<div><picture><source srcset="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=90&amp;w=200&amp;fm=webp 200w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=90&amp;w=400&amp;fm=webp 400w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=90&amp;w=800&amp;fm=webp 800w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=80&amp;w=1600&amp;fm=webp 1600w" type="image/webp" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><source srcset="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=90&amp;w=200 200w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=90&amp;w=400 400w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=90&amp;w=800 800w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=80&amp;w=1600 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><img src="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/2SKv4tHTkjO96rSP4SS2Iu/87b18e94f21eacd721dbe2ac24a88c5d/bgp-route-viewer-spike.png?q=80&amp;w=800" alt="BGP Route Viewer showing origination" loading="lazy" width="100%" height="auto"></picture></div>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Conversely, when we look at the propagation of the corresponding “more-specific” 149.154.160.0/22, we see that nearly the entire internet believed (correctly!) that AS62041 (Telegram) was the origin. While AS208293 shows up in red in the ball-and-stick diagram along the bottom, it can hardly be seen in the upper stacked plot, which depicts route propagation by origin.</p>
<div><picture><source srcset="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=90&amp;w=200&amp;fm=webp 200w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=90&amp;w=400&amp;fm=webp 400w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=90&amp;w=800&amp;fm=webp 800w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=80&amp;w=1600&amp;fm=webp 1600w" type="image/webp" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><source srcset="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=90&amp;w=200 200w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=90&amp;w=400 400w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=90&amp;w=800 800w, https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=80&amp;w=1600 1600w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px"><img src="https://images.ctfassets.net/6yom6slo28h2/51o8y6IEJZnm7ehxutN4hj/fe94a5563b3a3fd40eb8865738acd7b7/bgp-route-viewer-propagation.png?q=80&amp;w=800" alt="BGP Route Viewer showing propagation" loading="lazy" width="100%" height="auto"></picture></div>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">The lack of propagation of a BGP route with AS208293 as the origin of 149.154.160.0/22 is due to the fact that there was already an existing route to compete with (originated by AS62041), but also because the route from Iraq was <a href="https://rpki-validator.ripe.net/ui/149.154.160.0%2F22/AS208293?include=related_alloc,related_less_specific" rel="noopener" target="_blank">RPKI-invalid</a>, dramatically <a href="https://www.kentik.com/blog/how-much-does-rpki-rov-reduce-the-propagation-of-invalid-routes/">limiting its reach</a>.</p>

<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">The challenge of measuring the positive impact of any security mechanism is that it often requires knowledge of the incidents that didn’t occur as a result of its use. RPKI is no different. While it likely didn’t have the potential to be another Pakistan/YouTube incident, BGP non-events like this are what RPKI success looks like.</p>
<p font-size="18,20" font-weight="300" color="body">Of course, this is little solace to the Iraqi users who must now employ a VPN to circumvent this IP-level blockage. Censoring Telegram will do little to protect the personal data of any Iraqis, but it does cut them off from a popular communication tool and source of news and information.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[70 years ago, an Anglo-US coup condemned Iran to decades of oppression (205 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://theconversation.com/70-years-ago-an-anglo-us-coup-condemned-iran-to-decades-of-oppression-but-now-the-people-are-fighting-back-211698</link>
            <guid>37191220</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 17:45:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://theconversation.com/70-years-ago-an-anglo-us-coup-condemned-iran-to-decades-of-oppression-but-now-the-people-are-fighting-back-211698">https://theconversation.com/70-years-ago-an-anglo-us-coup-condemned-iran-to-decades-of-oppression-but-now-the-people-are-fighting-back-211698</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37191220">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>The <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/w3cswpt1#:%7E:text=In%201953%20Iran's%20democratically%20elected,British%20and%20American%20intelligence%20services.">1953 coup d'etat</a> in Iran ushered in a period of exploitation and oppression that has continued – despite a subsequent revolution that led to huge changes – for 70 years. Each year on August 19, the anniversary of the coup, millions of Iranians ask themselves what would have happened if the US and UK had not conspired all those years ago to overthrow Iran’s democratically elected leader. </p>

<p>Iran, the Middle East and, arguably, the whole world may well have been profoundly different. Apart from rewriting the destiny of Iran and its neighbours, the coup paved the way for a series of imperialist interventions and the toppling of democratically elected governments across the global south. Perhaps Washington might have thought twice before plotting coups in <a href="https://www.zinnedproject.org/news/tdih/jacobo-arbenz-guzman-deposed/">Guatemala in 1954</a>, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/poverty-matters/2011/jan/17/patrice-lumumba-50th-anniversary-assassination">Congo in 1961</a> or <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2023/aug/18/1973-coup-chile-democratic-socialism-still-matters-britain">Chile in 1973</a>, if they’d been unable to overthrow Iran’s prime minister, Mohammad Mosaddegh, so easily and profitably.</p>

<p>As the democratically elected leader of Iran from 1951 to 1953, Mosaddegh championed nationalisation of Iran’s oil industry. This had previously been in the hands of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anglo-Persian_Oil_Company">Anglo-Persian Oil Company</a> –  a British company, founded in 1909 after the discovery of a large oil field in Iran, which would later become BP. </p>

<figure>
            <a href="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1000&amp;fit=clip"><p><img alt="Portrait of former Iranian prime minister Mohammad Mosaddegh" data-src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=237&amp;fit=clip" data-srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=768&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=768&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=768&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=965&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=965&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=965&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543447/original/file-20230818-19-81nz7l.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=237&amp;fit=clip"></p></a>
            <figcaption>
              <span>Iran’s prime minister Mohammad Mosaddegh was overthrown by an Anglo-US coup in 1953.</span>
              
            </figcaption>
          </figure>

<p>In March 1951, Iran’s parliament <a href="https://archive.nytimes.com/www.nytimes.com/library/world/mideast/032551iran-oil-vote.html">voted to proceed with nationalisation</a>. This caused consternation in the west – most notably in Britain, where the prospect of nationalisation was seen as potentially hugely damaging to the economy. Furthermore, it would have undermined Britain’s influence in the Middle East. Plotting to depose Mosaddegh began in earnest.</p>

<p>In the event, the coup – named <a href="https://foreignpolicy.com/2017/06/20/64-years-later-cia-finally-releases-details-of-iranian-coup-iran-tehran-oil/">Operation Ajax</a> –  was a joint venture between the CIA and MI6. The shah, Mohammad Reza Pahlavi, who had recently fled the country after an earlier plot to remove Mossadegh had failed, returned to Iran.</p>

<p>Within a short period, he had tightened his grip on the country’s security services and imposed a dictatorial regime which ruled through brutality and fear. Pahlavi banned all opposition political parties, and many of the activists who participated in the movement for nationalisation of oil were arrested or fled the country. </p>

<h2>Government by fear</h2>

<p>In 1957, the shah established an internal security service, <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SAVAK">Sazman-e Ettel'at va Amniyat-e Keshvar</a></em> (Savak), which essentially ran Iran at the shah’s bidding. From then until 1975, only two major political parties were allowed to operate, the People’s Party (<em>Ḥezb-e Mardom</em>) and the New Iran Party (<em>Ḥezb-e Iran-e Novin</em>), and all parliamentary candidates had to be approved by Savak.</p>

<p>Both parties in reality were wholly under the shah’s control. The parliament only existed to rubber-stamp his decisions, as did the prime minister – who the shah appointed. </p>

<p>In 1975, the shah took his domination of Iranian politics further, <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/1975/03/03/archives/shah-decrees-iran-a-oneparty-nation.html">establishing a single party</a>, the Party of Resurrection of the Iranian Nation (<em>Hezb-e Rastakhiz</em>), which all Iranians were obliged to join. By 1979, when Iran <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/articles/the-iranian-revolution-a-timeline-of-events/">rose up in a popular revolution</a>, it was a virtual absolute monarchy, with the shah’s will enforced by the dreaded Savak secret police.</p>

<p>Within months of the revolution, though, Iran’s religious authorities took control under the leadership of Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. The Islamic Republic quickly <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/archive/politics/1980/06/07/khomeini-is-reported-to-have-a-savak-of-his-own/dfc8e0a4-85b5-4a35-9723-c8a57caabae6/">established its own secret police, Savama</a> – <em>[Sazman-e Ettelaat Va Amniat Meli Iran](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ministry_of_Intelligence</em>(Iran))_ – which used many of the same brutal methods as Savak.</p>

<h2>‘Woman, Life, Freedom’</h2>

<p>This week, Iranians will recall the 1953 coup as they prepare protests ahead of the anniversary of the “Woman, Life, Freedom” uprising. This movement began in September 2022 after the <a href="https://theconversation.com/iran-on-fire-once-again-women-are-on-the-vanguard-of-transformative-change-191297">death of Mahsa Amini</a> at the hands of the morality police – who <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-middle-east-66218318">patrol the streets</a> tasked with enforcing the laws on Islamic dress code in public – for the “crime” of not wearing her hijab (headscarf) in the approved manner. </p>

<figure>
            <p><img alt="Iranian women living in exile in London hold up pictures of Mahsa Amini at the hands of Iran's morality police in September 2022." data-src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" data-srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/543453/original/file-20230818-27-h1hccg.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip"></p>
            <figcaption>
              <span>Iranian women living in exile in London protest the murder of Mahsa Amini at the hands of Iran’s morality police in September 2022.</span>
              <span><span>Stephen Chung/Alamy Live News</span></span>
            </figcaption>
          </figure>

<p>The resulting explosion of unrest has posed the most serious challenge to the Islamic Republic in its history. Although the state tried to <a href="https://theconversation.com/iran-is-using-every-effort-to-crush-protesters-intent-on-a-revolution-except-hearing-them-out-193684">crush the demonstrations</a> from the beginning, the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2023/jul/24/theres-no-other-option-but-to-fight-iranian-women-defiant-as-morality-police-return">protesters have defied</a> police brutality and the prospect of severe punishment, which included public executions and <a href="https://www.hrw.org/news/2022/12/13/iran-death-sentences-against-protesters">hundreds of deaths of protesters</a> at the hands of the security forces.</p>

<p>At the same time as battling the oppression of their own state apparatus, ordinary Iranians are also suffering under the brutal US-imposed regime of sanctions. In the past five years, these sanctions – reimposed by Donald Trump after he unilaterally pulled the US out of the Iran Nuclear Deal, which had been signed by his predecessor Barack Obama in 2015 – have devastated the Iranian economy. Soaring inflation and devaluation of the national currency have caused <a href="https://www.ft.com/content/c86fccb4-f56e-43b7-a596-29c036cb4ec1?accessToken=zwAGAzIWvP-IkdPIb8y09W5Dt9OllinANstOwQ.MEUCIB-C6PA2kZTxATwPKPY1n-zam6BzvbSibbybEmV1FFyZAiEAhZTNZOtTm3l-gtkRtQYHI-C5I9UpYRKxm-s5hZRRBjc&amp;sharetype=gift&amp;token=b91228d2-5530-4fe4-bbf3-071a531111a6">serious hardship</a> for ordinary Iranians.</p>

<p>As they <a href="https://theconversation.com/iran-unions-and-civil-rights-groups-demand-democracy-and-social-justice-201422">fight for a better future</a>, Iranians clearly grasp how, 70 years after the coup snuffed out their fledgling democracy, their internal struggles are still being influenced by foreign powers. </p>

<p>And they ask themselves if Mahsa Amini, and also <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2022/oct/08/mother-says-police-beat-daughter-to-death-in-iranian-protests">Nika Shahkarami</a> and <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2022/oct/07/another-teenage-girl-dead-at-hands-of-irans-security-forces-reports-claim">Sarina Esmailzadeh</a> – two other women beaten to death by members of the state apparatus for protesting – as well as hundreds of other young Iranians, would still be paying with their lives in Iran’s struggle for basic rights today if the 1953 coup had not happened.</p>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Aviation navigation log on $20 receipt printer (241 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps.html</link>
            <guid>37190743</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 16:57:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps.html">https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37190743">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p>
          Howdy! I’m Carlos and I like tech and planes (among other things like
          having massive servings of pasta). I’m currently studying for my
          commercial license in Europe. So far most of my flight training has
          happened on a Piper PA28 (the -180 variant)
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image2.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>my school's plane doesn't look this pretty</figcaption>
        <p>
          It’s from the late 60s, often there are at least 1 or 2 things that
          don’t work properly and it shows - the thing is old! I imagine at some
          point I’ll jump into modern jets, and so I am happy to spend the first
          few hundred hours being as much of an ‘aviator’ as possible.
        </p>
        <p>
          As a bit of background, these planes are single pilot operation, so
          the idea is that whoever is flying is doing the navigating, the
          radios, the checklist, the flying, the communicating and the looking
          out and in. It can get busy.
        </p>
        <p>
          The one thing on this plane that is just hard to adapt to is how
          cramped it is and hot it can get - I’m talking about 38C/100F in a
          vibrating machine for 3h. And I say that with the knowledge of all the
          other issues this plane has (magnetos may drop excessively, gyro
          basically useless, fuel pump is old…).
        </p>
        <p>
          We get these things called kneeboards, that provide a ‘comfy’ space
          for us to write down things like the weather reports, the tower
          instructions and how accurate our routing plan is as we follow it
          along.
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image7.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
          how comfortable is that! does it come with a cupholder?
        </figcaption>
        <p>
          Whilst this picture looks pretty spacious, my plane is more cramped
          than that, and I’m sitting at a weirder angle. In my kneeboard /
          floating around the plane I have: 
          </p><ul>
            <li><a href="https://live.staticflickr.com/3070/5823042998_7de069bf04_b.jpg">Checklist</a> (before taking off checklist, taxiing checklist, …)</li>
            <li><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sectional_aeronautical_chart">Map</a> (big unfolding 1:400 map) (like the ones in the cartoons that open and open and open)</li>
            <li>Piece of paper to jot on (weather, tower instructions, tic tac toe..)</li>
            <li>Nav log (more on this soon)</li>
          </ul>    
        
        <p>
            All of those documents have to be hot swapped for one another at different phases of the flight, and so there is actually a pretty big market for kneeboards and all the shapes and sizes they can come in. 
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image1.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
          the kneeboard, the cargo pants of the air
        </figcaption>
        <p>
            The Nav log is the term we give for a paper with point-to-point instructions from one waypoint to another. It typically has a lot of information to help us navigate (and even more info that we really use but had to write down to work out other things). Here’s a sample, but don’t worry too much about reading it.

        </p>
        <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image3.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
          an example of a Navigation Log
        </figcaption>
        <p>
            Realistically, out of all those numbers, I’m only really looking at a few because things like the wind correction angle only really matter so that I can work out other information (except in some edge cases).
        </p>
        <p>
            Since I’ve grown happy with how I work out the items in the Nav log (an important skill when you are in training), now I occasionally use this tool (screenshot below) which automatically fills most of those fields for me. For the most part it is repetitive work, like “how do my heading and wind interact with each other, hmm let me see.. <basic math="" here="">”. 
        </basic></p>
        <p>
            I simply look at my 1:400 map and then pick out the waypoints in this browser tool. This allows me to prep other parts of my fight that I might be doing that lesson whilst still having a fleshed out Nav log!
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image5.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
          one of the tools available for flight planning
        </figcaption>
        <p>
            I then get a PDF which I can then copy by hand into my Kneeboard nav log. Sweet!
        </p>
        <p>
            Like I said I also like computers and toyin’ around with them, and so the other day I bought a receipt printer. Why? Well… 
            </p><ul>
                <li>they seemed super cool for small projects</li>
                <li>don’t use ink</li>
                <li>can get them second hand easily</li>
                <li>plug and play into Linux (/dev/usb/lp0)</li>
                <li>look cute (mostly through the use of googly eyes</li>
              </ul>   
        
        <p>
            So then I thought… hey… what about the windshield pillar or a-pillar (if you speak cars) in the plane?
        </p>
        <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image4.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
          it's strange to find unsued space in a cockpit
        </figcaption>
        <p>
            I mean, that thing is in the middle of the cockpit, serves no function (other than the obvious one of preventing a total structural collapse) and is strangely receipt sized.. surely.. I could use that to alleviate some of my issues with the cramped kneeboard. 
        </p>
        <p>
            Why don’t I make a <a href="https://github.com/kiloamp/fliprep">git project</a> that will let me have nicely formatted receipt prints of my nav log.  
        </p>
        <p>
            I thought the Navlog would be the easiest thing to do so that’s where I started. Oh how wrong I was.
        </p>
        <p>
            Knowing that I’ll be using SkyVector for the foreseeable future I wrote a quick (ish) script to grab their Nav log. Ideally I could export a Navlog in some format like the Garmin one, but not really - only a weirdly formatted PDF. 
        </p>
        <p>
            Anyways, fair enough -- I’ll just grab the whole PDF text with Ctrl+A and then ask the user to paste it into my script.
        </p>
        <p>
            Thanks to: 
            </p><ul>
                <li>Regex (special weird code that searches for patterns in code)
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            think “take this ‘he3ll4o, $$th3er8e’ and remove everything that isn’t a letter
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>String splitting (less weird looking code that lets you play around with a chunk of text)
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            think “from the above example, split hello there into [“hello”], [“there”]
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
                <li>Some math to fill in here and there 
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            think “once we have [speed] and [distance] from the PDF work out the time taken”

                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </li>
              </ul>  
            
            <p>
                I actually got a somewhat pretty looking Python dictionary / JSON of every leg of the journey. 
            </p>
            <pre>{
    "from": null,
    "to": null,
    "wind_direction": null,
    "wind_speed": null,
    "temp": null,
    "temp_deviation": null,
    "TAS": null,
    "Track": null,
    "WCA": null,
    "TH": null,
    "Var": null,
    "Magnetic Heading": null,
    "Ground Speed": null,
    "Distance": null,
    "ETA": null,
    "CumulativeETA": null
}</pre>
            <p>
                Then that JSON was exported into a PHP file (thanks <a href="https://github.com/mike42/escpos-php/">Mike42’s escpos-php/ library</a>!) which is what I’m using for formatting text in the receipt printer (mostly just font size and text-wrapping) and boom!
            </p>
            <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image9.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
                version 1 -- still with a few things to add!
            </figcaption>
            <p>
                I have to say it works surprisingly well. I use that to quickly understand where I am whilst I play with the map and communicate on our area’s busy air to air frequency. 
            </p>
            <p>
                I don’t consider this to be dangerous since I also carry with me the full Nav log, so at any doubt I have all the other details, but hey, it never hurts to have extra easily-accessible information in unused space! 
            </p>
            <p>
                The script also works for simpler things, like printing the lesson plan if you want to. Hopefully in version 2 I can make this feature a bit more extensive, and maybe have some nicer formatting, maybe a QR reference to the lesson plan, etc..etc… 
            </p>
            <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image6.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
                the lesson plan is normally on an internal web app, I’d rather sellotape it to the plane! 
            </figcaption>
            <p><img src="https://carloslagoa.com/blog/flipreps/flipreps_files/image8.png" alt="alt text"></p><figcaption>
                the welcome screen!
            </figcaption>
        </div><p>
        <h3>
            Thank you so much for reading! <i>Feedback? Ideas? Hate? Coffee? </i>
        </h3>
        <h3>
            me(at)carloslagoa.com
        </h3>
    </p></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenZFS – add disks to existing RAIDZ (172 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/pull/15022</link>
            <guid>37190493</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 16:35:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/pull/15022">https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/pull/15022</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37190493">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
  
  <task-lists disabled="" sortable="">
    <div>
      <h3 dir="auto">Motivation and Context</h3>
<p dir="auto">This feature allows disks to be added one at a time to a RAID-Z group, expanding its capacity incrementally. This feature is especially useful for small pools (typically with only one RAID-Z group), where there isn't sufficient hardware to add capacity by adding a whole new RAID-Z group (typically doubling the number of disks).</p>
<p dir="auto">For additional context as well as a design overview, see Matt Ahrens' talk at the <a href="https://wiki.freebsd.org/DevSummit/202106" rel="nofollow">2021 FreeBSD Developer Summit</a> (<a href="https://youtu.be/3SUKJye54aI?t=6166" rel="nofollow">video</a>) (<a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1FeQgEwChrtNQBHfWSNsPK3Y53O5BnPh3Cz5nRa5GAQY/edit#slide=id.p" rel="nofollow">slides</a>), and a <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2021/06/raidz-expansion-code-lands-in-openzfs-master/" rel="nofollow">news article from Ars Technica</a>.</p>
<h3 dir="auto">Description</h3>
<h4 dir="auto">Initiating expansion</h4>
<p dir="auto">A new device (disk) can be attached to an existing RAIDZ vdev, by running <code>zpool attach POOL raidzP-N NEW_DEVICE</code>, e.g. <code>zpool attach tank raidz2-0 sda</code>. The new device will become part of the RAIDZ group. A <em>raidz expansion</em> will<br>
be initiated, and the new device will contribute additional space to the RAIDZ group once the expansion completes.</p>
<p dir="auto">The <code>feature@raidz_expansion</code> on-disk feature flag must be <code>enabled</code> to initiate an expansion, and it remains <code>active</code> for the life of the pool. In other words, pools with expanded RAIDZ vdevs can not be imported by older releases of the ZFS software.</p>
<h4 dir="auto">During expansion</h4>
<p dir="auto">The expansion entails reading all allocated space from existing disks in the RAIDZ group, and rewriting it to the new disks in the RAIDZ group (including the newly added device).</p>
<p dir="auto">The expansion progress can be monitored with <code>zpool status</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto">Data redundancy is maintained during (and after) the expansion. If a disk fails while the expansion is in progress, the expansion pauses until the health of the RAIDZ vdev is restored (e.g. by replacing the failed disk and waiting<br>
for reconstruction to complete).</p>
<p dir="auto">The pool remains accessible during expansion. Following a reboot or export/import, the expansion resumes where it left off.</p>
<h4 dir="auto">After expansion</h4>
<p dir="auto">When the expansion completes, the additional space is available for use, and is reflected in the <code>available</code> zfs property (as seen in <code>zfs list</code>, <code>df</code>, etc).</p>
<p dir="auto">Expansion does not change the number of failures that can be tolerated without data loss (e.g. a RAIDZ2 is still a RAIDZ2 even after expansion).</p>
<p dir="auto">A RAIDZ vdev can be expanded multiple times.</p>
<p dir="auto">After the expansion completes, old blocks remain with their old data-to-parity ratio (e.g. 5-wide RAIDZ2, has 3 data to 2 parity), but distributed among the larger set of disks. New blocks will be written with the new data-to-parity<br>
ratio (e.g. a 5-wide RAIDZ2 which has been expanded once to 6-wide, has 4 data to 2 parity). However, the RAIDZ vdev's "assumed parity ratio" does not change, so slightly less space than is expected may be reported for newly-written blocks, according to <code>zfs list</code>, <code>df</code>, <code>ls -s</code>, and similar tools.</p>
<h4 dir="auto">Manpage changes</h4>
<p dir="auto">zpool-attach.8:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="NAME
     zpool-attach — attach new device to existing ZFS vdev

SYNOPSIS
     zpool attach [-fsw] [-o property=value] pool device new_device

DESCRIPTION
     Attaches new_device to the existing device.  The behavior differs depend‐
     ing on if the existing device is a RAIDZ device, or a mirror/plain
     device.

     If the existing device is a mirror or plain device ...

     If the existing device is a RAIDZ device (e.g. specified as &quot;raidz2-0&quot;),
     the new device will become part of that RAIDZ group.  A &quot;raidz expansion&quot;
     will be initiated, and the new device will contribute additional space to
     the RAIDZ group once the expansion completes.  The expansion entails
     reading all allocated space from existing disks in the RAIDZ group, and
     rewriting it to the new disks in the RAIDZ group (including the newly
     added device).  Its progress can be monitored with zpool status.

     Data redundancy is maintained during and after the expansion.  If a disk
     fails while the expansion is in progress, the expansion pauses until the
     health of the RAIDZ vdev is restored (e.g. by replacing the failed disk
     and waiting for reconstruction to complete).  Expansion does not change
     the number of failures that can be tolerated without data loss (e.g. a
     RAIDZ2 is still a RAIDZ2 even after expansion).  A RAIDZ vdev can be
     expanded multiple times.

     After the expansion completes, old blocks remain with their old data-to-
     parity ratio (e.g. 5-wide RAIDZ2, has 3 data to 2 parity), but distrib‐
     uted among the larger set of disks.  New blocks will be written with the
     new data-to-parity ratio (e.g. a 5-wide RAIDZ2 which has been expanded
     once to 6-wide, has 4 data to 2 parity).  However, the RAIDZ vdev's
     &quot;assumed parity ratio&quot; does not change, so slightly less space than is
     expected may be reported for newly-written blocks, according to zfs list,
     df, ls -s, and similar tools."><pre><code>NAME
     zpool-attach — attach new device to existing ZFS vdev

SYNOPSIS
     zpool attach [-fsw] [-o property=value] pool device new_device

DESCRIPTION
     Attaches new_device to the existing device.  The behavior differs depend‐
     ing on if the existing device is a RAIDZ device, or a mirror/plain
     device.

     If the existing device is a mirror or plain device ...

     If the existing device is a RAIDZ device (e.g. specified as "raidz2-0"),
     the new device will become part of that RAIDZ group.  A "raidz expansion"
     will be initiated, and the new device will contribute additional space to
     the RAIDZ group once the expansion completes.  The expansion entails
     reading all allocated space from existing disks in the RAIDZ group, and
     rewriting it to the new disks in the RAIDZ group (including the newly
     added device).  Its progress can be monitored with zpool status.

     Data redundancy is maintained during and after the expansion.  If a disk
     fails while the expansion is in progress, the expansion pauses until the
     health of the RAIDZ vdev is restored (e.g. by replacing the failed disk
     and waiting for reconstruction to complete).  Expansion does not change
     the number of failures that can be tolerated without data loss (e.g. a
     RAIDZ2 is still a RAIDZ2 even after expansion).  A RAIDZ vdev can be
     expanded multiple times.

     After the expansion completes, old blocks remain with their old data-to-
     parity ratio (e.g. 5-wide RAIDZ2, has 3 data to 2 parity), but distrib‐
     uted among the larger set of disks.  New blocks will be written with the
     new data-to-parity ratio (e.g. a 5-wide RAIDZ2 which has been expanded
     once to 6-wide, has 4 data to 2 parity).  However, the RAIDZ vdev's
     "assumed parity ratio" does not change, so slightly less space than is
     expected may be reported for newly-written blocks, according to zfs list,
     df, ls -s, and similar tools.
</code></pre></div>
<h4 dir="auto">Status</h4>
<p dir="auto">Matt Ahrens' original pull request (<a data-error-text="Failed to load title" data-id="918240803" data-permission-text="Title is private" data-url="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/issues/12225" data-hovercard-type="pull_request" data-hovercard-url="/openzfs/zfs/pull/12225/hovercard" href="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/pull/12225">#12225</a>) has been rebased here to current master branch and updated to incorporate recent code cleanups in the OpenZFS codebase. This feature is believed to be complete. However, like all PR's, it is subject to change as part of the code review process. Since this PR includes on-disk changes, it shouldn't be used on production systems before it is integrated to the OpenZFS codebase. Tasks that still need to be done before integration:</p>
<ul>
<li> Additional code cleanup in <code>ztest</code> code</li>
<li> <code>zloop</code> changes to drive coverage of this feature</li>
<li> Address test failures in <code>ztest</code> runs</li>
<li> Document the high-level design in a "big theory statement" comment</li>
<li> Remove verbose logging</li>
<li> Detection of MBR partitions using reserved boot area (FreeBSD BTX boot loader)</li>
<li> Address any performance concerns</li>
</ul>
<h3 dir="auto">Acknowledgments</h3>
<p dir="auto">Thank you to the <a href="https://freebsdfoundation.org/" rel="nofollow">FreeBSD Foundation</a> for commissioning this work in 2017 and continuing to sponsor it well past the original time estimates!<br>
Thank you to <a href="https://www.ixsystems.com/" rel="nofollow">iXsystems</a> for sponsoring the final push to land this feature into OpenZFS.</p>
<p dir="auto">Thanks also to contributors <a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/FedorUporovVstack/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/FedorUporovVstack">@FedorUporovVstack</a>, <a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/stuartmaybee/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/stuartmaybee">@stuartmaybee</a>, <a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/thorsteneb/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/thorsteneb">@thorsteneb</a>, and <a data-hovercard-type="user" data-hovercard-url="/users/Fmstrat/hovercard" data-octo-click="hovercard-link-click" data-octo-dimensions="link_type:self" href="https://github.com/Fmstrat">@Fmstrat</a> for portions<br>
of the implementation.</p>
<p dir="auto">Sponsored-by: The FreeBSD Foundation<br>
Sponsored-by: iXsystems, Inc.<br>
Sponsored-by: vStack<br>
Contributions-by: Stuart Maybee <a href="mailto:stuart.maybee@comcast.net">stuart.maybee@comcast.net</a><br>
Contributions-by: Fedor Uporov <a href="mailto:fuporov.vstack@gmail.com">fuporov.vstack@gmail.com</a><br>
Contributions-by: Thorsten Behrens <a href="mailto:tbehrens@outlook.com">tbehrens@outlook.com</a><br>
Contributions-by: Fmstrat <a href="mailto:nospam@nowsci.com">nospam@nowsci.com</a><br>
Contributions-by: Don Brady <a href="mailto:dev.fs.zfs@gmail.com">dev.fs.zfs@gmail.com</a></p>
<h3 dir="auto">How Has This Been Tested?</h3>
<p dir="auto">Tests added to the ZFS Test Suite (<code>functional/raidz</code>) and <code>ztest</code>, in addition to manual testing.</p>
<h3 dir="auto">Types of changes</h3>

<ul>
<li> Bug fix (non-breaking change which fixes an issue)</li>
<li> New feature (non-breaking change which adds functionality)</li>
<li> Performance enhancement (non-breaking change which improves efficiency)</li>
<li> Code cleanup (non-breaking change which makes code smaller or more readable)</li>
<li> Breaking change (fix or feature that would cause existing functionality to change)</li>
<li> Library ABI change (libzfs, libzfs_core, libnvpair, libuutil and libzfsbootenv)</li>
<li> Documentation (a change to man pages or other documentation)</li>
</ul>
<h3 dir="auto">Checklist:</h3>
<ul>
<li> I have updated the documentation accordingly.</li>
<li> I have read the <a href="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/blob/master/.github/CONTRIBUTING.md"><strong>contributing</strong> document</a>.</li>
<li> I have added <a href="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/tree/master/tests">tests</a> to cover my changes.</li>
<li> I have run the ZFS Test Suite with this change applied.</li>
<li> All commit messages are properly formatted and contain <a href="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/blob/master/.github/CONTRIBUTING.md#signed-off-by"><code>Signed-off-by</code></a>.</li>
</ul>
<h3 dir="auto">Pull Request Comments</h3>
<p dir="auto">Please limit comments here to code review/feedback and testing questions/results.</p>
<p dir="auto">For generic discussions about RAID-Z, or discussions on future enhancements to RAIDZ expansion, please use the <a href="https://github.com/openzfs/zfs/discussions/">OpenZFS discussions</a>.</p>
    </div>
  </task-lists>
  
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[When to invest in marketing (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.briefmix.com/startup/setting-objectives-kpis</link>
            <guid>37190037</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 15:57:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.briefmix.com/startup/setting-objectives-kpis">https://www.briefmix.com/startup/setting-objectives-kpis</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37190037">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I once joined a company as a consultant - in the previous 12 months, they'd spent their entire $1,500,000 marketing budget on Google/Facebook  ads. Using Hubspot we could track leads through the funnel and look at exactly how many customers this money had generated. The answer was 0. In total, the ads brought in two leads to the website who never even booked a demo for the product. For <strong><em>$1,500,000.</em></strong></p><p>We ultimately managed to turn the ship around (more on that later in the series) but the lesson stands: marketing can be expensive and drain your runway. This is why accelerators like YC prefer cold outreach / emailing prospects during the early days of your company - it's free.</p><p>But how do you know if your business is ready to invest in marketing? To answer this question, you'll need to understand if your company have some form of product market fit - PMF. There are many ways you can define PMF:</p><pre>In 2009, Sean Ellis, also known as the founder of Growth Hacking, wrote that he identify Product-Market fit with the help of a survey. He asks the users of a product however they would be disappointed if the product would no longer be available. If at least 40% of users say they would be very disappointed, it probably means that you have Product-Market Fit.<p>Further, he adds that “Admittedly this threshold is a bit arbitrary, but I defined it after comparing results across nearly 100 startups. Those that struggle for traction are always under 40%, while most that gain strong traction exceed 40%.”</p></pre><p>There are more abstract definitions which say that PMF has been achieved when your company is drowning in demand - without time or resources to scale. I don't like this definition as much because it's only the ultimate form of PMF from a VC perspective - I've seen plenty of companies with PMF who are not in the aforementioned situation. If a kid sells lemonade on a sunny day, they can still make bank even if the line to the stand isn't running around the block.</p><p>If you don't have any PMF, don't invest money in marketing - you might end up like the examples mentioned in the introduction. The goal of marketing is to find a predictable method where if you spend e.g. $1,000 marketing dollars and expect a statistical 3x return of $3,000 in profit which should scale with your marketing budget. Marketing research can help you find customers who would be a good fit for your product, but if so it needs to be conducted in a cheap fashion (more on this later). Instead, invest your budget in product development to reach PMF.<br></p><h3>If you have product market fit</h3><p>Congratulations! You've got over the hardest part of starting a startup and can start investing in marketing.</p><p>The basis of a good marketing strategy is aligning it with your business objective(s) - no more lofty "number of likes" metrics. Start at the top - here are some examples of marketing objectives to choose from:</p><ul><li><strong>Boost Customer Acquisition:</strong> Attract new customers to expand your customer base and drive revenue growth.</li><li><strong>Increase Market Share:</strong> Expand the percentage of the market your business serves, often achieved by outperforming competitors or acquiring new customers.</li><li><strong>Market penetration:</strong> If your startup is expanding to new markets, the marketing objective could be to increase market penetration in those regions.</li><li><strong>Improve Brand Awareness:</strong> Enhance the recognition and visibility of your brand among the target audience, leading to increased trust and customer loyalty.</li><li><strong>Enhance Customer Retention:</strong> Focus on strategies to retain existing customers, thereby reducing churn and fostering long-term relationships (marketing team can help with this too).</li><li><strong>Improve Employee Engagement (internal communication):</strong> Foster a positive work culture and invest in employee development to increase productivity and reduce turnover.<br></li></ul><p>This is usually agreed on a leadership level based on what can be accomplished with the soon to be approved marketing budget. For this exercise, let's imagine a SaaS business named ApiHub, targeting B2B customers looking for an API to power their e-commerce business:</p><p><strong>Company wide business objective for end of year (EOY):</strong></p><ul><li>Increase revenue by $8,000,000</li></ul><p><strong>Selected marketing objective:</strong></p><ul><li>Boost Customer Acquisition: Get 666,250 additional visitors to our website before EOY.</li></ul><p>How did we arrive at this number? As a rule of thumb, the pipeline in startup SaaS businesses usually comes from:</p><ul><li>Marketing: 40%</li><li>Cold-outreach/sales: 40%</li><li>Partnerships: 20%</li></ul><p>Hence,  $8,000,000 x 0.4 / $3,000 Annual Contract Value (ACV) = 1,066 customers before EOY.</p><p>This is where your website analytics comes in handy - e.g. last year, we know that we had 1,200,000 visitors on our SaaS website. Of them, 2,000 became paying customers - hence the conversion rate from visitor to customer is 2,000 / 1,200,000 =  0.16%. If we want to understand how many additional website visitors we need to generate 1,066 more customers, we calculate (1,066 / 16) x  10,000 = 666,250 additional visitors.</p><h3>How the heck do we get 666,250 new visitors?</h3><p>Now what? We need to dig deeper to get to specific marketing strategies and tasks to be able to execute on. Many companies use <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Objectives_and_key_results" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OKRs</a> to drill down sequential marketing objectives and specify key results that ladder back up to our overarching target. But I prefer a "effectiveness framework" used in many agencies instead.</p><pre>In 2005, the UK grocery chain Sainsbury's set up a big sales goal to recover profit over a period of declining sales. With a simple equation, agency BBDO calculated that the marketing portion of this sales goal would be achieved if they got each shopper to spend an extra £1.14 every time they shopped.<p>This led to the campaign 'Try Something New Today', encouraging each shopper to spend an extra £1.14 every time they shopped. Analysis had shown that customers were 'sleep-shopping' and in a rut with the things they buy and cook. By using TV, press, radio and in-store advertising, Sainsbury's gave its customers simple meal ideas, which encouraged them to try new things and spend more on their shopping. The success of this campaign has generated £550 million in sales over two years.</p></pre><p>This is a really great effectiveness case study where Sainsbury's managed to impact the bottom line using a clear marketing objective derived from their business objective. I recommend watching their short case study <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MopXVY7KswA" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>.</p><p>The idea of an effectiveness framework is to clearly map out what objectives you need to hit, what consumer behaviour change needs to happen and the role and tasks of comms you need to achieve.</p><p>For our API business, the beginning of an effectiveness map might look something like this:</p><p><img src="https://images.prismic.io/briefmix/1df3946c-4153-4c97-b2c4-71263cde026e_Screen+Shot+2023-08-18+at+10.23.35.png?auto=compress,format" alt="Briefmix Effectiveness Map"></p><p>You can view and download this template <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1uFPNbZF8--Z4wH7Y3tyWaiir66umCMPaRvgv3uVJgwk/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here</a>. We have also started to add KPIs next to the map which will be important to measure during the year to make sure our efforts are on track.</p><p>This is only the beginning to the map as we have yet to decide about the brand, marketing mix, tactics and channels. As we progress through the course, we will loop back to this map and fill it out further.</p><p>And there we have it! Before we can start filling out the rest of the framework with tactics, we need to have a good understanding of our brand and what we stand for. Let’s start by understanding why a third of Coca Cola's market value comes from its brand:</p><p><a href="https://briefmix.com/startup/create-new-brand">How do you define a brand? -&gt;</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Twitter/X has removed all media posted before 2014 (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/tomcoates/status/1692922211416334597</link>
            <guid>37189872</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 15:41:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/tomcoates/status/1692922211416334597">https://twitter.com/tomcoates/status/1692922211416334597</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37189872">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/tomcoates/status/1692922211416334597: Error [ERR_FR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS]: Maximum number of redirects exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Speakers of different languages remember visual scenes differently (174 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adh0064</link>
            <guid>37189556</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 15:09:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adh0064">https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adh0064</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37189556">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.science.org/doi/10.1126/sciadv.adh0064: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rust devs push back as Serde project ships precompiled binaries (108 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/rust-devs-push-back-as-serde-project-ships-precompiled-binaries/</link>
            <guid>37189462</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 15:00:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/rust-devs-push-back-as-serde-project-ships-precompiled-binaries/">https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/rust-devs-push-back-as-serde-project-ships-precompiled-binaries/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37189462">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p><img alt="rust" height="900" src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/content/hl-images/2021/04/03/rust-bg.jpeg" width="1600"></p>
<p>Serde, a popular Rust (de)serialization&nbsp;project,&nbsp;has decided to ship its <em>serde_derive </em>macro as a&nbsp;precompiled binary.</p>
<p>The move has generated a fair amount of push back among developers who worry about&nbsp;its future&nbsp;legal and&nbsp;technical implications, along with a potential for supply chain attacks, should the maintainer&nbsp;account&nbsp;publishing these&nbsp;binaries be compromised.&nbsp;</p>
<p>According to the Rust package&nbsp;registry, crates.io,&nbsp;<em>serde</em> has been downloaded <a href="https://crates.io/crates/serde" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">over 196 million times</a> over its lifetime, whereas the <em><a href="https://crates.io/crates/serde_derive" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">serde_derive</a></em>&nbsp;macro has scored&nbsp;more than 171 million downloads, attesting to the project's&nbsp;widespread circulation.</p>
<h2>Serde&nbsp;macro goes precompiled: there's no way to opt-out</h2>
<p>About three weeks ago, a Rust programmer using the Serde project in their application noticed something odd.</p>
<p>"I'm working on packaging serde for Fedora Linux, and I noticed that recent versions of <em>serde_derive</em> ship a precompiled binary now," <a href="https://github.com/serde-rs/serde/issues/2538#issue-1825383332" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">wrote</a>&nbsp;Fabio Valentini, a Fedora Packaging Committee member.</p>
<p>"This is problematic for us, since we cannot, under no circumstances (with only very few exceptions, for firmware or the like), redistribute precompiled binaries."</p>
<p>Serde&nbsp;is a commonly used&nbsp;<em>ser</em>ialization&nbsp;and <em>de</em>serialization&nbsp;framework for Rust data structures that, <a href="https://serde.rs/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">according to its website</a>,&nbsp;is designed to conduct these operations "efficiently and generically."</p>
<p>"The Serde ecosystem consists of data structures that know how to serialize and deserialize themselves along with data formats that know how to serialize and deserialize other things," states the project's website. Whereas, "<a href="https://serde.rs/derive.html#using-derive" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">derive</a>" is one of its macros.</p>
<p>Valentini&nbsp;further&nbsp;inquired&nbsp;to the project maintainers, how were these new&nbsp;binaries "actually produced," and if it would be possible for him&nbsp;to recreate the binaries, as opposed to&nbsp;consuming precompiled versions.</p>
<p>David Tolnay, who is the primary Serde maintainer, <a href="https://github.com/serde-rs/serde/issues/2538#issuecomment-1654783988" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">responded</a> with potential workarounds at the time. But, that's not to say that everyone is pleased.</p>
<p>Following an influx of comments from developers as to why the decision wasn't best suited for the project, Tolnay <a href="https://github.com/serde-rs/serde/issues/2538#issuecomment-1682519944" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">acknowledged the feedback</a>, prior to closing&nbsp;the GitHub issue.</p>
<p>His justification for shipping precompiled binaries is reproduced in whole below.</p>
<div><p>"The precompiled implementation is the only supported way to use the macros that are published in <em>serde_derive</em>.</p><p>
If there is implementation work needed in some build tools to accommodate it, someone should feel free to do that work (as I have done for Buck and Bazel, which are tools I use and contribute significantly to) or publish your own fork of the source code under a different name.</p><p>
Separately, regarding the commentary above about security, the best path forward would be for one of the people who cares about this to invest in a Cargo or crates.io RFC around first-class precompiled macros so that there is an approach that would suit your preferences; <em>serde_derive</em> would adopt that when available."</p></div>
<p>BleepingComputer has approached Tolnay with additional questions prior to publishing.</p>
<h2>"First .NET's Moq and now this."</h2>
<p>Some Rust developers request that&nbsp;precompiled binaries be kept&nbsp;<em>optional&nbsp;</em>and separate from the original "serde_derive" crate, while others have likened the move&nbsp;to the <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/popular-open-source-project-moq-criticized-for-quietly-collecting-data/" target="_blank">controversial code change</a> to the Moq .NET project&nbsp;that sparked backlash.</p>
<p>"Please consider moving the precompiled serde_derive version to a different crate and default serde_derive to building from source so that users that want the benefit of precompiled binary can opt-in to use it," <a href="https://github.com/serde-rs/serde/issues/2538#issuecomment-1661893000" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">requested</a> one user.</p>
<p>"Or vice-versa.&nbsp;Or any other solution that allows building from source without having to patch serde_derive."</p>
<p>"Having a binary shipped as part of the crate, while I understand the build time speed benefits, is for security reasons not a viable solution for some library users."</p>
<p>Users&nbsp;<a href="https://github.com/serde-rs/serde/issues/2538#issuecomment-1684708897" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">pointed out</a> how the change could impact entities that are&nbsp;"legally not allowed to redistribute pre-compiled binaries, by their own licenses," specifically mentioning government-regulated environments.</p>
<p>"...First .NET's Moq and now this," said Jordan Singh, an Australia-based developer, in a <a href="https://archive.is/Aqxco#issuecomment-1684657021-permalink" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">comment</a> that was later removed.</p>
<p>"If this is to force cargo devs to support a feature then this is terrible way around doing it. At-least give us reproducible binaries. I'm sick of devs of popular crates/libraries taking everyone hostage with absurd decisions."</p>
<p>Philadelphia-based Donald Stufft <a href="https://twitter.com/dstufft/status/1692705666593357909" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">cautioned against</a> the risks of getting into the business of "shipping binaries" on social media:</p>
<div>
<figure><img alt="Developer cautions against the move" height="221" src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/images/news/u/1164866/2023/Aug/rust-serde/tweet1.jpg" width="500"><figcaption><strong>Developer cautions against the "shipping binaries" business</strong></figcaption></figure></div>
<p>Rust programmer Nathan West, who goes by <em>Lucretiel</em>, specifically <a href="https://twitter.com/Lucretiel/status/1692760873243160740" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">highlighted</a> the supply-chain risks posed by precompiled binaries, should the&nbsp;maintainer&nbsp;account get compromised:&nbsp;</p>
<div>
<figure><img alt="supply chain risk" height="245" src="https://www.bleepstatic.com/images/news/u/1164866/2023/Aug/rust-serde/tweet2.jpg" width="500"><figcaption><strong>Supply chain risks associated with shipping precompiled&nbsp;binaries</strong></figcaption></figure></div>
<p>"Is not this the exact way they'd go about it? Ship it silently as a semi-plausible change to how <em>serde</em> works, intransigently ignore all criticism of the decision," wrote West.</p>
<p>"This is *exactly* the reason that everyone has such a reflexive opposition to moves like this."</p>
<p>"Trust on the internet isn't perfect; we *don't* know that that's really [the maintainer]&nbsp;posting in GitHub. That's why we have layers and proxies of defense; sketchy sh*t is rejected because it's not worth the risk.&nbsp;</p>
<p>Technologist&nbsp;Sanket Kanjalkar&nbsp;called the transition to ship&nbsp;binaries without a way of opting-out "<a href="https://twitter.com/sanket1729/status/1692698203572109355" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">a step backward</a>."</p>
<p>But, a security professional who goes by Lander, has <a href="https://twitter.com/landaire/status/1692688116925305176" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">a slightly different take</a>:</p>
<p>"This Rust drama about <em>serde_derive</em> shipping a precompiled binary is kind of funny," writes Lander.</p>
<p>"On one hand, I understand people's concern. On the other hand, who cares? nobody's reading proc macro <em>code/build.rs</em> code for every project they pull in anyways. An opt-out would be a good idea tho."</p>
<p>Whether you agree with the project's decision to serve its macros precompiled or not, it is a good practice&nbsp;to routinely inspect&nbsp;any source code and&nbsp;software binaries prior&nbsp;to incorporating these into your projects.</p>
<p><em>Thanks to&nbsp;<a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mobiuscog/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener">Michael Kearns</a>&nbsp;for the tip off.</em></p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tesla repossessed my car due to an extreme oversight on their end (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://old.reddit.com/r/RealTesla/comments/15u8wuv/tesla_repossessed_my_car_due_to_an_extreme/</link>
            <guid>37189216</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 14:35:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://old.reddit.com/r/RealTesla/comments/15u8wuv/tesla_repossessed_my_car_due_to_an_extreme/">https://old.reddit.com/r/RealTesla/comments/15u8wuv/tesla_repossessed_my_car_due_to_an_extreme/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37189216">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>I have posted this to four other Tesla related subreddits only to have them removed so hopefully this one sticks..</p>

<p>I have had a horrible experience with Tesla and their team in the past couple of days. My family purchased our new car a couple months ago and was enjoying it up until a few days ago when I tried to get the car into gear and it demanded that I input the password. Having not set up a password previously, I contacted Tesla about the issue. </p>

<p>While I was waiting to speak with a representative, I noticed that my car was no longer linked to my account on the app, nor could I log into my Tesla account. After waiting on hold for two hours, I was finally able to get through to a representative who informed me that I needed to contact Tesla Financial about this issue. I called the number provided immediately but they did not pick up as they were outside of working hours.</p>

<p>“Not a problem.” I thought. I’d call back again tomorrow and sort this out. I left my car in the parking lot at work overnight and had a family member pick me up and drop me off the next morning. While I’m working the next day, my boss informs me that there is a tow truck outside to tow my car. Confused, I went out to the parking lot and was told by the towing company that Tesla is repossessing my vehicle. </p>

<p>This is where my confusion grew. We had paid for the vehicle IN FULL at the time we picked it up from the dealership, but the towing company is just doing what tesla told them to do. so they took my car.</p>

<p>Shortly afterward, my father received a phone call from Tesla Financial and he asked them what was going on. They told him that Tesla had been trying to reach out to us multiple times through phone and email about a debt they have been attempting to collect on the car. </p>

<p>My father had been out of the country for the past couple months so any phone calls would not have reached him. He did not receive a single voicemail about this issue either. He looked through his emails and noticed that he did in fact receive only two emails on July 27 and July 28, stating that we had not yet paid for the car and that the full cost of the vehicle is still at large. These emails went ignored as he believed them to be a phishing attempt because we had already PAID IN FULL at the dealership. He also believed that Tesla could not have made such a huge mistake like this.</p>

<p>My father explained this over the phone but the representative did not budge. This Tesla representative was rude and unprofessional for the entire phone call—going so far as to yell at my father over the phone.</p>

<p>A different Tesla representative sent us an email that seemed to be a copy paste of what they had sent my father back in July and that this car is now being considered for repossession. I shot an email back explaining AGAIN that this car had been paid for in full already and that we have been very dissatisfied by how Tesla had been handling this situation.</p>

<p>Up until this point, we were under the impression that Tesla was repossessing our vehicle without any warning because the two emails they sent to us regarding this seemed to be a phishing scam. Again they left no voicemails about this either. </p>

<p>The Tesla representative then emailed back this statement:</p>

<p>“I am having the team fully post the funds of the cashier's check. I am redrafting the documents and title/lien to your name instead of [BANK]. I have attached documents. Once funds post I can then restore access to the vehicle and release title/lien to your name.”</p>

<p>Basically saying that they had the check this whole time but due to some internal oversight had not cashed it. And they came after us, accused us of not paying, and repossessed our vehicle. Not only that, they incorrectly had the title of our car under the bank’s name rather than our own.</p>

<p>The next day, we received another email stating that the car is now back under our name and it can be picked up from the tow yard. </p>

<p>No apology. No restitution. </p>

<p>My father emailed them back saying he was glad the issue was resolved but was disappointed that there was no restitution offered, not even an apology. </p>

<p>They then emailed back the equivalent of saying “well we did try to contact you about this.” </p>

<p>I shot back an email stating that we are frustrated because it seems like this was an internal accounting issue that we should not have been contacted about or been involved in, in the first place. </p>

<p>Now we find ourselves carless for four days and will have to go out of our way to pick up a car that was wrongly repossessed. </p>

<p>And still Tesla offers no apology, restitution, and no guarantee that they are taking steps to prevent anything like this from happening in the future.</p>

<p>EDIT: the car was paid for with a combination of card and CASHIER’S check. Cashiers check means the amount of money is withdrawn from the bank when it’s ISSUED not cashed. so no, we did not notice extra money sitting in our account because it had already been withdrawn.</p>

<p>UPDATE: we got the car back today and there is no damage to it. we have been talking about getting an attorney or at least taking this to small claims court but in the end the decision comes down to what my dad wants to do as he owns the car. </p>

<p>will probably not be updating again because i’m tired of thinking about this but we’ll see. i’m really upset with tesla and would return the car if i could.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cheems, the Shiba Inu meme dog, has died (226 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.the-sun.com/news/8879390/cheems-balltze-dog-meme-cheemsburger-viral-cancer/</link>
            <guid>37189067</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 14:21:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.the-sun.com/news/8879390/cheems-balltze-dog-meme-cheemsburger-viral-cancer/">https://www.the-sun.com/news/8879390/cheems-balltze-dog-meme-cheemsburger-viral-cancer/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37189067">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>A BELOVED dog at the centre of a meme craze has died after a battle with cancer.</p>
<p>Pup Balltze, also known as Cheems, <a href="https://www.the-sun.com/news/8879479/cheems-dog-meme-dead/">died age 12 during surgery</a> and tributes have flown in from around the world for the much loved pooch. </p>
<figure><div data-index="160651"><p><a href="#"><img alt="Cheems died at the old age of 12" height="960" width="960" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg" data-credit="Instagram" data-sizes="(max-width: 375px) 335px, (max-width: 520px) 480px, 620px" data-img="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" data-srcset="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=335 335w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=480 480w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=620 620w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=670 670w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=960 960w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=1240 1240w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=1440 1440w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=1860 1860w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=1340 1340w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=1920 1920w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?w=2480 2480w" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897706-1.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" role="img"></a></p><p><span>5</span></p></div><figcaption><span>Cheems died at the old age of 12</span><span>Credit: Instagram</span></figcaption></figure>
<figure><div data-index="160652"><p><a href="#"><img alt="He was fighting Leukaemia in his old age" height="960" width="960" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg" data-credit="Instagram" data-sizes="(max-width: 375px) 335px, (max-width: 520px) 480px, 620px" data-img="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" data-srcset="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=335 335w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=480 480w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=620 620w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=670 670w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=960 960w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=1240 1240w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=1440 1440w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=1860 1860w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=1340 1340w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=1920 1920w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?w=2480 2480w" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897703.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" role="img"></a></p><p><span>5</span></p></div><figcaption><span>He was fighting Leukaemia in his old age</span><span>Credit: Instagram</span></figcaption></figure>
<p>A photo of Cheems went viral in the early 2010s and he gained a following on many social media platforms.</p>
<p>The meme version of "Cheems" known for liking cheeseburgers, which it pronounces "Cheemsburger".</p>
<p>Many photos of Cheems use the awkward picture taken by his owner in 2017 to express their discomfort or weakness at situations.</p>
<p>His uncomfortable expression captured the hearts of millions who found Cheems all too relatable.</p>
<div><div><p><img alt="Twitter logo replaced with mystery icon leaves millions baffled" width="295" height="188" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/04/lb-doge.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=360&amp;h=240&amp;crop=1" role="img" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/04/lb-doge.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=360&amp;h=240&amp;crop=1"></p></div><div><p><img alt="Doge Killer price prediction: Will LEASH hit $5,000 in 2022?" width="295" height="188" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JF-US-DOGE-KILLER-CHART-FEB-2022.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=360&amp;h=240&amp;crop=1" role="img" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2022/02/JF-US-DOGE-KILLER-CHART-FEB-2022.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=360&amp;h=240&amp;crop=1"></p></div></div>
<p>On his official Instagram, his owner posted: "Please don't be sad, please remember the joy that Balltze brought to the world. </p>
<p>"A Shiba Inu with a round smiling face connecting you and me, he has helped many people during the pandemic and brought a lot of joy to many of you, but now his mission has completed.</p>
<p>"I believe he is running freely in the sky and having a lot of delicious food with his new friends. He will always be inside my heart. I hope he can continue to bring joy to everyone in the online world, that’s my only humble request."</p>
<p>Fans flooded the comment section with condolences to the hilarious pup and his family.</p>
<div data-slide-count="4" data-slide-count-tablet="4" data-rail-type="section"><p><section><h2>Most read in The US Sun</h2></section></p></div>
<p>One commented: "I never thought I'd be saying I shed a tear for the passing of a dog that I never even met but Cheems truly was special."</p>
<p>Another said: "He is a legend of the Internet world, a meme founder and now, he is immortal."</p>
<figure><div data-index="160653"><p><a href="#"><img alt="His face was the centre of many memes" height="905" width="640" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg" data-credit="Know Your Meme" data-sizes="(max-width: 375px) 335px, (max-width: 520px) 480px, 620px" data-img="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=640" data-srcset="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=335 335w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=480 480w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=620 620w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=670 670w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=960 960w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=1240 1240w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=1440 1440w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=1860 1860w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=1340 1340w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=1920 1920w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?w=2480 2480w" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/owner-dog-said-dog-completed-838898029.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=640" role="img"></a></p><p><span>5</span></p></div><figcaption><span>His face was the centre of many memes</span><span>Credit: Know Your Meme</span></figcaption></figure>
<figure><div data-index="160654"><p><a href="#"><img alt="Cheems fought Leukaemia valiantly this past year" height="960" width="960" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg" data-credit="Instagram" data-sizes="(max-width: 375px) 335px, (max-width: 520px) 480px, 620px" data-img="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" data-srcset="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=335 335w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=480 480w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=620 620w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=670 670w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=960 960w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=1240 1240w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=1440 1440w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=1860 1860w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=1340 1340w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=1920 1920w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?w=2480 2480w" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897700.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" role="img"></a></p><p><span>5</span></p></div><figcaption><span>Cheems fought Leukaemia valiantly this past year</span><span>Credit: Instagram</span></figcaption></figure>
<figure><div data-index="160655"><p><a href="#"><img alt="The smiling pooch brought joy to millions" height="960" width="960" data-src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg" data-credit="Instagram" data-sizes="(max-width: 375px) 335px, (max-width: 520px) 480px, 620px" data-img="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" data-srcset="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=335 335w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=480 480w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=620 620w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=670 670w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=960 960w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=1240 1240w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=1005 1005w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=1440 1440w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=1860 1860w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=1340 1340w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=1920 1920w, https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?w=2480 2480w" src="https://www.the-sun.com/wp-content/uploads/sites/6/2023/08/meme-dog-dead-meme-dog-838897705.jpg?strip=all&amp;w=960" role="img"></a></p><p><span>5</span></p></div><figcaption><span>The smiling pooch brought joy to millions</span><span>Credit: Instagram</span></figcaption></figure>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI-generated art lacks copyright protection, D.C. court says (157 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.bloomberglaw.com/ip-law/ai-generated-art-lacks-copyright-protection-d-c-court-rules</link>
            <guid>37188791</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 13:51:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/ip-law/ai-generated-art-lacks-copyright-protection-d-c-court-rules">https://news.bloomberglaw.com/ip-law/ai-generated-art-lacks-copyright-protection-d-c-court-rules</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37188791">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Artwork created by artificial intelligence isn’t eligible for copyright protection because it lacks human authorship, a Washington, D.C., federal judge decided Friday.</p><p>Judge <bw-person data-terminal-id="15169224" data-id="00000161-7711-d8ae-adf9-ffb515750000" data-name="Beryl Alaine Howell">Beryl A. Howell</bw-person> of the US District Court for the District of Columbia agreed with the US Copyright Office’s decision to deny a copyright registration to computer scientist Stephen Thaler, who argued a two-dimensional artwork created by his AI program “Creativity Machine” should be eligible for protection. </p><p>The ruling is the first in the country to establish a boundary on the legal protections for AI-generated artwork, which has exploded in popularity with the rise of products like OpenAI Inc.'s ChatGPT and DALL-E, Midjourney, and Stable Diffusion.</p><p>Howell found that “courts have uniformly declined to recognize copyright in works created absent any human involvement,” citing cases where copyright protection was denied for celestial beings, a cultivated garden, and a monkey who took a selfie.</p><p>“Undoubtedly, we are approaching new frontiers in copyright as artists put AI in their toolbox to be used in the generation of new visual and other artistic works,” the judge wrote. </p><p>The rise of generative AI will “prompt challenging questions” about how much human input into an AI program is necessary to qualify for copyright protection, Howell said, as well as how to assess the originality of AI-generated art that comes from systems trained on existing copyrighted works. </p><p>But this case “is not nearly so complex” because Thaler admitted in his application that he played no role in creating the work, Howell said.</p><p>Thaler, the president and CEO of Imagination Engines, sued the office in June 2022 following its denial of his application to register the AI-generated art piece titled “A Recent Entrance to Paradise.”</p><p>His attorney, Ryan Abbott of Brown Neri Smith &amp; Khan LLP, said he plans to appeal the judgment. “We respectfully disagree with the court’s interpretation of the Copyright Act,” Abbott said.</p><p>The Copyright Office said in a statement that it believes the court reached the correct result and the office is reviewing the decision.</p><p>The office recently issued guidance on the copyrightability of works created with the assistance of AI, which attorneys said introduced <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/ip-law/ai-copyright-guide-has-lawyers-asking-where-to-draw-the-line">additional murkiness</a> in the AI authorship debate.</p><p>The Copyright Office in February <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/ip-law/ai-comic-art-dispute-leaves-copyright-protections-open-ended">granted</a> a limited copyright registration for an AI-assisted graphic novel, which attorneys said could crack the door open further to protect such works. </p><p>Thaler’s motion for summary judgment, which Howell denied in the Friday order, argued that permitting AI to be listed as an author on copyrighted works would incentivize more creation, which is in line with copyright law’s purpose of promoting useful art for the public.</p><p>“Denying copyright to AI-created works would thus go against the well-worn principle that '[c]opyright protection extends to all ‘original works of authorship fixed in any tangible medium’ of expression,” Thaler argued in his <a href="https://www.bloomberglaw.com/public/document/THALERvPERLMUTTERetalDocketNo122cv01564DDCJun022022CourtDocket/4?doc_id=X334L5RDNRF9EUPPB886AI13DKJ">motion</a>.</p><p>Register of Copyrights Shira Perlmutter, who leads the office, <a href="https://news.bloomberglaw.com/ip-law/ai-created-work-isnt-protectable-copyright-office-tells-judge">defended</a> the office’s decision to reject Thaler’s application on the grounds that it wasn’t created by a human. </p><p>“The Office’s conclusion that copyright law does not protect non-human creators was a sound and reasoned interpretation of the applicable law,” the agency wrote in its <a href="https://www.bloomberglaw.com/public/document/THALERvPERLMUTTERetalDocketNo122cv01564DDCJun022022CourtDocket/4?doc_id=X334L5RDNRF9EUPPB886AI13DKJ">cross-motion</a> for summary judgment, which Howell granted Friday.</p><p>The Department of Justice represents the Copyright Office.</p><p>The case is <a href="https://www.bloomberglaw.com/public/document/THALERvPERLMUTTERetalDocketNo122cv01564DDCJun022022CourtDocket/5?doc_id=X7E62VT5QQT84BRJVKSNVMDPLJV">Thaler v. Perlmutter</a>, D.D.C., No. 1:22-cv-01564, ordered 8/18/23.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WD refused to answer our questions about its self-wiping SanDisk SSDs (233 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/23837513/western-digital-sandisk-ssd-corrupted-deleted-questions</link>
            <guid>37188736</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 13:46:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/23837513/western-digital-sandisk-ssd-corrupted-deleted-questions">https://www.theverge.com/23837513/western-digital-sandisk-ssd-corrupted-deleted-questions</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37188736">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Eleven days ago, we sent these questions to Western Digital’s head of PR and <a href="https://www.theverge.com/22291828/sandisk-extreme-pro-portable-my-passport-failure-continued">published them publicly</a> on <em>The Verge</em>: </p><div><ul><li>Why are these drives still on sale?</li><li>Will you offer free data recovery services to affected customers? When?</li><li>Are you proactively warning customers and retailers who have already purchased these drives that significant data loss is possible?</li><li>If not, why not?</li><li>What, exactly, is going wrong with these drives?&nbsp;</li><li>How did this happen?&nbsp;</li></ul></div><div><p>What’s the fuss? For months, the company has been laughably silent about how its pricey portable SanDisk Extreme SSDs <em>might lose all your data</em>. <a href="https://www.theverge.com/22291828/sandisk-extreme-pro-portable-my-passport-failure-continued">It happened to my colleague Vjeran Pavic <em>twice</em></a>. It happened <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/sandisk-extreme-ssds-are-still-wiping-data-after-firmware-fix-users-say/">to <em>Ars Technica</em></a>. It happened <a href="https://petapixel.com/2023/08/08/sandisk-portable-ssds-are-failing-so-frequently-we-can-no-longer-recommend-them/">to <em>PetaPixel</em></a>. </p></div><div><p>Months after our inquiries, Western Digital continues to sell these drives <a href="https://www.theverge.com/22291828/sandisk-extreme-pro-portable-my-passport-failure-continued#:~:text=broken%20state%20of%20the%20internet%20means%20Western%20Digital%20doesn%E2%80%99t%20have%20to%20work%20very%20hard%20to%20keep%20selling%20these%20drives">due to deep discounts, fake Amazon reviews, and issues with Google Search</a> that rank favorable results far higher than warnings about potential failures.  </p></div><p>We have now received a response from Western Digital head of PR Robin Schultz, but nothing about the company’s stance has changed. Schultz repeatedly refused to answer any of our questions. Her statement doesn’t even contain an acknowledgment of the issue and has no specific timeline for any real answers. </p><p>The only reason we’re printing Western Digital’s statement is so you can see it for yourself:</p><div><blockquote><p>In response to recent reports of concerns about specific Western Digital portable SSD products, we want to assure our valued customers that we are taking all measures necessary to address any product-related issues. We understand the significance of our products to our customers and we take these matters very seriously. We are conducting a comprehensive review to gain a thorough understanding of the issues.</p></blockquote></div><p>After getting the statement, we asked Schultz three times whether Western Digital would answer our questions. Each time, she deflected. She also wouldn’t provide any idea of when the company might share its conclusions — if ever.</p><p>There <em>is</em> one possible reason Western Digital is finally speaking up and yet saying nothing: the company just got sued. <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/08/17/western_digital_sandisk_ssd_lawsuit/">As <em>The Register</em> reports</a>, California resident Nathan Krum has filed a prospective class action lawsuit, citing breach of contract, fraudulent and unfair business practices, and many other claims. Krum is suing over both the SanDisk Extreme drive itself and damages for any data lost. You can read the full complaint at the bottom of this story.</p><p>And that’s just lawsuit number one: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2023/08/sandisk-extreme-ssds-are-worthless-multiple-lawsuits-against-wd-say/">Ars Technica reports</a> there are two more. Three SanDisk SSD lawsuits in total, each seeking class-action status for the same failures. </p><div><p>Western Digital was already forced into <a href="https://www.wdrednasharddrivesettlement.com/">a class action settlement</a> over a previous questionable practice: in 2020, the company brazenly tried to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gadgets/2020/05/western-digital-gets-sued-for-sneaking-smr-disks-into-its-nas-channel/">sneak SMR drives into its “WD Red” lineup</a> marketed for network-attached storage devices. The company <a href="https://www.bursor.com/result/western-digital-class-action-settlement/">paid $5.7 million</a> to settle those claims.</p></div><div><p>The company’s tricks didn’t end there: Western Digital’s NAS disks have started <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/6/13/23759368/western-digital-three-years-warning-synology-nas">triggering warnings even if there’s nothing wrong with a drive</a>, seemingly to scare people into buying new ones simply after three years have gone by.</p></div><p>I won’t be buying a Western Digital or SanDisk product anytime soon.</p><p><em><strong>Update, 12:25AM ET: Added that there are actually three lawsuits, not just one, against WD.</strong></em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Rivet – Open-source game server management with Nomad and Rust (228 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet</link>
            <guid>37188659</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 13:38:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet">https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37188659">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/media/banner.png"><img alt="rivet_logo" src="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/raw/main/media/banner.png"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <i>Managed game servers, matchmaking, and DDoS mitigation that lets you focus on building your game.</i>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/philosophy/LICENSING.md"><img alt="License Apache-2.0" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/8532ad71172eacef102102d90a612f655ee02107f1c1101a343c20aa3bf22271/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6c6963656e73652f72697665742d67672f72697665743f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/license/rivet-gg/rivet?style=flat-square"></a>
  <a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/processes/VERSIONING.md"><img alt="Calendar versioning" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/3ae761bdf6bfa04c91603e35eaf158f30f7df00b6aedf7427b6856a78aee417c/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f63616c7665722d595959592e4d494e4f522e4d4943524f2d3232626664612e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/calver-YYYY.MINOR.MICRO-22bfda.svg?style=flat-square"></a>
  <a href="http://makeapullrequest.com/" rel="nofollow"><img alt="PRs Welcome" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/0ff11ed110cfa69f703ef0dcca3cee6141c0a8ef465e8237221ae245de3deb3d/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f5052732d77656c636f6d652d627269676874677265656e2e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/PRs-welcome-brightgreen.svg?style=flat-square"></a>
  <a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/graphs/commit-activity"><img alt="GitHub commit activity" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/a0ad7e15753b18faf1cd4b710917d83ce2fe0245a3d29693cb37dab83ad08e1b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f636f6d6d69742d61637469766974792f6d2f72697665742d67672f72697665743f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/commit-activity/m/rivet-gg/rivet?style=flat-square"></a>
  <a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/issues"><img alt="GitHub closed issues" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/b0d042f36c8b8388e1e1ca736dc1e3d0fd16b1371f4ab9123f061f8b2709eab2/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6769746875622f6973737565732d636c6f7365642f72697665742d67672f72697665743f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/github/issues-closed/rivet-gg/rivet?style=flat-square"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a href="https://rivet.gg/" rel="nofollow">Home</a> - <a href="https://rivet.gg/docs" rel="nofollow">Docs</a> - <a href="https://twitter.com/rivet_gg" rel="nofollow">Twitter</a> - <a href="https://discord.gg/BG2vqsJczH" rel="nofollow">Discord</a>
</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">👾 Features</h2>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Everything is accessible from an easy to use <a href="https://rivet.gg/docs/general/gui-cli-api" rel="nofollow">GUI, CLI, or API</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rivet.gg/docs/serverless-lobbies" rel="nofollow">Serverless Lobbies</a> for auto-scaling game lobbies</li>
<li><a href="https://rivet.gg/docs/matchmaker" rel="nofollow">Flexible matchmaker</a> for placing players in lobbies with no wait times</li>
<li><a href="https://rivet.gg/docs/cdn" rel="nofollow">CDN</a> for hosting assets and webpages with a custom domain or provided rivet.game subdomain</li>
<li><a href="https://rivet.gg/docs/serverless-lobbies/concepts/game-guard" rel="nofollow">Game Guard</a> for DDoS mitigation and managed WebSocket SSL, TCP+TLS, and UDP</li>
<li>Streamlined DevOps for teams</li>
<li>Unified logging &amp; monitoring &amp; analytics</li>
<li>No downtime deploys with easy rollbacks</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/media/splash_screenshot.png"><img alt="rivet_screenshot" src="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/raw/main/media/splash_screenshot.png"></a>
</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">🚀 Getting Started</h2>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Rivet Cloud</h3>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://rivet.gg/" rel="nofollow">Rivet Cloud</a> is the fastest way to get your game up and running. Sign up at <a href="https://rivet.gg/" rel="nofollow">rivet.gg</a> and get a free game server.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Self-hosting</h3>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/getting_started/DEVELOPMENT.md">setup guide</a> to develop &amp; deploy Rivet yourself.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📐 Architecture</h2>
<p dir="auto">Below is a simplified architecture diagram of a Rivet cluster.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/media/simplified_architecture.png"><img src="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/raw/main/media/simplified_architecture.png" alt="Architecture"></a></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">📖 Documentation Overview</h2>
<blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Looking for documentation on building a game with Rivet?</strong></p>
<p dir="auto">Visit our <a href="https://rivet.gg/docs" rel="nofollow">documentation for game developers</a>!</p>
</blockquote>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Getting Started</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/getting_started/PROJECT_STRUCTURE.md">Project Structure</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/getting_started/DEVELOPMENT.md">Developing on Rivet</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/libraries/chirp/ERROR_HANDLING.md">Error Handling</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Philosophy</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/philosophy/WHY_OPEN_SOURCE.md">Why open source</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Architecture</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/infrastructure/SBOM.md">Software Bill of Materials</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><strong>About</strong></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/rivet-gg/rivet/blob/main/docs/about/MISSING_FEATURES.md">Notable missing features</a></li>
</ul>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: A simple, open-source Notion-like avatar generator (128 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.avatartion.com</link>
            <guid>37188102</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 12:32:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.avatartion.com">https://www.avatartion.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37188102">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Why old books smell so good (266 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/19/why-do-old-books-smell-so-good/</link>
            <guid>37188015</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 12:21:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/19/why-do-old-books-smell-so-good/">https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/19/why-do-old-books-smell-so-good/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37188015">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

							<p>Have you ever wandered into an old library or dusty bookshop and paused to breathe in that familiar vanilla-coffee-grassy scent wafting off the aged tomes? That nostalgic olfactory experience is thanks to a bouquet of chemical compounds.</p>
<p>Modern books smell different because of changes in manufacturing, while old books release distinctive <a href="https://www.epa.gov/indoor-air-quality-iaq/what-are-volatile-organic-compounds-vocs" target="_blank" rel="noopener">volatile organic compounds</a> (VOCs) as they slowly decay. Scientists are <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2009/nov/13/scientists-preserving-books-smell" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sniffing out these VOCs</a> to reveal secrets about a book’s age, condition, and history.</p>
<p><img data-attachment-id="41391" data-permalink="https://scienceswitch.com/2023/08/19/why-do-old-books-smell-so-good/why-old-books-smell-so-good/" data-orig-file="https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png" data-orig-size="1200,628" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Why Old Books Smell So Good" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=616" title="Why Old Books Smell So Good" src="https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=616" alt="Why Old Books Smell So Good" srcset="https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png 1200w, https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=150&amp;h=79 150w, https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=300&amp;h=157 300w, https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=768&amp;h=402 768w, https://scienceswitch.files.wordpress.com/2023/08/why-old-books-smell-so-good.png?w=1024&amp;h=536 1024w" sizes="(max-width: 1200px) 100vw, 1200px"></p>
<h3>The Chemistry of Paper</h3>
<p>Paper is made of <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/medicine-and-dentistry/cellulose-fiber" target="_blank" rel="noopener">cellulose fibers bound by lignin</a>, while inks and bindings add other organic compounds. Cellulose is a polymer made of long glucose chains, while lignin is a complex polymer found in plant cells.</p>
<p>Over time, light, heat, and moisture cause the paper and compounds to break down, releasing VOCs that vaporize into the air. The manufacturing process also affects the VOCs released as the book ages.</p>
<h3>Telltale Scents</h3>
<p>An almond scent comes from <a href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/240" target="_blank" rel="noopener">benzaldehyde</a> in the paper. <a href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/Vanillin" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Vanillin</a>, the main compound in vanilla, is responsible for a sweet vanilla fragrance. <a href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/Ethylbenzene" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ethylbenzene</a>, used in inks and paints, has a sweet plastic smell. <a href="https://pubchem.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/compound/2-Ethylhexan-1-ol" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2-Ethyl hexanol</a>, found in solvents and scents, smells lightly floral.</p>
<p>New books use modern chemicals like hydrogen peroxide and alkyl ketene dimers, so they give off different VOCs. The VOCs can also indicate exposure to smoke, water damage, or other aging factors.</p>
<h3>Reading the Chemical Clues</h3>
<p>Scientists can analyze the VOCs from an old book to determine its age and condition. The mix of compounds can reveal if a book came from an early print shop versus a late 19th century press. They can also identify degradation and preservation needs.</p>
<p>Librarians and historians use VOC analysis to study collections and even match orphaned books with the libraries they came from based on chemical fingerprints. It provides clues to an old tome’s origins and secrets as it aged over decades or centuries.</p>
<h3>The Life Story in a Whiff</h3>
<p>So next time you get a whiff of an old book, take a moment to enjoy that aromatic time capsule. Its scent has a story to tell, echoing the people, places, and processes that brought an ancient text to you. With each sniff, we get a little closer to understanding our bibliophilic past.</p>
<p><span><iframe width="616" height="347" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/olLi1guxvkI?version=3&amp;rel=1&amp;showsearch=0&amp;showinfo=1&amp;iv_load_policy=1&amp;fs=1&amp;hl=en&amp;autohide=2&amp;wmode=transparent" allowfullscreen="true" sandbox="allow-scripts allow-same-origin allow-popups allow-presentation"></iframe></span></p>
<hr>
<p><strong>FAQs</strong></p>
<h2>Why do old books smell the way they do?</h2>
<p>Old books release volatile organic compounds (VOCs) as they slowly decay over time. The specific VOCs depend on the paper, inks, and binding materials used, which give old books their distinctive scents.</p>
<h2>Do new and old books smell different?</h2>
<p>Yes, new books tend to smell more crisp and fresh, while old books have mustier, sweeter scents. This is because new book manufacturing uses different chemicals that produce different VOCs as they break down.</p>
<h2>What chemicals cause that nostalgic old book smell?</h2>
<p>Compounds like benzaldehyde, vanillin, ethylbenzene, and 2-ethyl hexanol are often responsible for old book scents. Benzaldehyde has an almond-like scent, vanillin smells like vanilla, ethylbenzene is sweet and plastic-y, and 2-ethyl hexanol is lightly floral.</p>
<h2>Can scientists learn about a book’s history from its smell?</h2>
<p>Yes, analyzing the volatile organic compounds released by a book can reveal details about its age, manufacturing origins, condition, and past exposure to elements like smoke or water. This helps determine preservation needs.</p>
<h2>How does paper decomposition create VOCs?</h2>
<p>Paper is made of cellulose and lignin. Over time, heat, light, and moisture cause these polymers to break down and release VOCs, which enter the air. The specific VOCs depend on the paper production process.</p>
<h2>Do libraries and museums use VOC analysis?</h2>
<p>Libraries and museums are beginning to use VOC analysis to identify preservation needs in collections. It can also help match orphaned books by chemical fingerprint to determine their original source library.</p>

			
			
							
						</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amsterdam to use “noise cameras” against too loud cars (436 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nltimes.nl/2023/08/11/amsterdam-use-noise-cameras-loud-cars</link>
            <guid>37187837</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 11:56:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nltimes.nl/2023/08/11/amsterdam-use-noise-cameras-loud-cars">https://nltimes.nl/2023/08/11/amsterdam-use-noise-cameras-loud-cars</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37187837">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
      <article role="article">

      
  
  

  <div>
          
    
          <p>
                Friday, 11 August 2023 - 16:10
      </p>
    
        


  </div>

  
  
      
    
      
  
   
      
      <div><p>Amsterdam has started the fight against noisy motorcycles and cars. On Friday, the city placed electric road signs in two places to warn road users if their vehicles are too loud. The warnings will eventually be replaced by “noise cameras,” which, like speed cameras, automatically send a fine to the offending driver, Parool reports.</p>

<p>The test with the noise signs will start at the Stadhouderskade in the city center and Molenaarsweg in Amsterdam-Noord. The installation consists of a noise meter and a screen a little further on. If the meter registers too much noise, the driver will see the message “Te luid” - “Too loud” in Dutch. Later this month, more sound meters and signs will be installed on Europaboulevard in Zuid and on Tussen Meer in Nieuw-West. </p>

<p>The municipality hopes that the signs alone will already alert road users to the noise their vehicles make and prompt them to do something about it, a spokesperson told Parool.</p>

<p>Rotterdam is conducting a similar experiment in collaboration with Amsterdam. It is part of a broader approach, the municipality of Amsterdam spokesperson said. “Other measures we are taking include a simpler way of enforcement and a feasibility study by TNO into the application of the noise camera. We try to reduce noise nuisance in various ways.”</p>

<p>The noise camera consists of a box containing four microphones that can detect precisely where a sound is coming from. The box is connected to a regular speed camera, which takes a photo of the license plate to issue a fine. If the data from the current experiment proves reliable, Amsterdam and other large cities will ask the Cabinet to have the technology certified. </p>

</div>
  
          
  

</article>










  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Windy.com: global weather website with live filters (278 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.windy.com</link>
            <guid>37187760</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 11:41:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.windy.com">https://www.windy.com</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37187760">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><a id="contrib" href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/copyright" target="_blank">© OpenStreetMap contributors</a><section id="bottom-wrapper"><nav id="mobile-menu"><span id="icon-home" data-icon="]"></span><span data-do="bcast,openSearch" data-icon=""></span> <span data-do="rqstOpen,fav-layers" data-icon="" data-plugin="fav-layers"></span> <span data-do="rqstOpen,favs" id="mobile-avatar" data-icon="k"></span><div data-do="rqstOpen,menu" id="menu-burger" data-icon="d"><p>!</p></div></nav><nav id="plugins-bottom"></nav></section><nav id="plugins-bottom-desktop"></nav><span data-plugin="detail-rhpane"></span><div id="logo-wrapper"><a id="logo" target="_top" data-do="bcast,back2home"><img alt="Windy.com" src="https://www.windy.com/img/logo201802/logo-text-windycom-white.svg"></a></div><a id="open-in-app" data-do="bcast,openapp" data-t="MENU_MOBILE"></a><div id="search"><div id="menu-burger2" data-tooltipsrc="MENU" data-do="rqstOpen,tools"><p>d</p></div><p>F</p><div id="fav"><p>m</p><p>k</p></div><p>j</p><p></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Stable Diffusion in pure C/C++ (258 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/leejet/stable-diffusion.cpp</link>
            <guid>37187663</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 11:26:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/leejet/stable-diffusion.cpp">https://github.com/leejet/stable-diffusion.cpp</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37187663">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="git clone --recursive https://github.com/leejet/stable-diffusion.cpp
cd stable-diffusion.cpp"><pre><code>git clone --recursive https://github.com/leejet/stable-diffusion.cpp
cd stable-diffusion.cpp
</code></pre></div><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cd stable-diffusion.cpp
git pull origin master
git submodule update"><pre><code>cd stable-diffusion.cpp
git pull origin master
git submodule update
</code></pre></div><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cmake .. -DGGML_OPENBLAS=ON
cmake --build . --config Release"><pre><code>cmake .. -DGGML_OPENBLAS=ON
cmake --build . --config Release
</code></pre></div><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="usage: ./bin/sd [arguments]

arguments:
  -h, --help                         show this help message and exit
  -M, --mode [txt2img or img2img]    generation mode (default: txt2img)
  -t, --threads N                    number of threads to use during computation (default: -1).
                                     If threads <= 0, then threads will be set to the number of CPU physical cores
  -m, --model [MODEL]                path to model
  -i, --init-img [IMAGE]             path to the input image, required by img2img
  -o, --output OUTPUT                path to write result image to (default: .\output.png)
  -p, --prompt [PROMPT]              the prompt to render
  -n, --negative-prompt PROMPT       the negative prompt (default: &quot;&quot;)
  --cfg-scale SCALE                  unconditional guidance scale: (default: 7.0)
  --strength STRENGTH                strength for noising/unnoising (default: 0.75)
                                     1.0 corresponds to full destruction of information in init image
  -H, --height H                     image height, in pixel space (default: 512)
  -W, --width W                      image width, in pixel space (default: 512)
  --sample-method SAMPLE_METHOD      sample method (default: &quot;eular a&quot;)
  --steps  STEPS                     number of sample steps (default: 20)
  -s SEED, --seed SEED               RNG seed (default: 42, use random seed for < 0)
  -v, --verbose                      print extra info"><pre><code>usage: ./bin/sd [arguments]

arguments:
  -h, --help                         show this help message and exit
  -M, --mode [txt2img or img2img]    generation mode (default: txt2img)
  -t, --threads N                    number of threads to use during computation (default: -1).
                                     If threads &lt;= 0, then threads will be set to the number of CPU physical cores
  -m, --model [MODEL]                path to model
  -i, --init-img [IMAGE]             path to the input image, required by img2img
  -o, --output OUTPUT                path to write result image to (default: .\output.png)
  -p, --prompt [PROMPT]              the prompt to render
  -n, --negative-prompt PROMPT       the negative prompt (default: "")
  --cfg-scale SCALE                  unconditional guidance scale: (default: 7.0)
  --strength STRENGTH                strength for noising/unnoising (default: 0.75)
                                     1.0 corresponds to full destruction of information in init image
  -H, --height H                     image height, in pixel space (default: 512)
  -W, --width W                      image width, in pixel space (default: 512)
  --sample-method SAMPLE_METHOD      sample method (default: "eular a")
  --steps  STEPS                     number of sample steps (default: 20)
  -s SEED, --seed SEED               RNG seed (default: 42, use random seed for &lt; 0)
  -v, --verbose                      print extra info
</code></pre></div><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="./bin/sd -m ../models/sd-v1-4-ggml-model-f16.bin -p &quot;a lovely cat&quot;"><pre><code>./bin/sd -m ../models/sd-v1-4-ggml-model-f16.bin -p "a lovely cat"
</code></pre></div><p dir="auto">Using formats of different precisions will yield results of varying quality.</p><div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="./bin/sd --mode img2img -m ../models/sd-v1-4-ggml-model-f16.bin -p &quot;cat with blue eyes&quot; -i ./output.png -o ./img2img_output.png --strength 0.4"><pre><code>./bin/sd --mode img2img -m ../models/sd-v1-4-ggml-model-f16.bin -p "cat with blue eyes" -i ./output.png -o ./img2img_output.png --strength 0.4
</code></pre></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: Why did Microsoft, Meta, and PayPal update their ToS today? (186 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37185461</link>
            <guid>37185461</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 04:17:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37185461">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="37186344"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186344" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186344&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>I tried to read some of  them to see what has changed. I really tried...<p>If any lawyers from the future are reading this: It was impossible for me to see what I was agreeing to. Furthermore, I was  not given a chance to not agree with these (unknown) changes.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186803"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186803" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186803&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>It is spectacular how incompetent lawyers are providing service to the public that pays them eventually, they are only able to communicate to other lawyers, so why should we use their services at all? We can get into trouble without them the same easy being cluless either way.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186842"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186842" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186842&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Lawyers are not paid to provide a service to the public, you got that mixed up. They’re writing code to protect the company that hired them. The language used by the law is not the common language because the latter is prone to bugs.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37186404"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186404" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186404&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The answer to this is to not agree to it (your “chance” is to stop using the service).</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186717"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186717" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186717&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>This “solution” is a non-starter. People like to imagine that we have a marketplace with degrees of freedom in all directions, but we don’t. We have to make choices, and often that just means choosing the least bad option.<p>But it is interesting to note how we got here.</p><p><a href="https://www.npr.org/2023/07/13/1187543648/terms-and-conditions-of-service-contracts-clickwrap" rel="nofollow noreferrer">https://www.npr.org/2023/07/13/1187543648/terms-and-conditio...</a></p><p>To summarize the podcast episode, contracts used to be individually tailored, but businesses found that too onerous and just wrote boilerplate contracts for all customers to sign. Then they decided the signing part became too onerous for businesses so courts decided that using the product was enough to agree to terms. So now we’re at a point where not using the product is legitimately the only way not to agree to whatever terms the company decides.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186493"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186493" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186493&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Exactly. And it's actually quite easy for some of these products (except maybe for PayPal if you don't have a bank account).</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186554"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186554" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186554&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Yeah, just change place of work everytime when company asks you to do somwthing with any Microsoft product.<p>Is this your solution?
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186588"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186588" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186588&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Are the terms for Microsoft business customers different to those for end users, with regards to privacy and tracking? Can my ssl232@mycompany.com email provided by Office365 get tracked around the internet just the same as ssl232@gmail.com?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186621"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186621" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186621&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>If this is your work account then switching is down to your employer and they probably have a legal dept to understand all ToS anyway. But any ToS change shouldn't affect you much because you shouldn't be using it for personal stuff.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186645"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186645" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186645&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I don't think the venn diagram of <i>companies using outlook/office365</i> and <i>companies with a well resourced legal department</i> has as much overlap as one might hope</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186755"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="5"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="200"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186755" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186755&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>As the other comment hints: most companies don't have lawyers. And then they'd probably be specialized in another area. Only very large companies can afford to have legal staff looking at some random ToS change.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                                          <tr id="37186864"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186864" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186864&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Project idea: a Gmail filter that automatically burns all this junk mail every time it rolls into my inbox. Nobody reads this stuff except journalists and lawyers, yet I cannot unsubscribe.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186210"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186235"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186235" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186235&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>That seems to be a decision by the commission, not the the high court.<p>These two bodies tend to counter each other a lot, I would expect to have a court ruling in 2 years that cancels this decision.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186364"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186364" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186364&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>On this particular subject, it's basically realpolitik.<p>Court: "US law is incompatible with ours"</p><p>Executive: "Yeah but I'm sure we can all get along &lt;wink wink&gt;..."
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186573"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37186353"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186353" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186353&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Whatsapp's in-app notification regarding the TOS change references an EU ruling, so this is the likely cause.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37185720"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185805"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185972"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186150"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186382"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186056"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186056" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186056&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I like where this discussion is headed. Scrape the ToS and keep a record of that. Are ToS's copywrited?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186240"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186240" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186240&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The problem is that these documents aren't served from standardized or predictable URLs across every service provider or regulatory body. I work with a firm who charge heaps of money to provide large companies with publicly available documents. Why do they pay? Because finding the latest copy of 25 different legal docs is a pain in the ass because the entire internet is a broken mess of 404s, over a long enough timeline.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186370"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37186196"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186196" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186196&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>GitHub is also ran by a untrustworthy megacorp with a ToS. Just wait til the ToS changes to where you can’t use it to told others accountable.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186333"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="4"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="160"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186333" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186333&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>I think that one of the benefits of dvcs is that it's relatively easy to move to another provider or self host, and that everyone that cloned has a copy.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37186125"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186125" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186125&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Why does such a thing need to be a business to begin with? Just host a github or expose this functionality on wikipedia.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186557"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186557" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186557&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Hosting is not the problem that generates the need for a business.<p>The problem is having people available to do the work that is needed to keep the system useful and up-to-date, which includes writing code that will parse the ToS, maintaining it, and upgrading programming languages, packages ... and most probably lawyers.</p><p>So where those diffs are hosted is a tiny cost of what is needed to make it work.</p><p>All these require effort. 
And effort can be paid with one of two things: time and money. And for someone to have time to work full-time on this, they need to have ... money to sustain themselves.</p><p>Thus this kind of project needs money =&gt; that either can be a grant, donation from a big entity, or business model. Donations from users are not working for long-term sustainability in most cases of good projects for society. Or at least I don't know a successful project like this.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186326"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186326" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186326&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>No one said it had to be a business. They were making the point that its hard to keep something like that running and maintained for free.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186375"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186420"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37186526"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37185861"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185880"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185929"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37185929" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37185929&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>The fun thing with ToS is that you know every large company with a ToS (or EULA for that matter) has analytics and knows exactly how long you read that ToS (if you did at all), and is smart enough to know objectively if you read it or did not read it.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186215"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186215" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186215&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>Well, perhaps.<p>For a little while, (and I should resume this behavior) I would capture TOS and save them away to read at leisure.</p><p>Because what happens, especially with fiddly mobile apps, is that you're granted a single glimpse at the <i>bona fide</i> link to TOS/EULA, and never again will you find how you got there. (Sometimes the link fails right off the bat, giving you zero opportunity to read through the terms!)</p><p>So I would take advantage of that and save it, by any means necessary: screen scrape, copy-paste, print-as-PDF, take photo of screen with second device, whatever it took, because they could make it difficult!</p><p>But then I would usually end up with a copy of the contract that I could later call up and check on. So, your suggestion that analytics can determine my dwell time on the document when it's presented to me, that's not going to be indicative of how much time I really spent reading it after copying and saving it.</p><p>I've found that this is a good practice, and not for the reason you're thinking of. I've found that I'm extraordinarily bad at reading legal documents like this (including my lease, employment contract, benefits and insurance docs, you name it) because even if I think I understand, I didn't get it, and it's pointless anyway because negotiating the wording is not on the table.</p><p>But it's a good practice to save these, because of this: there are often instructions included about how to resolve disputes and claims against the company. These instructions usually follow a strict procedure and they have rules about what you can do. They also have contact info, and again, you will never ever find this contact info anywhere else ever again if you don't save the EULA at first opportunity. They will tell you what kind of arbitration or court proceedings are acceptable, they will tell you the complaints procedure from start to end, time frames, and what to expect at each point. This info is gold, and it's not going to be available when you come to have a dispute, and you're not even going to be aware of the procedure at that point, and so you will automatically be disqualified and lose any dispute because you didn't follow procedure. Have fun!
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186213"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186213" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186213&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>The good thing is that if you relinquish more personal data by accepting the changed ToS, it is not valid or legal in the EU, since the GDPR requires you to ask consent explicitly, unambiguously, and and in simple terms, and per use case (so, not buried in a ToS). Moreover, you should have the option to deny consent per use of personal data.<p>I wonder if they are serving different ToS in the EU (haven't received anything from Microsoft yet).
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37185881"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37185881" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37185881&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>If the T&amp;Cs are at a public URL, then an alternative way is to self host changedetection.io and monitor for changes.<p>I run it to see changes to my competitors websites. Well that’s the idea - I don’t actually monitor it LOL. I just have it running in Docker.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186673"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186460"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186239"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185989"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185943"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185791"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186425"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37185741"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="37186057"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37186057" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37186057&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Since I have not gotten any emails from these services, it would be good if you share your present jurisdiction.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186084"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186691"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37186070"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186427"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186677"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37186290"><td></td></tr>
                      <tr id="37185800"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185792"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37185792" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37185792&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>If we scrape the tos to a git repo, and update it, we can diff it to a telegram bot, then pipeline to openai to summarize.</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185487"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185817"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37185817" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37185817&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><p><span>PayPal already has an “Updates” page for their legal agreements. It describes which agreement is updated when and when that change takes effect.<p>I also received the PayPal email notification, but when clicking through the link the only legal agreement change this month was a week ago and was related to how much of your user data is available to a user visiting your PayPal.me page. Highly unlikely this is a coordinated change with Meta and MSFT.
              </p></span></p></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185716"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_37185716" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=37185716&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D37185461"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p><span>Quick someone put the ToS in a git repo so we can incrementally see the diffs on each update and comment on its impacts. Is this possible?</span></p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185802"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37185743"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185877"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37185955"><td></td></tr>
                        <tr id="37186115"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="37185854"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="37186113"><td></td></tr>
                  </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cruise told by CA DMV to reduce robotaxi fleet 50% following crash (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/18/cruise-told-by-regulators-to-immediately-reduce-robotaxi-fleet-50-following-crash/</link>
            <guid>37184904</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 02:30:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/18/cruise-told-by-regulators-to-immediately-reduce-robotaxi-fleet-50-following-crash/">https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/18/cruise-told-by-regulators-to-immediately-reduce-robotaxi-fleet-50-following-crash/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37184904">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<p id="speakable-summary">Cruise, the self-driving car subsidiary of GM, has been asked to reduce its robotaxi fleet by 50% in San Francisco <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/18/cruise-robotaxi-involved-in-a-crash-with-fire-truck-one-passenger-injured/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">following a crash</a> Thursday night with a fire truck.</p>
<p>The California Department of Motor Vehicles, the agency that regulates the testing and deployment of autonomous vehicles in the state, requested the reduction in operations. The state agency said it is investigating “recent concerning incidents” involving Cruise vehicles in San Francisco. It called for Cruise to reduce its fleet by 50% and have no more than 50 driverless vehicles in operation during the day and 150 driverless vehicles in operation at night until the investigation is complete.</p>
<p>“Safety of the traveling public is the California DMV’s top priority,” the DMV said in a statement issued Friday evening, adding that it has the right, following the investigation to suspend or revoke testing and/or deployment permits if it determines there’s an unreasonable risk to public safety. “The primary focus of the DMV’s regulations is the safe operation of autonomous vehicles and safety of the public who share the road with these vehicles.”</p>
<p>Cruise told TechCrunch it is complying with the request. Cruise also <a href="https://getcruise.com/news/blog/2023/further-update-on-emergency-vehicle-collision/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">issued a blog post</a> giving the company’s perspective of how and why the crash occurred.</p>
<p>“Over one hundred people lose their lives every day on American roadways, and countless others are badly injured, Cruise said in a statement sent via email. “We believe it’s clear that Cruise positively impacts overall road safety, and look forward to working with the CA DMV to make any improvements and provide any data they need to reinforce the safety and efficiency of our fleet.”</p>
<p>Cruise has had a series of snafus, including at least <a href="https://www.wafb.com/2023/08/15/driverless-cars-stall-causing-traffic-jam-san-francisco/" target="_blank" rel="noopener" data-mrf-link="https://www.wafb.com/2023/08/15/driverless-cars-stall-causing-traffic-jam-san-francisco/">10 of its driverless cars reportedly stalling</a> and blocking traffic, which threatens to derail its commercial plans. The string of glitches come just a week after <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/10/cruise-and-waymo-win-robotaxi-expansions-in-san-francisco/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">winning approval</a> from the California Public Utilities Commission to expand commercial operations in San Francisco.</p>
<p>The CPUC, the agency that regulates ride-hailing operations including those involving robotaxis, approved Cruise and Waymo on August 10 for final permits that allow the companies to operate 24 hours a day, seven days a week, expand their fleets and charge for rides throughout the city.</p>
<p>The latest Cruise incident occurred Thursday night when a Cruise robotaxi and an emergency vehicle crashed and left a passenger injured. Cruise said in a social media post that one of its self-driving Chevy Bolt EVs entered an intersection on a green traffic light at Polk and Turk streets when it was struck by an emergency vehicle that appeared to be en route to an emergency scene.</p>
<p>Earlier this week, the San Francisco City Attorney David Chiu <a href="https://techcrunch.com/2023/08/17/san-francisco-presses-cpuc-to-halt-waymo-cruise-robotaxi-expansions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">filed motions with the CPUC</a> to pause Cruise and Waymo’s plans to charge for robotaxi rides in the city at all hours. Chiu’s arguments parallel comments made by residents and other city officials during a public hearing ahead of the CPUC’s vote.</p>
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How to Roman Republic 101, Part IIIb: Imperium (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://acoup.blog/2023/08/18/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-iiib-imperium/</link>
            <guid>37184884</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2023 02:27:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/08/18/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-iiib-imperium/">https://acoup.blog/2023/08/18/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-iiib-imperium/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37184884">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
		
<p>This is the second section of the third part of our planned five part series (<a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/07/21/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-i-spqr/">I</a>, <a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/07/27/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-ii-romans-assemble/">II</a>, <a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/08/11/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-iiia-starting-down-the-path-of-honors/" data-type="post" data-id="20435">IIIa</a>) on the structure of the Roman Republic during the third and second centuries, the ‘Middle’ Republic.  Last week we discussed the overall structure of the ‘career path’ for a Roman politician and the first few offices along that path.  <strong>This week we’re going to look at the upper-steps of that career path, the offices of praetor and consul and the particular set of powers they possess, called <em>imperium</em></strong>, along with the pro-magistrate forms of these positions.  Now I should note at the outset that we have skipped one office on our way through, the tribunes of the plebs; we’ll get to that office <em>next</em> week to discuss its oddities and unusual powers.</p>



<p>The praestorship and the consulship are the highest Roman offices (the censorship being more of a ‘victory lap’) and the two offices that wield direct military and judicial authority.  These are also the offices where competition in the <em>cursus honorum</em> starts to get fierce, as the eight quaestors must compete for just six praetorships and those six praetors can expect to compete for just two – always two – consulships.  It is worth keeping in mind as we go through this that on the one hand <strong>these offices are largely confined to a small Roman elite, the <em>nobiles</em>, composed of families (both patrician and plebeian) that have been successful in politics over generations</strong>, but at the same time <strong>it is the popular assemblies which choose ‘winners’ and ‘losers’ from among the <em>nobiles</em></strong> by deciding who gets to proceed to the next round of the political elimination context, and who is forever going to sit in the Senate as a former quaestor and nothing more.</p>



<p>Now I am the only one of this blog who gets to have <em>imperium</em> (apparently <em>ACOUP</em> operates in the imperial where I have <em>imperium</em> and the guest-posters are my <em>legati</em>), but <a href="https://www.patreon.com/user?u=20122096" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.patreon.com/user?u=20122096">Patrons at the <em>patres et matres conscripti</em></a> level can still advise me on how to use my <em>imperium</em>!  You don’t even have to have held the quaestorship!  As always, if you like this, please share it! If you want updates whenever a new post appears, you can click below for email updates or follow me on twitter (@BretDevereaux) for updates as to new posts as well as my occasional ancient history, foreign policy or military history musings, assuming there is still a Twitter by the time this post goes live.  I am also on Bluesky (@bretdevereaux.bsky.social) and (less frequently) Mastodon (@bretdevereaux@historians.social).</p>










<p>What connects these offices in particular is that they confer <em>imperium</em>, a distinctive concept in Roman law and governance.  The word <em>imperium</em> derives from the verb <em>impero</em>, ‘to command, order’ and so in a sense <em>imperium</em> simply means ‘command,’ but in its implication it is broader.  <em>Imperium</em> was understood to be the power of the king (Cic. <em>Leg. </em>3.8), encompassing both the judicial role of the king in resolving disputes and the military role of the king in leading the army.  In this sense, <em>imperium</em><strong> is the power to deploy violence on behalf of the community: both <em>internal </em>(judicial) violence and <em>external </em>(military) violence</strong>.</p>



<p>That power was represented visually around the person of magistrates with <em>imperium</em> through the lictors (Latin: <em>lictores</em>), attendants who follows magistrates with <em>imperium</em>, mostly to add dignity to the office but who also could act as the magistrates ‘muscle’ if necessary.  The lictors carried the <em>fasces</em>, a set of sticks bundled together in a rod; often in modern depictions the bundle is thick and short but in ancient artwork it is long and thin, the ancient equivalent of a police-man’s less-lethal <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baton_(law_enforcement)" data-type="link" data-id="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Baton_(law_enforcement)">billy club</a>.  That, notionally non-lethal but still violent, configuration represented the <em>imperium</em>-bearing magistrate’s civil power within the <em>pomerium</em> (recall, this is the sacred boundary of the city).  When passing beyond the <em>pomerium</em>, an axe was inserted into the bundle, turning the the non-lethal crowd-control device into a lethal weapon, reflective of the greater power of the <em>imperium-</em>bearing magistrate to act with unilateral <em>military</em> violence outside of Rome (though to be clear the consul couldn’t just murder you because you were on your farm; this is symbolism).  The consuls were each assigned 12 lictors, while praetors got 6.  Pro-magistrates had one fewer lictor than their magistrate versions to reflect that, while they wielded <em>imperium</em>, it was of an inferior sort to the actual magistrate of the year.</p>



<figure><img data-lazy-fallback="1" data-attachment-id="20629" data-permalink="https://acoup.blog/2023/08/18/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-iiib-imperium/attachment/455806001/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?fit=1455%2C2500&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1455,2500" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="455806001" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?fit=175%2C300&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?fit=596%2C1024&amp;ssl=1" decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="596" height="1024" src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=596%2C1024&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=596%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 596w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=175%2C300&amp;ssl=1 175w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=768%2C1320&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=894%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 894w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=1192%2C2048&amp;ssl=1 1192w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=1200%2C2062&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=1100%2C1890&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?w=1455&amp;ssl=1 1455w" sizes="(max-width: 596px) 100vw, 596px" data-recalc-dims="1" data-lazy-srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=596%2C1024&amp;ssl=1 596w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=175%2C300&amp;ssl=1 175w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=768%2C1320&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=894%2C1536&amp;ssl=1 894w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=1192%2C2048&amp;ssl=1 1192w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=1200%2C2062&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=1100%2C1890&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?w=1455&amp;ssl=1 1455w" data-lazy-src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/455806001.jpg?resize=596%2C1024&amp;is-pending-load=1#038;ssl=1" data-old-srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"><figcaption>From the <a href="https://www.britishmuseum.org/collection/object/G_1983-1229-1" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.britishmuseum.org/collection/object/G_1983-1229-1">British Museum</a> (inv. 1983,1229.1) a bronze figurine dating to the late first century showing a lictor bearing the fasces as they would be carried outside of the pomerium, with the axe inserted.</figcaption></figure>



<p>What is notable about the Roman concept of <em>imperium</em> is that it is a single, unitary thing: multiple magistrates can have <em>imperium</em>, you can have greater or lesser forms of <em>imperium</em>, but you cannot break apart the component elements of <em>imperium</em>.<span id="easy-footnote-1-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-1-20553" title="I should note here that Drogula (in <em><a href=&quot;https://amzn.to/3YDkX6I&quot; data-type=&quot;link&quot; data-id=&quot;https://amzn.to/3YDkX6I&quot;>Commanders and Command</a></em> (2015)) understands <em>imperium</em> a bit differently than this more traditional version I am presenting (in line with Lintott&amp;#8217;s understanding).  He contends that <em>imperium</em> was an entirely military power which was not necessary for judicial functions and was not only indivisible but also, at least early on, did not come in different degrees.  In practice, I&amp;#8217;m not sure the Romans were ever so precise with their concepts as Drogula wants them to be."><sup>1</sup></a></span>  This is a real difference from the <em>polis</em>, where the standard structure was to take the three components of royal power (religious, judicial and military) and split them up between different magistrates or boards in order to avoid any one figure being too powerful.  <strong>For the Romans, the royal authority over judicial and military matters were unavoidably linked because they were the same thing, <em>imperium</em>, and so could not be separated.</strong>  That in turn leads to Polybius’ awe at the power wielded by Roman magistrates, particularly the consuls (Polyb. 6.12); a <em>polis</em> wouldn’t generally focus so much power into a single set of hands constitutionally (keeping in mind that tyrants are <em>extra</em>-constitutional figures).</p>



<p>So what does <em>imperium</em> empower a magistrate to do?  All magistrates have <em>potestas</em>, the power to act on behalf of the community within their sphere of influence.  <em>Imperium</em> is the subset of magisterial <em>potestas</em> which covers the provision of violence for the community and it comes in two forms: the power to raise and lead armies and the power to organize and oversee courts.  Now we normally think of these powers as cut by that <em>domi et militiae</em> (“at home and on military service”) distinction we discussed<a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/07/21/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-i-spqr/" data-type="link" data-id="https://acoup.blog/2023/07/21/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-i-spqr/"> earlier in the series</a>: at home <em>imperium</em> is the power to organize courts (which are generally jury courts, though for some matters magistrates might make a summary judgement) and abroad the power to organize armies.  But as we’ll see when we get to the role of magistrates and pro-magistrates in the provinces, the power of legal judgement conferred by <em>imperium</em> is, if anything, <strong>more</strong> intense outside of Rome.  <strong>That said it is absolutely the case that <em>imperium</em> is <em>restrained</em> within the <em>pomerium</em> and far less restrained outside of it</strong>.</p>



<figure><img data-lazy-fallback="1" data-attachment-id="20631" data-permalink="https://acoup.blog/2023/08/18/collections-how-to-roman-republic-101-part-iiib-imperium/attachment/656476001/" data-orig-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?fit=1854%2C912&amp;ssl=1" data-orig-size="1854,912" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="656476001" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?fit=300%2C148&amp;ssl=1" data-large-file="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?fit=1024%2C504&amp;ssl=1" decoding="async" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="504" src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1024%2C504&amp;ssl=1" alt="" srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1024%2C504&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=300%2C148&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=768%2C378&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1536%2C756&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1200%2C590&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1100%2C541&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?w=1854&amp;ssl=1 1854w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px" data-recalc-dims="1" data-lazy-srcset="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1024%2C504&amp;ssl=1 1024w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=300%2C148&amp;ssl=1 300w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=768%2C378&amp;ssl=1 768w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1536%2C756&amp;ssl=1 1536w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1200%2C590&amp;ssl=1 1200w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1100%2C541&amp;ssl=1 1100w, https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?w=1854&amp;ssl=1 1854w" data-lazy-src="https://i0.wp.com/acoup.blog/wp-content/uploads/2023/08/656476001.jpg?resize=1024%2C504&amp;is-pending-load=1#038;ssl=1" data-old-srcset="data:image/gif;base64,R0lGODlhAQABAIAAAAAAAP///yH5BAEAAAAALAAAAAABAAEAAAIBRAA7"><figcaption>From the <a href="https://www.britishmuseum.org/collection/object/C_G-2680" data-type="link" data-id="https://www.britishmuseum.org/collection/object/C_G-2680">British Museum</a> (inv. G.2680) a gold stater (minted in 42 BC) showing on the obverse Brutus as consul with two lictors accompanying him.</figcaption></figure>



<p>There were limits on the ability of a magistrate with <em>imperium</em> to deploy violence within the <em>pomerium</em> against citizens.  The <em>Lex Valeria</em>, dating to the very beginning of the <em>res publica</em> stipulated that in the case of certain punishments (death or flogging), the victim had the right of <em>provocatio</em> to call upon the judgement of the Roman people, through either an assembly or a jury trial.  That limit to the consul’s ability to use violence was reinforced by the <em>leges Porciae</em> (passed in the 190s and 180s), which protected civilian citizens from summary violence from magistrates, even when outside of Rome.  That said, on campaign – that is, <em>militae</em> rather than <em>domi</em> – these laws did not exempt citizen soldiers from beating or even execution as a part of military discipline and indeed Roman military discipline struck Polybius – himself an experienced Greek military man – as harsh (Polyb. 6.35-39).</p>



<p>In practice then, the ability of a magistrate to utilize <em>imperium</em> within Rome was hemmed in by the laws, whereas when out in the provinces on campaign it was far less limited.  A second power, <em>coercitio</em> or ‘coercion’ – the power of a higher magistrate to use minor punishments or force to protect public order – is sometimes presented as a distinct power of the magistrates, but I tend to agree with Lintott (<em>op. cit.</em>, 97-8) that this rather overrates the importance of the coercive powers of magistrates within the <em>pomerium</em>; in any case, the day-to-day maintenance of public order generally fell to minor magistrates.</p>



<p>While <em>imperium</em> was a ‘complete package’ as it were, the Romans clearly understood certain figures as having an <em>imperium</em> that outranked others, thus dictators could order consuls, who could order praetors, the hierarchy neatly visualized by the number of lictors each had.  This could create problems, of course, when Rome’s informal systems of hierarchy conflicted with this formal system, for instance at the Battle of Arausio, the pro-consul Quintus Servilius Caepio refused to take orders from the consul, Gnaeus Mallius Maximus, because the latter was his social inferior (being a <em>novus homo</em>, a ‘new man’ from a family that hadn’t yet been in the Senate and thus not a member of the <em>nobiles</em>), despite the fact that by law the <em>imperium</em> of a sitting consul outranked that of a pro-consul.  The result of that bit of insubordination was a military catastrophe that got both commanders later charged and exiled.</p>



<p>Finally, a vocabulary note: it would be reasonable to assume that the Latin word for a person with <em>imperium</em> would be <em>imperator</em><span id="easy-footnote-2-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-2-20553" title="Pronunication note because this bothers me when I hear this word in popular media: it is not imPERator, but impeRAtor, because that &amp;#8216;a&amp;#8217; is long by nature, and thus keeps the stress."><sup>2</sup></a></span> because that’s the standard way Latin words form.  And I will say, from the perspective of a person who has to decide at the beginning of each thing I write what circumlocution I am going to use to describe “magistrate or pro-magistrate with <em>imperium</em>,” it would be remarkably fortunate if <em>imperator</em> meant that, but it doesn’t.  Instead, <em>imperator</em> in Latin ends up swallowed by its idiomatic meaning of ‘victorious general,’ as it was normal in the republic for armies to proclaim their general as <em>imperator</em> after a major victory (which set the general up to request a triumph from the Senate).  In the imperial period, this leads to the emperors monopolizing the term, as all of the armies of Rome operated under their <em>imperium</em> and thus all victory accolades belonged to the emperor.  That in turn leads to <em>imperator</em> becoming part of the imperial title, from where it gives us our word ’emperor.’</p>



<p>That said, the circumlocution I am going to use here, because this isn’t a formal genre and I can, is ‘<em>imperium</em>-haver.’  I desperately wish I could use that in peer reviewed articles, but I fear no editor would let me (while Reviewer 2 will predictably object to ‘general’ ‘commander’ or ‘governor’ for all being modern coinages).<span id="easy-footnote-3-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-3-20553" title="And yes, really, I have had reviewers object to &amp;#8216;general&amp;#8217; or &amp;#8216;commander&amp;#8217; to mean &amp;#8216;the magistrate or pro-magistrate with <em>imperium</em> in the province.&amp;#8217;  There is no pleasing Reviewer 2."><sup>3</sup></a></span></p>



<p>On to our first set of <em>imperium</em>-havers!</p>



<h2>Praetors  </h2>



<p>The six praetors are the junior <em>imperium-</em>possessing magistracy and though all of the praetors were elected together, by the Middle Republic the job of being praetor might vary quite a lot depending on which role you were assigned by the Senate.  You will recall that the praetorship is an old office, originally taking the place of chief magistrate which later becomes the consulship (note Livy 3.5.11-12, 7.3.5-8; Cic. <em>Leg</em>. 3.8; Fest. 249L; Gell. 11.18.8, 20.1.47; Plin. <em>NH</em> 18.12 see also Varro <em>Ling</em>. 5.80), though at some point the title of the chief magistrate shifted being consul and the praetor (just one of them) served as a junior assistant to the consuls.  We’re not well informed about the praetorship in this early form, but it seems likely it had a similar role in organizing the courts, while the consuls led the armies.  In any case the number of praetors increases rapidly in the last half of the third century, with a second added in c. 242, two more in 228 and two more in 198/7, giving the total of six.</p>



<p>Because the praetors had <em>imperium</em>, they could in theory lead armies and organize courts the same as consuls (though they lacked some of the other distinctive consular powers we’ll discuss in a moment) but in practice the responsibilities of the praetors were usually quite distinct and split into two large categories: praetors assigned a <em>provincia</em> (which again, you should read as ‘job’ not ‘province’) at Rome and praetors assigned a <em>provincia</em> outside of Rome.</p>



<p>The two praetors operating normally in Rome were terms the <em>praetor urbanus</em> and <em>praetor peregrinus</em> and their responsibility was almost entirely focused on the court system.  The <em>praetor urbanus</em> was primarily concerned with legal disputes involved two citizen parties, while any issue involving foreigners came under the jurisdiction of the <em>praetor peregrinus</em>, though the latter was sometimes also deployed out of Rome on special duties, at which point the <em>praetor urbanus</em>, who almost always remained in Rome, would handle both.  On coming into office, the <em>praetor urbanus</em> (and probably also the <em>praetor peregrinus</em>) issued the <em>edictum praetoris</em> (‘Praetor’s edict’) which set out how he intended to carry out his office.  Early on, these edicts seem mostly to have been restricted to changes in procedure or the assessment of damages, but by the first century praetorian edicts could lay out substantive law creating what later Roman jurists would term the <em>ius praetorium</em> (‘praetorian law’), which sat alongside the main law code itself, the <em>ius civile</em> (‘civil law’).  Mostly what these edicts lay out seem to be procedures or the conditions under which the praetor will grant a cause of action.  By the time the edict is fully developed, praetors seem to be seeking and getting advice from an emerging class of legal experts, <em>iuris prudentes</em> (‘men learned at law’ = ‘legal consult’) to craft what must often have been pretty formulaic edicts.<span id="easy-footnote-4-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-4-20553" title="To be clear, these are not <em>professional</em> lawyers, but rather generally elites who had taken a special interest in the law and thus become experts, on whom other elites holding offices might rely."><sup>4</sup></a></span></p>



<p>We’ll cover the Roman legal process towards the end of this series but we may cover the praetor’s role here in brief.  When a case was raised – and Roman law understands all cases as disputes just like Greek law does, though unlike in most Greek <em>poleis</em>, some Roman magistrates seem to have had an expectation to act as quasi-public prosecutors for certain kinds of infractions – it was brought before the praetor, either <em>urbanus</em> for an issue involving citizens or <em>peregrinus</em> for an issue involving at least one non-citizen.  At this point the matter was <em>in iure</em> (‘at law’) and the praetor held a sort of preliminary hearing to determine if there was a cause of action (thus the importance of this question in the praetor’s edict) and then to assign a judge (a <em>iudex</em>) who would administer the trial and to set a formula (<em>formula</em>, gotta love Latin), which functioned rather like jury instructions, naming the relevant parties, describing their dispute and setting out the consequences should the matter be ruled in favor of one or the other (this stage of the case is <em>apud iudicem</em>, ‘before a judge’).  Note that the praetor doesn’t make a ruling, but merely lays out the formula.</p>



<p>For more serious matters that required a jury court to resolve, a potential prosecutor went before the praetor, who then assigned the case to the relevant court or assembly (as assemblies, especially early on, could act as courts) and set a date for the trial.  Interestingly, for jury trials, no <em>formula</em> was provided by the praetor.</p>



<p>What about the praetors who weren’t assigned to Rome?  As the sphere of Roman military activity expanded beyond Italy, it became necessary to have more commanders in the field, and this is where we get the additional praetors.  Because a praetor has <em>imperium</em>, they can function as a sort of ‘mini-consul.’  That said, praetors don’t tend to get assigned the sorts of jobs consuls do.  If Rome needs three major field armies, the Senate generally doesn’t send a praetor to command the third, rather it sends a pro-consul (which makes a degree of sense when you think about it; you want an experienced commander).</p>



<p>Instead, praetors in the field tend to be assigned to putative ‘quiet’ provinces or auxiliary support functions.  The standard praetorian provinces were <em>Corsica et Sardinia</em> (one province) and Sicily, later joined by the two Spains (<em>Hispania Citerior</em>, ‘Nearer Spain’ and <em>Hispania Ulterior</em>, ‘Further Spain), when they were quiet.  When a major military action flared up on this areas, the response wasn’t to send a praetor with a large army, but to assign a consul or a pro-consul to the province instead, though because these assignments are made annually that tends to mean that trouble flares up, the praetor with his smaller army tries to manage it and if he fails and is defeated, <em>then</em> a consul is sent out with a major army.</p>



<p>Now I don’t want to get entirely off-track detailing what a Roman commander does in his overseas <em>provincia</em>; I may add a supplemental post on this one describing what Roman provincial government looks like in the Republic (though for the curious, the book to read is F.K. Drogula, <a href="https://amzn.to/3qxEjh1" data-type="link" data-id="https://amzn.to/3qxEjh1"><em>Commanders and Command</em> </a>(2015); it’s a bit dry, but quite thorough).  But in brief a praetor in his overseas <em>provincia</em> is going to have command of whatever military forces are there, generally less than the standard two-legion consular army (sometimes a lot less!).  If there is no active military campaign to be done, the praetor will transit around the province.  Because he has <em>imperium</em>, he can resolve disputes as a court and in the provinces – because <em>imperium</em> is stronger outside of Rome – he can do so summarily so long as Roman citizens are not involved.  He can enforce these resolutions on non-Romans in the province because he has a Roman army and the implicit backing of the rest of the Roman state.  Note that the praetor in his province doesn’t take over day-to-day garden variety law and order issues; those are still handled by local governments, according to local laws.</p>



<p>Generally the expectation is that a praetor is going to use his mix of military force and his ability to resolve disputes and deliver judgements to keep good order in the region and to make sure that Rome’s taxes are collected.  In practice within those confines, there’s a lot of latitude, though the Senate may make certain specific demands as part of a praetor’s assignment.  The praetor is also assisted by an assigned quaestor who handles the financial side of things and is expected to consult a small council of advisors, a <em>consilium</em>, when making decisions.  Finally, beginning in 149, there is a permanent court in Rome which has the job of handling the cases of governors who exceeded their mandate in the provinces, the <em>quaestio de repetundis</em>; the name literally means ‘the court for things you need to give back’ because the primary concern was governors extorting money and taking bribes in their provinces.  So the praetor’s latitude is not infinite.</p>



<p>As the number of active <em>provinciae</em> became too large for even the larger number of praetors and the two consuls, the Senate took to having former praetors serve as ‘pro-praetors,’ a kind of pro-magistrate, but we’ll talk about them below, after we’ve discussed the most important Roman magistrate, the consuls.</p>



<h2>The Consuls</h2>



<p>The consuls, always a pair, are the senior magistrates of the Roman Republic.  While the censors, if there are any in office, may be themselves senior consulars (that is, ex-consuls), the sitting consuls are still the most powerful magistrates.  Consuls wield <em>imperium</em>, but of a greater degree than any other magistrate or pro-magistrate (save a dictator), allowing them to in theory give orders to other magistrates (though this doesn’t happen often).  The consuls also lead Rome’s primary field armies through the Middle Republic (this shifts only with Sulla’s reforms in 83).</p>



<p>While in theory the consuls’ possession of <em>imperium</em> meant they could superintend the courts, they generally didn’t (some Late Republic exceptions, like Pompey presiding over the trial of Titus Annius Milo are remarkable for being unusual).  Instead, we most often see consuls in two roles: moving major legislation and leading Rome’s main field armies.  In the former case, technically the praetors could legislate as well as the consuls, but in practice major laws tended to be proposed by either the consuls or the plebeian tribunes.</p>



<p>Each consul would also command a major field army.  The Romans do not do army-command-by-committee (unlike Athens), so under normal circumstances the consuls each had independent command over their own army.  The standard strength of a consular army was two legions (8,400 infantry, 600 cavalry) plus two <em>alae</em> of <em>socii</em> (varies but roughly the same size, with somewhat more cavalry), meaning that each consul in the Middle Republic goes to war with a chunky c. 20,000 man army.  It was only in rare circumstances that these armies would be combined and such combined ‘double consular’ armies often caused problems if the consuls couldn’t get along or agree on a strategic vision.</p>



<p>That said, how many troops a consul might have and where he would be expected to take them was largely determined by the Senate.  The Senate, as we’ll see, assigns <em>provincia</em> (again, think ‘jobs’ not ‘provinces’) – even to the consuls – and it also directs the quaestors on how resources are to be allocated.  That includes conscription (the <a href="https://acoup.blog/2023/06/16/collections-how-to-raise-a-roman-army-the-dilectus/" data-type="post" data-id="19439"><em>dilectus</em>) </a>and we see repeatedly that consuls do not feel they can hold a <em>dilectus</em> without the consent of the Senate; they can take volunteers without senatorial approval, but a draft, no.  Likewise, unless they can find volunteer <em>funding</em>, they are reliant on quaestors releasing funds, quaestors who are always going to do what the Senate tells them to do.</p>



<p>However, the Senate can’t come on campaign with the consuls and so once in the field, dealing with whatever problem the Senate has suggested they deal with, the consuls have a great deal of command independence and nearly limitless authority.  Whereas at Rome consular authority is constrained by laws and the plebeian tribunes (whose powers end at the <em>pomerium</em>), in the field they can implement strict military discipline and command their armies as they see fit.  That extends to considerable latitude when it comes to negotiating with foreign states (neutral or hostile), though any treaty they make must be ratified back in Rome (technically requiring approval of an assembly but in practice this depends on if the Senate approves).</p>



<p>Now with such sweeping powers the Romans were naturally concerned that the consuls might usurp the state, so they instituted a few basic checks on this.  One of these checks is simply the existence of the plebeian tribunes, but we’ll talk about those next time.  But also it was clearly established that there must <em>always</em> be two consuls.  Not one, not three.  <em>Two</em>.  If one consul dies, another must be immediately elected; this replacement consul was called a <em>consul suffectus</em> (the year was still dated from the two consuls elected at the beginning, the <em>consules ordinarii</em>).  Because only a consul had the authority to hold a consular election, you needed a system to handle situations where both consuls were indisposed at once (either both dead or one dead and one abroad with the army); the solution was a rare official, the <em>interrex</em>, who only had the authority to hold an election for the consulship.</p>



<p>Once you’ve ensured there are always two consuls, the next trick is to make sure they can check each other.  To ensure that, consuls were given some substantial powers.  The most famous of these was <em>veto</em>, Latin for “I forbid!”  Just by saying the word, a consul could block any action by any other magistrate, <em>including the other consul</em>.  The power had to be exercised in person, which limited it: if you really wanted to prevent your colleague from doing something he <em>really</em> wanted to do, you best be prepared to follow him around in person every day to keep vetoing it.  A supercharged for of veto consuls could also exercise was <em>iustitium</em>, declaring a stop to all state business; this could be used to stop any meeting of a popular assembly or of the Senate so long as the assembly had not dispersed into voting groups.</p>



<p>The final check on the consuls is pretty simple: they only serve for one year.  After which it is generally expected that there be a respectable interval (usually around 10 years) before you can run for the consulship again.  <strong>While in office, any Roman with <em>imperium</em> is immune from prosecution</strong>, but can be prosecuted immediately on leaving office for any crimes they may have done while in office.  Consequently, a consul’s freedom of action is going to be limited by their concern about potentially having to face a jury after their one-year term is complete.  Even if they aren’t worried about that, once their year is done they go back to being just another senator, so good relations with the rest of the Senate is a good idea.</p>



<p>In part because one of the <em>other</em> things the Senate decides on are…</p>



<h2>Pro-Magistrates</h2>



<p>Roman expansion put strains on all of these systems.  <strong>Fundamentally, the Roman system remained one designed for a small city-state</strong>.  Everything – military command, attending the Senate, passing legislation, using veto power – needed to be done in person by magistrates who only had a single year in office.  While Roman territory and the scope of Rome’s wars remained small, that sort of system worked fine.  As Roman territory and Rome’s wars expanded, it put all sorts of strains on that system: how to handle multi-year campaigns which kept the armies in the field?  How to handle having more commands than magistrates?</p>



<p>The solution was to extend (prorogue) a magistrate’s authority, making them a pro-magistrate (‘pro’ meaning ‘standing in for’).  It’s tricky to pin down exactly when the Romans first did this as our sources for early Rome (Livy and Dionysius of Halicarnassus) tend to use terms for proconsular power (<em>pro consule</em> or ἀνθύπατον ἀρχὴν) long before prorogation seems to have been used in Rome.  Generally, we think that the first genuine prorogation happens in 327 as part of the run-up to the Second Samnite War (Livy 8.23).<span id="easy-footnote-5-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-5-20553" title="On this, see Drogula, <em>op. cit.</em> 27."><sup>5</sup></a></span>  The problem here was two-fold: Rome’s evident shift to year-round campaigning meaning that the army needed a continous commander in the field as in this case where it was conducting a siege, combined with the greater distances – the commander, Q. Pubilius Philo, is besieging Naples – making swift changes in command difficult.</p>



<p>Prorogation becomes common and regular during the Punic Wars.  The First Punic War, taking place primarily in Sicily, demanded the use of prorogation to cover the lag time between elections in Rome and commanders arriving in Sicily, as well as to allow single commanders to conduct more complex campaigns.  By the Second Punic War, which takes place in Italy, Sicily, Gaul, Spain, North Africa and Illyria (much of that <em>simultaneously</em>) it was also necessary to prorogue commanders in order to simply get enough field commanders with <em>imperium</em> for all of the armies Rome was deploying.  Indeed, in the crazy days of the Second Punic War, at points the Senate prorogued men who had never held office before, <em>privati cum imperio</em> (private citizens with <em>imperium</em>), though this is discontinued and replaced by a system whereby prorogued commanders will have first held the relevant office at some point.</p>



<p>The expanding number of areas of Roman overseas control pushed this further as more regions meant more <em>provinciae</em> (in the sense of ‘jobs’) which demanded more <em>imperium</em>-havers to handle.  New praetors were eventually made for Sicily, Corsica-and-Sardinia and the two Spains, but by the mid-second century the Romans are regularly assigning <em>imperium</em>-havers to Gaul (Cisalpine or Transalpine), Africa, Greece and Macedonia and of course also need magistrates with <em>imperium</em> in Italy to handle the regular functions of government.<span id="easy-footnote-6-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-6-20553" title="Macedonia as a permanent province is added in 147, Africa in 146 and Asia in 129, followed by Gallia Narbonensis in 120.  No new praetors are created for this province; they&amp;#8217;re handled by promagistrates when things are calm enough not to require a consul."><sup>6</sup></a></span></p>



<p>One of the pressures here is that by this point it was clearly locked into tradition that there were only ever two consuls.  It had not <em>always</em> been that way; back when the Romans had military tribunes with consular powers, they had three of them.  But by the third century, there were always and could only be two consuls.  But that’s a problem because even if you have spare praetors, you don’t assign praetors to <em>major</em> military commands, so if you have <em>three</em> major military commands, you don’t send a praetor, you assign a proconsul.</p>



<p>The result of all of this is that each year the most pressing military problems generally got a consul assigned to them.  Often the military problem from last year that was on-going would see its ex-consul prorogued to continue handling it.  Likewise, the new praetors would be sent out to replace the governors in quiet provinces, with the remainder who weren’t replaced prorogued to hold down the fort for another year.  Later it is going to become quite common for former praetors and consuls who had returned to Rome to be dispatched back out to the provinces to do a stint as a promagistrate, but the common use of this is really a consequence of the Sullan reforms and for the most part belongs to the first century.  Most third and second century promagistrates are having an existing command <em>extended</em> rather than being sent out fresh.</p>



<p>Extensions of this sort, I should note, were generally fairly short.  The longest run I can think of in this period is that of Publius Cornelius Scipio Africanus who is <em>privati cum imperio</em> <em>pro consule</em> (‘private citizen with pro-consular imperium’) from 210 to 206, mostly as a product of his father and uncle having been the local Roman commanders in Spain and Scipio having taken over when they were both killed, leading to an irregular, emergency command.  He’s then consul in 205, before having his command prorogued from 204 to 201 to complete his invasion of Africa (technically, he’s assign to Sicily with permission to invade Africa if an opportunity presented itself).</p>



<p>Far more typical for even an exceptional commander was something like Scipio Aemilianus’ experience.  Consul in 147, he is prorogued to complete the destruction of Carthage in 146.  Then, consul in 134, he is prorogued to complete the destruction of Numantia in 133.  And that was that.  The point here being that the heavy reliance on proconsuls to conduct the main effort in Roman wars, often with longer commands (most famously Caesar’s <em>eight years</em> in Gaul or Pompey’s back-to-back eastern commands from 67 to 62) visible in the Late Republic was not common practice in the Middle Republic.</p>



<p>One significant legal quirk of prorogation is that while a consul or a praetor at least notionally had <em>imperium</em> which traveled (though in practice they would be expected to focus on the <em>provincia</em> the Senate assigned them), the <em>imperium</em> of a promagistrate, who after all only ‘stood in for’ the actual magistrate of the year, was in fact restricted to their defined sphere of action.</p>



<p>My plan once we’ve gone through the whole Roman system <em>for Romans</em> is to add two more posts on this series (perhaps not coming right away), one covering how the Roman Republic interacts with the <em>socii</em> and another briefly describing the shape of Roman governance in the provinces<span id="easy-footnote-7-20553"></span><span><a href="#easy-footnote-bottom-7-20553" title="Places, not jobs, for once."><sup>7</sup></a></span>  But for now, that’s enough on <em>imperium</em>.  Next week, we’re going to look at two very strange major offices, the tribunate and the censorship, plus discuss what we know of the key minor offices of the republic.</p>
<ol><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-1-20553"></span>I should note here that Drogula (in <em><a href="https://amzn.to/3YDkX6I" data-type="link" data-id="https://amzn.to/3YDkX6I">Commanders and Command</a></em> (2015)) understands <em>imperium</em> a bit differently than this more traditional version I am presenting (in line with Lintott’s understanding).  He contends that <em>imperium</em> was an entirely military power which was not necessary for judicial functions and was not only indivisible but also, at least early on, did not come in different degrees.  In practice, I’m not sure the Romans were ever so precise with their concepts as Drogula wants them to be.<a href="#easy-footnote-1-20553"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-2-20553"></span>Pronunication note because this bothers me when I hear this word in popular media: it is not imPERator, but impeRAtor, because that ‘a’ is long by nature, and thus keeps the stress.<a href="#easy-footnote-2-20553"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-3-20553"></span>And yes, really, I have had reviewers object to ‘general’ or ‘commander’ to mean ‘the magistrate or pro-magistrate with <em>imperium</em> in the province.’  There is no pleasing Reviewer 2.<a href="#easy-footnote-3-20553"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-4-20553"></span>To be clear, these are not <em>professional</em> lawyers, but rather generally elites who had taken a special interest in the law and thus become experts, on whom other elites holding offices might rely.<a href="#easy-footnote-4-20553"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-5-20553"></span>On this, see Drogula, <em>op. cit.</em> 27.<a href="#easy-footnote-5-20553"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-6-20553"></span>Macedonia as a permanent province is added in 147, Africa in 146 and Asia in 129, followed by Gallia Narbonensis in 120.  No new praetors are created for this province; they’re handled by promagistrates when things are calm enough not to require a consul.<a href="#easy-footnote-6-20553"></a></li><li><span id="easy-footnote-bottom-7-20553"></span>Places, not jobs, for once.<a href="#easy-footnote-7-20553"></a></li></ol>	</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>