<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 21:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gumroad's Interestingly Timed "Open-Source" Play (146 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tedium.co/2025/04/06/gumroad-open-source-doge-drama/</link>
            <guid>43603999</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 19:01:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tedium.co/2025/04/06/gumroad-open-source-doge-drama/">https://tedium.co/2025/04/06/gumroad-open-source-doge-drama/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43603999">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>In terms of unexplainable quirks</strong> I have as a human being, the weirdest one is this: Gum freaks me out. I hate the idea of it, to the point where I dislike the word.</p><p>It really bothers me, like nails on a chalkboard. I’ve never understood why. And it’s to the point where I’ve kind of checked out of things I might like just because their name references the word. (Apologies to <em>Stereogum</em>, I’m sure your music publication is just great, the problem is your name.)</p><p>So I’ve never been a <a href="https://gumroad.com/">Gumroad</a> user outside of a couple of random purchases here and there. I just couldn’t get past the name. But nonetheless, I respected the role it played in creating what we call the creator economy.</p><p>And I’m also an advocate for the creator economy becoming less platform-driven. Someone recently made the point to me that the recent rise in low-code and AI-based tooling is likely going to separate out the platforms that solve tough problems—the Stripes of the world—from those that simply put a nice interface on a problem. And having access to tools that you operate yourself is a way to get there.</p><p>Which is why, when I saw that the company had announced it was open-sourcing its application the other day, I got past my weird linguistic quirk and saw something that could be a big deal. I think we need more creator economy things in the self-hostable category, and putting Gumroad in that category feels like it could be a huge kick in the arm for that space.</p><p>So I did what I always do: I posted about it. It saw a little bit of pickup, particularly on Mastodon. I noted a quirk of the company’s open-source license that doesn’t truly make it open-source according to commonly accepted definitions, but I otherwise just passively shared it.</p><p>But with a little retrospect and a little more digging, I’m feeling less excited about it. In fact, I’m slightly frustrated with myself that I shared it so passively. There are some real problems with Gumroad that make it a terrible foundation for a creator economy that puts the creator in control. And there’s also a big issue with its leadership that almost went unnoticed on the very same day that the news was announced.</p><p>So, now, rather than just sharing it, I’m writing about it.</p></div><div><figure><img src="https://proxy.tedium.co/CRFbdZkmkG855zMN1H6oTyq36KI=/1281x972/filters:quality(80)/uploads/Screenshot-From-2025-04-06-13-32-54.png" width="1281" height="972" loading="lazy" alt="Screenshot From 2025 04 06 13 32 54"><figcaption>Gumroad goes open source! But wait, about that …</figcaption></figure><h3>Why people are frustrated with Gumroad</h3><p>First, some existing users have pointed out some issues with the Gumroad service that have made it significantly less useful for the average user. Fellow traveler Evan Hildreth <a href="https://oddevan.com/2025/04/04/bumps-in-the-gumroad.html">pointed out two specific issues</a>: First, the platform changed its rules for when you could email end users, which was annoying but understandable, and more troublingly, the company seems to have replaced its customer support with LLMs almost entirely. As he wrote:</p><blockquote><p>Finally, I asked how to contact Gumroad support. It pointed me to the help site&nbsp;<em>that didn’t exist</em>&nbsp;and the contact form within. I eventually found an email on another page and sent a message there; the response was very obviously from the same chatbot.</p><p>Chatbots are fine as&nbsp;<em>one of many</em>&nbsp;options to access support information. But as the&nbsp;<em>only</em>&nbsp;option? When it’s been trained on a help site that references itself (and therefore references a site that doesn’t exist)?</p></blockquote><p>Additionally, the open-source licensing thing is kind of a fib—<a href="https://danb.me/blog/gumroad-is-not-open-source/">it’s more of a source-available license</a> that limits your ability to use the tool after you hit a certain threshold. It’s not unheard of for this kind of license to be used by companies looking to lean into self-hosting without losing their money train. I have suggested that it can provide a middle ground for folks getting started as long as they’re aware of its limitations.</p><p>FOSS die-hards may not agree, but this kind of threading-the-needle can be done well, and honestly, IMHO. A good example is the content-management framework <a href="https://directus.io/">Directus</a>, <a href="https://directus.io/bsl">which essentially makes it free to use</a> in most cases, unless you make more than $5 million in finances per year, at which point you need to start paying for it. Not purely open source, but it throws FOSS folks a bone by making it so that versions of the software that are more than three years old revert to the General Public License.</p><p>How does Gumroad do it? <a href="https://github.com/antiwork/gumroad/blob/main/LICENSE.md">Well</a> …</p><blockquote><p>You may use the software under this license only if (1) your company has less than 1 million USD (2024) total revenue in the prior tax year, and less than 10 million USD (2024) GMV (Gross Merchandise Value), or (2) you are a non-profit organization or government entity. Adjust the revenue threshold for inflation according to the United States Bureau of Labor Statistics’ consumer price index for all urban consumers, U.S. city average, for all items, not seasonally adjusted, 1982–1984=100 reference base. If you are a company and exceed either of the limits in (1), your license ends. You may contact the licensor to discuss an alternative license.</p></blockquote><p>So essentially, if you ever have a single good year, you’re stuck paying a custom license fee.</p><figure><img src="https://proxy.tedium.co/rHxSqatPcGK0hwrilTSx9e83T6U=/799x533/filters:quality(80)/uploads/4871933275_3a45618da0_c.jpg" width="799" height="533" loading="lazy" alt="4871933275 3a45618da0 c"><figcaption>I know, the image looks confusing and out of place in this story, but I promise you it is related. (<a href="https://flickr.com/photos/eschipul/4871933275/">eschipul/Flickr</a>)</figcaption></figure><h3>Announcing an open-source shift as a big story drops</h3><p>But if that’s all Gumroad was doing, I wouldn’t feel compelled to say anything. The reason I’m speaking up <a href="https://www.wired.com/story/doge-department-of-veterans-affairs-ai/">is because of this <em>Wired</em> story,</a> released on the very same day Gumroad announced its “open source” license, which may have had the effect of minimizing the story’s viral impact. So I guess maybe a guy with a blog and a distaste for Gumroad’s name can give it a second stab.</p><p>The story is about DOGE, but it points out something curious:</p><blockquote><p>On March 25, tech staffers and contractors at the VA noticed an unfamiliar name trying to push changes that could impact VA.gov code. It was Sahil Lavingia, a newcomer to the agency listed in the VA’s internal directory as an adviser to the chief of staff, Christopher Syrek.</p></blockquote><p>Who’s Sahil Lavingia, you might ask? Why, the founder and CEO of Gumroad! It’s not even the central point of the piece, but the fact is, if you’re supporting Gumroad—a tool that, notably, has survived as long as it did because of <a href="https://republic.com/gumroad-march-2021">a high-profile crowdfunding campaign</a>—you’re allowing its CEO the financial freedom to work in the Department of Veterans Affairs, at the behest of DOGE, for free.</p><p>When submitted a list of questions about his work for DOGE, Lavingia told <em>Wired</em>: “Sorry, I’m not going to answer these, besides to say I’m unpaid. And a fan of your work!”</p><p>And the reason he has all this free time? Simple: As the piece notes, he achieved financial stability with Gumroad by replacing nearly all of its employees with automation. (Hence why Evan Hildreth can’t get any damn support.) Which is now what he wants to do with the VA, as the piece explains.</p><p>There’s a lot more there—which I recommend checking out the full piece to get a grasp on, but suffice it to say: If you disagree with this, now may be a good time to stop using Gumroad. It’s not like you’re going to find a support person there anyway.</p><figure><img src="https://proxy.tedium.co/0vIQut_MdPMJhq9aLiSEWzIH8-I=/1000x750/filters:quality(80)/uploads/GumballMachine.jpg" width="1000" height="750" loading="lazy" alt="Gumball Machine"><figcaption>No reason you have to use someone else’s gumball machine. (<a href="https://unsplash.com/photos/woman-in-green-jacket-standing-beside-stainless-steel-round-container-4nsrOXYL-90">Pete Alexopoulos/Unsplash</a>)</figcaption></figure><h3>Maybe it’s time to shake up the creator economy calculus?</h3><p>May I make a suggestion? If the tech firm you’re relying on to make money is using AI and low-code tools to offer their service to you anyway, what’s stopping you from just doing the same thing? You can make a Gumroad or a Patreon. It’s easier than ever—<a href="https://tedium.co/2025/03/20/snap-fasteners-tariffs-history/">I just featured a guy in the newsletter who did just that</a>.</p><p>To me, I think that there is a real opportunity to take away the reins from middlemen who extract value rather than add it by leaning into things we host ourselves. Creators, for too long, have given too much power away to the company that made our lives mildly more convenient. If they’re trying to optimize to the nubs, destroying quality of service in the process, why even bother letting them have a lane in the middle?</p><p>To be clear, not everyone’s a bad player—and I will stand up for services I think do it well. (I like Ko-Fi, and personally <a href="https://ko-fi.com/tedium/commissions?commissionAlias=caf0972c99&amp;openCommissionsMenu=True#buyShopCommissionModal">just launched something there</a> last week.) But if users get lost in the shuffle on a given platform, what’s the point of sticking with them?</p><p>AI is not everyone’s cup of tea, so if you don’t use it, don’t use it. Nobody’s asking you to be a vibe coder over here. But I think there’s a real opportunity to work around the current system’s deficiencies for creators, if they want to go down that road. If the makers of these platforms are optimizing everything to within an inch of its life, why couldn’t creators do that?</p><p>Plus, you could give it a name that doesn’t have the word “gum” in it. Which I personally would appreciate.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Recent AI model progress feels mostly like bullshit (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/4mvphwx5pdsZLMmpY/recent-ai-model-progress-feels-mostly-like-bullshit</link>
            <guid>43603453</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 18:01:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/4mvphwx5pdsZLMmpY/recent-ai-model-progress-feels-mostly-like-bullshit">https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/4mvphwx5pdsZLMmpY/recent-ai-model-progress-feels-mostly-like-bullshit</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43603453">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.lesswrong.com/posts/4mvphwx5pdsZLMmpY/recent-ai-model-progress-feels-mostly-like-bullshit: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[E.U. Prepares Major Penalties Against X (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/03/technology/eu-penalties-x-elon-musk.html</link>
            <guid>43603307</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 17:47:05 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/03/technology/eu-penalties-x-elon-musk.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/03/technology/eu-penalties-x-elon-musk.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43603307">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/04/03/technology/eu-penalties-x-elon-musk.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Federal cuts disrupt repairs to iconic U.S. trails (115 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/pacific-crest-appalachian-trail-federal-layoffs-934a5526570569b625f5d854ec339a04</link>
            <guid>43603111</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 17:24:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/pacific-crest-appalachian-trail-federal-layoffs-934a5526570569b625f5d854ec339a04">https://apnews.com/article/pacific-crest-appalachian-trail-federal-layoffs-934a5526570569b625f5d854ec339a04</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43603111">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>CAMPO, Calif. (AP) — Hiking the Pacific Crest Trail is a challenge, especially for adventurers making the entire run from Southern California to Canada, and Eric Kipperman’s job is to greet them at the start and lay bare the difficulties ahead.</p><p>He has lately begun warning that the journey may be even tougher. Following cuts by the Trump administration, plans to clear downed trees and rebuild storm-battered stretches in 2025 have been scrapped.</p><p>“This year, we’re going to have less trail work done on the trails, so just know that going into your hike, safety is the most important thing,” Kipperman told a group of backpackers from Europe and the United States at the trailhead near Campo, California, an hour’s drive east of San Diego. </p><p>He cautioned there is “no trail” at all in parts of the 2,650-mile (4,265 kilometers) path through California, Oregon and Washington state.</p>
    
<p>The cutbacks are not just on the West Coast. Ahead of the busy summer hiking season, funding freezes and mass layoffs also are disrupting repairs on the East Coast’s Appalachian Trail after nearly 500 miles (800 kilometers) were damaged by <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/hurricane-helene-fema-federal-aid-congress-rollins-e982f8d36a31ef0b1fb7e3e19e426c72">Hurricane Helene</a></span>, underscoring how President Donald Trump’s <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-elon-musk-federal-workers-layoffs-d295d4bb2cdd5023c27d9cb03754e81b">dramatic downsizing of the U.S. government</a></span> is touching even the nation’s remote backcountry where vacationers, wanderers and escapists alike retreat to leave modern life behind. </p>



<p>Wildfires and more intense storms due in part to climate change have been taking a toll on the legendary trails. The federal cuts threaten their very existence, according to the Pacific Crest Trail Association and the Appalachian Trail Conservancy, which oversee their preservation in partnership with the government and receive millions in federal dollars.</p>
    
    
    
<p>The U.S. Forest Service called the situation “dynamic and evolving” in an email to The Associated Press, but said they are committed to ensuring public safety and access to recreation areas that are vital to local economies.</p>
    
<p>The Trump administration has let go some 3,400 workers at the <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/fired-federal-workers-wildfires-season-trump-west-d915e8ea272b7265912d7eafdbf7420a">U.S. Forest Service</a></span>, and nearly <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-national-parks-open-workers-fired-burgum-279dac0653f3e1af839b14668bf3d2d7">1,500</a></span> at the <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-national-park-firings-doge-grand-teton-baedee0a748a6374eafb6f95aac5dadc">National Park Service</a></span>, including trail repair specialists. The associations said the cuts also led to the rescinding of job offers for seasonal crews with technical skills to rebuild boardwalks, bridges and campsites and train thousands of volunteers. </p><p>Courts have ordered federal agencies to rehire thousands of workers, but some say they are <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/trump-fired-federal-workers-rehired-ac9afd4165c3110d7d7ee6c81eba0101">not coming back</a></span>.</p><p>“For hikers, they’re going to be crawling, navigating, working their way through downed trees across the trail that won’t get cut out,” said Justin Kooyman, director of the Pacific Crest Trail operations. “It’s going to make for a little more rough and tumble.”</p>
    
<h2>A backlog of projects</h2><p>While the trails are not in total disarray and many hikers may not see any damaged areas, maintenance is critical to their existence, the associations say. More than 20 miles (32 kilometers) of the Appalachian Trail remain closed following Helene and downed trees could fuel wildfires. </p><p>Last month, the Appalachian Trail turned 100 years old. The footpath stretches 2,193 miles (3,530 kilometers) between Georgia’s Springer Mountain and Maine’s Mount Katahdin. </p><p>Its founder, the late forest scientist Benton MacKaye, saw a need for a place to escape stress following the end of World War I and the 1918 flu epidemic. </p><p>The Appalachian Trail and Pacific Crest Trail officially became the country’s first National Scenic Trails under the 1968 National Trails System Act. Completing them has come to symbolize the strength of the human spirit, inspiring books and movies. Only a fraction are thru-hikers, a term for those who walk the trails from end to end. Many don’t succeed and several people have died trying. Most users hike for a day or two to enjoy the breathtaking beauty.</p><p>“I am so concerned with what seems to be a general lack of appreciation for what these protected outdoor spaces can bring to not just our physical well-being but to our souls,” said Sandi Marra, head of the Appalachian Trail Conservancy. “If we lose these things, we are really going to be lost as a species, and definitely as a country.”</p>
    
<p>The Pacific Crest Trail Association said it is operating with a third less federal grant money than anticipated. The Appalachian Trail Conservancy said at least $1.5 million is at risk from federal downsizing.</p><p>The National Park Service said its funding has continued for the Appalachian Trail as it works to “address challenges collaboratively and seek solutions” to support the footpath’s “enduring legacy.”</p><p>Both trails already had a backlog of projects. Wildfires have scorched nearly 250 miles (400 kilometers) of the Pacific Crest Trail in recent years. </p><p>The disruption exacerbates the deteriorating conditions and the spread of invasive plant species, which will ultimately increase costs, said Megan Wargo, head of the Pacific Crest Trail Association. </p>
    
<h2>Cutting back </h2><p>The Pacific Crest Trail crosses searing desert and traverses forests of giant sequoias, the world’s largest trees, before climbing by snow-covered peaks in the rugged Sierra Nevada. After snaking over 50 mountain passes, it ends in Washington’s remote Pasayten Wilderness at the Canadian border.</p><p>As the trail’s popularity grew through social media and the bestselling memoir “Wild” that inspired a Hollywood film, drawing less experienced backpackers, the association hired what they call “crest runners.”</p><p>Kipperman is one of two at the southern end. Their duties include greeting hikers at the Mexican border, checking their permits and providing safety tips before they set off. The crest runners normally work from March until August, covering the hottest, riskiest months for that section. </p><p>Last year, a crest runner also worked the northern end at the Canadian border. But this year they only will be at the southern end until mid-May unless more federal funds are unfrozen.</p><p>Kipperman, whose trail name is “Pure Stoke,” is infectiously cheery as he rattles off the dangers from rattlesnakes to dehydration and distributes bags for discarded toilet paper. He steers clear of discussing politics and instead talks about protecting water quality, burying human waste, packing out trash and building safe campfires.</p><p>“Remove the ego. Address the situation. See if going forward is really the right thing for you,” Kipperman said, warning hikers to beware that Mile 225 or so is washed out. </p><h2>Plowing ahead </h2><p>After hearing Kipperman’s spiel, backpacker Joshua Suran said he planned to try helping restore the trail where possible.</p><p>Marias Michel of Germany trudged over, concerned about the weight of his backpack draped with gear, water bottles and a pair of Crocs. After quitting his job, he said he needed to do the trail, calling it “a resetting, a big detox.”</p><p>He was aware of the federal cuts but said he couldn’t worry about that.</p><p>“I’m just going to be learning by doing because I don’t want to be too much up here,” Michel said, pointing to his head. “I want to test myself. No expectations. It’s an attempt until you make it.”</p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Peter Navarro Invented an Expert for His Books, Based on Himself (2019) (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/16/us/politics/peter-navarro-ron-vara.html</link>
            <guid>43602777</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 16:39:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/16/us/politics/peter-navarro-ron-vara.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/16/us/politics/peter-navarro-ron-vara.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43602777">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2019/10/16/us/politics/peter-navarro-ron-vara.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Self-Driving Teslas Are Fatally Rear-Ending Motorcyclists More Than Any Other (302 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fuelarc.com/news-and-features/self-driving-teslas-are-fatally-striking-motorcyclists-more-than-any-other-brand-new-analysis/</link>
            <guid>43601421</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 13:51:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fuelarc.com/news-and-features/self-driving-teslas-are-fatally-striking-motorcyclists-more-than-any-other-brand-new-analysis/">https://fuelarc.com/news-and-features/self-driving-teslas-are-fatally-striking-motorcyclists-more-than-any-other-brand-new-analysis/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43601421">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-id="27ad23c5" data-element_type="widget" data-widget_type="theme-post-content.default">
					
<p>Among motorcyclists, there is a <a href="https://www.rideapart.com/news/608732/why-tesla-autopilot-ignores-bikes/">persistent rumor</a> that Teslas are dangerous to ride around in traffic. Whether it’s their silent electric drivetrain, extreme acceleration, or self-driving technology supposedly failing to see motorcycles, every biker seems to know someone who’s had a close call with a Tesla.</p>



<p>Our new analysis of data from the NHTSA on self-driving crashes proves this rumor to be true. Since 2022, Teslas in self-driving mode have been involved in five fatal motorcycle crashes (or more).</p>



<p>It’s not just that self-driving cars in general are dangerous for motorcycles, either: this problem is unique to Tesla. Not a single other automobile manufacturer or ADAS self-driving technology provider reported a single motorcycle fatality in the same time frame.</p>



<p>So, why are Teslas involved in self-driving crashes that kill motorcyclists? Let’s interrogate the data and get to the bottom of it.</p>



<h2><strong>TL;DR: Self-Driving Teslas Rear-End Motorcyclists, Killing at Least 5</strong></h2>



<p>Brevity is the spirit of wit, and I am just not that witty. This is a long article, here is the gist of it:</p>



<ul>
<li>The NHTSA’s self-driving crash data reveals that Tesla’s self-driving technology is, by far, the most dangerous for motorcyclists, with five fatal crashes <em>that we know of</em>.</li>



<li>This issue is unique to Tesla. Other self-driving manufacturers have logged zero motorcycle fatalities in the same time frame.</li>



<li>The crashes are overwhelmingly Teslas rear-ending motorcyclists.</li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Self-Driving Teslas Are Fatally Striking Motorcyclists From Behind</strong></h2>



<p>I learned to ride a motorcycle on a military base, and the sergeant was brutally honest.</p>



<p>He said: <strong>“If you’re going to die on the bike, it’s going to be your own fault.”</strong></p>



<p>Welcome to being a motorcyclist. Our margin of error is slim, and mistakes are easily fatal. It’s rough out here on two wheels. Helmet and jacket, <em>strongly encouraged.</em></p>



<p>Rider error, while tragic, is a fact of life. So the first item to rule out is whether the motorcyclists themselves are causing these accidents.</p>



<p><strong>The good news:</strong> we can largely rule out rider error in these crashes. The NHTSA reports the crash location on the self-driving vehicle, so we can tell whether the Tesla was t-boned or rear-ended.</p>



<p>That’s not the case for the self-driving Tesla motorcycle fatalities reported to the NHTSA.</p>



<p>According to the <a href="https://static.nhtsa.gov/odi/ffdd/sgo-2021-01/SGO-2021-01_Incident_Reports_ADAS.csv">NHTSA data</a>:</p>



<ul>
<li>3 out of 5 cases show the Tesla sustained front-end impacts, or front and left-side impacts, or (grimly) front and bottom impacts.</li>



<li>2 out of 5 cases had crash direction marked as “unknown” in the manufacturer’s reporting to the government.</li>
</ul>



<p>Those two “unknown” cases are both in Florida. One of them, in Boca Raton, was a Tesla rear-ending a motorcycle stopping at a traffic light. The final Florida case has fewer details available.</p>



<p>That means that, in 100% of Tesla’s fatal self-driving motorcycle crashes where we know the direction of travel, the Tesla was behind the motorcyclist before impact. The self-driving Teslas are fatally striking the motorcyclists from behind.</p>



<h2>We’d Love to Tell You More, But Tesla’s Self-Driving Data Is Redacted</h2>



<p>It would be helpful to have the official crash narratives for context. The NHTSA requires that automobile manufacturers and self-driving technology providers offer that context in their governmental crash reporting.</p>



<p>Tesla is unique in that they request all of their narrative data be redacted, along with many other data points, citing “confidential business information” or “personally identifiable information” about the victim.</p>



<p><strong>Learn more about that here:</strong> <a href="https://fuelarc.com/tech/redacted-tesla-asked-for-redactions-on-every-self-driving-crash-reported-to-the-nhtsa-since-2021/">Tesla Asked for Redactions on Every Self-Driving Crash Reported to the NHTSA Since 2021</a></p>



<p>This limits journalists’ ability to see the full picture behind these crashes and what might be causing them.</p>



<p>Speaking of investigations… why did the Department of Government Efficiency (DOGE) <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/us/doge-cuts-nearly-half-unit-overseeing-autonomous-vehicles-safety-washington-post-2025-02-21/">cut the NHTSA’s self-driving safety office staff by almost half</a>? Why cut back on the small office capable of investigating Tesla’s unredacted safety data? Seems like an odd place to start cutting costs.</p>



<p>Anyway, here is how we constructed our study.</p>



<h3><strong>A Note on Methodology</strong></h3>



<p>To be included in the NHTSA’s self-driving crash reporting, known as the “<a href="https://www.nhtsa.gov/laws-regulations/standing-general-order-crash-reporting">Standing General Order,</a>” the car’s self-driving technology must have been active within 30 seconds of the crash.</p>



<p>We don’t have access to internal Tesla data, which could tell us whether self-driving was still active at the moment of impact. We can only infer from what we do have. </p>



<p>This is good and bad: bad in that it is not as granular as we would like, but good in that it is standardized. Every manufacturer is held to the same standard.</p>



<p>For the rest, we’ve tracked down each crash in local news reporting. Read those narratives below.</p>



<h2><strong>Filling in Tesla’s Self-Driving Crash Redactions with Press Coverage</strong></h2>



<p>It’s hard to hide the truth in the 21st century. We have city names and months for each fatal motorcycle crash involving a Tesla in self-driving mode. Most of the other significant data is redacted at Tesla Inc’s request, but I’ve done more with less. That’s enough to start connecting the dots with public news reports and police reports.</p>



<p>Below, I’ve linked publicly available reporting for each case to support our conclusions above. The details are distressing, so if you’d rather avoid reading about fatal car accidents, <a href="#engineering">skip ahead to my conclusions</a>.</p>



<h3>April 2024, Snohomish WA:</h3>



<p><strong>NHTSA Report ID 13781-7567.</strong></p>



<p>The self-driving subject vehicle is a 2022 Tesla Model S. The Tesla fatally struck a motorcyclist from behind in low-speed stop and go traffic on a highway near Seattle.</p>



<p>The driver reports that he was looking at his cellphone with his Tesla’s Full-Self Driving mode engaged. Allegedly, the driver heard a bang, his Tesla suddenly accelerated, and he struck the unmoving motorcyclist in front of him from behind, pinning the motorcyclist under the Tesla.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/31/tesla-in-crash-that-killed-motorcyclist-was-using-self-driving-system-authorities-say.html">https://www.cnbc.com/2024/07/31/tesla-in-crash-that-killed-motorcyclist-was-using-self-driving-system-authorities-say.html</a></p>



<p>Interestingly, the Washington State Highway Patrol determined that Full-Self Driving was active not from a governmental collaboration with the NHTSA or similar, but by downloading the data directly from the Tesla’s computer after seeking a warrant.</p>



<p>The driver was arrested for vehicular homicide, due to being distracted by his cellphone. Documents here with witness statements in the police reports:</p>



<p><a href="https://www.opb.org/article/2025/01/15/tesla-may-face-less-accountability-for-crashes-under-trump">https://www.opb.org/article/2025/01/15/tesla-may-face-less-accountability-for-crashes-under-trump</a></p>



<p>Of further interest, the Tesla feature to brake after a crash has occurred (automatic emergency braking) can be disengaged by pressing the accelerator pedal. The Tesla’s onboard data reports that the accelerator pedal was pressed 95-100% continuously for 10 seconds after the collision. A witness reports that the Tesla’s front wheels were spinning while up in the air, which means that no brake was being applied, even after the impact where the motorcyclist was pinned beneath the vehicle.</p>



<p>This is a tragically easy mistake to make, for a driver dazed and confused in a crash situation. It’s amazing that no technical system enforces braking in a more difficult-to-override way when sensors detect a crash has occurred.</p>



<h3>August 2023, Green Cove Springs FL:</h3>



<p><strong>NHTSA Report ID 13781-6205.</strong></p>



<p>The self-driving subject vehicle is a 2023 Tesla Model Y. Details are extremely scant, just what is unredacted in the NHTSA reporting. I really wish we had access to the unredacted data!</p>



<p>This one, I do not include in our fatality totals. The injury severity was reported to the NHTSA as “unknown.” The airbags on the Tesla deployed during a crash involving a motorcycle, which is consistent with serious or fatal injuries to motorcycle riders, but we just can’t know for sure with the data redactions.</p>



<p>I couldn’t find any local news coverage for the crash in rural Florida in several hours of trying. If anybody knows more about this case, please let me know on the <a href="https://fuelarc.com/contact/">Contact</a> page!</p>



<p>I include this case to point out: there are countless Tesla self-driving crashes where the data is so heavily redacted that it is simply not possible to tell what is going on. That’s why I say there are “at least 5” self-driving Tesla accidents that have killed motorcyclists, I highly suspect that some of those “unknown” or redacted data points are motorcycle crashes.</p>



<h3>August 2022, Boca Raton FL:</h3>



<p><strong>NHTSA Report ID 13781-3713.</strong></p>



<p>The self-driving subject vehicle is a 2020 Tesla Model 3. The Tesla fatally struck a motorcyclist from behind at above 100MPH on a 45MPH speed limit road in suburban Boca Raton. The motorcyclist was properly stopping at a yellow light, according to police reports.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.palmbeachpost.com/story/news/crime/2025/02/12/boca-raton-attorney-richard-dorfman-who-killed-motorcyclist-ingrid-noon-tesla-gets-2-year-plea-deal/78411624007">https://www.palmbeachpost.com/story/news/crime/2025/02/12/boca-raton-attorney-richard-dorfman-who-killed-motorcyclist-ingrid-noon-tesla-gets-2-year-plea-deal/78411624007</a></p>



<p>The driver was arrested for vehicular homicide and DUI manslaughter charges just under a year after the fatal crash. He plead guilty, reducing a potential sentence of 30 years to just 2 years in prison. In his guilty plea, he specified that he was relying on Tesla’s self-driving technology while intoxicated.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.cnn.com/2022/10/17/business/tesla-motorcycle-crashes-autopilot/index.html">https://www.cnn.com/2022/10/17/business/tesla-motorcycle-crashes-autopilot/index.html</a></p>



<p>You might wonder how a vehicle with self-driving technology was traveling more than double the speed limit into a yellow light with a motorcyclist braking in front of them. This <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/teslamotors/comments/p6m2q9/advanced_autopilot_question_what_does_the/">Reddit thread explains the feature</a>. </p>



<p>Certain Tesla self-driving technologies are speed capped, but others are not. Simply pressing the accelerator will raise your speed in certain modes, and as we saw in the police filings from the Washington State case, pressing the accelerator also cancels emergency braking. </p>



<p>That’s how you would strike a motorcyclist at such extreme speed, simply press the accelerator and all other inputs are apparently overridden.</p>



<h3>July 2022, Bluffdale UT:</h3>



<p><strong>NHTSA Report ID 13781-3488.</strong></p>



<p>The self-driving subject vehicle is a 2020 Tesla Model 3. The Tesla fatally struck a motorcyclist from behind on a Utah highway. Final speed of the Tesla prior to crashing into the motorcyclist was reported to the NHTSA was 61MPH.</p>



<p><a href="https://kjzz.com/news/local/motorcyclist-dies-after-being-hit-by-tesla-reportedly-on-autopilot">https://kjzz.com/news/local/motorcyclist-dies-after-being-hit-by-tesla-reportedly-on-autopilot</a></p>



<p>The driver reports that they did not see the motorcyclist, which will sound immediately familiar to any of my readers who are motorcyclists. As is typical in fatal motorcycle crashes with no exacerbating human factors like alcohol or distraction, we could find no record that charges were filed.</p>



<p>This accident was probed by the NHTSA’s investigation teams.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.insurancejournal.com/news/midwest/2022/08/08/679062.htm">https://www.insurancejournal.com/news/midwest/2022/08/08/679062.htm</a></p>



<h3>April 2022, reported to the NHTSA as an unknown city in Florida:</h3>



<p><strong>NHTSA Report ID 13781-3470.</strong></p>



<p>The self-driving subject vehicle is a 2020 Tesla Model Y.</p>



<p>I can find literally zero news reporting on this fatal accident involving a Tesla self-driving vehicle, so we need to rely on the NHTSA data to assemble the narrative. It’s starting to become apparent why this data is so heavily redacted, connecting the dots is difficult!</p>



<p>The Tesla was traveling straight on a highway when it was involved in a fatal crash with a motorcycle. No further details are available. This is the only motorcycle fatality reported to the NHTSA where we are not certain that they were rear-ended by the Tesla.</p>



<p>The address of the crash was redacted as “[MAY CONTAIN PERSONALLY IDENTIFIABLE INFORMATION]” which limits our ability to locate the narrative details.</p>



<h3>July 2022, Riverside CA:</h3>



<p><strong>NHTSA Report ID 13781-3332.</strong></p>



<p>The self-driving subject vehicle is a 2021 Tesla Model Y. The Tesla fatally struck a motorcyclist from behind in the HOV lane on a California freeway.</p>



<p><a href="https://techxplore.com/news/2022-08-agency-probes-tesla-motorcyclists.html">https://techxplore.com/news/2022-08-agency-probes-tesla-motorcyclists.html</a></p>



<p>This is an alarmingly common trend in our analysis. Not an edge-case, no difficult weather or lighting conditions, simply a self-driving Tesla killing a motorcyclist by rear-ending them at speed.</p>



<p>This accident was probed by the NHTSA’s investigation teams.</p>



<p><a href="https://www.insurancejournal.com/news/midwest/2022/08/08/679062.htm">https://www.insurancejournal.com/news/midwest/2022/08/08/679062.htm</a></p>







<h2>Engineering Failures and Human Error Cascade to Cause Fatal Self-Driving Accidents</h2>



<p>Self-driving Teslas developed such a reputation for ramming into parked emergency vehicles from behind that the <a href="https://static.nhtsa.gov/odi/rcl/2023/RCLRPT-23V838-8276.PDF">NHTSA launched an investigation in 2022</a>. Confusingly, the NHTSA is <em>currently </em>investigating whether the subsequent recall was effective. What the agency uncovered through close analysis of the unredacted self-driving crash data went far beyond firetrucks and police cruisers.</p>



<p>As part of its review, the Office of Defects Investigation (ODI) at the NHTSA found that Teslas had a general tendency to experience “frontal plane crashes.” Essentially, driving straight into obstacles in their path. </p>



<p>The issue wasn’t limited to emergency vehicles. Teslas using self-driving software were crashing into all sorts of things: barriers, stopped cars, <em>and motorcycles</em>.</p>



<p>The NHTSA extensively reviewed Tesla’s self-driving crash data, which it has unredacted access to. The findings? A vast majority of these crashes occurred in situations where a visible hazard should have been detected and avoided well before impact.</p>



<h4>Self-Driving Teslas Have Plenty of Time to Avoid Frontal-Plane Crashes… They Just Don’t</h4>



<p>Here’s a telling table from <a href="https://static.nhtsa.gov/odi/rcl/2023/RCLRPT-23V838-8276.PDF">the NHTSA report</a>, showing that <strong>fully 93% of hazards</strong> in crashes would have been visible to a human in time to either avoid the accident entirely or at least take action to mitigate the severity of the accident:</p>



<figure><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="624" height="207" src="https://fuelarc.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/frontal-plane-visible-hazard-table.png" alt="" srcset="https://fuelarc.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/frontal-plane-visible-hazard-table.png 624w, https://fuelarc.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/04/frontal-plane-visible-hazard-table-300x100.png 300w" sizes="(max-width: 624px) 100vw, 624px"></figure>



<p>The government’s report has this damning quote, couched in dense bureaucratic language:</p>



<blockquote>
<p>“In certain circumstances when Autosteer is engaged, if a driver misuses the SAE Level 2 advanced driver-assistance feature such that they fail to maintain continuous and sustained responsibility for vehicle operation and are unprepared to intervene, fail to recognize when the feature is canceled or not engaged, and/or fail to recognize when the feature is operating in situations where its functionality may be limited, there may be an increased risk of a collision.”</p>
</blockquote>



<p>In the case of the motorcycle crashes, the pattern is clear: Tesla’s self-driving technology either fails to detect the motorcyclist or does not apply the brakes once the motorcycle is detected. The human driver, meanwhile, is responsible for stepping in and braking manually… a task they fail to complete, because they are not paying attention, a situation which the Tesla’s attention detection system has also failed to recognize. When both the technology and the human backup fail, the result is a fatal collision.</p>



<p>This is a natural <em>and enragingly obvious</em> outcropping of Level 2 self-driving technology. <em>Of course</em> drivers will get bored of watching their car drive itself for hours on end. Simply having a hand on the wheel is not a sufficient measure of the driver paying attention, and Tesla’s other technical measures apparently do not work reliably. Motorcyclists pay for that stupid design decision with their lives.</p>



<h2>Watch a Tesla Freak Out in FSD Mode Behind a Motorcyclist</h2>



<p>Sometimes, seeing the technology in action helps illustrate what’s going wrong. In this video, a Tesla running a recent version of its <em>unfortunately named </em>“Full Self-Driving” (FSD) software behaves erratically when following a motorcycle.</p>



<figure><p>
<iframe title="Did Tesla FSD v12.3.6 Forget How to Drive Behind a Motorcycle?! Very Weird..." width="800" height="450" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0G6dofV3Jh8?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p></figure>



<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0G6dofV3Jh8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch the clip here.</a></p>



<p>The Tesla appears to struggle with maintaining a consistent follow distance. At times, it leaves an absurdly long gap between itself and the motorbike, which could be an indication that the system is compensating for weak sensor performance when detecting range on motorcycles.</p>



<p>The video creator even calls attention to the odd behavior, and the comment section is full of people reporting similar experiences… along with the usual Tesla defenders who downplay or dismiss the issue, or attack the video as a fraud. Whether those defenders are diehard fans, bots, or a mix of both is up for debate.</p>



<p>The bottom line? Tesla’s self-driving technology has serious issues with detecting and responding safely to motorcycles. When the system struggles, it leaves human drivers to pick up the slack when they have been lulled into inattention by a false sense of competency from the self-driving system. That’s a deadly combination, as evidenced by five (or more) fatal Tesla collisions with motorcyclists.</p>



<p>Of course, all of us are watching Tesla’s planned rollout of self-driving taxis <em>with no human driver</em>, <a href="https://x.com/elonmusk/status/1906727530607808546">slated for Austin in less than 60 days</a>. If you’re a motorcycle rider like me, you might avoid the city limits of Austin TX for a minute, just to see how things shake out.</p>
				</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How the Atlantic's Jeffrey Goldberg Got Added to the White House Signal Chat (119 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/06/signal-group-chat-leak-how-it-happened</link>
            <guid>43601213</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 13:12:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/06/signal-group-chat-leak-how-it-happened">https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/06/signal-group-chat-leak-how-it-happened</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43601213">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p><a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/donaldtrump" data-link-name="in body link">Donald Trump</a>’s national security adviser Mike Waltz included a journalist in the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/signal-group-chat-leak" data-link-name="in body link">Signal group chat</a> about plans for US strikes in Yemen after he mistakenly saved his number months before under the contact of someone else he intended to add, according to three people briefed on the matter.</p><p>The mistake was one of several missteps that came to light in the White House’s internal <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/03/pete-hegseth-signal-chat-dod-investigation" data-link-name="in body link">investigation</a>, which showed a series of compounding slips that started during the 2024 campaign and went unnoticed until Waltz created the group chat last month.</p><p>Trump briefly considered firing Waltz over the episode, more angered by the fact that Waltz had the number of <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/mar/27/who-is-jeffrey-goldberg-atlantic-signal-chat-leak" data-link-name="in body link">Jeffrey Goldberg</a>, the editor of the Atlantic – a magazine he despises – than the fact that the military operation discussion took place on an unclassified system such as Signal.</p><figure id="bba94387-2f9c-4a24-bcef-61ab5a98123a" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:3,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Trump fires six national security staffers after meeting with far-right activist Laura Loomer&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;bba94387-2f9c-4a24-bcef-61ab5a98123a&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/03/laura-loomer-trump-meeting&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;design&quot;:0,&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0}}"></gu-island></figure><p>But <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/mar/27/trump-fire-waltz-signal-atlantic-leak" data-link-name="in body link">Trump decided against firing him</a> in large part because he did not want the Atlantic and the news media more broadly to have the satisfaction of forcing the ouster of a top cabinet official weeks into his second term. Trump was also mollified by the findings of the internal investigation.</p><p>The disclosures nonetheless triggered a “forensic review” by the White House information technology office, which found that Waltz’s phone had saved Goldberg’s number as part of an unlikely series of events that started when Goldberg emailed the Trump campaign last October.</p><p>According to three people briefed on the internal investigation, Goldberg had emailed the campaign about a story that criticized Trump for his attitude towards wounded service members. To push back against the story, the campaign enlisted the help of Waltz, their national security surrogate.</p><p>Goldberg’s email was forwarded to then Trump spokesperson Brian Hughes, who then copied and pasted the content of the email – including the signature block with Goldberg’s phone number – into a text message that he sent to Waltz, so that he could be briefed on the forthcoming story.</p><p>Waltz did not ultimately call Goldberg, the people said, but in an extraordinary twist, inadvertently ended up saving Goldberg’s number in his iPhone – under the contact card for Hughes, now the spokesperson for the national security council.</p><p>A day after that <a href="https://www.theatlantic.com/politics/archive/2024/10/trump-military-generals-hitler/680327/" data-link-name="in body link">Goldberg story was published</a>, on 22 October, Waltz appeared on CNN to defend Trump. “Don’t take it from me, take it from the 13 Abbey Gate Gold Star families, some of whom stood on a stage in front of a 30,000 person crowd and said how he helped them heal,” Waltz said.</p><p>According to the White House, the number was erroneously saved during a “contact suggestion update” by Waltz’s iPhone, which one person described as the function where an iPhone algorithm adds a previously unknown number to an existing contact that it detects may be related.</p><p>The mistake went unnoticed until last month when Waltz sought to add Hughes to the Signal group chat – but ended up adding Goldberg’s number to the 13 March message chain named “Houthi PC small group”, where several top US officials discussed plans for strikes against the Houthis.</p><p>Waltz said in the immediate aftermath of the incident that he had never met or communicated with Goldberg. He also suggested on Fox News that Goldberg’s number had been “sucked” into his phone, seemingly in reference to how his iPhone had saved Goldberg’s number.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-13">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-13" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>The White House did not comment on this story, and the investigation did not resolve the extent of Waltz’s relationship with Goldberg, if any. Reached by phone on Saturday, Goldberg said: “I’m not going to comment on my relationship with Mike Waltz beyond saying I do know him and have spoken to him.”</p><figure id="9a921bb7-7ce1-4c0e-931f-a29319abbbf1" data-spacefinder-role="richLink" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement"><gu-island name="RichLinkComponent" priority="feature" deferuntil="idle" props="{&quot;richLinkIndex&quot;:15,&quot;element&quot;:{&quot;_type&quot;:&quot;model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.RichLinkBlockElement&quot;,&quot;prefix&quot;:&quot;Related: &quot;,&quot;text&quot;:&quot;Mike Waltz’s team set up at least 20 Signal chats for national security work – report&quot;,&quot;elementId&quot;:&quot;9a921bb7-7ce1-4c0e-931f-a29319abbbf1&quot;,&quot;role&quot;:&quot;richLink&quot;,&quot;url&quot;:&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/apr/02/trump-mike-waltz-signal-groups&quot;},&quot;ajaxUrl&quot;:&quot;https://api.nextgen.guardianapps.co.uk&quot;,&quot;format&quot;:{&quot;design&quot;:0,&quot;display&quot;:0,&quot;theme&quot;:0}}"></gu-island></figure><p>Trump was briefed on the findings of the forensic review last week around the time he decided to keep Waltz, a person familiar with the matter said. Trump accepted Waltz’s mea culpa and has <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/us-news/2025/mar/29/trump-signalgate-media-lapse-us-administration" data-link-name="in body link">publicly defended him</a> in recent weeks since the group chat situation became public.</p><p>When Trump left the White House on Thursday, he was joined aboard Marine One by his chief of staff, Susie Wiles, his personnel chief, Sergio Gor, and Waltz, which aides took as a show of support for the embattled national security adviser.</p><p>Waltz also appears to have also engendered some sympathy from inside Trump’s orbit over the group chat because the White House had authorized the use of Signal, largely because there is no alternative platform to text in real time across different agencies, two people familiar with the matter said.</p><p>Previous administrations, including the Biden White House, did not develop an alternative platform to Signal, one of the people said. As a temporary solution, the Trump White House told officials to use Signal as they had done during the transition instead of regular text-message chains.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Neutron Stars Hint at Another Dimension (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nautil.us/neutron-stars-hint-at-another-dimension-1202180/</link>
            <guid>43600704</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 11:41:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nautil.us/neutron-stars-hint-at-another-dimension-1202180/">https://nautil.us/neutron-stars-hint-at-another-dimension-1202180/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43600704">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                        
            <p><span>I</span>n the mid 19th century, a strange idea was growing heavy in the ether: There might be dimensions beyond the three we experience. To some—including eminent scientists of the day—these were the realms of spirits and the supernatural, accessed through tabletop seances. To Charles Hinton, a British mathematician and science-fiction writer at the time, it was something that could be puzzled out, modeled in things like his “tesseract” four-dimensional cube.</p>
      
    <p>In the intervening century and a half, spiritualism and mainstream science having parted ways, the serious search for these extra dimensions has only intensified. Lately, physicists have proposed a new way to “see” into a new dimension—by looking deep into the hearts of collapsed, dead stars that have been behaving strangely.</p><p>The concerted scientific journey into extra dimensions began with Hermann Minkowski, Einstein’s former teacher, who realized that “space by itself, and time by itself, have vanished into the merest shadows” and that only a unification of them, spacetime, exists. Spacetime means that the universe truly is four-dimensional, just that one of the dimensions is that of time, rather than an additional one of space. One extra dimension discovered.</p><p>But might there be more?</p>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div><p>Beginning in the middle of the 20th century, scientists began to speculate that there might indeed be more to the universe. And that speculation was born from an unlikely source: the astounding weakness of gravity.</p><blockquote><p>If the “braneworld” hypothesis is true, then we have no idea just how magnificent the universe is.</p></blockquote><p>The force of gravity is weak. And not just a little bit weak. It’s so much weaker than the other three fundamental forces—electromagnetism and the strong and weak nuclear forces—that it’s almost impossible to provide analogies. Gravity could be a trillion trillion times stronger than it is, and it would still be the weakest of the forces by many orders of magnitude.</p><p>The origin of the strengths of the fundamental forces of nature remains an outstanding problem in physics. We don’t know why electromagnetism has the strength that it does, why the strong force is so strong, and why the weak force is so weak. But gravity sticks out like a sore thumb. All the other forces may be weaker or stronger than the others, but they’re at least in the same ballpark. Gravity isn’t even on the same planet.</p>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div><p>The thinking goes that if we can understand why gravity is so especially weak, we might be able to use that as a way to discern why the other forces are so strong.</p><p>And maybe the answer lies in an extra dimension.</p><p>In 1999, theoretical physicists Lisa Randall and Raman Sundrum proposed a wild restructuring of the cosmos. In their model, what we call the universe is really a “brane”—a three-dimensional expansion of our usual conceptions of a membrane.</p><p>But our brane is not the entire universe. In their model, it’s embedded in something much larger, dubbed the “bulk.” The bulk has an extra spatial dimension, and our brane universe floats along inside of it like a piece of paper caught in the ocean currents. We can’t see the bulk, touch the bulk, experience the bulk, or otherwise interact with the bulk because our entire universe—all the particles and forces of nature—are restricted to life on the brane.<strong> </strong>It stretches the mind in a way that’s almost a throwback to the early days of the search for an extra dimension—when, in 1884, Edwin Abbot published his satirical book <em>Flatland: A Romance of Many Dimensions</em>, in which geometric figures inhabit a <a href="https://nautil.us/the-case-for-fewer-dimensions-235645/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">two-dimensional universe</a> that is rocked when a sphere, a three-dimensional object, intersects with their world.</p>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div><figure><img width="800" height="460" alt="In Body Image" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/CC7cdY2m-Sutter_BREAKER.png?auto=compress&amp;fit=scale&amp;fm=png&amp;h=589&amp;ixlib=php-3.3.1&amp;w=1024&amp;wpsize=large" srcset="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/CC7cdY2m-Sutter_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1600 800w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/CC7cdY2m-Sutter_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1200 600w,https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/CC7cdY2m-Sutter_BREAKER.png?q=65&amp;auto=format&amp;w=800 400w" loading="lazy"><figcaption><strong>WEIRD VIBRATIONS:&nbsp;</strong>Neutron stars’ super-strong jets of radiation might be made narrower by an additional dimension we haven’t otherwise been able to detect. A new X-ray telescope from the European Space Agency might reveal more. <em>Image by ART-ur / Shutterstock.</em></figcaption></figure><p>The brane-bulk model is a speculative idea for sure, but a fun one. Like the beleaguered citizens of Flatland, if the “braneworld” hypothesis is true, then we have no idea just how magnificent the true extent of the universe is.</p><p>And so it’s worth finding ways to investigate whether this literally outside-the-box idea has any merit—to find if we can poke our heads into the fifth dimension. Physicists just need some way to pierce the veil of the brane and peer into the realm of the bulk. To try this, they have enlisted gravity.</p><p>Gravity, the thinking goes, can escape our brane and extend into the bulk. That explains why it’s so weak. All the other forces must play in only three spatial dimensions, while gravity can extend itself out to four, spreading itself much too thin in the process.</p>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div><p>Physicists can try to peek into the extra dimensions of the bulk at tiny scales using experiments that can fit on a tabletop—granted in setups much different than 19th-century spiritualists’ gatherings. These exquisite devices test the strength of Earth’s gravity as microscopic objects move over minute distances. They then compare the movements of those particles to see if there are any deviations from the gravitational phenomena predicted by Einstein’s theory of general relativity. So far, no evidence for extra dimensions <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1805.03082" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">has emerged from those experiments</a>.</p><p>So other physicists have turned away from the tabletop and to the stars for answers. Specifically, <a href="https://nautil.us/the-inside-of-a-neutron-star-looks-spookily-familiar-235699/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">neutron stars</a>. These are the ultra-dense leftover cores of giant stars. This tremendous density makes them excellent laboratories for studying gravity under extreme conditions, where it might crack open our historical models.</p><p>If our running knowledge of gravity is mistaken, and our universe is really a brane floating in the bulk, then it might just show up in ever-so-slight differences in the behavior of neutron stars. This is because the brane-bulk interaction might change how gravity is working, ever so slightly—but just enough for us to detect it in those extreme environments.</p><blockquote><p>Neutron stars are perhaps the most exotic objects in the entire universe known so far.</p></blockquote>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div><p>In particular, the extra dimension could make itself known by supplying an extra source of energy, something that physicists have dubbed “dark radiation,” and an extra source of pressure, called “dark pressure.” Dark radiation acts like an invisible form of light that can carry and transport energy; dark pressure is an extra source of support against the usual inward pull of gravity. Both of these appear as terms in the modified equations of gravity, additions that are absent in our usual conceptions of general relativity, our current best treatment of the gravitational force.</p><p>Which brings us back to neutron stars. Neutron stars are perhaps the most exotic objects in the entire universe known so far—rivaling even black holes. They are best described as atoms the size of cities, composed of ultra-dense nuclear matter compressed into even more incomprehensible densities. A single teaspoonful of neutron star guts would outweigh the Great Pyramid at Giza. Their gravities are so strong that they can force light to orbit around them. If the twin phantoms of dark radiation and dark pressure from the additional dimension are in fact changing how gravity works, it could influence how compact neutron stars can be, how efficiently they radiate heat, and even the arrangement of their internal composition. Which would be helpful because some neutron stars seem to be acting in odd, unexpected ways.</p><p>In 2019, the LIGO detector, a pair of kilometer-long laser interferometers in Louisiana and Washington, measured gravitational waves emanating from the merger of a black hole with … something else. The black hole had a mass of around 23 solar masses. Its companion had a mass of only 2.6 solar masses. That’s far too small to be a black hole … but also a little too big to be a neutron star. Which sent physicists searching for an explanation for the massiveness of the other, mysterious object.</p><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2501.10730" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Recent calculations have shown</a> that an extra dimension, in the form of bulk, can potentially explain the extra heft of that companion. It’s not a slam-dunk case, but it is an intriguing hint.</p>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div><p>Other recent observations of binary neutron star systems have revealed odd fluctuations in brightness that are almost, <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/308/3/718/973461" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">but not quite</a>, perfectly regular. While researchers think that the complex gravitational interaction between the neutron stars and the material surrounding them gives rise to these almost-periodic fluctuations, they haven’t been able to pin down the exact cause. Some theorists have proposed that it is nothing less than the brane-bulk interaction that changes gravity just enough to create <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/0812.0720" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">this off-beat rhythm</a>.</p><p>And even beyond gravity, other forces might also be giving hints of this extra dimension. Neutron stars can host the strongest magnetic fields in the known universe, boasting strengths up to quadrillions of times greater than the Earth’s field. These magnetic fields are strong enough to literally rip apart anything that wanders too close. As the neutron star rotates, the spinning super-strong magnetic field creates an electric field, which spirals into a beam of radiation that jets out of the axis of the star. Physicists discovered that the braneworld would <a href="https://www.worldscientific.com/doi/abs/10.1142/S0218271819501281#:~:text=Rev.%20D96%20(2017)%20104001%5D%20show%20that%20the,magnetized%20neutron%20star%2C%20in%20particular%20at%20the" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">weaken the interplay</a> of magnetic and electric fields enough to lower their strength, leading to a narrower beam of radiation. While this particular hypothesis hasn’t been tested yet, it could be soon with a new X-ray telescope from the European Space Agency.</p><p>This effect cannot be replicated in the laboratory, as attempts to create magnetic fields even billions of times weaker than these make all of our equipment melt. So physicists will continue to keep their eyes on the stars for a window into an extra dimension. <img decoding="async" src="https://assets.nautil.us/sites/3/nautilus/nautilus-favicon-14.png?fm=png" alt=""></p><p><em>Lead image: Jurik Peter / Shutterstock</em></p>
          <div>
            <p>ADVERTISEMENT</p>
            
            
      <p>
        Nautilus Members enjoy an ad-free experience. 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/concierge-login" data-ev-act="login" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Log in
        </a> 
        or 
        <a href="https://nautil.us/join" data-ev-act="subscribe" data-ev-cat="article-ad" data-ev-label="in body ad">
          Join now
        </a>.
      </p>
          </div>              
                            <ul>
                                      <li>
                      <div>
                        <h6>
                          Paul M. Sutter                        </h6>
                        <p>
                          Posted on <time datetime="2025-04-04T15:51:33-05:00">April 4, 2025</time>
                        </p>
                      </div>
                                                <p>
                            Paul M. Sutter is a research professor in astrophysics at the Institute for Advanced Computational Science at Stony Brook University and a guest researcher at the Flatiron Institute in New York City. He is the author of <i>Your Place in the Universe: Understanding our Big, Messy Existence.</i>                          </p>
                                            </li>
                                  </ul>
            <div>
  <p><img src="https://nautil.us/wp-content/themes/nautilus-block-theme/images/icons/logo-icon.svg" alt="new_letter"></p><div>
    <h4>Get the Nautilus newsletter</h4>
    <p>Cutting-edge science, unraveled by the very brightest living thinkers.</p>
  </div>

  
</div>        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The "S" in MCP Stands for Security (463 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://elenacross7.medium.com/%EF%B8%8F-the-s-in-mcp-stands-for-security-91407b33ed6b</link>
            <guid>43600192</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 09:42:28 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://elenacross7.medium.com/%EF%B8%8F-the-s-in-mcp-stands-for-security-91407b33ed6b">https://elenacross7.medium.com/%EF%B8%8F-the-s-in-mcp-stands-for-security-91407b33ed6b</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43600192">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://elenacross7.medium.com/%EF%B8%8F-the-s-in-mcp-stands-for-security-91407b33ed6b: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[SeedLM: Compressing LLM Weights into Seeds of Pseudo-Random Generators (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/seedlm-compressing</link>
            <guid>43599967</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 08:53:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/seedlm-compressing">https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/seedlm-compressing</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43599967">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main"><div><p><span>Authors</span>Rasoul Shafipour, David Harrison, Maxwell Horton, Jeffrey Marker, Houman Bedayat, Sachin Mehta†, Mohammad Rastegari†, Mahyar Najibi, Saman Naderiparizi</p></div><div><p>Large Language Models (LLMs) have transformed natural language processing, but face significant challenges in widespread deployment due to their high runtime cost. In this paper, we introduce SeedLM, a novel post-training compression method that uses seeds of a pseudo-random generator to encode and compress model weights. Specifically, for each block of weights, we
find a seed that is fed into a Linear Feedback Shift Register (LFSR) during inference to efficiently generate a random matrix. This matrix is then linearly combined with compressed coefficients to reconstruct the weight block. SeedLM reduces memory access and leverages idle compute cycles during inference, effectively speeding up memory-bound tasks by trading compute for fewer memory accesses. Unlike state-of-the-art methods that rely on calibration data, our approach is data-free and generalizes well across diverse tasks. Our experiments with
Llama3 70B, which is particularly challenging, show zero-shot accuracy retention at 4- and  3-bit compression to be on par with or better than state-of-the-art methods, while maintaining performance comparable to FP16 baselines. Additionally, FPGA-based tests demonstrate that 4-bit SeedLM, as model size increases, approaches a 4x speed-up over an FP16 Llama 2/3 baseline.</p>
<p>† Meta</p></div><section><p><h2>Related readings and updates.</h2></p><div><div data-testid="card-compress-compare"><p>*Equal Contributors
To deploy machine learning models on-device, practitioners use compression algorithms to shrink and speed up models while maintaining their high-quality output. A critical aspect of compression in practice is model comparison, including tracking many compression experiments, identifying subtle changes in model behavior, and negotiating complex accuracy-efficiency trade-offs. However, existing compression tools poorly support…</p><p><a href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/compress-compare" aria-label="See full paper details regarding Compress and Compare: Interactively Evaluating Efficiency and Behavior Across ML Model Compression Experiments">See paper details</a></p></div><div data-testid="card-lossless-compression"><p>This paper was accepted at the ICML 2021 conference as well as the Theory and Practice of Differential Privacy workshop at the ICML 2021 conference.
Locally Differentially Private (LDP) Reports are commonly used for collection of statistics and machine learning in the federated setting. In many cases the best known LDP algorithms require sending prohibitively large messages from the client device to the server (such as when constructing…</p><p><a href="https://machinelearning.apple.com/research/lossless-compression" aria-label="See full paper details regarding Lossless Compression of Efficient Private Local Randomizers">See paper details</a></p></div></div></section></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Video footage appears to contradict Israeli account of Gaza medic killings (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g2z103nqxo</link>
            <guid>43599864</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 08:32:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g2z103nqxo">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c4g2z103nqxo</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43599864">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-component="text-block"><p>Mobile phone footage has emerged that appears to contradict Israel's account of why soldiers opened fire on a convoy of ambulances and a fire truck on March 23, <!-- --><a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/crkxm1rg6k1o">killing 15 rescue workers<!-- --></a>. <!-- --></p><p>The video, published by the Palestine Red Crescent Society (PRCS), shows the vehicles moving in darkness with headlights and emergency flashing lights switched on - before coming under fire. The PRCS said the video was obtained from the phone of a paramedic who was killed.<!-- --></p><p>The Israel Defense Forces (IDF) initially denied the vehicles had their headlights or emergency signals on. <!-- --></p></div><div data-component="text-block"><p>But in response to the new video, the IDF told the BBC: "All claims, including the documentation circulating about the incident, will be thoroughly and deeply examined to understand the sequence of events and the handling of the situation".<!-- --></p><p>A surviving paramedic previously <!-- --><a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/ckgere1y740o">told the BBC<!-- --></a> that the ambulances were clearly marked and had their internal and external lights on. <!-- --></p><p>The latest video, which the PRCS said had been shown to the UN Security Council, shows the marked vehicles drawing to a halt on the edge of the road, lights still flashing, and at least two emergency workers stepping out wearing reflective clothing.<!-- --></p><p>The windscreen of the vehicle being filmed from is cracked and shooting can then be heard lasting for several minutes as the person filming says prayers. He is understood to be one of the dead paramedics.<!-- --></p><p>The footage was found on his phone after his body was recovered from a shallow grave one week after the incident. The bodies of the eight paramedics, six Gaza Civil Defence workers and one UN employee were found buried in sand, along with their wrecked vehicles. It took international organisations days to negotiate safe access to the site.<!-- --></p><p>Israel claimed a number of Hamas and Islamic Jihad militants had been killed in the incident, but it has not provided any evidence or further explained the threat to its troops.<!-- --></p><p>Israel's Foreign Minister Gideon Saar earlier this week echoed the army account, saying "the IDF did not randomly attack an ambulance".<!-- --></p><p>The IDF promised to investigate the circumstances after a surviving paramedic questioned its account. <!-- --></p><p>In an interview with the BBC, <!-- --><a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/articles/ckgere1y740o">paramedic Munther Abed said<!-- --></a>: "During day and at night, it's the same thing. External and internal lights are on. Everything tells you it's an ambulance vehicle that belongs to the Palestinian Red Crescent. All lights were on until the vehicle came under direct fire."<!-- --></p><p>He also denied he or his team had any militant connections.<!-- --></p><p>"All crews are civilian. We don't belong to any militant group. Our main duty is to offer ambulance services and save people's lives. No more, no less," he said.<!-- --></p><p>Speaking at the United Nations yesterday the President of the PRCS, Dr Younis Al-Khatib, referred to the video recording, saying: "I heard the voice of one of those team members who was killed. His last words before being shot…'forgive me mum, I just wanted to help people. I wanted to save lives'. It's heartbreaking".<!-- --></p><p>He called for "accountability" and "an "independent and thorough investigation" of what he called an "atrocious crime".<!-- --></p><p>One paramedic is still unaccounted for following the 23 March incident.<!-- --></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Standard Ebooks: liberated ebooks, carefully produced for the true book lover (859 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://standardebooks.org</link>
            <guid>43599637</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 06 Apr 2025 07:36:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://standardebooks.org">https://standardebooks.org</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43599637">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
	<h2>Free and liberated ebooks,<br> carefully produced for the true book lover.</h2>
	<picture>
		<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/devices@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/devices.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
		<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/devices@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/devices.png 1x" type="image/png">
		<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/devices@2x.png" alt="Ereaders with a Standard Ebook open.">
	</picture>
	<p>Standard Ebooks is a volunteer-driven project that produces new editions of public domain ebooks that are lovingly formatted, open source, free of U.S. copyright restrictions, and free of cost.</p>
	<p>Ebook projects like <a href="https://www.gutenberg.org/">Project Gutenberg</a> transcribe ebooks and make them available for the widest number of reading devices. Standard Ebooks takes ebooks from sources like Project Gutenberg, formats and typesets them using a carefully designed and professional-grade style manual, fully proofreads and corrects them, and then builds them to create a new edition that takes advantage of state-of-the-art ereader and browser technology.</p>
	<p>Standard Ebooks aren’t just a beautiful addition to your digital library—they’re a high quality standard to build your own ebooks on.</p><a href="https://standardebooks.org/ebooks">Browse our library of free ebooks</a>
	<section>
		<h2>What makes Standard Ebooks different?</h2>
		<section>
			<h3>Modern &amp; consistent typography</h3>
			<div>
				<div>
					<p>Other free ebooks don’t put much effort into professional-quality typography: they use "straight" quotes instead of “curly” quotes, they ignore details like em- and en-dashes, and they look more like early-90’s web pages instead of actual books.</p>
					<p>Standard Ebooks applies a rigorous and modern <a href="https://standardebooks.org/manual">style manual</a> when developing each and every ebook to ensure they meet a professional-grade and consistent typographical standard. Our ebooks look <em>good</em>.</p>
				</div>
				<figure>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-bad@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-bad.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-bad@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-bad.png 1x" type="image/png">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-bad@2x.png" alt="An example of bad typography." height="150" width="300">
					</picture>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-good@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-good.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/typography-good@2x.png" alt="An example of Standard Ebooks typography." height="150" width="300">
					</picture>
					<img alt="An arrow pointing from bad typography to good typography." src="https://standardebooks.org/images/arrow-down.png">
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
		<section>
			<h3>Full proofing with careful corrections</h3>
			<div>
				<div>
					<p>Transcriptions from other sources are often filled with typos or suffer from issues like inconsistent spelling, missing accent marks, or missing punctuation. Submitting corrections to such sources can be difficult or impossible, so errors are rarely fixed.</p>
					<p>At Standard Ebooks, we do a careful and complete readthrough of each ebook before releasing it, checking it against a scan of the original pages to fix as many typos as possible. Even if we <em>do</em> miss something, our ebooks are stored in the hugely popular Git source control system, allowing anyone to easily submit a correction.</p>
				</div>
				<figure>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/proofreading@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/proofreading.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/proofreading@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/proofreading.png 1x" type="image/png">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/proofreading@2x.png" alt="A text with proofreader’s marks." height="200" width="400">
					</picture>
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
		<section>
			<h3>Rich &amp; detailed metadata</h3>
			<div>
				<p>Our ebooks include complete, well-researched, and consistent metadata, including original, detailed book blurbs and links to encyclopedia sources. Perfect for machine processing or for extra-curious, technically-minded readers.</p>
				<figure>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/metadata@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/metadata.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/metadata@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/metadata.png 1x" type="image/png">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/metadata@2x.png" alt="Ebook metadata displayed in an ereader program." height="200" width="400">
					</picture>
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
		<section>
			<h3>State-of-the-art technology</h3>
			<div>
				<div>
					<p>Each Standard Ebook takes full advantage of the latest ereader technology, including:</p>
					<ul>
						<li>
							<p>Hyphenation support,</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>Popup footnotes,</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>High-resolution and scalable vector graphics,</p>
						</li>
						<li>
							<p>Ereader-compatible tables of contents,</p>
						</li>
					</ul>
					<p>and more. One of our goals is to ensure our ebooks stay up-to-date with the best reading experience technology can provide. Just because it’s a classic doesn’t mean it has to use old technology.</p>
				</div>
				<figure>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/endnote@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/endnote.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/endnote@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/endnote.png 1x" type="image/png">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/endnote@2x.png" alt="A screenshot of a popup endnote." height="150" width="300">
					</picture>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/toc@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/toc.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/toc@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/toc.png 1x" type="image/png">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/toc@2x.png" alt="A screenshot of an ebook’s table of contents." height="150" width="300">
					</picture>
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
		<section>
			<h3>Quality covers</h3>
			<div>
				<div>
					<p>Everyone knows a book is judged by its cover, but most free ebooks leave it to your ereader software to generate a drab default cover.</p>
					<p>Standard Ebooks draws from a vast collection of public domain fine art to create attractive, unique, appropriate, and consistent covers for each of our ebooks.</p>
				</div>
				<figure>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/covers@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/covers.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/covers@2x.jpg 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/covers.jpg 1x" type="image/jpg">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/covers@2x.jpg" alt="An ebookshelf featuring Standard Ebooks covers." height="125" width="400">
					</picture>
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
		<section>
			<h3>Clean code &amp; semantic markup</h3>
			<div>
				<div>
					<p>Our strict coding standards allow technologists and ebook producers to use Standard Ebooks files as reliable, easy to read, and robust bases for their own work—not to mention as models of what well-crafted ebook files look like. Common code patterns are repeated through different ebooks, so the code never surprises you.</p>
					<p>Each ebook is also enhanced with careful standards-based semantic markup that opens the gateway for exciting new kinds of machine processing.</p>
				</div>
				<figure>
					<picture>
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/code@2x.avif 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/code.avif 1x" type="image/avif">
						<source srcset="https://standardebooks.org/images/code@2x.png 2x, https://standardebooks.org/images/code.png 1x" type="image/png">
						<img src="https://standardebooks.org/images/code@2x.png" alt="The source code for an ebook." height="200" width="400">
					</picture>
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
		<section>
			<h3>Free, open-source, &amp; public domain</h3>
			<div>
				<div>
					<p>We use the popular Git source control system to track each and every change made to our ebooks. Anyone can easily see a history of changes, or contribute their own changes with the click of a mouse.</p>
					<p>And while all of the ebooks we feature and the cover art we draw from are <em>already</em> believed to be in the public domain in the U.S., Standard Ebooks releases all of the work we put in to each ebook into the public domain too. That makes each and every one of our ebook files not just free, but <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gratis_versus_libre">libre</a> too—because the world deserves more unrestricted culture.</p>
				</div>
				<figure>
					<img alt="The Git SCM logo." src="https://standardebooks.org/images/git.svg" height="150" width="150">
					<img alt="The no-copyright symbol." src="https://standardebooks.org/images/no-copyright.svg" height="150" width="150">
					<img alt="The anti-DRM symbol." src="https://standardebooks.org/images/no-drm.svg" height="137" width="150">
				</figure>
			</div>
		</section>
	</section>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple's Darwin OS and XNU Kernel Deep Dive (416 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tansanrao.com/blog/2025/04/xnu-kernel-and-darwin-evolution-and-architecture/</link>
            <guid>43597778</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 23:46:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tansanrao.com/blog/2025/04/xnu-kernel-and-darwin-evolution-and-architecture/">https://tansanrao.com/blog/2025/04/xnu-kernel-and-darwin-evolution-and-architecture/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43597778">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-astro-cid-gjtny2mx="">    <article data-astro-cid-gjtny2mx="">  <p>This post is the result of me going down a several week long XNU rabbit-hole
after reading <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/03/08/kernel_sanders_apple_rearranges_xnu/">this post by Thomas Claburn on
Exclaves</a>,
more on that later. I’ve tried my best to condense all the information into a
single blog post. I’ve also tried to keep sections self-contained so you can
skip around using the table of contents, this does come at the cost of
repeating myself in some places, so thanks in advance for your patience. While
I’m confident of my understanding on this topic, some errors are inevitable
when dealing with content this dense, if you spot any errors, assume them to be
mine and please reach out so I can correct it, also let me know your thoughts
by reaching out via email or mastodon. Thanks in advance and let’s begin!</p>
<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Apple’s Darwin operating system is the Unix-like core underpinning macOS, iOS,
and all of Apple’s modern OS platforms. At its heart lies the XNU kernel – an
acronym humorously standing for “X is Not Unix.” XNU is a unique <strong>hybrid
kernel</strong> that combines a Mach microkernel core with components of BSD Unix.
This design inherits the rich legacy of Mach (originating from 1980s
microkernel research) and the robust stability and POSIX compliance of BSD. The
result is a kernel architecture that balances modularity and performance by
blending microkernel message-passing techniques with a monolithic Unix kernel
structure. We’ll go through a chronological exploration of Darwin and XNU’s
evolution – from Mach and BSD origins to the modern kernel features in macOS on
Apple Silicon and iOS on iPhones. We’ll follow this with a deep dive into the
architectural milestones, analyze XNU’s internal design (Mach-BSD interaction,
IPC, scheduling, memory management, virtualization), and examine how the kernel
and key user-space components have adapted to new devices and requirements over
time.</p>
<h2 id="darwin-and-xnu-development-history">Darwin and XNU Development History</h2>
<h3 id="mach-microkernel-origins-19851996">Mach Microkernel Origins (1985–1996)</h3>
<p>Darwin’s story begins with <strong>Mach</strong>, a project at Carnegie Mellon University
(1985) led by Richard Rashid and Avie Tevanian. Mach was envisioned as a
next-generation <strong>microkernel</strong> to address the growing complexity of UNIX
kernels. Instead of a single large kernel binary, Mach provided only
fundamental low-level functions – <strong>memory management</strong> (virtual memory,
address spaces), <strong>CPU scheduling</strong> (threads and tasks), and <strong>inter-process
communication</strong> (IPC via message passing). Higher-level services (file systems,
networking, device drivers, etc.) were intended to run as user-space <em>servers</em>
on top of Mach. This separation promised improved reliability (a crashed driver
wouldn’t crash the whole system) and flexibility (multiple OS personalities
could run concurrently). In fact, Mach’s design allowed running several
“personalities” – for example, UNIX and another OS – on one microkernel, a
concept analogous to modern virtualization.</p>
<p>By 1990, Mach had progressed to <strong>Mach 2.5</strong>, which was a microkernel but still
co-located some BSD kernel code in kernel space for performance. The true
microkernel version, <strong>Mach 3.0</strong>, arrived in 1991–1994. Mach’s <strong>virtual
memory (VM) system</strong> was influential beyond the project – it was adopted by
4.4BSD and later FreeBSD as their memory management subsystem. Importantly,
Mach introduced the concept of <strong>tasks</strong> (encapsulating an address space and
resources, roughly equivalent to a process) and <strong>threads</strong> (unit of CPU
execution) as first-class kernel objects. It also implemented an efficient VM
with copy-on-write and memory object abstractions, and a message-based IPC
mechanism using <strong>Mach ports</strong>.</p>
<p>Parallel to Mach’s development, <strong>NeXT Computer</strong> (founded by Steve Jobs in
1985) needed a modern OS for its workstations. NeXT adopted Mach early:
<strong>NeXTSTEP</strong>, released in 1989, was built on a Mach 2.5 kernel with a 4.3BSD
Unix subsystem layered on top. Crucially, NeXTSTEP’s kernel (later named
<strong>XNU</strong>) was not a pure microkernel system with user-space servers; instead, it
took Mach and <strong>integrated the BSD code into the kernel address space</strong> for
speed. In other words, NeXT used Mach’s abstractions (tasks, threads, IPC, VM)
and ran a BSD kernel <em>in kernel mode</em> on top of Mach primitives. This hybrid
approach sacrificed some of Mach’s extreme modularity in favor of performance:
it avoided the heavy context-switching and messaging overhead that plagued
fully microkernel systems of the era. NeXTSTEP’s kernel also included an
object-oriented driver framework called <strong>DriverKit</strong> (written in Objective-C)
to develop device drivers as objects, reflecting NeXT’s preference for
higher-level languages.</p>
<p>By the mid-1990s, Apple’s original Mac OS (classic Mac OS) was aging and lacked
modern OS features like proper multitasking and memory protection. In 1996,
Apple sought an existing OS as its foundation for the future. The company
acquired NeXT in December 1996, choosing NeXTSTEP as the core of the new <strong>Mac
OS X</strong>. With this acquisition, NeXT’s Mach/BSD hybrid kernel came to Apple,
bringing along the engineering leadership of Avie Tevanian (Mach co-author) as
Apple’s VP of Software. Apple named the new OS project <strong>Rhapsody</strong>, which
would later become Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X.</p>
<h3 id="rhapsody-to-mac-os-x-integrating-mach-30-and-bsd-19972005">Rhapsody to Mac OS X: Integrating Mach 3.0 and BSD (1997–2005)</h3>
<p>After acquiring NeXT, Apple set out to merge the NeXTSTEP kernel with
additional features and hardware support needed for Macs. The kernel was
further updated with newer Mach and BSD technology. Notably, Apple incorporated
code from <strong>OSFMK 7.3</strong>, the Open Software Foundation’s Mach 3.0 kernel, into
XNU. This meant the Mach portion of XNU now drew from Mach 3.0’s true
microkernel lineage (including contributions from University of Utah’s Mach 4
research). On the BSD side, the NeXTSTEP kernel’s 4.3BSD subsystem was upgraded
with <strong>4.4BSD and FreeBSD</strong> code. This brought in a more modern BSD
implementation with features like improved networking and a robust filesystems
infrastructure. By combining Mach 3.0 and FreeBSD elements, Apple shaped XNU
into a powerful hybrid: Mach provided the low-level kernel architecture and
abstractions, while BSD provided the <strong>Unix APIs and services</strong> on top.</p>
<p>Apple also replaced NeXT’s old DriverKit with a new driver framework called
<strong>I/O Kit</strong>, written in a subset of C++. I/O Kit introduced a object-oriented
device driver model within the kernel, supporting features like dynamic device
matching and hot-plugging in a robust way. The choice of C++ (minus exceptions
and multiple inheritance, using Embedded C++ subset) for I/O Kit was likely to
improve performance and avoid the runtime overhead of Objective-C in the
kernel. By the late 1990s, XNU was thus composed of three core parts: the Mach
microkernel layer (now OSFMK 7.3 based), the BSD layer (largely
FreeBSD-derived), and the I/O Kit for drivers.</p>
<p>Apple delivered the first developer previews of Mac OS X in 1999, and in 2000
released the open source Darwin 1.0, which exposed the XNU kernel and basic
Unix userland to developers. The commercial debut, <strong>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.0 (Cheetah)</strong>,
came in early 2001 (Darwin 1.3.1). While the initial releases were rough in
performance, they cemented the architectural paradigm. Key early milestones
included:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Mac OS X 10.1 (Puma, 2001)</strong> – Improved performance in threading and added
missing Unix features. Darwin 1.4.1 in 10.1 introduced faster thread
management and real-time threads support.</li>
<li><strong>Mac OS X 10.2 (Jaguar, 2002)</strong> – Darwin 6.0 brought the synchronicity of
the BSD layer with FreeBSD 4.4/5, plus large new features: IPv6 and IPSec
networking, the new <code>mDNSResponder</code> service for discovery
(Bonjour/Rendezvous), and journaling in HFS+ file system. It also upgraded
the toolchain (GCC3) and added modern Unix utilities.</li>
<li><strong>Mac OS X 10.3 (Panther, 2003)</strong> – Darwin 7.0/7.1 integrated <strong>FreeBSD 5</strong>
kernel improvements. This brought <strong>fine-grained kernel locking</strong> (moving
away from the earlier giant-lock model) to better utilize multiprocessors.
Panther’s kernel also introduced <strong>integrated BFS</strong> (basic firewall) and
other performance tuning like improved VM and I/O.</li>
</ul>
<p>Throughout these releases, XNU remained a 32-bit kernel (with limited 64-bit
user process support introduced in 10.4 for specific tasks). Apple maintained
support for PowerPC the Mac CPU architecture of choice in the early days while
also quietly keeping the Intel x86 compatibility (inherited from NeXTSTEP’s x86
support) in the source, preparing for future transitions.</p>
<p>A major architectural change arrived in <strong>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.4 (Tiger, 2005)</strong>. This
was the first version where Apple declared OS&nbsp;X to be <strong>UNIX&nbsp;03 certified</strong>,
meaning the system conformed to the Single UNIX Specification and could legally
use the UNIX name. Darwin 8 (Tiger’s core) achieved this UNIX certification by
virtue of the robust BSD layer integrated in XNU. Tiger also introduced new
kernel features like <strong>kqueue/kevent</strong> (from FreeBSD, for scalable event
handling), and laid groundwork for Intel Macs by keeping XNU cross-platform.
Apple then announced in 2005 the switch to Intel x86 processors for Macs. XNU’s
Mach foundations made such platform adaptability easier, as Mach abstracted
many low-level hardware details behind a portability layer. In early 2006,
Apple released <strong>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.4.4 for Intel</strong>, demonstrating XNU running on
x86_32 with much of the code shared with the PowerPC build.</p>
<h3 id="transition-to-64-bit-multi-core-and-iphone-os-20052010">Transition to 64-bit, Multi-Core and iPhone OS (2005–2010)</h3>
<p>By the mid-2000s, computing had shifted to multi-core 64-bit architectures, and
Apple’s OS had to evolve accordingly. <strong>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.5 Leopard (2007)</strong>, based
on Darwin 9, was a landmark release for XNU. It introduced extensive 64-bit
support: while earlier versions could run 64-bit user applications in limited
form, Leopard’s kernel itself could run in 64-bit mode on appropriate hardware
(x86-64) and support 64-bit drivers. Leopard also dropped official support for
older architectures like PowerPC G3 and brought in stronger security and
performance features: <strong>address space layout randomization (ASLR)</strong> to thwart
exploits, an advanced <strong>sandbox</strong> facility for restricting processes, and the
<strong>DTrace</strong> instrumentation framework from Solaris for low-level tracing.
Notably, Leopard was the last Mac OS X version to fully support PowerPC – Apple
was transitioning its entire lineup to Intel by this time.</p>
<p>In 2007, Apple also debuted the <strong>iPhone</strong> with “iPhone OS” (later named iOS),
which was built on Darwin as well. The first iPhone OS was based on Darwin 9
(same core as Leopard). This demonstrated the versatility of XNU: within the
same kernel version, Apple could target high-end PowerPC and x86 servers,
consumer Intel laptops, and resource-constrained ARM mobile devices. The kernel
gained support for the ARM architecture and tailor-made modifications for
mobile. For example, because early iPhones had very limited RAM and no swap,
the kernel’s memory management had to incorporate aggressive <strong>memory-pressure
handling</strong>. Apple introduced a <strong>Jetsam</strong> mechanism in iPhone OS, which
monitored low-memory conditions and killed background apps to free memory
(since traditional swapping to disk was not feasible on flash storage). iPhone
OS also ran all third-party apps in a <em>sandbox</em> by design and required strict
code signing for binaries – security measures facilitated by XNU’s Mach and BSD
layers (Mach’s task port and codesign enforcement in the kernel, with help from
user-space daemons like <code>amfid</code> for signature validation).</p>
<p><strong>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.6 Snow Leopard (2009)</strong> marked the maturation of XNU on 64-bit
Intel. Snow Leopard (Darwin 10) discontinued support for PowerPC entirely,
making XNU a dual-architecture kernel (x86_64 and i386 for Intel Macs). It
also was the first to ship with an <em>optional</em> fully 64-bit kernel on capable
Macs (most defaulted to 32-bit kernel with 64-bit userland, except Xserve).
Snow Leopard brought major concurrency advances: the introduction of <strong>Grand
Central Dispatch (libdispatch)</strong> for user-space task parallelization and kernel
support for <strong>dispatch queues</strong>. While <code>libdispatch</code> is a user-space library,
it works closely with the kernel, which provides the underlying thread pools
and scheduling for dispatch queues. Another addition was <strong>OpenCL</strong> for GPU
computing, again requiring tight integration between user frameworks and kernel
drivers. Snow Leopard’s streamlined focus on Intel and multi-core optimizations
made XNU more efficient.</p>
<p>On the mobile side, <strong>iPhone OS 3 (2009)</strong> and <strong>iOS 4 (2010)</strong> (renamed “iOS”
in 2010) evolved alongside, adding support for the Apple A4/A5 ARM chips and
features like multitasking. XNU’s scheduler was adapted in iOS 4 to handle the
concept of background apps with different priority bands (foreground,
background, etc.), and to support <strong>multi-core ARM SoCs</strong> as they appeared
(e.g., the Apple A5 in 2011 was dual-core). iOS and macOS kernels remained
largely unified, with conditional code for platform differences. By <strong>OS&nbsp;X 10.7
Lion (2011)</strong>, XNU dropped support for 32-bit Intel kernels entirely – it
required a 64-bit CPU on Mac, reflecting the industry’s move beyond 32-bit.
Lion (Darwin 11) also improved sandboxing and added full support for new
features like <strong>Automatic Reference Counting (ARC)</strong> in Obj-C (with compiler
and runtime changes reflected in the system).</p>
<h3 id="modern-macos-and-ios-evolution-20112020">Modern macOS and iOS Evolution (2011–2020)</h3>
<p>From 2011 onward, Apple’s OS releases came in a yearly cadence, and Darwin
continued to get incremental but significant enhancements to support new
hardware and features:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>OS&nbsp;X 10.8 Mountain Lion (2012)</strong> and <strong>10.9 Mavericks (2013)</strong> (Darwin 12
and 13) introduced power- and memory-optimizations in the kernel. Mavericks
added <strong>Compressed Memory</strong>, a kernel feature where inactive pages are
compressed in RAM to avoid swapping to disk. This was in line with iOS
techniques to cope with low RAM, and it benefited Macs by improving
responsiveness under memory pressure. Mavericks also implemented <strong>Timer
Coalescing</strong>, where the kernel aligns wake-ups from idle to reduce CPU power
usage. These changes show how the kernel adapted to energy-efficiency
demands, influenced by mobile design philosophies. Additionally, around this
time, Apple introduced <strong>App Nap</strong> and increased use of Quality-of-Service
(QoS) classes for threads, which required kernel scheduling awareness to
throttle or prioritize threads based on QoS hints (e.g., background vs
user-initiated tasks). XNU’s scheduler evolved to support these multiple
priority bands and energy-efficient scheduling.</li>
<li><strong>OS&nbsp;X 10.10 Yosemite (2014)</strong> and <strong>10.11 El Capitan (2015)</strong> (Darwin 14 and
15) continued the trend. A major security addition in El Capitan was <strong>System
Integrity Protection (SIP)</strong>. SIP (also called “rootless”) is enforced by the
kernel’s security framework, preventing even root user processes from
tampering with critical system files and processes. Implemented via the BSD
layer’s Mandatory Access Control (MAC) framework, SIP hardened the OS by
moving more trust into the kernel and away from user space. For iOS (iOS 9 in
2015), similar “rootless” concepts were applied. Darwin 15 also saw Apple
unifying the code base for OS X and iOS further, as they introduced
<strong>watchOS</strong> and <strong>tvOS</strong> (both also Darwin-based) – XNU had to accommodate
running on tiny Apple Watch hardware (S1 chip) up to powerful Mac Pros, with
scalable scheduling, memory, and I/O capabilities. By now, XNU supported
ARM64 (64-bit ARMv8, first used in iPhone 5s in 2013) and would go on to drop
32-bit ARM support for iOS by <strong>iOS 11 (2017)</strong>.</li>
<li><strong>macOS 10.12 Sierra (2016)</strong>, <strong>10.13 High Sierra (2017)</strong>, <strong>10.14 Mojave
(2018)</strong> (Darwin 16–18) brought filesystem evolution and further security.
High Sierra introduced <strong>APFS (Apple File System)</strong> as the new default
filesystem, replacing HFS+. APFS required kernel support for snapshots,
cloning, and encryption at the container level. XNU’s VFS layer (in the BSD
component) was extended to accommodate APFS’s advanced features and
performance characteristics. During this era, kext (kernel extension)
security was tightened – macOS High Sierra requires user approval for loading
third-party kexts, and macOS Mojave introduced stricter code signing checks
and hardened runtime for user-space processes that also influence how the
kernel validates and allows certain operations. Another adaptation was
graphics and external device support, High Sierra’s eGPU support via
Thunderbolt required hot-plug handling improvements in I/O Kit and scheduling
of external PCIe devices.</li>
<li><strong>macOS 10.15 Catalina (2019)</strong> (Darwin 19) was a significant modernization
step for XNU. Catalina was the first to <strong>deprecate most 32-bit code</strong> (only
64-bit apps, and the kernel had been 64-bit only for years already). More
notably, Apple introduced a new approach for device drivers: <strong>DriverKit</strong>,
reviving the name of NeXT’s old driver framework but with a new design.
DriverKit in modern macOS allows many drivers to run in user space as
<strong>Driver Extensions (dexts)</strong>, outside of the kernel. This is a shift towards
microkernel philosophy for third-party code – by moving drivers (USB,
network, etc.) to user-space processes, Apple improved system stability and
security (a buggy driver can’t crash the kernel if it’s outside it). XNU was
adapted to facilitate this: the kernel provides user-space drivers with
controlled access to hardware (via IPC and shared memory) instead of loading
their code as kexts. At the same time, Catalina split the OS filesystem into
a read-only system volume, reinforcing the kernel’s SIP protections (the
kernel now treats system files as immutable during runtime). These changes
show how even decades after its birth, XNU’s architecture can pivot to
incorporate more user-space responsibilities when beneficial, leveraging the
Mach IPC mechanisms to do so safely.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="apple-silicon-era-2020present">Apple Silicon Era (2020–Present)</h3>
<p>In 2020, Apple undertook another monumental transition: moving the Mac lineup
from Intel CPUs to Apple’s custom <strong>ARM64 SoCs</strong> (the <strong>Apple Silicon</strong> chips,
starting with M1). Darwin had long supported ARM due to iOS, but running macOS
on ARM64 introduced new challenges and opportunities. <strong>macOS 11 Big Sur
(2020)</strong>, corresponding to Darwin 20, was the first release for Apple Silicon
Macs. XNU was already cross-platform, but it now had to support a heterogeneous
<strong>big.LITTLE CPU architecture</strong>: Apple Silicon chips combine high-performance
cores and energy-efficient cores. The scheduler was enhanced to be
<strong>heterogeneity-aware</strong>, ensuring high-priority and heavy threads run on
performance cores, while background and low-QoS threads can be scheduled on
efficiency cores to save power. Apple likely utilizes the thread <strong>QoS
classes</strong> (which had been introduced in earlier macOS/iOS) to map threads to
appropriate core types – this is an extension of Mach scheduling concepts to a
new domain of asymmetric multiprocessing.</p>
<p>Another aspect of Apple Silicon is the unified memory architecture (shared
memory between CPU/GPU). While largely abstracted by frameworks, the kernel’s
memory manager works with the GPU drivers (which are now Apple’s own,
integrated via I/O Kit) to manage buffer sharing without expensive copies. The
Mach VM abstraction fits well here – memory objects can be shared between
user-space and the GPU with VM remapping rather than duplication. Additionally,
Apple Silicon brought hardware features like <strong>Pointer Authentication (PAC)</strong>
and <strong>Memory Tagging Extension (MTE)</strong> for security. XNU’s ARM64 backend had to
support PAC (which it does by using PAC keys in exception frames and system
pointers to mitigate ROP<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-1" id="user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">1</a></sup> attacks) and potentially MTE to detect memory
errors – these are deep architecture-specific enhancements in the kernel to
improve security on new hardware.</p>
<p>On the virtualization front, Apple Silicon prompted a reevaluation of
virtualization strategy. On Intel Macs, XNU has long supported virtualization
via the <strong>Hypervisor framework</strong> (introduced in macOS 10.10 Yosemite) which
allows user-space programs to run VMs using hardware VT-x support. With Apple
Silicon, macOS 11 introduced a new <strong>Virtualization framework</strong> built on top of
an in-kernel hypervisor for ARM64 (taking advantage of the ARM VMM features).
Notably, while the <strong>open-source XNU</strong> code does not include the Apple Silicon
hypervisor, the shipped kernel does initialize hypervisor support if running on
the appropriate Apple chip. This allows macOS on M1/M2 to run lightweight
virtual machines (for Linux, macOS guests, etc.) entirely from user-space
controllers, similar to Linux KVM. On iOS devices, Apple has kept the
hypervisor disabled or restricted (no public API), but the hardware capability
appeared with A14 chips. Enthusiasts quickly found that on jailbroken A14
devices, the hypervisor could be enabled to run Linux VMs<sup><a href="#user-content-fn-2" id="user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-ref="" aria-describedby="footnote-label">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Beyond CPU and virtualization, Apple Silicon Macs run many of the same daemons
and services as iOS, indicating a convergence in system architecture. The XNU
kernel now powers everything from servers (macOS), personal computers, phones,
watches, TVs, and even the <strong>bridgeOS</strong> (a variant of Darwin running on the
Apple T2/M1 auxiliary processors for device management). Darwin’s <strong>flexibility
and scalability</strong> stem from the Mach foundation: it abstracts hardware
specifics in a platform layer, so adding a new CPU architecture (PowerPC → x86
→ ARM64) or scaling down to limited hardware largely requires implementing the
Mach low-level interfaces (like pmap for MMU, thread context switches, etc.)
and leaving higher-level kernel logic untouched. This design has paid dividends
in Apple’s transitions.</p>
<p>In summary, over two decades, XNU has undergone major transformations while
retaining its core identity. <strong>Table 1</strong> highlights a timeline of Darwin/XNU
milestones and architectural changes:</p>































































































<table><thead><tr><th><strong>Year</strong></th><th><strong>Release (Darwin ver.)</strong></th><th><strong>Key Kernel Developments</strong></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>1989</strong></td><td>NeXTSTEP 1.0 (Mach 2.5 + 4.3BSD)</td><td>NeXT’s XNU kernel hybrid introduced: Mach microkernel with BSD in kernel space for performance. Drivers via Obj-C DriverKit.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>1996</strong></td><td>NeXT acquired by Apple</td><td>Rhapsody OS development begins, based on OpenStep. Mach 2.5 + 4.3BSD XNU to be upgraded with Mach 3 and FreeBSD.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>1999</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X Server 1.0 (Darwin 0.x)</td><td>First Darwin releases (0.1–0.3) as Apple integrates OSFMK Mach 3.0 (OSF/1) and FreeBSD into XNU.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2001</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.0 (Darwin 1.3)</td><td>Darwin 1.x: Core OS X launched with hybrid kernel, BSD userland, Cocoa APIs. Early performance tuning of Mach/BSD integration.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2003</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.3 (Darwin 7)</td><td>XNU sync with FreeBSD 5, bringing SMP scalability (fine-grained locking).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2005</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.4 (Darwin 8)</td><td>UNIX&nbsp;03 certified kernel. Intel x86 support readied (Mach portability layer leveraged).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2006</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X on Intel (Darwin 8.x)</td><td>Apple transitions Macs to x86. XNU supports <strong>Universal Binary</strong> drivers and Rosetta translation (user-space emulation of PowerPC on x86).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2007</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.5 (Darwin 9)</td><td>64-bit support in kernel (on x86_64); last PowerPC support. Security: NX support, ASLR, code signing, sandbox introduced. <strong>iPhone OS 1</strong> (Darwin 9) released on ARM, with XNU scaled to mobile (no swap, sandbox always on).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2009</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.6 (Darwin 10)</td><td>Intel-only (drops PowerPC). Fully 64-bit kernel on capable Macs; Grand Central Dispatch (kernel task queues); OpenCL support. iPhone OS -&gt; <strong>iOS 3</strong> (Darwin 10) adds improved power management.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2011</strong></td><td>Mac&nbsp;OS&nbsp;X 10.7 (Darwin 11)</td><td>Drops 32-bit kernel support on Mac; Requires x86_64. Expands sandboxing, FileVault 2 encryption (kernel crypto). <strong>iOS 5</strong> brings dual-core scheduling.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2013</strong></td><td>OS&nbsp;X 10.9 (Darwin 13)</td><td>Power optimizations: compressed memory, timer coalescing in kernel. Improved multicore scheduling with QoS introduction.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2015</strong></td><td>OS&nbsp;X 10.11 (Darwin 15)</td><td><strong>System Integrity Protection</strong> (kernel-enforced security). Enhanced AMFI (Apple Mobile File Integrity) for code signing in kernel and user helper (amfid). iOS 9 / watchOS debut (Darwin 15) on new device categories, kernel runs on Apple Watch (ARM Cortex-A7).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2017</strong></td><td>macOS 10.13 (Darwin 17)</td><td>New APFS filesystem default on Mac (already in iOS 10). Kernel changes for cloning, snapshots. Kext loading requires user approval. iOS 11 drops 32-bit ARM, fully 64-bit kernel.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2019</strong></td><td>macOS 10.15 (Darwin 19)</td><td>Legacy I/O Kit model shifts: <strong>DriverKit</strong> introduced for user-space drivers. System extensions modularize networking and endpoint security features out of kernel. macOS split system volume (read-only) to strengthen kernel’s protection of OS files.</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2020</strong></td><td><strong>macOS 11.0 (Darwin 20)</strong></td><td><strong>Apple Silicon support</strong> – XNU on ARM64 Mac (M1). Kernel adapts to heterogeneous cores, unified memory. Rosetta 2 translation tier (user-space JIT, with kernel enforcing memory protections for translated code). <strong>iOS 14</strong> – exposes new virtualization features for developers (e.g., running lightweight VMs on iPadOS).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2022</strong></td><td>macOS 13 (Darwin 22)</td><td>Continued refinement for Apple Silicon (e.g., high-power mode on M1 Max, kernel scheduling tweaks). <strong>iOS 16</strong> – XNU adds support for virtualizing iOS/macOS guests (used in Xcode Simulator and Developer Mode features).</td></tr><tr><td><strong>2024</strong></td><td>macOS 14 (Darwin 23)</td><td>Ongoing improvements (Memory tagging support and fine-tuning for M2/M3 chips). Darwin remains the common core for <strong>visionOS</strong> (Apple Vision Pro AR headset) as well.</td></tr></tbody></table>
<p><strong>Table 1:</strong> Timeline of Darwin/XNU evolution with selected kernel milestones and architectural changes.</p>
<p>This timeline shows how XNU’s Mach/BSD core proved to be a stable foundation
that Apple could incrementally enhance: adding 64-bit support, embracing
multicore, tightening security, and porting to new architectures, all while
retaining backward compatibility. Next, we delve into the internal architecture
of XNU – the hybrid kernel design that made all of this possible.</p>
<h2 id="xnu-kernel-architecture-and-design">XNU Kernel Architecture and Design</h2>
<p><img alt="MacOS-Architecture.png" width="2169" height="2048" loading="lazy" decoding="async" src="https://tansanrao.com/_astro/MacOS-Architecture.B0qOydhL_Z1GQHHd.webp"></p>
<blockquote>
<p>File: Diagram of Mac OS X architecture.svg. (2024, December 29). <em>Wikimedia
Commons</em>. Retrieved 22:59, April 3, 2025 from
<a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?title=File:Diagram_of_Mac_OS_X_architecture.svg&amp;oldid=976998015">https://commons.wikimedia.org</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<h3 id="hybrid-kernel-design-mach--bsd-integration">Hybrid Kernel Design: Mach + BSD Integration</h3>
<p>XNU’s kernel design is often described as a <strong>hybrid kernel</strong>, because it
merges characteristics of microkernels (Mach) and monolithic kernels (BSD). In
a traditional microkernel, the kernel provides minimal services (IPC,
scheduling, VM) and everything else runs as user-space servers. In a monolithic
UNIX kernel, all OS services run in kernel mode as one large program. XNU
attempts to get “the best of both”: it uses Mach to modularize and abstract
low-level functions, but co-locates the critical BSD services in kernel space
for efficiency.</p>
<p>In XNU, the Mach component and the BSD component <strong>run as a single kernel
entity</strong> – they are linked into one binary and share the same address space.
There is no Mach vs BSD protection boundary; Mach functions and BSD functions
call each other via normal function calls within the kernel, not via IPC
messages. This co-location avoids the significant context-switch overhead that
a pure Mach system would incur (where a Unix system call would require
messaging a user-space BSD server). As a result, standard UNIX system calls
(file I/O, socket operations, etc.) in XNU perform comparably to other
monolithic Unix kernels, since the BSD code executes directly in kernel mode.
For instance, when a process calls <code>read()</code>, it traps into the kernel and the
BSD file system code is invoked directly; there’s no Mach message to a separate
process as would happen in a Mach 3.0 microkernel with an external BSD server.</p>
<p><strong>Mach’s Role:</strong> Mach in XNU provides the core kernel <strong>infrastructure and
abstractions</strong>. Mach manages CPU <em>threads</em> and task address spaces, implements
low-level scheduling, and handles virtual memory management (memory mapping,
paging). It also provides the fundamental <strong>IPC mechanism</strong> – Mach messages
sent over Mach <em>ports</em> (communication endpoints). In XNU, every process (BSD
process) is backed by a Mach <strong>task</strong> and every thread by a Mach thread. The
Mach layer is responsible for creating and terminating tasks/threads, context
switching threads on the CPU, and implementing primitives like locks, timers,
and scheduling queues. It also implements the VM system: each task has a
virtual address map, memory regions are backed by Mach <strong>memory objects</strong>, and
Mach can perform copy-on-write copy optimizations and map propagation. Notably,
Mach supports <strong>IPC-based memory sharing</strong> – one task can send a memory object
(or a port right to it) to another, enabling efficient shared memory or
transfer of large buffers without copying.</p>
<p><strong>BSD’s Role:</strong> The BSD component sits logically “on top” of Mach and provides
the traditional <strong>OS personality</strong> and services. This includes managing
<strong>processes</strong> (the BSD process table, PID allocation, user IDs, signals, etc.),
<strong>POSIX threads</strong> (which are mapped to Mach threads), and the entire set of
UNIX system calls (file systems, networking, IPC, device I/O, etc.). The BSD
kernel in XNU is derived primarily from FreeBSD (with substantial
OpenBSD/NetBSD influences and custom Apple modifications). It handles things
like:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>VFS and File Systems:</strong> XNU’s BSD layer implements a VFS (Virtual File
System) and supports many file systems (HFS+, APFS, NFS, etc.). The file
system code runs in the kernel and interacts with storage drivers via I/O
Kit. Mach VM and BSD file systems meet when implementing memory-mapped files
– Mach calls into BSD to fetch pages from files on disk (via the vnode
pager).</li>
<li><strong>Network Stack:</strong> The entire TCP/IP stack (and other protocols like UDP,
ICMP, as well as higher-level sockets API) is in the BSD kernel. This code
came from BSD and is updated with modern standards. It interfaces with
network drivers (in I/O Kit) for packet send/receive.</li>
<li><strong>UNIX IPC:</strong> Besides Mach IPC, XNU provides traditional Unix IPC (signals,
pipes, SysV IPC, POSIX message queues, etc.) through the BSD layer. Signals,
for example, are implemented by the BSD kernel, but interestingly signals are
delivered using Mach exceptions under the hood – Mach exceptions are the
low-level mechanism, and the BSD code translates them to Unix signals for
processes as needed.</li>
<li><strong>Security and Credentials:</strong> The BSD layer manages user IDs, permissions,
access control, and integrates several security frameworks. For instance,
<strong>KAuth</strong> (Kernel Authorization) and the MAC Framework (Mandatory Access
Control) operate in the BSD layer. Features like the Sandbox, SIP, code
signing enforcement involve cooperation between BSD security modules and Mach
task port restrictions. The sandbox (Seatbelt) in macOS/iOS uses the
TrustedBSD MAC framework – when a system call is made, the MAC policy can vet
it. This happens in the BSD layer, though the sandbox’s configuration is set
from user space by launchd or other daemons.</li>
<li><strong>POSIX APIs and Environment:</strong> The BSD layer is what makes Darwin a UNIX. It
provides <code>/dev</code> management (which often links to I/O Kit devices), system
call table for standard C library calls, process forking (<code>fork()</code> is
implemented partly by Mach (VM copy-on-write) and partly by BSD (duplicating
file descriptors, etc.), and execve (loading binaries, setting up Mach task
states and BSD process states).</li>
</ul>
<p>In essence, one can think of Mach as the <strong>core kernel supervisor</strong> in XNU, and
BSD as a high-level kernel server that depends on Mach. The two are tightly
coupled – e.g., when a new BSD process is created via <code>fork()</code>, the kernel
internally calls Mach to create a new task and thread, then BSD code populates
the process structure and file descriptors. The BSD code calls Mach kernel
functions directly (not via message) using an internal API. Conversely, Mach
relies on some BSD services; for example, Mach has an abstraction called
“default pager” for managing swap. In XNU, the default pager is implemented
partly in user space (the <code>dynamic_pager</code> daemon) which uses Mach VM APIs to
create and manage swap files, but the BSD layer is involved in the actual file
I/O to the swap file. This shows a cooperative multi-tier design rather than
strictly separated layers.</p>
<p><strong>I/O Kit:</strong> The third pillar of XNU is the <strong>I/O Kit</strong>, Apple’s
object-oriented driver framework. I/O Kit runs in kernel space (as part of the
XNU kernel), but it is written in a restricted form of C++ for type-safety and
code reuse. The I/O Kit defines a class hierarchy for devices (buses, storage,
network, display, etc.) and drivers subclass these to implement support for
specific hardware. Drivers in I/O Kit live as C++ objects within the kernel,
but they interact with user space through well-defined interfaces. For
instance, an I/O Kit driver can publish properties accessible via the I/O
Registry, and can provide <strong>user client</strong> interfaces that allow user-space
applications or daemons to call into the driver in a controlled way. I/O Kit
also supports limited <strong>user-space drivers</strong> historically (via user clients),
but in practice, until recent DriverKit, most drivers ran in kernel. The Mach
component provides threading and synchronization primitives used by I/O Kit
(like locks and workloops), while the BSD component interacts with I/O Kit for
networking and disk I/O (e.g., the BSD filesystem code calls an I/O Kit disk
driver to read a block). The decision to use C++ in kernel (contrary to the
“not written in C++” myth; the core kernel logic is C, but drivers are C++
classes) was made to improve extensibility. By eliminating multiple inheritance
and exceptions, Apple ensured the kernel would not suffer C++ runtime overhead.
Many drivers can be loaded and unloaded dynamically as <strong>Kexts</strong> (kernel
extensions), which are essentially loadable bundles of I/O Kit C++ classes or
additional BSD/Mach code. XNU’s modularity in this sense is reminiscent of
other OS kernels that allow loadable modules, but Mach’s abstractions also help
here (each kext is essentially a Mach-O image loaded into kernel memory and
linked).</p>
<p><strong>Mach IPC and Message Passing:</strong> Even though XNU does not use Mach messages
for Unix <em>system calls</em>, Mach IPC is still heavily used throughout the system
for what we might call “RPC”-style interactions and for connecting
user-space services to kernel or to each other. Mach ports are the
foundation of various high-level features:</p>
<ul>
<li>Many kernel abstractions are represented as Mach ports to user space. For
example, each task (process) has a Mach port (the task port) that represents
its control handle. The kernel holds the rights, but certain privileged tasks
(like <code>launchd</code> or debugging tools) can obtain send rights to manipulate
other tasks (to start/stop them, inspect memory, etc.).</li>
<li>Mach <strong>notifications</strong> are used for event delivery. The WindowServer
(graphics system) receives user input events from the kernel via Mach
messages. Likewise, higher-level APIs like Grand Central Dispatch under the
hood use Mach ports to sleep threads waiting for events, leveraging Mach’s
port-set and message mechanism. The <code>kqueue/kevent</code> mechanism in BSD is
integrated: an event queue can wait on Mach port messages as well as file
descriptors, unifying the event sources.</li>
<li><strong>Inter-process Communication</strong> for system services: Apple’s entire <strong>XPC</strong>
framework (used by modern macOS/iOS for lightweight IPC between apps and
services) is built on Mach messages. Each XPC connection is essentially a
Mach port behind the scenes. The reason Mach IPC is chosen is its security
model – Mach ports have an associated rights system and live in the kernel,
so the kernel mediates who can send to whom. This allows checks like “is the
sender task entitled to send this message?” which is used in services like
the Keychain (securityd) to validate callers. Mach messages also support
carrying out-of-line memory (shared memory regions) and port rights, which is
extremely powerful for building higher-level RPC: you can send a file
descriptor (which is a BSD concept) as a Mach port right in a message,
enabling UNIX domain socket semantics via Mach. Under the hood, the file
descriptor send uses a Mach port representing that file in the receiving
task’s space.</li>
<li><strong>Remote Procedure Calls:</strong> Mach introduced MIG (Mach Interface Generator),
which is used to define interfaces where one side is in kernel and the other
in user. For example, the bootstrap server (launchd) and various system
servers use MIG to auto-generate code for sending/receiving messages. The
macOS <code>notify</code> system (for system-wide notifications) and many daemon APIs
are implemented with MIG definitions.</li>
</ul>
<p>Therefore, Mach IPC is a backbone for the macOS/iOS architecture beyond the
kernel boundary. It’s how user-space components talk to each other and to the
kernel in many cases. Even certain device drivers use Mach port notifications
(e.g., I/O Kit user clients might deliver an asynchronous event to a client via
a Mach message). The hybrid kernel thus uses Mach messaging where appropriate
(for asynchronous, out-of-band communication), and uses direct function calls
for in-kernel interactions. This hybrid approach retains Mach’s <strong>modularity</strong>
benefits – for instance, one can imagine refactoring a component to run in
user space with Mach messages without changing the other parts, since they
might already use a Mach port interface to talk to it. In fact, Apple did
exactly this with DriverKit: they moved certain drivers to user space and
replaced their in-kernel part with a Mach IPC conduit. The
performance-critical path (e.g., actual packet sending) might still be in
kernel, but higher-level policy or USB logic can be in a user process
communicating via Mach.</p>
<h3 id="scheduler-and-thread-management">Scheduler and Thread Management</h3>
<p>XNU’s scheduling is rooted in Mach’s scheduler, which was originally a
priority-based round-robin scheduler with support for threads and processor
sets. Over time, Apple has modified the scheduler significantly to meet the
needs of desktop and mobile. The scheduler manages threads (Mach threads)
across CPU cores (XNU supports SMP and on Apple Silicon, asymmetric cores). Key
points of XNU scheduling:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Priority Levels:</strong> Mach defines a range of thread priorities (0–127,
historically) with certain bands reserved for real-time, kernel, and normal
threads. Apple uses these priorities along with abstractions called
<strong>“sched_pri”</strong> and <strong>“base_pri”</strong> for each thread. Time-sharing threads have
priorities that can float based on usage (to implement favoring I/O-bound
threads), whereas real-time threads have fixed priorities. The highest
priorities are for critical kernel threads or timers.</li>
<li><strong>Run Queues:</strong> In classic Mach, each processor or processor-set had a run
queue for threads. XNU has per-CPU run queues for efficiency. It also has
mechanisms for <strong>scheduler interrupts</strong> to load-balance or preempt when
necessary.</li>
<li><strong>Extended Policies:</strong> Apple added features like <strong>container-level
prioritization</strong>. When iOS introduced App Sandbox with backgrounding, the
scheduler got a concept of a “task role” or “priority group”. In Darwin 9
(Leopard/iPhone OS), an “improved hierarchical process scheduling model” was
noted, which suggests that threads were grouped by tasks or by “workload”,
possibly to enforce limits on background tasks. This is likely the origin of
<strong>boosts and throttles</strong> that iOS uses to ensure the foreground app gets more
CPU than background apps.</li>
<li><strong>Quality of Service (QoS):</strong> In iOS 8 / OS X 10.10 and beyond, Apple
introduced QoS classes (user-interactive, user-initiated, default, utility,
background, etc.) for threads. The kernel scheduler integrates QoS by mapping
them to priority bands and scheduling deadlines. Threads created by Grand
Central Dispatch or NSThreads inherit a QoS that influences their scheduling
priority and which core they run on. This was further refined on Apple
Silicon where the scheduler might steer “background QoS” threads to
efficiency cores. Internally, XNU’s <code>sched_prim.c</code> and <code>sched_perf.c</code> (for
performance controller) handle these decisions. There is also an interface
for the kernel to ask the power management firmware about energy vs
performance (used in macOS’s power management QoS).</li>
<li><strong>Realtime and Multimedia:</strong> macOS supports realtime threads for audio or
critical tasks. The scheduler has a realtime queue and will preempt other
work to run RT threads to meet latency requirements. Also, since Mac OS X
10.4, XNU has <strong>scheduler deadlines</strong> for real-time threads (used for audio
playback, etc.), which is an EDF-like (Earliest deadline first) feature.</li>
<li><strong>Idle and Power:</strong> On mobile devices, the scheduler cooperates with the
power management to aggressively idle cores. Mach scheduler invokes an idle
thread when no work is available, and in iOS, if all cores are idle, the
system can enter low-power states quickly. Timer coalescing (10.9 Mavericks)
means the scheduler tries to batch wakeups – effectively, if several threads
have timers expiring, it aligns them to let CPU sleep longer intervals.</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, XNU’s scheduler has evolved from Mach’s general-purpose design to one
aware of <strong>multi-core</strong> and <strong>heterogeneous</strong> cores, <strong>energy vs performance</strong>
trade-offs, and <strong>workload groupings</strong> (like apps vs system daemons vs kernel
threads). It still uses Mach’s thread data structures, but many scheduling
algorithms have been tuned by Apple (sometimes influenced by developments in
FreeBSD or other OSes).</p>
<h3 id="memory-management-and-virtual-memory">Memory Management and Virtual Memory</h3>
<p>Memory management in XNU is primarily handled by Mach’s VM subsystem, which is
one of Mach’s strongest components. Key aspects:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Virtual Address Space:</strong> Each Mach task has a virtual address space
represented by a set of <strong>VM maps</strong> and <strong>VM regions</strong>. When a process (task)
is created, it starts with a copy of the parent’s address space. Mach’s VM is
inherently copy-on-write – <code>fork()</code> doesn’t duplicate all memory immediately;
instead, both parent and child share pages marked copy-on-write until either
writes, then a fault triggers an actual copy. This makes <code>fork()</code> efficient
despite potentially large processes.</li>
<li><strong>Memory Objects and Pagers:</strong> Mach introduces the concept of <em>memory
objects</em> to represent a backing store for memory (like a file or the swap
area) and <em>pagers</em> which supply data to those memory objects on demand. In
XNU, the <strong>default pager</strong> (for anonymous memory) is implemented by the
<code>dynamic_pager</code> user-space daemon which manages swap files. That is, when the
kernel decides to evict a page from RAM, Mach will send a message to the
default pager indicating the page should be written to swap. The
<code>dynamic_pager</code> then writes to the swap file (via normal file I/O). This is a
classic microkernel design: the <strong>pager runs in user space</strong>, meaning the
policy of how to manage swap space is not fixed in kernel. By adjusting or
replacing dynamic_pager, one could change swapping behavior (e.g., macOS’s
dynamic_pager can create multiple swap files on demand). File memory is
managed by a different pager: the <strong>vnode pager</strong> inside the kernel (this one
is not user-space, but part of XNU’s BSD layer) which interacts with file
system code to read/write file data for memory mapped files. Having this
modular pager design made features like <strong>compressed memory</strong> feasible to
implement – in Mavericks, an in-kernel compression pager was added: when
pressure is high, instead of immediately paging to disk, XNU can compress
inactive pages and keep them in a reserved VM object (the “compressor pool”)
in RAM. The VM considers that as a form of pseudo-swapping (faster than
disk). Only if compression is insufficient does it resort to disk swap via
dynamic_pager.</li>
<li><strong>Physical Memory Management:</strong> XNU abstracts physical memory operations in a
machine-dependent layer called <strong>pmap</strong> (physical map). The pmap manages page
tables or equivalent structures on each architecture. When Mach allocates a
new VM region, it uses pmap to map virtual pages to physical frames. On
ARM64, pmap also integrates with security features (like marking pages with
the appropriate permission keys for PAC, or handling aliasing issues with
caches). The kernel uses a <strong>zone allocator</strong> for many kernel memory
structures (zones are pools for objects of fixed size, like VM map entries,
IPC port structures, etc.). There’s also a general-purpose <strong>kernel malloc</strong>
(kmem) for variable sizes. Notably, the XNU kernel employs strategies to
mitigate fragmentation and has guard pages for certain allocations to detect
overruns (on debug kernels, typically).</li>
<li><strong>Shared Memory and Map Inheritance:</strong> Mach VM allows tasks to share regions
– either explicitly via Mach IPC (sending a port for a memory object) or via
inheritance (a child can inherit memory from parent on fork with
copy-on-write or shared semantics). This is how the dynamic linker works in
macOS: the shared cache of frameworks is mapped into every process at launch
via a shared memory region provided by <code>dyld</code>. Mach makes this efficient by
mapping the same physical pages into all tasks read-only.</li>
<li><strong>Kernel Virtual Memory:</strong> The kernel itself has a virtual address space.
Mach manages kernel memory similarly to user memory, but there are
differences: the kernel uses a single map for all of kernel space, and some
regions are wired (non-pageable). XNU historically had a 32-bit kernel for
which it used tricky schemes like a shared address space with user processes
(in early OS X on 32-bit, kernel and user shared space to avoid costly
segment switches, but on 64-bit this was not an issue). Modern XNU (64-bit)
uses a separate address space for kernel, with portions (like the shared
cache, comm page) mapped into user for communication.</li>
<li><strong>Memory Protection:</strong> Mach’s design enforces that one task cannot access
another task’s memory unless explicitly allowed. This is basic memory
protection via separate address spaces. The only controlled sharing is via
Mach VM APIs or if the kernel (or a privileged daemon) maps memory into
another task (used by things like the debugger or by the system frameworks to
implement features like XPC shared memory). The kernel also zero-fills memory
on allocation to avoid leakage between processes.</li>
<li><strong>Evolution for Apple Silicon:</strong> On Apple Silicon, with large physical memory
and unified memory, XNU’s VM had to consider not having distinct GPU memory.
Instead, I/O Kit drivers for GPU allocate from general memory with certain
attributes (e.g., contiguous, protected). The pmap might have optimizations
for the extremely large virtual address space (ARMv8.5 supports 52-bit VA).
Also, memory tagging (MTE) if used would mean the kernel must manage tag
bits in pointers and memory; Apple hasn’t announced using it, but the
hardware is there on M2. If enabled, the kernel would tag allocations and
check tags on load/store, catching use-after-free or overflow.</li>
</ul>
<p>XNU’s VM is regarded as quite advanced due to its Mach heritage – it was built
for 64-bit from the start (Mach had 64-bit addressing on 32-bit hardware via
abstractions), and it’s relatively decoupled from the rest of kernel logic,
which is why Apple could plug in new features (compressor, different
pagers) without massive overhaul.</p>
<h3 id="virtualization-support">Virtualization Support</h3>
<p>While Mach’s original vision could be seen as a form of virtualization
(multiple OS personalities on one kernel), modern hardware virtualization is a
different beast. XNU did not originally include a hypervisor in early releases,
but as virtualization became important, Apple added support. On <strong>Intel Macs</strong>,
XNU gained the ability to manage the hardware virtualization extensions (Intel
VT-x) around 2014. Apple provided a <strong>Hypervisor.framework</strong> API to developers
from OS&nbsp;X 10.10 onward, enabling user-space virtualization without third-party
kernel extensions. Under the hood, a kernel extension (or part of XNU) would
configure VMX operations, allowing a user-space process to act as a virtual
machine monitor. This was used by tools like <strong>xhyve</strong> (a port of FreeBSD’s
bhyve to macOS), and by virtualization apps when running without their own
drivers.</p>
<p>On <strong>Apple Silicon (ARM64)</strong>, the approach is similar conceptually: XNU on
these devices can act as a Type-2 hypervisor using ARM’s virtualization
extensions (EL2 on ARM). Apple introduced a more full-featured
<strong>Virtualization.framework</strong> in macOS 11, which builds on an in-kernel
hypervisor to let developers run Linux or even macOS VMs in user space. One
design decision on Apple Silicon was to not allow arbitrary third-party
hypervisors in kernel; instead, the hypervisor is part of XNU but only
accessible via Apple’s frameworks with proper entitlements (to maintain
security).</p>
<p>From a kernel perspective, the XNU hypervisor functionality includes: managing
<strong>guest physical memory</strong>, handling <strong>trap and emulate</strong> for sensitive
instructions, and exposing virtual CPU interfaces to user space (for instance,
allowing a user program to set register state and run a vCPU until the next VM
exit). The Mach scheduling is leveraged to schedule vCPUs (which are just
threads from the host’s point of view). The memory subsystem is used to map
guest memory. On Apple Silicon, features like Stage 2 page tables for guests
are managed likely by an in-kernel hypervisor module.</p>
<p>Additionally, XNU supports containers and emulation in various ways (not full
virtualization but worth noting): the <strong>XNU kernel supports multiple user-space
“personalities”</strong> only in a limited sense now (for example, the Rosetta 2
x86_64 code translator on ARM is not a separate OS but it does require the
kernel to manage alternate CPU context for x86 state). The kernel includes an
<strong>x86 emulator</strong> or at least support for handling x86 code segmentation, etc.,
when Rosetta translates x86 code to ARM64 – primarily done in user space by
Rosetta’s JIT, the kernel might assist e.g. with syscall translation or by
providing an x86_64 syscall ABI on ARM.</p>
<p>The design choices around virtualization emphasize security and performance:
Apple’s approach is to keep the hypervisor simple and lean and to strongly
isolate guest OSes from the host (different Mach task, limited communication).
As of iOS 15, Apple even allows <strong>virtualization on iOS</strong> (to run Linux inside
an iPad app, for example, which some developers have demoed), indicating the
XNU hypervisor is capable on mobile as well, though subject to entitlement.</p>
<p>In summary, virtualization in XNU spans from the conceptual Mach
multi-personality support (not widely used in products outside early Classic
environment on OS&nbsp;X which ran Mac OS 9 in a para-virtualized setup), to robust
hardware-assisted virtualization on modern Macs.</p>
<h3 id="secure-computing">Secure Computing</h3>
<p>MacOS uses two complementary but distinct isolation mechanisms—<strong>Secure
Enclaves</strong> and the more recently introduced <strong>exclaves</strong>—to protect sensitive
operations and data.</p>
<p>The <strong>Secure Enclave</strong> is a dedicated, hardened subsystem integrated into
Apple’s SoCs (found in iPhones, iPads, Macs with T2 or Apple Silicon, etc.). It
runs its own microkernel‐based operating system (historically a variant of L4
called sepOS) and is used to manage and protect cryptographic keys, biometric
data, and other sensitive information. Its design isolates critical data even
if the main application processor or kernel is compromised. In short, it’s a
“trusted box” built into the hardware that handles security‑critical tasks
independently.</p>
<p><strong>Exclaves</strong>, by contrast, are a newer security innovation (first appearing in
macOS 14.4 and iOS 17) that further subdivide the operating system’s
privileges. Instead of having all sensitive operations run in the same
privileged domain as the main XNU kernel, Apple is now isolating key resources
into separate, “externally located” domains. These resources—such as Apple ID
services for virtual machines, audio buffers, sensor data, and even components
that manage indicator lights—are pre‑configured at boot and are managed by
specialized kernel extensions (e.g., ExclaveKextClient.kext,
ExclaveSEPManagerProxy.kext, and ExclavesAudioKext.kext) along with private
frameworks.</p>
<p>In geographical terms, an enclave is a territory entirely enclosed within
another, which aptly describes the Secure Enclave’s containment within the SoC.
An exclave, on the other hand, is a fragment that is separated from the main
territory yet still associated with it—mirroring how these isolated resources
exist outside the main XNU kernel while remaining tightly integrated with the
overall system. This separation means that even if the main kernel is
compromised, the operations running in exclaves remain insulated, offering
additional defense in depth.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Darwin and XNU offer a fascinating case study of an operating system that is
<em>neither fully microkernel nor monolithic</em>, but a judicious mix. Its evolution
illustrates trade-offs in OS design: performance vs. modularity, generality vs.
specialization. XNU’s Mach-based core, once considered a performance liability,
has proven to be a strength in adapting to new architectures and enabling
system-wide features (like seamless multi-OS integration on Apple Silicon, or
fine-grained sandboxing). Meanwhile, the BSD layer ensured that developers and
applications have a rich, POSIX-compliant environment, with all the expected
UNIX tools and APIs, greatly smoothing the adoption and software portability
for the platform.</p>
<p>In the modern era, as hardware trends move towards specialized processors and
increased parallelism, XNU continues to incorporate new techniques (e.g.,
dispatch queues, QoS scheduling, and direct support for machine learning
accelerators through drivers) while maintaining robustness. The Darwin OS,
through open source releases, also provides researchers a window into a
commercial-grade hybrid kernel (albeit not a very good window), inspiring
efforts in OS architecture that blend ideas from both camps of the classic
microkernel debate.</p>
<p>Apple’s Darwin has thus grown from a niche NeXTSTEP OS to the core of millions
of devices, all the while <strong>tracing a line of continuity back to Mach and
BSD</strong>. Each major transition – be it new CPU architectures (PowerPC→Intel→ARM),
new device categories, or new security paradigms – has been met by XNU with an
architectural answer: <em>extend</em> (not rewrite) the kernel, <em>integrate</em> components
tightly when needed, and <em>isolate</em> through Mach IPC when possible. This
balanced evolution of Darwin’s kernel showcases a successful long-term OS
design, one that remains at the forefront of commercial operating systems while
rooted in decades of operating systems research.</p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Singh, Amit. <em>Mac OS X Internals: A Systems Approach</em>. Addison-Wesley, 2006
(for historical and architectural insights).</li>
<li>Apple Developer Documentation – Kernel Architecture Overview (<a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/archive/documentation/Darwin/Conceptual/KernelProgramming/Architecture/Architecture.html">Kernel
Architecture
Overview</a>).</li>
<li>Wikipedia: <em>XNU Kernel</em> (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XNU">XNU -
Wikipedia</a>), <em>Darwin OS</em> release history
(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Darwin_(operating_system)">Darwin (operating system) -
Wikipedia</a>).</li>
<li>Chisnall, David. “What Is Mac OS X?” InformIT (2010) (<a href="https://www.informit.com/articles/article.aspx?p=1552774">What Is Mac OS X? | A
Mach-O System |
InformIT</a>).</li>
<li>24C3: <em>Inside the Mac OS X Kernel</em> (Ilja van Sprundel, 2007) (<a href="https://fahrplan.events.ccc.de/congress/2007/Fahrplan/attachments/986_inside_the_mac_osx_kernel.pdf">Inside the Mac
OS X
Kernel</a>).</li>
<li>Mazurek, Karol. “Snake&amp;Apple X.NU” Medium (2024) (<a href="https://karol-mazurek.medium.com/snake-apple-x-nu-0bc5c36170da">Snake&amp;Apple X.NU |
Medium</a>).
(Security-focused kernel internals series).</li>
</ul>
<section data-footnotes="">
<ol>
<li id="user-content-fn-1">
<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Return-oriented_programming">Return-oriented
programming</a> is
a computer security exploit technique that allows an attacker to execute
code in the presence of security defenses such as executable-space
protection and code signing. <a href="#user-content-fnref-1" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 1">↩</a></p>
</li>
<li id="user-content-fn-2">
<p><a href="https://worthdoingbadly.com/hv/">Hardware-accelerated virtual machines on jailbroken iPhone 12 / iOS 14.1
| Worth Doing Badly</a> <a href="#user-content-fnref-2" data-footnote-backref="" aria-label="Back to reference 2">↩</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>   </article> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The ADHD Body Double: A Unique Tool for Getting Things Done (321 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://add.org/the-body-double/</link>
            <guid>43597425</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 05 Apr 2025 22:45:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://add.org/the-body-double/">https://add.org/the-body-double/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=43597425">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
			
<p>Can something as simple as another person’s presence make it easier to stay on task?</p>



<p>While there’s no research to prove its effectiveness, ADHD body doubling is helping many people get things done – starting with my client, David.</p>



<p>When I first met David, he was a retired vice president of a major corporation. In his “retirement,” he ran three businesses out of his home office, two of them overseas.</p>



<p>Observing David in his workspace, I found him to be quite organized. He wasn’t sitting eyeball-high in papers. In fact, he hardly had any papers around him at all.</p>



<p>He had working systems in place, but felt terribly disorganized and distracted.</p>



<p>David contacted me because I specialize in coaching <a href="https://add.org/adhd-in-adults/">adults with Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD)</a>. During my twenty-three years of coaching, I have gathered many tools and strategies for helping clients accomplish desired change and create order out of chaos.</p>



<p>The tool I want to share with you today is one born of the unique mix of client and coach inventing together. I call it <em>the body double.</em></p>



<p><em><strong>Originally published in 1996, this article was republished on February 20th, 2025.</strong></em></p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1920" height="1280" src="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online.jpg" alt="A man reading an article online" srcset="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online.jpg 1920w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online-300x200.jpg 300w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online-768x512.jpg 768w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online-800x533.jpg 800w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/A-man-reading-an-article-online-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px"></figure>



<h2><strong>What Is ADHD Body Doubling?</strong></h2>



<p>The methodology of ADHD body doubling is a productivity strategy used by individuals with ADHD to finish possibly annoying jobs while having another person beside them. This person is the body double. The body double’s duty is to keep the individual with ADHD focused on the task at hand to reduce potential distractions and increase motivation.</p>



<p>David had been surprised by a recent diagnosis of ADD, which explained his lifelong difficulty accomplishing mundane tasks that others seemed to handle with ease.</p>



<p>As a VP in the corporate world, he had always had an executive assistant to connect the dots and pull loose ends together. Now, however, he had the time to do these tasks. He even had the will to do them. He just couldn’t stay on track.</p>



<p>David’s wife also ran a business out of their home and had her own well-organized office. She offered to advise him, but they both quickly agreed this just didn’t work.</p>



<p>That’s when they asked for help.</p>



<p>First, I helped David modify his storage systems. Then, together, we honed his time management and prioritization systems.</p>



<p>Nothing, however, seemed to address the problem of his inattention and distraction. There were days, too many days, when he easily got off track or found it hard to transition from one task to another.</p>



<p>Frustrated, puzzled, and somewhat embarrassed, he confessed, “You know, it seems that, sometimes, if I just have my wife sitting in a chair nearby, I can accomplish more than if I’m alone.”</p>



<p>Though reluctantly, David had identified a strategy that really worked for him. I instantly realized that I had seen this same effect before with other clients.</p>



<p>There were times when just having someone in proximity (not advising, sorting, or strategizing) brought clarity and focus. I felt it. I knew my clients felt it, too.</p>



<p>This phenomenon of <em>just being there</em>, which David first described out loud, I named the body double.</p>



<figure><img decoding="async" width="1280" height="853" src="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double.jpg" alt="Working productively with a body double" srcset="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double.jpg 1280w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double-300x200.jpg 300w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double-768x512.jpg 768w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double-800x533.jpg 800w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Working-productively-with-a-body-double-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px"></figure>



<h2><strong>How Does Body Doubling Work?</strong></h2>



<p>For many people with ADHD, finding the motivation to get the ball rolling can be quite a challenge. This can lead to procrastination. <a href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/full/10.1080/00050067.2023.2218540#abstract" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><sup>[1]</sup></a> They may also find themselves easily distracted by unrelated thoughts or activities<a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC10421702/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><sup>[2]</sup></a></p>



<p>This is where body doubling comes into play!&nbsp;</p>



<p>To start body doubling, all you need is a family member, colleague, or peer. It can be done physically or virtually, as long as someone is present while you work. You and your body double will agree on a set time and block the session out on your calendar.&nbsp;</p>



<p>The aim of a body doubling session is for you and your body double to work alongside each other. You don’t have to do the same thing. What’s most important is that both of you are working on <em>something</em>. That could be doing the laundry, paying bills, exercising, or completing a work project.&nbsp;</p>



<p>It also helps to share your goals with your body double at the start of the session. This allows them to hold you accountable for what you need or want to achieve.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Body doubling is effective because it helps create a strong sense of accountability. That extra bit of pressure from being watched can go a long way toward holding you responsible. That way, you’re more likely to follow through on your actions.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Body doubling can also help to mix things up. It adds freshness to a boring routine. This can be helpful since the ADHD brain craves novelty.<a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s40806-024-00400-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><sup>[3]</sup></a></p>



<h2><strong>Why Does Body Doubling Work?</strong></h2>



<p>There are a few possible explanations as to why a body double works as a strategy for getting through challenging or boring tasks. In the moment, it can counter <a href="https://add.org/signs-of-adhd/">ADHD symptoms</a> that sap motivation, focus, and energy.</p>



<h3><strong>A Supportive Presence Adds Motivation</strong></h3>



<p>The simplest is that the body double serves as a physical anchor for the distracted individual who feels more focused by the presence of another person in their space.</p>



<p>The distracted person feels responsible to and for the body double.</p>



<p>This perception translates as­–<em>I can’t waste this gift of time.</em></p>



<p>Another explanation might be that the body double serves as a kind of <em>mirror – </em>a calm reflection for the individual with ADHD of how their <a href="https://add.org/sensory-overload-adhd/">over-stimulated mind and body</a> would like to be at the moment.</p>



<p>This concept is called ADHD mirroring. It happens when someone with ADHD follows the behaviors of other people, often unconsciously, to fit in. In many cases, ADHD mirroring can be draining, as it takes energy to mask symptoms of ADHD by copying others.&nbsp;</p>



<p>However, in the case of body doubling, the unconscious act of mirroring can be beneficial. Watching someone else stay focused on a task can naturally encourage the person with ADHD to do the same.&nbsp;</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1280" src="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique.jpg" alt="People with ADHD practicing the body double technique" srcset="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique.jpg 1920w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique-300x200.jpg 300w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique-768x512.jpg 768w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique-800x533.jpg 800w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/People-with-ADHD-practicing-the-body-double-technique-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px"></figure>



<h3><strong>It Provides a Model of Calm Focus</strong></h3>



<p>The body double becomes a model of control and a mirror, confidently reflecting the message: <em>I can concentrate. I am working. I am focused</em>.</p>



<p>This theory might actually carry some weight. In the 1980s, neuroscientist Giacomo Rizzolatti, MD, along with colleagues at the University of Parma, made a serendipitous discovery while researching macaque monkeys. They observed that specific neurons in the macaque’s brain fired when watching another monkey, or a human, reach for a peanut. They named these neurons “mirror neurons.”<a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/whats-so-special-about-mirror-neurons/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><sup>[4]</sup></a></p>



<p>The researchers theorized that mirror neurons also existed in humans and were the likely explanation for our ability to emulate and empathize with others.</p>



<p>As much as this makes sense and sounds like the perfect validation for the body double effect, please note that the scientific community is somewhat divided about whether humans actually have mirror neurons.</p>



<p>So, the mirror neuron theory does not give us a definitive answer.</p>



<h3><strong>Adds Positive Energy to the Workspace</strong></h3>



<p>I have one more explanation to offer as to why the body double might work.</p>



<p>In Eastern cultures, energy is referred to as chi (or qi). It is viewed as being either in or out of balance in the human body and the surrounding environment.</p>



<p>Acupuncturists move chi, or energy, to recreate balance and promote health. There are many forms of exercise and meditation, tai chi and chi gong, to name a few, which are about the management and flow of energy.</p>



<p>Feng shui (fung shway) is the 5,000-year-old art of balancing positive and negative chi in the space around us, with the goal of optimizing healthy energy in one’s living and working space.</p>



<p>What would chi have to do with a body double? The body double might be a chi balancer or protective barrier helping to contain and calm the energy in and around the person with ADHD. The body double might also be a buffer against distracting energy from the outside, ready to bombard the vulnerable <a href="https://add.org/adhd-brain/">ADHD brain</a>.</p>



<p>Whichever explanation you prefer, there’s no denying the effectiveness of the body double.</p>



<p>Consider this strategy a gift from David and the many other ADHDers who have experienced its magic. If a task requires your attention and seems impossible to complete alone – beg, borrow, or pay for a body double to sit in the chair next to you.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1280" height="853" src="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together.jpg" alt="Colleagues working together" srcset="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together.jpg 1280w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together-300x200.jpg 300w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together-1024x682.jpg 1024w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together-768x512.jpg 768w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together-800x533.jpg 800w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/04/Colleagues-working-together-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px"></figure>



<h2><strong>Benefits of Body Doubling</strong></h2>



<p>Body doubling can be a powerful tool, especially if you struggle with focus and motivation.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you’re not already convinced to give it a try, here are the possible benefits of body doubling:&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Improved focus:</strong> Having a body double helps you stay accountable. This technique creates positive reinforcement by gently nudging you to focus and stay on track.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Increased motivation:</strong> The presence of someone else can create a sense of accountability and novelty, increasing your motivation to get the ball rolling.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Reduced procrastination:</strong> By planning and setting aside time to work alongside someone else, you’re more likely to get started when the time comes. This helps you avoid postponing and delaying your tasks.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Improved time management:</strong> You can dedicate a specific time block in your day to body doubling sessions. This reduces wasted time due to delays and can save time by minimizing distractions.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Improved mood:</strong> Having someone around you when you work can create a positive atmosphere and reduce stress. Your body double can also serve as a source of support, cheering you on as you reach your session goals.&nbsp;</li>



<li><strong>Boosted productivity:</strong> When focused and motivated, you’re bound to get more done in less time.&nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<p>Of course, if you want to reap these benefits and get the best results, it’s essential to find a suitable body double. The right body double won’t distract you or create <em>too much</em> pressure. Instead, their presence should help you feel encouraged, empowered, and ready to tackle your to-do list!&nbsp;</p>



<h2><strong>What to Look for in a Body Double</strong></h2>



<p>Who and what should you look for in a body double?</p>



<p>Find someone who can be quiet and independent. They can sit, read, knit, or work quietly on a laptop. Their job is to not engage with you.</p>



<p>It requires energy to instruct, supervise, or be interrupted by another person, and that expenditure of energy equates to distraction.</p>



<p>This is not to say that you do not need to hire outside help – a professional organizer or office assistant.</p>



<p>You may also consider finding an <a href="https://add.org/how-to-find-an-adhd-coach/">ADHD coach</a> to help you identify the best strategies for you.</p>



<p>I encouraged David to hire a student, retiree, or fellow church member to sit and keep him company. His wife may not be the best person for the job, but he could use her in a pinch.</p>



<p>Following our discovery, David occasionally hired short-term office support help, who sometimes served as a body double and other times as office assistants. Knowing when to hire someone to help with office work or with just paying the bills is a valuable skill in getting things done.</p>



<p>There are also many different ways to try this technique. Some people prefer body doubling for longer periods, while others find shorter sessions with small breaks in between more effective.</p>



<p>You can also choose between in-person groups, online sessions with your camera and microphone on, or virtual focus groups with a chat-only feature.</p>



<p>Additionally, try to experiment with different times of the day. Some ADHDers find that body doubling boosts their productivity in the morning but doesn’t work as well in the evening, or vice versa.</p>



<p>Ultimately, not all body-doubling techniques work for everyone. To find what works best for you, you can test it with different people, groups, timings, and structures.</p>



<p>Regardless of the approach, body doubling can be an effective accountability tool for hitting your daily goals.</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1920" height="1280" src="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work.jpg" alt="Colleagues focused on their work" srcset="https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work.jpg 1920w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work-300x200.jpg 300w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work-1024x683.jpg 1024w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work-768x512.jpg 768w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work-800x533.jpg 800w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work-1536x1024.jpg 1536w, https://add.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Colleagues-focused-on-their-work-600x400.jpg 600w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px"></figure>



<h2><strong>Where to Find a Body Double?</strong></h2>



<p>One of the best places to find a suitable body double is in your own community. You can get a friend or family member to work alongside you physically or virtually.</p>



<p>Alternatively, you can consider hiring someone to spend time sitting beside you as you get things done.</p>



<p>Virtual body doubling can also work wonders. You can work with a group or partner from anywhere in the world at any time. For this, you’d typically be matched through an online platform.</p>



<p>Various websites and apps can connect you to a body double from their own community. For instance, FocusMate allows you to connect with a virtual body double from anywhere in the world to co-work and get things done.</p>



<p>Another example is the <a href="https://add.org/adda-virtual-peer-support-group-studyhall-pomodoro-style/">ADDA Productivity PowerHour+ support group</a>, which combines body doubling with another time management strategy called the Pomodoro technique. You’d participate in these sessions with a group of ADDA members.</p>



<h2><strong>Using Body Doubling for ADHD</strong></h2>



<p>In lieu of any proven scientific explanation, the body double is a chair holder, space taker-upper, karmic anchor, or a wedge between you and the door.</p>



<p>Hopefully, it might be a helpful tool in your magic bag of tricks to use at just the right time to get a job done and stay on track.</p>



<h2><strong>Using External Accountability to Boost Your Productivity</strong></h2>



<p>Because of how the ADHD brain is wired, being productive can be easier said than done. The good news is that you don’t have to rely on willpower alone!&nbsp;</p>



<p>External accountability is one of many practical tools for boosting productivity. Body doubling enables you to find this external accountability in an easy and structured way.&nbsp;</p>



<p>If you’d like to learn more about adult ADHD, <a href="https://add.org/adda-plus/">ADDA+</a> offers 200+ webinars, peer support groups, work groups, and much more.</p>



<p>Linda Anderson, MA, MCC, SCAC, is a master certified coach, a leader in the field of ADHD coaching, and the founder of <a href="https://gettingclear.com/">Getting Clear</a>.</p>



<h2><strong>References</strong></h2>



<p>[1] Ruth Netzer Turgeman, &amp; Pollak, Y. (2023). Using the temporal motivation theory to explain the relation between ADHD and procrastination. Using the Temporal Motivation Theory to Explain the Relation between ADHD and Procrastination, 58(6), 1–9. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/00050067.2023.2218540" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://doi.org/10.1080/00050067.2023.2218540</a></p>



<p>‌[2] Osborne, J. B., Zhang, H., Carlson, M., Shah, P., &amp; Jonides, J. (2023). The association between different sources of distraction and symptoms of attention deficit hyperactivity disorder. Frontiers in psychiatry, 14, 1173989. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1173989" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyt.2023.1173989</a></p>



<p>[3] Anne-Laure Le Cunff. (2024). Distractibility and Impulsivity in ADHD as an Evolutionary Mismatch of High Trait Curiosity. Evolutionary Psychological Science. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40806-024-00400-8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://doi.org/10.1007/s40806-024-00400-8</a></p>



<p>[4] Thomas, B. (November 6, 2012) What’s So Special about Mirror Neurons? Scientific American. Retrieved May 1, 2016, from <a href="http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/whats-so-special-about-mirror-neurons/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">http://blogs.scientificamerican.com/guest-blog/whats-so-special-about-mirror-neurons/</a></p>
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>