<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 08:30:03 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[IMG_0001 (402 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://walzr.com/IMG_0001/</link>
            <guid>42314547</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 04:46:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://walzr.com/IMG_0001/">https://walzr.com/IMG_0001/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42314547">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Between 2009 and 2012, iPhones had a built-in "Send to YouTube" button in the Photos app. Many of these uploads kept their default IMG_XXXX filenames, creating a time capsule of raw, unedited moments from random lives. </p><p>Inspired by <a href="https://ben-mini.github.io/2024/img-0416" target="_blank">Ben Wallace</a>, I made a bot that crawled YouTube and found 5 million of these videos! Watch them below, ordered randomly.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Phoenix LiveView 1.0.0 is here (438 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.phoenixframework.org/blog/phoenix-liveview-1.0-released?release=1.0</link>
            <guid>42312301</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 22:28:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.phoenixframework.org/blog/phoenix-liveview-1.0-released?release=1.0">https://www.phoenixframework.org/blog/phoenix-liveview-1.0-released?release=1.0</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42312301">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.phoenixframework.org/blog/phoenix-liveview-1.0-released?release=1.0: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[My son (9 yrs old) used plain JavaScript to make a game, and wants your feedback (515 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.armaansahni.com/game/</link>
            <guid>42312121</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 22:08:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.armaansahni.com/game/">https://www.armaansahni.com/game/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42312121">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.armaansahni.com/game/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Egoless Engineering (480 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://egoless.engineering</link>
            <guid>42311069</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 20:38:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://egoless.engineering">https://egoless.engineering</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42311069">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://egoless.engineering: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: My C compiler compiled itself (140 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/keyvank/30cc</link>
            <guid>42311031</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 20:35:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/keyvank/30cc">https://github.com/keyvank/30cc</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42311031">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">30 C Compiler!</h2><a id="user-content-30-c-compiler" aria-label="Permalink: 30 C Compiler!" href="#30-c-compiler"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>30cc</code> (Pronounced as <em>CCC</em>, because in the Persian language, the number 30 is pronounced as C) is a toy C compiler written in C, which is strong enough to compile itself 🤝 This was my first attempt in writing a self-hosting software! What is a self-hosting software?</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Imagine <code>30cc</code> gets strong enough to be able to compile itself.</li>
<li>I will first compile <code>30cc</code> with <code>gcc</code> to get the <code>30cc</code> compiler's binary.</li>
<li>I will then use the <code>gcc</code>-generated <code>30cc</code> binary file to compile the <code>30cc</code> again.</li>
<li>I now have a <code>30cc</code>-compiled version of <code>30cc</code>, which I can use for further developing the compiler!</li>
<li>I can forget about <code>gcc</code>, as if it never existed! Beautiful hah? <code>30cc</code> is now all alive by itself!</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><code>30cc</code> emits x86-64 assembly as its output. The outputs are totally unoptimized, but that's fine, the project aims to be educational.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>You'll first need to bootstrap the compiler by running <code>make</code>. This will compile the 30cc compiler and store its binary in <code>a.out</code>.</li>
<li>Then run <code>./build.py</code>. This will use the bootstrapped 30cc-compiler to compile 30cc itself. It then again uses the 30cc-compiled compiler to compile 30cc once again. The final compiler is then stored as <code>./30cc</code>.</li>
<li>In the end, you will have 3 binary files which should all behave the same:
<ol dir="auto">
<li><code>a.out</code> which is the bootstrapped gcc-compiled version of 30cc</li>
<li><code>30cc_gcc</code> which is the output of gcc-compiled 30cc compiler, compiling the 30cc compiler</li>
<li><code>30cc</code> which is the output of 30cc-compiled 30cc compiler, compiling the 30cc compiler</li>
</ol>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Running independent source-files through <code>make</code>:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="make run program=./examples/inp.c arguments=something"><pre><code>make run program=./examples/inp.c arguments=something
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contribute</h2><a id="user-content-contribute" aria-label="Permalink: Contribute" href="#contribute"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Tests</h3><a id="user-content-tests" aria-label="Permalink: Tests" href="#tests"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To run tests use</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="python scripts/test.py update"><pre><code>python scripts/test.py update
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Then check the output of the tests.</p>
<p dir="auto">If you are on mac use <code>./scripts/test_mac.sh</code> to run the tests in docker.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Text Editing Hates You Too (2019) (114 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://lord.io/text-editing-hates-you-too/</link>
            <guid>42310461</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 19:48:14 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://lord.io/text-editing-hates-you-too/">https://lord.io/text-editing-hates-you-too/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42310461">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://lord.io/text-editing-hates-you-too/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Tube Computer (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.thetubecomputer.com/</link>
            <guid>42309790</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 18:54:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.thetubecomputer.com/">https://www.thetubecomputer.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42309790">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="a1935d0447e10099871f84ce814e14d1" data-plugin="TextArea"><p>My stepdaughter is a senior Product Manager and my stepson is a Chartered Engineer and he frequently works as a Project Manager. They would know how to manage this project. Luckily they are too successful and busy to ever read this, thank goodness!</p>



<p>I tried doing the project management on a PC but gave up, and instead used 3 coloured pens, A4 paper and self adhesive address labels to cover up my mistakes. I simply found it easier. The only problem I discovered is that the paper gets a bit thick after several layers of amendments, but the big advantage is that can always find your latest version, it's simply the thickest.</p>



<p>The main thing I discovered was that the first time I tried almost anything I failed, but the annoying experience often enabled future success.</p>



<p>I first started by stabbing at various bits of the idea. Eventually I was able to define what I wanted to do. I now realise that this definition, was the most important part of the whole project management!</p>



<p>The program seemed to consist of many complex components, all of which I needed to understand, to be able to build The Tube Computer.</p>



<p>How do thermionic vacuum tubes work, how do you design a PCB, and how on earth do you get from a NOR gate, to a memory register, via microcodes from a clock, binary counters, and a ROM, to actually run software. And what exactly is a microcode anyway. At times, in fact most of the time, it all just seemed impossible.</p>



<p>The main solutions I found were, firstly to keep the number of unique sub systems to an absolute minimum. Secondly to use double triode tubes to halve the physical size, which also reduced the construction time. And thirdly, to design multi layer printed circuit boards to reduce the inevitable build errors and produce a robust construction.</p>



<p>The Tube Computer has behaved itself so far, unlike a previous system that went BANG twice. The first time I pulled out plugs like my life depended on it, and Judy cried, “Everything all right!”. The second time I only slightly panicked, and Judy continued to decorate the Christmas tree, but later bought me a surprise present, a fire extinguisher!</p>



<p>But most important of all, is to have a lovely wife, who knows you're daft as a brush, and that life together is brilliant.</p>



<p>Best wishes, Mike and Judy.</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FTC takes action against Gravy Analytics, Venntel for selling location data (151 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-gravy-analytics-venntel-unlawfully-selling-location-data-tracking-consumers</link>
            <guid>42309429</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 18:25:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-gravy-analytics-venntel-unlawfully-selling-location-data-tracking-consumers">https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-gravy-analytics-venntel-unlawfully-selling-location-data-tracking-consumers</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42309429">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.ftc.gov/news-events/news/press-releases/2024/12/ftc-takes-action-against-gravy-analytics-venntel-unlawfully-selling-location-data-tracking-consumers: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon Nova (313 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/introducing-amazon-nova-frontier-intelligence-and-industry-leading-price-performance/</link>
            <guid>42309121</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 18:04:45 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/introducing-amazon-nova-frontier-intelligence-and-industry-leading-price-performance/">https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/aws/introducing-amazon-nova-frontier-intelligence-and-industry-leading-price-performance/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42309121">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section property="articleBody"> 
       <div id="amazon-polly-audio-tab"> 
            
            
            
           <p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/polly/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><img src="https://a0.awsstatic.com/aws-blog/images/Voiced_by_Amazon_Polly_EN.png" alt="Voiced by Polly" width="554" height="56"></a> 
           </p> </div> 
       <p>Today, we’re thrilled to announce <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/nova">Amazon Nova</a>, a new generation of state-of-the-art <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/what-is/foundation-models/">foundation models (FMs)</a> that deliver frontier intelligence and industry leading price performance, available exclusively in <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/">Amazon Bedrock</a>.</p> 
       <p>You can use Amazon Nova to lower costs and latency for almost any <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/ai/generative-ai/">generative AI</a> task. You can build on Amazon Nova to analyze complex documents and videos, understand charts and diagrams, generate engaging video content, and build sophisticated AI agents, from across a range of intelligence&nbsp;classes optimized for enterprise workloads.</p> 
       <p>Whether you’re developing document processing applications that need to process images and text, creating marketing content at scale, or building AI assistants that can understand and act on visual information, Amazon Nova provides the intelligence and flexibility you need with two categories of models: understanding and creative content generation.</p> 
       <p>Amazon Nova understanding models accept text, image, or video inputs to generate text output. Amazon creative content generation models accept text and image inputs to generate image or video output.</p> 
       <p><span><strong>Understanding models: Text and visual intelligence<br> </strong></span>The Amazon Nova models include three understanding models (with a fourth one coming soon) designed to meet different needs:</p> 
       <p><strong>Amazon Nova Micro</strong> – A text-only model that delivers the lowest latency responses in the Amazon Nova family of models at a very low cost. With a context length of 128K tokens and optimized for speed and cost, Amazon Nova Micro excels at tasks such as text summarization, translation, content classification, interactive chat and brainstorming, and simple mathematical reasoning and coding. Amazon Nova Micro also supports customization on proprietary data using fine-tuning and model distillation to boost accuracy.</p> 
       <p><strong>Amazon Nova Lite</strong> – A very low-cost multimodal model that is lightning fast for processing image, video, and text inputs to generate text output. Amazon Nova Lite can handle real-time customer interactions, document analysis, and visual question-answering tasks with high accuracy. The model processes inputs up to 300K tokens in length and can analyze multiple images or up to 30 minutes of video in a single request. Amazon Nova Lite also supports text and multimodal fine-tuning and can be optimized to deliver the best quality and costs for your use case with techniques such as model distillation.</p> 
       <p><strong>Amazon Nova Pro</strong> – A highly capable multimodal model with the best combination of accuracy, speed, and cost for a wide range of tasks. Amazon Nova Pro is capable of processing up to 300K input tokens and sets new standards in multimodal intelligence and agentic workflows that require calling APIs and tools to complete complex workflows. It achieves state-of-the-art performance on key benchmarks including visual question answering (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.08920">TextVQA</a>) and video understanding (<a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1904.03493">VATEX</a>). Amazon Nova Pro demonstrates strong capabilities in processing both visual and textual information and excels at analyzing financial documents. With an input context of 300K tokens, it can process code bases with over fifteen thousand lines of code. Amazon Nova Pro also serves as a teacher model to distill custom variants of Amazon Nova Micro and Lite.</p> 
       <p><strong>Amazon Nova Premier</strong> – Our most capable multimodal model for complex reasoning tasks and for use as the best teacher for distilling custom models. Amazon Nova Premier is still in training. We’re targeting availability in early 2025.</p> 
       <p>Amazon Nova understanding models excel in <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/what-is/retrieval-augmented-generation/">Retrieval-Augmented Generation (RAG)</a>, function calling, and agentic applications. This is reflected in Amazon Nova model scores in the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04744">Comprehensive RAG Benchmark (CRAG)</a> evaluation, <a href="https://gorilla.cs.berkeley.edu/blogs/8_berkeley_function_calling_leaderboard.html">Berkeley Function Calling Leaderboard (BFCL)</a>, <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05955">VisualWebBench</a>, and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.06070">Mind2Web</a>.</p> 
       <p>What makes Amazon Nova particularly powerful for enterprises is its customization capabilities. Think of it as tailoring a suit: you start with a high-quality foundation and adjust it to fit your exact needs. You can fine-tune the models with text, image, and video to understand your industry’s terminology, align with your brand voice, and optimize for your specific use cases. For instance, a legal firm might customize Amazon Nova to better understand legal terminology and document structures.</p> 
       <p>You can see the latest benchmark scores for these models on the <a href="http://aws.amazon.com/nova">Amazon Nova product page</a>.</p> 
       <p><span><strong>Creative content generation: Bringing concepts to life<br> </strong></span>The Amazon Nova models also include two creative content generation models:</p> 
       <p><strong>Amazon Nova Canvas</strong> – A state-of-the-art image generation model producing studio-quality images with precise control over style and content, including rich editing features such as inpainting, outpainting, and background removal. Amazon Nova Canvas excels on human evaluations and key benchmarks such as <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.11897#:~:text=We%20introduce%20TIFA%20(Text%2Dto,visual%20question%20answering%20(VQA).">text-to-image faithfulness evaluation with question answering (TIFA)</a> and <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.05977">ImageReward</a>.</p> 
       <p><strong>Amazon Nova Reel</strong> – A state-of-the-art video generation model. Using Amazon Nova Reel, you can produce short videos through text prompts and images, control visual style and pacing, and generate professional-quality video content for marketing, advertising, and entertainment. Amazon Nova Reel outperforms existing models on human evaluations of video quality and video consistency.</p> 
       <p>All Amazon Nova models include built-in safety controls and creative content generation models include watermarking capabilities to promote responsible AI use.</p> 
       <p>Let’s see how these models work in practice for a few use cases.</p> 
       <p><span><strong>Using Amazon Nova Pro for document analysis<br> </strong></span>To demonstrate the capabilities of document analysis, I downloaded the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/decision-guides/latest/generative-ai-on-aws-how-to-choose/guide.html">Choosing a generative AI service</a> decision guide in PDF format from the AWS documentation.</p> 
       <p>First, I choose <strong>Model access</strong> in the <a href="https://console.aws.amazon.com/bedrock">Amazon Bedrock console</a> navigation pane and request access to the new <strong>Amazon Nova</strong> models. Then, I choose <strong>Chat/text</strong> in the <strong>Playground</strong> section of the navigation pane and select the <strong>Amazon Nova Pro</strong> model. In the chat, I upload the decision guide PDF and ask:</p> 
       <p><code>Write a summary of this doc in 100 words. Then, build a decision tree.</code></p> 
       <p>The output follows my instructions producing a structured decision tree that gives me a glimpse of the document before reading it.</p> 
       <p><a href="https://d2908q01vomqb2.cloudfront.net/da4b9237bacccdf19c0760cab7aec4a8359010b0/2024/11/13/summary-decision-tree.png"><img src="https://d2908q01vomqb2.cloudfront.net/da4b9237bacccdf19c0760cab7aec4a8359010b0/2024/11/13/summary-decision-tree.png" alt="Console screenshot." width="1726" height="1250"></a></p> 
       <p><span><strong>Using Amazon Nova Pro for video analysis<br> </strong></span>To demonstrate video analysis, I prepared a video by joining two short clips (more on this in the next section):</p> 
        
       <p>This time, I use the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/sdk-for-python/">AWS SDK for Python (Boto3)</a> to invoke the Amazon Nova Pro model using the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/bedrock/latest/userguide/conversation-inference.html">Amazon Bedrock Converse API</a> and analyze the video:</p> 
       <pre><code>import boto3

AWS_REGION = "us-east-1"
MODEL_ID = "amazon.nova-pro-v1:0"
VIDEO_FILE = "the-sea.mp4"

bedrock_runtime = boto3.client("bedrock-runtime", region_name=AWS_REGION)
with open(VIDEO_FILE, "rb") as f:
    video = f.read()

user_message = "Describe this video."

messages = [ { "role": "user", "content": [
    {"video": {"format": "mp4", "source": {"bytes": video}}},
    {"text": user_message}
] } ]

response = bedrock_runtime.converse(
    modelId=MODEL_ID,
    messages=messages,
    inferenceConfig={"temperature": 0.0}
&nbsp;)

response_text = response["output"]["message"]["content"][0]["text"]
print(response_text)</code></pre> 
       <p>Amazon Nova Pro can analyze videos that are uploaded with the API (as in the previous code) or that are stored in an <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3/">Amazon Simple Storage Service (Amazon S3)</a> bucket.</p> 
       <p>In the script, I ask to describe the video. I run the script from the command line. Here’s the result:</p> 
       <p><code>The video begins with a view of a rocky shore on the ocean, and then transitions to a close-up of a large seashell resting on a sandy beach.</code></p> 
       <p>I can use a more detailed prompt to extract specific information from the video such as objects or text. Note that Amazon Nova currently does not process audio in a video.</p> 
       <p><span><strong>Using Amazon Nova for video creation<br> </strong></span>Now, let’s create a video using Amazon Nova Reel, starting from a text-only prompt and then providing a reference image.</p> 
       <p>Because generating a video takes a few minutes, the Amazon Bedrock API introduced three new operations:</p> 
       <p><strong>StartAsyncInvoke</strong> – To start an asynchronous invocation</p> 
       <p><strong>GetAsyncInvoke</strong> – To get the current status of a specific asynchronous invocation</p> 
       <p><strong>ListAsyncInvokes</strong> – To list the status of all asynchronous invocations with optional filters such as status or date</p> 
       <p>Amazon Nova Reel supports camera control actions such as zooming or moving the camera. This Python script creates a video from this text prompt:</p> 
       <p><code>Closeup of a large seashell in the sand. Gentle waves flow all around the shell. Sunset light. Camera zoom in very close.</code></p> 
       <p>After the first invocation, the script periodically checks the status until the creation of the video has been completed. I pass a random seed to get a different result each time the code runs.</p> 
       <pre><code>import random
import time

import boto3

AWS_REGION = "us-east-1"
MODEL_ID = "amazon.nova-reel-v1:0"
SLEEP_TIME = 30
S3_DESTINATION_BUCKET = "&lt;BUCKET&gt;"

video_prompt = "Closeup of a large seashell in the sand. Gentle waves flow all around the shell. Sunset light. Camera zoom in very close."

bedrock_runtime = boto3.client("bedrock-runtime", region_name=AWS_REGION)
model_input = {
    "taskType": "TEXT_VIDEO",
    "textToVideoParams": {"text": video_prompt},
    "videoGenerationConfig": {
        "durationSeconds": 6,
        "fps": 24,
        "dimension": "1280x720",
        "seed": random.randint(0, 2147483648)
    }
}

invocation = bedrock_runtime.start_async_invoke(
    modelId=MODEL_ID,
    modelInput=model_input,
    outputDataConfig={"s3OutputDataConfig": {"s3Uri": f"s3://{S3_DESTINATION_BUCKET}"}}
)

invocation_arn = invocation["invocationArn"]
s3_prefix = invocation_arn.split('/')[-1]
s3_location = f"s3://{S3_DESTINATION_BUCKET}/{s3_prefix}"
print(f"\nS3 URI: {s3_location}")

while True:
    response = bedrock_runtime.get_async_invoke(
        invocationArn=invocation_arn
    )
    status = response["status"]
    print(f"Status: {status}")
    if status != "InProgress":
        break
    time.sleep(SLEEP_TIME)

if status == "Completed":
    print(f"\nVideo is ready at {s3_location}/output.mp4")
else:
    print(f"\nVideo generation status: {status}")</code></pre> 
       <p>I run the script:</p> 
       <pre><code>Status: InProgress
. . .
Status: Completed

Video is ready at s3://BUCKET/PREFIX/output.mp4</code></pre> 
       <p>After a few minutes, the script completes and prints the output <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/s3/">Amazon Simple Storage Service (Amazon S3)</a> location. I download the output video using the <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/cli/">AWS Command Line Interface (AWS CLI)</a>:</p> 
       <div> 
        <pre><code>aws s3 cp s3://BUCKET/PREFIX/output.mp4 ./output-from-text.mp4</code></pre> 
       </div> 
       <p>This is the resulting video. As requested, the camera zooms in on the subject.</p> 
        
       <p><span><strong>Using Amazon Nova Reel with a reference image<br> </strong></span>To have better control over the creation of the video, I can provide Amazon Nova Reel a reference image such as the following:</p> 
       <p><a href="https://d2908q01vomqb2.cloudfront.net/da4b9237bacccdf19c0760cab7aec4a8359010b0/2024/11/20/nova-reel-seascape.png"><img loading="lazy" src="https://d2908q01vomqb2.cloudfront.net/da4b9237bacccdf19c0760cab7aec4a8359010b0/2024/11/20/nova-reel-seascape.png" alt="A seascape image." width="1280" height="720"></a></p> 
       <p>This script uses the reference image and a text prompt with a camera action (<code>drone view flying over a coastal landscape</code>) to create a video:</p> 
       <pre><code>import base64
import random
import time

import boto3

S3_DESTINATION_BUCKET = "&lt;BUCKET&gt;"
AWS_REGION = "us-east-1"
MODEL_ID = "amazon.nova-reel-v1:0"
SLEEP_TIME = 30
input_image_path = "seascape.png"
video_prompt = "drone view flying over a coastal landscape"

bedrock_runtime = boto3.client("bedrock-runtime", region_name=AWS_REGION)

# Load the input image as a Base64 string.
with open(input_image_path, "rb") as f:
    input_image_bytes = f.read()
    input_image_base64 = base64.b64encode(input_image_bytes).decode("utf-8")

model_input = {
    "taskType": "TEXT_VIDEO",
    "textToVideoParams": {
        "text": video_prompt,
        "images": [{ "format": "png", "source": { "bytes": input_image_base64 } }]
        },
    "videoGenerationConfig": {
        "durationSeconds": 6,
        "fps": 24,
        "dimension": "1280x720",
        "seed": random.randint(0, 2147483648)
    }
}

invocation = bedrock_runtime.start_async_invoke(
    modelId=MODEL_ID,
    modelInput=model_input,
    outputDataConfig={"s3OutputDataConfig": {"s3Uri": f"s3://{S3_DESTINATION_BUCKET}"}}
)

invocation_arn = invocation["invocationArn"]
s3_prefix = invocation_arn.split('/')[-1]
s3_location = f"s3://{S3_DESTINATION_BUCKET}/{s3_prefix}"

print(f"\nS3 URI: {s3_location}")

while True:
    response = bedrock_runtime.get_async_invoke(
        invocationArn=invocation_arn
    )
    status = response["status"]
    print(f"Status: {status}")
    if status != "InProgress":
        break
    time.sleep(SLEEP_TIME)
if status == "Completed":
    print(f"\nVideo is ready at {s3_location}/output.mp4")
else:
    print(f"\nVideo generation status: {status}")</code></pre> 
       <p>Again, I download the output using the AWS CLI:</p> 
       <div> 
        <pre><code>aws s3 cp s3://BUCKET/PREFIX/output.mp4 ./output-from-image.mp4</code></pre> 
       </div> 
       <p>This is the resulting video. The camera starts from the reference image and moves forward.</p> 
        
       <p><span><strong>Building AI responsibly<br> </strong></span>Amazon Nova models are built with a focus on customer safety, security, and trust throughout the model development stages, offering you peace of mind as well as an adequate level of control to enable your unique use cases.</p> 
       <p>We’ve built in comprehensive safety features and content moderation capabilities, giving you the controls you need to use AI responsibly. Every generated image and video include digital watermarking.</p> 
       <p>The Amazon Nova foundation models are built with protections that match its increased capabilities. Amazon Nova extends our safety measures to combat the spread of misinformation, child sexual abuse material (CSAM), and chemical, biological, radiological, or nuclear (CBRN) risks.</p> 
       <p><span><strong>Things to know<br> </strong></span><a href="http://aws.amazon.com/nova">Amazon Nova</a> models are available in <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/">Amazon Bedrock</a> in the US East (N. Virginia) <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/about-aws/global-infrastructure/regions_az/">AWS region</a>. Amazon Nova Micro, Lite, and Pro are also available in the US West (Oregon), and US East (Ohio) regions via <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/bedrock/latest/userguide/cross-region-inference.html">cross-Region inference</a>. As usual with <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/">Amazon Bedrock</a>, the pricing follows a pay-as-you-go model. For more information, see <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/pricing/">Amazon Bedrock pricing</a>.</p> 
       <p>The new generation of Amazon Nova understanding models speaks your language. These models understand and generate content in over 200 languages, with particularly strong capabilities in English, German, Spanish, French, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Arabic, Simplified Chinese, Russian, Hindi, Portuguese, Dutch, Turkish, and Hebrew. This means you can build truly global applications without worrying about language barriers or maintaining separate models for different regions. Amazon Nova models for creative content generation support English prompts.</p> 
       <p>As you explore Amazon Nova, you’ll discover its ability to handle increasingly complex tasks. You can use these models to process lengthy documents up to 300K tokens, analyze multiple images in a single request, understand up to 30 minutes of video content, and generate images and videos at scale from natural language. This makes these models suitable for a variety of business use cases, from quick customer service interactions to deep analysis of corporate documentation and asset creation for advertising, ecommerce, and social media applications.</p> 
       <p>Integration with Amazon Bedrock makes deployment and scaling straightforward. You can leverage features like <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/knowledge-bases/">Amazon Bedrock Knowledge Bases</a> to enhance your model with proprietary information, use <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/agents/">Amazon Bedrock Agents</a> to automate complex workflows, and implement <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/bedrock/guardrails/">Amazon Bedrock Guardrails</a> to promote responsible AI use. The platform supports real-time streaming for interactive applications, batch processing for high-volume workloads, and detailed monitoring to help you optimize performance.</p> 
       <p>Ready to start building with Amazon Nova? Give the new models a try in the <a href="https://console.aws.amazon.com/bedrock">Amazon Bedrock console</a> today, visit the Amazon Nova&nbsp;models section of the <a href="https://docs.aws.amazon.com/bedrock/latest/userguide/what-is-bedrock.html">Amazon Bedrock documentation</a>, and send feedback to <a href="https://repost.aws/tags/TAQeKlaPaNRQ2tWB6P7KrMag/amazon-bedrock">AWS re:Post for Amazon Bedrock</a>. You can find deep-dive technical content and discover how our Builder communities are using Amazon Bedrock at <a href="https://community.aws/">community.aws</a>. Let us know what you build with these new models!</p> 
       <p>— <a href="https://twitter.com/danilop">Danilo</a></p> 
       <!-- '"` --> 
      </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intel Launches Arc B-Series Graphics Cards (129 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/docs/discrete-gpus/arc/desktop/b-series/overview.html</link>
            <guid>42309010</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 17:54:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/docs/discrete-gpus/arc/desktop/b-series/overview.html">https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/docs/discrete-gpus/arc/desktop/b-series/overview.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42309010">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">


















    
    
    
        















    
    
        
        
        
        
        
        
        
    




    
    
        
    




    
    
    
    
    
        
    


    
    
        
    


    
    
        
    


    
    
        
    





























    


    

































    
        <div data-component="global-nav-redesign" data-component-id="1">
            <header role="banner">
                <nav role="navigation" aria-label="Main Navigation" data-igm="">
                    <!-- Brand and toggle get grouped for better mobile display -->
                    <div>

                        <div>
                            <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/homepage.html" alt="Intel homepage">
                                    
                                <img src="https://www.intel.com/content/dam/logos/intel-header-logo.svg" height="300" width="118" alt="Intel logo - Return to the home page">
                            </a>
                        </div>

                        

                        <!-- START MOBLE TOGGLE buttons -->
                        <div>


                            <!-- START: NON-signed in panel -->
                            <span id="not-logged-in-scenario">

    
        </span>


                            




















































<span id="logged-in-scenario">






</span>

                            
















    




<div id="panel-language-selector" aria-expanded="false" aria-selected="false">
                <h2>
                    
                        
                            Select Your Language
                        
                        
                    
                </h2>
            </div>


                            <!-- END: NON-sign in panel -->
                            

























    

    



    








    



















    
    
    
        
    


    
    <div aria-live="off" id="simplify-search" data-component="wa_skip_track" data-igm-search-content="" document-height="true">
                             
                                 
                            
                            <!-- Search Result Typeahead -->
                            <div id="igm-search-result" data-igm-search-results="">
                                    
                                        Sign In to access restricted content
                                </div>
                            <!-- Recent Searches: 1) display default search info if no search terms is available  -->
                            <!-- Recent Searches: 2) display recenter terms when available and hide default search info  -->
                            <div data-igm-search-related="">
                                <div>
                                    <!-- default search info -->
                                    <div>
                                        <h3>Using Intel.com Search</h3>
                                        <p>You can easily search the entire Intel.com site in several ways.</p>
                                        <ul>
                                            <li>
                                                Brand Name:
                                                <strong>
                                                    Core i9
                                                </strong>
                                            </li>
                                            <li>
                                                Document Number:
                                                <strong>
                                                    123456
                                                </strong>
                                            </li>
                                            <li>
                                                Code Name:
                                                <strong>
                                                    Emerald Rapids
                                                </strong>
                                            </li>
                                            <li>
                                                Special Operators:
                                                <strong>
                                                    “Ice Lake”, Ice AND Lake, Ice OR Lake, Ice*
                                                </strong>
                                            </li>
                                        </ul>
                                    </div>
                                    <!-- quick links is always visible on the recents overlay -->
                                    <div>
                                        <h3>Quick Links</h3>
                                        <p>You can also try the quick links below to see results for most popular searches.</p>
                                        <ul>
                                            <!--<li>
                                                <a class="quick-link" rel="noopener noreferrer"
                                                   href=https://ark.intel.com?wapkw=quicklink:product-specifications>
                                                    Product Specifications
                                                </a>
                                            </li>-->
                                            <li>
                                                <a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/overview.html?wapkw=quicklink:products">
                                                    Product Information
                                                </a>
                                            </li>
                                            <li><a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/support.html?wapkw=quicklink:support">
                                                Support
                                            </a>
                                            </li>
                                            <li>
                                                <a rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://downloadcenter.intel.com/?wapkw=quicklink:download-center">
                                                    Drivers &amp; Software
                                                </a>
                                            </li>
                                        </ul>
                                    </div>
                                    <!-- recent search terms -->
                                    <div data-component="wa_skip_track" data-component-id="1">
                                            <h3>Recent Searches</h3>
                                        </div>
                                </div>
                                <div>
                                    
                                        Sign In to access restricted content
                                </div>
                            </div>
                            
                                 <div data-igm-advanced-search="">
											<div data-component="wa_skip_track" data-component-id="1">
													<h3>Advanced Search</h3>
													<div>
															<h3>Only search in</h3>
															<div aria-label="Only Search In">
																<label for="search_title">
																	
																	Title</label>

																	<label for="search_description">
																	
																Description</label>

																	<label for="search_id">
																	Content ID</label>
															</div>

															
														</div>
												</div>
											<div>
												Sign in to access
												restricted content.
											</div>
										</div>
                                    
                        </div>


                        </div>
                        <!-- END MOBILE TOGGLE buttons -->
                    </div>
                </nav>
            </header>
        </div>

    
    


<div id="alertMsg" data-scroll-track="false">
                        <p>The browser version you are using is not recommended for this site.<br>Please consider upgrading to the latest version of your browser by clicking one of the following links.</p>
                        <div>
                            <ul>
                                
                                    <li><a href="https://support.apple.com/downloads/safari">Safari</a></li>
                                
                                    <li><a href="https://support.google.com/chrome/answer/95346?hl=en">Chrome</a></li>
                                
                                    <li><a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/edge">Edge</a></li>
                                
                                    <li><a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/new/">Firefox</a></li>
                                
                            </ul>
                        </div>
                    </div>


<main id="primary-content">



















    
    






<div id="contentDetailTemplate-1" data-component-id="1" role="main" data-component="contentDetailTemplate">
    

    
    

    
    <div>


<div role="region" aria-label="" id="accent-1" data-component="accentBlade" data-component-id="1">
                <header>
                                        
                </header>
                <div>
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/icon-arc-60-plus-fps:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon 60+ FPS" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/icon-arc-60-plus-fps.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Built for 1440p Gaming
        </h3>

        <p>Play many of the latest games at 60+ FPS in 1440p resolution.<sup>1</sup></p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                        
                        
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/geode-computer-icon:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="A computer icon" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/geode-computer-icon.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Smoother Experiences
        </h3>

        <p>Faster, more fluid gameplay with a combination of Intel® XeSS 2 upscaling technology and frame generation.</p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                            
                        
                        
                        
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/geode-fast-response-icon:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon of a mouse moving" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/geode-fast-response-icon.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Faster Responsiveness
        </h3>

        <p>A hyper-connected gaming experience with Intel® Xe Low Latency (XeLL), which reduces lag and input delays.</p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                        
                            
                        
                        
                    
                </div>
                
            </div>

<div role="region" aria-label="" id="accent-2" data-component="accentBlade" data-component-id="2">
                <header>
                                        
                </header>
                <div>
                    
                        
                        
                        
                        
                        
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/geode-ai-icon:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon of a chip with AI in the center" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/geode-ai-icon.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Powerful AI Engines
        </h3>

        <p>Unlock cutting-edge AI experiences, including upscaled gaming and next-gen creation capabilities.</p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                            
                        
                        
                        
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
            
            
        
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/geode-generative-ai-icon:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon of a pencil" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/geode-generative-ai-icon.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3><a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/docs/discrete-gpus/arc/software/ai-playground.html">
            Generative AI-ready</a>
        </h3>

        <p>Experiment with AI creation, such as editing effects and text-to-image applications, all easily accessible through Intel® AI Playground.<sup>3</sup></p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                        
                            
                        
                        
                    
                </div>
                
            </div>

<div role="region" aria-label="" id="accent-3" data-component="accentBlade" data-component-id="3">
                <header>
                                        
                </header>
                <div>
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/icon-arc-81-percent-faster:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon up to 81% faster" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/icon-arc-81-percent-faster.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Faster Video Editing
        </h3>

        <p>Dual media transcoder that enables up to 81% faster video exporting.<sup>1</sup></p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                        
                        
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/geode-bandwidth-icon:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon showing multiple arrows going in same direction" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/geode-bandwidth-icon.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Built for High Bandwidth Creation
        </h3>

        <p>The advanced Xe media engine utilizes parallel cores to speed up editing and content creation significantly.</p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                            
                        
                        
                        
                    
                        
                        <div>
    
        
        
            
            
        
    
    <div>
        
            
            
                <figure>
                    
                    
                        
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                            
                                
                            
                            
                            <picture>
                                <img src="https://intelcorp.scene7.com/is/image/intelcorp/geode-record-icon:1440-1080?wid=128&amp;hei=96&amp;fmt=webp-alpha" alt="An icon of a camcorder" width="128" height="96" loading="lazy" data-original-path="/content/dam/www/central-libraries/us/en/images/2024-10/geode-record-icon.png">
                            </picture>
                        
                                              
                        
                    
                </figure>
            
        
    </div>
    <div>
        <h3>
            Get Cross-Codec Support
        </h3>

        <p>Support for the most popular media codecs for worry-free image and video exporting, including AV1 encode and decode capability.</p>
    </div>
</div>
                        
                        
                            
                        
                        
                    
                </div>
                
            </div>

<div id="introtext_copy" data-component="introText" data-component-id="1">
                                
                                    
                                        
                                        
                                            <h2>Shop Intel® Arc™ Graphics for Desktops</h2>
                                        
                                    
                                
                                
                            </div>

<div data-component="partner-simple-card" data-component-id="1" id="partner-simple-card-1">
                <h2>Additional Resources</h2>
                
            </div>

</div>

    
    

    











    <div>
                    <h4>Product and Performance Information</h4>
                    
                    
                    
                        
                            
                        
                    
                        
                            <div><sup>2</sup><p>AI features may require additional purchase or specific compatibility requirements. See <a href="https://edc.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/performance/benchmarks/overview/">intel.com/performanceindex</a> for details. Results may vary. (As of August 2024.)</p>
</div>
                        
                    
                        
                            <div><sup>3</sup><p>AI features may require software purchase, subscription or enablement by a software or platform provider, or may have specific configuration or compatibility requirements. Data latency, cost, and privacy advantages refer to non-cloud-based AI apps. Learn more at <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/now/ai-pc-possibilities.html">intel.com/AIPC</a>.</p>
<p>AI playground is only compatible with select Intel Arc GPUs that meet minimum graphics memory requirements. Learn more about AI playground at <a href="https://game.intel.com/us/stories/introducing-ai-playground/">intel.com/ai-playground</a>.</p>
</div>
                        
                    
                        
                            
                        
                    
                    
                    
                </div>

    
    

    
</div>







    


</main>












































    







</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Amazon Aurora DSQL (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://aws.amazon.com/rds/aurora/dsql/</link>
            <guid>42308716</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 17:30:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://aws.amazon.com/rds/aurora/dsql/">https://aws.amazon.com/rds/aurora/dsql/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42308716">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-eb-tpl-n="awsm-rt/rt-text-media-grid-collection" data-eb-tpl-v="1.0.0" data-eb-ce="" data-eb-c-scope="benefits" data-eb-d-scope="DIRECTORIES" data-eb-locale="en-US" data-eb-31bca616="" data-eb-ssr-ce="" data-eb-tpl-ns="awsmRT" data-eb-slot="benefits" data-eb-slot-meta="{'version':'1.0','slotId':'benefits','experienceId':'778fdff8-5738-11ee-8c99-0242ac120002','allowBlank':true,'hasAltExp':false,'isRTR':false,'filters':{'limit':5,'query':'(id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-benefits-header-22\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-benefits-1-22\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-benefits-2-22\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-benefits-3-22\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-benefits-4-22\')'}}"> 
       
       
      <p><span data-eb-item-id="product-use-cases#aurora-dsql-benefits-header-22"> 
        <div data-rg-lang="en" data-rg-locale="en-US" lang="en-US" dir="ltr"> 
           <div> 
              <h3>Virtually unlimited scale</h3> 
              <p>
                Scales to meet any workload demand without database sharding or instance upgrades. It provides virtually unlimited horizontal scaling with the flexibility to independently scale reads, writes, storage, and compute. 
              </p> 
             </div> 
           <div> 
              <h3>Build always available apps</h3> 
              <p>
                Ensure application resiliency as all reads and writes to any Regional endpoint are strongly consistent and durable - and Aurora DSQL is designed for up to 99.999% availability with no single point of failure and automated failure recovery. 
              </p> 
             </div> 
           <div> 
              <h3>No infrastructure to manage</h3> 
              <p>
                Remove infrastructure management as there are no servers to provision, patch, manage, or upgrade. Aurora DSQL automatically handles updates without downtime and with zero impact on application performance. 
              </p> 
             </div> 
           <div> 
              <h3>Easy to use</h3> 
              <p>
                Create a new database in a few quick steps. Aurora DSQL is PostgreSQL-compatible, providing an easy-to-use developer experience for building new apps. 
              </p> 
             </div> 
          </div></span> 
      </p> 
     </div><div data-eb-tpl-n="awsm-rt/rt-qa-sampler" data-eb-tpl-v="1.0.0" data-eb-ce="" data-eb-c-scope="use-cases" data-eb-d-scope="DIRECTORIES" data-eb-locale="en-US" data-eb-d9d0c036="" data-eb-ssr-ce="" data-eb-tpl-ns="awsmRT" data-eb-hydrated="pending" data-eb-slot="use-cases" data-eb-slot-meta="{'version':'1.0','slotId':'use-cases','experienceId':'a2ff0a24-5bf2-11ee-8c99-0242ac120002','allowBlank':false,'hasAltExp':false,'isRTR':false,'filters':{'limit':5,'query':'(id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-use-cases-header\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-use-cases-1\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-use-cases-2\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-use-cases-3\' OR id \u003d \'aurora-dsql-use-cases-4\')'}}"> 
       
       
      <p><span data-eb-item-id="product-use-cases#aurora-dsql-use-cases-header"> 
        <div data-rg-theme="teal" data-rg-mode="light" data-rg-lang="en" data-rg-locale="en-US" lang="en-US" dir="ltr"> 
             <div data-eb-item-id="0"> 
              <div id="0-trigger" aria-controls="content-0" aria-expanded="false" tabindex="0" role="button"> 
               <h3>Build serverless applications at any scale</h3> 
                
              </div> 
              <div id="content-0" aria-labelledby="0-trigger"> 
                <p>Create cloud-native applications that will grow from start-up to enterprise scale without the need to upgrade or refactor along the way. Easily integrate with microservices and event-driven architectures.&nbsp;</p> 
               </div> 
             </div> 
             <div data-eb-item-id="1"> 
              <div id="1-trigger" aria-controls="content-1" aria-expanded="false" tabindex="0" role="button"> 
               <h3>Develop next-generation applications</h3> 
                
              </div> 
              <div id="content-1" aria-labelledby="1-trigger"> 
                <p>Design highly scalable applications and solutions for industries, such as banking, ecommerce, travel, and retail, with high availability and performance.</p> 
               </div> 
             </div> 
             <div data-eb-item-id="2"> 
              <div id="2-trigger" aria-controls="content-2" aria-expanded="false" tabindex="0" role="button"> 
               <h3>Deploy multi-Region applications</h3> 
                
              </div> 
              <div id="content-2" aria-labelledby="2-trigger"> 
                <p>Develop data-driven applications, such as payment services, mobile games, and social media apps, that require multi-Region scalability and resilience.</p> 
               </div> 
             </div> 
             <div data-eb-item-id="3"> 
              <div id="3-trigger" aria-controls="content-3" aria-expanded="false" tabindex="0" role="button"> 
               <h3>Build SaaS applications</h3> 
                
              </div> 
              <div id="content-3" aria-labelledby="3-trigger"> 
                <p>Support reliable, high-performance, and multi-tenant software as a service (SaaS) applications with flexible instance and storage scaling.</p> 
               </div> 
             </div> 
            </div></span> 
      </p> 
     </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Intel announces Arc B-series "Battlemage" discrete graphics with Linux support (400 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.phoronix.com/review/intel-arc-b580-battlemage#google_vignette</link>
            <guid>42308590</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 17:19:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/review/intel-arc-b580-battlemage#google_vignette">https://www.phoronix.com/review/intel-arc-b580-battlemage#google_vignette</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42308590">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content-bg">
						
						<!-- google_ad_section_start -->
<article>


<div>

<p>Succeeding the Intel <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/search/Arc+Graphics">Arc Graphics</a> discrete graphics cards that launched two years ago as the DG2/Alchemist series, the next-gen <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/search/Battlemage">Battlemage</a> graphics cards are being announced today. The embargo lifts today on the new Intel Arc B-Series graphics cards with initial availability next week. Like the prior generation Intel graphics and as discussed already in many Phoronix articles, Battlemage is still treated to fully open-source graphics driver support on Linux.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_2_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_2_med" alt="Intel Xe2 render slice"></a></p>
<p>Battlemage makes use of Xe2 graphics, similar to the recent integrated graphics with Lunar Lake.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_3_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_3_med" alt="Intel Xe 2nd gen core"></a></p>
<p>There's a lot of nice improvements over the two-year old Alchemist graphics.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_4_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_4_med" alt="Intel Xe2 vector engine"></a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_5_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_5_med" alt="Intel BMG-G21"></a></p>
<p>For the initial Battlemage graphics is the BMG-G21 GPU with 20 Xe cores, 160 XMX engines, 20 ray-tracing units, 192-bit GDDR6 video memory interface, and other upgrades. Intel is promoting up to a 70% improvement in performance per Xe core and up to a 50% performance per Watt improvement.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_6_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_6_med" alt="Intel BMG-G21 dGPU gains"></a></p>
<p>Being announced today are the Arc Graphics B580 and B570 graphics cards. The Arc B580 boasts the full 20 Xe cores, 2670MHz graphics clock, 12GB of GDDR6 video memory, and 190 Watt total board power rating. The Arc B570 meanwhile has 18 Xe cores, 2500MHz graphics clock, 10GB of GDDR6 video memory, and rated for 150 Watt board power. While the prior generation had a flagship Arc A770 model, no "Arc B750" or "Arc B770" is being announced today or any other higher-tier part past the Arc B500 series. This is a mid-range focused card primarily for 1440p gaming and less.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_8_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_8_med" alt="Intel Arc B570 and Arc B580 specs"></a></p>
<p>These new Battlemage graphics cards function on a PCIe 4.0 x8 interface and require one 8-pin PCI Express power connector. AV1, HEVC, AVC, VP9, and XAVC-H hardware acceleration is available but no VVC as found with Lunar Lake.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_9_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_9_med" alt="Intel Arc B580 performance"></a></p>
<p>Intel with their Windows benchmarks are promoting the Arc B580 as being 24% faster than the Intel Arc A750. Or against the NVIDIA competition they are promoting as 10% faster than the NVIDIA GeForce RTX 4060, again under Windows.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_10_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_10_med" alt="Intel Arc B580 performance against NVIDIA RTX 4060"></a></p>
<p>The Intel Arc B580 will be shipping next week for $249+ USD. The Arc B570 will be shipping 16 January at $219+ USD.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_11_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_11_med" alt="Intel Arc Battlemage pricing and launch dates"></a></p>
<p>Today's announcement just span the Intel Battlemage details. The review embargo has not yet passed and thus are not able to share any performance details or any new Linux details on the Intel Arc B580/B570 support. So the value add of Phoronix around the Linux performance and support details will come later... But needless to say, as has been covered in many Phoronix articles Intel has spent months already working on the open-source and upstream-oriented Linux support from the Xe kernel driver to the Mesa Iris OpenGL and ANV Vulkan drivers. Plus the Intel Compute Runtime stack for OpenCL and Level Zero. Those can check out the prior <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/search/Battlemage">Battlemage</a> coverage around all the upstream support.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.phoronix.com/image-viewer.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_1_lrg" target="_blank"><img src="https://www.phoronix.net/image.php?id=intel-arc-b580-battlemage&amp;image=intel_battlemage_1_med" alt="Intel Xe2"></a></p>
<p>So for launch day you can expect upstream support with <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/news/Linux-6.12-Intel-Xe2-Stable">the stable Linux 6.12 kernel</a> and latest Mesa graphics drivers as already covered in prior Phoronix articles on Mesa/kernel news. Beyond that you'll need to wait to hear all the performance details and more. But at this stage you can expect that I wouldn't have been invited to the Battlemage review briefings if the Linux support was in bad shape and struggling compared to Windows, etc. So stay tuned to learn more soon about Intel Arc B580 graphics on Linux.</p>
</div>

<p><strong>If you enjoyed this article consider <a href="https://www.phoronix.com/phoronix-premium">joining Phoronix Premium</a> to view this site ad-free, multi-page articles on a single page, and other benefits. <a href="https://www.paypal.com/cgi-bin/webscr?cmd=_s-xclick&amp;hosted_button_id=3778540">PayPal</a> or <a href="https://buy.stripe.com/28o02d1yG1Lp8H67ss">Stripe</a> tips are also graciously accepted. Thanks for your support.</strong></p>
<ins data-ad-format="autorelaxed" data-ad-client="ca-pub-0253814508491313" data-ad-slot="7279734770"></ins>

							


					
						</article>
						<div id="about-author">
								<header>About The Author</header>
								<p><img src="https://www.phoronix.com/assets/categories/michaellarabel.webp" alt="Michael Larabel"></p><p>Michael Larabel is the principal author of Phoronix.com and founded the site in 2004 with a focus on enriching the Linux hardware experience. Michael has written more than 20,000 articles covering the state of Linux hardware support, Linux performance, graphics drivers, and other topics. Michael is also the lead developer of the Phoronix Test Suite, Phoromatic, and OpenBenchmarking.org automated benchmarking software. <strong>He can be followed via <a href="https://twitter.com/MichaelLarabel">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/michaellarabel/">LinkedIn</a>, or contacted via <a href="https://www.michaellarabel.com/">MichaelLarabel.com</a>.</strong></p>
							</div>
<!-- google_ad_section_end -->
					</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Broadcom loses another big VMware customer (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/12/02/beeks_group_vmware_opennebula_migration/</link>
            <guid>42308184</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 16:44:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/12/02/beeks_group_vmware_opennebula_migration/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/12/02/beeks_group_vmware_opennebula_migration/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42308184">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Broadcom has lost another significant customer after UK-based cloud operator Beeks Group decided to adopt the open source OpenNebula stack.</p>
<p>Beeks offers virtual private servers and bare metal boxes for financial services providers and emphasizes low latency for both – and for the trading network it operates.</p>
<p>The biz told <i>The Register</i> it operates in over 20 datacenters and runs a fleet of 20,000-plus virtual machines and more than 3,000 bare metal servers. Most of the VMs now run under OpenNebula – an open source project that provides hybrid cloud features on multiple hypervisors but favors KVM.</p>

    

<p>Beeks head of production management Matthew Cretney told us it moved from VMware due to several factors. A bill from Broadcom for ten times the sum it previously paid for software licenses was one of them. Beeks's customers also told it that VMware was no longer seen as essential infrastructure.</p>

        


        

<p>The tech team also warned management that the quality of VMware's support services and innovation were falling.</p>
<p>A symptom of perceived innovation woes was that Beeks felt VMware's suite had a substantial management overhead – that meant too much of its server fleet was dedicated to managing VMs, not running them for clients.</p>

        

<p>The VMware stack's very nature as a platform to manage virtual machines didn't help, either. Some Beeks customers prefer bare metal, as even the isolation provided by virtualization doesn't satisfy their need for security and low latency. vSphere is not built to manage bare metal servers alongside VMs, and Beeks wanted one tool for both jobs.</p>
<h3>A challenging switch</h3>
<p>Migration wasn't easy. Beeks runs proprietary software that it had tied to VMware APIs, and that had to be rebuilt to interface with OpenNebula.</p>
<p>The open source project's tools to collect metrics Beeks and its clients value – regarding CPU performance, and utilization of CPU, disk, memory, and network resources – were not strong. That's an issue because an overtaxed CPU or disk can be the difference between pleasingly fast trades or missing an opportunity. As OpenNebula is open source, Beeks felt able to develop tools to collect that info – and succeeded to its satisfaction.</p>
<p>Shifting to OpenNebula meant a 200 percent increase in virtual machine efficiency – meaning more VMs on each server, and lower costs for Beeks and its clients.</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/28/broadcom_vmware_vcdx_snafu/">No, Broadcom did not just end VMware's flagship VCDX certification program</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/26/amazon_elastic_vmware_service_preview/">AWS bends to Broadcom's will with VMware Cloud Foundation as-a-service</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/20/hpe_vm_essentials_greenlake/">HPE lets loose VM Essentials to run on third-party platforms</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/18/vmware_vcenter_rce_exploited/">Critical 9.8-rated VMware vCenter RCE bug exploited after patch fumble</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Beeks still offers VMware services for customers that want it, but the majority of its VM estate is now on OpenNebula.</p>
<p>Broadcom has positioned VMware's Cloud Foundation (VCF) stack as ideal for organizations with large and complex IT estates. It argues that, while VCF has a substantial price tag, those who implement the entire suite of compute, storage, and network virtualization components will quickly enjoy ROI that proves the bundle represents exceptional value.</p>
<p>Beeks's offerings are a little unusual – and perhaps therefore an edge case for VCF. Broadcom could therefore argue that losing most of this particular customer's business isn't a blow.</p>

        

<p>Yet the UK cloud's decision comes after Broadcom also lost big names such as insurance giant <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/28/geico_vmware_openstack_migration/">Geico</a>, fintech <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/22/computershare_vm_migration_project/">Computershare</a>, <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/21/nutanix_vmware_migrations/">Boyd Gaming</a>, and <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/22/john_deere_vms_legacy/">John Deere</a> – with the post-acquisition licensing terms a common theme behind migration decisions.</p>
<p>US telecom titan AT&amp;T has <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/09/23/att_vmware_quit_claim_broadcom/">threatened</a> to quit VMware too, and claimed such a move would quickly pay for itself – but that may have been a negotiation tactic as it has since <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/11/22/broadcom_vmware_acquisition_first_anniversary/">settled</a> a dispute over a support services contract.</p>
<p>Beeks Group's experience of substantial savings is therefore another example for those considering what to do when their current VMware deals expire – and they face a decision about whether or not to buy into Broadcom's virtual vision. ®</p>                                
                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Skia Canvas: Browserless implementation of the HTML Canvas drawing API for node (228 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://skia-canvas.org/</link>
            <guid>42308051</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 16:34:18 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://skia-canvas.org/">https://skia-canvas.org/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42308051">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Skia Canvas is a browser-less implementation of the HTML Canvas drawing API for Node.js. It is based on Google’s <a href="https://skia.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Skia</a> graphics engine and, accordingly, produces very similar results to Chrome’s <code>&lt;canvas&gt;</code> element. The library is well suited for use on desktop machines where you can render hardware-accelerated graphics to a window and on the server where it can output a variety of image formats.</p><p>While the primary goal of this project is to provide a reliable emulation of the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Canvas_API" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">standard API</a> according to the <a href="https://html.spec.whatwg.org/multipage/canvas.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">spec</a>, it also extends it in a number of areas to take greater advantage of Skia's advanced graphical features and provide a more expressive coding environment.</p><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>Canvas</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>'skia-canvas'</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>let</span><span> canvas </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>new</span><span> </span><span>Canvas</span><span>(</span><span>400</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>400</span><span>)</span><span>,</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    ctx </span><span>=</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>getContext</span><span>(</span><span>"2d"</span><span>)</span><span>,</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    </span><span>{</span><span>width</span><span>,</span><span> height</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> canvas</span><span>;</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>let</span><span> sweep </span><span>=</span><span> ctx</span><span>.</span><span>createConicGradient</span><span>(</span><span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>PI</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>1.2</span><span>,</span><span> width</span><span>/</span><span>2</span><span>,</span><span> height</span><span>/</span><span>2</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>sweep</span><span>.</span><span>addColorStop</span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"red"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>sweep</span><span>.</span><span>addColorStop</span><span>(</span><span>0.25</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"orange"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>sweep</span><span>.</span><span>addColorStop</span><span>(</span><span>0.5</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"yellow"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>sweep</span><span>.</span><span>addColorStop</span><span>(</span><span>0.75</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"green"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>sweep</span><span>.</span><span>addColorStop</span><span>(</span><span>1</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>"red"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>ctx</span><span>.</span><span>strokeStyle</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> sweep</span><br></span><span><span>ctx</span><span>.</span><span>lineWidth</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>100</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>ctx</span><span>.</span><span>strokeRect</span><span>(</span><span>100</span><span>,</span><span>100</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>200</span><span>,</span><span>200</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>// render to multiple destinations using a background thread</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>async</span><span> </span><span>function</span><span> </span><span>render</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>// save a ‘retina’ image...</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>await</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>saveAs</span><span>(</span><span>"rainbox.png"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>density</span><span>:</span><span>2</span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>// ...or use a shorthand for canvas.toBuffer("png")</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>let</span><span> pngData </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>await</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>png</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>// ...or embed it in a string</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>let</span><span> pngEmbed </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>`</span><span>&lt;img src="</span><span>${</span><span>await</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>toDataURL</span><span>(</span><span>"png"</span><span>)</span><span>}</span><span>"&gt;</span><span>`</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>render</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>// ...or save the file synchronously from the main thread</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>canvas</span><span>.</span><span>saveAsSync</span><span>(</span><span>"rainbox.pdf"</span><span>)</span><br></span></code></pre></div><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>Canvas</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>'skia-canvas'</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>let</span><span> canvas </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>new</span><span> </span><span>Canvas</span><span>(</span><span>400</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>400</span><span>)</span><span>,</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    ctx </span><span>=</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>getContext</span><span>(</span><span>"2d"</span><span>)</span><span>,</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    </span><span>{</span><span>width</span><span>,</span><span> height</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> canvas</span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>for</span><span> </span><span>(</span><span>const</span><span> color </span><span>of</span><span> </span><span>[</span><span>'orange'</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>'yellow'</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>'green'</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>'skyblue'</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>'purple'</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx </span><span>=</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>newPage</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>fillStyle</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> color</span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>fillRect</span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span> width</span><span>,</span><span> height</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>fillStyle</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>'white'</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>arc</span><span>(</span><span>width</span><span>/</span><span>2</span><span>,</span><span> height</span><span>/</span><span>2</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>40</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>PI</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>fill</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>async</span><span> </span><span>function</span><span> </span><span>render</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>// save to a multi-page PDF file</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>await</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>saveAs</span><span>(</span><span>"all-pages.pdf"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>// save to files named `page-01.png`, `page-02.png`, etc.</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>await</span><span> canvas</span><span>.</span><span>saveAs</span><span>(</span><span>"page-{2}.png"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>render</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><br></span></code></pre></div><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>import</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span>Window</span><span>}</span><span> </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>'skia-canvas'</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>let</span><span> win </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>new</span><span> </span><span>Window</span><span>(</span><span>300</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>300</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>win</span><span>.</span><span>title</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>"Canvas Window"</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>win</span><span>.</span><span>on</span><span>(</span><span>"draw"</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>e</span><span> </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>let</span><span> ctx </span><span>=</span><span> e</span><span>.</span><span>target</span><span>.</span><span>canvas</span><span>.</span><span>getContext</span><span>(</span><span>"2d"</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>lineWidth</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>25</span><span> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>25</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>cos</span><span>(</span><span>e</span><span>.</span><span>frame</span><span> </span><span>/</span><span> </span><span>10</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>beginPath</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>arc</span><span>(</span><span>150</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>150</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>50</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>PI</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>stroke</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>beginPath</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>arc</span><span>(</span><span>150</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>150</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>10</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span><span> </span><span>2</span><span> </span><span>*</span><span> </span><span>Math</span><span>.</span><span>PI</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>stroke</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  ctx</span><span>.</span><span>fill</span><span>(</span><span>)</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>}</span><span>)</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DuckDuckGo Donates $25,000 to the Perl and Raku Foundation (274 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.perl.com/article/duckduckgo-donates-25-000-to-the-perl-and-raku-foundation/</link>
            <guid>42307223</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 15:34:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.perl.com/article/duckduckgo-donates-25-000-to-the-perl-and-raku-foundation/">https://www.perl.com/article/duckduckgo-donates-25-000-to-the-perl-and-raku-foundation/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42307223">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
              
              <p>Dec 3, 2024 by
              
              
                
                
                <a href="#author-bio-olaf-alders">Olaf Alders</a>
              
              </p>
              <img alt="" src="https://www.perl.com/images/duck-duck-go/Growth.jpg">
                <p><img src="https://www.perl.com/images/duck-duck-go/Logo-Horizontal-Registered2.svg" alt="DuckDuckGo Growth"></p>

<p>Today, on “Giving Tuesday”, <a href="https://www.perlfoundation.org/">The Perl and Raku Foundation
(TPRF)</a> is extremely pleased to announce <a href="https://spreadprivacy.com/2024-duckduckgo-charitable-donations">a
donation of $25,000 from
DuckDuckGo</a>.
Since 2011, DuckDuckGo has <a href="https://duckduckgo.com/donations">donated over 6 million
dollars</a> to organizations that align with
their “vision of raising the standard of trust online”.</p>

<p>TPRF is dedicated to
advancing the Perl and Raku programming languages through open-source
development, community engagement, and outreach to ensure their ongoing growth,
relevance, and accessibility. This support from DuckDuckGo will allow TPRF to
continue to do things like fund core Perl development, fund grants for
projects which are important to the community and otherwise to support the
community where it can.</p>

<p>Every donation sends a message that this work matters. On the occasion of this
gift, The Perl and Raku Foundation is deeply grateful to
<a href="https://duckduckgo.com/">DuckDuckGo</a> not only for its generosity but also for
its confidence in TPRF’s mission.</p>

<p>To learn more about TPRF’s current activities and goals for the future, please see
 <a href="https://www.perl.com/media/tprf/tprf-prospectus-2024.pdf">the TPRF 2024 prospectus</a></p>

<p>If your organization is interested in becoming a TPRF donor, please <a href="mailto:olaf@perlfoundation.org">reach out
to me</a>. I’d be more than happy to set up a
call so that we can discuss how a donor relationship with TPRF can
benefit your organization.</p>

              </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We switched from Next.js to Astro (and why it might interest you) (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.datocms.com/blog/why-we-switched-to-astro</link>
            <guid>42306742</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 14:56:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.datocms.com/blog/why-we-switched-to-astro">https://www.datocms.com/blog/why-we-switched-to-astro</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42306742">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main-content">  <p>If everything went according to plan, no one should have noticed anything. But for a few days now, this site has been completely new.</p><p><strong>We took our old Next 13 site and completely rewrote it in Astro! 🧑‍🚀🚀</strong></p><p>Not only that: we also moved from the classic Vercel hosting to a completely server-side rendering approach on a VPS, which allows our team an editing experience with immediate feedback, combined with a blazing-fast CDN for the website visitors.</p><p>Astro was a bet. We didn't know it well enough to be sure everything would go as expected. But <strong>the result was a complete success from every perspective</strong>, and the development experience was extremely educational and — not something to be taken for granted — <em>fun</em>.</p><p>The final architecture offers performance and consumption typical of a static site, coupled with instant and granular page-level invalidation thanks to our <a href="https://www.datocms.com/blog/introducing-datocms-cache-tags">Cache Tags</a>. The dream of every website. </p><p>This is part one of a series of articles in which we'll try to summarize our journey, sharing many cool little Astro details we discovered (or totally came up with) in the process. We hope they can be useful to those, who like us, manage a content-driven site and would like to consider an alternative to the classic Next/Nuxt/Svelte + Vercel/Netlify stack.</p><p>Now let’s be clear – by no means are we suggesting we’re <em>against </em>Next.js. Heck, we’re incredibly proud of the official <a href="http://next.js/">Next.js conference starter</a> which was originally built with DatoCMS in 2020! However, considering our content and sitemap, several factors came into play to make this decision.</p><h2> Why did you do it? <a data-anchor="why-did-you-do-it" id="why-did-you-do-it"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#why-did-you-do-it"></a></h2><p>There are many reasons why we needed to make BIG changes to our website.</p><h5> TypeScript <a data-anchor="typescript" id="typescript"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#typescript"></a></h5><p>Our Next site was a project born in 2019: five years in the magical frontend world is a geological era (unfortunately). At the time, there were no reliable typed GraphQL schema generators. The result was that the old site was written in pure JS, without TypeScript. Over time, as pages increased, we felt less and less comfortable making big modifications with the confidence of not breaking anything.</p><p>Hence the first objective: <strong>regain confidence by switching to a complete TypeScript codebase</strong>, where every GraphQL query would be fully typed. But since that meant rewriting a good chunk of our code anyways, why not consider alternatives to Next.js?</p><h5> Eating our own dog food <a data-anchor="eating-our-own-dog-food" id="eating-our-own-dog-food"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#eating-our-own-dog-food"></a></h5><p>Our product, DatoCMS, has changed A LOT since 2019. Yet our Next site wasn't leveraging some of the coolest features we've released in recent times, like <a href="https://www.datocms.com/blog/introducing-strict-mode-for-graphql-cda-get-the-best-typescript-dx">GraphQL "Strict Mode"</a> — which pairs wonderfully with TypeScript — but especially <a href="https://www.datocms.com/blog/introducing-datocms-cache-tags">Cache Tags</a>, which can offer top-notch performance through <strong>completely static and cached content</strong>, while still letting visitors access the latest version of any page, seconds after changes have been published.</p><p>We wanted a site that represented <strong>the state of the art of what DatoCMS can offer</strong>.</p><h5> A simpler mental model <a data-anchor="a-simpler-mental-model" id="a-simpler-mental-model"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#a-simpler-mental-model"></a></h5><p>In 2019, Next.js introduced <a href="https://nextjs.org/blog/next-9-3#next-gen-static-site-generation-ssg-support"><code>getStaticProps()</code></a> along with <a href="https://nextjs.org/blog/next-9-3#preview-mode">Draft Mode </a>— a revolutionary hybrid static/dynamic approach that was a breath of fresh air compared to our former Gatsby setup. The developer experience was delightful and straightforward.</p><p>Fast forward to today, and the React ecosystem has transformed dramatically. Setting up React is now so complex that React itself <a href="https://react.dev/learn/start-a-new-react-project">recommends using it exclusively through a framework</a>. Next.js and React have become almost indistinguishable, to the point where, at the time of its public launch, Next.js 15 was using... an unreleased React release candidate?</p><p>Starting with Next.js 14, the introduction of the app router, Server Components, and Incremental Regeneration (ISR) have <strong>exponentially increased complexity</strong>. Our team frequently encountered bewildering results and errors, with Next.js documentation offering little clarity about the underlying mechanics. We're not alone in this frustration — many developers are questioning the framework's direction (i.e. <a href="https://www.epicweb.dev/why-i-wont-use-nextjs">Why I Won't Use Next.js</a>).</p><p>While Next.js 15 addresses some issues, and is an incredibly powerful framework, it feels like React/Next is moving in a direction that isn't ours. <strong>For a content-driven site with static pages that look the same to every visitor, these increasingly sophisticated solutions feel like overkill </strong>and force us into unnecessary complexity.</p><p>Hence the last objectives:</p><ul><li><p><strong>return to a simple mental model</strong> that doesn't require a frontend degree to navigate without making massive errors.</p></li><li><p><strong>design a simple, standards-based architecture</strong> that offers maximum control and remains cost-effective.</p></li></ul><h2> Why Astro? <a data-anchor="why-astro" id="why-astro"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#why-astro"></a></h2><p>With these premises, choosing Astro as the reference framework was quite an obvious consequence.</p><p>To use DatoCMS Cache Tags, the only requirement at the "engine" level of the website is to offer a server-side rendering mode capable of freely manipulating the headers of each page's response, and <a href="https://docs.astro.build/en/reference/api-reference/">Astro checks the box</a>. This is certainly not a strict requirement: Next, Nuxt, SvelteKit... are all frameworks that offer server-side rendering.</p><p>The critical distinction lies in their core architectures. Next, Nuxt, and SvelteKit are built with complex, runtime browser rendering engines — a massive overhead for content-driven websites with minimal interactive elements. This approach introduces unnecessary mental overhead for developers, forcing them to constantly juggle the cognitive load of writing code that must execute flawlessly in both server and browser environments. It also increases the overall computational complexity and page size for the final visitor.</p><p>Astro takes a bold and clear position: it is firmly focused on server-side and static generation. Unlike its competitors, <strong>Astro categorically refuses browser-side rendering</strong>. It doesn't just minimize client-side rendering — it eliminates it entirely. And this goes exactly towards our goal: a simple mental model.</p><blockquote> <p>Wait, why not just use PHP then? 👀</p>  </blockquote><p>Because web development isn't black and white. No site can be completely absent of JavaScript — <em>certainly not ours!</em> And when you need to break free from pure server-side rendering and add interactive elements, Astro provides a seamless solution that PHP simply cannot match.</p><p>Having Vite as its engine, Astro allows you to effortlessly insert JavaScript code, handling all the bundling for you. Moreover: if for particular areas of the page you need strong browser-side interactivity, Astro allows you to insert entire <a href="https://docs.astro.build/en/concepts/islands/">interactive "islands"</a> of React/Vue/Svelte, limiting hydration only to those specific parts.</p><p>That's exactly what we, and most content-driven websites, need: the performance and simplicity of server-side rendering for the vast majority of the pages, combined with targeted, rich interactivity where necessary.</p><p><em>(Also, as you may recall, one of our goals was to incorporate a form of safety net through typed languages. PHP/Ruby/Python are not inherently typed, plus lack advanced tools like TypeScript for automatically managing the typing of GraphQL queries. So yeah, PHP will need to take a backseat for now. </em>🤷‍♂️<em>)</em></p><h2> The new stack <a data-anchor="the-new-stack" id="the-new-stack"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#the-new-stack"></a></h2><figure> <img-lightbox> <a href="https://www.datocms-assets.com/205/1732877403-schema.svg?auto=format&amp;fit=max&amp;w=2000"><img src="https://www.datocms-assets.com/205/1732877403-schema.svg"></a></img-lightbox>  <figcaption>Wow, that's a lot of arrows! (14 to be precise)</figcaption> </figure><p>Let's analyze it point by point what we came out with:</p><ul><li><p>The new site is written in Astro and uses the <a href="https://docs.astro.build/en/guides/integrations-guide/node/">Node adapter</a>, meaning the final output of a build is a <strong>Node.js server</strong> that needs to run on a physical server. Astro generates new server-side responses for each incoming request.</p></li><li><p>The server in question is a VPS on <a href="https://www.hetzner.com/">Hetzner</a>. The app deployment is managed by <a href="https://kamal-deploy.org/">Kamal</a>, and can occur manually from the command line or via GitHub Actions. With Hetzner's outrageous prices, you can acquire all the necessary hardware for the task, and more, for just €15/month.</p></li><li><p>The domain <code>www-draft.datocms.com</code> points directly to the Astro server.</p></li><li><p>The domain <code>www.datocms.com</code>, on the other hand, points to Fastly, a CDN that supports <a href="https://docs.fastly.com/en/guides/working-with-surrogate-keys">surrogate keys</a>. Fastly uses <code>www-draft.datocms.com</code> as the origin.</p></li><li><p>Astro pages, depending on whether the request host is either <code>www-draft</code> or <code>www</code>, will execute GraphQL requests to DatoCMS with the <a href="https://www.datocms.com/docs/content-delivery-api/api-endpoints#preview-mode-to-retrieve-draft-content"><code>X-Include-Drafts</code> header</a> either active or not. This allows our team to access draft content while regular visitors do not.</p></li><li><p>Astro also leverages <a href="https://www.datocms.com/blog/introducing-datocms-cache-tags">DatoCMS Cache Tags</a> to cache pages on Fastly indefinitely. In practical terms, Astro reads the <code>X-Cache-Tags</code> header for each GraphQL request made to DatoCMS, and applies those tags identically in its own response via the <code>Surrogate-Key</code> header.</p></li></ul><p>There's only one missing piece: cache invalidation. DatoCMS, through webhooks, sends cache invalidation tags to the Astro server with every content change on the CMS. Astro then uses those tags to <a href="https://docs.fastly.com/en/guides/purging-with-surrogate-keys">purge the Fastly cache</a> via an API call:</p><figure> <img-lightbox> <a href="https://www.datocms-assets.com/205/1732877411-schema2.svg?auto=format&amp;fit=max&amp;w=2000"><img src="https://www.datocms-assets.com/205/1732877411-schema2.svg"></a></img-lightbox>  <figcaption>Cache invalidation via DatoCMS Webhooks</figcaption> </figure><h2> How did it go? <a data-anchor="how-did-it-go" id="how-did-it-go"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#how-did-it-go"></a></h2><p>Honestly, <strong>we cannot be happier</strong> about the final result:</p><ul><li><p>Astro's support for TypeScript is excellent, and in general, it has allowed us to do everything we needed, even when we had to go outside "the norm".</p></li><li><p>The mental model of the architecture is extremely simple: <strong>everything's server-side generated. Period.</strong> No re-hydration, no huge client-side JavaScript bundles.</p></li><li><p>Our team can work on the content and see the results in real-time as they save their drafts through <a href="https://www.datocms.com/marketplace/plugins/i/datocms-plugin-web-previews">Web Previews</a> and <a href="https://www.datocms.com/docs/astro/real-time-updates">Real-time Updates</a>.</p></li><li><p>End visitors always get cached content from CDN (thanks to <a href="https://httpwg.org/specs/rfc5861.html#rfc.section.3"><code>stale-while-revalidate</code></a>), so the <strong>response is immediate</strong>.</p></li><li><p>Thanks to cache tags, <strong>cache purging is laser-precise</strong>, ensuring that only the pages that truly require updates are invalidated...</p></li><li><p>...yet, developers do not need to take any action to manage all the traditional complexity of caching. Once again, the mental model is straightforward, to the extent that <strong>you can forget about it</strong>.</p></li><li><p>Thanks to Fastly, <strong>cache purging happens in less than 150ms</strong>: if we accidentally publish incorrect content, we can correct it instantly, without having to wait minutes for a build to complete.</p></li><li><p>Complete builds and cache purging only occur when a new version of the repo is pushed. In our case, the <strong>total build time is approximately 3 minutes</strong>. We can probably improve this if we commit ourselves... the important feature, however, is that this time is <strong>independent of the number of pages</strong> on the site.</p></li><li><p>Last, but not least: <strong>hosting costs are ridiculously low</strong>.</p></li></ul><h2> How bad was the actual migration? <a data-anchor="how-bad-was-the-actual-migration" id="how-bad-was-the-actual-migration"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#how-bad-was-the-actual-migration"></a></h2><p>Our site is about a hundred different sections: from the beginning of the first tests to the full release, approximately <strong>two and a half months</strong> have passed. Not bad, considering it was never a full-time commitment, and that it has only been <a href="https://www.marcomezzavilla.com/">Marco</a> and me working on it.</p><p>Astro's <a href="https://docs.astro.build/en/basics/astro-syntax/">JSX-like syntax</a> made it pretty easy to transition all the components. Only the more complex components have remained in React as <a href="https://docs.astro.build/en/concepts/islands/">Astro Islands</a>, while small interactivity (<code>useState</code>, <code>useEffect</code>, etc.) has been <strong>converted into Web Components</strong> fairly easily. </p><h2> "I want the juicy details!" <a data-anchor="i-want-the-juicy-details" id="i-want-the-juicy-details"></a><a data-permalink="" href="#i-want-the-juicy-details"></a></h2><p>Good, because we can't wait to talk to you about it! 😜 After this first introduction to the overall architecture of the new site, the upcoming articles will explore in detail many practical topics related to Astro in conjunction with DatoCMS, and how we achieved clear, clean, and highly maintainable code.</p><p>These are just a few of the topics we want to discuss:</p><ul><li><p>Typed GraphQL schema;</p></li><li><p>GraphQL Fragment Colocation;</p></li><li><p>URL Building / SEO Management / Sitemaps;</p></li><li><p>Error management;</p></li><li><p>Astro Actions;</p></li><li><p>Replacing React with Web Components;</p></li><li><p>View Transitions;</p></li><li><p>SVGs;</p></li></ul><p>Whether you're considering a similar migration or just curious about modern web development best practices, we hope our journey inspires and informs yours. See you in the next episode! 👋</p>  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[South Korea President Yoon declares martial law (112 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/world/asia-pacific/south-korea-president-yoon-declares-martial-law-2024-12-03/</link>
            <guid>42306073</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 14:00:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/world/asia-pacific/south-korea-president-yoon-declares-martial-law-2024-12-03/">https://www.reuters.com/world/asia-pacific/south-korea-president-yoon-declares-martial-law-2024-12-03/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42306073">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/world/asia-pacific/south-korea-president-yoon-declares-martial-law-2024-12-03/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[South Korean president declares emergency martial law (575 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/south-korea-yoon-martial-law-997c22ac93f6a9bece68454597e577c1</link>
            <guid>42306020</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 13:53:50 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/south-korea-yoon-martial-law-997c22ac93f6a9bece68454597e577c1">https://apnews.com/article/south-korea-yoon-martial-law-997c22ac93f6a9bece68454597e577c1</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42306020">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) — South Korean President Yoon Suk Yeol declared an “emergency martial law,” Tuesday accusing the country’s opposition of controlling the parliament, sympathizing with North Korea and paralyzing the government with anti-state activities.</p><p>Yoon made the announcement in a televised briefing Tuesday, vowing to “eradicate pro-North Korean forces and protect the constitutional democratic order.” </p><p>It wasn’t immediately clear how Yoon’s step would affect the country’s governance and democracy. The move drew immediate opposition from politicians, including the leader of his own conservative party, Han Dong-hoon, who called the decision “wrong” and vowed to “stop it with the people.” Opposition leader Lee Jae-myung, who narrowly lost to Yoon in the 2022 presidential election, called Yoon’s announcement “illegal and unconstitutional.”</p>
    

<p>“Through this martial law, I will rebuild and protect the free Republic of Korea, which is falling into the depths of national ruin,” Yoon said during a televised speech, invoking South Korea’s formal name.</p><p>“I will eliminate anti-state forces as quickly as possible and normalize the country,” he said, while asking the people to believe in him and tolerate “some inconveniences.”</p>



<p>Yoon — whose approval rating has dipped in recent months — has struggled to push his agenda against an opposition-controlled parliament since taking office in 2022.</p>
    
    
    
<p>Yoon’s conservative People Power Party had been locked in an impasse with the liberal opposition Democratic Party over next year’s budget bill. The opposition has also been attempting to pass motions to impeach three top prosecutors, including the chief of the Seoul Central District Prosecutors’ Office, in what the conservatives have called a vendetta against their criminal investigations on Lee, who has been seen as the favorite for the next presidential election in 2027 in opinion polls.</p><p>Yoon has also been dismissing calls for independent investigations into scandals involving his wife and top officials, drawing quick, strong rebukes from his political rivals. The Democratic Party reportedly called an emergency meeting of its lawmakers following Yoon’s announcement.</p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Tweaking Stunt Island's 30-year-old 3D Engine (182 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://annali.netlify.app/2024/11/20/tweaking-stunt-island</link>
            <guid>42305954</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 13:44:59 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://annali.netlify.app/2024/11/20/tweaking-stunt-island">https://annali.netlify.app/2024/11/20/tweaking-stunt-island</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42305954">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page">
	  <p><a href="https://annali.netlify.app/">Annali da Samarcanda</a></p>
	  <p>Alberto Marnetto's Notebook</p>
	  <hr>
      

<p>Note: the patch is available at the end of the article (<b><a href="#download">HERE</a></b>). This post is about its making-of.</p>

<h3 id="intro">Intro</h3>

<p>Stunt Island is a flight simulator from the year 1992. You can read more about it in my <a href="https://annali.netlify.app/2024/11/15/stunt-island-elegy">previous post</a>.</p>

<p>Last month I finally beat the game, winning all the missions and getting the title of “Stuntman of the year”. While I was replaying the videos of my attempts, as well as some fan-made SI films in the channel, I wondered if I could somehow mitigate the obvious limitations of the rendering engine.</p>

<p>Also, I was always fascinated by the art of reverse engineering, and I thought this could be a good opportunity to learn something in this field. Assembly is not new to me, but dealing with an archaic DOS program, working without gdb’s features and any kind of debug symbols means entering an entirely different world.</p>

<p>I spent a dozen of hours learning the tools of the trade and trying to figure out the puzzle, and I was very happy of my eventual success. After finding and patching the right location in the executable, the engine got some extra horsepower. No extra resolution unfortunately, but many more details, as one can see in the comparisons below.</p>


<p>
<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/comparison"><b>Click here for the interactive comparison</b></a>
</center>
</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-flight-1x.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-flight-1x.png" alt="drawing" width="320">
</a>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-flight-8x.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-flight-8x.png" alt="drawing" width="320">
</a>
<figcaption>Mission 29, vanilla game (left) and patched (right)</figcaption>
</center>



<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-setdesign-1x.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-setdesign-1x.png" alt="drawing" width="320">
</a>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-setdesign-8x.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-setdesign-8x.png" alt="drawing" width="320">
</a>
<figcaption>Scenario editor, vanilla game (left) and patched (right)</figcaption>
</center>

<p>For a video comparison, one can check out <a href="https://youtu.be/AZMDm-2IIzc?si=7q4pK-dFhUyMhEyJ"><b>this “remaster” of the movie <em>Mickey’s Revenge</em></b></a>, courtesy of Doug Armknecht’s “Stunt Island Central” channel.</p>

<p>In the following, I’ll show the process and some failed tries. Even if this is far from being a professional effort, I hope that publishing this can be of help to other learners, or maybe induce some experts to chime in and suggest improvements (in the name of Cunningham’s Law). Tutorials about debugging with DOSBox are rare to find, so I feel that even this small example can be useful.</p>

<p>Also, I hope to revive some interest in an old, but beautiful and unique game.</p>

<h3 id="start">Start</h3>

<p>Since I have never debugged DOS programs, the first step is to build up the toolset. I need</p>

<ul>
  <li>DOSBox debug to run and live-debug the game</li>
  <li>Ghidra to decompile and analyze the executable. There are other DOS-compatible decompilers around, but I liked Ghidra’s “late Nineties” UI, even if it does not render nicely on Linux. I used the older 10.4 version for compatibility with my Debian’s openjdk package.</li>
  <li>Bless, my favorite hex editor</li>
</ul>

<p>I start by opening the game executable in Ghidra. The first result is underwhelming:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-raw.png">
</a><a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-raw.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-raw.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>

</center>

<p>Just one function and a lot of non-decompiled bytes, that does not look good. Maybe the decompile process failed?</p>

<p>Let’s look at the function. I cannot grasp all the details, but it seems to be copying a buffer. This rings a bell – I remember reading some articles about self-decrypting executables. Could it be that the real game code is obfuscated and only revealed after the startup?</p>

<p>By the way, what does the file header look like?</p>

<div><pre><code>$ hexdump -C STUNT.EXE | head -5 
00000000  4d 5a 18 00 0d 01 00 00  02 00 20 1c ff ff e9 3c  |MZ........ ....&lt;|
00000010  80 00 00 00 0e 00 52 21  1c 00 00 00 4c 5a 39 31  |......R!....LZ91|
00000020  ff 3f e8 64 00 a3 12 62  89 16 14 62 e8 81 00 3b  |.?.d...b...b...;|
00000030  3e ec f9 75 04 3b 06 ef  76 1b ea fd c7 ff 0f 06  |&gt;..u.;..v.......|
00000040  1c 62 00 00 b4 43 cd 67  84 e4 75 37 4f 87 ee 16  |.b...C.g..u7O...|
</code></pre></div>

<p>Seeing the “LZ91” finally clicks for me. This game was probably compressed by some variant of the Lempel-Ziv algorithm. Some googling leads me first to <a href="https://www.lodsb.com/reversing-lz91-from-commander-keen">this article by Sam Russell</a> and then to <a href="https://moddingwiki.shikadi.net/wiki/UNLZEXE">the UNLZEXE unpacker</a>. Turns out that the original compression tool was authored by the prolific genius Fabrice Bellard.</p>

<p>OK, let’s decompress the executable and reload it in Ghidra:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-si-uncompressed.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-si-uncompressed.png" alt="drawing" width="600">
</a>
</center>

<p>Looks better. Can we make any sense of the functions?</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-complex.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-complex.png" alt="drawing" width="600">
</a>
</center>

<p>Nope, this is over my paygrade. But we are in 2024, maybe we can seek the help of a LLM? Copilot says:</p>

<p><small><blockquote>
This looks like assembly code mixed with some higher-level C code constructs, dealing with system-level operations. Here’s a bit of a breakdown:<br>
* Initial Setup: The function begins by initializing variables and handling some immediate checks and adjustments.<br>
* Comparisons and Bit Manipulations: It checks some global variables and performs bit shifts and comparisons to adjust the control flow based on these conditions.<br>
* System Calls: There are several system interrupt calls, likely interacting with hardware or the operating system.<br>
* Function Calls: The code calls other functions (like FUN_1f59_36f7, FUN_1f59_0bc2, and FUN_1f59_0c2c) which perform some specific tasks.<br>
* Loops: The code includes loops and conditional checks to perform repeated tasks or to continue execution based on certain conditions.<br>
* The main flow is about handling and manipulating certain global variables and possibly hardware states, based on the names and types used. However, without more context on these global variables and the overall program architecture, it's tough to pin down the exact purpose.
</blockquote>
</small></p>

<p>Oh, I see, “the code calls other functions which perform some specific tasks”. Awesome. Thanks all the same, AI. See you in some years, and let’s rely on carbon-based intelligence in the meanwhile.</p>

<h3 id="a-matter-of-detail">A matter of detail</h3>

<p>The static analysis has not yielded any result yet, but I have another idea. Stunt Island has a “Detail” setting:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-detail.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-detail.png" alt="drawing" width="640">
</a>
</center>

<p>My hope is to find out where the detail level (here, 75%) is stored in the memory, and to change it to 255, or to see how it is used in the rendering process.</p>

<p>Let’s fire up Dosbox debug. The best manual for the interface is <a href="https://www.vogons.org/viewtopic.php?t=3944">a thread on the Vogons forum</a>.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/dosbox-debug.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/dosbox-debug.png" alt="drawing" width="600">
</a>
</center>

<p>The GUI is nice, even if I miss the amenities of modern debugging, especially the function names. However, credit is due to the authors: they put in nice features like a branch predictor that shows whether a jump instruction will be taken, and in which direction (back or forward), assuming that the current status of registries and memory stays the same.</p>

<p>How to find the location of the detail level variable? I navigate again to the “Preferences” screen and spend a lot of time there, trying to devise a method to extract such information. My list of failed attempts includes:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Break on keyboard input: I set a breakpoint on keypress (<code>BPINT 16</code>) and press “Return” with the mouse pointing on the “plus” sign. The program breaks in a input-reading routine, but stepping through the code I lose my way before being able to understand what the program is doing. Considering I could be in the middle of a complex UI-drawing routine, I give up.</li>
  <li>Break on mouse move or click: there is a <a href="https://www.vogons.org/viewtopic.php?f=31&amp;t=83267">helpful guide</a> for that, but again I end up in a mysterious land.</li>
  <li>Break on pixel change: I manage to break the program when a pixel in the detail scroller changes (<code>bpmem a1000:3500</code>). Again, I cannot find the way out of the graphics code.</li>
  <li>In Ghidra, look for a printf format string with a number and a percent (something like <code>"%u%%"</code>): nothing found</li>
</ul>

<p>While looking for other ideas, I find a nice <a href="https://wiki.scummvm.org/index.php/HOWTO-Reverse_Engineering">list of techniques</a> by the makers of ScummVM. One of the options is “File Access”, which reminds me that the game must store its preferences somewhere. A quick search by date reveals that a file with the promising name <code>GAME.VAR</code> is updated every time I alter the settings. Let’s see how it changes when a different detail level is chosen. At 99% detail we have</p>

<div><pre><code>$ hexdump -C GAME.VAR 
00000000  70 fd ff 01 ff ff ff ff  ff ff 99 e7 0b 00 38 01  |p.............8.|
00000010  64 02 0b 00 57 01 64 02  00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00  |d...W.d.........|
00000020  00 00 00                                          |...|
00000023
</code></pre></div>

<p>Now let’s set 1% detail:</p>

<div><pre><code>$ hexdump -C GAME.VAR 
00000000  8f 02 ff 01 ff ff ff ff  ff ff 99 e7 0b 00 38 01  |..............8.|
00000010  64 02 0b 00 57 01 64 02  00 00 00 00 00 00 00 00  |d...W.d.........|
00000020  00 00 00                                          |...|
00000023
</code></pre></div>

<p>So the detail level is in the very first two bytes. Unluckily, it seems already to be scaled, with 100% = <code>0xffff</code>. No chance to simply set it higher. But let’s not lose hope so soon: we have now more information to find out where in the memory this value is stored, and maybe we can change something else in the 3D computations.</p>

<p>I need a breakpoint when <code>GAME.SAV</code> is written. According to an <a href="https://mrszeto.net/CIT/interrupts.htm">old but practical</a> guide to the interrupt table, a file write is triggered by calling interrupt <code>21h</code> with <code>40h</code> in registry <code>AH</code>. Dosbox can set a breakpoint on precisely this event:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-bpint-21-40.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-bpint-21-40.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>I change the detail level, close the preferences window and, bingo! Breakpoint triggered.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-config-save.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-config-save.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>The bytes to write are in <code>DS:DX</code>, so <code>1628:2FEA</code>. Let’s have a look:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-2fea.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-2fea.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>Yes, the 16-bit value at that address matches the detail level I set (<code>0x3d70/0xffff ~= 0.24</code>). I bet that this is a global variable and will stay there for the whole duration of the program, what I verify by starting a mission:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-detail-global.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-detail-global.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>The value is still there. Very nice.</p>

<h3 id="following-the-dataflow">Following the dataflow</h3>

<p>Now I have to see where this variable is used. Let’s go back to Ghidra, and look for the low two bytes.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-2fea.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-2fea.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>I am lucky, not too many occurences.</p>

<p>First location: <code>CS:4CDA</code>. Ghidra decompiles the code to</p>

<div><pre><code>    *(int *)0xb86 =
         (int)((ulong)*(uint *)0x2fea * 100 &gt;&gt; 0x10) + *(int *)0xa5a +
         (uint)((int)((ulong)*(uint *)0x2fea * 100) &lt; 0);
</code></pre></div>

<p>Not super clear, but the meaning becomes evident when I set a breakpoint there (<code>BP CS:4CD8</code>): the line is executed only when I open the preferences box. So the “100” in the code must be part of the rescaling to a percentage.</p>

<p>Second location: <code>CS:680E</code>. The assembly is clearer than the C equivalent:</p>

<div><pre><code>       1000:6809 a1 ea 91        MOV        AX,[0x91ea]
       1000:680c f7 26 ea 2f     MUL        word ptr [0x2fea]
       1000:6810 d1 e0           SHL        AX,0x1
       1000:6812 d1 d2           RCL        DX,0x1
       1000:6814 89 16 f2 91     MOV        word ptr [0x91f2],DX
</code></pre></div>

<p>So, the variable at <code>DS:91EA</code> get multiplied by the detail level, and then written at <code>DS:91F2</code>. No idea what <code>DS:91EA</code> is, though. I first think that this routine is calculating some per-polygon quantity, but it turns out that it is only run once per frame. Also, when I run some frames in mission 1 the variable at <code>DS:91EA</code> switches between <code>0x0999</code> and <code>0x7FFF</code>. Let’s ignore the matter: we now know that at <code>DS:91F2</code> something gets written that is proportional to the detail level. Moreover, with Detail set at 100% this variable is often set at <code>0xFFFD</code>, almost the maximum.</p>

<p>I look for <code>f2 91</code> in Ghidra: it only yields two occurrences. One is the fragment we just analyzed, the other is in the middle of some bytes that Ghidra did not decompile automatically.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-91f2.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-91f2.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>Well, there is no other place to look, so I ask Ghidra to decompile this section. Some attempts later, a plausible assembly appears:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-91f2-found.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-91f2-found.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>I ensure that the decompilation is right by setting a breakpoint at the start of the fragment (<code>BP CS:76E8</code>), and for added safety I verify that the program counter (<code>EIP</code>) really points to the locations shown in the listing. This code gets executed many, many times per frame – have I finally reached the goal?</p>

<h3 id="ace-gets-glasses">Ace gets glasses</h3>

<p>Let’s try to understand the code: first it decrements <code>AX</code> and executes what follows only if it’s still positive. Not sure what this means but some live debugging shows that the condition is met quite often anyway. The following calculation is easier to understand: in the x86 architecture, calling <code>MUL</code> multiplies <code>AX</code> by the operand, leaving the  result in <code>DX:AX</code>. With maximum detail, we know that <code>DS:91F2</code> will be set at <code>0xFFFD</code>, so that the multiplication becomes almost a 16-bit left shift, setting <code>DX</code> to <code>(AX_old - 1)</code>. The lower the detail, the lower <code>DX</code> will be. Then the code executes the following branch only if <code>CX &lt;= DX + BX</code>, otherwise it gets skipped.</p>

<p>In an <a href="https://fabiensanglard.net/stunt_island/">interview by Fabien Sanglard</a>, Stunt Island’s main programmer Adrian Stephens revealed an important aspect of the rendering engine: each 3D entity in the game is represented as a tree, and the game decides whether to render the (coarser) top nodes or the (finer) lower levels according to their distance from the observer. And we see here that a subroutine gets executed if <code>CX</code> is under a certain threshold, which gets bigger the bigger is the detail level. Let’s make the bold hypothesis that <code>CX</code> is the object distance, and <code>(DX + BX)</code> determines the distance threshold under which a higher-resolution model gets loaded.</p>

<p>I can test the hypothesis by overwriting the calculation with new code. Let’s start by setting the threshold to zero. Ghidra shows which bytes to insert:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-patch.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/ghidra-patch.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>I can do that in the live program:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/dd-patch-live.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/dd-patch-live.png" alt="drawing" width="800">
</a>
</center>

<p>The experiment works perfectly: all details disappear, Jackson City is reduced to flatland.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/flatland.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/flatland.png" alt="drawing" width="640">
</a>
</center>

<p>But what I want is the contrary: changing the code so that the max resolution gets used for all objects. Let’s just set the threshold to the max:</p>

<div><pre><code>SM cs:76f4 c7 c2 ff 7f 66 90 
(MOV DX, 0x7FFF ; NOP) 
</code></pre></div>

<p>This makes the engine totally unresponsive to the keyboard commands. I guess I was too greedy. My second try is more modest:</p>

<div><pre><code>SM cs:76f4 c7 c2 ff 4f 66 90 
(MOV DX, 0x4FFF ; NOP) 
</code></pre></div>

<p>And here we are: Stunt Island in the best detail you’ll ever get in a 320x200 window! Pity that the system is still just barely responsive: even with DOSBox’s CPU set to max performance, I cannot control my plane, and this is the best screenshot I am able to take before crashing.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/sr71-high-detail.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/sr71-high-detail.png" alt="drawing" width="640">
</a>
</center>

<p>But there is a better way to go sightseeing: the rendering routine is shared across flight sim, video player and set designer, and at least in the last mode I can take all the time I need to steer the camera. It takes some minutes to push the extremely sluggish control, but after a while I can frame Jackson City and surroundings, looking more gorgeous than ever!</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/set-des-high-detail.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/set-des-high-detail.png" alt="drawing" width="640">
</a>
</center>

<p>Now that I explored the limits, it’s time to turn back the dial and find some compromise to make the game playable. The current patch is brutal, it just uses a fixed threshold ignoring the original value in <code>DX</code>. We know that <code>DX</code> is approximately <code>AX_old * (detail_level/100)</code>, maxing out at <code>AX_old - 1</code> if the detail level is 100%. What about putting a multiple of <code>AX</code> there? The space is limited, only 6 bytes, but a bitshift is compact enough. After some experiments, I settle on</p>

<div><pre><code>89 c2 c1   MOV DX,AX 
e2 03      SHL DX,0x3
90         NOP
</code></pre></div>

<p>which would be the equivalent of a 800% detail. I patch it in using the Dosbox command:</p>

<div><pre><code>SM cs:76f4 89 c2 c1 e2 03 90  
</code></pre></div>

<p>And everything goes as hoped: the quality is great and the game (after cranking up Dosbox’s CPU to the max) runs quite fluidly. Time to celebrate!</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/final-quality.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/final-quality.png" alt="drawing" width="640">
</a>
</center>

<p>By the way, the fact that the three most significant bits of <code>DX</code> are discarded does not seem to lead to any noticeable glitch; I could add some code checking for overflow and saturating the value, but this would require more bytes than I am replacing. I might create the algorithm elsewhere and then <code>JMP</code> to it, but at the price of making the code slower and the patching process more difficult. The current version is simple and good enough for me, and after all one must leave some fun to future tinkerers.</p>

<h3 id="washing-the-dishes">Washing the dishes</h3>

<p>Before calling it a day, I still have some housework to do.</p>

<p>First, I need to edit the executables to avoid having to live-patch the code every time. Stunt Island provides not only the game executable (<code>STUNT.EXE</code>), but also a video encoder and a player (<code>MAKEONE</code> and <code>PLAYONE</code>), so that users can distribute and view their films without having to navigate through the game interface. To do a complete work, I want to patch all these files.</p>

<p>Fortunately, the rendering code is the same in all three executables. However, the detail variable is stored at different addresses, so the assembly is not the same. The easiest way to find the relevant location is to search for the instructions that follow the <code>MUL</code> (so the <code>ADD / CMP / JG</code> sequence): they only refer to register values, so their encoding (<code>03 D3 3B CA 7F 1B</code>) is the same in all the files to patch.</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/bless-search.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/bless-search.png" alt="drawing" width="600">
</a>
</center>

<p>Then, we move four bytes back, and we replace the “multiply by the detail level” segment (<code>F7 26 XX XX 03 D3</code>) with the “multiply by 8” code (<code>89 C2 C1 E2 03 90</code>).</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/bless-replace.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/bless-replace.png" alt="drawing" width="600">
</a>
</center>

<p>The operation works well on all three executables. The patched <code>PLAYONE</code> can only play films created by the patched <code>MAKEONE</code>, but this seems reasonable. I guess that the films created by the vanilla <code>MAKEONE</code> are missing the high-polygon versions of the far objects.</p>

<p>Second, I must create a patching program that can upgrade the game without embedding Disney’s code. It would be nice to just implement it as simple search and replace for the six bytes that need to be overwriten, but unfortunately there is the problem of the LZ compression. I cannot bundle <code>unlzexe</code>, whose copyright status is unclear, so I end up recompressing the patched executable and diffing it with the unpatched version. The compression smears my 3-byte change all over the file creating a big diff, but this seems to me the least worst method. The patcher then applies the diff to the original game file, which must be provided by the user. This should put the patch on the safe side, copyright-wise.</p>

<p>Finally, I am informed that Disney released a patch (“#3”) containing some features like an alternative beginner-friendly flight model. It would be good if the 800% mod also worked on this version. Luckily the renderer was not changed so the same patching method can be used. The only surprise happens when uncompressing the new <code>.EXE</code>: it turns that the compression method was slightly changed (from LZ091 to LZ091E), and <code>unlzexe</code> does not recognize the format. However, the algorithm is the same, just the magic number used for the format identification has changed. Commenting out the magic number check in the source code of <code>unlzexe</code> solves the problem: I can uncompress the file and create a patch using the same process of the original game.</p>

<p>So, here the best Stunt Island one can have, with the enhanced rendering engine and the quality-of-life improvements of Disney’s patch:</p>

<center>
<a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/final.png">
<img src="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/final.png" alt="drawing" width="640">
</a>
</center>

<h3 id="want-to-try-it-out">Want to try it out?</h3>

<p>To play the “definitive” version of Stunt Island, three steps are needed:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Get the original game, e.g. on <a href="https://www.gog.com/en/game/stunt_island">GOG</a> or <a href="https://store.steampowered.com/app/602970/Stunt_Island/">Steam</a></li>
  <li>(Optionally) download the “#3” patch from <a href="https://armknechted.com/sicentral/sifiles/index.html">Stunt Island Central</a>, copy it in the game directory, and run the executable in Dosbox</li>
  <li>Download the “8x” patch, copy it in the game directory, and run the Windows or Linux executable (doing it for DOS would have taken longer)</li>
</ul>

<p><a id="download"></a>
Downloads:</p>
<ul>
  <li><b><a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-8x.zip">PATCH</a></b> in zip format (recommended)</li>
  <li><b><a href="https://annali.netlify.app/assets/2024-11-20--tweaking-stunt-island/si-8x.7z">PATCH</a></b> in 7z format, password-protected, password = <code>stunt-island</code> (use in case your browser blocks the download of the zip version)</li>
</ul>


  

</div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Phishers Love New TLDs Like .shop, .top and .xyz (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/12/why-phishers-love-new-tlds-like-shop-top-and-xyz/</link>
            <guid>42305831</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 13:30:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/12/why-phishers-love-new-tlds-like-shop-top-and-xyz/">https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/12/why-phishers-love-new-tlds-like-shop-top-and-xyz/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42305831">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
												<p>Phishing attacks increased nearly 40 percent in the year ending August 2024, with much of that growth concentrated at a small number of new generic top-level domains (gTLDs) — such as <strong>.shop</strong>, <strong>.top</strong>, <strong>.xyz</strong> — that attract scammers with rock-bottom prices and no meaningful registration requirements, new research finds. Meanwhile, the nonprofit entity that oversees the domain name industry is moving forward with plans to introduce a slew of new gTLDs.</p>
<div id="attachment_68142"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-68142" decoding="async" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/phishtrap.png" alt="" width="748" height="457" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/phishtrap.png 776w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/07/phishtrap-768x469.png 768w" sizes="(max-width: 748px) 100vw, 748px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-68142">Image: Shutterstock.</p></div>
<p>A <a href="https://interisle.net/insights/phishing-landscape-2024-an-annual-study-of-the-scope-and-distribution-of-phishing" target="_blank" rel="noopener">study</a> on phishing data released by <strong>Interisle Consulting</strong> finds that new gTLDs introduced in the last few years command just 11 percent of the market for new domains, but accounted for roughly 37 percent of cybercrime domains reported between September 2023 and August 2024.</p>
<p>Interisle sources data about cybercrime domains from anti-spam organizations, including the <strong>Anti-Phishing Working Group</strong> (APWG), the <strong>Coalition Against Unsolicited Commercial Email</strong> (CAUCE), and the <strong>Messaging, Malware, and Mobile Anti-Abuse Working Group</strong> (M3AAWG).</p>
<p>The study finds that while <strong>.com</strong> and <strong>.net</strong> domains made up approximately half of all domains registered in the past year (more than all of the other TLDs combined) they accounted for just over 40 percent of all cybercrime domains. Interisle says an almost equal share — 37 percent — of cybercrime domains were registered through new gTLDs.</p>
<p>Spammers and scammers gravitate toward domains in the new gTLDs because these registrars tend to offer cheap or free registration with little to no account or identity verification requirements. For example, among the gTLDs with the highest cybercrime domain scores in this year’s study, nine offered registration fees for less than $1, and nearly two dozen offered fees of less than $2.00. By comparison, the cheapest price identified for a .com domain was $5.91.</p>
<p>Currently, there are around 2,500 registrars authorized to sell domains by the <strong>Internet Corporation for Assigned Names and Numbers</strong> (ICANN), the California nonprofit that oversees the domain industry.</p>
<div id="attachment_69689"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69689" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/interisle-top-xyz.png" alt="" width="749" height="503" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/interisle-top-xyz.png 862w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/interisle-top-xyz-768x516.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/12/interisle-top-xyz-782x525.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69689">The top 5 new gTLDs, ranked by cybercrime domains reported. Image: Interisle Cybercrime Supply Chain 2014.</p></div>
<p>Incredibly, despite years of these reports showing phishers heavily abusing new gTLDs, ICANN is shuffling forward on a plan to introduce even more of them. ICANN’s proposed <a href="https://newgtldprogram.icann.org/en/application-rounds/round2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">next round envisions</a> accepting applications for new gTLDs in 2026.</p>
<p><strong>John Levine </strong>is author of the book “The Internet for Dummies” and president of CAUCE. Levine said adding more TLDs without a much stricter registration policy will likely further expand an already plentiful greenfield for cybercriminals.</p>
<p>“The problem is that ICANN can’t make up their mind whether they are the neutral nonprofit regulator or just the domain speculator trade association,” Levine told KrebsOnSecurity. “But they act a lot more like the latter.”<span id="more-69531"></span></p>
<p>Levine said the vast majority of new gTLDs have a few thousand domains — a far cry from the number of registrations they would need just to cover the up-front costs of operating a new gTLD (~$180,000-$300,000). New gTLD registrars can quickly attract customers by selling domains cheaply to customers who buy domains in bulk, but that tends to be a losing strategy.</p>
<p>“Selling to criminals and spammers turns out to be lousy business,” Levine said. “You can charge whatever you want on the first year, but you have to charge list price on domain renewals. And criminals and spammers never renew. So if it sounds like the economics makes no sense it’s because the economics makes no sense.”</p>
<p>In virtually all previous spam reports, Interisle found the top brands referenced in phishing attacks were the largest technology companies, including Apple, Facebook, Google and PayPal. But this past year, Interisle found the <strong>U.S. Postal Service</strong> was by far the most-phished entity, with more than four times the number of phishing domains as the second most-frequent target (Apple).</p>
<p>At least some of that increase is likely from a prolific cybercriminal using the nickname <strong>Chenlun</strong>, who&nbsp;has been <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2023/10/phishers-spoof-usps-12-other-natl-postal-services/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">selling phishing kits targeting domestic postal services</a> in the United States and at least a dozen other countries.</p>
<p>Interisle says an increasing number of phishers are eschewing domain registrations altogether, and instead taking advantage of subdomain providers like <strong>blogspot.com</strong>, <strong>pages.dev</strong>, and <strong>weebly.com</strong>. The report notes that cyberattacks hosted at subdomain provider services can be tough to mitigate, because only the subdomain provider can disable malicious accounts or take down malicious web pages.</p>
<p>“Any action upstream, such as blocking the second-level domain, would have an impact across the provider’s whole customer base,” the report observes.</p>
<p>Interisle tracked more than 1.18 million instances of subdomains used for phishing in the past year (a 114 percent increase), and found more than half of those were subdomains at blogspot.com and other services operated by Google.</p>
<p>“Many of these services allow the creation of large numbers of accounts at one time, which is highly exploited by criminals,” the report concludes. “Subdomain providers should limit the number of subdomains (user accounts) a customer can create at one time and suspend automated, high-volume automated account sign-ups – especially using free services.”</p>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kagi Search API (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://help.kagi.com/kagi/api/search.html</link>
            <guid>42305767</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 13:22:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://help.kagi.com/kagi/api/search.html">https://help.kagi.com/kagi/api/search.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42305767">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><span>json</span></p><pre><code><span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>  </span><span>"</span><span>meta</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>id</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>69c3f5c4168f66b860e951c585550f1c</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>node</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>us-central1</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>ms</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>213</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>"</span><span>api_balance</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>123.456</span></span>
<span><span>  </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>  </span><span>"</span><span>data</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs - Wikipedia</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steven Paul Jobs (February 24, 1955 – October 5, 2011) was an American businessman, inventor, and investor best known for co-founding the technology company ...</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>thumbnail</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>/proxy/310px-Steve_Jobs_Headshot_2010-CROP_%28cropped_2%29.jpg?c=9cn5Kxse4yD05EJkf6QML9dK4clUbdQ9Oq4d5gDoyHBwiX43u0CCAEVi8DMCHFAXhMAIsLbp8IO0pmQf41WB6CWu9BNfAxhRqV-EQL_l_gnV1yD14xBDf5Sgj1vfjIF0aMOqcVwh-jMVcqkx3GjwnuZrt2Z8-tdYhu3uERcYzLTTqq5TKumyN0Q1c5n3utowEZhefA7WoUo3SNIB1-iHhCnijbEL5iAQo1iTroqppHk%3D</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>width</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>null,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>height</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>null</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Steve_Jobs_(film)</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs (film) - Wikipedia</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs is a 2015 biographical drama film directed by Danny Boyle and written by Aaron Sorkin. A British-American co-production, it was adapted from the ...</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>thumbnail</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>/proxy/310px-Steve_Jobs_Headshot_2010-CROP_%28cropped_2%29.jpg?c=9cn5Kxse4yD05EJkf6QML9dK4clUbdQ9Oq4d5gDoyHBwiX43u0CCAEVi8DMCHFAXhMAIsLbp8IO0pmQf41WB6CWu9BNfAxhRqV-EQL_l_gnV1yD14xBDf5Sgj1vfjIF0aMOqcVwh-jMVcqkx3GjwnuZrt2Z8-tdYhu3uERcYzLTTqq5TKumyN0Q1c5n3utowEZhefA7WoUo3SNIB1-iHhCnijbEL5iAQo1iTroqppHk%3D</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>width</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>310</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>height</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>300</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.apple.com/stevejobs/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Remembering Steve Jobs - Apple</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>He was a visionary that had the amazing ability to breath life into his ideas. He believed so passionately in his work that his creativity became both seductive ...</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.biography.com/business-leaders/steve-jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs: Biography, Apple Cofounder, Entrepreneur</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs was an American inventor, designer, and entrepreneur who was the cofounder, chief executive, and chairman of Apple Inc. Born in 1955 to two University of Wisconsin graduate students who ...</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.britannica.com/money/Steve-Jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs | Biography, Education, Apple, &amp; Facts | Britannica Money</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs, the visionary co-founder of Apple Inc., revolutionized technology and consumer electronics with his innovative products that ...</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>published</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>2024-09-30T00:00:00Z</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.amazon.com/Steve-Jobs-Walter-Isaacson/dp/1451648537</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs: 9781451648539: Isaacson, Walter: Books - Amazon.com</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Walter Isaacson&amp;#39;s “enthralling” (The New Yorker) worldwide bestselling biography of Apple cofounder Steve Jobs. Based on more than forty interviews with ...</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://hbr.org/2012/04/the-real-leadership-lessons-of-steve-jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>The Real Leadership Lessons of Steve Jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>The essence of Jobs, I think, is that his personality was integral to his way of doing business. He acted as if the normal rules didn&amp;#39;t apply to him.</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>published</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>2012-04-01T00:00:00Z</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UF8uR6Z6KLc</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs' 2005 Stanford Commencement Address - YouTube</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Drawing from some of the most pivotal points in his life, Steve Jobs, chief executive officer and ...</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>published</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>2008-03-07T00:00:00Z</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.forbes.com/profile/steve-jobs/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs - Forbes</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Apple cofounder Steve Jobs finally succumbed to cancer at the age of 56 on October 5th, leaving behind a legacy that changed the computer, music, film and ...</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://allaboutstevejobs.com/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Home | all about Steve Jobs.com</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs. This website is a repository of all things Steve Jobs — biography, pictures, videos of his keynotes and demos, quotes, interviews — you name it.</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.imdb.com/title/tt2080374/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs (2015) - IMDb</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>A film by Danny Boyle and Aaron Sorkin that depicts three pivotal moments in the life of Steve Jobs, the visionary leader of the digital revolution. Michael Fassbender, Kate Winslet, Seth Rogen and Jeff Daniels star in this drama nominated for two Oscars.</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0423418/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs - IMDb</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>IMDb provides an overview of the life and career of Steve Jobs, the visionary co-founder of Apple and Pixar. Learn about his achievements, innovations, challenges, and legacy in the fields of technology, entertainment, and design.</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0423418/bio/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs - Biography - IMDb</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Learn about the life and achievements of Steve Jobs, the visionary co-founder of Apple and Pixar. From his adoption and dropout to his cancer and legacy, discover his story and trivia on IMDb.</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.thoughtco.com/steve-jobs-biography-1991928</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Biography of Steve Jobs, Co-Founder of Apple Computers - ThoughtCo</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Learn about the life and achievements of Steve Jobs, the visionary entrepreneur who co-founded Apple Computers and Pixar Animation Studios. Explore his early years, inventions, business ventures, and legacy.</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.npr.org/2015/10/09/447165973/steve-jobs-the-story-of-the-man-behind-the-personal-computer</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs: The Story Of The Man Behind The Personal Computer</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>The Apple founder spoke with Fresh Air&amp;#39;s Terry Gross in 1996. Later, after he was diagnosed with cancer, Jobs asked Walter Isaacson to write his biography. Isaacson spoke to Fresh Air Oct. 25, 2011.</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>published</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>2015-10-09T00:00:00Z</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.npr.org/2011/10/05/123826622/apple-visionary-steve-jobs-dies-at-56</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs, Poet Of Computer World, Dies - NPR</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs (1955-2011) Apple has lost a visionary and creative genius, and the world has lost an amazing human being. Those of us who have been fortunate enough to know and work with Steve have ...</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>published</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>2011-10-05T00:00:00Z</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/06/business/steve-jobs-of-apple-dies-at-56.html</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs of Apple Dies at 56 - The New York Times</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Jim Wilson/The New York Times. By John Markoff. Oct. 5, 2011. Steven P. Jobs, the visionary co-founder of Apple who helped usher in the era of personal computers and then led a cultural ...</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>published</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>2011-10-06T00:00:00Z</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.businessinsider.com/steve-jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs' life and Apple career, from cofounder, to exile, to CEO</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Apple CEO Steve Jobs introduces the new iPod mini digital music player at the 2004 Macworld Conference and Expo in San Francisco. The player can hold up to 1,000 tunes, is about the size of a ...</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.entrepreneur.com/growing-a-business/who-was-steve-jobs-see-the-apple-founders-career-and-more/197538</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs Biography | Entrepreneur</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>An overview of Steve Jobs&amp;#39; life. Steven Paul Jobs was an American business owner, entrepreneur, investor and media proprietor. He was best known for co-founding and leading Apple, one of the most ...</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>url</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>https://www.computerhistory.org/blog/steve-jobs/</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>title</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs: From Garage to World’s Most Valuable Company</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>snippet</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>"</span><span>Learn how Steve Jobs and Steve Wozniak, two young electronics hobbyists, created the Apple-1 and launched the personal computer revolution. Explore their early adventures with Blue Boxes, Atari, HP and the Homebrew Computer Club.</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>},</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>{</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>t</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>"</span><span>list</span><span>"</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>[</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>Steve Jobs</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs death</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs net worth</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs quotes</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs movie</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs wife</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs daughter</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs biography</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs last words</span><span>"</span><span>,</span></span>
<span><span>        </span><span>"</span><span>steve jobs age</span><span>"</span></span>
<span><span>      </span><span>]</span></span>
<span><span>    </span><span>}</span></span>
<span><span>  </span><span>]</span></span>
<span><span>}</span></span></code></pre></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dependency management fatigue, or why I forever ditched React for Go+Htmx+Templ (191 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.erodriguez.de/dependency-management-fatigue-or-why-i-forever-ditched-react-for-go-htmx-templ/</link>
            <guid>42305348</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 12:16:33 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.erodriguez.de/dependency-management-fatigue-or-why-i-forever-ditched-react-for-go-htmx-templ/">https://blog.erodriguez.de/dependency-management-fatigue-or-why-i-forever-ditched-react-for-go-htmx-templ/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42305348">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>After getting to work on some personal projects using Go+HTMX+Templ this year, I have decided to give up on using React on any personal projects.</p><p>You can actually find a lot of compelling arguments for ditching React in favor of HTMX in the essays found in the HTMX official website.
But I feel that not that many people are speaking about <strong>dependency management fatigue</strong>.</p><h2 id="what-is-dependency-management-fatigue">What is dependency management fatigue?</h2><p>After working on my last personal project that used React (an <a href="https://github.com/erodrigufer/catDict">interactive Catalan dictionary</a>), I realized that I was spending too much time dealing with dependency updates of mostly React packages.
I would update my packages to their latest release, only to realize that their APIs had breaking changes that forced me to invest time refactoring my code.</p><p>I wanted to keep up with any dependency updates because my webapp was back then deployed as a publicly accessible service in an EC2 instance and I wanted to avoid any possible vulnerabilities.</p><h2 id="do-we-really-need-a-new-major-version-release">Do we really need a new major version release?</h2><p>Some of the worst offenders in this respect were <code>wouter</code> (a React router package) and <code>TanStackQuery</code> (which I was using to fetch, cache and manage state from the backend).
<code>wouter</code> is, as of December 2024, at major version 3, while <code>TanStackQuery</code> is at major version 5.</p><p>I wasn’t using these packages for minor, stylistic features in my webapp, they were fundamental for the proper working of my webapp.
If they broke, my webapp fatally broke as well, i.e. no more data fetching from the backend and no more correct routing.
There was nothing similar to <em>progressive enhancement</em> in this case.</p><p>The first time that one of these React libraries broke my application with a major version bump, I refactored my code without any questioning.</p><p>But the second time that this happened, it just felt odd.
I started asking myself:</p><ul><li>Is my webapp getting some actual <strong>benefits</strong> (apart from maybe security patches) from this major version release?</li><li>Is it necessary to literally <strong>break</strong> the API of a fundamental component in a React webapp <strong>5 times</strong> ?!?!</li><li>How much time am I losing on this, when I could be shipping new features or other products?</li></ul><p>The answers to these questions were:</p><ol><li>No, my webapp wasn’t getting any additional benefits.
I was already happy with the functionality of these packages.</li><li>I am not a core maintainer of these libraries, so it is hard for me to answer the second question.
But I would say no.
Plan your API design wisely.
Only ship features that you plan to maintain in the long-term.
Do not unnecessarily rename your exported objects.</li></ol><p>Look, I am really grateful for open source maintainers, and you can do whatever you want with your projects (I myself do the same with mine).
But if your goal is to sustain a happy userbase, I would say that appreciating the user’s precious time must be a big priority.</p><h2 id="i-just-dont-have-the-time-to-deal-with-this">I just don’t have the time to deal with this…</h2><p>Which gets me to one of the main points of this article.
Why is this such a big issue?</p><p>Well, at least for me, it boils down to me not having that much free time left.
So, if I somehow find some free time to work on my personal coding projects, I don’t want to waste it refactoring my code to work after the major version bump of a dependency.
I actually want to work on features or start new projects.</p><p>If you are building a product for a client, and you will charge for future maintenance work, then be my guest, use as many unstable dependencies as you like.
It might be in your own best financial interest to do so.
But if you are trying to build a product that requires as little upkeep as necessary after being shipped, I’ll stay as far as possible from the JS ecosystem.</p><h2 id="gohtmxtempl">Go+HTMX+Templ</h2><p>That is maybe the main reason why I will solely use Go+HTMX+Templ in my personal projects from now on.
This is maybe just anecdotal evidence, but the Go projects I’ve worked on let me focus on shipping features, while not ignoring general dependency/security updates.
The language itself has kept a remarkably stable stdlib and language specification.</p><p><a href="https://lobste.rs/s/xyvjbb/dependency_management_fatigue_why_i">Discuss in Lobsters</a></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Company claims 1k% price hike drove it from VMware to open source rival (202 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/12/company-claims-1000-percent-price-hike-drove-it-from-vmware-to-open-source-rival/</link>
            <guid>42304955</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2024 11:07:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/12/company-claims-1000-percent-price-hike-drove-it-from-vmware-to-open-source-rival/">https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/12/company-claims-1000-percent-price-hike-drove-it-from-vmware-to-open-source-rival/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42304955">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                      
                      
          <p>Companies have been discussing migrating off of VMware since Broadcom’s takeover a year ago led to higher costs and other <a href="https://arstechnica.com/information-technology/2024/06/price-hikes-of-over-2x-widely-expected-under-broadcoms-vmware-survey-finds/">controversial changes</a>. Now we have an inside look at one of the larger customers that recently made the move.</p>
<p>According to a report from <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/12/02/beeks_group_vmware_opennebula_migration/">The Register</a> today, Beeks Group, a cloud operator headquartered in the United Kingdom, has moved most of its 20,000-plus virtual machines (VMs) off VMware and to OpenNebula, an open source cloud and edge computing platform. Beeks Group sells virtual private servers and bare metal servers to financial service providers. It still has some VMware VMs, but “the majority” of its machines are currently on OpenNebula, The Register reported.</p>
<p>Beeks’ head of production management, Matthew Cretney, said that one of the reasons for Beeks' migration was a VMware bill for “10 times the sum it previously paid for software licenses,” per The Register.</p>
<p>According to Beeks, OpenNebula has enabled the company to dedicate more of its 3,000 bare metal server fleet to client loads instead of to VM management, as it had to with VMware. With OpenNebula purportedly requiring less management overhead, Beeks is reporting a 200 percent increase in VM efficiency since it now has more VMs on each server.</p>
<p>Beeks also pointed to customers viewing VMware as non-essential and a decline in VMware support services and innovation as drivers for it migrating from VMware.</p>
<p>Broadcom didn't respond to Ars Technica's request for comment.</p>
<h2>Broadcom loses VMware customers</h2>
<p>Broadcom will likely continue seeing some of VMware's older customers decrease or abandon reliance on VMware offerings. But Broadcom has emphasized the financial success it has seen (<a href="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2024/10/Broadcom-Inc.-Announces-Third-Quarter-Fiscal-Year-2024-Financial-Results-and-Quarterly-Dividend.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PDF</a>) from its VMware acquisition, suggesting that it will continue with its strategy even at the risk of losing some business.</p>

          
                      
                  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>