<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 18:30:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Ask HN: Recommendation for a SWE looking to get up to speed with latest on AI (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42256093</link>
            <guid>42256093</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 13:55:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42256093">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
            <tbody><tr id="42256405"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256405" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256405&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The poster's looking for articles, so this recommendation's a bit off the mark. I learned more from participating in a few Kaggle competitions (<a href="https://www.kaggle.com/competitions" rel="nofollow">https://www.kaggle.com/competitions</a>) than I did from reading about AI. Many folks in the community shared their homework, and by learning how to follow their explanations I developed a much more intuitive understanding of the technology. The first competition had a steep learning curve. I felt it was worth it. The application of having a specific goal and the provided datasets made the problem space more tractable.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256720"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256720" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256720&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Out of sheer curiosity, how much time did you spend on it on average? How much of this knowledge are you using now?</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256785"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256785" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256785&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Not the poster you responded to but I learned quite a bit from kaggle too.</p><p>I started from scratch, spent 2-4 hrs per day for 6 months &amp; won a silver in a kaggle NLP competition.  Now I use some of it now but not all of it. More than that, I'm quite comfortable with models, understand the costs/benefits/implications etc. I started with Andrew Ng's intro courses, did a bit of fastai, did Karpathy's Zero to Hero fully, all of Kaggle's courses &amp; a few other such things. Kagglers share excellent notebooks and I found them v helpful. Overall I highly recommend this route of learning.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257032"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256925"><td></td></tr>
                              <tr id="42256144"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256502"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42256403"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256403" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256403&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I don't think it's a good idea to kepp up to date at a daily/weekly cadence, unless you somehow directly get paid for it. It's like checking stocks daily, it doesn't lead to good investment decisions.</p><p>It's better to do it more batchy, like once every 6-12 months or so.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256452"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256452" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256452&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>How do you do that? Once you're out of the loop for half a year, it becomes harder to know what's important and what's not, I think.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257829"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257829" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257829&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Some ideas:</p><p>1. Buy O'reilly (and other tech) books as they come out. This will have a lag, but essentially somebody did this research &amp; summarization work, and wrote it up for you in chapters. Note that you don't have to read everything in a book. Also, $50 is a great investment if it saves you 10s of hours of time.</p><p>2. Talks on Youtube at conferences by industry leaders, like Yann LeCun, or maintainers of popular libraries, etc. Also, YT videos on the topic that are upvoted/linked.</p><p>3. If you're interested in hardcore research, look for review articles on arxiv.</p><p>4. Look at tutorials/examples in the documentation/repo of popular ML/AI libraries, like Pytorch.</p><p>5. Try to cover your blindspots. One way or another, you'll know how new AI is applied to SWE and related fields. But how is AI applied to perpendicular fields, like designing buildings, composing music, or balancing a budget? Trying to cover these areas will be tougher, because it will be more noisy, as most commenters will be non-experts compared to you. To get a feel for this, do something that feels unnatural, like watch TED talks that seem bullshity, read HBR articles intended for MBAs, and check out what Palantir is doing.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256624"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256624" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256624&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Every release is novel. Once something has been around for a while and is still being referenced, you know it’s worth learning.</p><p>Waiting 3-6 months to take a deep dive is a good pattern to prevent investing your time in dead-end routes.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257570"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257570" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257570&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Yes this is why I never buy the latest CPUs and try to never run the latest release of any software. Stay a (supported) release or two behind the bleeding edge, and you'll find stuff is more stable. Common bugs and other issues have been shaken out by the early adopters.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                              <tr id="42257627"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257627" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257627&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>For news-like content I follow accounts on X: @kimmonismus @apples_jimmy and the accounts of Antropic, Mistal, Gemini / DeepMind and OpenAI.
I think everyone who is really interested in the hot AI developments must also follow what comes from China. I follow <a href="https://chinai.substack.com/" rel="nofollow">https://chinai.substack.com/</a> but I am open to hear about other Chinese resources.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257607"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257387"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257387" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257387&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>I read about 30 LLM papers a couple months ago dated from 2018-2024. Mostly folks are publishing on the “how do we prompt better” problem, and you can kind of get the gist in about a day by reading a few blogs (RAG, fine tuning, tool use, etc). There is also more progress being made for model capabilities, like multi modality, and each company seems to be pushing in only slightly different directions, but essentially they are still black boxes.</p><p>It depends what you are looking for honestly “the latest things happening” is pretty vague. I’d say the place to look is probably just the blogs of OpenAI/Anthropic/Genini, since they are the only teams with inside information and novel findings to report. Everyone else is just using the tools we are given.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257629"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256529"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256529" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256529&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>The best place for the latest information isn't tech blogs in my opinion. It's the stable diffusion and local llama subreddits. If you are looking to learn about everything on a fundamental level you need to check out Andrej Karpathy on YouTube. There other some other notable mentions in other people's comments.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257251"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257251" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257251&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>New short course on FreeCodeCamp YouTube channel looks good -</p><p>Ollama Course – Build AI Apps Locally
<a href="https://youtu.be/GWB9ApTPTv4?feature=shared" rel="nofollow">https://youtu.be/GWB9ApTPTv4?feature=shared</a></p><p>As an aside, does anyone have any ideas about this: there should be an app like an 'auto-RAG' that scrapes RSS feeds and URLs, in addition to ingesting docs, text and content in the normal RAG way. Then you could build AI chat-enabled knowledge resources around specific subjects. Autogenerated summaries and dashboards would provide useful overviews.</p><p>Perhaps this already exists?</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257429"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257429" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257429&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>&lt;&lt; there should be an app like an 'auto-RAG' that scrapes RSS feeds and URLs,</p><p>I am not aware if that exists yet, but the challenge I see with it is rather simple: you get overwhelmed with information really quickly. In other words, you would still need human somewhere in that process to review those scrapes and the quality of that varies widely. For example, even on HN it is not a given a link will be pure gold ( you still want to check if it fits your use case ).</p><p>That said, as ideas goes, it sounds like a fun weekend project.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42257174"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257385"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257385" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257385&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>My issue with YouTube channels that focus on AI news is that they’re heavily incentivized to give you a frequent stream of attention-grabbing news. Week-by-week updates aren’t that helpful. It’s easy to miss the bigger picture and there’s too much content to feel like a good use of time.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257668"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257668" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257668&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>I agree with this statement, most YouTube channels are incentivized to keep repeating the same trivial information like how to compose prompts etc</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="42257363"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257363" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257363&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>First thing you need to do is change your LinkedIn to “AI evangelist” then go to your boss and say I want triple the pay. Then let the chips fall where they may. Oh also rename all your GitHub or personal projects to have AI in the name. You don’t actually have to do much else.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257076"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257364"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256542"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256542" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256542&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Simon's blog is fragmented because it's, well, a blog. It would be hard to find a better source to "keep updated on things AI" though. He does do longer summary articles sometimes, but mostly he's keeping up with things in real time. The search and tagging systems on his blog work well, too. I suggest you stick his RSS feed in your feed reader, and follow along that way.</p><p>Swyx also has a lot of stuff keeping up to date at <a href="https://www.latent.space/" rel="nofollow">https://www.latent.space/</a>, including the Latent Space podcast, although tbh I haven't listened to more than one or two episodes.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257239"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42256966"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256621"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257255"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257255" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257255&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>daveshap quit ai right? got agi pilled/"oneshotted by ayahuasca" as the kids say</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257285"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257285" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257285&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>He was only gone for a few days, IIRC. At any rate, he's back publishing AI related content again, and it looks like all (?) of his old content is back on his YT channel.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                        <tr id="42257131"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256497"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256497" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256497&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>As I was building up my understanding/intuition for the internals of transformers + attention, I found 3Blue1Brown's series of videos (specifically on attention) to be super helpful.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256557"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42256670"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="42257544"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257544" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257544&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Sadly, you'll have to include 4chan /g/'s local models general, which, unfortunately, seems to have top AI researchers posting there (anonymously)</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42256540"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256469"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256628"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256628" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256628&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Reproduce nanogpt.</p><p>Then find a small dataset and see if you can start getting close to some of the reported benchmark numbers with similar architectures.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256666"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256666" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256666&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Build a tool on top of the LLM layer for a specific use case. That'll get you up to speed. You haven't missed much.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256810"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42256810" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42256810&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div>
                  <p>Exactly. Avoid intentionally throw-away effort and instead attempt to build something specific and practical. Learn by doing.</p>
              </div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42257393"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257393" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257393&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Lots of good suggestions here already. I'd start by adding one quick note though. "AI" is more than just LLM's. Sure, the "current, trendy, fashionable" thing is all LLM's, but the field as a whole is still much larger. I'd encourage you to not myopically focus on LLM's to exclusion. Depending on your existing background knowledge, there's a lot to be said for going out and getting a copy of <i>Artificial Intelligence: A Modern Approach</i> and reading through it. Likewise for something like <i>Hands-On Machine Learning with Scikit-Learn, Keras, and Tensorflow</i>.</p><p>Beyond that: there are some decent sub-reddits for keeping up with AI happenings, a lot of good Youtube channels (although a lot of the ones that talk about the "current, trendy" AI stuff tend to be a bit tabloid'ish), and even a couple of Facebook groups. You can also find good signal by choosing the right people to follow on Twitter/LinkedIn/Mastodon/Bluesky/etc.</p><p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/artificial/" rel="nofollow">https://www.reddit.com/r/artificial/</a></p><p><a href="https://reddit.com/r/machineLearning/" rel="nofollow">https://reddit.com/r/machineLearning/</a></p><p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/LLM/" rel="nofollow">https://www.reddit.com/r/LLM/</a></p><p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/agi" rel="nofollow">https://www.reddit.com/r/agi</a></p><p><a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/ollama/" rel="nofollow">https://www.reddit.com/r/ollama/</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@matthew_berman" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@matthew_berman</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@TheAiGrid" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@TheAiGrid</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@WesRoth" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@WesRoth</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@DaveShap" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@DaveShap</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/MachineLearningStreetTalk" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/c/MachineLearningStreetTalk</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@twimlai" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@twimlai</a></p><p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/@YannicKilcher" rel="nofollow">https://www.youtube.com/@YannicKilcher</a></p><p>And you can always go straight to "the source" and follow pre-prints showing up in arXiv.</p><p><a href="https://arxiv.org/corr" rel="nofollow">https://arxiv.org/corr</a></p><p>For tools to make it easier to track new releases, arXiv supports subscriptions to daily digest emails, and also has RSS feeds.</p><p><a href="https://info.arxiv.org/help/subscribe.html" rel="nofollow">https://info.arxiv.org/help/subscribe.html</a></p><p><a href="https://info.arxiv.org/help/rss.html" rel="nofollow">https://info.arxiv.org/help/rss.html</a></p><p>There are also some bots in the Fediverse that push out links to new arXiv papers.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256846"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256354"><td></td></tr>
                <tr id="42256806"><td></td></tr>
                  <tr id="42256482"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256774"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256565"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42257064"><td><table>  <tbody><tr>    <td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td>
      <center><a id="up_42257064" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=42257064&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D42256093"></a></center>    </td><td><br><div><p>Are you wanting to get into LLMs in particular or something else? I am a software engineer also trying to make headways into so-called "AI", but I have little interest in LLMs. For one, it's suffering from a major hype bubble right now. The second reason is that because of reason one, it has a huge amount of attention from people who study and work on this every day. It's not something I have the time commitment for to compete with that. Lastly, as mentioned, I have no interest in it and my understanding of them leads me to believe they have few interesting applications besides generating a huge amount of noise in society and dumping heat. The Internet, like blogs, articles, and even YouTube, are already being overrun by LLM-generated material that is effectively worthless. I'm not sure of the net positive for LLMs.</p><p>For me personally, I prefer to work backwards and then forwards. What I mean by that is that I want to understand the basics and fundamentals first. So, I'm, slowly, trying to bone up on my statistics, probability, and information theory and have targeted machine learning books that also take a fundamental approach. There's no end to books in this realm for neural networks, machine learning, etc., so it's hard to recommend beyond what I've just picked, and I'm just getting started anyway.</p><p>If you can get your employer to pay for it, MIT xPRO has courses on machine learning (<a href="https://xpro.mit.edu/programs/program-v1:xPRO+MLx/" rel="nofollow">https://xpro.mit.edu/programs/program-v1:xPRO+MLx/</a> and <a href="https://xpro.mit.edu/courses/course-v1:xPRO+GenAI/" rel="nofollow">https://xpro.mit.edu/courses/course-v1:xPRO+GenAI/</a>). These will likely give a pretty up to date overview of the technologies.</p></div></td></tr>
        </tbody></table></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256640"><td></td></tr>
            <tr id="42256722"><td></td></tr>
            </tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Raspberry Pi CM5 is a faster, drop-in upgrade (176 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/raspberry-pi-cm5-2-3x-faster-drop-upgrade-mostly</link>
            <guid>42254379</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 09:15:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/raspberry-pi-cm5-2-3x-faster-drop-upgrade-mostly">https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2024/raspberry-pi-cm5-2-3x-faster-drop-upgrade-mostly</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42254379">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cm5-angle.jpeg" alt="Raspberry Pi Compute Module 5"></p>

<p>The Raspberry Pi <a href="http://raspberrypi.com/products/compute-module-5/">Compute Module 5</a> is smaller than a credit card, and I already have it gaming in 4K with an eGPU, running a Kubernetes cluster, and I even upgraded my NEC Commercial display from a CM4 to CM5, just swapping the Compute Modules!</p>

<p>The Compute Module 4 was hard to get for <em>years</em>. It launched right after the COVID supply chain crisis, leading to insane scalper pricing.</p>

<p>It was so <em>useful</em>, though, that Raspberry Pi sold every unit they made, and they're inside <em>everything</em>: from <a href="https://youtu.be/cbm03jtWWL0?t=2851">commercial 3D printers</a>, to <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2022/tv-thats-not-necs-pi-powered-55-display">TVs</a>, to <a href="https://pipci.jeffgeerling.com/boards_cm/blikvm-pci-express-card.html">IP KVM cards</a>.</p>

<p>After <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lky4FSfbc1E">pre-announcing the CM5</a> earlier this year, the biggest question was, is it a drop-in replacement?</p>

<p>Yes. <em>For the most part.</em></p>

<p>I've been testing it in <em>tons</em> of Compute Module boards, and it's been awesome seeing a 2-3x speedup just dropping in the new module.</p>

<p>It boots up in seconds, it has USB 3 instead of USB 2, and it's compatible with PCIe Gen 3 instead of Gen 2. The CPU is 2-3x faster, RAM is <em>3-4x</em> faster, <em>WiFi</em>'s faster, storage is faster... It's basically a Pi 5, but without the plugs. Most CM4 cases and accessories still work with it, just there's a LOT more bandwidth.</p>

<p>The big advantage to a Compute Module versus a Pi 5 is modularity. And I published a video today going over a ton of use cases enabled by various Compute Module carrier boards. All the ones I've tested were built for the CM4, but the CM5 is an instant drop-in upgrade:</p>

<div>
<p><iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/X4blR5Ua3S0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>
</div>

<p>I won't cover the individual use cases in this blog post. Rather, I'll focus on CM5 benchmarking and my notes from using the hardware a few weeks.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/CM5-Pricing-Table.png" alt="CM5 Launch Pricing Table"></p>

<p>The second-most-asked question is how much it will cost. Put simply, the 8GB CM5 is roughly the same price as the 8GB CM4. The 4GB module is $5 more, and the 2GB module is $10 more. So the cheapest CM5 is now $45 instead of $35—they're dropping the 1GB option from the lineup this generation. For any specific pricing information, please consult the <a href="https://datasheets.raspberrypi.com/cm5/cm5-product-brief.pdf">CM5 Product Brief</a>.</p>

<h2>Performance</h2>

<p>Good news: you can expect almost all the same numbers as a Pi 5 with the same amount of RAM.</p>

<p>Raspberry Pi made some quality of life improvements for management, too:</p>

<ul>
<li>You can edit the EEPROM (e.g. to change the <code>BOOT_ORDER</code>) without needing another computer</li>
<li>Raspberry Pi maintains <a href="https://github.com/raspberrypi/pi-gen-micro">pi-gen-micro</a> to build smaller custom Pi OS installations</li>
</ul>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.001.boot_.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - Boot time"></p>

<p>Right off the bat, the most refreshing difference is it boots up about 4 seconds faster.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.002.hpl_.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - HPL Linpack FP64"></p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.003.hpl-efficiency.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - HPL Efficiency"></p>

<p>Once it's running, the CPU is almost 3x faster. And it's also about 1.5x more efficient, according to my High Performance Linpack tests.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.004.linux_.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - Linux compile"></p>

<p>And of course, I had to test recompiling the Linux kernel. The CM5 obliterates the CM4, it's more than 3x faster.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.005.x264-4k.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - x264 4K Transcode"></p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.006.x264-1080p.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - x264 1080p Transcode"></p>

<p>Video encoding is also about 3x faster. I tested x264 transcoding both at 4K and 1080p resolutions, using Phoronix. All these benchmarks are helped by the faster LPDDR4x RAM on the CM5, which I tested using tinymembench:</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.007.ram_.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - RAM speed"></p>

<p>But all these speedups consume more power, at least at full blast: the CM5 uses almost <em>twice</em> the power flat out. But at idle, the CM5 uses a tiny bit <em>less</em>: I measured 2.3 watts at the wall:</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.008.power_.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - Power consumption"></p>

<p>And if you're deciding on which CM5 to buy, more RAM is better, at least if you're looking for raw performance.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.009.hpl-cm5.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - HPL on various RAM capacities"></p>

<p>You can save some money with less RAM, but don't expect the performance numbers on a 2 gig model to match the 8 gig model.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/Benchmarks-CM5.010.igpu_.png" alt="CM5 Benchmark - iGPU GLMark2 V3D performance"></p>

<p>The built-in graphics are much faster, too. Just testing with GLMark I saw the score jump from about 750 to 1916. It's not nearly as fast as even an older graphics card, but any improvement is welcome, especially for things like 4K displays.</p>

<p>You might've noticed, there was a third module in most of these graphs, except that last one. That's <em>another</em> CM5, <a href="https://radxa.com/products/cm/cm5/">this one being made by Radxa</a>. It uses a Rockchip RK3588S2, which is a monster in its own right, beating the Pi on <em>almost</em> every benchmark, including efficiency.</p>

<p>The elephant in the room is all the Compute Module clones. Because of the Pi shortages, every SBC maker on the planet built their own Compute Module. Though... some work better than others. A lot are <em>faster</em> than the Pi, but pricing is fairly similar, when you compare RAM and relative performance.</p>

<p>The big difference between the Pi and all the others, though, is support. I've written how other SBCs <em>could</em> become Pi-killers—I mean the hardware is often there—but they lack <em>support</em>.</p>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/compute-module-5-clones.jpg" alt="Compute Module 5 and Clones"></p>

<p>One big part of that is the breadth of options for the Pi, which may or may not work on other Compute Modules. And if you want to try, you can expect to debug hardware and OS issues yourself. Like I couldn't get a valid GLMark score for the Radxa, because I couldn't get an OS image to boot and use the built-in Mali GPU in time for this post! It's often a frustrating experience.</p>

<p>I regularly test other Compute Modules, though, and I post <em>all</em> my test data and experiences in my <a href="https://github.com/geerlingguy/sbc-reviews">sbc-reviews GitHub repo</a>.</p>

<h2>Hardware - CM5 IO Board</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cm5-io-board.jpeg" alt="CM5 IO Board"></p>

<p>Along with the CM5, Raspberry Pi's selling an updated IO board, for $20, with a few helpful changes. First, a power button, with the same behavior as the Pi 5. This would've saved <em>so</em> much time debugging graphics cards on the CM4.</p>

<p>Then, there's a new tiny fan header, the same one on the Raspberry Pi 5. Companies like EDAtec already have active coolers for the CM5, and I'll test some cooling options on my my 2nd channel, Level2Jeff.</p>

<p>On the port side, they got rid of the 12 volt barrel jack for power, and now they just use USB-C. They dropped down to two multipurpose Camera/Display ports. Each one has 4 lanes of MIPI bandwidth, just like the Pi 5.</p>

<p>There are still two full-size HDMI ports, an Ethernet port, and two USB type-A ports, but these are upgraded to USB 3. There's a microSD card that only works on Lite Compute Modules without eMMC, and finally an M.2 slot, with a little LED that blinks when you're using an SSD.</p>

<p>This is nice, because probably 99% of people buying these things would plug in storage. On the CM4, you had to use an awkward adapter card, but that's not required anymore.</p>

<p>Maybe we could see this on the Pi 5 someday? Or if not, maybe we could hack it using the Compute Module! That's foreshadowing...</p>

<h2>Hardware - CM5</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cm5-memory-emmc-silkscreen.jpeg" alt="CM5 Silkscreen - RAM and eMMC options"></p>

<p>The feature that'll make the biggest impact for <em>me</em>, since I use a lotta compute modules, is this new silkscreen up in the top corner. It has resistors for the RAM and storage sizes, so the specs are right up top.</p>

<p>The major changes from the CM4 include:</p>

<ul>
<li>BCM2712 D0 stepping SoC, with 4x Cortex A76 CPU cores at 2.4 GHz</li>
<li>RP1 chip for IO expansion (GPIO, MIPI Camera/Display, 2x USB 3.0 bus, Ethernet)</li>
<li>eMMC storage is moved to the bottom of the Compute Module</li>
<li>The Wireless chip has been raised up onto a short PCB mezzanine (I believe it can be had separately now, for system integrators, maybe?)</li>
<li>The RAM is now an LPDDR4x RAM module, sporting much higher speeds (and on-chip ECC)</li>
<li>The Pi 5 PMIC is included on the CM5 board, for USB-C PD negotation or direct 5V input like on the Pi 5</li>
</ul>

<p>Other things are familiar, like the switchable PCB antenna / u.fl connector, the 2x 200-pin hirose board to board connections, and the Broadcom BCM54210PE (which <a href="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/blog/2022/ptp-and-ieee-1588-hardware-timestamping-on-raspberry-pi-cm4">enables hardware PTP timestamping support</a>).</p>

<p>I've been testing the CM5 on various carrier boards, even with eGPUs and 10 Gbps NICs on the official IO Board, and all that testing can be seen in <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=l819Nnj5PNc">my YouTube video on the CM5</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p><img width="700" height="auto" src="https://www.jeffgeerling.com/sites/default/files/images/cm5-compute-blade.jpeg" alt="CM5 in Compute Blade"></p>

<p>But tying up the CM5, Raspberry Pi kept the price the same for the 8 gig model; those start at $75 for the Lite version. For 4 gig, they're going up five bucks, and for 2 gig, it's up 10 bucks, from $35 to $45.</p>

<p>They're dropping the 1 gig model from the lineup, and in reality, a lotta applications choke with less than 2 gigs of RAM, so I'm not surprised.</p>

<p>When the Compute Module 4 came out, it changed <em>literally</em> everything about the Compute Module. Including the form factor. That meant everything built for the CM1 and CM3 had to be redesigned, and it made many hardware developers angry.</p>

<p>Luckily, this time they kept the form factor, meaning for <em>most</em> things, it's a drop-in upgrade, where you get 2-3x faster performance, and at least for the larger models, the same price.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: App that asks 'why?' every time you unlock your phone (489 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.actureunlock&amp;hl=en_US</link>
            <guid>42254156</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 08:34:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.actureunlock&#x26;hl=en_US">https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.actureunlock&#x26;hl=en_US</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42254156">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-g-id="description"><p>Intenty helps you build a healthier relationship with your phone through gentle awareness prompts that appear right when you need them – at unlock. No blockers, no limits, just mindful choices.</p><p>🎯 Thoughtful nudges<br>Choose from carefully crafted default nudges or create your own:</p><p>* Intention - Set clear purposes for each phone session<br>* Necessity - Question if you really need to use your phone now<br>* Grounding - Return to the present moment<br>* Posture - Remember your physical wellbeing<br>* Minimalism - Stay focused on what truly matters</p><p>✨ Smart customisation</p><p>* Create personal nudges with your own prompts<br>* Control how often nudges appear with intensity settings<br>* Set cooldown periods to prevent prompt fatigue<br>* Export your data for personal insights</p><p>🎨 Minimalist design</p><p>* Clean, distraction-free interface<br>* Full-screen prompts for maximum impact<br>* Thoughtfully crafted user experience</p><p>🛡️ Privacy first</p><p>* Works 100% locally<br>* No ads or tracking<br>* No metrics or analytics collection<br>* Your phone, your data, your control</p><p>💡 Why it works<br>Instead of blocking apps or setting arbitrary limits, Intenty helps you build awareness naturally. Each unlock becomes an opportunity to check in with yourself, making mindful decisions about your phone use throughout the day. Perfect for anyone looking to check their phone less and use their phone more mindfully.</p><p>🌟 Who it's for<br>Perfect for anyone who wants to:</p><p>* Reduce mindless phone-checking<br>* Stay present and focused<br>* Build better digital habits<br>* Maintain productivity without restrictive blocks</p><p>Would you be ready to transform your relationship with your phone? Download Intenty today and make every unlock count.</p><p>🔐 Note on Intenty permissions usage: </p><p>Intenty might use quite permissive Android capabilities such as Display over other apps, Battery optimization disablement, or Accessibility service. All permissions are used exclusively for features to work locally on your device.</p><p>Accessibility service is used exclusively to let you quickly turn off your phone's screen with a Lock button. The service is optional, disabled by default, and does not collect nor share any data.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Wrote "Janet for Mortals" (193 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-for-mortals/</link>
            <guid>42253241</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 05:34:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-for-mortals/">https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-for-mortals/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42253241">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<div><p>I wrote a book.</p>
<p>It’s called <a href="https://janet.guide/"><em>Janet for Mortals</em></a>, and it’s free, and it’s on the internet, and you can read it right now.</p>
<p>And you <em>should</em> read it right now, instead of reading this blog post, because this blog post is not very interesting if you haven’t read the book. Heck, this blog post is not very interesting even if you <em>have</em> read the book. This blog post is a thinly-veiled promotion for my book to slip into my newsletter and RSS feed, with just enough additional content to pad it out to the length of a real post.</p>
<p>The book is about <a href="https://janet-lang.org/">Janet</a>, a programming language that <a href="https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-game/">I have written about before</a>. I’ve been using Janet a lot lately, and I’ve been having a lot of fun with it, and I think that more people should know about it so that they can have fun with it too. People like you.</p>
<p>I’m not really going to talk much about <em>why</em> you should read the book, or even why you should care about Janet in the first place – that will come in a later post. Instead, this is going to be a short retrospective of what it was like to write my first technical book.</p>
<hr>
<p>We’ll start with some numbers.</p>
<p>It took me twenty weeks to write the book, working in my spare time. I had originally estimated twelve weeks, which turned out to be a really good guess for how long I spent <em>writing</em> the book, but I didn’t account for how much time I would spend working on book-adjacent coding side quests.</p>
<p>The final book is pretty short: 44k words of English prose, if you don’t count any of the code snippets. I tried to find an example of a famous book with a similar word count to put that number in perspective, and the best I can do is <em>The Great Gatsby</em>, which clocks in at 47k words. It’s right on the border between novella- and novel-length, but it’s less than half as long as <a href="https://ianthehenry.com/posts/how-to-learn-nix/">my series of posts about Nix</a>, which is sort of terrifying.</p>
<p>But writing English words was only a fraction of the work. Over the course of those five months, I also spent a lot of time on:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://janet.guide/">the website itself</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ianthehenry/jimmy"><code>jimmy</code></a>, bindings to a C++ library of persistent data structures</li>
<li><a href="https://toodle.studio/">Toodle.Studio</a>, an interactive turtle graphics playground</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ianthehenry/cmd"><code>cmd</code></a>, a command-line argument parsing library</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ianthehenry/judge"><code>judge</code></a>, an inline snapshot testing framework</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ianthehenry/to-do"><code>to do</code></a>, a command-line todo list manager</li>
</ul>
<p>These things are not very interesting by themselves, but this blog post just exists to promote the book, so I’m going to reflect on them now. You are welcome to stop reading at any point and <a href="https://janet.guide/">go read the actual book instead</a>.</p>
<h2 id="the-website-2-weeks">The Website (2 weeks)</h2>
<p>The most interesting thing about <em>Janet for Mortals</em> is that it has a built-in repl. At any point you can press escape and pull it up, and it’s docked to the bottom of the page, just out of the way of the text. I’m sure that it’s not the first programming book to include a repl like this, but I’ve never actually seen it done before.</p>
<p>The editor portion of the repl is <a href="https://codemirror.net/">CodeMirror</a>, which I had used previously in <a href="https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-for-mortals/bauble.studio/">Bauble</a>. CodeMirror doesn’t know anything about Janet out of the box, but I had already implemented some basic <a href="https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-for-mortals/github.com/ianthehenry/codemirror-lang-janet">language support</a> when I wrote Bauble.</p>
<p>But I skipped a lot of the Janet language when I was writing the grammar for Bauble, like <code>``multi`backtick`quoted``</code> strings, because they didn’t really matter in Bauble’s constrained DSL. But they mattered for the book, so I had to spend time figuring out how to implement them.</p>
<p>But fleshing out the CodeMirror grammar (or more precisely, the <a href="https://lezer.codemirror.net/docs/guide/">Lezer</a> grammar that CodeMirror uses) had an unexpected side effect: it let me re-use the grammar to do syntax highlighting for the code snippets in the book itself.</p>
<p><em>Janet for Mortals</em> is just a static site, but no static site generators that I know of know how to highlight Janet code. For a long time the book was entirely black-and-white, which I don’t mind, but I knew I needed to add some color before I released it upon an unsuspecting public – I think Janet’s syntax is pretty unfamiliar to most people reading the book, and anything to make it look friendlier helps.</p>
<p>So I knew that I’d have to roll my own syntax highlighter of some kind, and I ended up just writing a simple static site generator in <a href="https://github.com/apenwarr/redo"><code>redo</code></a>, which was not a very good fit, but… well, least bad choice that I know of. The meat of the generator is written in JavaScript, so that I could plug in the Lezer grammar for free, but it’s all tied together by a fragile web of shell.</p>
<p>I used <a href="https://github.com/remarkjs/remark">Remark</a> to implement the parsing of the book’s source, and it was nice how much control I had over the generated output. I even added a simple extension to label code blocks, which was pretty easy.</p>
<p>I also re-used Remark in the client itself, as part of the repl. The docstrings in the Janet standard library are written in Markdown, and I’m actually parsing and rendering them to HTML on the fly as part of the repl autocomplete.</p>
<p>I spent a long time getting the repl autocomplete working well – because this book was written for newcomers to the Janet language, I thought that the help-as-you-type would be really useful for people trying to follow along in the repl.</p>
<p>Autocomplete works by dynamically querying the Janet environment via WebAssembly at repl startup. This means if you define a new symbol with a docstring, it won’t actually appear in the autocomplete output, but I think that’s… fine. I could re-generate the autocompletions after every command is run, but… I don’t think there’s much value in that.</p>
<p>The most interesting part of the repl is probably the <code>(report)</code> function, which takes a string and POSTs it to a simple web server that sticks it into a SQLite database for me to peruse later. It’s not really any different than a comment box, but I feel like there’s something fun about doing it from the repl. I’m really glad that I added it – it’s been fun reading people’s feedback, and I’ve fixed quite a few errors because of it. I’m sad that I didn’t implement any way to respond, though!</p>
<p>The backend for reports is <em>not</em> written in Janet; it’s a tiny Haskell application that just listens for POST requests and sticks them into a SQLite database.</p>
<p>There are people using Janet to make websites, but I am not one of them: the primary thing I want out of a web server is security, and I just don’t think Janet or its HTTP libraries are “battle-tested” enough for me to connect them to the internet.</p>
<p>I also just think the idea of using a dynamically-typed interpreted language to build a web service is crazy, when there are optimizing compilers <em>right there</em>, but that’s a whole other conversation.</p>
<h2 id="jimmy-1-week"><code>jimmy</code> (1 week)</h2>
<p>I spent a little bit of time writing bindings to <a href="https://github.com/arximboldi/immer">immer</a>, a library of persistent data structures. I never finished them, and probably won’t, at least not until I have a use for them. But as a demonstration of how to interop with C++ code from Janet, I think it was successful.</p>
<h2 id="httpstoodlestudio-2-weeks"><a href="https://toodle.studio/">https://toodle.studio</a> (2 weeks)</h2>
<p>Last year I wrote a little art playground called <a href="https://bauble.studio/">Bauble</a>. It was my first time embedding Janet in the browser, and I had a pretty tough time figuring out how to do that.</p>
<p>There weren’t a lot of resources back then about embedding Janet <em>period</em>, and doing it in the browser added an extra layer of difficulty. I’d never used WebAssembly or Emscripten before, or even TypeScript, and it turns out there are no tutorials on how to write TypeScript Emscripten WebAssembly Janet bindings, so I spent a while figuring out how all the pieces worked together.</p>
<p>And I’m glad I did, because I think the final product is really neat: it’s a website that is <em>not written in JavaScript</em>. I mean, a lot of it is. The UI is, still. But the actual application logic is all Janet.</p>
<p>I thought that that was a really useful superpower of Janet, and I wanted to make the technique more accessible. In fact this was a big motivation for writing this book about Janet – I wanted people to know that this was <em>possible</em> in the first place, and I wanted to make it easier to get started with it.</p>
<p>But <em>Janet for Mortals</em> doesn’t talk about Bauble at all. Bauble is actually not very interesting from an interop perspective: Bauble is completely stateless, and basically uses Janet to implement a pure function from strings to strings (they’re… pretty complicated strings; Bauble is a Janet-to-GLSL compiler, but they are strings nonetheless). I didn’t think it was a very good showcase for everything you can do with Janet, so I briefly considered talking about how I implemented the repl in the book, but I decided that that was far too boring. So I wrote <a href="https://toodle.studio/">Toodle.Studio</a> – an obvious fork of Bauble – instead.</p>
<p>Toodle.Studio <em>seems</em> a lot simpler than Bauble, but the interop with JavaScript is much more involved. Toodle.Studio has to execute long-running Janet programs asynchronously over time. It has to think about memory management, as the JavaScript code retains multiple references to the same Janet values. It has to pass complex nested data structures to and from Janet, going through C++ as an intermediary. It does a very simple version of all of these things, but it’s a pretty good showcase for the techniques.</p>
<p>But the most interesting part of Toodle.Studio isn’t the interop or the memory management. The most interesting part of Toodle.Studio is the logo.</p>
<p>I wasn’t really planning on making a logo – this is a demo project for a book, after all – but sadly I had no choice. When I was getting ready to release the website, I showed it to my partner, because it’s rare that I work on something comprehensible to normal human beings. I thought she’d like it, but she was <em>aghast</em>.</p>
<p>“You said you were working on turtle graphics,” she said. “Where are the turtles?”</p>
<p>I tried to explain that the turtles aren’t <em>really</em> turtles, that it’s like a flea circus, and the turtles are metaphors – but she was having none of it. The lack of turtles was a base betrayal, so I had to spend a day or so <a href="https://gist.github.com/ianthehenry/612c980f0db04ea3c2ccab2741475870">modeling a cute animated turtle in Bauble</a> to act as the logo. And making its eyes follow the mouse, of course.</p>
<p>Relationship repaired. The logo wound up being my favorite part of the site, and it was fun to get a chance to use Bauble to make something “real.”</p>
<h2 id="cmd-2-weeks"><code>cmd</code> (2 weeks)</h2>
<p>One of the things that I spent the most time on, oddly enough, was a command-line argument parsing library. The library itself only gets, like, three paragraphs of screen time in the book, but it was very important to me that it exist before the book came out, so that I could unambiguously claim that “Janet is an excellent scripting language.” Before <code>cmd</code>, that was still true, but the phrasing was more “Janet is a great choice for scripting and writing CLI tools, except that the argument parsing is kind of janky, sorry, but hey at least it’s better than Bash.”</p>
<p><code>cmd</code> was heavily inspired by <a href="https://ocaml.org/p/core/latest/doc/Core/Command/Param/index.html"><code>Core.Command</code></a>, which is the best command-line argument parsing library that I have ever used. I’m extremely spoiled by how easy it makes writing CLIs, and I wanted to replicate that experience in Janet. <code>cmd</code> is definitely not as good as <code>Core.Command</code> – types, my goodness, types make everything so much easier – but it has 95% of the features I care about, and the concise notation makes it more pleasant to use in ad-hoc scripts.</p>
<p>One thing that I miss, though, is that <code>Core.Command</code> autogenerates Bash completion functions. I want to add that to <code>cmd</code> one day – the API is designed so that that will be <em>possible</em> to do. But… so many projects, so little time.</p>
<h2 id="judge-1-week"><code>judge</code> (1 week)</h2>
<p><code>judge</code> was <a href="https://ianthehenry.com/posts/janet-game/judging-janet/">one of the first things that I wrote in Janet</a>, all the way back in 2021. I think that it worked pretty well considering that I didn’t know anything about Janet when I wrote it, but now I do, so I rewrote it from scratch. Not only is the API much nicer to use now, but the implementation is way simpler – and easier to make changes to.</p>
<p>The main differences between Judge v1 and Judge v2 are that tests can now appear inside regular source files, not just the <code>test/</code> directory, and I added the <code>test-macro</code> and <code>test-stdout</code> helpers, which are <em>extremely</em> useful. <a href="https://blog.janestreet.com/the-joy-of-expect-tests/">The OCaml equivalent of <code>test-stdout</code></a> is pretty much the only way that I write tests professionally, because OCaml doesn’t really have a way to embed arbitrary data in source code, so we turn everything into a string.</p>
<p>After publishing the book – which <a href="https://janet.guide/testing-and-debugging/">has a whole chapter on testing with Judge</a> – I had a chance to spend a little more time improving Judge, and I finally added an <code>--interactive</code> mode, which I’ve been wanting for a long time. And since I’m not spending all my time working on this book anymore, I’ve actually had a few opportunities to <em>use</em> the new Judge, and I gotta say: it’s nice. It’s really nice. I know I can’t impress upon you just how nice it is in this post – it really needs a demo, and I’m too lazy to record one right now – but I’m very happy with how it feels to use it to write Janet.</p>
<h2 id="to-do-2-hours"><code>to do</code> (2 hours)</h2>
<p>I picked this project to highlight for <a href="https://janet.guide/scripting/">the scripting chapter</a>, because it’s a non-trivial thing that I had done in Bash before, and actually found it pretty painful. Parsing multi-line text with Sed is not fun, and trying to do date manipulation with <code>date</code> in a way that works the same on macOS and Linux is… basically impossible, as far as I can tell. I quickly ran into the limits of my patience, and gave up on the idea some years ago.</p>
<p>It was really fun to return to this with the full power of PEGs and <a href="https://github.com/andrewchambers/janet-sh"><code>sh</code></a> and <a href="https://github.com/ianthehenry/cmd"><code>cmd</code></a> at my disposal. I immediately surpassed all of features of my original Bash todo list, and was able to add quite a few more (like <code>fzf</code> multi-select – good luck constructing null-terminated strings in Bash).</p>
<p>The book covers a very simplified version of the app – it can’t schedule tasks for the future, and there’s no concept of “skipping” tasks. Those features are important for <em>my</em> todo list workflow, but they are probably not important for <em>your</em> todo list workflow, so the book only discusses the core functionality of adding things to a list and crossing them off. I think that it makes a good starting point to run with and make your own – paired with <a href="https://github.com/ianthehenry/zsh-autoquoter"><code>zsh-autoquoter</code></a>, it’s actually a surprisingly useful app!</p>
<hr>
<p>If you put all of these projects together, I was writing code for almost half the time that I spent working on the book. Eight out of twenty weeks, plus some periods where I was doing both at once.</p>
<p>I didn’t really budget for that going into this. I thought that I’d improve Judge, and I thought that I’d write an argument parser. But I thought that writing an argument parser would be <em>way easier</em> than it actually was. And I thought that I’d just talk about Bauble – it never occurred to me that I’d write <em>another</em> art playground just because Bauble was <em>too easy</em>.</p>
<p>So that’s the story of writing the book. Or really, everything <em>but</em> writing the book. All the other things. The writing itself isn’t that interesting. I wrote it in Markdown, in Sublime Text, which is my favorite editor for writing long-form prose. I have nothing interesting to say about that part.</p>
<p>Two new versions of Janet came out while I was writing the book, and I did have to go back and update the chapters on debugging and native modules to keep up with changes to the language. I plan on keeping the book up to date with the latest Janet release – we’ll see how long I can keep that up.</p>
<hr>
<p>I haven’t done much to promote the book yet. I <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=35386405">submitted it to Hacker News</a>, and I <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/duwkz7">submitted it to Lobsters</a>, and I wrote <a href="https://twitter.com/ianthehenry/status/1641797578739306499">a very half-hearted tweet about it</a>. The reception was pretty much as good as I could have hoped for: it was on the Hacker News front page all day, and even held the number one spot for a while.</p>
<p>What does that actually mean? Well, according my Nginx access logs, I got:</p>
<ul>
<li>30,025 unique visitors on Friday</li>
<li>9,568 unique visitors on Saturday</li>
<li>3,777 unique visitors on Sunday</li>
</ul>
<p>Those numbers don’t mean very much, though. Those are just people who clicked on a link – the number of people who actually <em>read</em> the book is much, much smaller.</p>
<p>I don’t actually know how much smaller exactly, because I don’t have any client-side behavior-tracking analytics on the site. But I can sort of try to guess, by looking at my access logs. It seems like retention is not great:</p>
<ul>
<li>Chapter One had 22% as many visitors as the home page.</li>
<li>Chapter Two had 20% as many visitors as Chapter One.</li>
<li>Chapter Three had 69% as many visitors as Chapter Two.</li>
<li>Chapters Four and Nine, “<a href="https://janet.guide/pegular-expressions/">Pegular Expressions</a>” and “<a href="https://janet.guide/xenofunctions/">Xenofunctions</a>,” had more visitors than Chapter Three.</li>
</ul>
<p>I’m guessing that last bit is because people clicked on those chapters to see what they were about, which just goes to show that unique visitor count is not a very dependable metric.</p>
<p>My best attempt at answering the question “how many people are actually reading the book” is 387, as of the end of the launch weekend. So far 387 unique IP addresses have loaded five or more distinct chapters, which is probably a decent proxy for the metric I care about.</p>
<p>I really had no expectations for what these numbers would be before I launched the book. It’s a big time commitment to read a weird book about a programming language you’ve barely heard of, and 387 seems simultaneously low (compared to, say, any blog post) and high (I don’t think <em>I’ve</em> ever read a book off a HN link). But it’s more than zero!</p>
<p>Alright, I think that’s enough. I’ll close with some fun facts:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>The Janet language is named after an immortal being in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Good_Place"><em>The Good Place</em></a> who helps mortals navigate the afterlife, hence the title.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The chapter with the fewest visits is currently “Testing and Debugging,” despite being the third-to-last chapter. This does not surprise me at all, but I think it’s a shame: the last three chapters are by far the most interesting in the book, and the style of testing described in that chapter is one of the biggest productivity upgrades that I have personally experienced in my engineering career.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>So far I’ve received 494 reports from the built-in repl reporting feature. Most of these were of the “hey nice book” or “testing” variety, but I’ve gotten several dozen typo reports, clarification requests, or otherwise useful comments through it as well.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>The most interesting report was just “you should listen to this song: <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=46i3LbIbbhI">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=46i3LbIbbhI</a>.” No context, no explanation, and I have no way to reply for clarification. But… thanks! It’s a good song. I’m into it.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>A few people asked me questions without including any kind of contact info, so I have no way to answer them. I hope that they found peace, wherever they are. I’m not ignoring you. I just… I only implemented an extremely primitive one-way feedback function.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>I’m going to plug the book one last time.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>With feeling: <em><a href="https://janet.guide/">Janet for Mortals</a>!</em> Out now! The first infinity visitors get their copy for free!</p></div>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The capacitor that Apple soldered incorrectly at the factory (376 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2024/11/the-capacitor-that-apple-soldered-incorrectly-at-the-factory/</link>
            <guid>42253119</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 05:10:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2024/11/the-capacitor-that-apple-soldered-incorrectly-at-the-factory/">https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/2024/11/the-capacitor-that-apple-soldered-incorrectly-at-the-factory/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42253119">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				
<p>There have been <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/lciii-recap-apple-design-fault-47uf-reversed.27834/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">some past rumblings</a> on the internet <a href="https://tinkerdifferent.com/threads/lciii-c22-polarity.2708/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">about a capacitor being installed backwards</a> in Apple’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Macintosh_LC_III" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Macintosh LC III</a>. The LC III was a “pizza box” Mac model produced from early 1993 to early 1994, mainly targeted at the education market. It also manifested as various consumer Performa models: the 450, 460, 466, and 467. Clearly, Apple never initiated a huge recall of the LC III, so I think there is some skepticism in the community about this whole issue. Let’s look at the situation in more detail and understand the circuit. Did Apple actually make a mistake?</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/performa450.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="425" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/performa450-1024x425.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/performa450-1024x425.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/performa450-300x125.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/performa450-768x319.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/performa450.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>I participated in the discussion thread at the first link over a decade ago, but I never had a machine to look at with my own eyes until now. I recently bought a Performa 450 complete with its original leaky capacitors, and I have several other machines in the same form factor. Let’s check everything out!</p>



<p>Here’s the affected section of the board before I removed the original capacitors. You can see that all three of these caps (C19, C21, and C22) have their negative side pointing upward, matching the PCB silkscreen that has the + sign at the bottom.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/originalcaps.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="999" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/originalcaps-1024x999.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/originalcaps-1024x999.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/originalcaps-300x293.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/originalcaps-768x750.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/originalcaps.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>If the miscellaneous gunk and ugly appearance of the solder joints in this picture isn’t a warning sign that you should replace the SMD electrolytic capacitors in any classic Mac from the ’90s at this point, I don’t know what is! Let’s take a closer look at the circuit after I removed them and cleaned everything up a bit.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="1022" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved-1024x1022.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved-1024x1022.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved-300x300.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved-150x150.jpg 150w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved-768x767.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/capsremoved.jpg 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>Yikes, C21 leaked really badly and damaged the solder mask and the copper underneath. When I removed it, there was a big puddle of goo sitting there. I haven’t installed new capacitors on this board yet, but I’m probably going to need to scrape more of that dark crud from the copper and cover it all up with UV-curable solder mask. Luckily, it’s just the ground plane so it’s not a huge deal.</p>



<p>Anyway, the important thing to note in this picture is that the negative terminal of each capacitor goes to the ground plane. The positive terminals all head over to pins on the power supply connector.</p>



<p>What’s happening here is there is one bulk capacitor for each of the three power rails provided by the power supply. C19 is for +5V, C21 is for +12V, and C22 is for -5V. You can see the trace from C22’s positive terminal going directly to the -5V pin on the power supply connector.</p>



<p>This arrangement makes sense for the two positive power rails, but it’s backwards for the -5V rail. If the image above isn’t proof enough for you, here are a couple of pictures with my multimeter definitively showing that the positive terminal of C22 goes to -5V and the negative terminal goes to ground. That means when the system is powered on, there will be -5V across this capacitor.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter1.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="761" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter1-1024x761.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter1-1024x761.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter1-300x223.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter1-768x571.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter1.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter2.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="615" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter2-1024x615.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter2-1024x615.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter2-300x180.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter2-768x461.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/multimeter2.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>I really don’t need to do any additional analysis at this point in order to say that this is just plain wrong. You aren’t supposed to have a negative voltage across this type of capacitor. There’s a reason they have a marking that identifies the negative side. The voltage at the positive end should be greater than or equal to the voltage at the negative end. In other words, this capacitor’s positive end should have been connected to ground and the negative end should have been connected to -5V.</p>



<p>Let’s compare and contrast this circuit with the corresponding circuit on an original Mac LC, which uses the exact same power supply. This is another system with its original leaky caps:</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="931" height="1024" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps-931x1024.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps-931x1024.jpg 931w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps-273x300.jpg 273w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps-768x845.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps-1397x1536.jpg 1397w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lccaps.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 931px) 100vw, 931px"></a></figure>



<p>They installed it correctly on the original LC (and the LC II). -5V goes to the negative end of the capacitor, and ground goes to the positive end, resulting in a net voltage of positive 5 volts across it.</p>



<p>What about the LC 475, which is the successor to the LC III? If Apple miraculously discovered a special exception to the laws of physics during development of the LC III, I would expect them to have continued following this new rule with the design of the LC 475.</p>



<figure><a href="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lc475caps.jpg" target="_blank" rel=" noreferrer noopener"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="686" src="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lc475caps-1024x686.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lc475caps-1024x686.jpg 1024w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lc475caps-300x201.jpg 300w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lc475caps-768x515.jpg 768w, https://www.downtowndougbrown.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/lc475caps.jpg 1536w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>Nope! It’s back to the same (correct) orientation that was used on the original LC.</p>



<p>After seeing it myself and comparing the circuit with other Mac models of the era, I’m very confident that Apple made a boo-boo on the LC III. It’s not just a factory component placement issue; the PCB’s silkscreen is also incorrect. It’s basically the hardware equivalent of a copy/paste error when you’re writing code. I’m hoping to raise awareness of this mistake because all of the (very useful) recapping guide collections I’ve found on the Internet strangely fail to mention this reversed capacitor for some reason, even though it’s known to have caused problems for many people.</p>



<p>But, you may ask, why didn’t it matter with the original liquid-filled electrolytic capacitor fitted on the board? Why didn’t this cause a huge uproar back in the day? Why didn’t everyone’s LC III explode in a giant fireball? Well, for one, the original capacitor was obviously tolerant of this mistake. It was rated for 16V but only -5V was being put across it. According to what I’ve read online, that’s more than enough reverse voltage to permanently damage this type of capacitor, but it may not be enough to cause it to violently explode. Plus, it is only involved with the -5V rail, which is really only needed for the RS-422 serial ports. The capacitor might not have been doing its job properly if it was installed backwards, but it didn’t seem to really be hurting anything.</p>



<p>With the way that a lot of people in the hobby these days (including me) are using tantalum capacitors as replacements, I think it’s potentially dangerous that this backwards capacitor isn’t widely documented. Although the computer seems to work okay in this configuration with a normal electrolytic capacitor like what was installed by the factory, tantalum capacitors are not quite as forgiving when installed in reverse. <a href="https://retroviator.com/apple-macintosh-lc-iii/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Multiple people</a> online have observed that when they have a tantalum capacitor installed in the original incorrect orientation, they end up with an incorrect voltage on the -5V rail. The <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/lciii-recap-apple-design-fault-47uf-reversed.27834/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">original poster about this issue</a>, paul.gaastra, said that with the tantalum capacitor installed backwards it was drawing 1.3 amps (way too much) and the voltage was only -2.3V. At best, this is going to result in serial port problems. At worst, <a href="https://68kmla.org/bb/index.php?threads/lciii-recap-apple-design-fault-47uf-reversed.27834/page-2#post-525187" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">you’re asking for the capacitor to explode or catch on fire</a>. It’s probably not good for the power supply, either; it’s only rated for 75 mA on the -5V rail.</p>



<p>The bottom line is that Apple’s silkscreen markings and factory placement for C22 on the LC III are flat out wrong. There’s no other correct answer. Please, if you are recapping one of these machines, install C22 backwards from what the silkscreen on the PCB says. If you don’t believe me, or want to double check for yourself, you can easily verify this with a multimeter in continuity test mode with the system powered off. The positive end of the cap needs to be connected to ground, and the negative end needs to be connected to -5V. Using your multimeter’s DC voltage mode, if you power on the system, you should see 5V across the capacitor (negative probe to negative side of cap, positive probe to positive side of cap). That’s how it is on <em>every</em> other Mac with a -5V rail.</p>
			  
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenAI hits pause on video model Sora after artists leak access in protest (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/11/26/openai-sora-ai-video-model-artists-protest/</link>
            <guid>42252806</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 03:59:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/11/26/openai-sora-ai-video-model-artists-protest/">https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/11/26/openai-sora-ai-video-model-artists-protest/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42252806">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2024/11/26/openai-sora-ai-video-model-artists-protest/: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Didn't Need Kubernetes, and You Probably Don't Either (320 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://benhouston3d.com/blog/why-i-left-kubernetes-for-google-cloud-run</link>
            <guid>42252336</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 02:26:19 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://benhouston3d.com/blog/why-i-left-kubernetes-for-google-cloud-run">https://benhouston3d.com/blog/why-i-left-kubernetes-for-google-cloud-run</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42252336">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Kubernetes often represents the ultimate solution for container orchestration, but my experience has led me to leave it behind in favor of a simpler, cost-effective solution using <a href="https://cloud.google.com/run">Google Cloud Run</a>. This transition has made my infrastructure projects easier to manage, more scalable, and significantly cheaper. Here’s why I made this choice and how Cloud Run offers a better fit for my needs going forward.</p>
<h2>How I ended up on Kubernetes</h2>
<p>First, let's quickly look at how we ended up on Kubernetes. We has launched <a href="https://clara.io/">Clara.io (now sunset)</a>, an online 3D editor and rendering platform, in 2013. We cost optimized the platform by using bare metal machines from <a href="https://www.ovhcloud.com/">OVH</a> for both its primary servers, DBs and job workers. While it worked, bare metal machines were a source of potential failures and we did have some over the years. Luckily we had a redundant setup so our users never noticed. But it was a massive amount of work to provision, monitor and maintain.</p>
<p>So when we looked to remake the platform for <a href="https://threekit.com/">Threekit.com</a>, an enterprise focused re-imaging of Clara.io, we looked to switch to a managed compute setup. At the time in 2018, Kubernetes was just emerging as the industry solution as Azure, AWS and Docker converged on it in late 2017.</p>
<h2>Why I Left Kubernetes</h2>
<p>At first, Kubernetes seemed like the right approach for managing services at scale. But as we lived with it over the years since 2018, it became apparent that the complexity and costs were significant. Here’s a breakdown of the challenges we encountered:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<p><strong>Cost Overruns</strong>: Kubernetes comes with substantial infrastructure costs that go beyond DevOps and management time. The high cost arises from needing to provision a bare-bones cluster with redundant management nodes. Moreover, Kubernetes’s slow autoscaling meant I had to over-provision services to ensure availability, paying for unused resources rather than scaling based on demand.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Difficulty Managing Large Job Volumes</strong>: Handling a high volume of jobs on Kubernetes is tedious. Both the built-in scheduler and Argo introduced limitations and complexity, often failing to scale well under load or just being really complex.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><strong>Complexity Overload</strong>: Kubernetes is feature-rich, yet these “enterprise” capabilities turned even simple tasks into protracted processes. The result was added complexity without substantial benefits, making it more of an obstacle than a solution. If you have Kubernetes, you probably need at least one dedicated Kubernetes dev-ops engineer, if not a couple.</p>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Overall, Kubernetes proved difficult to provision, expensive to maintain, and time-consuming to manage. For companies or individual projects seeking simplicity and cost-effectiveness, it may not be the right choice. But it did get rid of the need for us to keep track of whether the hardware in our machines was breaking down and our manual provision processing.</p>
<h2>Embracing Cloud Run for a Simpler Setup</h2>
<p>Google Cloud Run offers a streamlined alternative to Kubernetes. Here’s how my new setup works:</p>
<h3>The Setup</h3>
<p>My infrastructure is now centered around <strong>Docker containers</strong>, with some running as auto-scaling services and others as tasks for long-running jobs. Google Cloud Run handles container deployment, scaling, downtime management, and running/retrying jobs eliminating many of the challenges I faced with Kubernetes.</p>
<h3>Why Cloud Run Is Ideal</h3>
<ol>
<li><strong>Cost Efficiency</strong>: Cloud Run charges only for the CPU and memory used during requests, making it highly cost-effective. For example, this personal project of mine, <a href="https://web3dsurvey.com/">Web3D Survey</a> sees 500,000 hits monthly and costs just <strong>$4/month</strong> for hosting, even though it is running all the time. They key is that Cloud Run charges based on the fraction of the CPU you use per second. The ability to scale to zero also means no charges for idle services.</li>
<li><strong>Fast, Reliable Autoscaling</strong>: Cloud Run scales in a few seconds, unlike Kubernetes, where scaling often took minutes. This quick scaling lets me handle surges reliably without over-provisioning.</li>
<li><strong>No Kubernetes Management Overhead</strong>: Cloud Run, built atop Google’s Borg, avoids the need for Kubernetes cluster management, simplifying deployments and cutting costs.</li>
<li><strong>Simple Async Tasks</strong>: Cloud Run Tasks allows me to execute up to 10,000 tasks per job, track their results with auto-retries with no need to manage job-running infrastructure or individual machines — a refreshing alternative to the complexity running this on Kubernetes was.</li>
</ol>
<h2>The Kubernetes Lock-In Trap</h2>
<p>One overlooked downside of Kubernetes is <strong>cluster lock-in</strong>. Once you start using Kubernetes-specific features, it becomes challenging to leverage resources outside the cluster. Integrating services across data centers or using dedicated resources in a colocation setup adds significant complexity. Kubernetes demands you stay within its ecosystem, effectively binding you to the infrastructure that supports it, making even simple expansions or migrations into costly, complex endeavors.</p>
<h2>Addressing Common Concerns</h2>
<p>Several questions arose from others when I shared my experience online, so here’s a deeper look into how this setup works:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Orchestration</strong>: I use GitHub Actions CI to handle CI/CD, leveraging workflows with dependencies and matrix strategies for builds across multiple services which only deploy if all tests/builds are successful.</li>
<li><strong>Storage</strong>: Managed databases or Cloud Storage cover shared data needs, eliminating the need to manage my own disks.</li>
<li><strong>Inter-Service Communication</strong>: For async communication, I leverage pub-sub messaging. When direct connections are absolutely necessary, each service has a dedicated domain-name.</li>
<li><strong>Security</strong>: Cloud Run supports internal-only services, and for public services, I secure routes using JWT.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Debunking Misconceptions</h2>
<h3>“Aren’t You Afraid of Being Locked into GCP?”</h3>
<p>Switching cloud providers, such as AWS, wouldn’t be overly complex since my setup is Docker-based, and migration would take about a week. In practice, few companies switch providers unless politics are involved, as the differences between major cloud services are minimal.</p>
<h3>“Cloud Run Is Just Managed Kubernetes, Right?”</h3>
<p>While Cloud Run uses Knative interfaces, it’s not a Kubernetes PaaS. Cloud Run runs on Google’s Borg, avoiding Kubernetes cluster overhead and allowing for simpler, cost-effective deployments. Even if it was based on Kubernetes underneath it hides the completely complexities, and cost of Kubernetes.</p>
<h2>Remaining Workflow Pains</h2>
<p>There are some pains I have with my current Cloud Run development workflow:</p>
<h3>Arbitrary Management of Services Names</h3>
<p>I do find that I need to manage my service names both locally and in the server in a unified way with clear configuration. Basically an abstraction layer. I know Kubernetes has one and I do miss that.</p>
<h3>Lack of Cloud Run Task Emulation</h3>
<p>There is no solution for running Cloud Run Tasks locally that I have found. I would like it to be able to just run an arbitrary command line locally in place of a docker container in a locally emulated Cloud Run Tasks environment that captures log output, trackings runs, etc. This would simplify development of tasks without having to build and deploy docker containers.</p>
<h2>My New Stack and Workflow</h2>
<p>My infrastructure is built around a reliable stack. You can view a simplistic prototype setup and practices in this <a href="https://github.com/bhouston/template-typescript-monorepo">TypeScript monorepo template</a>. Cloud Run enables me to deploy this stack efficiently, without the complexity or cost overheads Kubernetes brought.</p>
<h2>Final Thoughts</h2>
<p>For my projects, Cloud Run offers the perfect blend of <strong>cost savings, speed, scalability, and simplicity</strong>. While Kubernetes may suit some large enterprises, for agile projects where simplicity and efficiency matter, the managed environment of Cloud Run is transformative. If your infrastructure goals include reduced DevOps overhead, predictable costs, and responsive scaling, Cloud Run may be the solution you’ve been looking for.</p>
<p>(PS. Yes, I am sure there was another library/extension I should have added to Kubernetes to enable feature X, Y or Z, but this really is just further increasing the complexity. I don't want to have to exist inside of world of Kubernetes-specific lingo and techniques if they are not giving me benefits.)</p>
<p><em>This post was inspired by <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42041917">this discussion on Hacker News on 04/11/2025</a></em></p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Htmy – Async, pure-Python rendering engine (122 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://volfpeter.github.io/htmy/</link>
            <guid>42251919</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 01:10:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://volfpeter.github.io/htmy/">https://volfpeter.github.io/htmy/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42251919">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-md-component="container">
      
      
        
          
        
      
      <main data-md-component="main">
        <div data-md-component="content">
              <article>
                
                  

  
  


<p><img alt="Tests" src="https://github.com/volfpeter/htmy/actions/workflows/tests.yml/badge.svg">
<img alt="Linters" src="https://github.com/volfpeter/htmy/actions/workflows/linters.yml/badge.svg">
<img alt="Documentation" src="https://github.com/volfpeter/htmy/actions/workflows/build-docs.yml/badge.svg">
<img alt="PyPI package" src="https://img.shields.io/pypi/v/htmy?color=%2334D058&amp;label=PyPI%20Package"></p>
<p><strong>Source code</strong>: <a href="https://github.com/volfpeter/htmy">https://github.com/volfpeter/htmy</a></p>
<p><strong>Documentation and examples</strong>: <a href="https://volfpeter.github.io/htmy/">https://volfpeter.github.io/htmy</a></p>

<p><strong>Async</strong>, <strong>pure-Python</strong> rendering engine.</p>
<h2 id="key-features">Key features</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Async</strong>-first, to let you make the best use of <a href="https://github.com/timofurrer/awesome-asyncio">modern async tools</a>.</li>
<li><strong>Powerful</strong>, React-like <strong>context support</strong>, so you can avoid prop-drilling.</li>
<li>Sync and async <strong>function components</strong> with <strong>decorator syntax</strong>.</li>
<li>All baseline <strong>HTML</strong> tags built-in.</li>
<li><strong>Markdown</strong> support with tools for customization.</li>
<li>Async, JSON based <strong>internationalization</strong>.</li>
<li>Built-in, easy to use <code>ErrorBoundary</code> component for graceful error handling.</li>
<li><strong>Unopinionated</strong>: use the backend, CSS, and JS frameworks of your choice, the way you want to use them.</li>
<li>Everything is <strong>easily customizable</strong>, from the rendering engine to components, formatting and context management.</li>
<li>Automatic and customizable <strong>property-name conversion</strong> from snake case to kebab case.</li>
<li><strong>Fully-typed</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="installation">Installation</h2>
<p>The package is available on PyPI and can be installed with:</p>

<h2 id="concepts">Concepts</h2>
<p>The entire library -- from the rendering engine itself to the built-in components -- is built around a few simple protocols and a handful of simple utility classes. This means that you can easily customize, extend, or replace basically everything in the library. Yes, even the rendering engine. The remaining parts will keep working as expected.</p>
<p>Also, the library doesn't rely on advanced Python features such as metaclasses or descriptors. There are also no complex base classes and the like. Even a junior engineer could understand, develop, and debug an application that's built with <code>htmy</code>.</p>
<h3 id="components">Components</h3>
<p>Every class with a sync or async <code>htmy(context: Context) -&gt; Component</code> method is an <code>htmy</code> component (technically an <code>HTMYComponentType</code>). Strings are also components, as well as lists or tuples of <code>HTMYComponentType</code> or string objects.</p>
<p>Using this method name enables the conversion of any of your business objects (from <code>TypedDicts</code>s or <code>pydantic</code> models to ORM classes) into components without the fear of name collision with other tools.</p>
<p>Async support makes it possible to load data or execute async business logic right in your components. This can reduce the amount of boilerplate you need to write in some cases, and also gives you the freedom to split the rendering and non-rendering logic in any way you see fit.</p>
<p>Example:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span id="__span-1-1"><a id="__codelineno-1-1" name="__codelineno-1-1" href="#__codelineno-1-1"></a><span>from</span> <span>dataclasses</span> <span>import</span> <span>dataclass</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-2"><a id="__codelineno-1-2" name="__codelineno-1-2" href="#__codelineno-1-2"></a>
</span><span id="__span-1-3"><a id="__codelineno-1-3" name="__codelineno-1-3" href="#__codelineno-1-3"></a><span>from</span> <span>htmy</span> <span>import</span> <span>Component</span><span>,</span> <span>Context</span><span>,</span> <span>html</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-4"><a id="__codelineno-1-4" name="__codelineno-1-4" href="#__codelineno-1-4"></a>
</span><span id="__span-1-5"><a id="__codelineno-1-5" name="__codelineno-1-5" href="#__codelineno-1-5"></a><span>@dataclass</span><span>(</span><span>frozen</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>kw_only</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>slots</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-6"><a id="__codelineno-1-6" name="__codelineno-1-6" href="#__codelineno-1-6"></a><span>class</span> <span>User</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-7"><a id="__codelineno-1-7" name="__codelineno-1-7" href="#__codelineno-1-7"></a>    <span>username</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-8"><a id="__codelineno-1-8" name="__codelineno-1-8" href="#__codelineno-1-8"></a>    <span>name</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-9"><a id="__codelineno-1-9" name="__codelineno-1-9" href="#__codelineno-1-9"></a>    <span>email</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-10"><a id="__codelineno-1-10" name="__codelineno-1-10" href="#__codelineno-1-10"></a>
</span><span id="__span-1-11"><a id="__codelineno-1-11" name="__codelineno-1-11" href="#__codelineno-1-11"></a>    <span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>is_admin</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>bool</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-12"><a id="__codelineno-1-12" name="__codelineno-1-12" href="#__codelineno-1-12"></a>        <span>return</span> <span>False</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-13"><a id="__codelineno-1-13" name="__codelineno-1-13" href="#__codelineno-1-13"></a>
</span><span id="__span-1-14"><a id="__codelineno-1-14" name="__codelineno-1-14" href="#__codelineno-1-14"></a><span>class</span> <span>UserRow</span><span>(</span><span>User</span><span>):</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-15"><a id="__codelineno-1-15" name="__codelineno-1-15" href="#__codelineno-1-15"></a>    <span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>htmy</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Component</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-16"><a id="__codelineno-1-16" name="__codelineno-1-16" href="#__codelineno-1-16"></a>        <span>role</span> <span>=</span> <span>"admin"</span> <span>if</span> <span>await</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>is_admin</span><span>()</span> <span>else</span> <span>"restricted"</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-17"><a id="__codelineno-1-17" name="__codelineno-1-17" href="#__codelineno-1-17"></a>        <span>return</span> <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>tr</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-18"><a id="__codelineno-1-18" name="__codelineno-1-18" href="#__codelineno-1-18"></a>            <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>username</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-19"><a id="__codelineno-1-19" name="__codelineno-1-19" href="#__codelineno-1-19"></a>            <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>name</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-20"><a id="__codelineno-1-20" name="__codelineno-1-20" href="#__codelineno-1-20"></a>            <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>html</span><span>.</span><span>a</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>email</span><span>,</span> <span>href</span><span>=</span><span>f</span><span>"mailto:</span><span>{</span><span>self</span><span>.</span><span>email</span><span>}</span><span>"</span><span>)),</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-21"><a id="__codelineno-1-21" name="__codelineno-1-21" href="#__codelineno-1-21"></a>            <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>role</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-22"><a id="__codelineno-1-22" name="__codelineno-1-22" href="#__codelineno-1-22"></a>        <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-23"><a id="__codelineno-1-23" name="__codelineno-1-23" href="#__codelineno-1-23"></a>
</span><span id="__span-1-24"><a id="__codelineno-1-24" name="__codelineno-1-24" href="#__codelineno-1-24"></a><span>@dataclass</span><span>(</span><span>frozen</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>kw_only</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>slots</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-25"><a id="__codelineno-1-25" name="__codelineno-1-25" href="#__codelineno-1-25"></a><span>class</span> <span>UserRows</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-26"><a id="__codelineno-1-26" name="__codelineno-1-26" href="#__codelineno-1-26"></a>    <span>users</span><span>:</span> <span>list</span><span>[</span><span>User</span><span>]</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-27"><a id="__codelineno-1-27" name="__codelineno-1-27" href="#__codelineno-1-27"></a>    <span>def</span> <span>htmy</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Component</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-28"><a id="__codelineno-1-28" name="__codelineno-1-28" href="#__codelineno-1-28"></a>        <span># Note that a list is returned here. A list or tuple of `HTMYComponentType | str` objects is also a component.</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-29"><a id="__codelineno-1-29" name="__codelineno-1-29" href="#__codelineno-1-29"></a>        <span>return</span> <span>[</span><span>UserRow</span><span>(</span><span>username</span><span>=</span><span>u</span><span>.</span><span>username</span><span>,</span> <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>u</span><span>.</span><span>name</span><span>,</span> <span>email</span><span>=</span><span>u</span><span>.</span><span>email</span><span>)</span> <span>for</span> <span>u</span> <span>in</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>users</span><span>]</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-30"><a id="__codelineno-1-30" name="__codelineno-1-30" href="#__codelineno-1-30"></a>
</span><span id="__span-1-31"><a id="__codelineno-1-31" name="__codelineno-1-31" href="#__codelineno-1-31"></a><span>user_table</span> <span>=</span> <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>table</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-32"><a id="__codelineno-1-32" name="__codelineno-1-32" href="#__codelineno-1-32"></a>    <span>UserRows</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-33"><a id="__codelineno-1-33" name="__codelineno-1-33" href="#__codelineno-1-33"></a>        <span>users</span><span>=</span><span>[</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-34"><a id="__codelineno-1-34" name="__codelineno-1-34" href="#__codelineno-1-34"></a>            <span>User</span><span>(</span><span>username</span><span>=</span><span>"Foo"</span><span>,</span> <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Foo"</span><span>,</span> <span>email</span><span>=</span><span>"foo@example.com"</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-35"><a id="__codelineno-1-35" name="__codelineno-1-35" href="#__codelineno-1-35"></a>            <span>User</span><span>(</span><span>username</span><span>=</span><span>"Bar"</span><span>,</span> <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Bar"</span><span>,</span> <span>email</span><span>=</span><span>"bar@example.com"</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-36"><a id="__codelineno-1-36" name="__codelineno-1-36" href="#__codelineno-1-36"></a>        <span>]</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-37"><a id="__codelineno-1-37" name="__codelineno-1-37" href="#__codelineno-1-37"></a>    <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-1-38"><a id="__codelineno-1-38" name="__codelineno-1-38" href="#__codelineno-1-38"></a><span>)</span>
</span></code></pre></div>
<p><code>htmy</code> also provides a <code>@component</code> decorator that can be used on sync or async <code>my_component(props: MyProps, context: Context) -&gt; Component</code> functions to convert them into components (preserving the <code>props</code> typing).</p>
<p>Here is the same example as above, but with function components:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span id="__span-2-1"><a id="__codelineno-2-1" name="__codelineno-2-1" href="#__codelineno-2-1"></a><span>from</span> <span>dataclasses</span> <span>import</span> <span>dataclass</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-2"><a id="__codelineno-2-2" name="__codelineno-2-2" href="#__codelineno-2-2"></a>
</span><span id="__span-2-3"><a id="__codelineno-2-3" name="__codelineno-2-3" href="#__codelineno-2-3"></a><span>from</span> <span>htmy</span> <span>import</span> <span>Component</span><span>,</span> <span>Context</span><span>,</span> <span>component</span><span>,</span> <span>html</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-4"><a id="__codelineno-2-4" name="__codelineno-2-4" href="#__codelineno-2-4"></a>
</span><span id="__span-2-5"><a id="__codelineno-2-5" name="__codelineno-2-5" href="#__codelineno-2-5"></a><span>@dataclass</span><span>(</span><span>frozen</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>kw_only</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>,</span> <span>slots</span><span>=</span><span>True</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-6"><a id="__codelineno-2-6" name="__codelineno-2-6" href="#__codelineno-2-6"></a><span>class</span> <span>User</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-7"><a id="__codelineno-2-7" name="__codelineno-2-7" href="#__codelineno-2-7"></a>    <span>username</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-8"><a id="__codelineno-2-8" name="__codelineno-2-8" href="#__codelineno-2-8"></a>    <span>name</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-9"><a id="__codelineno-2-9" name="__codelineno-2-9" href="#__codelineno-2-9"></a>    <span>email</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-10"><a id="__codelineno-2-10" name="__codelineno-2-10" href="#__codelineno-2-10"></a>
</span><span id="__span-2-11"><a id="__codelineno-2-11" name="__codelineno-2-11" href="#__codelineno-2-11"></a>    <span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>is_admin</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>bool</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-12"><a id="__codelineno-2-12" name="__codelineno-2-12" href="#__codelineno-2-12"></a>        <span>return</span> <span>False</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-13"><a id="__codelineno-2-13" name="__codelineno-2-13" href="#__codelineno-2-13"></a>
</span><span id="__span-2-14"><a id="__codelineno-2-14" name="__codelineno-2-14" href="#__codelineno-2-14"></a><span>@component</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-15"><a id="__codelineno-2-15" name="__codelineno-2-15" href="#__codelineno-2-15"></a><span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>user_row</span><span>(</span><span>user</span><span>:</span> <span>User</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Component</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-16"><a id="__codelineno-2-16" name="__codelineno-2-16" href="#__codelineno-2-16"></a>    <span># The first argument of function components is their "props", the data they need.</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-17"><a id="__codelineno-2-17" name="__codelineno-2-17" href="#__codelineno-2-17"></a>    <span># The second argument is the rendering context.</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-18"><a id="__codelineno-2-18" name="__codelineno-2-18" href="#__codelineno-2-18"></a>    <span>role</span> <span>=</span> <span>"admin"</span> <span>if</span> <span>await</span> <span>user</span><span>.</span><span>is_admin</span><span>()</span> <span>else</span> <span>"restricted"</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-19"><a id="__codelineno-2-19" name="__codelineno-2-19" href="#__codelineno-2-19"></a>    <span>return</span> <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>tr</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-20"><a id="__codelineno-2-20" name="__codelineno-2-20" href="#__codelineno-2-20"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>user</span><span>.</span><span>username</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-21"><a id="__codelineno-2-21" name="__codelineno-2-21" href="#__codelineno-2-21"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>user</span><span>.</span><span>name</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-22"><a id="__codelineno-2-22" name="__codelineno-2-22" href="#__codelineno-2-22"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>html</span><span>.</span><span>a</span><span>(</span><span>user</span><span>.</span><span>email</span><span>,</span> <span>href</span><span>=</span><span>f</span><span>"mailto:</span><span>{</span><span>user</span><span>.</span><span>email</span><span>}</span><span>"</span><span>)),</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-23"><a id="__codelineno-2-23" name="__codelineno-2-23" href="#__codelineno-2-23"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>td</span><span>(</span><span>role</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-24"><a id="__codelineno-2-24" name="__codelineno-2-24" href="#__codelineno-2-24"></a>    <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-25"><a id="__codelineno-2-25" name="__codelineno-2-25" href="#__codelineno-2-25"></a>
</span><span id="__span-2-26"><a id="__codelineno-2-26" name="__codelineno-2-26" href="#__codelineno-2-26"></a><span>@component</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-27"><a id="__codelineno-2-27" name="__codelineno-2-27" href="#__codelineno-2-27"></a><span>def</span> <span>user_rows</span><span>(</span><span>users</span><span>:</span> <span>list</span><span>[</span><span>User</span><span>],</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Component</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-28"><a id="__codelineno-2-28" name="__codelineno-2-28" href="#__codelineno-2-28"></a>    <span># Nothing to await in this component, so it's sync.</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-29"><a id="__codelineno-2-29" name="__codelineno-2-29" href="#__codelineno-2-29"></a>    <span># Note that we only pass the "props" to the user_row() component (well, function component wrapper).</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-30"><a id="__codelineno-2-30" name="__codelineno-2-30" href="#__codelineno-2-30"></a>    <span># The context will be passed to the wrapper during rendering.</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-31"><a id="__codelineno-2-31" name="__codelineno-2-31" href="#__codelineno-2-31"></a>    <span>return</span> <span>[</span><span>user_row</span><span>(</span><span>user</span><span>)</span> <span>for</span> <span>user</span> <span>in</span> <span>users</span><span>]</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-32"><a id="__codelineno-2-32" name="__codelineno-2-32" href="#__codelineno-2-32"></a>
</span><span id="__span-2-33"><a id="__codelineno-2-33" name="__codelineno-2-33" href="#__codelineno-2-33"></a><span>user_table</span> <span>=</span> <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>table</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-34"><a id="__codelineno-2-34" name="__codelineno-2-34" href="#__codelineno-2-34"></a>    <span>user_rows</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-35"><a id="__codelineno-2-35" name="__codelineno-2-35" href="#__codelineno-2-35"></a>        <span>[</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-36"><a id="__codelineno-2-36" name="__codelineno-2-36" href="#__codelineno-2-36"></a>            <span>User</span><span>(</span><span>username</span><span>=</span><span>"Foo"</span><span>,</span> <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Foo"</span><span>,</span> <span>email</span><span>=</span><span>"foo@example.com"</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-37"><a id="__codelineno-2-37" name="__codelineno-2-37" href="#__codelineno-2-37"></a>            <span>User</span><span>(</span><span>username</span><span>=</span><span>"Bar"</span><span>,</span> <span>name</span><span>=</span><span>"Bar"</span><span>,</span> <span>email</span><span>=</span><span>"bar@example.com"</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-38"><a id="__codelineno-2-38" name="__codelineno-2-38" href="#__codelineno-2-38"></a>        <span>]</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-39"><a id="__codelineno-2-39" name="__codelineno-2-39" href="#__codelineno-2-39"></a>    <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-2-40"><a id="__codelineno-2-40" name="__codelineno-2-40" href="#__codelineno-2-40"></a><span>)</span>
</span></code></pre></div>
<h3 id="built-in-components">Built-in components</h3>
<p><code>htmy</code> has a rich set of built-in utilities and components for both HTML and other use-cases:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>html</code> module: a complete set of <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Glossary/Baseline/Compatibility">baseline HTML tags</a>.</li>
<li><code>md</code>: <code>MarkdownParser</code> utility and <code>MD</code> component for loading, parsing, converting, and rendering markdown content.</li>
<li><code>i18n</code>: utilities for async, JSON based internationalization.</li>
<li><code>BaseTag</code>, <code>TagWithProps</code>, <code>Tag</code>, <code>WildcardTag</code>: base classes for custom XML tags.</li>
<li><code>ErrorBoundary</code>, <code>Fragment</code>, <code>SafeStr</code>, <code>WithContext</code>: utilities for error handling, component wrappers, context providers, and formatting.</li>
<li><code>Snippet</code>: utility class for loading and customizing document snippets from the file system.</li>
<li><code>etree.ETreeConverter</code>: utility that converts XML to a component tree with support for custom HTMY components.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="rendering">Rendering</h3>
<p><code>htmy.HTMY</code> is the built-in, default renderer of the library.</p>
<p>If you're using the library in an async web framework like <a href="https://fastapi.tiangolo.com/">FastAPI</a>, then you're already in an async environment, so you can render components as simply as this: <code>await HTMY().render(my_root_component)</code>.</p>
<p>If you're trying to run the renderer in a sync environment, like a local script or CLI, then you first need to wrap the renderer in an async task and execute that task with <code>asyncio.run()</code>:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span id="__span-3-1"><a id="__codelineno-3-1" name="__codelineno-3-1" href="#__codelineno-3-1"></a><span>import</span> <span>asyncio</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-2"><a id="__codelineno-3-2" name="__codelineno-3-2" href="#__codelineno-3-2"></a>
</span><span id="__span-3-3"><a id="__codelineno-3-3" name="__codelineno-3-3" href="#__codelineno-3-3"></a><span>from</span> <span>htmy</span> <span>import</span> <span>HTMY</span><span>,</span> <span>html</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-4"><a id="__codelineno-3-4" name="__codelineno-3-4" href="#__codelineno-3-4"></a>
</span><span id="__span-3-5"><a id="__codelineno-3-5" name="__codelineno-3-5" href="#__codelineno-3-5"></a><span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>render_page</span><span>()</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>None</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-6"><a id="__codelineno-3-6" name="__codelineno-3-6" href="#__codelineno-3-6"></a>    <span>page</span> <span>=</span> <span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-7"><a id="__codelineno-3-7" name="__codelineno-3-7" href="#__codelineno-3-7"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>DOCTYPE</span><span>.</span><span>html</span><span>,</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-8"><a id="__codelineno-3-8" name="__codelineno-3-8" href="#__codelineno-3-8"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>html</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-9"><a id="__codelineno-3-9" name="__codelineno-3-9" href="#__codelineno-3-9"></a>            <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>body</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-10"><a id="__codelineno-3-10" name="__codelineno-3-10" href="#__codelineno-3-10"></a>                <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>h1</span><span>(</span><span>"Hello World!"</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-11"><a id="__codelineno-3-11" name="__codelineno-3-11" href="#__codelineno-3-11"></a>                <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>p</span><span>(</span><span>"This page was rendered by "</span><span>,</span> <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>code</span><span>(</span><span>"htmy"</span><span>)),</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-12"><a id="__codelineno-3-12" name="__codelineno-3-12" href="#__codelineno-3-12"></a>            <span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-13"><a id="__codelineno-3-13" name="__codelineno-3-13" href="#__codelineno-3-13"></a>        <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-14"><a id="__codelineno-3-14" name="__codelineno-3-14" href="#__codelineno-3-14"></a>    <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-15"><a id="__codelineno-3-15" name="__codelineno-3-15" href="#__codelineno-3-15"></a>
</span><span id="__span-3-16"><a id="__codelineno-3-16" name="__codelineno-3-16" href="#__codelineno-3-16"></a>    <span>result</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>HTMY</span><span>()</span><span>.</span><span>render</span><span>(</span><span>page</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-17"><a id="__codelineno-3-17" name="__codelineno-3-17" href="#__codelineno-3-17"></a>    <span>print</span><span>(</span><span>result</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-18"><a id="__codelineno-3-18" name="__codelineno-3-18" href="#__codelineno-3-18"></a>
</span><span id="__span-3-19"><a id="__codelineno-3-19" name="__codelineno-3-19" href="#__codelineno-3-19"></a>
</span><span id="__span-3-20"><a id="__codelineno-3-20" name="__codelineno-3-20" href="#__codelineno-3-20"></a><span>if</span> <span>__name__</span> <span>==</span> <span>"__main__"</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-3-21"><a id="__codelineno-3-21" name="__codelineno-3-21" href="#__codelineno-3-21"></a>    <span>asyncio</span><span>.</span><span>run</span><span>(</span><span>render_page</span><span>())</span>
</span></code></pre></div>
<h3 id="context">Context</h3>
<p>As you could see from the code examples above, every component has a <code>context: Context</code> argument, which we haven't used so far. Context is a way to share data with the entire subtree of a component without "prop drilling".</p>
<p>The context (technically a <code>Mapping</code>) is entirely managed by the renderer. Context provider components (any class with a sync or async <code>htmy_context() -&gt; Context</code> method) add new data to the context to make it available to components in their subtree, and components can simply take what they need from the context.</p>
<p>There is no restriction on what can be in the context, it can be used for anything the application needs, for example making the current user, UI preferences, themes, or formatters available to components. In fact, built-in components get their <code>Formatter</code> from the context if it contains one, to make it possible to customize tag property name and value formatting.</p>
<p>Here's an example context provider and consumer implementation:</p>
<div><pre><span></span><code><span id="__span-4-1"><a id="__codelineno-4-1" name="__codelineno-4-1" href="#__codelineno-4-1"></a><span>import</span> <span>asyncio</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-2"><a id="__codelineno-4-2" name="__codelineno-4-2" href="#__codelineno-4-2"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-3"><a id="__codelineno-4-3" name="__codelineno-4-3" href="#__codelineno-4-3"></a><span>from</span> <span>htmy</span> <span>import</span> <span>HTMY</span><span>,</span> <span>Component</span><span>,</span> <span>ComponentType</span><span>,</span> <span>Context</span><span>,</span> <span>component</span><span>,</span> <span>html</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-4"><a id="__codelineno-4-4" name="__codelineno-4-4" href="#__codelineno-4-4"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-5"><a id="__codelineno-4-5" name="__codelineno-4-5" href="#__codelineno-4-5"></a><span>class</span> <span>UserContext</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-6"><a id="__codelineno-4-6" name="__codelineno-4-6" href="#__codelineno-4-6"></a>    <span>def</span> <span>__init__</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>*</span><span>children</span><span>:</span> <span>ComponentType</span><span>,</span> <span>username</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>theme</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>None</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-7"><a id="__codelineno-4-7" name="__codelineno-4-7" href="#__codelineno-4-7"></a>        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>_children</span> <span>=</span> <span>children</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-8"><a id="__codelineno-4-8" name="__codelineno-4-8" href="#__codelineno-4-8"></a>        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>username</span> <span>=</span> <span>username</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-9"><a id="__codelineno-4-9" name="__codelineno-4-9" href="#__codelineno-4-9"></a>        <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>theme</span> <span>=</span> <span>theme</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-10"><a id="__codelineno-4-10" name="__codelineno-4-10" href="#__codelineno-4-10"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-11"><a id="__codelineno-4-11" name="__codelineno-4-11" href="#__codelineno-4-11"></a>    <span>def</span> <span>htmy_context</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Context</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-12"><a id="__codelineno-4-12" name="__codelineno-4-12" href="#__codelineno-4-12"></a>        <span># Context provider implementation.</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-13"><a id="__codelineno-4-13" name="__codelineno-4-13" href="#__codelineno-4-13"></a>        <span>return</span> <span>{</span><span>UserContext</span><span>:</span> <span>self</span><span>}</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-14"><a id="__codelineno-4-14" name="__codelineno-4-14" href="#__codelineno-4-14"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-15"><a id="__codelineno-4-15" name="__codelineno-4-15" href="#__codelineno-4-15"></a>    <span>def</span> <span>htmy</span><span>(</span><span>self</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Component</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-16"><a id="__codelineno-4-16" name="__codelineno-4-16" href="#__codelineno-4-16"></a>        <span># Context providers must also be components, as they just</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-17"><a id="__codelineno-4-17" name="__codelineno-4-17" href="#__codelineno-4-17"></a>        <span># wrap some children components in their context.</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-18"><a id="__codelineno-4-18" name="__codelineno-4-18" href="#__codelineno-4-18"></a>        <span>return</span> <span>self</span><span>.</span><span>_children</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-19"><a id="__codelineno-4-19" name="__codelineno-4-19" href="#__codelineno-4-19"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-20"><a id="__codelineno-4-20" name="__codelineno-4-20" href="#__codelineno-4-20"></a>    <span>@classmethod</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-21"><a id="__codelineno-4-21" name="__codelineno-4-21" href="#__codelineno-4-21"></a>    <span>def</span> <span>from_context</span><span>(</span><span>cls</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>"UserContext"</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-22"><a id="__codelineno-4-22" name="__codelineno-4-22" href="#__codelineno-4-22"></a>        <span>user_context</span> <span>=</span> <span>context</span><span>[</span><span>cls</span><span>]</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-23"><a id="__codelineno-4-23" name="__codelineno-4-23" href="#__codelineno-4-23"></a>        <span>if</span> <span>isinstance</span><span>(</span><span>user_context</span><span>,</span> <span>UserContext</span><span>):</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-24"><a id="__codelineno-4-24" name="__codelineno-4-24" href="#__codelineno-4-24"></a>            <span>return</span> <span>user_context</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-25"><a id="__codelineno-4-25" name="__codelineno-4-25" href="#__codelineno-4-25"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-26"><a id="__codelineno-4-26" name="__codelineno-4-26" href="#__codelineno-4-26"></a>        <span>raise</span> <span>TypeError</span><span>(</span><span>"Invalid user context."</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-27"><a id="__codelineno-4-27" name="__codelineno-4-27" href="#__codelineno-4-27"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-28"><a id="__codelineno-4-28" name="__codelineno-4-28" href="#__codelineno-4-28"></a><span>@component</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-29"><a id="__codelineno-4-29" name="__codelineno-4-29" href="#__codelineno-4-29"></a><span>def</span> <span>welcome_page</span><span>(</span><span>text</span><span>:</span> <span>str</span><span>,</span> <span>context</span><span>:</span> <span>Context</span><span>)</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>Component</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-30"><a id="__codelineno-4-30" name="__codelineno-4-30" href="#__codelineno-4-30"></a>    <span># Get user information from the context.</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-31"><a id="__codelineno-4-31" name="__codelineno-4-31" href="#__codelineno-4-31"></a>    <span>user</span> <span>=</span> <span>UserContext</span><span>.</span><span>from_context</span><span>(</span><span>context</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-32"><a id="__codelineno-4-32" name="__codelineno-4-32" href="#__codelineno-4-32"></a>    <span>return</span> <span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-33"><a id="__codelineno-4-33" name="__codelineno-4-33" href="#__codelineno-4-33"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>DOCTYPE</span><span>.</span><span>html</span><span>,</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-34"><a id="__codelineno-4-34" name="__codelineno-4-34" href="#__codelineno-4-34"></a>        <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>html</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-35"><a id="__codelineno-4-35" name="__codelineno-4-35" href="#__codelineno-4-35"></a>            <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>body</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-36"><a id="__codelineno-4-36" name="__codelineno-4-36" href="#__codelineno-4-36"></a>                <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>h1</span><span>(</span><span>text</span><span>,</span> <span>html</span><span>.</span><span>strong</span><span>(</span><span>user</span><span>.</span><span>username</span><span>)),</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-37"><a id="__codelineno-4-37" name="__codelineno-4-37" href="#__codelineno-4-37"></a>                <span>data_theme</span><span>=</span><span>user</span><span>.</span><span>theme</span><span>,</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-38"><a id="__codelineno-4-38" name="__codelineno-4-38" href="#__codelineno-4-38"></a>            <span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-39"><a id="__codelineno-4-39" name="__codelineno-4-39" href="#__codelineno-4-39"></a>        <span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-40"><a id="__codelineno-4-40" name="__codelineno-4-40" href="#__codelineno-4-40"></a>    <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-41"><a id="__codelineno-4-41" name="__codelineno-4-41" href="#__codelineno-4-41"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-42"><a id="__codelineno-4-42" name="__codelineno-4-42" href="#__codelineno-4-42"></a><span>async</span> <span>def</span> <span>render_welcome_page</span><span>()</span> <span>-&gt;</span> <span>None</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-43"><a id="__codelineno-4-43" name="__codelineno-4-43" href="#__codelineno-4-43"></a>    <span>page</span> <span>=</span> <span>UserContext</span><span>(</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-44"><a id="__codelineno-4-44" name="__codelineno-4-44" href="#__codelineno-4-44"></a>        <span>welcome_page</span><span>(</span><span>"Welcome back "</span><span>),</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-45"><a id="__codelineno-4-45" name="__codelineno-4-45" href="#__codelineno-4-45"></a>        <span>username</span><span>=</span><span>"John"</span><span>,</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-46"><a id="__codelineno-4-46" name="__codelineno-4-46" href="#__codelineno-4-46"></a>        <span>theme</span><span>=</span><span>"dark"</span><span>,</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-47"><a id="__codelineno-4-47" name="__codelineno-4-47" href="#__codelineno-4-47"></a>    <span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-48"><a id="__codelineno-4-48" name="__codelineno-4-48" href="#__codelineno-4-48"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-49"><a id="__codelineno-4-49" name="__codelineno-4-49" href="#__codelineno-4-49"></a>    <span>result</span> <span>=</span> <span>await</span> <span>HTMY</span><span>()</span><span>.</span><span>render</span><span>(</span><span>page</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-50"><a id="__codelineno-4-50" name="__codelineno-4-50" href="#__codelineno-4-50"></a>    <span>print</span><span>(</span><span>result</span><span>)</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-51"><a id="__codelineno-4-51" name="__codelineno-4-51" href="#__codelineno-4-51"></a>
</span><span id="__span-4-52"><a id="__codelineno-4-52" name="__codelineno-4-52" href="#__codelineno-4-52"></a><span>if</span> <span>__name__</span> <span>==</span> <span>"__main__"</span><span>:</span>
</span><span id="__span-4-53"><a id="__codelineno-4-53" name="__codelineno-4-53" href="#__codelineno-4-53"></a>    <span>asyncio</span><span>.</span><span>run</span><span>(</span><span>render_welcome_page</span><span>())</span>
</span></code></pre></div>
<p>You can of course rely on the built-in context related utilities like the <code>ContextAware</code> or <code>WithContext</code> classes for convenient and typed context use with less boilerplate code.</p>
<h3 id="formatter">Formatter</h3>
<p>As mentioned before, the built-in <code>Formatter</code> class is responsible for tag attribute name and value formatting. You can completely override or extend the built-in formatting behavior simply by extending this class or adding new rules to an instance of it, and then adding the custom instance to the context, either directly in <code>HTMY</code> or <code>HTMY.render()</code>, or in a context provider component.</p>
<p>These are default tag attribute formatting rules:</p>
<ul>
<li>Underscores are converted to dashes in attribute names (<code>_</code> -&gt; <code>-</code>) unless the attribute name starts or ends with an underscore, in which case leading and trailing underscores are removed and the rest of attribute name is preserved. For example <code>data_theme="dark"</code> is converted to <code>data-theme="dark"</code>, but <code>_data_theme="dark"</code> will end up as <code>data_theme="dark"</code> in the rendered text. More importantly <code>class_="text-danger"</code>, <code>_class="text-danger"</code>, <code>_class__="text-danger"</code> are all converted to <code>class="text-danger"</code>, and <code>_for="my-input"</code> or <code>for_="my_input"</code> will become <code>for="my-input"</code>.</li>
<li><code>bool</code> attribute values are converted to strings (<code>"true"</code> and <code>"false"</code>).</li>
<li><code>XBool.true</code> attributes values are converted to an empty string, and <code>XBool.false</code> values are skipped (only the attribute name is rendered).</li>
<li><code>date</code> and <code>datetime</code> attribute values are converted to ISO strings.</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="error-boundary">Error boundary</h3>
<p>The <code>ErrorBoundary</code> component is useful if you want your application to fail gracefully (e.g. display an error message) instead of raising an HTTP error.</p>
<p>The error boundary wraps a component component subtree. When the renderer encounters an <code>ErrorBoundary</code> component, it will try to render its wrapped content. If rendering fails with an exception at any point in the <code>ErrorBoundary</code>'s subtree, the renderer will automatically fall back to the component you assigned to the <code>ErrorBoundary</code>'s <code>fallback</code> property.</p>
<p>Optionally, you can define which errors an error boundary can handle, giving you fine control over error handling.</p>
<h3 id="sync-or-async">Sync or async?</h3>
<p>In general, a component should be async if it must await some async call inside.</p>
<p>If a component executes a potentially "long-running" synchronous call, it is strongly recommended to delegate that call to a worker thread an await it (thus making the component async). This can be done for example with <code>anyio</code>'s <code>to_thread</code> <a href="https://anyio.readthedocs.io/en/stable/threads.html">utility</a>, <code>starlette</code>'s (or <code>fastapi</code>'s) <code>run_in_threadpool()</code>, and so on. The goal here is to avoid blocking the asyncio event loop, as that can lead to performance issues.</p>
<p>In all other cases, it's best to use sync components.</p>
<h2 id="framework-integrations">Framework integrations</h2>
<p>FastAPI:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/volfpeter/fasthx">FastHX</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="why">Why</h2>
<p>At one end of the spectrum, there are the complete application frameworks that combine the server (Python) and client (JavaScript) applications with the entire state management and synchronization into a single Python (an in some cases an additional JavaScript) package. Some of the most popular examples are: <a href="https://github.com/reflex-dev/reflex">Reflex</a>, <a href="https://github.com/zauberzeug/nicegui/">NiceGUI</a>, <a href="https://github.com/reactive-python/reactpy">ReactPy</a>, and <a href="https://github.com/pydantic/FastUI">FastUI</a>.</p>
<p>The main benefit of these frameworks is rapid application prototyping and a very convenient developer experience (at least as long as you stay within the built-in feature set of the framework). In exchange for that, they are very opinionated (from components to frontend tooling and state management), the underlying engineering is very complex, deployment and scaling can be hard or costly, and they can be hard to migrate away from. Even with these caveats, they can be a very good choice for internal tools and application prototyping.</p>
<p>The other end of spectrum -- plain rendering engines -- is dominated by the <a href="https://jinja.palletsprojects.com/">Jinja</a> templating engine, which is a safe choice as it has been and will be around for a long time. The main drawbacks with Jinja are the lack of good IDE support, the complete lack of static code analysis support, and the (subjectively) ugly syntax.</p>
<p>Then there are tools that aim for the middleground, usually by providing most of the benefits and drawbacks of complete application frameworks while leaving state management, client-server communication, and dynamic UI updates for the user to solve, often with some level of <a href="https://htmx.org/">HTMX</a> support. This group includes libraries like <a href="https://github.com/answerdotai/fasthtml">FastHTML</a> and <a href="https://github.com/getludic/ludic">Ludic</a>.</p>
<p>The primary aim of <code>htmy</code> is to be an <strong>async</strong>, pure-Python rendering engine, which is as <strong>simple</strong>, <strong>maintainable</strong>, and <strong>customizable</strong> as possible, while still providing all the building blocks for (conveniently) creating complex and maintainable applications.</p>
<h2 id="dependencies">Dependencies</h2>
<p>The library aims to minimze its dependencies. Currently the following dependencies are required:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>anyio</code>: for async file operations and networking.</li>
<li><code>async-lru</code>: for async caching.</li>
<li><code>markdown</code>: for markdown parsing.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="development">Development</h2>
<p>Use <code>ruff</code> for linting and formatting, <code>mypy</code> for static code analysis, and <code>pytest</code> for testing.</p>
<p>The documentation is built with <code>mkdocs-material</code> and <code>mkdocstrings</code>.</p>
<h2 id="contributing">Contributing</h2>
<p>All contributions are welcome, including more documentation, examples, code, and tests. Even questions.</p>
<h2 id="license-mit">License - MIT</h2>
<p>The package is open-sourced under the conditions of the <a href="https://choosealicense.com/licenses/mit/">MIT license</a>.</p>












                
              </article>
            </div>
        
      </main>
      
        
      
    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hacker in Snowflake extortions may be a U.S. soldier (304 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/11/hacker-in-snowflake-extortions-may-be-a-u-s-soldier/</link>
            <guid>42251799</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:53:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/11/hacker-in-snowflake-extortions-may-be-a-u-s-soldier/">https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/11/hacker-in-snowflake-extortions-may-be-a-u-s-soldier/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42251799">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
												<p>Two men have been arrested for allegedly stealing data from and extorting dozens of companies that used the cloud data storage company <strong>Snowflake</strong>, but a third suspect — a prolific hacker known as <strong>Kiberphant0m </strong>— remains at large and continues to publicly extort victims. However, this person’s identity may not remain a secret for long: A careful review of Kiberphant0m’s daily chats across multiple cybercrime personas suggests they are a U.S. Army soldier who is or was recently stationed in South Korea.</p>
<p>Kiberphant0m’s identities on cybercrime forums and on Telegram and Discord chat channels have been selling data stolen from customers of the cloud data storage company Snowflake. At the end of 2023, malicious hackers discovered that many companies had uploaded huge volumes of sensitive customer data to Snowflake accounts that were protected with nothing more than a username and password (no multi-factor authentication required).</p>
<p>After scouring darknet markets for stolen Snowflake account credentials, the hackers began raiding the data storage repositories for some of the world’s largest corporations. Among those was <strong>AT&amp;T</strong>, which&nbsp;<a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/07/hackers-steal-phone-sms-records-for-nearly-all-att-customers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">disclosed in July</a> that cybercriminals had stolen personal information, phone and text message records for roughly 110 million people.&nbsp; <strong>Wired.com</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.wired.com/story/atandt-paid-hacker-300000-to-delete-stolen-call-records/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">reported in July</a>&nbsp;that AT&amp;T paid a hacker $370,000 to delete stolen phone records.</p>
<p>On October 30, Canadian authorities <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/2024/11/canadian-man-arrested-in-snowflake-data-extortions/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">arrested</a>&nbsp;<strong>Alexander Moucka,&nbsp;</strong>a.k.a.<strong>&nbsp;Connor Riley Moucka&nbsp;</strong>of Kitchener, Ontario, on a provisional arrest warrant from the United States, which has since indicted him on 20 criminal counts connected to the Snowflake breaches. Another suspect in the Snowflake hacks, <strong>John Erin Binns</strong>, is an American who is currently incarcerated in Turkey.</p>
<div id="attachment_69625"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69625" decoding="async" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/moucka-surveillance.png" alt="" width="749" height="575" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/moucka-surveillance.png 1137w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/moucka-surveillance-768x590.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/moucka-surveillance-782x600.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 749px) 100vw, 749px"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69625">A surveillance photo of Connor Riley Moucka, a.k.a. “Judische” and “Waifu,” dated Oct 21, 2024, 9 days before Moucka’s arrest. This image was included in an affidavit filed by an investigator with the Royal Canadian Mounted Police (RCMP).</p></div>
<p>Investigators say Moucka, who went by the handles <strong>Judische</strong> and <strong>Waifu</strong>, had tasked Kiberphant0m with selling data stolen from Snowflake customers who refused to pay a ransom to have their information deleted. Immediately after news broke of Moucka’s arrest, Kiberphant0m was clearly furious, and posted on the hacker community <strong>BreachForums</strong> what they claimed were the AT&amp;T call logs for <strong>President-elect</strong> <strong>Donald J. Trump</strong> and for <strong>Vice President Kamala Harris</strong>.</p>
<p>“In the event you do not reach out to us @ATNT all presidential government call logs will be leaked,” Kiberphant0m threatened, signing their post with multiple “#FREEWAIFU” tags. “You don’t think we don’t have plans in the event of an arrest? Think again.”</p>
<p>On the same day, Kiberphant0m posted what they claimed was the “data schema” from the <strong>U.S. National Security Agency</strong>.</p>
<p>“This was obtained from the ATNT Snowflake hack which is why ATNT paid an extortion,” Kiberphant0m wrote in a thread on BreachForums. “Why would ATNT pay Waifu for the data when they wouldn’t even pay an extortion for over 20M+ SSNs?”</p>
<div id="attachment_69624"><p><a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphant0m-nsa-schema.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69624" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphant0m-nsa-schema.png" alt="" width="750" height="239" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphant0m-nsa-schema.png 1417w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphant0m-nsa-schema-768x245.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphant0m-nsa-schema-782x249.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-69624">Kiberphant0m posting what he claimed was a “data schema” stolen from the NSA via AT&amp;T.</p></div>
<p>Also on Nov. 5, Kiberphant0m offered call logs stolen from Verizon’s push-to-talk (PTT) customers — mainly U.S. government agencies and emergency first responders. On Nov. 9, Kiberphant0m posted a sales thread on BreachForums offering a “SIM-swapping” service targeting Verizon PTT customers. In a SIM-swap, fraudsters use credentials that are phished or stolen from mobile phone company employees to divert a target’s phone calls and text messages to a device they control.</p>
<h2>MEET ‘BUTTHOLIO’</h2>
<p>Kiberphant0m joined BreachForums in January 2024, but their public utterances on Discord and Telegram channels date back to at least early 2022. On their first post to BreachForums, Kiberphant0m said they could be reached at the Telegram handle <strong>@cyb3rph4nt0m</strong>.</p>
<p>A review of @cyb3rph4nt0m shows this user has posted more than 4,200 messages since January 2024. Many of these messages were attempts to recruit people who could be hired to deploy a piece of malware that enslaved host machines in an Internet of Things (IoT) botnet.</p>
<p>On BreachForums, Kiberphant0m has sold the source code to “<strong>Shi-Bot</strong>,” a custom Linux DDoS botnet based on <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/tag/mirai/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">the Mirai malware</a>. Kiberphant0m had few sales threads on BreachForums prior to the Snowflake attacks becoming public in May, and many of those involved databases stolen from companies in South Korea.</p>
<p>On June 5, 2024, a Telegram user by the name “<strong>Buttholio</strong>” joined the fraud-focused Telegram channel “<strong>Comgirl</strong>” and claimed to be Kiberphant0m. Buttholio made the claim after being taunted as a nobody by another denizen of Comgirl, referring to their @cyb3rph4nt0m account on Telegram and the Kiberphant0m user on cybercrime forums.</p>
<p>“Type ‘kiberphant0m’ on google with the quotes,” Buttholio told another user. “I’ll wait. Go ahead. Over 50 articles. 15+ telecoms breached. I got the IMSI number to every single person that’s ever registered in Verizon, Tmobile, ATNT and Verifone.”</p>
<p>On Sept. 17, 2023, Buttholio posted in a Discord chat room dedicated to players of the video game <strong>Escape from Tarkov</strong>. “Come to Korea, servers there is pretty much no extract camper or cheater,” Buttholio advised.</p>
<p>In another message that same day in the gaming Discord, Buttholio told others they bought the game in the United States, but that they were playing it in Asia.</p>
<p>“USA is where the game was purchased from, server location is actual in game servers u play on. I am a u.s. soldier so i bought it in the states but got on rotation so i have to use asian servers,” they shared.<span id="more-69605"></span></p>
<h2>‘REVERSESHELL’</h2>
<p>The account @Kiberphant0m was assigned the Telegram ID number 6953392511. A review of this ID at the cyber intelligence platform <a href="https://www.flashpoint.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Flashpoint</a> shows that on January 4, 2024 Kibertphant0m posted to the Telegram channel “Dstat,” which is populated by cybercriminals involved in launching distributed denial-of-service (DDoS) attacks and selling DDoS-for-hire services [Full disclosure: Flashpoint is currently an advertiser on this website].</p>
<p>Immediately after Kiberphant0m logged on to the Dstat channel, another user wrote “hi buttholio,” to which Kiberphant0m replied with an affirmative greeting “wsg,” or “what’s good.” On Nov. 1, <a href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/ddos-site-dstatcc-seized-and-two-suspects-arrested-in-germany/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dstat’s website dstat[.]cc was seized</a> as part of “Operation PowerOFF,” an international law enforcement action against DDoS services.</p>
<p>Flashpoint’s data shows that @kiberphant0m told a fellow member of Dstat on April 10, 2024 that their alternate Telegram username was “<strong>@reverseshell</strong>,” and did the same two weeks later in the Telegram chat The Jacuzzi. The Telegram ID for this account is <strong>5408575119</strong>.</p>
<p>Way back on Nov. 15, 2022, @reverseshell told a fellow member of a Telegram channel called Cecilio Chat that they were a soldier in the U.S. Army. This user also shared the following image of someone pictured waist-down in military fatigues, with a camouflaged backpack at their feet:</p>
<div id="attachment_69628"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69628" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/reverseshell-fatigues.png" alt="" width="655" height="663"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69628">Kiberphant0m’s apparent alias ReverseShell posted this image on a Telegram channel Cecilio Chat, on Nov. 15, 2022. Image: Flashpoint.</p></div>
<p>In September 2022, Reverseshell was embroiled in an argument with another member who had threatened to launch a DDoS attack against Reverseshell’s Internet address. After the promised attack materialized, Reverseshell responded, “Yall just hit military base contracted wifi.”</p>
<p>In a chat from October 2022, Reverseshell was bragging about the speed of the servers they were using, and in reply to another member’s question said that they were accessing the Internet via South Korea Telecom.</p>
<p>Telegram chat logs archived by Flashpoint show that on Aug. 23, 2022, Reverseshell bragged they’d been using automated tools to find valid logins for Internet servers that they resold to others.</p>
<p>“I’ve hit US gov servers with default creds,” Reverseshell wrote, referring to systems with easy-to-guess usernames and/or passwords. “Telecom control servers, machinery shops, Russian ISP servers, etc. I sold a few big companies for like $2-3k a piece. You can sell the access when you get a big SSH into corporation.”</p>
<p>On July 29, 2023, Reverseshell posted a screenshot of a login page for a major U.S. defense contractor, claiming they had an aerospace company’s credentials to sell.</p>
<h2>PROMAN AND VARS_SECC</h2>
<p>Flashpoint finds the Telegram ID 5408575119 has used several aliases since 2022, including Reverseshell and <strong>Proman557</strong>.</p>
<p>A search on the username Proman557 at the cyber intelligence platform <a href="https://www.intel471.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Intel 471</a> shows that a hacker by the name “<strong>Proman554</strong>” registered on Hackforums in September 2022, and in messages to other users Proman554 said they can be reached at the Telegram account Buttholio.</p>
<p>Intel 471 also finds the Proman557 moniker is one of many used by a person on the Russian-language hacking forum <strong>Exploit</strong> in 2022 who sold a variety of Linux-based botnet malware.</p>
<p>Proman557 was eventually banned — allegedly for scamming a fellow member out of $350 — and the Exploit moderator warned forum users that Proman557 had previously registered under several other nicknames, including an account called “<strong>Vars_Secc</strong>.”</p>
<p>Vars_Secc’s thousands of comments on Telegram over two years show this user divided their time between online gaming, maintaining a DDoS botnet, and promoting the sale or renting of their botnets to other users.</p>
<p>“I use ddos for many things not just to be a skid,” Vars_Secc pronounced. “Why do you think I haven’t sold my net?” They then proceeded to list the most useful qualities of their botnet:</p>
<blockquote><p>-I use it to hit off servers that ban me or piss me off<br>
-I used to ddos certain games to get my items back since the data reverts to when u joined<br>
-I use it for server side desync RCE vulnerabilities<br>
-I use it to sometimes ransom<br>
-I use it when bored as a source of entertainment</p></blockquote>
<p>Flashpoint shows that in June 2023, Vars_Secc responded to taunting from a fellow member in the Telegram channel SecHub who had threatened to reveal their personal details to the federal government for a reward.</p>
<p>“Man I’ve been doing this shit for 4 years,” Vars_Secc replied nonchalantly. “I highly doubt the government is going to pay millions of dollars for data on some random dude operating a pointless ddos botnet and finding a few vulnerabilities here and there.”</p>
<p>For several months in 2023, Vars_Secc also was an active member of the Russian-language crime forum <strong>XSS</strong>, where they sold access to a U.S. government server for $2,000. However, Vars_Secc would be banned from XSS after attempting to sell access to the Russian telecommunications giant <strong>Rostelecom</strong>. [In this, Vars_Secc violated the Number One Rule for operating on a Russia-based crime forum: Never offer to hack or sell data stolen from Russian entities or citizens].</p>
<p>On June 20, 2023, Vars_Secc posted a sales thread on the cybercrime forum <strong>Ramp 2.0</strong> titled, “Selling US Gov Financial Access.”</p>
<p>“Server within the network, possible to pivot,” Vars_Secc’s sparse sales post read. “Has 3-5 subroutes connected to it. Price $1,250. Telegram: Vars_Secc.”</p>
<p>Vars_Secc also used Ramp in June 2023 to sell access to a “Vietnam government Internet Network Information Center.”</p>
<p>“Selling access server allocated within the network,” Vars_Secc wrote. “Has some data on it. $500.”</p>
<h2>BUG BOUNTIES</h2>
<p>The Vars_Secc identity claimed on Telegram in May 2023 that they made money by submitting reports about software flaws to <strong>HackerOne</strong>, a company that helps technology firms field reports about security vulnerabilities in their products and services. Specifically, Vars_Secc said they had earned financial rewards or “bug bounties” from <strong>reddit.com</strong>, the <strong>U.S.</strong> <strong>Department of Defense</strong>, and <strong>Coinbase</strong>, among 30 others.</p>
<p>“I make money off bug bounties, it’s quite simple,” Vars_Secc said when asked what they do for a living. “That’s why I have over 30 bug bounty reports on HackerOne.”</p>
<p>A month before that, Vars_Secc said they’d found a vulnerability in reddit.com.</p>
<p>“I poisoned Reddit’s cache,” they explained. “I’m going to exploit it further, then report it to reddit.”</p>
<p>KrebsOnSecurity sought comment from HackerOne, which said it would investigate the claims. This story will be updated if they respond.</p>
<p>The Vars_Secc telegram handle also has claimed ownership of the BreachForums member “<strong>Boxfan</strong>,” and Intel 471 shows Boxfan’s early posts on the forum had the Vars_Secc Telegram account in their signature. In their most recent post to BreachForums in January 2024, Boxfan disclosed a security vulnerability they found in <strong>Naver</strong>, the most popular search engine in South Korea (according to statista.com). Boxfan’s comments suggest they have strong negative feelings about South Korean culture.</p>
<p>“Have fun exploiting this vulnerability,” Boxfan wrote on BreachForums, after pasting a long string of computer code intended to demonstrate the flaw. “Fuck you South Korea and your discriminatory views. Nobody likes ur shit kpop you evil fucks. Whoever can dump this DB [database] congrats. I don’t feel like doing it so I’ll post it to the forum.”</p>
<p>The many identities tied to Kiberphant0m strongly suggest they are or until recently were a U.S. Army soldier stationed in South Korea. Kiberphant0m’s alter egos never mentioned their military rank, regiment, or specialization.</p>
<p>However, it is likely that Kiberphant0m’s facility with computers and networking was noticed by the Army. According to the U.S. Army’s website, the bulk of its forces in South Korea reside within the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eighth_Army_(United_States)" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Eighth Army</a>, which has a dedicated cyber operations unit focused on defending against cyber threats.</p>
<p>On April 1, 2023, Vars_Secc posted to a public Telegram chat channel a screenshot of the National Security Agency’s website. The image indicated the visitor had just applied for some type of job at the NSA.</p>
<div id="attachment_69656"><p><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69656" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiber-nsa-app.png" alt="" width="710" height="511"></p><p id="caption-attachment-69656">A screenshot posted by Vars_Secc on Telegram on April 1, 2023, suggesting they just applied for a job at the National Security Agency.</p></div>
<p>The NSA has not yet responded to requests for comment.</p>
<p>Reached via Telegram, Kiberphant0m acknowledged that KrebsOnSecurity managed to unearth their old handles.</p>
<p>“I see you found the IP behind it no way,” Kiberphant0m <a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiber-tg-replies.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener">replied</a>. “I see you managed to find my old aliases LOL.”</p>
<p>Kiberphant0m denied being in the U.S. Army or ever being in South Korea, and said all of that was a lengthy ruse designed to create a fictitious persona. “Epic opsec troll,” they claimed.</p>
<p>Asked if they were at all concerned about getting busted, Kiberphant0m called that an impossibility.</p>
<p>“I literally can’t get caught,” Kiberphant0m said, declining an invitation to explain why. “I don’t even live in the USA Mr. Krebs.”</p>
<p>Below is a mind map that hopefully helps illustrate some of the connections between and among Kiberphant0m’s apparent alter egos.</p>
<div id="attachment_69662"><p><a href="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphantom-mm.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><img aria-describedby="caption-attachment-69662" decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphantom-mm.png" alt="" width="1582" height="841" srcset="https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphantom-mm.png 1582w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphantom-mm-768x408.png 768w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphantom-mm-1536x817.png 1536w, https://krebsonsecurity.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/kiberphantom-mm-782x416.png 782w" sizes="(max-width: 1582px) 100vw, 1582px"></a></p><p id="caption-attachment-69662">A mind map of the connections between and among the identities apparently used by Kiberphant0m. Click to enlarge.</p></div>
<p>KrebsOnSecurity would like to extend a special note of thanks to the New York City based security intelligence firm <a href="https://www.unit221b.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unit 221B</a> for their assistance in helping to piece together key elements of Kiberphant0m’s different identities.</p>
											</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Marshall Brain died hours after alleging retaliation at NC State (205 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.technicianonline.com/news/popular-nc-state-professor-marshall-brain-dies-alleges-retaliation-for-ethics-complaints/article_152e5c80-ac2e-11ef-8b3f-036ac3c8d9bf.html</link>
            <guid>42251656</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:31:11 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.technicianonline.com/news/popular-nc-state-professor-marshall-brain-dies-alleges-retaliation-for-ethics-complaints/article_152e5c80-ac2e-11ef-8b3f-036ac3c8d9bf.html">https://www.technicianonline.com/news/popular-nc-state-professor-marshall-brain-dies-alleges-retaliation-for-ethics-complaints/article_152e5c80-ac2e-11ef-8b3f-036ac3c8d9bf.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42251656">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="article-body" itemprop="articleBody" false="">
                                <meta itemprop="isAccessibleForFree" content="true">
                                
                                
                                <p><em>Editor’s Note: This article contains reference to death.</em></p><p>Questions are surrounding the death of a popular NC State faculty member, whom NC State police found dead in his office on Nov. 20.&nbsp;</p><p>Police found Marshall Brain II, director of the Engineering Entrepreneurs Program, unconscious and nonresponsive in his office at Engineering Building II on Centennial Campus at 7:00 a.m.&nbsp;</p>
        <p>NC State Police Public Information Officer Conner Hartis confirmed police found Brain deceased upon their arrival. The Wake County Simulcast showed Brain’s wife called for a welfare check at 6:40 a.m. No cause of death has been released.&nbsp;</p><p>Hours before Brain’s death, he sent an email to colleagues saying two University department heads retaliated against him after he filed several ethics complaints months before his death.&nbsp;</p><p dir="ltr">University spokesperson, Mick Kulikowski, said the University has no comment on the allegations or Brain’s death. The University has also not issued a public statement on Brain’s death.</p><p>Brain graduated from the University with a master’s in computer science in 1992 and worked at the University since 2012. Brain was an author, entrepreneur and founder of the popular website <a href="http://howstuffworks.com/">HowStuffWorks.com</a>. The award-winning faculty member was an influential figure in the world of science and entrepreneurship on and off campus. His classes, which aimed to combine the worlds of engineering and entrepreneurship, were popular.&nbsp;</p><p>The email shared to Technician and posted online on a website dedicated to Brain’s legacy contains allegations of wrongdoing. Brain claims he was forced into retirement as retaliation for submitting numerous ethics complaints.</p><p>Brain wrote in the email that Stephen Markham, executive director of NC State’s Innovation and Entrepreneurship program, announced Brain’s retirement to the Innovation and Entrepreneurship team on Nov. 6, saying the retirement was effective Dec. 31, 2025. Brain was a member of the Innovation and Entrepreneurship Leadership team, alongside Markham.</p><p>Brain wrote that he was not retiring but instead was fired. Markham did not respond to multiple requests for comment in time for publication.&nbsp;</p><p>“I have just been through one of the most demoralizing, depressing, humiliating, unjust processes possible with the University,” Brain wrote. “The fact is that I am not ‘retiring.’ Instead, NC State terminated me on Oct. 29.”</p><p>Brain wrote that after submitting an ethics complaint concerning Veena Misra, head of the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, and bringing his concerns to her directly, Misra retaliated against him.&nbsp;</p><p>Brain’s complaint contained allegations of wrongdoing in the form of “untrue statements, incompetence, hiding info, bad faith dealings and unethical behavior” after a disagreement with Misra in August regarding repurposing the Engineering Entrepreneurs Program meeting space to accommodate a new hire.&nbsp;</p><p>“What came back was a sickening nuclear bomb of retaliation the likes of which could not be believed,” Brain wrote. “[Misra] excommunicated me from my department for reporting my concerns to her.”</p><p>Misra did not respond to Technician’s request for comment. Jim Pfaendtner, dean of the College of Engineering, responded on her behalf and referred Technician to Kulikowski.&nbsp;</p><p>Brain wrote he received an email a few weeks later from Srinath Ekkad, head of the Department of Mechanical and Aerospace Engineering, saying the department would no longer recommend students participate in Brain’s Engineering Entrepreneurs Program.&nbsp;</p>
        <p>Brain wrote that, after outlining his concerns to Ekkad about this message, Markham informed Brain he would be taking disciplinary action against him for “unacceptable behavior.”&nbsp;</p><p>Brandon Kashani, Brain’s former student and a startup mentor at NC State’s entrepreneurship clinic, received Brain’s email along with more than 30 others both within and outside of the University. Kashani said he met with Brain on Nov. 15, where Brain detailed the situation and correspondence with the University. Kashani described Brain as “heartbroken.”&nbsp;</p><p>“He felt like his reputation was tarnished, like everything he worked for was ruined, and the root of all that was he didn't get any support from the University, the University that he put all his life — the last 12 years — towards,” Kashani said. “And all he wanted to do was be heard.”</p><p>Brain wrote in the email that he believed the ethics complaint system’s framework was not properly used in addressing his concerns. The complaints were submitted through EthicsPoint, a reporting tool used by employees to report ethical concerns.&nbsp;</p><p>“My career has been destroyed by multiple administrators at NCSU who united together and completely ignored the EthicsPoint System and its promises to employees,” Brain wrote. “I did what the University told me to do, and then these administrators ruined my life for it.”</p><p>Kashani said Brain submitted numerous complaints through the EthicsPoint system and said tensions arose because Brain didn’t “play the political game” through his questioning of higher-ranking administrators.&nbsp;</p><p>“Marshall was caught in an imbalanced group of people with more power than him, and they didn't like him calling them out,” Kashani said. “... He was keeping people accountable. He didn't understand that political aspect of it, and they just wanted to get rid of him.”&nbsp;</p><p>Kevin Barry, Brain’s former student and a member of the Board of Advisors for NC State’s Innovation and Entrepreneurship Leadership program, said Brain was pivotal in the lives of students in this program and beyond.&nbsp;</p><p>“Marshall was a cornerstone of entrepreneurship at NC State, and a very key person who dedicated himself and was a real entrepreneur, and really dedicated himself to the students,” Barry said. “And he, through and through, down to the bone, had that love and desire to help students. So to see what's going on with him is just absolutely devastating and disgusting.”&nbsp;</p><p dir="ltr">Both Barry and Kashani said they are disappointed in the lack of a public statement from the University surrounding Brain’s death.&nbsp;</p><p dir="ltr">“It's been six days now, which is insane,” Kashani said. “And I know a lot of people are reaching out. There’s a lot of pressure, but there hasn't been any acknowledgement of mistakes that were made, systems that failed, no resignations, not even a call to celebrate Marshall's achievements.”&nbsp;</p><p>While Brain’s University <a href="https://entrepreneurship.ncsu.edu/people/mdbrain-2/">biography</a> remains on the Innovation and Entrepreneurship website, his page on the Computer and Electrical Engineering website <a href="https://ece.ncsu.edu/people/mdbrain/">no longer exists</a>.</p><p dir="ltr">This is a developing story.</p><p dir="ltr"><em>If you or someone you know is having difficulty processing grief or having a mental health emergency, the Counseling Center can be reached 24 hours a day at 919-515-2423. If you are in a crisis situation and need immediate help, please call the National Suicide Prevention Lifeline at 988. In the case of a life-threatening emergency, call 911.</em></p><p dir="ltr"><em>The Counseling Center’s website offers free online screenings, a plethora of self-help resources regarding mental health and wellness concerns and a comprehensive list of campus services available for those who need guidance. To view an exhaustive list, visit <a href="https://wellness.ncsu.edu/resources/">https://wellness.ncsu.edu/resources/</a>.</em></p><p dir="ltr"><em>If you’re seeking professional counseling or other mental health services on campus, visit the Counseling Center’s Getting Started page at <a href="https://counseling.dasa.ncsu.edu/get-started/make-an-appointment/">https://counseling.dasa.ncsu.edu/get-started/make-an-appointment/</a> to complete paperwork, set up an appointment and more.</em></p>
        
                                
                                
                            </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ISPs say their "excellent customer service" is why users don't switch providers (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/11/isps-say-their-excellent-customer-service-is-why-users-dont-switch-providers/</link>
            <guid>42251564</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:14:25 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/11/isps-say-their-excellent-customer-service-is-why-users-dont-switch-providers/">https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/11/isps-say-their-excellent-customer-service-is-why-users-dont-switch-providers/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42251564">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main">
            <article data-id="2063810">
  
  <header>
  <div>
    <div>
      <div>
        <p><span>
    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 40 40"><defs><clipPath id="section-tech-policy_svg__a"><path fill="none" d="M0 0h40v40H0z"></path></clipPath><clipPath id="section-tech-policy_svg__b"><path fill="none" d="M0 0h40v40H0z"></path></clipPath></defs><g clip-path="url(#section-tech-policy_svg__a)"><path fill="currentColor" d="M12.8 0 6.4 6.4 0 12.8l4 1.4L14.2 4z"></path><g clip-path="url(#section-tech-policy_svg__b)"><path fill="currentColor" d="M34.8 31.7c-4.4-10.4-6.1-23.6-6.1-23.6L15.4 5.4l-9.9 10 2.7 13.3s13.2 1.6 23.6 6.1c-.4 1.4 0 2.9 1.1 4 1.4 1.4 3.6 1.6 5.2.6L18.5 19.8c-1.6 1-3.8.8-5.2-.6-1.6-1.6-1.6-4.3 0-5.9s4.3-1.6 5.9 0c1.4 1.4 1.6 3.6.6 5.2L39.3 38c1-1.6.8-3.8-.6-5.2-1.1-1.1-2.6-1.4-4-1.1"></path></g></g></svg>
  </span>
  <span>
    Broadband customer service
  </span>
</p>
      </div>

      

      <p>
        ISPs tell FCC that mistreated users would switch to one of their many other options.
      </p>

      
    </div>

    <div>
    
    <p><span>
          Credit:

          
          Getty Images | Thamrongpat Theerathammakorn

                  </span>
          </p>
  </div>
  </div>
</header>


  

  
      
    
    <div>
                      
                      
          
<p>Lobby groups for Internet service providers claim that ISPs' customer service is so good already that the government shouldn't consider any new regulations to mandate improvements. They also claim ISPs face so much competition that market forces require providers to treat their customers well or lose them to competitors.</p>
<p>Cable lobby group NCTA-The Internet &amp; Television Association told the Federal Communications Commission in a <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/1122573117031/1">filing</a> that "providing high-quality products and services and a positive customer experience is a competitive necessity in today's robust communications marketplace. To attract and retain customers, NCTA's cable operator members continuously strive to ensure that the customer support they provide is effective and user-friendly. Given these strong marketplace imperatives, new regulations that would micromanage providers’ customer service operations are unnecessary."</p>
<p>Lobby groups filed comments in response to an FCC review of customer service that was <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/document/fcc-review-customer-support-offered-consumers">announced last month</a>, before the presidential election. While the FCC's current Democratic leadership is interested in regulating customer service practices, the Republicans who will soon take over opposed the inquiry.</p>
<p>USTelecom, which represents telcos such as AT&amp;T and Verizon, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/1122191898118/1">said</a> that "the competitive broadband marketplace leaves providers of broadband and other communications services no choice but to provide their customers with not only high-quality broadband, but also high-quality customer service."</p>
<p>"If a provider fails to efficiently resolve an issue, they risk losing not only that customer—and not just for the one service, but potentially for all of the bundled services offered to that customer—but also any prospective customers that come across a negative review online. Because of this, broadband providers know that their success is dependent upon providing and maintaining excellent customer service," USTelecom wrote.</p>

          
                      
                  </div>
                    
        
          
    
    <div>
          
          
<p>While the FCC Notice of Inquiry said that providers should "offer live customer service representative support by phone within a reasonable timeframe," USTelecom's filing touted the customer service abilities of AI chatbots. "AI chat agents will only get better at addressing customers' needs more quickly over time—and if providers fail to provide the customer service and engagement options that their customers expect and fail to resolve their customers' concerns, they may soon find that the consumer is no longer a customer, having switched to another competitive offering," the lobby group said.</p>
<h2>Say what?</h2>
<p>The lobby groups' description may surprise the many Internet users suffering from little competition and poor customer service, such as CenturyLink users who had to <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/05/centurylink-left-users-with-no-service-for-two-months-then-billed-them-239/">go without service</a> for <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/02/centurylink-left-customers-without-internet-for-39-days-until-ars-stepped-in/">over a month</a> because of the ISP's failure to fix outages. The FCC received very different takes on the state of ISP customer service from regulators in California and Oregon.</p>
<p>The Mt. Hood Cable Regulatory Commission in northwest Oregon, where Comcast is the dominant provider, <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/1121865526241/1">told the FCC</a> that local residents complain about automated customer service representatives; spending hours on hold while attempting to navigate automated voice systems; billing problems including "getting charged after cancelling service, unexpected price increases, and being charged for equipment that was returned," and service not being restored quickly after outages.</p>
<p>The California Public Utilities Commission (CPUC) <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/112272893230/1">told the FCC</a> that it performed a recent analysis finding "that only a fraction of California households enjoy access to a highly competitive market for [broadband Internet service], with only 26 percent of households having a choice between two or more broadband providers utilizing either cable modem or fiber optic technologies." The California agency said the result "suggests that competitive forces alone are insufficient to guarantee service quality for customers who depend upon these services."</p>

          
                  </div>
                    
        
          
    
    <div>
          
          
<p>CPUC said its current rulemaking efforts for California "will establish standards for service outages, repair response time, and access to live representatives." The agency told the FCC that if it adopts new customer service rules for the whole US, it should "permit state and local governments to set customer service standards that exceed the adopted standards."</p>

<h2>People with disabilities need more help, groups say</h2>
<p>The FCC also received a <a href="https://www.fcc.gov/ecfs/document/11221938607468/1">filing</a> from several advocacy groups focused on accessibility for people with disabilities. The groups asked for rules "establishing baseline standards to ensure high-quality DVC [direct video calling for American Sign Language users] across providers, requiring accommodations for consumers returning rental equipment, and ensuring accessible cancellation processes." The groups said that "providers should be required to maintain dedicated, well-trained accessibility teams that are easily reachable via accessible communication channels, including ASL support."</p>
<p>"We strongly caution against relying solely on emerging AI technologies without mandating live customer service support," the groups said.</p>
<p>The FCC's <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/FCC-24-110A1.pdf">Notice of Inquiry</a> on customer service was approved 3–2 in a party-line vote on October 10. FCC Chairwoman Jessica Rosenworcel <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/FCC-24-110A2.pdf">said</a> that hundreds of thousands of customers file complaints each year "because they have run into issues cancelling their service, are saddled with unexpected charges, are upset by unexplained outages, and are frustrated with billing issues they have not been able to resolve on their own. Many describe being stuck in 'doom loops' that make it difficult to get a real person on the line to help with service that needs repair or to address charges they believe are a mistake."</p>

          
                  </div>
                    
        
          
    
    <div>

        
        <div>
          
          
<p>If the FCC leadership wasn't changing hands, the Notice of Inquiry could be the first step toward a rulemaking. "We cannot ignore these complaints, especially not when we know that it is possible to do better... We want to help improve the customer experience, understand what tools we have to do so, and what gaps there may be in the law that prevent consumers from having the ability to resolve routine problems quickly, simply, and easily," Rosenworcel said.</p>
<h2>ISPs have a friend in Trump admin</h2>
<p>But the proceeding won't go any further under incoming Chairman Brendan Carr, a Republican chosen by President-elect Donald Trump. Carr <a href="https://docs.fcc.gov/public/attachments/FCC-24-110A3.pdf">dissented</a> from the Notice of Inquiry, saying that the potential actions explored by the FCC exceed its authority and that the topic should be handled instead by the Federal Trade Commission.</p>
<p>Carr said the FCC should work instead on "freeing up spectrum and eliminating regulatory barriers to deployment" and that the Notice of Inquiry is part of "the Biden-Harris Administration's efforts to deflect attention away from the necessary course correction."</p>
<p>Carr has made it clear that he is <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/11/trumps-fcc-chair-is-brendan-carr-who-wants-to-regulate-everyone-except-isps/">interested in regulating</a> broadcast media and social networks more than the telecom companies the FCC traditionally focuses on. Carr wrote a chapter for the conservative Heritage Foundation's Project 2025 in which he <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/11/trumps-likely-fcc-chair-wrote-project-2025-chapter-on-how-hed-run-the-agency/">criticized the FCC</a> for "impos[ing] heavy-handed regulation rather than relying on competition and market forces to produce optimal outcomes."</p>
<p>With Carr at the helm, ISPs are likely to get what they're asking for: No new regulations and elimination of at least some current rules. "Rather than saddling communications providers with unnecessary, unlawful, and potentially harmful regulation, the Commission should encourage the pro-consumer benefits of competition by reducing the regulatory burdens and disparities that are currently unfairly skewing the marketplace," the NCTA told the FCC, arguing that cable companies face more onerous regulations than other communications providers.</p>


          
                  </div>

                  
          






  <div>
  <div>
          <p><a href="https://arstechnica.com/author/jon-brodkin/"><img src="https://arstechnica.com/wp-content/uploads/2016/05/j.brodkin-11_2.jpg" alt="Photo of Jon Brodkin"></a></p>
  </div>

  <div>
    

    <p>
      Jon is a Senior IT Reporter for Ars Technica. He covers the telecom industry, Federal Communications Commission rulemakings, broadband consumer affairs, court cases, and government regulation of the tech industry.
    </p>
  </div>
</div>


  <p>
    <a href="https://arstechnica.com/tech-policy/2024/11/isps-say-their-excellent-customer-service-is-why-users-dont-switch-providers/#comments" title="144 comments">
    <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 80 80"><defs><clipPath id="bubble-zero_svg__a"><path fill="none" stroke-width="0" d="M0 0h80v80H0z"></path></clipPath><clipPath id="bubble-zero_svg__b"><path fill="none" stroke-width="0" d="M0 0h80v80H0z"></path></clipPath></defs><g clip-path="url(#bubble-zero_svg__a)"><g fill="currentColor" clip-path="url(#bubble-zero_svg__b)"><path d="M80 40c0 22.09-17.91 40-40 40S0 62.09 0 40 17.91 0 40 0s40 17.91 40 40"></path><path d="M40 40 .59 76.58C-.67 77.84.22 80 2.01 80H40z"></path></g></g></svg>
    144 Comments
  </a>
      </p>





  
              </div>
  </article>


  <div>
    <header>
      <svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" viewBox="0 0 40 26"><defs><clipPath id="most-read_svg__a"><path fill="none" d="M0 0h40v26H0z"></path></clipPath><clipPath id="most-read_svg__b"><path fill="none" d="M0 0h40v26H0z"></path></clipPath></defs><g clip-path="url(#most-read_svg__a)"><g fill="none" clip-path="url(#most-read_svg__b)"><path fill="currentColor" d="M20 2h.8q1.5 0 3 .6c.6.2 1.1.4 1.7.6 1.3.5 2.6 1.3 3.9 2.1.6.4 1.2.8 1.8 1.3 2.9 2.3 5.1 4.9 6.3 6.4-1.1 1.5-3.4 4-6.3 6.4-.6.5-1.2.9-1.8 1.3q-1.95 1.35-3.9 2.1c-.6.2-1.1.4-1.7.6q-1.5.45-3 .6h-1.6q-1.5 0-3-.6c-.6-.2-1.1-.4-1.7-.6-1.3-.5-2.6-1.3-3.9-2.1-.6-.4-1.2-.8-1.8-1.3-2.9-2.3-5.1-4.9-6.3-6.4 1.1-1.5 3.4-4 6.3-6.4.6-.5 1.2-.9 1.8-1.3q1.95-1.35 3.9-2.1c.6-.2 1.1-.4 1.7-.6q1.5-.45 3-.6zm0-2h-1c-1.2 0-2.3.3-3.4.6-.6.2-1.3.4-1.9.7-1.5.6-2.9 1.4-4.3 2.3-.7.5-1.3.9-1.9 1.4C2.9 8.7 0 13 0 13s2.9 4.3 7.5 7.9c.6.5 1.3 1 1.9 1.4 1.3.9 2.7 1.7 4.3 2.3.6.3 1.3.5 1.9.7 1.1.3 2.3.6 3.4.6h2c1.2 0 2.3-.3 3.4-.6.6-.2 1.3-.4 1.9-.7 1.5-.6 2.9-1.4 4.3-2.3.7-.5 1.3-.9 1.9-1.4C37.1 17.3 40 13 40 13s-2.9-4.3-7.5-7.9c-.6-.5-1.3-1-1.9-1.4-1.3-.9-2.8-1.7-4.3-2.3-.6-.3-1.3-.5-1.9-.7C23.3.4 22.1.1 21 .1h-1"></path><path fill="#ff4e00" d="M20 5c-4.4 0-8 3.6-8 8s3.6 8 8 8 8-3.6 8-8-3.6-8-8-8m0 11c-1.7 0-3-1.3-3-3s1.3-3 3-3 3 1.3 3 3-1.3 3-3 3"></path></g></g></svg>
      
    </header>
    <ol>
              <li>
                      <a href="https://arstechnica.com/space/2024/11/after-russian-ship-docks-to-space-station-astronauts-report-a-foul-smell/">
              <img src="https://cdn.arstechnica.net/wp-content/uploads/2023/02/52674646862_dbe4378754_k-768x432.jpg" alt="Listing image for first story in Most Read: After Russian ship docks to space station, astronauts report a foul smell" decoding="async" loading="lazy">
            </a>
                    
        </li>
                    <li>
                    
        </li>
                    <li>
                    
        </li>
                    <li>
                    
        </li>
                    <li>
                    
        </li>
                  </ol>
</div>


  

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[D-Link says it won't patch 60k older modems (241 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-says-it-wont-patch-60-000-older-modems-as-theyre-not-worth-saving</link>
            <guid>42249790</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 20:36:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-says-it-wont-patch-60-000-older-modems-as-theyre-not-worth-saving">https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-says-it-wont-patch-60-000-older-modems-as-theyre-not-worth-saving</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42249790">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">

<section>
<div itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div>
<picture data-new-v2-image="true">
<source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-1280-80.jpg.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)">
<img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-320-80.jpg" alt="" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ-1280-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ.jpg" data-pin-nopin="true" fetchpriority="high" crossorigin="anonymous">
</picture>
</div>
<meta itemprop="url" content="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/2qPQvs878xeAQsyMejbEPJ.jpg">
<meta itemprop="height" content="600">
<meta itemprop="width" content="338">
<figcaption itemprop="caption description">
<span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Future)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div id="article-body">
<hr><ul><li><strong>Security researchers find critical flaws in modems reaching End of Life</strong></li><li><strong>D-Link says it won't patch them, and recommends upgrading the hardware</strong></li><li><strong>There are some 60,000 vulnerable devices out there</strong></li></ul><hr><p>Older D-Link routers are potentially vulnerable to more than one critical security issue which could allow threat actors to take over the devices. However, since they have reached end-of-life status (EoL), the company says it will not be releasing any patches, and advises users to replace the endpoints with newer models.</p><p>The news comes shortly after we reported multiple <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-says-it-wont-fix-a-serious-security-flaw-affecting-60-000-older-nas-devices" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-says-it-wont-fix-a-serious-security-flaw-affecting-60-000-older-nas-devices">D-Link NAS</a> endpoints were found vulnerable to CVE-2024-10914, a command injection flaw with a 9.2 severity score - however the company again said it wouldn’t be issuing a fix, since the affected devices have all reached EoL.</p><p>Now, security researcher Chaio-Lin Yu (Steven Meow) found three bugs plaguing the D-Link DSL6740C modem. One is tracked as CVE-2024-11068, has a severity score of 9.8, and allows threat actors to change passwords through privileged API access. The other two are CVE-2024-11067, and CVE-2024-11066, and are a path traversal flaw and a remote code execution (RCE) flaw, with 7.5 and 7.2 scores, respectively.</p><h2 id="tens-of-thousands-of-vulnerable-endpoints-3">Tens of thousands of vulnerable endpoints</h2><p>Roughly 60,000 vulnerable devices are currently connected to the internet, the majority being located in Taiwan. The model isn’t even available in the US, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/d-link-wont-fix-critical-bug-in-60-000-exposed-eol-modems/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/d-link-wont-fix-critical-bug-in-60-000-exposed-eol-modems/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none"><em>BleepingComputer</em></a> states, since it reached EoL almost a year ago. With that in mind, D-Link said it wouldn’t be addressing the flaw, and suggests "retiring and replacing D-Link devices that have reached EOL/EOS."</p><p>The same model is also vulnerable to four additional high-severity command injection flaws, the publication states, citing information from the Taiwanese computer and response center (TWCERTCC). These flaws are tracked as CVE-2024-11062, CVE-2024-11063, CVE-2024-11064, and CVE-2024-11065.</p><p>Users who are unable to replace their routers at the moment are advised to at least restrict remote access, and set secure access passwords, to minimize the chance of compromise. This would be a wise move since routers are one of the most targeted endpoints out there.<a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/d-link-wont-fix-critical-bug-in-60-000-exposed-eol-modems/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.bleepingcomputer.com/news/security/d-link-wont-fix-critical-bug-in-60-000-exposed-eol-modems/" referrerpolicy="no-referrer-when-downgrade" data-hl-processed="none"><em></em></a></p><h3 id="section-you-might-also-like"><span>You might also like</span></h3><ul><li><a href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-routers-are-being-hacked-to-steal-customer-passwords-but-it-says-there-is-no-patch" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/pro/security/d-link-routers-are-being-hacked-to-steal-customer-passwords-but-it-says-there-is-no-patch">D-Link routers are being hacked to steal customer passwords — but it says there is no patch</a><a href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/snowflake-hacker-arrested-over-data-breach-and-extortion" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/pro/snowflake-hacker-arrested-over-data-breach-and-extortion"></a><a href="https://www.techradar.com/pro/amazon-confirms-employee-data-stolen-after-third-party-moveit-breach" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/pro/amazon-confirms-employee-data-stolen-after-third-party-moveit-breach"></a></li><li>Here's a list of the <a href="https://www.techradar.com/best/firewall" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/best/firewall">best firewalls</a> today</li><li>These are the <a href="https://www.techradar.com/news/best-endpoint-security-software" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.techradar.com/news/best-endpoint-security-software">best endpoint protection tools</a> right now</li></ul><div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-QpX6k48RS2gpEhPsQJjFML"><section><p>Sign up to the TechRadar Pro newsletter to get all the top news, opinion, features and guidance your business needs to succeed!</p></section></div>
</div>

<div id="slice-container-authorBio-QpX6k48RS2gpEhPsQJjFML"><p>Sead is a seasoned freelance journalist based in Sarajevo, Bosnia and Herzegovina. He writes about IT (cloud, IoT, 5G, VPN) and cybersecurity (ransomware, data breaches, laws and regulations). In his career, spanning more than a decade, he’s written for numerous media outlets, including Al Jazeera Balkans. He’s also held several modules on content writing for Represent Communications.</p></div>
</section>




<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h5>Most Popular</h5></p></div>








</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ZetaOffice: LibreOffice in the Browser (256 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://zetaoffice.net/</link>
            <guid>42249746</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 20:32:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://zetaoffice.net/">https://zetaoffice.net/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42249746">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

    <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100" id="home">
            <h2>LibreOffice in your browser</h2>
            <p>Work from any device, maintain control over your data with self-hosting<br>or our CDN, and enjoy seamless integration with your existing systems.</p>
            <div>
              <p><a href="#tryit">Try it out</a>
              <a href="#contact">Subscribe to Newsletter</a>
            </p></div>
          </div>

    <div id="customers" data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100">

        <p>
          <h2>Trusted by</h2>
        </p>
      </div>

    <div data-aos="fade-up" id="product">
        <p>
          <h2><span>Why choose</span> <span>ZetaOffice Web</span>?</h2>
        </p>

        <div>

          <div>
              
              <h3>Access from any device</h3>
              <p>ZetaOffice Web brings LibreOffice to your browser, so you can access your documents from any device easily.</p>
            </div><!-- End Service Item -->

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">
              
              <h3>No vendor lock-in</h3>
              <p>ZetaOffice Web gives you full control over your data without relying on third-party clouds.</p>
            </div><!-- End Service Item -->

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="300">
              
              <h3>Customizable Integration</h3>
              <p>ZetaOffice Web integrates with your systems, and its API lets you tailor it to your workflows.</p>
            </div><!-- End Service Item -->

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="400">
              
              <h3>Self-Hosted or CDN</h3>
              <p>ZetaOffice Web lets you self-host or use our CDN for faster global access, allowing you to choose the deployment that suits your needs.</p>
            </div><!-- End Service Item -->

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="500">
              
              <h3>Built on LibreOffice</h3>
              <p>ZetaOffice Web, based on LibreOffice, is fully compatible with existing documents, enabling easy transition.</p>
            </div><!-- End Service Item -->

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="600">
              
              <h3>Optimized Performance</h3>
              <p>Optimized for browser performance, ensuring a responsive experience while efficiently handling complex and large files.</p>
            </div><!-- End Service Item -->

        </div>

      </div>

    <section id="features">

      <!-- Section Title -->
      <div data-aos="fade-up">

        <p>
          <h2><span>ZetaOffice</span> <span>Suite</span></h2>
        </p>
      </div><!-- End Section Title -->

      <div>

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">
              <p><img src="https://zetaoffice.net/assets/img/writer.png" alt=""></p><h3>Writer</h3>
              <p>Comprehensive word processing with formatting and styling options</p>
            </div>

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">
              <p><img src="https://zetaoffice.net/assets/img/calc.png" alt=""></p><h3>Calc</h3>
              <p>Advanced spreadsheets with data analysis and charting tools</p>
            </div>

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">
              <p><img src="https://zetaoffice.net/assets/img/impress.png" alt=""></p><h3>Impress</h3>
              <p>Powerful multimedia presentations with various templates and transitions</p>
            </div>

        </div>

    </section>

    <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200" id="tryit">
                  <h3>Try it out yourself</h3>
                  <p>Check out our demos now so you can see if ZetaOffice Web suits your needs.</p>
                </div>

    <div id="download">

        <p>
          <h2>ZetaOffice <span>for Desktop</span></h2>
        </p>

        <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100">
            <p>
              ZetaOffice is also available as a native Desktop application for Linux and Windows. Download the Beta here.
            </p>

            <div>
              <div>
                <h3>Linux</h3>
                
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3>Windows</h3>
                
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

            </div>
          </div>

      </div>

    <div id="faq">
        <p>
          <h2>Frequently Asked Questions</h2>
        </p>

        <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="200">
              <div>
                <h3><span>1.</span> <span>What is ZetaOffice?</span></h3>
                <p>ZetaOffice is a robust office suite built on the powerful LibreOffice foundation.
                    ZetaOffice provides familiar functionalities with additional benefits like extended security updates.
                    ZetaOffice is available for the web, desktop and mobile devices (coming soon).</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3><span>2.</span> <span>Is ZetaOffice free?</span></h3>
                <p>ZetaOffice is open source software based on the powerful LibreOffice suite.
                    We offer paid packages that include the use of our high performance CDN and professional support options for your company.
                    Our ZetaOffice services are currently in an open beta program. Sign up for our newsletter to find out more as soon as there is news about our packages.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3><span>3.</span> <span>Can I integrate ZetaOffice with my existing solutions?</span></h3>
                <p>
                    Yes, ZetaOffice offers full compatibility with the LibreOffice UNO API, allowing seamless integration into your current workflows or applications.
                    This flexibility enables you to leverage the powerful features of ZetaOffice while maintaining your preferred ecosystem, enhancing productivity and user experience.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3><span>4.</span> <span>Is it possible to self-host ZetaOffice, or do I have to use the CDN?</span></h3>
                <p>Both options are possible. Check out our <a href="https://zetaoffice.net/demo.html">Demo</a> for examples of using the CDN.
                    For more information about self-hosting, please see the <a href="#contact">Contact</a> section below.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

              <div>
                <h3><span>5.</span> <span>Does ZetaOffice require any special browser or system requirements?</span></h3>
                <p>ZetaOffice Web is designed to function efficiently in most modern web browsers.
                    While specific performance may vary depending on the browser or device capabilities, there are generally no strict requirements.
                    As long as your browser supports HTML5 and a stable internet connection is available, you should be able to use ZetaOffice without any issues.</p>
                </div><!-- End Faq item-->

            </div>

      </div>

    <div id="about">

        <div>
          <p>We are allotropia</p>
          <h2>Empowering businesses with LibreOffice</h2>
        </div>

        <div>

          <div data-aos="fade-up" data-aos-delay="100">
            <p>
              Allotropia offers services and products to enhance LibreOffice.
              Our experts help organizations integrate it effectively, saving costs and improving efficiency.
            </p>
            <ul>
              <li><i></i> <span>Dedicated team of certified LibreOffice developers</span></li>
              <li><i></i> <span>Professional services focused on LibreOffice</span></li>
              <li><i></i> <span>Pioneering native browser integration for LibreOffice</span></li>
            </ul>
            <p><a href="https://www.allotropia.de/" target="_blank"><span>Who we are</span></a>
          </p></div>

          <p><img src="https://zetaoffice.net/assets/img/about-company-2.jpg" alt="">
          </p>

        </div>

      </div>

    <section id="contact">

      <!-- Section Title -->
      <p data-aos="fade-up">
        <h2>Contact us</h2>
      </p><!-- End Section Title -->

      <div data-aos="fade" data-aos-delay="100">
                <h3>Our office</h3>
                <p>Versmannstr. 4, 20457 Hamburg, Germany</p>
              </div>

    </section>

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Yes, it ‘looks like a duck,’ but carriers like the new USPS mail truck (124 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/26/us/usps-new-mail-trucks.html</link>
            <guid>42249545</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 20:13:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/26/us/usps-new-mail-trucks.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/26/us/usps-new-mail-trucks.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42249545">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2024/11/26/us/usps-new-mail-trucks.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[GenChess (254 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://labs.google/genchess</link>
            <guid>42248630</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 18:47:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://labs.google/genchess">https://labs.google/genchess</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42248630">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p>Loading...</p><div><p>AI outputs may sometimes be offensive or inaccurate.</p><div><p><a target="_blank" href="https://policies.google.com/privacy">Privacy</a><a target="_blank" href="https://policies.google.com/terms">Terms of Service</a></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Teen mathematicians tie knots through a mind-blowing fractal (297 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.quantamagazine.org/teen-mathematicians-tie-knots-through-a-mind-blowing-fractal-20241126/</link>
            <guid>42248584</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 18:43:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.quantamagazine.org/teen-mathematicians-tie-knots-through-a-mind-blowing-fractal-20241126/">https://www.quantamagazine.org/teen-mathematicians-tie-knots-through-a-mind-blowing-fractal-20241126/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42248584">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="postBody">
                <div>
        <p>
            Three high schoolers and their mentor revisited a century-old theorem to prove that all knots can be found in a fractal called the Menger sponge.        </p>
        
    </div>
<figure>
    
</figure>
<div>
            <h2>Introduction</h2>
            <div data-role="selectable">
    <p>In the fall of 2021, <a href="https://malors.com/">Malors Espinosa</a> set out to devise a special type of math problem. As with any good research question, it would have to be thought-provoking, its solution nontrivial — something others would want to study. But an additional constraint stumped him. Malors, then a graduate student in mathematics at the University of Toronto, wanted high school students to be able to prove it.</p>
<p>For years, Malors had been running summer workshops for local high schoolers, teaching them about basic ideas in mathematical research and showing them how to write proofs. But a few of his students seemed ready to do more — to find out what it means to do math when there is no answer key. They just needed the right question to guide them.</p>
<p>Malors finally found one while reading a textbook about chaos. In its pages, he came across a familiar object: a fractal, or self-similar shape, called the Menger sponge, which has a simple but elegant construction. First divide a cube into what looks like a Rubik’s cube. Remove the cube in the very center, along with the center cube of each of the six faces. Then repeat this process for each of the 20 remaining cubes. And repeat. And repeat. You’ll quickly see why the resulting fractal is called a sponge: With each iteration, its pores multiply exponentially.</p>
</div>
    </div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-08.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig1-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
            <p>Mark Belan/<em>Quanta Magazine</em></p>
        </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Ever since Karl Menger introduced his fractal sponge nearly a century ago, it has captured the imaginations of professional and amateur mathematicians alike. One reason: It looks cool. In 2014, hundreds of math enthusiasts participated in a global effort, called MegaMenger, to build finite, 200-pound versions of the sponge out of business cards. Because of its porous, foam-like structure, the sponge has also been used to model shock absorbers and exotic forms of space-time.</p>
<p>But most important, the fractal possesses various counterintuitive mathematical properties. Continue to pluck out ever smaller pieces, and what started off as a cube becomes something else entirely. After infinitely many iterations, the shape’s volume dwindles to zero, while its surface area grows infinitely large. Such is the weirdness of fractals: hovering somewhere between dimensions, occupying space without truly filling it.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img width="2560" height="1089" src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-scaled.webp" alt="A triptych of three teen students, one cutting yarn with their professor" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-scaled.webp 2560w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-1720x732.webp 1720w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-520x221.webp 520w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-768x327.webp 768w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-1536x654.webp 1536w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/NazarethMalorsVothBroden-Triptych-v3-2048x871.webp 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 2560px) 100vw, 2560px">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>Three high school students — Niko Voth (top right), Joshua Broden (bottom right) and Noah Nazareth (far left) — recently proved a new theorem about knots and fractals with the help of their mentor Malors, a mathematician at the University of Toronto.</p>
            <p>Clockwise from left: Somja Injac, Christian Voth and Timur Khayrullin</p>
        </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>When he first defined his sponge in 1926, Menger also proved that any conceivable curve — simple lines and circles, structures that look like trees or snowflakes, fractal dusts — can be deformed and then embedded somewhere on the sponge. They can be made to wind their way along the sponge’s convoluted contours without ever leaving its surface, hitting a hole, or intersecting themselves. The sponge, Menger wrote, was therefore a “universal curve.”</p>
<p>But this, Malors later realized, raised a new question. Menger had proved that you could find a circle in his sponge. But what about objects that were equivalent, in a certain sense, to the circle? Consider a mathematical knot: a string that’s been twisted and tied up, its ends then closed to form a loop. From the outside, it might look like a tangled mess. But an ant walking along it would eventually find itself back where it started, just as it would on a circle. In this way, every knot is equivalent, or “homeomorphic,” to a circle.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-09-1.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig2-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v1-1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    <div>
                            <p>Every knot is “homeomorphic” to the circle, meaning that it’s possible to map the points from one to the other while satisfying a simple set of conditions.</p>
                    </div>
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Menger’s statement didn’t distinguish between homeomorphic curves. His proof only guaranteed, for instance, that the circle could be found in his sponge — not that all homeomorphic knots could be, their loops and tangles still intact. Malors wanted to prove that you could find every knot within the sponge.</p>
<p>It seemed like the right mashup to excite young mathematicians. They’d recently had fun learning about knots in his seminar. And who doesn’t love a fractal? The question was whether the problem would be approachable. “I really hoped there was an answer,” Malors said.</p>
<p>There was. After just a few months of weekly Zoom meetings with Malors, three of his high school students — Joshua Broden, Noah Nazareth and Niko Voth — were able to show that <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03639">all knots can indeed be found inside the Menger sponge</a>. Moreover, they found that the same can likely be said of another related fractal, too.</p>
<p>“It’s a clever way of putting things together,” said <a href="https://sazdanovic.wordpress.ncsu.edu/">Radmila Sazdanovic<span>,</span></a> a topologist at North Carolina State University who was not involved in the work. In revisiting Menger’s century-old theorem, she added, Malors — who usually does research in the disparate field of number theory — had apparently asked a question that no one thought to ask before. “This is a very, very original idea,” she said.</p>
<h2><strong>A Different Way to See Knots</strong></h2>
<p>Broden, Nazareth and Voth had taken several of Malors’ summer workshops over the years. When he first taught them about knots in an earlier workshop, “it blew 14-year-old me’s mind,” said Voth.</p>
<p>But the Menger problem would be their first time moving beyond school workbooks with answer keys. “It was a little bit nerve-racking, because it was the first time I was doing something where truly nobody has the answer, not even Malors,” said Nazareth. Maybe there was no answer at all.</p>
<p>Their goal was essentially to thread a microscopic sewing needle through a cloud of dust — the material that remained of the sponge after many removals. They would have to stick the pin in the right places, tie the knotted tangles with immaculate precision, and never leave the sponge. If their thread ended up floating in the empty holes of the sponge for any knot, it was game over.</p>
<p>Not an easy task. But there was a way to simplify it. Knots can be depicted on a flat piece of paper as special diagrams called arc presentations. To create one, you start with information about how the strands of your knot pass in front of or behind each other. Then you apply a set of rules to translate this information into a series of points on a grid. Every row and column of the grid will contain exactly two points.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-10.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig3-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
            <p>Connect these points with horizontal and vertical lines. Any time two segments cross paths, draw the vertical one in front of the horizontal one.</p>
        </div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-11.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig4-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>Every knot can be represented in this gridlike way. Even though an arc presentation can sometimes look more complicated than other ways of drawing the knot, it makes it easier for mathematicians to study some of the knot’s most important properties.</p>
<p>When the students considered the diagrams of crisscrossing lines, they were reminded of the faces of the Menger sponge. It would be straightforward enough to place the horizontal lines of an arc presentation on one face of the sponge and the vertical lines on its opposite face. The difficulty would be in figuring out how to connect the knot — how to stretch it back into three dimensions. At every one of the arc presentation’s corners, the two faces would need to be connected through the interior of the sponge without accidentally hitting a hole.</p>
<p>To make sure that this was always possible, the mathematicians turned to what’s known as the Cantor set, a one-dimensional analog of the Menger sponge. To construct the set, start with a line segment and divide it into thirds. Remove the middle third, then do the same to the remaining two segments, and so on, ad infinitum. You’ll be left with a scattering of points.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-12.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig5-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>The team considered both a Menger sponge and a Cantor set that have undergone the same number of removal steps. At points on the sponge’s faces whose coordinates are both in the Cantor set, they realized, there shouldn’t be a hole. What’s more, there shouldn’t be holes anywhere directly behind those points either, thanks to the sponge’s repetitive design. A knot would therefore be free and clear to pass through without accidentally jumping off the material of the sponge.</p>
<p>All that was left, then, was for the students to show that they could always compress or stretch a given knot’s arc presentation so that all of its corners would line up with coordinates in the Cantor set. (Such compressing and stretching was allowed because it wouldn’t affect the arc presentation’s overall structure and, therefore, what knot it represents.)</p>
<p>To complete this final step, Broden, Nazareth and Voth took a shortcut. They proved that they could deform any arc presentation so that the points where its vertical and horizontal segments crossed were in the Cantor set. This automatically guaranteed that the larger number of corners would line up with the Cantor set, too. In other words, they could always embed a given knot in some iteration of the Menger sponge.</p>
</div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-13.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig6-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-06.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
            <p>Now that they’d answered Malors’ original question, they wanted to push their result further. They’d already started to investigate whether all knots could also be embedded in a tetrahedral version of the Menger sponge:</p>
        </div>
    <figure>
        <div>
                            <p><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v2-14-1.svg" alt="" decoding="async"><img src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Knots_in_Fractals-Fig7-crMarkBelan-Desktop-v1-1.svg" alt="" decoding="async">                </p>
                        </div>
        <figcaption>
    
</figcaption>
    </figure>
<div data-role="selectable">
    <p>“It was surprisingly annoying,” Broden said. Without the convenience of faces aligned directly opposite one another, their method for pushing knots through the fractal would no longer work.</p>
<h2><strong>Measured by Knots</strong></h2>
<p>It was at this stage, according to Malors, that the students learned the pain of math research — that a large part of the discipline involves struggling with the failure of a promising avenue of attack. “We’re facing math, and math has no mercy,” he said. “With math as presented to high schoolers, they’re usually protected from that.”</p>
<p>Malors, for his part, was convinced that a so-called trefoil knot couldn’t be found in the tetrahedron. During a Zoom call, the three students pushed back. They left the meeting, they recalled, feeling dispirited and frustrated. But they decided to stick to their instincts. A couple weeks later, to Malors’ surprise, they returned with a result: They had figured out a new way to map the trefoil knot’s arc presentation into the tetrahedron. They later proved that this could be done for all “pretzel” knots, the more general class of knots that the trefoil belongs to — although the question remains open for other kinds of knots.</p>
        
        
<p>Malors conjectures that the students’ methods might offer a way to measure the complexity of fractals more broadly. Not all fractals are guaranteed to admit all kinds of knots. Perhaps their structure can be better understood based on what types of knots they can and cannot hold.</p>
<p>At the very least, the work could inspire new art, akin to the 2014 MegaMenger contest. “It would be lovely to see this constructed out of physical materials,” said <a href="https://people.vcu.edu/~moorea14/">Allison Moore</a>, a knot theorist at Virginia Commonwealth University.</p>
<p>In the meantime, Broden, Nazareth and Voth have all graduated high school. Only Broden has decided to continue working on the tetrahedron problem — when he’s not busy with college coursework — but all three are considering math careers. “It feels meaningful that I’m trying to contribute to something bigger than myself, to the nature of truth,” Nazareth said. It all starts with asking the right question.</p>
</div>
                
                
            </div><div>
        <div data-name="next-post__image-wrapper">
    <p><img width="1720" height="728" src="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Distributed-Computing_crCarlos-Arrojo-HP-2048-1720x728.webp" alt="A man typing surrounded by interconnected computers" decoding="async" srcset="https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Distributed-Computing_crCarlos-Arrojo-HP-2048-1720x728.webp 1720w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Distributed-Computing_crCarlos-Arrojo-HP-2048-520x220.webp 520w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Distributed-Computing_crCarlos-Arrojo-HP-2048-768x325.webp 768w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Distributed-Computing_crCarlos-Arrojo-HP-2048-1536x650.webp 1536w, https://www.quantamagazine.org/wp-content/uploads/2024/11/Distributed-Computing_crCarlos-Arrojo-HP-2048.webp 2048w" sizes="(max-width: 1720px) 100vw, 1720px">    </p>
</div>
        
        <div>
                <h2>Next article</h2>
                <p>What Is Distributed Computing?</p>
            </div>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The industry structure of LLM makers (139 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://calpaterson.com/porter.html</link>
            <guid>42248496</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 26 Nov 2024 18:35:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://calpaterson.com/porter.html">https://calpaterson.com/porter.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=42248496">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
          
    <article>
        
        <p><time datetime="2024-11-26T00:00:00Z">November 2024</time></p>
        <p id="article-description">The Netscapes of AI</p>
        
        
<figure>
    
  <picture>
    
      
    

    
      <source srcset="https://calpaterson.com/images/photo/watford.avif" type="image/avif">
      <source srcset="https://calpaterson.com/images/photo/watford.webp" type="image/webp">
    
    <img src="https://calpaterson.com/images/photo/watford.jpeg" alt="image of early 20th century train advert for Watford" height="600" width="800">
  </picture>

    <figcaption>Railways improved the lives of millions - but investors were
    rewarded with a
    <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Railway_Mania">dramatic bust</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Large language models (LLMs) like Chat-GPT and Claude.ai are whizzy and cool.
A lot of people think that they are going to be The Future.  Maybe they are —
but that doesn't mean that building them is going to be a profitable business.</p>
<!-- This is the tricky bit about technologies.  Just because your technology gets -->

<!-- adopted, it does not folllow that you make much money.  Web browsers have -->

<!-- nearer 100% adoption than probably any piece of software around.  They are also -->

<!-- genuinely hard to make.  So they must be pretty profitable, right?  No - they -->

<!-- are a huge money loser.  The web browser business is so bad that few would even -->

<!-- count it as a business at all. -->

<p>In the 1960s, airlines were The Future.  That is why old films have so many
swish shots of airports in them.  Airlines though, turned out to be an
unavoidably rubbish business.  I've flown on loads of airlines that have gone
bust: Monarch, WOW Air, Thomas Cook, Flybmi, Zoom.  And those are all busts
from before coronavirus - times change but being an airline is always a bad
idea.</p>
<p>That's odd, because other businesses, even ones which seem really stupid, are
much more profitable.  Selling fizzy drinks is, surprisingly, an amazing
business.  Perhaps the best.  Coca-cola's return on equity has rarely fallen
below 30% in any given year.  That seems very unfair because being an airline
is hard work but making coke is pretty easy.  It's even more galling because
Coca-cola don't actually make the coke themselves - that is outsourced to
"bottling companies".  They literally just sell it.</p>
<h2>Industry structure - what makes a business good</h2>
<p>If you were to believe LinkedIn you would think a great business is made with
efficiency, hard work, innovation or some other intrinsic reason to do with how
hardworking, or clever, the people in the business are.  That simply is not the
case.</p>
<p>What makes a good business is industry structure.</p>
<h3>Airlines - unfavourable industry structure</h3>
<p>To be an airline is to be in an almost uniquely terrible market position.
For starters, there are only two makers of aeroplanes (Airbus and Boeing).  For
reasons of training and staff efficiency, you have to commit to one or the
other, which gives the aeroplane makers very strong pricing power.</p>
<p>And buyers of airline tickets are incredibly fickle and have no loyalty.  They will
switch from one "carrier" to another over even small differences in price.
Annoyingly, there are loads of other airlines and they're all running the same
routes as you!</p>
<p>Worse yet, starting a new airline is surprisingly easy.  Aircraft hold their
value so banks will happily lend against them.  There are loads of staff
available that new entrants can hire.  So randos will continually enter your
market, often selling tickets below cost for quite a while before they go bust.
And to top it off, there are plenty of substitutes for air travel - from
government-subsidised high speed trains to Zoom calls.</p>
<p>Airlines that get more efficient, work harder or come up with innovations
aren't going to be able to "capture" the value of what they've done.  If you
make more than the bare minimum to survive Airbus will notice that you're being
undercharged and you'll find that the next renewal on your service contract
eats up the difference.</p>
<h3>Fizzy-drinks - very favourable industry structure</h3>
<p>Being the Coca-cola company is pretty great though.</p>
<p>Coke is just water, colourant, flavouring, caffeine and sweetner.  Those are
all widely available and really cheap.  And as I said, you don't even have to
combine them yourselves - bottling companies will do that for you for almost
nothing.</p>
<p>Handily, consumers are really picky about what goes in their mouth.  The
unofficial motto of your main competitor is "Is Pepsi ok?".  This is despite
the fact that they are identical in both taste and colour.  And a significant
minority of people actually say no!</p>
<p>And it isn't easy for new competitors to enter the market.  They can't call
their new drink "coke" due to trademarks.  They have to call it something else.
And consumers will generally refuse it because drinking an alternative is
considered some kind of weird statement.</p>
<h2>What is industry structure?</h2>
<p>Classically, there are five basic parts ("forces") to a company's position:</p>
<ol>
<li>The power of their <strong>suppliers</strong> to increase their prices</li>
<li>The power of their <strong>buyers</strong> to reduce your prices</li>
<li>The strength of <strong>direct competitors</strong></li>
<li>The threat of any <strong>new entrants</strong></li>
<li>The threat of <strong>substitutes</strong></li>
</ol>
<p>It's industry structure that makes a business profitable or not.  Not
efficiency, not hard work and not innovation.</p>
<p>If none of the forces are very much against you, your business will do ok.  If
they are all against you, you'll be in the position of the airlines.  And if
they're all in your favour: brill, you're Coca-cola.</p>
<h2>The industry structure of LLM makers: OpenAI/Anthropic/Gemini/etc</h2>
<p>So is the position of LLM makers any good?  I'm afraid it's not good news.</p>
<p>LLM makers sometimes imply that their suppliers are cloud companies like Amazon
Web Services, Google Cloud, etc.  That wouldn't be so bad because you could
shop around and make them compete to cut the huge cost of model training.</p>
<p>Really though, LLM makers have only one true supplier: NVIDIA.  NVIDIA make the
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hopper_(microarchitecture)">chips</a> that all
models are trained on - regardless of cloud vendor.  And that gives NVIDIA
colossal, near total pricing power.  NVIDIA are more powerful relative to
Anthropic or OpenAI than Airbus or Boeing could ever dream of being.</p>
<p>How much power do buyers have over LLM token prices?  So far, it seems fairly
high.  Most LLM users seem willing to change from Chat-GPT to Claude, for
example.  It doesn't seem like brand loyalty is being built up.  And companies
that build AI into their businesses are starting to do so via abstraction
layers that allow them to switch model easily.  That makes LLMs
interchangeable - which is bad for those who sell them.</p>
<p>What's the strength of direct competitors?  Again, it is considerable.  There
are loads of LLM vendors and pricing <a href="https://a16z.com/llmflation-llm-inference-cost/">appears
competitive</a>.  Worst of all,
Facebook basically dump their model on the market for no cost.  It's
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Browser_wars#First_browser_war_(1995%E2%80%932001)">reminiscent of Internet
Explorer</a> -
not exactly a great portent.</p>
<p>And it seems fairly easy for new entrants to build brand new models.  That is
why there are so many LLM makers.  Most of the techniques for making LLMs are
openly published in papers.  Even bad models can gain customers if they are
cheap, which allows new entrants to gain a foothold.</p>
<p>The situation on substitutes is mixed.  Instead of having Chat-GPT write some
text you could pay a person to do it instead.  That is likely to be much more
expensive but also less likely to hallucinate, which might be important for
some usecases (law is the field least likely to use LLMs).  And then there is
the trend that <a href="https://calpaterson.com/metadata.html">metadata tends to displace artificial
intelligence</a> once particular application has been proved out -
so as soon as you find a solid usecase you stand to be replaced.</p>
<p>A single mildly positive point does not make a profitable business.  LLM makers
look a lot more like Netscape - who invented graphical web browsers, then went
bust - than Google, who made something good that ran on top of the the web
browsers.</p>
<h2>How are they raising so much money?</h2>
<p>If LLM makers seem cursed to an airline-style business destiny, how come they
are able to raise so much money?  OpenAI <a href="https://www.reuters.com/technology/artificial-intelligence/openai-closes-66-billion-funding-haul-valuation-157-billion-with-investment-2024-10-02/">raised $6.6
billion</a>
at a valuation of $157 billion less than two months ago.  That might be the
biggest VC round of all time.</p>
<p>What do they know that I don't?  It is a mystery - but let's consider the
options.</p>
<p>Perhaps they are hoping to develop their own chips to reduce their dependance
on NVIDIA.  $6.6 billion is not enough to build a new fab but it might be
enough to get a new chip designed which allows them to migrate off NVIDIA.
That would save them paying so much money for GPU time.  But, NVIDIA are
actually one of the investors in the round (although only a fairly small
amount) - so it's unlikely "develop an NVIDIA competitor" was on any of the
pitch deck slides.</p>
<p>Perhaps OpenAI are hoping to build a strong brand so that customers won't
switch to competitors so easily.  It's not impossible, there is proof the
<a href="https://calpaterson.com/amazon-premium.html">branding</a> and lock-in can work in technology - but it
seems difficult to manage given that LLMs themselves generically have a textual
interface - meaning that there is no real API as such - you just send text, and
it sends text back.</p>
<p>Can they do anything about new entrants?  Possibly.  If investing $6.6bn allows
them to develop a major improvement in their model then that would raise
everyone else's costs considerably and probably force some of their smaller
competitors out of the market.  The trouble is the money is the most fungible
of all goods (that is the point, after all) and that $6.6bn is not all that
much of it.  So this round wouldn't, by itself, be enough to dissuate others.
I used to work at a bank and I can tell you that individual bond raises can be
a lot more than $6.6bn.</p>
<p>It's worth saying that even companies that raise huge sums of money sometimes
turn out to have no viable business.  WeWork ultimately raised over $10bn at a
valuation of $47bn before it was realised that their business simply did not
make sense.  WeWork were valued at just $0.56bn in their most recent financial
restructuring - having lost well over 95% of what was invested.</p>
<h2>Not all AI companies are doomed</h2>
<p>If LLM makers aren't going to be good businesses, does that bode ill for The
Future?</p>
<p>Firstly, it does not mean the technology will be bad.  Whether the technology
ends up being good or not is mostly unrelated to whether Open
AI/Anthropic/Mistral/whoever makes any money off it.  Container virtualisation
technology is pretty well developed even though Docker made almost nothing on
it.  Web browsers are extremely advanced pieces of software even though making
a browser is such a bad business that most don't usually count it as a business
at all.  And CRMs are terrible despite the fact that Salesforce is tremendously
successful.  Technology success and business success are mostly unrelated.</p>
<p>And then: not all AI businesses are building models.  Ideally, if I were
running an AI business I would avoid building a model at all costs.  Building
your own models looks like a undifferentiated schlep.  Using a tiny bit of some
expensively trained model that Anthropic has produced could be very cost
effective and might make some business idea work that wouldn't have 5 years
ago.</p>
<h2>Beware software companies that aren't software companies</h2>
<p>Software companies are really good businesses.  You have no real suppliers,
your software is often unique (so no competitors) and the substitute is just
users doing the job themselves.  For this reason, software companies tend have
really great margins.</p>
<p>The problem is that not all technology companies are software companies.  If
you have a hugely powerful single supplier like NVIDIA then the economics of
your company are going to less like Microsoft Office and more like
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pan_Am">Pan-Am</a>.</p>
<hr>

<h2>Contact/etc</h2>



<hr>

<h2>Other notes</h2>
<p>The AI safety movement is a fantastic hypeman for LLMs as a technology.
Implying (pretty dubiously) that we are <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doomsday_Clock">10 minutes from
midnight</a> in some kind of
Ghost-in-The-Shell style AI crisis is in fact an extremely effective form of
product marketing.  Perhaps that is why OpenAI and others employ so many AI
safety specialists.</p>
<p>The Coca-cola company mainly sit back and rake in the megabucks - but they do
spend a little bit of their earnings on research.  And a little bit of a lot is
still significant.  It's interesting that that coke's market research has
discovered that coke works better as a gender segregated product: Coke Zero is
Diet Coke, but for men.</p>
<p>If you want to read more about industry structure and market strategy, the
place to start is with Michael Porter.  He reworked his famous essay <a href="https://hbr.org/2008/01/the-five-competitive-forces-that-shape-strategy">The Five
Forces that Shape Corporate
Strategy</a>
in 2008.  It's not the last word, but it probably should be the first word you
read if you want to learn more.  And if you like it, he has a lot more.</p>

    </article>

        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>