<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 15:30:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Forget ChatGPT: why researchers now run small AIs on their laptops (103 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02998-y</link>
            <guid>41609393</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 11:52:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02998-y">https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02998-y</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41609393">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                    <p>The website histo.fyi is a database of structures of immune-system proteins called major histocompatibility complex (MHC) molecules. It includes images, data tables and amino-acid sequences, and is run by bioinformatician Chris Thorpe, who uses artificial intelligence (AI) tools called large language models (LLMs) to convert those assets into readable summaries. But he doesn’t use ChatGPT, or any other web-based LLM. Instead, Thorpe runs the AI on his laptop.</p><article data-label="Related">
  <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02630-z" data-track="click" data-track-label="recommended article"><img alt="" src="https://media.nature.com/w400/magazine-assets/d41586-024-02998-y/d41586-024-02998-y_27689164.jpg"><p>Chatbots in science: What can ChatGPT do for you?</p></a>
 </article><p>Over the past couple of years, chatbots based on LLMs have won praise for their ability to write poetry or engage in conversations. Some LLMs have hundreds of billions of parameters — the more parameters, the greater the complexity — and can be accessed only online. But two more recent trends have blossomed. First, organizations are making ‘open weights’ versions of LLMs, in which the weights and biases used to train a model are publicly available, so that users can download and run them locally, if they have the computing power. Second, technology firms are making scaled-down versions that can be run on consumer hardware — and that rival the performance of older, larger models.</p><p>Researchers might use such tools to save money, protect the confidentiality of patients or corporations, or ensure reproducibility. Thorpe, who’s based in Oxford, UK, and works at the European Molecular Biology Laboratory’s European Bioinformatics Institute in Hinxton, UK, is just one of many researchers exploring what the tools can do. That trend is likely to grow, Thorpe says. As computers get faster and models become more efficient, people will increasingly have AIs running on their laptops or mobile devices for all but the most intensive needs. Scientists will finally have AI assistants at their fingertips — but the actual algorithms, not just remote access to them.</p><h2><b>Big things in small packages</b></h2><p>Several large tech firms and research institutes have released small and open-weights models over the past few years, including Google DeepMind in London; Meta in Menlo Park, California; and the Allen Institute for Artificial Intelligence in Seattle, Washington (see ‘Some small open-weights models’). (‘Small’ is relative — these models can contain some 30 billion parameters, which is large by comparison with earlier models.)</p><p>Although the California tech firm OpenAI hasn’t open-weighted its current GPT models, its partner Microsoft in Redmond, Washington, has been on a spree, releasing the small language models Phi-1, Phi-1.5 and Phi-2 in 2023, then four versions of Phi-3 and three versions of Phi-3.5 this year. The Phi-3 and Phi-3.5 models have between 3.8 billion and 14 billion active parameters, and two models (Phi-3-vision and Phi-3.5-vision) handle images<sup><a href="#ref-CR1" data-track="click" data-action="anchor-link" data-track-label="go to reference" data-track-category="references">1</a></sup>. By some benchmarks, even the smallest Phi model outperforms OpenAI’s GPT-3.5 Turbo from 2023, rumoured to have 20 billion parameters.</p><p>Sébastien Bubeck, Microsoft’s vice-president for generative AI, attributes Phi-3’s performance to its training data set. LLMs initially train by predicting the next ‘token’ (iota of text) in long text strings. To predict the name of the killer at the end of a murder mystery, for instance, an AI needs to ‘understand’ everything that came before, but such consequential predictions are rare in most text. To get around this problem, Microsoft used LLMs to write millions of short stories and textbooks in which one thing builds on another. The result of training on this text, Bubeck says, is a model that fits on a mobile phone but has the power of the initial 2022 version of ChatGPT. “If you are able to craft a data set that is very rich in those reasoning tokens, then the signal will be much richer,” he says.</p><article data-label="Related">
  <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02386-6" data-track="click" data-track-label="recommended article"><img alt="" src="https://media.nature.com/w400/magazine-assets/d41586-024-02998-y/d41586-024-02998-y_27484538.png"><p>ChatGPT for science: how to talk to your data</p></a>
 </article><p>Phi-3 can also help with routing — deciding whether a query should go to a larger model. “That’s a place where Phi-3 is going to shine,” Bubeck says. Small models can also help scientists in remote regions that have little cloud connectivity. “Here in the Pacific Northwest, we have amazing places to hike, and sometimes I just don’t have network,” he says. “And maybe I want to take a picture of some flower and ask my AI some information about it.”</p><p>Researchers can build on these tools to create custom applications. The Chinese e-commerce site Alibaba, for instance, has built models called Qwen with 500 million to 72 billion parameters. A biomedical scientist in New Hampshire fine-tuned the largest Qwen model using scientific data to create Turbcat-72b, which is available on the model-sharing site Hugging Face. (The researcher goes only by the name Kal’tsit on the Discord messaging platform, because AI-assisted work in science is still controversial.) Kal’tsit says she created the model to help researchers to brainstorm, proof manuscripts, prototype code and summarize published papers; the model has been downloaded thousands of times.</p><h2><b>Preserving privacy</b></h2><p>Beyond the ability to fine-tune open models for focused applications, Kal’tsit says, another advantage of local models is privacy. Sending personally identifiable data to a commercial service could run foul of data-protection regulations. “If an audit were to happen and you show them you’re using ChatGPT, the situation could become pretty nasty,” she says.</p><p>Cyril Zakka, a physician who leads the health team at Hugging Face, uses local models to generate training data for other models (which are sometimes local, too). In one project, he uses them to extract diagnoses from medical reports so that another model can learn to predict those diagnoses on the basis of echocardiograms, which are used to monitor heart disease. In another, he uses the models to generate questions and answers from medical textbooks to test other models. “We are paving the way towards fully autonomous surgery,” he explains. A robot trained to answer questions would be able to communicate better with doctors.</p><p>Zakka uses local models — he prefers Mistral 7B, released by the tech firm Mistral AI in Paris, or Meta’s Llama-3 70B — because they’re cheaper than subscription services such as ChatGPT Plus, and because he can fine-tune them. But privacy is also key, because he’s not allowed to send patients’ medical records to commercial AI services.</p><article data-label="Related">
  <a href="https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-024-02185-z" data-track="click" data-track-label="recommended article"><img alt="" src="https://media.nature.com/w400/magazine-assets/d41586-024-02998-y/d41586-024-02998-y_27488412.jpg"><p>Inside the maths that drives AI</p></a>
 </article><p>Johnson Thomas, an endocrinologist at the health system Mercy in Springfield, Missouri, is likewise motivated by patient privacy. Clinicians rarely have time to transcribe and summarize patient interviews, but most commercial services that use AI to do so are either too expensive or not approved to handle private medical data. So, Thomas is developing an alternative. Based on Whisper — an open-weight speech-recognition model from OpenAI — and on Gemma 2 from Google DeepMind, the system will allow physicians to transcribe conversations and convert them to medical notes, and also summarize data from medical-research participants.</p><p>Privacy is also a consideration in industry. CELLama, developed at the South Korean pharmaceutical company Portrai in Seoul, exploits local LLMs such as Llama 3.1 to reduce information about a cell’s gene expression and other characteristics to a summary sentence<sup><a href="#ref-CR2" data-track="click" data-action="anchor-link" data-track-label="go to reference" data-track-category="references">2</a></sup>. It then creates a numerical representation of this sentence, which can be used to cluster cells into types. The developers highlight privacy as one advantage on their GitHub page, noting that <a href="https://github.com/CelVoxes/ceLLama" data-track="click" data-label="https://github.com/CelVoxes/ceLLama" data-track-category="body text link">CELLama</a> “operates locally, ensuring no data leaks”.</p><h2><b>Putting models to good use</b></h2><p>As the LLM landscape evolves, scientists face a fast-changing menu of options. “I’m still at the tinkering, playing stage of using LLMs locally,” Thorpe says. He tried ChatGPT, but felt it was expensive, and the tone of its output wasn’t right. Now he uses Llama locally, with either 8 billion or 70 billion parameters, both of which can run on his Mac laptop.</p><p>Another benefit, Thorpe says, is that local models don’t change. Commercial developers, by contrast, can update their models at any moment, leading to different outputs and forcing Thorpe to alter his prompts or templates. “In most of science, you want things that are reproducible,” he explains. “And it’s always a worry if you’re not in control of the reproducibility of what you’re generating.”</p><p>For another project, Thorpe is writing code that aligns MHC molecules on the basis of their 3D structure. To develop and test his algorithms, he needs lots of diverse proteins — more than exist naturally. To design plausible new proteins, he uses <a href="https://huggingface.co/nferruz/ProtGPT2" data-track="click" data-label="https://huggingface.co/nferruz/ProtGPT2" data-track-category="body text link">ProtGPT2</a>, an open-weights model with 738 million parameters that was trained on about 50 million sequences<sup><a href="#ref-CR3" data-track="click" data-action="anchor-link" data-track-label="go to reference" data-track-category="references">3</a></sup>.</p><p>Sometimes, however, a local app won’t do. For coding, Thorpe uses the cloud-based GitHub Copilot as a partner. “It kind of feels like my arm’s chopped off when for some reason I can’t actually use Copilot,” he says. Local LLM-based coding tools do exist (such as Google DeepMind’s <a href="https://huggingface.co/google/codegemma-7b" data-track="click" data-label="https://huggingface.co/google/codegemma-7b" data-track-category="body text link">CodeGemma</a> and one from California-based developers <a href="https://docs.continue.dev/intro" data-track="click" data-label="https://docs.continue.dev/intro" data-track-category="body text link">Continue</a>), but in his experience they can’t compete with Copilot.</p><h2><b>Access points</b></h2><p>So, how do you run a local LLM? Software called <a href="https://ollama.com/" data-track="click" data-label="https://ollama.com/" data-track-category="body text link">Ollama</a> (available for Mac, Windows and Linux operating systems) lets users download open models, including Llama 3.1, Phi-3, Mistral and Gemma 2, and access them through a command line. Other options include the cross-platform app <a href="https://www.nomic.ai/gpt4all" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.nomic.ai/gpt4all" data-track-category="body text link">GPT4All</a> and <a href="https://github.com/Mozilla-Ocho/llamafile" data-track="click" data-label="https://github.com/Mozilla-Ocho/llamafile" data-track-category="body text link">Llamafile</a>, which can transform LLMs into a single file that runs on any of six operating systems, with or without a graphics processing unit.</p><article data-label="Related">
  <a href="https://www.nature.com/collections/fxvqrpnlcq" data-track="click" data-track-label="recommended article"><img alt="" src="https://media.nature.com/w400/magazine-assets/d41586-024-02998-y/d41586-024-02998-y_16573690.jpg"><p>NatureTech hub</p></a>
 </article><p>Sharon Machlis, a former editor at the website InfoWorld, who lives in Framingham, Massachusetts, wrote <a href="https://www.infoworld.com/article/2338922/5-easy-ways-to-run-an-llm-locally.html" data-track="click" data-label="https://www.infoworld.com/article/2338922/5-easy-ways-to-run-an-llm-locally.html" data-track-category="body text link">a guide to using LLMs locally</a>, covering a dozen options. “The first thing I would suggest,” she says, “is to have the software you choose fit your level of how much you want to fiddle.” Some people prefer the ease of apps, whereas others prefer the flexibility of the command line.</p><p>Whichever approach you choose, local LLMs should soon be good enough for most applications, says Stephen Hood, who heads open-source AI at the tech firm Mozilla in San Francisco. “The rate of progress on those over the past year has been astounding,” he says.</p><p>As for what those applications might be, that’s for users to decide. “Don’t be afraid to get your hands dirty,” Zakka says. “You might be pleasantly surprised by the results.”</p>
                </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Collapse of Self-Worth in the Digital Age (123 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://thewalrus.ca/collapse-of-self-worth-in-the-digital-age/</link>
            <guid>41609099</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 10:48:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://thewalrus.ca/collapse-of-self-worth-in-the-digital-age/">https://thewalrus.ca/collapse-of-self-worth-in-the-digital-age/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41609099">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article id="post-170627">

	
	
	
	<div>
		<!-- Ad-Auris -->
		
		<p><span>W</span><span>hen I was twelve,</span> I used to roller-skate in circles for hours. I was at another new school, the odd man out, bullied by my desk mate. My problems were too complex and modern to explain. So I skated across parking lots, breezeways, and sidewalks, I listened to the vibration of my wheels on brick, I learned the names of flowers, I put deserted paths to use. I decided for myself each curve I took, and by the time I rolled home, I felt lighter. One Saturday, a friend invited me to roller-skate in the park. I can still picture her in green protective knee pads, flying past. I couldn’t catch up, I had no technique. There existed another scale to evaluate roller skating, beyond joy, and as Rollerbladers and cyclists overtook me, it eclipsed my own. Soon after, I stopped skating. </p>

<p><span>Y</span><span>ears ago,</span> I worked in the backroom of a Tower Records. Every few hours, my face-pierced, gunk-haired co-workers would line up by my workstation, waiting to clock in or out. When we typed in our staff number at 8:59 p.m., we were off time, returned to ourselves, free like smoke.</p>
<p>There are no words to describe the opposite sensations of being at-our-job and being not-at-our-job even if we know the feeling of crossing that threshold by heart. But the most essential quality that makes a job a job is that when we are at work, we surrender the power to decide the worth of what we do. At-job is where our labour is appraised by an external meter: the market. At-job, our labour is never a means to itself but a means to money; its value can be expressed only as a number—relative, fluctuating, out of our control. At-job, because an outside eye measures us, the workplace is a place of surveillance. It’s painful to have your sense of worth extracted. For Marx, the poet of economics, when a person’s innate value is replaced with exchange value, it is as if we’ve been reduced to “a mere jelly.” </p>

<p>Not-job, or whatever name you prefer—“quitting time,” “off duty,” “downtime”—is where we restore ourselves from a mere jelly, precisely by using our internal meter to determine the criteria for success or failure. Find the best route home—not the one that optimizes cost per minute but the one that offers time enough to hear an album from start to finish. Plant a window garden, and if the plants are half dead, try again. My brother-in-law found a toy loom in his neighbour’s garbage, and nightly he weaves tiny technicolour rugs. We do these activities for the sake of doing them, and their value can’t be arrived at through an outside, top-down measure. It would be nonsensical to treat them as comparable and rank them from one to five. We can assess them only by privately and carefully attending to what they contain and, on our own, concluding their merit. </p>
<p>And so artmaking—the cultural industries—occupies the middle of an uneasy Venn diagram. First, the value of an artwork is internal—how well does it fulfill the vision that inspired it? Second, a piece of art is its own end. Third, a piece of art is, by definition, rare, one of a kind, nonfungible. </p>

<p>Yet the end point for the working artist is to create an object for sale. Once the art object enters the market, art’s intrinsic value is emptied out, compacted by the market’s logic of ranking, until there’s only relational worth, no interior worth. Two novelists I know publish essays one week apart; in a grim coincidence, each writer recounts their own version of the same traumatic life event. Which essay is better, a friend asks. I explain they’re different; different life circumstances likely shaped separate approaches. Yes, she says, but which one is <em>better</em>?</p>
<p><span>I</span><span>grew up</span> a Catholic, a faithful, an anachronism to my friends. I carried my faith until my twenties, when it finally broke. Once I couldn’t gain comfort from religion anymore, I got it from writing. Sitting and building stories, side by side with millions of other storytellers who have endeavoured since the dawn of existence to forge meaning even as reality proves endlessly senseless, is the nearest thing to what it felt like back when I was a believer.</p>
<p>I spent my thirties writing a novel and paying the bills as low-paid part-time faculty at three different colleges. I could’ve studied law or learned to code. Instead, I manufactured sentences. Looking back, it baffles me that I had the wherewithal to commit to a project with no guaranteed financial value, as if I was under an enchantment. Working on that novel was like visiting a little town every day for four years, a place so dear and sweet. Then I sold it.</p>
<p>As the publication date advanced, I was awash with extrinsic measures. Only twenty years ago, there was no public, complete data on book sales. Until the introduction of BookScan in the late ’90s, you just had to take an agent’s word for it. “The track record of an author was a contestable variable that was known to some, surmised by others, and always subject to exaggeration in the interests of inflating value,” says John B. Thompson in <em>Merchants of Culture</em>, his ethnography of contemporary publishing.</p>
<p>This is hard to imagine, now that we are inundated with cold, beautiful stats, some publicized by trade publications or broadcast by authors themselves on all socials. How many publishers bid? How big is the print run? How many stops on the tour? How many reviews on Goodreads? How many mentions on Bookstagram, BookTok? How many bloggers on the blog tour? How exponential is the growth in follower count? Preorders? How many printings? How many languages in translation? How many views on the unboxing? How many mentions on most-anticipated lists? I was glued to my numbers like a day trader.</p>

<p>I wanted to write my publicist to ask: Should I be worried my stats aren’t higher? The question blared constantly in my head: Did gambling years I could’ve been earning towards a house pay off? But I never did. I was too embarrassed. I had trained in the religion of art, and to pay mind to the reception of my work was to be a non-believer. During my fine arts degree, we heard again and again that <em>the only gauge for art is your own measure</em>, and when I started teaching writing, I’d preach the same thing. Ignore whatever publications or promotions friends gain; you’re on your own journey. It’s a purportedly anti-capitalist idea, but it repackages the artist’s concern for economic security as petty ego. My feelings—caring at all—broke code. Shame sublimated everything. </p>
<p>And when the reception started to roll in, I’d hear good news, but gratitude lasted moments before I wanted more. A starred review from <em>Publisher’s Weekly</em>, but I wasn’t in “Picks of the Week.” A mention from <em>Entertainment Weekly</em>, but last on a click-through list. Nothing was enough. Why? What had defined my adult existence was my ability to find worth within, to build to an internal schematic, which is what artists do. Now I was a stranger to myself. I tried to fix it with box breathing videos, podcasts, reading about <em>Anna Karenina</em>. My partner and I were trying for another baby, but cycles kept passing, my womb couldn’t grab the egg. A kind nurse at the walk-in said: <em>Sometimes your body is saying the time’s not right</em>. Mine was a bad place. </p>
<p>A few weeks after my book release, my friends and I and our little kids took a weekend vacation. They surprised me with a three-tiered cake matching my book cover, cradled on laps, from Toronto, through a five-hour traffic jam. In all the photos from that trip, I’m staring at my phone. I can hardly remember that summer.</p>
<p>My scale of worth had torn off, like a roof in a hurricane, replaced with an external one. An external scale is a relative scale; so of course, nothing’s enough. There is no top. </p>
<p>Then I was shortlisted for a major prize. It took me on a world tour, listed me alongside authors who are certifiable geniuses. I thought my endless accounting could stop, this had to be enough for me, I could get back to who I was. But I couldn’t. In London, I bought my two-year-old a bath toy, a little boat with a Beefeater. Today at bath time, the boat still gives me a sickly feeling, like it’s from the scene of a trauma. My centre was gone.</p>
<p><span>O</span><span>ne of at-job’s</span> defining qualities is how efficiently output is converted into a number. In 1994, Philip Agre described this as <a href="https://djp3.westmont.edu/classes/2017_01_CS195/readings/CaptureModelOfSurveillance.pdf" rel="noopener" target="_blank">the “capture model,”</a> or “the deliberate reorganization of industrial work activities to allow computers to track them in real time.” Gregory Sholette, the author of <em>Dark Matter: Art and Politics in the Age of Enterprise Culture</em>, describes how workers in a Pennsylvania factory spent their break covering a wall of the plant with “newspaper clippings, snapshots, spent soda cans, industrial debris, trashed food containers and similar bits and pieces.” They called it “Swampwall.” It reminds me of the sculpture on a high shelf in the back of a diner where I worked, composed of unusually shaped potatoes. Its form changed with each new tuber contributed by the cook on prep shift. </p>
<p>Such spontaneous projects are signs of life: physical evidence of the liberating fact that not all time at work can be measured or processed into productivity. Swampwall was inutile: a means to itself. It was allowed to flourish until the company was bought out by a global corporation, at which point the massive collaborative mural was “expunged.”</p>
<p>Thirty years after Agre coined the capture model, workforce management technology can track every moment at work as a production target. Amazon’s Units Per Hour score, Uber’s and Lyft’s (constantly shrivelling) base fares, and Domino’s Pizza Tracker have made it possible to time all time, even in the break room or toilet stall. These are extreme examples, but they’re echoed across the work world, with the datafication of parts of performance that used to be too baggy or obscure to crunch and so were ours to keep. “Wellness” apps provided as health benefits by corporate management that track fob swipes for office workers; case management software that counts advice by the piece for legal workers; shares, hover rate, and time on site that measure media workers; leaderboards for tech employees, ranking who worked longest. </p>
<p>There must exist professions that are free from capture, but I’m hard pressed to find them. Even non-remote jobs, where work cannot pursue the worker home, are dogged by digital tracking: a farmer says Instagram Story views directly correlate to farm subscriptions, a server tells me her manager won’t give her the Saturday-night money shift until she has more followers. Even religious guidance can be quantified by view counts for online church services, Yelp for spirituality. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/nov/10/ireland-catholic-priests-online-mass-reviews-causing-performance-anxiety" rel="noopener" target="_blank">One priest told the <em>Guardian</em></a>, “you have this thing about how many followers have you . . . it hits at your gut, at your heart.” </p>
<p>But we know all this. What we hardly talk about is how we’ve reorganized not just industrial activity but <em>any</em> activity to be capturable by computer, a radical expansion of what can be mined. Friendship is ground zero for the metrics of the inner world, the first unquantifiable shorn into data points: Friendster testimonials, the MySpace Top 8, friending. Likewise, the search for romance has been refigured by dating apps that sell paid-for rankings and paid access to “quality” matches. Or, if there’s an off-duty pursuit you love—giving tarot readings, polishing beach rocks—it’s a great compliment to say: “You should do that for money.” Join the passion economy, give the market final say on the value of your delights. Even engaging with art—say, encountering some uncanny reflection of yourself in a novel, or having a transformative epiphany from listening, on repeat, to the way that singer’s voice breaks over the bridge—can be spat out as a figure, on Goodreads or your Spotify year in review.  </p>

<p>And those ascetics who disavow all socials? They are still caught in the network. Acts of pure leisure—photographing a sidewalk cat with a camera app or watching a video on how to make a curry—are transmuted into data to grade how well the app or the creators’ deliverables are delivering. If we’re not being tallied, we affect the tally of others. We are all data workers.</p>
<p>Twenty years ago, anti-capitalist activists campaigned against ads posted in public bathroom stalls: too invasive, there needs to be a limit to capital’s reach. Now, ads by the toilet are quaint. Clocking out is obsolete when, in the deep quiet of our minds, we lack the pay grade to determine worth.</p>
<p><span>T</span><span>he internet</span> is designed to stop us from ever switching it off. It moves at the speed of light, with constantly changing metrics, fuelled by “‘ludic loops’ or repeated cycles of uncertainty, anticipation and feedback”—in other words, it works exactly like a Jackpot 6000 slot machine. (On a basic level, social media apps like Instagram operate like phone games. They’ve replaced classics like Snake or Candy Crush, except the game is your sense of self.)</p>
<p>The effect of gamification on artmaking has been dramatic. <a href="https://www.vox.com/culture/2024/2/1/24056883/tiktok-self-promotion-artist-career-how-to-build-following" rel="noopener" target="_blank">In Rebecca Jennings’s <em>Vox</em> long read</a> on the necessity of authorly self-promotion, she interviews William Deresiewicz, whose book <em>The Death of the Artist</em> breaks down the harsh conditions for artists seeking an income in the digital economy. Deresiewicz used to think “selling out”—using the most sacred parts of your life and values to shill for a brand—was “evil.” Yet this economy has made it so there’s “no choice” if you want a living. The very concept of selling out, he says, “has disappeared.” A few years ago, much was made of the fact that the novelist Sally Rooney had no Twitter account—this must explain her prolific output. But the logic is back to front: it’s only top-selling authors who can afford to forgo social media. Call it Deactivation Privilege. </p>
<p>It’s a privilege few of us can afford, if it’s the algorithm we need to impress rather than book reviewers of old. <a href="https://www.esquire.com/entertainment/books/a60924704/debut-fiction-challenges/" rel="noopener" target="_blank">In a nightmarish dispatch in <em>Esquire</em></a> on how hard it is for authors to find readers, Kate Dwyer argues that all authors must function like influencers now, which means a fire sale on your “private” life. As internet theorist Kyle Chayka puts it to Dwyer: “Influencers get attention by exposing parts of their life that have nothing to do with the production of culture.”</p>
<p>The self <em>is</em> the work, just ask Flaubert. But data collection’s ability to reduce the self to a figure—batted about by the fluctuations of its stock—is newly unbearable. There’s no way around it, and this self being sold alongside the work can be as painful for a writer of autofiction as it is for me, a writer of speculative fiction who invented an imaginary world. </p>
<p><span>I</span><span>tell you</span> all this not because I think we should all be very concerned about artists, but because what happens to artists is happening to all of us. As data collection technology hollows out our inner worlds, all of us experience the working artist’s plight: our lot is to numericize and monetize the most private and personal parts of our experience. </p>
<p>Certainly, smartphones could be too much technology for children, <a href="https://www.newyorker.com/news/the-new-yorker-interview/jonathan-haidt-wants-you-to-take-away-your-kids-phone" rel="noopener" target="_blank">as Jonathan Haidt argues</a>, and definitely, <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/books/2016/dec/26/the-attention-merchants-tim-wu-review" rel="noopener" target="_blank">as Tim Wu says</a>, attention is a commodity, but these ascendant theories of tech talk around the fact that something else deep inside, innermost, is being harvested too: our self-worth, or, rather, worthing. </p>
<p>We are not giving away our value, as a puritanical grandparent might scold; we are giving away our facility <em>to</em> value. We’ve been cored like apples, a dependency created, hooked on the public internet to tell us the worth. </p>
<p>Every notification ping holds the possibility we have merit. When we scroll, what are we looking for? </p>

<p><span>W</span><span>hen my eldest child</span> was in kindergarten, she loved to make art, but she detested the assignments that tried to make math fun by asking kids to draw. If I sat her down to complete one, she would stare rebelliously at her pencil or a strand of her hair rather than submit. Then one day, while drawing a group of five ants and a group of eight ants, my kindergartener started to sketch fast. She drew ants with bulbous limbs growing out of their bodies, like chains of sausages. “Bombombom!” she cried, flapping her arms up and down. “These are their muscles.” She continued to draw and mime pumping iron, giggling to herself, delighted to have planted something in her homework that couldn’t be accounted for in the metric of correct or incorrect. She had taken drawing back. </p>
<p><span>T</span><span>he ludic loop</span> of the internet has automated our inner worlds: we don’t have to choose what we like, or even if we like it; the algorithm chooses for us. Take Shein, the fast fashion leviathan. While other fast fashion brands wait for high-end houses to produce designs they can replicate cheaply, Shein has completely eclipsed the runway, using AI to trawl social media for cues on what to produce next. Shein’s site operates like a casino game, using “dark patterns”—a countdown clock puts a timer on an offer, pop-ups say there’s only one item left in stock, and the scroll of outfits never ends—so you buy now, ask if you want it later. </p>
<p>Shein’s model is dystopic: countless reports detail how it puts its workers in obscene poverty in order to sell a reprieve to consumers who are also moneyless—a saturated plush world lasting as long as the seams in one of their dresses. Yet the day to day of Shein’s target shopper is so bleak, we strain our moral character to cosplay a life of plenty. </p>
<p>Automation isn’t forced upon us: we crave it, oblivion, thanks to the tech itself. As the ascendant apparatus of the labour market, it’s squeezed already dire working conditions to a suffocation point, until all we desire is the sweet fugue of scroll, our decision maker set to “off.” </p>
<p><span>A</span><span>fter my novel</span> came out, whenever I met an author, I would ask, with increasing frenzy, how they managed the grisly experience of work going to market. I was comforted and horrified when everyone agreed it could be dispossessing. Then they all said the same thing: “I kept writing and I felt better.” That was the advice: keep writing. </p>
<p>The market is the only mechanism for a piece of art to reach a pair of loving eyes. Even at a museum or library, the market had a hand in homing the item there. I didn’t understand that seeking a reader for my story meant handing over my work in the same way I sold my car on Craigslist: it’s gone from me, fully, bodily, finally. Or, as Marx says, alienated. I hated that advice to keep writing, because if I wrote another book, I’d have to go through the cycle again: slap my self on the scale like a pair of pork chops again. Now, I realize the authors I met meant something else. Yes, sell this part of your inner life but then go back in there and reinflate what’s been emptied. It’s a renewable resource.  </p>
<p>When I grasp this, all of it becomes tolerable. It’s like letting out a line, then braiding more line. I can manage, because there’ll always be more line.  </p>
<p><span>I</span><span>will try to sell</span> this essay to a publication, and if successful, the publication will try to sell it to readers. If you are reading this, it’s a commodity now, fluctuating and fungible, like so much digital dust. </p>
<!-- AI CONTENT END 1 -->
		<div id="sexy_author_bio_widget-2"><p><a href="https://thewalrus.ca/author/thea-lim/" target="_top"><img alt="Thea Lim" src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20viewBox='0%200%2070%2070'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-src="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/a5dae45e6bea1e8e5104bdd5b15830f9?s=70&amp;d=mm&amp;r=pg" data-srcset="https://secure.gravatar.com/avatar/a5dae45e6bea1e8e5104bdd5b15830f9?s=140&amp;d=mm&amp;r=pg 2x" height="70" width="70"></a></p><p>Thea Lim is an author, a culture writer, and a creative writing teacher. Her most recent novel is <em>An Ocean of Minutes</em>.</p></div>	</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	
	<!-- .entry-footer -->

		
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ultra high-resolution image of The Night Watch (255 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/stories/operation-night-watch/story/ultra-high-resolution-image-of-the-night-watch</link>
            <guid>41608648</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 09:08:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/stories/operation-night-watch/story/ultra-high-resolution-image-of-the-night-watch">https://www.rijksmuseum.nl/en/stories/operation-night-watch/story/ultra-high-resolution-image-of-the-night-watch</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41608648">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div v-else="">


<gtm-scroll-tracker location="article_story" category="article" scroll-element-id="openPipModal" inline-template="">
  <div>
      

<div>
      
  <p>The new high-resolution image of The Night Watch represents a major advance in the state of the art for imaging paintings, setting records for both the resolution and the total size of the image. The sampling resolution is 5 µm (0.005 mm), meaning that each pixel covers an area of the painting that is smaller than a human red blood cell. Given the large size of The Night Watch, this results in a truly enormous image: it’s 925,000 by 775,000 pixels – 717 gigapixels – with a file size of 5.6 TB!</p>

    </div>

<div>
    <h2>Grid</h2>
<p>To create this huge image, the painting was photographed in a grid with 97 rows and 87 columns with our 100-megapixel Hasselblad H6D 400 MS camera. Each of these 8,439 separate photos was captured using a sophisticated laser-guided five-axis camera positioning system that can sense the precise location of the painting so that every photo is sharp – an error of even 1/8 mm in the placement of the camera would result in a useless image.</p>

  </div>

<div>
    <h2>New technology</h2>
<p>New technology allowed the previously-released 20 µm resolution image of The Night Watch to serve as the guide for  lining up these much higher-resolution images during the process of fusing the individual captures into a single monolithic image. The technology allows each of the other types of images collected during Operation Night Watch to be precisely aligned with each other, thereby allowing all of our data to be seen in context.</p>

  </div>

<div>
    <h2>Physical state of the painting</h2>
<p>Why create such an incredibly huge image? With this resolution, we can very clearly see the precise physical state of the painting. Lead soap protrusions, tiny cracks, the shapes of individual paint pigment particles, past retouches, and the beautiful details of Rembrandt’s painting technique are all extraordinarily clear. This enables researchers to understand the painting’s condition in order to make the best plan for future conservation treatments. It helps us to better understand how Rembrandt painted, and it creates an exquisite 'snapshot’ of The Night Watch at this moment in its history.</p>

  </div>
    </div>
</gtm-scroll-tracker>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Kamal Proxy – A minimal HTTP proxy for zero-downtime deployments (111 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/basecamp/kamal-proxy</link>
            <guid>41608350</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 07:55:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/basecamp/kamal-proxy">https://github.com/basecamp/kamal-proxy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41608350">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Kamal Proxy - A minimal HTTP proxy for zero-downtime deployments</h2><a id="user-content-kamal-proxy---a-minimal-http-proxy-for-zero-downtime-deployments" aria-label="Permalink: Kamal Proxy - A minimal HTTP proxy for zero-downtime deployments" href="#kamal-proxy---a-minimal-http-proxy-for-zero-downtime-deployments"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What it does</h2><a id="user-content-what-it-does" aria-label="Permalink: What it does" href="#what-it-does"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Kamal Proxy is a tiny HTTP proxy, designed to make it easy to coordinate
zero-downtime deployments. By running your web applications behind Kamal Proxy,
you can deploy changes to them without interruping any of the traffic that's in
progress. No particular cooperation from an application is required for this to
work.</p>
<p dir="auto">Kamal Proxy is designed to work as part of <a href="https://kamal-deploy.org/" rel="nofollow">Kamal</a>,
which provides a complete deployment experience including container packaging
and provisioning. However, Kamal Proxy could also be used standalone or as part
of other deployment tooling.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">A quick overview</h2><a id="user-content-a-quick-overview" aria-label="Permalink: A quick overview" href="#a-quick-overview"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To run an instance of the proxy, use the <code>kamal-proxy run</code> command. There's no
configuration file, but there are some options you can specify if the defaults
aren't right for your application.</p>
<p dir="auto">For example, to run the proxy on a port other than 80 (the default) you could:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="kamal-proxy run --http-port 8080"><pre><code>kamal-proxy run --http-port 8080
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Run <code>kamal-proxy help run</code> to see the full list of options.</p>
<p dir="auto">To route traffic through the proxy to a web application, you <code>deploy</code> instances
of the application to the proxy. Deploying an instance makes it available to the
proxy, and replaces the instance it was using before (if any).</p>
<p dir="auto">Use the format <code>hostname:port</code> when specifying the instance to deploy.</p>
<p dir="auto">For example:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000"><pre><code>kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This will instruct the proxy to register <code>web-1:3000</code> to receive traffic under
the service name <code>service1</code>. It will immediately begin running HTTP health
checks to ensure it's reachable and working and, as soon as those health checks
succeed, will start routing traffic to it.</p>
<p dir="auto">If the instance fails to become healthy within a reasonable time, the <code>deploy</code>
command will stop the deployment and return a non-zero exit code, allowing
deployment scripts to handle the failure appropriately.</p>
<p dir="auto">Each deployment takes over all the traffic from the previously deployed
instance. As soon as Kamal Proxy determines that the new instance is healthy,
it will route all new traffic to that instance.</p>
<p dir="auto">The <code>deploy</code> command also waits for traffic to drain from the old instance before
returning. This means it's safe to remove the old instance as soon as <code>deploy</code>
returns successfully, without interrupting any in-flight requests.</p>
<p dir="auto">Because traffic is only routed to a new instance once it's healthy, and traffic
is drained completely from old instances before they are removed, deployments
take place with zero downtime.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Host-based routing</h3><a id="user-content-host-based-routing" aria-label="Permalink: Host-based routing" href="#host-based-routing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Host-based routing allows you to run multiple applications on the same server,
using a single instance of Kamal Proxy to route traffic to all of them.</p>
<p dir="auto">When deploying an instance, you can specify a host that it should serve traffic
for:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000 --host app1.example.com"><pre><code>kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000 --host app1.example.com
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">When deployed in this way, the instance will only receive traffic for the
specified host. By deploying multiple instances, each with their own host, you
can run multiple applications on the same server without port conflicts.</p>
<p dir="auto">Only one service at a time can route a specific host:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000 --host app1.example.com
kamal-proxy deploy service2 --target web-2:3000 --host app1.example.com # returns &quot;Error: host is used by another service&quot;
kamal-proxy remove service1
kamal-proxy deploy service2 --target web-2:3000 --host app1.example.com # suceeds"><pre><code>kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000 --host app1.example.com
kamal-proxy deploy service2 --target web-2:3000 --host app1.example.com # returns "Error: host is used by another service"
kamal-proxy remove service1
kamal-proxy deploy service2 --target web-2:3000 --host app1.example.com # suceeds
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Automatic TLS</h3><a id="user-content-automatic-tls" aria-label="Permalink: Automatic TLS" href="#automatic-tls"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Kamal Proxy can automatically obtain and renew TLS certificates for your
applications. To enable this, add the <code>--tls</code> flag when deploying an instance:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000 --host app1.example.com --tls"><pre><code>kamal-proxy deploy service1 --target web-1:3000 --host app1.example.com --tls
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Specifying <code>run</code> options with environment variables</h2><a id="user-content-specifying-run-options-with-environment-variables" aria-label="Permalink: Specifying run options with environment variables" href="#specifying-run-options-with-environment-variables"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">In some environments, like when running a Docker container, it can be convenient
to specify <code>run</code> options using environment variables. This avoids having to
update the <code>CMD</code> in the Dockerfile to change the options. To support this,
<code>kamal-proxy run</code> will read each of its options from environment variables if they
are set. For example, setting the HTTP port can be done with either:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="kamal-proxy run --http-port 8080"><pre><code>kamal-proxy run --http-port 8080
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">or:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="HTTP_PORT=8080 kamal-proxy run"><pre><code>HTTP_PORT=8080 kamal-proxy run
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">If any of the environment variables conflict with something else in your
environment, you can prefix them with <code>KAMAL_PROXY_</code> to disambiguate them. For
example:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="KAMAL_PROXY_HTTP_PORT=8080 kamal-proxy run"><pre><code>KAMAL_PROXY_HTTP_PORT=8080 kamal-proxy run
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building</h2><a id="user-content-building" aria-label="Permalink: Building" href="#building"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To build Kamal Proxy locally, if you have a working Go environment you can:</p>

<p dir="auto">Alternatively, build as a Docker container:</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Trying it out</h2><a id="user-content-trying-it-out" aria-label="Permalink: Trying it out" href="#trying-it-out"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">See the <a href="https://github.com/basecamp/kamal-proxy/blob/main/example">example</a> folder for a Docker Compose setup that you can use
to try out the proxy commands.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Porsche's idea for a six-stroke internal combustion engine (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.motor1.com/news/734156/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine/</link>
            <guid>41607887</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 06:15:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.motor1.com/news/734156/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine/">https://www.motor1.com/news/734156/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41607887">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post_box"> <div> <p><span data-time="1726578000"></span><span>Sep 17, 2024</span><span> at</span> 1:00pm ET</p>  </div> <div>  <div> <ul> <li><strong>Porsche has patented a six-stroke internal combustion engine design.</strong></li> <li><strong>It uses a special crankshaft to create extra compression and power strokes per cycle.</strong></li> <li><strong>Nearly all combustion-powered vehicles use a four-stroke engine design.</strong></li> </ul> <hr> <p><a href="https://www.motor1.com/porsche/" data-inline-widget="internal-links" data-type-id="2" data-params="%7B%22alias%22%3A%22porsche%22%7D">Porsche</a>&nbsp;has revealed a strange (and possibly brilliant) idea for a six-stroke combustion engine. If you don't know the fundamentals of an internal combustion engine, we'll try to keep this simple. If you<em> do</em> know how engines work ... we'll still try and keep it simple.</p> <p>With very few exceptions every combustion-powered car uses a four-stroke engine: intake, compression, power, and exhaust. The intake stroke is where air and fuel come into the cylinder. Compression is when the piston pushes that mixture to the top of the cylinder. The mixture is ignited, shoving the piston back down for the power stroke. Exhaust is the final step, pushing the remaining gas out of the cylinder.</p> <section contenteditable="false" draggable="true" data-widget="image" data-border="" data-id="7893499"> <span> <svg> <use xlink:href="https://www.motor1.com/design/dist/critical/icons/sprite-common-4-aab71d103bb6c273cab9291678c627d9.svg#search"></use> </svg> </span> <picture> <source type="image/webp" srcset=" https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s5/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.webp 213w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s6/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.webp 445w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s4/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.webp 889w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s3/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.webp 1280w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s2/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.webp 1440w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s1/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.webp 1920w " sizes="(max-width: 767px) calc(100vw - 30px), (max-width: 1023px) calc(100vw - 50px), 649px"> <source type="image/jpeg" srcset=" https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s5/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.jpg 213w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s6/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.jpg 445w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s4/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.jpg 889w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s3/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.jpg 1280w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s2/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.jpg 1440w, https://cdn.motor1.com/images/mgl/3W4vj6/s1/porsche-six-stroke-combustion-engine-patent.jpg 1920w " sizes="(max-width: 767px) calc(100vw - 30px), (max-width: 1023px) calc(100vw - 50px), 649px"> <img src="https://cdn.motor1.com/images/static/16x9-tr.png" alt="Porsche Six-Stroke Combustion Engine Patent" width="16" height="9" loading="lazy"> </picture> <p>Porsche</p> </section> <p>Porsche designers reckon they can add another compression and power stroke to this process. Documents filed with the US Patent and Trademark Office specifically describe this as "six individual strokes that can be divided into two three-stroke sequences." The added steps would occur between the traditional power and exhaust stroke. The first sequence, then, would be intake-compression-power, followed by compression-power-exhaust.</p> <p>To do this, Porsche's patent shows a crankshaft spinning on a ring with two concentric circles—an annulus. This alternates the center point of rotation, effectively lowering the piston's travel (bottom dead center) slightly for the added strokes. That in turn changes the compression, since the piston isn't traveling as far up (top-dead-center) in the cylinder. And that also means this engine has <em>two</em> top and bottom dead centers.</p> <p>Why all the complexity? In short, this design has the potential to generate more power with better efficiency. In a typical engine, only one stroke in four actually makes power. This changes the formula to one stroke in three, and it also burns up the mixture more thoroughly. Of course, the downside is added complexity. Whether the gains are enough to justify the design remains to be seen.</p> <p>As with many patents, it's possible this could never see the light of day. It's certainly an interesting idea, but perhaps more importantly, it suggests Porsche is working very hard at <a href="https://www.motor1.com/news/714168/porsche-v8-continue-2030s/" data-inline-widget="internal-links" data-type-id="0" data-params="%7B%22article_edition_id%22%3A%22714168%22%2C%22section%22%3A%221%22%2C%22alias%22%3A%22porsche-v8-continue-2030s%22%7D">finding ways to keep combustion engines alive</a> amid the push for electric power.</p> <section contenteditable="false" draggable="true" data-widget="related-content" data-widget-size="content" data-params="%7B%22type_id%22%3A0%2C%22title_id%22%3A%22%22%2C%22items%22%3A%5B%7B%22article_edition_id%22%3A%22713952%22%2C%22title%22%3A%22Ferrari%20Wants%20to%20Build%20an%20Upside-Down%2C%20Hydrogen%2C%20Twin-Supercharged%20Inline-Six%22%2C%22alias%22%3A%22ferrari-hydrogen-hybrid-supercar-patent%22%2C%22section%22%3A%221%22%2C%22is_video%22%3A%220%22%2C%22images%22%3A%7B%22s5%22%3A%22https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.motor1.com%2Fimages%2Fmgl%2FwlZZzL%2Fs5%2Fferrari-hydrogen-hybrid-sports-car.jpg%22%7D%7D%2C%7B%22article_edition_id%22%3A%22667392%22%2C%22title%22%3A%22Mazda%20Patent%20Shows%20Another%20Rotary%20Sports%20Car%2C%20This%20Time%20A%20PHEV%20With%20AWD%22%2C%22alias%22%3A%22mazda-rotary-sports-car-patent%22%2C%22section%22%3A%221%22%2C%22is_video%22%3A%220%22%2C%22images%22%3A%7B%22s5%22%3A%22https%3A%2F%2Fcdn.motor1.com%2Fimages%2Fmgl%2FojBPol%2Fs5%2Fmazda-rotary-sports-car-new-patent.jpg%22%7D%7D%5D%7D"> <p>More Cool Patents:</p>  </section>  </div> <!-- new gallery place, attached gallery --> <p> Source: <span><span>US Patent and Trademark Office</span> via <a target="_blank" href="https://www.autoguide.com/auto/manufacturers/porsche/new-patent-shows-how-porsche-plans-to-keep-combustion-alive-44613226" rel="noopener">AutoGuide</a></span> </p> <!-- Author info bottom -->       </div> </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Inside Annapurna Interactive's Mass Walkout (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.ign.com/articles/what-the-heck-has-been-going-on-at-annapurna-interactive-an-investigation</link>
            <guid>41607166</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 03:05:27 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/what-the-heck-has-been-going-on-at-annapurna-interactive-an-investigation">https://www.ign.com/articles/what-the-heck-has-been-going-on-at-annapurna-interactive-an-investigation</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41607166">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section><p>Last week, <a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-09-12/annapurna-video-game-team-resigns-leaving-partners-scrambling" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Bloomberg reported</a> that 25 people comprising the <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/annapurnas-entire-gaming-team-has-resigned">entire staff of Annapurna Interactive</a> walked out the door in a group resignation. But while some of the circumstances around their departure emerged in the reporting, one pressing question was left unanswered: why?</p><p>Having spoken to multiple individuals close to the situation who requested anonymity due to fear of reprisal, as well as an Annapurna spokesperson, IGN has pieced together a somewhat complex answer. Disagreements over the direction of the Interactive division, chaotic departures, communication breakdowns, and a perceived lack of leadership transparency at Annapurna Interactive led to a staff walk-out that has left 25 individuals jobless, Annapurna leaders scrambling, and numerous developers concerned about their contracts with the publisher.</p><h2>A Company Divided</h2><p>Though the collapse of Annapurna Interactive as we once knew it started earlier this year, its roots lie in the company's historical leadership structure. Annapurna Interactive was initially conceived as the gaming division of Annapurna Pictures, which was founded by film producer and billionaire Megan Ellison in 2011. Annapurna Interactive itself was spun up in 2016, tapping a staff of industry veterans including including former Sony creative director Nathan Gary, former Sony executive producer Deborah Mars, and former Sony producer Hector Sanchez for leadership roles. Sanchez left the company in 2019, and former Capybara Games co-founder Nathan Vella was brought on that same year.</p><p>The film side of Annapurna's business has undergone well-publicized struggles. In 2018, it was <a href="https://variety.com/2018/film/news/annapurna-larry-ellison-megan-ellison-vice-1202975648/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">bleeding enough money</a> to prompt Ellison's father, multi-billionaire Larry Ellison, to step in. By 2019, Annapurna Pictures was reportedly <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/business/story/2019-08-07/annapurna-pictures-explores-bankruptcy-in-a-major-potential-blow-to-indie-film" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">teetering on bankruptcy</a>, and in the ensuing years its film and TV output slowed significantly. Variety reports that Ellison <a href="https://variety.com/2021/film/news/megan-ellison-annapurna-scott-rudin-temper-1234951651/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">disappeared from public life in 2019 almost entirely</a>, leaving her business to largely run itself during the height of the pandemic. She reemerged in 2021, only to name Gary president over all of Annapurna, with Mars and Vella stepping into co-head roles at the Interactive division.</p><output data-cy="article-video"></output><p>In the ensuing years, Annapurna Interactive continued to grow, releasing financial and critical successes such as Stray, Outer Wilds, What Remains of Edith Finch, and Cocoon. While the company claims the Annapurna Pictures side of the business hasn't struggled in recent years, saying that film and TV were more profitable than Annapurna Interactive in 2023, a spokesperson alleged to IGN that Gary was a less-than-ideal steward of Annapurna Pictures. Under his guidance, they claim, resources were pulled away from film and TV, key executives were pushed out, and the company was largely refocused on gaming. Annapurna tells IGN that Gary also elevated co-founder James Masi to chief administrative officer, a role the spokesperson suggested was unnnecessary at a company of Annapurna's size. Notably, Annapurna did launch an animation division under Gary's tenure that released the critically-acclaimed film Nimona just last year, though an Annapurna spokesperson reached out to IGN post-publication with the assertion that it was Ellison who brought in Nimona as the foundation for what would become the animation division. IGN has reached out to Gary, but he declined to comment.</p><p>IGN understands that opinions of Ellison within Annapurna Interactive prior to 2024 varied from indifference to latent mistrust given <a href="https://variety.com/2021/film/news/megan-ellison-annapurna-scott-rudin-temper-1234951651/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">previous reports on her behavior toward employees</a>. Anonymous sources I spoke to all cited a strong fear of reprisal from Ellison in particular, given her resources, history, and reach. A few people referenced creative or compensation disagreements during their time at Annapurna that contributed to a general feeling Ellison would not keep promises. Multiple sources we spoke to described Ellison as a largely hands-off leader and rarely present in the gaming division, an attitude that for years suited many of Annapurna Interactive's employees just fine.</p><h2>Ad-Verset effects</h2><p>This was the state of things at the start of 2024 according to our sources. Prior to March of this year, work at Annapurna Interactive was business-as-usual, they say, until employees were suddenly informed mid-month that James Masi had been unexpectedly let go. An Annapurna spokesperson confirmed Masi was made redundant, saying that Ellison had <a href="https://www.hollywoodreporter.com/movies/movie-features/megan-ellison-second-coming-nimona-1235842667/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">chosen to step back in</a> at the company and oversee the Annapurna Pictures side again in an effort to re-invest in the film and TV side of the business. As a part of this, Annapurna claims that Ellison reinstalled Gary as head of Interactive, and deemed Masi's role unnnecessary.</p><p>However, at this time, Gary also left the company. Annapurna claims he left of his own accord in response to Masi's firing and his change in role. But sources say employees were told in the following days by leadership within Annapurna Interactive that Gary had been fired along with Masi. The belief that two of their leaders had been fired seemingly out of the blue sparked confusion and fury, and a handful of individuals quit in protest, including at least one other Interactive leader.</p><output data-cy="article-video"></output><p>The sudden resignation of multiple key individuals came as a shock to the company, and IGN understands that Ellison held a video call with Annapurna employees to discuss what had happened and find a way to move forward. On the call, Ellison allegedly expressed a desire to keep the entire group, including those who had been fired or resigned, together. In the following days, all the departed staff returned, including Gary and Masi, and discussions began for a potential spin-off of the company that would allow Gary and Ellison to achieve their respective visions with minimal disruptions to partner developers.</p><p>Roughly, the plan was for Gary and the Annapurna Interactive staff to become a new company called Verset, with ownership split between Annapurna and Verset's leaders. Verset would oversee all currently existing signed Annapurna Interactive projects, with revenue split between itself and Annapurna proper in Annapurna's favor. It would also be free to sign its own, independent deals. Developers IGN spoke to report being made aware the spin-off was happening in the following months, and were reassured their contracts would be fulfilled.</p><p>While employees understood such a venture would take time to get off the ground, in the ensuing months a number of events occurred that made some skeptical of Ellison's commitment to parting with Annapurna Interactive. In early summer, sources tell us that employees discovered Hector Sanchez had been quietly rehired back at Annapurna by Ellison and was working on gaming projects without the knowledge of the rest of the Interactive staff. The news wasn't made official until August that Sanchez had been appointed president of interactive and new media at Annapurna — a title that seemed to some as potentially at odds with Vella and Mars' roles at Interactive.</p><output data-cy="article-video"></output><p>Annapurna, for its part, claims that talks between Ellison and Sanchez began as far back as February for Ellison to fund a new venture Sanchez was planning <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/posts/hectorsanchez_after-5-eventful-years-ive-reached-the-activity-7160635971250589696-MDwF/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">after departing Epic Games</a>. As talks continued, Annapurna says Sanchez began negotiating with Remedy Entertainment for a deal related to film and TV spin-offs of its properties. However, when spin-off negotiations began to crystalize at Annapurna Interactive, Ellison offered Sanchez a position at Annapurna. The intent, per the spokesperson, was for Verset to become the company's indie arm, and for Sanchez to lead efforts in the AAA and AA-gaming space, including transmedia properties.</p><p>Which is how, months later, <a href="https://www.ign.com/articles/control-and-alan-wake-tv-and-movies-on-the-way-thanks-to-new-annapurna-partnership">Annapurna announced it was partnering with Remedy Entertainment</a> on film, TV, and other projects including funding support for Control 2. The press release, which IGN received, referenced both Sanchez and Ellison. But it doesn't reference Annapurna Interactive at all, and IGN understands Annapurna Interactive employees were only informed the deal was happening that morning. Employees, unaware of Ellison's plans or the status of the spin-off, were confused, concerned, and frustrated about the direction of the company and the future of its Interactive division, Verset or no Verset.</p><output data-cy="article-video"></output><p>While all this was going on, sources say that discussions with Ellison regarding the spin-off appeared to have stalled out, and in August Annapurna officially terminated discussion. Annapurna claims this was due to Gary's lack of response to requests for feedback on legal drafts, and in a statement sent to IGN after publication, doubled down. "Any implication Annapurna was backtracking on the deal is false. We agreed to high-level deal terms and signed a term sheet in early April, which makes it all the more surprising that we never got a response."</p><p>Meanwhile, multiple people told IGN that in those final months, they began to see signs of Ellison exercising greater involvement over Annapurna Interactive's deals, projects, and budgets in a way that began to make them further uncomfortable with the direction the company was taking overall.</p><p>All of this came to a head at the end of August when all 25 Annapurna Interactive employees including Gary, Vella, Masi, and Mars signed a joint resignation letter. The group gave two weeks notice and departed the company together on September 6 leaving Ellison, Sanchez, and newly-hired chief strategy officer Paul Doyle working on a semblance of Annapurna's gaming efforts. Sources tell IGN that up to the letter being sent and after, the group asked Ellison to work with them on other possible solutions such as the aforementioned spin-off, but did not receive any interest.</p><p>IGN also understands that despite the two-week notice, partner developers did not learn about the sudden exodus of all their Annapurna contacts until a day or two before it occurred. Annapurna claims they didn't have enough time to collect developer contact information to alert them sooner, while Annapurna Interactive sources say they received no guidance from the company during that period as to who should tell developers, when, and how. An Annapurna spokesperson reached out post-publication to IGN to deny this, claiming it had active and open conversations with the Interactive staff on how to communicate the news.</p><h2>Annapurna Aftermath</h2><p>While IGN couldn't glean any details on the future of the 25 departed employees, there are some indications that the group is collectively working on some new venture together. A <a href="https://verset.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">website for Verset</a> appears to be online at the time of publication with a PR alias, which IGN reached out to for comment. IGN was also unable to find any posts or other discussions from the departed members indicating they were looking for employment elsewhere. Whatever their future plans, IGN understands that the group did not have a ready-made venture waiting when they left, as some have speculated. If they build anything new, it will be largely from scratch.</p><p>Meanwhile, at Annapurna itself, efforts are underway to right the ship. Multiple developers I spoke to expressed a mixture of frustration and confusion at the sudden departure, but several told me they felt confident in Sanchez's ability to honor existing obligations. Several individuals with projects at different stages of development told me about meetings they'd had with Sanchez in the wake of the event that they reported had reassured them. Sanchez has previously stated his intention both to backfill roles as well as work with outside agencies to fulfill Annapurna's contractual obligations, and IGN has confirmed this process is ongoing. Earlier this week, Annapurna also posted an <a href="https://annapurnainteractive.com/en/jobs/publishing-team" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">open role for a QA Manager</a> overseeing "multiple external QA teams."</p><output data-cy="article-video"></output><p>The unusual situation appears to have impacted a few specific projects in unique ways. On August 30, iam8bit <a href="https://x.com/iam8bit/status/1829618620776734871" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">shared an announcement</a> that an upcoming PlayStation 5 physical edition of Outer Wilds: Archaeologist Edition had suffered from a manufacturing error, and did not include the Echoes of the Eye expansion as expected. Annapurna Interactive at the time said it would "continue to investigate", while iam8bit offered either a digital DLC voucher to impacted customers, or a replacement corrected physical copy. Both Annapurna and Interactive sources have told IGN that this issue is unrelated to the resignations, and Annapurna reassured that it will not be impacted by the upheaval at the company.</p><p>Then there's Blade Runner. Last summer, Annapurna Interactive announced it would be developing its first in-house game, based on the Blade Runner franchise, titled Blade Runner 2033: Labyrinth. However, game director Chelsea Hash appears to be one of the 25 individuals who resigned, per LinkedIn, and IGN understands that all other full-time members of the development team joined her. Annapurna has told IGN that development on Blade Runner 2033 will continue despite the departure of its entire team.</p><p>An Annapurna spokesperson also shared the following statement when asked for further comment:</p><p>"The whole situation is a baffler, but now we're focused on moving forward. We've had really great conversations with an overwhelming majority of our existing development teams and are grateful for their partnership. If our inbox is any indication, a ton of developers continue to want to be a part of what we're building, and we look forward to seeing their pitches. We've also had an influx of quality job applicants and are excited to build a team passionate about our mission to tell original stories that aren't being told elsewhere. P.S. We're hiring."</p><div data-cy="quoteBox"><p>The whole situation is a baffler.</p></div><p>Annapurna has splintered into two groups, both of which are now working to pick up the pieces. The remains of Annapurna Interactive (or perhaps a future Verset) consist of 25 individuals who felt strongly enough about perceived mismanagement, poor communication, apparent spontaneous layoffs of leaders, and one another that they were willing to give up paychecks and stability at a time of overwhelming industry job and funding uncertainty. When IGN approached its sources close to this group about Annapurna's version of events (specifically, the conflicting information around Masi and Gary's alleged resignation/firing and the collapse of spin-off discussions), they reacted with skepticism, but did not feel they could safely provide more specific details.</p><p>Meanwhile, at Annapurna, a tiny leadership team is struggling to ensure that around 40 projects have the support they need, while the company's partners have been left at various stages of development and uncertainty as to what comes next.</p><p>Annapurna Interactive as we once knew it — a beloved publisher of critically-acclaimed, unique, beloved indie games — is no more. What, if anything, will rise to take its place?</p><p><em>Rebekah Valentine is a senior reporter for IGN. Got a story tip? Send it to rvalentine@ign.com.</em></p><p><em>Additional statements from an Annapurna spokesperson were added to this piece post-publication.</em></p></section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[I Like Makefiles (343 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://switowski.com/blog/i-like-makefiles/</link>
            <guid>41607059</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 02:37:44 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://switowski.com/blog/i-like-makefiles/">https://switowski.com/blog/i-like-makefiles/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41607059">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>

<div>
<p>I like makefiles. I first used a makefile more than ten years ago. Even back then, it looked like some ancient technology used by the graybeard Linux wizards. Years passed, and new build tools came and went, but I kept seeing makefiles still used here and there. I got used to them because they were part of some projects I joined. At some point, I started to like them. Today, they are often the first automation tool I use when I start a new project.</p>
<p>The reason I like makefiles is that they often follow an unwritten convention of implementing the same set of commands to get you up and running. When I find a project I know nothing about, and I see a <code>Makefile</code> file inside, chances are that I can run <code>make</code> or <code>make build</code> followed by <code>make install</code>, and I will get this project built and set up on my computer. Or at least I will get information on other steps I need to include.</p>
<p>I try to apply the same rule in my projects. If I open a folder with one of my old projects and run <code>make dev</code>, this will perform all the necessary steps to build the project and spin up a dev server. That's convenient because throughout the years, I used many different technologies, and each had different commands to build or deploy a project. I have old projects written in Jekyll, Hugo, 11ty, and all sorts of different Python web frameworks. With makefiles, when I come back to a project I haven't touched for months (or years), I don't have to remember the command to start a dev server with, let's say, Jekyll. I just run <code>make dev</code>, and this, in turn, fires up the corresponding Bundler commands. Even if I use tools like Docker or gulp in my project, I still use makefiles to orchestrate those tools. For example, I often write a <code>make build</code> command that builds all the necessary Docker images, passing additional parameters specific to a given project.</p>
<p>My makefiles are simple. I don't use conditional statements, flags or any other fancy features. Most of the tasks (they are technically called <em>targets</em>, but I always call them <em>tasks</em> in my head) consist of one or more shell commands. I could write bash scripts with a couple of functions instead, but makefiles are easier and faster to write.</p>
<p>Some common tasks that most of my personal projects<sup><a href="#fn1" id="fnref1">[1]</a></sup> contain include:</p>
<ul>
<li><code>dev</code> to start the development server</li>
<li><code>build</code> to build the project (if a build step is necessary)</li>
<li><code>deploy</code> to deploy/publish the project</li>
</ul>
<p>And that's really it. Sometimes, I include additional tasks like <code>watch</code> to automatically rerun the build task when I change any of the source files. But many of my projects can be managed with just two or three Make commands.</p>
<p>This blog that you're reading right now has a simple makefile with just one target:</p>
<pre data-language="makefile"><code><span>dev</span><span>:</span><br>	npm run dev</code></pre>
<p>And a more advanced project of mine uses the following makefile to run the dev server, watch for changes, build, encrypt and deploy the website:</p>
<pre data-language="makefile"><code><span># Run dev server</span><br><span>dev</span><span>:</span><br>	bundle exec jekyll serve --unpublished -w --config _config.yml,_config-dev.yml --livereload<p><span># Build assets</span><br><span>build</span><span>:</span><br>	npm run gulp build</p><p><span># Watch a specific folder and process assets</span><br><span>watch</span><span>:</span><br>	npm run gulp watch -- --wip</p><p><span># Build the website locally, encrypt and deploy to Netlify server</span><br><span>deploy</span><span>:</span><br>	JEKYLL_ENV<span>=</span>production bundle exec jekyll build<span>;</span> \<br>	make encrypt<span>;</span> \<br>	netlify deploy --prod</p><p><span># Encrypt the "_site" folder</span><br><span>encrypt</span><span>:</span><br>	npx staticrypt _site/*.html -r -d _site</p></code></pre>
<p><a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/make/">GNU Make</a> (the software that runs makefiles) is quite ubiquitous. If you're on Linux, you probably already have it installed. Even on my MacBook, I don't remember installing it explicitly. It must have come with some other tools that I installed in the past. Make is simple and doesn't require as many additional dependencies as some other build tools. This can be useful if you need a tool that will work in a restricted environment where installing additional packages is difficult or impossible for security reasons. Make will probably be already present in that environment. And if not, you can just take the commands from the makefile and run them manually in the shell. If gulp is not available on your server, you can't really take the JavaScript code and paste that into the terminal.</p>
<p>I'm not against other build tools. I like other build tools too. I'm excited when I find a new one that is better and faster than the one I was using before. But I will still use Make to orchestrate them because it gives me a set of familiar commands to manage all sorts of different setups with different tools.</p>
<hr>
<section>
<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>By "personal", I mean projects where the deployment process is much simpler than production-grade stuff. <a href="#fnref1">↩︎</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</section>
</div>
</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Working in the office 5 days/week to build company culture is a myth: PwC report (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.msn.com/en-us/money/other/working-in-the-office-5-days-a-week-to-build-company-culture-is-a-myth-pwc-report-says/ar-AA1qU17L</link>
            <guid>41606772</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 01:19:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.msn.com/en-us/money/other/working-in-the-office-5-days-a-week-to-build-company-culture-is-a-myth-pwc-report-says/ar-AA1qU17L">https://www.msn.com/en-us/money/other/working-in-the-office-5-days-a-week-to-build-company-culture-is-a-myth-pwc-report-says/ar-AA1qU17L</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41606772">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Apple Shares Full iPhone 16 and iPhone 16 Pro Repair Manuals (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/20/iphone-16-repair-manual/</link>
            <guid>41606530</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 00:17:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/20/iphone-16-repair-manual/">https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/20/iphone-16-repair-manual/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41606530">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main" id="maincontent"><article expanded="true"><div data-io-article-url="/2024/09/20/iphone-16-repair-manual/"><p>Following today's launch of the new <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/roundup/iphone-16/">iPhone 16</a> models, Apple has shared repair manuals for the <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120652">iPhone 16</a>, the <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120662">iPhone 16 Plus</a>, the <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120803">iPhone 16 Pro</a>, and the <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120828">iPhone 16 Pro Max</a>. The repair manuals provide technical instructions on replacing genuine Apple parts in the ‌iPhone 16‌ models, and Apple says the information is intended for "individual technicians" that have the "knowledge, experience, and tools" that are necessary to repair electronic devices.</p>
<p><img src="https://images.macrumors.com/t/DyvENV2KG5ztE-4KmOdRWXddhB0=/400x0/article-new/2024/09/apple-iphone-battery-repair.png?lossy" srcset="https://images.macrumors.com/t/DyvENV2KG5ztE-4KmOdRWXddhB0=/400x0/article-new/2024/09/apple-iphone-battery-repair.png?lossy 400w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/yEUxiBQZnvr46Va0nt6XzXTb0nk=/800x0/article-new/2024/09/apple-iphone-battery-repair.png?lossy 800w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/iUIKJQgB3N_lYIBo-1A3ddoJHkQ=/1600x0/article-new/2024/09/apple-iphone-battery-repair.png 1600w,https://images.macrumors.com/t/BOLPZc3YRFrN04Tgf5yZ0UPmptw=/2500x0/filters:no_upscale()/article-new/2024/09/apple-iphone-battery-repair.png 2500w" sizes="(max-width: 900px) 100vw, 697px" alt="apple iphone battery repair" width="880" height="600"><br>Apple <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120983">has support documents</a> on the tools that are required for various repairs, and while the ‌iPhone 16‌ tools aren't yet available on <a href="https://www.selfservicerepair.com/en-US/order">Apple's Self Service Repair website</a>, they'll likely be added soon.</p>
<p>Compared to prior <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/iphone/">iPhone</a> models, the ‌iPhone 16‌ and ‌iPhone 16‌ Plus are easier to repair. Apple is using an electric battery removal process, and the steps for accessing a battery to replace it are outlined in a <a href="https://support.apple.com/en-us/120642">separate support document</a>. Per Apple's instructions, a 9-volt battery and 9-volt battery clips can be applied to the ‌iPhone 16‌ battery to remove the adhesive that holds it in place.</p>
<p>Note that the simpler electricity-based battery removal process is limited to the ‌iPhone 16‌ and ‌iPhone 16‌ Plus. For the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/roundup/iphone-16-pro/">iPhone 16 Pro</a> and Pro Max, Apple is using standard adhesive tabs that need to be carefully pulled to release the battery.</p>
<p>Apple's instructions for all of the battery repairs include expensive equipment like an ‌iPhone‌ battery press to put a replacement battery back in place. The cost of the tools required for device repair and the cost of genuine components make self repair almost as expensive as getting a repair from an Apple retail location or an Apple Authorized Service Provider, so these manuals are really aimed at independent repair shops rather than individual consumers.</p>
<p>Apple <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/18/iphone-16-repairability-changes/">made other changes</a> to the ‌iPhone 16‌ models this year to improve repairability, enabling on-device configuration for the <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/guide/mask-face-id/">Face ID</a> camera, allowing LiDAR Scanner repair, and offering support for swapping the TrueDepth camera modules between ‌iPhone 16‌ and ‌iPhone 16 Pro‌ models.</p>
<p>In addition to offering repair instructions, Apple's manuals provide some insight into the internal structure of the new iPhones that we often don't see until there <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/20/iphone-16-pro-teardown-video/">are device teardowns</a>. The ‌iPhone 16 Pro‌, for example, has a metal casing for the battery, a change made for thermal reasons, and both Pro models have new casing structure that improves heat dissipation.</p>
</div></article><p><h2>Popular Stories</h2></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/17/rip-apple-id/">RIP, Apple ID</a></h3><p>Tuesday September 17, 2024 3:18 pm PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>The "Apple ID" era is officially over. The transition from "Apple ID" to "Apple Account" went from a rumor to an official announcement to something that has now been fully completed. As of this week, the account.apple.com website is fully updated with Apple Account branding. "Apple ID is now Apple Account," the page says. "You can still sign in with the same email address or phone...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/15/ios-18-available-tomorrow/">iOS 18 Available Now With These 8 New Features For Your iPhone</a></h3><p>Sunday September 15, 2024 10:09 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>Following over three months of beta testing, iOS 18 was finally widely released to the public on Monday, September 16. The update is available in the Settings app under General → Software Update on the iPhone XS and newer. Below, we have highlighted eight key new features included in iOS 18, and Apple shared a complete list of new features and changes last week. Note that Apple...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/19/apple-lists-3-more-states-committed-to-wallet-ids/">Apple Announces iPhone Driver's Licenses Will Come to These Additional U.S. States</a></h3><p>Thursday September 19, 2024 10:45 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>In select U.S. states, residents can add their driver's license or state ID to the Wallet app on the iPhone and Apple Watch, providing a convenient and contactless way to display proof of identity or age at select airports and businesses, and in select apps. The list of states where the feature is available currently includes Arizona, Maryland, Colorado, Georgia, Ohio, Hawaii, and most recently...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/18/apple-airpods-pro-2-firmware-7a302/">Apple Releases New AirPods Pro 2 and AirPods 4 Firmware</a></h3><p>Wednesday September 18, 2024 11:34 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>Apple today released a new firmware update for all AirPods Pro 2 and AirPods 4 models. The AirPods Pro 2 firmware has a build number of 7A302, up from 7A294, and the AirPods 4 firmware has a build number of 7A304. There is no word yet on what’s included in the firmware, but it comes just a week after Apple last updated the AirPods Pro 2 firmware to add iOS 18 features like support for head...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/18/apple-breaks-17-year-tradition/">Apple Just Broke a Tradition It Held for 17 Years</a></h3><p>Wednesday September 18, 2024 7:40 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/joe-rossignol/" rel="author">Joe Rossignol</a></p><p>It's the end of an era. It has been confirmed that the latest iPhones do not come with Apple stickers in the box, breaking a 17-year tradition dating back to the original iPhone. Marques Brownlee shared an unboxing video that confirms the new iPhone 16, iPhone 16 Plus, iPhone 16 Pro, and iPhone 16 Pro Max do not include Apple stickers in the box, as part of Apple's goal of removing plastic...</p></div><div><h3><a href="https://www.macrumors.com/2024/09/17/apple-pulls-ipados-18-m4-ipad-pro/">Apple Pulls iPadOS 18 for M4 iPad Pro After Bricking Complaints [Updated]</a></h3><p>Tuesday September 17, 2024 11:24 am PDT by <a href="https://www.macrumors.com/author/juli-clover/" rel="author">Juli Clover</a></p><p>Apple stopped signing the iPadOS 18 update for the M4 iPad Pro models, which means the new software is no longer available to be downloaded and installed at the current time. The update appears to have been pulled following complaints from some iPad Pro owners, who found that the update bricked their devices. There are reports on Reddit from iPad Pro users who had an interruption in the...</p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[CISA boss: Makers of insecure software are the real cyber villains (126 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theregister.com/2024/09/20/cisa_sloppy_vendors_cybercrime_villains/</link>
            <guid>41606493</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 21 Sep 2024 00:05:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/09/20/cisa_sloppy_vendors_cybercrime_villains/">https://www.theregister.com/2024/09/20/cisa_sloppy_vendors_cybercrime_villains/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41606493">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="body">
<p>Software suppliers who ship buggy, insecure code are the true baddies in the cyber crime story, Jen Easterly, boss of the US government's Cybersecurity and Infrastructure Security Agency, has argued.</p>
<p>"The truth is: Technology vendors are the characters who are building problems" into their products, which then "open the doors for villains to attack their victims," declared Easterly during a Wednesday <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://mwise.mandiant.com/conf24/home">keynote</a> address at Mandiant's mWise conference.</p>
<p>Easterly also implored the audience to stop "glamorizing" crime gangs with fancy poetic names. How about "Scrawny Nuisance" or "Evil Ferret," Easterly suggested.</p>

    

<p>Even calling security holes "software vulnerabilities" is too lenient, she added. This phrase "really diffuses responsibility. We should call them 'product defects,'" Easterly said. And instead of automatically blaming victims for failing to patch their products quickly enough, "why don't we ask: Why does software require so many urgent patches? The truth is: We need to demand more of technology vendors."</p>
<blockquote>

<p>Why does software require so many urgent patches? We need to demand more of vendors</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While everyone in the audience at the annual infosec conference has job security, Easterly joked, it's also the industry's role to make it more difficult for miscreants to compromise systems in the first place.</p>
<p>"Despite a multi-billion-dollar cyber security industry, we still have a multi-trillion-dollar software quality issue leading to a multi-trillion-dollar global cyber crime issue," Easterly lamented.</p>

        


        

<p>While no one would buy a car or board an airplane "entirely at your own risk," we do that every day with the software that underpins America's critical infrastructure, she added.</p>
<p>"Unfortunately we have fallen prey to the myth of techno exceptionalism," Easterly opined. "We don't have a cyber security problem – we have a software quality problem. We don't need more security products – we need more secure products."</p>
<ul>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/07/01/cisa_big_tech_security/">CISA director: US is 'not afraid' to shout about Big Tech's security failings</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/08/cisa_ransomware_rsac/">CISA boss: Secure code is the 'only way to make ransomware a shocking anomaly'</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/09/68_tech_firms_sign_cisas/">68 tech names sign CISA's secure-by-design pledge</a></li>

<li><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/10/dod_usb_attack/">'Four horsemen of cyber' look back on 2008 DoD IT breach that led to US Cyber Command</a></li>
</ul>
<p>This is a drum Easterly has been <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2023/02/28/cisa_easterly_secure_software/">beating</a> since she took the helm of the US cyber defense agency. She tends to bang it louder at industry events, such as the annual RSA Conference where she <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/08/cisa_ransomware_rsac/">told</a> attendees secure code "is the only way we can make ransomware and cyber attacks a shocking anomaly."</p>
<p>Naturally, if writing flawless code was super easy, it would be done without fail. Some developers are clearly careless or clueless, leading to vulnerabilities and other bugs, and sometimes skilled humans with the best intentions simply make mistakes. In any case, Easterly isn't happy with the current defect rate.</p>

        

<p>Also at RSAC, nearly 70 big names – including AWS, Microsoft, Google, Cisco, and IBM – <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/05/09/68_tech_firms_sign_cisas/">signed</a> CISA's Secure by Design pledge – a commitment to "make a good-faith effort to work towards" seven secure-software goals within a year, and be able to measurably show their progress.</p>
<p>At mWise, Easterly revealed that number has grown to nearly 200 vendors.</p>
<p>But the pledge remains voluntary, so software companies who fail to follow its guidelines – such as increasing the use of multi-factor authentication across their products and reducing default passwords – aren't going to be slapped down if they ignore it.</p>
<div>
<h2 title="Not so much when trying to convert coding veterans">Google says replacing C/C++ in firmware with Rust is easy</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/09/06/google_rust_c_code_language/"><span>READ MORE</span></a></p></div>
<p>Easterly wants that to change. She suggested technology buyers use their procurement power to pressure software vendors, by asking suppliers if they have signed the pledge – and, hopefully, done more than just put ink to paper in terms of building <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cisa.gov/sites/default/files/2023-10/Shifting-the-Balance-of-Cybersecurity-Risk-Principles-and-Approaches-for-Secure-by-Design-Software.pdf">secure-by-design</a> [PDF] products.</p>
<p>To this end, CISA just published <a target="_blank" rel="nofollow" href="https://www.cisa.gov/resources-tools/resources/secure-demand-guide">guidance</a> that organizations buying software can use, and questions they should ask manufacturers, to better understand if they are prioritizing security in the product development life cycle.</p>

        

<p>"Use your voice, take an active role, use your purchasing power to advance secure by design, by demanding it," Easterly urged.</p>
<p>And then cross your fingers and pray that more and more vendors really do begin to take things like pre-release <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/08/01/crowdstrike_lawsuit/">software testing</a> and <a target="_blank" href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/06/15/microsoft_brad_smith_congress/">secure code</a> to heart. ®</p>                                


                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How do archivists package things? The battle of the boxes (116 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/</link>
            <guid>41605774</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 21:45:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/">https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41605774">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page" role="main">

			
				
<article id="post-9591">
	<!-- .entry-header -->

	<div>
		
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240409_093520-3819877179-e1725479157965.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9738" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20240409_093520/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240409_093520-3819877179-e1725479157965.jpg" data-orig-size="3024,2044" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="20240409_093520" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240409_093520-3819877179-e1725479157965.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240409_093520-3819877179-e1725479157965.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" width="470" height="317" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240409_093520-3819877179-e1725479157965.jpg?w=470" alt=""></a></figure>







<p>It’s been a while since we posted one of our articles pulling back the curtains on archival work. To make up for that, here’s a special edition of our popular <a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/category/archives-faqs-and-facts/">Archives FAQs and Facts</a> series. For the first time, we’ll compare how archivists in two countries do things a little differently to achieve a common goal.</p>



<p>We’ll show you how archivists package (or “house”) the most common types of physical documents for long-term storage. That is, we’ll talk <em>boxes</em> and <em>files</em>. And we’ll benefit from the experience of special contributors from the United Kingdom to compare how archivists in Canada and the UK commonly do their packaging.</p>



<p>To make the comparison easier, we’ll even coin some technical terms that may spark discussions among archives fans and followers.</p>



<p>This post came about for a few reasons:</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Stereotype busting</strong>: Fictional archives are often a far cry from reality, leading to misunderstandings when new users approach real archives.</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><strong>Public curiosity</strong>: Individuals and organizations often contact archivists and conservators (experts on repairing and stabilizing physical media) for advice about properly packaging their own valuable records. Perhaps some of our practices, revealed here, can be adapted for home and office use.</li>
</ul>



<ul>
<li><strong>Professional curiosity</strong>: I (Samantha at the Region of Peel Archives) have long noticed some intriguing differences in packaging practices between archives in the UK and North America. The comparison is a great way to showcase basic preservation measures.</li>
</ul>


<div>
<figure><img data-attachment-id="9761" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/archivist-barbie-jpeg/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archivist-barbie-jpeg.jpg" data-orig-size="675,900" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Archivist Barbie jpeg" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archivist-barbie-jpeg.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archivist-barbie-jpeg.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" width="675" height="900" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archivist-barbie-jpeg.jpg?w=675" alt=""><figcaption><em>This box carried by Archivist Barbie on social media is instantly identifiable as a archival box by archives aficionados in North America – perhaps not so much in other countries. (Courtesy of a <a href="https://x.com/NCArchives/status/1682055889220694016">twitter thread</a> by the State Archives of North Carolina.</em>)</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Why is this post called the “<em>battle</em> of the boxes”? First, this is a tongue-in-cheek reference to the friendly rivalry between the two common packaging styles we’ll look at. Archivists themselves sometimes take their local practices for granted. We hope that archival workers, as well as interested members of the public, might learn something about one another.</p>



<p>Second, and more seriously, archivists wage war every day against the universe’s tendency to disorder. Boxes and files are just some of the weapons in our arsenal, as we strive to keep the self-knowledge of humanity safe for as long as possible.</p>



<p>It’s only fitting, then, to begin by thanking the members of the worldwide community of preservationists who helped me with this post. I’m particularly grateful to Lizzy Baker and Rachel Gill (Archives Lead and Archivist respectively at the <a href="https://twarchives.org.uk/">Tyne &amp; Wear Archives</a> in Newcastle, UK) and Shirley Jones (Head of Conservation at the <a href="https://www.wyjs.org.uk/archive-service/">West Yorkshire Archive Service</a>, Wakefield, UK) for sharing their experience.</p>



<p>Thank you also to Penelope Bertrand and Elise Rowsome, collection managers at <a href="https://library-archives.canada.ca/eng/">Library and Archives Canada</a>, and Professor Don Spanner at Western University for helpful conversations.</p>



<h2><strong>Archival scenery and stereotypes</strong></h2>



<p>Our exploration of archival packaging begins with popping a pervasive stereotype. In fact, this balloon of expectation rapidly deflates for anyone visiting archival storage for the first time.</p>



<p>Archives in movies and TV often have a certain <em>look</em>: a jumble of odd-sized papers and books (mostly books), crammed on shelves and tables. This stuff looks varied and intriguing. (It’s much easier for stuff to look intriguing when it’s exposed.)</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/movies-packaging.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9642" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/movies-packaging/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/movies-packaging.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1245" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="movies packaging" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/movies-packaging.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/movies-packaging.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" width="1024" height="390" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/movies-packaging.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Scenes from the films </em>The Ring<em> and </em>Nostradamus<em>. Horror comes in many forms.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Of course, real archival shelves do host traditionally vintage-looking items, especially large tomes. (These shelves are frequently employed as photo op backdrops when archives appear in the news.) But the archivist’s guilty secret is that most stocked archival shelves look comparatively bland: row on row of identical boxes, filled with identical files, and cryptically labelled. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/shelves.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9727" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/shelves/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/shelves.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1778" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="shelves" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/shelves.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/shelves.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="557" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/shelves.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>Region of Peel Archives in Brampton, Ontario, Canada. </em>Right: <em>Tyne &amp; Wear Archives in Newcastle, UK. (Courtesy of Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Why would regularly sized boxes and files be the norm, especially if archival records run the gamut from maps, postcards, and reports, to letters, handbills, and photographs? In a way this question has answered itself, but let’s unpack it – pun intended.</p>



<h2><strong>Some “handy” terminology</strong></h2>



<p>The first thing that often surprises people is that archivists overwhelmingly use paper or cardboard packaging. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Paper containers are lightweight and breathable. (Trapped stagnant environments are attractive to pests and mould). Archival containers are specially treated to be acid-free. They may also contain a buffering agent that helps neutralize incoming acid from old documents. Low-acid packaging considerably slows the breakdown of naturally acidic records, especially in the controlled climate of archival vaults. For all these reasons (and more), archivists don’t put records and photos in ring-binders or albums.</p>



<p>In this post, we’ll concentrate on the <strong><em>most common</em> <em>sizes and combinations</em></strong> of archival boxes and files. We’re going to refer to these containers as <strong>s<em>tandard packaging</em></strong><em>.</em></p>



<p>In this common archival packaging method, records are placed in standard archival files which are then packed in standard archival boxes. In fact, archival boxes and files are so very standard that archives users instantly spot them when they occasionally appear in the media.</p>



<p>One of the key advantages of standard packaging is that it universally accommodates a particular range of common document sizes. For convenience, we’ll call this range <strong><em>hand-scale documents</em></strong>: documents that can be held comfortably between our hands held not too far apart. This range of sizes arguably encompasses the majority of paper and photographic records produced in daily life over the centuries, both before and after paper sizes were standardized.</p>



<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hand-scale-documents-examples.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9643" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/hand-scale-documents-examples/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hand-scale-documents-examples.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,2573" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="hand-scale documents examples" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hand-scale-documents-examples.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hand-scale-documents-examples.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="807" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hand-scale-documents-examples.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Files of hand-scale documents at the Region of Peel Archives. </em>From top left clockwise<em>: early 19th  century, mid-late 19th century, late 20th twentieth century, early 20th century</em>.</figcaption></figure>



<h2><strong>The benefits of uniformity</strong></h2>



<p>The aim of standard packaging is to enclose groups of records – in this case, hand-scale documents of variable sizes – in smaller packages (files) housed in larger packages (boxes).</p>



<p>Why? It’s easier to <em>control</em> records packed up this way. And for archivists dealing with lots of rare or evidential records, control means stability, and stability means accessibility over the long term. After all, in the world of archives, “long-term” means hundreds of years, and “lots” means thousands of boxes containing millions of individual records.</p>



<div><p><strong>How standard packaging maximizes control</strong></p><p><strong><em>Preservation control</em></strong>:</p><p><strong>Separating</strong> large volumes of documents into small groups (like files) minimizes overcrowding and damage from creasing and curvature.</p><p><strong>Shielding</strong> documents protects them from dust, fading, errant mould spores, and modest amounts of liquid, like the blood, sweat, and tears of archivists.</p><p><strong>Stabilizing</strong> documents reduces damage from unnecessary movement, shifting, and handling. Same-sized items stored next to one another (including boxes) are generally more stable than oddly sized items.</p><p><strong><em>Administrative control</em></strong>:</p><p><strong>Storing</strong> boxes efficiently maximizes our use of shelf space. Archivists are always chasing ways to optimize every costly square centimeter of real estate, and standard packaging wastes the least amount.</p><p><strong>Locating</strong> boxes on kilometres of shelving is easier if the boxes can be assigned precise, documented positions. Compact sequentially shelved boxes are documented more readily than jumbled formless piles.</p><p><strong>Manufacturing</strong> standard-sized boxes and folders is more efficient for vendors. This means better prices for archivists, since archival-quality packaging is already expensive. (To stabilize particularly fragile or oddly shaped records, conservators sometimes design and construct custom-fitted containers.)</p><p><strong><em>Intellectual control</em></strong>:</p><p><strong>Understanding</strong> archival records requires structure. Archivists <a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2015/08/26/how-do-archivists-organize-collections/">analyze and organize</a> records, and then synthesize structured overviews called <a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2016/02/29/how-do-archivists-describe-collections-or-how-to-read-a-finding-aid/">archival descriptions or finding aids</a>. Physical packaging is linked to these descriptions so that people know what they’re looking at. For example, a physical folder of records will correspond to a “file” in an archival description.</p><p><strong>Labelling</strong> records is easier with regular, clean packaging. File labels link records to their descriptions.</p></div>



<h2><strong>How we do it</strong></h2>



<p>What does all this actually look like on the inside? We’re going to show you, and from two different perspectives. We’ll demonstrate how standard packaging works in &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Canada</strong>, representing North America</li>



<li>The <strong>UK, </strong>also representing some European countries</li>
</ul>



<p>As we’ll see, there is one major difference between the two styles. We’ll dub the North American style <strong>vertical</strong> <strong>standard packaging</strong> and the UK style <strong>horizontal</strong> <strong>(flat) standard packaging</strong>. I have found that verticalist and horizontalist practitioners feel strongly about the strengths of their own style. It will be interesting to see if this blog post generates any discussion, heated or otherwise. And of course there are a variety of exceptions to what follows. (We’ll return to those at the end of this post.)</p>



<p>So, let’s look at each style<a> with respect to two major categories:</a></p>



<ol>
<li>Basic supplies: the physical containers we rely on</li>



<li>Basic configuration: how we use those supplies properly</li>
</ol>



<h2><strong>CANADA: VERTICAL standard packaging</strong></h2>



<p>The following shows how we do common packaging at the Region of Peel Archives.</p>



<p>This style tends to be fairly standard across North America, down to the physical dimensions of our supplies. (Just to make sure of this, I reached out to several Canadian experts who corroborated my sense that this packaging style is indeed routine across the continent.)</p>



<h2><strong>A. Basic supplies</strong></h2>



<p>Standard packaging in North America relies on two basic physical containers: the <strong>file folder</strong> and the<strong> box</strong>. These supplies are supplemented by various <strong>enclosures and separators</strong> for use within files.</p>



<p>The classic North American <strong>archival folder</strong> (also called a file or a file folder) is a folded piece of acid-free card. The open edge of the file sports a tab or raised edge on which we write information about the file contents, keyed to the <a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2016/02/29/how-do-archivists-describe-collections-or-how-to-read-a-finding-aid/">archival description</a>.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/file-folder.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9645" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/file-folder/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/file-folder.jpg" data-orig-size="1000,750" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="file folder" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/file-folder.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/file-folder.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1000" height="750" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/file-folder.jpg?w=1000" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>The typical North American archival file folder</em>.</figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>Boxes</strong> for hand-scale documents generally come in two main styles:</p>



<p><strong>The Hollinger</strong> <strong>Box</strong>: In the North American archives world, the Hollinger Box is iconic. The term <em>Hollinger</em> is to boxes as <em>Kleenex</em> is to tissues: used for any narrow upright file box, even ones not actually made by the Hollinger company. These smaller filing boxes are lighter to carry and easier to store.</p>



<p><strong>The Bankers Box</strong>: A commonly used larger box is the classic “Bankers Box.” This size of box is typically used in records centres of large organizations. An acid-free version is used for modern administrative records in archives. This box can be, let’s say, taxing on staff in the large volumes in which it tends to accumulate.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archival-boxes.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9648" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/archival-boxes/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archival-boxes.jpg" data-orig-size="1000,750" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Archival boxes" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archival-boxes.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archival-boxes.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1000" height="750" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/archival-boxes.jpg?w=1000" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Typical North American archival boxes including (from the left) a Bankers box, a Hollinger box, and a half-Bankers box, a new favourite of the Region of Peel Archives. Some brands have removable lids while  others have hinged lids.</em></figcaption></figure></div>






<div>
<div><p><strong>Like a glove</strong></p><p>It’s worth pointing out the close fit between the North American file and box. The two supplies are complementary, based on dimensions that evolved with record keeping itself.</p><p>In organizational office cultures, paper sizes were <a href="https://archive.org/details/DunnA.D.NotesOnTheStandardizationOfPaperSizes">standardized differently in North America than in the rest of the world.</a> In North America, two popular sizes of hand-scale paper exist: “letter-size” paper (8.5 X 11 inches) and “legal-size” paper (8.5 X 14 inches). </p><p>At the Region of Peel Archives (and in many other North America archives) we predominantly use the larger  <strong>legal-size folders</strong> designed to accommodate legal-size paper, along with boxes designed to accommodate both. Both Hollinger and Bankers boxes come in lengths constructed for legal-size files.</p><p>Naturally, many of our records predate this standard sizing; but we find that legal-size folders and boxes accommodate the majority of hand-scale documents created over many centuries. This includes all the examples of hand-scale documents depicted above.</p></div>



<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_115001.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9689" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20230901_115001/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_115001.jpg" data-orig-size="1000,750" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="20230901_115001" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_115001.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_115001.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1000" height="750" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_115001.jpg?w=1000" alt=""></a></figure>
</div>







<p>Last on our list of basic supplies are a variety of <strong>enclosures</strong> that we use <em>within</em> files to help further stabilize documents.</p>



<p>Enclosures, such as paper or <a href="https://postalmuseum.si.edu/choosing-safe-plastics">archivally acceptable plastic</a> sleeves, tend to have at least one open edge. This reduces the level at which the record will stew in its own juices (in a “microclimate”) without exposure to air circulation.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240411_131116-1-1241821945-e1725382689365.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9655" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/20240411_131116/" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240411_131116-1-1241821945-e1725382689365.jpg" data-orig-size="1332,1000" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="20240411_131116" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240411_131116-1-1241821945-e1725382689365.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240411_131116-1-1241821945-e1725382689365.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="470" height="352" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240411_131116-1-1241821945-e1725382689365.jpg?w=470" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Some examples of enclosures and sleeves, both paper and archival plastic</em>.</figcaption></figure></div>


<h2><strong>B. Basic configuration</strong></h2>



<p>Now let’s look at how these supplies work together. </p>



<p>As we’ve already hinted, at the Region of Peel Archives, as in most of North America, we package hand-scale files <strong>vertically</strong> in boxes. Files are held in place by the files on either side of them.&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_151222-679877836-e1725388304768.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9656" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20230831_151222/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_151222-679877836-e1725388304768.jpg" data-orig-size="1000,1139" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="20230831_151222" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_151222-679877836-e1725388304768.jpg?w=263" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_151222-679877836-e1725388304768.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="470" height="535" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_151222-679877836-e1725388304768.jpg?w=470" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>A Hollinger box of records at the Region of Peel Archives.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>To protect documents filed this way, we need to package them properly. Here are some guidelines we observe.</p>



<h2>Packing files ready for boxes</h2>



<p><strong>File folders should not be overfilled and should be adjusted appropriately</strong>. File folders should be manually squared off at the bottom to accommodate the thickness of the records within them. North American file folders generally come with an array of pre-scored lines for this purpose.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/good-and-bad-files.png"><img data-attachment-id="9660" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/good-and-bad-files-2/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/good-and-bad-files.png" data-orig-size="1584,898" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="good and bad files" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/good-and-bad-files.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/good-and-bad-files.png?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="580" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/good-and-bad-files.png?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left and centre<em>: Correctly foldering a thick file of modern office paper, and a slim file of 19th century documents. </em>Right<em>: Incorrectly foldering some 19th century deeds.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Packing files into boxes</h2>



<p><strong>Boxes should be filled snuggly with files, but not overfilled</strong>. Both overfilling and underfilling a box could cause damage like folding or curvature. Archivists test the ideal fit by eye, as well as by ease of access to files, and ability to fit an average hand down the back of a filled box.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230815_140623.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9684" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20230815_140623/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230815_140623.jpg" data-orig-size="3024,4032" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.4&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;SM-N975U&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1692108383&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.3&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;250&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.025&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;latitude&quot;:&quot;43.685456&quot;,&quot;longitude&quot;:&quot;-79.757296972222&quot;}" data-image-title="20230815_140623" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230815_140623.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230815_140623.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="768" height="1024" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230815_140623.jpg?w=768" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>A vertically filled box seen from above. This box includes file folders containing documents of varying sizes, and also an unpublished bound volume (book). When bound volumes are stored in boxes, we make sure their spines are facing downwards so that the weight of the text block (the pages) does not pull away from the spine.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>Any space left in a partially filled box needs to be braced</strong> so that files don’t slump over. Slumping and curvature are the primary risks of this packaging style. Some archivists tip the box on its side while filling it, and ask archives researchers to do the same when removing files for use.</p>



<div>
<div><p><strong>Filling the gap</strong></p><p>At the Region of Peel Archives, we have invented our own way of filling gaps in boxes with an accordioned piece of polyethylene foam (Ethafoam) sheeting affectionately known (by us) as a “puff.”</p><p>We find that the folded sheeting adjusts itself nicely as the gap is gradually filled with files. This method is more efficient and less wasteful for us than constructing custom-fitted cardboard spacers, especially as we try eventually to use every inch of space in every box. </p><p>The “puffs” can be reused many times, unlike custom-made spacers.</p></div>



<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filled-file-folders-1-1.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9745" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/filled-file-folders-1-2/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filled-file-folders-1-1.jpg" data-orig-size="1288,3264" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="filled file folders (1)" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filled-file-folders-1-1.jpg?w=118" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filled-file-folders-1-1.jpg?w=404" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="404" height="1023" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filled-file-folders-1-1.jpg?w=404" alt=""></a></figure>
</div>







<h2>Controlling documents inside files</h2>



<p>Archival files commonly contain more than one document. There are a couple of reasons for this. Foldering every individual document would add a lot of bulk. More importantly, records are often <a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2015/08/26/how-do-archivists-organize-collections/">closely related to other record</a>s: storing them together as a set maintains and clarifies these conceptual chunks.</p>



<p>Inside files we use a variety of means to stabilize individual documents and protect them from one another. This is where “house style” may vary between North American archival institutions. Below are some ways we use to stabilize documents at the Region of Peel Archives.</p>



<p><strong>Keeping multipage documents together</strong>. A single document may have multiple parts, such as a multipage report, or letters with envelopes or inserts. To clarify which pages belong together in a file of multipage documents we may use a piece of buffered acid-free paper as a thin sub-folder for each. Generally speaking, we try to associate pages without altering or damaging them.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_145510-1525188161-e1725401097809.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9675" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20230831_145510/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_145510-1525188161-e1725401097809.jpg" data-orig-size="1332,1000" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="20230831_145510" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_145510-1525188161-e1725401097809.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_145510-1525188161-e1725401097809.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="470" height="352" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230831_145510-1525188161-e1725401097809.jpg?w=470" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>The pages of this document are kept together inside a file by using a folded piece of bond paper.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>Of course, some documents come to us clipped together with staples or paperclips. These are removed if corroded, but archivists decide whether to remove <em>all</em> non-archival clips on a case-by-case basis. (Whether and how to replace them with archival paperclips is <a href="https://balliolarchivist.wordpress.com/tag/paper-clips/">controversial</a> even among archivists!)</p>



<p><strong>Stabilizing fragile records</strong>. A particularly fragile document may be placed in an enclosure, such as a polyester sleeve. (Again, only some plastics are suitable for archival use.) This sleeve allows researchers to view and handle the record safely. Similarly, photographic records like slides, negatives, and photographs may require extra protection to ensure the photographic emulsion (image layer) is not damaged. We may also use acid-free tissue paper to protect photographs or other easily scratched surfaces.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/fragile-records.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9678" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/fragile-records/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/fragile-records.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1597" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="fragile records" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/fragile-records.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/fragile-records.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="501" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/fragile-records.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>Photographs interleaved with archival tissue paper to protect image surfaces.</em> Right: <em>A fragile 19th-century letter protected by a Mylar sleeve and backed by a stiff piece of card.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>Stabilizing small records</strong>. Small records like tiny cards and notes, or photographic slides, can shift around and be overlooked more easily within standard files, particularly when housed with larger associated records (think of snapshots enclosed in a letter). We may put smaller items in sleeves to bring them closer to standard document sizes.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/small-records.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9683" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/small-records/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/small-records.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1754" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="small records" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/small-records.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/small-records.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="550" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/small-records.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Small photographs and slides are inserted into paper or polypropylene sleeves to stabilize and keep them in order within larger files. (Large collections of same-sized photographs may be stored in other ways.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Packing boxes on shelves</h2>



<p>Both Hollinger and Bankers boxes are shelved in a single layer on shelves specially designed for their height. As boxes aren’t piled on top of on another, this allows for quick retrieval and return.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_141744.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9687" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20230901_141744/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_141744.jpg" data-orig-size="3024,4032" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.4&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;SM-N975U&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1693577865&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.3&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;200&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.016666666666667&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;latitude&quot;:&quot;43.685461899722&quot;,&quot;longitude&quot;:&quot;-79.757217199722&quot;}" data-image-title="20230901_141744" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_141744.jpg?w=225" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_141744.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="768" height="1024" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230901_141744.jpg?w=768" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Removing a North American archival box from its shelf. Hollinger-style boxes sometimes come with a pullstring or handle to aid retrieval.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>The labelling on boxes gives no detailed information about the records within. Rather an identification code links the box to information about its contents and allows archivists to find the box on kilometres of shelving.</p>



<h2><strong>UNITED KINGDOM: HORIZONTAL (FLAT) standard packaging</strong></h2>



<p>The following is my synthesis of common UK practice, based on chats and visits with UK archivists over the years. Most recently, Lizzy, Rachel, and Shirley (mentioned in the introduction) have been my primary informants. Many thanks to all three for the accompanying photographs.</p>



<p>Photographs from both their practices are included: in the UK, box and file dimensions vary more considerably between archival institutions than they do in North America.</p>



<h2><strong>A. Basic supplies</strong></h2>



<p>Archivists in the UK also rely on boxes and folders for basic archival packaging of hand-scale documents. However, the exact dimensions of these supplies are not as interrelated or universal as in North America. &nbsp;Rather, archives order boxes that work with their shelving or document types. Then an archivist or conservator will buy or make folders to fit within the footprint of their boxes. &nbsp;</p>



<p><strong>Files</strong> are physically constructed in a variety of ways. Sometimes archivists use folders made of acid-free card. These are somewhat similar to standard North American file folders, but unlike the latter, they generally include flaps which enclose records or two or more sides. For thinner sets of records, archivists may use large acid-free envelopes as a file. In lieu of a file folder, they may also wrap sets of records in acid-free paper or tissue.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-folders.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9733" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/uk-folders/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-folders.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1245" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="UK folders" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-folders.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-folders.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="390" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-folders.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>Four-flap folder as used in the West Yorkshire Archive Service. (Courtesy and copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service, Conservation)</em>. Right: <em>Two-flap folder in use at the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.</em> <em>(Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>Boxes </strong>for documents in the UK tend to be shallow, with removeable lids.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-boxes.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9691" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/uk-boxes/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-boxes.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,2051" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="UK boxes" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-boxes.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-boxes.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="643" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-boxes.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>An empty archive box as used by the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives, who have them specially made to fit their shelves. (Courtesy of Tyne &amp; Wear Archives)</em>. Right: <em>Archive boxes on the shelves at the West Yorkshire Archives. (Courtesy and copyright of West Yorkshire Archive Service, Wakefield.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p><strong>Other UK supplies</strong>: </p>



<p>As we’ll see shortly, in the UK <strong>cotton tape</strong> is widely used to tie each file shut. And, as in North America, archivists use various ways of stabilizing and associating records within files, including sleeves and paperclips.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-supplies.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9729" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/uk-supplies/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-supplies.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1369" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="UK supplies" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-supplies.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-supplies.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="429" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/uk-supplies.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Basic packaging supplies and enclosures at the West Yorkshire Archive Service (left) and Tyne &amp; Wear Archives (right). Copyright and courtesy of these archives.</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2><strong>B. Basic configuration</strong></h2>



<p>Most archivists in the UK store hand-scale document files flat, by stacking them in shallow boxes.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-and-contents-2-723930952-e1725406716807.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9694" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/box-and-contents-2/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-and-contents-2-723930952-e1725406716807.jpg" data-orig-size="3024,2613" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="Box and contents (2)" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-and-contents-2-723930952-e1725406716807.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-and-contents-2-723930952-e1725406716807.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="470" height="406" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-and-contents-2-723930952-e1725406716807.jpg?w=470" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>A filled box at the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives showing two ways of packaging files, in folders and in large envelopes (see below).</em> (<em>Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Packing files ready for boxes</h2>



<p>In UK document boxes, files are commonly tied shut with archival tape made of cotton or linen. The knot or bow is placed to the side of the file. The archival citation is printed on the file so that the file can be identified and retrieved.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/tied-folder-out-of-box-3750063843-e1725407004929.jpeg"><img data-attachment-id="9698" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/tied-folder-out-of-box/" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/tied-folder-out-of-box-3750063843-e1725407004929.jpeg" data-orig-size="1817,2283" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="tied folder out of box" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/tied-folder-out-of-box-3750063843-e1725407004929.jpeg?w=239" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/tied-folder-out-of-box-3750063843-e1725407004929.jpeg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="470" height="590" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/tied-folder-out-of-box-3750063843-e1725407004929.jpeg?w=470" alt=""></a><figcaption><em>Closed and tied four-flap folder at the West Yorkshire Archive Service. (Courtesy and copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service, Conservation).</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Packing folders into boxes</h2>



<p>Files are laid flat in their boxes, one on top of the next, until the box is full.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filling-uk-boxes.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9699" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/filling-uk-boxes/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filling-uk-boxes.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1376" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="filling UK boxes" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filling-uk-boxes.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filling-uk-boxes.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="431" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/filling-uk-boxes.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>Stack of thicker tied folders ready for stacking into their box. (Courtesy and copyright of West Yorkshire Archive Service.)</em> Right: <em>Loaded box of stacked files. (Courtesy and copyright of The John Goodchild Archive and Antiquarian Collection, West Yorkshire Archive Service, Wakefield.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<p>For this orientation to work, files must be packaged correctly.</p>



<ul>
<li><strong>Folders should not be overfilled</strong> past their capacity, to avoid curvature of records.</li>



<li><strong>The edges of records should be well clear</strong> of the edges of the folder before folding the flaps.</li>



<li><strong>The knot of the archival tape should be tied to the side</strong> so that a file on top doesn’t experience a pressure point from a knot on the file beneath it.</li>



<li><strong>Files should be stacked for maximum stability</strong> and protection: for instance, archivists place heavier, thicker, or broader files near the bottom of the stack to avoid damage to lighter, smaller packages.</li>



<li><strong>Boxes should be filled to the top </strong>so that the box lid does not buckle inwards from the weight of boxes placed on top of it. &nbsp;</li>
</ul>



<h2>Controlling records inside files</h2>



<p>As in North America, UK archives each have their own in-house preferences for controlling documents within files. The range of practices on both sides of the pond are very similar.</p>



<p>That said, one uniquely British way of controlling documents within files includes the use of the “treasury tag,” particularly for modern government files. The treasury tag is piece of cord with wide ends. Holes are punched through one corner of a stack of related papers or enclosures, and the cord loosely passed through them. The tag ensures that papers from a file can’t become disassociated while being used. You can learn more about how tags are applied in <a href="https://cdn.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documents/paper-files-preparation-guidance.pdf">guidance</a> from the UK’s National Archives. (Not all UK archives apply new tags, but many will receive records that have been tagged before reaching the archives.)</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/treasury-tags.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9701" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/treasury-tags/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/treasury-tags.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1376" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="treasury tags" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/treasury-tags.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/treasury-tags.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="431" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/treasury-tags.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>Treasury tags of different lengths made to accommodate different file thicknesses. Right: A file bound with a treasure tag. (Courtesy of the National Archives</em> <u><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20211103021220/https://cdn.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documents/information-management/preparation-of-records.pdf">Preparation of Records</a></u>.<em>)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2>Storing boxes on shelves</h2>



<p>Flat storage boxes in the UK are stacked one on top of the other within the limits of shelf depth and the pressure from accumulated weight.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-shelves-uk.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9708" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/box-shelves-uk/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-shelves-uk.jpg" data-orig-size="3264,1778" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="box shelves UK" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-shelves-uk.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-shelves-uk.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="557" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box-shelves-uk.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a><figcaption>Left: <em>Double stacks of boxes at the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives. (Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</em> Right:<em> Triple stacks of boxes at the West Yorkshire Archives</em>. <em>(Courtesy and Copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service, Wakefield.)</em></figcaption></figure></div>


<h2><strong>Face-off: advantages and disadvantages</strong></h2>



<p>Over the years, I’ve met archivists from both sides of the Atlantic who were initially surprised by one another’s packaging style. The generous professionals I spoke with for this post have risen to the challenge of direct comparison. Below is our collective sense of the relative strengths and weaknesses of our differing styles. We agree that both methods have advantages and disadvantages, and that both work as long as guidelines are observed.</p>



<h2>Vertical packaging</h2>



<p><strong>Advantages:</strong></p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230418_113608.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9703" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/20230418_113608/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230418_113608.jpg" data-orig-size="4032,3024" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;2.4&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;SM-N975U&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;1681817768&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;4.3&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;250&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0.0083333333333333&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;,&quot;latitude&quot;:&quot;43.685460972222&quot;,&quot;longitude&quot;:&quot;-79.757260972222&quot;}" data-image-title="20230418_113608" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230418_113608.jpg?w=300" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230418_113608.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="1024" height="768" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20230418_113608.jpg?w=1024" alt=""></a></figure></div>


<ul>
<li>Documents are gently suspended and don’t move around very much even if the box is jostled.</li>



<li>The only edge of a document touching its file (the bottom edge) is protected from damage or folding by this sandwiching of the entire document.</li>



<li>Records are free from the weight of other records being stored on top of them.</li>



<li>Stacks of larger items do not curve around stacks of smaller items. (Curvature of larger items around other items can be a problem with items stored on top of each other.)</li>



<li>One file can be easily removed without having to rummage through a pile, cutting down on handling.</li>



<li>Boxes are not weighed down by other boxes on top of them.</li>



<li>One box can be removed from a shelf without removing other boxes, again cutting down on handling.</li>



<li>By reading the top file tabs you can see at a glance what the box contains.</li>



<li>The open-at-the-top file allows for healthy air circulation.</li>



<li>Packaging, retrieving, and replacing documents, files, and boxes is relatively quick.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Disadvantages</strong>:</p>



<ul>
<li>Improperly filled files and boxes can cause curvature and damaged edges.</li>



<li>Contents of files can spill out if a box is dropped or tipped and the lid comes off.</li>



<li>When boxes are being filed, or when files are removed for use, the remaining files can slump.</li>
</ul>



<h2>Horizontal (flat) packaging</h2>



<p><strong>Advantages</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Flat storage ensures gravity is acting on documents equally at all points. This helps protect documents from problems with slumping and curvature.</li>



<li>As long as documents and boxes are not overweighted, horizontal storage helps to flatten and immobilize documents.</li>



<li>Folders that completely encase documents and are tied shut offer the maximum protection from dust and light, and from being dropped and scattered.</li>



<li>Folders of varying dimensions can be stacked in a single box.</li>
</ul>



<p><strong>Disadvantages</strong></p>



<ul>
<li>Sometimes multiple folders need to be removed from boxes to search for and remove a particular folder. This does increase overall handling of records.</li>



<li>Sometimes boxes may need to be moved to access other boxes below them. &nbsp;</li>



<li>Archives researchers don’t always retie tape appropriately, so archivists need to monitor tying. &nbsp;</li>



<li>Tape that is too tight or improperly tied can cause notching in the sides of records or files.</li>



<li>Packaging, retrieving, and replacing documents and their containers can be a little more time-consuming.</li>
</ul>



<h2><strong>Wrapping up</strong></h2>



<p>Interestingly, the horizontal versus vertical division we’ve looked at is echoed in archives around the world. Glimpses of archival storage on social media posts suggest that across Europe, for example, both methods are followed. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<p>What is the basis for what seems a big difference (to archivists anyway)? The answer likely lies in the emphasis on vertical storage in the US after the invention of the filing cabinet in the late 19th century – and the fact that many North American archives put down formal roots after this time. Media historian <a href="https://camd.northeastern.edu/people/craig-robertson/#:~:text=Craig%20Robertson%20is%20a%20media,storage%20and%20circulation%20of%20information.">Craig Robertson</a> has written a fascinating <a href="https://placesjournal.org/article/the-filing-cabinet-and-20th-century-information-infrastructure/">article</a> and now a <a href="https://www.upress.umn.edu/9781517909468/the-filing-cabinet/">book</a> on vertical storage and its role in office culture for those who wish to pursue a direct link to the archival <a href="https://www.hollingermetaledge.com/our-history/#:~:text=Hollinger%20Metal%20Edge%20was%20founded,of%20valuable%20documents%20and%20photographs.">Hollinger box</a>.</p>



<p>Aside from habits rooted in history, our preferences may be philosophical and aesthetic. British conservator Sheila Jones muses that there is a sense in which flat storage visually symbolizes a shift in status. Horizontal storage, she suggested in our conversation, gives us a sense that archival records are special: their active “work is done, and they may now lie down in their boxes” safely and behind the scenes.</p>



<p>Perhaps, in the end, we should focus on the ultimate goal of preservation. In that spirit, we return to some commonalities. Here are some caveats all our archivists wanted you to know.</p>


<div>
<figure><a href="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/wonky-uk-and-can.jpg"><img data-attachment-id="9706" data-permalink="https://peelarchivesblog.com/2024/09/10/how-do-archivists-package-things-the-battle-of-the-boxes/wonky-uk-and-can/#main" data-orig-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/wonky-uk-and-can.jpg" data-orig-size="1800,3264" data-comments-opened="1" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;1&quot;}" data-image-title="wonky UK and Can" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/wonky-uk-and-can.jpg?w=165" data-large-file="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/wonky-uk-and-can.jpg?w=470" tabindex="0" role="button" loading="lazy" width="565" height="1024" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/wonky-uk-and-can.jpg?w=565" alt=""></a><figcaption>Top: <em>Shallow flat boxes stacked one on top of the other at the Region of Peel Archives in Canada. </em>Bottom: <em>Shallow flat boxes turned on their sides in a single layer at the National Archives of the UK.</em> (<em>Courtesy of the <a href="https://cdn.nationalarchives.gov.uk/documents/paper-files-preparation-guidance.pdf">National Archives</a></em>.)</figcaption></figure></div>


<p>First, our packaging methods do overlap. For instance, the Region of Peel Archives routinely stores records in flat shallow boxes if those records are larger than our legal-size folders. We’ll even wrap certain types of records in acid-free paper, and tie wrappers shut with linen tape!</p>



<p>And in the UK, a few archives routinely store some records vertically. An interesting example is the <a href="https://www.nationalarchives.gov.uk/">National Archives</a> in the UK, which uses a hybrid method: shallow boxes are loaded flat, and then tied up with tape and turned on their sides in storage.</p>



<p>Second and relatedly, remember that our show-and-tell above applies to one <em>very common range of sizes and types of records</em>, that is, hand-scale documents. Most institutional archives collect records that fall outside this range. Indeed, the sheer variety and fragility of the world’s documentary heritage means archivists and conservators must show considerable ingenuity and skill in storing it safely. This blog post has not been able to cover a host of packaging challenges, including audiovisual and digital records (those are, as they say, another story). &nbsp;Below you’ll find a slideshow gallery of other packaging configurations. &nbsp;</p>



<p>Finally, what we’ve represented above is an ideal. The volume of valuable records increases exponentially and relentlessly year by year, at pace with the human activity that produces it. Archivists and conservators often need to triage repackaging: they must balance availability for public access against packaging perfection. For example, sometimes archivists must decide if the original containers in which files arrive might suffice for the short or the long term. In such cases, we will remove the most destructive elements of original packaging – such as plastics that eventually turn to gluey slime, or rusting paperclips – while retaining relatively stable original containers.</p>



<p>Archival work is, if nothing else, a compromise with reality. While we can’t halt time, we can slow down its effects using the humble ammunition of packaging.</p>



<h2><strong>Bonus gallery of packaging picks</strong></h2>



<p>We conclude with a casual stroll through archival packaging examples from both the UK and Canada that go beyond what we’ve explored above. (We feel morally obligated to point out that all boxes depicted below have lids, even when not shown!) We hope this slideshow demonstrates our unity of purpose and practice on both sides of the Atlantic.   &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p>



<div data-effect="fade"><ul><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1000" height="1333" alt="" data-id="9788" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240909_153939.jpg"><figcaption>A photograph album in a flat box at the Region of Peel Archives. Highly acidic albums and scrapbooks are a challenge if photos and other documents are glued into them, or pages feature important annotations. Often the best we can do is store the album as is, perhaps interleaving pages with acid-free tissue.</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3024" height="4032" alt="" data-id="9710" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240409_093312.jpg"><figcaption>Vellum (parchment) deed with wax seal, stabilized in a flat box at the Region of Peel Archives.</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3024" height="4032" alt="" data-id="9715" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/al.jpg"><figcaption>Custom-made box for a particularly fragile bound volume at the West Yorkshire Archive Service. (Anne Lister Diary No. 12, 1829 – 1830. SH:7/ML/E/12. Photograph courtesy and copyright of West Yorkshire Archive Service, Calderdale.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3024" height="4032" alt="" data-id="9713" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/box.jpg"><figcaption>A custom-made large shallow box constructed to house an illuminated vellum (parchment) document with an attached seal, shown on the conservation desk at the West Yorkshire Archive Service. (Inspeximus of Henry VIII, WYL100/HX/A/42, West Yorkshire Archive Service, Leeds. Photograph courtesy and copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1816" height="2420" alt="" data-id="9718" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/flat-maps-and-plans.jpeg"><figcaption>Large shelves for very large maps at the West Yorkshire Archive Service. (Courtesy and copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service, Wakefield.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="4032" height="3024" alt="" data-id="9716" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/hanging-storage.jpg"><figcaption>Hanging storage for framed items and historic signage at Tyne &amp; Wear Archives. (Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="2336" height="3504" alt="" data-id="9711" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/img_2666.jpg"><figcaption>Storage of large flat maps and plans at the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives. (Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1816" height="2420" alt="" data-id="9717" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/photographs-2.jpeg"><figcaption>Photographs housed in uniformly sized sleeves in a divided box. (Courtesy and copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service, Conservation.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3504" height="2336" alt="" data-id="9712" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/plan-box.jpg"><figcaption>Rolled plans in special slots at the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives. (Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1816" height="2420" alt="" data-id="9719" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/rolled-tyvek-plans.jpeg"><figcaption>Specialty storage for large rolled plans at the West Yorkshire Archive Service. (Courtesy and copyright of the West Yorkshire Archive Service, Wakefield.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3024" height="4032" alt="" data-id="9714" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/vertical-storage-of-glass-plate-negatives.jpg"><figcaption>Glass negatives stored vertically in a box at the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives. (Courtesy of the Tyne &amp; Wear Archives.)</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="4032" height="3024" alt="" data-id="9723" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/img_0329.jpg"><figcaption>Loose and bundled turn-of-the-century tickets from an abandoned railway route stored in a flat box at the Region of Peel Archives.</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="4032" height="3024" alt="" data-id="9724" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/img_0390.jpg"><figcaption>Awkwardly shaped and oversize records in a flat box at the Region of Peel Archives.</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3024" height="4032" alt="" data-id="9725" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/img_0405.jpg"><figcaption>Wrapped ledgers at the Region of Peel Archives.</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1000" height="1333" alt="" data-id="9754" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240904_110326.jpg"><figcaption>A growing collection of postcards housed in sleeves in a complementary box, at the Region of Peel Archives.</figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="1000" height="750" alt="" data-id="9756" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240904_114009.jpg"><figcaption>Map cabinets at the Region of Peel Archives, housing broadsides (posters), maps, plans, and other large-scale documents. </figcaption></figure></li><li><figure><img loading="lazy" width="3024" height="4032" alt="" data-id="9720" src="https://peelarchivesblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/20240411_133653.jpg"><figcaption>Fragile and compromised glass plate negative stabilized in a custom enclosure made by a conservator, at the Region of Peel Archives. </figcaption></figure></li></ul></div>



<p>Posted by Samantha Thompson, Senior Archivist</p>
			</div><!-- .entry-content -->

	</article><!-- #post-9591 -->

				
					<!-- #nav-below -->
	
				
	
	<!-- #comments .comments-area -->
			
			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Dropbox keeps threatening to delete my files (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://khromov.se/dropbox-keeps-threatening-to-delete-my-files/</link>
            <guid>41605719</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 21:36:30 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://khromov.se/dropbox-keeps-threatening-to-delete-my-files/">https://khromov.se/dropbox-keeps-threatening-to-delete-my-files/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41605719">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>

	
		<article>

					
	
	
			<section>
				
<p>For the past two years, I’ve been on the receiving end of a passive aggressive win-back campaign from Dropbox. The feud originally started when I migrated away from Dropbox and hence canceled my subscription while leaving them saddled with over a terabyte of my data to carry forever, like a camel in the digital desert. After all, why wouldn’t I? I was assured by their help forums that my files <strong>would not be deleted, no matter what</strong>:</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34.png"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="1024" height="244" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-1024x244.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-1024x244.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-300x72.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-768x183.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-1536x366.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-2048x488.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-1920x458.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-1680x400.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-1240x296.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-860x205.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-680x162.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-500x119.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-400x95.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-250x60.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-200x48.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-100x24.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-76x18.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.36.34-50x12.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>However, this hasn’t prevented Dropbox from trying to get me back. It all started innocently enough:</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39.png"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="56" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-1024x56.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-1024x56.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-300x17.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-768x42.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-1536x85.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-2048x113.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-1920x106.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-1680x93.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-1240x68.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-860x47.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-680x37.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-500x28.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-400x22.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-250x14.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-200x11.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-100x6.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-76x4.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-17-at-22.40.39-50x3.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>Thanks Dropbox, for letting me know and being there to help! Unfortunately, I had no desire to reactivate my account. Over the next couple of years, Dropbox has tried every trick in the book to get me back – they’ve tried letting me know I’m “100x over the limit”, stating things are “pretty urgent” and that I have to “Open ASAP”. I also appreciate the haphazard use of punctuation and emojis in this email chain. So far I’ve received over 50 emails. I’m honestly a bit sad about the person who has to presumably sit and come up with a new email title every week to keep cranking up the tension. At this point, I’m half expecting them to show up at my doorstep with a pleading look.</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41.png"><img decoding="async" width="1024" height="478" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-1024x478.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-1024x478.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-300x140.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-768x358.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-1536x717.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-2048x956.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-1920x896.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-1680x784.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-1240x579.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-860x401.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-680x317.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-500x233.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-400x187.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-250x117.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-200x93.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-100x47.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-76x35.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.37.41-50x23.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>Seeing as I was not impressed by being 100x over my limit, Dropbox tried 500x next. Surely this would get my attention!</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="94" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-1024x94.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-1024x94.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-300x27.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-768x70.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-1536x141.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-2048x188.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-1920x176.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-1680x154.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-1240x114.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-860x79.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-680x62.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-500x46.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-400x37.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-250x23.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-200x18.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-100x9.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-76x7.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.41.44-50x5.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>When that didn’t help either, Dropbox <strong>went back on its promise and finally threatened to delete my files</strong> in a series of countdown emails culminating with this 15 day reminder:</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="74" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-1024x74.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-1024x74.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-300x22.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-768x56.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-1536x112.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-2048x149.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-1920x140.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-1680x122.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-1240x90.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-860x63.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-680x49.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-500x36.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-400x29.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-250x18.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-200x15.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-100x7.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-76x6.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.42.53-50x4.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>They even tried setting a date!</p>



<figure><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="53" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-1024x53.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-1024x53.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-300x15.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-768x40.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-1536x79.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-2048x106.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-1920x99.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-1680x87.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-1240x64.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-860x44.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-680x35.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-500x26.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-400x21.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-250x13.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-200x10.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-100x5.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-76x4.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-01.05.28-50x3.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>



<p>The date came and went, but conspicuously, my files were not deleted, although the email linked to a more sternly worded support article <a href="https://help.dropbox.com/storage-space/over-quota" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">saying they would eventually delete data if over quota</a>. Clearly the policy had shifted, although <a href="https://www.dropboxforum.com/t5/Plans-and-Subscriptions/Will-I-lose-my-files-if-I-downgrade/td-p/306877" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">the now incorrect answer is still the top search result</a>. So far though, Dropbox decided to just pretend they never sent the previous email chain and went right back to their previous tactic of strongly suggesting an upgrade.</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1024" height="387" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-1024x387.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-1024x387.png 1024w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-300x113.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-768x290.png 768w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-1536x581.png 1536w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-2048x775.png 2048w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-1920x726.png 1920w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-1680x635.png 1680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-1240x469.png 1240w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-860x325.png 860w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-680x257.png 680w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-500x189.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-400x151.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-250x95.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-200x76.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-100x38.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-76x29.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.44.26-50x19.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></a></figure>



<p>Logging into the web portal, Dropbox gleefully told me I can “Upload anything”, in a bright red alert box, ending with a “Upgrade for more” button. But my files are still there, possibly waiting for when the emails finally get to me and make me resubscribe again.</p>



<figure><a href="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29.png"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="666" height="354" src="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29.png" alt="" srcset="https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29.png 666w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-300x159.png 300w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-500x266.png 500w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-400x213.png 400w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-250x133.png 250w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-200x106.png 200w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-100x53.png 100w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-76x40.png 76w, https://khromov.se/wp-content/uploads/2024/09/Screenshot-2024-09-18-at-00.34.29-50x27.png 50w" sizes="(max-width: 666px) 100vw, 666px"></a></figure>



<p><strong>What’s the lesson here?</strong> Perhaps it’s that we shouldn’t trust corporations to keep their word. Or maybe  that promising to host files in perpetuity for non-paying customers is a business model with some obvious flaws. Regardless, I’m curious to see how long this digital standoff will last. Will they eventually delete my files, or will I be receiving increasingly desperate emails well into my retirement years? Only time will tell!</p>



<p><em>Social share image generated using FLUX.</em></p>
				
			</section>

			
    

				
	<div>
			
			<p>Full-stack impostor syndrome sufferer &amp; Software Engineer at Schibsted Media Group</p>
			
		</div>
	
			
	

	<section>

		<a id="comments"></a>

		

	</section>


			
	


			
			<a href="https://khromov.se/svelte-5-brings-up-to-50-bundle-size-decrease-for-existing-svelte-4-apps/">
			
			
			<p>Next Post</p>
			<div>
				<p><span><span>Guides &amp; Tutorials</span></span></p><h3>Svelte 5 brings up to 50% bundle size decrease for existing Svelte 4 apps</h3>
				<p>Watch a video version of this blog post below! Svelte 5 brings a lot of changes, from...</p>
			</div>
		</a>
	

		</article>

	

			</section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Critical Exploit in MediaTek Wi-Fi Chipsets: Zero-Click Vulnerability (194 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.sonicwall.com/en-us/2024/09/critical-exploit-in-mediatek-wi-fi-chipsets-zero-click-vulnerability-cve-2024-20017-threatens-routers-and-smartphones/</link>
            <guid>41605680</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 21:28:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.sonicwall.com/en-us/2024/09/critical-exploit-in-mediatek-wi-fi-chipsets-zero-click-vulnerability-cve-2024-20017-threatens-routers-and-smartphones/">https://blog.sonicwall.com/en-us/2024/09/critical-exploit-in-mediatek-wi-fi-chipsets-zero-click-vulnerability-cve-2024-20017-threatens-routers-and-smartphones/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41605680">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

				<main role="main" itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="https://schema.org/Blog">

                    <article itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="https://schema.org/BlogPosting" itemprop="blogPost"><p><a href="https://blog.sonicwall.com/en-us/author/securitynews/"><span><img src="https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/ultimatemember/3368/profile_photo-190x190.png?1726884307" width="81" height="81" alt="Security News" data-default="https://blogtest.sonicwall.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/user_default-avatar.png" onerror="if ( ! this.getAttribute('data-load-error') ){ this.setAttribute('data-load-error', '1');this.setAttribute('src', this.getAttribute('data-default'));}"></span></a></p><div><header><h2><em></em></h2><br><time>September 19, 2024</time></header><div itemprop="text"><h3>Overview</h3>
<p>The SonicWall Capture Labs threat research team became aware of the threat CVE-2024-20017, assessed its impact and developed mitigation measures for the vulnerability. CVE-2024-20017 is a critical zero-click vulnerability with a CVSS 3.0 score of 9.8, impacting MediaTek Wi-Fi chipsets MT7622/MT7915 and RTxxxx SoftAP driver bundles used in products from various manufacturers, including Ubiquiti, Xiaomi and Netgear. The affected versions include MediaTek SDK versions 7.4.0.1 and earlier, as well as OpenWrt 19.07 and 21.02. This translates to a large variety of vulnerable devices, including routers and smartphones. The flaw allows remote code execution without user interaction due to an out-of-bounds write issue. MediaTek has released patches to mitigate the vulnerability and users should update their devices immediately. While this vulnerability was <a href="https://corp.mediatek.com/product-security-bulletin/March-2024" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">published</a> and patched back in March, only recently did a public <a href="https://github.com/mellow-hype/cve-2024-20017/tree/main" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">PoC</a> become available making exploitation more likely.</p>
<h3>Technical Overview</h3>
<p>The vulnerability resides in wappd, a network daemon included in the MediaTek MT7622/MT7915 SDK and RTxxxx SoftAP driver bundle. This service is responsible for configuring and managing wireless interfaces and access points, particularly with Hotspot 2.0 technologies. The architecture of wappd is complex, comprising the network service itself, a set of local services that interact with the device’s wireless interfaces, and communication channels between components via Unix domain sockets.&nbsp; Ultimately, the vulnerability is a buffer overflow as a result of a length value taken directly from attacker-controlled packet data without bounds checking and placed into a memory copy.&nbsp; This buffer overflow creates an out-of-bounds write.</p>
<h3>Triggering the Vulnerability</h3>
<p>The vulnerability exists in the IAPP_RcvHandlerSSB function where an attacker controlled length value is passed to the IAPP_MEM_MOVE macro as described in hyprdude’s <a href="https://blog.coffinsec.com/0day/2024/08/30/exploiting-CVE-2024-20017-four-different-ways.html" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">blog</a> and seen in Figure 1.</p>
<div itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject"><p><a href="https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/Figure1-6.png" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer"><img src="https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/Figure1-6.png" alt="" title="Figure1" itemprop="thumbnailUrl"></a></p></div>
<p><em>Figure 1: Vulnerable Code sourced from hyprdude</em></p>
<p>Prior to the last line which calls IAPP_MEM_MOVE, the only bounds check done is to check that the provided length does not exceed the maximum packet length of 1600 bytes. As the size of the destination struct is only 167 bytes, this results in a stack buffer overflow of up to 1433 bytes. To trigger this vulnerability an attacker must send a packet with the expected structures prepending the attack payload.&nbsp; These structures are referred to as the RT_IAPP_HEADER and the RT_IAPP_SEND_SECURITY_BLOCK within the code.&nbsp; To bypass validation checks the length of the RT_IAPP_HEADER struct needs to be small and the RT_IAPP_HEADER.Command field must be to 50.</p>
<h3>Exploitation</h3>
<p>The publicly available exploit code achieves remote code execution by using a global address table overwrite technique via a return-oriented programming (ROP) chain. This method leverages the `system()` call to execute commands, such as sending a reverse shell back to the attacker. The reverse shell is established using Bash and the existing Netcat tool on the chipset. Figure 2 illustrates how the reverse shell command is crafted and embedded within the payload to enable this exploitation tactic.</p>
<div itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject"><p><a href="https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/Figure2-8.png" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer"><img src="https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/Figure2-8.png" alt="" title="Figure2" itemprop="thumbnailUrl"></a></p></div>
<p><em>Figure 2: Reverse Shell Commands</em></p>
<h3>SonicWall Protections</h3>
<p>To ensure SonicWall customers are prepared for any exploitation that may occur due to this vulnerability, the following signatures have been released:</p>
<ul>
<li>IPS: 20322 MediaTek MT7915 wlan Service OOB Write 1</li>
<li>IPS: 20323 MediaTek MT7915 wlan Service OOB Write 2</li>
</ul>
<h3>Remediation Recommendations</h3>
<p>Due to the availability of the exploit code, it is highly recommended that users upgrade to the latest version of the firmware for their respective chipset.</p>
<h3>Relevant Links</h3>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://corp.mediatek.com/product-security-bulletin/March-2024" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">https://corp.mediatek.com/product-security-bulletin/March-2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://blog.coffinsec.com/0day/2024/08/30/exploiting-CVE-2024-20017-four-different-ways.html" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">https://blog.coffinsec.com/0day/2024/08/30/exploiting-CVE-2024-20017-four-different-ways.html</a></li>
<li><a href="https://securityonline.info/cve-2024-20017-cvss-9-8-zero-click-exploit-discovered-in-popular-wi-fi-chipsets-poc-published/" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">https://securityonline.info/cve-2024-20017-cvss-9-8-zero-click-exploit-discovered-in-popular-wi-fi-chipsets-poc-published/</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/mellow-hype/cve-2024-20017/tree/main" data-wpel-link="external" target="_blank" rel="external noopener noreferrer">https://github.com/mellow-hype/cve-2024-20017/tree/main</a></li>
</ul>

<div id="sexy-author-bio"><p><a href="https://blog.sonicwall.com/en-us/author/securitynews/" target="_top" data-wpel-link="internal"><img src="https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/ultimatemember/3368/profile_photo-190x190.png?1726884306" width="100" height="100" alt="Security News" data-default="https://blogtest.sonicwall.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/04/user_default-avatar.png" onerror="if ( ! this.getAttribute('data-load-error') ){ this.setAttribute('data-load-error', '1');this.setAttribute('src', this.getAttribute('data-default'));}"></a></p><p>The SonicWall Capture Labs Threat Research Team gathers, analyzes and vets cross-vector threat information from the SonicWall Capture Threat network, consisting of global devices and resources, including more than 1 million security sensors in nearly 200 countries and territories. The research team identifies, analyzes, and mitigates critical vulnerabilities and malware daily through in-depth research, which drives protection for all SonicWall customers. In addition to safeguarding networks globally, the research team supports the larger threat intelligence community by releasing weekly deep technical analyses of the most critical threats to small businesses, providing critical knowledge that defenders need to protect their networks.</p></div></div></div><span>
			<span itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject" itemprop="image">
					   <span itemprop="url">https://d3ik27cqx8s5ub.cloudfront.net/blog/media/uploads/sec-news-header-3.png</span>
					   <span itemprop="height">500</span>
					   <span itemprop="width">1200</span>
				  </span><span itemprop="publisher" itemtype="https://schema.org/Organization" itemscope="itemscope">
				<span itemprop="name">Security News</span>
				<span itemprop="logo" itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/ImageObject">
				   <span itemprop="url">https://blog.sonicwall.com/wp-content/uploads/images/logo/SonicWall_Registered-Small.png</span>
				 </span>
			  </span><span itemprop="author" itemscope="itemscope" itemtype="https://schema.org/Person"><span itemprop="name">Security News</span></span><span itemprop="datePublished" datetime="2024-09-19T05:57:13-06:00">2024-09-19 05:57:13</span><span itemprop="dateModified" itemtype="https://schema.org/dateModified">2024-09-19 05:57:13</span><span itemprop="mainEntityOfPage" itemtype="https://schema.org/mainEntityOfPage"><span itemprop="name">Critical Exploit in MediaTek Wi-Fi Chipsets: Zero-Click Vulnerability (CVE-2024-20017) Threatens Routers and Smartphones</span></span></span></article>
				<!--end content-->
				</main>

				

			</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Qualcomm Wants to Buy Intel (168 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/20/24249949/intel-qualcomm-rumor-takeover-acquisition-arm-x86</link>
            <guid>41605449</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 20:57:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/20/24249949/intel-qualcomm-rumor-takeover-acquisition-arm-x86">https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/20/24249949/intel-qualcomm-rumor-takeover-acquisition-arm-x86</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41605449">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>On Friday afternoon, <a href="https://www.wsj.com/business/deals/qualcomm-approached-intel-about-a-takeover-in-recent-days-fa114f9d?st=i5zay9xbq899g24&amp;reflink=article_copyURL_share"><em>The Wall Street Journal</em> reported</a> Intel had been approached by fellow chip giant Qualcomm about a possible takeover. While any deal is described as “far from certain,” according to the paper’s unnamed sources, it would represent a tremendous fall for a company that had been the most valuable chip company in the world, based largely on its x86 processor technology that for years had triumphed over Qualcomm’s Arm chips outside of the phone space. </p><p>It would also be a massive coup for Qualcomm, which reentered the desktop processor market this year <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/6/26/24186432/microsoft-windows-on-arm-qualcomm-copilot-plus-pcs-prism-emulator">as a part of Microsoft’s AI PC strategy</a> after years of dominance in mobile processors.</p><p>Intel, meanwhile, is arguably in its weakest position in years — while many of its businesses are still profitable, the company announced substantial cuts, shifts in strategy, <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/8/1/24210656/intel-is-laying-off-over-10000-employees-and-will-cut-10-billion-in-costs">and a 15-plus percent downsizing of its workforce this August</a> after reporting a $1.6 billion loss. </p><p>At the time, Intel CEO Pat Gelsinger said the company would stop all nonessential work and has since announced <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/16/24246599/intel-foundry-independent-spinoff">it will spin off its chipmaking business</a>, a part of the company that it had long touted as a strength over rival AMD and the many fabless chipmakers that rely on entities like Taiwan’s TSMC to produce all of their actual silicon. </p><p>Intel, too, recently had to partially rely on TSMC to produce its most cutting-edge chips as it continues to rebuild its own manufacturing efforts (<a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/4/2/24119454/intels-chipmaking-business-7-billion-loss">the costs of which</a> are responsible for most of Intel’s recent losses). And its own 18A manufacturing process <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/4/24235682/intel-18a-chipmaking-process-broadcom-test">reportedly ran into some recent trouble</a>.</p><p>While Intel’s chief rival, AMD, also had hard times over the years and had to claw its way back, gamers helped AMD every step of the way. Aside from the Nintendo Switch, whose processors are made by Nvidia, every major game console for the last decade has featured an AMD chip — and Intel <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/16/24246234/playstation-6-rumor-sony-intel-amd">reportedly lost out on a chance to change that with the future PlayStation 6</a>. </p><div><p>Intel also recently lost some faith with PC gamers after <a href="https://www.theverge.com/24216305/intel-13th-14th-gen-raptor-lake-cpu-crash-news-updates-patches-fixes-motherboards">two generations of its flagship chips were found vulnerable to strange crashes</a>, though Intel has since agreed to extend the warranties by multiple years and issued updates that could prevent damage.</p></div><p>Many of Intel’s woes are about silicon leadership, not just manufacturing or profits — the company isn’t a big player in AI server chips yet <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/2/1/24058186/ai-chips-meta-microsoft-google-nvidia">as Nvidia dominates</a>, nor even necessarily <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/7/30/24209938/amd-q2-2024-earnings-datacenter-ai-revenue">a notable small one like AMD</a>. Even its attempts to produce its own GPUs for gamers and creators <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2023/3/21/23650611/intel-raja-koduri-gpus-amd-nvidia-apple-leave-ai-startup">have yet to impress</a>.</p><p>And while Qualcomm, AMD, and Apple are all still smaller players in laptops, Intel has now <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/6/3/24169115/intel-lunar-lake-architecture-platform-feature-reveal">twice overhauled how it makes flagship laptop chips</a> to combat the growing threat of their seeming battery life and integrated graphics advantages. We’re waiting to see if its <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2024/9/3/24233957/intel-lunar-lake-core-ultra-200v-launch">new Lunar Lake chips</a> succeed in October and beyond.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Discord Reduced WebSocket Traffic by 40% (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://discord.com/blog/how-discord-reduced-websocket-traffic-by-40-percent</link>
            <guid>41604267</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 18:09:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://discord.com/blog/how-discord-reduced-websocket-traffic-by-40-percent">https://discord.com/blog/how-discord-reduced-websocket-traffic-by-40-percent</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41604267">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="heading-1"><p>At Discord, we’re always thinking about ways to improve our services and increase performance. After all, the faster our app gets, the sooner you can return to your friends and conversations!&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>Over the last six months, we embarked on a quest to support this endeavor, working to reduce the amount of bandwidth our clients use, especially on iOS and Android, hoping that decreasing bandwidth usage would lead to a more responsive experience.</p><h2>Background</h2><p>When your client connects to Discord, it receives real-time updates about what’s happening through a service that we call the “gateway.” Since late 2017, the client’s gateway connection has been compressed using zlib, making messages anywhere from 2 to 10 times smaller.</p><p>Since then, <a href="https://facebook.github.io/zstd/">zstandard</a> (originally released in 2015) has gained enough traction to become a viable replacement for zlib. Zstandard offers higher compression ratios and shorter compression times and supports <a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd#dictionary-compression-how-to">dictionaries</a>: a way to preemptively exchange information about compressed content, further increasing compression ratios and reducing the overall bandwidth usage.</p><p>We attempted to use zstandard in the past, but, at the time, the benefits weren’t worth the costs. Our testing in 2019 was desktop-only and used too much RAM. However, a lot can happen in five years! We wanted to give it another try, and the support for dictionaries appealed to us, especially as most of our gateway payloads are small and in a well-defined shape.</p><p>We believed the predictability of these payloads would be a perfect application of dictionaries to further reduce bandwidth usage.</p></div><div id="heading-2"><p>Armed with this knowledge, we put on our lab coats, slapped on our goggles, and started experimenting. On paper, we thought zstandard would be better than zlib but we wanted to validate this theory against our current workload.</p><p>We opted to do a “dark launch” of plain zstandard: the plan was to compress a small percentage of production traffic both with zlib and zstandard, collect a bunch of metrics, then discard the zstandard data. This allowed us to experiment with zstandard to quickly compare its results against zlib. Without this experiment, we would have to add zstandard support for our clients — desktop, iOS, and Android — which would require about a month’s lead time before we could fully determine the effects of zstandard. We didn’t know how well zstandard would perform and didn’t want to wait a whole month, but a dark launch allowed us to iterate over days as opposed to weeks.</p><p>Once we got our experiment set up and deployed onto our gateway cluster, we set up a dashboard to see how zstandard performed. We flipped the switch to start sending a teeeeeny bit of traffic through the dark launch code, and the initial results appeared to be… underwhelming. Zstandard was performing <em>worse</em> than zlib was.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5caa61ad96d1a395f51d_AD_4nXeCYg9XJmJM9EPtYhMpoXSrE89c5FHDpTPo-_g1CsEEAhiib-D8EUGRZlxPL9CDWw0hmSeRVdGLCJPqkwdIpt5oi80KsHQL5bxIJfOJ3dC76sFgSpj8Lh4f6lqEfsZXpdpywTPUdoEFsRo6WIPHiLyQMmt9.png" loading="lazy" alt="A compression ratio chart for Zstandard. The chart reads: “User Guild Settings Update: 12.26. Guild Emojis Update: 7.35. Ready Supplemental: 7.04. Thread Member List Update: 6.88.”"></p><figcaption>Zstandard compression ratio</figcaption></figure><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5d5aa15a87d53673cd47_AD_4nXdmCN0zlF9hxaVHFEwrEkJO5kEqsRq92ig73v31W-8gg9_yRUAryJqJC3jWGCzy3vJ_F1OvvUj9AQXwaYORhAmLoij9PWsswGH9-zagbN2AxVeG7Xs6fC0LEnZpCWZ5VjiTudVionBiCAhSz21suEQaNn0.png" loading="lazy" alt="A compression ratio chart for Zlib. The chart reads: “User Guild Settings Update: 13.95. Guild Member List Update: 9.86. Auto Moderation Action: 9.56. Voice Channel Effect Send: 9.27.” "></p><figcaption>Zlib compression ratio</figcaption></figure><p>To compare the performance of these two compression algorithms, we used their “compression ratio.” The compression ratio is measured by taking the uncompressed size of the payload and dividing it by the compressed size — a larger number is better.</p><p>Looking at the images above, which measure the compression ratio for the various dispatch types (<a href="https://discord.com/developers/docs/topics/opcodes-and-status-codes#gateway-gateway-opcodes">op 0</a>), with zlib, <strong>user_guild_settings_update</strong> has a compression ratio of 13.95 while with zstandard it has a compression ratio of 12.26.&nbsp;</p><p>The graph below further illustrates that zstandard performed worse than zlib: the average size of a <strong>MESSAGE_CREATE</strong> payload compressed with zlib was around 250 bytes, while with zstandard, the same payload was over 750!</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5d81a15a87d53673ff18_AD_4nXc_N1o4Qmj70b_Oh8Oh9xlMRZNw2hTyEkkFy8_hzYeDBJ-S99ejgt9MPkNp6kgVPoT_YX-NV-hMKMNFgSlOr1nerXGqpN_HCc3JvKoH86TMaM4II92Mw_NhbTVkCMy5g85ka153WCZ7-QHmsrEJ7j3mNqD8.png" loading="lazy" alt="A bar chart comparing compression methods to payload sizes. Zlib lands at just over 250 bytes, while zstandard reaches over 750 bytes."></p></figure><p>The same trend was observed for most other dispatches: zstandard was not outperforming zlib like we thought it would. What’s going on here?</p></div><div id="heading-3"><h2>Streaming Zstandard<br></h2><p>It turns out that one of the key differences between our zlib and zstandard implementations was that zlib was using streaming compression, while zstandard wasn’t.&nbsp;</p><p>As mentioned previously, most of our payloads are comparatively very small, only a few hundred bytes at most, which doesn’t give zstandard much historical context to work with to further optimize how it compresses future payloads. With streaming compression, the zlib stream is spun up when the connection is opened and exists until the websocket is closed. Instead of having to start fresh for every websocket message, zlib can draw on its knowledge of previously compressed data to inform its decisions on how to process fresh data. This ultimately leads to smaller payload sizes.</p><p>The question then became: “could we get zstandard to do this?” The answer to that was… “sorta.” Our gateway service is written in elixir, and while zstandard supports <a href="https://facebook.github.io/zstd/zstd_manual.html#Chapter7">streaming compression</a>, the various zstandard bindings for elixir/erlang we looked at didn’t.&nbsp;</p><p>We ultimately settled on using <a href="https://github.com/silviucpp/ezstd">ezstd</a> as it had dictionary support (more on that later).While it didn’t support streaming at the time,in the spirit of open source we forked ezstd to add support for streaming, which we later <a href="https://github.com/silviucpp/ezstd/pull/15">contributed back upstream</a>.</p><p>We then repeated the dark launch experiment, but with zstandard streaming and got the following results:</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb68683aeb8f2ee1063854_AD_4nXfRJh2JKRqLoQC5EiZuN5E8wmWEr5yAZGx07y5u_eTvqMYlzOVTTmdggzgp8-hJNWSlPklg7zjMyccyIaZkWF45AGSjvvmlhk-kzDIgaG004-6R_Ow_WnEuIbZHLvXes5AzunAPS9Jo0iA8MrZyD_vVHZ4.png" loading="lazy" alt=""></p><figcaption><strong>Message Create Compression Ratios</strong></figcaption></figure><p>‍</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5dc8045b706867911f67_AD_4nXc5poqnDTStFq1yAQdxKYlNM76Ikyol_-1Erb2E7IQK-MozKtL7u3BFjtSlkP9-RTZNzQFZFoP1Uxpq7PB4oNDRoc3mv0cxVvk4roDqtroLtGDfstiAsyVy_i6W4TSLCHH6JMu8QvJWoYRc7Y5UrDOMQo0.png" loading="lazy" alt="A bar chart comparing payload sizes of  Zlib streaming, zstandard, and zstandard streaming. Zlib streaming payloads are over 250 bytes, while zstandard hits over 750 bytes. Zstandard streaming payloads land at under 250 bytes."></p></figure><p>As the above data illustrates, zstandard streaming increased the compression ratio from 6 to almost 10 and dropped the payload size from 270 bytes to 166.</p><p>This trend held true for most of the other dispatches: zstandard streaming significantly outperforms zlib both in time to compress and compression ratio.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5dfe1481af30f65a3830_AD_4nXdEg8Tp2r5wYGbJoYw-s0ezvLu8cc6JMntlFtBC1k8MmK4Nh1cQ29yItE62RM1VSVCa9N663_OGdmYBAwmJfVxMlEvX0Vjr0t8H6Kucg3LgSrjaUvyRo_Wyw3vebN1ui4-wIOSVRGte9IAKysiZxdiLFwrI.png" loading="lazy" alt="A chart comparing MESSAGE_CREATE times between zlib streaming and zstandard streaming. Zlib streaming takes just over 100 microseconds, while zstandard streaming lands at under 50 microseconds."></p></figure><p>Looking once again at <strong>MESSAGE_CREATE</strong>, the compression time per byte of data is significantly lower for zstandard streaming than zlib, with zlib taking around 100 microseconds per byte and zstandard taking 45 microseconds.</p></div><div id="heading-4"><h2>Pushing Further</h2><p>While our initial experimentation proved that zstandard streaming outperformed zlib streaming, the remaining question we had was: “How far can we push this?” Our initial experiments used the default settings for zstandard and we wanted to know how high we could push our compression ratio by playing around with the compression settings.</p><p>So how far did we get?</p><h3>Tuning</h3><p>Zstandard is highly configurable and enables us to tweak various compression parameters. We focused our efforts on three parameters that we thought would have the biggest impact on compression: chainlog, hashlog, and windowlog. These parameters offer trade-offs between compression speed, memory usage, and compression ratio. For example, increasing the value of the chainlog generally improves the compression ratio, but at the cost of increasing memory usage and compression time.</p><p>We also wanted to ensure that with the settings we decided on, the compression contexts would still fit in memory on our hosts. While it’s simple to add more hosts to soak up the extra memory usage, extra hosts cost money and at some point, provide diminishing returns on the gains.</p><p>We settled on an overall compression level of 6, a chainlog and hashlog of 16, and a windowlog of 18. These numbers are slightly above <a href="https://github.com/facebook/zstd/blob/a761013b0390892e8728fc45171f831cf23c3792/lib/compress/clevels.h#L25">the default settings that you can see here</a> and would comfortably fit in the memory of a gateway node.</p><h3>Zstandard Dictionaries</h3><p>Additionally, we wanted to investigate if we could take advantage of zstandard’s dictionary support to compress data even further. By pre-seeding zstandard with some information, it can more efficiently compress the first few kilobytes of data.&nbsp;</p><p>However, doing this adds additional complexity as both the compressor (in this case, a gateway node) and the decompressor (a Discord client) need to have the same copy of the dictionary to communicate with each other successfully.</p><p>To generate a dictionary to use, we needed data… <em>and a lot of it</em>. Zstandard has a built-in way to generate dictionaries (<em>zstd --train</em>) from a sample of data, so we just had to collect a whooole buncha samples.&nbsp;</p><p>Notably, the gateway supports two encoding methods for payloads: JSON and <a href="https://www.erlang.org/doc/apps/erts/erl_ext_dist.html">ETF</a>, and a JSON dictionary wouldn’t perform as well on ETF (and vice versa) so we had to generate two dictionaries: one for each encoding method.</p><p>Since dictionaries contain portions of the training data and we’d have to ship the dictionaries to our clients, we needed to ensure that the samples we would generate the dictionaries from were free of any personally-identifiable user data. We collected data involving 120,000 messages, split them by ETF and JSON encoding, anonymized them, and then generated our dictionaries.</p><p>Once our dictionaries were built, we could use our gathered data to quickly evaluate and iterate on its efficacy without needing to deploy our gateway cluster.</p><p>The first payload we tried compressing was “READY.” As one of the first (and largest) payloads sent to the user, READY contains most of the information about the connecting user, such as guild membership, settings, and read states (What channels should be marked as read/unread). We compressed a single READY payload of 2,517,725 bytes down to 306,745 using the default zstandard settings which established a baseline. Utilizing the dictionary we just trained, the same payload was compressed down to 306,098 bytes – a gain of around 600 bytes.</p><p>Initially, these results seemed discouraging, but we next tried compressing a smaller payload, called TYPING_START, sent to the client so it can show the “XXX is typing…” notification. In this situation, a 636 byte payload compresses down to 466 bytes without the dictionary and 187 bytes with the dictionary. We saw much better results with our dictionaries against smaller payloads simply due to how zstandard operates.&nbsp;</p><p>Most compression algorithms “learn” from data that has already been compressed, but with small payloads, there isn’t any data for it to learn from. By preemptively informing zstandard what the payload is going to look like, it can make a more informed decision on how to compress the first few kilobytes of data before its buffers have been fully populated.</p><p>Satisfied with these findings, we deployed dictionary support to our gateway cluster and started experimenting with it. Utilizing the dark launch framework, we compared zstandard to zstandard with dictionaries.</p><p>Our production testing yielded the following results:</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5f2170b2edf1b422de56_AD_4nXfFOonNWIBnci1c-cNsmJKSC5uTEVj23McFJu-0dXGzFsoaZIyLciEpiqwJC_KSr2QP5U0nEEsba_AcriUbIcATZqRqYz7GN3qjn_UcU9QiR2TDIH_FiaANBNDnWgu3HlwgX83yHxNf3eE-Dzz1DMfWA3sd.png" loading="lazy" alt="A small chart comparing payload compression ratios of zstandard, with and without dictionaries. With dictionaries, the payload compression ratio is 6.63. Without dictionaries, the compression ratio is 6.4."></p><figcaption><strong>Ready Payload Size</strong></figcaption></figure><p>We specifically looked at the READY payload size as it’s one of the first messages sent over the websocket and would be most likely to benefit from a dictionary. As shown in the table above, the compression gains were minimal for READY, so we looked at the results for more dispatch types hoping dictionaries would give more of an edge for smaller payloads.&nbsp;</p><p>Unfortunately, the results were a bit mixed. For example, looking at the message create payload size that we’ve been comparing throughout this post, we can see that the dictionary actually made things worse.</p><p>‍</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5f49c09e80a03e4614c5_AD_4nXeZGwfQPGKphBAcy3Wpc2HH20FpO3wZ2Os9w7VC6adtmZTDnLH0B8MEAUPO1UoQhj9RlEdQL9czlCKW15PVC1El6hkXy52Rcx8TNzNsPJAWKvN7o7wYjwyFxj5aMyob27AOTmBjN20ZdcusTgc7FNJxt96s.png" loading="lazy" alt="A chart comparing MESSAGE_CREATE payload sizes between Zlib streaming, Zstandard, Zstandard streaming, and Zstandard Streaming Plus Dictionary. Zlib streaming’s payload is just over 250 byes and zstandard is over 750 bytes. The newest entries, Zstandard Streaming and Zstandard Streaming Plus Dictionary are both under 250 byes, but Zstandard Streaming without Dictionary has a slightly smaller file size."></p></figure><p>Ultimately, we decided not to continue with our dictionary experiments. The slightly improved compression dictionaries would provide was outweighed by the additional complexity they would add to our gateway service and clients. Data is a big driver of engineering at Discord, and the data speaks for itself: it wasn’t worth investing more effort into.</p><h3>Buffer Upgrading</h3><p>Finally, we explored increasing zstandard buffers during off-peak hours. Discord’s traffic follows a diurnal pattern, and the memory we need to handle peak demand is significantly more than what’s needed during the rest of the day.&nbsp;</p><p>On the surface, autoscaling our gateway cluster would prevent us from wasting compute resources during off-peak hours. However, due to the nature of gateway connections being long-lived, traditional autoscaling methods don’t work well for our workload. As such, we have a lot of extra memory and compute during off-peak hours. Having all this extra compute laying around raised the question: Could we take advantage of these resources to offer greater compression?</p><p>To figure this out, we built a feedback loop into the gateway cluster. This loop would run on each gateway node and monitor the memory usage by the clients connected to it. It would then determine a percentage of new connecting clients that should have their zstandard buffer upgraded. An upgraded buffer increases the windowlog, hashlog, and chainlog values by one, and since these parameters are expressed as a power of two, increasing these values by one will roughly double the amount of memory usage the buffer uses.</p><p>After deploying and letting the feedback loop run for a bit, the results weren’t as good as we had initially hoped. As illustrated by the graph below, over a 24 hour period, our gateway nodes had a relatively low upgrade ratio (Up to 30%), and was significantly less than we anticipated: around 70%.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5f89a5aa109682aa20c0_AD_4nXdu2egSUa4dMnBCuvHFxPFrrxdROCyeqCAs8AP95O-jHEYcKx5jUXDsiuw7bCAmXiDM9g9ewrch5e4i7TQMQi7CpaYvBVsJr_bKMTbU9KiDMOjsMC9V1wDnEK6YH-Ksox9c8oZf5e-Jdh1AtumuemXMKtI.png" loading="lazy" alt="A graph showing the upgrade ratio for each gateway host over a 24 hour period. From 00:00 to 03:00, the lines are distributed between 0 and 0.2 peaking at 00:00 and tapering off. From 03:00 to 18:00 there are no lines. From 18:00 to 23:59 the lines are distributed between 0 and 0.2 peaking around 22:00"></p></figure><p>After doing a bit of digging, we discovered that one of the primary issues that was causing the feedback loop to behave sub-optimally was memory fragmentation: the feedback loop looked at real system memory usage, but BEAM was allocating significantly more memory from the system than was needed to handle the connected clients. This caused the feedback loop to think that it had less memory to work with than was available.</p><p>To try and mitigate this, we did a little experimentation to tweak the BEAM allocator settings — more specifically, the <em>driver_alloc</em> allocator, which is responsible for (<em>shockingly</em>) driver data allocations. The bulk of the memory used by a gateway process is the zstandard streaming context, which is implemented in C using a <a href="https://www.erlang.org/doc/system/nif.html">NIF</a>. NIF memory usage is allocated by <em>driver_alloc. </em>Our hypothesis was that if we could tweak the <em>driver_alloc</em> allocator to more effectively allocate or free memory for our zstandard contexts, we’d be able to decrease fragmentation and increase upgrade ratio overall.</p><p>However, after messing around with the allocator settings for a little bit, we decided to revert the feedback loop. While we probably would have eventually found the right allocator settings to dial in, the amount of effort needed to tweak the allocators combined with the overall additional complexity that this introduced into the gateway cluster outweighed any gains that we would’ve seen if this was successful.</p><h3>Implementation and Rollout</h3><p>While the original plan was to only consider zstandard for mobile users, the bandwidth improvements were significant enough for us to ship to desktop users as well! Since zstandard ships as a C library, it was simply a matter of finding bindings in the target language —Java for Android, Objective C for iOS, and Rust for Desktop — and hooking them into each client. Implementation was straightforward for Java (<a href="https://github.com/luben/zstd-jni/">zstd-jni</a>) and Desktop (<a href="https://crates.io/crates/zstd-safe">zstd-safe</a>), as bindings already existed, however for iOS, we had to write our own bindings.</p><p>This was a risky change with the potential to render Discord completely unusable if things were to go wrong, so the rollout was gated behind an experiment. This experiment served three purposes: allow the quick rollback of these changes if things were to go wrong, validate the results we saw in the “lab,” and enable us to gauge if this change was negatively affecting any baseline metrics.</p><p>Over the course of a few months, we were able to successfully roll out zstandard to all of our users on all platforms.</p></div><div id="heading-5"><h2>Another Win: Passive Sessions V2<br></h2><p>While this next part isn’t directly related to the zstandard work, the metrics that guided us during the dark launch phase of this project revealed a surprising behavior. Looking at the actual size of dispatches that were sent to the client, passive_update_v1 stood out. This dispatch consisted of over 30% of our gateway traffic while the actual number of dispatches sent were comparatively small–around 2%.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb5fe0f048cb0591c16080_AD_4nXf-UwN9XBhbGiKeqVukeCH4gYs4jn2JZM7jEY_vzWGncfyKL9QJiQJgnm4bXQvPpNXzD4cCObgJjyH3KoPFwDnYYfPQEQbvvZAqiSYa9qkH7ykVYJCw7IFYZHtKKDkABq07Px_J2gMmX6ejg6ucUS_IWxFU.png" loading="lazy" alt="A pie chart with multiple sections. Of over a dozen sections, the ones that are pointed out are: Passive Update V1: 35.61%, Message Create: 20.04%, Ready: 11.66%, Guild Member List Update: 8.5%, Presence Update: 2.67%."></p></figure><p>We employ passive sessions to avoid sending most messages that a server generates to clients that may not even open the server. For example, a Discord server could be very active sending thousands of messages per minute, but if a user isn’t actually reading those messages, it doesn’t make sense to send them and waste their bandwidth. Once you tab into the server, a passive session will be “upgraded” into a normal session and receive the full firehose of dispatches from that guild.</p><p>However, passive sessions still need to be periodically sent a limited amount of information, which is the purpose of PASSIVE_UPDATE_V1. Periodically, all passive sessions will receive an update with a list of channels, members, and members in voice so your client can still be kept in sync with the server.</p><p>Diving into the actual contents of one of those PASSIVE_UPDATE_V1 dispatches, we would send <em>all</em> of the channels, members, or members in voice, even if only a single element changed. Passive sessions were implemented as a means to scale Discord servers to hundreds of thousands of users and it worked well at the time. </p><p>However as we’ve <a href="https://discord.com/blog/maxjourney-pushing-discords-limits-with-a-million-plus-online-users-in-a-single-server">continued to scale</a>, sending these snapshots which consist of mostly redundant data was no longer sufficient. To fix this, we introduced a new dispatch that only sends the delta of what’s changed since the last update. This dispatch, aptly named PASSIVE_UPDATE_V2, significantly reduced the overall bandwidth from 35% of the gateway’s bandwidth to 5%, equating to a 20% reduction cluster-wide.</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb602c922d2dd61dbb8ad2_AD_4nXf8mgenY8u6qMaex3kvnEvd2xZty8fNW7sc139x4hEnnF8kQpJyKCzM3dpl5XULIRjgrBqljIb1ti3FBua6dxP3_4C2YKS8bEwYGsI6ofgRZ0xAALjFDgh-tXRxgL_JoVOzQ6StLLkCzYdtmW6UJHImxEwa.png" loading="lazy" alt="An additional pie chart with multiple sections. The sections that are pointed out are: Message Create: 28.31%, Reader: 21.86%, Guild Member List Update: 10.17%, Passive Update V2: 4.73%/4.7%. Voice State Update: 3.68%, and Guild Update: 1.01%. "></p></figure><p>‍</p><p>‍</p></div><div id="heading-6"><h2>B I G Savings</h2><p>Through the combined effects of Passive Sessions v2 and zstandard, we were able to reduce the gateway bandwidth used by our clients by almost 40%. That’s a LOT of data!&nbsp;</p><p>‍</p><figure><p><img src="https://cdn.prod.website-files.com/5f9072399b2640f14d6a2bf4/66eb605a048df7ca5e92d7cf_AD_4nXesiM1r_vEP3jlBiL4A0FryF6xUh8bKLxem8z-HObi-aFHRbQ2TlhJ-Rys4HScOw8_RsQhkx-w3uLE39WVR-_JXfHcoPVHFv4gmdFMwUWpT9Evhn2bPHqlQjh_r2bSRM1xez4cYHjMHw96IlH8MhDZ7VKzl.png" loading="lazy" alt="A graph of the outgoing bandwidth on the gateway cluster showing dates from January 2024, to April 2024. The line on the chart moves up and down diurnally up until April 18, which is demarcated with a red line labeled “zstandard”. The line then trends downwards until around May 30, 2024 also demarcated with a red line labeled “Passive Sessions v2.” The line levels oout after this, significantly lower than where it started."></p></figure><p>The chart shows the relative outgoing bandwidth of the gateway cluster from January 1 2024 to August 12, 2024, with the two demarcations being the zstandard rollout in April, followed by passive sessions v2 in late May.</p><p>While the passive sessions optimization was an unintended side-effect of the zstandard experimentation, it shows that with the right instrumentation and by looking at graphs with a critical eye, big savings can be achieved with a reasonable amount of effort.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Docker Desktop Alternative (398 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://container-desktop.com/</link>
            <guid>41604262</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 18:08:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://container-desktop.com/">https://container-desktop.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41604262">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
    <div>
      <div>
        <h2>Cross-platform desktop integrated application with consistent UI</h2>
        <p>Container Desktop works on Windows, Mac and Linux providing the same graphical interface.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <h2>Learning tool for the powerful <span>podman</span> command line interface</h2>
        <p>Container Desktop is great for skills improvement and learning features of 'podman'.</p>
      </div>
    </div>
    <div>
      <h2>Essentials at your fingertips</h2>
      <p>
        The dashboard offers just the essential features so that the users can feel right at home.
        <br>
        See below what you can manage with Container Desktop.
      </p>
      <video controls="" poster="https://container-desktop.com/videos/demo.png" width="100%" autoplay="">
        <source src="https://container-desktop.com/videos/demo.mp4" type="video/mp4">
      </video>
    </div>

    <div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/000-CrossPlatform.png">
      </p>
      <div>
        <h2>Cross Platform</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Application looks the same everywhere, no mental mapping!</li>
          <li>Completely informs its users of where it stores logs and settings.</li>
          <li>Allows users to debug and understand what is happening behind the scenes.</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div>
      <div>
        <h2>Multiple engines</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Fast native on <strong>Linux</strong> only</li>
          <li>Virtualized for any OS</li>
          <li>LIMA for MacOS</li>
          <li>WSL for Windows</li>
          <li>Both <strong>podman</strong> and <strong>docker</strong> engines</li>
          <li>Others are planned</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/ConnectionManager.png">
      </p>
    </div>

    <div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/PodmanContainers.png">
      </p>
      <div>
        <h2>Containers</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Be informed about the origin and status of your container environment.</li>
          <li>Quickly access logs, environment variables, mounts, opened ports and monitoring stats.</li>
          <li>Perform common maintenance operations, stop, restart and remove easily.</li>
          <li>Direct access to the exposed services using your browser.</li>
          <li>Gain control of all that happens in the container using the terminal console.</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div>
      <div>
        <h2>Images</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Be informed about the origin and status of local image store, their registry, name and tag.</li>
          <li>Immediately spawn new containers from image, customize name, port mappings and available mounts.</li>
          <li>Quickly access image build-up, check their impact and debug their setup.</li>
          <li>In-depth configuration viewer.</li>
          <li>
            Perform common maintenance operations, pull latest updates to refresh the images, push latest changes to a
            distributed image project.
          </li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/006-ImageActions.png">
      </p>
    </div>

    <div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/ImageSecurity.png">
      </p>
      <div>
        <h2>Security</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>In-depth awareness of security checks</li>
          <li>Be informed of know vulnerabilities</li>
          <li>Helps creating and maintaining secure systems</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div>
      <div>
        <h2>Networks</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Create and reuse networks at any moment.</li>
          <li>Know detailed setup of each network</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/NetworkCreate.png">
      </p>
    </div>

    <div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/PodmanPods.png">
      </p>
      <div>
        <h2>Pods</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Full power of pods on supported engines</li>
          <li>Access logs, processes and details.</li>
          <li>Generate kube and perform common actions</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div>
      <div>
        <h2>Machines</h2>
        <ul>
          <li>Manage all available podman virtual machines, create new ones or decommission what is redundant.</li>
        </ul>
      </div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/011-MachineTerminal.png">
      </p>
    </div>

    <div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/013-SecretsInspect.png">
      </p>
      <div>
        <h2>Secrets</h2>
        <p>Be aware of all available secrets, define new ones or purge old from existence.</p>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div>
      <div>
        <h2>Volumes</h2>
        <p>Manage shared volumes across containers, limit repetition and also be portable.</p>
      </div>
      <p><img src="https://container-desktop.com/img/015-VolumeActions.png">
      </p>
    </div>
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Inngest 1.0 – Open-source durable workflows on every platform (156 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.inngest.com/</link>
            <guid>41604042</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 17:33:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.inngest.com/">https://www.inngest.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41604042">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><header><p>Inngest's durable functions replace queues, state management, and scheduling to enable any developer to write reliable step functions faster without touching infrastructure.</p></header><p><img alt="Screenshot of Inngest's dashboard" loading="lazy" width="1530" height="840" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fhero%2F2024-08-function-dashboard.png&amp;w=1920&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fhero%2F2024-08-function-dashboard.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fhero%2F2024-08-function-dashboard.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p></div><div><div><p>Powerful SDKs</p><h2>Simple APIs for reliable software</h2><p>Drop our SDK into your existing codebase to add durable execution via step functions in seconds. No queues, workers, or additional state management required.</p></div><div><div><p>Flexible enough for all use cases, powerful enough for advanced requirements.</p><div><div><h3>Run on serverless, servers, or both.</h3><p>Deploy your Inngest functions to your existing platform or infra. Inngest securely invokes your jobs wherever the code runs.</p></div><div><h3>Multi-tenant concurrency, throttle, debounce, priority, and more.</h3><p>Control exactly how your functions are run with built-in flow control. Forget about queues, workers, and customer logic.</p></div><div><h3>Batching, fan-out, and scheduling</h3><p>Essentials for any type of job or workflow creation.</p></div></div></div><div><pre><code><span>export</span><span> </span><span>const</span><span> processVideo = inngest.createFunction(
</span><span>  { </span><span>id</span><span>: </span><span>"process-video"</span><span>,
</span><span>    </span><span>concurrency</span><span>: { </span><span>limit</span><span>: </span><span>5</span><span>, </span><span>key</span><span>: </span><span>"event.data.userId"</span><span> } },
</span><span>  { </span><span>event</span><span>: </span><span>"video/uploaded"</span><span> },
</span><span>  </span><span>async</span><span> ({ event, step }) =&gt; {
</span>
<span>    </span><span>// step.run is a code-level transaction:  it retries automatically</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span>// on failure and only runs once on success.</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span>const</span><span> transcript = </span><span>await</span><span> step.run(</span><span>'transcribe-video'</span><span>,
</span><span>      </span><span>async</span><span> () =&gt; deepgram.transcribe(event.data.videoUrl)
</span>    )
<!-- -->
<span>    </span><span>// function state is automatically managed for fault tolerance</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span>// across steps.</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span>const</span><span> summary = </span><span>await</span><span> step.run(</span><span>'summarize-transcript'</span><span>,
</span><span>      </span><span>async</span><span> () =&gt; llm.createCompletion({
</span><span>        </span><span>model</span><span>: </span><span>"gpt-4o"</span><span>,
</span><span>        </span><span>prompt</span><span>: createSummaryPrompt(transcript),
</span>      })
<!-- -->    )
<!-- -->
<span>    </span><span>// easily chain a series of calls without managing infrastructure.</span><span>
</span><span>    </span><span>await</span><span> step.run(</span><span>'write-to-db'</span><span>,
</span><span>      </span><span>async</span><span> () =&gt; db.videoSummaries.upsert({
</span><span>        </span><span>videoId</span><span>: event.data.videoId,
</span>        transcript,
<!-- -->        summary,
<!-- -->      })
<!-- -->    )
<!-- -->  }
<!-- -->);</code></pre></div></div></div><div><div><p>Write functions in any language.</p></div><div><p>Functions run on your own infrastructure: serverless, servers, or edge.</p></div></div><div><blockquote><p>I wanted to find a solution that would let us just write the code, not manage the infrastructure around queues, concurrency, retries, error handling, prioritization... I don't think that developers should be even configuring and managing queues themselves in 2024.</p></blockquote></div><div><div><p>Effortless development</p><h2>Made for modern engineering teams</h2><p>We've built Inngest to enable every developer to build reliable, scalable systems with less effort, more confidence, and fewer headaches.</p></div><div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/usp-apis-for-reliability.svg" alt="Inngest SDK APIs"></p><div><p>Use our SDK primitives to write code that automatically retries on error, runs in parallel, sleeps for days, or waits for additional input.</p><p>It's durable execution, built for <em>every developer</em>.</p></div></div><div><h3>Write reliable, fault-tolerant code with ease</h3></div></div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/usp-flow-control.svg" alt="Flow control graphic and methods"></p><div><p>Flow Control is essential for building resilient systems with durable execution. Configure <em>how</em> and <em>when</em> you</p><p>Throttle, multi-tenant concurrency controls, prioritization, rate limiting, batching, and more in a line of code.</p></div></div><div><h3>Flow control for resilient systems</h3></div></div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/usp-local-dev.svg" alt="Local development starts with one command"></p><div><p>Our open source Dev Server spins up an Inngest environment on your machine in a single command, with a UI to test and debug functions faster and easier then ever before.</p><p>No more battling clunky local setups for queues and workers.</p></div></div><div><h3>Local development that developers love</h3></div></div></div></div><div><blockquote><p>The DX and visibility with Inngest is really incredible. We are able to develop functions locally easier and faster that with our previous queue. Also, Inngest's tools give us the visibility to debug issues much quicker than before.</p></blockquote></div><div><div><p>Orchestration + Flow control</p><h2>Orchestration and flow control necessary for resilient systems</h2><p>Complete control over how your functions are executed without re-inventing the wheel. Inngest's built-in tools allow you to build complex workflows and run high volume jobs with fairness across your user base.</p></div><div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-concurrency-global.svg"></p><h3>Fair, multi-tenant concurrency</h3><p>Prevent noisy neighbor issues by limiting the concurrent resources each account or user consumes. Just a couple of lines of code.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/concurrency?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn more <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-workflow.svg"></p><h3>Step orchestration &amp; workflows</h3><p>Create step functions in code with orchestration and state automatically managed. Build complex pipelines of reliable business logic in minutes.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/features/inngest-functions/steps-workflows?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn more <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-batch.svg"></p><h3>Batching</h3><p>Coalesce many requests into a single function run for high-volume, low cost execution — without code, orchestration, or infra changes.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/batching?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn more <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-throttle.svg"></p><h3>Throttle and rate-limiting</h3><p>Use throttling and rate-limiting to manage throughput across your functions. Handle spikes of traffic and ensure limited resources are protected, applying limits at a global or even user specific level.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/throttling?ref=homepage-orchestration">Throttling<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/rate-limiting?ref=homepage-orchestration">Rate limiting<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-priority.svg"></p><h3>Dynamic prioritization</h3><p>Push paid or high-value users to the front of the queue while still ensuring fairness and quality-of-service for other users.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/priority?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn more <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-debounce.svg"></p><h3>Debouncing</h3><p>Prevent wasted work and costs by debouncing functions triggered within a time window.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/debounce?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn more <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/platform/icon-pause.svg"></p><h3>Pause for input or events</h3><p>Write functions that "wait for" additional input or events and automatically resume when matching events are received. No state management or polling required.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/features/inngest-functions/steps-workflows/wait-for-event?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn about waitForEvent<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M12 22C6.47715 22 2 17.5228 2 12C2 6.47715 6.47715 2 12 2C17.5228 2 22 6.47715 22 12C22 17.5228 17.5228 22 12 22ZM12 20C16.4183 20 20 16.4183 20 12C20 7.58172 16.4183 4 12 4C7.58172 4 4 7.58172 4 12C4 16.4183 7.58172 20 12 20ZM13 12H17V14H11V7H13V12Z"></path></svg><h3>Sleep, scheduling, and cron</h3><p>Sleep directly in code — in serverless functions, servers, or on the edge — and schedule functions for the future using dates or cron expressions.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/features/inngest-functions/steps-workflows/sleeps?ref=homepage-orchestration">Sleeps<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/delayed-functions?ref=homepage-orchestration">Scheduling<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/scheduled-functions?ref=homepage-orchestration">Crons<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M12 22C6.47715 22 2 17.5228 2 12C2 6.47715 6.47715 2 12 2C17.5228 2 22 6.47715 22 12C22 17.5228 17.5228 22 12 22ZM12 20C16.4183 20 20 16.4183 20 12C20 7.58172 16.4183 4 12 4C7.58172 4 4 7.58172 4 12C4 16.4183 7.58172 20 12 20ZM12 10.5858L14.8284 7.75736L16.2426 9.17157L13.4142 12L16.2426 14.8284L14.8284 16.2426L12 13.4142L9.17157 16.2426L7.75736 14.8284L10.5858 12L7.75736 9.17157L9.17157 7.75736L12 10.5858Z"></path></svg><h3>Declarative cancellation</h3><p>Automatically cancel functions whenever events happen in your system — without API calls, recording job IDs, or storing state.</p><p><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/cancel-running-functions?ref=homepage-orchestration">Learn more <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M16.1716 10.9999L10.8076 5.63589L12.2218 4.22168L20 11.9999L12.2218 19.778L10.8076 18.3638L16.1716 12.9999H4V10.9999H16.1716Z"></path></svg></a></p></div></div></div><div><blockquote><p>The DX and code simplicity it brings is unmatched, especially around local development. We're currently working to migrate some of our larger systems over and it’s a joy to see all the complexity it replaces, and with a much better story around partial failures and retries.</p></blockquote></div><div><div><p>Observability + Recovery</p><h2>Monitor, debug, and recover from issues</h2><p>Run in production with confidence with observability and recovery tools built into Inngest. Dig into traces to debug errors, monitor function and system health, and recovery from incidents with build-in tooling.</p></div><div><div><p><img alt="Screenshot of Debug your functions with traces" loading="lazy" width="1149" height="582" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fo11y%2Ftracing.png&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fo11y%2Ftracing.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fo11y%2Ftracing.png&amp;w=3840&amp;q=75"></p></div><div><p><img alt="Screenshot of Full observability" loading="lazy" width="307" height="140" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/o11y/metrics.svg"></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/platform/monitor/observability-metrics?ref=homepage-observability">Full observability<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M13.1717 12.0007L8.22192 7.05093L9.63614 5.63672L16.0001 12.0007L9.63614 18.3646L8.22192 16.9504L13.1717 12.0007Z"></path></svg></a></h3><p>Rapidly diagnose system wide issues with metrics including volume, error rates, backlog and throughput.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="Screenshot of Bulk function replay" loading="lazy" width="307" height="140" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/o11y/replay.svg"></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/platform/replay?ref=homepage-observability">Bulk function replay<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M13.1717 12.0007L8.22192 7.05093L9.63614 5.63672L16.0001 12.0007L9.63614 18.3646L8.22192 16.9504L13.1717 12.0007Z"></path></svg></a></h3><p>Leave dead letter queues in the past. Replay failed or cancelled functions in bulk to get your system back to green.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="Screenshot of React to urgent issues" loading="lazy" width="307" height="140" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fo11y%2Ffunction-actions.png&amp;w=384&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fo11y%2Ffunction-actions.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fhomepage%2Fo11y%2Ffunction-actions.png&amp;w=640&amp;q=75"></p><div><h3><a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/guides/pause-functions?ref=homepage-observability">React to urgent issues<!-- --> <svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M13.1717 12.0007L8.22192 7.05093L9.63614 5.63672L16.0001 12.0007L9.63614 18.3646L8.22192 16.9504L13.1717 12.0007Z"></path></svg></a></h3><p>Quickly respond to urgent issues by pausing functions or cancelling runs in bulk. Resume and replay to recover.</p></div></div></div></div><div><blockquote><p>Configuration with Inngest is really easy. When we read our code base, we can immediately understand what it is and what it does. We are going to be gradually migrating most features to Inngest.</p></blockquote></div><div><div><p>Local Development</p><h2>Unparalleled local development workflow</h2><p>Our open source Dev Server runs on your machine for a complete local development experience, with production parity. Get instant feedback on your work and deploy to prod with full confidence.</p></div><video src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/video/2024-09-dev-server-4k.mp4" autoplay="" loop="" muted=""></video><div><div><h3>Visual debugging in <em>real-time</em></h3><p>No more parsing terminal logs. Watch your functions execute step-by-step in your browser.</p></div><div><h3>Single binary, zero dependencies</h3><p>One command to install and run. No external services, databases, or dependencies.</p></div><div><h3>Iterate faster</h3><p>Replay functions in one click for a faster feedback loop than ever before.</p></div></div></div><div><blockquote><p>Inngest changed how I build TypeScript applications. I can't stress enough how much I love using Inngest. The ease of use and developer experience is unparalleled</p></blockquote></div><div><div><p>Enterprise ready</p><h2>Security, scalability, and compliance</h2><p>We take security and reliability seriously. Our platform complies with the security standards you need to run your business.</p></div><div><div><div><h3><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M5 3V19H21V21H3V3H5ZM19.9393 5.93934L22.0607 8.06066L16 14.1213L13 11.121L9.06066 15.0607L6.93934 12.9393L13 6.87868L16 9.879L19.9393 5.93934Z"></path></svg>Billions of functions per month</h3><p>Our platform has been put to the test and designed to scale so your team can just focus on building a great product.</p></div><div><h3><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M12 1L20.2169 2.82598C20.6745 2.92766 21 3.33347 21 3.80217V13.7889C21 15.795 19.9974 17.6684 18.3282 18.7812L12 23L5.6718 18.7812C4.00261 17.6684 3 15.795 3 13.7889V3.80217C3 3.33347 3.32553 2.92766 3.78307 2.82598L12 1ZM12 3.04879L5 4.60434V13.7889C5 15.1263 5.6684 16.3752 6.7812 17.1171L12 20.5963L17.2188 17.1171C18.3316 16.3752 19 15.1263 19 13.7889V4.60434L12 3.04879ZM12 7C13.1046 7 14 7.89543 14 9C14 9.73984 13.5983 10.3858 13.0011 10.7318L13 15H11L10.9999 10.7324C10.4022 10.3866 10 9.74025 10 9C10 7.89543 10.8954 7 12 7Z"></path></svg>End-to-end encryption</h3><p>Data is encrypted in transit and at rest, so you can trust that your data is safe. Use our<!-- --> <a href="https://www.inngest.com/docs/features/middleware/encryption-middleware?ref=homepage-enterprise">encryption middleware</a> <!-- -->for additional control.</p></div><div><h3><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M3 6H21V18H3V6ZM2 4C1.44772 4 1 4.44772 1 5V19C1 19.5523 1.44772 20 2 20H22C22.5523 20 23 19.5523 23 19V5C23 4.44772 22.5523 4 22 4H2ZM13 8H19V10H13V8ZM18 12H13V14H18V12ZM10.5 10C10.5 11.3807 9.38071 12.5 8 12.5C6.61929 12.5 5.5 11.3807 5.5 10C5.5 8.61929 6.61929 7.5 8 7.5C9.38071 7.5 10.5 8.61929 10.5 10ZM8 13.5C6.067 13.5 4.5 15.067 4.5 17H11.5C11.5 15.067 9.933 13.5 8 13.5Z"></path></svg>SSO and SAML</h3><p>Secure your account with single sign-on and SAML.</p></div><div><h3><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M20 2C20.5523 2 21 2.44772 21 3V21C21 21.5523 20.5523 22 20 22H6C5.44772 22 5 21.5523 5 21V19H3V17H5V15H3V13H5V11H3V9H5V7H3V5H5V3C5 2.44772 5.44772 2 6 2H20ZM19 4H7V20H19V4ZM14 8V11H17V13H13.999L14 16H12L11.999 13H9V11H12V8H14Z"></path></svg>HIPAA BAA Available</h3><p>Our system was built with healthcare in mind to handle sensitive data.</p></div></div><p><img src="https://www.inngest.com/assets/homepage/gradient-graphics/enterprise.svg" alt="Enterprise ready"></p></div><p><a target="" href="https://www.inngest.com/contact?ref=homepage-enterprise">Chat with a solutions engineer<svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="24" height="24" fill="currentColor"><path d="M13.1717 12.0007L8.22192 7.05093L9.63614 5.63672L16.0001 12.0007L9.63614 18.3646L8.22192 16.9504L13.1717 12.0007Z"></path></svg></a></p></div><div><blockquote><p>Recently we migrated a lot of our infrastructure to  reduce technical overhead and save costs. One of the key moves was going from GCP Composer (Airflow) to Inngest. This unified our backend and reduced our bill by 50x!!</p></blockquote></div><div><div><p>Developer love</p><h2>What devs are saying about Inngest</h2><p>Don't just take our word for it, this is what developers think about Inngest.</p></div><div><div><p><img alt="Image of Erik Munson" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Ferikmunson.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Ferikmunson.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Ferikmunson.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Erik Munson<span>@<!-- -->erikmunson</span></span></p><p>I've worked on workflow systems before and am consistently amazed with the <span>@inngest</span> team's ability to do them better than anyone else. it takes me a few lines of app code to do things that would've been huge projects for an entire team in past jobs, largely due to work like this</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Taj English" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Flisted-b-taj-english.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Flisted-b-taj-english.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Flisted-b-taj-english.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Taj English<span>@<!-- -->KINGiTAJ</span></span></p><p>Today @listedBApp says goodbye to Kafka and I couldn't be more excited to be replacing it with <span>@inngest</span>. Not every day do you get to replace a major infra component that improves DX, saves money and enables faster innovation :rocket:</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of David" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fdavid-dzhng.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fdavid-dzhng.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fdavid-dzhng.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>David<span>@<!-- -->dzhng</span></span></p><p>For anyone who is building multi-step AI agents (e.g AutoGPT type systems), I highly recommend building it on top of a job queue orchestration framework like <span>@inngest</span>, the traceability these things provide out of the box is super useful, plus you get timeouts &amp; retries for free.</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Jesse Thomson" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjessethomson11.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjessethomson11.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjessethomson11.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Jesse Thomson<span>@<!-- -->jessethomson11</span></span></p><div><p>I think the game has changed with <span>@inngest</span>.</p><p>To me, it is the missing piece for making a JS/TS a serious backend contender.</p><p>It has queuing, rate limits, backoff, &amp; everything else you named, without needing to muck around with SQS. 10/10 recommend</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Patrick Göler von Ravensburg" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fproductlane-patrick.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fproductlane-patrick.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fproductlane-patrick.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Patrick Göler von Ravensburg<span>@<!-- -->patrick_gvr</span></span></p><div><p>Headache prevented by <span>@inngest</span> and their concurrency feature 🤯</p><p>This function potentially runs for a long time and this allows us to not run this function again when the previous function hasn't finished based on the combination specified in 'key'.<img alt="Image of Inngest function" loading="lazy" width="400" height="124" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fproductlane-image.jpg&amp;w=640&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fproductlane-image.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fproductlane-image.jpg&amp;w=828&amp;q=75"></p></div></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Stefan Wirth" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fnafetswirth.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fnafetswirth.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fnafetswirth.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Stefan Wirth<span>@<!-- -->NafetsWirth</span></span></p><div><p>Started playing around with <span>@inngest</span> for scheduled tasks and background jobs.</p><p>Highly recommended, super simple to set up and amazing DX.</p><p>Support also very responsive.</p><p>Great job guys!</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Guillermo Rauch" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Frauchg.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Frauchg.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Frauchg.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Guillermo Rauch<span>@<!-- -->rauchg</span></span></p><div><p>So excited to see <span>@inngest</span> grow. It's the perfect tool to help orchestrate complex AI workloads.</p><p>Behind every successful generative AI product, there are queues and pipelines, increasingly powered by Inngest.</p></div></div><div><p><img alt="Image of James Q Quick" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjamesqquick.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjamesqquick.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjamesqquick.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>James Q Quick<span>@<!-- -->jamesqquick</span></span></p><p>Tried <span>@inngest</span> for the first time today and …WOW! I'm really excited to fit this into some of my app ideas!</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Ray Amjad" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Frayamjad.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Frayamjad.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Frayamjad.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Ray Amjad<span>@<!-- -->theramjad</span></span></p><p>I love this product so much! I spent 2 days setting up some background workers on Render.com and it was a total pain in the ass. I gave up and I got my background jobs set up in under 10 minutes with Inngest.</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Michael Roberts" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fmichaeljroberts.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fmichaeljroberts.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fmichaeljroberts.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Michael Roberts<span>@<!-- -->codewithbhargav</span></span></p><p>Yeh so <span>@inngest</span> is perhaps one of the best SaaS platforms I have EVER used, incredible stability and crystal clear APIs. Love it already!</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of Bhargav" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fcodewithbhargav.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fcodewithbhargav.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fcodewithbhargav.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>Bhargav<span>@<!-- -->codewithbhargav</span></span></p><p><span>@inngest</span> feels like a cheat code. Beautifully done!</p></div><div><p><img alt="Image of JB" loading="lazy" width="36" height="36" decoding="async" data-nimg="1" srcset="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjulianbenegas8.jpg&amp;w=48&amp;q=75 1x, https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjulianbenegas8.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75 2x" src="https://www.inngest.com/_next/image?url=%2Fassets%2Fcustomers%2Fsocial-proof%2Fjulianbenegas8.jpg&amp;w=96&amp;q=75"><span>JB<span>@<!-- -->julianbenegas8</span></span></p><p>ok, <span>@inngest</span> is incredible... really clear messaging, great docs, fast and well designed dashboard, great DX, etc... highly recommend.</p></div></div></div><div><div><a href="https://www.inngest.com/discord"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="4em" height="4em" fill="currentColor"><path d="M19.3034 5.33716C17.9344 4.71103 16.4805 4.2547 14.9629 4C14.7719 4.32899 14.5596 4.77471 14.411 5.12492C12.7969 4.89144 11.1944 4.89144 9.60255 5.12492C9.45397 4.77471 9.2311 4.32899 9.05068 4C7.52251 4.2547 6.06861 4.71103 4.70915 5.33716C1.96053 9.39111 1.21766 13.3495 1.5891 17.2549C3.41443 18.5815 5.17612 19.388 6.90701 19.9187C7.33151 19.3456 7.71356 18.73 8.04255 18.0827C7.41641 17.8492 6.82211 17.5627 6.24904 17.2231C6.39762 17.117 6.5462 17.0003 6.68416 16.8835C10.1438 18.4648 13.8911 18.4648 17.3082 16.8835C17.4568 17.0003 17.5948 17.117 17.7434 17.2231C17.1703 17.5627 16.576 17.8492 15.9499 18.0827C16.2789 18.73 16.6609 19.3456 17.0854 19.9187C18.8152 19.388 20.5875 18.5815 22.4033 17.2549C22.8596 12.7341 21.6806 8.80747 19.3034 5.33716ZM8.5201 14.8459C7.48007 14.8459 6.63107 13.9014 6.63107 12.7447C6.63107 11.5879 7.45884 10.6434 8.5201 10.6434C9.57071 10.6434 10.4303 11.5879 10.4091 12.7447C10.4091 13.9014 9.57071 14.8459 8.5201 14.8459ZM15.4936 14.8459C14.4535 14.8459 13.6034 13.9014 13.6034 12.7447C13.6034 11.5879 14.4323 10.6434 15.4936 10.6434C16.5442 10.6434 17.4038 11.5879 17.3825 12.7447C17.3825 13.9014 16.5548 14.8459 15.4936 14.8459Z"></path></svg></a><h4>Join our Discord community</h4><p>Join our Discord community to ask questions, share feedback, and have a direct line to shaping the future of Inngest!</p><p><a target="_blank" href="https://www.inngest.com/discord">Join the community</a></p></div><div><a href="https://github.com/inngest/inngest"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="4em" height="4em" fill="currentColor"><path d="M12.001 2C6.47598 2 2.00098 6.475 2.00098 12C2.00098 16.425 4.86348 20.1625 8.83848 21.4875C9.33848 21.575 9.52598 21.275 9.52598 21.0125C9.52598 20.775 9.51348 19.9875 9.51348 19.15C7.00098 19.6125 6.35098 18.5375 6.15098 17.975C6.03848 17.6875 5.55098 16.8 5.12598 16.5625C4.77598 16.375 4.27598 15.9125 5.11348 15.9C5.90098 15.8875 6.46348 16.625 6.65098 16.925C7.55098 18.4375 8.98848 18.0125 9.56348 17.75C9.65098 17.1 9.91348 16.6625 10.201 16.4125C7.97598 16.1625 5.65098 15.3 5.65098 11.475C5.65098 10.3875 6.03848 9.4875 6.67598 8.7875C6.57598 8.5375 6.22598 7.5125 6.77598 6.1375C6.77598 6.1375 7.61348 5.875 9.52598 7.1625C10.326 6.9375 11.176 6.825 12.026 6.825C12.876 6.825 13.726 6.9375 14.526 7.1625C16.4385 5.8625 17.276 6.1375 17.276 6.1375C17.826 7.5125 17.476 8.5375 17.376 8.7875C18.0135 9.4875 18.401 10.375 18.401 11.475C18.401 15.3125 16.0635 16.1625 13.8385 16.4125C14.201 16.725 14.5135 17.325 14.5135 18.2625C14.5135 19.6 14.501 20.675 14.501 21.0125C14.501 21.275 14.6885 21.5875 15.1885 21.4875C19.259 20.1133 21.9999 16.2963 22.001 12C22.001 6.475 17.526 2 12.001 2Z"></path></svg></a><h4>Open Source</h4><p>Inngest's core and all SDKs are open source. Explore our code bases, weigh in on RFCs, and contribute on GitHub.</p><p><a target="_blank" href="https://github.com/inngest/inngest">View project on GitHub</a></p></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Put this touch sensor on a robot and learn super precise tasks (331 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://any-skin.github.io</link>
            <guid>41603865</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 17:11:48 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://any-skin.github.io">https://any-skin.github.io</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41603865">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://any-skin.github.io: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Federal civil rights watchdog sounds alarm over Feds use of facial recognition (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://therecord.media/federal-civil-rights-watchdog-facial-recognition-technology-report</link>
            <guid>41603698</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 16:51:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://therecord.media/federal-civil-rights-watchdog-facial-recognition-technology-report">https://therecord.media/federal-civil-rights-watchdog-facial-recognition-technology-report</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41603698">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://therecord.media/federal-civil-rights-watchdog-facial-recognition-technology-report: Error: timeout of 10000ms exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Visualizing Weather Forecasts Through Landscape Imagery (514 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape</link>
            <guid>41603546</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2024 16:31:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape">https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=41603546">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Weather as Landscape</h2><a id="user-content-weather-as-landscape" aria-label="Permalink: Weather as Landscape" href="#weather-as-landscape"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Visualizing Weather Forecasts Through Landscape Imagery</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/house.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/house.png" alt="house"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Traditional weather stations often display sensor readings as raw numerical data. Navigating these dashboards can be overwhelming and stressful, as it requires significant effort to locate, interpret, and visualize specific parameters effectively.</p>
<p dir="auto">Viewing a landscape image feels natural to the human eye. The calming effect of observing landscape elements reduces stress and requires minimal effort, allowing for a more relaxed visual experience.</p>
<p dir="auto">The method below demonstrates how to encode weather information within a landscape image, with no or minimal reliance on numerical data.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Encoding principles</h2><a id="user-content-encoding-principles" aria-label="Permalink: Encoding principles" href="#encoding-principles"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The landscape depicts a small house in the woods. The horizontal axis of the image represents a 24-hour timeline, starting from the current moment on the left, marked by the house, and extending to the conditions of the next day on the right. Various landscape elements distributed along the vertical axis symbolize weather events and conditions. The further an event is from the present, the farther it is positioned to the right in the image.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/encode.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/encode.png" alt="encode"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The following information can be encoded within the landscape image:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Time markers to simplify timeline navigation:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Sunrise and sunset times</li>
<li>Noon and midnight</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Weather forecast information:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Wind direction and strength</li>
<li>Temperature fluctuations</li>
<li>Maximum and minimum temperature values</li>
<li>Cloud cover</li>
<li>Precipitation</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Current weather conditions:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Temperature</li>
<li>Atmospheric pressure</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Non weather events:
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Birthdays</li>
<li>Holidays</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Implementation</h2><a id="user-content-implementation" aria-label="Permalink: Implementation" href="#implementation"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The image generation code is written in <a href="https://www.python.org/" rel="nofollow">Python</a> using the <a href="https://python-pillow.org/" rel="nofollow">Pillow</a> library and is based on data from <a href="https://openweathermap.org/" rel="nofollow">OpenWeather</a>. The image is designed specifically for use on a 296x128 E-Ink display. The code tested on Python 3.9.</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Event image</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/sun_00.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/sun_00.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Sunrise</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/moon_00.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/moon_00.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Sunset</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/cloud_30.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/cloud_30.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Cloud cover</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/house_00.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/house_00.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Current time position</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/flower_00.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/flower_00.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Midnight</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/flower_01.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/flower_01.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Midday</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/palm_03.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/palm_03.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>South wind</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/east_03.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/east_03.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>East wind</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/tree_03.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/tree_03.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>West wind</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/pine_02.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/pine_02.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>North wind</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/rain.png"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/rain.png" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>Rain</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h2><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>&nbsp;Landscape&nbsp;image&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/weather_test.bmp"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/weather_test.bmp" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>It’s around noon, with clear skies and a few clouds expected. A moderate north wind will develop overnight. Temperatures are currently rising but will begin to fall after sunset, reaching their lowest point before sunrise. During this time, the wind is expected to shift to the northeast.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/test_20240903_043826.bmp"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/test_20240903_043826.bmp" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>The sun is rising and it will be a hot sunny day with a light southeast breeze. The temperature will remain high even after sunset, and the wind will shift to the east, becoming stronger throughout the evening.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/test_09B0B1083315.bmp"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/test_09B0B1083315.bmp" alt="example"></a></td>
<td>It will be cold and rainy throughout the day and night. The south wind will shift to the northeast overnight.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running the code</h2><a id="user-content-running-the-code" aria-label="Permalink: Running the code" href="#running-the-code"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Preparing environment Linux</h4><a id="user-content-preparing-environment-linux" aria-label="Permalink: Preparing environment Linux" href="#preparing-environment-linux"></a></p>

<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="source .venv/bin/activate"><pre><code>source .venv/bin/activate
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Preparing environment Windows</h4><a id="user-content-preparing-environment-windows" aria-label="Permalink: Preparing environment Windows" href="#preparing-environment-windows"></a></p>


<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Image creation test</h4><a id="user-content-image-creation-test" aria-label="Permalink: Image creation test" href="#image-creation-test"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Update <strong>OWM_KEY</strong> variable in the weather_landscape.py file with your OpenWeather API key.</p>

<p dir="auto"><h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Run server</h4><a id="user-content-run-server" aria-label="Permalink: Run server" href="#run-server"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardware</h2><a id="user-content-hardware" aria-label="Permalink: Hardware" href="#hardware"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/pic/hardware.jpg"><img src="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/raw/main/pic/hardware.jpg" alt="Setup"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The hardware setup includes an <a href="https://www.adafruit.com/product/3269" rel="nofollow">ESP32 development board</a> and <a href="https://www.waveshare.com/2.9inch-e-paper-module.htm" rel="nofollow">2.9inch E-Ink display module</a>. Currently, the setup only displays an image sourced from the internet, updating every 15 minutes. It is uncertain whether the image generation code can be adapted for use with MicroPython on the ESP32 at this time.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/lds133/weather_landscape/blob/main/esp32/README.md">More information</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>