<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 20:00:04 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Boys and Men in the United States Are Struggling. The Left Should Talk About It (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jacobin.com/2023/09/boys-men-work-despair-struggling-wages-education/</link>
            <guid>37586942</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 17:22:04 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jacobin.com/2023/09/boys-men-work-despair-struggling-wages-education/">https://jacobin.com/2023/09/boys-men-work-despair-struggling-wages-education/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586942">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-content">

                <!-- Antescript -->

                
                  
                

                <!-- Intro -->
                
                  
                    
    <dl>
      <dt>Interview by</dt>
      
        <dd>
          <a href="https://jacobin.com/author/david-sirota">David Sirota</a>
        </dd>
      
    </dl>
  
                  
                

                
                  
                    <section id="ch-0">
                      <p>Statistics show that men and boys in the United States today disproportionately suffer from a number of serious problems. Since the 1970s, they’ve seen their wages stagnate and are now far less likely than women to attend or graduate from college. Even more seriously, men are much more likely than women to be afflicted by “deaths of despair”: deaths due to suicide or alcohol or drug abuse. These trends are affecting boys and men across racial groups, and especially working-class boys and men.</p>
<p>Richard Reeves, a senior fellow at the Brookings Institution, is the author of <a href="https://www.brookings.edu/books/of-boys-and-men/"><i>Of Boys and Men: Why the Modern Male Is Struggling, Why It Matters, and What to Do About It</i></a>. For the <a href="https://www.levernews.com/the-american-masculinity-crisis/"><i>Lever Time</i></a><i> </i>podcast, <i>Jacobin </i>editor at large David Sirota interviewed Reeves about the crisis afflicting men, how right-wing politicians have weaponized it to promote a reactionary agenda, and how the Left might come up with a better response to men’s problems. This transcript has been edited for length and clarity.</p>

                    </section>
                  
                

                <!-- Main Content -->

                
    
      
        <section id="ch-1">
          
            
            <hr>
          
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>What are some of the most telling signals that the modern male is struggling — and specifically as a group, as distinct from the struggles of the population writ large?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>Let’s start with the economy and the labor market, where the well-told story about wage stagnation is particularly acute for men. Most American men earned less in 2019 than most American men did in 1979.</p>
<p>Of course, it’s also true that wages didn’t grow that quickly for working-class women by comparison to other women. But women’s wages did grow across the board — just faster at the top than at the bottom — whereas for men you saw wage stagnation.</p>
<p>What that means is that the only reason that middle-class American households saw any rise in their household incomes at all over that period was because of women. It was women’s work, women’s wages. So there’s all kinds of downstream consequences.</p>
<p>Then if we turn to something like education, what we see is a massive overtaking by girls and women of men, such that there’s now a bigger gender gap in education today than there was in 1972. On college campuses, for example, women are further ahead of men now than men were ahead of women when we passed Title IX in 1972.</p>
<p>Some of the consequences for that are difficulties around family formation and deaths of despair. There’s been lots of discussion of deaths of despair — which are from suicide, alcohol, or drugs — but maybe a little less attention to the fact that men are at least three times higher risk of one of those deaths of despair than women are. Deaths of despair are largely a male — and largely a working-class male — problem.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>There has been a gender wage gap for a very long time. Are you saying that what we’ve seen is that the gap has somewhat narrowed not just because women’s wages are going up, but also because men’s wages have stagnated or actually dropped? There’s an alternate history where everything is improving for both men and women, but it improves more quickly for women to deal with historic disparities. But you’re saying that’s not happening: it’s a negative story for men.</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>In terms of earnings, yes. The gender pay gap is typically measured at the median. So when people hear that women earn eighty-two or eighty-three cents on the dollar versus men, what’s being referred to there is median pay. One reason why the gender pay gap has narrowed over the last few decades is that women’s wages have risen quite sharply at the median — 30-something percent or more — but part of it is because male wages have dropped at the median.</p>
<p>That’s not the main reason for the narrowing, but it’s one of the reasons, and I don’t think it’s controversial to suggest that that’s bad news. If we’d seen similar levels of women’s wage growth at the median, and we hadn’t seen wage stagnation for men, it’s not clear to me that that would have been a worse world. I don’t think many people want to close the gender wage gap by crashing male wages.</p>

<p>At the top of the distribution, men and women have seen rising wages. Up toward that eightieth or ninetieth percentile, women have seen faster wage growth, but both men and women have seen it.</p>
<p>My overall understanding of these labor market trends over the last few decades is that we’ve seen a narrowing of the gender wage gap, for the reasons we just discussed, and a sharp widening of the class wage gap. They’re pulling in different directions. So the gap between the median and the top has gotten much wider, but the gap between men and women at each level has gotten narrower.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>I want to ask about the maleness part of this, in looking at wages, jobs, education levels, health care, deaths of despair, and so on. How much of this is related to maleness, however we define that, rather than other factors like economic inequality, geography, or education? How do we narrow in on this as a problem of maleness specifically?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>There is enough evidence that some of these problems do break quite strongly along male-female lines, so as to justify the attention on men in particular. The male suicide rate is four times higher than the female suicide rate. It has risen by 25 percent in the last decade and rose very sharply between 2020 and 2021, 8 percent for young men alone. And there wasn’t an increase for women.</p>
<p>That isn’t to say that female suicide isn’t a problem; of course it is. Sometimes, when I’m drawing attention to the gaps in education, people will say, no one cared when it was the other way around, when women were that far behind men. To that, my answer is: yeah, people did care. And we did a whole bunch of stuff about it, and quite rightly too. We passed laws; we had significant campaigns to try and overcome it.</p>
<p>To some extent, it becomes an empirical question as to whether there’s enough of a gender gap here on whatever the issue is to say, we should look at that. I would say the same is true the other way around. For example, the gender pay gap we’ve just talked about — just because 40 percent of women earn more than the average man now doesn’t mean there isn’t still an issue about gender pay gaps.</p>
<p>I’d look at the data on it and say, is there a strong enough pattern here to make you think this is worth looking at through that lens? There’ll be a whole bunch of issues where you’re like, “There isn’t much to see here in terms of gender.”</p>
<p>But there are other issues where there clearly is, in one direction or the other, and then I think we should be gender sensitive. We should also look at how that intersects by class, by race, and so on. So we might talk about the gender pay gap, but we shouldn’t forget the fact that white women now earn a lot more than black men.</p>
<p>That wasn’t true in 1979. So white women have seen very strong increases in their wages, such that for every dollar earned by a white woman, a black man earns about eighty-four cents, which is similar to the gender gap.</p>
<p>The point of that is not to say that the gender gap isn’t important and real. It is just to say that it’s very important that we don’t look at these things just through one lens, but try to look at them through different lenses.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>What is fueling this dynamic? Is it mostly the economic issues that you mentioned? Does it have to do with the changing nature of our culture? Is it something in our politics?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>I put it under three headings. Number one is, almost independently of everything else, the education system isn’t doing very well by lots of our boys and men now. We have a ten percentage point drop in the share of male teachers, incredible underinvestment in apprenticeships and vocational forms of learning, and all kinds of changes in school environments that mean that we’re not serving them very well.</p>
<p>That’s not to suggest that there aren’t plenty of girls who aren’t being served well too. But overall, young men hit the labor market or college or whatever less well-prepared as a result of the education system. The single biggest risk factor for dropping out of college, controlling for everything else, is being male. They struggle throughout education; they might struggle to land in the labor market.</p>
<p>The second bucket is that the labor market has been transformed in the last forty or fifty years in such a way as to make it much more difficult for men with modest levels of education to do OK.</p>

<p>We can have a very long discussion as to why that is: globalization, deunionization, loss of all kinds of jobs, and so on. It’s not because women came into the labor market; it’s because of these other external shocks to the labor market.</p>
<p>Then bucket number three is the most contentious one, in a way. The fact that women have seen such a massive increase in their economic independence means that the basis upon which men and women form families and relationships has been significantly transformed. In the space of not much more than a generation, the presumption of the male breadwinner has largely unraveled. In my view, that’s a great thing.</p>
<p>However, I think that has left a lot of men struggling to catch up with a culture where their role as a breadwinner has been undermined by economic brute facts, and then has been undermined by changes in their relationships to women, and they’ve come into it ill-served as well. So you have underskilled men facing a labor market that’s become a bit more hostile than the one their dads faced, and women who are saying, “Well, I might not need you.” I think all of those feed off each other.</p>

              </div>
          
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      David Sirota
                </span></p><p>In the past several years, we’ve seen right-wing politicians like Josh Hawley and Ted Cruz talk about the so-called attack on masculinity. We’ve seen YouTubers whose entire business model seems to be repackaging and selling one version of masculinity. We’ve seen gun marketing trying to fuse masculinity with the idea of buying weapons, owning weapons, shooting weapons.</p>
<p>Why do you think these messages have become so effective? What do you think would be a more constructive counternarrative to those kinds of messages?</p>

              </div>
            <div>
                <p><span>
                  
                    
                      Richard Reeves
                </span></p><p>I think they’re effective because, first, they identify some real problems. Hawley’s a great example of this. If you read some passages of Hawley’s book or [listen to him speak], I’m like, yeah, that’s the same data that I’ve got. Yes, I’m with you so far, senator.</p>
<p>But then what he does is he says, these men are struggling, and you know why? And he doesn’t say because of what’s happened to the economy, or because of what’s happening elsewhere. He says, “Because of the Left. Because the Left is obsessed with toxic masculinity, and birthing people, and so on. The Left hates masculinity. The Left hates men. The Left would rather have a world where we got rid of men.”</p>
<p>It’s a straw woman that he creates. He says, “It’s feminism’s fault,” and “If you’re feeling pissed off, if you’re struggling as a man, I hear you, it’s their fault, vote for me. Do I have any policy prescriptions? No, because I’m a culture warrior and so I don’t need to actually be able to do anything about it.” But what he and what others do is successfully wrap together these real anxieties that a lot of men fee or that women feel on behalf of the men in their lives.</p>
<p>He says that’s also about the Second Amendment, and that’s also about Americanism; that’s also about religion. It gets wrapped up into this sense of being a real Christian American white man. Masculinity, Hawley says, is the tip of the spear of the Left’s attack against America.</p>

<p>I don’t think that’s even plausibly true. But I know why he’s doing that — because it’s visceral. You can attach a bunch of other things to that visceral sense of your identity as a man being under attack.</p>
<p>That doesn’t only work with Christian white men, although I’ve just mentioned them. I was very struck by a poll that found that half of American men now agree that “today, men are sometimes criticized just for acting like men” — that’s the quote in the survey — and black men are more likely to say that’s true.</p>
<p>A more positive response would be to say, we get it, here are a bunch of problems. For example, would it be a terrible idea to have an office of men’s health focused on issues around suicide and male mental health? Would it be a good idea if the [Centers for Disease Control and Prevention] recognized the suicide gap facing men and had some work around that?</p>
<p>Would it be a terrible idea to have a recruitment drive for male teachers? We have a massive recruitment drive for women into STEM and, most recently, women into construction. I’m here for that. But what about the fact that we have emptied out, not only education, but social work and psychology of men?</p>
<p>You have an infrastructure bill that will create jobs largely for men. Two-thirds of the jobs in the infrastructure bill will go to men: black men as much as white men, and Hispanic men a little bit more, because they’re so represented in the construction industry. Don’t hide from that fact, as the administration does when they’re challenged on it.</p>
<p>Own it. Make it a feature, not a bug. And say, “Here are all the things we’re doing on behalf of women.” There’s lots more to do for women. But the fact that this bill is the first piece of legislation for a long time that will specifically help working-class men of all races and ethnicities — I’m proud of that as a Democrat, because working-class men have had it pretty rough for the last few years.</p>
<p>Why not say that? Simple things like that, I believe, would take the wind out of the sails of the attack from the Right. The silence on these issues from the Left creates this huge political opening for the Right. And they’re seizing it.</p>

              </div>
          
        </section>
      
    
  

              </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DALL·E 3 (550 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://openai.com/dall-e-3</link>
            <guid>37586900</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 17:18:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://openai.com/dall-e-3">https://openai.com/dall-e-3</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37586900">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><strong>Core Research and Execution</strong><br>Gabriel Goh, James Betker, Li Jing, Aditya Ramesh</p><p><strong>Research Contributors—Primary</strong><br>Tim Brooks, Jianfeng Wang, Lindsey Li, Long Ouyang, Juntang Zhuang, Joyce Lee, Prafulla Dhariwal, Casey Chu, Joy Jiao</p><p><strong>Research Contributors—Secondary</strong><br>Jong Wook Kim, Alex Nichol, Yang Song, Lijuan Wang, Tao Xu</p><p><strong>Inference Optimization</strong><br>Connor Holmes, Arash Bakhtiari, Umesh Chand Koppaka, Zhewei Yao, Samyam Rajbhandari, Yuxiong He<br></p><p><strong>Product—Primary</strong><br>Yufei Guo, Luke Miller, Joyce Lee, Wesam Manassra, Anton Tananaev, Chester Cho, Rachel Lim</p><p><strong>Product—Secondary</strong><br>Dave Cummings, Rajeev Nayak, Sriya Santhanam<br></p><p><strong>Safety—Primary</strong><br>Sandhini Agarwal, Michael Lampe, Katarina Slama, Kim Malfacini, Bilva Chandra, Ashyana-Jasmine Kachra, Rosie Campbell, Florencia Leoni Aleman, Madelaine Boyd, Shengli Hu, Johannes Heidecke</p><p><strong>Safety—Secondary</strong><br>Lama Ahmad, Chelsea Carlson, Henry Head, Andrea Vallone, CJ Weinmann, Lilian Weng</p><p><strong>﻿Communications</strong><br>Alex Baker-Whitcomb, Ryan Biddy, Ruby Chen, Thomas Degry, Niko Felix, Elie Georges, Lindsey Held, Chad Nelson, Kendra Rimbach, Natalie Summers, Justin Wang, Hannah Wong, Kayla Wood<br></p><p><strong>Legal and Public Policy</strong><br>Che Chang, Jason Kwon, Fred von Lohmann, Ashley Pantuliano, David Robinson, Tom Rubin, Thomas Stasi<br></p><p><strong>Special Thanks</strong><br>Alec Radford, Mark Chen, Katie Mayer, Mikhail Bilenko, Mikhail Parakhin, Bob McGrew, Mira Murati, Greg Brockman, Sam Altman</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Cancer expert gets experimental treatment for incurable tumour,phenomenal result (144 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-09-20/melanoma-richard-scolyer-georgina-long-early-results/102879818</link>
            <guid>37584578</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 14:27:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-09-20/melanoma-richard-scolyer-georgina-long-early-results/102879818">https://www.abc.net.au/news/2023-09-20/melanoma-richard-scolyer-georgina-long-early-results/102879818</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584578">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Richard Scolyer is at the forefront of melanoma treatment and research, but a devastating cancer diagnosis of his own has made him the self-described "patient zero" in a new frontier of brain cancer treatment.</p><section role="contentinfo" aria-label="key points" data-component="KeyPoints" data-uri="coremedia://teaser/102879824"><h2 data-component="Heading">Key points:</h2><ul data-component="List" role="list"><li data-component="ListItem"><span></span>Richard Scolyer is undergoing a rare treatment because he's both a clinician and cancer researcher</li><li data-component="ListItem"><span></span>The early results have shown a&nbsp;10-fold increase in the immune cells in the tumour</li><li data-component="ListItem"><span></span>His co-medical director Georgina Long said she felt compelled to try something groundbreaking</li></ul></section><p>A medical director of Melanoma Institute Australia, Professor Scolyer was diagnosed with an incurable brain cancer in June.&nbsp;</p><p>Since then, he and his colleagues have gone down a path of experimental treatment, and have given a National Press Club address, announcing they've "generated in 10 weeks discoveries that would normally take years".</p><p>Professor Scolyer said his brain cancer diagnosis came suddenly, and without warning.</p><p>"No one saw it coming, least of all me. I was fit, having represented Australia at the world aquathon championships in Ibiza in early May," he said.</p><p>In June, he travelled to Poland with his wife Katie Nicoll, and the day before had gone hiking in the mountains.</p><p>"I woke the next morning not feeling quite right," he said.</p><p>"I had a brief phone call with my mum back in Tasmania. I don't remember much after that. I know now I had a seizure."</p><p>He was rushed to hospital and after a number of tests, Professor Scolyer was diagnosed with glioblastoma IDH wild-type, a cancer that's considered incurable and usually fatal within six to nine months.</p><p>One of the first phone calls Professor Scolyer's wife made from Poland was to his Melanoma Institute Australia co-medical director, Georgina Long.</p><p>"Nothing had prepared me for that phone call from Katie in Poland," Professor Long said.</p><p>"When I got that call, I got a physical pain like nothing I've ever experienced before and it was grief for what Richard and his family were about to go through and for the thought of losing my dear friend and colleague."</p><figure role="group" data-component="VerticalArticleFigure" aria-labelledby="102879842" data-uri="coremedia://imageproxy/102879842"><img alt="Richard Scolyer and Georgina Long addressing the National Press Club" sizes="(max-width: 543px) 543px," srcset="https://live-production.wcms.abc-cdn.net.au/361b88e01a9b4899cea11d38092791b0?impolicy=wcms_crop_resize&amp;cropH=3333&amp;cropW=4444&amp;xPos=278&amp;yPos=0&amp;width=862&amp;height=647 543w, https://live-production.wcms.abc-cdn.net.au/361b88e01a9b4899cea11d38092791b0?impolicy=wcms_crop_resize&amp;cropH=3333&amp;cropW=5000&amp;xPos=0&amp;yPos=0&amp;width=862&amp;height=575" src="https://live-production.wcms.abc-cdn.net.au/361b88e01a9b4899cea11d38092791b0?impolicy=wcms_crop_resize&amp;cropH=3333&amp;cropW=5000&amp;xPos=0&amp;yPos=0&amp;width=862&amp;height=575" loading="lazy" data-component="Image" data-lazy="true"><p><figcaption id="102879842" data-component="VerticalArticleFigure__figcaption" aria-live="polite"> <!-- -->Richard Scolyer and Georgina Long addressing the National Press Club in Canberra.<span data-component="Byline"><span data-component="Text">(<span>AAP:&nbsp;Bianca De Marchi</span>)</span></span></figcaption></p></figure><h2 data-component="Heading">The melanoma expert takes on glioblastoma</h2><p>Professor Long said after that phone call, she started researching glioblastoma, speaking to experts and looking up clinical trials.</p><p>"It was a barren landscape. You could count the number of immunotherapy clinical trials for glioblastoma almost on one hand," she said.</p><p>With no clinical trials available, Professor Long said she felt obligated to "try something groundbreaking."</p><p>Melanoma Institute Australia has been at the forefront of treatments like immunotherapy, that have drastically improved survival rates for the deadly skin cancer.</p><p>Rather than go down the usual treatment path for glioblastoma of surgery, radiotherapy and chemotherapy, they decided to try to treat Professor Scolyer in a similar way to their melanoma patients.</p><p>"There was initial resistance from some in the oncology community," Professor Scolyer said.</p><p>"But Katie and I spent many hours writing long letters detailing what I wanted to do and why."</p><p>Professor Scolyer was given immunotherapy, designed to activate the immune system to attack the cancer.</p><p>They also used the specific genome of his cancer to design a vaccine to target it.</p><h2 data-component="Heading">Early results 'nothing short of phenomenal'</h2><p>Twelve days after he was given the immunotherapy drugs, Professor Scolyer had surgery to have the bulk of his tumour removed.</p><p>It was then tested, to see if the drugs had an effect.</p><p>"Yes, Richard is a patient of only one, but early scientific results are nothing short of phenomenal," Professor Long said.</p><p>They found there was a 10-fold increase in the immune cells in the tumour, that they were activated against the cancer and they were bound to the drug.</p><p>"Proving something that we'd already shown in melanoma, that there is no blood brain barrier and historically conceptualised, preventing the drugs from reaching the tumour," Professor Long said.</p><p>"We could not have hoped for better results."</p><p>But the pair said it was too early to say whether those scientific results mean a better prognosis for Professor Scolyer.</p><h2 data-component="Heading">The experimental treatment a unique situation</h2><p>Professor Scolyer said at this stage the experimental treatment he has undergone won't be available to other patients.</p><p>"I can only do this because I'm a cancer researcher and clinician and so inherently understand the risks," he said.</p><p>"This treatment may extend or shorten my life."</p><p>The co-medical directors said pharmaceutical companies have been reluctant to invest in glioblastoma research, but their early results mean some are starting to pay attention.</p><p>They are hopeful it will lead to clinical trials.</p><p>They have called for a change in approach to cancer research and treatment, such as looking beyond the confines of one cancer, designing better clinical trials and embedding research in clinical care.</p><p>"We know we're not curing as many cancers as we could," Professor Scolyer said.</p><p>"Today we call on the cancer research field to collectively re-think its approach to tackling cancer. Think big and be courageous."</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Car allergic to vanilla ice cream (737 pts)]]></title>
            <link>http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~wkw/humour/carproblems.txt</link>
            <guid>37584399</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 14:14:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~wkw/humour/carproblems.txt">http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~wkw/humour/carproblems.txt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584399">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Svelte 5: Runes (373 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://svelte.dev/blog/runes</link>
            <guid>37584224</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:59:32 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/runes">https://svelte.dev/blog/runes</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584224">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="main"><article> <p>Rethinking 'rethinking reactivity'</p>    <!-- HTML_TAG_START --><p>In 2019, Svelte 3 turned JavaScript into a <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/svelte-3-rethinking-reactivity">reactive language</a>. Svelte is a web UI framework that uses a compiler to turn declarative component code like this...</p>
<pre><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>let</span><span> count </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>0</span><span>;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>function</span><span> </span><span>increment</span><span>() {</span></span>
<span><span>		count </span><span>+=</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>;</span></span>
<span><span>	}</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>&lt;</span><span>button</span><span> </span><span>on</span><span>:</span><span>click</span><span>=</span><span>{increment}&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	clicks: {count}</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>button</span><span>&gt;</span></span></code></pre><p>...into tightly optimized JavaScript that updates the document when state like <code>count</code> changes. Because the compiler can 'see' where <code>count</code> is referenced, the generated code is <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/virtual-dom-is-pure-overhead">highly efficient</a>, and because we're hijacking syntax like <code>let</code> and <code>=</code> instead of using cumbersome APIs, you can <a href="https://svelte.dev/blog/write-less-code">write less code</a>.</p>
<p>A common piece of feedback we get is 'I wish I could write all my JavaScript like this'. When you're used to things inside components magically updating, going back to boring old procedural code feels like going from colour to black-and-white.</p>
<p>Svelte 5 changes all that with <em>runes</em>, which unlock <em>universal, fine-grained reactivity</em>.</p>
<div>
<figure>
<p>
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/RVnxF3j3N8U" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe>
</p>

<figcaption>Introducing runes</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>

<h2 id="before-we-begin">Before we begin<a href="#before-we-begin"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Even though we're changing how things work under the hood, Svelte 5 should be a drop-in replacement for almost everyone. The new features are opt-in — your existing components will continue to work.</p>
<p>We don't yet have a release date for Svelte 5. What we're showing you here is a work-in-progress that is likely to change!</p>
<h2 id="what-are-runes">What are runes?<a href="#what-are-runes"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><blockquote>
<p><strong>rune</strong> /ro͞on/ <em>noun</em></p>
<p>A letter or mark used as a mystical or magic symbol.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Runes are symbols that influence the Svelte compiler. Whereas Svelte today uses <code>let</code>, <code>=</code>, the <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/declaring-props"><code>export</code></a> keyword and the <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/reactive-declarations"><code>$:</code></a> label to mean specific things, runes use <em>function syntax</em> to achieve the same things and more.</p>
<p>For example, to declare a piece of reactive state, we can use the <code>$state</code> rune:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
<span>	let count = 0;
</span><span>	let count = $state(0);
</span>
	function increment() {
		count += 1;
	}
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;button on:click={increment}&gt;
	clicks: {count}
&lt;/button&gt;
</code></pre><p>At first glance, this might seem like a step back — perhaps even <a href="https://twitter.com/stolinski/status/1438173489479958536">un-Svelte-like</a>. Isn't it better if <code>let count</code> is reactive by default?</p>
<p>Well, no. The reality is that as applications grow in complexity, figuring out which values are reactive and which aren't can get tricky. And the heuristic only works for <code>let</code> declarations at the top level of a component, which can cause confusion. Having code behave one way inside <code>.svelte</code> files and another inside <code>.js</code> can make it hard to refactor code, for example if you need to turn something into a <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/writable-stores">store</a> so that you can use it in multiple places.</p>
<h2 id="beyond-components">Beyond components<a href="#beyond-components"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>With runes, reactivity extends beyond the boundaries of your <code>.svelte</code> files. Suppose we wanted to encapsulate our counter logic in a way that could be reused between components. Today, you would use a <a href="https://learn.svelte.dev/tutorial/custom-stores">custom store</a> in a <code>.js</code> or <code>.ts</code> file:</p>
<pre><p>ts</p><p><code><p><span>import</span><span> { <data-lsp lsp="(alias) function writable&amp;lt;T>(value?: T | undefined, start?: StartStopNotifier&amp;lt;T> | undefined): Writable&amp;lt;T>&amp;#10;import writable">writable</data-lsp> } </span><span>from</span><span> </span><span>'svelte/store'</span><span>;</span></p><p><span>export</span><span> </span><span>function</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="function createCounter(): {&amp;#10;  subscribe: (this: void, run: Subscriber&amp;lt;number>, invalidate?: Invalidator&amp;lt;number> | undefined) => Unsubscriber;&amp;#10;  increment: () => void;&amp;#10;}">createCounter</data-lsp></span><span>() {</span></p><p><span>	</span><span>const</span><span> { </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const subscribe: (this: void, run: Subscriber&amp;lt;number>, invalidate?: Invalidator&amp;lt;number> | undefined) => Unsubscriber">subscribe</data-lsp></span><span>,</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const update: (this: void, updater: Updater&amp;lt;number>) => void">update</data-lsp></span><span> } </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="(alias) writable&amp;lt;number>(value?: number | undefined, start?: StartStopNotifier&amp;lt;number> | undefined): Writable&amp;lt;number>&amp;#10;import writable">writable</data-lsp></span><span>(</span><span>0</span><span>);</span></p><p><span>	</span><span>return</span><span> {</span></p><p><span>		<data-lsp lsp="(property) subscribe: (this: void, run: Subscriber&amp;lt;number>, invalidate?: Invalidator&amp;lt;number> | undefined) => Unsubscriber">subscribe</data-lsp></span><span>,</span></p><p><span>		</span><span><data-lsp lsp="(property) increment: () => void">increment</data-lsp></span><span>:</span><span> () </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const update: (this: void, updater: Updater&amp;lt;number>) => void">update</data-lsp></span><span>((<data-lsp lsp="(parameter) n: number">n</data-lsp>) </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> <data-lsp lsp="(parameter) n: number">n</data-lsp> </span><span>+</span><span> </span><span>1</span><span>)</span></p><p><span>	};</span></p><p><span>}</span></p></code></p></pre><p>Because this implements the <em>store contract</em> — the returned value has a <code>subscribe</code> method — we can reference the store value by prefixing the store name with <code>$</code>:</p>
<pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
<span>	import { createCounter } from './counter.js';
</span><span>
</span><span>	const counter = createCounter();
</span><span>	let count = 0;
</span><span>
</span><span>	function increment() {
</span><span>		count += 1;
</span><span>	}
</span>&lt;/script&gt;

<span>&lt;button on:click={increment}&gt;
</span><span>	clicks: {count}
</span><span>&lt;button on:click={counter.increment}&gt;
</span><span>	clicks: {$counter}
</span>&lt;/button&gt;
</code></pre><p>This works, but it's pretty weird! We've found that the store API can get rather unwieldy when you start doing more complex things.</p>
<p>With runes, things get much simpler:</p>
<pre><code><span>import { writable } from 'svelte/store';
</span>
export function createCounter() {
<span>	const { subscribe, update } = writable(0);
</span><span>	let count = $state(0);
</span>
	return {
<span>		subscribe,
</span><span>		increment: () =&gt; update((n) =&gt; n + 1)
</span><span>		get count { return count },
</span><span>		increment: () =&gt; count += 1
</span>   };
}
</code></pre><pre><code>&lt;script&gt;
	import { createCounter } from './counter.js';

	const counter = createCounter();
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;button on:click={counter.increment}&gt;
<span>	clicks: {$counter}
</span><span>	clicks: {counter.count}
</span>&lt;/button&gt;
</code></pre><p>Note that we're using a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/JavaScript/Reference/Functions/get">get property</a> in the returned object, so that <code>counter.count</code> always refers to the current value rather than the value at the time the function was called.</p>
<h2 id="runtime-reactivity">Runtime reactivity<a href="#runtime-reactivity"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Today, Svelte uses <em>compile-time reactivity</em>. This means that if you have some code that uses the <code>$:</code> label to re-run automatically when dependencies change, those dependencies are determined when Svelte compiles your component:</p>
<pre><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>export</span><span> </span><span>let</span><span> width;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>export</span><span> </span><span>let</span><span> height;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// the compiler knows it should recalculate `area`</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// when either `width` or `height` change...</span></span>
<span><span>	$</span><span>:</span><span> area </span><span>=</span><span> width </span><span>*</span><span> height;</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// ...and that it should log the value of `area`</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>// when _it_ changes</span></span>
<span><span>	$</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>console</span><span>.log</span><span>(area);</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span></code></pre><p>This works well... until it doesn't. Suppose we refactored the code above:</p>
<pre><p>ts</p><p><code><p><span>const</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const multiplyByHeight: (width: any) => number">multiplyByHeight</data-lsp></span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> (<data-err><data-lsp lsp="(parameter) width: any">width</data-lsp></data-err>) </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> <data-lsp lsp="(parameter) width: any">width</data-lsp> </span><span>*</span><span> <data-err><data-lsp lsp="any">height</data-lsp></data-err>;</span></p><span><span>Parameter 'width' implicitly has an 'any' type.<br>Cannot find name 'height'.</span><span>7006<br>2304</span></span><span>Parameter 'width' implicitly has an 'any' type.<br>Cannot find name 'height'.</span><p><span>$</span><span>:</span><span> <data-err><data-lsp lsp="any">area</data-lsp></data-err> </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span><data-lsp lsp="const multiplyByHeight: (width: any) => number">multiplyByHeight</data-lsp></span><span>(<data-err><data-lsp lsp="any">width</data-lsp></data-err>);</span></p><span><span>Cannot find name 'area'.<br>Cannot find name 'width'.</span><span>2304<br>2304</span></span><span>Cannot find name 'area'.<br>Cannot find name 'width'.</span></code></p></pre><p>Because the <code>$: area = ...</code> declaration can only 'see' <code>width</code>, it won't be recalculated when <code>height</code> changes. As a result, code is hard to refactor, and understanding the intricacies of when Svelte chooses to update which values can become rather tricky beyond a certain level of complexity.</p>
<p>Svelte 5 introduces the <code>$derived</code> and <code>$effect</code> runes, which instead determine the dependencies of their expressions when they are evaluated:</p>
<pre><code><span><span>&lt;</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>let</span><span> { width</span><span>,</span><span> height } </span><span>=</span><span> $</span><span>props</span><span>(); </span><span>// instead of `export let`</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	</span><span>const</span><span> </span><span>area</span><span> </span><span>=</span><span> $</span><span>derived</span><span>(width </span><span>*</span><span> height);</span></span>
<span></span>
<span><span>	$</span><span>effect</span><span>(() </span><span>=&gt;</span><span> {</span></span>
<span><span>		</span><span>console</span><span>.log</span><span>(area);</span></span>
<span><span>	});</span></span>
<span><span>&lt;/</span><span>script</span><span>&gt;</span></span></code></pre><p>As with <code>$state</code>, <code>$derived</code> and <code>$effect</code> can also be used in your <code>.js</code> and <code>.ts</code> files.</p>
<h2 id="signal-boost">Signal boost<a href="#signal-boost"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Like every other framework, we've come to the realisation that <a href="https://knockoutjs.com/">Knockout</a> was right all along.</p>
<p>Svelte 5's reactivity is powered by <em>signals</em>, which are essentially <a href="https://dev.to/this-is-learning/the-evolution-of-signals-in-javascript-8ob">what Knockout was doing in 2010</a>. More recently, signals have been popularised by <a href="https://www.solidjs.com/">Solid</a> and adopted by a multitude of other frameworks.</p>
<p>We're doing things a bit differently though. In Svelte 5, signals are an under-the-hood implementation detail rather than something you interact with directly. As such, we don't have the same API design constraints, and can maximise both efficiency <em>and</em> ergonomics. For example, we avoid the type narrowing issues that arise when values are accessed by function call, and when compiling in server-side rendering mode we can ditch the signals altogether, since on the server they're nothing but overhead.</p>
<p>Signals unlock <em>fine-grained reactivity</em>, meaning that (for example) changes to a value inside a large list needn't invalidate all the <em>other</em> members of the list. As such, Svelte 5 is ridonkulously fast.</p>
<h2 id="simpler-times-ahead">Simpler times ahead<a href="#simpler-times-ahead"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>Runes are an additive feature, but they make a whole bunch of existing concepts obsolete:</p>
<ul>
<li>the difference between <code>let</code> at the top level of a component and everywhere else</li>
<li><code>export let</code></li>
<li><code>$:</code>, with all its attendant quirks</li>
<li>different behaviour between <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> and <code>&lt;script context="module"&gt;</code></li>
<li>the store API, parts of which are genuinely quite complicated</li>
<li>the <code>$</code> store prefix</li>
<li><code>$$props</code> and <code>$$restProps</code></li>
<li>lifecycle functions (things like <code>onMount</code> can just be <code>$effect</code> functions)</li>
</ul>
<p>For those of you who already use Svelte, it's new stuff to learn, albeit hopefully stuff that makes your Svelte apps easier to build and maintain. But newcomers won't need to learn all those things — it'll just be in a section of the docs titled 'old stuff'.</p>
<p>This is just the beginning though. We have a long list of ideas for subsequent releases that will make Svelte simpler and more capable.</p>
<h2 id="try-it">Try it!<a href="#try-it"><span>permalink</span></a></h2><p>You can't use Svelte 5 in production yet. We're in the thick of it at the moment and can't tell you when it'll be ready to use in your apps.</p>
<p>But we didn't want to leave you hanging. We've created a <a href="https://svelte-5-preview.vercel.app/">preview site</a> with detailed explanations of the new features and an interactive playground. You can also visit the <code>#svelte-5-runes</code> channel of the <a href="https://svelte.dev/chat">Svelte Discord</a> to learn more. We'd love to have your feedback!</p>
<!-- HTML_TAG_END --></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: uBlock Origin filters to remove distractions (291 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/mig4ng/ublock-origin-filters</link>
            <guid>37584134</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:53:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/mig4ng/ublock-origin-filters">https://github.com/mig4ng/ublock-origin-filters</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584134">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">ublock-origin-filters</h2>
<p dir="auto">My uBlock Origin filters to remove unnecessary distractions from some websites.</p>
<p dir="auto">For each website I have very specific tasks I do.
I optimize for allowing those tasks, while disabling everything else that might distract me.</p>
<p dir="auto">These are my preferences, feel free to use the filters directly from this repository or fork them.</p>
<p dir="auto">If I miss anything or you think I would benefit from something else, open an issue, pull request or send me an email (my github username at gmail.com).</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">YouTube</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Objective:</strong> Remove all distractions, recommended videos, auto-play, suggestions (everywhere), shorts. Most of the time I only want to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>watch a video;</li>
<li>search something;</li>
<li>upload something.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note:</em> Right now I am using Unhook (the Firefox extension). It works well but it might be possible to replace it with a filter too (<a href="https://letsblock.it/filters" rel="nofollow">https://letsblock.it/filters</a>).</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Twitter</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Objective:</strong> Remove all distractions, feed, sidebar, etc. Most of the time I only want to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>see the tweet feed in a specific profile I have opened;</li>
<li>see a tweet content and it's comments;</li>
<li>tweet something.</li>
</ul>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">LinkedIn</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Objective:</strong> Remove all distractions, feed, sidebar, etc. Most of the time I only want to:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>see a profile, company;</li>
<li>read a specific post;</li>
<li>reply to messages;</li>
<li>post something.</li>
</ul>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: ElectricSQL, Postgres to SQLite active-active sync for local-first apps (319 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://electric-sql.com/</link>
            <guid>37584049</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:46:55 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://electric-sql.com/">https://electric-sql.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584049">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="docusaurus_skipToContent_fallback"><main><a href="https://electric-sql.com/docs/intro/local-first"></a><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Access rules</li><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Sync shapes</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Live queries</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Local writes</li></ul><div role="tabpanel"><div><p>Craft how data syncs <span>on and off </span><span>onto </span> your app using <a href="https://electric-sql.com/docs/usage/data-access/shapes">Shapes</a>.</p><p>Shapes allow you to manage <a href="https://electric-sql.com/docs/intro/sync-controls">dynamic partial replication</a> between Postgres in the cloud and SQLite in the local<!-- -->&nbsp;<!-- -->app.</p></div><div><pre tabindex="0"><code><span><span>const</span><span> shape </span><span>=</span><span> </span><span>await</span><span> db</span><span>.</span><span>projects</span><span>.</span><span>sync</span><span>(</span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  where</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    owner_id</span><span>:</span><span> auth</span><span>.</span><span>user_id</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>}</span><span>,</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  include</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    issues</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>      include</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>        comments</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>          include</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>{</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>            author</span><span>:</span><span> </span><span>true</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>          </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>        </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>      </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>    </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span>  </span><span>}</span><span></span><br></span><span><span></span><span>}</span><span>)</span><span>;</span><br></span></code></pre></div></div></div><div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/quotes/anurag.png" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Anurag Goel</h3><h4>Founder<span> - </span><a href="https://render.com/">Render</a></h4><p>ElectricSQL is a great choice for a <span>local-first</span> sync layer that you can run anywhere yourself.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/quotes/johannes.png" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Johannes Schickling</h3><h4>Founder<span> - </span><a href="https://www.prisma.io/">Prisma</a></h4><p>I’m very impressed with ElectricSQL’s approach to sync and their thoughtful API&nbsp;design.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/quotes/jose.png" loading="lazy"></p><h3>José Valim</h3><h4>Creator<span> - </span><a href="https://elixir-lang.org/">Elixir</a></h4><p>ElectricSQL brings the full power of the Erlang VM to local-first software development.</p></div></div><div><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Instant reactivity</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Realtime multi‑user</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Conflict‑free offline</li></ul></div><div><div><p>For</p><h2>Operational simplicity</h2></div><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Simple to operate</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Cheaper to&nbsp;run</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Reliable by design</li></ul></div></div><div><ul role="tablist" aria-orientation="horizontal"><li role="tab" tabindex="0" aria-selected="true">Standard open‑source</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Drop‑in compatible</li><li role="tab" tabindex="-1" aria-selected="false">Existing applications</li></ul><div role="tabpanel"><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/icons/open-source.svg" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Open source</h3><p><span>Apache 2.0 license. Open development on </span><a href="https://github.com/electric-sql/electric">GitHub</a><span> and </span><a href="https://discord.electric-sql.com/">Discord</a>. Contributions welcome.</p></div><div><p><img src="https://electric-sql.com/img/icons/self-host.svg" loading="lazy"></p><h3>Self-host</h3><p>One horizontally scalable sync service. No complex infra or durability requirements.</p></div></div></div><div><p><h2>Join the community</h2></p></div><div><p><h2>Become a design partner</h2></p><p><img loading="lazy" src="https://electric-sql.com/img/home/splash.svg"></p></div></div></main></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[British journalist held by police at Luton airport for five hours without arrest (234 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.theguardian.com/media/2023/sep/20/british-journalist-held-by-police-at-luton-airport-for-five-hours-without-arrest</link>
            <guid>37584038</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:46:06 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/media/2023/sep/20/british-journalist-held-by-police-at-luton-airport-for-five-hours-without-arrest">https://www.theguardian.com/media/2023/sep/20/british-journalist-held-by-police-at-luton-airport-for-five-hours-without-arrest</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37584038">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="maincontent"><p>A British freelance journalist who previously worked in the Kurdish-controlled part of Syria was held by counter-terrorism police at Luton airport for five hours without being arrested last month under controversial powers of detention.</p><p>Matt Broomfield, 29, said he was met by police as he got off a plane from Belgrade with his girlfriend on 24 August and was taken aside for questioning, where he was asked “do you consider your reporting objective” and his opinions of the British state. <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/uk/police" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Police</a> told Broomfield they were engaged in “a mopping up operation”. They seized his phone and laptop and have since refused to return them. After the questioning ended, he was allowed to proceed and no police action has followed.</p><p>Broomfield was detained under schedule 7 of the Terrorism Act 2000, used routinely by counter-terrorism officers to question people at airports for up to six hours at a time. Police say it is a tool to keep the public safe, but critics say the power is overused to the point of harassment.</p><p>The National Union of Journalists has written on Broomfield’s behalf to Matt Jukes, the policing lead for counter-terrorism, to ask for a justification for his detainment in the absence of criminal proceedings, and for his computer and phone to be immediately returned.</p><p>Officers focused on Broomfield’s writing, much of which is sympathetic to the <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/kurds" data-link-name="in body link" data-component="auto-linked-tag">Kurds</a>, and a three-year period ending in 2020 when he ran a news and information service in Kurdish-controlled north-east Syria. “They asked who I had met and interviewed,” he said.</p><p>Broomfield was held for two months <a href="https://dm-aegean.bordermonitoring.eu/2021/11/10/detained-and-banned-from-europe-a-british-journalist-in-the-eu-migrant-detention-system/?fbclid=IwAR1McCkjqtWtOz6qVdVy13B6xgCMgsaH8zCxJ0g2vFy56wsYfdmxS47offY" data-link-name="in body link">in Greek migrant detention centres</a> in 2021 after being denied permission to cross the border into Italy. He was told he was banned from the EU’s Schengen area at the request of Germany, which he believes was because of his media and advocacy work.</p><p>He was flown to the UK where he was subjected to a schedule 7 stop. After that, Broomfield, who is now based in Belgrade, says he was allowed to re-enter the UK “several times” without issue – until the latest stop last month.</p><p>Kurdish soldiers were instrumental in the defeat of Islamic State in north-east Syria in 2019, with air support from the US and UK, and remain in effect in control of the region. Turkey has long been hostile to the Kurds, who aspire to their own state based on territory in Turkey, Syria, Iraq and Iran.</p><p>Broomfield said: “It seems clear the Schengen ban and my harassment by the UK police are driven by direct or indirect pressure from Turkey, on the basis of my work and reporting in Rojava and around the Kurdish issue.”</p><p>He said the UK should have no interest “in the anti-democratic prosecution of legitimate journalism”.</p><p>British Kurds told the Guardian they were routinely stopped under schedule 7. Ali Gul Ozbek, 58, a pharmacist from Friern Barnet, north London, and a former mayor of Haringey council, said he had been stopped every time he went abroad since around 2012, both on the way out and on the way back.</p><p>The most recent stop was in July when Ozbek, a British citizen, went to visit his uncle in Geneva, Switzerland. “It is a form of torture. They ask the most basic questions that could be answered by a primary school student. I am an ordinary Kurd, I do not have any link with any Kurdish political organisations.”</p><p>Official figures show <a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/statistics/operation-of-police-powers-under-the-terrorism-act-2000-quarterly-update-to-june-2023/operation-of-police-powers-under-the-terrorism-act-2000-and-subsequent-legislation-arrests-outcomes-and-stop-and-search-great-britain-quarterly-u" data-link-name="in body link">2,498 people were stopped</a> under schedule 7 powers in the year to 30 June, down 6% from a year before. The detainees are a wide range of people, including those with the loosest of links to the Kurdish movement.</p><figure data-spacefinder-role="inline" data-spacefinder-type="model.dotcomrendering.pageElements.NewsletterSignupBlockElement"><a data-ignore="global-link-styling" href="#EmailSignup-skip-link-13">skip past newsletter promotion</a><p id="EmailSignup-skip-link-13" tabindex="0" aria-label="after newsletter promotion" role="note">after newsletter promotion</p></figure><p>Ann Marie Davies, from Cardiff, was detained by counter-terrorism police for about four hours at Bristol airport in July as she returned from a holiday in Portugal, her first since the Covid pandemic, with her husband and teenage daughter.</p><p>“I asked the police why my passport was flagged and they said they didn’t know. The questions were very broad: they asked why I was interested in human rights. But they also asked whether I supported the PKK [a Kurdish political party banned in Turkey] and I said I didn’t and I didn’t support terrorist organisations,” she said.</p><p>Davies, who trains medical students, believes she was stopped because “I sympathise with the Kurdish cause in a general sense” and because she was involved in organising a Kurdish cultural event in Cardiff last November. Police took her DNA and photograph; her phone and Kindle were searched before she was allowed to leave.</p><p>The Home Office said<strong> </strong>schedule 7 enabled officers to stop, question, detain and search a person to determine whether they are or have been involved in terrorism. “Examinations have been instrumental in securing evidence to convict,” a spokesperson said.</p><p>Iida Kayhko, a doctoral researcher in security studies at Royal Holloway, University of London, said the belief in the British Kurdish community was that UK police were reflecting pressure from Ankara after President Recep Tayyip Erdoğan’s election victory in May, which has reinforced Kurdish repression within Turkey.</p><p>“It would seem that British counter-terrorism policing is being made use of to pursue the Erdoğan government’s aims of stifling Kurdish political expression,” she said.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: 78% MNIST accuracy using GZIP in under 10 lines of code (199 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://jakobs.dev/solving-mnist-with-gzip/</link>
            <guid>37583593</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 13:00:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://jakobs.dev/solving-mnist-with-gzip/">https://jakobs.dev/solving-mnist-with-gzip/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37583593">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p><img src="https://jakobs.dev/media/gzip.png" alt="GZIP"></p>
<p>We can 'solve' MNIST up to ~78% accuracy with the following code-golfed obscurity:</p>
<div data-language="python"><pre><code>c <span>=</span> <span>lambda</span> z<span>:</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>z<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>

<span>def</span> <span>ncd</span><span>(</span>x<span>,</span> y<span>)</span><span>:</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>(</span>c<span>(</span>x <span>+</span> y<span>)</span> <span>-</span> <span>min</span><span>(</span>c<span>(</span>x<span>)</span><span>,</span> c<span>(</span>y<span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>/</span> <span>max</span><span>(</span>c<span>(</span>x<span>)</span><span>,</span> c<span>(</span>y<span>)</span><span>)</span>

cls <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>(</span>x<span>,</span> c<span>(</span>x<span>)</span><span>,</span> l<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> l <span>in</span> training_set<span>]</span>

correct_predictions <span>=</span> <span>sum</span><span>(</span><span>[</span>np<span>.</span>array_equal<span>(</span>Counter<span>(</span>
    <span>[</span>l <span>for</span> _<span>,</span> _<span>,</span> l <span>in</span> <span>sorted</span><span>(</span><span>[</span><span>(</span>ncd<span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> x<span>)</span><span>,</span> x<span>,</span> l<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> _<span>,</span> l <span>in</span> cls<span>]</span><span>,</span>
     key<span>=</span><span>lambda</span> t<span>:</span> t<span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>:</span><span>5</span><span>]</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>.</span>most_common<span>(</span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>,</span> label<span>)</span>
     <span>for</span> x1<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> test_set<span>]</span><span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p>If you just want to see the code sample, <a href="https://github.com/Jakob-98/mono/blob/main/python/gzip_mnist/mnist_gzip.ipynb">here</a> is a link to the Jupyter Notebook containing the code to run this experiment.</p>
<p>Lets dive into why and how: yesterday while in the one-hour train ride from Eindhoven to Rotterdam, I was inspired by the post <a href="http://pepijndevos.nl/2023/07/15/chatlmza.html">text generation from data compression</a> and the (quite controversial) paper on <a href="https://aclanthology.org/2023.findings-acl.426/">parameter free text classification</a> to play around with using compression as an image classification mechanism. Previously, I worked on image compression for computer vision on the edge, so interested in applying the technique to the most seminal yet basic dataset, I attempted to use GZIP + K-NN as a classification mechanism for the MNIST (handwritten digits) dataset.</p>
<p>Breaking down the technique, it boils down to two components: GZIP and NCD (Normalized Compression Distance) as a similarity metric, and k-NN (k-Nearest Neighbors) for classification. In this approach, GZIP is essentially our tool which gives us a way to measure the complexity or information content of individual data points. NCD provides a normalized measure of how similar two data points are, based on how much more (or less) effort it takes to compress them together compared to compressing them separately.</p>
<p>For each test sample, the algorithm computes its NCD with every training sample (in our case, 100 training samples), sorts them, and selects the k smallest distances. The majority class among these k=5 closest neighbors is then predicted as the label for the test sample. As this is quite computationally expensive, I only took a subset of the test images to arrive at my accuracy measure. Of course, it would be more correct to use the full set, but I leave this an an exercise to the reader ;).</p>
<p>Here is a less obscured version of the algorithm:</p>
<div data-language="python"><pre><code><span>def</span> <span>compute_ncd</span><span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> x2<span>)</span><span>:</span>
    <span>"""Compute the Normalized Compression Distance (NCD) between two samples."""</span>
    Cx1 <span>=</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>x1<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
    Cx2 <span>=</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>x2<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
    Cx1x2 <span>=</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span><span>(</span>x1 <span>+</span> x2<span>)</span><span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span>
    
    <span>return</span> <span>(</span>Cx1x2 <span>-</span> <span>min</span><span>(</span>Cx1<span>,</span> Cx2<span>)</span><span>)</span> <span>/</span> <span>max</span><span>(</span>Cx1<span>,</span> Cx2<span>)</span>

<span>print</span><span>(</span><span>"Classifying test samples..."</span><span>)</span>

k <span>=</span> <span>5</span>  <span># Number of neighbors to consider</span>
correct_predictions <span>=</span> <span>0</span>  <span># Counter for correct predictions</span>
actual_labels <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>]</span>
predicted_labels <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>]</span>

<span># Cache compressed lengths for training samples</span>
compressed_lengths <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>(</span>x<span>,</span> <span>len</span><span>(</span>gzip<span>.</span>compress<span>(</span>x<span>.</span>tobytes<span>(</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>)</span><span>,</span> label<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> training_set<span>]</span>

<span>for</span> <span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> actual_label<span>)</span> <span>in</span> tqdm<span>(</span>test_set<span>[</span><span>:</span><span>100</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>:</span>
    <span># Calculate NCD for each training sample</span>
    distances <span>=</span> <span>[</span><span>(</span>compute_ncd<span>(</span>x1<span>,</span> x<span>)</span><span>,</span> label<span>)</span> <span>for</span> x<span>,</span> _<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> compressed_lengths<span>]</span>
    
    <span># Get k nearest neighbors and predict label</span>
    neighbors <span>=</span> <span>sorted</span><span>(</span>distances<span>,</span> key<span>=</span><span>lambda</span> x<span>:</span> x<span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>:</span>k<span>]</span>
    top_k_class <span>=</span> <span>[</span>label <span>for</span> _<span>,</span> label <span>in</span> neighbors<span>]</span>
    predicted_class <span>=</span> Counter<span>(</span>top_k_class<span>)</span><span>.</span>most_common<span>(</span><span>1</span><span>)</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span><span>[</span><span>0</span><span>]</span>
    
    <span># Update predictions and counts</span>
    actual_labels<span>.</span>append<span>(</span>actual_label<span>)</span>
    predicted_labels<span>.</span>append<span>(</span>predicted_class<span>)</span>
    correct_predictions <span>+=</span> <span>(</span>predicted_class <span>==</span> actual_label<span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> after writing this post, I found <a href="https://www.blackhc.net/blog/2019/mnist-by-zip/">this article</a> by Andreas Kirsch taking a similar approach back in 2019. His approach reaches around 35% accuracy.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Gokrazy is cool (150 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://xeiaso.net/blog/gokrazy</link>
            <guid>37583234</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 12:14:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://xeiaso.net/blog/gokrazy">https://xeiaso.net/blog/gokrazy</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37583234">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>When you deal with Linux, you end up hearing about "distributions" as different "flavors" of Linux combined with a bunch of other tools. This is mostly true, but it's slightly missing the forest for the trees.</p>
<p>Consider this famous and often misunderstood quote by Richard Stallman:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I'd just like to interject for a moment. What you're referring to as Linux is in fact, GNU/Linux, or as I've recently taken to calling it, GNU plus Linux.Linux is not an operating system unto itself, but rather another free component of a fully functioning GNU system made useful by the GNU corelibs, shell utilities and vital system components comprising a full OS as defined by POSIX.</p>
</blockquote>
<figure><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/hero/vroom.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/hero/vroom.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image vroom" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/hero/vroom-smol.png"></picture><figcaption>Nikon D3300, 35mm f/1.8 DX, a red formula one style car speeds along a racetrack with visible tire skidmarks. Photo by Xe Iaso</figcaption></figure>
<p>Many pages of ink have been spilled over analyzing this quote, and a lot of them fall short of really getting at the heart of the matter. What this actually means is something like this:</p>
<p>By itself, Linux is useless. It does boot the system, it does interface with hardware, but without a bunch of other tools, it's not very useful. It's like a car without a steering wheel, or a boat without a rudder. It does something, but it's not very useful. The real value of things like the GNU project, systemd, openrc and other tools in that vein is that they make Linux useful. They make it into a complete system that you can use to do things. They are the proverbial steering wheel and rudder in the metaphor.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/mara/hacker/128" alt="Mara is hacker">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#mara"><b>Mara</b></a>&gt; Fun fact, if you try to boot a Linux kernel without an init process, it'll just panic and crash!</p></div>
<p>Most Linux systems on the face of the planet are built with GNU tools and utilities. In order to compile the Linux kernel, you need to use <a href="https://gcc.gnu.org/">GCC</a>. In order to run <code>ls</code> to list files in the current directory, you need to use <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/coreutils/coreutils.html">GNU coreutils</a>. Every dynamically linked program uses <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/">glibc</a> for performing basic system interactions like writing to files or opening network sockets. Everything is built on top of the GNU toolset. This is why Stallman is so adamant about calling it GNU/Linux. It's not that he's trying to take credit for Linux, it's that he's trying to give credit to the GNU project for making Linux useful.</p>
<p>However, there's a lot of room for nuance here. For example, <a href="https://alpinelinux.org/">Alpine Linux</a> is a Linux distribution that uses <a href="https://musl.libc.org/">musl libc</a> instead of <a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/libc/">glibc</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BusyBox">busybox</a> instead of GNU coreutils. It's still a Linux distribution, but it doesn't use the GNU toolset. It's still a Linux distribution, but it's not GNU/Linux.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/mara/hacker/128" alt="Mara is hacker">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#mara"><b>Mara</b></a>&gt; Also, for the record you can build the Linux kernel with clang, but that's a whole other can of worms. For one, GCC supports many more targets than clang likely ever will, but in general there are some compromises you need to make until clang implements some GCC-specific compiler extensions a bit better. Google, Facebook, and a few other companies do run LLVM compiled kernels in production though, so it's probably closer to viable than you think. Especially if you use ChromeOS or Android.</p></div>
<p>So, what is a Linux distribution? It's a collection of tools that make Linux useful. It's a collection of tools that make Linux into a complete system. It's not a "flavor" of Linux (though this conceptually can exist with alternative kernels like the Zen kernel patchset), it's a system that just so happens to make Linux useful.</p>
<p>As a counter-argument, consider the reason why Linux runs on more devices worldwide than there are people: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Android_(operating_system)">Android</a>. Android does use the Linux kernel, but it doesn't use any GNU tools in the stack at all. You can't take programs that are compiled against other Linux distributions and run them on Android. You can't take programs that are compiled against Android and run them on other Linux distributions.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/aoi/wut/64" alt="Aoi is wut">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#aoi"><b>Aoi</b></a>&gt; Wait, so does this mean Android's not a Linux distribution? What is it then?</p></div>
<p>I'm going to argue that Android is not a Linux distribution unto itself. Android is a Linux <em>implementation</em>. It uses the Linux kernel, but that's where the similarities with the rest of the ecosystem end. Android is its own little world where there's just enough system tools to get the system running, but once you get into the UI, it's a completely different world. It's a completely different ecosystem. It's a completely different operating system.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/aoi/wut/64" alt="Aoi is wut">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#aoi"><b>Aoi</b></a>&gt; So what's the difference between a Linux distribution and a Linux implementation?</p></div>

<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/cadey/enby/64" alt="Cadey is enby">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#cadey"><b>Cadey</b></a>&gt; It's a bit of a fuzzy line, but I'd say that a Linux distribution is a collection of discrete tools that make Linux useful, and a Linux implementation is a cohesive collection of bespoke tools that make Linux into a complete system. Really, you could argue that if it has <code>/bin/sh</code>, it's a Linux distribution.</p></div>
<h2>gokrazy</h2>
<p><a href="https://gokrazy.org/">gokrazy</a> is a Linux implementation that I've used off and on for a few years now. It's a very interesting project because everything on the system is written in Go save the kernel. The init process is in Go (and even listens over HTTP to handle updates!), every userland process is written in Go, and even the core system services are written in Go.</p>
<p>Out of the box a gokrazy install comes with these basic tools:</p>
<ul>
<li>The <code>init</code> process that is mandated to be the parent of all userland processes by the Linux kernel.</li>
<li>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_Host_Configuration_Protocol">DHCP</a> client that automatically configures the network interface.</li>
<li>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_Time_Protocol">NTP</a> client that automatically sets the system clock.</li>
<li>A little tool to save randomness from the kernel to a file so that it can be used to seed the random number generator on boot (because the Raspberry Pi doesn't have a robust hardware random number generator)</li>
</ul>
<p>That's it. Everything else from the web UI to A/B update logic is written in Go. It boots in literal seconds, uses an insanely small amount of RAM out of the box, and runs with nearly zero overhead. When you configure your gokrazy install to run additional software, you do so by adding the Go command path to a configuration file and then updating to trigger a reboot into the new version.</p>
<p>Here's an example of what my gokrazy virtual machine's file tree looks like:</p>
<pre><code><span>/ # tree etc gokrazy user
</span><span>etc
</span><span>├── breakglass.authorized_keys
</span><span>├── gokr-pw.txt
</span><span>├── gokrazy
</span><span>│   └── sbom.json
</span><span>├── hostname
</span><span>├── hosts
</span><span>├── http-port.txt
</span><span>├── https-port.txt
</span><span>├── localtime
</span><span>├── machine-id
</span><span>├── resolv.conf -&gt; /tmp/resolv.conf
</span><span>└── ssl
</span><span>    └── ca-bundle.pem
</span><span>
</span><span>gokrazy
</span><span>├── dhcp
</span><span>├── heartbeat
</span><span>├── init
</span><span>├── ntp
</span><span>└── randomd
</span><span>
</span><span>user
</span><span>├── breakglass
</span><span>├── fbstatus
</span><span>├── qemu-guest-kragent
</span><span>├── serial-busybox
</span><span>├── tailscale
</span><span>├── tailscaled
</span><span>└── waifud-gok-agent
</span></code></pre>
<p>That is the <em>entire</em> system. It's all stripped down to these few programs, configuration files, and one symlink for DNS resolution. This is a very minimal system, and it's all you need to run statically linked Go programs. It's very easy to deploy your own services to it too. It's probably the easiest platform I know of that lets you just deploy a Go binary and have it run as a service, automatically restarting when it crashes.</p>
<h2>The tooling</h2>
<p>When I used gokrazy back in the day, you had to use a command line called <code>gokr-packer</code> that you passed a bunch of command line flags to with information about all the Go programs you wanted to run on the machine, configuration for those programs, and any other meta-information like where the update tool should push the image to. It was a bit of a pain to use, but it worked. Recently the <a href="https://gokrazy.org/quickstart/"><code>gok</code></a> tool was added to the project, and this has been <em>revolutionary</em> when it comes to using and administrating gokrazy installs.</p>
<p>Essentially, <code>gok</code> is a wrapper around the existing <code>gokr-packer</code> logic with a JSON file to store your configuration details. It's a lot easier to use, understand, and automate. You don't have to remember command line flags or maintain unwieldy scripts. You just edit a JSON file and push updates with <code>gok update</code>. It's amazingly simple.</p>
<h2>Setting up a gokrazy machine</h2>
<p>As an example, I'm going to show you how to install a bunch of tailnet addons to a gokrazy machine. I'm also going to assume that you don't have a gokrazy install set up yet, so we'll need to install it. To do this, we'll need to do a few simple things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Install the <code>gok</code> tool.</li>
<li>Create your <code>gok</code> configuration.</li>
<li>Install Tailscale on the machine.</li>
<li>Create your "seed" image with <code>gok overwrite</code>.</li>
<li>Boot it on your Raspberry Pi or VM.</li>
<li>Push any updates to the image to the machine with <code>gok update</code>.</li>
</ul>
<p>First, let's install the <code>gok</code> tool. In order to do this, you need to have the <a href="https://golang.org/doc/install">Go toolchain</a> installed. Once you have that, you can run <code>go install</code> to install the <code>gok</code> tool:</p>
<pre><code><span>go install github.com/gokrazy/tools/cmd/gok@main
</span></code></pre>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/mara/hacker/128" alt="Mara is hacker">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#mara"><b>Mara</b></a>&gt; You may want to ensure that <code>~/go/bin</code> is in your <code>$PATH</code> variable so that you can run it by the name <code>gok</code> instead of <code>~/go/bin/gok</code>.</p></div>
<p>Next, create a new gokrazy configuration with <code>gok new</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok new -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>This will create a configuration named <code>casa</code> (cf: Spanish for "house") in <code>~/gokrazy/casa</code>. This is where all of your configuration files will live. You can edit the configuration file with <code>gok edit</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok edit -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<details>
<summary>If you are making a virtual machine</summary>
<p>If you are making a virtual machine, you will need to override the kernel and firmware packages. You can do this by adding the following to your configuration file:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>  </span><span>// ...
</span><span>  "</span><span>KernelPackage</span><span>": "</span><span>github.com/rtr7/kernel</span><span>",
</span><span>  "</span><span>FirmwarePackage</span><span>": "</span><span>github.com/rtr7/kernel</span><span>",
</span><span>  </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>You will need to prefix the <code>gok overwrite</code> and <code>gok update</code> commands with <code>GOARCH=amd64</code> to ensure that Go builds x86_64 binaries instead of ARM binaries:</p>
<pre><code><span>GOARCH=amd64 gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>If you don't do this, you will get arm64 binaries being built. This may require manual recovery of your virtual machine.</p>
</details>
<p>Let's make our lives easier by installing <a href="https://tailscale.com/">Tailscale</a> on the machine. By default, gokrazy will announce its hostname over DHCP, which usually makes most consumer routers pick it up and then lets you ping it by name. When you have <a href="https://tailscale.com/kb/1081/magicdns/">MagicDNS</a> enabled, Tailscale can take over this logic and prevent you from accessing the machine by name.</p>
<p>However, Tailscale is written in Go and doesn't require any of the services that most Linux distributions provide in order to function. It's a perfect fit for gokrazy. You can install it with <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add tailscale.com/cmd/tailscaled
</span><span>gok add tailscale.com/cmd/tailscale
</span></code></pre>
<p>And be sure to add the <code>mkfs</code> service to create a persistent partition on <code>/perm</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/gokrazy/mkfs
</span></code></pre>
<p>Next, fetch an <a href="https://tailscale.com/kb/1085/auth-keys/">auth key</a> from <a href="https://login.tailscale.com/admin/settings/keys">the admin console</a> and make sure you check that it's reusable. Then, add the following to your configuration file under the <code>PackageConfig</code> block:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>tailscale.com/cmd/tailscale</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>up</span><span>",
</span><span>                 </span><span>// paste your key here!
</span><span>                "</span><span>--authkey=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>"
</span><span>            ]
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    }
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>

<p>This will make your machine automatically connect to Tailscale on boot.</p>
<p>Next, we need to create our "seed" image with <code>gok overwrite</code>. First, figure out what the device node for your SD card is. On Linux, you can do this with <code>lsblk</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>lsblk
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then look for the one that has the same size as your SD card. In my case, it's <code>/dev/sdd</code>. Once you have that, you can run <code>gok overwrite</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok overwrite --full /dev/sdd
</span></code></pre>
<p>However if you want to write the image to a file (such as if you are doing mass distribution or making a VM image), you need to use <code>gok overwrite</code> with a file instead of a device node. This will create a 16 GB image:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok overwrite -i casa --full gokrazy.img --target_storage_bytes 17179869184
</span></code></pre>
<p>Once you have your image, you can write it to your SD card with <code>dd</code> (or <a href="https://etcher.balena.io/">balenaEtcher</a>) or import it into your virtual machine hypervisor of choice.</p>
<p>Once you have your image written to your SD card, you can boot it on your Raspberry Pi or VM.</p>
<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/aoi/wut/64" alt="Aoi is wut">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#aoi"><b>Aoi</b></a>&gt; Wait, so how do I log in with a shell?</p></div>

<div>
    <p><img src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/sticker/cadey/enby/64" alt="Cadey is enby">
    </p>
    <p>&lt;<a href="https://xeiaso.net/characters#cadey"><b>Cadey</b></a>&gt; You don't. gokrazy doesn't have a login prompt. It's a single-user system. There is <a href="https://github.com/gokrazy/breakglass"><code>breakglass</code></a> as a tool of last resort to modify things, but you only have a very minimal subset of busybox to work with, so it should be avoided if at all possible.</p></div>
<p>Once you have your machine booted and it responds to pings over Tailscale, you can open its HTTP interface in your browser. If you called your machine <code>casa</code>, you can open it at <a href="http://casa/"><code>http://casa</code></a>. It will prompt you for a username and password. Your username is <code>gokrazy</code>, and the password is near the top of your <code>config.json</code> file. When you log in, you'll see a screen like this:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/gokrazy-ui-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>This is the gokrazy web UI. It lets you see the status of your machine and any logs that are being generated by your applications. You can also start, stop, and restart any of your applications from here. It's a very simple UI, but it's fantastic for debugging and monitoring.</p>
<h2>Tailnet addons</h2>
<p>Now that we have a Gokrazy system up and running, let's add some programs to it! I'm going to list a couple tailnet addons that give your tailnet superpowers. These are all written in Go, so they're a perfect fit for gokrazy.</p>
<p>Today I'm going to show you how to install these tools into your tailnet:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tailscale/golink">golink</a> - a URL shortener at <code>http://go</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tailscale/tmemes">tmemes</a> - an internal meme generator you can host at <code>http://memegen</code></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip">tclip</a> - a pastebin you can host at <code>http://paste</code></li>
</ul>
<p>These tools help you augment your tailnet by giving you tools that will make you and your team's life a lot easier. A URL shortener helps you link to complicated Google Docs URLs. A meme generator gives you a new innovative way to let off steam. A pastebin lets you share text with your team without having to worry about the service you're using going offline due to no fault of your own.</p>
<h3>golink</h3>
<p>To install golink, we need to add the <code>golink</code> binary to the configuration. You can do this with <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/tailscale/golink/cmd/golink
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then configure it with <code>gok edit</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>github.com/tailscale/golink/cmd/golink</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>--sqlitedb=/perm/home/golink/data.db</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>Environment</span><span>": [
</span><span>                </span><span>// the same one from before
</span><span>                "</span><span>TS_AUTHKEY=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            </span><span>// don't start the service until NTP catches up
</span><span>            "</span><span>WaitForClock</span><span>": </span><span>true
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    }
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>And finally push it with <code>gok update</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>It'll build the image, push it out over Tailscale, trigger a reboot, and be back up in the span of a minute. Once it's back up, you can open the web UI again and see the status of your <code>golink</code> instance at <a href="http://casa/status?path=%2fuser%2fgolink">http://casa/status?path=%2fuser%2fgolink</a>:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/golink" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>And then you can start using short URLs at <a href="http://go/">http://go</a>:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/golink-ui-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>And that's it! You now have a super minimal VM running small programs that let you do useful things to you. You can add more programs to your configuration file and push them with <code>gok update</code> to add more functionality to your machine. You can even add your own programs to the configuration file and push them to your machine. It's a very simple system, but it's very powerful.</p>
<h3>tmemes</h3>
<p>Google is infamous for having an internal service named <a href="https://www.buzzfeednews.com/article/reyhan/inside-googles-internal-meme-generator">memegen</a>. This allows Googlers to make internal-facing memes about the slings and arrows that impact them as highly paid programmers. This is an internal service inside Google that has a lot of serious investment of time and energy to make it the best possible experience it can be. It's to the point that reportedly people can keep up with how an all-hands meeting is going by the tone of the sarcastic memes that are being posted to memegen.</p>
<p>The main reason this is run inside Google is to avoid information leaking via memes. Yes, this is an actual threat model.</p>
<p>Thanks to the magic of Tailscale, you can make your own private memegen using <a href="https://github.com/tailscale/tmemes">tmemes</a>. tmemes is a tailnet addon that lets you post image macro templates and layer wisdom over it in the form of text.</p>
<p>Here's an example meme:</p>
<p><a href="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy.jpg" target="_blank"><picture><source type="image/avif" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy.avif"><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy.webp"><img loading="lazy" alt="hero image blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy" src="https://cdn.xeiaso.net/file/christine-static/blog/2023/gokrazy/society-if-gokrazy-smol.png"></picture></a></p>
<p>To add tmemes to your gokrazy machine, you can use <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/tailscale/tmemes/tmemes
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then open your config with <code>gok edit</code> and add the following to your <code>PackageConfig</code> block:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>github.com/tailscale/tmemes/tmemes</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>Environment</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>TS_AUTHKEY=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                </span><span>// change this to your desired hostname
</span><span>                "</span><span>--hostname=memegen</span><span>",
</span><span>                </span><span>// change this to your username on Tailscale
</span><span>                "</span><span>--admin=Xe@github</span><span>",
</span><span>                "</span><span>--store=/perm/home/tmemes</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>WaitForClock</span><span>": </span><span>true
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    },
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then push it with <code>gok update</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then you can head to <a href="http://memegen/">http://memegen</a> and upload a template to make your own dank memes.</p>
<p>If you want to integrate your own tools with tmemes, you can check out the <a href="https://github.com/tailscale/tmemes/blob/main/docs/api.md">API documentation</a>. This should help you do whatever it is you want with a meme generator as a service.</p>
<h3>tclip</h3>
<p>Sometimes you just need a place to paste text and get a URL pointing to it. <a href="https://tailscale.dev/blog/tclip">tclip</a> is a tool that you can add to your tailnet and get exactly that. It's a very simple tool, but it's very useful. It's also written in Go, so it's a perfect fit for gokrazy. <a href="https://tailscale.dev/blog/tclip-updates-092023">Their recent update to remove Cgo dependencies</a> makes it possible to run your tclip node on a gokrazy machine.</p>
<p>To add tclip to your gokrazy machine, you can use <code>gok add</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok add github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip/cmd/tclipd
</span></code></pre>
<p>Then open your config with <code>gok edit</code> and add the following to your <code>PackageConfig</code> block:</p>
<pre><code><span>{
</span><span>    </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    "</span><span>PackageConfig</span><span>": {
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>        "</span><span>github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip/cmd/tclipd</span><span>": {
</span><span>            "</span><span>CommandLineFlags</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>--data-location=/perm/home/tclip/</span><span>"
</span><span>            ],
</span><span>            "</span><span>WaitForClock</span><span>": </span><span>true</span><span>,
</span><span>            "</span><span>Environment</span><span>": [
</span><span>                "</span><span>TS_AUTHKEY=tskey-auth-hunter2-hunter2hunter2hunter2</span><span>",
</span><span>                "</span><span>USE_FUNNEL=true</span><span>" </span><span>// Remove this if you don't want to use Funnel
</span><span>            ]
</span><span>        },
</span><span>        </span><span>// ...
</span><span>    }
</span><span>}
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then push it with <code>gok update</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>gok update -i casa
</span></code></pre>
<p>And then you can start using it by heading to <a href="http://paste/">http://paste</a>. Install the command-line tool on your development workstation with <code>go install</code>:</p>
<pre><code><span>go install github.com/tailscale-dev/tclip/cmd/tclip@latest
</span></code></pre>
<p>Here's an example tclip link if you want to see what it looks like in practice: <a href="https://paste.shark-harmonic.ts.net/paste/696b9b02-90ac-4adc-a33d-d749bb6f460f">interjection.c</a>. It's a very simple tool, but it's very useful.</p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>gokrazy is insanely cool. It's the <em>easiest</em> way to deploy Go services to your homelab. It integrates seamlessly with Tailscale, and is something that I'm very excited to see grow and mature. I'm very excited to see what the future holds for gokrazy, and I'm very excited to see what people do with it.</p>
<p>I've seen signs that they're going to be adding an automatic update process, and that has me <em>very</em> excited. I'm also excited to see what other services people add to the gokrazy ecosystem. I'm hoping to add a few of my own in the future, and I'm hoping to see what other people do with it.</p>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: SeaGOAT – local, “AI-based” grep for semantic code search (173 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT</link>
            <guid>37583219</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 12:13:09 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT">https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37583219">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text">
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
  <p dir="auto">
    <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/blob/main/assets/logo-small.png"><img src="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/raw/main/assets/logo-small.png" alt="Logo" width="200"></a>
    <b>SeaGOAT</b>
  </p>
</h2>
<p dir="auto">A code search engine for the AI age. SeaGOAT is a local search tool that
leverages vector embeddings to enable to search your codebase semantically.</p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/blob/main/assets/demo-slideshow.gif"><img src="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/raw/main/assets/demo-slideshow.gif" alt="" data-animated-image=""></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto"><em>Note: I was recently laid off my job and I am looking for new
opportunities. If you need a Senior Full Stack Developer,
<a href="mailto:github@daniel-kantor.com">contact me</a>! I have experience with
React, Node and Python and I'm located in Spain (European Union).
10+ years in software development professionally.</em></p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting started</h2>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install SeaGOAT</h3>
<p dir="auto">In order to install SeaGOAT, you need to have the following
dependencies already installed on your computer:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Python 3.11 or newer</li>
<li>ripgrep</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat">bat</a> (<strong>optional</strong>, highly recommended)</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">When <code>bat</code> is <a href="https://github.com/sharkdp/bat#on-ubuntu-using-apt">installed</a>,
it is used to display results as long as color is enabled. When SeaGOAT is
used as part of a pipeline, a grep-line output format is used. When color is
enabled, but <code>bat</code> is not installed, SeaGOAT will highlight the output using
pygments. Using <code>bat</code> is recommended.</p>
<p dir="auto">To install SeaGOAT using <code>pipx</code>, use the following command:</p>

<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">System requirements</h3>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Hardware</h4>
<p dir="auto">Should work on any decent laptop.</p>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Oporating system</h4>
<p dir="auto">SeaGOAT is designed to work on Linux (<em>tested</em> ✅),
macOS (<a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/178" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/178/hovercard">partly tested, <strong>help</strong></a> 🙏)
and Windows (<a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/179" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/179/hovercard"><strong>help needed</strong></a> 🙏).</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Start SeaGOAT server</h3>
<p dir="auto">In order to use SeaGOAT in your project, you have to start the SeaGOAT server
using the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="seagoat-server start /path/to/your/repo"><pre>seagoat-server start /path/to/your/repo</pre></div>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Search your repository</h3>
<p dir="auto">If you have the server running, you can simply use the
<code>gt</code> or <code>seagoat</code> command to query your repository. For example:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="gt &quot;Where are the numbers rounded&quot;"><pre>gt <span><span>"</span>Where are the numbers rounded<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can also use
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Regular_expression" rel="nofollow">Regular Expressions</a>
in your queries, for example</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="gt &quot;function calc_.* that deals with taxes&quot;"><pre>gt <span><span>"</span>function calc_.* that deals with taxes<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Stopping the server</h3>
<p dir="auto">You can stop the running server using the following command:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="seagoat-server stop /path/to/your/repo"><pre>seagoat-server stop /path/to/your/repo</pre></div>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Development</h2>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Requirements</strong>:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://python-poetry.org/" rel="nofollow">Poetry</a></li>
<li>Python 3.11 or newer</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/BurntSushi/ripgrep">ripgrep</a></li>
</ul>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Install dependencies</h3>
<p dir="auto">After cloning the repository, install dependencies using the following command:</p>

<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running tests</h3>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Watch mode (recommended)</h4>

<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Test changed files</h4>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="poetry run pytest .  --testmon"><pre>poetry run pytest <span>.</span>  --testmon</pre></div>
<h4 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Test all files</h4>

<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Manual testing</h3>
<p dir="auto">You can test any SeaGOAT command manually in your local development
environment. For example to test the development version of the
<code>seagoat-server</code> command, you can run:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="poetry run seagoat-server ~/path/an/example/repository"><pre>poetry run seagoat-server <span>~</span>/path/an/example/repository</pre></div>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">FAQ</h2>
<p dir="auto">The points in this FAQ are indications of how SeaGOAT works, but are not
a legal contract. SeaGOAT is licensed under an open source license and if you
are in doubt about the privacy/safety/etc implications of SeaGOAT, you are
welcome to examine the source code,
<a href="https://github.com/kantord/SeaGOAT/issues/new">raise your concerns</a>,
or create a pull request to fix a problem.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How does SeaGOAT work? Does it send my data to ChatGPT?</h3>
<p dir="auto">SeaGOAT does not rely on 3rd party APIs or any remote APIs and executes all
functionality locally using the SeaGOAT server that you are able to run on
your own machine.</p>
<p dir="auto">Instead of relying on APIs or "connecting to ChatGPT", it uses the vector
database called ChromaDB, with a local vector embedding engine and
telemetry disabled by default.</p>
<p dir="auto">Apart from that, SeaGOAT also uses ripgrep, a regular-expression based code
search engine in order to provider regular expression/keyword based matches
in addition to the "AI-based" matches.</p>
<p dir="auto">While the current version of SeaGOAT does not send your data to remote
servers, it might be possible that in the future there will be <strong>optional</strong>
features that do so, if any further improvement can be gained from that.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why does SeaGOAT need a server?</h3>
<p dir="auto">SeaGOAT needs a server in order to provide a speedy response. SeaGOAT heavily
relies on vector embeddings and vector databases, which at the moment cannot
be replace with an architecture that processes files on the fly.</p>
<p dir="auto">It's worth noting that <em>you are able to run SeaGOAT server entirely locally</em>,
and it works even if you don't have an internet connection. This use case
does not require you to share data with a remote server, you are able to use
your own SeaGOAT server locally, albeit it's also possible to run a SeaGOAT
server and allow other computers to connect to it, if you so wish.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Does SeaGOAT create AI-derived work? Is SeaGOAT ethical?</h3>
<p dir="auto">If you are concerned about the ethical implications of using AI tools keep in
mind that SeaGOAT is not a code generator but a code search engine, therefore
it does not create AI derived work.</p>
<p dir="auto">That being said, a language model <em>is</em> being used to generate vector
embeddings. At the moment SeaGOAT uses ChromaDB's default model for
calculating vector embeddings, and I am not aware of this being an ethical
concern.</p>
<h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">What programming langauges are supported?</h3>
<p dir="auto">Currently SeaGOAT is hardcoded to only process files in the following
formats:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Text Files</strong> (<code>*.txt</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Markdown</strong> (<code>*.md</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Python</strong> (<code>*.py</code>)</li>
<li><strong>C</strong> (<code>*.c</code>, <code>*.h</code>)</li>
<li><strong>C++</strong> (<code>*.cpp</code>, <code>*.cc</code>, <code>*.cxx</code>, <code>*.hpp</code>)</li>
<li><strong>TypeScript</strong> (<code>*.ts</code>, <code>*.tsx</code>)</li>
<li><strong>JavaScript</strong> (<code>*.js</code>, <code>*.jsx</code>)</li>
<li><strong>HTML</strong> (<code>*.html</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Go</strong> (<code>*.go</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Java</strong> (<code>*.java</code>)</li>
<li><strong>PHP</strong> (<code>*.php</code>)</li>
<li><strong>Ruby</strong> (<code>*.rb</code>)</li>
</ul>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Rp2040 runs unmodified PalmOS 5.2.8 (110 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://twitter.com/dmitrygr/status/1704350983877198013</link>
            <guid>37582940</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 11:37:43 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://twitter.com/dmitrygr/status/1704350983877198013">https://twitter.com/dmitrygr/status/1704350983877198013</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37582940">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://twitter.com/dmitrygr/status/1704350983877198013: Error [ERR_FR_TOO_MANY_REDIRECTS]: Maximum number of redirects exceeded]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Google settles account settings lawsuit less than one week after being filed [pdf] (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://oag.ca.gov/system/files/attachments/press-docs/Filed%20stamped%20Google%20Complaint.pdf</link>
            <guid>37582565</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 10:38:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://oag.ca.gov/system/files/attachments/press-docs/Filed%20stamped%20Google%20Complaint.pdf">https://oag.ca.gov/system/files/attachments/press-docs/Filed%20stamped%20Google%20Complaint.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37582565">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We have successfully completed our migration to RAM-only VPN infrastructure (286 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mullvad.net/en/blog/2023/9/20/we-have-successfully-completed-our-migration-to-ram-only-vpn-infrastructure/</link>
            <guid>37581485</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 07:38:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mullvad.net/en/blog/2023/9/20/we-have-successfully-completed-our-migration-to-ram-only-vpn-infrastructure/">https://mullvad.net/en/blog/2023/9/20/we-have-successfully-completed-our-migration-to-ram-only-vpn-infrastructure/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37581485">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <p>Today we announce that we have completely removed all traces of disks being used by our VPN infrastructure!</p>

<p>In early 2022 we announced the<a href="https://mullvad.net/blog/2022/1/12/diskless-infrastructure-beta-system-transparency-stboot/"> beginning of our migration</a> to using diskless infrastructure with our bootloader known as “stboot”.</p>

<h2>Completing the transition to diskless infrastructure</h2>

<p>Our VPN infrastructure has since been audited with this configuration twice (<a href="https://mullvad.net/blog/2023/8/9/infrastructure-audit-completed-by-radically-open-security/">2023</a>, <a href="https://mullvad.net/blog/2022/6/22/vpn-server-audit-found-no-information-leakage-or-logging-of-customer-data/">2022</a>), and all future audits of our VPN servers will focus solely on RAM-only deployments.</p>

<p>All of our VPN servers continue to use our custom and extensively slimmed down Linux kernel, where we follow the mainline branch of kernel development. This has allowed us to pull in the latest version so that we can stay up to date with new features and performance improvements, as well as tune and completely remove unnecessary bloat in the kernel.</p>

<p>The result is that the operating system that we boot, prior to being deployed weighs in at just over 200MB. When servers are rebooted or provisioned for the first time, we can be safe in the knowledge that we get a freshly built kernel, no traces of any log files, and a fully patched OS.</p>
        </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[‘Less than half’ fresh produce sold globally makes any profit (177 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.fruitnet.com/main-navigation/less-than-half-fresh-produce-sold-globally-makes-any-profit/256025.article</link>
            <guid>37581316</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 07:15:10 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.fruitnet.com/main-navigation/less-than-half-fresh-produce-sold-globally-makes-any-profit/256025.article">https://www.fruitnet.com/main-navigation/less-than-half-fresh-produce-sold-globally-makes-any-profit/256025.article</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37581316">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><p><h3>New report suggests massive increase in production and operating costs over past three years has left around 60 per cent of supply unprofitable</h3></p><div><p>Three-fifths of the fresh fruit and vegetables traded commercially around the globe are now sold at a loss or breakeven price, following an unprecedented increase in production and operating costs during the pandemic.</p>
<p>What’s more, those cost increases appear to have greatly reduced the amount of investment going into new projects, which means the effects of that inflation are likely to be felt for some time.</p>
<p>Those are two of the key findings published in a new report by the Global Coalition of Fresh Produce (GCFP), an international thinktank which brings together industry associations including Freshfel Europe, IFPA, CPMA, and Shaffe.</p>
<p>The report, which is based on the results of a survey conducted in early 2023, looked at the increasing cost of fruits and vegetable production around the world, as well as its impacts on the industry and consumers.</p>
<p>“We conducted this global survey to shed light on the challenges experienced by actors in the fresh produce supply chain worldwide,” says GCFP chair Ron Lemaire. “The narrative highlighted in this report will help the industry, its partners and all government levels understand the current impacts of the increase in production and operating costs, and work together to address them.”</p>
<p><strong>Stark conclusions</strong></p>
<p>The report states that producers of fresh fruits and vegetables around the world experienced “unprecedented increases” in production and operating costs during the Covid-19 pandemic, regardless of where in the world they operated. Those increases, the report says, were driven by costs of fertiliser (up 60 per cent worldwide), construction (+48 per cent), fuel and gas (+41 per cent), shipping rates (+40 per cent), and electricity (+40 percent).</p>
<p>Most operators were able to increase their selling prices, the report finds, with rises of 11 per cent in Europe, 13 per cent in Oceania and South America, 14 per cent in North America and 23 per cent in Africa.</p>
<p>However, these increases were “not enough” to compensate for the rise in production and operating costs, the coalition discovered, leaving nearly three-fifths of the global industry “selling at a loss or breaking even”.</p>
<p>Higher costs have also affected strategic and operational choices, it notes: “Certain producers have reduced their output, while some traders have reduced their export activities or switched to produce with lower shipping costs.”</p>
<p>Eighty percent of respondents noted that they had chosen to delay or cancel investment in their businesses, not only in capital and equipment but also in innovation and expansion. “This means that the impacts of the rise in costs will be felt for years to come,” the authors comment.</p>
<p><a href="https://producecoalition.net/publications/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">The final report is available on the Global Coalition of Fresh Produce website</a>.</p>
<p>The Global Coalition of Fresh Produce brings together fresh produce associations from around the world, based on their joint vision to “create resilient global value chains for fruits and vegetables that bring a myriad of economic, environmental and societal benefits”.</p>
<p>Current members are Afruibana, AEBE, Australian Fresh Produce Alliance, AusVeg, CPMA, Colead, Freshfel Europe, FVGC, IFPA, Shaffe, and United Fresh New Zealand.</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OpenTF renames itself to OpenTofu (375 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/opentofu</link>
            <guid>37581132</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 06:44:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/opentofu">https://github.com/opentofu</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37581132">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="" data-view-component="true">
  

  <div>
    
    <article itemprop="text">
<p dir="auto">OpenTofu's goal is to ensure Terraform remains truly open source and proposes returning it to a fully open license. We urge HashiCorp to reconsider and switch Terraform back to an open source license, avoiding fragmentation of the community.</p>
<p dir="auto">For further details and the full text of the manifesto, you can visit the <a href="https://opentofu.org/" rel="nofollow">OpenTofu website</a>.</p>
<h2 dir="auto">Contact</h2>
<p dir="auto">If you have questions or feedback to share, you can reach the team behind this manifesto by emailing us at <a href="mailto:pledge@opentf.org">pledge@opentf.org</a>.</p>
</article>
  </div>


  

     

    <div>

  <h2>
        Pinned

    <svg style="box-sizing: content-box; color: var(--color-icon-primary);" width="16" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" fill="none" data-view-component="true">
  <circle cx="8" cy="8" r="7" stroke="currentColor" stroke-opacity="0.25" stroke-width="2" vector-effect="non-scaling-stroke" fill="none"></circle>
  <path d="M15 8a7.002 7.002 0 00-7-7" stroke="currentColor" stroke-width="2" stroke-linecap="round" vector-effect="non-scaling-stroke"></path>
</svg>
    <span role="status" aria-live="polite" data-error-text="Something went wrong." data-success-text="Order updated."></span>
  </h2>

      <ol>
      <li>
  <div>
      


      <p>
        OpenTofu lets you declaratively manage your cloud infrastructure.
      </p>

      <p>
          <span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span>

          <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/opentofu/stargazers">
            <svg aria-label="stars" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M8 .25a.75.75 0 0 1 .673.418l1.882 3.815 4.21.612a.75.75 0 0 1 .416 1.279l-3.046 2.97.719 4.192a.751.751 0 0 1-1.088.791L8 12.347l-3.766 1.98a.75.75 0 0 1-1.088-.79l.72-4.194L.818 6.374a.75.75 0 0 1 .416-1.28l4.21-.611L7.327.668A.75.75 0 0 1 8 .25Zm0 2.445L6.615 5.5a.75.75 0 0 1-.564.41l-3.097.45 2.24 2.184a.75.75 0 0 1 .216.664l-.528 3.084 2.769-1.456a.75.75 0 0 1 .698 0l2.77 1.456-.53-3.084a.75.75 0 0 1 .216-.664l2.24-2.183-3.096-.45a.75.75 0 0 1-.564-.41L8 2.694Z"></path>
</svg>
            6.6k
          </a>
          <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/opentofu/forks">
            <svg aria-label="forks" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
            174
          </a>
      </p>
    </div>
</li>

      <li>
  <div>
      


      <p>
        The OpenTF Manifesto expresses concern over HashiCorp's switch of the Terraform license from open-source to the Business Source License (BSL) and calls for the tool's return to a truly open-source …
      </p>

      <p>
          <span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">HTML</span>
</span>

          <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/manifesto/stargazers">
            <svg aria-label="stars" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M8 .25a.75.75 0 0 1 .673.418l1.882 3.815 4.21.612a.75.75 0 0 1 .416 1.279l-3.046 2.97.719 4.192a.751.751 0 0 1-1.088.791L8 12.347l-3.766 1.98a.75.75 0 0 1-1.088-.79l.72-4.194L.818 6.374a.75.75 0 0 1 .416-1.28l4.21-.611L7.327.668A.75.75 0 0 1 8 .25Zm0 2.445L6.615 5.5a.75.75 0 0 1-.564.41l-3.097.45 2.24 2.184a.75.75 0 0 1 .216.664l-.528 3.084 2.769-1.456a.75.75 0 0 1 .698 0l2.77 1.456-.53-3.084a.75.75 0 0 1 .216-.664l2.24-2.183-3.096-.45a.75.75 0 0 1-.564-.41L8 2.694Z"></path>
</svg>
            35.4k
          </a>
          <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/manifesto/forks">
            <svg aria-label="forks" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
            1.1k
          </a>
      </p>
    </div>
</li>

</ol>

</div>


    <div id="org-profile-repositories">
      <h3>
        
        Repositories
      </h3>
      
      <div id="org-repositories" data-delay-results="">
    <p><span data-autosearch-results="">Showing 10 of 45 repositories</span></p><div data-view-component="true">
  
  
    <ul data-view-component="true">
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">
        <p><a itemprop="name codeRepository" data-hovercard-type="repository" data-hovercard-url="/opentofu/opentofu/hovercard" href="https://github.com/opentofu/opentofu" data-view-component="true">
          opentofu
</a>
        <span title="Label: Public" data-view-component="true">
          Public
</span></p><p itemprop="description" data-view-component="true">
            OpenTofu lets you declaratively manage your cloud infrastructure.
</p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span>


        <span data-view-component="true">
          0
</span>
        <span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-azurerm/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          4,216
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-azurerm/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-azurerm/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-20T08:26:01Z">Sep 20, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">
        <p><a itemprop="name codeRepository" data-hovercard-type="repository" data-hovercard-url="/opentofu/manifesto/hovercard" href="https://github.com/opentofu/manifesto" data-view-component="true">
          manifesto
</a>
        <span title="Label: Public" data-view-component="true">
          Public
</span></p><p itemprop="description" data-view-component="true">
            The OpenTF Manifesto expresses concern over HashiCorp's switch of the Terraform license from open-source to the Business Source License (BSL) and calls for the tool's return to a truly open-source license.
</p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span>


        <span data-view-component="true">
          0
</span>
        <span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-hcp/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          45
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-hcp/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-hcp/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-20T04:26:16Z">Sep 20, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google/stargazers" data-view-component="true">
          
          2
</a>
        <p><span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          1,653
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-20T01:27:59Z">Sep 20, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span>


        <span data-view-component="true">
          0
</span>
        <span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google-beta/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          237
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google-beta/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-google-beta/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-20T01:26:12Z">Sep 20, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-aws/stargazers" data-view-component="true">
          
          2
</a>
        <p><span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-aws/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          8,326
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-aws/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-aws/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-20T01:21:14Z">Sep 20, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">


        <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/.github/stargazers" data-view-component="true">
          
          6
</a>

        <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/.github/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          1
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/.github/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/.github/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-20T01:10:25Z">Sep 20, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span>


        <span data-view-component="true">
          0
</span>
        <span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-hcs/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          9
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-hcs/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-hcs/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-19T20:27:41Z">Sep 19, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
        <li data-view-component="true">          <div data-view-component="true" itemprop="owns" itemtype="http://schema.org/Code" itemscope="itemscope">

        <p><span>
  <span></span>
  <span itemprop="programmingLanguage">Go</span>
</span>


        <span data-view-component="true">
          0
</span>
        <span data-view-component="true">
          MPL-2.0
</span></p><a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-vsphere/forks" data-view-component="true">
          <svg aria-label="fork" role="img" height="16" viewBox="0 0 16 16" version="1.1" width="16" data-view-component="true">
    <path d="M5 5.372v.878c0 .414.336.75.75.75h4.5a.75.75 0 0 0 .75-.75v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0v.878a2.25 2.25 0 0 1-2.25 2.25h-1.5v2.128a2.251 2.251 0 1 1-1.5 0V8.5h-1.5A2.25 2.25 0 0 1 3.5 6.25v-.878a2.25 2.25 0 1 1 1.5 0ZM5 3.25a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Zm6.75.75a.75.75 0 1 0 0-1.5.75.75 0 0 0 0 1.5Zm-3 8.75a.75.75 0 1 0-1.5 0 .75.75 0 0 0 1.5 0Z"></path>
</svg>
          430
</a>
      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-vsphere/issues" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>

      <a href="https://github.com/opentofu/terraform-provider-vsphere/pulls" data-view-component="true">
        
        0
</a>
      <p><span data-view-component="true">
          Updated <relative-time datetime="2023-09-19T20:23:19Z">Sep 19, 2023</relative-time>
</span></p></div>
</li>
</ul>  
</div></div>
  </div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[FAA authorizes Zipline to deliver commercial packages using drones (491 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.faa.gov/newsroom/faa-authorizes-zipline-deliver-commercial-packages-beyond-line-sight</link>
            <guid>37580141</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 03:42:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.faa.gov/newsroom/faa-authorizes-zipline-deliver-commercial-packages-beyond-line-sight">https://www.faa.gov/newsroom/faa-authorizes-zipline-deliver-commercial-packages-beyond-line-sight</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37580141">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="page-wrapper" data-off-canvas-main-canvas="">

    
 
 
    <section>
    
  <h2>Site Notification</h2>
  
  
      <h2>Site Notification</h2>
    
  
  </section>

 



    <main id="main" aria-label="Site main">

      
      
      <section id="main-wrapper" role="main">
                    <a id="main-content" tabindex="-1"></a>
                    <!--PAGEWATCH-->
                      

<article data-history-node-id="121896" role="article" about="/newsroom/faa-authorizes-zipline-deliver-commercial-packages-beyond-line-sight" typeof="schema:Article">
  <div>
        
    

    <!--PAGEWATCH-->
    
      
      <p> Monday, September 18, 2023</p>
    
        
          <div><p>The FAA authorized Zipline International, Inc., to deliver commercial packages around Salt Lake City and Bentonville, Arkansas, using drones that fly beyond the operator’s visual line of sight. Read the approval letters <a href="https://www.regulations.gov/document/FAA-2020-0499-0033">here</a> and <a href="https://www.regulations.gov/document/FAA-2020-0529-0009">here</a>. Zipline is an FAA-certificated Part 135 operator and will use its Sparrow drone to release the payload via parachute. Data collected from these operations will inform the FAA’s ongoing policy and rulemaking activities.&nbsp;</p><p>
&nbsp;
The FAA is focused on developing standard rules to make BVLOS operations routine, scalable and economically viable. The agency chartered the <a href="https://www.faa.gov/regulations_policies/rulemaking/committees/documents/index.cfm/committee/browse/committeeID/837">Beyond Visual Line of Sight Aviation Rulemaking Committee</a> on June 9, 2021 to provide safety recommendations to the FAA. We are reviewing their <a href="https://www.faa.gov/regulations_policies/rulemaking/committees/documents/media/UAS_BVLOS_ARC_FINAL_REPORT_03102022.pdf">final report</a>.</p><p>
&nbsp;&nbsp;
The FAA’s long-term goal is to safely integrate drones into the National Airspace System rather than set aside separate airspace exclusively for drones. This approach is consistent with the <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/112th-congress/house-bill/658/text/pl">FAA Modernization and Reform Act of 2012</a> and the <a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/114th-congress/house-bill/636/text">FAA Extension, Safety, and Security Act of 2016</a>. The 2016 Act directed the FAA, in conjunction with NASA, to continue developing a plan for <a href="https://www.faa.gov/uas/research_development/traffic_management">Unmanned Aircraft System Traffic Management (UTM)</a>, which will assist in integration efforts.</p><p>
&nbsp;
Learn more <a href="https://www.regulations.gov/document/FAA-2023-1256-0001">here</a> and <a href="https://www.faa.gov/newsroom/faa-seeks-public-input-drone-operations">here</a>.</p></div>
              
      
        <!--/PAGEWATCH-->

    
    

  </div>
</article>


                    <!-- Sub Content Region -->
                                                            <!--/PAGEWATCH-->
                  </section>

    </main>

     

  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Add extra stuff to a “standard” encoding? Sure, why not (209 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2023/09/19/badlib/</link>
            <guid>37580123</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 03:38:49 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2023/09/19/badlib/">https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2023/09/19/badlib/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37580123">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://rachelbythebay.com/w/2023/09/19/badlib/: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[100 Parking Tickets (2004) (148 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://100parkingtickets.com/</link>
            <guid>37580113</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 03:35:13 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://100parkingtickets.com/">https://100parkingtickets.com/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37580113">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><!-- InstanceBeginEditable name="Main" -->
      <h2>The Story:</h2>
      <p>So I was new to California</p>
      <p>Along with a new convertible, I decide to get some personalized plates.</p>
      <p>I could not believe my luck, when I found out that my initials "NV" (ph. "envy") were available. Not that I think anyone would be envious of me in my Miata, but it seemed like a good idea at the time.</p>
      <p><img src="https://100parkingtickets.com/photos/NV.gif" width="328" height="166"></p>
      <p>But then, I started to get random parking tickets from Los Angeles. Where my car has never been. For every type of car. Except a Mazda. Which is what I drive. No problem, right? Just call them up, deal with a healthy level of skepticism when I tell them the ticket isn't mine...
        no really. I would ask them what make &amp; color the ticket is for. I would ask them what make &amp; color my car is. They would always be different. Even a highly skeptical city clerk can't argue with that.</p>
      <p>Then the notices of unpaid violations slowly start to come in from all over California. Because when the license plate is Not Visible, the charming traffic wardens enter "NV" as the license plate. Sometimes they would explain that it was a training issue and they would soon stop bugging me with
        tickets.</p>
      <p>Then the city of Oakland  has a computer upgrade. The first day I get five tickets. The next day... three. And they kept on sending them. For every type of car imaginable including BMW's and Porsches, every car imaginable, except for a white two door Mazda.</p>
      
      <p><img src="https://100parkingtickets.com/photos/oakland.jpg"></p>
      <p>Now I know what you are thinking, BMW's &amp; Porsches don’t park in Oakland.  I was surprised too. But more than that, I was tired of sitting on hold for twenty minutes, waiting to talk to a skeptical city employee. So I returned the custom plates to the DMV, and someone at Oakland told me that all fifty tickets would be put under administrative review.</p>
      <p>Problem solved? Not even. First, the DMV refused to issue me my registration, until I got a piece of paper saying I was not guilty. Then I received a notice that the Franchise Tax Board wanted to garnish my wages. Not with cilantro either. Then I get a notice stating that any tax refund I get will be going to the City of Oakland.</p>
      <p>That is when I started feeling a little irate.</p>
      <p>And a little wiser. I tried calling my local police department, to see if there was a bench warrant out for my arrest. The friendly officer told me that I would have to come to the office... in person. And I swear, she said this with what sounded like a straight face.</p>
      <p>As a last resort, I started to post the story on the internet. You never know. Someone might want a collection of over fifty parking violations from seven different counties for all different makes and models. The asking price was the total owed on all the tickets... $3000.</p>
      <p>
        The only thing that made me feel a little better, was that the lovely folks at Oakland told me someone driving a BMW had the license plates "NV". So if you see a BMW owner with the plates "NV", give him a wave. Tell him you work for the City of Oakland. For the traffic violations department. See if he goes green. You know, from envy.      </p>
      <p>NV</p>
      
      <!-- InstanceEndEditable --></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ruby 3.3's YJIT Runs Shopify's Production Code 15% Faster (155 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://railsatscale.com/2023-09-18-ruby-3-3-s-yjit-runs-shopify-s-production-code-15-faster/</link>
            <guid>37579926</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 02:57:08 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://railsatscale.com/2023-09-18-ruby-3-3-s-yjit-runs-shopify-s-production-code-15-faster/">https://railsatscale.com/2023-09-18-ruby-3-3-s-yjit-runs-shopify-s-production-code-15-faster/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37579926">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <h2 id="ruby-32-yjit-is-battle-tested">Ruby 3.2 YJIT is Battle-Tested</h2>

<p>Shopify deploys YJIT on business-critical services in production,
such as <a href="https://shopify.engineering/how-shopify-reduced-storefront-response-times-rewrite">Storefront Renderer</a>,
the software that powers all online storefronts on Shopify’s platform, and <a href="https://shopify.engineering/shopify-monolith">Shopify’s Monolith</a>.
As of the Ruby 3.2 release, YJIT sped up our Storefront Renderer by <a href="https://twitter.com/paracycle/status/1605706245955997697">10% on average</a>.</p>

<p>Storefront Renderer is a complex application. Your more reasonable-sized app might get better/worse results.
Here are some other YJIT performance results in production outside Shopify:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Discourse: <a href="https://blog.discourse.org/2023/05/running-ruby-3-2s-yjit-in-production-at-discourse/">15.8-19.6% speedup</a></li>
  <li>Lobsters: <a href="https://lobste.rs/s/m9ivcf/we_turned_lobste_rs_into_rails_benchmark#c_fkud5w">26% speedup</a></li>
  <li>CompanyCam: <a href="https://ruby.social/@mcphat/111075935007519631">20-40% speedup</a></li>
  <li>GMO Pepabo: <a href="https://shimoju.jp/2023/08/10/ruby-3-2-yjit-with-rails-6-1/">18% speedup</a> (in Japanese)</li>
  <li>Timee: <a href="https://tech.timee.co.jp/entry/2023/05/10/133000">10% speedup</a> (in Japanese)</li>
  <li>STORES: <a href="https://product.st.inc/entry/2023/05/31/130809">6.5-7.5% speedup</a> (in Japanese)</li>
  <li>MedPeer: <a href="https://tech.medpeer.co.jp/entry/2023/05/09/100000">2.8% speedup</a> (in Japanese)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="performance-tips-for-production-deployments">Performance Tips for Production Deployments</h2>
<p>We sometimes hear people say YJIT doesn’t speed up their application or uses too much memory.
The following documentation covers some tips for tuning YJIT in such cases.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/master/doc/yjit/yjit.md#performance-tips-for-production-deployments">Performance Tips for Production Deployments</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/master/doc/yjit/yjit.md#saving-yjit-memory-usage">Saving YJIT Memory Usage</a></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://railsatscale.com/2023-06-05-monitoring-yjit-in-production/">Monitoring YJIT in Production</a>
might also help you get more insight.</p>

<h2 id="ruby-33-yjit-is-even-faster">Ruby 3.3 YJIT is Even Faster</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.ruby-lang.org/en/news/2023/09/14/ruby-3-3-0-preview2-released/">Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 has been released</a>
on Sep 14th, 2023. We compared the performance of Ruby 3.2 YJIT, Ruby 3.3-preview2 YJIT, and Ruby 3.3-preview2 interpreter
on the Storefront Renderer. It’s a large-scale service with the following properties:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Depends on over 220 Ruby gems</li>
  <li>Over 4.5 million e-commerce sites are built with Shopify (source: <a href="https://builtwith.com/">builtwith.com</a>)</li>
  <li>Capable of serving over 75 million requests per minute, 3TB/minute of traffic</li>
  <li>1.27 million requests per second</li>
  <li>Processed over 197B$ in transaction volume in 2022</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="ruby-33-yjit-is-13-faster-than-ruby-32-yjit">Ruby 3.3 YJIT is 13% faster than Ruby 3.2 YJIT</h2>

<p>We deployed Ruby 3.2.2 YJIT and Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT to different clusters that receive an equal amount of traffic.
We compared their response times in a 24-hour window on a weekday.</p>

<p><img src="https://railsatscale.com/2023-09-18-ruby-3-3-s-yjit-runs-shopify-s-production-code-15-faster/3.2-3.3-yjit.png" alt="Ruby 3.3 YJIT vs Ruby 3.2 YJIT"></p>

<p>The numbers and the graph show Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT’s average/p50/p90/p99 response time speedup ratio over
Ruby 3.2.2 YJIT’s. Higher is better for Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT.</p>

<p>This shows that Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT is 13% faster than Ruby 3.2.2 YJIT on average.
If you’re using Ruby 3.2 YJIT, upgrading Ruby to 3.3 should give you a 13% speedup.</p>

<h2 id="ruby-33-yjit-is-15-faster-than-the-ruby-33-interpreter">Ruby 3.3 YJIT is 15% faster than the Ruby 3.3 interpreter</h2>

<p>During the same 24-hour window, we also deployed Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 interpreter to another cluster.
We compared its performance against that of the cluster with Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT.</p>

<p><img src="https://railsatscale.com/2023-09-18-ruby-3-3-s-yjit-runs-shopify-s-production-code-15-faster/3.3-interp-yjit.png" alt="Ruby 3.3 YJIT vs Ruby 3.3 interpreter"></p>

<p>The numbers and the graph show Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT’s average/p50/p90/p99 response time speedup ratio over
Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 interpreter’s. Higher is better for Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT.</p>

<p>When you run Ruby 3.3 interpreter, just enabling YJIT will give you a 15% speedup.</p>

<h2 id="why-is-it-faster">Why is it faster?</h2>

<h3 id="new-register-allocator">New register allocator</h3>

<p>The CRuby interpreter writes and reads temporary values on memory.
Ruby 3.2 YJIT used to work in the same way for compatibility reasons,
but Ruby 3.3 YJIT is able to allocate registers to those operations.
In general, accessing CPU registers is much faster than communicating with memory,
so Ruby code runs faster with the optimization.</p>

<h3 id="more-code-now-gets-jit-compiled">More code now gets JIT compiled</h3>

<p>Ruby 3.3 YJIT supports compiling more kinds of Ruby code than Ruby 3.2 YJIT.
When a method has optional arguments, Ruby 3.2 YJIT compiles only one combination of parameter precenses,
but Ruby 3.3 YJIT handles multiple combinations.
Ruby 3.2 YJIT does not compile code that is executed after <code>break</code>, <code>next</code>, <code>redo</code>, <code>retry</code>, etc.,
but Ruby 3.3 YJIT does.
Ruby 3.2 YJIT gives up compiling a method call when it does not support the method call type,
but Ruby 3.3 YJIT falls back to an implementation that can handle anything.</p>

<p>In a nutshell, more code runs on JIT with Ruby 3.3 YJIT than Ruby 3.2 YJIT, so it’s faster.</p>

<h2 id="towards-the-ruby-330-release">Towards the Ruby 3.3.0 release</h2>

<h3 id="reducing-memory-overhead">Reducing memory overhead</h3>
<p>Since Ruby 3.3.0-preview2 YJIT generates more code than Ruby 3.2.2 YJIT, this can result in YJIT having a higher memory overlead.
We put a lot of effort into making metadata more space-efficient, but it still uses more memory than Ruby 3.2.2 YJIT.
We’re looking into skipping compilation of paths that are less frequently executed.</p>

<h3 id="optimizing-method-calls">Optimizing method calls</h3>
<p>Ruby’s method calls are complex. YJIT code spends a lot of time bookkeeping frames for method calls.
We’re working on making any method calls faster by packing frame metadata into a single pointer
and lazily materializing its fields when necessary. Hopefully, it will greatly speed up method calls
as well as reducing the code size.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>Ruby 3.2 YJIT has optimized the production workloads of Shopify and other companies.
We encourage you to enable YJIT in production.
Once Ruby 3.3 is released, it should make your application even faster.</p>

<h2 id="references">References</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/master/doc/yjit/yjit.md#command-line-options">This document</a> explains how to enable YJIT.
As a reminder, the following links may help you troubleshoot performance problems with YJIT.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/master/doc/yjit/yjit.md#performance-tips-for-production-deployments">Performance Tips for Production Deployments</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/ruby/ruby/blob/master/doc/yjit/yjit.md#saving-yjit-memory-usage">Saving YJIT Memory Usage</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://railsatscale.com/2023-06-05-monitoring-yjit-in-production/">Monitoring YJIT in Production</a></li>
</ul>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A simple web server written in Awk (187 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/crossbowerbt/awk-webserver</link>
            <guid>37579595</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 02:02:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/crossbowerbt/awk-webserver">https://github.com/crossbowerbt/awk-webserver</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37579595">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-target="readme-toc.content">
            <article itemprop="text"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Simple webserver written in gawk</h2>
<p dir="auto">A simple webserver written in GNU awk, that supports directory listing and download of files from the directory where it is launched.</p>
<p dir="auto">It is born as an experiment, to demonstrate the power of the awk language.</p>
<h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2>
<p dir="auto">The script must be executed through a TCP wrapper.</p>
<p dir="auto">I use this little shell script that requires socat:</p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="while [ 1 ]; do
	socat TCP-LISTEN:8888,reuseaddr EXEC:&quot;gawk -f webserver.awk&quot;
	sleep 1
done "><pre><code>while [ 1 ]; do
	socat TCP-LISTEN:8888,reuseaddr EXEC:"gawk -f webserver.awk"
	sleep 1
done 
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">You can then connect to the local 8888 port with your browser. Enjoy!</p>
</article>
          </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Shaving 40% Off Google’s B-Tree Implementation with Go Generics (2022) (106 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.scylladb.com/2022/04/27/shaving-40-off-googles-b-tree-implementation-with-go-generics/</link>
            <guid>37578850</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2023 00:13:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2022/04/27/shaving-40-off-googles-b-tree-implementation-with-go-generics/">https://www.scylladb.com/2022/04/27/shaving-40-off-googles-b-tree-implementation-with-go-generics/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37578850">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                        <p>There are many reasons to be excited about generics in Go. In this blog post I’m going to show how, using the generics, we got a 40% performance gain in an already well optimized package, the <a href="https://github.com/google/btree" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Google B-Tree</a> implementation.</p>
<p>A <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/B-tree" target="_blank" rel="noopener">B-Tree</a> is a kind of self-balancing tree. For the purpose of this blog post it’s sufficient to say that it is a collection. You can add, remove, get or iterate over its elements. The Google B-Tree is well optimized, measures are taken to make sure memory consumption is correct. There is a benchmark for every exported method. The benchmark results show that there are zero allocations in the B-Tree code for all operations but cloning. Probably it would be hard to further optimize using traditional techniques.</p>
<h2>ScyllaDB and the University of Warsaw</h2>
<p>We have had a longstanding relationship with the Computer Science department at the University of Warsaw. You may remember some of our original projects, including those integrating <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2020/08/05/scylla-student-projects-part-i-parquet/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Parquet</a>, an <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2020/08/25/scylla-student-projects-part-ii-implementing-an-async-userspace-file-system/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">async userspace filesystem</a>, or a <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2020/11/17/scylla-student-projects-part-iii-kafka-client-for-seastar-and-scylla/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Kafka client for Seastar</a>. Or more recent ones like a system for <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2021/09/07/linear-algebra-in-scylla/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">linear algebra</a> in ScyllaDB or a design for a new <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/2021/07/13/scylla-rust-driver-update-and-benchmarks/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rust driver</a>.</p>
<p>This work was also part of our ongoing partnership with the University of Warsaw.</p>
<h2>Making Faster B-Trees with Generics</h2>
<p>While working on a new Scylla Go Driver with students of University of Warsaw, we ported the B-tree code to <a href="https://github.com/Michal-Leszczynski/btree" target="_blank" rel="noopener">generics</a>. (If you’re not familiar with generics in Go, check out <a href="https://go.dev/doc/tutorial/generics" target="_blank" rel="noopener">this tutorial</a>.).</p>
<p>The initial result: the generics code is faster by 20 to 30 percent according to the Google benchmarks (<a href="https://github.com/google/btree/issues/41" target="_blank" rel="noopener">link to issue we opened</a>). Below a full benchmark comparison done with benchstat.</p>

<p>This is great but within those numbers there is a troubling detail. The zero allocations is not something that you would normally see given that the functions accept an interface as a parameter.</p>

<p>For the rest of the blog post we’ll focus on benchmarking the <code>ReplaceOrInsert</code> function responsible for ingesting data. Let’s consider a simplified benchmark.</p>

<p>The results show even greater improvement: 31% vs. 27%, and allocations drop from 1, in case of the interface based implementation, to 0 in the case of generics.</p>

<p>Let’s try to understand what happens here.</p>
<h2>The Additional Allocation</h2>
<p>The Google benchmarks operate on a B-tree of integers <a href="https://github.com/google/btree/blob/ac7cc57f11e692c57831c3d9bcffb4b7a649b738/btree.go#L885" target="_blank" rel="noopener">hidden by an Item interface</a>. They use pre-generated random data in a slice. When an Item is passed to the <code>ReplaceOrInsert</code> function the underlying integer is already on the heap, technically we are copying a pointer. This is not the case when a plain integer needs to be converted to an Item interface — the parameter values start “escaping to heap”.</p>
<p>Go has a feature of deciding if a variable you initialized should live in the function’s stack or in the heap. Traditionally the compiler was very “conservative” and when it saw a function like <code>func bind(v interface{})</code> anything you wanted to pass as <code>v</code> would have to go to heap first. This is referred to as variable escaping to the heap. Over the years the compiler has gotten smarter, and calls to local functions or functions in other packages in your project can be optimized, preventing the variables from escaping. You can check for yourself by running&nbsp; <code>go build -gcflags="-m" .</code> in a Go package.</p>
<p>In the below example Go can figure out that it’s safe to take a pointer to the main functions stack.</p>

<p>As you can see the compiler informs us that variables do not escape to heap.</p>

<p>By changing the ToString implementation to</p>

<p>we see that the variables and literal values do start escaping.</p>

<p>In practical examples, when calling a function that accepts an interface as a parameter, the value almost always escapes to heap. When this happens it not only slows down the function call by the allocation, but also increases the GC pressure. Why is this important? The generics approach enables a truly zero allocation API, with zero GC pressure added as we will learn in the remainder of this blog post.</p>
<h2>Why is it faster?</h2>
<p>The B-tree, being a tree, consists of nodes. Each node holds a list of items.</p>

<p>When the Item is a pre-generics plain old interface, the value it holds must live separately somewhere on the heap. The compiler is not able to tell what is the size of an Item. From the runtime perspective an interface value is an unsafe pointer to data (word), a pointer to its type definition (typ), a pointer to interface definition (ityp); see <a href="https://github.com/golang/go/blob/357c9141369361101345f3048a6b2b3e149299d5/src/reflect/value.go#L180" target="_blank" rel="noopener">definitions in the reflect package</a>. It’s easier to digest than the runtime package. In that case we have items as a slice of int pointers.</p>
<p>On the other hand, with generic interface</p>

<p>and a generic type definition</p>

<p>items are a slice of ints — this reduces the number of small heap objects by a factor of 32.</p>
<p>Enough of theory, let’s try to examine a concrete usage. For the purpose of this blog I wrote a test program that is a scaled up version of my benchmark code.</p>

<p>We are adding 100 million integers, and the degree of the B-tree (number of items in a node) is 1k. There are two versions of this program: one uses generics, the other plain old interface. The difference in code is minimal, it’s literally changing <code>btree.New(degree)</code> to <code>btree.New[btree.Int](degree)</code> in line 13. Let’s compare data gathered by running both versions under `<code>/usr/bin/time -l -p</code>`.</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td></td>
<td>generics</td>
<td>interface</td>
<td>delta</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>real</td>
<td>11.49</td>
<td>16.59</td>
<td>-30.74%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span><strong>user</strong></span></td>
<td>11.27</td>
<td>18.61</td>
<td><span><strong>-39.44%</strong></span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span><strong>sys</strong></span></td>
<td>0.24</td>
<td>0.6</td>
<td><span><strong>-60.00%</strong></span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><strong>maximum resident set size</strong></td>
<td><span>2334212096</span></td>
<td><span>6306217984</span></td>
<td><span><strong>-62.99%</strong></span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>average shared memory size</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>average unshared data size</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>average unshared stack size</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>page reclaims</td>
<td><span>142624</span></td>
<td><span>385306</span></td>
<td>-62.98%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>page faults</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>swaps</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>block input operations</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>block output operations</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>messages sent</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>messages received</td>
<td>0</td>
<td>0</td>
<td></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>signals received</td>
<td>600</td>
<td>843</td>
<td>-28.83%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>voluntary context switches</td>
<td>25</td>
<td>48</td>
<td>-47.92%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>involuntary context switches</td>
<td>1652</td>
<td>2943</td>
<td>-43.87%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>instructions retired</td>
<td><span>204760684966</span></td>
<td><span>288827272312</span></td>
<td>-29.11%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>cycles elapsed</td>
<td><span>37046278867</span></td>
<td><span>60503503105</span></td>
<td>-38.77%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>peak memory footprint</td>
<td><span>2334151872</span></td>
<td><span>6308147904</span></td>
<td>-63.00%</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><span><strong>HeapObjects</strong></span></td>
<td><span>236884</span></td>
<td><span>50255826</span></td>
<td><span><strong>-99.53%</strong></span></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>HeapAlloc</td>
<td><span>2226292560</span></td>
<td><span>6043893088</span></td>
<td>-63.16%</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Here using generics solves a version of <em>N</em>+1 problem for slices of interfaces. Instead of one slice and <em>N</em> integers in heap we now can have just the slice of ints. The results are profound, the new code behaves better in every aspect. The wall time duration is down by 40%, context switches are down by 40%, system resources utilization is down by 60% — all thanks to a 99.53% reduction of small heap objects.</p>
<p>I’d like to conclude by taking a look at top CPU utilization.</p>
<p><code>go tool pprof -top cpu.pprof</code></p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>generics</td>
<td>interface</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code><span>Type: cpu<br>
Time: Apr 5, 2022 at 10:23am (CEST)<br>
Duration: 11.61s, Total samples = 11.05s (95.18%)&lt;<br>
Showing nodes accounting for 10.77s, 97.47% of 11.05s total<br>
Dropped 52 nodes (cum &lt;= 0.06s)<br>
flat&nbsp; flat% &nbsp; sum%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; cum &nbsp; cum%<br>
4.96s 44.89% 44.89%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 4.96s 44.89%&nbsp; runtime.madvise<br>
4.61s 41.72% 86.61%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 4.61s 41.72%&nbsp; runtime.memclrNoHeapPointers<br>
0.64s&nbsp; 5.79% 92.40%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.64s&nbsp; 5.79%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.items[...].find.func1<br>
0.19s&nbsp; 1.72% 94.12%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.83s&nbsp; 7.51%&nbsp; sort.Search<br>
0.08s&nbsp; 0.72% 94.84%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 5.82s 52.67%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree..insert<br>
0.08s&nbsp; 0.72% 95.57%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.08s&nbsp; 0.72%&nbsp; runtime.mmap<br>
0.07s&nbsp; 0.63% 96.20%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.90s&nbsp; 8.14%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.items[...].find<br>
0.05s&nbsp; 0.45% 96.65%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 5.88s 53.21%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree..ReplaceOrInsert<br>
0.05s&nbsp; 0.45% 97.10%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 4.19s 37.92%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree..insertAt (inline)<br>
0.04s&nbsp; 0.36% 97.47%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.61s&nbsp; 5.52%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree..maybeSplitChild<br>
0 &nbsp; &nbsp; 0% 97.47%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.57s&nbsp; 5.16%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree..split</span></code></td>
<td><code><span>Type: cpu<br>
Time: Apr 5, 2022 at 10:31am (CEST)<br>
Duration: 16.69s, Total samples = 18.65s (111.74%)<br>
Showing nodes accounting for 17.94s, 96.19% of 18.65s total<br>
Dropped 75 nodes (cum &lt;= 0.09s)<br>
flat&nbsp; flat% &nbsp; sum%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; cum &nbsp; cum%<br>
9.53s 51.10% 51.10%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 9.53s 51.10%&nbsp; runtime.madvise<br>
2.62s 14.05% 65.15%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.62s 14.05%&nbsp; runtime.memclrNoHeapPointers<br>
1.09s&nbsp; 5.84% 70.99%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 1.31s&nbsp; 7.02%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.items.find.func1<br>
0.93s&nbsp; 4.99% 75.98%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.73s 14.64%&nbsp; runtime.scanobject<br>
0.67s&nbsp; 3.59% 79.57%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.67s&nbsp; 3.59%&nbsp; runtime.heapBits.bits (inline)<br>
0.44s&nbsp; 2.36% 81.93%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 1.75s&nbsp; 9.38%&nbsp; sort.Search<br>
0.30s&nbsp; 1.61% 83.54%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.30s&nbsp; 1.61%&nbsp; runtime.markBits.isMarked (inline)<br>
0.27s&nbsp; 1.45% 84.99%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.03s 10.88%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.items.find<br>
0.27s&nbsp; 1.45% 86.43%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 3.35s 17.96%&nbsp; runtime.mallocgc<br>
0.26s&nbsp; 1.39% 87.83%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.26s&nbsp; 1.39%&nbsp; runtime.(*mspan).refillAllocCache<br>
0.25s&nbsp; 1.34% 89.17%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.60s&nbsp; 3.22%&nbsp; runtime.greyobject<br>
0.24s&nbsp; 1.29% 90.46%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.26s&nbsp; 1.39%&nbsp; runtime.heapBits.next (inline)<br>
0.23s&nbsp; 1.23% 91.69%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.23s&nbsp; 1.23%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.Int.Less<br>
0.20s&nbsp; 1.07% 92.76%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.20s&nbsp; 1.07%&nbsp; runtime.memmove<br>
0.20s&nbsp; 1.07% 93.83%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.20s&nbsp; 1.07%&nbsp; runtime.mmap<br>
0.15s &nbsp; 0.8% 94.64%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.47s 13.24%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.(*items).insertAt (inline)<br>
0.12s&nbsp; 0.64% 95.28%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.27s&nbsp; 1.45%&nbsp; runtime.findObject<br>
0.08s&nbsp; 0.43% 95.71%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 5.44s 29.17%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.(*node).insert<br>
0.03s&nbsp; 0.16% 95.87%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 5.48s 29.38%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.(*BTree).ReplaceOrInsert<br>
0.02s&nbsp; 0.11% 95.98%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.84s&nbsp; 4.50%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.(*node).maybeSplitChild<br>
0.02s&nbsp; 0.11% 96.09%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.45s&nbsp; 2.41%&nbsp; runtime.convT64<br>
0.01s 0.054% 96.14%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 9.83s 52.71%&nbsp; runtime.(*mheap).allocSpan<br>
0.01s 0.054% 96.19%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.82s 15.12%&nbsp; runtime.gcDrain<br>
0 &nbsp; &nbsp; 0% 96.19%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.78s&nbsp; 4.18%&nbsp; github.com/google/btree.(*node).split</span></code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>You can literally see how messy the interface profile is, how gc starts kicking in killing it… It’s even more evident when we focus on gc.</p>
<p><code>go tool pprof -focus gc -top cpu.pprof</code></p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>generics</td>
<td>interface</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><code><span>Type: cpu<br>
Time: Apr 5, 2022 at 10:23am (CEST)<br>
Duration: 11.61s, Total samples = 11.05s (95.18%)<br>
Active filters:<br>
focus=gc<br>
Showing nodes accounting for 0.29s, 2.62% of 11.05s total<br>
flat&nbsp; flat% &nbsp; sum%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; cum &nbsp; cum%<br>
0.19s&nbsp; 1.72%&nbsp; 1.72%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.19s&nbsp; 1.72%&nbsp; runtime.memclrNoHeapPointers<br>
0.02s&nbsp; 0.18%&nbsp; 1.90%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.02s&nbsp; 0.18%&nbsp; runtime.(*mspan).refillAllocCache<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 1.99%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.02s&nbsp; 0.18%&nbsp; runtime.(*fixalloc).alloc<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.08%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; runtime.(*mheap).allocNeedsZero<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.17%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; runtime.(*mspan).init (inline)<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.26%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; runtime.heapBits.bits (inline)<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.35%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; runtime.markrootSpans<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.44%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; runtime.recordspan<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.53%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.02s&nbsp; 0.18%&nbsp; runtime.scanobject<br>
0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; 2.62%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.01s&nbsp; 0.09%&nbsp; runtime.stkbucket</span></code></td>
<td><code><span>Type: cpu<br>
Time: Apr 5, 2022 at 10:31am (CEST)<br>
Duration: 16.69s, Total samples = 18.65s (111.74%)<br>
Active filters:<br>
focus=gc<br>
Showing nodes accounting for 6.06s, 32.49% of 18.65s total<br>
Dropped 27 nodes (cum &lt;= 0.09s)<br>
flat&nbsp; flat% &nbsp; sum%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; cum &nbsp; cum%<br>
2.62s 14.05% 14.05%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.62s 14.05%&nbsp; runtime.memclrNoHeapPointers<br>
0.93s&nbsp; 4.99% 19.03%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.73s 14.64%&nbsp; runtime.scanobject<br>
0.67s&nbsp; 3.59% 22.63%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.67s&nbsp; 3.59%&nbsp; runtime.heapBits.bits (inline)<br>
0.30s&nbsp; 1.61% 24.24%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.30s&nbsp; 1.61%&nbsp; runtime.markBits.isMarked (inline)<br>
0.27s&nbsp; 1.45% 25.68%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 3.35s 17.96%&nbsp; runtime.mallocgc<br>
0.26s&nbsp; 1.39% 27.08%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.26s&nbsp; 1.39%&nbsp; runtime.(*mspan).refillAllocCache<br>
0.25s&nbsp; 1.34% 28.42%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.60s&nbsp; 3.22%&nbsp; runtime.greyobject<br>
0.24s&nbsp; 1.29% 29.71%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.26s&nbsp; 1.39%&nbsp; runtime.heapBits.next (inline)<br>
0.12s&nbsp; 0.64% 30.35%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.27s&nbsp; 1.45%&nbsp; runtime.findObject<br>
0.08s&nbsp; 0.43% 30.78%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.08s&nbsp; 0.43%&nbsp; runtime.spanOf (inline)<br>
0.06s&nbsp; 0.32% 31.10%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.06s&nbsp; 0.32%&nbsp; runtime.(*mspan).base (inline)<br>
0.06s&nbsp; 0.32% 31.42%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.06s&nbsp; 0.32%&nbsp; runtime.(*mspan).init (inline)<br>
0.06s&nbsp; 0.32% 31.74%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.06s&nbsp; 0.32%&nbsp; runtime.heapBitsSetType<br>
0.04s&nbsp; 0.21% 31.96%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.04s&nbsp; 0.21%&nbsp; runtime.(*mSpanStateBox).get (inline)<br>
0.04s&nbsp; 0.21% 32.17%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.04s&nbsp; 0.21%&nbsp; runtime.pthread_kill<br>
0.04s&nbsp; 0.21% 32.39%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.04s&nbsp; 0.21%&nbsp; runtime.usleep<br>
0.01s 0.054% 32.44%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 0.10s&nbsp; 0.54%&nbsp; runtime.(*mheap).allocSpan<br>
0.01s 0.054% 32.49%&nbsp; &nbsp; &nbsp; 2.82s 15.12%&nbsp; runtime.gcDrain</span></code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>The generic version spent <strong>0.29s</strong> (<strong>2.62%</strong>) in GC while the interface version spent <strong>6.06s</strong> accounting for, hold your breath, <em><strong>32.49% of the total time!</strong></em></p>
<p><a href="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9.png"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9.png" alt="" width="800" height="242" srcset="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9.png 1999w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-300x91.png 300w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-1100x332.png 1100w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-768x232.png 768w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-1536x464.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20width='800'%20height='242'%20viewBox='0%200%20800%20242'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-src="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9.png" data-srcset="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9.png 1999w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-300x91.png 300w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-1100x332.png 1100w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-768x232.png 768w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image2-9-1536x464.png 1536w"></a><em>Generics: CPU profile flame focused on GC related function</em></p>

<p><a href="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5.png"><img decoding="async" src="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5.png" alt="" width="800" height="263" srcset="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5.png 1999w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-300x99.png 300w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-1100x362.png 1100w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-768x253.png 768w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-1536x506.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" data-old-src="data:image/svg+xml,%3Csvg%20xmlns='http://www.w3.org/2000/svg'%20width='800'%20height='263'%20viewBox='0%200%20800%20263'%3E%3C/svg%3E" data-src="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5.png" data-srcset="https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5.png 1999w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-300x99.png 300w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-1100x362.png 1100w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-768x253.png 768w, https://www.scylladb.com/wp-content/uploads/image3-5-1536x506.png 1536w"></a><em>Interface: CPU profile flame focused on GC related functions</em></p>
<h2>Conclusion</h2>
<p>By shifting the implementation from one using interfaces, to one using generics, we were able to significantly improve performance, minimize garbage collection time, and minimize CPU and other resource utilization, such as heap size. Particularly with heap size, we were able to reduce HeapObjects by <strong>99.53%</strong>.</p>
<p>The future of Go generics is bright especially in the domain of slices.</p>

<p><a href="https://resources.scylladb.com/scylladb-engineering" target="_blank" rel="noopener">EXPLORE MORE SCYLLADB ENGINEERING CONTENT</a></p>
<h2>Want to be a ScyllaDB Monster?</h2>
<p>We’re definitely proud of the work we do with the students at the University of Warsaw. Yet ScyllaDB is a growing company with a talented workforce drawn from all over the world. If you enjoy writing high performance generic Go code, <a href="https://www.scylladb.com/company/careers/co/engineering/B4.424/back-end-golang-team-leader/all/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">come join us</a>. Or if you specialize in other languages or talents, check out our full list of careers at ScyllaDB:</p>
<p><a href="https://www.scylladb.com/company/careers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CAREERS AT SCYLLADB</a></p>



                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[A small community of unofficial Apple technicians in Cuba (153 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://restofworld.org/2023/underground-apple-techs-cuba/</link>
            <guid>37577354</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 21:52:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://restofworld.org/2023/underground-apple-techs-cuba/">https://restofworld.org/2023/underground-apple-techs-cuba/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37577354">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
				<!-- Article Start -->
				
<p>Months after Ángel García Padrón fixed a German journalist’s MacBook Pro in his small Havana repair shop, she sent him an email. García Padrón had mended her waterlogged laptop after her home in Cuba flooded, but when the journalist took it to an official Apple Store in Berlin, the authorized repair person had expressed disbelief, saying there was no trace of any water damage at all. “Then my Cuban repairman must be a magician,” she recounted telling the Apple worker. García Padrón is used to conjuring these sorts of tricks on a daily basis — the skills required to deal with Apple products in Cuba require a special sort of magic.</p>



<p>Even though prohibition limiting the exportation, re-exportation, sale, and supply of Apple products to Cuba was <a href="https://www.bis.doc.gov/index.php/documents/pdfs/2796-20210811-fact-sheet-supporting-the-cuban-people-s-right-to-seek-receive-and-impart-information-through-safe-and-secure-access-to-the-internet/file">eased in 2015</a>, getting a hold of, operating, and maintaining them can still be a challenge. This is in part because basic replacement parts are difficult to import, since they cannot be purchased directly from Apple. It’s not just hardware, either: Downloading apps or software updates is tricky because Cuban IP addresses are blocked. And setting up a new Apple ID with two-factor verification requires a phone number from outside Cuba.</p>



<p>García Padrón is part of an exclusive circle of Apple enthusiasts who are defying Cuba’s constraints to create profitable repair businesses. In little more than a decade, these Cuban Apple technicians have evolved from casual tinkerers to a small yet thriving community of celebrity repairers, respected by locals and foreigners alike.</p>



<p>The absence of official Apple stores and product resellers in Cuba has fostered a community-driven ecosystem that relies on unofficial suppliers and a transnational network of individuals who can travel abroad to buy hardware replacement parts. Technicians told <em>Rest of World</em> there are only a handful of Apple repair shops in Cuba, mostly clustered in Havana; it’s difficult to pinpoint the exact number as there are no official statistics.</p>



<p>Orlando Gutiérrez is one Cuban trailblazer who opened Meca Móvil, his own iPhone repair shop in Havana’s Vedado neighborhood. Finding an Android repairperson, he told <em>Rest of World</em>, is easy enough. “You might even find a few on a single block,” he said. “But a Mac technician is the holy grail.”</p>



<p>From the moment Meca Móvil officially opened its doors in 2011, Gutiérrez began to service the phones of Cuba’s elite creative class and local celebrities — the type of people who had the means to travel abroad and buy an Apple device back then. One of his loyal customers was the reggaeton singer Yosdani Jacob Carmenates, or Jacob Forever, known for his chart-topping track <em>La Gozadera</em>. Gutiérrez said the singer bought an iPhone during a visit to Miami, but then found that he was completely unable to use it upon his return to Havana. He couldn’t install apps or update his phone’s software — until he visited Meca Móvil.&nbsp;</p>



<p>These cases are the easiest to fix, said Gutiérrez. The first step is to install a virtual private network (VPN) to disguise the device’s presence in Cuba. For VIP customers like Jacob Forever, Meca Móvil’s Apple troubleshooters would also install a bundle of commonly used apps. Back when he first started out, before 3G connectivity was widely available, Gutiérrez vividly remembers clients asking for apps like the offline version of Wikipedia (which he described as “Cuban Google”). Though times have changed — clients now ask for Duolingo, online banking app Banca Remota, or streaming platforms like Netflix — this service remains much the same. Though Meca Móvil shut down in 2015, Gutiérrez is now an <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@CubaGeek">Apple-specialized YouTuber</a>.</p>



<p>This arrangement proved particularly valuable during a time when <a href="https://restofworld.org/2020/the-life-and-death-of-snet-havanas-alternative-internet/">public internet access points in Cuba were scarce</a> and unaffordable for most people. Some Apple technicians discovered a workaround by securing state jobs that guaranteed internet connectivity, allowing them to regularly download apps and software they would later install in customers’ devices. Despite the Cuban peso’s devaluation over the past several years, the cost of installing an app package has consistently stayed within the range of $1–$5.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Now, as Cubans have gained <a href="https://restofworld.org/2023/cuba-e-commerce-boom/">greater access to tech from abroad</a>, services like creating Apple IDs and removing carrier locks on iPhones are still in demand — for which local technicians have developed their own creative strategies. To create an Apple ID, without which many of the phone’s functions won’t work, repair people must provide a foreign phone number to pass the two-factor authentication process. To accomplish this, they use free websites like TextNow, which offer users unlimited SMS messages and calls from outside of Cuba.</p>



<figure><blockquote><p>“There’s a magic in fixing what others would have otherwise discarded.”</p></blockquote></figure>



<p>Many Cubans will often ask repair people like García Padrón to install Windows on their Apple laptops. While MacBooks have become a status symbol across Havana’s universities and creative industries, many still prefer the Windows operating system as it’s easier to use in Cuba.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Users with iPhones from U.S. cellphone carriers like AT&amp;T, Verizon, or T-Mobile need a technician to remove the lock tying the device to its carrier so it can be used with a Cuban SIM card. Technicians also offer recurring services, such as periodically updating devices, which allows them to develop a sustainable business model and loyal customer base.</p>



<p>These Apple repair shops thrived after 2011, when an economic reform authorized <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/latinoamerica-cuba-reforma-trabajo-idLTASIE7060I020110107">75,000 licenses</a> for entrepreneurs to establish small businesses, ranging from rental homes to electronic repair. However, while the licenses granted legality to the technicians’ economic activity, limitations persist regarding their capacity to import equipment and replacement parts from abroad.</p>



<p>In April, <a href="https://www.facebook.com/michel.alvarezmorales/posts/10228678629012525?ref=embed_post">Michel Álvarez Morales expressed his frustration on Facebook</a> after a Hanchen LCD screen separator machine — commonly used to repair smartphones — was confiscated by Cuban Customs because the technician did not have an import permit. Technicians responded to the post, complaining<strong> </strong>about the difficulties they face in procuring simple tools like screwdrivers, microscopes, or welding machines.&nbsp;</p>



<p>During the pandemic, when there was a limited number of flights to Cuba, 23-year-old Chris Gámez Ruiz needed to fix his MacBook Air’s keyboard. The Havana resident had purchased the laptop via Facebook for about 12,000 Cuban pesos (around $100 at the time). While he wasn’t drawn to the laptop’s design, he bought it as a “status symbol,” he told <em>Rest of World</em>, despite the fact that its keyboard was already broken when he bought it.</p>



<p>Gámez Ruiz hired one of Cuba’s most sought-after MacBook technicians: Raiko Israel Pupo Hondal, the founder of Railab, an Apple repair shop in the Reparto Kohly neighborhood of Havana. A year after graduating with a degree in telecommunications, Pupo Hondal began working at a laptop repair shop, where he discovered the unique satisfaction of tackling challenging Mac-related issues that left other technicians stumped.&nbsp;</p>



<p>Pupo Hondal first tried to order a replacement keyboard from abroad, but was unsuccessful. He then decided to replace it with another old keyboard that “only” had four broken keys. Gámez Ruiz was happy enough with the repair and paid Pupo Hondal with a broken iMac. After all its useful pieces were extracted, the iMac was displayed as a decorative piece in Railab, alongside a collection of other old and gutted Mac computers that have been recycled over a span of six years.&nbsp;</p>



<p>“We Cubans are used to doing more with less,” Pupo Hondal told <em>Rest of World.</em> “Each Mac we successfully fix is a Mac we rescue from being discarded as waste — and even those we can’t fix, find new purpose in saving others. There’s a magic in fixing what others would have otherwise discarded.”</p>
				<!-- Article End -->
							</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Can’t send email more than 500 miles (2002) (1028 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://web.mit.edu/jemorris/humor/500-miles</link>
            <guid>37576633</guid>
            <pubDate>Tue, 19 Sep 2023 21:05:20 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://web.mit.edu/jemorris/humor/500-miles">https://web.mit.edu/jemorris/humor/500-miles</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=37576633">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>