<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2024 01:00:05 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[WhatsApp Messaging Interoperability (125 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://developers.facebook.com/m/messaging-interoperability/</link>
            <guid>39633936</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 20:02:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/m/messaging-interoperability/">https://developers.facebook.com/m/messaging-interoperability/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39633936">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-click-area="Main" id="rebrandBodyID"><div><p>Enable users on your app in Europe to exchange messages with users on WhatsApp in Europe, in accordance with the Digital Markets Act (DMA).</p></div><div><h3><span>Learn about interoperating with WhatsApp </span></h3><p>To be considered eligible to interoperate with WhatsApp, you must be able to comply with the terms of the Reference Offer, which reflect requirements of the DMA. This includes being an app that provides messaging services to end users in Europe. It also includes being able to meet the technical requirements outlined in the Developer Documentation Overview. </p></div><div><h3><span>Steps to interoperate with WhatsApp </span></h3><div><ol><li><b>Review:</b> Review the Reference Offer, Developer Documentation Overview, and Application Guidelines above.</li><li><b>Apply:</b> If you believe you qualify, complete the form that’s linked in the Application Guidelines. </li><li><b>Review:</b> If you meet eligibility requirements, we will send you our detailed Developer Documentation under NDA for review of the detailed technical requirements for interoperating. </li><li><b>Sign:</b> If you can fulfill the relevant terms and technical requirements set out in the Reference Offer and want to request interoperability with WhatsApp, sign the WhatsApp Interoperability Agreement that we will provide to you.</li><li><b>Build:</b> Start building interoperability. </li><li><b>Enable:</b> Complete the milestones outlined in the detailed Developer Documentation to enable interoperability. </li><li><b>Launch:</b> Work with WhatsApp on a joint plan to launch interoperability.</li></ol></div></div><div><div><p><h4><span>Ready to take the next step to interoperate with WhatsApp? </span></h4></p></div><div><p>Complete the form that’s linked in the Application Guidelines. We will then review and reply back with next steps. </p><p><a href="#" data-ms="{&quot;creative&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;creative_detail&quot;:&quot;MessagingInterop_GetStarted_readyTo_PDF_GetStartedWithWhatsApp_fileGroupLink&amp;device_type=desktop&quot;,&quot;create_type&quot;:&quot;MessagingInterop_GetStarted_readyTo_PDF_GetStartedWithWhatsApp_fileGroupLink&quot;,&quot;create_type_detail&quot;:&quot;&quot;}" role="button"></a><a href="https://scontent.fzrh3-1.fna.fbcdn.net/v/t39.8562-6/430216078_923566252559088_8876735975651197200_n.pdf?_nc_cat=108&amp;ccb=1-7&amp;_nc_sid=b8d81d&amp;_nc_ohc=jbf_1hYpeYUAX916hCw&amp;_nc_ht=scontent.fzrh3-1.fna&amp;oh=00_AfBOQa2JHCafVvt6LL9BtI20iRBZOhfoax4fy7BACqbrng&amp;oe=65EEFC11" target="_blank">Get started with WhatsApp</a></p></div></div><div><p>For clarity, developers’ Interoperability Agreements with WhatsApp (as may be updated from time to time), govern developers’ use and access to the interoperable messaging services of WhatsApp (as applicable), and supersede any other developer terms(i.e., the <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/terms/" data-ms="{&quot;creative&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;creative_detail&quot;:&quot;MessagingInterop_Disclaimer_PlatformTerms_Link&amp;device_type=desktop&quot;,&quot;create_type&quot;:&quot;MessagingInterop_Disclaimer_PlatformTerms_Link&quot;,&quot;create_type_detail&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Platform Terms</a> and the <a href="https://developers.facebook.com/devpolicy/" data-ms="{&quot;creative&quot;:&quot;link&quot;,&quot;creative_detail&quot;:&quot;MessagingInterop_Disclaimer_DeveloperPolicies_Link&amp;device_type=desktop&quot;,&quot;create_type&quot;:&quot;MessagingInterop_Disclaimer_DeveloperPolicies_Link&quot;,&quot;create_type_detail&quot;:&quot;&quot;}">Developer Policies</a>) found elsewhere on this website. </p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Pile is a 825 GiB diverse, open-source language modelling data set (312 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://pile.eleuther.ai/</link>
            <guid>39631516</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 17:14:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://pile.eleuther.ai/">https://pile.eleuther.ai/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39631516">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
        <div>
          <div>
            <h2>What is the Pile?</h2>
            <p>
              The Pile is a <span>825 GiB</span> diverse, open
              source language modelling data set that consists of 22 smaller,
              high-quality datasets combined together.
            </p>
            
          </div>
          <div>
            <h2>Download</h2>
            <p>The Pile is hosted by <a href="https://the-eye.eu/">the Eye</a>.</p>
            
            <p>
              Have a model that uses or evaluates on the Pile?
              <a href="mailto:contact@eleuther.ai">Let us know</a>!
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <h2>Why is the Pile a good training set?</h2>
            <p>
              Recent work has shown that especially for large models, diversity
              in data sources improves general cross-domain knowledge of the
              model, as well as downstream generalization capability. In our
              evaluations, not only do models trained on the Pile show moderate
              improvements in traditional language modeling benchmarks, they
              also show significant improvements on Pile BPB.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <h2>Why is the Pile a good benchmark?</h2>
            <p>
              To score well on Pile BPB (bits per byte), a model must be able to
              understand many disparate domains including books, github
              repositories, webpages, chat logs, and medical, physics, math,
              computer science, and philosophy papers. Pile BPB is a measure of
              world knowledge and reasoning ability in these domains, making it
              a robust benchmark of general, cross-domain text modeling ability
              for large language models.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div>
            <h2>Citing</h2>
            <p>
                If you use the Pile or any of the components, please cite us!
            </p>
            <pre>@article{pile,
  title={The {P}ile: An 800GB Dataset of Diverse Text for Language Modeling},
  author={Gao, Leo and Biderman, Stella and Black, Sid and Golding, Laurence and Hoppe, Travis and Foster, Charles and Phang, Jason and He, Horace and Thite, Anish and Nabeshima, Noa and Presser, Shawn and Leahy, Connor},
  journal={arXiv preprint arXiv:2101.00027},
  year={2020}
}
                </pre>
            
          </div>
        </div>
        <!-- Right Column -->
        <div>
            <h2>Leaderboard</h2>
            <p>
              * indicates potential test-set overlap. Zero-shot indicates that
              not all of the components of the Pile were present in the training
              data.
            </p>
            <table>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th>Rank</th>
                  <th>Model</th>
                  <th>Test BPB</th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>1.</p>
                    <p><span>Jan 1.2021</span></p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>GPT-3 (Zero-Shot)*</p>
                    <p>OpenAI</p>
                  </td>
                  <td><p>0.7177</p></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td>
                    <p>2.</p>
                    <p><span>Jan 1.2021</span></p>
                  </td>
                  <td>
                    <p>GPT-2 (Zero-Shot)*</p>
                    <p>OpenAI</p>
                  </td>
                  <td><p>1.2253</p></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
            
          </div>
      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HP Tries Desperately to Make 'Printer as a Subscription' a Thing (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.techdirt.com/2024/03/07/hp-tries-desperately-to-make-printer-as-a-subscription-a-thing/</link>
            <guid>39631402</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 17:06:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2024/03/07/hp-tries-desperately-to-make-printer-as-a-subscription-a-thing/">https://www.techdirt.com/2024/03/07/hp-tries-desperately-to-make-printer-as-a-subscription-a-thing/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39631402">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="storywrap-433747">


<h3>from the <i>behold-our-self-immolation</i> dept</h3>

<p>When last we checked in with Hewlett Packard (HP), the company&nbsp;<a href="https://www.techdirt.com/2024/01/11/hp-hit-with-yet-another-lawsuit-over-bricking-printers-that-use-third-party-ink-cartridges/">had just been sued</a>&nbsp;(for the second time) for crippling customer printers if owners attempt to use cheaper, third-party printer cartridges. It was just the latest in a long saga where printer manufacturers use DRM or dodgy software updates to wage all out war on consumer choice.</p>
<p>There hasn’t been a whole lot of introspection going on at the company since. Shortly after the lawsuit HP CEO Enrique Lores&nbsp;<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QPRMyQSZGuY">went on CNBC</a>&nbsp;to double down on the company’s position. First by making up claims that HP <strong>has</strong> to be obnoxious about cartridges to protect consumer security (false), then by basically stating that any consumer who intelligently shops for cartridges is a “bad investment.” </p>
<p>This week HP unveiled its latest plan on this track: printing as a service. The company’s new “<a href="https://www.hp.com/us-en/all-in-plan/printers.html">All-In Plan</a>” requires that you pay anywhere from $7 a month to $36 a month to rent a printer with a set printable page limit. During your rental, HP sends you, of course, their ink cartridges. </p>
<p>As Ars Technica notes, the printer must remain connected to the internet for monitoring. And the company’s <a href="https://www.hp.com/us-en/privacy/privacy.html?jumpid=in_R11928_%2Fus%2Fen%2Fcorp%2Fprivacy-central%2Fprivacy-statements&amp;utm_medium=af&amp;utm_source=aw&amp;utm_campaign=Skimlinks&amp;utm_content=78888_Skimlinks_">privacy policy</a> effectively gives HP full control over, well, everything: </p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>“Subject to the terms of this Agreement, You hereby grant to HP a non-exclusive, worldwide, royalty-free right to use, copy, store, transmit, modify, create derivative works of and display Your non-personal data for its business purposes..”</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>And of course the subscription comes with long term contracts and early termination fees should you not subscribe for the full two-year term. All told, the tone-deafness is fairly stunning. </p>
<p>Paying for the same several-hundred dollar printer for all eternity is precisely the sort of concept Lores has been pushing for a while. The problem is it’s not clear that anybody <em>actually wants this</em>. It’s also not really clear that paying up to $36 for a printer you never really own makes much value sense. Printers inherently aren’t that expensive. And ink isn’t either, if companies aren’t being restrictive tyrants. </p>
<p>For HP, none of that matters. Lores isn’t thinking about building quality products or building solid relationships. He’s thinking exclusively of finding creative ways to goose profits and deliver Wall Street improved quarterly returns <strong>at any cost</strong>. You can’t do that by simply providing users a quality, affordable product people like; you inevitably have to start cutting corners and nickel-and-diming users. </p>
<p>Once they’ve established renting a printer as a norm, they’ll just steadily jack the rental price skyward as they make the underlying value proposition steadily worse. Ultimately the business becomes less and less about making popular quality products, and more and more about making unnecessarily convoluted subscriptions with creative restrictions and ever-skyrocketing monthly prices. </p>
<p>
Filed Under: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/consumers/" rel="tag">consumers</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/drm/" rel="tag">drm</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/enrique-lores/" rel="tag">Enrique Lores</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/ink-cartridges/" rel="tag">ink cartridges</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/printers/" rel="tag">printers</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/rentals/" rel="tag">rentals</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/subscription/" rel="tag">subscription</a>, <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/tag/tone-deaf-2/" rel="tag">tone-deaf</a>
<br>
Companies: <a href="https://www.techdirt.com/company/hp/" rel="category tag">hp</a>
</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Sweden Is a NATO Member (454 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.government.se/press-releases/2024/03/sweden-is-a-nato-member/</link>
            <guid>39631139</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 16:43:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.government.se/press-releases/2024/03/sweden-is-a-nato-member/">https://www.government.se/press-releases/2024/03/sweden-is-a-nato-member/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39631139">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<section>
<div><p>Press release from <a href="https://www.government.se/tx/2069">Prime Minister's Office</a>, <a href="https://www.government.se/tx/2077">Ministry for Foreign Affairs</a></p></div>

<p>
<span>Published <time datetime="07 March 2024">07 March 2024</time></span>
</p>
</section>
<p>
Just before 17.30 CET, Sweden’s instrument of accession was deposited with the United States Government, as depositary of the North Atlantic Treaty. Therefore, Sweden is now a member of NATO.</p>
<p>NATO is an intergovernmental organisation with both a political and a military dimension. As a member, Sweden becomes part of NATO’s collective defence. Sweden is NATO’s 32nd member country.</p>
<div>
<h2>Press contact</h2>
<div><p><address>
<span>Hanna Strömberg</span><br>
<span>Press Secretary to Prime Minister Ulf Kristersson</span>
<br>
<span>
<span>Phone (switchboard)</span>
<span>
<a href="tel:+46 8 405 10 00">+46 8 405 10 00</a>
</span>
</span>
<br>
<span>
<span>Mobile</span>
<span>
<a href="tel:">+46 76 128 61 69</a>
</span>
</span>
<br>
<a href="https://www.government.se/contacts/" data-code="c2thbmxzaGFubmFAc3Ryb21iZXJnaW5ncmVnaW5ncmVnZXJpbmdza2Fuc2xpZXRAc2V5">email to Hanna Strömberg</a>
</address>
</p><p><address>
<span>Anna Erhardt</span><br>
<span>Press Secretary to Minister for Foreign Affairs Tobias Billström</span>
<br>
<span>
<span>Phone (switchboard)</span>
<span>
<a href="tel:+46 8 405 10 00">+46 8 405 10 00</a>
</span>
</span>
<br>
<span>
<span>Mobile</span>
<span>
<a href="tel:">+46 76 130 85 34</a>
</span>
</span>
<br>
<a href="https://www.government.se/contacts/" data-code="c2thbmxzYW5uYUBlcmhhcmR0aW5ncmVnaW5nZ292QHNlcg==">email to Anna Erhardt</a>
</address>
</p></div>
</div>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You cannot simply publicly access private secure links, can you? (279 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/security-tools/soar/urlscan/hybrid-analysis/data-leaks/urlscan.io/cloudflare-radar%22/2024/03/07/url-database-leaks-private-urls.html</link>
            <guid>39630985</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 16:29:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/security-tools/soar/urlscan/hybrid-analysis/data-leaks/urlscan.io/cloudflare-radar%22/2024/03/07/url-database-leaks-private-urls.html">https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/security-tools/soar/urlscan/hybrid-analysis/data-leaks/urlscan.io/cloudflare-radar%22/2024/03/07/url-database-leaks-private-urls.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39630985">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
        <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p><em>turns out, you can even search for them with powerful search engines!</em></p>

<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>

<p>Popular malware/url analysis tools like <a href="https://urlscan.io/">urlscan.io</a>, <a href="https://www.hybrid-analysis.com/">Hybrid Analysis</a> and <a href="https://radar.cloudflare.com/scan">Cloudflare radar url scanner</a> store a large number of links for intelligence gathering and sharing. It is however not so widely known that these services also store a large amount of <strong>private</strong> and <strong>sensitive</strong> links, thanks to:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Sensitive links mistakenly submitted by users for scanning unaware that these are public information</li>
  <li>Misconfigured scanners and extensions submitting private links scanned from emails as public data</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="so-what-are-all-these-links-you-refer-to">So what are all these links you refer to?</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Files shared using cloud storage tools (e.g. <code>Dropbox</code>, <code>iCLoud</code>, <code>Sync</code>, <code>Egnyte</code>, <code>Ionos Hidrive</code>, <code>AWS S3</code>)</li>
  <li>Cloud connected <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network-attached_storage">NAS</a> tools (e.g. <code>Western Digital Mycloud</code>)</li>
  <li>Corporate communication (e.g. <code>Slido</code>, <code>Zoom</code>, <code>Onedrive</code>, <code>Airtable</code>)</li>
  <li>Password reset links, Oauth sign-in links</li>
</ul>

<p>All these have one thing in common, the way they are so widely used allows anyone to access their services using a single private link containing random identifiers to ensure security of the links. Sometimes, they can be protected further using a password or passphrase, in those cases just having access to the links does not result in data exposure.</p>

<p>Some screenshots I grabbed from urlscan.io before they were filtered out after I reached out to them (they were quick to respond):</p>

<p><img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/mycloud.png" alt="Western digital mycloud">
<img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/egnyte.png" alt="Egnyte">
<img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/s3.png" alt="AWS S3"></p>

<p>A lot of these submissions came from <a href="https://urlscan.io/search/#task.tags:%22falconsandbox%22">falconsandbox</a> as shown in tags by urlscan.io, so I broadened my analysis to include Hybrid Analysis (<a href="https://www.crunchbase.com/organization/payload-security">owned by Crowdstrike</a>) as well.</p>

<p><img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/ha_icloud.png" alt="iCloud"></p>

<p><img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/ha_google_photos.png" alt="Google Photos"></p>

<p><img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/google_drive.png" alt="Google Drive"></p>

<p>Another new tool with potential to become more widely used and already containing some private links as public data is <a href="https://radar.cloudflare.com/">Cloudflare Radar</a>.</p>

<p><img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/cloudflare.png" alt="Cloudflare google photos">
<img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/cf1.png" alt="Cloudflare link">
<img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/cf2.png" alt="Cloudflare invoices"></p>

<p>Some broad categories of sensitive content I came across:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Private files including tax documents, invoices, photos, business communications</li>
  <li>Shared secrets using <a href="https://onetimesecret.com/">onetimesecret</a></li>
  <li>Smart home device recordings</li>
  <li>Meeting recordings stored in the cloud</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/data.png" alt="Leaks"></p>

<h2 id="who-is-responsible">Who is responsible?</h2>

<p>Now that is a tough one to answer. From <a href="https://hybrid-analysis.com/terms">terms and conditions of use</a> from Hybrid Analysis:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Hybrid Analysis analyses, publishes, and shares Submitted Content from users as part of providing a cybersecurity community resource and is not responsible for the content or information which may incidentally appear in such submissions or be included in automatically-generated reports.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From urlscan.io:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You specifically acknowledge that urlscan shall not be liable for any user content or conduct.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>You are responsible for all content posted and activity that occurs under your account.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As such, there does not seem to be any mechanism in place to review the existing content and flag/remove potentially sensitive links. Implementing it in an automated fashion might also not be trivial.</p>

<p>As a security researcher, it is also hard to figure out the source of these links. I came across this <a href="https://positive.security/blog/urlscan-data-leaks">wonderful analysis by Positive Security</a> who focused on urlscan.io and used canary tokens to detect potential automated sources (security tools scanning emails for potentially malicious oinks), and also reached out via email to users. I was able to validate this behavior using canary links as well.</p>

<h2 id="we-are-threat-hunters-all-your-links-are-belong-to-us">We are Threat hunters! All your links are belong to us!</h2>

<p><a href="https://urlscan.io/pricing/urlscanpro/">urlscan Pro</a> allows access for paid users/companies to a broader category of scans, including not just <code>Public</code> but also <code>Unlisted</code> scans.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Unlisted means that the scan will not be visible on the public page or search results, but will be visible to customers of the urlscan Pro platform. We only admit customers to urlscan Pro which are either vetted security researchers or reputable corporations. <a href="https://urlscan.io/blog/2022/07/27/scan-visibility-best-practices/">Source</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="https://github.com/TheHive-Project/Cortex/blob/master/README.md">Cortex-Analyzers</a> from <a href="https://thehive-project.org/">TheHive</a> is an example I would like to outline.</p>

<p>It explicitly uses <code>public</code>:<code>on</code> configuration for scans in urlscan.io analyzer, making the links appear as <code>unlisted</code> even if an account’s visibility in urlscan is set to Private. These can then easily be accessed by urlscan pro users and platforms based on that information.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/TheHive-Project/Cortex-Analyzers/blob/master/analyzers/Urlscan.io/urlscan.py#L28">https://github.com/TheHive-Project/Cortex-Analyzers/blob/master/analyzers/Urlscan.io/urlscan.py#L28</a></li>
</ul>

<p>I would expect much more sensitive information to be prone to leaks in this manner, although the data is not public but only visible to urlscan pro users. I hope they vet the users carefully.</p>

<p>Counts for scans in each category from <code>urlscan.io</code> for last 24 hours:</p>

<ul>
  <li>398563 <code>Public</code></li>
  <li>328147 <code>Unlisred</code></li>
  <li>955432 <code>Private</code></li>
</ul>

<p>I used canary tokens to establish:</p>

<ul>
  <li>A link submitted to <code>urlscan.io</code> as <code>unlisted</code>, was accessed 12 times within 1 hour of submission</li>
  <li>A link submitted to <code>hybrid-analysis.com</code> via the <code>API</code> (not through the browser with explicit warning of them being <code>public</code> content), was accessed 10 times within 1 hour of submission</li>
  <li>Some IP addresses accessed both unique links submitted to these services simulataneously and use source IP anonymization services.</li>
</ul>

<p><a href="https://vin01.github.io/piptagole/assets/threat_hunter_ips.txt">a list of these IP addresses is here</a></p>

<h2 id="how-to-get-sensitive-links-removed">How to get sensitive links removed?</h2>

<p>Urlscan and Hybrid Analysis allow flagging the links to get them removed.</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://urlscan.io/docs/faq/">https://urlscan.io/docs/faq/</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.hybrid-analysis.com/knowledge-base/removing-uploaded-sensitive-files">https://www.hybrid-analysis.com/knowledge-base/removing-uploaded-sensitive-files</a></li>
</ul>

<p>For Hybrid Analysis, it is a bit more complex. Quoting from their knowledge base link above:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>All files submitted to the public Sandbox at https://www.hybrid-analysis.com/ will be searchable and available to the world.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Even if the checkbox “Do not share my sample with the community” is checked, the screenshots and actual report will still be made available. The “do not share” portion only applies to the actual input sample.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>This does leave me with mixed feelings. I am quite sure that this problem is here to stay. Perhaps a default of “keep the scans private” would work best, but would defeat the purpose of most of threat intelligence and analysis sharing practices in security community. Be mindful of scan visibility while using these services.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, bounty hunters are using this already to report leaked data to companies directly ;) Hell, one of my submissions to a notable payment processing company even turned out to be a “Duplicate”, so I am definitely not the first one to notice this in the wild.</p>

<h2 id="disclaimer">Disclaimer</h2>

<p>If you choose to access some of these links/files from url databases, please be wary of actual malicious files and links. Some of these are just phishing attempts and may contain actual malware. Please use a sandbox environment.</p>

<h2 id="helpful-links">Helpful links</h2>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://positive.security/blog/urlscan-data-leaks">urlscan.io’s SOAR spot: Chatty security tools leaking private data (2022)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://urlscan.io/docs/search/">urlscan.io Search API Reference</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://www.hybrid-analysis.com/docs/api/v2">Falcon Sandbox Public API</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://radar.cloudflare.com/scan">Cloudflare Radar URL Scanner</a></li>
</ul>

  </div>
</article>

      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[How the Great Green Wall Is Holding Back the Sahara Desert (132 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://kottke.org/24/03/how-the-great-green-wall-is-holding-back-the-sahara-desert</link>
            <guid>39630926</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 16:23:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://kottke.org/24/03/how-the-great-green-wall-is-holding-back-the-sahara-desert">https://kottke.org/24/03/how-the-great-green-wall-is-holding-back-the-sahara-desert</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39630926">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>









<div id="extras-container">




<p>This site is made possible by <a href="https://kottke.org/members">member support</a>. ❤️</p>

<p>Big thanks to <a href="https://www.arcustech.com/">Arcustech</a> for hosting the site and offering amazing tech support.</p>

<p>When you buy through links on kottke.org, I may earn an affiliate commission. Thanks for supporting the site!</p>

<p><strong>kottke.org.</strong> home of fine hypertext products since 1998.</p>

<p><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/burgers" title="burgers">🍔</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/death" title="death">💀</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/photography" title="photography">📸</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/crying%20at%20work" title="crying at work">😭</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/black%20holes" title="black holes">🕳️</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/Old%20Custer" title="Old Custer">🤠</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/film%20school" title="film school">🎬</a>&nbsp; <a href="https://kottke.org/tag/potatoes" title="potatoes">🥔</a></p></div>

<div id="content-container">
<p>posted <time datetime="2024-03-07T15:58:11Z">Mar  7 @ 10:58 AM</time> by <a href="http://www.kottke.org/">Jason Kottke</a><span>  ·  <span>gift link</span></span>



</p>




<p><iframe loading="lazy" width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/WCli0gyNwL0" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></p>

<p><a href="https://thegreatgreenwall.org/">THe Great Green Wall</a> being built in Africa to halt the southern progress of the Sahara Desert is a favorite public works project of mine — it’s massive, ambitious, long-term, important, and if it works, the effect will repay the cost <a href="https://www.wfp.org/resilience-building">many times over</a>. This video takes a quick look at some of the work being done on the wall in Senegal.</p>

<p>See also <a href="https://kottke.org/21/09/the-circular-drought-resistant-gardens-of-senegal">The Circular, Drought-Resistant Gardens of Senegal</a>.</p>

<ul><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/Africa">Africa</a></li><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/Sahara%20Desert">Sahara Desert</a></li><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/Senegal">Senegal</a></li><li><a href="https://kottke.org/tag/video">video</a></li></ul>






</div>




</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Berkeley Software Distribution (137 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.abortretry.fail/p/the-berkley-software-distribution</link>
            <guid>39630457</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 15:46:22 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.abortretry.fail/p/the-berkley-software-distribution">https://www.abortretry.fail/p/the-berkley-software-distribution</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39630457">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><p>The first public presentation of UNIX was made at the Symposium on Operating Systems Principles at the IBM Research Center in Yorktown Heights in October of 1973. Dennis Ritchie is quoted as saying it was beautiful day, and Ken Thompson layered his own memories with a thick coating of modesty:</p><blockquote><p><em>The audience was several hundred. I was pretty nervous. The response was the normal, polite applause. I don't recall any questions.</em></p></blockquote><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg" width="1200" height="675" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/b9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:675,&quot;width&quot;:1200,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;https://d1bqvdqmynqyrb.cloudfront.net/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fresearch-website-prod-cms-uploads.s3.us.cloud-object-storage.appdomain.cloud%2FYKT_Andydrone_0055_b02e15eac1.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="https://d1bqvdqmynqyrb.cloudfront.net/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fresearch-website-prod-cms-uploads.s3.us.cloud-object-storage.appdomain.cloud%2FYKT_Andydrone_0055_b02e15eac1.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75" title="https://d1bqvdqmynqyrb.cloudfront.net/_next/image?url=https%3A%2F%2Fresearch-website-prod-cms-uploads.s3.us.cloud-object-storage.appdomain.cloud%2FYKT_Andydrone_0055_b02e15eac1.jpg&amp;w=1200&amp;q=75" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fb9ace03e-5fa3-43df-875b-6989e389b156_1200x675.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption>The IBM Research Center in Yorktown Heights, image from IBM</figcaption></figure></div><p>In contrast to Thompson stating that he didn’t recall any questions… the two were immediately asked for copies of the operating system, and this wasn’t a simple matter for AT&amp;T. The American Telephone and Telegraph company had been established as a legal, nation-wide monopoly in the USA via the Kingsbury Commitment in late 1913. This position was further cemented during World War I when the United States’ federal government nationalized the phone system. Following the end of the war, the phone system went back into the hands of AT&amp;T and the company achieved some rather remarkable regulatory capture with the Willis Graham Act of 1921 and the Communications Act of 1934. This complicated legal history presented a very serious question to AT&amp;T’s legal department when people began asking for UNIX: were computer operating systems part of the common carrier services of the phone company and therefore required to be distributed? If they were not, then the company needn’t distribute UNIX at all, but if they were indeed, then it was only a matter of time before the FCC would force AT&amp;T to distribute UNIX. In the end, the decision was made to distribute UNIX to universities and research centers at the cost of the media plus shipping. Somehow, quite magically, this resulted in a nice round number of $150.00 (or around $927 in 2024) for Katholieke Universiteit in Nijmegen, The Netherlands in December of 1974. There are some rather important points within the license that Katholieke was granted. Licensees were granted source code for the operating system as computer systems of the day weren’t standardized in any meaningful way. The license then granted free use and modification within the university, but disallowed any spread outside. Specifically, the license mentioned that employees and students had access.</p><div data-component-name="FileToDOM"><div><p><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack.com%2Fimg%2Fattachment_icon.svg"></p><div><p>UNIX license from Western Electric to Katholieke</p><p>438KB ∙ PDF file</p></div><p><a href="https://www.abortretry.fail/api/v1/file/ea99ff77-8f06-4c00-ae95-2a1f60410a44.pdf" rel=""><span>Download</span></a></p></div><p>UNIX license from Western Electric to Katholieke</p><p><a href="https://www.abortretry.fail/api/v1/file/ea99ff77-8f06-4c00-ae95-2a1f60410a44.pdf" rel=""><span>Download</span></a></p></div><p><span> At this point in the computer industry, user groups were somewhat common. IBM had </span><a href="https://www.abortretry.fail/p/the-history-of-gm-naa-io-and-share" rel="">SHARE</a><span>, and that had inspired similar groups around DEC, Burroughs, Rand, and so on. It was therefore somewhat natural that a group would form around UNIX. Thus, Mel Ferentz and Lou Katz organized a meeting of UNIX users in New York on the 15th of May in 1974. Around twenty people were in attendance, and by this time there were just over thirty UNIX installations outside of AT&amp;T and its subsidiaries. This user group grew to become USENIX over time. Following the user group’s formation, a mailing list started. From the first list on the 30th of July in 1975, we have the following organizations listed as installation/user sites: AT&amp;T, Brooklyn College, Carleton College, Case Western Reserve University, The Children's Museum, City University of New York, Columbia University, Duke Medical Center, East Brunswick High School, Harvard University, Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Heriot-Watt University, Johns Hopkins University, Knox College, Naval Postgraduate School, Oregon Museum of Science, Polytechnic University of NY, Princeton University, Rand Corporation, St. Olaf College, Stanford University, The Spence School, University Catholique de Louvain, University of Alberta, University of California (Berkeley), University of Manitoba, University of North Carolina, University of Saskatchewan, University of Texas (Dallas), University of Toronto, University of Utah, University of Waterloo, and the University of Wisconsin. As we know from the license granted to Katholieke, there were more UNIX user sites than this, but they weren’t members of the user group (or at least not at first).</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg" width="720" height="576.4417177914111" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:522,&quot;width&quot;:652,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:720,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F3926f41f-c121-450b-8e10-e46ccc1c5448_652x522.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Dennis Ritchie (standing), Ken Thompson at the teletype, PDP-11 1972</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>In this early time period, UNIX only ran on the PDP-11, but that changed in 1976. The first port was at Princeton where UNIX was ported to the IBM 360 in late 1976. From the history I can find, this wasn’t a fully functional port until later in the following year. The second port was to the Interdata 7/32 at Wollongong University by Richard Miller on the 4th of February in 1977. This was an interesting one as the UNIX kernel was running on top of the Interdata operating system at first. The Wollongong port became a stand-alone and fully functional port on the 28th of April in 1977. The next target was the Interdata 8/32 in 1977 which was undertaken by Ritchie and Steve Johnson (author of yacc, lint, pcc). But, porting efforts took off only after John Lions at the University of New South Whales wrote a commentary on the UNIX sources and distributed them as a book, </span><em>Code and Commentary</em><span>, for teaching students about operating systems. Western Electric tried to stop dissemination, but this was apparently impossible. Likewise, modifications of UNIX began circulating following the release of Lions’ book, and a culture we would recognize today as “</span><em>open source</em><span>” began to develop helped in no small part by AT&amp;T’s policies regarding UNIX that essentially stated UNIX would have no advertising, no support, no bug fixes, and payment in advance. To color the time period more thoroughly, Bob Kahn and Vint Cerf published the first description of TCP/IP in 1974 and by January of 1976 there were sixty three hosts on ARPAnet, and UNIX while being used globally would run only on hardware that cost over $9000 (around $48000 in 2024).</span></p><p>Professor Robert (Bob) Fabry was at the Symposium on Operating Systems Principles where UNIX had first been announced and he was very excited. Returning to UC Berkeley where he was then employed, he assembled a group to purchase a PDP-11/45. As this was a large purchase, he coordinated the departments of computer science, math, and statistics. With the machine purchased, Fabry then ordered a tape of UNIX from Thompson. The actual installation of UNIX was first undertaken by Keith Standiford in January of 1974. In 1973/1974, it was somewhat routine for Thompson himself to be involved in nearly every UNIX installation for a licensee. The folks at Berkeley seemed to be interested in doing everything themselves, but things didn’t go well. Eventually, Standiford reached out to Thompson, and Thompson would connect to the University’s 11/45 over a three hundred baud acoustic coupler to remotely debug crash dumps from New Jersey. I personally like to imagine that it was a Novation CAT 300, but I haven’t been able to find a model number of the modem, and I haven’t found any reference to what system Thompson was actually using. Plus, the Novation CAT 300 wouldn’t be released for several years.</p><p>Following the purchase of the PDP-11/45, the departments involved began having issues with scheduling time on the machine. Berkeley bought several more computers. One of these was a PDP-11/70, and its arrival coincided with the arrival of Thompson as a visiting professor. Thompson, Bob Kridle, and Jeff Schriebman then setup V7 UNIX on the 11/70. Shortly after the installation was completed, two graduate students, Chuck Haley and William Nelson (Bill) Joy, arrived on campus. They were intrigued by the computer system, and they began hacking on Thompson’s Pascal compiler. Within a few weeks (from what I have been able to find), the teletypes attached to the 11/70 were replaced with ADM-3 screen terminals.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg" width="1456" height="1435" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1435,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;undefined&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="undefined" title="undefined" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F98f22ee6-2f34-4ffd-b8bd-b37fb059cbe5_1887x1860.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>ADM-3, image by Chris Jacobs, CC BY-SA 3.0</figcaption></figure></div><p>For Bill Joy, using ed or em on a screen terminal wasn’t really sufficient. He took a detour from hacking on Pascal, and he created the ex editor. Together with Pascal, the V7 UNIX at Berkeley was notably better than other UNIX systems of the time. In early 1978, Bill Joy began offering the Berkely Software Distribution. The first copy we know to make it out of Berkeley was to Tom Ferrin at UCSF on the 9th of March in 1978. The license was signed on the 13th, the media was an 800 bpi tape, and on the tape was the “Unix Pascal system” and the “Ex text editor.” Credits were made to W.N. Joy, S.L. Graham, C.B. Haley, K. Thompson for Pascal, and to W.N. Joy for Ex.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg" width="1200" height="630" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:630,&quot;width&quot;:1200,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;Bill Joy, Silicon Valley Visionary, on the Future of Batteries ...&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="Bill Joy, Silicon Valley Visionary, on the Future of Batteries ..." title="Bill Joy, Silicon Valley Visionary, on the Future of Batteries ..." srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd5b8a872-0970-4832-8b53-86c19f7c8543_1200x630.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Bill Joy</figcaption></figure></div><p>BSD (now referred to as 1BSD) shipped around thirty copies in the first half of 1978. Somewhere around June, Pascal had been further improved, the C shell had been written, vi had been written (by Joy), and termcap had been written (by Joy). These new tools comprised the bulk of the Second Berkely Software Distribution or 2BSD. Joy was the man running the show, and he’d answer the phone, create the tapes, incorporate feedback, package, and mail the software. Seventy five copies of 2BSD were sent out.</p><p>The DEC VAX was first introduced in 1977. It was a 32 bit ISA with virtual memory. In the first half of 1978, Professor Richard Fateman at Berkeley was looking for a machine with a lot of memory for a project of his. The VAX-11/780 met his requirements and his budget, and he got some folks together to purchase it with a bit of help from the National Science Foundation. The VAX did have one disadvantage in the minds of those at UC Berkeley; the VAX ran VMS. Luckily, UNIX had already been ported to VAX as UNIX/32V (V7 UNIX variant) by John Reiser and Tom London at Bell Labs. This port, however, didn’t take advantage of the main VAX feature, virtual memory, which limited the available memory to 1MB.</p><p>This had to be fixed. For Fateman, virtual memory was a requirement, and UNIX was a requirement. He then contacted Professor Domenico Ferrari about getting virtual memory support in UNIX. One of the graduate students working with Ferrari, Özalp Babaoğlu, then set about this task. Along the way, Babaoğlu reached out to Joy for assistance. Joy helped integrate Babaoğlu’s memory system into 32V and helped him debug the resulting UNIX variant.</p><p>The new version of UNIX was good. Joy knew that the 32 bit VAX running UNIX would render the 16 bit PDP-11 obsolete, and he started porting 2BSD to 32V. Peter Kessler and Marshall Kirk McKusick worked on porting Pascal, while Joy handled ex, vi, C shell, and many other BSD utilities. The group had completed their work by the end of 1979, and Joy shipped 3BSD in December.</p><p><span>At this point, it’s important to delineate the family tree. 1BSD and 2BSD were improvements to UNIX version 6 while 3BSD was an improvement to 32V which was itself of a port and modification of UNIX version 7. During the creation of 3BSD, 2BSD had continued to see additions, fixes, and releases. One important distinction to be made is that the filename for the kernel in 3BSD became </span><em>vmunix</em><span> for virtual memory UNIX.</span></p><p>Computer hardware and software were highly varied in 1979 and most often nothing was compatible with anything else. For the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, this was an issue. They felt that the best they could hope for was unity at the operating system level for the growing network of networks, ARPAnet, and to this end they chose to standardize on UNIX due to its proven portability resulting from having been written in C. This same system would also be used by DARPA for work in the VLSI Project. In the autumn of 1979, Fabry reached out to DARPA offering 3BSD as the solution to their problem. Initially, this wasn’t well received, but the success of 3BSD that December changed opinions. Fabry secured an eighteen month contract with DARPA that began in April of 1980. This contract stipulated that Berkeley’s new Computer Systems Research Group would add the features to 3BSD needed by DARPA which was left rather open. In a technical report on the matter, the government doesn’t actually list anything too specific.</p><div data-component-name="FileToDOM"><div><p><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack.com%2Fimg%2Fattachment_icon.svg"></p><div><p>ARPA Standard UNIX Report</p><p>182KB ∙ PDF file</p></div><p><a href="https://www.abortretry.fail/api/v1/file/2c12ca84-b921-4d68-97a1-c046f60372c4.pdf" rel=""><span>Download</span></a></p></div><p>ARPA Standard UNIX Report</p><p><a href="https://www.abortretry.fail/api/v1/file/2c12ca84-b921-4d68-97a1-c046f60372c4.pdf" rel=""><span>Download</span></a></p></div><p>Fabry hired Laura Tong to be the project administrator, and Fabry then set about finding a tech lead. On an evening in early March, Joy rang Fabry at his home and expressed his desire to lead UNIX development, and Fabry agreed. Unlike earlier BSD releases (and on-going releases of 2BSD) a more robust system of distribution needed to be in place to handle a higher number of orders. Tong setup just such a system, and had Fabry coordinate with Bob Guffy at AT&amp;T as well as the university’s lawyers to find license terms that would satisfy all parties. The system that Joy and the software team would create was 4BSD which was available in October of 1980. This release brought job control to the C shell initially developed by Jim Kulp and integrated by Joy, delivermail (predecessor of sendmail), job control signals that worked more reliably (so if you sent SIGHUP the job would actually hangup), the curses library, the control-z suspend/resume functionality we know today, a filesystem that supported block sizes up to 1K, and greater hardware support. Notably, 4BSD supported the VAX-11/750. Like prior BSD releases, 4BSD included the Pascal compiler and that saw still more improvements, and it included the Franz Lisp system by Richard Fateman. 4BSD saw nine months as the system de jour, and about one hundred fifty copies were shipped. Licenses were per institution and not per machine, and estimates are that the distribution was running on about five hundred computers.</p><p>4BSD drew criticism from David Kashtan at Stanford Research Institute. He’d run some benchmarks on VMS and BSD and he claimed that VMS was the clear winner. This didn’t sit well with Joy. He went and made a series of performance improvements to BSD (mostly in vmunix), and a few weeks later released a paper rebutting Kashtan’s claims and showing that BSD was every bit the match to VMS. The improved kernel was coupled with Kevin Robert Elz’s auto-configuration and a system featuring them was released as 4.1BSD in June of 1981, and 4.1BSD for VAX became 2.8BSD for the PDP-11.. This version was current for two years and shipped four hundred copies. This version was good enough to win CSRG another two years of funding from DARPA, and the CS department at Berkeley also saw funding.</p><p>Interestingly, the reason for a point release was political. The CSRG had wanted to call this release 5BSD, but AT&amp;T blocked that name. AT&amp;T were releasing System V UNIX at the time, and they felt that a Berkeley release also named “five” would confuse customers. Point releases of 4.?BSD were then the agreed upon solution.</p><p>The new funding round came with some more concrete goals. Specifically, DARPA wanted a better filesystem with higher throughput, support for multi-gigabyte adress spaces, better IPC, and integrated networking. Marshall Kirk McKusick outlines how these decisions were made:</p><blockquote><p><em>To assist in defining the new system, Duane Adams, Berkeley's contract monitor at DARPA, formed a group known as the "steering committee" to help guide the design work and ensure that the research community's needs were addressed. This committee met twice a year between April 1981 and June 1983. It included Bob Fabry, Bill Joy, and Sam Leffler of the University of California at Berkeley; Alan Nemeth and Rob Gurwitz of Bolt, Beranek, and Newman; Dennis Ritchie of Bell Laboratories; Keith Lantz of Stanford University; Rick Rashid of Carnegie-Mellon University; Bert Halstead of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology; Dan Lynch of The Information Sciences Institute; Duane Adams and Bob Baker of DARPA; and Jerry Popek of the University of California at Los Angeles. Beginning in 1984, these meetings were supplanted by workshops that were expanded to include many more people.</em></p></blockquote><p><span>What was developed largely by McKusick, Joy, Sam Leffler, and Rob Gurwitz is astounding. These developments were iterated in releases 4.1a, 4.1b, and 4.1c but ultimately culminated in 4.2 which was released in August of 1983. The two largest innovations were the Berkeley Sockets API and the Berkeley Fast File System. The sockets interface allowed multiple different network protocols to be used at any time and exposed them as files. The Berkeley FFS allowed blocksizes from 128 bytes to larger than 4096 bytes if needed. Thus, with Berkeley’s FFS, a system operator could optimize either for disk use or for disk performance. 4.2BSD included a full TCP/IP stack and NFS support as well. Starting in the early iterated releases, small tools like </span><code>rcp</code><span>, </span><code>rsh</code><span>, </span><code>rlogin</code><span>, and </span><code>rwho</code><span> appeared to demonstrate capabilities. These were intended to be short lived, but those familiar with UNIX will certainly recognize them. 4.2BSD also brought disk quota facilities, a better install process, better documentation, and some new filesystem related system calls.</span></p><p>Events less visible to users also occurred between 1982 and 1983. Joy left the project in late spring of 1982 for Sun Microsystems, but still spent a little time that summer working on IPC and reorganizing the UNIX kernel sources to isolate machine dependent code. Once at Sun, contributions to BSD continued with Sun sending their modifications for running BSD on the Motorola 68000 back to Berkeley. Leffler then took over Joy’s previous duties. Joy’s work, however, would make BSD the single most easily ported operating system for about the next twenty years. Pauline Schwartz was hired to take over distribution duties in April of 1983. In June of 1983, Fabry went on sabbatical and Ferrari and Susan Graham took over running the CSRG. In 1984, Leffler went to work for Lucasfilm and Mike Karels took over as the UNIX dev lead. He’d previously worked on the 2.?BSD series for the PDP-11. Later that year McKusick joined CSRG full-time.</p><p>4.2BSD gained over a thousand site licenses in a year and a half, and most UNIX system vendors actually shipped 4.2BSD (or a system based on it) rather than AT&amp;T’s System V UNIX.  Likewise, many varieties of corporate UNIX would be based upon 4.1c or 4.2BSD such as SunOS and DEC Ultrix. An important point at this time is that BSD’s codebase was largely divergent from that of AT&amp;T while still mostly maintaining compatibility. Additionally, AT&amp;T had started shipping UNIX without source, and those customers who bought AT&amp;T’s commercial UNIX would often then separately obtain BSD sources if they wanted to modify some aspect of the system. For those using microcomputers, Microsoft’s (and SCO’s) XENIX was the standard.</p><p>Over on the PDP-11, a mixture of 4.1a and 4.1c formed 2.9BSD, but 4.2BSD never showed up.</p><p>In 1976, comic artist Phil Foglio drew the first versions of Beastie as T-shirt art for Mike O’Brien as payment for unlocking a safe.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg" width="688" height="833" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:833,&quot;width&quot;:688,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:&quot;\\begin{pic}{foglio.ps}{foglio}{Phil Foglio's 1976 artwork}\n\\end{pic}&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="\begin{pic}{foglio.ps}{foglio}{Phil Foglio's 1976 artwork}
\end{pic}" title="\begin{pic}{foglio.ps}{foglio}{Phil Foglio's 1976 artwork}
\end{pic}" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F1b00a913-e45d-44e7-b206-763ebac84cd4_688x833.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>T-shirt art of BSD by Phil Foglio</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Much of this is largely a pun on services being called daemons, and UNIX making heavy use of pipes, with </span><code>/dev/null</code><span> being a bit bucket. The daemon, Beastie, gained lasting association with BSD via a drawing by John Lasseter of Lucasfilm being used on the cover of the </span><em>Unix System Manger’s Manual</em><span> that was published in 1984 by USENIX for 4.2BSD.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png" width="726" height="1026.609375" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:905,&quot;width&quot;:640,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:726,&quot;bytes&quot;:920315,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F0cfe4090-7d76-4d07-acfd-0eadab7936cd_640x905.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Cover of the manual, image from jacobelder.com</figcaption></figure></div><p>While 4.2BSD was successful and mostly well received, it did get some complaints. The majority of the complaints were centered on performance. The team then spent two years improving performance, refining the networking stack, and they felt that they were ready to announce an impending release at USENIX in June of 1985. This didn’t go well. The fine folks of Bolt, Beranek, and Newman (part of the steering commitee) noted that 4.2BSD had shipped without the final version of the their networking code, and was instead using a heavily modified version of their initial prototype. After some bickering back and forth, DARPA provided both network stacks to Mike Muuss (author of ping) of the Ballistics Research Laboratory for testing. Berkeley’s code was better. 4.3BSD was released in June of 1986.</p><p>Keith Bostic joined CSRG in 1986 with the condition that he be allowed to continue and to complete a prior project. He was working to port 4.3BSD to the PDP-11. This meant that a 250K minimal system on VAX would be made to fit in the 64K address space of the PDP-11… no one thought this would work. No one. The man was clearly mad, but despite what madness may have lurked within him, Bostic made it work using a set of overlays and auxiliary processor states, and this formed the 2.10BSD release. He also began attending USENIX and he’d announce the progress of the removal of all AT&amp;T code from BSD which started in 1986 at thirty five percent AT&amp;T license free, and the announcement was met with widespread cheers and applause. This became important due to price increases from AT&amp;T. As of the 24th of February in 1984, the price for a commercial license of UNIX System V Release 2 with source for a single CPU stood at $43000 (about $126000 in 2024), and each additional CPU was a further $16000 (nearly $47000 in 2024). For educational institutions, the price was lower at $800 (or $2300 in 2024) and an additional $400 for each CPU.</p><p>Getting well into the 1980s, it became rather obvious to CSRG members that VAX wouldn’t go on forever. Computer Consoles Inc had opened a development center in Irvine and there they developed a proprietary minicomputer called the Power 6/32 code named Tahoe. This new platform was aimed to compete directly with VAX. In need of an operating system, CCI turned to CSRG. CCI provided the team several machines and the team set about porting 4.3BSD to the 6/32. This became 4.3BSD-Tahoe in June of 1988. Importantly, they were able to push forward Joy’s work of separating machine dependent code from the rest of the system, and 4.3BSD-Tahoe introduced an OSI network protocol stack, improved the kernel’s virtual memory system, and introduced more efficient TCP/IP support. Unfortunately, 4.3BSD-Tahoe was short lived as CCI changed their company’s focus, and Sperry and Burroughs released rebranded minicomputers based on the Power 6/32 platform. Where this effort did live on, however, was in a merger of 4.3BSD-Tahoe and 2.10BSD into 2.11BSD for the PDP-11. The Tahoe effort also meant that much of the BSD codebase had been rewritten furthering the aim of removing AT&amp;T licensed code.</p><p>BSD was released in source format only. Any prospective user would be required to compile his or her system from source entirely. Given this, any user would first need to acquire an AT&amp;T source license before he/she would be able to make use of BSD. As noted previously, UNIX license fees were ridiculous. Yet, the TCP/IP stack in 4.3BSD was unique to Berkeley. Several software developers requested that BSD’s networking code be offered separately from UNIX, and this was done in June of 1989 as Networking Release 1. Pricing for a tape from Berkeley was $400 (around $983 in 2024), but the license terms allowed for free modification, free redistribution, and free application to any use case provided that the copyright notices on Berkeley’s code remain in place, and that products incorporating the code mention in documentation that code from the University of California and its contributors was included. It was also available via anonymous FTP shortly following the initial release. This newsgroup post was made on the 7th of December in 1988, but other documentation states public availability was November:</p><blockquote><pre><code>Path: utzoo!utgpu!watmath!clyde!att!osu-cis!tut.cis.ohio-state.edu!mailrus!
ames!pasteur!ucbvax!OKEEFFE.BERKELEY.EDU!bostic
From: bos...@OKEEFFE.BERKELEY.EDU (Keith Bostic)
Newsgroups: comp.bugs.4bsd.ucb-fixes
Subject: V1.73 (BSD Networking Software, Release #1)
Message-ID: &lt;8812070154.AA18358@okeeffe.Berkeley.EDU&gt;
Date: 7 Dec 88 01:54:54 GMT
Sender: dae...@ucbvax.BERKELEY.EDU
Organization: University of California at Berkeley
Lines: 374
Approved: ucb-fi...@okeeffe.berkeley.edu

We are happy to announce the availability of the first release of the BSD networking software. It consists of the standard user level applications, (along with their manual pages and some related documentation) and some kernel and C library support. It should be noted that this software has only been tested for compilation and operation on 4.3BSD and 4.3BSD-tahoe. A complete list of files is attached to this message.

The TCP and IP code is approximately the same as that recently made
available via the ARPANET and Usenet. Several new algorithms are used in TCP, in particular Van Jacobson's slow start and dynamic window size
selection algorithms and Phil Karn's modification to the roundtrip timing algorithm. These changes increase throughput and reduce congestion and retransmission. Several fixes were made in the handling of IP options and other gateway support.

This software suite is copyright The Regents of the University of California and may be freely redistributed. No previous license, either AT&amp;T or Berkeley is required. The release costs $400.00 US. To request an order form, please contact our distribution office by phone at 415-642-7780, or by email at bsd-d...@ucbarpa.berkeley.edu or uunet!ucbarpa!bsd-dist, or by U.S. Mail at:

	CSRG, Computer Science Division
	University of California
	Berkeley, CA  94720

Mike Karels
Kirk McKusick</code></pre></blockquote><p>Rather than including the file list, I will simply note that this release was very complete. It included arp, ftp clients and servers (yes, plural on both), route, telnet, dns tools, ifconfig, inetd, pieces of the BSD libc, sendmail, syslog, ping, and uucp.</p><p>While the networking release was being made, 4.3BSD development continued. A new virtual memory system was implemented from MACH at Carnegie-Melon with the porting and merging work done by Mike Hibler. The interface for that VM system was, however, a purely Berkeley design adhering to the architecture descriptions found in 4.2BSD. The NFS system was upgraded to be Sun-compatible via the use of Rick Macklem’s work at the University of Geulph. This became 4.3BSD-Reno.</p><p>The original BSD license in Reno:</p><blockquote><p><em>Copyright (c) 1987 Regents of the University of California. All rights reserved. </em></p><p><em>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms are permitted provided that this notice is preserved and that due credit is given to the University of California at Berkeley. The name of the University may not be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific written prior permission. This software is provided ``as is'' without express or implied warranty.</em></p></blockquote><p>The license of Tahoe read:</p><blockquote><p><em>Copyright (c) 1987 Regents of the University of California. All rights reserved. </em></p><p><em>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms are permitted provided that the above copyright notice and this paragraph are duplicated in all such forms and that any documentation, advertising materials, and other materials related to such distribution and use acknowledge that the software was developed by the University of California, Berkeley. The name of the University may not be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific prior written permission. THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED ``AS IS'' AND WITHOUT ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, WITHOUT LIMITATION, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTIBILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.</em></p></blockquote><p>Keith Bostic was still as avid as ever to rid BSD of AT&amp;T code and free it from the heavy costs that came with that code. At a meeting of CSRG, he mentioned the popularity of the networking release and he proposed an expanded release that would include more than networking. Discussion went on for a while, but eventually McKusick and Karels took up the kernel work with Bostic handling the utilities and C library.  Obviously, this would be a seriously large undertaking for a single individual, and Bostic figured that others would be willing to help. Bostic then encouraged people to coordinate over the budding Internet with people across the globe submitting contributions. He also encouraged people to contribute at USENIX. In a little over a year, most of the utilities and libraries had been rewritten with major contributions coming from Bill Jolitz, Donn Seeley, Trent Hein, Vadim Antonov, Mike Karels, Igor Belchinsky, Pace Willisson, Jeff Polk, and Tony Sanders. Karels and McKusick hadn’t actually expected Bostic to succeed, but with the work completed, Bostic walked into their office with his head held high and inquired as to their progress on the kernel. The two then went off to work on it file by file, removing everything originally included in the 32V release, but they were short by six files. Rather than getting a new license and name created by the university’s lawyers, the group reused what they had and this became Network Release 2 announced on the 3rd of July in 1991.</p><blockquote><pre><code>Path: gmdzi!unido!fauern!ira.uka.de!sol.ctr.columbia.edu!spool.mu.edu!
caen!zaphod.mps.ohio-state.edu!cis.ohio-state.edu!ucbvax!OKEEFFE.BERKELEY.EDU!bostic
From: bos...@OKEEFFE.BERKELEY.EDU (Keith Bostic)
Newsgroups: comp.bugs.4bsd.ucb-fixes
Subject: V1.95 (BSD Networking Software, Release #2)
Message-ID: &lt;9107032314.AA06592@okeeffe.Berkeley.EDU&gt;
Date: 3 Jul 91 23:14:59 GMT
Sender: dae...@ucbvax.BERKELEY.EDU
Organization: University of California at Berkeley
Lines: 36
Approved: ucb-fi...@okeeffe.berkeley.edu

We are happy to announce the availability of the second release of the
BSD networking software. The distribution includes approximately 75% of
the utilities distributed as part of 4.3BSD-Reno and the C library  (along with manual pages and some related documentation), and much of the kernel. We wish to *strongly* emphasize, however, that significant portions of the kernel are missing and that no binary support is supplied for any architecture. Please note also that this software has only been tested for compilation and operation on 4.3BSD-Reno.

This release is intended for system developers and others who wish to
preview or experiment with the most recent Berkeley system. It may also
be useful as an update to earlier BSD or BSD-derived systems, although
substantial work will be required to integrate portions of this release
into older systems. This distribution is *not* intended to be used on
production systems, nor is it intended for sites without the expertise
to find and fix problems that are encountered.

This software suite is Copyright (C) 1991 The Regents of the University
of California and may be freely redistributed without further charge.  No previous license, either from AT&amp;T or Berkeley is required.  The release costs $850.00 US on 6250 BPI 9-track magnetic tape or 8mm Exabyte cassette or $950.00 US on 1600 BPI 9-track magnetic tape. The distribution is approximately 90Mb in size. To request an order form, please contact our distribution office by phone at 415-642-7780, or by sending email to bsd-d...@ucbarpa.berkeley.edu or uunet!ucbarpa!bsd-dist, or by U.S. Mail at:

	CSRG, Computer Science Division
	University of California
	Berkeley, CA  94720

Mike Karels
Kirk McKusick
Keith Bostic
Keith Sklower
Marc Teitelbaum</code></pre></blockquote><p>Less than a year later, Bill Jolitz replaced the missing kernel pieces and compiled everything for the PC-compatible Intel 80386 platform, and he released this new distribution as 386/BSD. Only a few short months later, a group of 386/BSD users formed NetBSD to continue enhancements and releases of Jolitz’s system. This occurred because Jolitz still had a full-time job, and the number of bug fixes, enhancements, and additions coming into his project were beyond his capabilities to manage alone. NetBSD has and continues to emphasize porting NetBSD to absolutely everything, including but not limited to ARM, MIPS, i386, AMD64, SPARC, PowerPC, Motorola 68K, SH3, HPPA, Itanium, RISC-V, and VAX. If your toaster has a chip in it, NetBSD will probably run on it. NetBSD has also engaged in some research and experimentation that has led to many security and system hardening technologies, an amazing package management system, kernel level hardware virtualization, and some surprising levels of backward compatibility. As is the BSD tradition, NetBSD has also merged in changes from systems like Solaris with ZFS.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg" width="725" height="543.3867735470942" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:374,&quot;width&quot;:499,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:725,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9930c00b-0270-4a9d-ae51-bfa22c05721d_499x374.jpeg 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>A toaster at the Linux World Expo in 2005, running NetBSD</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>While NET2 was being worked on and released, the last version of 2.11BSD was also being prepared and released, but this time by USENIX. On the 14th of March in 1991, Steven M. Schultz posted the following to </span><code>comp.sys.dec.micro</code><span>:</span></p><blockquote><pre><code>      Second Distribution of Berkeley PDP-11 Software for UNIX
                             Release 2.11
                        (Revised January 1991)

The USENIX Association is pleased to announce the distribution of a new release of the "Second Berkeley Software Distribution" (2.11BSD).

This release will be handled by USENIX, and is available to all V7,  System III, System V, and 2.9BSD licensees. The Association will continue to maintain the non-profit price of $200. The release will consist of two 2400 ft. 1600 bpi tapes or one TK50 tape cartridge
(approximately 80M) and approximately 100 pages of documentation.

If you have questions about the distribution of the release, or require  800 bpi tapes, please contact USENIX. USENIX's address and phone number is as follows:

     2.11BSD
     USENIX Association
     2560 Ninth St. Suite 215
     Berkeley, CA  94710
     +1-415-528-8649

USENIX may also be contacted by electronic mail at:

     {ucbvax,decvax}!usenix!office

If you have technical questions about the release, please contact Steven M. Schultz at:

     s...@wlv.imsd.contel.com
     wlbr!wlv!sms

This release is in celebration of the 20th anniversary of the PDP-11!  Work has been ongoing since the release of 2.10.1BSD in January 1989.  This release incorporates all fixes and changes posted to the USENET newsgroup comp.bugs.2bsd since 2.10.1BSD was released.

Present in this release are several more missing pieces from the 4.3BSD distribution:

1) the kernel logger (/dev/klog)
2) the namei cache and argument encapsulation calling sequence
3) readv(2)/writev(2) as system calls rather thane mulation/compatibility routines
4) shadow password file implementation (the May 1989 4.3BSD update)
5) a TMSCP (TK50/TU81) driver with standalone support (boot-block and standalone driver)
6) Pronet and LH/DH IMP networking support
7) the portable ascii archive file format (ar, ranlib)
8) the Unibus Mapping Register (UMR) handling of the network was rewritten to avoid allocating excessive UMRs.
9) the necessary mods to the IP portion of the networking were made to allow traceroute (which is present in 2.11BSD) to run
10) long filenames in the file system

This last addition is the reason a coldstart kit is necessary. The 4.3BSD on-disk directory structure has been ported (along with the
utilities that know about on-disk directories via the raw filesystem: fsck, ncheck, icheck, dcheck, etc.) and is not compatible with previous versions of UNIX for the PDP-11.

A limited amount of filesystem backward compatibility with earlier  versions of 2BSD (2.9BSD, 2.10BSD and 2.10.1BSD) is present in a version of dump(8) which can read old filesystems. The disk partition sizes have not changed from 2.10.1BSD (the urge to standardize the haphazard partition sizes was suppressed in the interest of backwards compatibility). The restor(8) utility automatically converts old dump 
tapes to the new format on input.

The constant MAXNAMLEN is now 63 instead of 14. While it is possible the limit could be higher, with MAXPATHLEN at 256 a MAXNAMLEN of 63 was  judged sufficient.

MANY other fixes and changes have also been made, see the "Changes To The Kernel" document which describes the changes made to both the kernel and the application programs.

Steven M. Schultz
Contel Federal Systems
31717 La Tienda Drive
Westlake Village CA 91359
s...@wlv.imsd.contel.com
wlbr!wlv!sms</code></pre></blockquote><p><span>A few months after the NetBSD group formed, the FreeBSD group formed. They chose to target the PC architecture specifically and to make their system a bit easier to use. In contrast to NetBSD which was solely a product offered over the internet, the FreeBSD group offered their product on CD-ROM. FreeBSD did expand to ARM, PowerPC, and MIPS, and like NetBSD they did continue the CSRG spirit of research and experimentation with things like bhyve virtualization and jails. Additionally, they have continued the legacy of borrowing the best bits of other systems like dtrace, and ZFS, but also via their immense collection of software in </span><code>ports</code><span>.</span></p><p><span>Richard L. Adams Jr (Rick) was the founder of one of the earliest internet service providers (if not </span><em>the</em><span> first), UUNET, after first creating SLIP (TCP/IP over serial). He also maintained the most popular usenet transport in the early 1980s, B News. After the release of 386/BSD, he got together with Keith Bostic, Marshall Kirk McKusick, Mike Karels, and Bill Jolitz and the group founded Berkeley Software Design, Inc otherwise known as BSDi. Their first product was BSD/386 based off of Networking Release 2 and it first released in January of 1992. Their system retailed for $995 (about $2160 in 2024). The target market for BSDi was the nascent internet infrastructure market. In their advertising they touted their “</span><em>99% discount over System V</em><span>” and advised interested parties to contact 1-800-its-unix.</span></p><p>Of course, this didn’t sit well with Unix System Labs (AT&amp;T subsidiary). Shortly after BSDi began sales, they received a cease and desist from USL with a particular request to stop using the phone number that included “it’s UNIX,” as the ownership of the UNIX trademark was firmly in USL’s hands. BSDi complied changing their advertisements, the number, and explaining that BSD wasn’t precisely UNIX. This, however, wasn’t quite enough. USL brought a lawsuit against BSDi seeking an injunction against the sale of BSD/386. As part of the suit, USL claimed that BSDi’s product contained USL code and trade secrets, and that further sales of BSDi’s product would irreparably harm USL. BSDi then claimed that they shouldn’t be held liable for any code contained in Berkeley’s original source offerings, but that they were completely willing to discuss the six added, BSDi-original files. BSDi’s argument won and USL was required to restate their complaint or have the case dismissed. USL then filed suit against both BSDi and the University of California with roughly the same complaints but this time seeking an injunction against the sale and distribution of both Networking Release 2 and BSD/386. The employees of both CSRG and BSDi were deposed.</p><p>In December of 1992, US District Judge Debevoise in New Jersey took the arguments for injunction under advisement. Six weeks later, he dismissed all but two of the complaints and suggested that the matter should be taken to a state court before being heard in a federal court. The University listened and filed a lawsuit against USL the following Monday in California. The suit by the University of California claimed that USL had failed to provide credit to the University for BSD code contained within System V as required by their prior licensing agreement. The University of California wasn’t asking for financial compensation but rather that USL reprint all of their System V documentation with proper credit and attribution for BSD code, that USL notify licensees of their mistake, and that USL run advertisements in print news publications informing the public of USL’s mistake.</p><p>On the 21st of December in 1992, Novell announced that it would be acquiring Unix System Laboratories including the UNIX copyright, trademarks, and licensing contracts. The LA Times stated that this transaction was completed with an exchange of stock wherein all of the shares of USL would be traded for twelve million three hundred thousand shares of Novell, and after which USL would be a wholly owned subsidiary of Novell. Discussions around a settlement of legal proceedings began in the summer of 1993, but were not resolved until January of 1994. The result was that three files were removed from Networking Release 2, minor changes were made to a few other files, and USL copyrights were added to about seventy files though the license of those files would continue to be the BSD license. On the part of USL, they agreed that with those terms met, the company would not bring litigation against any company, group, or user who used or distributed the resulting open source BSD system.</p><p>That resulting system was 4.4BSD-Lite and 4.4BSD-Encumbered in March of 1994. 4.4BSD-Encumbered included the prior USL code and required a USL UNIX license. 4.4BSD-Lite was fully free and open source software. This version was merged into FreeBSD 2.0, NetBSD 1.0, and a newly named BSD/OS which was previously BSD/386. For CSRG, the revenue received from 4.4BSD allowed the group to continue as a part-time effort integrating bug fixes and enhancements made locally and from the BSD community. As focus shifted into the other distributions like BSD/OS, NetBSD, and FreeBSD the rate of submissions to Berkeley slowed. The final release from the University was 4.4BSD-Lite Release 2 in June of 1995. This version was merged into FreeBSD 3.0, Rhapsody (and later Darwin), NetBSD 1.3, OpenBSD 2.3, and BSD/OS 3.0.</p><p>By 1995, BSDi’s BSD/OS was the most common operating system used in the datacenters of the early internet. This is a market that BSDi had intentionally targeted, and this would prove to be a sword of Damocles. The strand of hair holding the sword broke as the Dot Com Bubble began bursting and BSDi merged with Walnut Creek which itself was later sold to Wind River Systems.</p><p>Today, BSD is among the most common operating systems on Earth despite people not recognizing it as such. Modern macOS descends from 4.4BSD, as do NetBSD, OpenBSD, FreeBSD, Dragonfly BSD, and a few others. In the past, various versions of BSD formed the basis of SunOS, DYNIX, NeXTSTEP, Ultrix, and Tru64. Various editions of BSD were merged into AT&amp;T UNIX, and this means that modern commercial UNIX systems like AIX and HP-UX are also running some BSD code. BSD has been used in many commercial products owning to its permissive licensing, and some of the most notable of those are the Sony Playstation 3, 4, and Vita, the Netflix Open Connect Appliance, Juniper routers, Isilon IQ clustered storage systems, Dell Compellent storage systems, and the Weather Channel’s IntelliStar forecast computer. </p><p>I now have readers from many of the companies whose history I cover, and many of you were present for time periods I cover. A few of you are mentioned by name in my articles. All corrections to the record are welcome; feel free to leave a comment.</p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Hurried Thoughts: You're Wrong About Tidal-Locking (199 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2024/03/hurried-thoughts-youre-wrong-about.html</link>
            <guid>39629225</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 14:08:26 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2024/03/hurried-thoughts-youre-wrong-about.html">https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2024/03/hurried-thoughts-youre-wrong-about.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39629225">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="post-body-6326268091893787447">

<p><span>I've already talked about tidal-locked planets at length
    <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2020/12/an-apple-pie-from-scratch-part-ivd.html">in the past</a>
    (<a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2019/06/an-apple-pie-from-scratch-part-ii-stars.html#tidallockedplanets">several</a>
    <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2019/09/an-apple-pie-from-scratch-part-iva.html#tidallocking">times</a>), and there won't be much new here for my regular readers, I just figured
    it'd be nice to have a single <i>relatively</i> short place to address the
    most common myths about tidal-locked planets, and particularly their
    climate, for easy reference.</span>
</p>

<p><span>The very short version is that the popular perception of tidal-locked
    planets</span><span>—</span><span>hostile worlds split between a burning desert on the lit hemisphere, ice on
    the dark side, and, at best, a thin "twilight strip" of habitable
    temperatures in between, wracked by gale-force winds</span><span>—</span><span>is not a strictly impossible scenario in all its particulars, but our
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/ac135c/meta">current best climate models</a></span><span><span><sup>1</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
    predict (and
    <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0019103597957936">have</a></span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
    for quite some time now) that tidal-locked planets in the habitable zone
    with Earth-like atmospheres and quantities of surface water can more
    typically expect
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/aa9f1f/meta">far more hospitable conditions</a></span><span><span><sup>3</sup></span></span><span></span><span>, with comfortable temperatures and moderate prevailing winds across the
    lit hemisphere; that the hottest part of the planet
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1702.08463.pdf">will usually actually be the wettest</a></span><span><span><sup>4</sup></span></span><span></span><span>; and that this habitable climate state may actually be
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1307.0515">more stable</a></span><span><span><sup>5</sup></span></span><span> in some ways than
    that of a planet more like our own.</span>
</p>

<p><span>For a more detailed explanation, let's back up a bit and set the scene.
    <b>Tidal-locking</b> describes a phenomenon whereby the tidal influence of a
    star on a planet (or between a planet and moon) causes the planet's rotation
    to slow until one side of the planet faces permanently towards the star, and
    the opposite side faces away. Because the planet still orbits in a loop
    around the star, this requires that it also rotates around once on its axis
    to keep that star-side face pointed to the star, so this is also sometimes
    called a <b>1:1 spin-orbit resonance</b>; for every 1 orbit, the planet
    spins around exactly once. The tidal influence of the star helps ensure this
    exact timing, hence the "locking" aspect. There are other spin-orbit
    resonances that tidal forces might lock a planet into, like the
    <b>3:2 spin-orbit resonance</b> of Mercury (the planet spins 3 times for
    every 2 orbits), but whether these planets should also be called
    "tidal-locked" varies between sources; in colloquial usage, "tidal-locking"
    is used almost exclusively to refer to the 1:1 resonance.</span>
</p>


<p><span>The strength of tidal forces is strongly dependent on the distance between
    the planet and star. Smaller <b>red dwarf stars</b> that are substantially
    dimmer than our sun have habitable zones that are correspondingly much
    closer to the star, so any habitable-zone planets of these stars are much
    more likely to be tidal-locked. These are by far the most common type of
    star in the universe, accounting for over 3/4 of the total number, so the
    habitability of tidal-locked planets is a major factor in the prevalence in
    habitability in the cosmos generally.<br></span>
</p>

<p><span>Unsurprisingly, keeping one side of the planet pointed at the star has a
    profound effect on how light from the star</span><span>—and thus heat</span><span>—is spread over the planet's surface. On Earth, a flat surface directly
    facing the sun (with no obstructions and ignoring filtering by the
    atmosphere) receives about 1360 Watts per square meter (W/</span><span>m</span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span>) of light. But Earth's rotation and axial tilt spread out this light, such
    that the average light any single part of the surface receives across the
    whole year (averaging together summer, winter, day, and night) varies
    between a bit over 400&nbsp;</span><span>W/</span><span>m</span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span>
    near the equator and under 180&nbsp;</span><span>W/</span><span>m</span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span>
    at the poles (subtracting out the light reflected away by the surface and
    atmosphere leaves about 2/3 of that light on average being actually absorbed
    as heat).</span>
</p>

<p><span>On a tidal-locked world in the same orbit, the <b>substellar point</b> in
    the middle of the daylight side, which faces most directly towards the star,
    would get that full 1360&nbsp;</span><span>W/</span><span>m</span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span>
    of light continuously.</span><span>
    The heating would decline towards the edge of the dayside, falling to
    0&nbsp;</span><span>W/</span><span>m</span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span>
    at the <b>terminator</b>, the line dividing the day and night hemispheres;
    over 2/3 of the dayside hemisphere's area would receive more light than the
    average for Earth's equator. The entire nightside receives no light from the
    star at all, save perhaps some meager twilight at the edges refracting
    through the atmosphere.</span>
</p>

<div>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiybNLfXvXkwuF890E4wtzpvAUk2UnzoKi_NOGV1iEKvJk3vG4m5JmQ2FGAjpTIlGr1jHVKFQsjPcStYDcgK0bHIiNPffgjscezJ4c2bdNbgxF7i2pWlEE8dnD-kwp1udMhC_jkwoFBSjsXzD__6Nx_20Ue4PFwl3X6Kl5Ll1ws7Gr5NgHqE4nSeU2ScX3X/s1392/insol.png"><img data-original-height="339" data-original-width="1392" height="156" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiybNLfXvXkwuF890E4wtzpvAUk2UnzoKi_NOGV1iEKvJk3vG4m5JmQ2FGAjpTIlGr1jHVKFQsjPcStYDcgK0bHIiNPffgjscezJ4c2bdNbgxF7i2pWlEE8dnD-kwp1udMhC_jkwoFBSjsXzD__6Nx_20Ue4PFwl3X6Kl5Ll1ws7Gr5NgHqE4nSeU2ScX3X/w640-h156/insol.png" width="640"></a>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Average insolation across the surface of Earth (left) and a
          tidal-locked planet in the same orbit (right)
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>

<p><span>It's understandable, then, that when the prospect of tidal-locked planets
    was
    <a href="https://www.rand.org/content/dam/rand/pubs/commercial_books/2007/RAND_CB179-1.pdf">first being considered</a></span><span><span><sup>6</sup></span></span><span></span><span>, such extreme contrasts in lighting and heating were expected to be
    accompanied by an extreme climate, split between a scorching hot dayside and
    bitter cold nightside.&nbsp;</span><span>Perhaps somewhere in between, near the terminator, there should be at least
    a thin strip of more hospitable temperatures, but that didn't guarantee
    habitability either. </span><span>
    A
    <a href="https://articles.adsabs.harvard.edu/cgi-bin/nph-iarticle_query?bibcode=1981NASCP2156..115C&amp;db_key=AST&amp;page_ind=2&amp;plate_select=NO&amp;data_type=GIF&amp;type=SCREEN_GIF&amp;classic=YES">common concern</a></span><span><span><sup>7</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
    was that any water on the planet's surface and perhaps even </span><span>C</span><span>O</span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span>
    would become trapped as ice on the nightside, leaving the dayside bone dry
    and even hotter for lack of the moderating influence of water. In the worst
    scenario, sequestration of ices on the nightside and heat-driven escape of
    atmospheric gasses to space on the dayside might remove such a planet's
    atmosphere entirely.<p>Even those who imagined a habitable strip
    imagined it dimly lit, being so close to the terminator, and wracked by
    vicious winds; the planet's strong temperature contrast would create a
    powerful convection cell, with air rising on the dayside, moving at high
    altitude to the nightside, and then descending and shooting back towards the
    dayside close to the surface; prospects for complex life in this constantly
    buffeted twilight strip would be, well, dim.</p></span>
</p>

<div>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjQHIZkM5nN1fnLPOpzL6HutOPWgFTOKc4zSMSMDx8qbr6fwMnM39y3bjoH5w4wma5aM3syKw_zgvRmCI9N8TixiZuVVV4QFVw2sHo8bjiXwdW4m7TCWRIT0j1rbonyOCcNA5ndgjZ0kHIfYlB-ahLn0L7gzgS5GFCVBbF2KFXv8dzRQQrWGnzMJqiRXcDW/s1384/299515_2_En_5_Fig6_HTML.png"><img data-original-height="363" data-original-width="1384" height="168" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjQHIZkM5nN1fnLPOpzL6HutOPWgFTOKc4zSMSMDx8qbr6fwMnM39y3bjoH5w4wma5aM3syKw_zgvRmCI9N8TixiZuVVV4QFVw2sHo8bjiXwdW4m7TCWRIT0j1rbonyOCcNA5ndgjZ0kHIfYlB-ahLn0L7gzgS5GFCVBbF2KFXv8dzRQQrWGnzMJqiRXcDW/w640-h168/299515_2_En_5_Fig6_HTML.png" width="640"></a>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          A cross-section through the atmosphere of a tidal-locked planet,
          showing air circulation from the center of the dayside to the
          nightside, with the terminator in the center; the "temperature
          inversion" shows a portion of the lower atmosphere where temperature
          rises with altitude, rather than falling.
          <a href="https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-030-25550-3_5">Stevenson 2019</a><span><span><sup>8</sup></span></span>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <br>
</div>
<p><span>This picture of tidal-locked planets as marginally habitable at best but
    more likely prone to complete collapse into dry, sterile, perhaps even
    airless worlds prevailed
    <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/BF00644211">well into the 1990s</a></span><span><span><sup>9</sup></span></span><span></span><span>, but as computing technology improved and we finally gained some
    capability to simulate the climates of such worlds in detail, which painted
    a
    <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0019103597957936">far different picture</a></span><span><span><sup>2</sup></span></span><span></span><span>.</span>
</p>

<p><span>As it turns out, even an atmosphere substantially thinner than Earth's
    could distribute enough heat to the nightside to prevent atmospheric
    freeze-out, and a more Earth-like atmosphere could keep temperatures
    globally within
    <a href="https://agupubs.onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.3894/JAMES.2010.2.13">about the same range</a></span><span><span><sup>10</sup></span></span><span>
    we experience on Earth. Water, too, can
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/2041-8205/796/2/L22/meta">easily avoid</a></span><span><span><sup>11</sup></span></span><span>
    becoming completely trapped on the nightside, and global oceans could then
    help distribute heat
    <a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/pdf/10.1073/pnas.1315215111">even more evenly</a></span><span><span><sup>12</sup></span></span><span>
    across the surface.</span>
</p>

<p><span>In fact, in some circumstances, tidal-locking might even make a habitable
    climate more stable. Near the inner edge of the habitable zone, where the
    sun's light is more intense, the slow rotation and global convection may
    allow for warm planets to develop a permanent cloud formation that reflects
    away much of the star's light, keeping temperatures moderate
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1307.0515">even in orbits</a></span><span><span><sup>5</sup></span></span><span> where a planet
    with Earth-like rotation would boil from runaway greenhouse warming. At the
    habitable zone's outer edge, this cooling effect would be weaker, and the
    sharp gradient in heating from the star on the dayside
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/ab487d">would help prevent</a></span><span><span><sup>13</sup></span></span><span>
    runaway cooling and ice formation of the sort that may have caused Earth to
    freeze over completely in the past.</span>
</p>

<p><span>So, let's take a quick look at what modern modelling predicts the actual
    climate of a tidal-locked planet with otherwise Earth-like properties should
    look like.
    <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/aa9f1f/meta">Temperatures across the dayside</a></span><span><span><sup>3</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
    could easily vary by less than 30&nbsp;</span><span>°C</span><span>, and the nightside would tend to be even more uniform. Ice could still
    cover much of the nightside, but it needn't stop exactly at the terminator;
    it could extend well into the dayside while still leaving a substantial warm
    region, it could be restricted only to some nightside pockets,
    or&nbsp;</span><span>the nightside could even&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.pnas.org/doi/pdf/10.1073/pnas.1315215111">thaw out completely</a><span><span><sup>12</sup></span></span><span></span><span>. Ice cover on Earth has varied considerably over its history through
    warmer and cooler climates, and much the same would be true here.</span>
</p>

<div>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhMiV_MjTHqqQ68HTnP2aTo8ZVHY2PNwCNRzLx-XuUU6njRURfOVI1e4m0OsG7kzv6tMSLJu0UaXdfnVR8O5wY7dMJ6yKAFstJPyyhETEHfbDQ2oLsxsq5HMG_QPNmmExr4dw6_txRuSDypU5ntnBoQzv_0lQaKxV-xjt5Q3APZfy0Jh5Rno3RMiLq3FLwm/s718/apjaa9f1ff7_lr.jpg"><img data-original-height="580" data-original-width="718" height="516" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhMiV_MjTHqqQ68HTnP2aTo8ZVHY2PNwCNRzLx-XuUU6njRURfOVI1e4m0OsG7kzv6tMSLJu0UaXdfnVR8O5wY7dMJ6yKAFstJPyyhETEHfbDQ2oLsxsq5HMG_QPNmmExr4dw6_txRuSDypU5ntnBoQzv_0lQaKxV-xjt5Q3APZfy0Jh5Rno3RMiLq3FLwm/w640-h516/apjaa9f1ff7_lr.jpg" width="640"></a>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Modelled surface temperature and prevailing winds (key shows 5 m/s) of
          all-ocean tidal-locked planets with a range of indicated orbital
          periods, appropriate to the habitable zone of stars with the indicated
          effective temperatures.
          <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/aa9f1f/meta">Haqq-Misra et al. 2018</a><span><span><sup>3</sup></span></span>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>

<p><span>For most cases, near-surface winds would indeed tend to converge on the
    center of the dayside, but in speed and strength would typically be no worse
    than a stiff breeze, comparable to the trade winds in our tropics. Planets
    orbiting the very smallest stars, with short orbital periods of under 20
    days, might have more complex patterns, but I'll
    <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2020/12/an-apple-pie-from-scratch-part-ivd.html#rotation">point you elsewhere</a></span><span>
    for that discussion.</span>
</p>

<div>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiAXz9SUXbyPaKbHYZVvGPSQ5M1WgmGwOqDTuJAQ85btSaeLqw6j96gkcWNJcakCHtISPfmZm8NYgQjb7GMGUSIa2hK719eU7KuLM2r886iMNpi4D7I9S_RcYxV1eW8fVM2cxzJBbnLRkRGkrKS_QoYqtKEmGgXjjzzat4s2wKlgdc3DVyqprDCh9DsAtTy/s702/Screenshot%202024-01-13%20160916.png"><img data-original-height="525" data-original-width="702" height="299" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiAXz9SUXbyPaKbHYZVvGPSQ5M1WgmGwOqDTuJAQ85btSaeLqw6j96gkcWNJcakCHtISPfmZm8NYgQjb7GMGUSIa2hK719eU7KuLM2r886iMNpi4D7I9S_RcYxV1eW8fVM2cxzJBbnLRkRGkrKS_QoYqtKEmGgXjjzzat4s2wKlgdc3DVyqprDCh9DsAtTy/w400-h299/Screenshot%202024-01-13%20160916.png" width="400"></a>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Precipitation in a climate model of Proxima b with a
          nitrogen-dominated atmosphere; the black line indicates the limit of
          freezing temperatures in this model.
          <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1702.08463.pdf">Boutle et al. 2018</a><span><span><sup>4</sup></span></span>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div>

<p><span>Conversely to the image of a dayside desert, the warmest part of the
    dayside, near the center, will actually
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1702.08463.pdf">tend to be the wettest</a></span><span><span><sup>4</sup></span></span><span></span><span>.
    Those converging winds would pull in moisture from across the planet, and
    the rising convection would encourage frequent widespread rain. Though some
    climate models briefly predicted a single permanent cyclone in the center of
    the dayside, it
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2004.03007.pdf">now seems more likely</a></span><span><span><sup>14</sup></span></span><span></span><span> to
    be a less organized mass of stormy and rainy weather, with frequent cloud
    cover but some prospect for occasional breaks. Farther from the center of
    the dayside, rain would taper off, but the unusual atmospheric structure
    (cool winds towards the dayside near the surface, hot winds towards the
    nightside at high altitude) would encourage frequent fog.</span>
</p>

<p><span>Ocean currents could shift around heat considerably: on a planet with no
    continents, they'd tend to carry heat east, north and south of the center of
    the dayside, such that rather than the typically expected "eyeball" pattern
    of a circular region of open ocean surrounded by ice,
    <a href="https://ostd.pku.edu.cn/research_highlights/21455.htm">you might expect</a></span><span><span><sup>15</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
    more of a lobster shape extending onto the nightside. This tendency may vary
    depending on orbital period, though, and the presence of landmasses blocking
    free flow of currents could weaken their overall influence.</span>
</p>

<div>
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjrdEPPDJkJBFfi9B-hbctbz6NOQmnIGxWree0UIFIfYL-env64RovXjj8OKwRiXrBx2p_4P7iNXbshc3CdFgGdyxxUJcsLJLPLJPRNntq99XsTdYnAWW_NpZAhfxiOP_kvT2aoUmz7_PeJokE4c7f_b5CJfhaz-Z544axVnL7uuRveThxUJ4_ALbxhXEPG/s450/001aa0c1c3a1142f655023.png"><img data-original-height="222" data-original-width="450" height="316" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEjrdEPPDJkJBFfi9B-hbctbz6NOQmnIGxWree0UIFIfYL-env64RovXjj8OKwRiXrBx2p_4P7iNXbshc3CdFgGdyxxUJcsLJLPLJPRNntq99XsTdYnAWW_NpZAhfxiOP_kvT2aoUmz7_PeJokE4c7f_b5CJfhaz-Z544axVnL7uuRveThxUJ4_ALbxhXEPG/w640-h316/001aa0c1c3a1142f655023.png" width="640"></a>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Modelled ice cover (left) and surface temperature (right) of a
          tidal-locked planet without (top) and with (bottom) fully modelled
          ocean currents.
          <a href="https://ostd.pku.edu.cn/research_highlights/21455.htm">Peking University</a><span><span><sup>15</sup></span></span>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
  <p><span>Various additional factors could influence the climate in other ways, but
    I've discussed that all in detail
    <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2020/12/an-apple-pie-from-scratch-part-ivd.html">elsewhere</a></span><span>.</span>
</p></div>

<p><span>Exactly why the old image of inhospitable tidal-locked worlds has persisted
    this long, well after the scientific community&nbsp;<a href="https://funkyscience.net/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/Tarter-et-al.-2007.pdf">has moved past it</a></span><span><span><sup>16</sup></span></span><span>, I couldn't say, though it certainly doesn't help when even </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alien_Worlds_(TV_series)">recent high-budget media claiming scientific accuracy</a><span>
    repeats the old myths. A planet of stark climate extremes is admittedly a
    fairly compelling image, capturing the imagination of speculative authors
    for
    <a href="https://archive.org/details/macmillansmagazi88macmuoft/page/140/mode/1up">over a century</a></span><span>
    now, but a more hospitable world with vast regions of tropical climate under
    eternal sunshine have their own potential as well.&nbsp;</span>
</p>

<p><span>But if you do like the concept of a habitable twilight strip between
    hemispheres of desert and ice, don't despair; though we shouldn't view this
    as the default climate of tidal-locked worlds, but it can still be achieved
    in the right circumstances.&nbsp;</span><span>A lower total volume of surface water, larger nightside continents, and
    lower geothermal heat </span><a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/2041-8205/796/2/L22/meta">will all encourage</a><span><span><sup>11</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
    trapping of water in nightside ice, potentially allowing for drying out of
    the dayside. A dryer dayside and optionally a thinner atmosphere will weaken
    distribution of heat, allowing the center of the dayside to become hotter
    while still allowing the nightside glaciers to spread to the terminator
    (though they might not reach it evenly on all sides; expect them to more
    reliably appear to the dayside's western edge). Meltwater from these
    glaciers
    <a href="https://www.aanda.org/articles/aa/full_html/2013/06/aa21042-13/aa21042-13.html">could feed into</a></span><span><span><sup>17</sup></span></span><span></span><span> a fairly broad habitable strip; evaporated water would be carried by
    winds into the dayside, but so long as the overall supply isn't too high,
    too little would accumulate there to cause rain and would instead return
    with high-atmosphere winds to snow down on the nightside glaciers</span><span>—and the habitable region might see some sporadic rainfall or fog as well
    (there could also be slightly wetter climates where only a small region in
    the center of the dayside receives rain, separated from the glacial
    meltwater region by vast deserts). Winds over this habitable strip would
    probably be stiffer than for the more moderate climate state, but still not
    relentless gales.<br></span>
</p>


<p><span>That about covers the main issues I wanted to cover today, but while I'm
    here, I might as well go over a few other common myths and misunderstandings
    regarding tidal-locked planets (and other bodies) as well.</span>
</p>
<div>
  <h3>
    <span>Tidal-Locked Moons<br></span>
  </h3>
  <p><span>Just as a planet can tidal-lock to its star, a moon can tidal-lock to its
      planet. Indeed, because tidal forces scale strongly with distance and
      moon-planet distances are generally far smaller than planet-star
      distances, almost all moons in the solar system are tidal-locked (the few
      known exceptions, like
      <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hyperion_(moon)">Hyperion</a></span><span>, are
      due to the influence of a much larger neighboring moon causing chaotic
      rotation), and we can probably expect this to be the norm for other star
      systems as well.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>But tidal-locking of a moon to its planet means that it points one face
      to that planet and so rotates once for each orbit of the planet. Relative
      to the star, the moon thus spins around about once per orbit of the
      planet, and so should experience a regular day and night cycle in about
      that time (because the planet is moving around the star as the moon orbits
      the planet, the moon needs to complete either slightly more or slightly
      less</span><span>—depending on the orientation of the orbits</span><span>—</span><span>than one full orbit to rotate back around to face the star again; our
      moon, for example, completes an orbit every 27.3 Earth days, but requires
      29.5 Earth days for one of its days). Tidal-locking to the planet can have
      interesting implications for the day-night cycle of the planet-facing side
      of the moon due to potential eclipses by day and reflected light from the
      planet by night, but in general the climate should resemble that of a
      planet with equivalently long days rather than that of a tidal-locked
      planet (because many moons have quite long orbital periods, these climates
      might still be quite different from Earth's).<br></span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>Tidal-locking of a moon to the planet's star rather than the planet is,
      so far as I can tell, not possible. The physics governing whether a moon
      can be kept in orbit of a planet at all (i.e., the <b>Hill radius</b>) and
      those governing the strength of tidal forces are fundamentally related
      such that any moon in any stable orbit of a planet must necessarily
      experience stronger tidal forces from the planet than from the star. The
      star might still have some influence on the moon's motion, but the balance
      of forces should always drive the moon's rotation towards locking with its
      motion around the planet and not the star.<p>I've occasionally
      heard it proposed that a moon might have an orbit as long as its planet's
      year, such that it can be simultaneously tidal-locked to both planet and
      star, but this doesn't work out either; again, the
      <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2019/09/an-apple-pie-from-scratch-part-iva.html#limitsandstability">physics works out</a></p></span><span>
      such that no moon can have an orbital period longer than about 58% the
      length of the planet's year, and realistically we'd expect most to have
      orbits limited to about 1/5 the length of the year. There is a point
      directly between the planet and star (the <b>L1 Lagrange point</b>) where
      their gravitational influence balances out such that a body can remain
      temporarily locked between the two, following the planet's orbit, but it's
      unstable, like a pencil balanced on its tip; any small perturbation will
      nudge the body away, such that it eventually moves off into another orbit,
      either of the planet or star.<br></span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>Incidentally, a planet can also be tidal-locked to its moon, facing one
      side towards it as it orbits around the planet. Whether or not the balance
      of tidal forces favors this is more variable, depending on the particulars
      of the relative masses and distances of the objects involved (and in
      <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/0004-637X/754/1/51">some cases</a></span><span><span><sup>18</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      it may change over the planet's lifetime). If it does happen, much of what
      is true for the surface climate and conditions of a tidal-locked moon are
      true of this sort of planet as well. We can also generally expect that the
      moon is already tidal-locked to the planet at this point, such that
      they're <b>mutually tidal-locked</b>, permanently facing each other, as is
      the case for Pluto and Charon.<br></span>
  </p>
  
  
</div>
<h3>
  <span>Polar Orientation<br></span>
</h3>
<p><span>A common exchange I see online is one person</span><span>
    asking what might happen if a planet had one of its poles pointed towards
    its star, and another person responding that this is equivalent to
    tidal-locking. In a very abstract and conceptual sense this is a reasonable
    response, in that tidal-locking is a realistic case for the idea of having a
    part of a planet permanently facing the star, but in the strictest sense
    it's not true; a tidal-locked planet still rotates, and so still has poles,
    which should usually be somewhere along the terminator, facing at right
    angles to the star rather than towards it.</span>
</p>

<div>
  <p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhEdGOs9-MxKH7_t6lpn_ARZHFfAI2mPjdCGDYng94icvjmNWWGLPszT4enakqKNeC2Fq_z5MYo0ZBVH0pdIr3PU33xHUXK8uDOvR97M898PuhNhtzDnhbOMn0oYDfDJWe_4es9ccYu2tiYlm3dXVdM3ieiRoc5xbEXgKtjFsIUqLZhi4hzeUmRv6Ra4h75/s640/planet%20diagram.png"><img data-original-height="424" data-original-width="640" height="424" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhEdGOs9-MxKH7_t6lpn_ARZHFfAI2mPjdCGDYng94icvjmNWWGLPszT4enakqKNeC2Fq_z5MYo0ZBVH0pdIr3PU33xHUXK8uDOvR97M898PuhNhtzDnhbOMn0oYDfDJWe_4es9ccYu2tiYlm3dXVdM3ieiRoc5xbEXgKtjFsIUqLZhi4hzeUmRv6Ra4h75/w640-h424/planet%20diagram.png" width="640"></a>
  </p>
</div>

<p><span>Fair enough, but I sometimes also hear it proposed that perhaps a planet
    could actually keep one of its poles pointed towards the star if there was
    some secondary rotation turning the planet in addition to its main rotation
    around its poles. In isolation, this simply isn't geometrically possible;
    objects in 3-dimensional space can only ever rotate around one axis at a
    time. There would need to be some outside force continuously acting on the
    planet to alter its rotation to allow this to happen. Earth does experience
    some <b>precession</b></span><span>—continuous alteration of its rotational axis</span><span>—due to the influence of the other planets, and this is partially
    responsible for our cycle of cooler glacial periods and warmer interglacials
    (as shifts in axial tilt alter the amount of heating the polar regions get).
    But this is a minor shift over thousands of years. To have one of the poles
    kept pointed directly at the star at all times would, in terms of momentum
    change and energy required, be the equivalent of of stopping Earth's
    rotation completely, starting it at the same rate in the opposite direction,
    stopping the rotation again, and restarting the initial rotation every
    single orbit.</span>
</p>

<p><span>Earth has a total of 2.14 * 10</span><span><span><sup>29</sup></span></span><span>
    J of energy bound up in its rotation; for a planet with similar properties
    and rotation, this twice-over stopping and starting would require 4 times
    this amount of energy, 8.56 * 10</span><span><span><sup>29</sup></span></span><span>
    J, every orbit. Assuming a year as long as Earth's, that's a continuous
    power input of 2.71 * 10</span><span><span><sup>22</sup></span></span><span>
    W. The total power of sunlight striking Earth (before even accounting for
    what's promptly reflected away) is only 1.74 * 10</span><span><span><sup>17</sup></span></span><span>
    W. Thus, even assuming there was some outside influence capable of providing
    that much power in that specific way, if even a tiny portion of that energy
    was ultimately released as heat (and really we wouldn't expect it to be an
    efficient process at all), it would be plenty sufficient to push the climate
    far past the bounds of habitability and roast the surface, perhaps even
    melting the planet entirely.</span>
</p>

<p><span>Setting that scenario aside, a planet that has one of its poles facing
    towards the sun at one point of the year and then continues on its orbit
    with a constant rotational axis</span><span>—</span><span>pointing each pole towards the sun in turn at opposite seasons</span><span>—</span><span>is a possibility (Uranus is close to this orientation) and has
    <a href="https://worldbuildingpasta.blogspot.com/2022/08/climate-explorations-obliquity.html">its own intriguing implications</a></span><span>
    for the surface climate.</span>
</p>

<p><span>A tidal-locked planet also doesn't need to have its poles pointed at exact
    right angles from the star at all times. Usually we would expect that,
    because the same tidal forces that cause tidal-locking also reduce axial
    tilt, a tidal-locked planet should have no tilt, but the influence of
    multiple other planets or stars
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.17908">might lock one</a></span><span><span><sup>19</sup></span></span><span></span><span> into a
    "Cassini state" with some constant effective tilt relative to its orbit. In
    this case, the star would seem to shift north and then back south in the sky
    over the course of an orbit, and the terminator would shift as well,
    allowing for parts of the planet to have periods of day and night. Orbital
    eccentricity
    <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1710.01405">can similarly</a></span><span><span><sup>20</sup></span></span><span></span><span> shift the
    terminator around over the course of the planet's orbit, with the combined
    effect of shifting orientation relative to the sun called
    <b>libration</b>.</span>
</p>
<div>
  <h3>
    <span>Tidal-Locking Limits<br></span>
  </h3>
  <p><span>As mentioned, tidal-locking is expected to be more common in the
      habitable zones of smaller stars, because of how much stronger tidal
      forces should be in the closer habitable zones of these stars. Because of
      doubts about the habitability of tidal-locked planets</span><span>—</span><span>which, even with better and more encouraging climate modelling, still
      cannot be entirely dismissed without empirical evidence</span><span>—researchers investigating the limits of habitability around other stars
      have often found it prudent to indicate which stars are likely to have
      mostly tidal-locked planets. This is why you'll often see charts of the
      habitable zone marked with a line indicated as a "tidal-locking limit" or
      something similar.</span>
  </p>
  
  
  <p><span>This is a convenient way to make the implications of these charts
      readable both for those skeptical and optimistic about the prospects for
      habitable tidal-locked planets, but I think non-researchers sometimes
      misunderstand that line as an absolute limit; all planets on one side of
      the line <i>must</i> be tidal-locked and all those on the other side can
      <i>never</i> be tidal-locked.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>In reality, whether or not a particular planet becomes tidal-locked
      depends on a number of factors beyond just distance from the star. First
      off, tidal-locking takes time; usually these charts assume an age of 4.5
      billion years, presuming that we're interested in habitable worlds with
      intelligent life and that might take about as long as it did on Earth. But
      depending on why you're interested in tidal-locking, you might be
      considering much younger or older planets.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span><table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi0pXWDlwKg172ZCV5nZC21KOnWVBaCYbSxTzWiFlLBJAc57K_1yWqa-oTIfUs23czPeJbLFI2Gsck5DDgCOmSHYY2vTs9xyIJ9ODuFbxqqoeXag-GbD1h-bxcb8vZLdxMnD3eEvR5Dz_xn19fz1xeLAeoKMQxUtEXGdTyZBi0R9WQJ2BzV13HT6BGBHzj4/s1186/tide1.png"><img data-original-height="777" data-original-width="1186" height="420" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEi0pXWDlwKg172ZCV5nZC21KOnWVBaCYbSxTzWiFlLBJAc57K_1yWqa-oTIfUs23czPeJbLFI2Gsck5DDgCOmSHYY2vTs9xyIJ9ODuFbxqqoeXag-GbD1h-bxcb8vZLdxMnD3eEvR5Dz_xn19fz1xeLAeoKMQxUtEXGdTyZBi0R9WQJ2BzV13HT6BGBHzj4/w640-h420/tide1.png" width="640"></a>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Tidal-locking limits at different ages ("byr" indicates planet age
              in billions of years) for Earth-like planets (dissipation factor
              of 100) with 12-hour initial days. Dark green indicates the
              conventional habitable zone, light green is a very optimistic
              habitable zone allowing for
              <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/0004-637X/778/2/109/meta">very low surface water</a><span><span><sup>22</sup></span></span><span></span>
              near the star or
              <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/aa60c8">up to 50% atmospheric hydrogen</a><span><span><sup>23</sup></span></span><span></span>
              far from the star.<br>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <br></span>
  </p>
  <p><span>The time tidal-locking takes also depends strongly on the initial
      rotation rate of the planet after it has formed; usually something like
      12-13 hour days are assumed for the purpose of drawing these limits in
      habitable zone diagrams (I'm not totally sure why, presumably based on
      some model of Earth's rotational evolution), but in reality it could vary
      greatly depending on random factors like the last few large impacts during
      formation. A planet might just happen to form with very slow rotation
      close to the synchronous rate, so in principle there's no strict outer
      limit where tidal-locking becomes impossible (though the further from the
      star, the more precisely the initial rotation has to happen to match the
      synchronous rate, so the chances of this happening drop pretty
      precipitously past a couple AU from a sun-mass star, for example). At the
      other extreme, a planet can only start out spinning so fast before it
      would tear itself apart with the centrifugal forces (in Earth's case the
      limit is about 2-hour days), so that gives us a more definitive inner
      limit where tidal-locking may be unavoidable (in this simple model,
      anyway).</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span><table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiaEvCGJxJocOBV1p7L-_zHSCA9Kgo6Cxmq3ZvNLJJJjL3afBKpzKWkJ6CjaLbZtxcsj0UjBOPDqw8GsTfCbigECq17BtDJkRpnhSSVwv0DCbm2tZwlbsDKmJXvsQ1WdupdnD1iHiFiAThoihHpwZrzq-kUHI_cshKDfUYHlXMk8jbEZdvxMoWe51StDxW9/s1186/tide2.png"><img data-original-height="777" data-original-width="1186" height="420" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiaEvCGJxJocOBV1p7L-_zHSCA9Kgo6Cxmq3ZvNLJJJjL3afBKpzKWkJ6CjaLbZtxcsj0UjBOPDqw8GsTfCbigECq17BtDJkRpnhSSVwv0DCbm2tZwlbsDKmJXvsQ1WdupdnD1iHiFiAThoihHpwZrzq-kUHI_cshKDfUYHlXMk8jbEZdvxMoWe51StDxW9/w640-h420/tide2.png" width="640"></a>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              "h" indicates initial rotation rate in hours.<br>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <br></span>
  </p>
  <p><span>Finally, the planet's size and the nature of its response to tidal forces
      also have a small influence on the tidal-locking rate. The latter is a bit
      hard to pin down in a model so often represented as a single "dissipation
      factor"; it's generally taken to be about 12 for modern earth, but based
      on some models of the Earth's orbital evolution, may have been as high as
      100 in the past.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span><table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiftxcGRs0iww1JAAHBx_gPhq0WXgn5Iry5TlJSLD3z8ytjDJbsNUdVlrWaXEmzpqQ5yhujjOFPgoCVL63rFPkJsJnWAffxx5GVKW3FNDfziklj9GcFgxF0aQbH3IHW3p927xEHpDiW4aqGE98SojQCXLJdOiYAsQV_NY2nlAcgh9_Fnqpt1vKrvG-uEDMX/s1554/tide3.png"><img data-original-height="1554" data-original-width="1186" height="640" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEiftxcGRs0iww1JAAHBx_gPhq0WXgn5Iry5TlJSLD3z8ytjDJbsNUdVlrWaXEmzpqQ5yhujjOFPgoCVL63rFPkJsJnWAffxx5GVKW3FNDfziklj9GcFgxF0aQbH3IHW3p927xEHpDiW4aqGE98SojQCXLJdOiYAsQV_NY2nlAcgh9_Fnqpt1vKrvG-uEDMX/w488-h640/tide3.png" width="488"></a>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              "M" indicates mass relative to Earth and "Q" indicates dissipation
              factor; assuming an Earthlike composition, the 0.1 M planet has
              49% Earth's radius and the 10 M planet has 179%.<br>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <br></span>
  </p>
  <p><span>Altogether, combinations of these factors give us a pretty wide grey zone
      where tidal-locking <i>may</i>&nbsp;occur depending on the particulars of
      the planet in question&nbsp;</span><span>(and this is all based on a fairly simplistic model of tidal-locking;
      more detailed modelling can&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.semanticscholar.org/paper/Tidal-locking-of-habitable-exoplanets-Barnes/b28e84a87b58e4d6e0aba43923c35c7138322963">complicate matters further</a><span><span><sup>24</sup></span></span><span></span><span>).</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span><p><a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEj7bsEpoM8XZyA1d8xgHa8R46lffHs_3vON1T9km9beFgdgs2Z9buOLdz7cFDxtu56ztMCMK9QSxI_kl0Ec5SsNO3xmnobiMy0fSLAZtqt2uiUMPFXFrnABjYD20kfVx8pktFHkghVG06MmtxXWktg_LTflE2pPxIaEv2AITH4iXyS8mrBdlxKyVp1FZ4km/s1186/tide4.png"><img data-original-height="777" data-original-width="1186" height="420" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEj7bsEpoM8XZyA1d8xgHa8R46lffHs_3vON1T9km9beFgdgs2Z9buOLdz7cFDxtu56ztMCMK9QSxI_kl0Ec5SsNO3xmnobiMy0fSLAZtqt2uiUMPFXFrnABjYD20kfVx8pktFHkghVG06MmtxXWktg_LTflE2pPxIaEv2AITH4iXyS8mrBdlxKyVp1FZ4km/w640-h420/tide4.png" width="640"></a></p></span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>This still leaves a significant range of stars below around 2/3 the sun's
      mass where tidal-locking seems inevitable across at least part of the
      habitable zone, but there are more complex factors that may play into
      that, which brings us to...</span>
  </p>
  <p>
    <h3>
      <span>Maybe Planets Won't Tidal-Lock<br></span>
    </h3>
  </p>
  <p><span>This isn't a widespread claim but it has started appearing lately in
      response to a couple recent papers investigating how additional tidal
      influences might prevent tidal-locking of planets that<span>—</span>based on the sort of simple modelling we went over above<span>—we would expect to lock otherwise.</span></span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span><span>First is a
        <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1502.01952.pdf">2015 paper</a></span></span><span><span><sup>24</sup></span></span><span></span><span><span> modelling the influence of a planet's thermal tide, a bulging of
        its atmosphere due to thermal expansion by day, and finding that in some
        cases it could act against the influence of the gravitational tides to
        prevent full tidal-locking, instead settling a planet into rotation
        slightly faster or slower than 1:1 resonance. The implications have
        seemingly been a bit garbled in interpretation; I've heard it claimed
        that the paper implies that any planet with an atmosphere will avoid
        tidal-locking around stars more than 1/4 the sun's mass, but the paper
        itself claims that an atmosphere 10 times denser than Earth's could
        prevent tidal locking for planets in the outer edge of the habitable
        zone of stars about 28% the sun's mass, but a more Earthlike atmosphere
        likely wouldn't stop tidal-locking near the inner HZ edge even for stars
        almost 70% the sun's mass.</span></span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span><table>
        <tbody>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhkP3rvZKUGgR-0WF0tmHEikKEdMUFxqiP6q-h10hpm55VCftdknP97BmnYGEJEhyphenhyphenB5FqNFJUIMs8jg-_Sih2Co5d7Nic-Sf6Gq3TSzbqL6150G1_PZhlh6xPFmjgOvWxICJTASrED7suEdkAHQpppf4WolMJc1krzbHhyphenhyphenNB0CxfV2nk_PJTbegE_NTqnHD/s602/Screenshot%202024-01-24%20141139.png"><img data-original-height="583" data-original-width="602" height="388" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEhkP3rvZKUGgR-0WF0tmHEikKEdMUFxqiP6q-h10hpm55VCftdknP97BmnYGEJEhyphenhyphenB5FqNFJUIMs8jg-_Sih2Co5d7Nic-Sf6Gq3TSzbqL6150G1_PZhlh6xPFmjgOvWxICJTASrED7suEdkAHQpppf4WolMJc1krzbHhyphenhyphenNB0CxfV2nk_PJTbegE_NTqnHD/w400-h388/Screenshot%202024-01-24%20141139.png" width="400"></a>
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Limits at which thermal tides prevent tidal-locking for different
              atmospheric pressures (10 bar, 1 bar, and a Venus-like atmosphere
              of ~100 bar); you can see there's a nonlinear relationship between
              atmosphere and tidal-locking tendency. Dots are known exoplanets.
              <a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/1502.01952.pdf">Leconte et al. 2015</a><span><span><sup>25</sup></span></span>
            </td>
          </tr>
        </tbody>
      </table>
      <span><br></span></span>
  </p>
  <p><span>Finer complexities like the planet's climate (affecting the thermal
      tides) and ocean geometry (affecting the gravitational tides) likely have
      an influence as well, and could perhaps allow for a planet to resist
      tidal-locking for a period of its history only to fall into it later
      on.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>A more
      <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/472/3/3217/4082845">recent</a></span><span><span><sup>26</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/488/4/5739/5542728">set</a></span><span><span><sup>27</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/524/4/5708/7230370">of</a></span><span><span><sup>28</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/2041-8213/acbd33/meta">papers</a></span><span><span><sup>29</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      has examined the tidal influence of multiple planets on each other in
      tightly-packed systems such as TRAPPIST-1. In these cases it seems that,
      though a planet may tidal-lock initially, the competing influences may
      cause chaotic shifts between synchronous and non-synchronous rotation, and
      substantial drift of the planet's orientation even when close to
      synchronous. Because such tightly-packed systems are expected to be common
      for small stars, this might indicate that such irregular rotation is the
      norm, rather than perfect tidal-locking. But the TRAPPIST-1 system is an
      extreme case, being near the minimum size for a main sequence star and so
      having its planets in very close orbits, with quite a few planets packed
      closely together even for a star of its type</span><span>—</span><span>the closest approach between the two innermost planets is less than twice
      the distance from the Earth to the Moon. For a more moderate case, say, a
      planet pair orbiting a star half the sun's mass, these chaotic
      interactions
      <a href="https://academic.oup.com/mnras/article/472/3/3217/4082845">can still occur</a></span><span><span><sup>26</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      but it seems to take a substantially larger neighboring planet orbiting
      quite close in something near to an orbital resonance. Planets in more
      loosely packed systems (or completely alone) could still experience tidal
      locking around any of these stars.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>Still, because this mechanism is strongest for the smallest stars, it
      neatly fills the gaps left by the other mechanisms that could prevent
      tidal-locking; there is, it seems no range of stellar masses for which
      perfect 1:1 synchronous rotation is the only guaranteed outcome for
      habitable-zone planets, nor is there a specific range beyond which
      tidal-locking is forbidden, though the overall trends definitely still
      favor more frequent tidal-locking for smaller stars.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>Besides these new proposals, it's been known for some time that planets
      with some initial orbital eccentricity
      <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0019103507003077">could end up</a></span><span><span><sup>30</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      locked into various other types of spin-orbit resonances, giving them a
      more regular day and night cycle</span><span>—though a quite slow one. Such resonances aren't necessarily as stable,
      though; in the habitable zones of the smallest stars, they could be
      accompanied by
      <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.3847/1538-4357/aab845">intense tidal heating</a></span><span><span><sup>31</sup></span></span><span></span><span>, enough to partially melt their interiors and alter their tidal dynamics
      enough to break the resonance and settle into the more typical 1:1
      resonance.</span>
  </p>
  
  <p><span>As mentioned, a large, close-orbiting moon could also outcompete a star's
      influence and force the planet to tidal-lock to it rather than the star,
      giving the planet more regular days and nights. However, in any such case
      the overall interactions between star, planet, and moon will cause the
      moon's orbit to migrate towards or away from the planet (more likely the
      latter for the mutually tidal-locked state), and the moon can only migrate
      so far before escaping the planet's orbit or falling below its Roche limit
      and breaking apart. The closer the planet to the star and the stronger the
      tidal forces involved, the quicker this will happen, so Earthlike
      habitable-zone planets orbiting stars less than about half the sun's mass
      <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160910022520id_/http://barnesos.net/publications/papers/2014.03.IJA.Sasaki.LongevityofMoonsaroundHabitablePlanets.pdf">are unlikely</a></span><span><span><sup>32</sup></span></span><span></span><span>
      to be able to retain a moon for as long as Earth's current age.</span>
  </p>
  
  <table>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>
          <a href="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgoq2Rz8qGEGtT0KO3uu2N9SNs_L5t0sQSFZdHPwlOGMQ5cRs4dJ2cbqynGwWFfMrcpsCrBdiQMydVxxqu3DOiYoZFXJJrdsP5Hj0dFSD4B4wi-0GJpCHX-L9Z5JdYv7QmM7NDlq7im_ahgaVfu2IOcnJDi6UfXxlyaBiILwGJ7xVOTKeIqL1kqBgix2xE7/s578/moon%20limit.png"><img data-original-height="402" data-original-width="578" height="446" src="https://blogger.googleusercontent.com/img/b/R29vZ2xl/AVvXsEgoq2Rz8qGEGtT0KO3uu2N9SNs_L5t0sQSFZdHPwlOGMQ5cRs4dJ2cbqynGwWFfMrcpsCrBdiQMydVxxqu3DOiYoZFXJJrdsP5Hj0dFSD4B4wi-0GJpCHX-L9Z5JdYv7QmM7NDlq7im_ahgaVfu2IOcnJDi6UfXxlyaBiILwGJ7xVOTKeIqL1kqBgix2xE7/w640-h446/moon%20limit.png" width="640"></a>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          Rough limits for where planets in Earthlike habitable orbits can
          retain moons of varying composition for at least 5 billion years. <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20160910022520id_/http://barnesos.net/publications/papers/2014.03.IJA.Sasaki.LongevityofMoonsaroundHabitablePlanets.pdf">Sasaki and Barnes 2014</a><span><span><sup>32</sup></span></span></td>
        <td><br></td>
        <td><br></td>
        <td><br></td>
        <td><br></td>
        <td><br></td>
        <td><br></td>
        <td>&nbsp;</td>
        <td>&nbsp;</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</div><h3><span><span><span face="&quot;arial&quot; , sans-serif"><a href="https://www.patreon.com/worldbuildingpasta">Buy me a cup of tea (on Patreon)</a> <br></span></span></span></h3><p><span><span>1 Colose, C. M., Haqq-Misra, J., Wolf, E. T., Del Genio, A. D., Barnes, R., Way, M. J., &amp; Ruedy, R. (2021). Effects of Spin–Orbit Resonances and Tidal Heating on the Inner Edge of the Habitable Zone. The Astrophysical Journal, 921(1), 25.<br>2 Joshi, M. M., Haberle, R. M., &amp; Reynolds, R. T. (1997). Simulations of the atmospheres of synchronously rotating terrestrial planets orbiting M dwarfs: conditions for atmospheric collapse and the implications for habitability. Icarus, 129(2), 450-465.<br>3 Haqq-Misra, J., Wolf, E. T., Joshi, M., Zhang, X., &amp; Kopparapu, R. K. (2018). Demarcating circulation regimes of synchronously rotating terrestrial planets within the habitable zone. The Astrophysical Journal, 852(2), 67.<br>4 Boutle, I. A., Mayne, N. J., Drummond, B., Manners, J., Goyal, J., Lambert, F. H., ... &amp; Earnshaw, P. D. (2017). Exploring the climate of Proxima b with the Met Office Unified Model. Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, 601, A120.<br>5 Yang, J., Cowan, N. B., &amp; Abbot, D. S. (2013). Stabilizing cloud feedback dramatically expands the habitable zone of tidally locked planets. The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 771(2), L45.<br>6 Dole, S. H. (1970). Habitable planets for man. American Elsevier Publishing Company.<br>7 Cohen, M. (1981). Stellar influences on the emergence of intelligent life. In In: Life in the universe; Proceedings of the Conference, Moffett Field, CA, June 19, 20, 1979.(A82-22976 09-55) Cambridge, MA, MIT Press, 1981, p. 115-118. (Vol. 2156, pp. 115-118).<br>8 Stevenson, D. S., &amp; Stevenson, D. S. (2019). Atmospheric Circulation and Climate. Red Dwarfs: Their Geological, Chemical, and Biological Potential for Life, 171-218.<br>9 Kasting, J. F. (1996). Planetary atmosphere evolution: Do other habitable planets exist and can we detect them?. Astrophysics and space science, 241, 3-24.<br>10 Merlis, T. M., &amp; Schneider, T. (2010). Atmospheric dynamics of Earth‐like tidally locked Aquaplanets. Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems, 2(4).<br>11 Yang, J., Liu, Y., Hu, Y., &amp; Abbot, D. S. (2014). Water trapping on tidally locked terrestrial planets requires special conditions. The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 796(2), L22.<br>12 Hu, Y., &amp; Yang, J. (2014). Role of ocean heat transport in climates of tidally locked exoplanets around M dwarf stars. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 111(2), 629-634.<br>13 Checlair, J. H., Olson, S. L., Jansen, M. F., &amp; Abbot, D. S. (2019). No snowball on habitable tidally locked planets with a dynamic ocean. The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 884(2), L46.<br>14 Sergeev, D. E., Lambert, F. H., Mayne, N. J., Boutle, I. A., Manners, J., &amp; Kohary, K. (2020). Atmospheric convection plays a key role in the climate of tidally locked terrestrial exoplanets: Insights from high-resolution simulations. The Astrophysical Journal, 894(2), 84.<br>15 Hu, Y. (2015). Exo-oceanography, climate, and habitability of tidal-locking exoplanets in the habitable zone of M dwarfs. IAU General Assembly, 29, 2245847.<br>16 Tarter, J. C., Backus, P. R., Mancinelli, R. L., Aurnou, J. M., Backman, D. E., Basri, G. S., ... &amp; Young, R. E. (2007). A reappraisal of the habitability of planets around M dwarf stars. Astrobiology, 7(1), 30-65.<br>17 Leconte, J., Forget, F., Charnay, B., Wordsworth, R., Selsis, F., Millour, E., &amp; Spiga, A. (2013). 3D climate modeling of close-in land planets: circulation patterns, climate moist bistability, and habitability. Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, 554, A69.<br>18 Sasaki, T., Barnes, J. W., &amp; O'Brien, D. P. (2012). Outcomes and duration of tidal evolution in a star–planet–moon system. The Astrophysical Journal, 754(1), 51.<br>19 Millholland, S. (2023, September). Spin Dynamics of Planets in Resonant Chains: An Abundance of High Obliquities. In AAS/Division of Dynamical Astronomy Meeting (Vol. 55, No. 5, pp. 401-05).<br>20 Wang, Y., Liu, Y., Tian, F., Hu, Y., &amp; Huang, Y. (2017). Effects of eccentricity on climates and habitability of terrestrial exoplanets around M dwarfs. arXiv preprint arXiv:1710.01405.<br>21 Kasting, J. F., Whitmire, D. P., &amp; Reynolds, R. T. (1993). Habitable zones around main sequence stars. Icarus, 101(1), 108-128.<br>22 Zsom, A., Seager, S., De Wit, J., &amp; Stamenković, V. (2013). Toward the minimum inner edge distance of the habitable zone. The Astrophysical Journal, 778(2), 109.<br>23 Ramirez, R. M., &amp; Kaltenegger, L. (2017). A volcanic hydrogen habitable zone. The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 837(1), L4.<br>24 Barnes, R. (2017). Tidal locking of habitable exoplanets. Celestial Mechanics and Dynamical Astronomy, 129, 509-536.<br>25 Leconte, J., Wu, H., Menou, K., &amp; Murray, N. (2015). Asynchronous rotation of Earth-mass planets in the habitable zone of lower-mass stars. Science, 347(6222), 632-635.<br>26 Vinson, A. M., &amp; Hansen, B. M. (2017). On the spin states of habitable zone exoplanets around M dwarfs: the effect of a near-resonant companion. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 472(3), 3217-3229.<br>27 Vinson, A. M., Tamayo, D., &amp; Hansen, B. M. (2019). The chaotic nature of TRAPPIST-1 planetary spin states. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 488(4), 5739-5747.<br>28 Shakespeare, C. J., &amp; Steffen, J. H. (2023). Day and night: habitability of tidally locked planets with sporadic rotation. Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, 524(4), 5708-5724.<br>29 Chen, H., Li, G., Paradise, A., &amp; Kopparapu, R. K. (2023). Sporadic Spin-orbit Variations in Compact Multiplanet Systems and Their Influence on Exoplanet Climate. The Astrophysical Journal Letters, 946(2), L32.<br>30 Dobrovolskis, A. R. (2007). Spin states and climates of eccentric exoplanets. Icarus, 192(1), 1-23.<br>31 Makarov, V. V., Berghea, C. T., &amp; Efroimsky, M. (2018). Spin-orbital tidal dynamics and tidal heating in the TRAPPIST-1 multiplanet system. The Astrophysical Journal, 857(2), 142.<br>32 Sasaki, T., &amp; Barnes, J. W. (2014). Longevity of moons around habitable planets. International Journal of Astrobiology, 13(4), 324-336.</span></span></p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Source Code for Area 51 (2005) by Midway Studios Austin Found at Garage Sale (131 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/ProjectDreamland/area51</link>
            <guid>39629213</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 14:07:53 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/ProjectDreamland/area51">https://github.com/ProjectDreamland/area51</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39629213">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Area 51 (2005) Source Code Release</h2><a id="user-content-area-51-2005-source-code-release" aria-label="Permalink: Area 51 (2005) Source Code Release" href="#area-51-2005-source-code-release"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Welcome to the unofficial release of the Area 51 (2005) video game source code! This project aims to resurrect and preserve a piece of early 2000s video game history for enthusiasts, historians, and developers alike. Below is a brief overview of the source code details, its origin, and guidance on how the community can help bring this game into the modern era.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Historical Overview of Area 51</h2><a id="user-content-historical-overview-of-area-51" aria-label="Permalink: Historical Overview of Area 51" href="#historical-overview-of-area-51"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Initial Release</strong>: Area 51 was originally released on April 25, 2005, for PC, PS2, and Xbox. It has become a memorable cult classic.</li>
<li><strong>Air Force Sponsorship</strong>: In a unique turn of events, the game was sponsored by the United States Air Force and released as freeware for PC.</li>
<li><strong>Abandonware Status</strong>: Despite the game's initial success and the novel sponsorship, it eventually fell into obscurity, becoming abandonware. The game's support and distribution were discontinued, leaving it in a state where it was difficult for fans to access or play on modern systems.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Source Code Snapshot Details</h2><a id="user-content-source-code-snapshot-details" aria-label="Permalink: Source Code Snapshot Details" href="#source-code-snapshot-details"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Snapshot Date</strong>: The source code is a snapshot from 2005-03-31 10:40:19, just before the game's official release.</li>
<li><strong>Discovery</strong>: It was found at a garage sale of a former THQ developer.</li>
<li><strong>Contents</strong>: This release includes the source code for the Entropy engine, game logic, and targets for PC, PS2, Xbox, and an early version for GameCube. Additionally, debug symbols for various platforms are available in the release. Assets are not included, but those can be recovered from the retail game files.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">How to Contribute</h2><a id="user-content-how-to-contribute" aria-label="Permalink: How to Contribute" href="#how-to-contribute"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The main goal is to get the source code into a buildable state on modern systems. Whether you're interested in game development, historical preservation, or simply a fan of Area 51, here's how you can help:</p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li><strong>Building the Project</strong>: Assistance is needed to compile and run the game on contemporary hardware. If you have experience with game development, legacy systems, or cross-platform development, your expertise is invaluable.</li>
<li><strong>Documentation and Research</strong>: Insights into the original development environment, including compilers, libraries, and tools, would greatly assist the restoration effort.</li>
<li><strong>Debugging and Porting</strong>: Once buildable, the project will require debugging and potentially porting to newer platforms to reach a wider audience.</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting Started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting Started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">To contribute, please fork the repository, make your changes, and submit a pull request with your updates. For discussion, collaboration, and support, join our community on platforms like Discord or participate in GitHub Discussions for this project.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Releases</h2><a id="user-content-releases" aria-label="Permalink: Releases" href="#releases"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://github.com/ProjectDreamland/area51/releases/">Here</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Eloquent JavaScript 4th edition (2024) (722 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://eloquentjavascript.net/</link>
            <guid>39629044</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 13:52:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://eloquentjavascript.net/">https://eloquentjavascript.net/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39629044">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="cover">

  <p>
    <a href="https://nostarch.com/ejs3">
      <img src="https://eloquentjavascript.net/img/cover.jpg" alt="Cover image">
    </a>
  </p>

  <h2>Eloquent JavaScript<p>4th edition (2024)</p></h2>

  <p>This is a book about JavaScript, programming, and the wonders of
  the digital. You can read it online here, or buy your own
  <a href="https://nostarch.com/ejs3">paperback copy</a> (3rd edition).</p>

  <p>Written by Marijn Haverbeke.</p>

  <div>
  <p>Licensed under
  a <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">Creative
  Commons attribution-noncommercial license</a>. All code in this book
  may also be considered licensed under
  an <a href="https://eloquentjavascript.net/code/LICENSE">MIT license</a>.</p>

  <p>Illustrations by various artists: Cover
  by <a href="http://www.pechane.com/">Péchane Sumi-e</a>. Chapter
  illustrations by <a href="http://madalinatantareanu.com/">Madalina
  Tantareanu</a>. Pixel art in Chapters 7 and 16 by Antonio Perdomo
  Pastor. Regular expression diagrams in Chapter 9 generated
  with <a href="https://regexper.com/">regexper.com</a> by Jeff
  Avallone. Village photograph in Chapter 11 by Fabrice Creuzot. Game
  concept for Chapter 16 by <a href="http://lessmilk.com/">Thomas
  Palef</a>.</p>
  </div>

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ex-Google engineer charged with stealing AI trade secrets (257 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://apnews.com/article/china-google-justice-department-63156ade1e564d15d92adbef91e9c5da</link>
            <guid>39628842</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 13:33:46 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://apnews.com/article/china-google-justice-department-63156ade1e564d15d92adbef91e9c5da">https://apnews.com/article/china-google-justice-department-63156ade1e564d15d92adbef91e9c5da</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39628842">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
                                        <p>WASHINGTON (AP) — A former software engineer at Google has been charged with stealing artificial intelligence trade secrets from the company while secretly working with two companies based in China, the Justice Department said Wednesday.</p><p>Linwei Ding, a Chinese national, was arrested in Newark, California, on four counts of federal trade secret theft, each punishable by up to 10 years in prison.</p><p>The case against Ding, 38, was announced at an American Bar Association conference in San Francisco by Attorney General Merrick Garland, who along with other law enforcement leaders has repeatedly warned about the threat of Chinese economic espionage and about the national security concerns posed by advancements in artificial intelligence and other developing technologies.</p><p>“Today’s charges are the latest illustration of the lengths affiliates of companies based in the People’s Republic of China are willing to go to steal American innovation,” FBI Director Christopher Wray said in a statement. “The theft of innovative technology and trade secrets from American companies can cost jobs and have devastating economic and national security consequences.”</p>




    

<p>Google said it had determined that the employee had stolen “numerous documents” and referred the matter to law enforcement.</p><p>“We have strict safeguards to prevent the theft of our confidential commercial information and trade secrets,” Google spokesman Jose Castaneda said in a statement. “After an investigation, we found that this employee stole numerous documents, and we quickly referred the case to law enforcement. We are grateful to the FBI for helping protect our information and will continue cooperating with them closely.” </p>
    
<p>A lawyer listed as Ding’s defense attorney had no comment Wednesday evening.</p><p>Artificial intelligence is the main battleground for competitors in the field of high technology, and the question of who dominates can have major commercial and security implications. Justice Department leaders in recent weeks have been sounding alarms about how foreign adversaries could harness AI technologies to negatively affect the United States.</p>
    

<p>Deputy Attorney General Lisa Monaco said in a speech last month that the administration’s multi-agency Disruptive Technology Strike Force would place AI at the top of its enforcement priority list, and <span><a data-gtm-enhancement-style="LinkEnhancementA" href="https://apnews.com/article/fbi-election-interference-wray-2024-campaign-ai-a0c4a95c818839b18f919c6d648c4dcf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wray told a conference last week</a></span> that AI and other emerging technologies had made it easier for adversaries to try to interfere with the American political process.</p><p>Garland echoed those concerns at the San Francisco event, saying Wednesday that, “As with all evolving technologies, (AI) has pluses and minuses, advantages and disadvantages, great promise and the risk of great harm.”</p><p>The indictment unsealed Wednesday in the Northern District of California alleges that Ding, who was hired by Google in 2019 and had access to confidential information about the company’s supercomputing data centers, began uploading hundreds of files into a personal Google Cloud account two years ago.</p><p>Within weeks of the theft starting, prosecutors say, Ding was offered the position of chief technology officer at an early-stage technology company in China that touted its use of AI technology and that offered him a monthly salary of about $14,800, plus an annual bonus and company stock. The indictment says Ding traveled to China and participated in investor meetings at the company and sought to raise capital for it. </p>
    

<p>He also separately founded and served as chief executive of a China-based startup company that aspired to train “large AI models powered by supercomputing chips,” the indictment said. </p><p>Prosecutors say Ding did not disclose either affiliation to Google, which described him Wednesday as a junior employee.</p><p>He resigned from Google last Dec. 26. </p><p>Three days later, Google officials learned that he had presented as CEO of one of the Chinese companies at an investor conference in Beijing. Officials also reviewed surveillance footage showing that another employee had scanned Ding’s access badge at the Google building in the U.S. where he worked to make it look like Ding was there during times when he was actually in China, the indictment says.</p>
    

<p>Google suspended Ding’s network access and locked his laptop, and discovered his unauthorized uploads while searching his network activity history. </p><p>The FBI in January served a search warrant at Ding’s home and seized his electronic devices, and later executed an additional warrant for the contents of his personal accounts containing more than 500 unique files of confidential information that authorities say he stole from Google.</p>
                                    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Flyde – an open-source visual programming language (216 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde</link>
            <guid>39628285</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 12:33:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde">https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39628285">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
    <a href="https://www.flyde.dev/" rel="nofollow">
    <img src="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde/assets/3727015/eb1afa4a-0887-4cf2-99b5-35d4f1f6ee2a" height="40">
    </a>
</h2><a id="user-content-------------" aria-label="Permalink: " href="#------------"></a></div>
<p dir="auto">
    <i>Visual Programming. For Developers.</i> Open-source, runs in <strong>VS Code</strong>.<br>Integrates with existing <strong>TypeScript</strong> code, browser and Node.js.
</p>

<p><a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/3727015/310876162-5d2d917b-48f6-49db-a1a9-e7fe685c408f.gif?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk4MzExMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTgzMDgwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8zNzI3MDE1LzMxMDg3NjE2Mi01ZDJkOTE3Yi00OGY2LTQ5ZGItYTFhOS1lN2ZlNjg1YzQwOGYuZ2lmP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDMwNyUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDAzMDdUMTcwMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZjI5ZjM5NGRiMzZiY2M5ZTM3MzE5YzcxN2RlNzUxNzEzYWEyYTNmYjk0ZTkxMjQ0YzdhZDkwMTdmMzliYjBhYiZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.-FrE-Uw6VuABwGwmQElQh15_aMxfU6RfwB076wu75VE"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/3727015/310876162-5d2d917b-48f6-49db-a1a9-e7fe685c408f.gif?jwt=eyJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiIsInR5cCI6IkpXVCJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3MDk4MzExMDQsIm5iZiI6MTcwOTgzMDgwNCwicGF0aCI6Ii8zNzI3MDE1LzMxMDg3NjE2Mi01ZDJkOTE3Yi00OGY2LTQ5ZGItYTFhOS1lN2ZlNjg1YzQwOGYuZ2lmP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI0MDMwNyUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNDAzMDdUMTcwMDA0WiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9ZjI5ZjM5NGRiMzZiY2M5ZTM3MzE5YzcxN2RlNzUxNzEzYWEyYTNmYjk0ZTkxMjQ0YzdhZDkwMTdmMzliYjBhYiZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QmYWN0b3JfaWQ9MCZrZXlfaWQ9MCZyZXBvX2lkPTAifQ.-FrE-Uw6VuABwGwmQElQh15_aMxfU6RfwB076wu75VE" data-animated-image=""></a>
</p>
<div dir="auto"><h5 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">
<p dir="auto"><strong>VSCode Extension ✔️</strong> · <strong>Runtime Library ✔️</strong> · <strong>Integrates with Existing Code ✔️</strong>
<br>
<strong>Rich Standard Library ✔️</strong> · <strong>Visual Debugger ✔️</strong> · <strong>TypeScript Support ✔️</strong></p>
</h5><a id="user-content-vscode-extension-️--runtime-library-️--integrates-with-existing-code-️rich-standard-library-️--visual-debugger-️--typescript-support-️" aria-label="Permalink: VSCode Extension ✔️ · Runtime Library ✔️ · Integrates with Existing Code ✔️Rich Standard Library ✔️ · Visual Debugger ✔️ · TypeScript Support ✔️" href="#vscode-extension-️--runtime-library-️--integrates-with-existing-code-️rich-standard-library-️--visual-debugger-️--typescript-support-️"></a></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Introduction</h2><a id="user-content-introduction" aria-label="Permalink: Introduction" href="#introduction"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><code>Flyde</code> is an open-source visual programming language built to integrate with your existing codebase. It allows you to create and run visual programs and is designed to complement and enhance traditional textual coding, not to replace it. It includes a <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=flyde.flyde-vscode" rel="nofollow">VSCode extension</a>, seamlessly integrates with existing TypeScript/JavaScript code and runs on Node.js and in the browser.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick Start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick Start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Playground</h3><a id="user-content-playground" aria-label="Permalink: Playground" href="#playground"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The easiest way to experiment with Flyde is to visit the <a href="https://flyde.dev/playground" rel="nofollow">online playground</a>, which allows you to create and run flows in the browser.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Running locally</h3><a id="user-content-running-locally" aria-label="Permalink: Running locally" href="#running-locally"></a></p>
<ol dir="auto">
<li>Install the <a href="https://marketplace.visualstudio.com/items?itemName=flyde.flyde-vscode" rel="nofollow">VSCode extension</a></li>
<li><code>mkdir my-flyde-project &amp;&amp; cd my-flyde-project</code></li>
<li>Open your project in VSCode</li>
<li>Command Palette (Ctrl+Shift+P) -&gt; <code>Flyde: New visual flow</code></li>
<li>Check out the <a href="https://www.flyde.dev/docs/integrate-flows" rel="nofollow">Integrating with Existing Code</a> guide to learn how to integrate your flows with your code</li>
</ol>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Who is Flyde for?</h2><a id="user-content-who-is-flyde-for" aria-label="Permalink: Who is Flyde for?" href="#who-is-flyde-for"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>For Novice Developers and Non-Technical Users:</strong> Flyde offers a welcoming entry point into programming by simplifying the creation and management of applications. It allows those new to development, or from non-technical roles, to construct complex logic through a visual interface. By transforming intricate code concepts into accessible, visual blocks, Flyde makes programming more intuitive and approachable.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>For Team Collaboration Across Roles:</strong> Flyde fosters a collaborative environment that transcends technical barriers. It is a tool that empowers team members like product managers and data engineers to contribute directly to the codebase. Through visual programming, Flyde turns business logic and data processes into shared projects that everyone can contribute to and understand, thus democratizing innovation.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>For Educators in Programming:</strong> Flyde is a compelling resource for educators aiming to provide hands-on, practical programming education. It's a tool that blends the ease of visual learning with the robustness of real-world programming concepts, making it a valuable addition to any curriculum that seeks to engage students in the fundamentals of coding through an interactive and visually driven experience.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto"><strong>For Seasoned Developers</strong> Even experienced developers can benefit from Flyde's visual approach to building APIs and microservices. It offers a new dimension of efficiency, enabling seasoned professionals to design, prototype, and manage their services visually while retaining the flexibility and power of traditional coding. Flyde's open-source nature invites extension and customization, and for those seeking a managed cloud solution, <a href="https://www.trigg.dev/?ref=readme" rel="nofollow">Trigg.dev</a> provides a commercial platform with robust, cloud-hosted capabilities.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">And many more!</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Flyde is an open-source project. We are committed to a fully transparent development process and highly appreciate any contributions. Whether you are helping us fix bugs, proposing new features, improving our documentation, or spreading the word - we would love to have you as a part of the Flyde community. Please refer to our <a href="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde/blob/main/CONTRIBUTING.md">contribution guidelines</a> and <a href="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde/blob/main/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md">code of conduct</a>.</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>
<p dir="auto">Bug Report: If you see an error message or encounter an issue while using Flyde, please create a <a href="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=type%3A+bug&amp;template=bug.yaml&amp;title=%F0%9F%90%9B+Bug+Report%3A+">bug report</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Feature Request: If you have an idea or if there is a capability that is missing, please submit a <a href="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde/issues/new?assignees=&amp;labels=type%3A+feature+request&amp;template=feature.yml">feature request</a>.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p dir="auto">Documentation Request: If you're reading the Flyde docs and feel like you're missing something, please submit a <a href="https://github.com/flydelabs/flyde/issues/new">documentation request</a>.</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">Not sure where to start? Join our discord and we will help you get started!</p>
<a href="https://flyde.dev/discord" rel="nofollow">
    <img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/9a5b04ff1a89caefb5c78184944460860c456d4000b8efea79566ffbacd13697/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f646973636f72642d3732383964612e7376673f7374796c653d666c61742d737175617265266c6f676f3d646973636f7264" alt="discord" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/discord-7289da.svg?style=flat-square&amp;logo=discord">
  </a>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Learn more</h2><a id="user-content-learn-more" aria-label="Permalink: Learn more" href="#learn-more"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Check out the official website at <a href="https://flyde.dev/" rel="nofollow">https://flyde.dev</a> for more information.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Everything needed to run a Flyde file is <em>MIT-licensed</em>. That includes:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><code>@flyde/core</code></li>
<li><code>@flyde/resolver</code></li>
<li><code>@flyde/runtime</code></li>
<li><code>@flyde/stdlib</code></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">The UI library and other nodes of the toolkit are GNU AGPLv3 licensed.</p>
<p dir="auto">In other words, using Flyde flows in your software is permitted without any limitation. However, if you use Flyde's visual editor in your own work, it must be open-sourced as well. More about <a href="https://choosealicense.com/licenses/agpl-3.0/" rel="nofollow">GNU APGLv3</a> here</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[ECJ finds IAB Europe responsible for TCF consent spam popups across the Internet (142 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/european-court-of-justice-finds-iab-europe-responsible-for-tcf-consent-spam-popups-across-the-internet/</link>
            <guid>39627624</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 11:16:15 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/european-court-of-justice-finds-iab-europe-responsible-for-tcf-consent-spam-popups-across-the-internet/">https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/european-court-of-justice-finds-iab-europe-responsible-for-tcf-consent-spam-popups-across-the-internet/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39627624">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>


  
<p><strong>7 March 2024</strong></p>



<p><strong><em>Europe’s top court rules that IAB Europe is responsible under the GDPR for the “TCF” consent spam popups that appear on almost every website</em></strong> </p>



<p>Europe’s highest court today delivered a judgement about the consent spam popups that have plagued people for years all over the Internet in Europe. The Court has ruled that IAB Europe, a tracking industry association, is responsible under the GDPR for the “Transparency and Consent Framework” (TCF)  consent system. Google, Amazon, Microsoft, TikTok, and hundreds of other tracking-based online advertising companies rely on IAB Europe’s consent system, which Europe’s data protection authorities have already found to be in violation of the GDPR following our complaint.</p>



<p>IAB Europe commits multiple violations of the GDPR in its processing of personal data in the context of its TCF and the “Real-Time Bidding” (RTB) online advertising system. The TCF has been used to falsely legitimise the indiscriminate broadcasting of personal data of millions of people in Europe to companies everywhere, including to companies in China and Russia.<a id="_ftnref1" href="#_ftn1"><sup>[1]</sup></a> This happens 71 trillion times per year.<a id="_ftnref2" href="#_ftn2"><sup>[2]</sup></a></p>



<p>IAB Europe argued that it is not responsible under the GDPR as a “data controller” because it allegedly only sets the rules for how data should be used, but does not process the data itself. The Court rightly rejected this, and confirmed that IAB Europe, as management body for the TCF, is a “data controller” under the GDPR.</p>



<p>The Court’s ruling today shows just how broad the protection of people’s personal data is in Europe. The online tracking and advertising industry is surreptitiously collecting and broadcasting highly sensitive data about everyone who uses the internet. Today’s decision will force the industry to change profoundly. Google, Amazon, Microsoft, and so on can no longer evade their responsibilities by claiming that the data they use is not protected by the law.</p>



<p>“<em>People across Europe have been plagued by fake “consent” popups every day on almost every website and app since the GDPR was introduced almost six years ago</em>”, said Dr Johnny Ryan of ICCL Enforce. “<em>IAB Europe has sought to evade its responsibility for this charade. But the European Court of Justice has set it straight. This decision will not only end the biggest spam operation in history. It will deal a mortal wound to the online tracking-based advertising industry.</em>” </p>



<p><strong>The Court’s summary&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2024-03/cp240044en.pdf">https://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2024-03/cp240044en.pdf</a></p>



<p><strong>Background&nbsp;</strong></p>



<p>The questions answered by the Court today were posed complainants coordinated by Enforce, a unit of the Irish Council for Civil Liberties (ICCL). The group of complainants includes:&nbsp;Dr Johnny Ryan of <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/enforce/">Enforce</a>, Katarzyna Szymielewicz of the&nbsp;<a href="https://en.panoptykon.org/">Panoptykon Foundation</a> (Poland),&nbsp;<a href="https://www.bitsoffreedom.nl/">Stichting Bits of Freedom</a>&nbsp;(the Netherlands),&nbsp;<a href="https://www.liguedh.be/">Ligue des Droits Humains</a> (Belgium),&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/Jausl00s">Dr Jef Ausloos</a>, and&nbsp;<a href="https://twitter.com/PiDewitte">Dr Pierre Dewitte</a>. The ruling follows complaints about the insecurity of the online advertising “Real-Time Bidding” (RTB) system that Dr Ryan initiated in 2018.</p>



<p>On 2 February 2022 the Belgian Data Protection Authority, in agreement with 27 other EU data protection authorities, ruled that the “TCF” consent spam system is illegal.<a href="#_ftn3" id="_ftnref3"><sup>[3]</sup></a> This decision meant that the entire online advertising had unlawfully processed the data of everyone in Europe for years.</p>



<p>However, this was appealed at the Brussels Markets Court. First, IAB Europe appealed the substance of the decision, and the complainants appealed against part of its implementation. Questions that the complainants proposed were referred by the Brussels Markets Court to the European Court of Justice in September 2023.</p>



<p>The Brussels Markets Court can now proceed to rule on the matter with certainty that IAB Europe is indeed responsible, and that the data concerned are protected by the GDPR.</p>



<p>We wish to thank our lawyers, Frederic Debusseré and Ruben Roex of Timelex.</p>



<p>We are reading the decision in detail, and will publish our more detailed analysis at a later point.</p>



<p><strong>Full decision here:</strong></p>



<p><a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/fiche.jsf?id=C%3B604%3B22%3BRP%3B1%3BP%3B1%3BC2022%2F0604%2FP&amp;language=en">https://curia.europa.eu/juris/fiche.jsf?id=C%3B604%3B22%3BRP%3B1%3BP%3B1%3BC2022%2F0604%2FP&amp;language=en</a></p>



<p><strong>Contact</strong></p>



<p>For media queries: taragrace.connolly@iccl.ie +353 (0) 87 4157162</p>







<h2 id="h-notes">Notes </h2>



<p><a href="#_ftnref1" id="_ftn1">[1]</a> Europe’s Hidden Security Crisis, ICCL, 2023 (URL: <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/europes-hidden-security-crisis/">https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/europes-hidden-security-crisis/</a>), p. 8.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref2" id="_ftn2">[2]</a> Europe’s Hidden Security Crisis, ICCL, 2023 (URL: <a href="https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/europes-hidden-security-crisis/">https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/europes-hidden-security-crisis/</a>), p. 6.</p>



<p><a href="#_ftnref3" id="_ftn3">[3]</a> <a href="https://www.gegevensbeschermingsautoriteit.be/publications/beslissing-ten-gronde-nr.-21-2022-english.pdf">https://www.gegevensbeschermingsautoriteit.be/publications/beslissing-ten-gronde-nr.-21-2022-english.pdf</a></p>
  

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Beautiful SAR images of the ocean reveal shipping lanes, wind farms (241 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.datadesk.eco/p/sky-lapse-in-two-tone</link>
            <guid>39627443</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 10:48:39 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.datadesk.eco/p/sky-lapse-in-two-tone">https://blog.datadesk.eco/p/sky-lapse-in-two-tone</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39627443">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><article><div dir="auto"><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png" width="1456" height="861" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/cda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:861,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fcda47dba-ab0d-4275-af29-68ca9686b7c0_1474x872.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a><figcaption>2023 in the busy English Channel, where shipping lanes are clearly visible.</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>The </span><a href="https://www.esa.int/Applications/Observing_the_Earth/Copernicus/Sentinel-1" rel="">European Space Agency’s Sentinel-1</a><span> satellite paints a striking picture of our changing energy system at sea.</span></p><p><span>Sentinel-1 uses </span><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Synthetic-aperture_radar" rel="">synthetic-aperture radar,</a><span> which can detect objects at sea and through clouds, making offshore infrastructure and shipping lanes visible as constellations of sparkling white dots.</span></p><p>Our economy at sea has tended to be a blind spot for satellite imagery services, with the eyes in the sky taking much more interest in what is happening on land. The world’s most well-known satellite imagery service — Google Earth — does not serve pictures of the ocean at all, which just appears as a vast mass of fuzzy blue on the platform.</p><p><span>Yet the </span><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/d77fff4d-a9c6-4224-89fc-b3b08d1d833b" rel="">ocean economy is growing faster than the global economy</a><span>. Most of the international trade in fossil fuels still takes place over the sea —&nbsp;</span><a href="https://www.eia.gov/international/analysis/special-topics/World_Oil_Transit_Chokepoints" rel="">60% of the world’s oil production transits by sea</a><span>. It is also a key venue of the energy transition with the rapid expansion of offshore wind and with the seabed, which is also a </span><a href="https://www.reuters.com/graphics/MINING-DEEPSEA/CLIMATE/zjpqezqzlpx/" rel="">controversial new frontier for the mining of critical minerals</a><span>.</span></p><p><span>Inspired by some similar images shared by </span><a href="https://twitter.com/wallacetim" rel="">Tim Wallace</a><span> in 2020, we’ve created a series of black-and-white composite renderings of some of the points of flux in the global energy system. Created in </span><a href="https://earthengine.google.com/" rel="">Google Earth Engine</a><span>, these pictures are effectively annual timelapse images based on Sentinel-1’s radar, consisting of multiple snapshots taken by the satellite across 2023. Offshore wind farms, shipping lanes and oil and gas infrastructure glimmer like constellations of stars in a sea of black.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif" width="1057" height="733" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/e44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:733,&quot;width&quot;:1057,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_lossy/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fe44a26bf-f555-4370-9459-ed38e1e031f4_1057x733.gif 1456w" sizes="100vw"></picture></div></a><figcaption>The build-out of the massive Hornsea offshore wind farms (1 &amp; 2).</figcaption></figure></div><p>The North Sea now glitters with the world’s largest offshore wind farms. Often difficult to see clearly with non-commercial satellite imagery, Sentinel-1’s radar imaging picks out the turbines as matrices of fine white dots.</p><p><span>Hornsea 2, the world’s biggest offshore wind farm located off the Yorkshire coast, came online in August 2022. Alongside its sister project Hornsea 1, the cluster is made up of 339 windmills and covers an area of 335 square miles, it can provide enough electricity to power </span><a href="https://orsted.co.uk/energy-solutions/offshore-wind/our-wind-farms/hornsea2" rel="">2.4 million homes</a><span>. Sentinel-1 provides a beautiful picture of its growth.</span></p><p><span>Zooming out from Hornsea, you can see many other constellations off the East Coast of England, especially around the mouth of the Humber. </span><a href="https://renewables-map.robinhawkes.com/#8.01/53.689/0.955" rel="">Robin Hawkes has built a beautiful map</a><span> that lets you visualise the power generated by any of these farms at a given moment.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png" width="1033" height="594" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:594,&quot;width&quot;:1033,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:886771,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F9b52bfe9-71c6-4399-b140-d73bfe58229e_1033x594.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>2023 view of the Humber offshore wind cluster in the North Sea.</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Some of the other clusters of light are offshore oil and gas rigs — a fundamental but declining part of the North Sea economy. According to the </span><em><a href="https://www.ft.com/content/d77fff4d-a9c6-4224-89fc-b3b08d1d833b" rel="">Financial Times</a></em><span>, offshore wind turbines now exceed the number of oil platforms globally.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png" width="1456" height="734" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/d6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:734,&quot;width&quot;:1456,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fd6c7a6e9-eaec-423d-956e-d1cc0d6dc6df_1600x807.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Traces of tankers at Dörtyol across 2023 — how many were carrying forbidden Russian oil destined for Europe?</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>Dörtyol is a lesser-known oil port in Turkey and the transit point at the heart of our investigation with </span><a href="https://www.pogo.org/investigations/the-pentagon-is-buying-fuel-made-with-russian-oil" rel="">POGO</a><span> and </span><em><a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/business/2023/11/14/russian-oil-sanctions-us-greece-turkey/" rel="">The Washington Post</a></em><span> into the potential laundering of Russian oil  into European refineries, which supply both US and UK naval bases. Global crude oil, diesel, and gasoline flows have been reconfigured as Europe’s sanctions on Russian oil have bitten since their introduction in 2023. Some Russian hydrocarbon molecules have seemingly continued to flow into Europe but have taken more indirect routes via places like Dörtyol or </span><a href="https://energyandcleanair.org/publication/the-laundromat-how-the-price-cap-coalition-whitewashes-russian-oil-in-third-countries/" rel="">India’s Jamnagar refinery</a><span>.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png" width="837" height="507" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/fb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:507,&quot;width&quot;:837,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:null,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:null,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Ffb779f9a-95b3-47c8-8df9-a872028c4f1a_837x507.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Strait of Malacca in 2023.</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>One-third of the world’s seaborne crude oil and </span><a href="https://www.nippon-foundation.or.jp/en/what/projects/safe_passage" rel="">half of globally traded goods</a><span> move through the Strait of Malacca. The shipping lanes are intensely crowded, especially around Singapore, one of the world’s great trading hubs, and you can see them clearly in the radar imagery. </span><a href="https://www.transportenvironment.org/discover/broken-promise-how-enis-refineries-are-still-relying-on-palm-oil-based-products/" rel="">Our research with Transport &amp; Environment</a><span> tracked the movement of tankers carrying palm oil from Indonesia to European biofuel refineries that had supposedly phased out the controversial feedstock.</span></p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png" width="710" height="504" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:504,&quot;width&quot;:710,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:307981,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:true,&quot;topImage&quot;:false,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:null}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2F97dafec7-87d6-492a-9ba6-73837795e47f_710x504.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" loading="lazy"></picture></div></a><figcaption>Panama Canal with traces of vessels to the South (Pacific) and North (Atlantic).</figcaption></figure></div><p><span>You can make out a snake of white light through the Panama Canal, which connects the Atlantic and Pacific and through which, until recently, 13,000 to 14,000 vessels passed a year. Our friend, Seb over at </span><em><a href="https://www.energyflux.news/p/the-panama-paradox-us-lng-drought-gas-trade" rel="">Energy Flux</a></em><span>, has recently written about the droughts affecting the canal preventing the passage of LNG tankers and how these may ultimately lead to fragmentation of the global LNG market and lower LNG prices in Europe as the route to take American LNG to Asia becomes longer and more expensive.</span></p></div></article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: TinyWasm – A tiny WebAssembly Runtime written in Rust (149 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm</link>
            <guid>39627410</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 10:44:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm">https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39627410">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><div dir="auto">
    <p><a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/blob/main"><img src="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/raw/main/tinywasm.png" width="100px"></a>
    </p>
    <p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">TinyWasm</h2><a id="user-content-tinywasm" aria-label="Permalink: TinyWasm" href="#tinywasm"></a></p><p>
    A tiny WebAssembly Runtime written in Rust
</p></div>

<p dir="auto"><a href="https://docs.rs/tinywasm" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/1544f008877416cd01a38f3e153fc6294d9a32455812d402b1fd86f2cbfa18c8/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f646f637372732f74696e797761736d3f6c6f676f3d72757374" alt="docs.rs" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/docsrs/tinywasm?logo=rust"></a> <a href="https://crates.io/crates/tinywasm" rel="nofollow"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/9e48f97234ed02bbd6ea8901bfb3078376baba3686c4318e9c5fbf95dbcd6a30/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6372617465732f762f74696e797761736d2e7376673f6c6f676f3d72757374" alt="Crates.io" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/crates/v/tinywasm.svg?logo=rust"></a> <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/blob/main/LICENSE-APACHE"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/be7aa47174b229c7fb9aa8776fc50c591e255764a50adb16b351ccab7cf49e3c/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f6372617465732f6c2f74696e797761736d2e737667" alt="Crates.io" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/crates/l/tinywasm.svg"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why TinyWasm?</h2><a id="user-content-why-tinywasm" aria-label="Permalink: Why TinyWasm?" href="#why-tinywasm"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong>Tiny</strong>: TinyWasm is designed to be as small as possible without significantly compromising performance or functionality (&lt; 6000 lines of code).</li>
<li><strong>Portable</strong>: TinyWasm runs on any platform that Rust can target, including other WebAssembly Runtimes, with minimal external dependencies.</li>
<li><strong>Lightweight</strong>: TinyWasm is easy to integrate and has a low call overhead, making it suitable for scripting and embedding.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Status</h2><a id="user-content-status" aria-label="Permalink: Status" href="#status"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">As of version <code>0.3.0</code>, TinyWasm successfully passes all the WebAssembly 1.0 tests in the <a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/testsuite">WebAssembly Test Suite</a>. Work on the 2.0 tests is ongoing. This enables TinyWasm to run most WebAssembly programs, including executing TinyWasm itself compiled to WebAssembly (see <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/blob/main/examples/wasm-rust.rs">examples/wasm-rust.rs</a>). The results of the testsuites are available <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/tree/main/crates/tinywasm/tests/generated">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto">The API is still unstable and may change at any time, so you probably don't want to use it in production <em>yet</em>. TinyWasm isn't primarily designed for high performance; it focuses more on simplicity, size, and portability. More details on its performance can be found in <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/blob/main/BENCHMARKS.md">BENCHMARKS.md</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Future Development</strong>: The first major version will focus on improving the API and adding support for <a href="https://wasi.dev/" rel="nofollow">WASI</a>. While doing so, I also want to further simplify and reduce the codebase's size and improve the parser's performance.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Supported Proposals</h2><a id="user-content-supported-proposals" aria-label="Permalink: Supported Proposals" href="#supported-proposals"></a></p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Proposal</th>
<th>Implementation Status</th>
<th>Version</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/mutable-global/blob/master/proposals/mutable-global/Overview.md"><strong>Mutable Globals</strong></a></td>
<td>Fully implemented</td>
<td>0.2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/spec/blob/master/proposals/multi-value/Overview.md"><strong>Multi-value</strong></a></td>
<td>Fully implemented</td>
<td>0.2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/spec/blob/master/proposals/sign-extension-ops/Overview.md"><strong>Sign-extension operators</strong></a></td>
<td>Fully implemented</td>
<td>0.2.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/spec/blob/master/proposals/bulk-memory-operations/Overview.md"><strong>Bulk Memory Operations</strong></a></td>
<td>Fully implemented</td>
<td>0.4.0</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/reference-types/blob/master/proposals/reference-types/Overview.md"><strong>Reference Types</strong></a></td>
<td>Partially implemented</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/multi-memory/blob/master/proposals/multi-memory/Overview.md"><strong>Multiple Memories</strong></a></td>
<td>Partially implemented</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/memory64/blob/master/proposals/memory64/Overview.md"><strong>Memory64</strong></a></td>
<td>Partially implemented</td>
<td>N/A</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Usage</h2><a id="user-content-usage" aria-label="Permalink: Usage" href="#usage"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">TinyWasm can be used through the <code>tinywasm-cli</code> CLI tool or as a library in your Rust project. Documentation can be found <a href="https://docs.rs/tinywasm" rel="nofollow">here</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Library</h3><a id="user-content-library" aria-label="Permalink: Library" href="#library"></a></p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">CLI</h3><a id="user-content-cli" aria-label="Permalink: CLI" href="#cli"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">The CLI is mainly available for testing purposes, but can also be used to run WebAssembly programs.</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="$ cargo install tinywasm-cli
$ tinywasm-cli --help"><pre>$ cargo install tinywasm-cli
$ tinywasm-cli --help</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Feature Flags</h2><a id="user-content-feature-flags" aria-label="Permalink: Feature Flags" href="#feature-flags"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><strong><code>std</code></strong><br>
Enables the use of <code>std</code> and <code>std::io</code> for parsing from files and streams. This is enabled by default.</li>
<li><strong><code>logging</code></strong><br>
Enables logging using the <code>log</code> crate. This is enabled by default.</li>
<li><strong><code>parser</code></strong><br>
Enables the <code>tinywasm-parser</code> crate. This is enabled by default.</li>
<li><strong><code>archive</code></strong><br>
Enables pre-parsing of archives. This is enabled by default.</li>
<li><strong><code>unsafe</code></strong><br>
Uses <code>unsafe</code> code to improve performance, particularly in Memory access.</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">With all these features disabled, TinyWasm only depends on <code>core</code>, <code>alloc</code> ,and <code>libm</code> and can be used in <code>no_std</code> environments.
Since <code>libm</code> is not as performant as the compiler's math intrinsics, it is recommended to use the <code>std</code> feature if possible (at least <a href="https://github.com/rust-lang/rfcs/issues/2505" data-hovercard-type="issue" data-hovercard-url="/rust-lang/rfcs/issues/2505/hovercard">for now</a>), especially on wasm32 targets.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Inspiration</h2><a id="user-content-inspiration" aria-label="Permalink: Inspiration" href="#inspiration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Big thanks to the authors of the following projects, which have inspired and influenced TinyWasm:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://github.com/wasmi-labs/wasmi">wasmi</a> - an efficient and lightweight WebAssembly interpreter that also runs on <code>no_std</code> environments</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/wasm3/wasm3">wasm3</a> - a high performance WebAssembly interpreter written in C</li>
<li><a href="https://wazero.io/" rel="nofollow">wazero</a> - a zero-dependency WebAssembly interpreter written in go</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/rhysd/wain">wain</a> - a zero-dependency WebAssembly interpreter written in Rust</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">I encourage you to check these projects out if you're looking for a more mature and feature-complete WebAssembly interpreter.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Licensed under either of <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/blob/main/LICENSE-APACHE">Apache License, Version 2.0</a> or <a href="https://github.com/explodingcamera/tinywasm/blob/main/LICENSE-MIT">MIT license</a> at your option.</p>
<p dir="auto">Unless you explicitly state otherwise, any contribution intentionally submitted for inclusion in TinyWasm by you, as defined in the Apache-2.0 license, shall be dual licensed as above, without any additional terms or conditions.</p>
<p dir="auto"><strong>Note:</strong> The GitHub repository contains a Submodule (<code>crates/tinywasm-parser/data</code>) which is licensed only under the <a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/spec/blob/main/test/LICENSE">Apache License, Version 2.0</a>. This data is generated from the <a href="https://github.com/WebAssembly/spec/tree/main/test">WebAssembly Specification</a> and is only used for testing purposes and not included in the final binary.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Nikon to acquire RED (547 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nikon.com/company/news/2024/0307_01.html</link>
            <guid>39625919</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 07:01:42 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nikon.com/company/news/2024/0307_01.html">https://www.nikon.com/company/news/2024/0307_01.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39625919">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>

<!-- /.c-heading-header -->

<p>TOKYO - Nikon Corporation (Nikon) hereby announces its entry into an agreement to acquire 100% of the outstanding membership interests of RED.com, LLC (RED) whereby RED will become a wholly-owned subsidiary of Nikon, pursuant to a Membership Interest Purchase Agreement with Mr. James Jannard, its founder, and Mr. Jarred Land, its current President, subject to the satisfaction of certain closing conditions thereunder.</p>
<p>Since its establishment in 2005, RED has been at the forefront of digital cinema cameras, introducing industry-defining products such as the original RED ONE 4K to the cutting-edge V-RAPTOR [X] with its proprietary RAW compression technology. RED's contributions to the film industry have not only earned it an Academy Award but have also made it the camera of choice for numerous Hollywood productions, celebrated by directors and cinematographers worldwide for its commitment to innovation and image quality optimized for the highest levels of filmmaking and video production.</p>
<p>This agreement was reached as a result of the mutual desires of Nikon and RED to meet the customers’ needs and offer exceptional user experiences that exceed expectations, merging the strengths of both companies. Nikon's expertise in product development, exceptional reliability, and know-how in image processing, as well as optical technology and user interface along with RED’s knowledge in cinema cameras, including unique image compression technology and color science, will enable the development of distinctive products in the professional digital cinema camera market. </p>
<p>Nikon will leverage this acquisition to expand the fast-growing professional digital cinema camera market, building on both companies' business foundations and networks, promising an exciting future of product development that will continue to push the boundaries of what is possible in film and video production.</p>

<h2>Overview of RED.com, LLC</h2>

<table>
<colgroup>
<col>
<col>
</colgroup>
<tbody>
<tr>
<th>Company name</th>
<td>RED.com, LLC</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Head office location</th>
<td>Foothill Ranch, California, U.S.A.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Representatives</th>
<td>Jarred Land, President</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Foundation</th>
<td>2005 (Establishment)</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Number of employees</th>
<td>Approximately 220</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<th>Business</th>
<td>Design, development, manufacture, sales, and provision of services of professional digital cinema cameras</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>

<p>The information is current as of the date of publication. It is subject to change without notice.</p>

<dl>
<dt>Share</dt>
<dd>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.facebook.com/" target="_blank" onclick="click_send('/External-link_www.facebook.com/'); return true;"><svg viewBox="0 0 24 24" role="img" aria-label="Facebook"></svg></a></li>
<li><a href="https://twitter.com/share" target="_blank" onclick="click_send('/External-link_twitter.com/share'); return true;"><svg viewBox="0 0 29.793 24" role="img" aria-label="Twitter"></svg></a></li>
<li><a href="https://linkedin.com/share" target="_blank" onclick="click_send('/External-link_linkedin.com/share'); return true;"><svg viewBox="0 0 24.001 24" role="img" aria-label="LinkedIn"></svg></a></li>
</ul>
</dd>
</dl><!-- /.c-sns-button -->

</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Fractional scales, fonts and hinting (207 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.gtk.org/2024/03/07/on-fractional-scales-fonts-and-hinting/</link>
            <guid>39625917</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 07:01:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.gtk.org/2024/03/07/on-fractional-scales-fonts-and-hinting/">https://blog.gtk.org/2024/03/07/on-fractional-scales-fonts-and-hinting/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39625917">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Leadership is a hell of a drug (350 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ludic.mataroa.blog/blog/leadership-is-a-hell-of-a-drug/</link>
            <guid>39624842</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 03:42:47 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ludic.mataroa.blog/blog/leadership-is-a-hell-of-a-drug/">https://ludic.mataroa.blog/blog/leadership-is-a-hell-of-a-drug/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39624842">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">
        

        

        <div itemprop="articleBody">
            <p>Last week, I received the following invitation to a compulsory on-site meeting, following management's repeated engagements with some sort of Agile shaman.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You have been invited to:  </p>
<p>Compulsory On-Site: Continuous Improvement Playback &amp; Strategy  </p>
<p>Notes:
This will be an all-morning meeting so arrive energized as we hit the ground running on Monday morning  </p>
<p>The Leadership Team</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Oh <em>man</em>, where do I even <em>start</em> to make fun of this? There's so much here.</p>
<p>Firstly, why did you clowns make it a compulsory on-site event? Do you <em>really</em> think that it was worth dragging everyone into the office against their will because we needed to listen to you talk for four hours in a row? That level of self-regard is narcissistic to such a degree that I have screeched so far past horror that I've looped around to arrive at a grudging respect. I can only imagine this is the equivalent of a meditator achieving perfect concentration on the breath, but instead it is the all-consuming feeling that people like listening to you say the word strategy for <em>four hours</em>.</p>
<p>Secondly, do we really need to "be energised" and "hit the ground running" for a goddamn four hour meeting on a Monday.? Are you trying to help me sell cryptocurrency or get involved in a pyramid scheme? Half of us just write SQL for enterprise dashboards that no one reads, you absolute sickos. You don't work at SpaceX - the <em>largest</em> project we're working on right now is a big spreadsheet that is nonetheless six months behind schedule. <em>Sleeping</em> is higher energy than that.</p>
<p>Thirdly, did you have a stroke and forget how to talk like a human? Continuous Improvement Playback and Strategy? How about "Our plans to improve working conditions for 2024", you fucking weirdos? Does the part of your brain that produces normal speech ossify naturally as part of becoming an enterprise manager, or is that a prerequisite for the job?</p>
<p>Fourthly, given that half of you love turning up on stages and talking about your decades of leadership experience, why did you need someone from outside the organization who doesn't know a damn thing about our work to come in and tell you how you're screwing up? I'll tell you for free! That is a <em>breathtaking</em> level of disconnection.</p>
<p>Finally, and most importantly, what kind of maniac signs off on something as "The Leadership Team"? That's what we're talking about today - leadership.</p>
<h2 id="i">I.</h2>
<p>I've spoken to plenty of people that I'd actually call good leaders in the past year but I strongly hold that theory is no substitute for lived experience. And I've never formally held a position of leadership in an organization. Nonetheless, at some point we must concede you don't have to be a chef to notice that not only is this cake unbaked, it is a slurry of yolk, whites, eggshells, and flour that someone has flung into a bucket and declared finished.</p>
<p>Of course, leadership is not like baking a cake. There are no yolks, eggshells, or flour. However it occurred to me after writing the above that all of my would-be leaders since getting to Australia have been white despite all the engineers being Asian, so maybe I'm onto something.</p>
<p>David Whyte's <a href="https://davidwhyte.com/pages/consolations"><em>Consolations</em></a> is a beautiful book on the quiet re-association of words with all the little connotations they have that fall to the wayside amidst the modern coarsening of them. The blending of <em>leadership</em> with <em>management</em> is one such coarsening that I think needs to be addressed before we continue. They describe radically different things that are merely occasionally carried out by the same person.</p>
<p>Management is mundane and unsexy, and that's <em>fine</em>. Not everything that requires a manic Silicon Valley energy. You can roster employees for the next shift at McDonald's with basically none of what we'd call leadership. Just be halfway competent, have a basic understanding of what you're doing, and ensure the thing gets done by the people that are paid to do the thing. The supermarket remains open because of the relatively efficient repetition of this task every day. Calling yourself "The Management Team" is not offensive to my eyes, and while I am certain that the word "management" is deployed in retail stores by petty tyrants across the globe with all the subtlety of a tactical nuclear device, the warning bells do not sound loudly to my ears.</p>
<p>But leadership, oh <em>baby</em>, that's what everyone wants to do. Managing is mundane and leadership is exciting. A manager handles trivialities, like hiring and firing. A leader has the privilege of serving as a shining moral beacon, soothing the trouble, reading the psychodynamic eddies (read: vibes) in the organization. At its best, it is a genuinely noble endeavor, not carried out by whoever happens to be at the top of an organizational chart, but whoever has the capacity to encourage other people to be their best selves at a given moment. The most inspiring person in my life yesterday was not anyone that gives talks about how amazing their own skills are, but the seven year old in the house next door who was drilling table tennis so determinedly that I guiltily got some piano practice in.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I have <em>never</em> experienced anything I'd call leadership from anyone that has called themselves a member of "the leadership team". From my friends, yes. From some serious thinkers, yeah. From "leadership", not even close. Instead, society presents us with an endless parade of people parroting nonsense ranging from the insanely over-excited ("Get shit done! Woo!") to the utterly soulless ("Continuous Improvement Playback &amp; Strategy"). Shut the fuck up! All we do is land the output of APIs in a warehouse, guys. You sound <em>insane</em>.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>King: "That's not a luxury, though, coffee and socks are not a luxury."<br>
Pudi: "All right - give me a luxury - what luxury should I have?"<br>
King: "Private plane."<br>
Pudi: "... Larry, I'm on Ducktales."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>These people are running some horrific version of leadership that consists entirely of them turning up and repeating the same tired cliches on a loop. Reduce silos. Be more Agile. We must go forward, not backwards. Can you imagine how fucked in the head you'd have to be to imagine you can hold a <em>four hour</em> unrehearsed session and that you <em>expect it to be so good that you demand everyone be there for it</em>?</p>
<p>There is something genuinely scary about the idea of people so caught up in their own self-image that they think leadership is turning up on stage to dispense divine corporate manna unto the huddles masses, then expectantly waiting for the choir to raise their voices in sickly-sweet supplication: "That's a great idea, boss."</p>
<h2 id="ii-thoughtfulness">II. Thoughtfulness</h2>
<p>The most scathing condemnation I have of the majority of people that would call themselves leaders is the fact that... well, most of them don't read, or proudly proclaim that they do most of their study on LinkedIn. I have heard <em>multiple</em> people say the latter without a hint of shame. And with this, I cannot help but question whether they're bad at technology, or bad at <em>everything</em>.</p>
<p>The majority of people that unironically call themselves leaders seem to be fighting a constantly losing rearguard action around what their area of competence actually is. Leadership in the absence of a <em>skill</em> is just aspiring to run a cult of personality. I am assured that while they can't program, they know a lot about running I.T projects. Then all our projects run late, but I am assured they actually know a lot about finance. Then we are unprofitable, but I am assured they know a lot about retaining staff. Then the staff leave, and I have most recently been assured that they are working hard on increasing salaries - that <em>must</em> be the reason everyone is leaving because it couldn't be that they've lost faith in leadership.</p>
<p>Why is it <em>so easy</em> for the readers here to assure me that they have actual competence in some domain, but it is impossible for all these dorks? All they would have to do is say <em>one sentence</em> that indicated some level of original thought - I'm not even hard to trick! There are so many domains that I don't know much about that they could basically string together any insightful-sounding series of syllables and I'd conclude they're smart.</p>
<p>Consider this: the lawyer I mentioned in <a href="https://ludic.mataroa.blog/blog/on-authenticity-and-whats-worth-doing/">this post</a> had opinions on whether statically typed languages are superior to dynamically typed languages, and had engaged in some complex meta-cognition. See, they reflected on how every time they felt that something in Go was ugly, it later turned out that Go was well-designed and they simply didn't understand the issues being designed around. This turned into a rough rule that seeing a problem with Go <em>typically</em> reflected a flaw in their own understanding, thus <em>flaw with Go</em> is actually best processed as <em>flaw in own brain</em> until proven otherwise.</p>
<p>I don't know much about Go, but that's not important. What <em>is</em> important is that I'm on my knees, arms outstretched, gazing up at the sky, tears streaming down my face, and begging to have one question answered:</p>
<p>Why does a practicing lawyer have more thoughts on programming than every CTO I've had a 1:1 with at a big company?</p>
<h2 id="iii-ego">III. Ego</h2>
<p>If someone doesn't have the ability to award someone else status or money, they're told they're a good <em>manager</em>. This is usually a person whose job it is to hover in the air, screaming, while the organization channels all their dysfunction like bolts of Atlassian-branded lightning into their twitching, smoking mortal coil. This hopefully gives the people beneath them time to actually do their jobs uninterrupted for up to ten seconds. When that person burns out, you discard their charcoal corpse, slap in a new one, and set the machine going once again. That job is horrible and we all thank you for your service, you glorious bastards.</p>
<p>However, if a person <em>can</em> provide someone status or money, they will be told that they're a great <em>leader</em>, and by the way, I heard that there might a role opening up on that new prestigious project and I'd like to throw my hat in the ring. Being called a leader shoots an LD50 dose of status-infused dopamine directly into the average person's system, and this is absolutely exploited to the hilt by every grifter under the sun.</p>
<p>I can only imagine that this is extremely corrosive for your development as a person, but it is also <em>dreadfully obvious</em> when it happens. A few years ago, I had dinner with a guy in his early twenties who had a very successful non-profit take off. He was very seriously despairing at how many events he was being invited to where people would fawn over him despite the fact he was twenty-one. I believe his exact words were a very sarcastic "Society isn't broken at all!" with a <em>very</em> distressed look on his face. If a twenty-one year old could figure out that adulation is unhealthy, what's everyone else's excuse?</p>
<p>It is tragic to see how easy it is to push the ego button on some people. Someone once wrote in and referred to LinkedIn as the "clout factory", and it is hard not to think about almost all non-athletic awards in this way. These processes become so easily corrupted that I think the most impressive thing a person can do is reject all awards on the principle that they're bad for you spiritually. I'll leave it to the reader to decide how prescient this is, but Taleb wrote the following in 2007, which I think those Americans among you will appreciate:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Nor did the committee come to us practitioners to ask us our opinions; instead it relied on an academic vetting process that, in some disciplines, can be corrupt all the way to the marrow. After that award I made a prediction: "In a world in which these two get the Nobel, anything can happen. Anyone can become president."</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Of course, the Agile consultant I mentioned above has done <em>something</em> to flatter the leadership team, though the specifics are invisible to the rest of us. It might have been as simple as calling them <em>leadership</em> a lot, and the consultant might genuinely be unaware that this is the secret to their success. After flattering leadership for a while, they arranged some group sessions with the teams and <em>immediately</em> blundered away all their reputation, with such brilliant questions as:</p>
<p>"Rate how well you think you understand our strategy going into 2024? We know leadership hasn't put out a strategy yet." Well, this question doesn't make any fucking sense then, does it?</p>
<p>"Rate how well-trained you are at Agile, on a scale of 1 - 5?" Firstly, what the hell does this even mean? Do you mean Scrum? Secondly, someone said 2 and the Agile folks rounded his answer up to 3 for no discernible reason.</p>
<p>I can only conclude that, behind the scenes, they had spent the past few weeks just telling management whatever they wanted to hear, and didn't think the peasants were smart enough to feel patronized by all this.</p>
<h2 id="iv-doing-better">IV. Doing Better</h2>
<h2 id="management-again">Management, Again</h2>
<p>The best <em>manager</em> I've ever worked for was Healthscope's Dave Coulter, who has been mentioned previously <a href="https://ludic.mataroa.blog/blog/fury-driven-development/">here</a>. The only reason I say <em>manager</em> instead of <em>leader</em> is that we worked in an organization that was fundamentally disempowering, so we spent most of our time trying the conventional corporate wisdom of "educating our stakeholders", which did not work, I've never seen work, and I've never met someone that has seen it cause <em>true</em> organizational transformation. But he did the hard work, knew the tools, <em>read</em>, and took care of the team. It was <em>really simple</em>, and I learned that there's no real trick to this. Use your brain and your empathy.</p>
<p>Also he <em>is</em> in an organizationally-sanctioned leadership role now, but has never called himself a "leader" <em>because that would indicate fucking madness</em>.</p>
<h2 id="leadership-again">Leadership, Again</h2>
<p>The best <em>leader</em> I've ever worked for was, to everyone's surprise including my own, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/stephen-deutsch-au">Stephen Deutsch</a> in the state government (the surprise is because the government is genuinely pretty bad at most things). I was burned out on tech work by the time I got to him, and I remember <em>still</em> enjoying working with him. We were in the fire service, which occupies a place of huge civic importance in the Australian psyche, and he would turn up and be absolutely honest every single day. Right as the latent burnout from my previous role reached a crescendo, I told him I intended to leave for a place that was offering me three days of work a week so I could do some recovering.</p>
<p>Over the course of a call, he commiserated, shared his own struggles with me, and then <em>completely unilaterally disarmed</em>. He got me an offer to work there for three days a week, explained that it would never be as stable as taking a permanent role doing the same elsewhere, further explained that I currently had a lot of power due to the way their budget and projects were set up, and otherwise completely collapsed his own negotiating position so that I would have the tools to take care of myself. It made his life substantially harder in exchange for making mine much easier.</p>
<p>I ended up leaving, and he made the decision to leave easier, yes. But we stayed in touch because you don't run into people like that every day. He's a co-director with me now, I play board games with his friends every week, and that disarmament was so radical that I still think "J'ds hasfak 'ds'" every time it comes up, which I dare everyone to recognize without looking up.</p>
<h2 id="getting-involved-myself">Getting Involved Myself</h2>
<p>I've considered getting into a leadership role myself to see what it's really like, but this is complicated by a few things.</p>
<p>The first one is that I don't think leadership roles should really exist in many domains, as I've indicated earlier. Leadership should naturally flow between team members based on the task being performed, competence of each member, and psychodynamic energy (read again: vibes) on any given day. Taking a role as a team lead somewhere sounds almost paradoxical - the whole goal would be to <em>not</em> behave as a team lead, which is clearly not how the organization functions or they wouldn't have a role called team lead. I can certainly <em>imagine</em> a version of a team lead that encourages a healthy culture, but this would run counter to the true values of most companies.</p>
<p>The second issue is that I think I'd be good at it, which strikes me as a huge CAUTION! sign. Everyone knows what I mean, and everyone must also concede that this is also a sign of how dire the situation is out in the real world. When I tell my teammates that I think I can design a simple application, their first thought is (hopefully) not "Wow, he must be about to fucking <em>bomb</em> this!". When I tell <em>myself</em> that I think I could do a decent job managing two juniors, my first thought is "I might be a sociopath". The people that consistently rate as the most insane authority figures I've seen over the past few years have been the ones that said "I'm a natural leader" during the interview process.</p>
<p>However, it is also incredibly common for people to remark that those most suited for "leadership" roles are those that don't <em>want</em> leadership roles. I think that protects from the worst excesses of getting a narcissist in charge, but doesn't actually consistently produce <em>great</em> leadership. I asked Stephen about this, and he happily said that he loves leadership roles (and I can confirm that I never felt like a subordinate working with him). Simultaneously, one of the most senior people in my current reporting chain is a great person that was forced to take up leadership despite promises that they wouldn't have to. Haven't seen them in months. Great person, lots of respect for them, sadly absolutely useless to me. I don't think they'd even disagree with that assessment, they'd just feel guilty. So I guess that whole line of thought belongs in the dumpster if you want to pursue human flourishing rather than limp sustainably onward.</p>
<p>This is still something I'm mulling over, but I reckon it's best not to force it by explicitly looking for a role in the space. It'll happen organically or it won't, and there's no point doing it at mediocre organizations. Instead, I thought it would be nice to share some reading and my thoughts on doing it right before wrapping up.</p>
<h2 id="some-reading">Some Reading</h2>
<p>I've mentioned <em>High Output Management</em> before, and I think this is really the quintessential book on management devoid of leadership (and that's not a bad thing). It's full of nothing other than guidance on how to manage operations smoothly and not screw up your meetings. Can't go wrong with it, even though everyone has qualms with some part or another.</p>
<p>I've been enjoying <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Managing-Humans-Humorous-Software-Engineering/dp/1430243147">Managing Humans</a> but something that really bothers me is... well, the environments described in it are accurate, but they also suck. There's a huge amount of stuff in it about managing rumors, organizational politics, and so on. All the ugliness is baked right in. It's probably the perfect book for someone that wants to do a good job at a huge company that has no real chance for reaching the Nirvana of everyone being high-performing and psychologically comfortable - and that's fine, some of us have to work at those places, but I know the readers <em>here</em> don't want to, so there's limited long-term utility to developing those skills.</p>
<h2 id="pivotal-software">Pivotal Software</h2>
<p>What I've <em>really</em> been into these days has been covering some of the original Extreme Programming material and, more uniquely, talking with some of the people that used to work down in Pivotal Software. There's a lot to write about this, but I had a three-hour long conversation with <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jessetalford/">Jesse Alford</a> a few weeks ago, and was immediately intrigued by what the experience of working there sounded like. Jesse himself was brilliant, but there's also a lot of material on their functioning that I had never heard of before.</p>
<p>Their alumni community is some sort of cult where they're all chasing the high of working at an organization that good again. There's a <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/radio-free-xp/id1707924562">podcast</a> dedicated to spreading some of their operating model out there, hosted by alumni with plenty of other alumni coming on as guests. Every single episode slaps and has leadership wisdom that makes most other sources seem tragically oversimplified. Here's <a href="https://www.simplermachines.com/mr-reciprocity/">a big essay</a> on what made working there so special.</p>
<p>Hell, I read a book called <a href="https://davidmarquet.com/turn-the-ship-around-book/"><em>Turn The Ship Around!</em></a> which I <em>really</em> enjoyed on leadership - I dare say it was the best book on the topic I've ever read, or at least as good as a leadership book can possibly get. I wrote up a whole post on it, really thought about it, then realized that I wasn't comfortable publishing it because I didn't have enough experience <em>and</em> the author does management consulting now, which I thoroughly distrust. Lo and behold, here is the author <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/nudge-61-with-david-marquet/id1707924562?i=1000633646689">on their podcast</a>, with admittedly terrible microphone quality, making statements that are socially expensive enough about the median employer for me to be willing to endorse his book. I can't recommend the book and the episode highly enough, in that order.</p>
<p>I'm hoping to spend the next few weeks getting deep into the Pivotal lore/cult and figuring out what worked so well for them.</p>
<h2 id="v">V.</h2>
<p>I stare at the invitation for a long moment.</p>
<p>It is from someone in the C-suite.</p>
<p>I <em>ensure</em> that my response is going to be sent to the organizer.</p>
<p>I click decline.</p>
<p>No one remarks on my absence, and I receive only these messages from the attending engineers:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I'm bored of hearing the word strategy.</p>
<p>Someone just turned around and asked me "Wtf are they saying?"</p>
<p>They are suggesting dumb shit.</p>
<p>The world has gone mad.</p>
<p>Absolutely hilarious.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Leadership is a hell of a drug.</p>
        </div>
    </article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Signs you're about to be acquired (2020) (147 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://yolken.net/blog/youre-about-to-be-acquired</link>
            <guid>39624464</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 02:30:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://yolken.net/blog/youre-about-to-be-acquired">https://yolken.net/blog/youre-about-to-be-acquired</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39624464">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div aria-label="Content">
      <article itemscope="" itemtype="http://schema.org/BlogPosting">

  

  <div itemprop="articleBody">
    <p>Over the course of my tech career thus far, I’ve been through two acquisitions. In each case,
I was just a normal employee without any special inside knowledge, and found out only a few days
before the deals were publicly announced. In retrospect, however, there were some clear signs
in the weeks leading up to the announcements that something unusual was going on.</p>

<p>I’d like to share what these early indicators were so that you can be on the lookout for them
in your workplace.</p>

<h2 id="background-my-acquisition-experiences">Background: My acquisition experiences</h2>

<p>My first acquisition occurred in 2013, when my employer, <a href="https://mopub.com/">MoPub</a>, was acquired
by <a href="https://twitter.com/">Twitter</a>. I had joined the year before when the company was around 45
employees. Over the course of that year, the company had done really well, and by the time we were
acquired we had more than doubled in size.</p>

<p>The second acquisition happened in 2020 (just a few weeks ago!), when
<a href="https://segment.com/">Segment</a> was bought by <a href="https://twilio.com/">Twilio</a>. As with MoPub,
this happened about a year after I started. But, in this case, I had joined the company at
a much later stage, when it was around 500 employees, and growth was a bit lower.</p>

<p>The post-acquisition experiences were super interesting, but I’m going to save talking
about them for a later post.</p>

<h2 id="signs-an-acquisition-is-coming">Signs an acquisition is coming</h2>

<h3 id="founders-and-executives-are-distracted">Founders and executives are distracted</h3>

<p>Getting a multi-hundred million or multi-billion dollar acquisition deal across the line requires
a massive amount of effort. It starts with initial discussions then evolves into full-fledged
negotiations, sometimes with multiple suitors at once. Once the outline of a deal is reached, the
potential acquirer spends several weeks doing due diligence and peppering company insiders
with detailed questions about the business.</p>

<p>Dealing with all this plus the prospect of a massive payday down the line is super
distracting. Unless you’re an amazing actor (which few people are), it’s hard to pretend that
you’re still super excited about the weekly product plan, the company’s regular all-hands meetings,
and other mundane, day-to-day operational details.</p>

<p>In both the MoPub and Segment cases, I noticed this change in behavior in the founders and
non-founder executives beginning a few weeks before the acquisitions happened. Everyone involved
still did their day-to-day jobs, but they became much more distant, as if they were
preoccupied with something bigger.</p>

<p>A single person going through this transformation wouldn’t be suspicious- they could be dealing
with a personal issue or maybe they decided to leave the company and start interviewing elsewhere.
Multiple people doing this at the same time, however, is too much of a coincidence and suggests
that some big, company-level change like an acquisition is brewing.</p>

<h3 id="increased-focus-on-security">Increased focus on security</h3>

<p>A big chunk of the due diligence process that happens before a deal is signed involves evaluating
security vulnerabilities in the acquiree and then, as the deal gets closer, fixing any critical
issues found. No acquirer wants to pay hundreds of millions of dollars for a company and then have
hackers get in and steal all of the customer data and intellectual property.</p>

<p>In the case of Segment, we had a strong security team that handled these issues. MoPub, however,
had no security team and, in fact, had pretty lax security practices. In the weeks before the
acquisition, I remember some of my colleagues going in and cleaning up things that no one had cared
one iota about before, such as plugging vulnerabilities in our UIs and removing
the numerous opportunities for <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SQL_injection">SQL injection attacks</a>
in our backend systems.</p>

<p>At the time, I didn’t think anything of it, but in retrospect I should have been suspicious
that these efforts were quietly going on in the background, without any attacks to motivate them
or any announcements about a change in engineering priorities.</p>

<h3 id="lack-of-urgency-around-hiring-and-retention">Lack of urgency around hiring and retention</h3>

<p>Hiring engineers takes a lot of work (many, many hours of interviews and meetings), and once
they’ve joined, they’re really expensive to have on staff. Likewise, keeping engineers happy
and retaining them after they’ve been around for a few years is also time and money intensive.</p>

<p>When an acquisition is going on, these activities can drop a few notches on the priority ladder. Executives and others become too busy (see discussion above), and large investments in talent
could reduce the short-term value of the company. Moreover, it’s a little awkward to be selling
candidates on your cool, fast-moving startup when you know that you’re about to gobbled up by
a larger company.</p>

<p>In both the MoPub and Segment cases, hiring slowed down to a trickle in the periods leading up
to the acquisitions. At the time, however, both businesses were growing a lot, and I felt that
we desperately needed more hands on deck to keep systems up-and-running and continue developing
new products. The urgency around hiring just seemed out-of-whack with the need. There also didn’t
seem to be any urgency around retaining people who were thinking of leaving (and then ended
up quitting).</p>

<h3 id="unusual-meetings-and-meeting-changes">Unusual meetings and meeting changes</h3>

<p>Because of the complexity of large tech acquisitions, it’s hard to predict exactly what will
happen when. A deal could be signed suddenly at 3AM on a Saturday night, or it might drag on
for months longer. This, combined with the fact that executives are super distracted and busy,
means that meetings are likely to be moved, cancelled, or inserted at weird times.</p>

<p>A few days before the Twitter deal was announced, the CEO of MoPub summoned a bunch of us to
the office on a Sunday. Nothing like that had <em>ever</em> happened before. At the meeting, he told us
about the acquisition (this was when I learned!) and explained that he needed us to sign some
paperwork about our equity before the agreement could be finalized.</p>

<p>At Segment, the last company all-hands before the acquisition was cancelled at the last minute.
That had never, ever happened before. I never found out the real reason, but I suspect that
the pending acquisition played either a direct (e.g., they were hoping to make an announcement)
or indirect (e.g., the people on the agenda were too busy) role.</p>

<p>I didn’t stalk executives’ calendars, but if I had done this I probably would have seen even
more obvious signs of unusual activity- meetings very early in the morning or late at night,
meeting details being hidden after previously being open all the time, etc.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>If you’re working at a private tech company, an acquisition can happen at any time, without
warning. Be on the lookout for the signs discussed above, as well as other, unusual activity,
which could mean something big is about to happen!</p>

  </div>

  
  
  

  
</article>



    </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[PFAS 'forever chemicals' to officially be removed from food packaging, FDA says (246 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.livescience.com/health/food-diet/pfas-forever-chemicals-to-officially-be-removed-from-food-packaging-fda-says</link>
            <guid>39623857</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 01:04:58 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.livescience.com/health/food-diet/pfas-forever-chemicals-to-officially-be-removed-from-food-packaging-fda-says">https://www.livescience.com/health/food-diet/pfas-forever-chemicals-to-officially-be-removed-from-food-packaging-fda-says</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=39623857">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-widget-type="contentparsed" id="content">
<section>
<div itemprop="image" itemscope="" itemtype="https://schema.org/ImageObject">
<div>
<picture><source type="image/webp" alt="Close-up image of the hands of a waiter giving two small brown takeout boxes to a customer in a restaurant" onerror="if(this.src &amp;&amp; this.src.indexOf('missing-image.svg') !== -1){return true;};this.parentNode.replaceChild(window.missingImage(),this)" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-320-80.jpg.webp 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-480-80.jpg.webp 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-650-80.jpg.webp 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-970-80.jpg.webp 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1024-80.jpg.webp 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1200-80.jpg.webp 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1920-80.jpg.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg"><source type="image/jpeg" alt="Close-up image of the hands of a waiter giving two small brown takeout boxes to a customer in a restaurant" onerror="if(this.src &amp;&amp; this.src.indexOf('missing-image.svg') !== -1){return true;};this.parentNode.replaceChild(window.missingImage(),this)" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg"><img src="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-320-80.jpg" alt="Close-up image of the hands of a waiter giving two small brown takeout boxes to a customer in a restaurant" onerror="if(this.src &amp;&amp; this.src.indexOf('missing-image.svg') !== -1){return true;};this.parentNode.replaceChild(window.missingImage(),this)" srcset="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-320-80.jpg 320w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-480-80.jpg 480w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-650-80.jpg 650w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-970-80.jpg 970w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1024-80.jpg 1024w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1200-80.jpg 1200w, https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC-1920-80.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1000px) 600px, calc(100vw - 40px)" data-original-mos="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg" data-pin-media="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg"></picture>
</div>
<meta itemprop="url" content="https://cdn.mos.cms.futurecdn.net/T7ukLm3Qg9Cj46ZFNpiXgC.jpg">
<meta itemprop="height" content="600">
<meta itemprop="width" content="338">
<figcaption itemprop="caption description">
<span>PFAS chemicals will no longer be used in food packaging in the U.S., according to a new announcement from the FDA.</span>
<span itemprop="copyrightHolder">(Image credit: Luis Alvarez via Getty Images)</span>
</figcaption>
</div>

<div itemprop="articleBody" id="article-body">

<p>Manufacturers will no longer use harmful "forever chemicals" in food packaging products in the U.S., according to the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA).</p><p>In a <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.fda.gov/food/cfsan-constituent-updates/fda-announces-pfas-used-grease-proofing-agents-food-packaging-no-longer-being-sold-us" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.fda.gov/food/cfsan-constituent-updates/fda-announces-pfas-used-grease-proofing-agents-food-packaging-no-longer-being-sold-us"><u>statement released Feb. 28</u></a>, the agency declared that grease-proofing materials that contain <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/65364-pfas.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/65364-pfas.html"><u>per- and polyfluoroalkyl substances</u></a> (PFAS) will not be used in new food packaging sold in the U.S. These include PFAS used in fast-food wrappers, microwave popcorn bags, takeout boxes and pet food bags. The FDA's announcement marks the completion of a voluntary phase-out of the materials by U.S. food packaging manufacturers.&nbsp;</p><p>This action will eliminate the "major source of dietary exposure to PFAS," <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/fda-organization/jim-jones" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.fda.gov/about-fda/fda-organization/jim-jones"><u>Jim Jones</u></a>, deputy commissioner for human foods at the FDA, said in an associated <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-industry-actions-end-sales-pfas-used-us-food-packaging" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-industry-actions-end-sales-pfas-used-us-food-packaging"><u>statement</u></a>. Companies told the FDA that it could take up to 18 months to completely exhaust the market supply of these products following their final date of sale. However, most of the affected manufacturers phased out the products faster than they initially predicted, the agency noted.&nbsp;</p><p>"This FDA-led effort represents a positive step forward as we continue to reevaluate chemicals authorized for use with, and in, food," Jones said. "It underscores an important milestone in the protection of U.S. consumers from potentially harmful food-contact chemicals."</p><p><strong>Related: </strong><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/pfas-forever-chemicals-broken-down" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/pfas-forever-chemicals-broken-down"><u><strong>Scientists find a simple way to destroy 'forever chemicals' — by beheading them</strong></u></a></p><p>PFAS are a diverse group of synthetic chemicals that <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.urmc.rochester.edu/news/story/pfas-what-you-need-to-know" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.urmc.rochester.edu/news/story/pfas-what-you-need-to-know"><u>resist water, oil, heat and stains</u></a>, which is why they've historically been used in a wide variety of products, including food packaging, household cleaners and nonstick cookware. PFAS are super durable chemicals that can <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7657368/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7657368/"><u>take years to break down</u></a>, hence why they're often called "<a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8583519/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC8583519/"><u>forever chemicals</u></a>."&nbsp;</p><p>Once discarded, PFAS can leak into the environment as they slowly break down, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.cdc.gov/biomonitoring/PFAS_FactSheet.html" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.cdc.gov/biomonitoring/PFAS_FactSheet.html"><u>accumulating in soil, rivers and lakes</u></a>, for instance. The chemicals can also enter the body when people consume <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/pfas/health-effects/PFAS-exposure-and-your-body.html" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/pfas/health-effects/PFAS-exposure-and-your-body.html"><u>water or food that's been exposed to the chemicals</u></a> during production or packaging, or when they breathe in dust tainted with PFAS. They can <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/pfas/health-effects/us-population.html" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.atsdr.cdc.gov/pfas/health-effects/us-population.html"><u>accumulate in a person's blood</u></a> and in <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/51939-breast-feeding-babies-chemicals-pfas.html" target="_blank" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/51939-breast-feeding-babies-chemicals-pfas.html"><u>breast milk</u></a>.&nbsp;</p><p>Numerous studies have demonstrated the potential health effects of being exposed to different PFAS. For example, the chemincals have linked to disruptions in the <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/chemical-processed-foods-preservative-immune-system.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/chemical-processed-foods-preservative-immune-system.html"><u>immune system</u></a>, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/63487-chemicals-environment-weight-gain.html" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/63487-chemicals-environment-weight-gain.html"><u>weight gain</u></a> and <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36334833/" target="_blank" data-url="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/36334833/"><u>decreased fertility</u></a> in a mixture of animal and human studies, as well as cell-based research.&nbsp;</p><p>The FDA's February announcement is several years in the making. As an initial step <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.fda.gov/food/cfsan-constituent-updates/fda-announces-voluntary-phase-out-industry-certain-pfas-used-food-packaging" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.fda.gov/food/cfsan-constituent-updates/fda-announces-voluntary-phase-out-industry-certain-pfas-used-food-packaging"><u>in 2020</u></a>, the agency announced that it was working with manufacturers to voluntarily phase out the use of certain PFAS in food packaging, such as grease-proofing agents on paper and paperboard products. The goal was to phase out these products within three years.&nbsp;</p><p>The FDA's new announcement marks a "huge win for the public," <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://physics.nd.edu/people/graham-peaslee/" target="_blank" data-url="https://physics.nd.edu/people/graham-peaslee/"><u>Graham Peaslee</u></a>, a professor of physics at the University of Notre Dame who studies PFAS, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2024/02/28/pfas-water-food-forever-chemicals-fda/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.washingtonpost.com/wellness/2024/02/28/pfas-water-food-forever-chemicals-fda/"><u>told The Washington Post</u></a>. &nbsp;&nbsp;</p><p>"Nobody reads the wrapper of their hamburger to see if it has PFAS or not," Peaslee told the news outlet. "It's going to be a huge win that we don't have to worry about where it ends up," he said.&nbsp;</p><p>Removing PFAS from food packaging is a "great step in the right direction," <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.peds.uw.edu/directory/sheela_sathyanarayana/1330" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.peds.uw.edu/directory/sheela_sathyanarayana/1330"><u>Dr. Sheela Sathyanarayana</u></a>, a professor of pediatrics at the University of Washington School of Medicine in Seattle, <a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/food-packaging-forever-chemicals-pfas-no-longer-sold-in-u-s-fda/" target="_blank" data-url="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/food-packaging-forever-chemicals-pfas-no-longer-sold-in-u-s-fda/"><u>told CBS News</u></a>.&nbsp;</p><p>However, although food packaging is the main way people are exposed to PFAS through their diets, there are also "many sources of PFAS in our environment," Sathyanarayana noted. These include drinking water and meat and dairy products, she said, since livestock and poultry can be exposed to PFAS in a variety of ways during production.&nbsp;</p><p>Again, it could take 18 months for leftover stocks of PFAS-containing food packaging to be removed from the market. In the meantime, "the FDA will continue to conduct research and update our evaluations using the most up-to-date science to ensure that our risk determinations continue to be accurate," Jones said.&nbsp;</p><p><em>Ever wonder why </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/health/exercise/why-is-it-harder-for-some-people-to-build-muscle-than-others" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/health/exercise/why-is-it-harder-for-some-people-to-build-muscle-than-others"><u><em>some people build muscle more easily than others</em></u></a><em> or </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="https://www.livescience.com/health/why-do-freckles-come-out-in-the-sun" data-before-rewrite-localise="https://www.livescience.com/health/why-do-freckles-come-out-in-the-sun"><u><em>why freckles come out in the sun</em></u></a><em>? Send us your questions about how the human body works to </em><a data-analytics-id="inline-link" href="mailto:community@livescience.com?subject=%20Health%20Desk%20Q" target="_blank"><u><em>community@livescience.com</em></u></a><em> with the subject line "Health Desk Q," and you may see your question answered on the website!&nbsp;</em></p>
</div>
<div data-hydrate="true" id="slice-container-newsletterForm-articleInbodyContent-WjwJ3D6jdRGfpBm92AZU6X"><section><p>Get the world’s most fascinating discoveries delivered straight to your inbox.</p></section></div>
<div id="slice-container-authorBio-WjwJ3D6jdRGfpBm92AZU6X"><p>Emily is a health news writer based in London, United Kingdom. She holds a bachelor's degree in biology from Durham University and a master's degree in clinical and therapeutic neuroscience from Oxford University. She has worked in science communication, medical writing and as a local news reporter while undertaking journalism training. In 2018, she was named one of MHP Communications' 30 journalists to watch under 30. (<a href="mailto:emily.cooke@futurenet.com" target="_blank">emily.cooke@futurenet.com</a>)&nbsp;</p>
</div>


</section>




<div id="slice-container-relatedArticles"><p><h5>Most Popular</h5></p></div>








</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>