<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>HN100 - Readable Contents</title>
        <link>https://hn.algolia.com/api/v1/search_by_date?tags=%28story,poll%29&amp;numericFilters=points%3E100</link>
        <description>Uses Readability to add bodies to the RSS feed</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:30:02 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Underrated reasons to be thankful V (101 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://dynomight.net/thanks-5/</link>
            <guid>46073033</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 20:37:51 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://dynomight.net/thanks-5/">https://dynomight.net/thanks-5/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46073033">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<article>
  <header>
    <img src="https://dynomight.net/img/valley.jpg">
    

  </header>  

  <section>
    

    <ol>
  <li>
    <p>That your dog, while she appears to love you only because she’s been adapted by evolution to appear to love you, really does love you.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That if you’re a life form and you cook up a baby and copy your genes to them, you’ll find that the genes have been degraded due to oxidative stress et al., which isn’t cause for celebration, but if you find some other hopefully-hot person and randomly swap in half of their genes, your baby will still be somewhat less fit compared to you and your hopefully-hot friend on average, but now there is variance, so if you cook up several babies, one of them might be as fit or even fitter than you, and that one will likely have more babies than your other babies have, and thus complex life can persist in a universe with increasing entropy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That if we wanted to, we surely <em>could</em> figure out which of the 300-ish strains of rhinovirus are circulating in a given area at a given time and rapidly vaccinate people to stop it and thereby finally “cure” the common cold, and though this is too annoying to pursue right now, it seems like it’s just a matter of time.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That if you look back at history, you see that plagues went from Europe to the Americas but not the other way, which suggests that urbanization and travel are great allies for infectious disease, and these both continue today but are held in check by sanitation and vaccines even while we have lots of tricks like UVC light and high-frequency sound and air filtration and waste monitoring and paying people to stay home that we’ve barely even put in play.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That while engineered infectious diseases loom ever-larger as a potential very big problem, we also have lots of crazier tricks we <em>could</em> pull out like panopticon viral screening or toilet monitors or daily individualized saliva sampling or engineered microbe-resistant surfaces or even dividing society into cells with rotating interlocks or having people walk around in little personal spacesuits, and while admittedly most of this doesn’t sound awesome, I see no reason this shouldn’t be a battle that we would win.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That clean water, unlimited, almost free.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That dentistry.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That tongues.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That radioactive atoms either release a ton of energy but also quickly stop existing—a gram of Rubidium-90 scattered around your kitchen emits as much energy as ~200,000 incandescent lightbulbs but after an hour only 0.000000113g is left—or don’t put out very much energy but keep existing for a long time—a gram of Carbon-14 only puts out the equivalent of 0.0000212 light bulbs but if you start with a gram, you’ll still have 0.999879g after a year—so it isn’t actually <em>that</em> easy to permanently poison the environment with radiation although Cobalt-60 with its medium energy output and medium half-life is unfortunate, medical applications notwithstanding I still wish Cobalt-60 didn’t exist, screw you Cobalt-60.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That while curing all cancer would only increase life expectancy by ~3 years and curing all heart disease would only increase life expectancy by ~3 years, and preventing all accidents would only increase life expectancy by ~1.5 years, if we did all of these at the same time and then a lot of other stuff too, eventually the effects would go nonlinear, so trying to cure cancer isn’t actually a waste of time, thankfully.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That the peroxisome, while the mitochondria and their stupid Krebs cycle get all the attention, when a fatty-acid that’s too long for them to catabolize comes along, who you gonna call.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That we have preferences, that there’s no agreed ordering of how good different things are, which is neat, and not something that would obviously be true for an alien species, and given our limited resources probably makes us happier on net.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That cardamom, it is cheap but tastes expensive, if cardamom cost 1000× more, people would brag about how they flew to Sri Lanka so they could taste chai made with fresh cardamom and swear that it changed their whole life.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That Gregory of Nyssa, he was right.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That Grandma Moses, it’s not too late.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That sleep, that probably evolution first made a low-energy mode so we don’t starve so fast and then layered on some maintenance processes, but the effect is that we live in a cycle and when things aren’t going your way it’s comforting that reality doesn’t stretch out before you indefinitely but instead you can look forward to a reset and a pause that’s somehow neither experienced nor skipped.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That, glamorous or not, comfortable or not, cheap or not, carbon emitting or not, air travel is very safe.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That, for most of the things you’re worried about, the markets are less worried than you and they have the better track record, though not the issue of your mortality.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That sexual attraction to romantic love to economic unit to reproduction, it’s a strange bundle, but who are we to argue with success.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That every symbolic expression recursively built from differentiable elementary functions has a derivative that can also be written as a recursive combination of elementary functions, although the latter expression may require vastly more terms.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That every expression graph built from differentiable elementary functions and producing a scalar output has a gradient that can itself be written as an expression graph, and furthermore that the latter expression graph is always the same size as the first one and is easy to find, and thus that it’s possible to fit very large expression graphs to data.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That, eerily, biological life and biological intelligence does not appear to make use of that property of expression graphs.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That if you look at something and move your head around, you observe the entire light field, which is a five-dimensional function of three spatial coordinates and two angles, and yet if you do something fancy with lasers, somehow that entire light field can be stored on a single piece of normal two-dimensional film and then replayed later.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That, as far as I can tell, the reason five-dimensional light fields can be stored on two-dimensional film simply cannot be explained without quite a lot of wave mechanics, a vivid example of the strangeness of this place and proof that all those physicists with their diffractions and phase conjugations really are up to something.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That disposable plastic, littered or not, harmless when consumed as thousands of small particles or not, is popular for a reason.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That disposable plastic, when disposed of correctly, is literally carbon sequestration, and that if/when air-derived plastic replaces dead-plankton-derived plastic, this might be incredibly convenient, although it must be said that currently the carbon in disposable plastic only represents a single-digit percentage of total carbon emissions.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That rocks can be broken into pieces and then you can’t un-break the pieces but you can check that they came from the same rock, it’s basically cryptography.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That the deal society has made is that if you have kids then everyone you encounter is obligated to chip in a bit to assist you, and this seems to mostly work without the need for constant grimy negotiated transactions as Econ 101 would suggest, although the exact contours of this deal seem to be a bit murky.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That of all the humans that have ever lived, the majority lived under some kind of autocracy, with the rest distributed among tribal bands, chiefdoms, failed states, and flawed democracies, and only something like 1% enjoyed free elections and the rule of law and civil liberties and minimal corruption, yet we endured and today that number is closer to 10%, and so if you find yourself outside that set, do not lose heart.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>That if you were in two dimensions and you tried to eat something then maybe your body would split into two pieces since the whole path from mouth to anus would have to be disconnected, so be thankful you’re in three dimensions, although maybe you could have some kind of jigsaw-shaped digestive tract so your two pieces would only jiggle around or maybe you could use the same orifice for both purposes, remember that if you ever find yourself in two dimensions, I guess.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>(<a href="https://dynomight.net/thanks/">previously</a>, <a href="https://dynomight.net/thanks-2/">previously</a>, <a href="https://dynomight.net/thanks-3/">previously</a>, <a href="https://dynomight.net/thanks-4">previously</a>)</p>


  </section>

  <hr>

  

  <section>
    
    
    <p>Comments at
      
        <a href="https://lemmy.world/post/39398444">lemmy</a> or 
        <a href="https://dynomight.substack.com/p/thanks-5">substack</a>.
      
      

  </p></section>
  <hr>
  <section>

    <!-- <h3>related internet content opportunities</h3> -->

<span>Related</span>
<p>
    <a href="https://dynomight.net/arguments-3/">Things to argue about over the holidays instead of politics III</a> · 
    
          <a href="https://dynomight.net/#lists">lists</a>
    
    </p>

      <p>
    <a href="https://dynomight.net/thanks-4/">Underrated reasons to be thankful IV</a> · 
    
          <a href="https://dynomight.net/#lists">lists</a>
    
    </p>

      <p>
    <a href="https://dynomight.net/travel/">Obvious travel advice</a> · 
    
          <a href="https://dynomight.net/#life">life</a>
    
          <a href="https://dynomight.net/#lists">lists</a>
    
    </p>

      <p>
    <a href="https://dynomight.net/things/">Things that don't work</a> · 
    
          <a href="https://dynomight.net/#lists">lists</a>
    
    </p>

      

  </section>
  <hr>
  

</article>


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[LinkedIn is loud, and corporate is hell (143 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ramones.dev/posts/linkedin-is-loud/</link>
            <guid>46072988</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 20:30:21 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ramones.dev/posts/linkedin-is-loud/">https://ramones.dev/posts/linkedin-is-loud/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46072988">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><section>
            <blockquote>
<p>Disclaimer: this is based on emotions and not much else</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I'm so tired of reading the same post 10x because everyone wants to be included.</p>
<p>What's hot right now is the CloudFlare outage. Everyone misses the actual issue which was that there were no (automated) tests/QA that were done to prevent this bug. Even a feature flag would've been sufficient so they could've seen the issue early-on.</p>
<p>This is what every LinkedIn poster does:</p>
<ul>
<li>Open ChatGPT</li>
<li>"Rewrite this linkedin post about the cloudflare outage"</li>
<li><em>AI steers towards the use of <code>.unwrap()</code></em></li>
<li><em>LinkedIn man doesn't fact check anything or reads the post-mortem</em></li>
</ul>
<p>Result:
"Le unwrap is le dangerous. Here's how the unwrap works"</p>
<p>I'm so fucking tired. I don't care about your company, nor do I care about you. I don't care because YOU don't care either about what you post. You don't care about your career, only how it looks. In hindsight, this is the perfect representation of how LLM's function, so I'm not surprised managers are best friends with ChatGPT.</p>
<p>I'm not surprised corporate social media is lifeless, but I'm surprised no one actually cares. How do these people stay motivated to do anything. It can't just be money, right?</p>
<p>I added a disclaimer because I do feel like this post is very short-sighted. This feeling roots into the fact I'm tired of corporate hell, and these feelings resulted in me not being very productive at work. This also resulted in me being let go soon (also known as a PIP!).</p>
<p>You can skip this part if you don't care about my career.</p>
<p>When I started out at $COMPANY, it was mostly building tools with, from time to time, a manager doing a check-up. This worked amazingly, as I had time to learn and improve, and I was able to deliver.</p>
<p>Fast-forward a few months, we now have 3 managers, 1 dev (hi), and a buttload of busywork that needs to be done yesterday. From what I understand, a manager is supposed to be your safetynet and keep the context switching to a minimum. Tickets should feel like little updates, yet they take up 40% of my work (which could've been spent on solutioning). Since I'm the lead dev, any busywork will move tickets further back. This also means I'm to blame, because I should've been way earlier with alerting <em>them</em> about the project's drift. I'M NOT A PM! It's my job to make the project and keep you up to date. If this isn't sufficient then go to the PM (oh wait, that's not me!). Another big issue I have with this workflow is that we're sometimes moving priorization mid-cycle due to client requests. This is fine if it wasn't low priority stuff a client <em>wants</em> but doesn't <em>need</em>.</p>
<p>I get almost nothing done and I've grown tired of living in Linear. I wouldn't say I'm burnt-out. Similarly to an orgasm, you'd know if you had one. The company has turned into a startup with only the shortcomings and all of the corporate hell I wanted to avoid.</p>
<p>As I mentioned before, I'm being let go in January (as well as other people at the company). 2026 is going to start interestingly, but I think it would be free-ing. I still wish everyone at the company the best, because there are some smart and kind people I will miss.</p>

        </section></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[AI CEO – Replace your boss before they replace you (366 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://replaceyourboss.ai/</link>
            <guid>46072002</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 18:37:41 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://replaceyourboss.ai/">https://replaceyourboss.ai/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46072002">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pakistan says rooftop solar output to exceed grid demand in some hubs next year (190 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/pakistan-says-rooftop-solar-output-exceed-grid-demand-some-hubs-next-year-2025-11-22/</link>
            <guid>46070915</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 16:42:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/pakistan-says-rooftop-solar-output-exceed-grid-demand-some-hubs-next-year-2025-11-22/">https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/pakistan-says-rooftop-solar-output-exceed-grid-demand-some-hubs-next-year-2025-11-22/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46070915">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.reuters.com/sustainability/boards-policy-regulation/pakistan-says-rooftop-solar-output-exceed-grid-demand-some-hubs-next-year-2025-11-22/: Error: Request failed with status code 401]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Same-day upstream Linux support for Snapdragon 8 Elite Gen 5 (311 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.qualcomm.com/developer/blog/2025/10/same-day-snapdragon-8-elite-gen-5-upstream-linux-support</link>
            <guid>46070668</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 16:19:03 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.qualcomm.com/developer/blog/2025/10/same-day-snapdragon-8-elite-gen-5-upstream-linux-support">https://www.qualcomm.com/developer/blog/2025/10/same-day-snapdragon-8-elite-gen-5-upstream-linux-support</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46070668">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Unparsable&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[We're Losing Our Voice to LLMs (328 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://tonyalicea.dev/blog/were-losing-our-voice-to-llms/</link>
            <guid>46069771</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:51:01 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://tonyalicea.dev/blog/were-losing-our-voice-to-llms/">https://tonyalicea.dev/blog/were-losing-our-voice-to-llms/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46069771">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article>
  
  <p><img src="https://tonyalicea.dev/assets/blogimages/coloredpencils.png" alt="Colored pencils">
</p>

<p>Social media has become a reminder of something precious we are losing in the age of LLMs: <strong>unique voices</strong>.</p>
<p>Over time, it has become obvious just how many posts are being generated by an LLM. The tell is the voice. Every post sounds like it was posted by the same social media manager.</p>
<p>If you rely on an LLM to write all your posts, you are making a mistake.</p>
<p>Your voice is an asset. Not just what you want to say, but how you say it.</p>
<p>Your voice is unique. It is formed from your lifetime of lived experiences. No one's voice will be exactly like yours.</p>
<p>Your voice becomes recognizable. Over many posts it becomes something people subconsciously connect with, recognize, trust, and look forward to.</p>
<p>Your voice provides the framework for the impression you leave in a job interview, while networking at a meet-up, or with a co-worker.</p>
<p>Years ago I got a job thanks to my blog posts. A manager wanted my voice influencing their organization. Your voice is an asset.</p>
<p>Your voice matures and becomes even more unique with time and practice.</p>
<p>LLMs can rob you of that voice, and the rest of us lose something precious in the process.</p>
<p>Having an LLM write "in your voice" is not the same. Your voice is not static. It changes with the tides of your life and state of mind. Your most impactful message may come because it was the right moment and you were in the right frame of mind.</p>
<p>Let your voice grow with use. Let it be unique.</p>
<p>Do not let one of your greatest assets fade into atrophy, wilted by cognitive laziness.</p>
<p>Write in <em>your</em> voice.</p>
<p>I do not care what the linguistic remix machine juggles into being.</p>
<p>I care what you have to say.</p>

</article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Show HN: Runprompt – run .prompt files from the command line (102 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/chr15m/runprompt</link>
            <guid>46069556</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:26:35 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/chr15m/runprompt">https://github.com/chr15m/runprompt</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46069556">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">runprompt</h2><a id="user-content-runprompt" aria-label="Permalink: runprompt" href="#runprompt"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">A single-file Python script for running <a href="https://github.com/google/dotprompt">.prompt files</a>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="#quick-start">Quick start</a> | <a href="#examples">Examples</a> | <a href="#configuration">Configuration</a> | <a href="#providers">Providers</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Quick start</h2><a id="user-content-quick-start" aria-label="Permalink: Quick start" href="#quick-start"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="curl -O https://raw.githubusercontent.com/chr15m/runprompt/main/runprompt
chmod +x runprompt"><pre>curl -O https://raw.githubusercontent.com/chr15m/runprompt/main/runprompt
chmod +x runprompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Create <code>hello.prompt</code>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="---
model: anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514
---
Say hello to {{name}}!"><pre><span>---</span>
<span><span>model</span>: <span>anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514</span></span>
<span>---</span>
Say hello to <span>{{</span><span>name</span><span>}}</span>!</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Run it:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export ANTHROPIC_API_KEY=&quot;your-key&quot;
echo '{&quot;name&quot;: &quot;World&quot;}' | ./runprompt hello.prompt"><pre><span>export</span> ANTHROPIC_API_KEY=<span><span>"</span>your-key<span>"</span></span>
<span>echo</span> <span><span>'</span>{"name": "World"}<span>'</span></span> <span>|</span> ./runprompt hello.prompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Examples</h2><a id="user-content-examples" aria-label="Permalink: Examples" href="#examples"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">In addition to the following, see the <a href="https://github.com/chr15m/runprompt/blob/main/tests">tests folder</a> for more example <code>.prompt</code> files.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Basic prompt with stdin</h3><a id="user-content-basic-prompt-with-stdin" aria-label="Permalink: Basic prompt with stdin" href="#basic-prompt-with-stdin"></a></p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="---
model: anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514
---
Summarize this text: {{STDIN}}"><pre><span>---</span>
<span><span>model</span>: <span>anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514</span></span>
<span>---</span>
Summarize this text: <span>{{</span><span>STDIN</span><span>}}</span></pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="cat article.txt | ./runprompt summarize.prompt"><pre>cat article.txt <span>|</span> ./runprompt summarize.prompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The special <code>{{STDIN}}</code> variable always contains the raw stdin as a string.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Structured JSON output</h3><a id="user-content-structured-json-output" aria-label="Permalink: Structured JSON output" href="#structured-json-output"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Extract structured data using an output schema:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="---
model: anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514
input:
  schema:
    text: string
output:
  format: json
  schema:
    name?: string, the person's name
    age?: number, the person's age
    occupation?: string, the person's job
---
Extract info from: {{text}}"><pre><span>---</span>
<span><span>model</span>: <span>anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514</span></span>
<span><span>input</span>:</span>
<span>  <span>schema</span>:</span>
<span>    <span>text</span>: <span>string</span></span>
<span><span>output</span>:</span>
<span>  <span>format</span>: <span>json</span></span>
<span>  <span>schema</span>:</span>
<span>    <span>name?</span>: <span>string, the person's name</span></span>
<span>    <span>age?</span>: <span>number, the person's age</span></span>
<span>    <span>occupation?</span>: <span>string, the person's job</span></span>
<span>---</span>
Extract info from: <span>{{</span><span>text</span><span>}}</span></pre></div>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo &quot;John is a 30 year old teacher&quot; | ./runprompt extract.prompt
# {&quot;name&quot;: &quot;John&quot;, &quot;age&quot;: 30, &quot;occupation&quot;: &quot;teacher&quot;}"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>"</span>John is a 30 year old teacher<span>"</span></span> <span>|</span> ./runprompt extract.prompt
<span><span>#</span> {"name": "John", "age": 30, "occupation": "teacher"}</span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Fields ending with <code>?</code> are optional. The format is <code>field: type, description</code>.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Chaining prompts</h3><a id="user-content-chaining-prompts" aria-label="Permalink: Chaining prompts" href="#chaining-prompts"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Pipe structured output between prompts:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="echo &quot;John is 30&quot; | ./runprompt extract.prompt | ./runprompt generate-bio.prompt"><pre><span>echo</span> <span><span>"</span>John is 30<span>"</span></span> <span>|</span> ./runprompt extract.prompt <span>|</span> ./runprompt generate-bio.prompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">The JSON output from the first prompt becomes template variables in the second.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">CLI overrides</h3><a id="user-content-cli-overrides" aria-label="Permalink: CLI overrides" href="#cli-overrides"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Override any frontmatter value from the command line:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="./runprompt --model anthropic/claude-haiku-4-20250514 hello.prompt
./runprompt --name &quot;Alice&quot; hello.prompt"><pre>./runprompt --model anthropic/claude-haiku-4-20250514 hello.prompt
./runprompt --name <span><span>"</span>Alice<span>"</span></span> hello.prompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Configuration</h2><a id="user-content-configuration" aria-label="Permalink: Configuration" href="#configuration"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Environment variables</h3><a id="user-content-environment-variables" aria-label="Permalink: Environment variables" href="#environment-variables"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Set API keys for your providers:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export ANTHROPIC_API_KEY=&quot;...&quot;
export OPENAI_API_KEY=&quot;...&quot;
export GOOGLE_API_KEY=&quot;...&quot;
export OPENROUTER_API_KEY=&quot;...&quot;"><pre><span>export</span> ANTHROPIC_API_KEY=<span><span>"</span>...<span>"</span></span>
<span>export</span> OPENAI_API_KEY=<span><span>"</span>...<span>"</span></span>
<span>export</span> GOOGLE_API_KEY=<span><span>"</span>...<span>"</span></span>
<span>export</span> OPENROUTER_API_KEY=<span><span>"</span>...<span>"</span></span></pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">RUNPROMPT_* overrides</h3><a id="user-content-runprompt_-overrides" aria-label="Permalink: RUNPROMPT_* overrides" href="#runprompt_-overrides"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Override any frontmatter value via environment variables prefixed with <code>RUNPROMPT_</code>:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="export RUNPROMPT_MODEL=&quot;anthropic/claude-haiku-4-20250514&quot;
./runprompt hello.prompt"><pre><span>export</span> RUNPROMPT_MODEL=<span><span>"</span>anthropic/claude-haiku-4-20250514<span>"</span></span>
./runprompt hello.prompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto">This is useful for setting defaults across multiple prompt runs.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Verbose mode</h3><a id="user-content-verbose-mode" aria-label="Permalink: Verbose mode" href="#verbose-mode"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Use <code>-v</code> to see request/response details:</p>
<div dir="auto" data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="./runprompt -v hello.prompt"><pre>./runprompt -v hello.prompt</pre></div>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Providers</h2><a id="user-content-providers" aria-label="Permalink: Providers" href="#providers"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Models are specified as <code>provider/model-name</code>:</p>
<markdown-accessiblity-table><table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Provider</th>
<th>Model format</th>
<th>API key env var</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Anthropic</td>
<td><code>anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514</code></td>
<td><code>ANTHROPIC_API_KEY</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OpenAI</td>
<td><code>openai/gpt-4o</code></td>
<td><code>OPENAI_API_KEY</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Google AI</td>
<td><code>googleai/gemini-1.5-pro</code></td>
<td><code>GOOGLE_API_KEY</code></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>OpenRouter</td>
<td><code>openrouter/anthropic/claude-sonnet-4-20250514</code></td>
<td><code>OPENROUTER_API_KEY</code></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table></markdown-accessiblity-table>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://openrouter.ai/" rel="nofollow">OpenRouter</a> provides access to models from many providers (Anthropic, Google, Meta, etc.) through a single API key.</p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[TPUs vs. GPUs and why Google is positioned to win AI race in the long term (242 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.uncoveralpha.com/p/the-chip-made-for-the-ai-inference</link>
            <guid>46069048</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 13:28:34 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.uncoveralpha.com/p/the-chip-made-for-the-ai-inference">https://www.uncoveralpha.com/p/the-chip-made-for-the-ai-inference</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46069048">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div dir="auto"><p>Hey everyone,</p><p>As I find the topic of Google TPUs extremely important, I am publishing a comprehensive deep dive, not just a technical overview, but also strategic and financial coverage of the Google TPU.</p><p>Topics covered:</p><ul><li><p>The history of the TPU and why it all even started?</p></li><li><p>The difference between a TPU and a GPU?</p></li><li><p>Performance numbers TPU vs GPU?</p></li><li><p>Where are the problems for the wider adoption of TPUs</p></li><li><p>Google’s TPU is the biggest competitive advantage of its cloud business for the next 10 years</p></li><li><p>How many TPUs does Google produce today, and how big can that get?</p></li><li><p>Gemini 3 and the aftermath of Gemini 3 on the whole chip industry</p></li></ul><p>Let’s dive into it.</p><div><figure><a target="_blank" href="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png" data-component-name="Image2ToDOM" rel=""><div><picture><source type="image/webp" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_424,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_848,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_webp,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 1456w" sizes="100vw"><img src="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png" width="1024" height="1024" data-attrs="{&quot;src&quot;:&quot;https://substack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com/public/images/ff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png&quot;,&quot;srcNoWatermark&quot;:null,&quot;fullscreen&quot;:null,&quot;imageSize&quot;:null,&quot;height&quot;:1024,&quot;width&quot;:1024,&quot;resizeWidth&quot;:null,&quot;bytes&quot;:1683293,&quot;alt&quot;:null,&quot;title&quot;:null,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;image/png&quot;,&quot;href&quot;:null,&quot;belowTheFold&quot;:false,&quot;topImage&quot;:true,&quot;internalRedirect&quot;:&quot;https://www.uncoveralpha.com/i/179815720?img=https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png&quot;,&quot;isProcessing&quot;:false,&quot;align&quot;:null,&quot;offset&quot;:false}" alt="" srcset="https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_424,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 424w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_848,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 848w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_1272,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 1272w, https://substackcdn.com/image/fetch/$s_!H_F9!,w_1456,c_limit,f_auto,q_auto:good,fl_progressive:steep/https%3A%2F%2Fsubstack-post-media.s3.amazonaws.com%2Fpublic%2Fimages%2Fff173524-b98d-4a2b-9f77-7a130ad395a7_1024x1024.png 1456w" sizes="100vw" fetchpriority="high"></picture></div></a></figure></div><p><strong>The history of the TPU and why it all even started?</strong></p><p>The story of the Google Tensor Processing Unit (TPU) begins not with a breakthrough in chip manufacturing, but with a realization about math and logistics. Around 2013, Google’s leadership—specifically Jeff Dean, Jonathan Ross (the CEO of Groq), and the Google Brain team—ran a projection that alarmed them. They calculated that if every Android user utilized Google’s new voice search feature for just three minutes a day, the company would need to double its global data center capacity just to handle the compute load.</p><p>At the time, Google was relying on standard CPUs and GPUs for these tasks. While powerful, these general-purpose chips were inefficient for the specific heavy lifting required by Deep Learning: massive matrix multiplications. Scaling up with existing hardware would have been a financial and logistical nightmare.</p><p><span>This sparked a new project. Google decided to do something rare for a software company: build its own custom silicon. The goal was to create an </span><strong>ASIC (Application-Specific Integrated Circuit)</strong><span> designed for one job only: running TensorFlow neural networks.</span></p><p>Key Historical Milestones:</p><ul><li><p><span>2013-2014:</span><strong> </strong><span>The project moved really fast as Google both hired a very capable team and, to be honest, had some luck in their first steps. The team went from design concept to deploying silicon in data centers in just 15 months—a very short cycle for hardware engineering.</span></p></li><li><p><span>2015:</span><strong> </strong><span>Before the world knew they existed, TPUs were already powering Google’s most popular products. They were silently accelerating Google Maps navigation, Google Photos, and Google Translate.</span></p></li><li><p><span>2016</span><strong>:</strong><span> Google officially unveiled the TPU at Google I/O 2016.</span></p></li></ul><p>This urgency to solve the “data center doubling” problem is why the TPU exists. It wasn’t built to sell to gamers or render video; it was built to save Google from its own AI success. With that in mind, Google has been thinking about the »costly« AI inference problems for over a decade now. This is also one of the main reasons why the TPU is so good today compared to other ASIC projects.</p><p><strong>The difference between a TPU and a GPU?</strong></p><p>To understand the difference, it helps to look at what each chip was originally built to do. A GPU is a “general-purpose” parallel processor, while a TPU is a “domain-specific” architecture.</p><p>The GPUs were designed for graphics. They excel at parallel processing (doing many things at once), which is great for AI. However, because they are designed to handle everything from video game textures to scientific simulations, they carry “architectural baggage.” They spend significant energy and chip area on complex tasks like caching, branch prediction, and managing independent threads.</p><p>A TPU, on the other hand, strips away all that baggage. It has no hardware for rasterization or texture mapping. Instead, it uses a unique architecture called a Systolic Array.</p><p>The “Systolic Array” is the key differentiator. In a standard CPU or GPU, the chip moves data back and forth between the memory and the computing units for every calculation. This constant shuffling creates a bottleneck (the Von Neumann bottleneck).</p><p>In a TPU’s systolic array, data flows through the chip like blood through a heart (hence “systolic”).</p><ol><li><p>It loads data (weights) once.</p></li><li><p>It passes inputs through a massive grid of multipliers.</p></li><li><p>The data is passed directly to the next unit in the array without writing back to memory.</p></li></ol><p>What this means, in essence, is that a TPU, because of its systolic array, drastically reduces the number of memory reads and writes required from HBM. As a result, the TPU can spend its cycles computing rather than waiting for data.</p><p>Google’s new TPU design, also called Ironwood also addressed some of the key areas where a TPU was lacking:</p><ul><li><p>They enhanced the SparseCore for efficiently handling large embeddings (good for recommendation systems and LLMs)</p></li><li><p>It increased HBM capacity and bandwidth (up to 192 GB per chip). For a better understanding, Nvidia’s Blackwell B200 has 192GB per chip, while Blackwell Ultra, also known as the B300, has 288 GB per chip.</p></li><li><p>Improved the Inter-Chip Interconnect (ICI) for linking thousands of chips into massive clusters, also called TPU Pods (needed for AI training as well as some time test compute inference workloads). When it comes to ICI, it is important to note that it is very performant with a Peak Bandwidth of 1.2 TB/s vs Blackwell NVLink 5 at 1.8 TB/s. But Google’s ICI, together with its specialized compiler and software stack, still delivers superior performance on some specific AI tasks.</p></li></ul><p>The key thing to understand is that because the TPU doesn’t need to decode complex instructions or constantly access memory, it can deliver significantly higher Operations Per Joule.</p><p>For scale-out, Google uses Optical Circuit Switch (OCS) and its 3D torus network, which compete with Nvidia’s InfiniBand and Spectrum-X Ethernet. The main difference is that OCS is extremely cost-effective and power-efficient as it eliminates electrical switches and O-E-O conversions, but because of this, it is not as flexible as the other two. So again, the Google stack is extremely specialized for the task at hand and doesn’t offer the flexibility that GPUs do.</p><p><strong>Performance numbers TPU vs GPU?</strong></p><p>As we defined the differences, let’s look at real numbers showing how the TPU performs compared to the GPU. Since Google isn’t revealing these numbers, it is really hard to get details on performance. I studied many articles and alternative data sources, including interviews with industry insiders, and here are some of the key takeaways.</p><p>The first important thing is that there is very limited information on Google’s newest TPUv7 (Ironwood), as Google introduced it in April 2025 and is just now starting to become available to external clients (internally, it is said that Google has already been using Ironwood since April, possibly even for Gemini 3.0.). And why is this important if we, for example, compare TPUv7 with an older but still widely used version of TPUv5p based on Semianalysis data:</p><ul><li><p>TPUv7 produces 4,614 TFLOPS(BF16) vs 459 TFLOPS for TPUv5p</p></li><li><p>TPUv7 has 192GB of memory capacity vs TPUv5p 96GB</p></li><li><p>TPUv7 memory Bandwidth is 7,370 GB/s vs 2,765 for v5p</p></li></ul><p>We can see that the performance leaps between v5 and v7 are very significant. To put that in context, most of the comments that we will look at are more focused on TPUv6 or TPUv5 than v7.</p><p>Based on analyzing a ton of interviews with Former Google employees, customers, and competitors (people from AMD, NVDA &amp; others), the summary of the results is as follows.</p><p>Most agree that TPUs are more cost-effective compared to Nvidia GPUs, and most agree that the performance per watt for TPUs is better. This view is not applicable across all use cases tho.</p><p>A Former Google Cloud employee:</p><div><p>»If it is the right application, then they can deliver much better performance per dollar compared to GPUs. They also require much lesser energy and produces less heat compared to GPUs. They’re also more energy efficient and have a smaller environmental footprint, which is what makes them a desired outcome.</p><p>The use cases are slightly limited to a GPU, they’re not as generic, but for a specific application, they can offer as much as 1.4X better performance per dollar, which is pretty significant saving for a customer that might be trying to use GPU versus TPUs.«</p><p><span>source: </span><a href="https://www.alpha-sense.com/uncoveralpha/" rel="">AlphaSense</a></p></div><p>Similarly, a very insightful comment from a Former Unit Head at Google around TPUs materially lowering AI-search cost per query vs GPUs:</p><p>»TPU v6 is 60-65% more efficient than GPUs, prior generations 40-45%«</p><p>This interview was in November 2024, so the expert is probably comparing the v6 TPU with the Nvidia Hopper. Today, we already have Blackwell vs V7.</p><p>Many experts also mention the speed benefit that TPUs offer, with a Former Google Head saying that TPUs are 5x faster than GPUs for training dynamic models (like search-like workloads).</p><p>There was also a very eye-opening interview with a client who used both Nvidia GPUs and Google TPUs as he describes the economics in great detail:</p><div><p>»If I were to use eight H100s versus using one v5e pod, I would spend a lot less money on one v5e pod. In terms of price point money, performance per dollar, you will get more bang for TPU. If I already have a code, because of Google’s help or because of our own work, if I know it already is going to work on a TPU, then at that point it is beneficial for me to just stick with the TPU usage.</p><div><p><span>In the long run, if I am thinking I need to write a new code base, I need to do a lot more work, then it depends on how long I’m going to train. I would say there is still some, for example, of the workload we have already done on TPUs that in the future because as Google will add newer generation of TPU, they make older ones much cheaper.</span></p><p><span>For example, when they came out with v4, I remember the price of v2 came down so low that it was practically free to use compared to any NVIDIA GPUs.</span></p></div><p>Google has got a good promise so they keep supporting older TPUs and they’re making it a lot cheaper. If you don’t really need your model trained right away, if you’re willing to say, “I can wait one week,” even though the training is only three days, then you can reduce your cost 1/5.«</p><p><span>source: </span><a href="https://www.alpha-sense.com/uncoveralpha/" rel="">AlphaSense</a></p></div><p>Another valuable interview was with a current AMD employee, acknowledging the benefits of ASICs:</p><p>»I would expect that an AI accelerator could do about probably typically what we see in the industry. I’m using my experience at FPGAs. I could see a 30% reduction in size and maybe a 50% reduction in power vs a GPU.«</p><p>We also got some numbers from a Former Google employee who worked in the chip segment:</p><p>»When I look at the published numbers, they (TPUs) are anywhere from 25%-30% better to close to 2x better, depending on the use cases compared to Nvidia. Essentially, there’s a difference between a very custom design built to do one task perfectly versus a more general purpose design.«</p><p>What is also known is that the real edge of TPUs lies not in the hardware but in the software and in the way Google has optimized its ecosystem for the TPU.</p><p>A lot of people mention the problem that every Nvidia »competitor« like the TPU faces, which is the fast development of Nvidia and the constant »catching up« to Nvidia problem. This month a former Google Cloud employee addressed that concern head-on as he believes the rate at which TPUs are improving is faster than the rate at Nvidia:</p><p>»The amount of performance per dollar that a TPU can generate from a new generation versus the old generation is a much significant jump than Nvidia«</p><p>In addition, the recent data from Google’s presentation at the Hot Chips 2025 event backs that up, as Google stated that the TPUv7 is 100% better in performance per watt than their TPUv6e (Trillium).</p><p>Even for hard Nvidia advocates, TPUs are not to be shrugged off easily, as even Jensen thinks very highly of Google’s TPUs. In a podcast with Brad Gerstner, he mentioned that when it comes to ASICs, Google with TPUs is a »special case«. A few months ago, we also got an article from the WSJ saying that after the news publication The Information published a report that stated that OpenAI had begun renting Google TPUs for ChatGPT, Jensen called Altman, asking him if it was true, and signaled that he was open to getting the talks back on track (investment talks). Also worth noting was that Nvidia’s official X account posted a screenshot of an article in which OpenAI denied plans to use Google’s in-house chips. To say the least, Nvidia is watching TPUs very closely.</p><p>Ok, but after looking at some of these numbers, one might think, why aren’t more clients using TPUs?</p><p><strong>Where are the problems for the wider adoption of TPUs</strong></p><p><span>The main problem for TPUs adoption is the ecosystem. Nvidia’s CUDA is engraved in the minds of most AI engineers, as they have been learning CUDA in universities.</span><strong> </strong><span>Google has developed its ecosystem internally but not externally, as it has used TPUs only for its internal workloads until now. TPUs use a combination of JAX and TensorFlow, while the industry skews to CUDA and PyTorch (although TPUs also support PyTorch now). While Google is working hard to make its ecosystem more supportive and convertible with other stacks, it is also a matter of libraries and ecosystem formation that takes years to develop.</span></p><p>It is also important to note that, until recently, the GenAI industry’s focus has largely been on training workloads. In training workloads, CUDA is very important, but when it comes to inference, even reasoning inference, CUDA is not that important, so the chances of expanding the TPU footprint in inference are much higher than those in training (although TPUs do really well in training as well – Gemini 3 the prime example).</p><p>The fact that most clients are multi-cloud also poses a challenge for TPU adoption, as AI workloads are closely tied to data and its location (cloud data transfer is costly). Nvidia is accessible via all three hyperscalers, while TPUs are available only at GCP so far. A client who uses TPUs and Nvidia GPUs explains it well:</p><div><p>»Right now, the one biggest advantage of NVIDIA, and this has been true for past three companies I worked on is because AWS, Google Cloud and Microsoft Azure, these are the three major cloud companies.</p><p>Every company, every corporate, every customer we have will have data in one of these three. All these three clouds have NVIDIA GPUs. Sometimes the data is so big and in a different cloud that it is a lot cheaper to run our workload in whatever cloud the customer has data in.</p><p>I don’t know if you know about the egress cost that is moving data out of one cloud is one of the bigger cost. In that case, if you have NVIDIA workload, if you have a CUDA workload, we can just go to Microsoft Azure, get a VM that has NVIDIA GPU, same GPU in fact, no code change is required and just run it there.</p><p>With TPUs, once you are all relied on TPU and Google says, “You know what? Now you have to pay 10X more,” then we would be screwed, because then we’ll have to go back and rewrite everything. That’s why. That’s the only reason people are afraid of committing too much on TPUs. The same reason is for Amazon’s Trainium and Inferentia.«</p><p><span>source: </span><a href="https://www.alpha-sense.com/uncoveralpha/" rel="">AlphaSense</a></p></div><p>These problems are well known at Google, so it is no surprise that internally, the debate over keeping TPUs inside Google or starting to sell them externally is a constant topic. When keeping them internally, it enhances the GCP moat, but at the same time, many former Google employees believe that at some point, Google will start offering TPUs externally as well, maybe through some neoclouds, not necessarily with the biggest two competitors, Microsoft and Amazon. Opening up the ecosystem, providing support, etc., and making it more widely usable are the first steps toward making that possible.</p><p>A former Google employee also mentioned that Google last year formed a more sales-oriented team to push and sell TPUs, so it’s not like they have been pushing hard to sell TPUs for years; it is a fairly new dynamic in the organization.</p><p><strong>Google’s TPU is the biggest competitive advantage of its cloud business for the next 10 years</strong></p><p>The most valuable thing for me about TPUs is their impact on GCP. As we witness the transformation of cloud businesses from the pre-AI era to the AI era, the biggest takeaway is that the industry has gone from an oligopoly of AWS, Azure, and GCP to a more commoditized landscape, with Oracle, Coreweave, and many other neoclouds competing for AI workloads. The problem with AI workloads is the competition and Nvidia’s 75% gross margin, which also results in low margins for AI workloads. The cloud industry is moving from a 50-70% gross margin industry to a 20-35% gross margin industry. For cloud investors, this should be concerning, as the future profile of some of these companies is more like that of a utility than an attractive, high-margin business. But there is a solution to avoiding that future and returning to a normal margin: the ASIC.</p><p>The cloud providers who can control the hardware and are not beholden to Nvidia and its 75% gross margin will be able to return to the world of 50% gross margins. And there is no surprise that all three AWS, Azure, and GCP are developing their own ASICs. The most mature by far is Google’s TPU, followed by Amazon’s Trainum, and lastly Microsoft’s MAIA (although Microsoft owns the full IP of OpenAI’s custom ASICs, which could help them in the future).</p><p>While even with ASICs you are not 100% independent, as you still have to work with someone like Broadcom or Marvell, whose margins are lower than Nvidia’s but still not negligible, Google is again in a very good position. Over the years of developing TPUs, Google has managed to control much of the chip design process in-house. According to a current AMD employee, Broadcom no longer knows everything about the chip. At this point, Google is the front-end designer (the actual RTL of the design) while Broadcom is only the backend physical design partner. Google, on top of that, also, of course, owns the entire software optimization stack for the chip, which makes it as performant as it is. According to the AMD employee, based on this work split, he thinks Broadcom is lucky if it gets a 50-point gross margin on its part.</p><p>Without having to pay Nvidia for the accelerator, a cloud provider can either price its compute similarly to others and maintain a better margin profile or lower costs and gain market share. Of course, all of this depends on having a very capable ASIC that can compete with Nvidia. Unfortunately, it looks like Google is the only one that has achieved that, as the number one-performing model is Gemini 3 trained on TPUs. According to some former Google employees, internally, Google is also using TPUs for inference across its entire AI stack, including Gemini and models like Veo. Google buys Nvidia GPUs for GCP, as clients want them because they are familiar with them and the ecosystem, but internally, Google is full-on with TPUs.</p><p>As the complexity of each generation of ASICs increases, similar to the complexity and pace of Nvidia, I predict that not all ASIC programs will make it. I believe outside of TPUs, the only real hyperscaler shot right now is AWS Trainium, but even that faces much bigger uncertainties than the TPU. With that in mind, Google and its cloud business can come out of this AI era as a major beneficiary and market-share gainer.</p><p>Recently, we even got comments from the SemiAnalysis team praising the TPU:</p><div><p><span>»Google’s silicon supremacy among hyperscalers is unmatched, with their TPU 7</span><sup>th</sup><span> Gen arguably on par with Nvidia Blackwell. TPU powers the Gemini family of models which are improving in capability and sit close to the pareto frontier of $ per intelligence in some tasks«</span></p><p><span>source: </span><a href="https://semianalysis.com/" rel="">SemiAnalysis</a></p></div><p><strong>How many TPUs does Google produce today, and how big can that get?</strong></p><p>Here are the numbers that I researched:</p></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The State of GPL Propagation to AI Models (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/</link>
            <guid>46068777</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 12:48:12 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/">https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46068777">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div>
<p>When GitHub Copilot was launched in 2021, the fact that its training data included a vast amount of Open Source code publicly available on GitHub attracted significant attention, sparking lively debates regarding licensing. While there were issues concerning conditions such as attribution required by most licenses, there was a particularly high volume of discourse suggesting that the conditions of copyleft licenses, such as the GNU General Public License (GNU GPL), would propagate to the model itself, necessitating that the entire model be released under the same license. The propagation of the GPL is a concept that many modern software engineers have naturally accepted; thus, for an engineer with a straightforward sensibility, it is a perfectly natural progression to think that if GPL code is included in some form, copyleft applies and the license propagates.</p>



<p>However, as of 2025, the theory that the license of the source code propagates to AI models trained on Open Source code is not seen as frequently as it was back then. Although some ardent believers in software freedom still advocate for such theories, it appears they are being overwhelmed by the benefits of AI coding, which has overwhelmingly permeated the programming field. Amidst this trend, even I sometimes succumb to the illusion that such a theory never existed in the first place.</p>



<p>Has the theory that the license of training code propagates to such AI models been completely refuted?</p>



<p>Actually, it has not. This issue remains an indeterminate problem where lawsuits are still ongoing and the judgments of major national governments have not been made clear. In this article, I will explain the current situation of this license propagation theory, namely “GPL propagates to AI models trained on GPL code,” and connect it to points of discussion such as the legal positioning of models and the nature of the freedom we pursue in the AI domain.</p>



<ol><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#the-current-standing-in-two-lawsuits">The Current Standing in Two Lawsuits</a><ol><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#doe-v-github-copilot-class-action-the-persisting-claim-of-open-source-license-violation">Doe v. GitHub (Copilot Class Action): The Persisting Claim of Open Source License Violation</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#gema-v-openai-the-theory-treating-memory-in-models-as-legal-reproduction">GEMA v. OpenAI: The Theory Treating “Memory” in Models as Legal Reproduction</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#possibilities-derived-from-the-current-status-of-the-two-lawsuits">Possibilities Derived from the Current Status of the Two Lawsuits</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#treatment-under-japanese-law">Treatment under Japanese Law</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#arguments-negating-the-theory-of-license-propagation-to-models">Arguments Negating the Theory of License Propagation to Models</a><ol><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#arguments-for-negation-at-the-copyright-law-layer">Arguments for Negation at the Copyright Law Layer</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#arguments-for-negation-at-the-gpl-text-layer">Arguments for Negation at the GPL Text Layer</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#arguments-for-negation-at-the-technical-layer">Arguments for Negation at the Technical Layer</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#practical-and-policy-arguments-for-negation">Practical and Policy Arguments for Negation</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#the-stance-of-osi-and-fsf">The Stance of OSI and FSF</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#summary">Summary</a></li><li><a href="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/#references">References</a></li></ol>



<p><strong>Note:&nbsp;</strong>This article is an English translation of a post&nbsp;<a href="https://shujisado.com/2025/11/25/gpl_propagation_to_ai_models/">originally written in Japanese.</a>&nbsp;While it assumes a Japanese reader, I believe it may also be useful for an English-speaking audience.</p>



<hr>



<h2 id="the-current-standing-in-two-lawsuits">The Current Standing in Two Lawsuits</h2>



<p>First, let us organize what the “GPL propagation theory to AI models” entails. This is the idea that when an AI model ingests GPL code as training data, the model itself constitutes a derivative work (derivative) of the GPL code; therefore, when distributing the model, the copyleft conditions of the GPL, such as the obligation to disclose source code, apply. In other words, it is not a question of whether the output of the model is similar to the GPL code, but a theory that “since the model itself is a derivative containing GPL code, the GPL extends to the model.” While there were many voices supporting this theory around 2021, as mentioned earlier, it is no longer the mainstream of the discussion today. However, two major ongoing lawsuits can be cited as grounds that this theory has not been completely denied. These are <em>Doe v. GitHub</em> (the Copilot class action) filed in the United States and <em>GEMA v. OpenAI</em> filed in Germany. I will explain the history and current status of each lawsuit below.</p>



<h3 id="doe-v-github-copilot-class-action-the-persisting-claim-of-open-source-license-violation">Doe v. GitHub (Copilot Class Action): The Persisting Claim of Open Source License Violation</h3>



<p>In the Copilot class action filed at the end of 2022 in relation to GitHub Copilot, anonymous developers became plaintiffs and argued that GitHub, Microsoft, and OpenAI trained their models on source code from public repositories without permission, inviting massive license violations through Copilot. Specifically, they viewed it as problematic that when Copilot reproduces part of the code that served as the training source in its output, it does not perform the author attribution or copyright notice required by licenses such as MIT or Apache-2.0 at all, and furthermore, it indiscriminately trains on and outputs code under licenses that impose copyleft conditions like the GPL, thereby trampling on license clauses. The plaintiffs claimed this was a contractual violation of open source licenses and also sought damages and injunctions, asserting that it constituted a violation of the Digital Millennium Copyright Act (DMCA) under copyright law.</p>



<p>In this case, several decisions have already been handed down by the United States District Court for the Northern District of California, and many of the plaintiffs’ claims have been dismissed. What were dismissed were mainly peripheral claims such as DMCA clause violations, privacy policy violations, unjust enrichment, and torts, but some DMCA violations and the claim of “violation of open source licenses” (breach of contract) are still alive. Regarding the latter specifically, the argument is that despite the plaintiffs’ code being published under licenses like GPL or MIT, the defendants failed to comply with the author attribution or the obligation to publish derivatives under the same license, which constitutes a contractual violation. Although the court did not recognize claims for monetary damages because the plaintiffs could not demonstrate a specific amount of damage, it determined that there were sufficient grounds for the claim for injunctive relief against the license violation itself. As a result, the plaintiffs are permitted to continue the lawsuit seeking an order prohibiting the act of Copilot reproducing others’ code without appropriate license indications.</p>



<p>As is clear from the above history, “violation of open source licenses in training data” is still being contested in court in the Copilot litigation, and this is one of the reasons why the theory of license propagation to models has not been completely denied. The plaintiffs’ claim in this lawsuit does not directly demand the release of the model itself under the GPL, but it legally pursues the point that license conditions were ignored in the process of training and output; consequently, it suggests that “if the handling does not follow the license of the training data, the act of providing the model could be illegal.” Furthermore, the court has not clearly rejected this logic at this stage and has indicated a judgment that the use of open source code is accompanied by license obligations, and providing tools that ignore this could constitute a tort subject to injunction.</p>



<p>However, it is necessary to note that the claims in the Copilot litigation are legally framed as breach of contract (license) or DMCA violation, and are not a direct copyright argument that “the model is a derivative work of GPL code.” No judgment has been shown stepping so far as to mandate the disclosure of the entire model under the GPL license. The actual judgment is conservative, stating “monetary damages have not been shown, but there is room for future injunctive relief,” and does not mention the obligation to disclose the model itself. In other words, at present, there is no judicial precedent directly addressing the “GPL propagation theory to models,” and the situation is one where the issue raised regarding license violation of the source code remains alive in the judicial arena.</p>



<h3 id="gema-v-openai-the-theory-treating-memory-in-models-as-legal-reproduction">GEMA v. OpenAI: The Theory Treating “Memory” in Models as Legal Reproduction</h3>



<p>Another important lawsuit is the case where the German music copyright collective GEMA sued OpenAI. This is a copyright lawsuit concerning the unauthorized training and output of lyrics by an AI model, not AI code generation, but it carries significant theoretical implications related to “license propagation to models” even if not directly related to GPL.</p>



<p>In November 2025, the Munich I Regional Court handed down a judgment on this lawsuit, indicating regarding the matter where the ChatGPT model had memorized and reproduced the lyrics of 9 famous German songs, that the act of “memory” inside the model itself falls under the act of reproduction under copyright law. According to the judgment, the lyrics under the plaintiff’s management were “fixed” in the models of ChatGPT’s GPT-4 and 4o, and the situation was such that the lyrics were output almost verbatim just by the user giving a simple prompt. Based on this, the court determined that the model contains “parameters that memorized the work” internally, and if it is possible to reproduce an expression substantially identical to the original work for a human by means of an appropriate prompt, that memory itself falls under “reproduction” in Article 16 of the German Copyright Act. Furthermore, it determined that the act of actually outputting lyrics in response to a prompt is also a separate act of reproduction, and providing lyrics to the user falls under the act of making available to the public (public transmission). Also, it ruled that since all of these are done without the permission of the rights holder, they deviate from the scope justified by the TDM (Text and Data Mining) exception in the EU DSM Copyright Directive.</p>



<p>The important point of this judgment is that it clearly acknowledged that “if a work is recorded inside the model in a reproducible form, that state itself can constitute copyright infringement.” The court cited the text of the EU InfoSoc Directive that “reproduction includes copies in any form or manner, and does not need to be directly perceptible to humans,” and stated that in the spirit of this, even if the lyrics are encoded within the model’s parameters, it amounts to the creation of a reproduction. It went as far as to mention that “encoding in the form of probabilistic weights does not prevent it from being considered a copy,” showing a strong recognition that differences in technical formats cannot avoid the nature of reproduction under copyright law. Also, since the fact that the model could output the lyrics was not coincidental but highly consistent, it was factually found that “the direct incorporation of the essential part of the training data” occurred rather than the result of statistical learning. As a result, the Munich District Court recognized OpenAI’s liability for injunction and damages regarding the output act of the lyrics in question, and further ordered the provision of information regarding training data and output content for the future. However, this judgment is the first instance, and since OpenAI has indicated an intention to appeal, it is expected to be a continuing dispute.</p>



<p>The noteworthy theory shown by this GEMA judgment is the extension of the concept of reproduction under copyright law to the interior of the model. That is, if the work used as training data remains within the model and can be reproduced with a simple operation, it means the model already contains a reproduction of that work. This theory is groundbreaking in that it deems “the model contains the source work,” and indeed, in a commentary by Osborne Clarke, it is evaluated that “in contrast to the judgment of the English High Court in the <em>Getty v. Stability AI</em> case, the Munich District Court explicitly recognized the possibility that the AI model contains copies of the training material.” Standing on this view, the model is not merely a result of analysis, but depending on the case, can be evaluated as an aggregate of the training data itself.</p>



<p>However, it is necessary to keep in mind that this judgment is based on an extreme case where a complete match output was obtained with short text such as lyrics. The court itself stated, “Normally, temporary reproduction for learning remains within the purpose of analysis and does not infringe on the rights holder’s market, but in this case, the model holds the work in a restorable form and exceeds the scope of analysis,” emphasizing that the judgment is limited to “cases where the model performs complete reproduction.” Also, as the UK case shows, judicial decisions vary by country, and a legal consensus on this issue has not yet been formed.</p>



<p>Nevertheless, the judgment this time, which declared that the recording of a work inside a model is a reproduction, can become a major basis supporting the license propagation theory. This is because, while the premise for discussing GPL propagation is “whether the model can be said to be a reproduction or derivative work of the GPL code,” the logic of the Munich District Court legally certified exactly that “a model can be a reproduction of training data”.</p>



<h3 id="possibilities-derived-from-the-current-status-of-the-two-lawsuits">Possibilities Derived from the Current Status of the Two Lawsuits</h3>



<p>From the two lawsuits above, we can consider the path through which the theory of license propagation to AI models might be recognized in the future.</p>



<p>Let us assume the worst-case scenario from the perspective of AI operators, where these lawsuits are finalized with the plaintiffs winning. In the Copilot litigation, the judgment that “model providers must comply with the license conditions of the training source code” would be established, and in the GEMA litigation, the legal principle that “the model encompasses reproductions of the work” would be established. When these two intersect, the conclusion that “since an AI model containing GPL code is a reproduction or derivative work of the GPL code, the conditions of the GPL directly apply to its provision” is theoretically derived. That is, the possibility emerges that the theory of GPL propagation to models is effectively ratified by the judiciary.</p>



<p>Specifically, if the model memorizes and contains GPL code fragments internally, the act of distributing or providing that model to a third party may be regarded as the distribution of a reproduction of GPL code; in that case, the act of distribution under conditions other than GPL would be evaluated as a GPL license violation. If a GPL violation is established, there would be room to argue for remedies such as injunctions and claims for damages, as well as forced GPL compliance demanding the disclosure of the entire model under the same license, just as in the case of ordinary software. In fact, the remedies GEMA sought from OpenAI included disclosure regarding training data and output content, and although this is in the context of musical works, this can be said to be a type of disclosure request to make transparent “what the model learned and contains.” In the case of a GPL violation as well, the possibility cannot be denied that demands such as “disclosure of the GPL code parts contained inside the model” or “source disclosure in a form that allows reconstruction of the model” would emerge in seeking license compliance.</p>



<p>Even if not reaching such an extreme conclusion, an intermediate scenario could involve imposing certain restrictions on model providers. For example, the Copilot litigation might be settled or judged by taking measures such as “attaching a license and author attribution at the time of output if existing code of a certain length or more is included in the generated code,” or technically mandating the implementation of filters so that GPL code fragments are not extracted or reproduced from the model. In fact, GitHub, the developer of Copilot, has already introduced an optional feature that “excludes from suggestions if the candidate code matches existing code on large-scale repositories,” attempting to reduce litigation risk. Also regarding OpenAI, there are reports that it strengthened filters so that ChatGPT does not output copyrighted lyrics as they are, in response to the GEMA judgment.</p>



<p>While these are not license propagation itself legally, in practice, they indicate that the industry is steering in the direction of “ensuring the model does not potentially infringe license conditions.” In the future, there is a possibility that guidelines for excluding data with specific license terms like GPL at the model training stage, or mechanisms and systems to guarantee that there is no license-infringing output by conducting output inspections after training, will be established.</p>



<p>In any case, until these two lawsuits are completely settled and the subsequent legislative response is determined, the “theory of GPL propagation to models” has not completely disappeared. It is a scenario that could suddenly become realistic depending on future judgments, and even if the plaintiffs lose in the lawsuits, there is a possibility that support for this theory will reignite within the open source community. It is necessary to note that while it is currently an “undetermined theory not shouted as loudly as before,” that does not mean it has been legally completely denied and resolved. As our community, we need to carefully consider countermeasures while observing these trends and taking into account the legal systems of each country and opposing arguments described in the latter half of this article.</p>



<h3 id="treatment-under-japanese-law">Treatment under Japanese Law</h3>



<p>Based on the trends of the overseas lawsuits mentioned above, I will also organize the relationship between AI models, copyrighted works, and licenses under Japanese law. In Japan, Article 30-4 of the Copyright Act, introduced by the 2018 amendment, exists as a provision that comprehensively legalizes reproduction acts associated with machine learning. Furthermore, in March 2024, the Copyright Division of the Council for Cultural Affairs of the Agency for Cultural Affairs published a guideline-like document titled “Thought on AI and Copyright” (hereinafter “the Thought”), presenting a legal organization divided into the development/training stage and the generation/utilization stage of generative AI.</p>



<p>According to “the Thought,” reproduction performed basically for the purpose of AI training is legal as long as it satisfies “information analysis not for the purpose of enjoying the thoughts or sentiments expressed in the work” as defined in Article 30-4. Therefore, acts of collecting and reproducing a wide range of data from the internet to create a training dataset for research and development purposes can be done without the permission of the rights holders in principle. However, what is important is whether an “purpose of enjoyment” is mixed into that training act. “The Thought” states that if training is conducted with the purpose of “intentionally reproducing all or part of the creative expression of a specific work in the training data as the output of generative AI,” it is evaluated as having a concurrent purpose of enjoying the work rather than mere information analysis, and thus lacks the application of Article 30-4. As a typical example of this, “overfitting” is cited, and acts such as making a model memorize specific groups of works through additional training to cause it to output something similar to those works are judged to have a purpose of enjoyment.</p>



<p>Furthermore, “the Thought” also mentions the legal treatment of trained models, stating first that “trained models created by AI training cannot be said to be reproductions of the works used for training in many cases.” This is the view that since the model can generate outputs unrelated to the original in response to various inputs in a general-purpose manner, the model itself is not a copy of any specific work.</p>



<p>However, “the Thought” simultaneously acknowledges the possibility that, exceptionally, in cases where “the trained model is in a state of generating products with similarity to the work that was training data with high frequency,” the creative expression of the original work remains in the model, and it may be evaluated as a reproduction. It also points out that in such cases, the model is positioned as a machine for copyright infringement, and a claim for injunction may be recognized. In short, usually the model is merely statistical data and not the work itself, but if it has turned into a device for spewing out specific works almost as they are, it can be treated as an infringing item; this thinking shares parts with the content of the GEMA judgment.</p>



<p>It is necessary to note that the above organization is strictly a discussion of the scope of application of rights limitation provisions (exception provisions) under the Copyright Act, and does not touch upon the validity of contracts or license clauses. The Agency for Cultural Affairs document discusses from the perspective of “whether it is copyright infringement or not,” and does not deny that even if the training act is legal, contractual liability may arise if it violates terms of service or open source licenses separately. Also, no in-depth view has been shown regarding the propagation of copyleft clauses like the GPL. In Japan’s Copyright Act, there is no override provision where rights limitation provisions like Article 30-4 take precedence over contract conditions, and the “Contract Guidelines on Utilization of AI and Data” by the Ministry of Economy, Trade and Industry suggests the possibility that if there is a contract prohibiting data use between parties, that contract takes precedence.</p>



<p>Therefore, if the license is regarded as a valid contract, even if “training is legal” under Article 30-4 of the Copyright Act, the risk remains that it becomes a “violation of license conditions” under contract law, and it can be said that at least there is no official view organizing the theory of GPL propagation to models. In other words, currently, while the legality of model training acts is recognized quite broadly under the Copyright Act, license violation is left to general civil theory, and there is no clear guideline on, for example, “whether the act of publicly distributing a model trained on GPL code constitutes a GPL license violation.” Overall, the legal organization in Japan is in a situation of “safe in principle at the copyright layer, but blank at the contract layer.” Hence, the discussion in Japan regarding the theory of GPL propagation to models relies on future judicial judgments and legislative trends, and at present, there is no choice but to consider operational guidelines carefully following the organization by the Agency for Cultural Affairs.</p>



<hr>



<h2 id="arguments-negating-the-theory-of-license-propagation-to-models">Arguments Negating the Theory of License Propagation to Models</h2>



<p>As seen in the previous sections, the theory of GPL propagation to models is not legally zero. However, many legal experts and engineers point out that this theory has serious detrimental effects. Here, I present representative arguments negating the theory of license propagation to models from the layers of copyright law, GPL text, technology, and practical policy.</p>



<h3 id="arguments-for-negation-at-the-copyright-law-layer">Arguments for Negation at the Copyright Law Layer</h3>



<p>First, under copyright law, it is unreasonable to regard an AI model as a “derivative work” or “reproduction” of the training source works. In many cases, the expressions of specific works are not stored inside the model in a form recognizable to humans. The model merely holds statistical abstractions where text and code have been converted into weight parameters, and that itself is not a creative expression to humans at all. A “derivative work” under copyright law refers to a creation that incorporates the essential features of the expression of the original work in a form that can be directly perceived, but one cannot directly perceive the creativity of the original code from the model’s weights. In other words, the model does not show the nature of a work directly enough to be evaluated as encompassing the original code. For example, the High Court of Justice in the UK stated in the judgment of the <em>Getty v. Stability AI</em> case that “the Stable Diffusion model itself is not an infringing copy of the training images,” showing a negative view on regarding the model itself as a reproduction of works. Thus, there are many cautious positions internationally regarding regarding the model itself as an accumulation of works or a compilation work.</p>



<p>Also, the output generated by the model involves probabilistic and statistical transformations, and in many cases, things that do not resemble the training source at all are output. Even if a match or similarity occurs by chance, it is difficult to prove whether it is a reproduction relying on the original or an accidental similarity. It is not realistic to conduct the certification of reliance and similarity required to discuss copyright infringement for the entire model. Ultimately, in the framework of copyright law, there is no choice but to judge “whether the model relies on a specific work” on a work-by-work basis, and recognizing uniform copyrightability or infringing nature for the model itself is a large leap. As organized in Japanese law where the model is not considered a reproduction in most cases, the schematic of model equals work is considered unreasonable under copyright law.</p>



<h3 id="arguments-for-negation-at-the-gpl-text-layer">Arguments for Negation at the GPL Text Layer</h3>



<p>Next, looking at the license text and intent of the GPL itself, doubts are cast on the interpretation that GPL propagates to AI models. For example, in the text of GPLv2, the target of copyleft is limited to “derivative works” of the original code provided under GPL and “works that contain the Program.” Typically, this has been interpreted as software created by modifying or incorporating GPL code, or software combined (linked) with GPL code. In the case of an AI model, it is extremely unclear which part of the original GPL code the model “contains.” Even if the model could memorize fragments of the GPL code used for training, it is a tiny fraction when viewed from the entire model, and most parts are occupied by parameters unrelated to the GPL code. There is no clear assumption shown by the GPL drafters as to whether a statistical model that may partially encapsulate information derived from GPL code can be said to be “a work containing the Program”.</p>



<p>Furthermore, GPLv3 requires the provision of software source code in a “preferred form for modification.” If an AI model is a GPL derivative, the problem arises as to what that preferred form for modification would be. The model weights themselves have low readability and editability for humans, and are hard to call a “preferred form for modification.” If we ask whether the training data is the source code, the original trained GPL code itself cannot be said to be the source of the model, nor is it clear if it refers to the entire vast and heterogeneous training dataset. It is difficult to define what should be disclosed to redistribute the model under GPL compliance, and it could lead to an extreme conclusion that all code and data used for model training must be disclosed. While this is what some freedom believers aim for, it can only be said to be unrealistic in reality, and it deviates from the point of the GPL’s intent to enable users to modify and build from source. Thus, existing GPL provisions are not designed to directly cover products like AI models, and forcing their application causes discrepancies in both text and operation.</p>



<p>In fact, in the “Open Source AI Definition” compiled by the OSI (Open Source Initiative) in 2023, regarding “information necessary for modification” of the model, it stopped at stating that sufficiently detailed information about the training data should be disclosed, and did not require the provision of the training data itself in its entirety. Also, it states that model weights and training code should be published under OSI-approved licenses.</p>



<p>In addition, the FSF (Free Software Foundation) itself does not believe that the current GPL interpretation alone can guarantee freedom in the AI domain, and announced in 2024 that it has started formulating “conditions for machine learning applications to be free.” There, the directionality is shown that “the four freedoms should be guaranteed to users including not only software but also raw training data and model parameters,” but this conversely is a recognition that this is not guaranteed under current licenses. The FSF also points out that “since model parameters cannot be said to be source comprehensible to humans, modification through retraining is more realistic than direct editing,” and can be said to be cautious about treating models on the extension of existing GPL. Overall, claiming GPL propagation univocally to AI models that fall outside the wording and assumptions of GPL provisions is unreasonable from the perspective of interpretation.</p>



<h3 id="arguments-for-negation-at-the-technical-layer">Arguments for Negation at the Technical Layer</h3>



<p>There are also strong counterarguments from a technical perspective against the theory of GPL propagation to models. AI models, particularly those called large language models, basically hold huge statistical trends internally and do not store the original code or text as they are like a database. Returning a specific output for a specific input is merely generation according to a probability distribution, and it is not guaranteed that the same output as the training data is always obtained. If the model does not perform verbatim reproduction of training data except for a very small number of exceptional cases, evaluating it as “containing GPL code” within the model does not fit the technical reality. In fact, the OpenAI side argued in the GEMA lawsuit that “the model does not memorize individual training data, but merely reflects knowledge learned from the entire dataset in parameters.” This argument was not accepted by the Munich District Court, but that was because there was a clear example of lyric reproduction; conversely, unless there is a clear example of reproduction, the view would be that “the model is a lump of statistical knowledge”.</p>



<p>Furthermore, although it has been confirmed that models can output fragments of training data, that proportion is considered extremely limited when viewed from the whole. Regarding the whole as a reproduction based on the existence of partial memory is like claiming the whole is a reproduction of a photograph just because it contains a tiny mosaic-like fragment in an image, which is an excessive generalization. Technically, it is difficult to quantitatively measure how far specific parameters of the model retain the influence of the original data, and the correspondence between the model and training data remains statistical and difficult to draw a line. Therefore, criteria such as “how similar must it be for GPL to propagate?” cannot be established in the first place. The judgment of infringement or not has to be done on an individual output basis, and this would not be consistent with the idea of applying a single license to the entire model. From the technical aspect, since the model is basically a statistical transformation and the majority is unrelated to GPL code, applying GPL collectively can be said to be irrational.</p>



<h3 id="practical-and-policy-arguments-for-negation">Practical and Policy Arguments for Negation</h3>



<p>Finally, major demerits can be pointed out regarding the theory of license propagation to models from practical and policy perspectives. What would happen if this GPL propagation theory were legally recognized? As an extreme example, if 1 million code repositories were used for training a certain large-scale model, all the various licenses contained in them (GPL, MIT, Apache, proprietary, etc.) would “propagate” to the model, and the model provider would have to distribute the model in a form that complies with all 1 million license clauses. As a practical matter, there would be combinations where conditions contradict, such as GPLv2 and Apache-2.0, and attaching and managing a huge collection of copyright notices for one model is nothing but unrealistic. Applying all licenses to an AI model created from training data with mixed licenses is practically bankrupt, and eventually, the only thing that can be done to avoid it would be to exclude code with copyleft licenses like GPL from the training data from the start.</p>



<p>Is such a situation really desirable for our community? The spirit of the GPL is to promote the free sharing and development of software. However, if asserting excessive propagation to AI models causes companies to avoid using GPL code, and as a result, the value held by GPL software is not utilized in the AI era, it would be putting the cart before the horse. In the field of software development, many companies take a policy of not mixing GPL code into their own products, but similarly, if it becomes “do not include GPL in our AI training data,” GPL projects could lose value as data sources. Furthermore, the current legal battles surrounding AI are leaning more towards monetary compensation and regulatory rule-making, and the reality is that they are proceeding in a different vector from the direction of code sharing idealized by GPL. If only the theory of GPL propagation to models walks alone, in reality, only data exclusion and closing off to avoid litigation risks will progress, and there is a fear that it will not lead to the expansion of free software culture.</p>



<p>Policy-wise as well, governments of each country are carefully considering the use of copyrighted works in AI, but at present, there is no example establishing an explicit rule that “license violation of training data generates legal liability for the model.” Even in the EU AI Act, while there are provisions regarding the quality and transparency of training data, it does not demand compliance with open source licenses. Rather, from the perspective of promoting open science and innovation, the movement to allow text and data mining under rights limitations is strong. In Japan as well, as mentioned earlier, the direction is to broadly recognize information analysis use under Article 30-4, and the policy of forcibly applying licenses to AI models is not mainstream in current international discussions.</p>



<p>Based on the above, the theory of license propagation to models is highly likely to cause disadvantages to open source on both practical and policy fronts, and can be said not to be a realistic solution. What is important is how to realize the “freedom of software,” which is the philosophy of open source, in the AI era; the opinion that this should be attempted through realistic means such as ensuring transparency and promoting open model development rather than extreme legal interpretations is potent, and this is something I have consistently argued as well.</p>



<hr>



<h2 id="the-stance-of-osi-and-fsf">The Stance of OSI and FSF</h2>



<p>I will also organize what stance major organizations in the open source (and free software) community are currently taking in relation to the theory of GPL propagation to AI models. Representative organizations are the Open Source Initiative (OSI) and the Free Software Foundation (FSF); while they share the goal of software freedom, they do not necessarily take the same approach regarding AI models and training data.</p>



<p>First, the OSI formulated the “Open Source AI Definition” (OSAID) in 2024, defining the requirements for an AI system to be called open source. This definition states that the four freedoms (use, study, modify, redistribute) similar to software should be guaranteed for AI systems as well, and defines requirements regarding “forms necessary for modification” to realize that, requiring the disclosure of the following three elements.</p>



<ul>
<li>Data Information: Provide sufficiently detailed information about the data used for training so that a skilled person can reconstruct an equivalent model.
<ul>
<li>This does not make publishing the training data itself in its entirety mandatory, but requires disclosing the origin, scope, nature, and acquisition method if there is data that cannot be published, listing data that can be published, and providing information on data available from third parties.</li>
</ul>
</li>



<li>Code: Publish the complete set of source code for training and running the model under an OSI-approved license.</li>



<li>Parameters: Publish the model weights (parameters) under OSI-approved conditions.</li>
</ul>



<p>It should be noted that while OSI states that information regarding the code used for training and training data is indispensable in addition to model weights to realize “Open Source AI,” it does not require the complete disclosure of the training data itself. This is a flexible stance that, for example, if raw data cannot be published due to privacy or confidentiality, explaining the nature of the data by clarifying that fact can substitute. Also, the legal mechanism to ensure free use of model parameters is an issue to be clarified in the future, and at present, no conclusion has been reached on legal rights control (e.g., presence or absence of copyrightability) over parameters either.</p>



<p>As can be read from these, the OSI promotes opening up AI models at the level of the open source definition in principle, but keeps the handling of training data to requirements at the information disclosure level. Thereby, it can be said that the OSI avoids adopting the theory of license propagation to models to demand training data disclosure, and is exploring a realistic solution that first guarantees transparency and reproducibility. In principle, it could be said that the OSI denied the GPL propagation theory at the time of publishing the OSAID definition. Note that I am probably the one who sealed the mandatory argument for training data in the final stage of this definition’s formulation process, and I believe this was the correct judgment.</p>



<p>On the other hand, the FSF and FSF Europe (FSFE) take a stance more faithful to fundamental principles. FSFE declared as of 2021 that “for an AI application to be free, both its training code and training data must be published under a free software license.” That is, to modify or verify the model, one must be able to obtain it including the training data, and therefore both must be free. Also, the FSF itself stated in a 2024 statement, “Under current understanding, for an ML application to be called free, all training data and the scripts processing it must satisfy the four freedoms,” trying to extend the requirements of freedom to data. Thus, FSF/FSFE stands on the position that a model with undisclosed training data is unfree as a whole even if the software part is free.</p>



<p>However, the FSF simultaneously states to the effect that “whether a non-free machine learning application is ethically unjust depends on the case,” mentioning that there can be “legitimate moral reasons” for not being able to publish training data (personal information) of a medical diagnosis AI, for example. In that case, it implies that although that AI is non-free, its use might be ethically permitted due to social utility. One can see an attitude of seeking a compromise between the FSF’s ideal and reality here, but in any case, there is no mistake that the FSF ultimately aims for freedom including training data.</p>



<p>So, does the FSF support the theory of GPL propagation to AI models? Not necessarily. Their claim is closer to an ethical standard or ideal image rather than legal enforceability, and they are not arguing that it applies to models as an interpretation of the current GPL license. Rather, as mentioned before, they are at the stage of trying to create new standards and agreements. Even in the white paper on the Copilot issue funded by the FSF, while legal points such as copyright and license violation are discussed, substantially it has a strong aspect of being told as a GPL compliance problem for users (downstream developers) concerned that they bear the risk of GPL violation if Copilot’s output contains GPL code fragments. This is a caution to developers using AI coding tools rather than GPL application to the model itself, and is different from an approach forcing GPL compliance directly on model providers.</p>



<p>The Software Freedom Conservancy (SFC) naturally has a strong interest in this issue but is also cautious in some respects. The SFC started the protest campaign “Give Up GitHub” against GitHub in 2022, condemning Copilot’s methods as contrary to the philosophy of open source, and is also involved in the Copilot class action. However, in an SFC blog post, regarding this lawsuit, it showed concern about “the risk of interpretations deviating from the principles of the open source community being brought in,” and called on the plaintiffs’ side to comply with community-led GPL enforcement principles as well. The SFC also states that Copilot’s act is an “unprecedented license violation,” and while not fully denying the GPL propagation theory, it can be interpreted as fearing that a judicial precedent undesirable for the community might be created depending on the result of the legal battle. The SFC might be said to be carefully balancing between the aspect of pursuing GPL propagation and the risk of entrusting it to the judiciary.</p>



<p>Finally, what is concerned as the free software camp is that excessive propagation of licenses might conversely invite results that impair freedom. Both OSI and FSF ultimately want to make AI something open that anyone can utilize, but they are carefully assessing whether increasing the purity of legal theory in demands for full data disclosure really leads to achieving the objective. Considering the demerits such as the avoidance of open data due to excessive propagation interpretation or the atrophy effect due to a flurry of lawsuits, I feel that the major organizations share a commonality in that it is essential not to lose sight of the big picture of spreading freedom. Rather than inciting GPL application to models, the pursuit of realistic solutions such as how to make models and data open and which parts should be relaxed in line with reality will likely continue in the future.</p>



<hr>



<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>



<p>I have looked at the current state of the theory of GPL propagation to AI models above, and as a conclusion, this theory is in a halfway position where “it is not touted as loudly as before, but it has not completely disappeared.” As a result of points such as license violation of training data and reproduction within the model beginning to be scrutinized in lawsuits like the Copilot class action and <em>GEMA v. OpenAI</em>, it even appears that the hurdle for infringement certification is lowering. In fact, the Munich District Court’s judgment deemed model memory as reproduction, and the claim of open source license violation survives in the Copilot litigation.</p>



<p>However, on the other hand, the hurdle for the propagation of licenses like GPL remains high. There is a large gap between infringement being recognized and the conclusion that the entire model must be disclosed under GPL etc. immediately. What the current lawsuits are seeking is also injunctions and damages, not the forced GPL-ization of the model. There are zero examples where the judiciary supported the theory of GPL propagation to models itself, and it is a legally uncharted territory. Even if that claim were attempted somewhere in the future, it would face the legal, technical, and practical counterarguments mentioned earlier.</p>



<p>However, the situation has fluid parts, and there is a possibility that the line will shift depending on the policies of each country and the trends of the community. For example, if pressure from rights holder groups strengthens in Europe, there is a possibility that guidelines including license compliance will be formulated. Also, if a consensus is formed within the community regarding the state of copyleft in the AI era, a new license might appear. If such changes occur, a phase where the theory of propagation to models is re-evaluated will also arrive.</p>



<p>To offer my personal opinion, what is important at this moment is the perspective of how to balance software freedom and freedom in the AI domain. Instead of blindly trying to apply the philosophy of copyleft to AI, it is necessary to think about what is best to maximize freedom while considering the technical nature and industrial structure peculiar to AI. Fortunately, solutions to practical problems such as the open publication of large-scale AI models, dataset cleaning methods, and automated attachment of license notices are already being explored by the open source community. Promoting such voluntary efforts and supporting them with legal frameworks as necessary will likely be the key to balancing freedom and development.</p>



<p>The theory of GPL propagation to models is a point where judgment is divided on whether it is an ideal to be pursued or a nightmare to be avoided. However, as stated in this article, seeing the situation in the current year of 2025, it is not a situation where it will become reality immediately, and the majority of the community is likely maintaining a cautious stance. Although it is speculated that trial and error will continue in the judicial, legislative, and technical aspects in the future, as our community, we need to continue exploring the point of compatibility between technological innovation and software freedom without jumping to hasty conclusions. That process itself can be said to be a new challenge in the AI era on the extension of the free software spirit.</p>



<h2 id="references">References</h2>



<ul>
<li>GitHub Copilot litigation: <a href="https://githubcopilotlitigation.com/">https://githubcopilotlitigation.com/</a></li>



<li>GEMA v. OpenAI Judgment text: <a href="https://aifray.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/42-O-14139-24-Endurteil.pdf">https://aifray.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/42-O-14139-24-Endurteil.pdf</a></li>



<li>GEMA vs. OpenAI | AI memorisation is a reproduction relevant to copyright law, and the TDM exception does not help in LLM training, Munich I Regional Court holds: <a href="https://www.osborneclarke.com/insights/gema-vs-openai-ai-memorisation-reproduction-relevant-copyright-law-and-tdm-exception-does">https://www.osborneclarke.com/insights/gema-vs-openai-ai-memorisation-reproduction-relevant-copyright-law-and-tdm-exception-does</a></li>



<li>Impressions on GEMA v. OpenAI (Munich I Regional Court) Judgment: <a href="https://shujisado.com/2025/11/15/gema-v-openai/">https://shujisado.com/2025/11/15/gema-v-openai/</a></li>



<li>Draft thought on AI and Copyright, Agency for Cultural Affairs: <a href="https://www.bunka.go.jp/seisaku/bunkashingikai/chosakuken/pdf/94037901_01.pdf">https://www.bunka.go.jp/seisaku/bunkashingikai/chosakuken/pdf/94037901_01.pdf</a></li>



<li>Contract Guidelines on Utilization of AI and Data: <a href="https://www.meti.go.jp/policy/mono_info_service/connected_industries/sharing_and_utilization/20180615001-1.pdf">https://www.meti.go.jp/policy/mono_info_service/connected_industries/sharing_and_utilization/20180615001-1.pdf</a></li>



<li>Open Source AI: <a href="https://opensource.org/ai">https://opensource.org/ai</a></li>



<li>Is publication of complete training data necessary for AI models to be Open Source?: <a href="https://shujisado.com/2025/02/18/need_for_training_data_in_opensource_ai/">https://shujisado.com/2025/02/18/need_for_training_data_in_opensource_ai/</a></li>



<li>Controlling technology at the age of Artificial Intelligence: a Free Software perspective: <a href="https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/artificial-intelligence.en.html">https://fsfe.org/freesoftware/artificial-intelligence.en.html</a></li>



<li>FSF is working on freedom in machine learning applications: <a href="https://www.fsf.org/news/fsf-is-working-on-freedom-in-machine-learning-applications">https://www.fsf.org/news/fsf-is-working-on-freedom-in-machine-learning-applications</a></li>



<li>Give Up GitHub!: <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/GiveUpGitHub/">https://sfconservancy.org/GiveUpGitHub/</a></li>



<li>On the filing of the Class Action Law Suit over GitHub’s Copilot: <a href="https://sfconservancy.org/news/2022/nov/04/class-action-lawsuit-filing-copilot/">https://sfconservancy.org/news/2022/nov/04/class-action-lawsuit-filing-copilot/</a></li>
</ul>



<figure><img data-attachment-id="252" data-permalink="https://shujisado.org/2025/11/27/gpl-propagates-to-ai-models-trained-on-gpl-code/chatgpt-image-2025%e5%b9%b411%e6%9c%8827%e6%97%a5-21_13_41/" data-orig-file="https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png" data-orig-size="1536,1024" data-comments-opened="0" data-image-meta="{&quot;aperture&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;credit&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;camera&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;caption&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;created_timestamp&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;copyright&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;focal_length&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;iso&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;shutter_speed&quot;:&quot;0&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;orientation&quot;:&quot;0&quot;}" data-image-title="ChatGPT Image 2025年11月27日 21_13_41" data-image-description="" data-image-caption="" data-medium-file="https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=300" data-large-file="https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=1024" width="1024" height="682" src="https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=1024" alt="" srcset="https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=1024 1024w, https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=150 150w, https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=300 300w, https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=768 768w, https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png?w=1440 1440w, https://shujisado.org/wp-content/uploads/2025/11/chatgpt-image-2025e5b9b411e69c8827e697a5-21_13_41.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 1024px) 100vw, 1024px"></figure>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Arthur Conan Doyle explored men’s mental health through Sherlock Holmes (192 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://scienceclock.com/arthur-conan-doyle-delved-into-mens-mental-health-through-his-sherlock-holmes-stories/</link>
            <guid>46068015</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 10:54:02 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://scienceclock.com/arthur-conan-doyle-delved-into-mens-mental-health-through-his-sherlock-holmes-stories/">https://scienceclock.com/arthur-conan-doyle-delved-into-mens-mental-health-through-his-sherlock-holmes-stories/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46068015">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div itemprop="articleBody">
<p><strong>Note:</strong> This article is republished from <em>The Conversation</em> under a Creative Commons license. It includes links to external sites that may earn a commission for purchases. We did not add these links and have kept the original content intact.</p>



<p>Arthur Conan Doyle was not just one of the world’s best crime fiction writers. He was a progressive wordsmith who brought light to controversial and taboo subjects. One of those taboo subjects was male vulnerability and mental health problems – a topic of personal significance to the author.</p>



<p>Doyle was a <a href="https://theconversation.com/topics/children-10" target="_blank" rel="noopener">vulnerable child</a>. His father, Charles, <a href="https://www.nationalgalleries.org/art-and-artists/artists/charles-altamont-doyle#:%7E:text=Doyle%20did%2C%20however%2C%20suffer%20from,the%20creator%20of%20Sherlock%20Holmes" target="_blank" rel="noopener">was an alcoholic</a>, which led to financial troubles in the family. Charles was admitted to an asylum in 1881 and spent the next 12 years in various <a href="https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/advances-in-psychiatric-treatment/article/arthur-conan-doyle-the-many-faces-of-sherlock-holmes/3AEE8A3782A8F420740219E88A34FE53" target="_blank" rel="noopener">mental care establishments</a>. So began Doyle’s interest in male vulnerability and mental health.</p>



<p>The character of Sherlock Holmes is a true expression of male vulnerability that does not equate it with weakness. Doyle does not represent Holmes as infallible, but as a man others can relate to – he battles with drug addiction, loneliness and depression. His genius thrives in part because of these vulnerabilities, not despite them.</p>




<p>Many of Doyle’s Sherlock Holmes stories examine male characters facing emotional catastrophe, betrayal or moral dilemmas. In works such as <a href="https://uk.bookshop.org/a/15793/9781913603380" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Man with the Twisted Lip</a> (1891), <a href="https://uk.bookshop.org/a/15793/9781913603403" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Adventure of the Engineer’s Thumb</a> (1892) and <a href="https://uk.bookshop.org/a/15793/9781782266594" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Stockbroker’s Clerk</a> (1894), Holmes’s male clients approach him with problems layered with emotional turmoil, fear and failure.</p>



<p>In The Man with the Twisted Lip, for example, a man named Neville St Clair hides his double life. He tells his family that he is a respectable entrepreneur going to London on business. In reality he is begging on the city streets. He lives this double life due to fear and shame over the inability to pay off his debts. “It was a long fight between my pride and the money,” he explains, “but the dollars won at last.”</p>



<p><strong>Also Read: </strong><a href="https://scienceclock.com/who-looks-smarter-the-quick-thinker-or-the-careful-thinker/"><strong>Who Looks Smarter: The Quick Thinker or the Careful Thinker?</strong></a></p>



<p>“I would have endured imprisonment, ay, even execution, rather than have left my miserable secret as a family blot to my children,” St Clair says. In having his character consider execution to protect his and his family’s reputation, Doyle explored the societal expectations of Victorian masculinity and how men struggled with such pressures.</p>




<p>The Stockbroker’s Clerk also examines male suicide, as well as economic and professional anxieties. When Holmes reveals the crimes of Harry Pinner, the man attempts suicide rather than face prison.</p>



<p>In The Engineer’s Thumb, hydraulic engineer Victor is treated physically by Watson and mentally by Holmes. As Doyle writes: “Round one of his hands he had a handkerchief wrapped, which was mottled all over with bloodstains. He was young, not more than five-and-twenty, I should say, with a strong masculine face; but he was exceedingly pale and gave me the impression of a man who was suffering from some strong agitation, which it took all his strength of mind to control.”</p>



<p>The physical injury marks Victor as a victim of physical violence. Watson suggests that Victor is using all his mental capabilities to keep calm about his severe pain. Holmes treats Victor’s mind as he listens to his story: “Pray lie down there and make yourself absolutely at home. Tell us what you can, but stop when you are tired, and keep up your strength with a little stimulant.”</p>



<p><strong>Also Read: <a href="https://scienceclock.com/study-of-3-million-finnish-adults-finds-non-voters-tend-to-die-earlier/">Study of 3 Million Finnish Adults Finds Non-Voters Tend to Die Earlier</a></strong></p>




<p>Holmes is a protector, a confidante and a comforter in this scene. He provides Victor with breakfast, induces him to lie down and offers him a stimulant (more than likely brandy).</p>



<p>The extremity of violence that Victor has endured has escalated to mental trauma. In having Holmes treat Victor’s mental trauma while Watson treats his physical pain, Doyle showed the importance psychological support for men of the age.</p>



<p>Holmes was a highly popular character. To contemporary readers, his drug use and dysfunctional clients were seen as markers of his genius rather than a reflection of the significant social issues that men faced during this period. But today, they offer a window into the mental struggles of Victorian men, and a point of connection between readers of the past and present.</p>



<hr>



<p><em>Looking for something good? Cut through the noise with a carefully curated selection of the latest releases, live events and exhibitions, straight to your inbox every fortnight, on Fridays. <a href="https://theconversation.com/uk/newsletters/something-good-156" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sign up here</a>.</em></p>




<hr>



<p><em>This article features references to books that have been included for editorial reasons, and may contain links to <a href="http://bookshop.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bookshop.org</a>. If you click on one of the links and go on to buy something from <a href="http://bookshop.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">bookshop.org</a> The Conversation UK may earn a commission.</em></p>



<p><a href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/emma-linford-1297058" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Emma Linford</a>, Honorary research associate, English literature, <em><a href="https://theconversation.com/institutions/university-of-hull-1191" target="_blank" rel="noopener">University of Hull</a></em></p>



<p><strong>This article is republished from <a href="https://theconversation.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Conversation</a> under a Creative Commons license. Read the <a href="https://theconversation.com/arthur-conan-doyle-explored-mens-mental-health-through-his-sherlock-holmes-stories-246728" target="_blank" rel="noopener">original article</a>.</strong></p>



<hr>







<!-- CONTENT END 1 -->
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Ray Marching Soft Shadows in 2D (2020) (175 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.rykap.com/2020/09/23/distance-fields/</link>
            <guid>46066695</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 07:31:24 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.rykap.com/2020/09/23/distance-fields/">https://www.rykap.com/2020/09/23/distance-fields/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46066695">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div role="main">
        




<article>
  

<p><em>Disclaimer: the demos on this page use WebGL features that aren’t available on some mobile devices.</em></p>

<p>A couple of weeks ago I tweeted a video of a toy graphics project (below). It’s not done, but a lot of people liked it which was surprising and fun! A few people asked how it works, so that’s what this post is about.</p>



<p>Under the hood it uses something called a distance field. A distance field is an image like the one below that tells you how far each pixel is from your shape. Light grey pixels are close to the shape and dark grey pixels are far from it.</p>

<img src="https://www.rykap.com/images/ray-marching/distance-field.png">

<p>When the demo starts up, it draws some text on a 2D canvas and generates a distance field of it. It uses <a href="https://github.com/ryankaplan/gpu-distance-field">a library I wrote</a> that generates distance fields really quickly. If you’re curious how the library works, I wrote about that <a href="http://rykap.com/graphics/skew/2016/02/25/voronoi-diagrams/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Our lighting scheme works like this: when processing a particular pixel we consider a ray from it to the light, like so…</p>

<img src="https://www.rykap.com/images/ray-marching/ray-march-1.png">

<p>If the ray intersects a glyph, the pixel we’re shading must be in shadow because there’s something between it and the light.</p>

<p>The simplest way to check this would be to move along the ray in 1px increments, starting from the pixel we’re shading and ending at the light, repeatedly asking the distance field if we’re distance 0 from a shape. This would work, but it’d be really slow.</p>

<p>We could pick some specific length like 30px and move in increments of that size, but then we risk jumping over glyphs that are smaller than 30px. We might think we’re not in shadow when we should be.</p>

<p><strong>Ray marching’s core idea is this: the distance field tells you how far you are from the closest glyph. You can safely advance along your ray by that distance without skipping over any glyphs.</strong></p>

<p>Let’s walk through an example. We start as pictured above and ask the distance field how far we are from any glyph. Turns out in this case that the answer is 95px (pictured left). This means that we can move 95px along our ray without skipping over anything!</p>

<img src="https://www.rykap.com/images/ray-marching/ray-march-2.png">

<p>Now we’re a little closer to the light. We repeat the process until we hit the ascender of the b! If the b glyph weren’t there, we’d have kept going until we hit the light.</p>

<p>Below is a demo that shows the ray marching steps for a given pixel. The red box is the pixel we’re shading, and each circle along the ray represents a ray marching step and the distance from the scene at that step.</p>

<p>Try dragging the light and the pixel around to build an intuition for it.</p>



<p>Below is GLSL to implement this technique. It assumes you’ve defined a function <code>getDistance</code> that samples the distance field.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>vec2</span> <span>rayOrigin</span> <span>=</span> <span>...;</span>
<span>vec2</span> <span>rayDirection</span> <span>=</span> <span>...;</span>

<span>float</span> <span>rayProgress</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span>
<span>while</span> <span>(</span><span>true</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>rayProgress</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>distance</span><span>(</span><span>rayOrigin</span><span>,</span> <span>lightPosition</span><span>))</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// We hit the light! This pixel is not in shadow.</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>1</span><span>.;</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>float</span> <span>sceneDist</span> <span>=</span> <span>getDistance</span><span>(</span>
    <span>rayOrigin</span> <span>+</span> <span>rayProgress</span> <span>*</span> <span>rayDirection</span><span>);</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>sceneDist</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>0</span><span>.)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// We hit a shape! This pixel is in shadow.</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>rayProgress</span> <span>+=</span> <span>sceneDist</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>It turns out that some pixels are really expensive to process. So in practice we use a for-loop instead of a while loop – that way we bail out if we’ve done too many steps. A common “slow case” in ray marching is when a ray is parallel to the edge of a shape in the scene…</p>



<p>The approach I’ve described so far will get you a scene that looks like the one below.</p>



<p>It’s cool, but the shadows are sharp which doesn’t look very good. The shadows in the demo look more like this…</p>

<img src="https://www.rykap.com/images/ray-marching/desired-shadows.png">

<p>One big disclaimer is that they’re not physically realistic! Real shadows look like hard shadows where the edges have been fuzzed. This approach does something slightly different: all pixels that were previously in shadow are still fully in shadow. We’ve just added a penumbra of partially shaded pixels around them.</p>

<p>The upside is that they’re pretty and fast to compute, and that’s what I care about! There are three “rules” involved in computing them.</p>

<p><strong>Rule 1:</strong> The closer a ray gets to intersecting a shape, the more its pixel should be shadowed. In the image below there are two similar rays (their distances to the shape pictured in yellow and green). We want the one that gets closer to touching the corner to be more shadowed.</p>

<img src="https://www.rykap.com/images/ray-marching/rule-1.png">

<p>This is cheap to compute because the variable <code>sceneDist</code> tells us how far we are from the closest shape at each ray marching step. So the smallest value of <code>sceneDist</code> across all steps is a good approximation for the yellow and green lines in the image above.</p>

<p><strong>Rule 2:</strong> if the pixel we’re shading is far from the point where it almost intersects a shape, we want the shadow to spread out more.</p>

<img src="https://www.rykap.com/images/ray-marching/rule-2.png">

<p>Consider two pixels along the ray above. One is closer to the almost-intersection and is lighter (its distance is the green line). The other is farther and darker (its distance is the yellow line). In general: the further a pixel is from its almost intersection, the more “in shadow” we should make it.</p>

<p>This is cheap to compute because the variable <code>rayProgress</code> is the length of the green and yellow lines in the image above.</p>

<p>So: we previously returned <code>1.0</code> for pixels that weren’t in shadow. To implement rules 1 and 2, we compute <code>sceneDist / rayProgress</code> on each ray marching step, keep track of its minimum value, and return that instead.</p>

<div><pre><code><span>vec2</span> <span>rayOrigin</span> <span>=</span> <span>...;</span>
<span>vec2</span> <span>rayDirection</span> <span>=</span> <span>...;</span>
<span>float</span> <span>rayProgress</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
<span>float</span> <span>stopAt</span> <span>=</span> <span>distance</span><span>(</span><span>samplePt</span><span>,</span> <span>lightPosition</span><span>);</span>
<span>float</span> <span>lightContribution</span> <span>=</span> <span>1</span><span>.;</span>
<span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>int</span> <span>i</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>64</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>rayProgress</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>stopAt</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>lightContribution</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>// `getDistance` samples our distance field texture.</span>
  <span>float</span> <span>sceneDist</span> <span>=</span> <span>getDistance</span><span>(</span>
    <span>rayOrigin</span> <span>+</span> <span>rayProgress</span> <span>*</span> <span>rayDirection</span><span>);</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>sceneDist</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>0</span><span>.)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// We hit a shape! This pixel is in shadow.</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>lightContribution</span> <span>=</span> <span>min</span><span>(</span>
    <span>lightContribution</span><span>,</span>
    <span>sceneDist</span> <span>/</span> <span>rayProgress</span>
  <span>);</span>

  <span>rayProgress</span> <span>+=</span> <span>sceneDist</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>// Ray-marching took more than 64 steps!</span>
<span>return</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>This ratio feels kind of magical to me because it doesn’t correspond to any physical value. So let’s build some intuition for it by thinking through why it might take on particular values…</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>If <code>sceneDist / rayProgress &gt;= 1</code>, then either <code>sceneDist</code> is big or <code>rayProgress</code> is small (relative to each other). In the former case we’re far from any shapes and we shouldn’t be in shadow, so a light value of <code>1</code> makes sense. In the latter case, the pixel we’re shadowing is really close to an object casting a shadow and the shadow isn’t fuzzy yet, so a light value of <code>1</code> makes sense.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The ratio is <code>0</code> only when <code>sceneDist</code> is <code>0</code>. This corresponds to rays that intersect an object and whose pixels are in shadow.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>And here’s a demo of what we have so far…</p>



<p><strong>Rule #3</strong> is the most straightforward one: light gets weaker the further you get from it.</p>

<p>Instead of returning the minimum value of <code>sceneDist / rayProgress</code> verbatim, we multiply it by a <code>distanceFactor</code> which is <code>1</code> right next to the light, <code>0</code> far away from it, and gets quadratically smaller as you move away from it.</p>

<p>All together, the code for the approach so far looks like this…</p>

<div><pre><code><span>vec2</span> <span>rayOrigin</span> <span>=</span> <span>...;</span>
<span>vec2</span> <span>rayDirection</span> <span>=</span> <span>...;</span>
<span>float</span> <span>rayProgress</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
<span>float</span> <span>stopAt</span> <span>=</span> <span>distance</span><span>(</span><span>samplePt</span><span>,</span> <span>lightPosition</span><span>);</span>
<span>float</span> <span>lightContribution</span> <span>=</span> <span>1</span><span>.;</span>
<span>for</span> <span>(</span><span>int</span> <span>i</span> <span>=</span> <span>0</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span> <span>&lt;</span> <span>64</span><span>;</span> <span>i</span><span>++</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>rayProgress</span> <span>&gt;</span> <span>stopAt</span><span>)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// We hit the light!</span>
    <span>float</span> <span>LIGHT_RADIUS_PX</span> <span>=</span> <span>800</span><span>.;</span>

    <span>// fadeRatio is 1.0 next to the light and 0. at</span>
    <span>// LIGHT_RADIUS_PX away.</span>
    <span>float</span> <span>fadeRatio</span> <span>=</span>
      <span>1</span><span>.</span><span>0</span> <span>-</span> <span>clamp</span><span>(</span><span>stopAt</span> <span>/</span> <span>LIGHT_RADIUS_PX</span><span>,</span> <span>0</span><span>.,</span> <span>1</span><span>.);</span>

    <span>// We'd like the light to fade off quadratically instead of</span>
    <span>// linearly.</span>
    <span>float</span> <span>distanceFactor</span> <span>=</span> <span>pow</span><span>(</span><span>fadeRatio</span><span>,</span> <span>2</span><span>.);</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>lightContribution</span> <span>*</span> <span>distanceFactor</span><span>;</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>// `getDistance` samples our distance field texture.</span>
  <span>float</span> <span>sceneDist</span> <span>=</span> <span>getDistance</span><span>(</span><span>rayOrigin</span> <span>+</span> <span>rayProgress</span> <span>*</span> <span>rayDirection</span><span>);</span>
  <span>if</span> <span>(</span><span>sceneDist</span> <span>&lt;=</span> <span>0</span><span>.)</span> <span>{</span>
    <span>// We hit a shape! This pixel is in shadow.</span>
    <span>return</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
  <span>}</span>

  <span>lightContribution</span> <span>=</span> <span>min</span><span>(</span>
    <span>lightContribution</span><span>,</span>
    <span>sceneDist</span> <span>/</span> <span>rayProgress</span>
  <span>);</span>

  <span>rayProgress</span> <span>+=</span> <span>sceneDist</span><span>;</span>
<span>}</span>

<span>// Ray-marching took more than 64 steps!</span>
<span>return</span> <span>0</span><span>.;</span>
</code></pre></div>

<p>I forget where I found this soft-shadow technique, but I definitely didn’t invent it. Inigo Quilez <a href="https://www.iquilezles.org/www/articles/rmshadows/rmshadows.htm">has a great post on it</a> where he talks about using it in 3D.</p>

<p>Inigo’s post also talks about a gotcha with this approach that you might have noticed in the demos above: it causes banding artifacts. This is because Rule 1 assumes that the smallest value of <code>sceneDist</code> across all steps is a good approximation for the distance from a ray to the scene. This is not always true because we sometimes take very few ray marching steps.</p>

<p>So in my demo I use an improved approximation that Inigo writes about in his post. I also use another trick that is more effective but less performant: instead of advancing by <code>sceneDist</code> on each ray marching step, I advance by something like <code>sceneDist * randomJitter</code> where <code>randomJitter</code> is between <code>0</code> and <code>1</code>.</p>

<p>This improves the approximation because we’re adding more steps to our ray march. But we could do that by advancing by <code>sceneDist * .3</code>. The random jitter ensures that pixels next to each other don’t end up in the same band. This makes the result a little grainy which isn’t great. But I think looks better than banding… This is an aspect of the demo that I’m still not satisfied with, so if you have ideas for how to improve it please tell me!</p>

<p>Overall my demo has a few extra tweaks that I might write about in future but this is the core of it. Thanks for reading! If you have questions or comments, let me know <a href="https://twitter.com/ryanjkaplan">on Twitter</a>.</p>

<p><em>Thank you to Jessica Liu, Susan Wang, Matt Nichols and Kenrick Rilee for giving feedback on early drafts of this post! Also, if you enjoyed this post you might enjoy working with me at <a href="https://www.figma.com/careers/">Figma</a>!</em></p>

</article>






  
  
  






      </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mixpanel Security Breach (198 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://mixpanel.com/blog/sms-security-incident/</link>
            <guid>46066522</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 07:02:40 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://mixpanel.com/blog/sms-security-incident/">https://mixpanel.com/blog/sms-security-incident/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46066522">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><div><p><span>Out of transparency and our desire to share with our community, this blog post contains key information about a recent security incident that impacted a limited number of our customers.&nbsp;On November 8th, 2025, Mixpanel detected a smishing campaign and promptly executed our incident response processes. We took comprehensive steps to contain and eradicate unauthorized access and secure impacted user accounts. We engaged external cybersecurity partners to remediate and respond to the incident.</span></p></div><div><p><span>We proactively communicated with all impacted customers.&nbsp;If you have not heard from us directly, you were not impacted. We continue to prioritize security as a core tenant of our company, products and services. We are committed to supporting our customers and communicating transparently about this incident.&nbsp;</span></p></div><div><p><h2><span><strong>What we did in response</strong></span></h2></p></div><div><ul><span><li>Secured affected accounts</li><li>Revoked all active sessions and sign-ins</li><li>Rotated compromised Mixpanel credentials for impacted accounts</li><li>Blocked malicious IP addresses</li><li>Registered IOCs in our SIEM platform</li><li>Performed global password resets for all Mixpanel employees</li><li>Engaged third-party forensics firm to advise on containment and eradication measures</li><li>Performed a forensic review of authentication, session, and export logs across impacted accounts</li><li>Implemented additional controls to detect and block similar activity going forward.</li><li>Engaged with law enforcement and external cybersecurity advisors</li></span></ul></div><div><p><h2><span><strong>What you should know</strong></span></h2></p></div><div><ul><span><li>If you received a communication from us, please review it for the steps we have taken to secure your account, as well as next steps.&nbsp;</li><li>If you did not receive a communication from us, no action is required. Your accounts were not impacted.</li></span></ul></div><div><p><span>If you have any questions about this incident, please contact support@mixpanel.com.</span></p></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Nerd Reich – Silicon Valley Fascism and the War on Democracy (253 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Nerd-Reich/Gil-Duran/9781668221402</link>
            <guid>46066482</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 06:53:17 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Nerd-Reich/Gil-Duran/9781668221402">https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Nerd-Reich/Gil-Duran/9781668221402</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46066482">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.simonandschuster.com/books/The-Nerd-Reich/Gil-Duran/9781668221402: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Linux Kernel Explorer (523 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://reverser.dev/linux-kernel-explorer</link>
            <guid>46066280</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 06:17:37 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://reverser.dev/linux-kernel-explorer">https://reverser.dev/linux-kernel-explorer</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46066280">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>The kernel isn't a process—it's the system. It serves user processes, reacts to context, and enforces separation and control.</p><ul><li><strong>The Kernel Is Not a Process</strong>: It's the always-present authority bridging hardware and software.</li><li><strong>Serving the Process</strong>: Orchestrates syscalls, interrupts, and scheduling to keep user tasks running.</li><li><strong>System of Layers</strong>: Virtual, mapped, isolated, and controlled—structure at runtime.</li></ul><div><h4>📚 Study Files</h4><div><p><span>init/main.c</span></p><p><span>kernel/fork.c</span></p><p><span>include/linux/sched.h</span></p><p><span>arch/x86/kernel/entry_64.S</span></p></div></div><div><div><div><p>1</p><!-- --><p>. </p><!-- --><p>What is the fundamental difference between the kernel and a process?</p></div><div><p><span>A<!-- -->.</span><span>The kernel is a special process with elevated privileges</span></p><p><span>B<!-- -->.</span><span>The kernel is not a process—it's the system itself that serves processes</span></p><p><span>C<!-- -->.</span><span>The kernel is just a library that processes link against</span></p><p><span>D<!-- -->.</span><span>There is no difference; they are the same thing</span></p></div></div><div><div><p>2</p><!-- --><p>. </p><!-- --><p>How does the kernel primarily serve user processes?</p></div><div><p><span>A<!-- -->.</span><span>By running as a background daemon</span></p><p><span>B<!-- -->.</span><span>By orchestrating syscalls, interrupts, and scheduling</span></p><p><span>C<!-- -->.</span><span>By providing a GUI interface</span></p><p><span>D<!-- -->.</span><span>By compiling user code</span></p></div></div><div><div><p>3</p><!-- --><p>. </p><!-- --><p>What characterizes the kernel's system of layers?</p></div><div><p><span>A<!-- -->.</span><span>Physical, tangible, and direct</span></p><p><span>B<!-- -->.</span><span>Simple and flat with no hierarchy</span></p><p><span>C<!-- -->.</span><span>Virtual, mapped, isolated, and controlled</span></p><p><span>D<!-- -->.</span><span>User-accessible and modifiable</span></p></div></div></div></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[HNInternal: Tell HN: Happy Thanksgiving (475 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46065955</link>
            <guid>46065955</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 05:21:16 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46065955">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><tbody><tr id="46072467"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072467" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072467&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Happy thanksgiving all. In an era where algorithms on other platforms seem optimized for outrage and engagement bait, I'm grateful for HN's optimization for curiosity. It's one of the few places left where I can open a thread on a topic I disagree with and actually expect to have my mind changes -- or at least understand the opposing view better -- by the top comment.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072317"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072317" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072317&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>^^7</p><p>cheers to all you glorious bastards. i disagree with you on most things and quibble over pettiest crap, but know it is all in good fun. we are prolly in the weirdest point in computer history and get to see it make it through ( or not.. either is fine ). its a secret, but those annual affirtation are one of my favorite traditions.</p><p>here is to all the fun convos yet to come.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46066132"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46066132" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46066132&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Sixteen years here, and the half-life decay of this community has been slower than anywhere else. That takes real, consistent work, and we have been lucky to have it. Through good times and rough ones, including the loss of Aaron Swartz (who I only knew of through HN), this has stayed a place for real conversation.</p><p>The grit, curiosity, and people building things have always been inspiring.</p><p>Thanks for all the discussions over the years.</p><p>Happy Thanksgiving!</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072221"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072382"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072019"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072019" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072019&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Just completed 7 years on HN. This is the only social network I'm active on (if you don't count whatsapp). Awesome folks and amazing discussions!!</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072142"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072254"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072254" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072254&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Eighteen years here. I am not American but I think this is a holiday that we can all celebrate as reminder that we should be grateful for what and specially for who we have, independently what we don't have.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072172"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072146"><td></td></tr><tr id="46066891"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46066891" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46066891&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Seems weird to say, but I've been posting here for seventeen years now. And in that time, can I say that the quality of the discourse has slipped some? Well... if I'm being honest, probably yeah. A little. But at the same time, I can still honestly say that HN is still easily the best community of this sort on the 'net, at least that I'm aware of. OK, Lobste.rs has some merit, but the problem there is that  the community there is arguably still a little too small, and you just don't get the variety and volume of interesting discussion you get here. But the level of discourse is high there as well.</p><p>Anyway, I find HN to be a wonderful refuge from a lot of the absurdity that's "out there" and I will happily throw in my own "Thanks, guys!" to dang and tomhow. And to pg for starting this whole thing back in the day.</p><p>Happy Thanksgiving, everyone, and here's to more years to come!</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46071937"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072246"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072326"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071922"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46071922" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46071922&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>15 years here too. I turn 40 today. Grateful for this community. I quit social media years ago but still enjoy the discourse here.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072139"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072186"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072366"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072165"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072070"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071945"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072225"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072033"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072212"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071798"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071940"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072195"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072195" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072195&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Been lurking since 2011 or so. Dare I say that the average level of discourse has finally fallen to a level where I feel comfortable participating after over ten years of just reading.</p><p>That being said HN was and continues to be one of the most valuable resources for geeks on the net.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46071944"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46071944" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46071944&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Hey, community! Thank you for this opportunity to connect and feel closeness to the best  parts and people in our industry.</p><p>Thank you for your open mindedness, smarts, stupid fun and lovable nerdiness.</p><p>I feel at home here.</p><p>One thing that makes me sad are dystopian fears. Not sure if this is warranted or not, but certainly get my dose of dread from HN. But thank you for being so sensitive and caring in this.</p><p>Happy thanksgiving.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072312"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071964"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072102"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072141"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072030"><td></td></tr><tr id="46066119"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072075"><td></td></tr><tr id="46069702"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071046"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="0"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="0"></td><td><center><a id="up_46071046" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46071046&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Happy Thanksgiving!</p><p>Use this day to eat good food, converse with relatives, and rest from the usual madness.  Peace on Earth.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46071853"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072201"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071917"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46071917" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46071917&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Wasn't Thanksgiving a practice before people came to the US? The US now does it, but they didn't start it. I only know it because I'm Dutch and I wanted to see if the Dutchies were somehow involved (because they are way more often than they should be). Here's a source I quickly found but there are many sources on it [1].</p><p>There's more to Thanksgiving than only the US.</p><p>[1] <a href="https://www.iamexpat.nl/lifestyle/lifestyle-news/how-netherlands-played-role-history-thanksgiving" rel="nofollow">https://www.iamexpat.nl/lifestyle/lifestyle-news/how-netherl...</a></p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46071864"><td></td></tr><tr id="46071885"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46071885" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46071885&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>this always gets brought up, but realistically no one ever cares or brings this up from the perspective of celebrating American origins, but rather just a reminder to be thankful for things in your life that matter to you. I don't see the problem with this</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46071902"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="1"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="40"></td><td><center><a id="up_46071902" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46071902&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>North American natives were exterminating and enslaving each other long before the Europeans got there.</p><p>Nobody has anything to be proud of.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072239"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072239" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072239&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>The term "slave" encompasses a lot of wildly different kinds of unfree labor. The racialized system most people think of from transatlantic slavery is a very recent thing.</p><p>Nothing resembling that was widespread in precolumbian North America. The earliest similar systems I'm aware of took root in the 17th and 18th centuries, well into the early colonial period.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072304"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="3"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="120"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072304" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072304&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>Research what the Iroquois did to the Huron people, what the Apache did to the Pueblos, and what the Aztecs did to everybody.</p><p>The continent what a slaughter show for thousands of years.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072194"><td><table><tbody><tr><td indent="2"><img src="https://news.ycombinator.com/s.gif" height="1" width="80"></td><td><center><a id="up_46072194" href="https://news.ycombinator.com/vote?id=46072194&amp;how=up&amp;goto=item%3Fid%3D46065955"></a></center></td><td><br>
<div><p>While it was (mostly?) unintentional, the biological warfare committed by Europeans makes for a different story than anything that happened before they arrived. The Americas weren't a paradise, but neither were they a slaughterhouse.</p></div></td></tr></tbody></table></td></tr><tr id="46072059"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072219"><td></td></tr><tr id="46072232"><td></td></tr></tbody></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Music eases surgery and speeds recovery, study finds (188 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c231dv9zpz3o</link>
            <guid>46065817</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 04:55:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c231dv9zpz3o">https://www.bbc.com/news/articles/c231dv9zpz3o</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46065817">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><article><p data-component="headline-block"><h2>Music eases surgery and speeds recovery, Indian study finds</h2></p><div data-testid="byline-new" data-component="byline-block"><p><span data-testid="byline-new-contributors"><div data-testid="byline-new-contributors-contributor-0"><p><span>Soutik Biswas</span><span data-testid="byline-new-contributors-contributor-0-role-location">India correspondent</span></p></div></span></p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251120-101800-81b2dab7dc-web-2.34.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/6712/live/6ce97290-c89b-11f0-bd7c-1744b857cc58.jpg.webp" loading="eager" alt="BBC A patient with headphones playing music during surgery in a hospital in Delhi"><span>BBC</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>A patient with headphones playing music during surgery in a hospital in Delhi</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>Under the harsh lights of an operating theatre in the Indian capital, Delhi, a woman lies motionless as surgeons prepare to remove her gallbladder.</p><p>She is under general anaesthesia: unconscious, insensate and rendered completely still by a blend of drugs that induce deep sleep, block memory, blunt pain and temporarily paralyse her muscles.</p><p>Yet, amid the hum of monitors and the steady rhythm of the surgical team, a gentle stream of flute music plays through the headphones placed over her ears.</p><p>Even as the drugs silence much of her brain, its auditory pathway remains partly active. When she wakes up, she will regain consciousness more quickly and clearly because she required lower doses of anaesthetic drugs such as propofol and opioid painkillers than patients who heard no music.</p><p>That, at least, is what a <a target="_blank" href="https://mmd.iammonline.com/index.php/musmed/article/view/1111">new peer-reviewed study</a> from Delhi's Maulana Azad Medical College and Lok Nayak Hospital suggests. The research, published in the journal Music and Medicine, offers some of the strongest evidence yet that music played during general anaesthesia can modestly but meaningfully reduce drug requirements and improve recovery.</p><p>The study focuses on patients undergoing laparoscopic cholecystectomy, the standard keyhole operation to remove the gallbladder. The procedure is short - usually under an hour - and demands a particularly swift, "clear-headed" recovery.</p><p>To understand why the researchers turned to music, it helps to decode the modern practice of anaesthesia.</p><p>"Our aim is early discharge after surgery," says Dr Farah Husain, senior specialist in anaesthesia and certified music therapist for the study. "Patients need to wake up clear-headed, alert and oriented, and ideally pain-free. With better pain management, the stress response is curtailed." </p><p>Achieving that requires a carefully balanced mix of five or six drugs that together keep the patient asleep, block pain, prevent memory of the surgery and relax the muscles.</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251120-101800-81b2dab7dc-web-2.34.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/1dd7/live/f3017100-c2c1-11f0-8669-5560f5c90fbe.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="Getty Images Indian surgeons medical team performing surgery in operation theater at hospital"><span>Getty Images</span></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>Patients need to wake up clear-headed and ideally pain-free after surgery</figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>In procedures like laparoscopic gallbladder removal, anaesthesiologists now often supplement this drug regimen with regional "blocks" - ultrasound-guided injections that numb nerves in the abdominal wall. </p><p>"General anaesthesia plus blocks is the norm," says Dr Tanvi Goel, primary investigator and a former senior resident of Maulana Azad Medical College. "We've been doing this for decades."</p><p>But the body does not take to surgery easily. Even under anaesthesia, it reacts: heart rate rises, hormones surge, blood pressure spikes. Reducing and managing this cascade is one of the central goals of modern surgical care. Dr Husain explains that the stress response can slow recovery and worsen inflammation, highlighting why careful management is so important.</p><p>The stress starts even before the first cut, with intubation - the insertion of a breathing tube into the windpipe.</p><p>To do this, the anaesthesiologist uses a laryngoscope to lift the tongue and soft tissues at the base of the throat, obtain a clear view of the vocal cords, and guide the tube into the trachea. It's a routine step in general anaesthesia that keeps the airway open and allows precise control of the patient's breathing while they are unconscious.</p><p>"The laryngoscopy and intubation are considered the most stressful response during general anaesthesia," says Dr Sonia Wadhawan, director-professor of anaesthesia and intensive care at Maulana Azad Medical College and supervisor of the study.</p><p>"Although the patient is unconscious and will remember nothing, their body still reacts to the stress with changes in heart rate, blood pressure, and stress hormones."</p><p>To be sure, the drugs have evolved. The old ether masks have vanished. In their place are intravenous agents - most notably propofol, the hypnotic made infamous by <a target="_self" href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/newsbeat-15634083">Michael Jackson's death</a> but prized in operating theatres for its rapid onset and clean recovery. "Propofol acts within about 12 seconds," notes Dr Goel. "We prefer it for short surgeries like laparoscopic cholecystectomy because it avoids the 'hangover' caused by inhalational gases."</p><p>The team of researchers wanted to know whether music could reduce how much propofol and fentanyl (an opioid painkiller) patients required. Less drugs means faster awakening, steadier vital signs and reduced side effects.</p><p>So they designed a study. A pilot involving eight patients led to a full 11-month trial of 56 adults, aged roughly 20 to 45, randomly assigned to two groups. All received the same five-drug regimen: a drug that prevents nausea and vomiting, a sedative, fentanyl, propofol and a muscle relaxant. Both groups wore noise-cancelling headphones - but only one heard music.</p><p>"We asked patients to select from two calming instrumental pieces - soft flute or piano," says Dr Husain. "The unconscious mind still has areas that remain active. Even if the music isn't explicitly recalled, implicit awareness can lead to beneficial effects."</p></div><figure><div data-component="image-block"><p><img src="https://static.files.bbci.co.uk/bbcdotcom/web/20251120-101800-81b2dab7dc-web-2.34.1-2/grey-placeholder.png" aria-label="image unavailable"><img sizes="(min-width: 1280px) 50vw, (min-width: 1008px) 66vw, 96vw" srcset="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/240/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 240w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/320/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 320w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 480w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/640/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 640w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/800/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 800w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1024/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 1024w,https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/1536/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp 1536w" src="https://ichef.bbci.co.uk/news/480/cpsprodpb/dd22/live/a51ebd90-c2c0-11f0-bd8a-f3f60edded8d.jpg.webp" loading="lazy" alt="A pilot on eight patients led to a full trial of 56 adults randomly assigned to two groups "></p></div><p data-component="caption-block"><figcaption>A pilot involving eight patients led to a full trial of 56 adults randomly assigned to two groups </figcaption></p></figure><div data-component="text-block"><p>The results were striking.</p><p>Patients exposed to music required lower doses of propofol and fentanyl. They experienced smoother recoveries, lower cortisol or stress-hormone levels and a much better control of blood pressure during the surgery. "Since the ability to hear remains intact under anaesthesia," the researchers write, "music can still shape the brain's internal state."</p><p>Clearly, music seemed to quieten the internal storm. "The auditory pathway remains active even when you're unconscious," says Dr Wadhawan. "You may not remember the music, but the brain registers it."</p><p>The idea that the mind behind the anaesthetic veil is not entirely silent has long intrigued scientists. Rare cases of "intraoperative awareness" show patients recalling fragments of operating-room conversation. </p><p>If the brain is capable of picking up and remembering stressful experiences during surgery - even when a patient is unconscious - then it might also be able to register positive or comforting experiences, like music, even without conscious memory.</p><p>"We're only beginning to explore how the unconscious mind responds to non-pharmacological interventions like music," says Dr Husain. "It's a way of humanising the operating room."</p><p>Music therapy is not new to medicine; it has long been used in psychiatry, stroke rehabilitation and palliative care. But its entry into the intensely technical, machine-governed world of anaesthesia marks a quiet shift.</p><p>If such a simple intervention can reduce drug use and speed recovery - even modestly - it could reshape how hospitals think about surgical wellbeing.</p><p>As the research team prepares its next study exploring music-aided sedation, building on earlier findings, one truth is already humming through the data: even when the body is still and the mind asleep, it appears a few gentle notes can help the healing begin.</p></div></article></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Coq: The World's Best Macro Assembler? (2013) [pdf] (138 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://nickbenton.name/coqasm.pdf</link>
            <guid>46065698</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 04:34:56 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://nickbenton.name/coqasm.pdf">https://nickbenton.name/coqasm.pdf</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46065698">Hacker News</a></p>
&lt;Not HTML&gt;]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[DIY NAS: 2026 Edition (385 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://blog.briancmoses.com/2025/11/diy-nas-2026-edition.html</link>
            <guid>46065034</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:54:23 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2025/11/diy-nas-2026-edition.html">https://blog.briancmoses.com/2025/11/diy-nas-2026-edition.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46065034">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div><p>Fourteen years ago, my storage needs outpaced my capacity and I began to look into building a network attached storage server. I had a few criteria in mind and was curious to see if anyone had _ recently_ shared something similar, but I couldn’t find anything that was relevant.</p>

<p>In fact,  I found that the communities I was looking for answers in were actively hostile towards what I wanted to do.  This resulted in my decision <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2012/01/do-it-yourself-network-attached-storage.html" title="My First DIY NAS: Building a NAS: Choosing Hardware">to build my own DIY NAS</a> and share that as one of my very first blogs.</p>

<p>Much to my surprise, people were very interested in that blog! Ever since, I’ve been building a similar DIY NAS machine almost every year trying to satisfy the curiosity of other prospective DIY NAS builders.</p>

<p>Here are those criteria:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Small form factor</strong>: It’s not the case for me any more, but at the time the space was limited in my office. I always assume that space in everybody’s office is limited. As a result, I want my DIY NAS builds to occupy as little of that office space as I can.</li>
  <li><strong>At least six drive bays</strong>: Back when I built my NAS, it took about four drives’ worth of storage to meet my storage needs. Plus I desired two empty drive bays for future use. However, in the years since hard drive capacities have increased dramatically. At some point in the future, I may reduce this to four drive bays.</li>
  <li><strong>An integrated, low power CPU</strong>: I intend my DIY NAS to run 24 hours a day, 7 days a week, and 52 weeks a year. When it comes to power consumption, that can do some damage on your electric bill! Thankfully our electricity here isn’t as expensive as others’ in the United States, or even further outside its borders, but I try and keep power consumption in mind when picking components for a DIY NAS build.</li>
  <li><strong>Homelab potential</strong>: It does not take up a lot of CPU horsepower for a NAS to serve up files, which means that on modern hardware there’s a lot of untapped potential in a DIY NAS for virtual machines or containers to self-host services.</li>
</ol>

<p>It’s important to remember that <strong><em>these are my criteria</em></strong>, and not necessarily yours. Every DIY NAS builder should be making their own list of criteria and reconcile all of their component purchases against the criteria that’s important to them.</p>

<h2 id="is-it-even-a-good-time-to-build-a-nas">Is it even a good time to build a NAS?</h2>

<p>As I prepared to build this NAS, component prices disappointed me. Hard drives, SSDs, and RAM prices were all rising. Based on what I’ve been told, I expect Intel CPU prices to increase as well. My contact at Topton has been encouraging me to stock up on motherboards while they still have some in inventory. Based on what’s been explained to me, I expect the motherboard’s prices to rise and for their availability to potentially dwindle.</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/ssd_prices.png" target="_blank"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/ssd_prices_600.png" alt="1TB NVMe SSD prices"></a></p>

<p>In short, the economy sucks and the price of DIY NAS components is a pretty good reflection of just how sucky things are becoming. I briefly considered not publishing a DIY NAS build this year hoping that things would improve a few months down the road. But then I asked myself, “What if it’s even worse in a few months?”</p>

<p>I sure hope things get better, but I fear and expect that they’ll get worse.</p>

<h2 id="motherboard-and-cpu">Motherboard and CPU</h2>
<p>I built <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2023/03/diy-nas-2023-edition.html" title="DIY NAS: 2023 Edition">my first DIY NAS with a Topton motherboard in 2023</a>. Each DIY NAS since then has also featured a Topton motherboard. My only complaint about the motherboards has been that buying them from one of the Chinese e-tail sites like AliExpress is considered problematic by some. With every DIY NAS build, I try and go through all the motherboards that I can find  while searching for something with a better value proposition, but for each of the past three years I’ve landed on the latest offering from Topton.</p>

<p><a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" target="_blank" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/topton_n22_175.png"></a>For the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>, I chose the <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a> with the <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/sku/231803/intel-processor-n100-6m-cache-up-to-3-40-ghz/specifications.html" title="Intel® Processor N100">Intel Core 3 N355</a> CPU. The motherboard is similar to last year’s <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/127014563991" title="Topton N18 N100/N150/N305 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard:6xSATA/2xM.2/2x2.5GbE/1x10GbE">Topton N18</a> but has incrementally more compelling features, particularly the extra 2 SATA ports, the PCI-e x1 slot, and the N355 CPU!</p>

<ul>
  <li>Mini-ITX Form Factor</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/sku/231803/intel-processor-n100-6m-cache-up-to-3-40-ghz/specifications.html" target="_blank" title="Intel® Processor N100">Intel® Processor Core 3 N355</a>
    <ul>
      <li>8 cores / 8 threads / Max Turbo 3.9GHz</li>
      <li>15 W TDP</li>
      <li>Integrated GPU with Intel Quick Sync Video</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>1 x DDR5 SO-DIMM</li>
  <li>8 x SATA 3.0 Ports (Asmedia ASM1164)</li>
  <li>2 x M.2 NVMe Slots (PCIe 3.0 x1)</li>
  <li>1 x 10Gbps NIC (Marvell AQC113C)</li>
  <li>2 x 2.5Gbps NICs (Intel i226-V)</li>
  <li>1 x PCI-e x1 or M.2 E-Key slot</li>
</ul>

<p>I opted for the motherboard with the <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/sku/231803/intel-processor-n100-6m-cache-up-to-3-40-ghz/specifications.html" target="_blank" title="Intel® Processor N100">Intel Core 3 N355</a> CPU. This makes the server a more capable homelab machine than prior years’ DIY NAS builds. The extra cores and threads come in handy for streaming media, replacing your cloud storage, facilitating home automation, hosting game servers, etc.</p>

<h2 id="case">Case</h2>
<p>Just like Topton has been making great motherboards for DIY NAS machines, JONSBO has been steadily releasing great cases for DIY NAS machines. This year SilverStone Technology released a new case, the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/SilverStone-Technology-hot-swappable-Performance-SST-CS383/dp/B0FDPNRYG9?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=61605bf99f3551af48cd50574aa64608&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="SilverStone Technology CS383 8-Bay hot-swappable high Performance Full Tower NAS Chassis, SST-CS383">CS383</a> (<a href="https://www.silverstonetek.com/en/product/info/computer-chassis/cs383/" title="SilverStone Technology CS383 Specs">specs</a>) which I was <strong><em>very interested</em></strong> in buying one for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>. Unfortunately it carries a pretty hefty price tag to go along with all of its incredible features!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/jonsbo-n4_200.png"></a>The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a> (<a href="https://www.jonsbo.com/en/products/N4Black.html" title="JONSBO N4 Case specs">specs</a>) is a third the price, adheres to my “smaller footprint” criteria, and it is rather impressive on its own. It’s a <em>tiny</em> bit larger case than last year’s DIY NAS, but I really like that it has drive bays for six 3.5” drives and two 2.5” drives.</p>

<p>Although, it’s peculiar in that two of the 3.5” drive bays (and the two 2.5” drive bays) aren’t attached to a SATA backplane and can’t be swapped anywhere as easily as the other four 3.5” bays. However, this peculiar decision seems to have caused the JONSBO N4 to sell for a bit less ($20-$40) than similar offerings from JONSBO. At its price, it’s a compelling value proposition!</p>

<h3 id="case-fan">Case Fan</h3>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09C6DQDNT?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=a917ad99ae5994be300a55a6e8fc8fe2&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Noctua NF-A12x25 PWM chromax.Black.swap, Premium Quiet Fan, 4-Pin (120mm, Black) "><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/NF-A12x25_175.png"></a>In the past, I’ve found that the fans which come with JONSBO cases are too noisy. They’ve been noisy for two reasons; the design quality of the fans make them  loud. And the fans are constantly running at their top speed because of the fan header they’re plugged into on the cases’ SATA backplanes.</p>

<p>I anticipated that fan efficiency and noise would be a problem, so I picked out the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09C6DQDNT?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=a917ad99ae5994be300a55a6e8fc8fe2&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Noctua NF-A12x25 PWM chromax.Black.swap, Premium Quiet Fan, 4-Pin (120mm, Black) ">Noctua NF-A12x25 PWM</a> to solve it. Firstly, swapping in a high-quality fan that pushes more air <strong><em>and</em></strong> generates less noise–especially at its top speed–is a good first step. Secondly, I’d address the problem by plugging the fan into the motherboard’s <code>SYS_FAN</code> header instead of on the SATA backplane. This provides the opportunity to tune the fan’s RPMs directly in the BIOS and generate far less noise.</p>

<h2 id="ram">RAM</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Crucial-4800MHz-Laptop-Memory-CT32G48C40S5/dp/B09RVNMGFH?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=8a98ba9480c4e010efbe51f71f992fbd&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Crucial 32GB DDR5 RAM 4800MHz (CT32G48C40S5)"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/CT32G48C40S5-C16A1_175.png"></a>The first time I first asked myself, “Should I even build the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>?” came as I was checking prices on DDR5 memory. Thankfully for me I had leftover RAM after purchasing DDR5 4800MHz SODIMMs for the <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2024/11/diy-nas-2025-edition.html" title="DIY NAS: 2025 Edition">DIY NAS: 2025 Edition</a>,  <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2025/03/an-all-flash-diy-nas-that-fits-in-my-pocket.html" title="An all-flash DIY NAS that fits in my pocket!">the Pocket Mini NAS</a>, and then again for the <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2025/09/diy-nas-2025-texas-linux-fest-edition.html" title="DIY NAS: 2025 Texas Linux Fest Edition">DIY NAS that I built and gave away at 2025’s Texas Linux Fest</a>. I was personally thankful that I had one brand new  32GB DDR5 4800MHz SODIMM laying around, but I was wildly disappointed for everybody who will try and follow this build when I saw the price of those same SODIMMs.</p>

<p>Regardless, I felt a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Crucial-4800MHz-Laptop-Memory-CT32G48C40S5/dp/B09RVNMGFH?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=8a98ba9480c4e010efbe51f71f992fbd&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Crucial 32GB DDR5 RAM 4800MHz (CT32G48C40S5)">Crucial 32GB DDR5 4800MHz SODIMM</a> (<a href="https://www.crucial.com/memory/ddr5/CT32G48C40S5" title="Crucial 32GB DDR5-4800 SODIMM specs">specs</a>) was the right amount of RAM to get started with for a DIY NAS build in 2025. Whether you just need storage or you wish to also host virtual machines, you will benefit from having more than the bare minimum recommendation of RAM. I really wanted to buy a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Crucial-5600MT-5200MT-4800MT-CT48G56C46S5/dp/B0C79T2CP7?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=36fd2ef6ac56fee00617824bfe0a0676&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" title="Crucial 48GB DDR5 RAM, 5600MHz (or 5200MHz or 4800MHz) Laptop Memory, SODIMM 262-Pin, Compatible with 13th Gen Intel Core and AMD Ryzen 6000 - CT48G56C46S5 ">48GB DDR5 4800MHZ SODIMM</a> for this DIY NAS build, but I couldn’t talk myself into spending the $250-$300 that it would’ve wound up costing.</p>

<h2 id="storage">Storage</h2>

<p>A quick disclaimer about all the drives that I purchased for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>, I already had all of them! I tend to buy things when I see them on sale and as a result, I have a collection of brand new parts for machines in my homelab or for upcoming projects. I raided that collection of spare parts for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>.</p>

<h3 id="boot-drive">Boot Drive</h3>

<p>If you ranked the drives in your DIY NAS in order of importance, the boot drive should be the least-important drive. That is <strong><em>not</em></strong> saying that boot drive isn’t performing an important function, but I am suggesting that you shouldn’t invest a bunch of energy and money into picking the optimal boot drive.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0963SGYGF?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=335ccbcac1cb1beb1ad0bbbe951f4cea&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Silicon Power 128GB A55 SATA SSD (SU128GBSS3A55S25AH)"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/sp-a55-128gb_175.png"></a>Because the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a> has a pair of 2.5” drive bays, I decided that a 2.5” SATA SSD would be ideal for the boot drives. As a rule of thumb, I try and spend less than $30 per boot drive in my DIY NAS builds.</p>

<p>Ultimately I selected a pair of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0963SGYGF?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=335ccbcac1cb1beb1ad0bbbe951f4cea&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Silicon Power 128GB A55 SATA SSD (SU128GBSS3A55S25AH)">128GB Silicon Power A55 SSDs</a> (<a href="https://www.silicon-power.com/product-detail/ace_a55/" title="Silicon Power 128GB A55 SATA SSD specs">specs</a>). I’ve used these before, I’d use them again in the future, and I even have four of their higher capacity (1TB) SSDs in a pool in my own NAS.</p>

<h3 id="app-and-virtual-machine-nvme-ssds">App and Virtual Machine NVMe SSDs</h3>

<p>Self-hosting apps and virtual machines on your DIY NAS has really exploded in the past few years. The developers of NAS appliance packages have made it much easier and the self-hosted products themselves have become as good–or often better–than things you’re probably subscribing to today. Because of that, I saved the highest-performing storage options on the <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" target="_blank" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a> for apps and VMs.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07ZGJVTZK?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=27613853bea52aac53f1068188e5c5e3&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Teamgroup MP44 1TB NVMe SSD"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/SiliconPower-SSD-P34A60-Product_175.png"></a>However, it’s important to point out that these M.2 slots are PCI-e version 3 and capped at a single PCI-e lane. This is a consequence of the limited number of PCI-e lanes available for each of the CPU options available for  the <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a> (N100, N150, N305, and N355).</p>

<p>I opted for a NVMe drive that was a good value rather than a high performer and chose two of the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07ZGJVTZK?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=27613853bea52aac53f1068188e5c5e3&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Teamgroup MP44 1TB NVMe SSD">Silicon Power 1TB M.2 NVMe SSDs (SP001TBP34A60M28)</a> (<a href="https://www.silicon-power.com/product-detail/PCIe_Gen_3x4_P34A60/">specs</a>).</p>

<h3 id="bulk-storage-hard-disk-drives">Bulk Storage Hard Disk Drives</h3>
<p><a href="https://serverpartdeals.com/collections/hard-drives" target="_blank" title="ServerPartDeas: One of Brian's favorite places to shop for hard drives."><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2025/diynas/pp/ST18000NM003D_175.png"></a>Thanks to rising prices, I opted to do like I’ve done with past DIY NAS builds and skip buying hard drives for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>.</p>

<p>When planning your DIY NAS, it is good to always remember that <strong><em>storage will ultimately be your costliest and most important expense</em></strong>.</p>

<p>Here’s a few things to consider when buying hard drives:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Determine your hardware redundancy preferences. I recommend having two hard disk drives’ worth of redundancy (RAIDZ2, RAID6, etc.)</li>
  <li>Focus on price-per-terabyte when comparing prices of drives.</li>
  <li>Do some <a href="https://github.com/Spearfoot/disk-burnin-and-testing" target="_blank" title="Spearfoot's disk-burnin-and-testing Script on GitHub">burn in testing</a> of your hard drives before putting them to use.</li>
  <li>When buying new drives of the same model, try and buy them from multiple vendors to increase the chances of buying drives manufactured in separate batches.</li>
  <li>Plan Ahead! Understand the rate that your storage grows so that you can craft a strategy to grow your storage down the road.</li>
  <li>Being cheap today can and will paint you into a corner that’s quite expensive to get out of.</li>
  <li>Understand that RAID is not a backup!</li>
</ol>

<p>Thankfully, I’ve collected a bunch of my own decomissioned hard drives which I used to thoroughly test this DIY NAS build.</p>

<h2 id="sata-cables">SATA Cables</h2>
<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B08C2LJBLW?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=18fa5e170ef32c966b38bd844a0b8b35&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="OIKWAN SFF-8643 Host to 4 X SATA Breakout Cable"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/sff-8643-cable_175.png"></a>One of the under-the-radar features of the <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a> might be one of my favorite features! The motherboard’s Asmedia ASM1164 SATA controllers sit behind two SFF-8643 connectors. These connectors provide two advantages for these motherboards:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Saves room on the motherboard’s PCB.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B08C2LJBLW?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=18fa5e170ef32c966b38bd844a0b8b35&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="OIKWAN SFF-8643 Host to 4 X SATA Breakout Cable">SFF-8643 to 4x SATA breakout cables</a> reduces the amount of cable management hassle.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="power-supply">Power Supply</h2>
<p>The one thing that I have routinely disliked about building small form factor DIY NAS machines is the price tag that accompanies a small form factor power supply (SFX) like is required with the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B075M5FRQS?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=a8eca3bbe367f280660bd7085d88d1e0&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="SilverStone Technology SX500-G 500W SFX Fully Modular 80 Plus Gold PSU"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/pp/SX500-G_175.png"></a>I wound up choosing the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B075M5FRQS?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=a8eca3bbe367f280660bd7085d88d1e0&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" title="SilverStone Technology SX500-G 500W SFX Fully Modular 80 Plus Gold PSU">SilversStone Technology SX500-G</a> (<a href="https://www.silverstonetek.com/en/product/info/power-supplies/SX500-G/" title="SilverStone Technology SX500-G 500W specs">specs</a>) which I had used earlier in the year for the <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2025/09/diy-nas-2025-texas-linux-fest-edition.html" title="DIY NAS: 2025 Texas Linux Fest Edition">DIY NAS I gave away at Texas Linux Fest</a>. Its 500W rating exceeds the needs of all the components that I’d picked out for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>. Plus the power supply’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/80_Plus">80 Plus Gold</a> rating aligns well with my criteria for power efficiency.</p>



<p>Regardless of whether it was called FreeNAS, TrueNAS, TrueNAS CORE, TrueNAS SCALE, or now <a href="https://www.truenas.com/truenas-community-edition/" target="_blank" title="TrueNAS Community Edition">TrueNAS Community Edition</a>, the storage appliance product(s) from iXSystems have always been my go-to choice. For each yearly DIY NAS build, I wander over to the <a href="https://www.truenas.com/software-status/">TrueNAS Software Status page</a> and look at the state of the current builds.</p>

<p>I’m conservative with my personal NAS setup. However, for these blog builds, I typically choose Early Adopter releases. This year that’s <a href="https://www.truenas.com/docs/scale/25.10/gettingstarted/versionnotes/" target="_blank" title="TrueNAS 25.10 (Goldeye) Version Notes">TrueNAS 25.10.0.1 (aka Goldeye)</a>. I enjoy being able to use these DIY NAS builds as a preview to the latest and greatest that TrueNAS has to offer.</p>

<p>I repeatedly choose TrueNAS because it’s what I’ve become accustomed to; it’s legitimately an enterprise-grade storage product, which is exactly the quality of solution that I want my data to depend on. At the same time it does not feel like you need a specialized certification and a truckload of enterprise storage experience to meet set up a NAS that exceeds your needs at home.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.truenas.com/truenas-community-edition/" target="_blank" title="TrueNAS Community Edition"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/truenas_open_storage-logo-full-color-rgb.png"></a></p>

<p>Many times I have been asked, “Why not <em>&lt;insert NAS appliance or OS here&gt;</em>?”  My answer to that question is, TrueNAS has always done everything that I need it to and they haven’t given me any reason to consider anything else. As a result, there’s never been a need for me to evaluate something else.</p>

<h2 id="partslist">Final Parts List</h2>

<table>
	<tbody><tr>
		<th>Component</th>
		<th colspan="2">Part Name</th>
		<th>Qty</th>
		<th>Cost</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>Motherboard</td>	
		<td><a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" target="_blank">Topton N22 (w/ N355 CPU) NAS Motherboard</a></td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.toptonpc.com/product/intel-n100-6-bay-nas-motherboard-110g-2i226-v-2-5g-3lan-6sata3-0-2m-2-nvme-1ddr5-4800mhz-soft-router-firewall-itx-mainboard/" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>1</td>	
		<td>$446.40</td>	
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>CPU</td>	
		<td>Intel Core 3 N355</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/sku/241639/intel-core-3-processor-n355-6m-cache-up-to-3-90-ghz/specifications.html" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>1</td>	
		<td>N/A</td>	
	</tr>		
	<tr>
		<td>Memory</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Crucial-5200MHz-4800MHz-Laptop-CT32G52C42S5/dp/B0BNXYRR9Y?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=acb7e10801bf0cf26d03423c185819cb&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">
Crucial RAM 32GB DDR5 4800MHz SODIMM (CT32G48C40S5) </a></td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.crucial.com/memory/ddr5/CT32G48C40S5" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>1</td>	
		<td>$172.96</td>	
	</tr>	
	<tr>
		<td>Case</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">JONSBO N4</a></td>
		<td><a href="https://www.jonsbo.com/en/products/N2White.html" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>1</td>	
		<td>$121.59</td>	
	</tr>
		<tr>
		<td>Case Fan</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B09C6DQDNT?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=a917ad99ae5994be300a55a6e8fc8fe2&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">Noctua NF-A12x25 PWM chromax.Black.swap</a></td>
		<td><a href="https://www.noctua.at/en/products/nf-a12x25-pwm-chromax-black-swap" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>1</td>	
		<td>$37.95</td>	
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>Power Supply</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B075M5FRQS?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=a8eca3bbe367f280660bd7085d88d1e0&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">SilverStone 500W SFX Power Supply SST-SX500-G)</a></td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.silverstonetek.com/en/product/info/power-supplies/SX500-G/" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>1</td>	
		<td>$142.34</td>	
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>Boot Drive</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B0963SGYGF?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=335ccbcac1cb1beb1ad0bbbe951f4cea&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">Silicon Power 128GB A55 SATA SSD</a></td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.silicon-power.com/product-detail/ace_a55/" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>2</td>	
		<td>$21.97</td>	
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<td>Apps/VM Drives</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07ZGJVTZK?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=27613853bea52aac53f1068188e5c5e3&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">Silicon Power 1TB - NVMe M.2 SSD (SP001TBP34A60M28) </a></td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.teamgroupinc.com/en/product-detail/ssd/TEAMGROUP/mp44/mp44-TM8FPW001T0C101/" target="_blank">specs</a></td>	
		<td>2</td>	
		<td>$99.99</td>	
	</tr>			
	<tr>
		<td>SATA Cables</td>	
		<td><a href="https://www.amazon.com/SATA-III-Cable-1M-Set-6Gbps-SATA-Replacement-Computer-Server/dp/B09Q359C7Z?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=02df14f462c50c4b883f5daa8709f653&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank">OIKWAN SFF-8643 Host to 4 X SATA Breakout Cable</a></td>	
		<td>N/A</td>	
		<td>2</td>	
		<td>$11.99</td>	
	</tr>	
	<tr>
		<td colspan="4">Price <i>without</i> Storage: </td>
		<td>$989.36</td>
	</tr>		
	<tr>
		<td colspan="4">Total Price: </td>
		<td>$1,189.34</td>
	</tr>
</tbody></table>




<h2 id="hardware-assembly-bios-configuration-and-burn-in">Hardware Assembly, BIOS Configuration, and Burn-In</h2>

<h3 id="hardware-assembly">Hardware Assembly</h3>

<p>I wanted the smallest possible DIY NAS. The <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a> case initially felt too large since it accommodates Micro ATX motherboards. However, I grew to accept its slightly larger footprint. However, putting the <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a> into the case felt roomy and luxurious. Building the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> compared to prior years’ felt a lot like coming home to put on sweatpants and a t-shirt after wearing a suit and tie all day long.</p>

<p>I wasn’t too fond of the cable-management of the power supply’s cables. The layout of the case pretty much makes the front of the power supply inaccessible once it is installed. One consequence of this is that the power cable which powered the SATA backplane initially prevented the 120mm case fan from spinning up. That issue was relatively minor and was resolved with zip ties.</p>

<p>Overall, I felt pretty good about the assembly of the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>, but things would take a turn for the worse when I decided to fill all the 3.5-inch drive bays up with some of my decommissioned 8TB HDDs. Now this is probably my fault, I wouldn’t be surprised at all that the manual of the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a> warned me against this, but putting the drives in last turned out to be a major pain in the neck for each of the four drive bays <strong><em>without</em></strong> a SATA backplane.</p>

<p><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/800/diynas2026_backwards.png" alt="DIY NAS: 2026 Edition with half its drives installed backwards!"></p>

<p>I had wrongly guessed that you accessed those drives’ power and data ports from the front of the case. I worked really hard to route the cables and even managed to install all of the drives before realizing my error and learning my lesson.  I’m understanding now why the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a> is cheaper than all of its siblings. Partly because there’s a missing SATA backplane, but also because those other 4 drive bays’ layout is frustrating.</p>

<p>Don’t let my last couple paragraphs sour you on the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4</a>, though. I still really like its size, it feels big when you’re working in it with a Mini ITX motherboard. If you wind up deciding to use the JONSBO N4, then I suggest that you put those four drives and their cables in first before you do anything else. That would’ve made a world of difference for me. Actually looking at the documentation before getting started might have saved me quite a bit of aggravation, too!</p>

<p>If I have ruined the JONSBO N4 for you, then check out the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mini-ITX-Chassis-Computer-Aluminum-Support/dp/B0CMVBMVHT?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=9140995b2e4f34809c8202effd2750ac&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N3 Mini-ITX NAS PC Chassis">JONSBO N3</a>. It’s <strong><em>eight</em></strong> 3.5-inch drive bays pair up really nicely with the <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a>. You can see what I thought of the JONSBO N3 by reading the <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2024/09/diy-nas-2024-edition-and-econonas.html" title="DIY NAS: 2024 Edition">DIY NAS: 2024 Edition</a> blog.</p>



<h3 id="bios-configuration">BIOS Configuration</h3>

<p>Generally speaking, I do as little as I possibly can in the BIOS. Normally I strive to only set the time and change the boot order. However, I did a bit more for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> since I’m using the <code>SYS_FAN</code> header for the fan which is responsible for cooling the hard drives.  Here are the changes that I made in the BIOS:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Set the <strong>System Date</strong> and <strong>System Time</strong> to Greenwich Mean Time
    <ol>
      <li>Advanced
        <ol>
          <li>Hardware Monitor ( Advanced)
            <ol>
              <li>Set <strong>SYS SmartFan Mode</strong> to  <code>Disabled</code>.</li>
              <li>Set the <strong>Manual PWM Setting</strong> (for <code>SYS_FAN</code>) to 180.</li>
            </ol>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </li>
      <li>Set <strong>PWRON After Power Loss</strong> to <code>Always On</code></li>
      <li>Boot
        <ol>
          <li>Set <strong>Boot Option #1</strong> to the TrueNAS boot device.</li>
        </ol>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>I’m not at all interested in venturing into the rabbit’s hole of trying to completely minimize how much power the NAS uses. However, I imagine there’s some opportunities for power savings lurking in the BIOS. I didn’t go looking for them myself, but if you’re intrepid enough to do so here’s a few suggestions that I have to save some additional power:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Disable the onboard audio.</li>
  <li>Disable any network interfaces that you don’t wind up using.</li>
  <li>Tinker with the CPU settings.</li>
  <li>Got other suggestions?  <em>Share them in the comments!</em></li>
</ul>

<h3 id="burn-in">Burn-In</h3>

<p>Because all of the hardware is brand-new to me brand-new components are not guaranteed to be free of defects, I always do a little bit of burn-in testing to establish some trust in the hardware that I’ve picked out for each DIY NAS build. While I think doing <em>some</em> burn-in testing critically important, I also think the value of subsequent burn-in testing drops the more that you do. Don’t get too carried away and do your own  burn-in testing in moderation!</p>

<h4 id="memtest86"><a href="https://www.memtest.org/" target="_blank" title="Memtest86+">Memtest86+</a></h4>

<p>I <em>always</em> use Memtest86+ to burn-in the RAM. I always run at least 3+ passes of Memtest86+. Typically, I run many more passes because I tend to let the system keep running additional passes overnight. Secondarily, running these many passes give the CPU a little bit of work to do and there’s enough information displayed by Memtest86+ to give me confidence in the CPU and its settings.</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/diynas2026-memtest_1280.png"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/diynas2026-memtest_600.png" alt="Memtest86+"></a></p>

<h4 id="hard-drives">Hard Drives</h4>

<p>The failure rate of hard drives is highest when the drives are new and then again when they’re old. Regardless of type of hard drives that I buy or when I buy them, I always do some disk burn in. I tend to run <a href="https://github.com/Spearfoot/disk-burnin-and-testing" target="_blank" title="Spearfoot's disk-burnin-and-testing Script on GitHub">Spearfoot’s Disk Burn-in and Testing script</a> on all of my new drives. However executing this script against all of the drives can take quite a long time, even if you use something like  <code>tmux</code> to run the tests in parallel.</p>

<h2 id="initial-truenas-ce-setup">Initial TrueNAS CE Setup</h2>

<p>There’s always a little bit of setup that I do for a new TrueNAS machine. This isn’t intended to be an all inclusive step-by-step guide for all the things you should do with your DIY NAS. Instead, it’s more of a list of things I kept track of while I made sure that the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> was functional enough for me to finish writing this blog. That being said, I do think your NAS would be rather functional if you decided to do the same configuration.</p>

<ol>
  <li>Updated the hostname to <code>diynas2026</code>
    <ol>
      <li><em>Note:  This is only to avoid issues with another NAS on my network.</em></li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Updated the timezone.</li>
  <li>Enabled the following services and set them to start automatically.
    <ol>
      <li>SMB</li>
      <li>SSH</li>
      <li>NFS</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
  <li>Enabled password login for the <code>truenas_admin</code> user.
    <ul>
      <li><em>Note: If I were planning to use this DIY NAS long-term, I wouldn’t have done this. Using SSH keys for authentication is a better idea</em>.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Edited the TrueNAS Dashboard widgets to reflect the 10Gb interface (<code>enp1s0</code>).</li>
  <li>Created a pool named <code>flash</code> which consisted of mirrored vdev using the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/B07ZGJVTZK?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=27613853bea52aac53f1068188e5c5e3&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Teamgroup MP44 1TB NVMe SSD">Teamgroup MP44 1TB NVMe SSDs</a>.</li>
  <li>Created a pool named <code>rust</code> which consisted of a single RAID-Z2 vdev using eight hard drives that I had sitting on my shelf after they were decomissioned.</li>
  <li>Configured the Apps to use the <code>flash</code> pool for the apps’ dataset.</li>
  <li>Made sure that the System Dataset Pool was set to <code>flash</code>.</li>
  <li>Confirmed that there were Scrub Tasks set up for the <code>flash</code> and <code>rust</code> pools.</li>
  <li>Created a dataset on each pool for testing;  <code>flash-test</code> and <code>rust-test</code></li>
  <li>Installed the <a href="https://github.com/AnalogJ/scrutiny" target="_blank" title="Scrutiny: WebUI for smartd S.M.A.R.T monitoring">Scrutiny</a> app found in the App Catalog.</li>
</ol>

<p>If I were planning to keep this NAS and use it for my own purposes, I would also:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Set up a <a href="https://www.truenas.com/docs/scale/25.10/scaletutorials/credentials/certificates/settingupletsencryptcertificates/" target="_blank" title="Creating ACME Certificates">Let’s Encrypt certificate</a>.</li>
  <li>Hook up the NAS to <a href="https://networkupstools.org/stable-hcl.html" target="_blank" title="Network UPS Tools Hardware Compatability List">a compatible UPS</a>, enable the UPS service, and configure the UPS service to shut down the NAS before the battery runs out of juice.</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.truenas.com/docs/scale/25.10/scaleuireference/toptoolbar/alerts/alertsettingsscreen/" target="_blank" title="TrueNAS Scale Alert Settings Screens">Set up system email alert service</a>.</li>
  <li>Create <a href="https://www.truenas.com/docs/scale/25.10/scaletutorials/dataprotection/replication/" target="_blank" title="TrueNAS Replication Tasks">replication tasks</a> to back up critical data to my <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/2024/06/one-3d-printed-nas-wasn-t-enough-so-i-printed-two-more.html" title="One 3D-printed NAS wasn't enough, so I printed two more!">off-site NAS</a>.</li>
  <li>Add the new NAS to my Tailscale tailnet using the <a href="https://github.com/truenas/apps/tree/master/ix-dev/community/tailscale" target="_blank" title="Tailscale from the official TrueNAS App Catalog">Tailscale app from the official catalog</a>.</li>
  <li>As the NAS is seeded with data, create and maintain a suite of <a href="https://www.truenas.com/docs/scale/25.10/scaletutorials/dataprotection/periodicsnapshottasksscale/" target="_blank" title="Adding Periodic Snapshot Tasks">snapshot tasks</a> tailored to the importance of the different data being stored on the NAS.</li>
  <li>Set up S.M.A.R.T. tests for all of the drives:
    <ol>
      <li>Weekly Short Test</li>
      <li>Monthly Long Test</li>
    </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

<h2 id="benchmarks">Benchmarks</h2>

<p>Just about every year, I benchmark each DIY NAS build and almost always come to the same conclusion; the NAS will outperform your network at home. Your first bottleneck is almost always going to be the network and the overlwhelming majority of us have gigabit networks at home–but that’s slowly changing since 2.5Gbps and 10Gbps network hardware has started to get reasonable lately.</p>

<p>Even though I always come to the same conclusion, I still like to do the benchmarks for two reasons:</p>

<ol>
  <li>It helps me build confidence that the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> works well.</li>
  <li>People tend to enjoy consuming benchmarks <strong><em>and</em></strong> it’s fun for me to see the DIY NAS’ network card get saturated during the testing.</li>
</ol>

<h3 id="throughput">Throughput</h3>

<p>I like to do three categories of tests to measure the throughput of the NAS:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Use <a href="https://iperf.fr/" target="_blank" title="iPerf - The ultimate speed test tool for TCP, UDP and SCTP">iperf3</a> to benchmark throughput between my NAS and another machine on my network.</li>
  <li>Benchmark the throughput of the pool(s) locally on the NAS using <code>fio</code>.</li>
  <li>Set up SMB shares on each of the pools and then benchmark the throughput when using those shares.</li>
</ol>

<p>Every year I try and mention that Tom Lawrence from <a href="https://lawrencesystems.com/" target="_blank">Lawrence Systems</a> published <a href="https://youtu.be/TASYaWTkg0U">a great video about benchmarking storage with FIO</a> and shared <a href="https://forums.lawrencesystems.com/t/linux-benchmarking-with-fio/11122">the FIO commands from his video in their forums</a>. I use these FIO commands constantly as a reference point for testing ZFS pools’ throughput. Importantly I’d like to point out that, in that same video, Tom says something very wise:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://youtu.be/TASYaWTkg0U?t=53" target="_blank">There are lies, damn lies, and then there are benchmarks!</a></p>
</blockquote>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Tool</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Pool</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Test<br>Size</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Random<br>Write<br>IOPS</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Random<br>Read<br>IOPS</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Sequential<br>Write<br>(MB/s)</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Sequential<br>Read<br>(MB/s)</strong></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>FIO</td>
      <td><code>flash</code></td>
      <td>4G</td>
      <td>1906.00</td>
      <td>2200.00</td>
      <td>548.00</td>
      <td>1214.00</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>FIO</td>
      <td><code>flash</code></td>
      <td>32G</td>
      <td>2132.00</td>
      <td>3012.00</td>
      <td>544.00</td>
      <td>1211.00</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>FIO</td>
      <td><code>rust</code></td>
      <td>4G</td>
      <td>1352.00</td>
      <td>108.00</td>
      <td>367.00</td>
      <td>530.00</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>FIO</td>
      <td><code>rust</code></td>
      <td>32G</td>
      <td>1474.00</td>
      <td>326.00</td>
      <td>368.00</td>
      <td>544.00</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CrystalDiskMark</td>
      <td><code>flash</code></td>
      <td>4GiB</td>
      <td>5858.89</td>
      <td>50409.91</td>
      <td>1104.64</td>
      <td>956.70</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CrystalDiskMark</td>
      <td><code>flash</code></td>
      <td>32GiB</td>
      <td>4193.36</td>
      <td>31047.36</td>
      <td>635.42</td>
      <td>946.20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CrystalDiskMark</td>
      <td><code>rust</code></td>
      <td>4GiB</td>
      <td>5226.50</td>
      <td>46239.01</td>
      <td>756.23</td>
      <td>655.32</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>CrystalDiskMark</td>
      <td><code>rust</code></td>
      <td>32GiB</td>
      <td>3794.43</td>
      <td>12809.33</td>
      <td>759.38</td>
      <td>677.02</td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>



<p>What do I think these benchmarks and my use of the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> tell me?  In the grand scheme of things, not a whole lot.</p>

<p>However, these benchmarks do back up what I expected, the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> is quite capable and more than ready to meet my storage needs. I especially like that the CrystalDiskMark benchmark of the SMB shares were <strong><em>both faster than a SATA SSD</em></strong>, and the throughput to the share on the <code>flash</code> pool practically saturated the NAS’ 10GbE network connection.</p>

<h4 id="fio-tests">FIO Tests</h4>

<p>Every time I benchmark a NAS, I seem to either be refining what I tried in prior years or completely reinventing the wheel. As a result, I wouldn’t recommend comparing these results with results that I shared in prior years’ DIY NAS build blogs. I haven’t really put a ton of effort into developing a standard suite of benchmarks. Things in my homelab change enough between DIY NAS blogs that trying to create and maintain an environment for a standard suite of benchmarks is beyond what my budget, spare time, and attention span will allow.</p>

<p>I’m going to paste these <code>fio</code> commands here in the blog for my own use in future DIY NAS build blogs. If you wind up building something similar, these <em>might</em> be helpful to measure your new NAS’ filesystem’s performance and compare it to mine!</p>

<div><pre><code>## Random Write IOPS
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1 --name=test --filename=test --bs=128k --size=4G --readwrite=randwrite --ramp_time=10
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1 --name=test --filename=test --bs=128k --size=32G --readwrite=randwrite --ramp_time=10

## Random Read IOPS
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1 --name=test --filename=test --bs=128k --size=4G --readwrite=randread --ramp_time=10
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1 --name=test --filename=test --bs=128k --size=32G --readwrite=randread --ramp_time=10

## Sequential Write (MB/s)
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1 --name=test --filename=test --bs=4M --size=4G --readwrite=write --ramp_time=10
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1 --name=test --filename=test --bs=4M --size=32G --readwrite=write --ramp_time=10

## Sequential Read (MB/s)
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1  --name=test --filename=test --bs=4M --size=4G --readwrite=read --ramp_time=10
fio --randrepeat=1 --ioengine=libaio --direct=1  --name=test --filename=test --bs=4M --size=32G --readwrite=read --ramp_time=10
</code></pre></div>

<p><a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/combined-network-throughput.png"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/800/combined-network-throughput.png" alt="Perfmon of Networkthroughput for reading files over SMB and during iperf3 tests."></a></p>

<h3 id="power-consumption">Power Consumption</h3>

<p>One not-so-obvious cost of running a DIY NAS is how much power it consumes. While I specifically tried to pick items that were efficient in terms of power consumption, it’s also important to realize that all the other bells and whistles on the awesome <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" target="_blank" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N18 NAS motherboard</a> consume power, too. And that the biggest consumer of power in a NAS is almost always the hard disk drives.</p>

<p>Thanks to my tinkering with <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/categories/home-automation/" title="Home Automation blogs">home automation</a>, I have a plethora of <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0CJR4QZ45?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=331f4bd20d1cfe3c50b64077966b0ecc&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Minoston Z-Wave 800 Series Zwave Plug with Energy Monitoring, Power Meter Z-Wave Outlet Switch (MP31ZP)">smart outlets</a> which are capable of power monitoring. I used those smart outlets for most of my power monitoring. But I also have a <a href="https://www.amazon.com/P3-P4400-Electricity-Usage-Monitor/dp/B00009MDBU?crid=BQE7RDYQK9CM&amp;th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=c0efb3c2ef49e3049ce3e77825adedc0&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" title="P3 P4400 Kill A Watt Electricity Usage Monitor">Kill a Watt P400</a> that I also use for some of the shorter tests:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Power consumed during a handful of specific tasks:
    <ul>
      <li>Idle while running TrueNAS</li>
      <li>RAM Burn-in (~14 passes of Memtest86+)</li>
      <li>An 8-hour throughput benchmark copying randomly-sized files to the NAS using SMB.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Total consumed during the build, burn-in, and use of the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>.</li>
</ul>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th><strong>Task</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Duration</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Max Wattage</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Avg. Wattage</strong></th>
      <th><strong>Total Consumption</strong></th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Boot</td>
      <td>10 min.</td>
      <td>200.00 W</td>
      <td>120.00 W</td>
      <td>0.02 kWh</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Idle</td>
      <td>3 hr.</td>
      <td>90.00 W</td>
      <td>66.67 W</td>
      <td>0.20 kWh</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>RAM Burn-in</td>
      <td>18 hr.</td>
      <td>104.00 W</td>
      <td>91.67 W</td>
      <td>1.65 kWh</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>SMB Benchmark of HDDs</td>
      <td>8 hr.</td>
      <td>107.00 W</td>
      <td>85.00 W</td>
      <td>0.68 kWh</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td><strong>Total</strong></td>
      <td><strong>108 hr.</strong></td>
      <td><strong>237.80 W</strong></td>
      <td><strong>66.49 W</strong></td>
      <td><strong>7.17 kWh</strong></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>



<h2 id="what-about-an-econonas">What about an EconoNAS?</h2>

<p><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/ai-dollar-bill-sign.png">Shortly before prices skyrocketed, I decided I wasn’t very interested in doing a separate EconoNAS builds. Several months ago, I realized that there were several off-the-shelf NAS machines that were more-than-capable of running TrueNAS and they were selling at economical prices that couldn’t be topped by a DIY approach. I will dive deeper into this in a future blog, eventually … <strong><em>maybe</em></strong>?</p>

<p>All that being said–it’d be incredibly easy to make some compromises which result in the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> becoming quite a bit more economical. Here’s a list of changes that I would consider to be more budget-friendly:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Different motherboard/CPU combo: <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/127014563991" target="_blank" title="Topton N18 N100/N150/N305 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard:6xSATA/2xM.2/2x2.5GbE/1x10GbE">N18 w/ N100 CPU</a> (-$224), <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/127014563991" title="Topton N18 N100/N150/N305 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard:6xSATA/2xM.2/2x2.5GbE/1x10GbE">N18 w/ N150 CPU</a> (-$214), or <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/127525459090" title="Topton N22 Motherboard w/ N150 CPU on Brian's eBay Store">N22 w/ N150 CPU</a> (-$180)</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/4ai7M2V" target="_blank">16GB of DDR5 RAM</a> (-$39) instead of 32GB.</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/4qSQBLa" target="_blank">Thermal Right TL-C12015 Slim Fan</a> instead of the Noctua NF-A12x25 (-$26)</li>
  <li><a href="https://amzn.to/3LFJSnP" target="_blank">Apevia SFX-AP500W Power Supply</a> (-$104)</li>
  <li>Skip the redundancy for the boot pool (-$22)</li>
</ul>

<p>Altogether, these savings could add up to more than $400, which is pretty considerable!  If you made all of these changes, you’d have something that’s going to be nearly equivalent to the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> but at a fraction of the price.</p>

<p><a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/ai-brian-ock-buying-drives.png"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/ai-brian-ock-buying-drives_640.png" alt="Brian as a Super Villian shopping for economical DIY NAS deals!"></a></p>

<h2 id="what-am-i-going-to-do-with-the-diy-nas-2026-edition">What am I going to do with the DIY NAS: 2026 Edition?!</h2>

<p>My DIY NAS is aging quite gracefully, but I’ve recently been wondering about replacing it. Shortly before ordering all the parts for the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>, I briefly considered using this year’s DIY NAS build to replace my personal NAS. However, I decided not to do that. Then prices skyrocketed and I shelved the idea of building a replacement for my own NAS and I nearly shelved the idea of a DIY NAS in 2026!</p>

<p>So that begs the question, “What is Brian going to do with the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>?”</p>

<p>I’m going to auction it off on the <a href="https://www.ebay.com/str/briancmosesdotcom" target="_blank" title="briancmosesdotcom store on eBay">briancmosesdotcom store on eBay</a>! Shortly after publishing this blog, I’ll list it on eBay. In response to skyrocketing prices for PC components, I’m going to do a no-reserve auction. At the end of the auction, the highest bidder wins and hopefully they’ll get a pretty good deal!</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/127527163731" target="_blank"><img src="https://blog.briancmoses.com/images/2026/diynas/ebay-auction_800.png" alt="eBay auction of the DIY NAS: 2026 Edition"></a></p>

<h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2>

<p>Overall, I’m pleased with the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em>. The <a href="https://s.click.aliexpress.com/e/_c2zJj1aF" target="_blank" title="Topton N22 N355 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard (8xSATA3, 2xM.2, 1x10Gbps, 2x2.5Gbps)">Topton N22 motherboard</a> is a significant improvement over last year’s <a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/127014563991" title="Topton N18 N100/N150/N305 Mini-ITX NAS Motherboard:6xSATA/2xM.2/2x2.5GbE/1x10GbE">Topton N18 motherboard</a>, primarily due to its extra two SATA ports. This provides 33.3% more gross storage capacity.</p>

<p>While testing, I found the <a href="https://www.intel.com/content/www/us/en/products/sku/231803/intel-processor-n100-6m-cache-up-to-3-40-ghz/specifications.html" target="_blank" title="Intel® Processor N100">Intel Core 3 N355 CPU</a> somewhat excessive for basic NAS functions. However, the substantial untapped CPU horsepower offers luxurious performance potential. This makes the build compelling for anyone planning extensive self-hosting projects.</p>

<p>I have mixed feelings about the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0D1YH7D3J?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=5636db0ca3c62e86da5f02b641c0f283&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="JONSBO N4 Black NAS Pc Case, Walnut Wood, 8-Drive Bay/6 x 3.5-inch HDD (4 hot-swap,2 Non hot-swap),2 x 2.5-inch SSD, Micro ATX Chassis">JONSBO N4 case</a>. The four right-side drive bays lack SATA backplane connectivity. Without creative cabling solutions, individual drive replacement becomes challenging. However, the case’s ~$125 price point compensates for this inconvenience. I anticipate that those the cost savings will justify the compromise for most builders. If I were to build the <em>DIY NAS: 2026 Edition</em> all over again, I’d be tempted to use the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Mini-ITX-Chassis-Computer-Aluminum-Support/dp/B0CMVBMVHT?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=9140995b2e4f34809c8202effd2750ac&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" title="JONSBO N3 Mini-ITX NAS PC Chassis">JONSBO N3 case</a> or even the <a href="https://www.jonsbo.com/en/products/N6Black.html" title="JONSBO N6">JONSBO N6</a> which isn’t quite obtainable, yet.</p>

<p>The DIY NAS: 2026 Edition delivers excellent performance and superior specifications. In my opinion, it represents better value than off-the-shelf alternatives:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/QNAP-TS-832PX-4G-High-Capacity-10GbE-2-5GbE/dp/B08P42JR89?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=8d7e5630a6e8c1a01d6f791658a8652e&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="QNAP TS-832PX-4G 8 Bay High-Capacity NAS with 10GbE SFP+ and 2.5GbE ">QNAP TS-832PX-4G</a> ($880)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Asustor-Lockerstor-Enterprise-Attached-Quad-Core/dp/B07Y2BJZKC?th=1&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=9ba0f3af9b719585c327dbf5b1d14c9a&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="Asustor Lockerstor 8 AS6508T 8 Bay NAS - Network Storage Enclosure, Quad Core 2.1GHz CPU, 8GB RAM DDR4, M.2 NVMe SSD ">Asustor Lockerstor 8 AS6508T</a> ($960)</li>
  <li><a href="https://www.amazon.com/UGREEN-DXP8800-Plus-Attached-Diskless/dp/B0D22HGH4N?&amp;linkCode=ll1&amp;tag=diynas2026-20&amp;linkId=351f2f13b717fb8ca116986ad227ec9c&amp;language=en_US&amp;ref_=as_li_ss_tl" target="_blank" title="UGREEN NASync DXP8800 Plus 8-Bay Desktop NAS, Intel i5 1235u 10-Core CPU, 8GB DDR5 RAM, 128G SSD, 2X 10GbE, 2X M.2 NVMe Slots, 8K HDMI, 2X TBT4, Network Attached Storage (Diskless) ">UGREEN NASync DXP8800</a> ($1200)</li>
</ul>

<p>Building your own NAS provides significant advantages. Years later, you can upgrade RAM, motherboard, case, or add PCI-e (x1) expansion cards. These off-the-shelf alternatives offer severely limited upgrade paths.</p>

<p>Is 2026 finally the year that you decide to build your DIY NAS?  I hope that it is!  Share your experience building your NAS in the comments below or come tell us about it in the <a href="https://blog.briancmoses.com/discord" title="The Butter, What?! Discord Server">#diynas-and-homelab channel on the Butter, What?! Discord server</a>!</p>

<!-- Tiny Slider Script: diynas2026-->


<!-- Tiny Slider Script: diynas2026-assembly-->


</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Green Card Interviews End in Handcuffs for Spouses of U.S. Citizens (221 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/26/us/trump-green-card-interview-arrests.html</link>
            <guid>46065015</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:51:31 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/26/us/trump-green-card-interview-arrests.html">https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/26/us/trump-green-card-interview-arrests.html</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46065015">Hacker News</a></p>
Couldn't get https://www.nytimes.com/2025/11/26/us/trump-green-card-interview-arrests.html: Error: Request failed with status code 403]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Penpot: The Open-Source Figma (684 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://github.com/penpot/penpot</link>
            <guid>46064757</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:14:36 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://github.com/penpot/penpot">https://github.com/penpot/penpot</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46064757">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div data-hpc="true"><article itemprop="text"><themed-picture data-catalyst-inline="true"><picture>
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: dark)" srcset="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/6f4a230c051d6c3d15a0286b0441f113c4baac20752ab4ec7e276e329f2273c0/68747470733a2f2f70656e706f742e6170702f696d616765732f726561646d652f6769746875622d6461726b2d6d6f64652e706e67" data-canonical-src="https://penpot.app/images/readme/github-dark-mode.png">
  <source media="(prefers-color-scheme: light)" srcset="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/c1fc85084a7b31db77a330977ca9b00c97390ee20b0aec50c70561657a554721/68747470733a2f2f70656e706f742e6170702f696d616765732f726561646d652f6769746875622d6c696768742d6d6f64652e706e67" data-canonical-src="https://penpot.app/images/readme/github-light-mode.png">
  <img alt="penpot header image" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/c1fc85084a7b31db77a330977ca9b00c97390ee20b0aec50c70561657a554721/68747470733a2f2f70656e706f742e6170702f696d616765732f726561646d652f6769746875622d6c696768742d6d6f64652e706e67" data-canonical-src="https://penpot.app/images/readme/github-light-mode.png">
</picture></themed-picture>
<p dir="auto">
<a href="https://www.mozilla.org/en-US/MPL/2.0" rel="nofollow"><img alt="License: MPL-2.0" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/0d433bf1013a998c8b0db6c4c9eefd9edae1111aad142e998918e179fdd5c54a/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f4d504c2d322e302d626c75652e737667" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/MPL-2.0-blue.svg"></a>
<a href="https://community.penpot.app/" rel="nofollow"><img alt="Penpot Community" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/608d7ad63d5dd51331463cdcc583715033bf50f77ea52e68f94cb7ea26f95e1b/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f646973636f757273652f706f7374733f7365727665723d6874747073253341253246253246636f6d6d756e6974792e70656e706f742e617070" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/discourse/posts?server=https%3A%2F%2Fcommunity.penpot.app"></a>
<a href="https://tree.taiga.io/project/penpot/" title="Managed with Taiga.io" rel="nofollow"><img alt="Managed with Taiga.io" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/3352207d59d443f294c31f36995ecedf5212b7e7b1ed4b7d4ca825f0c739e5c2/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f6d616e61676564253230776974682d54414947412e696f2d3730396631342e737667" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/managed%20with-TAIGA.io-709f14.svg"></a>
<a href="https://gitpod.io/#https://github.com/penpot/penpot" rel="nofollow"><img alt="Gitpod ready-to-code" src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/c01324668ea00cd2b02dc9fbf541676fb30543b69ef99a070d62a110917126d0/68747470733a2f2f696d672e736869656c64732e696f2f62616467652f476974706f642d72656164792d2d746f2d2d636f64652d626c75653f6c6f676f3d676974706f64" data-canonical-src="https://img.shields.io/badge/Gitpod-ready--to--code-blue?logo=gitpod"></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
    <a href="https://penpot.app/" rel="nofollow"><b>Website</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://help.penpot.app/user-guide/" rel="nofollow"><b>User Guide</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://penpot.app/learning-center" rel="nofollow"><b>Learning Center</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://community.penpot.app/" rel="nofollow"><b>Community</b></a>
</p>
<p dir="auto">
    <a href="https://www.youtube.com/@Penpot" rel="nofollow"><b>Youtube</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://peertube.kaleidos.net/a/penpot_app/video-channels" rel="nofollow"><b>Peertube</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/penpot/" rel="nofollow"><b>Linkedin</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://instagram.com/penpot.app" rel="nofollow"><b>Instagram</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@penpot/" rel="nofollow"><b>Mastodon</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/penpot.app" rel="nofollow"><b>Bluesky</b></a>  •
    <a href="https://twitter.com/penpotapp" rel="nofollow"><b>X</b></a>
</p>
<br>
<details open="">
  <summary>
    
    <span>Penpot_OpenYourEyes_.mp4</span>
    <span></span>
  </summary>

  <video src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/210353798/451453487-7c67fd7c-04d3-4c9b-88ec-b6f5e23f8332.mp4?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8yMTAzNTM3OTgvNDUxNDUzNDg3LTdjNjdmZDdjLTA0ZDMtNGM5Yi04OGVjLWI2ZjVlMjNmODMzMi5tcDQ_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMTI3JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTEyN1QwNjMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1mOTFiYjA4NDU1Mzk5OGFiZTY3ZGIwNjZlNzRhY2E0OGI5NmUxM2UxMmI3MzFjZDhhMjI0YWIzMDBmNGMyNDJlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.JAjDN-7eHZr_4NbEoQTO4qnSCwwq2ptsgERx06UQVdc" data-canonical-src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/210353798/451453487-7c67fd7c-04d3-4c9b-88ec-b6f5e23f8332.mp4?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8yMTAzNTM3OTgvNDUxNDUzNDg3LTdjNjdmZDdjLTA0ZDMtNGM5Yi04OGVjLWI2ZjVlMjNmODMzMi5tcDQ_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMTI3JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTEyN1QwNjMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT1mOTFiYjA4NDU1Mzk5OGFiZTY3ZGIwNjZlNzRhY2E0OGI5NmUxM2UxMmI3MzFjZDhhMjI0YWIzMDBmNGMyNDJlJlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.JAjDN-7eHZr_4NbEoQTO4qnSCwwq2ptsgERx06UQVdc" controls="controls" muted="muted">

  </video>
</details>


<p dir="auto">Penpot is the first <strong>open-source</strong> design tool for design and code collaboration. Designers can create stunning designs, interactive prototypes, design systems at scale, while developers enjoy ready-to-use code and make their workflow easy and fast. And all of this with no handoff drama.</p>
<p dir="auto">Available on browser or self-hosted, Penpot works with open standards like SVG, CSS, HTML and JSON, and it’s free!</p>
<p dir="auto">The latest updates take Penpot even further. It’s the first design tool to integrate native <a href="https://penpot.dev/collaboration/design-tokens" rel="nofollow">design tokens</a>—a single source of truth to improve efficiency and collaboration between product design and development.
With the <a href="https://penpot.app/dev-diaries" rel="nofollow">huge 2.0 release</a>, Penpot took the platform to a whole new level. This update introduces the ground-breaking <a href="https://penpot.app/penpot-2.0" rel="nofollow">CSS Grid Layout feature</a>, a complete UI redesign, a new Components system, and much more.
For organizations that need extra service for its teams, <a href="https://cal.com/team/penpot/talk-to-us" rel="nofollow">get in touch</a></p>
<p dir="auto">🎇 Design, code, and Open Source meet at <a href="https://penpot.app/penpotfest" rel="nofollow">Penpot Fest</a>! Be part of the 2025 edition in Madrid, Spain, on October 9-10.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Table of contents</h2><a id="user-content-table-of-contents" aria-label="Permalink: Table of contents" href="#table-of-contents"></a></p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="#why-penpot">Why Penpot</a></li>
<li><a href="#getting-started">Getting Started</a></li>
<li><a href="#community">Community</a></li>
<li><a href="#contributing">Contributing</a></li>
<li><a href="#resources">Resources</a></li>
<li><a href="#license">License</a></li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Why Penpot</h2><a id="user-content-why-penpot" aria-label="Permalink: Why Penpot" href="#why-penpot"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Penpot expresses designs as code. Designers can do their best work and see it will be beautifully implemented by developers in a two-way collaboration.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Plugin system</h3><a id="user-content-plugin-system" aria-label="Permalink: Plugin system" href="#plugin-system"></a></p>
<p dir="auto"><a href="https://penpot.app/penpothub/plugins" rel="nofollow">Penpot plugins</a> let you expand the platform's capabilities, give you the flexibility to integrate it with other apps, and design custom solutions.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Designed for developers</h3><a id="user-content-designed-for-developers" aria-label="Permalink: Designed for developers" href="#designed-for-developers"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Penpot was built to serve both designers and developers and create a fluid design-code process. You have the choice to enjoy real-time collaboration or play "solo".</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Inspect mode</h3><a id="user-content-inspect-mode" aria-label="Permalink: Inspect mode" href="#inspect-mode"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Work with ready-to-use code and make your workflow easy and fast. The inspect tab gives instant access to SVG, CSS and HTML code.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Self host your own instance</h3><a id="user-content-self-host-your-own-instance" aria-label="Permalink: Self host your own instance" href="#self-host-your-own-instance"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Provide your team or organization with a completely owned collaborative design tool. Use Penpot's cloud service or deploy your own Penpot server.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Integrations</h3><a id="user-content-integrations" aria-label="Permalink: Integrations" href="#integrations"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Penpot offers integration into the development toolchain, thanks to its support for webhooks and an API accessible through access tokens.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Building Design Systems: design tokens, components and variants</h3><a id="user-content-building-design-systems-design-tokens-components-and-variants" aria-label="Permalink: Building Design Systems: design tokens, components and variants" href="#building-design-systems-design-tokens-components-and-variants"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Penpot brings design systems to code-minded teams: a single source of truth with native Design Tokens, Components, and Variants for scalable, reusable, and consistent UI across projects and platforms.</p>

<p dir="auto">
 <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/210353798/492141777-cce75ad6-f783-473f-8803-da9eb8255fef.jpg?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8yMTAzNTM3OTgvNDkyMTQxNzc3LWNjZTc1YWQ2LWY3ODMtNDczZi04ODAzLWRhOWViODI1NWZlZi5qcGc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMTI3JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTEyN1QwNjMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT02YTIzZjUwNTM0ZDg1MGU0NWUyNzM1NjMyNDdlMThkZmMxMzQ0YzhjZDQ4MDNlMTU0MzA2Y2YzNGFmZjRiYTI3JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.NF2okr9Jy_WMyKYXacnLGLgmJSIbxJ3fEoFS7zRXFQI"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/210353798/492141777-cce75ad6-f783-473f-8803-da9eb8255fef.jpg?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii8yMTAzNTM3OTgvNDkyMTQxNzc3LWNjZTc1YWQ2LWY3ODMtNDczZi04ODAzLWRhOWViODI1NWZlZi5qcGc_WC1BbXotQWxnb3JpdGhtPUFXUzQtSE1BQy1TSEEyNTYmWC1BbXotQ3JlZGVudGlhbD1BS0lBVkNPRFlMU0E1M1BRSzRaQSUyRjIwMjUxMTI3JTJGdXMtZWFzdC0xJTJGczMlMkZhd3M0X3JlcXVlc3QmWC1BbXotRGF0ZT0yMDI1MTEyN1QwNjMwMDFaJlgtQW16LUV4cGlyZXM9MzAwJlgtQW16LVNpZ25hdHVyZT02YTIzZjUwNTM0ZDg1MGU0NWUyNzM1NjMyNDdlMThkZmMxMzQ0YzhjZDQ4MDNlMTU0MzA2Y2YzNGFmZjRiYTI3JlgtQW16LVNpZ25lZEhlYWRlcnM9aG9zdCJ9.NF2okr9Jy_WMyKYXacnLGLgmJSIbxJ3fEoFS7zRXFQI"></a>
</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Getting started</h2><a id="user-content-getting-started" aria-label="Permalink: Getting started" href="#getting-started"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Penpot is the only design &amp; prototype platform that is deployment agnostic. You can use it in our <a href="https://design.penpot.app/" rel="nofollow">SAAS</a> or deploy it anywhere.</p>
<p dir="auto">Learn how to install it with Docker, Kubernetes, Elestio or other options on <a href="https://penpot.app/self-host" rel="nofollow">our website</a>.
<br></p>
<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer nofollow" href="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/2c5f051576d896757ae0630691a5067d45d1184b19adf4c4d995b87df72a1897/68747470733a2f2f736974652d6173736574732e706c61736d69632e6170702f32313638636635323464643534336361656666333233383465623965613061312e737667"><img src="https://camo.githubusercontent.com/2c5f051576d896757ae0630691a5067d45d1184b19adf4c4d995b87df72a1897/68747470733a2f2f736974652d6173736574732e706c61736d69632e6170702f32313638636635323464643534336361656666333233383465623965613061312e737667" alt="Open Source" data-canonical-src="https://site-assets.plasmic.app/2168cf524dd543caeff32384eb9ea0a1.svg"></a>
</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Community</h2><a id="user-content-community" aria-label="Permalink: Community" href="#community"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">We love the Open Source software community. Contributing is our passion and if it’s yours too, participate and <a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/help-us-improve-penpot/7" rel="nofollow">improve</a> Penpot. All your designs, code and ideas are welcome!</p>
<p dir="auto">If you need help or have any questions; if you’d like to share your experience using Penpot or get inspired; if you’d rather meet our community of developers and designers, <a href="https://community.penpot.app/" rel="nofollow">join our Community</a>!</p>
<p dir="auto">You will find the following categories:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/ask-for-help-using-penpot/6" rel="nofollow">Ask the Community</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/technical/8" rel="nofollow">Troubleshooting</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/help-us-improve-penpot/7" rel="nofollow">Help us Improve Penpot</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/madewithpenpot/9" rel="nofollow">#MadeWithPenpot</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/announcements/5" rel="nofollow">Events and Announcements</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/inside-penpot/21" rel="nofollow">Inside Penpot</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/penpot-in-your-language/12" rel="nofollow">Penpot in your language</a></li>
<li><a href="https://community.penpot.app/c/design-and-code-essentials/22" rel="nofollow">Design and Code Essentials</a></li>
</ul>

<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/5446186/320413592-6ac62220-a16c-46c9-ab21-d24ae357ed03.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81NDQ2MTg2LzMyMDQxMzU5Mi02YWM2MjIyMC1hMTZjLTQ2YzktYWIyMS1kMjRhZTM1N2VkMDMucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI1MTEyNyUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNTExMjdUMDYzMDAxWiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9MDQ1ZGQxMGQ2NTExZTFjYjAwMDY5ZjFiNmNiNzllYWFjZmQwNzczNDRmZjY3NDE1MmEwZDY0MjYwODdkYjFjMyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QifQ.imeTph-Hw-93Jq36UmxJwCiVVvB51q4m_8xkx00iJzk"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/5446186/320413592-6ac62220-a16c-46c9-ab21-d24ae357ed03.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81NDQ2MTg2LzMyMDQxMzU5Mi02YWM2MjIyMC1hMTZjLTQ2YzktYWIyMS1kMjRhZTM1N2VkMDMucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI1MTEyNyUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNTExMjdUMDYzMDAxWiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9MDQ1ZGQxMGQ2NTExZTFjYjAwMDY5ZjFiNmNiNzllYWFjZmQwNzczNDRmZjY3NDE1MmEwZDY0MjYwODdkYjFjMyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QifQ.imeTph-Hw-93Jq36UmxJwCiVVvB51q4m_8xkx00iJzk" alt="Community"></a>
</p>

<p dir="auto"><h3 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Code of Conduct</h3><a id="user-content-code-of-conduct" aria-label="Permalink: Code of Conduct" href="#code-of-conduct"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Anyone who contributes to Penpot, whether through code, in the community, or at an event, must adhere to the
<a href="https://help.penpot.app/contributing-guide/coc/" rel="nofollow">code of conduct</a> and foster a positive and safe environment.</p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Contributing</h2><a id="user-content-contributing" aria-label="Permalink: Contributing" href="#contributing"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">Any contribution will make a difference to improve Penpot. How can you get involved?</p>
<p dir="auto">Choose your way:</p>
<ul dir="auto">
<li>Create and <a href="https://penpot.app/libraries-templates.html" rel="nofollow">share Libraries &amp; Templates</a> that will be helpful for the community</li>
<li>Invite your <a href="https://design.penpot.app/#/auth/register" rel="nofollow">team to join</a></li>
<li>Give this repo a star and follow us on Social Media: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@penpot/" rel="nofollow">Mastodon</a>, <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/Penpot" rel="nofollow">Youtube</a>, <a href="https://instagram.com/penpot.app" rel="nofollow">Instagram</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/penpotdesign" rel="nofollow">Linkedin</a>,  <a href="https://peertube.kaleidos.net/a/penpot_app" rel="nofollow">Peertube</a>, <a href="https://twitter.com/penpotapp" rel="nofollow">X</a> and <a href="https://bsky.app/profile/penpot.app" rel="nofollow">BlueSky</a></li>
<li>Participate in the <a href="https://community.penpot.app/" rel="nofollow">Community</a> space by asking and answering questions; reacting to others’ articles;  opening your own conversations and following along on decisions affecting the project.</li>
<li>Report bugs with our easy <a href="https://help.penpot.app/contributing-guide/reporting-bugs/" rel="nofollow">guide for bugs hunting</a> or <a href="https://github.com/penpot/penpot/issues">GitHub issues</a></li>
<li>Become a <a href="https://help.penpot.app/contributing-guide/translations" rel="nofollow">translator</a></li>
<li>Give feedback: <a href="mailto:support@penpot.app">Email us</a></li>
<li><strong>Contribute to Penpot's code:</strong> <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TpN0osiY-8k" rel="nofollow">Watch this video</a> by Alejandro Alonso, CIO and developer at Penpot, where he gives us a hands-on demo of how to use Penpot’s repository and make changes in both front and back end</li>
</ul>
<p dir="auto">To find (almost) everything you need to know on how to contribute to Penpot, refer to the <a href="https://help.penpot.app/contributing-guide/" rel="nofollow">contributing guide</a>.</p>

<p dir="auto">
  <a target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer" href="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/5446186/320413622-fea18923-dc06-49be-86ad-c3496a7956e6.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81NDQ2MTg2LzMyMDQxMzYyMi1mZWExODkyMy1kYzA2LTQ5YmUtODZhZC1jMzQ5NmE3OTU2ZTYucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI1MTEyNyUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNTExMjdUMDYzMDAxWiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9MWIyY2Q2OGFjMTRmYzM2ZmRiMTkyZjExZWUzNTNlMmE5YTg4MzI3MzU1Zjg3OWE3NWQzMjI4YjE1NGU0Y2Q1YyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QifQ.aexCcjmHLC-KhcY6cBBOcnx1zLRflqht7aOfy8uxjRE"><img src="https://private-user-images.githubusercontent.com/5446186/320413622-fea18923-dc06-49be-86ad-c3496a7956e6.png?jwt=eyJ0eXAiOiJKV1QiLCJhbGciOiJIUzI1NiJ9.eyJpc3MiOiJnaXRodWIuY29tIiwiYXVkIjoicmF3LmdpdGh1YnVzZXJjb250ZW50LmNvbSIsImtleSI6ImtleTUiLCJleHAiOjE3NjQyMjUzMDEsIm5iZiI6MTc2NDIyNTAwMSwicGF0aCI6Ii81NDQ2MTg2LzMyMDQxMzYyMi1mZWExODkyMy1kYzA2LTQ5YmUtODZhZC1jMzQ5NmE3OTU2ZTYucG5nP1gtQW16LUFsZ29yaXRobT1BV1M0LUhNQUMtU0hBMjU2JlgtQW16LUNyZWRlbnRpYWw9QUtJQVZDT0RZTFNBNTNQUUs0WkElMkYyMDI1MTEyNyUyRnVzLWVhc3QtMSUyRnMzJTJGYXdzNF9yZXF1ZXN0JlgtQW16LURhdGU9MjAyNTExMjdUMDYzMDAxWiZYLUFtei1FeHBpcmVzPTMwMCZYLUFtei1TaWduYXR1cmU9MWIyY2Q2OGFjMTRmYzM2ZmRiMTkyZjExZWUzNTNlMmE5YTg4MzI3MzU1Zjg3OWE3NWQzMjI4YjE1NGU0Y2Q1YyZYLUFtei1TaWduZWRIZWFkZXJzPWhvc3QifQ.aexCcjmHLC-KhcY6cBBOcnx1zLRflqht7aOfy8uxjRE" alt="Libraries and templates"></a>
</p>

<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">Resources</h2><a id="user-content-resources" aria-label="Permalink: Resources" href="#resources"></a></p>
<p dir="auto">You can ask and answer questions, have open-ended conversations, and follow along on decisions affecting the project.</p>
<p dir="auto">💾 <a href="https://help.penpot.app/technical-guide/" rel="nofollow">Documentation</a></p>
<p dir="auto">🚀 <a href="https://help.penpot.app/technical-guide/getting-started/" rel="nofollow">Getting Started</a></p>
<p dir="auto">✏️ <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PLgcCPfOv5v54WpXhHmNO7T-YC7AE-SRsr" rel="nofollow">Tutorials</a></p>
<p dir="auto">🏘️ <a href="https://help.penpot.app/technical-guide/developer/architecture/" rel="nofollow">Architecture</a></p>
<p dir="auto">📚 <a href="https://penpot.app/dev-diaries.html" rel="nofollow">Dev Diaries</a></p>
<p dir="auto"><h2 tabindex="-1" dir="auto">License</h2><a id="user-content-license" aria-label="Permalink: License" href="#license"></a></p>
<div data-snippet-clipboard-copy-content="This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.

Copyright (c) KALEIDOS INC"><pre><code>This Source Code Form is subject to the terms of the Mozilla Public
License, v. 2.0. If a copy of the MPL was not distributed with this
file, You can obtain one at http://mozilla.org/MPL/2.0/.

Copyright (c) KALEIDOS INC
</code></pre></div>
<p dir="auto">Penpot is a Kaleidos’ <a href="https://kaleidos.net/" rel="nofollow">open source project</a></p>
</article></div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Functional Data Structures and Algorithms: a Proof Assistant Approach (105 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://fdsa-book.net/</link>
            <guid>46064680</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 02:04:57 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://fdsa-book.net/">https://fdsa-book.net/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46064680">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="wrapper">
  
  <h2>A Proof Assistant Approach</h2>
  <h3>
  <a href="https://www.proof.cit.tum.de/~nipkow/">Tobias Nipkow</a>,
  <a href="https://www.tcs.ifi.lmu.de/mitarbeiter/jasmin-blanchette_de.html">Jasmin
  Blanchette</a>,
  <a href="http://cl-informatik.uibk.ac.at/users/meberl/">Manuel Eberl</a>,
  <a href="https://se.linkedin.com/in/alejandro-g%C3%B3mez-londo%C3%B1o-001a1943">Alejandro
  Gómez-Londoño</a>,
  <a href="https://people.utwente.nl/p.lammich">Peter Lammich</a>,
  <a href="http://cl-informatik.uibk.ac.at/csternagel">Christian Sternagel</a>,
  <a href="https://home.in.tum.de/~wimmers">Simon Wimmer</a>,
  <a href="https://lcs.ios.ac.cn/~bzhan/">Bohua Zhan</a></h3>
  <h3><a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/book/10.1145/3731369">Published by ACM Books</a></h3>

<p> This book is an introduction to data structures and algorithms for
functional languages, with a focus on proofs. It covers both
functional correctness and running time analysis. It does so in a
unified manner with inductive proofs about functional programs and
their running time functions.  All proofs have been
machine-checked by the proof assistant <a href="https://isabelle.in.tum.de/">Isabelle</a>. The pdf contains
links to the corresponding Isabelle theories.
</p>

<p>
Click on an image to download the pdf of the whole book:
</p>
<p>
<a href="https://fdsa-book.net/functional_data_structures_algorithms.pdf">
<img src="https://fdsa-book.net/cover.png" alt="Functional Data Structures
  and Algorithms">
</a>
</p>
<p>
<a href="https://fdsa-book.net/functional_data_structures_algorithms.pdf">
  <img src="https://fdsa-book.net/toc1.png" alt="Table of contents 1">
</a>
<a href="https://fdsa-book.net/functional_data_structures_algorithms.pdf">
  <img src="https://fdsa-book.net/toc2.png" alt="Table of contents 2">
</a>
</p>
<p>
This book is meant to evolve over time. If you would like to contribute, get in touch! 
</p>
</div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Migrating the Main Zig Repository from GitHub to Codeberg (850 pts)]]></title>
            <link>https://ziglang.org/news/migrating-from-github-to-codeberg/</link>
            <guid>46064571</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 01:49:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[<p>URL: <a href="https://ziglang.org/news/migrating-from-github-to-codeberg/">https://ziglang.org/news/migrating-from-github-to-codeberg/</a>, See on <a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=46064571">Hacker News</a></p>
<div id="readability-page-1" class="page"><div id="content" role="main">
    
      <p><a id="back" href="https://ziglang.org/news/">
        ← Back to
        <b>News</b>
        page
      </a></p>
    <h3>November 26, 2025</h3>
    
    <p><a href="https://codeberg.org/ziglang/zig" target="_blank">https://codeberg.org/ziglang/zig</a></p><p>Ever since <a href="https://codeberg.org/ziglang/zig/src/commit/8e08cf4bec80b87a7a22a18086a3db5c2c0f1772" target="_blank"><code>git init</code> ten years ago</a>, Zig has been hosted on GitHub. Unfortunately, when it <a href="https://github.blog/news-insights/company-news/github-microsoft/" target="_blank">sold out to Microsoft</a>, the <a href="https://craphound.com/category/enshittification/" target="_blank">clock started ticking</a>. “Please just give me 5 years before everything goes to shit,” I thought to myself. And here we are, 7 years later, living on borrowed time.</p><p>Putting aside GitHub’s <a href="https://www.vox.com/recode/2019/10/9/20906605/github-ice-contract-immigration-ice-dan-friedman" target="_blank">relationship with ICE</a>, it’s abundantly clear that the talented folks who used to work on the product have moved on to bigger and better things, with the remaining losers eager to inflict some kind of bloated, buggy JavaScript framework on us in the name of progress. Stuff that used to be snappy is now sluggish and often entirely broken.</p><p>More importantly, Actions is <a href="https://github.com/actions/runner/issues/3792#issuecomment-3182746514" target="_blank">created by monkeys</a> and <a href="https://github.com/actions/runner/issues/385" target="_blank">completely neglected</a>. After the <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/github-ceo-developers-embrace-ai-or-get-out-2025-8" target="_blank">CEO of GitHub said to “embrace AI or get out”</a>, it seems the lackeys at Microsoft took the hint, because GitHub Actions started “vibe-scheduling”; choosing jobs to run seemingly at random. Combined with other bugs and inability to manually intervene, this causes our CI system to get so backed up that not even master branch commits get checked.</p><p>Rather than wasting donation money on more CI hardware to work around this crumbling infrastructure, we’ve opted to switch Git hosting providers instead.</p><p>As a bonus, we look forward to fewer violations (exhibit <a href="https://github.com/ziglang/zig/pull/25974" target="_blank">A</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ziglang/zig/pull/24983" target="_blank">B</a>, <a href="https://github.com/ziglang/www.ziglang.org/pull/502" target="_blank">C</a>) of our <a href="https://ziglang.org/code-of-conduct/#strict-no-llm-no-ai-policy">strict no LLM / no AI policy</a>, which I believe are at least in part due to GitHub aggressively pushing the “file an issue with Copilot” feature in everyone’s face.</p><h2>GitHub Sponsors</h2><p>The only concern we have in leaving GitHub behind has to do with GitHub Sponsors. This product was key to Zig’s early fundraising success, and it <a href="https://ziglang.org/news/2025-financials/">remains a large portion of our revenue today</a>. I can’t thank <a href="https://devonzuegel.com/" target="_blank">Devon Zuegel</a> enough. She appeared like an angel from heaven and single-handedly made GitHub into a viable source of income for thousands of developers. Under her leadership, the future of GitHub Sponsors looked bright, but sadly for us, she, too, moved on to bigger and better things. Since she left, that product as well has been neglected and is already starting to decline.</p><p>Although GitHub Sponsors is a large fraction of Zig Software Foundation’s donation income, <strong>we consider it a liability</strong>. We humbly ask if you, reader, are currently donating through GitHub Sponsors, that you consider <a href="https://ziglang.org/zsf/">moving your recurring donation to Every.org</a>, which is itself a non-profit organization.</p><p>As part of this, we are sunsetting the GitHub Sponsors perks. These perks are things like getting your name onto the home page, and getting your name into the release notes, based on how much you donate monthly. We are working with the folks at Every.org so that we can offer the equivalent perks through that platform.</p><h2>Migration Plan</h2><p>Effective immediately, I have made <a href="https://github.com/ziglang/zig/" target="_blank">ziglang/zig on GitHub</a> read-only, and the canonical origin/master branch of the main Zig project repository is <code>https://codeberg.org/ziglang/zig.git</code>.</p><p>Thank you to the Forgejo contributors who helped us with our issues switching to the platform, as well as the Codeberg folks who worked with us on the migration - in particular <a href="https://codeberg.org/earl-warren" target="_blank">Earl Warren</a>, <a href="https://codeberg.org/fnetX" target="_blank">Otto</a>, <a href="https://codeberg.org/Gusted" target="_blank">Gusted</a>, and <a href="https://codeberg.org/mfenniak" target="_blank">Mathieu Fenniak</a>.</p><p>In the end, we opted for a simple strategy, sidestepping GitHub’s aggressive vendor lock-in: leave the existing issues open and unmigrated, but start counting issues at 30000 on Codeberg so that all issue numbers remain unambiguous. Let us please consider the GitHub issues that remain open as metaphorically “copy-on-write”. <strong>Please leave all your existing GitHub issues and pull requests alone</strong>. No need to move your stuff over to Codeberg unless you need to make edits, additional comments, or rebase. <strong>We’re still going to look at the already open pull requests and issues</strong>; don’t worry.</p><hr><p>In this modern era of acquisitions, weak antitrust regulations, and platform capitalism leading to extreme concentrations of wealth, non-profits remain a bastion defending what remains of the commons.</p><p>Happy hacking,</p><p>Andrew</p>
    
  </div></div>]]></description>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>